hello friends hello greetings whatever time zone you're in it's lovely
to be with you in this moment in time so
so today we continue with our practice with our exploration of the refrain
of the satipatana which turns out to be very
important very important as as we explored
yesterday the spatial expansion internal external
and today we explore the next part of the phrase of the refrain
which is expanding the temporal aspect which is the rising and passing away and
arising and passing away so
during the guided meditation i will um in make make some invitations bring some
invitations after we've settled uh with our body with the breath i'll
bring some invitations for us to explore this temporal aspect of
arising passing and rising and passing away as the refrain
invites and there's a lot more i'd love to share
with you during the uh the brief darmet afterwards because this this part if you
thought yesterday the internal external dimension was was important um
yeah the the temporal aspect is even more important for for reasons i will i
will explain is of of the highest importance in in
in our practice for the purpose of awakening and for the purpose of insight
so so
so let us begin let us begin our practice together let us land let us land in our
bodies
landing in this moment
arriving arriving arriving [Music]
in this moment in time
and releasing relinquishing everything that has come before
relinquishing the past
relinquishing thoughts of the past as well as the future
planned thinking not that there's anything wrong with planning thinking in our daily life
but in this moment in time in this moment in time
we relinquish what's not needed
we give up joyfully we give up
ah we release entanglements in order to arrive here
in this precious important ever fleeting moment
of aliveness taking refuge
taking refuge
in our hearts
in the goodness of our practice and the goodness of coming together of our intention in this moment
ah and relaxing the body
releasing entanglements
relaxing the body all the nooks and crannies
that are tight maybe the forehead
the jaw ah neck and shoulders
their arms our hands
our chest the abdomen releasing releasing into the sit bones
the entire weight of the upper body released
onto the cushion or the chair your sit bones
releasing the legs
upper legs lower legs and feet
releasing relaxing taking refuge
allowing the sensations the sensations throughout the
body to be prominent
the sensations of hardness softness
the contact points between the cushion
and our bottom
sensations of
coolness warmth soften this hardness
at our hands where our hands touch each other or our lap
feeling of warmth and coolness
in our face
maybe at the nostrils where the air rushes in and out
perhaps sensations of tingling
anywhere in the body
with a feeling of expansion of the breath the flow
and pressure
internally pushing
supporting
this body this body it dance
it dance of sensations a dance of sensations
a dance of sensations
anywhere awareness sati
mindfulness turns to it tends to clearly knows
clearly knows clear comprehension sample
a dance of sensations
hardness softness
tingling
flow [Music]
pushing [Music]
heat
coolness
movement
at the touch points contact points of the body with the cushion the chair
the hands the lips the breath [Music]
or just simply anywhere in the body these sensations so many of
them let awareness be wide
let awareness be why to notice to contain
this dance
and notice how sensations arise
let yourself be curious about sensations arising
see them witness them know them arising come into being
being known
and sensations passing
the knowing passing maybe for something that was prominent
minutes ago or moments ago
no longer sensed
uh
you can also open the sounds if you wish
of the sphere of awareness sphere of the sentence
sounds arising
sounds passing
sensation sounds arising in passing
river of experience constant flow
not constant
a waterfall of experience so many molecules of water
moving moving moving
giving the impression of the waterfall has a fixed thing but it's
always moving shifting
sensation sounds
pleasant unpleasant neutral feeling toned vaden
they're rising and passing arising
staying for a little bit perhaps and then passing
choosing one of the spheres i named sensations or sounds
or feeling tone for some people sounds are easiest
for some others know your own
proclivity to be aware of arising and passing of this phenomena
the aspect of the phenomena
choose one sphere let's say sounds and stay with it
not switching back and forth in the soundscape notice
the soundscape sounds arising and passing
arising and passing
of a phenomenon
of thoughts
a river of experience
and as we bring this sitting period together to a close
letting there be appreciation for ourselves
for having shown up as best as we've been able to letting go of any judgment
even if there was one moment of clear comprehension seeing arising and passing
that's enough it's planting a seed appreciating that you showed up
one moment is infinitely more than zero moments
and appreciating there is goodness in our intention in our practice in the seeds
that we sow individually and collectively
trusting trusting that inner goodness
and offering offering our practice offering our efforts
our intentions our actions aligned with our intentions
today this period of practice to the benefit of all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere especially those especially those
who are unsafe afraid feeling threatened
with a lot of suffering in war zones around this world of ours
offering offering our practice our hearts
to them specially not turning away
human beings just like us
may all beings everywhere all things everywhere including ourselves
be safe be happy
have good health and have ease in their lives
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
be free
thank you thank you for your practice everyone
so hello again hello again everyone
so for today's practice we're continuing with
exploring the significance of the instructions in the refrain
of the sati patana
[Music]
invitations to practice with arising and passing away
of different phenomena the um the
refrain actually just for to remind us just as a reminder
i will put up again the structure and the structure of the satipatana
there are four sections just as a reminder and from the bottom there is body feelings or feeling tone
which you've already studied with guild the past few weeks there is mind and there's dharmas
and the refrain shows up between [Music]
or after every teaching after every teaching as an emphasis
and as i discussed yesterday and on monday the significance of the refrain
and you can listen to that again if you wish by the way this um drawing
this this is from piccolio's book and i have this uploaded into audiodharma
if you want to look at it it's associated with the talks from these mornings
and also the refrain itself the paragraph of the refrain i have it included
in the text of the the youtube if you go back to youtube
you'll see the text of the the refrain so so today we have come to this part of
the refrain which is one abides contemplating the nature of
arising in the body or one abides contemplating the nature
of passing away in the body or one abides contemplating the nature
of both rising and passing away in the body and again the word body here repeats
after the six sections having to do with the body the word is feelings for the section
after the feeling section and of course mind and dhammas so it's
not always the body it changes so so one contemplates the nature of
arising and passing away of all phenomena all phenomena and in the
guided meditation i was inviting you to to uh explore a rising and passing of
sensations in the body and also sounds
is part of the experience of the body too it's in that sphere it's in the sense spheres the first satipatana
also invited you to explore a feeling tone which you've already explored with
with gil feeling toned pleasant unpleasant neutral oh yes it rises and passes away
maybe we didn't focus on that i just brought it in and even thoughts you can
see gosh they just arise and pass away it's this stream it's a stream of
experience like a waterfall of experience waterfall of experience
oh so i'd like to speak a few minutes about the importance of this instruction
even perhaps maybe i would i would yeah i would venture to say even more important than the one we discussed
yesterday which already seemed wow this is important the internal external aspect instead of just being internal
so here we go so according to the discourses not seeing the arising and passing away
of phenomena is simply ignorance while regarding all phenomena as
impermanent is is knowledge and understanding is
wisdom so the one definition of wisdom
is seeing arising and passing away seeing arising and passing away as well
as seeing a rising and passing away which is impermanent on nietzsche
which uh also seeing a nietzsche
leads to seeing dukkha unsatisfactoriness
and also seeing the nature of the selfless nature and personal
nature of all things they're all connected and in fact in the sutas
there is a central importance placed on the direct experience
of seeing the impermanence of all phenomena all phenomena
it is so important it's of central importance and as some of you might be
new for you some of you know the teachings have heard of the teachings on
on the three characteristics anit duka annatta impermanence
unsatisfactoriness and and not self or selflessness or
ungovernability so many ways to translate that it's not no self by the way it doesn't mean that there is no
self yes there is a self it's not not it's not self it's not personal
so so coming back to the refrain studying observing
knowing contemplating one abides contemplating the nature of arising
one abides contemplating the nature of passing one abides contemplating the nature of both rising and passing
this contemplation one gets to see experience impermanence
ah it's a river of experience it's just passing it's passing
and what is impermanent cannot be satisfactory
because it just changes all the time you can't hang your hat on it it's it's like it's
satisfactory one moment it's pleasant one moment it's not possible another moment it's it keeps changing so it's
unsatisfactory it's just doesn't give me lasting satisfaction
and whatever does give lasting satisfaction
what is unsatisfactory also it appreciate the selfless nature
it's not personal it's not personal so
so impermanence really is the foundation for realizing
dukkha for the other two the other two uh
uh marks of existence the three are called the three marks of
of existence and
the insight into arising and passing away is the key aspect of insight insight
knowledges that opens up the four stages of awakening again some
of you might have heard about the four stages of awakening the four
stages of nibbana the unfolding of those four
stages the progress of inside what's called progressing through those stages of
awakening what unleashes this progress or what is
significant what is really significant is insight into impermanence that unleashes
all the other key insights and in fact in the vibhanga sutta in the
samyuttan nikaya insight into arising and passing away or
phenomena is highlighted as the distinction between
a mere establishment of satipatana and its complete and full development
let me say that again that this point is so important that i want to say it again
so in the vibanga suta of samyutta nikaya they make a distinction between
just establishing sati patana and its complete and full development
okay so the difference is establishing the four foundations of mindfulness for
foundations of awareness the establishing is becoming aware of the phenomena itself the
feeling tones the sensations the breath just knowing them right
but what leads to the full development complete and full development which is
bhavana bhavana is this inside interarising and passing
away a phenomena so it's not just phenomena itself studying the phenomena itself but studying that it rises and
passes away that leads to the full development that leads to awakening that
peace is needed
so that this highlights even further the importance of the refrain
that the teachings of the satipatana sutta may not suffice
on their own might not suffice on their own for the task of developing penetrative insight
but actually developing a comprehensive and equanimous vision of impermanence is
needed and quoting also from bikonago here but
but for us to really appreciate seeing arising and passing away is so important
it's so important so a couple more words and then wrapping up
um it is said that when the buddha gave the
first sermon to the five monks who became fully enlightened in the anata
laka nasuta he act he did he took them through the same door
through the five aggregates uh which yeah you'll actually study in in a few
weeks and it's in the fourth satipattana the five aggregates of existence
which really cover all aspects all aspects of existence
so the buddha invited them to see the arising and passing away of all
aspects of the five aggregates of experience five aggregates of experience
after they saw impermanence then they saw that oh
what's impermanent cannot yield to you lasting satisfaction and therefore does
not qualify um as i me or myself and they they became
fully enlightened through this doorway so and and this seeing the impermanence of
the five aggregates is so important that by the way when you get again in a few
weeks when you get to the aggregates in the satipat as gil covers it you'll notice that the
arising and passing away to see the arising and passing away
isn't just in the refrain but it's also in the text of the sati patana sutta
itself it shows up in both places it's pretty cool so watch out for that when that comes
fascinating so so just the last word to say that
through this insight into impermanence we lose this assumption of
stability temporal stability of both the perceiver which is
the perceiver us and the perceived objects internal external there's no
permanence it's it's always shifting and moving
and in this way all notions of of stability in the way stability or
fixedness fixedness like i'm this way i'm always this way like oh the world is
always it just they vanish and one experience is a radical paradigm
shift when you see it in every aspect of phenomena no leaf
left unturned no stone left unturned and
a distinctive feature of stream entry which is the first stage of enlightenment
is this comprehensive realization of impermanence let me say that one more time
distinctive feature of stream entry is this comprehensive realization of
impermanence so cannot highlight the importance of this
part of the refrain strongly enough [Music]
these teachings are so sublime so beautiful and so freeing and they can
completely change our frame of reference completely change our frame of reference
and lead to freedom it's not just stories that are told for reserved for some special
beings this can happen to us in this very life it can happen to us so trust
trust in your practice thank you dear sangha thank you for your
practice and thank you for your kind kind attention i look forward to being with you
tomorrow to continue this exploration with sati patana oh one whole invitation
i always like to give you invitations for the day notice arising and passing notice
arising and passing internally externally notice arising and passing of all
phenomena thoughts preoccupations sensations sound just notice arising and
passing internally and you'll see this perceiver and the perceived is the
cc of experience thank you so much