okay it's good to see everyone nice to see all of you joining hello
this always feels nice to know how many people are out there from so many different places
so we can feel connected in our worldwide sangha as someone said in
their comment so why don't we go ahead and get started
let's sit together so just bringing the attention
to your body your mind sitting here
however you are now and just finding
your spot settling in letting go of whatever you had to do to
get here so that you can be here
if you're comfortable doing so you can close your eyes
but you don't have to and just allow the posture
to settle into something that's upright and also relaxed
connecting in with the sense of the straightness of the spine
by the place that you're sitting [Music] your seat against the cushion or the chair is a
solid foundation and then the body rising up from that
sometimes i have the image of a sea plant rising off the sea floor
so it's held at the bottom and then the rest of the body can kind of float upward
softening the eyes the jaw the neck
softening the shoulders the arms
down through the torso area
just relaxing the muscles that are around that straight spine [Music]
muscles of the chest the belly the low back
releasing any bracing in the legs
and feeling all the way into the feet
so just bringing the attention through the body
to invite some degree of ease
and then turning the attention toward perhaps the sensations of breathing
or the body sitting whatever feels easier to connect to
and just allowing the mind to naturally know what's happening with the body or the
breath in a simple way
maybe opening to sounds also in a simple way
we don't have control over what we'll hear next so it can be useful
just to connect to the sounds
the intention for this sit is to invite this connection to
simplicity in the body and in the mind
so we have a simple object like the breath or the posture
[Music]
we can maybe even see how simple that could get so instead
of oh that's my back and i need to sit in a certain posture so that my
cervical vertebra are at the right angle
we can just feel a slight amount of pressure
shifting easing of the pressure
or in the breath simple sensations like the touch of the air against the
upper lip or the nostrils the
coolness of the air as it goes in
simple feelings like expansion or the touch of the clothing on the skin
shifting i sometimes call these the elemental
sensations of the breath very simple
not about concepts like body parts or difficulties
simple
when we have a simple connection to the body and the breath
that encourages the mind also to be simple
we can feel that a lot of thoughts are complicated
they're about complicated abstract ideas
intricate stories trade-offs and balances
hopes and fears
and what if all of that was just for this sitting just thought
we don't need to figure any of that out now
so bringing our mindfulness back to the very simple
aspects of having mind and a body
it could even be said if it's not simple it's not mindfulness
if the mind has gotten complicated
and we just tuned back in to something simple
a sound an elemental sensation
a simple label of thought
um
[Music]
we may begin to sense that simplicity is connected with ease
allow the body to relax
allow the mind to rest in non-complication
[Music] and sense the particular form of ease that comes from simplicity
the distinctive flavor of that
sometimes the mind is dissatisfied with simplicity
wishes for something more stimulating
and even that is simple it's just the simple dissatisfaction of the mind
another thing to notice
and if there's any sense of joy or
peace associated with inclining toward the simple
that can also be noticed
it's even a simple kind of happiness that's possible for humans
just resting with the body and mind in a simple way
to cultivate simplicity is not to become simplistic
in fact cultivating simplicity allows the mind
to be more open and available
so that we can see more nuance
maybe more subtlety in situations that we're in
so perhaps feeling into how the simple mind
can be responsive
has more flexibility than a mind that is
caught up in complicated scenarios
many concepts and
ideas feeling the openness of the simple mind
so we can sense how this kind of simplicity
the simplicity that comes with awareness and mindfulness
it's actually a service to the world
to have this openness this ability to respond
not having so many preconceived ideas or knowing already what something is as we
come into it it makes us more caring more able to
help others if we're so inclined toward that
it's the complicated knotted up mind and body
that can't be easily of service
so maybe for today an idea could be to
approach your life with a sense of seeing it in a simple way
some new situation oh i wonder what this is i won't assume that i know
already or even a familiar emotion or feeling that comes up
oh yeah there's that same feeling of anger i know anger
maybe you don't what if we just looked at it in a simple
way and the same with other people could we
see our partner fresh not the way we know they already are
or our children or our pets
people that we meet
so that we might offer something of benefit today
it comes when we are not so caught up in complication
some way that we can help
[Music]
okay so today i'm i'm traveling over the um
yesterday and today and i stayed overnight at a friend's house which is where i am this morning
and they have a completely beautiful home they've lived here for a long time and
it's grown to be a space with a lot of love and care in it and it seems like everywhere the eye falls
there's some beautiful thing that they've brought from somewhere and
used to decorate the place so i think it's the perfect setting for our uh topic this week of desire and
letting go yesterday we talked about sense pleasure and sense desire
and i find it intriguing how people hear the buddha's teachings about this um
how they hear it compared to what the teachings actually say and what the teachings say is that these
things simply that these things are not ultimately satisfying and that they're
not the deepest form of human happiness whereas what people tend to hear is they
hear judgment or right and wrong or some directive to stop enjoying things or to
get rid of things that's an interesting reaction to explore in your mind
so being here in this beautiful place is the perfect setting to talk about
renunciation which is today's topic so yesterday we talked about how
not only the buddha's teachings but also our practice enables us to see
that sense desire and sensual pleasures are not they're not all that they're cracked up
to be you know they're not ultimately satisfying and the word as we said for this whole sense domain that we humans
find so enticing is comma the long a comma
so the buddha also talked about a term called me comma
and that is the word that's usually translated as renunciation but please
hold on to your associations with that word um it's going to be a little bit different
so it's an interesting word nicoma necoma can be resolved into its
linguistic roots in two different ways one of them is
near plus comma the negation of comma essentially so that would mean something like
restraint of sensual desire uh doing so out of wisdom and we'll talk about that in a moment
and then another way to resolve it is uh nis plus committee
which is a verb and the verbal form would be knee committee which means something like walk away
from and uh the related noun nakama would mean
leaving a life of pursuing cinch pleasures or more abstractly turning away from greed hatred and
delusion and it may be that there's a play on words and both of those meanings are
intended in the word new comma so it's interesting right because the first meaning of opposing sense pleasure
tends to invite our common association of renunciation with grim austerity
and then the second meaning of about letting go of great hatred and delusion well that's the aim of the
buddhist path that's very inspiring and it's what peace and the deepest happiness are
so there seems to be something of a contrast maybe in our associations so we see that we're going to have to
maybe release our english our associations with the english word renunciation
so let's see you know more carefully where this word nakama is used in the
buddhist teachings and how how the buddha meant that word so we're talking today about
two triads two sets of three of qualities that are are contrasting
each other they're almost opposing each other and one of them is an unskillful triad or unwholesome and the other is a
skillful triad of qualities so in the unskillful one
comma is put together with ill will and cruelty so we have sense desire ill will and
cruelty linked together on one side so as we saw yesterday uh sense desire
and pleasure don't come off too well in buddhist teachings they're linked to ill will and cruelty
and then the skillful one is the opposite it's me comma or renunciation and non-ill will and
non-cruelty so we see that renunciation which we could
also call letting go is connected with qualities of care and kindness
the absence of ill will and cruelty so this is where we have to suspend our common western associations with
renunciation it's different in buddhism i don't think that there's a single
maybe a better single word to translate the word nakama if i had to translate it as one single word okay probably
renunciation is good but the range of meaning is different in the dharma than
it is in our common associations so these two triads
in the teachings these two sets of three are connected to some important
activities of our mind it's connected to intentions thoughts
and perceptions so that's and those are important movements of mind
so for example um in the eightfold path the second step
is wise intention or right intention or appropriate
intention and the definition the very definition
of wise intention is the intention of renunciation the intention of non-ill
will and the intention of non-cruelty that's the definition so it's the second step of the april
path and then there's also a suta where the buddha talks about this
is before his awakening he talks about how he looked at his own thoughts so we're now looking at thoughts rather
than intentions and i want to read a section from that suta
he says as i abided thus diligent ardent and resolute a thought
of sensual desire and the word is comma there arose in me i understood thus
this thought of sensual desire has arisen in me this leads to my own affliction to
others affliction and to the affliction of both it obstructs wisdom causes difficulty and leads away from nibana
and then he says a thought of renunciation has arisen in me me comma
this does not lead to my own affliction or to others affliction or to the affliction of both it aids wisdom does
not cause difficulties and leads to nibana and then there are other
sutas that mention that sensual thoughts have a kind of a blinding or obscuring qualities to them whereas renunciation
thoughts uh remove blindness and produce vision and have sort of openness and clarity
to them and sometimes as i said that triad applies to perceptions sonia
instead of thoughts so um [Music] so it's interesting we'll have to check
for ourselves if that's really true but it does seem to me that when my thought my my thoughts are very much caught up
in things that i want or even things that i enjoy there's a little bit of narrowing a
little bit of um yeah of obstruction in some way whereas
when i even if i'm in the presence of things that are beautiful like i am here in this house
uh if it's not a sense of grasping onto it then there's just a feeling of openness and clarity i
can see those things and uh and my mind is still wise
so the the suta that i just read about thought also includes a famous line that
some of you may have heard it's even quoted out of context in other traditions uh it says
whatever a person frequently thinks and ponders upon that becomes the inclination of their
mind so that suggests that renunciation this
word nakama can become a beneficial predisposition of the mind if you will
so i like to name nikama as an attitude that's a word i'm trying to
choose to capture intentions thoughts and perceptions is that we could have an attitude of me comma
and what does that mean practically maybe what it would mean is that we
would walk around the world with the view or the idea that situations are
opportunities to release the binding of unhelpful desires
so just to be to give a concrete example suppose we find ourselves struggling in
some way we are irritated by somebody or we're
frustrated that we can't get something to work or we're impatient we're waiting for something to
happen and it's not coming so we're struggling in some way and if if we have mindfulness at that moment
and we realize oh i'm struggling right now maybe the thought would occur
what would i have to let go of to make this easier so that would be the attitude of
renunciation what would i have to let go of to make this easier this is vastly different from the
approach of most people or in most situations so instead of wishing for that thing
that i'm trying to get or that result that i'm trying to create we would realize that our desire for
ease or for peace or for not struggling is more important in that moment
maybe we realize that we'd rather figure out how to help someone than try to get them to be the way we want them
to be so this attitude of renunciation helps
redirect our mind in helpful ways if we were to live by this attitude of
letting go of things that are not helpful letting go of unbeneficial desires
the effect of that is to gradually elevate our desires remember when we talked about the
diversity of desires there were five and the fourth and fifth kinds
i named were kind of the elevated human desires the desire to help others the
desire to be ethical and eventually the desire to be free these are the helpful
desires that support the spiritual path so renunciation
the attitude of letting go moves the mind toward the more beneficial kinds of desire
if we can't let go of sense desire and sense pleasure and sort of ordinary
wishes that the mind comes up with i would suggest that we're not going to be able to fully realize
the the better forms of happiness that are available for humans we have to let go of one to get the one that's better
so in the texts in the buddhist teachings the affective or emotional quality
that's associated with me comma is described in terms that are clearly
positive so the words for it are things like delight happiness even bliss
i want to read just a couple of examples so here's one there are these two kinds of happiness
what to sensual happiness and the happiness of renunciation
of these two kinds of happiness the happiness of renunciation is the poor most
so that's a fairly just a straightforward kind of prose uh description of it and then there's
also i want to offer also a verse it says even the gods envy the awakened ones the
mindful ones the wise ones who are intent on meditation
and delight in the peace of renunciation how about that even the gods envy those
who know how to delight in the peace of renunciation so
this word renunciation i hope what we're doing is reshaping our ideas about it
how it's used in the buddhist teachings may not be what your gut reaction to it is
and to see that there's there are choices about which pleasures we go for
and the uh the ones in the sense domain are real enough we have them we may be
surrounded by them and there are options that are better and we can incline the
mind toward them by having this willingness to let go this willingness to be open which is also associated of course with
non-ill will and non-cruelty so good things good ways for the mind to be directed
so thank you and we'll continue our exploration tomorrow