so hello and welcome to this monday morning meditation
where we begin the third foundation for mindfulness for the cultivation the
growth of awareness and this third foundation is usually
called is in palis called cheetah c-i-t-t-a
and in english it's sometimes known as mind state in this context sometimes the word cheetah simply refers
to mind and sometimes we can appreciate what it is maybe sometimes by
the attitude of mind that's present the general mood of the mind the kind of gestalt
uh feeling sense awareness of our inner mentality
the kind of whole of all the inner mental life may be
in in the west we often point to the head as being the
the locus the place of the mind a long asian tradition in buddhism is to
point to the heart as a center for the mind
i like to think of it as as related it's related to the quality
of our inner life that part of our inner life that
may or may not be influenced by events around us the circumstances of our life and things
and that in the deeper deeper places of the mind deeper capacities of the
mind is kind of how we feel and sense and
experience ourselves independent of kind of when we're on our own in our
in our more private private sense of our experience
so uh we'll just do a general uh meditation on the mind
and and then tomorrow we'll go on to
other aspects of it so to begin to take an alert
relaxed meditation posture
and lower your eyes to maybe 45 degrees to the floor
and if it's comfortable gently close your eyes
and before doing anything else notice
what's the general state of your mind right now
it's a general state of your inner life
that may or may not be independent from what's the circumstances that's happening right now
are you more on the agitated end of the spectrum or
more calm
are you more settled or more activated
are you uneasy in any way or is the inner state at ease
are you comfortable with your inner life inner state of mind state of heart
or is there a discomfort about it
whatever way it is let it be that way
but with breathing right in the middle of it perhaps or imagining that you can
breathe accompanying how your
state of mind is state of heart
gently take a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in deeply
breathing out
as you exhale relaxing your body
as you exhale relaxing
around the state of your mind your heart
and letting your breathing return to normal
then maybe if you continue relaxing on the exhale
begin by relaxing the mind
whatever it is for you the mind is
maybe it's the place where you from which you think
where there might be some tension or pressure or agitation
on the exhale let that relax and soften
or maybe there's a pervasive mood
that somehow is related to the functioning of your mind your mental
activity
as you exhale relax the body
as if relaxing the body
so settling around your mood your attitude
relaxing the face
the shoulders
the belly
and then a gentle awareness of your body breathing
in being aware of breathing there's kind of a meeting a meeting
place of the mind and the body the body has its sensations
and the mind somehow knows it
experiences it
and what would it be like to have a balanced awareness
knowing the body's experience
and aware of the mind knowing
with irregularity the constancy of breathing in and breathing out
as a massage or as a gentle
connection
to your state of mind the state of mind
through which you're attending aware of breathing
with the focus being on the rhythm of breathing
breathing with however your mind is however your inner
state is just breathing with it so that you're not reacting to it or
caught in it for or against it
a regular breathing heat coming and going
is a general quality or state of your mind
predominantly [Music] colored by desires
what you want or the wanting mind
or is it predominantly colored by aversion
wanting something different something to go away
or is it colored by confusion uncertainty
whatever way it might be breathe with it with
a gentle way of brushing against it
not needing to fix anything or concerned with anything but awareness brushing fast brushing
through how your mind is
one breath at a time
whether your mind is happy or sad
elated or in the blues eager or reluctant
whatever state way it is
breathe with it breathe through it
a kind of refuge and breathing so you're less reactive to how you are
on the inside just accompanying it with the breathing
knowing the state of your mind whatever it might be
and see if the knowing of it or the feeling of it whichever it is
you can know it with space as if there is a lots of space surrounding it
so rather than being caught in the web of how we feel
the knowing is wider more spacious
and however we are is within
that field of open field of experience
and as we come to the end of this sitting
familiar again with the state of your mind
the mood of the mind the attitude
how has it changed from the beginning of the meditation
and perhaps now at the end of the inhale or as you inhale as you begin to exhale
can the mind relax more deeply
or can you relax deep into the mind
to where the mind maybe is quiet
still
maybe where the mind is calm
like the ocean a few feet under the waves the ocean is quiet and calm
whatever the turbulence of your surface is dropping down into
your quiet place
and then turning your gaze out across the world
and see if your gaze your way of considering
the world that you live in to look upon it kindly
let yourself be still and gaze upon the world kindly
wish having good will well wishing for this world
wishing well wishing happiness for those who suffer and those who don't
wishing for the peace for those who are
not in peace and those who are
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so with this talk i'm going to introduce the third foundation for awareness
third foundation upon which to cultivate and grow our capacity to be aware and mindful
and with the this third foundation there's a real turning point
in the satipatana that's begun in this end of the second foundation
and that is from to turn from the being aware mostly of the body in some way or
other to the mind and on the way there the second
foundation we're aware of kind of the feelings the things that are pleasant and unpleasant that have to do
with the sense contact that reacts and responds to whatever
contact there is and uh and that pleasure
and delight pleasure well-being and also sometimes what's unpleasant
that doesn't belong to any world of sense contact but it's more like a welling up inside a
sense the inner life responds to some kind of deeper
wellspring that doesn't have to do with the thoughts we think
um the memories we have the what's happening around us circumstances
in the world and um and it kind of is pointing to the spiritual this nod of the flesh just
kind of like the spiritual side the dharma the dharma pleasure that can come with practice
and this sets the stage for this third foundation where now we're looking not at the body and not that weatherings are
pleasant or unpleasant but we're looking at the state of the mind
and the word mind is cheetah c-i-t-t-a and this word is used a lot referred to
this concept referred to a lot by the buddha but it's never defined exactly what it
is and it comes from the word
um uh that for the probably a word for thinking
and so it's related to the world of thinking the world of mentality
um but exactly we know what that the inner life of the mind is or what it is
is not defined because it's not meant to be reified it's not meant to be made into something
the mind is some general broad sense we have that's very very
personal that you can't exactly pinpoint this is exactly what the mind is
but maybe it's the kind of gestalt of the mental functionings we have
and the impression or the feeling or the sense we have of how that gestalt how that whole
is and um and the definition of that whole or what it is varies from day to day
from person to person perhaps and it's not so important to know exactly what it is
as to know what it is for you and so maybe for you it changes from
over time what you associate with the mind but it is an inner reference point of
something to be mindful of to be aware of and what's the quality what's the
characteristics of what you call what you say is your mind or your state of
mind and um so um
the state of mind is maybe a little bit more enduring sometimes than sensations of the body
sometimes sensation of the body maybe more enduring than some of the flickerings of the mind
but the general state or general mood of the mind the inner mental life what is it like
for you whatever the mind is it's it's uh colored or shaped
by the activities of the mind so it gets colored one way if there's a lot of desire intense
desire greed and it kind of the mind gets shaped by it or it gets
colored by it so he's looking at the world through this filter of desire and there's a kind of maybe a searching for
something wanting something it can be colored by aversion
and so not wanting pushing away resistance it can be colored by confusion
it can be colored by generosity by a sense of openness and
can be colored by love by compassion it can be colored by wisdom
the mind the mind itself is not a thing but it's kind of like something that is
influenced very much by what we're doing so one of the ways it's uh the shape of
it or the feeling or the sense of it changes is uh if we're really preoccupied in
some kind of thought some problem and really focused on it the mind might seem very small and contracted
but if we're really relaxed and at ease the mind might feel very spacious and open
and so the size of the mind the feeling the mind being open or closed
might vary depending on how preoccupied and unpreoccupied we are
so um and so in this third foundation we're starting to
become aware of how the the quality the characteristics
of this mind that we have and and this is becoming familiar with um
with the allow gives a foundation for big uh for really a sense to become aware of
um for the fourth foundation of mindfulness how the operations of the mind
the colors and shapes the mind you can return to get a sense
and feeling for something that i would like to i refer to or think of associate with
the quality of our inner life as we get to know that quality of our inner life the quality of our mind
then we can have some role in shaping it or seeing how it changes
and simply knowing it this power of knowing of mindfulness of
being present for something is not a a
non-influential act it's an act that kind of
without trying to change anything or it's a kind of things shift a little bit when we're fully present for it
if we're fully present for a mind that's kind of agitated with desires and
wanting and then the knowing is clear enough there's kind of space for that holding it
we see that the mind is not only desirous there's also the mindfulness which is
independent it's kind of wider or separate or distinct that knows
the quality of desire in the mind same thing with aversion same thing with delusion
the the mind can know itself and in the in the knowing
if the knowing is clear enough then the mind is more than whatever
uh desire or aversion or confusion it might have
and and so the knowing of it creates space in a sense or openness or
or some kind of um breathing room
for how the mind is and then we find we're not so contracted by it or caught in it and there's we can
see oh it's a quality of the mind but we don't that we don't have to identify
or say this is who i am some people have a
some kind of vague probably idea or feeling of i am the i am-ness how i who
i am or the fact that i am i exist and that for some people is closely connected to the mind as well
and um and the buddhism doesn't emphasize there's a self or this sense of i am
but whatever that is for you if you have that this fits a little bit under this category of mindfulness of the mind
where it's possible to bring attention and awareness and hold the quality or be aware of the
texture or the feeling tone or the experience of
the sense of eminence the sense of just beingness that resides someplace within
and i think for me this this fits into the category of mindfulness of the mind
and and we start getting familiar with um how the mind changes and morphs and
it's different at different times and over time especially for meditators we learn that the mind is flexible this
fluid it's changeable we learn that stopping and being present and knowing
not just barreling ahead with our concerns and preoccupation but pausing and taking a good look to recognize
what's there begins to uh have a wonderful influence on the contracted mind or the agitated
mind something begins to shift and change in that regard we start becoming familiar with what
it's like when the mind is not preoccupied when it's not desirous or
angry or afraid the mind is more open and generous and
loving and to start feeling some of the wonderful ways the mind can be
and in the buddhist tradition the wonderfulness of the mind is sometimes referred to as the beauty of
the mind that the mind can be can be experienced with something amazingly beautiful
i would say that for me i've been to many beautiful places in the world seen beautiful arts all kinds
of wonderful things and i i would say the most beautiful thing that i've ever seen
is the purified mind the bright clear mind
and and so we can start getting a glimpse of the beauty of the mind that's not
beautiful necessarily because we've done wonderful things in the world or that
everyone loves us or something but it's a beautiful mind in and of itself
independent of uh what's happening in the world around us
and we're cultivating this beautiful mind by discovering how not to get caught
by the unwholesome mind the mind that is challenged by desire
and greed and fear and agitation and restlessness and dismay and
sadness grief all kinds of things that catches the mind of course those things are there
and we're not denying them the practice of this third foundation
is to know this is how the mind is this is what's going on in the mind just know it
and it can be hard with the mind but this is the radical and i would say revolutionary kind of
movement of the mind which is to whatever state that's in to
discover how to simply know it this is how it is
and in that simple knowing this is how it is to not be
wedded to it not be caught in it not be reactive to it it's almost like you step back
a couple of steps and turn around and look and see what the mind has been up to we've been enmeshed in the mind and
we pause we breathe we take those backward steps and then we look back and we see it in a whole new way
and we have some spaciousness around it some openness and that spaciousness
becomes part of the quality of the mind's beauty or
and now the spaciousness uh some of the beauty of the mind has to do with the
clarity of the mind and that cleared the mind sometimes becomes a feeling really feeling of
brightness in the mind the mind becomes bright luminous and the mind is no longer being defined
by the particular thoughts concerns and attitudes we have but it becomes
and and as a result it becomes like the fog has cleared and there's this brightness and clarity
in the mind that can be beautiful
so um that's that's the topic for this week the third
foundation for awareness and cultivating awareness developing this
aware mind and what's kind of
poignant about this is that as the awareness of the mind develops
the mind the awareness and the mind at some point don't become so separate
and an awareness kind of becomes the mind or the mind becomes just mostly a field of
awareness it's not all of what it is but at first we might feel like we're aware
of the mind and then the mind becomes the awareness almost and shifts and we'll see how that goes
by the end of the week so thank you and
i look forward to this time and then
continue tomorrow thank you
you