so so welcome welcome to happier and
as always we start by warming the space with meta by saying hello
simple hello hi and i start by saying hi i'm nikki i'm in mountain view california
unseated olonyland and who is here who would like to say hello you can unmute yourself if you
like you can type in chat take it away
hello i'm dave in o'carver hi dave i'm neil in soon to be snowy new
hampshire are you kneeling soon to be snowy new hampshire is it pretty chilly out there
uh for you it would be it's like 20 or something oh for you it's nothing
if it starts with the two it's okay welcome
may happy hour warm your heart even if the outside it's cold
yeah hi linda this is linda in utah and i'm jealous of neil
because we have no snow so
and it's 12 degrees you're having mutita for neal enjoying
the snow as much as he is and the warm balmy 20s
elaine says hi from belmont anybody else wants to say hi
uh hi this is wayne in uh richmond in actually anyway came home from school today having been
told i have coveted oh no so sorry to hear that oh it's
not anything oh hope hope he doesn't develop into anything terrible
holding you holding you with care oh
richard says expecting two feet of snow in boston okay
all right anybody else wants to say hi before yes
this is clear in new york and i'm very excited about the two feet of snow because we're hoping for it too
so i this is sweet i love all these you know the baby loving of the snow
it's very sweet it's very special and and anything can be special so let's
let's get formally started just for the people in california we sometimes get our skis out and ski down
park avenue well thank you i appreciate hearing that having good detail for you
no snow in capitola says aurora so let's let's formally start everyone let's formally start
by uh i'll change the settings at this point so unmuting accidentally won't be
possible and thank you neil for sharing information about happy hour
google groups in chat in case you're new to happier it's a great
forum for getting the quotes and poetry and connecting with other members
it's sweet so and also at this time i changed the settings so
the chat if any will only come to host but let's keep that quiet also and only
if something is urgent like my sound drops off otherwise let's keep that
quiet it'll open it up later and last but not least i'll turn on recording
for the sake of audio dharma
here we go okay all right
hello hello and warm welcome everyone
wherever in the world you're joining from as mentioned earlier in our in our
hellos whether it's snowy no snow temperature is in the 20s ones or
60s oops anyway so um [Music]
yeah warm welcome warm welcome so for today's practice together for
today's practice and community given that right now as we
as in this moment in time as we are gathered together
on zoom and youtube to practice um
the funeral of tiknot han is being held right now
and it's being live streamed his cremation and funeral so i figured this was
a sweet time to dedicate our practice to practice and happy or
inspired by his teachings inspired by his teachings i know diana shared
a um poem or paragraph
by him so i think i like to do that again tonight so i pulled out my my
yellowed copy of pieces every step by take not han
and and i wanted to read just
a couple of paragraphs from the very beginning of the book
and and for uh to inspire us to inspire us for
our practice tonight so this first so the book for those who may not be familiar with
it pieces every step is is these very short chapters i need
chapters about maybe a page sometimes couple pages sometimes half a page and the very first
chapter is called 24 brand new hours so let it wash over you
these paragraphs so take not hand
who is everywhere now supporting us in our
practice i believe he said every morning
every morning when we wake up we have 24 brand new hours to live
what a precious gift what a precious carrot
we have the capacity to live in a way that these 24 hours will bring peace
joy and happiness to ourselves and others
such beautiful simple and profound teaching i'll continue
we can smile breathe walk and eat our meals
in a way that allows us to be in touch with the abundance of happiness that is
available that's a profound statement everyone happiness that is available
it's not that we have to search for it look for it happiness that's available here and now
if we change the way if we shift the perspective of the way we're looking
we can smile breathe walk and eat our meals in a way that allows us to be in touch with the abundance of happiness
that is available we are very good at preparing to live but not very good at living
we know how to sacrifice 10 years for a diploma and we are willing we are willing to
work very hard to get a job a car a house and so on but we have difficulty remembering that
we are alive in the present moment the only moment there is for us to be
alive every breath we take every step we make
can be filled with peace joy and serenity we need only to be awake
alive in the present moment this
paragraph especially resonated with me as many of you know is the course befriending mortality that i've been
teaching started this past week on wednesday so i've been really sitting with reflections and
about being alive and and and uh what does it mean to appreciate
being alive in this moment in this moment in this amazing mysterious miraculous
moment and this is what he's pointing to we are so good at preparing to live
always looking the future oh i will be happy when all everything is
okay i will be happy when i have my degree i will be happy when i have the perfect job the perfect
relationship the perfect this the i will be happy when i don't have to work so hard it's just like
the mentality of future orientation future orientation
and as he says but not very good at living not very good at living
he he is very gently pointing very gently pointing us right here right
now right here right now
every breath we take every step we make can be filled with peace
joy and serenity and we know this we know this in this sangha we know this that as we turn
you know as we turn our minds our hearts we can be
distracted and stressed out and we perhaps we come to happy hour and we sit and we practice together
and realize oh there is peace here yeah i had a hard day i had a rough day
and it's okay there's peace here right now in this tired body in this moment there's happiness there's joy there's
gratitude and this is something we have been exploring together
now over zoom and and youtube over the past two years now in every session it's
right here it's already here it's already here we just turn our
attention our perspective to it it's already here saying hello i'm here
so
and i want to offer this this
meditate this um [Music]
i guess what do i call it well he says he calls it um he says there okay he
says there are many extras there are so many exercises that we can do to help us breathe consciously
besides a simple in-out exercise we can recite these four lines silently as we breathe in and out and many of you might
be already familiar with these four simple lines and i know that i have used
them before and then just they just bring joy and calm so so i'd like to invite us
to practice with these four simple lines tonight breathing in
i calm my body breathing out i smile
dwelling in the present moment i know
this is a wonderful moment read them one more
time breathing in i calm my body
breathing out i smile and let yourself smile we've explored that before in
in on this in the previous sessions breathing out i smile
dwelling in the present moment i know this is a wonderful moment
so there's a lot more commentary but um [Music] well maybe i'll just say a little more
breathing and i call my body reciting this line is like drinking a glass of cool lemonade on a hot day isn't that
sweet i just love his language you can feel the coolness permeate your
body when i breathe in and recite this line i actually feel my breath calming
my body and mind breathing out i smile you know a smile
can relax hundreds of muscles in your face wearing a smile on your face is a sign
that you are a master of yourself and we also know that
by the way smiling changes has has other impacts not just in the muscles of the
face but also other physiological and psychological impacts so please do smile
dwelling in the present moment while i sit here i don't think of anything else
i sit here and i know exactly where i am
and the last one i know this is a wonderful moment it is a joy to sit stable
and at ease and return to our breathing or smiling our true nature
our appointment with life is in the present moment i love that our
appointment with life we all have an appointment with life our appointment with life is in the
present moment if we do not have peace and joy right now
when will we have peace and joy tomorrow
or after tomorrow what is preventing us from being happy
right now that's such a profound teaching
as we follow our breathing we can say simply calming smiling present moment
wonderful moment this exercise is not just for beginners
many of us who have practic practice meditation and conscious breathing for 40 or 50 years continue to practice in
the same way because this kind of exercise is so important
and so easy so
so with gratitude appreciation for the gifts of take not on let us begin our formal
practice tonight sitting together breathing together smiling together
so i invite you to sit however is comfortable for you
you can move to a cushion or even lie down if that's what your
body calls for i'm going to sit for
i'm gonna sit cross-legged cross-legged here on my chair
and landing arriving
here here
breathing in breathing in i calm my body
let's start with calming the body ah dear body
calming calming calming the body
as if your body was as a child sweetheart sweetheart
it's okay it's okay or maybe a pet
a beloved pet petting [Music] the child the pet this body
breathing in i calm my body
calming settling breathing out i smile
breathing out i smile knowing that smiling relaxes your body your heart
your mind breathing in my calm
[Music] my body
here calm soothed
age in breath calming soothing soothing
each in-breath like a lullaby
each in-breath calming the body
bringing care love to the body
breathing and i calm my body
age in breath calming soothing collecting
and breathing out i smile
i greet i create myself i greet this body
i greet the world
i greet my appointment with life in this moment right here right now
this important appointment the most important one i have
with myself here now a reason to smile
breathing in i call my body breathing out i smile
and spend some time with the first couple of phrases and really settle into them
before adding the others
breathing in i call my body breathing out i smile
now bringing in the other phrase after
bringing in breathing in breathing and i calm my body
bringing bringing attention to the body not in the head
combing the body being embodied feeling the body
breathing and i calm my body
breathing out i smile
and really do smile what do you have to lose
experiment be a scientist of your mind yes
lovely smile breathing out i smile
see the shifts that the smiling can make in your heart space
notice notice if something opens up
something opens up when you smile
maybe a little bit of brightness
breathing in i call my body ah dear body
breathing out i smile
dwelling dwelling
in this dwelling in the present moment
dwelling in the present moment
dwelling living resting abiding
spaciously embracing the present moment
right here right now
i know i know this is a wonderful moment
i know deep deep in my heart
i know this is a wonderful moment
filled with miracles amazing to be alive
dwelling in the present moment i know this is a wonderful moment
breathing in i calm my body
breathing out i smile and see if you when you smile
when you exhale see if your body relaxes some more it just settles some more
see for yourself
dwelling in the present moment
i know this is a wonderful moment
of course the phrases when you say them in full will spread over multiple breaths it's not a problem take your
time
dwelling in the present moment
i know this is a wonderful moment
it's okay also to take one phrase and just rest with it for a few breaths
because sometimes the mind can get a little confused like wait what comes afterwards
to say dwelling in the present moment
relish that for a few breaths
they know this is a wonderful moment
just acknowledging that bringing that into our heart space can actually
make us realize the goodness the beauty the grace of this present moment
i know this is a wonderful moment
you're welcome to stay with the long forms resting dwelling
[Music] each sentence or move to the short form
calming smiling [Music]
present moment wonderful moment
you can synchronize the words the phrases with your breath
as you breathe in calming breathing out smiling
breathing in present moment breathing out a wonderful moment
if you wish
meeting meeting this moment right here not past not future
wishing for something different wanting something that wasn't right here
meeting this present moment right here with a smile
this moment present moment wonderful moment
wow this is a wonderful moment
i'm alive i have awareness i'm conscious
this gift of being human
is mystery being part of this amazing
ongoing
form is called humanity i'm a part of this me this being
in this moment i'm participating by just being alive this wonderful moment
precious moment
call me smiling
present moment wonderful moment
how lucky are we to be able to sit and meditate together in this present moment
and for the last moments of this practice maybe connecting with one of the phrases that
really came alive for you again
or maybe all of them don't have to choose
filling your heart one last time [Music]
with the goodness of this practice with your own goodness
goodness of the present moment met with a smile
may all beings everywhere including ourselves meet the present moments of their lives
with awareness appreciation [Music] with a smile may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
and thanks to thai affectionate name of
take not han for the beautiful beautiful gift of his
teachings and his presence in this world for
becoming the human being that he became through all the practice all the
challenges all the beauty all the suffering that he had in his life
to gift so many gifts to us so
with appreciation to him so we have time for reflections if you
like to share the spirit of sharing your practice with others
for the benefit of all beings you can raise your hand your zoom hand or type in chad if you type
privately to me only i will not read your name just the comment
if it's public then i'll read your name also fred please
thank you uh tomorrow marks one year since my wife's death and i
began to come to the sangha shortly after that and i just want to take this moment to
thank you nikki and to thank each of you in the sangha individually and as a body
for a tremendous amount of help through the past year thank you
thank you so much fred for sharing for
allowing us for letting us in to hold this important anniversary with you
and um [Music] and thank you for your practice
and supporting everyone with your practice in this sangha
showing up not just for yourself but for everyone else deep appreciation from everyone
oh to you yeah thank you fred
[Music]
space floor is open for other reflections [Music]
about the practice tonight or anything else for that matter
were there any particular guidance instructions
from tai that that really resonated for you or lit up for you
something opened up for you if you're willing to share for the benefit of others
or anything else for that matter
we are a quiet bunch tonight i think somebody's trying to raise their
hand but actually that's the clap there
somebody raised their hand they'll ask you to unmute
so i was at the store so i wasn't quite sure what you were talking about but i
think that you're mentioning about um every day you have a 24 hours
to make a day bright or something like that
i i was reading i was reading from uh since you joined late i was reading from
pieces every step which is a book by tik natan i was reading the very first chapter and yeah that's that's what he
was writing oh i see yeah so so i think that these days i'm like
almost every single day um i'm very like negative
my friends told me you're very uh why don't you just see uh take things like positively every single
day i mean every day that would be really nice having a different perspective of the
same things but you know it was not really easy but when i heard that words
from you and i'm thinking oh yeah right
well things not gonna go as always that you want it and a lot of things makes me
really disappointed too but i still have a 24 hours every day making
things brighter and nicer make it oh yeah something like that so
it's it was kind of struck me uh when i heard that sentence and yeah
yeah beautiful i appreciate that yeah and so if if it really spoke to you then i would recommend
finding um pieces every step this book by take not on because there's so much simple wizard no it's just the first
chapter i read uh parts of it paragraphs of it and also i would maybe say one more thing in
what you shared about oh yeah this this negativity that we bring in this it's really a perspective that we bring in
to our day to every moment of of living and having a different perspective
can shift our our lives our perception because it's it's really
deeply deeply you know is this what i'm about to say it both seems like a very simple
sentence but it's actually a profound insight and mystical insight that everything
everything is our perception everything is our perception everything
even when you say well i'm disappointed things are not going my way that's also a perception because if one is limited
to this limited view of me me me i want this it's good for me like ah actually even that is a perception so
it's a radically different way of being in the world so i'll leave you with that thank you
vicky please
i i was thinking about some of the pressures some of the things that
seem to be obligations to do and how to be in peace with that and and actually do them
because peace he seems to be [Music]
sitting and quiet and how to stay with that as we
take care of things that are what i i should do you know but i prefer
to prune the garden how to stay in peace with less desirable
lists of things to do because it's it's a perception but if i don't do them
you know the bills won't get paid so if i'm
you're cutting out a little bit here and there so it's just to make sure i hurt with the reflection that you're sharing
that when you're sitting quietly in meditation that lots of different things are coming up and
and how to be no no in meditation is very peaceful
but during the day each step is uh if i'm useful i'll be sitting
oh actually i would like to to challenge you you how can you be peaceful in the
middle of busyness in the middle of doing this and that and the other can
you hold your peace and it is possible if it weren't possible i wouldn't suggest it vicky that right yeah
yeah so having peace you know this i'm not saying anything you don't know but
having peace doesn't mean that you'll just sit and meditate all day it's it's how can we train ourselves in this
practice i mean being a good buddhist or a good practitioner isn't that you just check out and you just you know hang out
it's like you in every interaction in ways that you show up you have peace
yeah yeah we're bringing that in yeah i think i got the point yeah right yes is that what you're talking
about i mean not that i'm peaceful every moment no but that's the intention
yeah yeah beautiful yes yeah cultivation and it is possible
yeah thank you yeah [Music] and one
um private reflection thank you for helping us grieve ties death and
share him being everywhere now yeah so thank you for that reflection i so
appreciated his words of yeah
so dear ones this is the time that we turn to
hold each other to practice in small groups in small
breakout groups so if you can stay that would be lovely because it's so sweet to connect with
with sangha it's and just connect with practitioners and if you have to go it's okay no no
judgements at all so i'm going to open up the rooms take
care of yourselves take care of each other 15 minutes of maybe 15 seconds silent
silent meta smiling how about that let's bring in 15 seconds of silently smiling
at yourself and each other just like wow these amazing human beings and um
and then yeah share as little or as much as you like here we go okay welcome back everyone
we've got a couple minutes left for any last minute reflections comments
questions neil please
so the instruction the first phrase is i forget while i breathe in i relax the
body right and it seems really difficult for me to relax on the inhale
yeah yeah i see heads nodding here so yeah yeah yeah it
okay yeah so right right and you know
i i mean i'm okay not doing it that way but i mean why did he word it that way
if you know if it's there's not some point to it oh yeah yeah so i'm so glad you brought
this up so here are the two pointers i would give
first the way he words it actually is breathing in i calm the body
and there's a difference between relaxing and calming
tune into that meal and you'll feel a difference because
the in-breath can be calming to the body it can be tuned into how the
wow how the in-breath wow how the in birth can be calming
it can be so like something that has not yet been opened up for you to be opened
up it's not right away it's not on the surface it takes a little bit of tuning into but i
have no doubt that you will you'll feel it you'll tune into it
does that sound okay it sounds exciting i look forward to it i'm excited for you neil being excited
awesome thank you thanks thanks so much for asking that for the benefit as much as
yourself and everyone else yeah sweet so dear ones we have come to the end of
our practice time together so thank you so much for joining happy hour
for practicing for your own sake in the sake of others in the world and also tonight for joining together to
honor this this amazing beautiful precious teacher
um whom we have been gifted
we were gifted and we're still gifted so may all beings be well may all beings be
free including ourselves
[Music] thank you friends