good morning good afternoon good evening good night
all over the world in fact warm and cold
wet and dry one Dharma
or greetings let's begin with some sitting together foreign
so settling into our
upright meditative posture
upright and alert whether we are reclined or
sitting with a free spine
first sensing into the support the ground the seat
and from a connection with that steady supportive base
sensing our way up the spine aligning little by little
as we do this you may notice your breath adjusting itself
and now may be a good time to take a few long slow deep breaths
yeah arriving with the body
letting go of any obvious holding
foreign
letting the breath return to normal its natural rhythm
[Music]
foreign
settling in with the breathing foreign
with the breathing
clear with the breathing
[Music]
thank you [Music]
thank you
to clearly know this breath
this breath recognizing
breathing in recognizing breathing out
confident in the clear recognition
this spread
foreign [Music]
[Music]
foreign
confident
confident in the clear recognition
this in breath this out breath
foreign
if there is wavering
if there is uncertainty
breathing in confident
in clearly knowing uncertainty
confident in clearly knowing wavering
foreign
[Music]
clearly knowing this breath in
this breath out
confident in the clear knowing
foreign
all right
[Music]
foreign
sitting comes to an end
to relax let go of
any effort with the meditation
is to relax a body her mind
and to appreciate any little bit of goodness or well-being that's arising
in any little bit
so that recognition can nourish us
foreign
my confidence and clear knowing
May everyone we encounter benefit
and may the benefits of our practice together extend far and wide
thank you
foreign [Music]
so hello again deep appreciation
for this week of reflection together my name is kodo
yeah so deep appreciation for five days considering the five lay
precepts what a pleasure to do that in Sangha
foreign for this morning our fifth day
is I'll make some some brief comments about the fifth uh precept
and then I would like to as we have been this whole week do a recitation of the
precepts but I'd like to do a longer form and in the ancient language of the poly
so I'll I'll share that with you and then I would like to make some time at the end for questions
so maybe a bit to cover in about 12 minutes and I may stay a few minutes after if
there are extra questions so let's begin with the
fifth precept which is put this way
for the sake of our training together I undertake the precept to abstain from
intoxicants that are a cause for heedlessness
clear confident with the time that we have one of the
maybe more evocative things that we could put forth is a simple observation
that the Buddha as far as I am aware and these early teachings
never praised the use of intoxicants
in fact spoke against it strongly consistently so
the Buddha prohibited the use of alcohol wine intoxicating Liquors for
the monastics and then in the in the 10 rules for novice monastics which were then the
model for of the five lay precepts
and um out of curiosity I was looking up the origin story where did this rule come
from because the um the video the monastic rules are just full of these these um
stories of a time before a monastic Rule and then something happens and then the
Buddha says ah yes now there will be a rule we will train in this way so the story is something like
there's this um there's this venerable monastic I think at the time is an attendant of the
Buddha perhaps not Ananda but another monastic and they're wandering on alms round and
the folks um uh say oh don't don't go over to this cave there's a dangerous serpent in this
cave to make a long story short the attendant the monastic I think his name is
venerable sagata goes into the cave and has what more or
less amounts to a um meditative battle
uh with this uh with this dangerous serpent
sort of peacefully subdues this dangerous serpent sometime later comes out and the lay
people are standing at a respectful distance and they say oh venerables this group of
monks what can we what can we give you what's hard for you to get that we the late people can offer
and the the group of monks say oh there are these there are these intoxicants
there are these Liquors that are really hard for us to get you can give us those so every house in the town apparently
then gives to the monastics these drinks so this this attendant
venerable sagata goes from house to house and then sometime later as you might imagine
according to the according to the writing he's found sort of face down um unconscious next to the path and the
Buddha says oh manastics pick him up let's take him back
so this previously strong
meditator venerable respectable Monk Is found unconscious at the at the least a um a
bit embarrassing then they take him back to back to the monastery and he's sort
of rolling around in his sleep the monastics put him down with their with uh with his head toward the Buddhas
while he can sleep the sign of respect in Ancient India and while he's rolling around he
ends up putting his feet toward the Buddha a sign of disrespect at the time
and this is when the Buddha makes the proclamation and he says things along the lines of it's oh it's unseemly it's
uh I have it here how does he put it it's not fitting
for sagata it's not becoming it's not suitable it's not worthy
it's not allowable and it's in the wake of this that the Buddha then makes this rule
of abstaining from intoxicants um
so I think with the time we have I'll I'll maybe leave some of the reflection to what do you suppose the Buddha's
motivation was what were the intentions that the Buddha was um
had for himself and then what qualities was he trying to imbue in the Sangha
what were the qualities what were the consequences that he saw uh through through this act that he
wanted to prevent qualities consequences intentions
so um the one I will highlight before we move
on to the next piece very very important quality in the Buddhist teaching very important
ancient word uh apamada heed fullness
infamous this um this precept encourages us to undertake the
abstinence from intoxicants that are a cause for heedlessness famada and that
is the Mind becomes blinded or in influenced in such a way that it's care
for skillful qualities gets lost let's care for skillful qualities gets
lost and in contrast
one who is accomplished in the Restraint of these precepts is said to shine
glow be eliminated to be accomplished in virtue and blameless
they're heedful
foreign other note
which I think I'll save for the very end so some very brief reflection on this
fifthly precept but I would like to take a moment now and offer a longer
recitation [Music] of these precepts in poly as that's uh
the recitation has been part of our practice all week let me share this with you so that you
can see foreign
that link if it shows up
because of time I'll refrain from much explanation here and just offer the recitation and then if there are
questions we can do those at the end this may take about three minutes and in case anyone needs to go I'd like
to say thank you so much as a Sangha for
supporting this aspect of a teacher trainee spending the week with me and these
Reflections on the precepts I I have a very clear sense
um both from my my training as a priest at Zen Center and then as a teacher trainee here
um that the entire community
trains a teacher so my deep gratitude
looks like I need to adjust something in the document here
maybe give that a try
there so
um [Music]
foreign
[Music]
foreign [Music]
and then the precepts me [Music]
soon [Music]
[Music]
the army
so long form amateurs refuges precepts
and I hope these Reflections this week have been supportive for for you for us in terms of
considering how to live um live a dharmic life with ethical
reflection uh to consider how we might apply these precepts in our own life come back to
them again and again um and how to live well how to live
wisely how to live in a way that benefits us and benefits everyone
so now I'd like to um open um the chat for more questions
and I can stay behind probably until about 750 Pacific so a few minutes at least
um anything you'd like to ask I saw a question earlier about um
what to do if you know someone is speaking an untruth to you is there something
is there something
um is there something you can say and do and there's this there's this teaching in the dhamapada of uh to conquer a liar
with truth it's at least encouraging
um to conquer a liar with truth
how that's done that's definitely particular to circumstance
what's coming to my mind to share right now without knowing is that we can always protect our own
commitment to truthfulness um someone someone may
say something untruthful May lie to us actually um
you know one-on-one situation and we can protect truthfulness in ourselves
we can protect it in ourselves whether or not they're willing to say something true
if you choose to engage very simple ways without it without as
much without even any charge could be something like
oh I'm not sure that that is true I'm not sure that that is accurate
and there's no there's no Barb there's no Revenge there's no like demand in
what you're saying is just offering the simple observation oh I'm not sure I'm not sure that that's true
um and one of the guiding criteria here for me is how to proceed
peacefully how to proceed in a way that that supports peace and the interaction and
then beyond so that's something general and then the um
the particulars really depend on context you know if there are other questions
yeah thank you for all the thanks this is lovely
oh someone asked a question earlier about if the other uh recordings would be posted that's my
understanding though I'm I'm not so uh in the know about how that works
foreign and about Zoom
I understand that sometimes we also meet on zoom in addition to YouTube this being my first time
um I went with just YouTube and maybe by the next time I'll be able to do
um I'll be able to do YouTube also or be able to do Zoom also
yeah these are good questions the um
there's no simple answer for the question this very commonly
comes up actually the uh the Holocaust question would we lie to hide someone
and um the there there's no simple answer to this
question but what it raises is the fact that
um we continuously have to navigate what is a wise peaceful non-harming life
and the something to note about something like the Buddhist precepts is
um for for us as lay practitioners there's no there's no like overarching Authority
in any place at all that interprets the precepts that like
this way is the is the right way for you to apply this to your life we can give advice we can encourage a reflection but
there's no Final Answer Authority anywhere um
so truly we have to study closely my my sense of the as I was saying yesterday
the developmental model of working with these precepts is something like
starting where it's simple start where it's simple where we're not working at the edge cases like the the
Holocaust example is what I'm referring to as an edge case because it's particularly complicated
so um well complicated in some ways and quite
simple than others maybe I'll say that but the developmental model for the training is to begin where it's easy
begin where it's clear start observing things like cause and effect
within yourself what qualities are generated what intentions are are evoked what are the consequences of your
actions and then let that wisdom let that wisdom grow let that wisdom
expand and then what we learn where it's simple can guide us and where it's difficult
oh will I be here next week I won't I won't actually um next week
another teacher trainee May Elliott will be teaching an introduction to
mindfulness meditation I think should be covering uh covering five aspects of
the instructions that we do well to practice over and over again
and then maybe last question before I go that I happen to catch as it went by was um
um what do we do when we realize we've gone against Our intention or broken a precept
as I mentioned yesterday the the model that I take from
um from the Buddha is um is a simple one
it's one first recognizing that this is the fact recognizing that I've gone
against my intention or I've broken a precept that I commit was committed to for myself for
um so recognizing and then laying that open
laying that open that means with a good Dharma friend someone you trust a mentor teacher uh
let telling them telling them confession so recognizing
laying it open and then making a resolve
that in the future we'll try to do something differently and try to do this differently
ever pointing ourselves toward skillfulness non-harming and not
suffering
so this dhamapata verse I think will be the last thing I'll say and then I'll say
farewell translated by Gill uh verse 53.
just as from a heap of flowers many garlands can be made
so you with your mortal life should do many skillful things
maybe so may we continue this reflective
dharmic life for the benefit of ourselves and
for the benefit of others for the benefit of both for the benefit of the whole world
without exception please take care see you again