hello friends hi hi everyone
if you can hear me okay if the audio is alright give me a thumbs up
audio's good fantastic welcome welcome to happy hour hi
i'm nikki in mountain view california on seated oloney land and
as always starting ipr by warming the space with meta
with saying hello so who would like to help um warm up the space
feel in new hampshire hi neil
leslie and santa cruz delighted to see you for the second time today nikki oh
hi good to see you hi denise in illinois hello
hi hi wendy from folsom california hi wendy
jennifer from las vegas the second time today good to see you hi jennifer
and it's nice to see you also people i see for the second time i kind of felt you in this space for those who don't
know what they're referring about i'm i'm subbing for gail this week um at 7 00 a.m so i'm teaching both at 7
00 a.m and at 6 00 p.m so yay good to see you on different topics of course
and that's through youtube so i don't see for folks i i see their remarks their comments
um on youtube which is sweet bill says hi from dallas hi bill hi elizabeth from
spokane hi amy from oahu aloha anybody else wants to
say hi hi hugh
steve from houston is here hi steve welcome welcome my friend oakland hi friend
terry from moss beach hi carrie was it yes terry hi terry welcome
from burlingame hi um i think i'm hearing the names but not
all of them quite clearly yeah and there is hugh lovely to see you
twice today uh thank you for practicing twice today and hi violet from san francisco
and margarita from el paso barbara from alameda and hello all the
friends for joining us on youtube richard pat
julie and don from dc i think the space is nicely warmed i feel warmed up my
heart is warmed up all these all these greetings friendlinesses shared hellos
expressions of meta uh once twice today so very sweet so let's get started
let's get started oh yes and julie joining us from the uk
the early hours in the uk good you're good sport julie yeah very
early hours so we are definitely international right now with folks joining from lots of different time
zones so so let's formally begin i changed the settings at this time
so uh accidental unmuting will not be enabled
and thank you neil for posting information about the happier google groups if you're new to happier
we have a google groups the information is shared you're welcome to
join and change also the settings uh for the chat uh you can send
the whole host chat if something dramatic happens like if my voice drops out and i'm not
knowing that otherwise let's keep that channel quiet because it can be quite distracting to get chats while i'm
giving a teaching i'll open it up afterwards and
last but not least um oh yes turning on recording for the sake of
audio dharma here we go
okay all right so formally hello
and welcome this moment in time wherever you are dear sangha makes me happy to see you
the few of you i see a little strip on top of
the zoom room so so
for our practice for today i'd like to um
invite us in the practice that's been coming up for me which is the sense of
appreciation and [Music] and [Music] radical i would say radical gratitude
um for for the body for having a body for their
being a body for their for aliveness for having senses even if
this sense of knowing this perceiving in this plane of existence of ours
even if it's challenge if even if it's painful even if it's difficult but
[Music] um yeah um so
so trying to think how much i want to say instead of just leading you into it
just leading you gradually into it and i feel like my heart is um
as being called to not be saying so much but just inviting you into the
the experiential space um guiding you together guiding you
taking you there as well as i'm able to as as a as a guide
[Music] so whatever you need for this practice will be shared with you
whatever arises or does not arise it's not a problem it's not a mistake as long as
you have kindness towards it even if it's a crowd of sorrows just be
kind be be kind to yourself to whatever arises
so so without further ado let's practice
together so
arriving arriving in the seat arriving in this moment
ah i'm opening our senses far and wide as if you're opening your heart
wide to itself
even if their challenge is present
breaking down the barn door
opening the windows trusting trusting
ah seeing that openness sunshine in the
heart space especially the sunshine of meta
of care of kindness is healing
opening your senses as you close your eyes opening your sentences
opening the sensations of the body your sit bones
opening every cell of your body if you can [Music]
the sensations present
the air cool its wand
as if your body your senses holy sense is hearing
feeling touching even perhaps seeing as your eyes are
closed just some colors perhaps or darkness or light
getting out of your head not so much in the space of thought and
thinking and
wondering but in the world of the senses this body
this fathom-long body
all the senses the sensations of the body are not so overwhelming perhaps but soothing
soothing in the way of grounding you even if the sensations themselves say there is
unpleasantness in the back or the neck or somewhere
but the fact that these sensations ground you
tether you here here
here dear heart fear dear mind you're alive we're here you're sensing you're feeling
not so much thinking about him but being immersed
as if it's carnival
can you sense perhaps even just a little bit of the joyousness
the vibrations the aliveness
the body breathing
sensing hearing
as if you're relaxing the body open soft
doesn't take any energy or effort
it's as if you're floating on top of the water you're floating
all these senses caressing you
[Music]
soothing grounding
washing over you opening you up for something different
not the usual thought patterns
whatever you usually fall into no not today
let there's be space for something else who knows what
doesn't matter we don't know it's good that we don't know the unexpected
the delight
sensing feeling grounded in the body
the joy of the senses
radical gratitude
for the bounty this mystery
of all these sensations a touch warm heaviness
lightness tingling coolness warmth
light
hearing
how amazing to have a body to be embodied
awakening happens in this long fathom body
awakening love compassion [Music]
all of it expressed right here so get to know
get to love appreciate the earthy humanness
precious impermanence of having this body
but pleasant unpleasant neutral doesn't matter
let your heart be nourished
by the stream of knowing this right here
what's passing through and we often take for granted
this
here here there's so much here already
don't need thoughts distractions release them
let yourself be immersed this stream that's already here nourishing
can fill your heart with abundance so much here
that may not be here tomorrow appreciate
open up to
your heart fully drenched in this stream
of the body perceptions that are here
grounded joyful celebrating even
joy nourishes the heart
let your heart have a party
with the bounty
sensations vibrations the body your bottom your hands your heart
your face your abdomen bottom of your feet
each breath
pretty awesome lots of all pretty awesome
what's here
even if it's unpleasant as i'm guiding you there's plenty plenty
of unpleasant sensations in my body known as pain
and yet it's delightful wow all these sensations
what a bounty what a joy to be able to feel and sense
foreign
this
do
celebrating the body this vehicle
for our life our awakening or expression in this world
kindness compassion love celebrating this body
even if it's our teacher with pain challenges malfunction disease celebrating
nevertheless not in spite of but because
of all that it offers us
all the goodness all the challenges
wow
and can we offer this body
can we offer this body as a vehicle
for goodness to others through our deeds
actions thoughts speech
this body as a vehicle an offering to the life horse
in service of goodness
in service
our awakening others bringing goodness forth
as much as possible in the world this impermanent vehicle
is fruit of the earth our body offered
our actions our kindness
expressed through thoughts words
physical actions
you might imagine yourself if you like seeing yourself doing what you love
maybe it's work maybe it's caring for others
maybe it's your passion maybe it's arts
maybe it's meditation [Music] body offering
itself wholeheartedly
to the life force
it's not for ours it's not for us to keep or take with us it's impermanent
this body has a function to cherish to appreciate
and to be generous
how else do you express your kindness your care your love
your goodwill other than the axe of this body
in the last minutes of this practice period
is formally take the time to appreciate
thank this body this mystery
of billions of cells
so many different levels and layers of function understanding perception
the cells synapses organs
perceptions thoughts etc all of this appreciating this body
and this awesome mystery for thee for being
your my unique vehicle for sensing feeling knowing
in the world
and for offering acting
yes it ages yes it falls sick
thank you for all that you do including the challenges you give me
may i grow may i appreciate but this body
is my vehicle for awakening
to give my gift to others
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
be embodied feel the glory the gloriousness of
having a body whatever it's shake or form
may our cultivation towards goodness appreciation [Music]
awakening kindness serve all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes for reflections if you wish to offer any
reflections thoughts from this practice if something came up
ah an aha moment as a gift to others
something might have opened up or a challenge
appreciation in chat and private you're welcome thank you don i see your hand please
yeah thank you so much nikki and the um your the statement of offering uh
our body i i thought it was that one through struck a core with me i liked that one and
anyway i thought it was an interesting perspective
thank you thank you don right before you mute yourself the part i missed hearing that the part that you said uh resonated
with you was did you highlight a particular part which or or at one point you said um
to offer a body for you know kindness to others or
yes yes yes that yeah yeah thanks for
highlighting that yeah um it's true it's
this is our vehicle right this is how we speak and act and pick up a phone and
call up a friend who's having challenges and take care of ourselves feed ourselves
all of it yeah thanks don richard
hi hi uh i i just sort of feel like like my
body's there all the time i don't have to work to make it appear you know i mean i don't have to like focus or
i instead i just sort of just fall into it you know i mean partly because i often
um meditate on my back so i have this sense of just falling and
and relaxing into it as opposed to all of the you know look
this look at this part of the body and look at that part of the body and you know that kind of thing
[Music] yeah so would you like me to comment on
that is that what the question is about or is it just a just a statement
yeah so but i would like to comment on that of course because what you're saying is like well that's what i do but
it's so so uh yes richard many of us have
a tendency of what is easy for us we've done that and we keep doing that
but that's that could be limiting that could be limiting so this
meditation was an invitation um and if you are showing up this
morning actually it's 7 am it's an invitation to to not just do the usual have blinders
on okay this is what i always do this is the path i always could be a lovely path not to say it's
not a wonderful path it might have lots of flowers but it's the same path what if you go down
different paths wow different things could open up um maybe there's a different path to
awakening that's actually your body has access to that you have never even imagined just because this is easy and
you always do this and of course so so consider that
no thank you you're welcome thank you for bringing that up barbara
hi hi came up for me today was a
an opportunity well to appreciate a little pain
i had a routine dental appointment this morning and uh so
you know routine teeth cleaning and i said you know since i'm here i gotta say
that i have sort of a ache in the side of my face and it's been there for weeks
could you take a look at it and they look down and they go oh yeah your bite is off let's just polish it here and and
do that there and and so i'm like oh thank you so much it was such a gift
that i had just this little uh
aching that that was informing me nice nice i like that
thanks for watching yeah yeah i appreciate it it's interesting so this appreciation for the pain as a signal
but it's as as a way to oh yeah this is what's going on let's let's you know let's
bring attention here and and also in a way i like to tie it into what i was
bringing today in the practice today which is really shifting opening up to this
possibility of completely shifting the perception about
unpleasant sensation or even pain as being bad i mean not not just finding
value in it in what you're saying but i'm taking it one level beyond that i mean as i was
sharing with you and letting you win as you're sitting here i have pain in my
body and yet there can be gratitude there can be celebration like yes
this i have a body that senses that has it has pain it's it's it's
um how do i say that it's it's just a celebration for everything
in life not it's i mean there's this saying um um
the great way is easy for those who have no preferences so it's the great way
it's like can there be a moment maybe not always but there's no preference yet this is
wow sensation unpleasant sensation wow this is amazing feel the sensations here how amazing to
be human and how these sensations true so i appreciate what you said and i'm using
it as a as an opportunity to add this on top of it thank you thank you thanks barbara it's
lovely so dear ones um
let's turn towards practicing in small groups and let's consider small
groups actually as an opportunity to express kindness
this is you've been expressing appreciation gratitude this wow this sense of wonder as i've been inviting
you to experience for yourself or this body now what if you express the sense of wonder
with two other human beings who are conscious and can speak and
act out of kindness remember your body is a vehicle for kindness can you show
up in the room as a vehicle for kindness this is practice
practice for being out in the world with your family loved ones strangers people you
have difficulty with people who get on your nerves can you be a vehicle for kindness
share kindness in these small groups so the invitation is for you to say just
one nugget whatever you want to share and if that that silence you want to share silence
and hold kindness that's fine the next person will say one nugget the next person will say one nugget and we come
back to you let's go in reverse alphabetical order and just
say something offering kindness not managing the group not
um serving as a facilitator just showing up with your own kindness
here this is what i have my body as a vehicle and let's see what what might arise in
this space opportunity to share kindness
with each other and maybe the prompt i'll add one more thing the prompt is
how do you take joy how do you take joy in your body being a vehicle in the world for
kindness for service
okay so with that
i'm creating the rooms and [Music]
all right be kind to yourselves be kind to each other here we go
the rooms will close in a few seconds and they are closed everybody's back
okay welcome back everyone we have uh a couple of minutes if any reflections
that have come up that you would like to share um
you can also type them in chat if you type them to me in a person they'll be private
sarah hi nikki
so i had a cool image come up during the meditation and when i shared it in group
um people seemed to to really like it as well but this image of
um unwrapping some unwrapping gifts of sensations like having a sensation come
up and like opening it as if it were like this beautifully wrapped present to be able
to fully embrace it and really acknowledge it
more completely a lot of times i'll push things away or kind of half-ass feel them and
this was a good image really supportive to like feel more fully
oh that's so beautiful thanks for sharing that sarah that is lovely this
gift that you're unwrapping this this this same sense of
delight and appreciation and gladness oh this sensation is a gift that is so cool
so i'm gonna ask you wait i think you already muted um where did you go raise
your hand again so i can ask you to add me oh there you are uh so was this for any sensation or particular sensations
like pleasant unpleasant was a particular quality to it so i i was using it a lot of times with
um emotions disguised as sensations that came up
through like my torso and um no it's for it's for anything a
lot of times yeah if some emotion comes up or some feeling and i don't want to feel it i'm
like eh but in this meditation it just presented itself as like okay you can
fully unwrap this you can like let it out let it really take up space
beautiful i am i am so attached this is such a beautiful image to to not just
let it be but also embrace it really accept it as a gift hey you are a gift you're unpleasant
unpleasant vader not pleasant feeling tone dear emotion dear sensation and yet you are a gift let me unwrap you and see
what your potential is here so beautiful thank you for sharing that that's so lovely
thank you makes me happy yay so dear ones
thank you for bringing your bodies to this practice thank you for bringing
your heart your mind your bodies uh to practice aligning your bodies with
your intention may all beings be well may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you all take good care see you tomorrow morning for those of
you who show up at 7