so good morning and um
the um foreign
for the dark little Dharma talks this week is loving kindness is Mehta
and I thought I would offer you a guided meditation on meta that Maybe
brought you in to one way to do it the practice
and it's meant to be a very simple practice it's meant to be um
what I want to offer and it's best not to try too hard
to relax and and to um
and to uh just kind of feel
the tenderness inside so to take a meditation posture
and
gently close your eyes
and perhaps there's a way that you can gentle your insights
gentle yourself into your body
if you're agitated if you have a lot of energy or concerns
no worry perhaps take a moment to feel
your body against whatever surface it's resting on your cushion your chair your bed on the
floor and feel the solidity of that contact
and taking a few long slow deep breaths and as you exhale
see if you can Release Yourself to the pull of gravity
in those places where the body is touching a surface
if you're sitting upright stay upright
but settle firmly into the place where you
are in contact with the surface
so there's a kind of definitiveness to being here
and this place you are recognizing that you are here
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and on the inhale recognize that you're here now at this
time then an inhale only happens in the
present moment
establishing yourself here at this time where this valuable important function
of breathing is occurring
and rather than having the mind there and then
to begin to settle the mind Here and Now
now as you breathe in here as you exhale
in here as you exhale to relax your body
to go through the body and relax the face the shoulders
the chest and the belly
and as you continue to feel any the energy of your mind any agitation
pressure tension
pulling or tightening associated with the mind
and as you exhale perhaps you can relax and soften the
mind maybe imagining it's like a wave
that Smooths out to the
mind becomes a wide flat surface of a peaceful Lake
and the waves of thinking become quieter
and then to search inside yourself
for some place where you feel in inner warmth
or an inner tenderness may be associated with a heart area
a place where things are gentle and peaceful
maybe it's also a place that feels a bit vulnerable
maybe it's a place where you associate with love or compassion kindness
not as an idea but when it's strong for you the place
in your body that it vibrates or is activated
and feeling that place that it might be tender or warm
as you breathe breathe through it
breathe with it
breathing in now with this warm tender place
breathing out through it or with it here and in this place
and if you feel no warmth or tenderness now that's fine
but you might see if you can remember a time in your life well you did feel that
or think about a person or a being it's easy for you to feel
great appreciation or Delight love
and then is there a place in your body that somehow is associated
with how you feel in this way
and perhaps from this tender place or soft warm place
you can appreciate yourself and how it might be possible to have
this warmth love or kindness spread through your body
even though if it doesn't do that just the idea that it could
it's a potential can be inspiring and
inspiring for you to stay close intimate with this place of warmth and
tenderness inside
and maybe you can feel some inner capacity however simple and
slight it might be for kindness
for maybe a gentle kindness or a warm kindness
or a sense of good will
ingness for a few moments to suspend
other attitudes ideas
for these moments
to connect to what's inside that has a quality of Good Will or
kindness breathe with it
and as you exhale imagine that that good will
radiates outwards like a light bulb shining in all directions
and as it shines and radiates it passes
outwards through your whole body
like a light is turned on or
a wonderful warmth is turned on
and spreads through your body
and perhaps as you exhale imagine that this radiance spreads out
from you out into the world
almost as if your breathing begins in the place of warmth or kindness
expands as you breathe in in spreads outwards
as you exhale
allowing the thinking mind to become quieter and stellar
so you can better feel and sense and imagine
your good will your kindness encompassing more and more of the world
radiating outwards in all directions radiating spreading
being transmitted out
on the gentle waves of exhale
you might think of having a small half smile
turning up the corners of your mouth just a teeny bit
and if there's any slight Delight or joy that comes with
doing that or slight pleasure
maybe let that Mingle with your kindness your good will
your meta that radiates out from you in all
directions
imagining that you are you're warmth your kindness as it spreads
brings a sense of peace and warmth and love
to every being touches
like the morning sun that when it shines
begins to warm up the creatures that feel its rays
and if it helps the thinking mind be quieter and if it helps you to stay more in this
meditation on the exhale you can very gently softly
say a word like love or meta
or kindness
with a word being kind of a pointer or fuel
for the sense of Good Will that radiates from you
from the tenderness Within
as you breathe in to open and expand the place of warmth
Within
and as you exhale to let that open warmth
bread and radiate outwards through your body into the world
an abundance of Love spilling out in all directions
breathing in and breathing out
radiating whatever sense of
care appreciation
you have for this world of beings for others
putting aside for now any other more complicated relationships
to people just for the Simplicity of now
your own good will your own love is so precious so valuable
give yourself a chance to feel it and be with it breathe with it
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
take a few moments to reflect
on how this meditation has been for you
and how it might suggest or Inspire or
a way to enter the world with greater
kindness Greater Love or good will
and how as you get up and go about your day
how you might enact in small ways and big ways
greater expressions and have kindness and good will
care meta
for the people around you for the world around you
not just leaving it to chance that you'll be a kind person today
but to think about small or big ways that you might actually do this today
and then to wish that this be so
and may we live in such a way
that we contribute to the welfare and happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe and healthy may all beings everywhere be free
foreign [Music]
teachings of the Buddha there's a record of a conversation of someone
coming to the Buddha and with a great enthusiasm for mindfulness
and said that um when people practice mindfulness then
everything goes better for them everything is works out well for people who are mindful
and the Buddha said actually it's a little different
it's when people have mindfulness and loving kindness that everything goes
well that everything is is good in a certain way
and so it's remarkable that the Buddha to emphasize so much mindfulness really brought in loving kindness as a
companion as a partner to a mindfulness and it's a experience of many uh
certainly I've heard this from teachers fellow teachers and my own experience that
as mindfulness gets stronger or as loving kindness gets stronger they
kind of merge that's uh with the well-developed mindfulness
loving kindness seems to come along with it and with very strong developed
loving-kindness mindfulness comes along with it and maybe with mind throwing mindfulness
it kind of opens up and releases all the places were held back closed and so the
natural tenderness can be there that from which care and good will and love can radiate
and as as loving kindness gets stronger and stronger when more and more in the
present moment uh we're not thinking about other things it's so compelling to be here and now
when uh Meto is strong that mindfulness comes along with that
so the two can be seen as partners um and some people find they don't need to
practice loving-kindness in order to have it grow with loving kindness
but there's also prac the practice of loving-kindness and some people will intentionally do practice do meditations
and loving-kindness um or even go and met a Retreats or the whole Retreats where the primary thing
they're cultivating is this loving kindness or meta this warmth
and um it is um uh quite something
to have the primary activity focus of the Mind be
love be kindness and that just like you
would maybe if you're focusing on the breathing and you can get really concentrated and feel you're right there
with every breath and it feels so delightful to kind of be finally in the present moment and the mind is not
scattered and distracted and just really present so in the same way one can do that with
this with the practice of loving kindness and rather than
the primary characteristics of the mind is preoccupation or Neurosis or anger or
resentment or hurry or fear or
wanting to get things and get things done and I mean all the kind of things
that often can preoccupy a person that's go through the daily life rather than the mind being preoccupied
that way the mind is occupied with loving kindness with metha as the
primary focus the primary characteristic of what we think what we feel what we
experience in the body and what we're motivated by and kind of a gathering together just this this unification this
Oneness with just loving kindness and it's a phenomenal thing to have it
become strong and the predominant kind of way of being is one then that's
saturated filled with this kind of Good Will and love and um
you know I I so it's just a great thing and
and um it's a way of experiencing a deep peace
for some people the practice of and kindness is phenomenally healing that um as they get strong and begins to
kind of uh be a medicine almost for the places inside that are wounded or hurt
or afraid or closed and it's warmth hence it kind of kind of settle things
and relax things and open things for us the Buddha gave this kind of
visualization he said imagine there that there is an easily accessed
pond with clear delightful refreshing cool water if a tired parched and thirsty hot
person scorched and exhausted by the hot weather came across the pond the water would be
used to quench both the person's thirst and the hot weather fever
it is the same for a person who becomes a practitioner and after learning the
Buddha's teachings cultivates loving kindness
for this person gains inner peace and because of this inner peace cultivates
what is appropriate for the path of liberation
so here the loving kindness can provide this cool reflection guide we
um kind of sense of peace to a person you know it's maybe a little bit uh point out that you know in the that
guided meditation I just did I emphasized warmth and here in this example the Buddha gave
he talks about coolness and this might represent the difference between
two different cultures that English was kind of
evolved in a cold England where warmth it was really the
nice thing in India being a very hot country at times that coolness is really
valued there so either way and uh so this practice of loving
kindness can meditation and loving kindness can be developed and the idea that one would have a designated time to
really develop or grow or expand or I like to use the word release the care
The Good Will that's within us you know and that person would spend time doing that is a great gift to the
world to really let this precious resource something the Buddha called a wealth
inner wealth that loving-kindness or love or Good Will and let that actually
become strong not to leave it to an accident not to leave it to just oh it'll just
appear when it does and and uh and um you know here some days
and other days is not here but to actually take time to cultivate develop
it make it strong make it easily accessible easily called upon in a way
that's sincere and it's authentic and um so
um here's one description of a state of meditation
that a very strong state of meditation so it's what maybe what's possible
um and hopefully it's inspiring to know this is a human possibility to have the
feeling of this meta be this strong as is this description describes so the first half of it is describe someone
getting um um kind of for this this situation
preparing oneself to have very strong loving-kindness and meditation
Delight is born when one sees oneself purified and freed
of greed ill will anger Revenge contempt
bossiness Envy deceit and wrong View
so isn't that kind of great the light is born when one sees and once that one is
purified and freed from greed ill will anger Revenge contempt and so forth
when delighted Joy is born when joyful the body becomes tranquil
someone whose body is tranquil feels happy for someone whose body is tranquil the
Mind becomes concentrated now with this concentrated mind
this is a description of very strong state of loving-kindness
one abides pervading the east with a mind accompanied with
loving-kindness and likewise the South the west and the North
above below and all around everywhere and all over when pervades the whole
world with a mind accompanied with loving-kindness extensive expanded Limitless
free from hatred and ill will even if it was just a mind that was free
of hatred and ill will ill will it be pretty good and wonderful since those are so painful and
for this world of ours but to actually cultivate the sense the
radiance the the the the fullness of loving-kindness that it feels like it
radiates and spreads from us in all directions um the east south west north and all
around everywhere kind of filling us filling the field of our awareness
filling what seems like the whole world with it it's that strong it's not pervasive it's like a wonder you know we
say sometimes if someone has whose anger has a cloud hanging over them you kind of feel this Radiance of of maybe anger
or hostility from them it's possible to feel a Radiance of love
and kindness in oneself it kind of radiates and spreads outward it's phenomenal that we have this capacity to
get so centered and so focused and so absorbed into these beautiful beautiful
States and uh some people say no it can't be true or
it's too artificial or it's too sweet or you can't be safe in those States
um well it's we're talking about meditation state so
um we're talking about a meditation State and so what we do when we come out of
meditation is it may be different um but it's said that loving-kindness is
one of the ways to create tremendous safety for ourselves to be kind and friendly in this world
um and uh some people will feel that practicing
this way is kind of selfish or self-absorbed or just doing something for everyone's own pleasure
um but I would say that it's the opposite that we benefit certainly from it but it really allows us to go into
the world to benefit the world to be better citizens helpful people do not
cause harm in the world to actually care about other people in a profound way
and um and this is what I hope we can have is a world where we care about each
other and live together and with Good Will and kindness and support
um
so um
so the practice of loving kindness and um and what I offer you today is sometimes called a practice of radiating
loving kindness that's very different from the more classic way of practicing a loving-kindness which is to use
phrases and to progressively kind of do it for different categories with oneself
a benefactor a neutral person an enemy and to spread it out from there
and um both are great practices but some people find it simpler and less
complicated so you just do the radiance and and this seems to be how the Buddha taught it because the Buddha gave no
instructions for this uh you know the different categories and using words to
cultivate loving kindness so um [Music]
someone asked for a citation I read a few different things but one of them is from the middle length discourses
discourse number 40. so um I hope that you will give some
reflection today and about loving kindness and and Care Goodwill and maybe
you can even have conversations with people about what their experience is with Goodwill and how they evoke it and
how they practice it how they spread it what the value they see in it and experiment a little bit and see if you
can go about the day with a experimenting with practicing a bit more
Goodwill than you would have been if you hadn't uh heard this suggestion
so thank you very much and uh wonderful to be here with you and and we'll finish
this series on meta tomorrow with the topic of meta and liberation
thank you