and as psychologists would tell us that
in that taking it personally we
we're endeavoring to [Music]
live we're endeavoring to [Music]
have the life we're living um
become to flourish
you know so uh
and and so we there is a way in which each moment of
contact with experience stimulates something uh
quite deep in us and especially when we're practicing mindfulness when
we're opening to it as it is so this notion
of
wisdom it is what it is and compassion
we have a deep deep impulse to take it personally
and and to find within some expression of our being
so now i'll give some guidance around meditation
and if you could keep those that notion of wisdom and compassion
the practice of mindfulness is to be aware to let each moment be what it is
and for us with our human and psychological
impulses that can have a great variety of expression
and as we start to sit if we can just sort of let that
proposition sink in
in this 30 minutes or so this 25 minutes now
we will um evoke
the narrative of our life we will evoke
the psychological significance and associated thoughts and memories and
emotions that arise for us
in the moment and it is what it is
and it's a deeply personal experience
it can that evoke within us a kind of steady deliberateness
as you start to come into awareness of your being
noticing your state of mind
it is what it is
and it's also this ongoing expression
of relating psychologically to being
with its psychological significance and its emotional
expression
and in seated meditation you know whether you're sitting cross-legged
or sitting in a chair or even if you're standing
there's a the long-standing tradition
of bringing awareness to the body so that as our experience unfolds
it it's like we are embodying it
and as you bring awareness to the body
inviting the body to find a stability
the classic way is that we
notice where we're making contact with the earth
whether we're sitting in the cushion and sitting in a chair
however we're entering the moment of awareness
and if you can notice that contact
in any way sort of press died very gently
it makes sense to press down with the sit bones usually that's
in the center of where we're making contact
and then defined an brightness
anatomically that can be described as
so the pelvis settles down makes contact
finds its stability and then the torso rises up
from the pelvis from the
hips
and as it rises up
the chest opens the shoulders wide
not in a strenuous way just like releasing
any way in which your body is contracting
in each time we sit we go through
process of discovery what's going on in my body
in this sin
how is it embodying
this at this moment
letting the chest open
letting the muscles of the face relax
as we bring these guiding
ways of paying attention acknowledging that
we're not trying to dictate just trying to open up
awareness in the body and your body will react respond
in whatever way it does it is what it is
and then to become aware of the breath
and noticing what happens when you bring attention to the breath
what's noticed
this might have an agenda
there's the morning happy judging
we can and usually do take anything
and everything personal
so weird that's what it is
can you offer yourself this moment
a deep acceptance of what you are
sometimes it can be helpful
to open with the inhale to receive
whatever is happening in the moment
thought physical sensation the memory
and emotion just breathe it in
and let it be embodied
and with the exhale
release so be it
return let go
nature of life is changed
can you awareness have a compassion
can tenderly hold what's arising
in consciousness
can there be a deliberateness in acceptance
of just now just as it is
however it is
however it's being related to
uh
[Music]
each time we meditate each time we practice mindfulness
we're opening to a
greater being
i think we all know especially if you've read something on buddhism
the term dukkha which is generally translated as
suffering but this this too
the this is do and cup
means consciousness and the do
means constricted contracted
and then there's another term that you may know
it's the same consciousness but the su means
expanded or opening opening consciousness
and then the same way the dukkha is usually translated as suffering
the sukkah is usually translated as pleasant experience
so so this way in sitting
where we're inviting a deliberateness
a steadiness we're inviting an acceptance
we're inviting sukkah
we're we're inviting dukkha to soften
and we do it in the context
of subjective because experience
each moment that arises for us is an extraordinary product of the complexity of being
there's all sorts of influences and habit energies
that bring forth more
there's so many ways to dissect it neurologically psychologically
somatically
and in the throes of all of that we're taking it personally
whether it's inwardly arisen or it's the product to
of external eggs influences
what someone said to us what someone did
it can be made with this essence of mindfulness
which is inviting expansion which is inviting acceptance
which is inviting liberation
and then we carry the glimpses the tastes
of that liberation of percussion and into our life
so maybe today you can think about
that process especially as you're in the midst of your
activities your interactions
sometimes it's very helpful to ask ourselves okay
how is that being held in the body are my shoulders tightening
is my chest constricting is my mind constricted
and becoming agitated
and there's a way in which the emotionality of it all can be like an energy
when we open to emotion we open to emotion
we open to [Music] an intriguing way
in which our body and consciousness respond
to the significance of psychological being in that moment
in the midst of that motion in the midst of that activity
can there be a kind of stability that arises from
acceptance and acceptance is the blend
of the wisdom and compassion so be it
this is what it is and
we take it personally and there's can that
evoke a tenderness
because often in taking it personally we're imbuing it
with something of our own anxieties and desires
and struggles you know it's not like we will dukkah for
ourselves it arises out of our being as we are attempting to live
as we're attempting to make our life flourish
it's evoking you know it's asking for compassion
it's asking for a deep appreciation of the human condition our own
and everyone else's
can we bring that opening to greater being to our day
can can you hold it on a feeling level can you hold it on a physical somatic
level can you hold it as an attitude
like when someone says something aggressive or disturbing for you
can you remind yourself with the kind of compassionate patients
oh they're going through something so be it
so thank you please
enjoy your day and hopefully find the moments of sukkah
thank you