well good evening everyone welcome
last week diana asked me if i would give a talk this evening since both
she and gil are teaching a a week-long retreat at irc
and it's been several years since i've given a talk so
a little rusty so hopefully you'll um
so hopefully you'll bear with me
uh i thought tonight i would talk a little bit about
what brought me to practice what what brought me to
imc and also what keeps me practicing what supports the continual practice
so i'll start with a little bit of history i came to imc in
january of 1998 when we were meeting in palo alto
and the reason i came was because i
there was an inescapable unsatisfactoriness in my life
i had good friends i had a good job good health
and yet there was something that just seemed uh off
you know i couldn't put my finger on it um i couldn't quite get any of the usual
remedies for dissatisfaction or unhappiness
that are offered by our culture to really work as well as i'd like it to
and so a friend of mine had told me about spirit rock a meditation center up in marin county
and i looked at their website and one of their links was to this place in palo
alto insight meditation center which was only about
10 minutes from where i lived so i went there
and on the very first night gill was just finishing
the last of a four-week series on the fornible truths
and in i'll summarize those rather briefly
he was talking about how there's this thing called dukkha
sometimes you're translated as suffering or stress
or dissatisfaction one teacher
translates it as a bummer-ness the bummer-ness of a life
so it can come in all sorts of forms and intensities but basically this
this dissatisfaction which i was feeling
and the teaching around that calling it a noble truth was
that rather than trying to push it aside or coveter it over or replace it with
something else the instruction was to really pay
attention to it that there was some value something important
about investigating this unsatisfactoriness this
this dukkha as he called it so it was both the first noble truth was
both both a description but also an encouragement
for action to really recognize it when it was operating
it required some action on my part on the part of a meditator
the second noble truth was that there's a cause for this
and the cause is clinging trying to hold on
if it's a pleasant experience trying to hold on to the pleasantness hold on to
something or if it's unpleasant experience trying
to hold on to the absence of this experience
and of course the problem with that is that the things that one often tries to cling to are
uncling-able if that's a word that they're you you that there are things that you just
can't cling cling to because they're going to change
they come about by conditions and they disappear when
conditions change and so it's not that we can make
our experience just the way we want it but it's how we're relating to this
this experience this this taking this attitude that we're going to try to hold on
for dear life to something that can't be held onto
and the action associated with that is to release the clinging somehow to
release the third noble truth has to do with
experiencing the ending of dukkha the ending of suffering
and that's something to be realized and this might not even be
like a once and you're done experience it might be that the clinging ends
and the suffering ends for a second
for a minute for an hour however long undoubtedly you'll start clinging again
but you know just having that recognizing that experience of
at least temporarily being free of the dukkha
is something to be experienced
and then finally the fourth noble truth was that there's a path
to be developed so that this this recognition this release and this
experience of freedom can come more often
and when i heard that talk i knew
this is the place for me to be you know gil was talking about exactly what i was
experiencing and offering a certain i'll say a certain hope
that through practice through actions of my my own
i could lead a life with less dissatisfaction or maybe more
satisfaction more happiness
and that was just transformational for me to hear that talk
um and so i found him inspiring
now at that point i didn't know i had heard about this mindfulness meditation but i had
really never learned how to do it or what it was that first night i had
i had over the previous uh six or seven years i had learned transcendental meditation so
i did that the first night and then fortunately the the very next monday
there was an introduction introductory course to mindfulness meditation
45 minute course and it was taught by this woman margaret
and she explained to us about paying attention to the the
the very simple experiences that of life you know of the breath of
bodily sensations of of emotions of thoughts
and the thing that struck me was just her presence
she had she was kind she was thoughtful
there's a serenity about her and i remember after the end of the
first class that i took with her thinking that if she's the product of this
practice this is what i want to be doing i want the qualities that she's
expressing and even though i had taken the course the
next month i took it again just to have more of that same experience of
of being in her presence
um so uh the inspiration from gil and the uh
the clarity and the the uh
cognitive experience of hearing his his dharma talk and the following week having this
experience of the presence that margaret displayed
really let me know that i was on i was where i wanted to be or at least
starting a path starting a practice
and in the coming months about half the time gil would have a guest speaker
often people from spirit rock or from san francisco zen center
some various monastics and some people that came from i don't know
where but they were all inspiring
and one of the things that i also liked about imc in that in those first
weeks and months that i was there was that
people are just left you alone it was fine to just come in
sit listen to the talk and then
just walk out into the night you know luxuriating in what i had just heard you
know just reflecting on it thinking about it feeling what it felt like to
have heard these teachings that i had never heard before
and i didn't have to stop and chit chat i didn't have to put on a social persona
or explain explain why i was there and i
didn't have to explain myself i could just i could just come and go and people left me alone
and i really valued that for uh
a number of months i i don't know exactly how long
and i really saw it as a solitary practice like this is something that i'm
doing for me it's my happiness
my tranquility my peace of mind
and in some ways that's true i mean nobody nobody can meditate for you
nobody can listen to talks for you nobody can have the insights that come
from this practice you can't job it out it's it requires
your own inspiration motivation determination
uh you know you've you've there there's some part of it
that really takes your commitment and your time and your
energy to do the practice
over time i don't know maybe that within four to eight months roughly although
it's it's it's a little hard for me to remember back then
i noticed that i wanted to talk to people about the practice i wanted to talk to someone
and i found that my non-practicing friends although they would be patient with me they'd listen
they just couldn't figure out what i was talking about or why
you know why would you pay attention to dissatisfaction why would you pay attention to suffering it just didn't
didn't make sense to them and i was
knew enough that i i couldn't really put this in words that that maybe made
sense for example like when i talked about doing
meta loving-kindness practice where you wish well
for someone even though they they're not wishing
well back for you you know this sort of unilateral well-wishing for other
people um you know wasn't the usual transactional
well-wishing that people were used to you know they said well if they if the person doesn't wish
you well back i mean how long is that going to last you're going to give up pretty quickly so that was just one example of the kind of
thing that i was learning about that just didn't connect
and so about the time that i was wanting to talk to other people
a couple of people that were also monday night regulars started coming up to me and saying well
how'd you like to have coffee you know like how about if we meet for a meal before the monday nights sit
and let's let's talk about this and so i formed a few uh informal
uh friendships that way and you know started to have a few discussions
and i also thought well if i want to talk about this
what i really need to do is talk with a master
the maestro like gil so i went to him and you know i i think i asked him if he would meet with me
once a week to have a discussion and you know he was like well he you
know he wouldn't do that but uh i could schedule interviews with him and so for a time i
met with him about once a month um
and those were useful for me uh although i did find that
maybe not consciously or not subconsciously i really wanted
i wanted to look good in his eyes i wanted to be a good buddhist
and at some point he related to me this story that when he was
a young zen practitioner at san francisco zen center that one of his teachers
told him that much of what he was going to learn about
buddhism he was going to learn from his peers and when he told me that i
sort of thought that it was a polite brush off i didn't you know thought he
was like yeah you know talk to some of these other people
but i took him at his word and i found that that actually was true that i that
there was a way that um having these discussions
about the things that i didn't understand i'm not sure that i believed or
had experienced with other people really helped the practice that it that
it wasn't just about learning facts or learning
from somebody that had already experienced things but it was the talking to other people about it
um a questioning that really
helped clarify things for me
and so the next year i did a a 10-day retreat with gil and two of his friends
john and mary and on that retreat i learned several
things those teachers started to say
more than once that we don't do this practice for ourselves alone
now i kind of thought that i was doing this for myself alone you know i didn't
it was fine with me if other people benefited from it but i didn't that wasn't my motivation to uh
to support other people or to to to benefit them in some way
but on that retreat i noticed what support i was getting from the other
yogis we weren't talking to each other but just the fact that other people were
showing up and sitting you know session after session
was inspiring and helped me keep sitting even though it was a
you know periods of of of pain you know to to just sit for 45
minutes at a time one person in particular who was um
inspiring to me was there was a woman that was sitting there retreat who was i think
eight months pregnant now from what i understand
at that point in pregnancy you're probably uncomfortable all the time
the body's just and yet she was just sitting there so
still with a serene look on her face and i just thought wow
that is that was inspiring to me you know and that she was doing it not
only for herself but i imagined doing it also for this soon-to-be-born
uh child and so there was a way in which my heart
opened um by being around
the other practitioners
and after that retreat i i found myself
making friends with some of the other yogi's on that retreat andrea fellow was
on that retreat jen lemus and
some other other people who are now teachers
and so i did start to get that sense of oh yeah maybe maybe there is something that
is going on beyond this particular body this particular heart and mind
and then less than a year later that the following spring i did a 14-day retreat with gil
and because so many people had cancelled it turned out it was just gill and 12
yogis at this little zendo uh
jikoji up on skyline and
there was such an intimacy to it it rained the first 12 of the 14 days
it was cold we just had a couple little uh wood
stoves to keep us warm in which you know one person this guy peter would just
like every between every sitting he'd put more wood in the fire he kept us warm he
took care of us the water system broke so we had no running water we had to
bathe in the pond and carry water from the creek for other dishwashing and
the local fire department brought in drinking water for us each day but there was something up
about about that particular retreat that made
me feel so close to these other people i mean these other 11 people well 12
including gil
yeah that it it's a retreat i'll never forget i mean it was it was on the antithesis of some of
these uh golden palace type retreat centers where it's you know it's warm and it's
comfortable and every you know the lights go on and off on their own this was really just
pretty primitive but um
but because there were so few people gill would give us interviews every single day
and at the end of that retreat i was invited
by a couple that was on it to join what they call the kaliana mita group
sometimes it's translated as spiritual friends or beautiful friends
people that wanted to talk about the dharma and about their experiences
and create a sense of community
and so i didn't know what this what this was but since they invited me
i thought well at least go a couple of times and see see what's what's up with it
um and
you know we would always start we'd always sit together for 45 minutes we'd have a meal together so there was that
sense of community from sharing a meal and then we did this thing called a
listening circle where we'd set a timer
and each person had something like about maybe four to six
minutes to say whatever it was they wanted to say
and everyone else just listened there was no
questions or comments or advice or
clarifications one person just said whatever it was
that wanted to be said including nothing at all and everyone
else just was as present as they could be just listened
um and at first you know i would sort of
plan well what am i going to say and what's you know what i need to i need to get this i need to
rehearse what i'm going to say but over time i came to trust
that what wanted to be heard from me would emerge i didn't need to plan it i didn't need
to you know somehow have some agenda
that as we trusted each other and the and the listening
deepened uh that i learned to trust myself i learned to trust that what wanted to be
seen would emerge
i also learned that four or five minutes can go by pretty fast
and so that it was important to really
in some ways get to the point you know to
to not waste time on things that weren't so important but really kind of
you know what what's really going on you know some deep honesty
and so that was very helpful for me you know particularly talking about
um what was working for me in practice and
also what wasn't what you know where where was i stuck
that group lasted about uh two years roughly
and then the couple moved away and then i was invited into another
group and that group i still meet with we've been meeting now
for about 20 years
and then over time there were some neighborhood groups that i was in
there's one that i'm in right now in mountain view
each group has a somewhat different structure way of doing things
but the commonality is that willingness to listen to each other
and trust that
we can talk about what what's going on in
practice for us
one of the things i like to say is it's a great pro it's a great place to talk about how you fail as a buddhist
you know there's a lot of times when you you know you you like to think of yourself as this
swell well-practiced buddhist person um
and there's a value in that but there's also value in seeing you know talking about what
you know kind of what um what things aren't working what you know
what it what have you done that you regretted
um and that's for me that's really been a way to grow
in a way that i don't think i could do just on my own if i was just sitting at
home meditating and listening to talks and reading books
um for a while it was in a group that was
supporting somebody that was dying somebody that had cancer and we thought it was only going to last a few weeks
and he ended up lasting a couple years
i started another group thinking about peers since i'm a
senior age male i started a group of other senior age males
and so we could talk about uh
you know what it's like to have a body that's breaking down you know that's
that's starting to starting to fail and and how what do we still aspire to what keeps us
practicing how to how to become
uh
not resigned to but in accord with our mortality
so those those are some of the things that came out of that group
i was also in the social group called the dharma friends where we would go and see movies or go
for hikes there's a book group
that's started back in the 90s that's still meeting here once a month
so i'm telling you all of this because uh my belief
is that that it's there's a real value
in connecting with others in this practice there's a saying that i've heard
over a number of times about how one of the buddha's disciples
had one time told somebody that noble friends and noble
conversations are half of the holy life
and the buddha corrected him and he said no it's not half of the holy life it's it's all of the holy life
so our the way we
respond to support or in community with others
is integral to this process of becoming free
i don't really know if it's possible to become free on your own
um so i'd like to encourage people
to start well so first of all i want to say i know the value of solitude and and
that was really important to me being able to practice without being
um involved in a social interaction that was
unwelcome and i'd also like to encourage people
that feel like they're at a point where they want to be able to connect with other people
to look for ways to connect i know it's been difficult over the last
couple years with the pandemic you know at one point we used to have like
60 or 80 people in this room on a monday night you know now we've got a handful
um but there are
there are um virtual ways of meeting uh sunday mornings
there's a a zoom after the sunday talk people are starting to meet out in the
parking lot outside of imc on on monday sunday mornings
uh there's a lot of small group discussion that goes on through the
um what is it oh the the happy hour groups monday through friday
there's the way of meeting people through either day long
classes or there are some even like eight to 12 month classes that are being
offered now by imc and other places
just this afternoon i was in the dharma mentor training program where we we meet once a month
and split split off into small groups to talk
i think gil and diana are offering some courses on
ethics as enlightenment and to others that that they rotate through so
i can't give you an exhaustive list of how you might make the kind of
connections to support practice through
dialogue but if you i'm sure if you start looking around
you'll you'll find ways so
so i appreciate your tuning in tonight to this talk
and i'll be available for questions or comments
for the next couple minutes either from those of you who are here at imc in person or
um nancy will monitor the chat on youtube
if you want to offer a question that way so
thank you
jim um this is nancy um
can you say more about the groups that you are part of um are those ones the
neighborhood groups that you can sign up through the website or did you
create a group on your own uh yeah that's a that's a good question this was i think the first group was
maybe 10 or 15 years ago and about every three years imc would
put out a call for if people were interested in joining a group
that they could send in their
contact information and their zip code and they would be matched with other
people and usually those groups started out with a kind of a fixed
agenda you know readings and things like that and then might over time
uh deepen um i don't know whether they're doing
that right now but if you're interested i'm sure that if you send an email to the
main imc email site
that they could let you know what's available some of the groups the first group that
i was in lasted for maybe four years and then disbanded
another one that was an existing group that had was already
ongoing invited me to join them and that that one i imagine going for
some time so i think if you contact imc they could
let you know what uh what groups are available
i know that there are links on imc website for
individual practice discussion with a teacher and then group practice discussions
and i believe that you need to email to get hooked up with a neighborhood
sangha that meets regularly i think that's right
um and the sati center also is
teaching a number of classes that gil and a number of other teachers
have small groups great thank you thank you nancy
yeah oh well not one other um
program that imc has is this eightfold path program it's
i think the eightfold path is a nine month series and
that has small group interactions every month for each of the
elements and if you want you can sign up to get a mentor so you can
have somebody to talk to once a month that can
offer encouragement and sound you out that way so that
the current cycle i think is just coming to an end right now but it usually starts again in the fall maybe
september
jim one other thing is that there is a new
beginner meditation program that's starting in august
that we'll be meeting in person at imc okay
it's supposed to be on the calendar already okay so that what you said that was in august
yeah so there's also an introductory meditation course in-person course that's starting in august so that's
another way to make connection
do you see anything on the
thank you very much i appreciate what you had to share uh definitely
identify with that dissatisfaction and bummer-ness so
[Music] i guess i'm in the right place too
yeah it's about it's about finding your own path and i'm
trying to figure out how to how to do that so all of these suggestions are of
lots of different things different ways to start down a path is is
a little overwhelming but also very helpful so thank you on that and then
um i hear a lot of from people that
practice about you know letting go
and i imagine that's letting go of the suffering or
i i don't know what that means when people say oh you know it's all the first step is letting it letting go okay
let i i get the concept of clinging but if i'm
already just kind of softening yeah then what what does it
mean to let go yeah well that's an excellent question i mean
you know i'd start with just saying that that's like what does it mean to let go um
i'm trying to remember there was one of the one of the monastics said that um
something like 80 percent of the time they're sitting in meditation [Music]
knowing they need to let go and can't so i don't think that it's strictly
something that the ego or the intellect can do i think it's
to a certain extent it's seeing the suffering
and seeing what is it that what is it that we're just not
um you know if you can see the connection between what you're clinging to and the
suffering then the clinging may
dissolve on its own but you i don't i i believe you can't make
it happen and you can't definitely make it happen on your time schedule you know it's it's kind of it's kind of
like sitting with it until so don't just knock three times and turn around yeah
okay yeah so thank you
okay okay well it's um one minute to nine so
thank you all for your attention and
if this has been helpful then
stay with it and if it's not helpful just let it go
thank you