so hello everyone welcome to our meditation time together
and one of the supports for meditation is
our meditation posture and there's many dimensions many
elements to the value of the meditation posture but one of them uh the simple one that
i'd like to offer today is familiarity
that to more or less take the same posture meditation after meditation
when you sit down to meditate and take that posture
the associations with meditation the channels of meditation the habits the
the orientation towards meditation can kind of begin to click in
like your body knows what to do and uh so it becomes it doesn't have to be so
much of a mental effort to meditate because the body participates it kind of
takes the posture and and our awareness kind of enters our body and
there's places of maybe some comfort from the familiarity oh this is
my meditation place this isn't how i am and and then that familiarity that physical
sense of familiarity can make it easier to
be oriented towards the present moment here and now in this body
and and that we need help sometimes because of how strong the
occurrence of thinking is that maybe takes us away from
the present moment so
to assume your meditation posture
and sometimes if you do it slowly and
kind of carefully that supports this movement towards
familiarity and entering into entering into the present moment through your posture
sometimes i've seen that the longer someone meditates the more time
they take to get into their posture kind of moving back and forth
kind of adjusting their knees maybe twisting a little bit maybe
moving their heads just all kinds of kind of getting everything kind of lined up and
and coordinated cooperate cooperating
with being present here and now
and lowering your gaze
perhaps if it's comfortable closing your eyes
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths
and those deep breaths can also be part of this entering the posture or
returning to your posture to your body that's here and now
a deep breath and on the exhale a long exhale in which
you relax the shoulders the belly
a kind of letting go that they somehow in the center of your being
and letting go into the pull of gravity
letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
around the eyes the jaws cheeks
if it helps the mouth be a little bit more relaxed let the teeth fall away from each other
slightly so the lips are very lightly touching
perhaps relaxing your scalp or even just imagining the scalp as a
relaxing
relaxing the shoulders on the exhale
taking time to feel the release or softening of the shoulders
and perhaps how it settles you more into your torso
softening the belly soft belly as you breathe
and then turning your attention to the breathing itself now
centering yourself in the body breathing
maybe imagining that the sensations are breathing
like a river ever flowing river wherever
repeating wave is washing up on the shore
and for you to settle back and watch how all the aspects are
breathing the details of breathing come and go
the inhale comes begins
and ends it disappears the exhale begins
and ends
if there is a pause between the exhale and inhale
that pause kind of begins and ends
and within the inhale there are particular sensations
that are the manifestation
of inhaling
and rather than hanging on to each sensation see them as a
river flowing through
whereas a constantly changing wave washing up on a sandy shore
with all the little the foam and the little
waves and
and all the detailed sensations of inhale they come and they go they appear and
they disappear don't hold on to anything
but see if you can settle back and just allow those sensations to wash through
you wash through awareness
and the exhale as well all the sensations of exhale settle back
relax let them flow through you
as they appear and they disappear and for this meditation you're more
centering yourself on the flow of coming and going
appearing and disappearing
your mind wanders off in thought let go of your thinking
and let go into the flow of breathing
the sensations of your body as you breathe
almost like you're receiving it like the sand receives the
waves or you're floating on it like you're floating on the river flowing
and then gently expanding your awareness that as you experience breathing in
the flow of sensations you begin to be aware of the flowing
sensations of the body
being aware of the coming and going vibration
tingling glowing
way in which sensations come and go in the body as well
and so the flow of sensations and breathing is centered
in a larger field of flow and
comings and goings
the best you can centering yourself in the flow and
vibrant moving changing sensations of breathing and
body
any place maybe where there's a hardness or things are coagulated or
bunched up
as you exhale see if that can be relaxed or softened
opened or expanded so that everything
is somehow participating or joining
the dynamic way in which sensations
come and go and appear and disappear the vibrancy
tingling flowing glowing
if you are thinking a lot relax the contracted mind
relax the thinking muscle
so the mind too can somehow float on the
flow of change throughout the body
maybe even becoming a flow of change
and if what is hard and closed is in the heart
perhaps for a little bit you can open your heart relax
so the heart also floats supported let's float supported by the
flow of sensations it's okay to open the heart
to allow it to be to float to be held
by all the flow in the body
to have the awareness centered on all that's changing in the
body all the sensations coming and going
is said to be healing
because it begins to dissolve the places of contraction and holding
resistance the more things flow
the more health moves through us
and it is liberating the more we can
relax into the changing nature of life the less we're holding on
clinging resisting
and over time we can become the change
become the dynamic process of flow
of our explanatory experience
and as we come to the end of the sitting
with with time we'll discover that opening to the
changing dynamic nature of the body is moving towards wellness moving
towards healthiness to wholesomeness
to freedom and may it be that what we learn
but wellness and freedom
that we carry that with us into the world
and perhaps sharing just by the nature of who we are and how we are sharing that wellness
that freedom with others
may the ways that we develop and grow in this practice
may it be for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be well
may all beings be healthy
may all beings discover the wholesome body the
wholesomeness embodied within
may all beings discover freedom as it flows through our veins
flows through our muscles and bones
may we live harmoniously in this changing world
knowing how to float and open
to the rhythms of change the comings and goings of things
may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so we're talking about the refrain of the satipatana sutum
and the first line which we covered somewhat maybe never complete
is a line that goes in this way
one abides observing that the body
internally the body in terms of the body internally
what observes the body in regards to the body externally
that's the first line the second line is when abides observing
the arising dhamma what observes arising uh observing
the ceasing of dhamma what observes the arising and ceasing of
dhamma and the word dhamma here dharma usually in english
is um it's not a hundred percent sure exactly what this means uh
beaker body translates it as nature that isn't quality and nature of something
so observing the nature of arising in the body
observing the nature of ceasing in the body observing the nature of arising and
ceasing in the body that's because the emphasis here
is not that what the sensation is in and of itself but rather that the
process by which all sensations in the body have a have a way in which they appear
and disappear and as that's tuning into the flow the changing nature the appearing
and disappearing arising and passing um is uh is is uh what this practice opens up to
when we're able to be centered and stable in the present moment when
we're able to kind of settle back to abide and observe
without the mind jumping into thoughts jumping into concepts and ideas and reactions it's just there very quietly
to observe what's happening the um
so it's another meaningless word dhamma is just experience
uh it's the particular experiences that come so whatever experience that arises in
the body we see it as a rising whatever experiences pass we see it as
passing whatever experiences both see arise and pass
in the body we're observed that what this the third one means arising and
passing is that some things last very short time
they just uh almost as soon as they arise they're already passing away like you know a sound
of a bell you know it's it's there suddenly it appears but then you're aware of it
fading away and um and sometimes that happens quite quickly some sounds like if i snuff my
fingers it both kind of arises appears and disappears almost at the same time
and so as the mind gets more and more still and quiet this magic begins uh appearing and that
is that all the things that we thought were a solid uh turns out their solidity
is partly a function of perceiving it conceptually perceiving it
through an idea maybe subconsciously that way
or seems solid because we're kind of holding on to it or we're contracted around it but as we get deeper and deeper more
relaxed and settled and be able to tune in to the to the momentary processes we see that
even something which is remains in the remaining it's coming and going
arising and passing it's um so like for example there might be
you know you might have a constant rustling of the leaves in the in the tree in the wind and just kind of say
it's oh just rustling all the time it's just constant but in fact the rustling if you really
tune into it is a lot of small little rustle sensations of leaves that are coming and going and coming and going
and but the aggregate we take to be you know more of a continuous kind of solid
thing so the same thing with the body the aggregate of pain in my knee can seem
like solid pain but if we can settle enough and quiet enough and just open to the
and receive the the sensations of the pain often what happens is that
we drop below the aggregate level and to the to the more uh particular sensations
that make up the total and we see that those are sparking and passing away
there's a dance of sensations all the time even in something that felt like it was solid
and the stance of sensations and comings and goings begins as we keep practicing becomes
more and more the orientation of what we are aware of this can happen uh naturally by itself
it's not like we have to go looking for it in fact to look for it this kind of way of being too soon is uh leads to kind of
certain kind of imbalance and uh even
meditation imbalance meditation or challenge meditation it's better just let it
appear as we get more and more settled into the practice more more here and relaxing to
the place where we can just abide and observe in a very relaxed way
but what can help and support this is to know that this is valuable
sometimes when people learn mindfulness practice they're supposed to always know something you know you know really go in
there and know that's that's pain that's tightening that's clenching that's warm that's coolness that's
and um and so it's kind of like focusing on the kind of i don't know if that concept is the right word here to say
but on the thing but at some point what we're interested in is not the thing
but to have a deeper intimacy that allows us to see to perceive to sense to feel
that whatever thing that's there whatever dhamma is um
is arising and passing how it's sparking out and so the the word anicha a n i c c a
often translated as impermanence literally means in constant in constancy
because some things are when we use the word impermanent england english some people
think it means it it's not going to last sooner or later
but the individual pieces of sound are in constant they come and go
and our breathing is you know as long as we're alive our breathing is constant
uh you know it doesn't you know you know it's not impermanent you know in a final way until we die
but the um it's impermanent or inconstant in that it it uh
it's it's uh not co in breath is not constantly there the in-breath is inconstant because it
uh it yields to the exhale the exhale is not constant because it
yields the inhale and so but they appear there's they're in
constantly uh continuously there they're in constantly
continuously reappearing and so a lot of what we see in the body
is a better uh described not as impermanent but as in constancy we see the
inconsistencies flow the change moving and um
so this uh if if at that time at that time when we're able just rest in that experience abide
and observe abide and just sense where the observing is akin to
receptive awareness so if the idea of seeing the observing with is
not quite the right metaphor for you there might be some other like feeling
it's the receptive feeling receptive perceiving is closer to what it is than
than actively looking as a deep as we deepen into this kind of world of inconstancy
it's not even receptive anymore because that replies lit implies a little bit of a separation from the experience or
duality or being a little bit active like i'm i'm the one receiving
it's just things appearing and disappearing without us receiving it or
actively going to it it's just flowing in this field of awareness
and um so there's a whole bunch of degrees by
which this happens sometimes we just feel uh hints of it or small degrees sometimes it's very all pervasive
and um the but whatever degree it is uh it does represent a movement towards
a kind of healthiness in the body because um the contracted and tight and
solid solid feeling of the body is normal as it is not like necessarily a problem in ordinary life
maybe even needed an ordinary life but um it also can be the place where
we get physiologically congested or things get tense or tight or restricted
and and the blood circulation nerve circulation i
don't know exactly all the energies that exist in the body don't flow as smoothly and as we kind of open up to this kind
of flowing nature vibrant nature it can feel like like the health is flowing
through our body even if someone is sick maybe with incurable
disease to have access to this level of meditation it just feels like that this
feels healthy and whether it actually heals disease that's a whole other issue but
it certainly feels good to have this deep relaxation and opening and probably is good for the immune system and things
but more important for in buddhism it's a stepping stone where it says opening
it's a it's a a it it's a
way of being that begins showing us the potential for freedom in a deep way
and um and that'll be the topic for tomorrow so um
abiding observing uh the body and its nature and it's a
rising nature in the arising experiences
abiding observing the body in its seizing experiences abiding observing the body in the rising
and ceasing of all these experiences um
so um thank you and um
i look forward to being here with you tomorrow