hello from redwood city imc and
wishing you all well for this day
i want to begin with um teeny teaching
if i ask you to evoke an image of a river
you might think of a river that you've seen in your life and it would have a particular maybe it
would be very unique each one of us would have a very you know
your own image
if i write the word
river r-i-v-e-r on a piece of paper
that word will maybe reside in that paper as long as the paper exists
if i take watercolors and go out to a river
and paint the letters watercolor color on the
surface of the river that
word will not persist very long
even if the water is almost completely still and placid and flat and hard
hardly you can't see any movement in the river at all because it's so still and you write the words
river on it paint it it's not going to stay maybe not even long enough to see the
word so when we
come up with a word river in our mind the image you had of your river that
asked you to do the beginning maybe went away for a few moments as i thought about talked about riding on top of
river but the weak
the idea of river comes into consciousness maybe because i'm talking about it
maybe because you see a river talking about a river it comes into consciousness we pull it out of our
memory or the particular ways the brain stores the idea of a river someplace
but the conscious awareness of river is there as fleetingly in consciousness
as it is on a running str uh running river
almost as much as much it's there the concept of river is there but it'll change and influx and
disappear as other things appear into consciousness and it doesn't reside in consciousness
very long unless we're obsessed by the idea river
and we can't stop thinking about river then the idea
maybe persists and it might seem like we're always thinking about river but even then
it's probably not all the time you might be making sentences about a river
like oh my river is the best river and the word river
just there is part of the stream in the moment the river the concept of rivers there
in the background there might be some other kind of feeling or sense that their
memory of this is what i'm talking about but the concept the idea the word for
river is fleeting and simple so this analogy is important to
understand the buddha's teachings on sanya
usually translated as perception but it it refers to
the simplest conceptual recognition of
anything at all so river door
person whatever it might be there is usually it's one word that conceptually kind of recognizes or
identifies this is what the object of attention is the object of seeing or hearing or something
and um and and uh in the practice of vipassana
as the practice settles down uh we're beginning to appreciate the fleetingness
of the concepts that we live our life by the fleeting is not in terms of how they stay in memory or stay kind of
persist as something that we can tap into but but the actual
coming into full consciousness there's just a moment of recognition a door
river person and that that that is there just for fleeting it's
like the river of consciousness it appears for a moment on it and then consciousness keeps flowing and it
dissolves it might return might return frequently so we think it's continuous
but it comes and goes this is important because many one of
the areas of clinging and of suffering is we cling to our concepts we cling to
ideas even the idea of suffering is uh is a something we can cling to hold on
to and we can cling to clinging the idea of
clinging oh it's important to cling as practice deepens we become aware of
the uh the fluidity the changeable nature the dissolving nature of concepts
as they appear in the mind they have some reality to them
so for example if i feel an itch the itch might persist for a few seconds
but the concept itch is that very fleeting it flows in and flows out it flows in and there's a
question should i scratch and there's a question is what should i do about it or
then i'm looking at something else and then i come back to it but the concept
is and so in this particular foundation of mindfulness what we're looking at today
is the fleeting nature of simple concepts as they appear
not as as they are relevant they might be relevant continuously but as they appear in the mind
so breathing in the concept of an inhale the concept itself is a fleeting moment
that maybe is repeated the exhale the body
posture attention itself so as we get into this meditation perhaps
this can become a little bit relevant so
assuming a meditation posture
and sitting in a way taking a posture that expresses both alertness
and relaxation and each of those words is a concept
taking a posture alertness relaxation
all these concepts flow through as we speak and we hear
then we respond to
and though saying of each word the existence of the word being spoken
is brief the word dissolves in the river of time
gently closing your eyes
and settling in feeling your whole body sitting here
and taking a deep breath in
and relaxing on the exhale
and breathing normally on the exhale continue to relax in the
body settling in to this body
then settling into your breathing
and as you breathe there are ever so simple concepts that
appear that recognizing recognizes what's happening as we're breathing
those concepts might be verbal with a thought
they might be quieter and seemingly without words but still a recognition
that the inhale is an inhale exhale and exhale
for the recognition of beginning to inhale ending the exhale
movement pressure release
mindfulness builds on the simple recognition of what's happening
as it's happening
in any kind any thought mental idea concept
of breathing as useful as it might be
is fleeting it appears and it disappears
and if you're involved in thinking you're probably involved in a different
river being swept away and thinking about things that are not here
and now
if you're in commentary about here now you're probably removed from your
experience
to enter into the direct experience
and very relaxedly openly know the experience experience the experience
is to practice mindfulness
and to know the fleeting nature of the individual
concepts as they appear in the mind
is a means to begin to relax the grip we have on our thoughts and ideas
leaving them alone
even distracted thoughts are made up of individual concepts that are fleeting
that appear and disappear what happens if you tune into the
fleeting nature of concepts ideas thoughts
each word and a thought disappears almost as soon as it's spoken
and as we come to the end of the sitting
if we can appreciate the fleeting nature of individual concepts and ideas
then we can appreciate the concepts which are useful
but at the same time not let them be a barrier for
perceiving and seeing what's here in particular
when we're not stuck in ideas of how people are
we can maybe take in and register or see and feel and
sense people in a deeper way in a fresh way
freedom from being stuck in concepts
allows for more clear seeing of others
clear feeling of them with our hearts
we don't then come with our preconceived ideas
when we meet other people well we might come with preconceived ideas but we don't linger in them we see
them pass
we can see with fresh eyes it may it be that our ability to see
feed others freshly with fresh eyes fresh heart fresh mind
lets us be a clean channel
for care and goodwill for basic friendship and friendliness
maybe this practice clears the channels of communication
of perception of connection
so we see people kind of anew and fresh and fully
in their humanity in a way that maybe we respect and
revere others just for being human and being alive
and in this clear clean channel of connection
may it carry out into the world or are well wishing
for the world may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
and may we live in a way that contributes to that possibility for others
may we be an agent for peace
and happiness
[Music]
i'll be back in a moment
so yeah so the recorder that we have we can i can turn it on and off up here once
but once i turned it off i in order to be able to turn on again i have to go
over to the recording station we have and push button there
so hopefully that will be fixed soon
so
we're in the fourth foundation of mindfulness looking at the mindfulness of the five
usually called five aggregates of clinging or the five
groups of clinging the five divisions of how we take our whole experience as human
beings and and and cling
and so the buddha divides clinging when we cling to almost anything we're actually clinging to these five areas
and it's not quite uh just you know who we are but it also has to do with anything at
all they can kind of fit into this these categories
the refrain of the satiputana sutta that we talked about many weeks ago which is the direction in which the
mindfulness practice is going comes to a place where we see the
the inconstant nature of our experience the flow of experience the appearing and
disappearing of experience and in this repetition of emphasis over and
over again the rising and passive experience is uh an alternative to being stuck
alternative to being caught up in some thought or idea or concept or feeling or anything
it's an alternative to clinging and so you know if you're in a if the river
is flowing and you want to stop the river you grab it or you put up your hand to block it
it doesn't work the river just keeps flowing but the stress of trying to hold the river back
remains in our hands as we start to block it but if we can appreciate that what the river does is it flows
then we might allow ourselves to be carried if it's a nice river safe river be to be floated along in the
current of the river and we can go far and we can make it to the eventually maybe to the great
peaceful ocean and um and so the same thing with uh our
experiences is much more fluid and and uh and changeable and
and uh then our concepts
uh tell us concepts ideas when we cling to them hold on to them or we are obsessed by
them we it gives a kind of sense of continuity a kind of constancy to what we think is there what we think is
going on so that we can we think we can cling it works to cling
but we see that these concepts these ideas are part of the river of change
then we can learn to float on them which means we don't reject the concepts but we see their fluid
in constant nature they're they're so in this uh
uh the five aggregates the five heaps five groups groupings
is um there is um the third one is sannya
s-a-n-n-a and it's um usually translated into english as
perception but i don't know i don't think that's a appropriate translation
i think perception seems to imply too much
non-conceptual perception seeing hearing tasting
that we we perceive at these different scent stores the word sanya has a meaning of to mark
something to to label it and
and so it's the simple concept we have of things there there are things that we uh we
might see that we don't have any concept for we might not even have a word for him we say it's something
just something and some of these concepts are very fluid and changeable
a i have here this wonderful bowl through the bell
and we call it a bell but um if i didn't have any uh bowls to eat my breakfast with this
will make a perfect uh bowl rather than amusing it as a bell and becomes a bone because my breakfast bowl
and or my soup bowl or something or it might be that i don't need the
bell anymore but i have a lot of pens and it becomes a pen holder and they
stick in there or it becomes some other holder that what this uh what this object is
is changeable and uh it can be a flower pot and
depend and we could label it by its function often and so
the concept we have so some things is functional and the function can change and so the
label changes and this points to the idea that the concepts are fluid and changeable and
they're not absolute they are um relative and provisional and
situational and the same thing with our ideas of
safety the ideas of well-being and happiness and suffering
there these ideas as they appear as ideas as concepts are simple concepts
that then we get caught in and we get involved in associations and complicated
stories and ideas about them to be mindful of sanya of these
simple conceptual concepts i prefer to translate sanya's concepts
these simple concepts gives us the vantage point
to be wise about how we get swept away in the more complicated ideas we have
and so as practice deepens um we start seeing that all the concepts
we have in as concepts as ideas as the as the
recognizing function of the mind is there very very briefly
and then it appears again and again so um
like even if i if i say make up the sentence i am speaking words
then those words each of those is a concept i
am speaking words uh just like we can speed read and we it
all kind of blurs together into one large concept or one you know we understand the meaning overall
but if we step back and see or feel or recognize that each
individuality of each of those words before we string them together and make it into a larger meaning
i am speaking words and they can't go around in ordinary
life paying attention to this kind of detail of concepts all the time
it's just not efficient it's efficient to kind of string words together in a sentence and just get the meaning right away
but as meditation quiets and we can still learn and in meditation
then there are times when we see the exquisite uh exquisite uh
appearance of a concept like uh sometimes at the end of meditation
when i open my eyes before i have a concept there's a seeing but
there isn't quite the recognition there's a shape a color there's something
kind of briefly and then i can feel or see or recognize that my mind
then makes makes a concept not that like right now i'm looking at my laptop a
laptop and um the um
and uh and that little gap between what i would call perception just kind of taking in this the data the sense
data the site objects without the concept and then
recognizing the overlay of the concept on top of it so i might see a bell like this
and i just you know as i pointed out this doesn't have to be a bell it can be a bowl it could be a pen holder it could
be all kinds of things flower pot and it's so because all those things are not
inherent in the object it's possible to see the object without
the label and then see the label arise
and in the mind the thought arise bell and it can be exquisite to see that
rather than just having it on automatic pilot and see the brilliance of the mind that
makes these concepts and see it arise without any clinging or holding on or grasping or any kind of extra baggage
just a bell bull and um and so in deep meditation and
quiet still meditation then this is where the exquisiteness gets more and more special
where so many we're down at the kind of a primary primal kind of level of experience
and we kind of see the arising the beginning of this complicated worlds we live in
but we're not seduced by the complicated world we're able to kind of see it as
just the arising of a concept that gives birth to other concepts and ideas and we can just stay there watching it
appear and dissolve and come and go and it can be a little bit like as
delightful as sitting on the riverbank watching the river go by maybe spending many long periods of time
just watching the flow of the current little waves the flow
and it's just something very relaxing and nice to see that so the same thing is possible to see that current
the river of concepts as they appear and in mindfulness practice we're using
little bit this these concepts to help us stay present
and that's you the the idea of a mental label where we add a little didn't we we
repeat the concept maybe the original concept is almost subconscious
as it appears or but then we use a mental note to recognize
river for looking at the river in as we're breathing in out towards a breathing out
warmth if we feel warm restless if you feel restless
and it's a way of kind of using that little bit more emphatic note it's a little bit more
uh intentional note it's a way of staying in the flow of the present moment being right there being
right there being right there with it letting it just flow and move through as it does
so um and as we do so
we begin letting go of clinging and as we let go of clinging in a deeper and deeper way then at some point this flow
of experience doesn't get limited by the particular groupings of the five
aggregates but rather it becomes because that itself is a concept each of these
five aggregates are concepts that the mind has produced which is what the buddha says
and that the those concepts begin to dissolve because there are secondary concepts there are more abstract concepts
and they dissolve and then at some point the awareness doesn't become so selective
one aspect of our experience but it becomes more panoramic where awareness just here and present in
a panoramic way and and we just in the flow of experience
without grouping them into these five groups
so you might today as you go about your day
maybe [Music] see if you can notice
the arising of concepts and the provisional nature of them they
the fluid nature of them and what would sometimes say the empty nature of them there
and um and uh or notice the opposite notice how they
seems the concepts are so solid and real and important and it has to be this way
um what we add to it that to this simplicity of just these
like simple concepts that appear in the mind so thank you very much
and continue tomorrow