so in the world of in here in the United States of spiritual care the field of
spiritual care pastoral care or chaplaincy care
there was a theologian named Henry nowin
who uh was kind of foundational for establishing kind of a general
field of or the ethos understanding of spiritual
care in hospitals and Chapman sea and things like that and he had a very there's a very famous
quote they're teaching from him which I don't remember exactly how it is but
um it goes something like this that to offer spiritual care
uh is to create an empty space
in which to welcome the stranger this works particularly well like in
chaplaincy where you're meeting people you don't know chaplain is meeting some people they don't know but um but they create the empty space
in which to welcome the stranger and um
and so what is this empty space that's that we create and I think it's easier to point out
what we the opposite that we create we fill the space with our opinions with our assertiveness where even sometimes
there's no space where people if we talk too much to take care of them if we're taking the initiative and
working on them and we fill the space with our judgments we fill the space with our conceit like
I'm special I'm going to be the spiritual caregiver or I'm this and that or sometimes it's negative definitions
of ourselves we have and so kind of the kind of people can feel that we're so you know the emotions
and the and the ideas that were kind of living under that there's no space
for the other and in offering spiritual care that's the purpose it's to kind of kind of
clear the air so people can breathe so people can be themselves so people can feel like it's
okay to be themselves and they're not being judged or put into a box or and so to recognize that this
person is welcomed here as they are completely as they are and that's so important for this kind of spiritual
care because that's the foundation that kind of acceptance is the foundation to
let someone Blossom let someone find themselves let someone grow and develop and
kind of become even more who they actually are in some way so we could but we also can do this to
ourselves we can create an empty space in which to welcome ourselves
a kind space in which they welcome ourselves and what do we do that gets in the way
of that one of the ways is that we live we Define ourselves in a lot of ways and
that the way that which we kind of fill the space with definitions of ourselves
is one of the things that meditation can help clear out and there are other ways that humans can
find ways to clear out the space for themselves clear out all the definitions that we're operating under
I mean sometimes you know here here locally someone might go down to the to
a to the coast and walk along the shore or the sand it's just big open expanse sometimes and that can be a place where
so much Falls away and is forgotten away from society and there's a kind of space there just be and not be defined
sometimes somehow the magnitude the magnificence of the Great Pacific Ocean and the sky and the size of it and
again just kind of give a very different perspective of who we are where the where whereas from an urban environment
it's so easy to be to Define by you know our job our relationships our
traffic patterns are you know all kinds of things but sometimes in the night sky
and looking at a clear you know dark sky where the all the stars are shining and kind of a very different
kind of feeling for who we are that maybe creates a kind of empty space where we're not defined
and um and so meditation can be one of those places where and it's actually an
important uh function or or opportunity of meditation is to discover how to be
present how to breathe to be attentive with a kind of empty space for ourselves
without definition this is represented a little bit I think
or very powerfully by how the Buddha referred to himself we call him the Buddha we'll keep saying
Buddha Buddha Buddha it wasn't called Buddha as often in the
ancient to his time when he was alive as much as we're calling him that these days
as we kind of settled on this is his name but it's really a Epitaph it's it's not really a given name
means the awakened one and he there were people who called him that he seldom called himself that many
people called him by his given name gotama and um
but uh how he referred to himself when he was he used this very enigmatic
phrase that was maybe not original to him it might have been already a title for
Spiritual teachers in his time and the word in poly is tatagata
and tatagata is made up of this word Tata which
is a very simple uh word that means like this
or thus or so and the Gata part is lots of people have
written about what this word Gata is but we find it that I've used repeatedly as
a suffix that just means something like the one the the thing so the thing that is the
one that is so the one who is like this and imagine if someone you go to someone
and you say like what are you and who are you and they say oh
I'm like this you get what you see kind of I'm like this maybe maybe they don't even say
anything to you they just open their arms and just like here right yeah you know they don't Define themselves
it could be a little bit irritating
but um uh there's also something very profound about that where uh where the kind of the way this
the self way of seeing and holding oneself is in this empty space where
everything's allowed to be there is welcomed but there's a idea let's not
Define it in any one particular way any one particular way of definition
Narrows the field doesn't allow for the fullness of what a
person is it doesn't allow for the fullness of what a person can grow into in the next minute in the next moment
and so to not be defined the Buddha did Define himself at times
and he recognized that it's appropriate to Define it's a little bit ringing is it ringing a little bit maybe it's a
little bit too loud let's see is that the better now you're always welcome to say something if the
sound is not good so um the
um so the Buddha did you know say there's a time and place to Define
people and and he wanted to Define people by
what they do so if you're farmering farming then
you're a farmer he said if you're a selling Goods you're a merchant if
you're a ruler if you're ruling people then you're a ruler if you're a thief he
says if you steal if you steal then you're a thief
but uh it's a very clearly this is provisional these are just conventions
these are just ways of referring to People by what they're doing that just helps us
organize our life in efficient way I mean imagine if you go to a hospital say you have a big illness maybe big
surgery is needed brain surgery you know and you really wanted to be care about it but that particular day
you go to the hospital they decided you know defining everyone in the hospital by what they do it's just that's old hat
and it limits everyone too much we're today in the hospital everybody who works where works there is not going to
have any definition no one's me recognized as a surgeon or as a janitor
or as an administrative person we're just there working and so then you know we need someone to
come and do surgery everyone shows up
you know the whole Hospital thing works so much more efficiently if people kind of are
known by their function and what they've been trained to do but when they leave the hospital and
they take off their maybe their uniform and like you know then
they don't have to be defined that way anymore some people want to continue to be
defined that way outside of their work they're holding on to it their status their power their their
all kinds of things come with certain roles and so people will hold on what is
it you better Define me this way let me tell you who I am outside of the context of what they're
doing and uh like for me um you know I spent a lot of time
teaching but there was a time where it was a beginning teacher I would go home to my
wife and she said to me Gil you're using that voice again
[Laughter]
so you know I you know that's the place I can't be a teacher right at home so there's places where you better drop it
you know put it aside and um and so um
and so this ability to be defined while we're doing something
and drop it when we're not doing it the ability to be defined functionally
in the right place by what we're doing in certain situations but to also have the ability to create
for ourselves in an empty space where of course you're allowed to be who you are
but maybe there is no R maybe there is no thing that you are in terms of fixed
static thing in Buddhism the idea is that uh it's uh
um who we are is what we're becoming it's always dynamic
it's always changing we're constant in a constant state of becoming and renewing
and developing and growing and transforming and changing Buddhism has this very Dynamic view of
what a human being is and so because of that the idea of a
fixed definition limits the open space in which we can
grow into the next moment the next moment the next moment
so we come to meditation and part of what's possible in meditation is to let
go of all the definitions let go of all the judgments let go of it
all sometimes it's for some people it might be easier to do for the external
definitions in meditation maybe that you know the profession we have for example
or the place we have in a family it was kind of eye-opening for me when I
was in my 20s and I was talking to a zen teacher about my relationship to my father
and the zen teacher said to me you know your father
there was a time when your father was not a father it was just a person and chances are
once you grow you know once you've kind of really left home I was I had already left home but I guess I hadn't
um uh you know you know he has a life outside of being a father you know and and I said really
it's like oh I just thought that's who he was he's the father and suddenly he
became much more multi-dimensional and I and I kind of created space for my father to be something Beyond just a
father so it might be some meditation is a place where the external definitions how
we are in society maybe can drop away some maybe a little bit easier sometimes than
how we do it for ourselves on the inside how we've internalized these things and uh not a few people will Define
themselves by their shortcomings will Define themselves by their by
negative judgments I'm to this some to that you know for me when I was young in my
20s I was def I kind of I had a wonderful amazing capacity to
feel guilty and uh I was just guilty if I breathed
somehow just like no matter what that was you know before I did something I was guilty
before I even knew I was going to do something I was guilty and um because
and I and it was only when I started doing my meditation practice my zen practice I saw how pervasive it was the
first time I saw it was I was walking across the meditation hall floor
and I felt guilty in the way I was walking and I said what what's going on here
and so we might think we're somehow inadequate or we're not worthy we've
sometimes done I feel that way because we've internalized judgments from society and we did our society societies do
terrible things to each other judging each other by their race and their gender and their sexual
orientation and there's class status and all kinds of things that we do size and
age and and then sometimes people internalize it and so they go around feeling that
somehow you know they're not unlimited they're not filled with huge unlimited
potential to become something in a inner way but rather they're held limited by
these judgments these ideas these Concepts that were caught in and so the amazing thing that's possible
in meditation is to not just calm down meditations often associated with
becoming calm but the calmness is just the kind of the tip of the iceberg of what can happen as
the mind gets still there and quieter and one of the things that can happen is that
um the activity of the Mind to judge the activity of the mind to
Define takes a break takes a vacation
and we come to a time when we feel ourselves we experience ourselves without any definition
so that like the Buddha at those moments if someone said who are you what are you
it would be a sincere answer to just go like to lift your arms out
you know wide and spread them wide and just like to hear it you know just in the gesture imply just this
or maybe you say who you know someone says who are you what are you I'm this
no definition beyond that and they have to just kind of somehow deal with that
or take that in or but that seems sincere anything else seems like it
maybe limits it or narrows it or and um and uh
so to come to a place where this sincere answer is this this is who I am
sincere place is we've created an empty space in which to welcome ourselves
empty space to allow whatever we're kind of meant to be or whatever
the conditions come together to move through us and wants to grow and develop and express itself
that we we kind of begin creating space when seeing that and discovering it
one of the advantages of doing this at the empty space this non-definition
is we can see much more clearly when we begin defining ourselves
we can see more clearly when we begin acting and you know becoming something
and if in fact what you're becoming is the hateful one
you'll be the one who hates the hater you can see that
clearly and in that clarity where you haven't been judging yourself
you haven't been criticizing yourself or feeling guilty you continue to not criticize yourself
you continue not feeling guilty but you recognize for example the hate
that arises and you recognize this is not good this is not useful
this limits me this really limits me in fact the Buddha said that very clearly
he said create hate and delusion are limiters
they'd limit people they kind of you know and um
and so we can feel the cost of having hate in a way that we can't if we're living an active stressed racing
around life and we don't even you know just feels like like
hate can just feel like just I don't know it's an automatic pilot
and people don't realize that they were hating until after they're arrested for
road rage because they were so beside themselves and what they've caught up in
this ability to come into some modicum of an empty space where we can Welcome
All Of Who We Are can help us be much more responsible for
what we are and what arises within us without judgment without criticism and we can learn to recognize when
what's coming through us is healthy and not a problem and when it has uh
motivated by unhealthy things like uh greed and lust or conceit or hate
this is a hugely powerful insight to have and to see that and then to work with
that and practice with it then maybe return to the empty space because the empty space that welcomes a
stranger is a kind space is a place of kindness a place that
allows for the heart's care to be there it's a Caring Place remember the Henry now and as quote was
a quote for people who are caregivers spiritual
caregivers that's a space they're creating for their care so to have that care
for ourselves have us care for others to just by have a discovering how not to
how to breathe be alive be attentive without definition
maybe in a way that can be a bit like okay
very very clean glass have you ever gone up to a glass door
and tried to walk through it without realizing it was a glass I've done that
it's just so clear so clean and clear I don't see it but you know if the glasses they're fine like we have here for the
birds the decal on the door that defines us a door for the birds so they know but you know or the dirt the window is
dirty or or or you know tinted or whatever it defines but what's really clear
then you know it kind of has no definition so the mind can become like a clear
window or even better an open window
so um so to sit meditate
and to see what our mind is doing without judgment
to see what our mind is doing dedicated to create an open welcoming
space for all of it can allow
the warm open space can allow that tension to unwind it can allow the the
stress that's behind so much of our everyday Behavior to settle and quiet
and the stress behind defining ourselves the stress behind being caught in self-definitions and self-judgments has
a chance to relax and relax and relax and so you can follow the path
of that relaxation follow the path to less and less
being defined by anything until you find that the absence of
definition provides a freedom and a capacity
to welcome everyone in a friendly space
so those are my thoughts today so do you have any thoughts
did anybody have any comments or questions if you could use the mic the Camille's going to give you to you
hi thank you um yeah yeah thank you um just what you're
talking about is what I'm really working with right now and I'm really realizing how much I hate
and I think a lot of it comes from obviously projection of self-hatred but
also I'm just using like um like trusting my own
um inner guidance as far as where my hate goes like
sometimes I mean I I knew someone who was a Buddhist teacher who hit her dog things like that and I had so much hate
I I just anyone who hurts an animal I just it just fills me with a rage
and um so I don't even really know where I'm going with this but I guess I have a lot
of confusion sometimes about like what to accept what to reject and my own inner guidance but knowing
that I also just don't have it all figured out so I feel like things are really tight at the same time but also
really spacious and I don't know I just it feels really groundless right now and it's it's scary yeah well I certainly
appreciate the clarity in which you can talk about this hate that you have at rage I mean that's quite phenomenal to
have that kind of clarity and to be able to have the the willingness to say it publicly like this
I take this to be really healthy what you just did so I think I think you're on a I think
you're in a good path and the fact that you're kind of feeling groundless at
this particular juncture probably there's no way around that do you think it is a groundless time to kind of come
to terms with it to deal with the see it so clearly and the fact that you can hold both both some kind of more
spacious wave and to struggle with this hate and rage I
think you're in probably in good hands with yourself and I think the probably just go continue because the the hate that
you're feeling the rage you're feeling it probably needs uh that that friendly
welcoming space it's probably something actually it's probably a symptom of something deeper
yeah yeah and so don't feed the hate but make room for it befriend it so it
has space and time and because it might begin to settle enough that you can feel what the what's
actually underneath it and uh and I don't want to limit you what it might be yeah but just to give
you a hint thank you [Laughter] that I think a high percentage of people
who have hate and rage somewhere underneath it there's a deep sense of hurt
and So eventually it's the hurt that really needs your attention and care and
to be sidetracked too much by believing the hate or acting on the hate is actually disservice to what really needs
the needs the attention thank you
hello can you hear me yes thank you um
thank you for what you shared today your teaching resonated for me
not only in what I'm working on right now but in relation to a kind of tangential idea which might be relatable
for others which is one of the things I discover when I'm meditating in that
when I'm in the open space when all has fallen away and I'm in the Stillness is
that that is where there's space Not only to let go of defining but to let go of self-judgment to work with my thought
life to be able to notice that I am believing my thoughts and to then choose
to not only allow starting with the allowance and then for me there's prayer involved as well
so in connecting to to source and opening and in that I'm creating
space and I'm deeply grateful that you put some words to what happens there
very nice thank you and very nice and they're just to add something to what you said is that as you're doing what
you're doing making that space seeing your thoughts and what you believe it's probably a process of continuing
ability to open more space New Dimensions of more space and then you see more and more deeply what some of
the thought patterns are and which ones are healthy and which are not foreign
yes thank you Gail for today's talk so
continuing on some of the points that have been raised I just wanted to ask if you mentioned we need to create an open
space where we don't have judgments but often we come with judgments and you
know it's tight and restricted so is the path of going from the Titan restricted
space to open non-judging is it basically acknowledging what's coming
and giving space for what's coming and is that the path by which it happens or does it happen through developing you
know a meditation practice it's a great great question and so
hopefully my my response will address it one of the really important
abilities we have as human beings that maybe is underappreciated
is the capacity to have the veto over what we do to say I'm not going to say that I'm not
going to do that we don't necessarily have a control over what the mind
kicks up the thoughts their motivations what we feel like we want to say what we
want to do that is maybe outside of our control to always and that's why it's good not to
be able to judge ourselves for what comes because it's not necessarily in our control what comes
but we do have and that's what we want to have as a minimum in Buddhist practice we want to have the ability to
have the veto power and so okay I'm not going to say that
and I'm not going to act on that and so learning to be restrained to be at peace
to be at ease in not doing is a phenomenal capacity
it doesn't sound very exciting to be restrained right I mean we come to IMC and learn how to be restrained
I mean no one's going to come it just feels like you know that's too
restrained that's too limited that's too something but it's actually the opposite that as we learn not to act on
the unhealthy motivations unhealthy harmful things that we mind is capable of doing
or not or if we're unsure whether it's healthy or harmful to maybe hold back
we actually then get closer to that place of being undefined being unlimited at being free we're actually exercising
our freedom in doing the veto power does that address your concern yes thank
you so what you're saying is keep doing the vetoing until you go from a constricted space into an open space in
the mind and eventually develops all the time like not just during meditation yeah especially if you're in social work
you know there are times of course where you want to kind of give free reign to
what's going on in the mind and sometimes meditation is that place when I used to go to the gym I worked in
exercise machines that was a time I gave free reign to my mind and I would sometimes close my eyes doing some of
the exercises and just let let complete freedom to let mine do whatever it wanted to do or if I go for a walk up in
the hills here um and uh there have been times when I've been really angry and I go for a
while I'm not going to do anything to anyone I'm not going to say anything or do anything but I'm going to go walk fast up in the hills
and let that just kind of course through me so I'm not restrict not I'm not suppressing anything
I'm not repressing anything it's very important to see it clearly but what the veto power is over is
causing harm with it thank you again
thank you good morning and thank you for thanks very much for the talk Gail
um so I've become become aware that sometimes kind of building on what you were you were just saying um that I can either have a response to
someone that seems unkind or even an immature reaction
so it just strikes me that it's almost like I have a bunch of three-year-olds and seven-year-olds
within me yes and I've kind of got to say no no kids we're not going to do that right yeah yeah but sometimes it
comes out and you do it but sometimes we believe much of the times sometimes you need to call on the inner adult yes
exactly exactly or or the inner grandparents if you have good references
for that and so we have we have all these capacities we can't necessarily control
of whether this inner kids are doing you know having a party but uh but you know you do have the veto
power about what's what what spills out and hopefully by nurturing them over
time you can help them maybe grow up a little bit yes I think very much so very
very much so yes is there a mic over there
where's the other mic oh you have it there okay hi good morning
um um I think going back to you know having that veto power is a way to have
inner love for yourself but then also external love for those that you're talking to having that
respect and so I'm glad you brought that up because I think that's very important it's something that I think a lot of
people miss these days because they just care about I have an opinion I have an opinion I
have an opinion but it's not more of you know well maybe what I'm saying is going to be hurtful to that particular person
yeah and I'm glad you brought up the space about not making not only making space for a
stranger but making space for yourself because I think a lot of us just forget that uh who we were
and kind of comparing that to who we've become and I think that's something that
gets lost in some sort of translation as we're growing older and older and older
um we forget that you know hey um I'm so busy with my external life that I forget that I need to you know
take a step back and go who was it before and what am I missing and I think that's
something that a lot of people can you know take advantage of
um by the way off topic you have a great aura I'm just
I'm seeing that I'm seeing that in you um but uh yeah I think that's I mean it's
important for people to be kind to each other yeah overall great great yeah thank you that was really well said
thank you very much and and so as it just reinforces again it
says it a different way you know important meditation can be
thank you for the talk um I was thinking when you were talking about how the Buddha defined people by
their jobs Merchant teacher doctor and so forth and then you spoke personally
about your teaching voice when you got home and were with your wife so I was
thinking about fixed views and that's one thing that makes us uh suffer fixed
view of oneself if I'm this I need to behave and respond in a particular way
so you hinted at it but I wonder if you could speak to how having this fixed
view of self doctor teacher lawyer brilliant physician can really be
something that we cling to and cause some difficulty in our lives more suffering
yeah well if we went one is a little bit well when I come back to what you said I
think if we took if there's too crowded with too many definitions and activities there's no space for love there's no
space for kindness there's no space for inquiry there's no space for deeper
self-discovery and and then but if we cling to like these roles these jobs and stuff it can
be a headache for the people around you you know because they're happy you're expecting them to participate in the
idea you know you better treat me that you know I'm like you know you know you better treat me with the
right respect because you know guess who I am you know and I'm this way and yeah and I noticed for myself I was a
teacher for a number of years and defining myself or thinking I was teacher uh was a heavy load to carry so
it's much more liberating and freeing psychologically to to say oh I'm just
who I am or I am the I I am what you see basically rather than having to put on the role of a
teacher all the time so that that was a a weight that I um somehow got
rid of at some point but it can be a pretty heavy burden for people there are people who would prefer that
when they meet strangers or something that the strangers don't ask them what do you do the first you know right away because
somehow that immediately defines them too much you know they don't want to be defined so quickly by what they do
and other people love it and then in between It's just sometimes a very very nice way to connect so how
do you know where in that Spectrum it is it depends on the context the person but so I think we should stop and um but
we'll if you want to come out in the parking lot now I think it's warm enough uh bring a folding chair with you and we
can sit in the circle take off masks and outside and um and continue the
discussion maybe we often do this on Sundays so everyone's welcome to stay and thank you for being here today and
thank you for your great comments and questions