so welcome
uh good to um good to be with you
so uh let's settle in
so in any given moment a million things will be right
and a million will be wrong
and we afford ourselves the luxury
of not needing to sort all of that out
being supported by the million things that are right and
being softened by the million things that are wrong
although it feels maybe unsafe or irresponsible or something
to momentarily put down the world
it's actually important for our heart
rather than living in the realm of hope and fear we put all
of our hope into this moment
and rest
we don't always associate letting go
with joy
maybe we associate it with renunciation or with how
it can feel to unclench the closed fist of clinging
the movement from clenched to un unclenched
often has a flavor a flavor of grieving
and that's all real
but there's also this deep link between letting go and being re-born into
a world of experience where so much joy
is possible
the heart that lets go is carefree
and at ease and totally
not territorial
let's go steps out of comparing mind
becomes so porous to the joy of others
we call it mudita
sympathetic joy joy in the face of the others
happiness good fortune
and so as we said we sense in what
needs to be put down
what can be surrendered release that go
such that i become more porous to the joy of others
the delight of others it becomes utterly unthreatening
we put down our egoic clinging in our reborn
into a world of experience where so much joy is possible
anything might bring it
so calling to mind someone whose uh
well-being good fortune
is uh totally unintimidating for you something
unthreatening
does not evoke comparison [Music]
just bringing their face to mind
now of course there's dukkha in their life
it's a given
but there's much goodness happiness welfare
and so we attuned to that
we make our heart porous
and we just receive their joy
silently wishing our own mind
may your happiness continue
increase
i'm picturing their face
their face in the wake of this uh
joy happiness their good fortune
the particularities of their smile
i imagine what their inner life what their body must feel like
amidst their joy success
i just let that into my body
may your happiness continue
that increase
and we just abide suspended
in some delight
when there is no self
there's just the world
the happiness of others is known
precisely as our own
in these last few minutes
the wishes that all the happiness in the world
increase
my all beings revel
happiness made increase
and we even might extend it out beyond
the beings born now
to the future maybe even the distant future
all the potential happiness contained in this moment
may all that goodness all that
richness may that increase may it be born
and increased
b
so um
thank you good to um good to sit with you
um excuse me the uh topic modita
some pathetic joy and um
you know sometimes when i think about um
you know joy i think of um kind of like those awkward family photos where the children are
wearing these like very forced very artificial smiles that
look basically like grimaces you know it's like
be joyful modita sympathetic joy is a tricky one yeah
it's a tricky one right because um joy is just like this this spontaneous
upwelling it's a little maybe a little trickier to incline the
mind in a way that feels spontaneous and alive
and so i promise not to command you to be joyful you know um
so a colleague a friend of mine uh tawari
salah sometimes she she's like uh the queen of met of uh of mudita you
know she sometimes just i don't know when she talks about it or guides something she just like goes for
it and uh i wind up in like a slightly
disregulated ecstatic blur of delight she's just like
sometimes relentless with it and um anyway so i wanted to uh to share share
a little bit of what she said this is from a retreat we did a year ago
um it's a couple paragraphs from her so she says um we've come to
my favorite favorite moment in all of dhamma
i don't know when i opened this pandora's box it's not the way i grew up with this energy i don't know
anywhere in my life i would say oh yeah joy is what i would call life i grew up
in a very difficult childhood spent the bulk of my life poor on welfare
joy would not be the underlying feature of experience that i would point out
but somewhere in dumb i stumbled upon this mudita and it's been a game changer for me
so let me see if i can try to help you see where i'm pointing to there's a great difference between
mudita and the kind of worldly joy that we try to access regularly in our lives
i imagine that each one of us on this call there's 56 of us we all get two
joys two moments of joy in our lives this year that's all you get two opportunities of
joy and if you're like me we've already used them up
so there's no joy for the rest of the year you've already had it
so the only way you can access a level of joy is it has to come from someone else
if i start telling you about some joy i have because you're human you'll feel it
if i begin to cry you'll feel that if i tell you about some sadness some difficulty in my life you'll feel that
and likewise i realized that i could feel the joy of another
person and there would never be a day or a moment in time
when i would not feel joy never it's not possible there are like billions of people on the
earth and at any given moment somebody somewhere is experiencing joy and all i
have to do is to be willing to tap into that joy and feel it with them
my granddaughter's four years old and she's learning about jokes and she just starts laughing
she'll say something like and then they said
go away [Laughter] laughing uproariously
and i'm laughing and that is not even funny but i'm laughing because she's laughing so hard like she told some
great joke it's just another way of experiencing the human condition that we're all
interconnected so yeah
uh let us um lean on each other's joy
let us lean on each other's joy and emits amidst pain
you know it can sometimes feel like joy is a
a way of cheating on one's grief you know it can
feel like a certain kind of adultery like cheating on one's grief
but one of the
shifts in dharma practice is that our emotional life becomes more
supple and a moment of joy does not cancel out
the grief it's just like we our emotional life it's more yeah it's more fluid and
supple and so a moment of grief can just be followed by peace
and then joy and then maybe the heart circles back to whatever
it's pain it might be connected to
but the joy is not cheating on the pain it's okay
and our are we can depart from our kind of homeostatic baseline
into yeah maybe even deep joy
sometimes it's um it's easier to talk about removing the
obstacles to joy rather than creating joy right i can't chide you you know smile
be happy right and so instead the practice is is really
like to examine well what obstructs mudita what obstructs this like delighting in the
welfare of others possessiveness
comparing mind envy
um the machinations of ego
the reflex of of ego is really to um
to incorporate all goodness into itself it's like my ego tolerates
no goodness outside itself it must appropriate everything
that is a very fragile dangerous way of living
to not tolerate goodness outside oneself or to need for that goodness to affirm
one's own egoic process that's a fragile way of living
and so we're gonna have to actually step in some ways out of self to truly enjoy
other people's happiness to truly enjoy it
now it just feels important to acknowledge like modita is not a public policy you know
so when i say we must relinquish envy or something like this i am not talking
about public policy the disparities in health and wealth
are not sustainable what i'm talking about here and there's
they're very understandable reasons for things like envy
i'm talking to the heart of a of a practitioner
we're going to have to step out of some of these egoic forces to truly delight
in the welfare of others so there's an essayist um
talking about the seven deadly sins lost gluttony greed laziness wrath pride envy
and said of the seven deadly sins
only envy is no fun at all and isn't
that true isn't that true
um envy is um is usually about um
two people and jealousy about three
and wanting someone something has versus
wanting someone some relationship connection in the case of jealousy
and of course these forces likely have real evolutionary benefit yeah they've
been encoded in to us and still it's important to remember that
evolution doesn't care about enlightenment
even a little yeah we're here we're here
because we're the sufferers yeah this is a evolutionary psychologist
despite the manifold unhappiness jealousy creates jealousy
has a crystalline functional logic precise purposes and supreme sensibility
it exists today in modern humans because those in the evolutionary past who were indifferent
to the sexual contact that their mates had with others lost the evolutionary contest to those
who became jealous as the descendants of successful ancestors modern humans
carry with them the passions that led to their forbearers success
the legacy of the success is a dangerous passion that creates unhappiness but the
unhappiness motivated adaptive action over evolutionary
history
the to move against the
the forces of jealousy of envy is to move in some ways against the
stream the the dumb is against the stream
and these mechanisms of the mind um
envy uh especially really shows us where
we're identified where we're identified
um it envy envy highlights the insanity really of
egoic life
identification wherever we are identified it impairs our love
and our capacity to access joy to receive the joy
of another in an unthreatening unintimidating way in a way that does not diminish ourselves
that does not evoke the comparing mind this is mature card
envy is the product of a wound to self-importance and the fruit of an illusion what can other people's
happiness possibly deprive us of nothing of course
only the ego can be wounded by it and feel it as pain
these are the results of our having forgotten our innermost potential for
affection and peace
when we uh feel sufficient
yeah when the kind of all the the egoic melodramas of worthiness and
unworthiness of my deserving undeserving
when all of that fades we are
we can delight in the well-being of others
when we're fluid in ourselves and we ask am i that
no am i that
no
then there's less and less to defend and the delight of others
is totally unthreatening just rushes into our heart
very natural easeful joyous
sorry for this for your consideration
you