mm-hmm so good day on this Friday
and uh delighted to be here with all of you
so one of the themes for this week has been the way that uh
certain states can exist together sometimes in a spectrum where the degree
to which one or the other is depends where we are in the Spectrum and sometimes maybe we don't necessarily
see as a spectrum we see it as being quite this distinct but that they
things can coexist and happily one of the things that can co-exist
is we can cling that we can be attached we can be holding on we can be
um heavily resisting something or and at the same time
be aware of that who in a way that is free that is not clinging
it's possible to have very clear sense of knowing
or of an open kind of awareness within which
we know there is clinging but the knowing is free
The Knowing feels a light it has like no weight
The Knowing feels maybe kind of I don't know if allowing is the right
way or accepting is allowing is the right word or accepting is the right word but the knowing is equanimous the
knowing is not a hostage or not caught in
what is known and so this uh ability to do both is
actually very significant for doing this practice because some of us will have a very
strong tendency to identify to lock into different states and especially if
there's a things were critical about ourselves or strong very impulses which are
of attachment we could kind of so get so preoccupied with so caught in it
that um that it's almost like we become it or it's inconceivable being without it or
it feels like we have to struggle with it or fight it or with it but when we have a clear sense
of this knowing this awareness this way of recognizing
that is not caught is not entangled with it just simply
knows the Simplicity of it without identifying with it without seeing making it a
problem without making the knowing of it a problem maybe some things need to be
addressed in their issues but the knowing is independent of the problem it just knows
and that's a phenomenally useful reference point for finding our way
because then we're not um beholden to the attachment to the clinging we're
not under its influence which paradoxically we are if we're fighting it or criticizing it or upset about it
and so the fact that we can hold to both be attached and know it in an unattached
way so that'll be kind of the orientation for this this meditation
and so to assume your meditation posture
and gently close your eyes and straight off here
what is the most obvious thing that you're aware of for yourself right now
and whatever is obvious right now for you see if you can experiment
with recognizing that's how it is in a relaxed recognition
as if you're sitting back and gazing upon it
even if you are upset with it or have reactions to it perhaps that's which knows
doesn't have to just know it
some people the idea of gazing upon it can provide a little bit healthy
distance where the mind's eye is not the continent your Seas what's there
so then to maybe with a reference point with a
sense of just knowings unentangled awareness
become aware of your body and let there be a few long slow deep
breaths
if any of you have ever gone scuba diving
were you aware of the vastness of the water around you very attentive to it
and also it's so precious each breath
and so here it's so wonderful the vast this of
awareness of consciousness of knowing
and within it the preciousness of breathing breathing deeply and relaxing
letting your breathing return to normal
and maybe with relaxing on every exhale see if there can be the breathing the
relaxation while the same time knowing it
with ease knowing it lightly openly not needing it to be anything or
not a source of judgment just knowing
breathing simply resting
in the knowing that allows things to be as they are
The Knowing that's not confined
by what is known and to practice that
first and foremost with the breathing staying
connected to the breathing with a lightness like a feather touch
with maintaining that feather touch breath after breath after breath lightly
staying in the unencumbered knowing
foreign
remember to come back to knowing being aware
but as you come back to it enter into it
appreciate whatever degree of Freedom you find in knowing
knowing is free from what is known
no clinging
and hopefully you feel delightful attraction
to this present moment capacity to know
without being entangled
and it's not so important to what you know so let yourself know whatever is
happening in the present but take refuge in The Knowing that's
unentangled
there's a strong tendency to identify with what we cling to
what we're preoccupied with
and so when we know it that knowing can be influenced by that clinging
to relax and almost maybe know from the back of the skull
to know somewhat
removed from where the clinging is
into no peacefully lightly
the clinging itself
perhaps you can know with more freedom
if you have a small smile on your face
it's just a teeny turning up of the corners of the mouth
and maybe that brightens the awareness enough
for a stronger sense of unconstricted knowing
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to again maybe make a smile on your face
because a smile on the face can make it harder
to be grim to be harder to be attached
the harder to resist
and to not resist your capacity
to gaze upon the world kindly
take gaze upon the world in a friendly way
what would it be like if you were a friend to all that lives
maybe even there's hope that with warm and kind enough friendliness
you'll befriend even the enemies even the people used
have animosity towards to have a smile on your face
to disarm your hostility animosity
and to take the risk to gaze upon all that lives
in a friendly way
and may it be that these
360 people now of you all sitting here
may it be that that becomes a Force a force
of kindness her friendliness that we carry out into
the world today May whatever benefit in merits we have
from this meditation together spread from each of us in all directions
out into the world so we contribute to the welfare and happiness of others
may it be our wish that this meditation
is for the happiness the safety the peace and the freedom
of those upon whom we gaze upon today may we gaze upon them
in a friendly way
thank you [Music]
so then we come to the last talk on the topic of conditioned
consciousness and our connection to being aware to being
conscious is quite variable and sometimes we have no connection at
all we could be so caught up in something so preoccupied so besides ourselves that
we're besides our suffering we lose ourselves in what we're doing we are we
can end up saying I didn't I don't know what I was thinking or what I was doing I didn't even know what I was saying
when I said it um we can be so wrapped up in something that the very idea that we can be aware
and conscious is far from the Mind far from what we're preoccupied with
and it's possible to be in states where um it's just like so obvious that we're
conscious it's like this like the main game in town is being aware and conscious maybe in a relaxing wonderful
day off laying under a tree in the park and looking up at the clouds and the sky and
and there's not much to see but it's uh there's a clear sense of wow
I'm aware I'm present I'm conscious I'm alive this is quite something and uh and
the sense of Consciousness there is really strong and then from that place of being in a
day off on the park looking at the sky so we might something might happen in
the park that um we feel we feel we lose some of that
openness that lightness that kind of awe because we get caught in something maybe
the ice cream truck goes by and that's enough to kind of oh that's like brings
up all kinds of memories from childhood and and you get absorbed in that then the fact there are clouds and Sky
disappears the fact that you're kind of have capacity for Consciousness disappears over the idea the memories or
the idea of wanting ice cream or someone gets up in a soapbox not too far away in the park and starts
pontificating loudly about political views that are abhorrent to you and you feel the
contraction of the heart contraction of the mind and and irritation and and with
that if you try to notice what's happened through that Consciousness you notice the conscious self might feel
contracted or tight or or there might even be a resistance in the mind to even
notice that that you're aware in Consciousness because the strong pull into the world of irritation or anger or
fear whatever it might be connected to that so that our connection to Consciousness
our connection to being aware is quite variable and but I think that's having said
saying it that way is a little bit off or very bites off it implies that Consciousness is something
stationary static thing that we can a variable how we touch it or know it
but rather what Consciousness is is it it is shaped
by the state of the Mind so the in the in the park looking at the sky Consciousness that what we feel is
consciousness or awareness has been expanded has been created has been
imagined constructed to be Broad when we get preoccupied and tight
then that sense of awareness what awareness is has become tight and constructed there's not an awareness
that somehow exists offline or outside that's Broad and spacious the conscience
has become that way and this is a theory but it has just as valid as a theory
that there is this thing called Consciousness which is always Broad and we lose touch with it
and my suggestion is that we're still in touch with it but maybe but we're in
touch with something now that a conscious conscience of thus become contracted and tight and narrow
so in this way is continuing this idea that our sense our idea of what
Consciousness is what awareness is is variable and is influenced by all
kinds of things it's influenced by the degree of agitation but the degree of
of uh peace or calm that we have it's uh it's
uh influenced by how much clinging we have and how much Freedom we have
and so we contribute to that creation of
consciousness by the state of our mind and if this particular states of Mind
are valuable and useful then we want to kind of create the conditions for that to be there
in an open expansive free consciousness is invaluable
because it's a protection from clinging to protection from greed hate and
delusion it's a protection from Fear oftentimes it's a space within which some of the
best qualities of who we are have a chance to surface love can come for example
the rather than anger or blame and it's almost like the more
Consciousness is made to be Broad and open and receptive
the more space there is for some of the deeper beautiful workings of our hearts of our minds
so to begin appreciating our contribution to the how we
experience Consciousness how we experience awareness and to
use that awareness that's more light more open more non-reactive
to be aware of how we cling how we tight how we
resist and that's a fascinating way to an alternative to get collapsing into
our clinging getting sucked into it rather to know it so we can be clinging
and we can know it and the image I like to have is someone you know a tight fist that doesn't want to release itself and
a hand comes from underneath it and just holds it gently just gives it support
takes its weight and as it's as the fist feels the support then it begins to relax
so this this awareness that can no attachment can no clinging
uh it's it's kind of like there to offer support there to hold it there to be its
friend to accompany it so that the clinging is not condemned is not fought
with it's not denied not trying to pushed away but so the clinging has a
chance to uncleing so that the way that we're entangled can
be unentangled can disentangle itself and this way in which this
broader more equanimous knowing
that's independent of what is known that's not entangled with what's known
can meet then the clinging is one of the great powers of this
Buddhist practice it meets it and if you're patient you'll you can
discover that you don't have to do the uncleinging you don't have to do the
letting go listen to No to know with non-clinging
allows what's what's climate tooth allows the clinging the attachments we
have to slowly thaw to slowly unwind to slowly release
and so in this way in this lesson it excuse me
becomes more and more important the further we go in Dharma practice
that as as we get more and more concentrated more still more mindful the
mindfulness and meditation gets stronger the more and more important it becomes not to be the one who lets go not to be
the one who uncleings but rather to just allow the knowing
to be the the tenderizer the the dissolving agent just
no just know without any reactivity so that's becomes more important because
we keep practicing early in practice like the beginning of a sitting please by all means relax
relax your body let go of what is easy to let go of but then over time hopefully you'll
discover how wonderful how smile producing
it is to know without attachment to know
without being caught into or glued to what is being known
what is being known is allowed to be as it is and you can settle back and know
in a way that knowing maybe we'll be smile producing for you
how lucky we are to be able to know this way how delightful to know this way
how wonderful to know in a way that can bring forth all kinds of gifts
for the world and may it be
um may it be that you will
discover something about a liberated awareness
that allows you to be a gift a full of your full giftness
for this world so thank you
very much and um I look forward to being back here on
Monday