okay well my name is May Elliott doing a week-long study on the
foundations of a pasana meditation today's instructions are about emotions this
includes moods and mind States this is a really wide field
and learning to practice skillfully with it can I can have a huge impact on our
life on our lives and on a really simple level we're learning how to let emotions
come and go without tampering with them without fighting them or without judging
them so there's no practice I'd like to introduce you you to it's called raft
and it's an acronym that stands for recognize
allow feel and tease or tease apart so we'll
be going for these four parts of raft in the meditation today and then unpacking
them further in the talk at the end now raft is particularly useful for
difficult emotions and wounds sadness grief resentment anger Etc
um but for the sake of this meditation if there aren't any difficult emotions present you don't need to go looking for
that you can still apply this instruction to whatever mood or emotion is happening for you
and it might be a really subtle mood that's in the background and so we're not needing to dredge up anything
um intense with this let's go ahead and start our morning
meditation together can begin with a stable posture
both alert and relaxed
you might connect with your primary anchor that might be the breath for you
believe The Sounds in the room or a global sense of the bodily posture
foreign instructions with the breath to start but go ahead and apply them to whatever
your anchor is
so to help settle and collect the mind
we might take a few deep breaths
foreign
to resume a normal rhythm
allowing the mind to become interested in the breath
collecting here into the present moment
foreign
spots arise during the meditation you can gently release them
and glide right back to the breath
foreign
as we sit letting go of our preoccupations
letting go into the body into the felt sense of breathing
as we do this you might notice if a particular mood or
emotion is present
it's okay if it's overt it's okay if it's subtle
foreign
T background mood
maybe a little calm or contentment
maybe a little agitation or striving
foreign
it's going to begin with our emotions by simply recognizing what's happening
that's the first practice of raft we're recognizing
just knowing oh happiness
or oh this is sadness or self-judgment
whatever is being noticed can be noticed cleanly and simply
and it's okay if you don't have a name for the emotion if you can't figure out
what emotion it is that's totally fine
you might just note emotion
foreign
changes as we sit
the second part of this practice is allowing
whatever arises is welcome foreign
there is no need to resist anything that comes up in meditation
can you fold everything in nothing excluded
foreign
is no longer predominant we can return to your breath or your primary anchor
foreign whatever arises to be known in the light
of awareness nothing to fix
we'll move now to the third grade instruction feel
connecting with whatever mood or emotion may be present
can you experience it in the body Can you feel it in the body
emotions almost always have a physical manifestation
that might be tingling in the chest thank you a sense of lightness or heaviness
contraction in the belly or the forehead heat pressure
Etc
see if you can connect with whatever emotion or mood may be present
through the felt sense of the body
thank you
if it's helpful and you can apply a soft mental note to whatever you're
experiencing
tingling
tightness
warmth keeping the note light in the background
and the actual sensation in the foreground
foreign
whatever Sensations we find there to be
and a scientist
nothing personal
nothing's a problem
thank you
foreign
this last piece of working with emotions is
teas T's apart so for this piece of the practice it's
supposed to be simple we're teasing apart the difference between the storyline or any narrative
associated with the emotion we're teasing apart the
felt sense of the emotion and how it's experienced in the body
seeing the difference between mental and physical manifestations
we're getting clear about what's Extra
maybe there's an extra layer of self-judgment or resistance
or a wish to fix whatever emotion is present so teasing apart to be able to see that
thank you
foreign
the emotion from the identification with the emotion
every emotion will pass away
at that time we can return to our anchor we can return to the breath
foreign to stay present in the body
okay if we can learn to befriend our
emotional life when we're not at war with ourselves
with our inner world we can show up more fully and more
compassionately for others
May the beneficial energy of our practice here together benefit all
beings everywhere so they may be happy
safe and free from suffering
I okay
welcome back everyone I hope you enjoyed your sitting
for those just arriving my name is May Elliott and we are in the midst of a
five day series on the foundations of La pasana meditation so we're on day three
focusing on emotions day one was on breath day two was on the body
so I'd like to start with a story for you in my early 20s I got a one-way ticket
to India and at one point when I was in rishikesh on the banks of the Ganges and there
were tons of monkeys around us really fantastic and I had left my backpack on the beach
while climbing up on some rocks and I looked down to see that one of the monkeys had his little hand in my
backpack my lunch was in there and so I think it was somewhat enticing so I
scrambled down down from the rocks and I shooed the monkeys away only to gain the
attention of a whole pack of monkeys um and they didn't seem so threatened by
my attempts to fend them off so before I knew it several monkeys had
started closing in on me they were surrounding me and had very aggressive expressions
and I started feeling a pretty uneasy and I was backing up and found myself uh
backed up against the rapid-filled river and uh sort of hopped onto a tiny sliver
of Sandbar a foot or two offshore and I had a big stick and I was trying
to fend them off at the stick which I think they perceived as pathetically unthreatening
and it seemed ever more probable that I would be their lunch when to my
tremendous surprise a group of Whitewater Rafters appeared from
Upstream and in a blink I don't know even how it happened but I found myself scooped into
their boat and they kindly delivered me to the safety on the other Shore
so some of you may be familiar with the Buddhist teachings on the
parliaments the Perfections these refer to
the term parami refers to the wholesome Buddhist qualities like generosity and
patience and wisdom and I I actually love this word parami
because it's an ancient Pali pun it can be translated as Perfection pointing to
how these beautiful qualities of mind and heart perfect or I guess I should say how
these use practices perfect the mind and heart but it can also be translated as
crossing over paramet can be translatables crossing over and in this way through practicing we
learn to cross over to the other Shore we learn to cross over from the shore of delusion to the shore of Awakening from
confusion to Clarity from hatred to love when there's a way that all of these
practices we're doing together support us to cross over to the other Shore
you may remember uh w s Merwin quote that I shared on day one of this series
little breath Breathe Me Gently roaming
for I am a river I am learning to cross
when I was on the riverbank in rishikesh I was pretty scared and in that moment
of being rescued I was freed from that state of fear and that state of despair
uh the the emotional upheaval was transformed one could say so in the same
way whenever we're overcome with a difficult emotion can often feel like we're stranded you
can feel like we're overwhelmed or we're stuck and we could all use the benefit of a Lifeboat in those moments
so the practice I'd like to discuss further that we covered in the
meditation is this practice called raft it's an acronym so it stands for
recognize allow feel and to tease or tease apart
and um this practice is designed to keep you above water when struck by a strong
currents of emotion and it was originally uh the acronym was coined by the Insight teacher Tanya
Weiser so let's talk a little bit more or let's take a little more time to unpack this
okay so first when would we use raft
generally in meditation we would stay with the breath with um
with emotions in the background really giving the breath our soul attention
however if an emotion becomes compelling enough to pull you away from the breath
that's when you shift to give the emotion your full attention
so in short if it asks for your attention you can give it your attention
when an emotion becomes predominant in this way that's when we can apply these four aspects of raft
you don't need to apply all four aspects of raft at the same time
sometimes we might focus on just recognizing at other times just teasing apart maybe
just allowing or maybe just feeling so you might use them all at once can
consecutively or you might use different parts at different times so there's an element of creativity with us with
this to see what works for you so let's go through each now um with a little more detail on them
so recognizing this is a really basic principle of
mindfulness practice it's just knowing what's happening in the present moment
and this might be as simple as acknowledging
this is boredom or oh irritation what oh this is happiness so often we don't know
what's happening in our emotional life and before we know it we've snapped at our spouse or our co-worker when we
didn't even really notice that what was happening again aside was anger so the more clearly that we can get to know
these different emotions the more quickly we will identify them in the future
and the less likely it is that we'll be hijacked by them so just the simple Act of recognition
recognition can sometimes unhook the power of the emotion it's
really simple as ajan sumado would say it's like this
so we might be experiencing frustration we might go wrong frustration is like
this I don't know contentment is like this
so that's recognition the next is allowing so often when difficult emotions arise
we find ourselves pushing back against them we're aversive to them we don't
want them there and we're trying to find ways to get rid of them and often in meditation without even
realizing it we'll have something difficult a rise of pain in the body and a difficult emotion and then we'll try
to meditate our way out of it so we're kind of using meditation as a tool to get rid of something
um and if we notice that happening we can just notice it and see if there's room to soften and release
and really meditation is not the only way we try to get rid of our emotions that's maybe one of the more skillful
ways um that humans do all sorts of things you know excess food and drink entertainment argument suppression Etc
so uh so when we reject our emotional experience what ends up happening is
that we add an extra layer of Sufferin the Buddha talks about this process as
being like being shot by two Arabs the initial painful emotion is like being
struck by the first Arrow jealousy longing Etc
but when we reject our experience and try to get rid of it this experience of aversion or rejection is another layer
of suffering so that's like getting shot with a second Arrow so if we're sad and then we
say to ourselves oh this is ridiculous that I'm sad I shouldn't be sad about something so petty
and then we're filled with self-judgment for feeling sad then we've shot ourselves with a second Arrow said it's
the first Arrow the self-judgment's the second round we know from the second Noble Truth that
the source of suffering is craving aversion is just the other side of the
same coin when we reject our experience we suffer
so instead this is where allowing comes in and said can we allow our experience
this doesn't mean that we are justifying or condoning our emotions nor does it
mean that we're necessarily expressing it instead we're just making space for
it to be as it is allowing the emotion to be to express in the body without judgment
and there's so much Freedom that's available with difficult emotions if we can learn to relate to them as just
tides that move through us if allowing is difficult they can be
helpful to remember that um all of these emotions are impermanent
that will all pass on their own even if we tried to keep an emotion the same we
couldn't do it right um so everything is subject to change
there was once a spiritual Master walking on one shore of a river and his
disciple was walking on the other the other Shore and the disciple yelled across the
master master how do I get to the other Shore in essence so how do I cross the
river of samsara and get to the shore of Awakening and the master replied you are on the
other Shore so when we practice acceptance when we
practice allowing we realize that we don't have to strive to get to the other short or to get somewhere else or get
somewhere better you don't have to resist our experience to try to get a
better one when we practice allowing it's as though we've already arrived
Freedom can be found in the Here and Now Okay so we've done recognize and allow
and now we'll do filling the F of raft so this aspect
of raft involves really getting to know the sensations of the emotion in the body
so often emotions are carried by a really strong narrative or storyline and
in this practice we're letting go of of that Narrative of the thoughts associated with it and really feeling
the physical Sensations associated with their emotion and it's often used physical Sensations
that keep our stories spinning our storytelling mind is in a way Often by
thinking it's trying to to think its way out of the problem
it's trying to um to come up with some solution to
whatever is challenging us and is causing us to feel how we feel in the body
so for example if we're compulsively rehearsing a conversation it might because we're trying to figure
out the right thing to say and we really want to get the right comeback for this person that we're angry at and if we can
just really nail that response then we won't have to feel angry anymore so in a way we're trying to think our
way out of how we're feeling um so the thinking mind is problem
solving in a way such that the body can stop feeling the emotion
now instead this practice of feeling uh what it does is it subverts this
tendon it subverts the tendency to try to think our way out of our feelings
and instead it meets the emotion at its root that meets the emotion in the body
and we may get back the only place we can ever really address it which is in the now
so if you could use support in learning how to feel the body I suggest you go back to the meditation
and the the talk that we did yesterday on mindfulness of body it's really learn
the language of how the body feels dealing in the language of sensation
foreign
so in this uh in this piece we're teasing apart the different components of an emotional experience so that we
can start to see the different parts more clearly so emotions have many facets to them
both physical and mental and we can tease apart the physical experience from
the thoughts so we might notice that heaviness we might notice heaviness a slouched
posture maybe a lump in the throat um we recognize that part of sadness as
distinct from the thoughts about sadness which is distinct from the emotional
tone of sadness so that helps us get to know what's
really happening here and when we can really see clearly and tease apart carefully we can find where the
suffering is we can find where the source of suffering is and we can also find where the freedom
is so when we look more closely at the mind we can tease apart the emotion from the
reaction to the motion right this is what we talked about with the first arrow in the second Arrow so we can
start to see the difference between the first and the second arrow and we can see the difference between our grief and
the embarrassment about the Greeks and those are two different things and we get to see what
our judgments expectations and attitudes we have that are functioning in
relationship to the Primary Emotion maybe we might ask ourselves you know are we afraid of how are we afraid of
how we feel uh do we grasp hold of our feelings do we hate them
are we embarrassed by them are we identified with them these are all questions that
um that we can discover through this practice of teasing our part so here you have it that is raft r-a-f-t
recognized allow feel and tease tease apart so just as a reminder with these
you don't have to practice all four aspects each time you focus on a emotion
um please feel free to experiment to see what works for you and see what helps you relate to your emotions with less
reactivity and what you may find is that through doing this practice
rather than needing to solve our problems sometimes this practice can
dissolve our problems and
what we find is the more we practice the more clear it is that there are two
classes of emotional experience one class is of wholesome emotions
or excuse me of unwholesome emotions that involve craving aversion or
delusion and these are often emotions based in wanting or not wanting might be
desire anxiety competitiveness energy and particular feelings feelings that
raft is particularly helpful for now there's a second class of emotions
that are wholesome ones that manifest from a peaceful heart emotions like uh Joy or compassion
the para means like generosity patients loving kindness and these wholesome emotions are
cultivated in part just by knowing when they're present so we have so many moments throughout the day where it
might even just be a flicker but just a little flicker of contentment but a little flicker of Joy so don't miss
Feast when they're present really pause and soak them up when they come to visit because this condition is the mind
for allowing these wholesome states to arrive more frequently in the future
so I hope that today whatever emotions you encounter you can meet them with the
eye of practice and I hope that you remember that you
always have a raft on hand you always have what you need to cross the River
from delusion to Awakening so may you all arrive safely on the other Shore
thank you so much I hope you have a lovely day