greetings friends greetings good morning good afternoon good evening good day
whatever time zone you're joining in may it be may be mindful maybe good
maybe wholesome with awareness
lovely to be with you in this moment in time and to practice together
to practice together so so let us continue let us continue today
with our exploration um
where's the important profound teaching of karma so
so without further ado let's let's practice together let's um
land in our bodies arrive and of course i'll say more later about
the theme for today so arriving arriving here
every moment every moment a new arrival
every moment a new arrival
this self this what we call a self this being every moment a new one
no sensations no thoughts no emotions no experiences
hello hello hell no
greeting all that's arriving in this moment all that has been passed down
and is arriving in this moment and all that is being passed on
this moment right here just on the edge of receiving and passing on
and yet with its own intentionality its own
creation forming formations
so let us form wholesome formations
of awareness appreciation
wakefulness alertness
ease peace arriving arriving
arriving spaciously
in this moment in this body
letting the breath be received
each breath each inbra the entirety of the in-breath
the entirety of the out-breath the pauses in between
soothing calming the mind
calming a restless mind an agitated heart
soothing calming the body
all formations
awareness of this breath in the body
let the breath be natural let awareness be natural
not forced it's already here
let the body be natural
nature we are nature
receiving from nature giving to nature
our breath our being intertwined with nature
and if thoughts arise as they will
not a problem
that's what the natural inclination of this mind is in this moment
so not to see it as a problem having a spacious heart with a spacious
awareness spacious
easeful breath
letting it arise and pass without getting entangled
staying aware staying in your station of awareness
as to what's arising what's being handed down coming downstream
coming downstream from earlier actions thoughts
forming formations
nowhere spacious knowing
and as awareness knows
sensations in the body the breath thoughts
emotions sounds whatever is arising
see does what is passed down through causes and conditions
through past actions formations
doings makings especially thoughts patterns that are us
as the stream passes through observe no
be aware
no need for judgment for the person you were
previously are you even the same person you were a year ago
this self letting go of that concept for a moment
and just seeing these streams that are arise arrive in this moment
and deciding intending [Music] for the stream of kindness
awareness wisdom to be passed down from this moment
so not judging not hating not being
greedy
about what arises meeting with kindness with spaciousness
as much as possible and if that's not possible can there be
acceptance and ease equanimity that it's not possible in this moment
that too is planting the seeds of ease and
equanimity and wisdom instead of being reactive entangled
watching the stream being passed down and adding
drops as if taking a dropper
that has color in it and dropping a drop or two
of kindness acceptance ease wisdom patience
spaciousness into the stream into the stream in this present moment
as the stream is passed down one breath at a time
present here here
can we appreciate this moment a liveness
of awareness even if we were lost in thought a moment
ago it's okay in this moment a new arrival
fresh with possibilities like the spring
and as we bring the sitting to a close
appreciating appreciating what was
without judgment
through appreciation and kindness towards ourselves through the stream that was passed down
you can plant wholesome seeds
more kindness in the stream in the river as we pass it down
into the future so appreciating appreciating our good
fortune for being able to sit together
practice and community listen to the dharma
such good fortune
appreciating that we have showed up that we have done what we could
today in this moment as best as we could
with appreciation gratitude kindness this person who is me
and our sangha our community our beloved community
and intending in our heart to offer with generosity it's all about
generosity we receive generously we offer our goodness
the best of ourselves generously to others it's not for us to keep
it's not for us to keep
to share to offer the merit the goodness of our practice
to all beings everywhere
past present future
may all beings everywhere with whom we are
inextricably intertwined
may they all be happy well
free including ourselves
thank you for your practice
hello [Music] hello friends hello sangha
so today we continue our exploration with uh with karma with this important
profound teaching of karma so
[Music] the past few days
today being thursday the fourth day we are going to turn our attention
to this teaching and how it impacts our life
in the past few days we've discussed the three different aspects of karma as
action with intention the action of the mind the body
and speech all actions from different sense doors and the lead and the trailing edge what
is left from the action from the intention which is the leading edge
the action itself as well as the the trailing edge what is left what is
created what formations are created
so [Music] it's impossible perhaps i mean it is possible
but but um it's important to talk also to pay attention to talk a
little bit about rebirth as we talk about karma
so [Music] so in the west as as buddhism has come to the west
[Music] most or almost all of western buddhists
they don't hold they don't really subscribe to the idea of rebirth this
concept of rebirth so because in the west there is this concept of the self there is me there
i'm i'm here i'm um um [Music]
a fixed i have a fixed identity and thoughts and emotions etc this is the
fixed me whereas the idea of rebirth can actually loosen that it's it's concordant it goes
along with um with the idea of impersonality
ungovernability and control of uncontrollability so let me speak about that for a moment and just to say you
don't have to believe in anything you don't have to believe these are just invitations to consider a
different way of seeing so so for the next 10 minutes 9 10 minutes let us enter
into this world you know we're in this universe or in this world where perhaps we you know you don't believe that
there there is no rebirth for a moment for 10 minutes let's just enter
an alternate world um that we're um
the concept the idea that there was the reality of rebirth let's enter into that
together so
if if you were reborn if there was someone if there was
uh if you if you were reborn if you were a rebirth if there was rebirth and there was
someone else who was your say your previous self
you know they would probably they would have a different body different gender
different upbringing different language different memories different dreams different attitudes
all of that being different so would that still make you make them
the same person and if there was a being that
say was you were reborn as someone else in a future life assuming that is true
we've entered this universe together this thought experiment together where that is true
that person would still have a different gender upbringing and and language
learning memories dreams attitudes so they would be a different person could you still
consider them to be yourself right
so so there is no continuity of the self
in rebirth anyway because in buddhism in the buddhist doctrine it doesn't even
make sense to call yourself itself let another rebirth for it to be a
continuity continuation of yourself so the idea is that
even here in this one lifetime um
we are not this coherent independent
uh controlled being because we are made of causes and conditions
and interdependence strong interdependence with others with causes and conditions
so the idea of rebirth
is uh the idea of rebirth is that
as it is mentioned in the buddha in the suttas
the same way that milk changes into curds and then changes to butter
and then changes to ghee similarly and in the same way that
milk and milk curds and butter and ghee they all have the same they're all
connected they're all connected however they manifest very very differently
uh in the same way if there is if there is rebirth you know
you are manifesting very differently so there is not a sense of i'm still not the same person if they have this
different dreams and memories and parents and dispositions and everything so it's
uh there is not a self in the idea of rebirth that is kept
so if there is rebirth and the idea is that yes
i am heir to the actions of someone who is long dead
supposedly and and there
even though you know again my body nationality language all of that is different i have i have this composition
here in this life and yet that gives rise at least for me
being in this universe assuming that there is rebirth for me gives rise to a sense of gratitude that there was this
person who passed down it's like they were my ancestor there was some kind of ancestor
that were different beings the same way that my grandmother great great great
grandmother or grandfather they were different beings but they passed something down to me in terms of genes
in the same way the they were this this ancestor they passed
down this this you know previous rebir reborn itself
passed down these karmic formations that now i'm grateful for
and i'm the beneficiary of and in the same way
i pass down i pass down these karmic formations for the benefit
of someone else who in some ways is related to me the same way my children are related to
me or my my great great great grandchildren if i had any they would be related to me and
i want the best for them so basically the teaching of rebirth and
karma brings up the sense of it's really it pivots it it's based on a
um based on generosity and gratitude a sense of generosity that we have
received something we have received life first of all and
we have received these karmic formations and
we are going to make the best possible and pass it down
so it's like i don't know if you have the same feeling but when you
say stay at if a friend's place i like to leave it better than i found
it cleaner than i found it it's the same idea this this karma that
you have been passed down thank you can we make it better can we improve it
can we make it kinder can we make it more patient can we make it more
loving less reactive and pass it down to others
is that possible is that possible so
again all we really have is this moment's
knowledge is this moment's [Music] awareness
and our actions our intention our actions in this moment we don't really
know i mean that again now we can perhaps exit this universe or
rebirth is definitely true exit this thought experiment together but even if
it were true it wouldn't make much of a difference right in terms of oh i'm going to live forever and i'll come back
and i'm not gonna die no of course you're going to die it doesn't make any difference it just brings a sense of
perhaps interconnection that we already feel with
all the living beings in this moment in time who are living with us on this
planet because our life is strongly intertwined with theirs the
air we breathe our actions etc and
the same way we are intertwined we are in inextricably intertwined
with beings from the past and into the future
not just genetically but in some ways that um in some ways that maybe
actually from some of us give us inspiration aspiration to be kinder to
feel that the whatever remarks we make whatever we do
is is not without reverberations in the world not just in this moment but but wider
so so basically the teaching of karma and with respect
to rebirth makes us even realize even more that we're not living for ourselves for our
own benefit it's such a small minded thing that to think that i'm just living for myself me me me me
but we're living for the benefit of all beings whether or not we like it
and so with what quality do we live in this moment with what quality do we live
in this moment for the benefit of all beings it's not about me how do my actions how do my
intentions affect everyone so i thank you all i thank you for your
practice today thank you for your dedication
planting seeds wholesome seeds of kindness take good care of yourselves
and hope to see you tomorrow take care