hello everyone and welcome
and as an introduction to this meditation
we discover that often when we sit down to meditate that the mind is as other ideas
that we are concerned with things that we have a mental tendency to
fixate on certain certain kinds of thoughts ideas concerns that we have
and that the simple act of coming back to focus on the breathing
can be challenging because the mind has other ideas there's this strong tendency to
to be focused on the concerns or focus on the distractions or the fantasies or
whatever it might be and sometimes the mind when it's focused on its concerns
can be locked in sometimes there can be a strong force in that direction and
there's not the mind is not soft or in a receptive relaxed way because it's
concerned about something there's energy in it and so one of the things that happens in
meditation is softening of that kind of uh fixation of the mind or
preoccupation of the mind the energy that's so directed at our concerns
that sometimes is locked in and there's a softening that the yielding of that uh quieting of that
a stilling of it that happens and uh without that quieting and
softening of it meditation is a battle and uh to come back to the breath over and over again and
and sometimes it adds more tension sometimes because of uh
of uh you know the struggle between these two forces but if we understand that part of what
we're doing and returning to the breathing and even and focusing on the breathing is uh helping the mind begin to soften
the grip of those concerns often it's it's uh it's a tightness around
its energy it's it's kind of forceful directedness at certain concerns and preoccupations or even
uh even with the thinking itself
and then it might be more easier not to have this a battle but to find a kind of supportive way in a helpful way to
support that stilling softening of the mind so that we can stay more focused on the
breathing without that being fixated without that being tight
and so one of the ways to do this is to um of course the mind will wander off in
thought is to be very careful how you begin again with your breathing how you resume
the focus on the breathing it's important not to
jerk the mind back or forcefully put the mind back or or to be critical and upset with the
fact the mind wandered off in thought and is preoccupied but rather to find a way that
that's actually pleasant believe it or not a pleasant way of returning to the
breathing and being there that the very movement of returning or beginning again
or coming back to the breathing or letting the breathing come back into awareness it feels like a you know enjoyable
movement it's like a it's like a tai chi move that just feels so
beautiful or it feels like it's a very graceful
and so that even so much so we look forward to that movement of returning
and so that the very returning to the breathing then can contribute to the softening of
the thinking mind and then we come back and we do it over and
over again and slowly the thinking mind relaxes sometimes it relaxes because we relax
the thinking muscle sometimes we can actually quiet a little bit of thinking just to calm it down
just intentionally sometimes it just uh the fact that we're not reinforcing it but continually
pouring our mental attention into it our energy into it it uh it's not
doesn't get it stops being fed and so it quiets down sometimes with time our ability to stay
focused in the breathing improves not because it's a forceful attention but we've learned to have this kind of
steady committed attention to the breathing that where the interest now becomes stronger to stay there than
it is with the distractions so
so and the softening of the mind quieting
of the thinking mind and relaxing of it and settling of it
is uh brings us to a place where we can abide we can just dwell we kind of rest
with awareness rest and awareness rest with the experience of breathing or be stable in
it and that begins opening up new dimensions of mindfulness meditation
dimensions of the insight because we're not because we've kind of cleared out an
enough of the veils of thinking so we can be more subtle in the present moment with direct experience
so in this meditation maybe you can have some focus on
this softening of the mind the thinking mind softening relaxing quieting stilling
and part of that is how you return to the breathing and maybe however you often you wonder off be
content that now you get to practice this returning starting over again
in a you know you know looking experimenting to how to find a nice way to do it
so assuming an upright meditation posture
and
and maybe a little bit if you sway back and forth twist your body a little bit just gently
as a way of physically connecting to your body
and maybe making small adjustments so that you are a little bit better
aligned in your body for meditation
and then letting the the body come to stillness and maybe appreciating that stillness
more because you moved a little bit
and feeling the experience of eyes how does your how does your eyes feel right now
and if you haven't closed your eyes gently close your eyes and feel how the eyes are different
with the eyes closed
and see if you can soften your eyes relax them maybe having the eyes rest in their
sockets particularly helpful if we are still
kind of searching with the eyes even with the eyes closed
and then gently taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale maybe there's some way that you can
relax the thinking muscle softening any tension
tightness associated with thinking
almost as you exhale the mind
settles into the torso down
as if the mind has a chance to settle into a nice soft chair and relax finally
to relax after a long day of work a long life of working
letting your breathing return to normal
and still as you exhale to relax the body some more
the tensions of the mind are also often expressed in the body
soften the belly
soften in the shoulders
soften in the face
and then gently maybe lovingly
center your attention on the breathing
maybe with the idea that using your awareness
you will accompany your breathing
and every time you exhale let go of your thoughts
or if you can't let go of them see if you can quiet the thinking mind
bring greater calm do it
if you wonder often thought see if you can return to breathing
in an enjoyable way
and it might be enjoyable if you don't have a high
standard but be content with the best doing the best you can
over and over again sent settling into the breathing
accompanying the breathing with a
soft committed attention
one breath at a time
returning to your breathing
and with the mind as soft as as it possible
let your attention rest almost like the mind is resting
in the rhythm of breathing
as if the rhythm of breathing is like waves
moving across the ocean
awareness rides the waves up and down coming and going
floating on the breathing
as you exhale perhaps softening the mind
relaxing the thinking muscle
imagining the mind as a broad still quiet lake
cool peaceful
as you exhale letting go of your thinking
letting them your thoughts float away off the surface of the peaceful lake
in whatever is not peaceful
can you for a few moments be aware of that peacefully
calmly
and then to turn your attention your calm attention
outward into the world to the people you'll encounter today in
your neighborhoods stores
colleagues family friends that
who you hold in your heart
and while you're resting the mind
the kind of without fixating on anything
be aware of the people of the world their joys and their sorrows
the ways in which they live in all kinds of challenging ways
and to look upon it all gaze upon it with the eyes of care of compassion
quietly peacefully
gazing upon the world kindly
offer your care to the world
maybe through these words
may i contribute to the welfare and happiness of everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so hello and so in our continued
discussion of the exploration of the sati patana sutta
we're spending time now with the refrain there are 13 exercises in sati satipat
and we're staying now with the first one which has to do with breathing
but as this practice of breathing becomes more focused more
awareness grows then that awareness is available for insight and that's what the refrains are
about so let me kind of repeat what i've said a number of times now
that the exercises are an engagement a way of practicing
that uh is meant to heightened our sense of awareness to click to bring
more clear awareness stable awareness into the present moment
and the in this case breathing is helping us establish
awareness in the present moment present moment awareness and
the practices of knowing of feeling of relaxing are all there to support our ability for awareness to
become stable in the present moment soft awareness open awareness
clear awareness and um and so when when that starts becoming
stable that our awareness our mindfulness and then uh the description and the way
we know we're kind of ready for the insights of the refrain
is when we're able to abide observing our experience
and so the language the the palis viharati v-i-h-a-r-a-a-t-i
and it's um it's uh it means to abide or to dwell
and it's used uh in this teachings of the buddha for um
kind of for uh when once once awareness is strong once our capacity to stay present is
really stable and we then we can abide in different things we can abide in equanimity we can abide in calm
we can abide in deep concentration states we can abide in mindfulness we
can abide in awareness and um and so this word abide is actually a
very rich important word in the sutras and it's it's a kind of pointing us
it's kind of indicating where we're going with mindfulness practice we're not it's not only about being
mindful of our experience and seeing it clearly for what it is that's very important but it's also
about developing this capacity to have present moment awareness so we can abide in it
and we can abide in our experience and uh it goes along with observing
uh observing the experience and um and this observing as i've said
is an is a very spacious clear seeing that is not
interfering or judging or reacting or fixing our experience but we
just kind of settle back and just kind of see it clear that's now we can start seeing it clearly for what it is in a
clearer clearer way because by abiding we're not attacking by abiding we're not
reaching forward to grab or pulling away or doing stuff with our experience we're
just abiding with it and that allows us to come to this place of just perceiving things
in a very spacious relaxed way it's not easy to come there but this is
what the these the exercises the mindfulness exercises in this text are
supporting us and helping us to get there that way and you know it's sometimes takes
a long time to keep doing breath meditation and keep coming back and
it's so beneficial to do do this and then eventually we come to a place where the benefit starts uh
becoming that we could feel this abiding way of just being present
the reason why this is helpful and for the purposes of this path of liberation
is that it frees up the mind from being fixated on concepts and ideas
and stories and opinions imaginations that we have
and so for example
um to use my my example i've used a number of times of uh watching a river go by
just sitting on the banks of the river watching the river go by and then um
but then you know the mind starts thinking about the river and start thinking well this river is
not really flowing in the right location if it was a hundred yards further to the south
they're probably better there it's probably nicer to sit there and look at it get
more sun during the day and and we start thinking about ruminating about this river and
as we think about the river we're thinking about the river but we're thinking about the concept of
the river we're no longer actually just watching and deeply absorbed and watching the river
in and of itself as we get absorbed in the concept of the river
the concept of river of the river is just a concept and that has a certain kind of
permanence to it the concept maybe doesn't change so much it's just the river
but if we kind of wake up from this rumination and sit back on the riverbank and and
back to the river itself and just see the directly with the river we see that the river is actually a
dynamic process of change it's moving and flowing and
all the time and and it's the moving as we sit back and rest it's the moving and flowing
that allows us to settle back and just rest and be soft and relaxed and sometimes letting go of our thoughts
and letting go of anything else just absorbed and watching it go by that we can to we cannot
rest back and be absorbed in a nice restful abiding way if we're caught up in the
thoughts about we have to move the river and how we're going to do this and how much it's going to cost and who do i write to to make this happen
the mind then is kind of active and maybe even a little bit straining it's work to have those thoughts
and so so as the mind softens and relaxes and the thinking mind
does stops becoming a priority that we have to figure out everything or
by our thoughts or think everything out but we start relaxing enough to start
being with not with concepts with the direct experience then we start watching
the changing nature of things so it's kind of like watching um
seeing a single fall leaf fall from a tree and then uh immediately thinking about
you know oh no now i have to sweep soon i've got to sweep my yard and it's gonna be a lot of work
and and um and uh maybe i need to buy a new rake and
and then i'm kind of caught up in a world that doesn't allow me to really appreciate the the wonderful
fl uh flowing down of the leaf and um and then as though maybe the wind
picks up or as fall gets stronger um a lot of leaves begin falling at the same
time and i and i can't just fixate on one leaf falling i just had to sit back
and just kind of watch in a very broad spacious receptive way all the leaves just falling and
falling like snow just coming down so these this is um
as we develop this practice it turns out that so much of our experience of the body or
direct experience of the body is more akin to the river flowing or the leaves falling
than it is to a fixed concept and often we live in the world of fixed concepts ideas and we're relating to
what's happening in our experience through the lens of these concepts and ideas
and even the concept of breathing inhale is a concept if we
if that's not if we're not fixating or focusing on that concept but rather experience the
inhale experience the exhale we see that the inhale is made up of many many different sensations that are
coming and going it's kind of like a river of sensations that flow through
us as we breathe in as we breathe out and we start seeing that actually
the uh uh you know i've sometimes had trouble with my breathing and meditation and i got so
worked up about my breathing was wrong and i was you know like why can't i breathe better and
and what i learned to do was not to worry about these kinds of thoughts but rather to dip down into
the contracted breathing the tight breathing whatever difficulty i
had and just kind of start feeling it directly the experience itself
and the experience itself sooner or later you see it's actually made up of a lot of different
small sensations that are coming and going into existence they're there for a moment they pass away they come back in
a minute later the sensations of inhale are different in the sensations of exhale when the
inhale stops all the inhale sensations have passed away and the exhale sensations begin
and um and it might you know sound boring that you're just kind of being involved in these sensations
but it's uh not as you know it's just like watching a river and it's not to be relaxed and
it's absorbed in the beautiful flow of the process of the dynamic nature of experience
so in this refrain then as practice deepens then it says it
explains one abides observing
uh to use shorthand for today when abides observing the changing
experiences of the body one observes the arising and passing of
experiences in the body and um not that we're searching for it
and trying to look for change it's more like you know you're not the river looking you know trying to search for
how's the river changing how you know what's it's more like you settle back and relax
and you can watch it change so as mindfulness gets well established
as awareness is established and we can abide in in the present moment
in a way that just observes in a spacious relaxed way what we be what we now get tuned into
attuned to is the changing nature of sensations in the body
and and now the practice opens up in a different kind of way when we open up to
seeing this changing nature so we'll talk more about this because this is a probably this central insight
of insight meditation the insight into the changing nature the inconstant flow of sensations
and why it's so important and why it's so central and um and appreciate it so much
isn't probably not so obvious to people who are kind of uninitiated into this world
seems like there's much more important things to do in the world than look and see how things are changing in the body
and but i'll talk more about that tomorrow and go go a little bit further
into this particular section of the refrain which that says
abiding when observes the arising
experiences in the body one observes the passing away
experiences in the body and one observes the arising and passing the rising and
ceasing of experiences in the body so
that's for tomorrow so thank you very much