hello everyone welcome
and those of you who are greeting on chat thank you it's very nice those of
you who are not those on chat are doing it for all of you I would like to thank
you so so the insight
pentad the focus being on
the inside part of it how inside works and one of the important
places to have insight to really see clearly is the difference between
what we know what what for example what we have insight about what we know
and how we know so there's what we know and there's how
we know and many things that we though what we
know many things and what I'd like to suggest uh for this
for today that uh to have more attention to something that's often uh not noticed
often when we focus in meditation on what we can know like the it's usually
something tangible something that we can the senses can take in that we can in
the present moment something we can know because it's a rising or it's occurring in the present so breathing Body
Sensations feelings thoughts sounds Sensations
and um but one of the things that are very very important is insight deepens
is to be aware a little bit of what is absent
and uh and certain kinds of things that are absent uh we can feel when we know
recognize their absence there might be a short period of time where we can recognize the relief
of it not being there so for example before we rush headlong
into mindfulness of breathing and body here we might take a little bit of time to
notice that if there's any relief
that you might evoke sitting in your meditation posture
maybe you don't have to there's things you don't you're not doing and responsibilities you put down for these
30 minutes and and things that you don't have to
address things that don't are not present right now for you and it's just not so nice not to
have them here and um and so um
and so the absence of them can have a little bit of a nice effect I
thought this is good and to feel that goodness to feel that oh this it maybe allows for a different
kind of relaxation to happen a different kind of settling in and then we can take one step further
and that is uh in the knowing of the relief
is that knowing Pleasant or unpleasant does that knowing carry with it some of
the characteristics of the relief there's that knowing I feel spacious or at ease is it
or is it in a hurry ready to go on to the next thing and is it kind of pouncing or is it pulling
back or filled with some kind of desires or aversions or doubts about
what's going on and how simple can The Knowing be
to keep the knowing super simple there's what is known and then the
knowing so simple that direct knowing of what's here or sometimes what's not here
the relief of the what's not here that the The Knowing is so simple
that it's welcomed there's a good feeling it's it's appreciated to know this way
so there's a knowing and what is known so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and
and take a few moments now to feel if there's any relief
of just being here in this way maybe identifying two or three things
that are not present maybe the regular part of your life and
not they're not here in the moment as you're sitting here
and that's maybe part of the goodness of being here
and if you feel some relief of being here what's it like to know that relief
the simplest clearest kind of knowing of absence
of relief without commentary without
judgments just knowing the relief knowing the absence of whatever
is normally present especially the absence of the stress
that you might carry the preoccupations that you normally
carry
the impact that life events might have normally
to feel the relief and then also to recognize
a simple way of knowing that
in that Simplicity of knowing
knowing that it has no stress within it
there you will find the path to Freedom
stay close to knowing
in a way that feels relieving
that feels releasing no matter what you know
it's how you know
that you'll find the path to liberation
foreign
whatever degree of calm or subtleness that you might have
can you know that calmly and said and subtly settled away
can you know whatever is happening from a calm and subtled place
so that there is qualities of freedom
in the knowing
maybe some quality of knowing which is not something you do
but the kind of knowing that arises by itself
when we're present
thank you
sometimes mindfulness practice
is to bring ourselves to be so present
and available for our experience
that knowing arises on its own
and it can be challenging to do this
because this way of being present can feel vulnerable
but to be present in a relaxed and full way
so that knowing can be at ease relaxed
maybe knowing the relief of not asserting ourselves or
defending ourselves or judging and commentary about ourselves
just present knowing the freedom
of how we know
and when we allow ourselves to be this fully present for others
without defensiveness or assertiveness just fully present and available
to know them with a relaxed open awareness relaxed easy knowing
maybe something like kindness
good will will well up inside
will vibrate well radiate
maybe there's a good will love a care compassion
it's not a doing
but an arising
when we're fully present open presence to what is
kind of a good will
which is expressed in these sentiments
May others be happy
May others be safe
May others be peaceful May others be free
and may this good will that I feel
may it be known by others May others know
that they're held in Good Will fight friendliness kindness
and may we know each other that way may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so we come to the last Fifth and last talk on the insight pentad
and these are the
five qualities including Insight that that flow together that rise together
not as something that's constructed or made to happen but something that um
conditions each other or one leads to the other awakens to the other
triggers the other and um
you know many people would think that it would ends with Liberation the fourth of
these Insight pentats five qualities and um shouldn't that be enough
liberation but the Liberation itself uh is a condition for the arising of a fifth
quality and that's the knowledge that one is liberated knowledge that the mind is
liberated and um there are people who have some degree of
you know realization Liberation something that really sets them free
and they kind of know that they've had something significant but they don't really know it they don't
understand what's happened and this knowing of it is to understand something profound about it
and uh and uh as uh so many times for the Buddha it's uh uh it's a know
something specific it's not some generalized vague idea of
what Liberation is what freedom is because some people will have some profound feeling of peace or calm or
some letting go that happens that feels so relieving and releasing
but they don't understand what they've let go of they don't understand what they've opened up into and you know
what's really this experience like and without knowing that it's hard to
find the PATH there again it's hard to know what this path is really about then
some people will have some kind of wonderful experience of peace and and think well that's the point and
kind of try to get back there but they don't understand the conditions that led to it and they don't understand what it
is at the particular that that was experienced or came along with that
piece so they know kind of what they're working towards what it's about what the
kind of the um the the uh the North Star is that
they're kind of working for and um so I want to read to you what I started
talking about yesterday uh the Buddha uh gives a list of 17 specific
psychological States that can be known they can know that they're there these
are painful States and we can know when we're free of them when they're absent
and seeing that specificity of it or this is this was afflictive this was
painful and now wow it's no longer there it's been released
this is a part of the insights and it's also part of Liberation that shows the
kind of circular nature of it the spiral perhaps and so as we
experienced some real clear sense of the falling away the ceasing
of say hate and really experience ourselves take time to know that this is the absence of
hate not just know that it's peaceful but really no this is the absence of hate then we start getting the
information about what hate is about and the alternative that we become
increasingly disenchanted with hate we've increasingly
um uh it's up to start the underlying tendency to hate which is uh starts to
fade away and then there's a again a qualitatively different way of releasing hate
and then we know we've released it and then that's a kind of an Insight that the whole thing can develop further and
further so I want to read this list of 17 specific States
that the Buddha talks about that one could know their present and we could know when they're absent and for the
Buddha this is very significant it's in a discourse called the simile of the cloth in the middle length
discourses um the the list is
um Covetous covetousness
unethical greed ill will
anger resentment contempt insolence
Envy avarice deceit fraud obstacy
rivalry conceit arrogance vanity and carelessness
and uh or negligence so some of these
translations to English might not be exactly what there is in Pali so you
know we can maybe find other words that are a little bit a little bit more meaningful for us
but uh the idea is that if a person when we practice we can know that these they're
called afflictive because they hurt to have these present one can know that they're there
and feel the pain and um and it's possible that they can be let go of
either we let go of them or somehow they fade away they disappear they're not
there and if we know that they're there first really no wow
and sometimes you know this uh this is bad news to know that I have contempt but in the Dharma you want to know that
so-called bad news in an open non-reactive way it's really important
to feel to know the states of mind that are afflictive that are causing pain and
not to pretty them up or deny them or ignore them oh this is I'm living with
you know contempt with their resentment with greed
and then because we know something about knowing that's there the clarity of that
then allows the mindfulness the awareness practice to make room for it to fade away for us to be disinterested
and for it to fade away that won't happen if we ignore it and haven't really admitted to ourselves or these
are there so here we find the example that Buddha being you know in modern terms
psychological about the discussions of the path he's very specific about
psychological states that are being addressed so this is what we we can know
and then we can know when they're let go of when they're absent and that knowing of their absent in this
text if there's a way of knowing it which is inspiring
it's inspiring to know it's possible to be free of these things even if it's
temporarily to have the experience of the Mind wow I've been with this for my lifetime with
this for decades for a long time and I had no idea how there can be a
qualitative experience a good quality experience of it not being there
so this allowing shelves to know that we're liberated and really recognize that where the absence the freedom of
something that can give birth to an inspiration and to confidence
the Buddha calls it a verified confidence it's uh we have or verified Faith it's
verified because we know for ourselves that this is possible it's and even if some of these states come
back the confidence is there the trust is there that this is valuable this is a
direction to go this is important and then the Buddha in this text goes on
to say that this confidence and inspiration this is possible this is the Catalyst for the gladness
pentad the five qualities I talked about last week that also have this natural
flow to them that when there's inspiration there's gladness when there's gladness there can and we're
present for it and allow for the practice and practice with it in the context of it that uh morphs or changes
into joy that changes into a Tranquility physical tranquility and peace and that
can open up into a kind of a deep subtle feeling of happiness or contentment
that is a foundation for becoming unified for samadhi
and that's unification of samadhi that has that Focus that clarity then uh
Begins the insight pentad the insight
disenchantment fading away Liberation and then today knowledge of Liberation
knowing it so as I said before they kind of go to
spiral they support each other and move on and on and how Liberation is of some
kind even if it's very temporary of particular mental States so this is
something we can identify and know for ourselves um otherwise you know some people have
such a vague idea of what enlightenment is or freedom is that you know it's just
always kind of a Mythic event it's kind of like maybe not so relevant for me and it's good for the you know the you know
for the great meditators who go live in caves but what about my life in everyday life here where I'm dealing with you
know getting the kids to school and the work and all kinds of things
but uh by naming the psychological States the Buddha is kind of maybe making it really Irrelevant this is
what's important here and then he goes on in this text this
phenomenal text it talks about this natural flow of arising he talks about
from the inspiration comes the gladness pentad and from that the samadhi the the
unification gives rise to loving-kindness to Metta
and so the whole meta and then the Brahma viharas are all part of this
natural flow this it's almost like these this is an almost like inherent qualities within the or capacities or
potentials Within that um can be set free that can be open to be allowed to flow through us
so there's not something that's constructed or made to happen or engineered but something that we allow
for and that's the underlying theme of these uh two pentats gladness pentat and the
Insight pentad is that there are natural forces within us that can be Unleashed
and open up where we We Roll Along to what we open up to these wonderful
states of of deepening practice um
and um so it's insight
insight to what is insight to what is no longer there
inside the absence of afflictive states that have bothered us for a long time
and the absence of those afflictive States might give us a possibility to
become more aware of how we know how we're aware something so that how we're aware is not
afflictive so how aware doesn't partake or share with some of the greed or the
ill will aversion that's contempt to resentment that might
be with us but which influences how we know and so to begin finding a knowing which
is freeing and knowing which has qualities of freedom and ease and peace and then using that
to a way of knowing to know to practice mindfulness to be aware
and so that the very Act of knowing is part of the path of freedom is where we
find the freedom and allows us to go seek more and more clearly what's have What's um
so uh the um
so Insight in the inside pentad then uh
May your mindfulness practice lead to Insight and may the insight
open this world up of the Dharma moving through you
so thank you very much and I look forward to seeing you or being with you
again on Monday