so a warm hello from redwood city and
i'm happy to begin the week with you this way and
and as many of you know all of you know that the medium for
this path practice of mindfulness concentration of
compassion love that buddhism emphasizes is the present moment
it isn't that the present moment is the be-all and end-all of practice
but it's the entry point for something quite
significant that some of the greatest
experiences or possibilities for peace for happiness
for love for joy for relatedness to others
for compassionate and loving connections to the world
is the present moment there's something special about the present moment
that we can enter into it or sit in the middle of it that it allows us to touch into
something it's very very important that is not possible if we spend a lot
of time in rumination a lot of time thinking about things even
if that what we think about seems important and seems
and probably is important sometimes or whether it's fantasy and maybe
fantasies that do provide a certain degree of pleasure and
they are incomparable to the pleasure and the happiness and well-being
that can be accessed through really being here in the present moment
to not be ahead of oneself not be caught in desires of wanting things to be different in the way they
are but to really settle and be
here and so what is it about the present moment that it operates is such an important
medium such an important door for the depth of our experience
what is it that uh we can find here and what is it we can
be supported by and be cared by and care for
and that's the question for this meditation is uh
what is this present moment what are we connecting to and why is it so valuable
and are you willing to explore that question to really be curious and interested in the
gift of attention that goes into the present moment arises out of the present moment
so to take a meditation posture
and to
gently close your eyes and this closing of the eyes for people
who for whom this works is a beginning of this process of
tuning in to the present moment experience
no matter how mundane it might be
it's the way that we turn our attention to the present moment
that is a big part of what makes the present moment special that opens it
to something deep so turning the attention more fully here
taking a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in attentive to your present moment
experience
breathing out aware of your present moment experience
breathing in deeply and the sensations of the body
can ground you in the present moment
breathing out fully can connect us more fully to the present
moment experience of the body
and letting the breathing return to normal also as a way is this support for coming
here in the present moment take a few moments to relax
what you can in your body where the relaxing
is a further connecting to what's here and now
especially what's here and now in the body
relaxing the face
relaxing the shoulders
perhaps relaxing the arms and the elbows
adjusting your arms a little bit if that helps them be more relaxed
softening in the area of your heart
and relaxing in the belly soft belly
maybe a belly that relaxes downward and outward
suddenly something inside your whole area of your belly settles down into
the pelvic cavity a weight of support and ballast
and perhaps as you exhale
to relax the thinking mind
relax the anxiety to think
the pressure to think
and breathing normally
it isn't the abstract present moment we want to be aware of
the direct experience of what we can directly experience
often through the medium of the body the body is always in the present
and that way the body is a support for you an anchor here
here in the present
and becoming aware of how the body experiences breathing
being aware of breathing while turning on the light of awareness
that is shining on the present moment
the awareness is not pulled into the world of thinking rumination fantasy
but is attuned to the direct experience of the present
breathing
giving yourself over
to the simplicity of breathing
doesn't have to be complicated
but staying aware
of the rhythm breathing right from the beginning of the
in-breath to the end of the out-breath
just breathing here and now
whatever might be happening for you be aware of it as present moment
experience really just just what's happening now
here and now
there
in these minutes that you're meditating
in a sense you're forgiven of all the things you've done in the past
and you're freed from all the things you have to do in the future
you're allowed for these few minutes to just be alive breathing
here in the present moment you're allowed to put aside your
concerns your fantasies
to let that active part of the mind relax and settle
to just be here in the simplicity of direct experience
not needing to figure anything out maybe just
being attuned to the body breathing
the present moment is a radical time out
time out from the past the future
time out for concerns which are not here and now
a time out so that you can really enter the time now
time out so you can be time in here and now
and one of the opportunities of the present moment
is to feel the kind of inner
movements of tenderness of the heart
of care
that is known as compassion
a warm forgiving caring
tenderness that can be for oneself
or can radiate through this being of ours
the present moment is a doorway
the for developing compassion
one of the great treasures of the human heart
and how is it that you experience compassion
what is your way
and what is it like to experience compassion when the mind is quiet
the heart is quiet when there's a stillness of the body
so there aren't so many thoughts and feelings and
body movements that distract from
an inner quality of care compassion
loving sympathy
and sometimes it's the compassion we have
that enables a deeper connection to the present moment
a present moment which is paradoxically not troubled by anything
at ease in the sweetness of holding ourselves holding all things
in tender compassion
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to have the present moment be an opening of the heart of the mind
to reflect on all the beings of this world
and all the suffering of this world
and to have your compassion open outwards
as a force that extends itself that
spreads itself
that reaches out to touch all beings
rather than the suffering of all beings coming to touch us
and trouble us we extend ourselves towards all
suffering
as a loving force to quiet the flames of suffering the fever of suffering
may the extension of our compassion and love
help cool the fever fevers of the world
the fevers of greed and hatred and delusion
the fevers of suffering
may all beings be free of suffering
all beings be free of the agitation
any agitation from their difficulties
may all beings experience
the absence of hostility directed to them
the absence of our hostility
may all beings experience
full peace
may all beings be happy
may all beings know that they are cared for by others
that people do care
may all beings everywhere be happy
[Music]
so with um this talk i begin a five
part series on the brahmavihara of compassion
and it's hard to imagine buddhism without compassion
that it's one of the primary forces that have that has brought
buddhism down to us down through the ages it's one of the primary
movements or things that are awakened in us with awakening the more awake we
become the more compassion there is the more care and love
good will and i'd like to think of awakening this
famous english word for liberation enlightenment
is uh includes the awakening of compassion
and certainly for me one of the big surprises and treasures of
buddhist practice was the slow and gradual awakening of my compassion
it was so gradual and slow that i didn't really recognize that it was happening while it was
happening i wasn't oriented to notice it even though i was changing
and in retrospect after a few years of practice i looked back and seen that well maybe i didn't get
enlightened but i i certainly became compassioned
and discovered this wonderful quality in myself
and to my surprise it was a quality that was very satisfying to feel
it had kind of a has kind of a sweetness and a subtleness and a rightness to it
in and of itself compassion is not troubled by anything
and to come to this untroubled compassion is one of the great tasks of a lifetime
it's certainly easy to experience the suffering of oneself the suffering of others
and have certainly alarm and upset and distress around it
it's also possible to have qualities of compassion together with distress
but to be able to have a compassion without any distress is one of the great gifts that we can
give to the world and to ourselves and that come from buddhist practice
what is compassion um i almost
don't want to define it too much and sometimes i like to think that i
don't really know exactly what it is even though it's been one of the central
organizing principles for my life for much of my adult life i can't think of
very few things that are more important for me and how i live and what motivates me and how i orient myself to the world
than this compassion that's been awakened in me so it's clearly very important for me
and so it may be a little bit odd for me to say you know i can't
really define it exactly and perhaps it's because
over the years of my practice what i have called compassion has changed over time
and that maybe as i've developed or as circumstances have changed that the quality the characteristics of
compassion has not stayed the same in fact maybe there are different forms
of compassion and and so in the course of
time we tap into these different forms and shapes and characteristics of compassion so that we don't want to kind
of you know narrow it down to just just one thing this is what it is
um so a little bit reluctant to give a definition that way but it's you know also helpful to
understand some of the classic definitions of it and uh probably the most classic
buddhist definition in our tradition the theravadin tradition it doesn't come from the buddha who
never actually defined karuna and so it's a little bit
a guessing game really to think to understand what he actually meant by this word karuna the buddhist word for
compassion but buddha gosha a teacher who lives
about a thousand years after the buddha he provided a wonderful description of compassion karuna
and um he begins with uh the what he loves to do and
many buddhist teachers in asia love to do is they try to
connect uh the meaning of a word with words that are uh
similar sounding kind of like not quite the etymology game but a correspondence game
of uh similar sounding words and um
and so karuna you know k-a-r-u-a-n
u-n-a um and it's um so it starts with k-a
and so he has all these words that coincidentally are kind of start with k or uh kind of like a k a a
r in poly that then he sees as being kind of resonates with compassion or
gives the reason why it's called karuna and so maybe uh and so the word
compassion i've translated these words with english words that start with c uh c a
or c o to go along with this c the c o at the beginning
uh you know closest to meaning to what the pali words are so it is compassion
because it causes the hearts of good people to be moved by
the suffering of others so the hearts of good people to be moved by
the suffering of others and first you know what is it what does it mean to be a good person
the word can also mean an ethical person someone who does who lives trying their
best to not live from hatred and greed
lust trying to live from qualities of friendliness and good will
and kindness and wisdom and so as people who have
discovered this is why meditation is so helpful i think meditation helps us to become good people
it helps free us from these forces of hostility or ill will or the
things that we can do that hurt other people and to be strongly motivated not to hurt
and if we're such a person who's able to be in the present moment it's such an important place to be as a reference
point as a discovery of this life then to be in the presence of others
people suffering or know about it something inside of us moves some people translate this word as
trembles or shakes there's removed by the suffering of others
and the question is how are we moved how are we moved so there's no distress
so then the definition goes on further and says it is compassion because it combats
strikes and destroys the suffering of others it's a little bit paradoxical ironic to
use such violent terms in relationship to compassion but it does speak to the strong motivation to
really make a difference to really try to overcome suffering in this world and not
to just kind of accept in some kind of deep way but really have this goal this idea that it can end in some way or
other and then it is compassion
because it covers or moves covers or
those who suffer the word can also mean in pali moves or affects other people who suffer
so the compassion touches other people so it moves covers those who suffer
reaching out actually
reach here there's a different translation reaching out to pervade those who suffer
it is compassion because it covers those who suffer
so it moves those are sufferers so there's something that we reach out from the heart with the
idea of suffusing or spreading compassion now is this kind of
fanciful thinking to think that compassion can spread from us out into the world
is there a force like you know electricity that there are you know wave lengths of vibration that spread out
what is it i don't know and i don't i'm disinclined to
call it anything that but we do affect each other
we do pick up the cues the tone of voice the mannerisms of others that we can
feel sometimes the intentions of others and and to know that this this spreads
out is it means that to know that somehow people are touched by it it resonates in people
and for us to open our hearts and spread lovingkindness and compassion to the
world as if we're suffusing we're touching other people
who suffer a little bit more i want to say but this
ancient definition or discussion of it compassion is characterized as
supporting what reduces suffering i like this definition because it's not
necessarily saying we work directly to end suffering but we help reduce the
support for suffering the underlying causes for suffering and that's many
many things sometimes as things in the external world sometimes it's things within but whatever it is that supports people
to suffer or the condition for people to suffer that is addressed by people who have compassion
compassion uh this is next one is very important compassion functions
to not carry the suffering of others
compassion has the quality that when we have this karuna kind of compassion
we don't we're not burdened distressed by the suffering of others and that is
one of the key qualities of this compassion to not be distressed or burdened by it
and to be interested in alleviating suffering elsewhere
it it manifests as the absence of cruelty
its proximate cause is to see the helplessness of those overwhelmed by suffering
to see the helplessness of those overwhelmed by suffering i mean that really can touch the heart
in a deep way people suffer but there are some people have no ability because circumstances what's
happening in the world to their helpless they can't really help themselves and that really tugs the heart well if
they can't help themselves who's going to let me help them people are in war zones
people are in tremendous uh experiences of oppression and that you know the whole system is set up
around them the whole world is set up and there's no way out of their
oppressed state or terrible state they're in and that the other people are helpless
sometimes in their suffering and tugs on the heart and awakens this kind of karuna compassion
and compassion succeeds when it makes cruelty subside and fails
when it produces sorrow so
when cruelty subsides hostility subsides and sorrow
and there's no sorrow it doesn't elicit sorrow in us distress in us
so to have our hearts moved in such a way that we're not burdened not distressed
that there's absence of hostility and anger but a strong motivation
to help and support people to suffer less
that's kind of the general kind of parameters of what this compassion is and
and i think many times this part that it it doesn't involve being burdened there's no distress in it or sorrow
involved in compassion that is kind of the art that's kind of like the magic of it or the specialness of it
and some people cannot believe that or cannot justify that they feel like they has to
be sorrow and distress and and a sense of weight the weight of the world on their shoulders
but to have this compassion that is sweet
that the compassion that is this one of the great sources of being happy in the world
if we want to be happy live compassionately
but the compassion of karuna this a particular kind of compassion
that the buddha emphasizes or buddha gosha here emphasizes it's a it's a very special thing and
and in these few words that i had to talk about compassion what i hope is that
it will awaken in you as a curiosity and interest
and what is compassion for you and what does your compassion feel like
what reference do you have for compassion that is sweet compassion that is a source of
well-being compassion that is deeply moved by the suffering of the world but is not
burdened by it distressed by it what is that do you have any reference point for it
and if not maybe you can reflect on this and think about it and talk to people over the
next day about your relationship to compassion and how you understand it
so thank you very much
you