okay so welcome welcome everybody
a really warm welcome to
this moment whether you are
here live or you're listening to this
sometime in the future
wherever you may be whomever you may be
welcome
so last week
it was january 3rd
and i spoke about new year's resolutions
it seems like you know that's something
that
we can talk about around the
beginning of the year
and today i'd like to continue that
conversation but you might be thinking
but diana this is a dorma center
i mean
the
new year's new year's resolutions like
that's not fairy dharmic
and maybe i would just like to talk
about this just for a moment here that
sometimes i like to talk and many drama
teachers do this right where we talk
about a drama topic
unpack it explore it
poke around in there a little bit
and then talk about how we might
cultivate or develop or recognize or
something like this or feel experience
and maybe with some application to our
daily life
maybe not but sometimes there is this
too
maybe some way in which it might support
our meditation practice or whatever it
might be
but today i'd like to do kind of like
the opposite last week i did as well a
little bit of this let's take our daily
life
are some of these mundane things
new years of resolutions whether or not
we actually make them
this is something that
with this whole idea of this
a
new fresh start
whether it's at new year's or some other
time is a common practice that people do
that our culture does and
i imagine that many other cultures do
and so can we take something that's i'm
using this word mundane ordinary
maybe not spiritual
certainly in some ways
people practice
on new year's eve may not be fall into
the spiritual realm but this activity of
new year's resolutions of making them
can we take something as ordinary as
that
and bring it into our practice
or bring our practice to that or
maybe a way to say it is
is there any way in which we're making
this division this artificial division
between
mundane ordinary life
and dharma practice
our spiritual life our inner life
for those of you who have been
practicing a while you know that that
division doesn't really hold up
so tightly
some things that we
experience cultivate
i'll just use those words experience and
cultivate whether it's in our spiritual
life or whether it's in our daily life
affects the other right we're only one
person
we're a single person each of us
with
one heart and mind and body
so
if you're feeling this little protest
you might not be too but if you are
feeling this protest new year's
resolutions and a dharma talk
just an invitation to think about where
do we draw these distinctions and is it
helpful
is it helpful to draw these distinctions
and maybe we can bring the dharma to all
different aspects of our life
to
all of that
so maybe the more specifically i was
going to talk about
if we want to start a new behavior if we
want to cultivate a particular quality
if we want to develop a new habit
we don't use often use this word habit
sometimes habit refers to something that
we do
unknowingly but that i'm pointing to
things that that are intentional but we
do to support our lives
so this new behavior
so one way to really support new
behaviors for example a meditation
practice a regular meditation practice
maybe it's a loving kindness practice
compassion practice whatever it might be
in order to support it it's really
helpful
our environment
it can be tremendous support or it can
be something that we really struggle
against
and
maybe i'll
introduce this idea by telling a little
bit of a story
that comes out of this suit does i've
told this story about the suttas it's
one of my favorites so i tell it in a
number of different contexts
but maybe i'll tell the story first and
talk about a little bit so it's about
this person named megia who's um
at this time he is the attendant to the
buddha so this is before ananda is the
attendant to the buddha
and
megia
he's with the buddha but he wishes to go
elsewhere and meditate
and he wants to go to this beautiful
mango grove that he saw earlier he
thought it would be a good place to
meditate
and that buddha discourages him from
going
and
but
megia asks him three times and it's the
tradition or we see this so common in
the uh sutas that after a third time
there's a shift so i have to say no no
and third time okay yes
so
maybe reluctantly the buddha says okay
meg yeah you can go meditate because
megya was the buddha's attendant
he uh
i'm um
assuming that that buddha was expecting
that megia would whatever buddha's
attendant does that he would stay and
take care of that but instead megia
wanted to go meditate
so maggie goes off and meditates
and
he has a difficult time
and his meditation doesn't go well and
he even um exclaims out loud it is
amazing
that i am ensnared by these three bad
unwholesome thoughts
that is thoughts of sensual pleasure
thoughts of ill will thoughts of harming
so
then he goes and his meditation doesn't
go well and he goes back and it tells
the buddha
and the buddha responds by saying
for those whose freedom of mind is not
fully mature
there are five things that lead to
maturity
what five
here megia a monk has good friends
good companions
good comrades
this is the first thing that leads to
maturity
so when the
freedom of mind freedom of heart isn't
there there's these five things the
first one
is good friends good comrades
good companions good associates
i appreciate that there's this number of
um synonyms here and
we can interpret that a number of
different ways one way i interpret it as
not um
having this same level of intimacy
like we have people that maybe we just
say hi how are you nice to see you
and maybe we don't talk with them a lot
but somehow
just um there's familiarity
example
come to a meditation center
maybe even on the chat box on youtube
just to say hello
there's something about just recognizing
that other people are here
that other people are doing the same
behavior
that we're
supporting one another in this way
we shouldn't underestimate how powerful
this is the buddha lists it in the first
in this list of five things that when
the heart and the mind don't have full
maturity we can interpret that as
liberation
five things that support it number one
good friends
good spiritual companions
good associates
and we can interpret this word good
that i i'm saying
as um it's this translation this word
kaliana
and it might we could also understand it
as beautiful so beautiful is often
something that's uplifting
so
for me it's significant that this story
from the sutas
has megya who is the buddha's attendant
some might say the buddha is the world's
greatest meditation teacher
he's the buddha's attendant he has
ordained he has dedicated his life
to practice
and he's the buddhist attendant he has
access ready access to this fabulous
teacher
and he still has difficulties
and that buddha says to him something
that can be a support it's good friends
good associates
i'm not it's a list of five i'm not
going to list the other four of my point
here is the number one it's about the
good friends
so
why is this do we think that
the buddha is pointing to and i'm sure
many of you know there's lots of
different
stories or teaching points that the
buddha has made
about the importance of our associates
and our friends
and i
want to believe that the buddha
recognized something that all of us
recognize too but maybe we don't say it
so explicitly
that we learn behaviors from others
we could even say and it's true right
our earliest behaviors not so much that
we learn them but that we imitate them
right from kind of part of natural human
development that we imitate things and
but even as adults we pick up behaviors
and ways of speaking from others ways of
dressing from others of course this is
how fashion works right whether we
intend to or not you know kind of
clothing fashion changes
it's because people get influenced by
one another
whether they intend to or not
this is how dialects regional ways of
speaking get created
as we just you know slowly get
influenced by each other
either we intend to or not
and to be sure some of the power of
social media for good and maybe for ill
or
i shouldn't say maybe it's both good and
ill right
um
is this power of hitting a like button
or
you know this um
social
i forgot now what the word is but this
idea that well everybody else is doing
it so it must be okay but we only know
everybody else is doing it because we
hear about it on all the social media
platforms
so this tremendous power that
whether it's intentional or not that
other people have around us
so
if we want to have a support for our
meditation practice for our spiritual
practice
it can be a tremendous support to be
with others who have the similar
practice the similar
if not the same
activities behaviors things that they do
for
one because we influence each other as i
was just pointing out but also maybe to
be a little bit more specific about it
is that
if we see other people or
let's say meditating
right if you would have told me years
ago that i would be on youtube sitting
still with my eyes closed
right
it's that um
it's the
i didn't i certainly wouldn't think that
i'd be doing this but there's something
about when we do see other people doing
this it normalizes this and i have said
i'm sure as many of you have
have said
in enough retreats or drama talks
that's what we did
we
had a meditative posture
and meditated together
so it normalizes this behavior
maybe like oh it's actually not that
weird
maybe from the outside it's that it
seems weird right but there's a
collection there's a group of us it
doesn't seem weird at all
so
just to have this um
this behavior modeled by others also
maybe learning seeing like oh okay they
do it that way
maybe maybe that's helpful or they don't
do it the way i'm doing it i wonder why
or you know so not only does it
normalize but we can also learn from
them
like oh that's how you do it
and
there's a little bit uh
i could use this word peer pressure
that's whether it's explicit or not i
know certainly for me
when i was
sort of getting more and more active
here at imc and people were going off on
retreat
and my first meditation retreat was
not a pleasant experience
let's just say that to be sure it was
immensely impactful and ultimately
life-changing but it was not a pleasant
experience it was so difficult it was
really
difficult not everybody has that
experience to be sure but for me it was
hard and part of it was just physically
demanding and then when you're in
physical pain
just kind of you know or
we can collapse around that
but
i was seeing people around you know imc
going off on retreat and
as i
uh left that first retreat
that wasn't with imc it was in a
different tradition thinking like oh my
gosh i don't know if i ever want to do
that again
but there was
a little bit of
you know
this being influenced by others i felt
like okay maybe i should do this if
and boy am i glad i did
boy am i glad i did not because it was a
walk in the park easy peasy but
it just really helped support my
practice
so this idea that other people influence
us
and we can use this as a way to be a
support for our practice
so many things are available on zoom
these days it's astounding
to
find a group
that we resonate with
that supports our
practice it can be a tremendous support
whether it's on zoom whether it's on
person
if the
you are in a place a location in which
that's available
maybe when imc opens back up to come
back to imc
irc
we canceled to retreat because if
omacron shifted some over to online but
we are really striving to try to keep as
much as we can in person
safely
so that
if that's uh
in your
realm of practice or
to consider you know practicing in
person with others too
so that's one thing
about our environment that can be a
support for our new year's resolutions
really
creating the conditions in which it
makes it more likely that we would adopt
a new behavior
but
i also want to point out another dharma
teaching that's related to this
and that is
there's this three refuges these three
treasures the buddha the dharma and the
sangha
and i think the buddha had some
tremendous wisdom pointing to the sangha
as a refuge partly for just what i was
pointing to
the support to have a community of
people that are practicing together
but that's not only
the
reason that's not the only
benefit of the sangha
at the beginning of the anapanasati
sutra that is the suta that gives the
mindfulness of breathing instructions
and sometimes when we read suitas
we might
gloss over the part of it that's not
about the actual instructions
but this is really a foundational
text in this tradition
the mindfulness of breathing
and it begins with setting the scene
with
quite a few paragraphs talking about
how there are these monastics all
together
and there's the
senior monastics teaching the junior
monastics
and it's described in such a beautiful
way and that buddha coming and seeing
this and i don't have the quote here
but it is being very pleased by how
there's this helping of one another and
people practicing together
so
this idea of
just the
support
maybe
indirectly
by just showing up together but maybe
there's support or other people directly
also by
teaching one another as how that part of
the wave with this as suta shows
but there's another part of the sangha
and another part of this practice
is that
i've been talking about how we're
influenced by the our environment and
of course we're influenced by
those that are in powerful positions
either directly or indirectly often you
find people kind of like imitate those
who are in power
the sangha they have
when i'm using the word power i'm
thinking about their
power of
dedicating their life
to what's important to them
and there's this practice of
recollecting the sangha
and the buddha describes it this way
the sangha of the blessed ones disciples
who have practiced well
you have practiced straight forwardly
who have practiced methodically
who have practiced masterfully
so he's describing
this the sangha as these
disciples these followers
who have practiced
straightforwardly methodically
masterfully so he's referring to those
that have some meditative attainment so
i've
tasted
freedom
and so bringing to mind like yes other
people have been on this path before
and they have done this practice and
they have found some freedom
maybe we know people who we find
inspiring
we often we
know that it didn't just happen
overnight
but it's through the results of some
practice
but this is more specifically in the
tsutas there is this idea that
recollecting the sangha
being inspired by other people who
have
dedicated their life who have found
their way
to this practice
and that it brings some gladness to the
heart
some
uplift
the
polyurethamoja maybe some delight
and then last week i talked i talked
about the gladness penta
and i one so this recollection of the
sangha not only can we be like
influenced by those who
have gone before us and who have really
dedicated their life
but
this activity of recollecting them can
also
bring some joy some gladness some uplift
some
um
i don't know i find myself smiling when
i think about how many women
how many men
have
through the ages since the time of the
buddha
have dedicated their life and how many
have found freedom
and how many people have found freedom
as lay people as well right
so it doesn't have to be entirely
dedicating their life
but it brings a certain gladness
and then this gladness penthouse
of
gladness that
leads to joy
which leads to tranquility which leads
to happiness which leads to
concentrations or collectedness we might
say
and this flowing from one to the other
of this gladness
pentad
is another way and which can be a
support for new behaviors
this
the gladness joy tranquility happiness
concentration or
maybe concentration i could say
collectedness is a way also in which we
can kind of remain focused on
what is what we're doing here what our
priorities are what's important to us
so
an environment that's supportive
for
having new behaviors new activities new
things we want to do
being inspired by others
that have done this
being inspired in such a way that it
touches us
having some appreciation for people who
have found a way
people who
are teach others to
for themselves to find a way certainly i
have gratitude and appreciation for my
teachers
and then allow
this gladness
itself
to be a support
for practice not only for practice maybe
but for this
allow it to have this joy tranquility
and happiness
that leads to some collectedness and the
collectedness can be a support also
so in this way
we can think about new year's
resolutions like oh i'm you know
there's countless ones that we can do
right
but is there a way in which we can
actually think oh there's a dharma way
in which we can
use this as a support
for our new year's resolutions i've been
pointing to
support for developing a meditation
practice but many of the things that
i've been talking about here
can be applied to
other
new habits or behaviors we'd like to do
and then this way bringing the dorma to
new year's resolutions is that way also
we might kind of like meld or
knit together any divisions we might
have between okay this is ordinary
mundane stuff and this is dharma stuff
but is it is there really any need to
make a difference
maybe there's
no difference
maybe that's the
what we discover
with our practice
as there isn't
a time when the dharma is
on or off switch it on or off but
allowing it to blossom and permeate and
flow
in all areas of our life
and if we find that it's stuck and not
able to permeate certain areas
we could have some curiosity about that
what areas are we thinking that we
are excluding
what do we think that
needs to be separate
from our derma practice and
all the things that we're learning and
practicing and cultivating
so the dharma comes to new year's
resolutions
wishing you
a beautiful 2023.
thank you
you