so warm hello and I'm quite happy to be
both sitting here in my meditation posture and also to be here with all of you and
be able to share my meditation in a sense with you and do
this together so welcome everyone
the topic for this week's Dharma talks is
compassion and for those who meditate people who
meditate compassion the source of compassion or the reference point for compassion
is maybe very different than people most people who don't meditate
that I think when you when we do mindfulness meditation and discover how to really be present
for oneself so as not to be hindered by
doubt and ill will and desires and distractions to really learn how to sit here present
really present in the present moment with a sense of um well-being
or a sense of openness and kind of a groundedness in the present
that that groundedness in the presence in the sense of well-being that can come from that
sense of ease that can come from that that's the same
door the doorway for that the door that that opens is a doorway for compassion
another way another words compassion isn't something that
for if from that in Buddhist point of view it's something that comes along with or is built on
a deep sense of eat at ease that one has with oneself with one life
an ease that comes from not being caught in hindrances and cotton attachments and
clinging it's kind of like the the very
open presence that is the doorway for
well-being for oneself is also the doorway
for the compassionate concern or compassionate
response to the suffering of the world
and in the sense maybe that's one of the gifts of meditation practice
is to provide compassion with a kind of simplicity
or an absence of clinging an absence of hindrances an absence of the things that
get mixed up with compassion to cause distress
distressed compassion stress compassion so we'll sit here
uh with maybe if you wish with the idea
that we're opening up to our potential for
compassionate presence but we do it indirectly
that we're doing it by really being here curious interested
valuing with deep respect
for what it's like to be really here and present as if it's the doorway
to compassion the doorway to love without trying for it to be compassion
just stepping into the store away of Here and Now
so taking a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and taking a couple of moments here
to see if you could establish an attitude
of valuing
your embodied experience now
valuing being in the present moment
rather than being in a kind of virtual reality of ideas and thoughts
that are about the future or the past or fantasy
or about other places than right here
so an attitude of willingness
to be present here
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
as if you're breathing you're deep breathing is inviting you welcoming you
here in this body at this time
inviting you into the present moment and the long exhale
is a releasing a temporary releasing of your thoughts
and concerns and worries maybe imagining that you're putting
those things up on a Shelf and you can pick them up again after the meditation but for now
maybe you can accept the invitation the welcoming
to being here with this body at this time
and then letting your breathing return to normal
taking a few moments to relax your body further
the tensions of your face allowing them to soften
allowing the face to melt
as you exhale allowing the shoulders to soften
relax
allowing the shoulders to dissolve the tension that's there
softening the belly
giving some freedom to the belly
freedom to relax and hang forward hang down
to settle
and then as if you can take a loving hand and reach deep down inside of yourself
to the deepest place that's there in you to gently touch
with the deepest place that you can find and as you exhale
to relax the deepest places of tension
relax around the deepest places that you know you can feel
and then there's a can be a wonderful feeling that only is present in the
present moment which is a gentle tenderness softness Within
and perhaps you could now be tenderly aware
of your body breathing
or maybe the breath is tender and to hear being touched tenderly by
breathing
being touched differently by the inhale then the exhale
with the sensations of the body breathing
being a welcome an imitation for you
to be present for those experiences
noticing if your thinking mind takes you away from the present moment
takes you away from a deeper connection to hear to yourself
and if you notice that it does so and you can feel the difference between
being connected to yourself and not connected
choose being connected don't allow them thinking the
distractions to choose for you
choose to stay connected Here and Now do the body breathing
as you exhale relaxing the thinking muscle the thinking mind
softening the energy and the waves of thinking as if thinking are waves on the sea
let the waves quiet and listen
her present moment can be a door to discovering
he well-being sense of ease within you
not always easy to discover but maybe if you turn up the corners of
your lips a little bit for a little half smile quarter smile
perhaps it'd be a little bit easier to discover some feeling of well-being
however mild with being here and now
some pleasure and then to breathe with that well-being
let the well-being be whatever small it is to guide you
into a fuller connection to your body breathing
breathing with whatever sense of well-being or pleasure that might be here
in spite of whatever discomfort you might have notice what's too comfortable or
comforting Here and Now breathe with it
and as you breathe especially on the exhale let go of your thoughts
let the thinking mind become Stiller and more open and attentive
to hear and now
with the exhale settling in further into your
body into your being
with the exhale letting go into your
physical existence right now and on the inhale
to feel whatever goodness rightness
well-being might be
within you
letting go of striving and trying
more allowing yourself to feel and be present
allowing your body your breathing to come to you and
to Simply Let It Be
it might there be within you
someplace location for compassion
might there be some tenderness some warmth some love
within you however small and small hint
of something that feels a bit like the presence of
compassion a warmth
a kindness a love
something very simple that if it had words it would
wish you well and for you to be free of suffering
but it's so simple it has no words
it's just a attitude of feeling here
free of desires free of clinging a need
free of fear and worry
just a simple Inner Glow
of compassionate warmth wanting nothing
and for these minutes doing nothing just an attitude
breathing with that attitude having this attitude of compassion
guide you to a simple presence with the breathing
and then as we come to the end of this meditation
to feel perhaps your ability to be open and attentive and aware
of the world around you the people in your lives
people of your neighborhood and
in your wider community and across the lands
and then to see if the ten tender gentle attitude
of compassionate warmth warm compassion
that needs nothing is distressed by nothing just a warmth
just care a tenderness that's open
and have this attitude of Compassion Care love
warmth radiate from you
as if it could spread across the lands
that your compassion can be inclusive of all beings
breathing in and breathing out
and as we come there now to the very end of the sitting
to consider or to hold all beings
in your wish for their well-being may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe and healthy
may all beings be free
and may it be that on this day
that you share your compassion with someone else
very simple compassion maybe not with any words
but with your presence your attention your interest in them
your kindness your well-wishing
may all beings everywhere be happy
[Music]
so now in this continuing with this second talk on compassion karuna
um the so maybe as I said yesterday there are maybe many different definitions of confession and
maybe there are many forms of compassion as there are people
that compassion as wonderful it is and profound as it is we should be very careful not to put it
into like there's one thing we know what compassion is and um but even so in the range of what
compassion can be that the Buddhist idea of karuna
k-a-r-u-n-a has its own flavor its own particular way of being or aspect that's
I think quite worthwhile to learning and understanding this flavor of compassion
and um I don't know exactly if it's the case but I have been told or read that the
word karuna comes from the same root as the word karma meaning action
and um and that somehow in the pre-bootest time karuna referred to
something called sacred action a kind of special action which then
maybe the Buddha or the religious world of his time um uh you utilized to refer to something
that's close to what we call compassion but one of the characteristics of this
of the Buddha is this discussion about karuna is that he primarily talked about it as
something that's cultivated and experienced in meditation he had another word called anukampa
which was the expression of care maybe compassion that is translated into how
we act in the world act with Care Act with compassion but this very important word karuna as
primarily something that is cultivated in meditation discovered in meditation for many of us
and what makes that special I think is that meditation is a place where we're
settling in to discover how to be free of the hindrances
among other things to be free of ill will and to be free of compulsive desire
free of sloth torpor restlessness anxiety regrets and doubt
to be to discover how to not have any clingings to be deeply at ease and at
peace here and the whole experience of encountering suffering or being concerned with the
suffering of oneself and with others when the hindrances and clinging are not there or not in the Forefront not
complicating it gives compassion a very unique flavor
it's a compassion then that is free of tension free free of clinging
free of the distress that arises because of clinging and in particular one of the forms of uh
distress that can be born out of you know together with compassion out of contact with suffering
is related to all the ways in which we cling to self all the ways in which the
self is wounded or hurt or easily triggered or made of made frightened
and when this sense of self gets rectified gets harmonized gets softened
gets kind of dissolves in this wonderful field of
Good Will of meditation then um self and self-concern
self-preoccupation egotism is not it doesn't get tied up in
the compassion and so compassion then becomes free of
What's called the near enemy of compassion near enemy is
something that looks like compassion but isn't and sometimes it's called um pity
that we feel pity for people or certain kind of distressed feeling of
horror or alarm we really feel strongly motivated and concerned and caught in
the experience of suffering the suffering of others and we might call it and we worry about people and we might
call that compassion but maybe it's not quite compassionate looks like compassion but it isn't that kind of
karuna compassion this karuna that the reference point is this deep sense of
inner well-being and if we have that sense of well-being
and happiness within that comes from letting go of clinging and letting go of
self preoccupation then one of the kind of confusions
around compassion um uh is that if we're compassionate
we're altruistic that we we don't have any concern with
ourselves and we just give ourselves completely over to caring for other people as if we don't matter and it's
fine for us to stay up you know all night and exhaust ourselves and do it you know do whatever we can because
we're supposed to be compassionate but when the reference point is the source of well-being and meditation
then it becomes obvious that we're harming ourselves when we
don't give any attention to ourselves and so the compassion this karuna and
Buddhism is not an altruistic compassion but it's also not a selfish compassion
it's a compassion that kind of glow I like to think of it as as a glowing from
the inside from our heart outwards and it takes care of the first human
being that it encounters for glowing from the heart and the first
human being that this Compassionate Care encounters will be yourself
everything between your from the center of your heart outwards
and so that also is uh warrants this care This Love This Good Will this
wanting to you know to feel and uh to wanting well-being for you yourself
and it flows out from there because as we get centered nothing gets stuck
nothing gets limited these feelings these attitudes there's an openness that
is inclusive of the world around us and others but it's not the inclusion and a concern
for others where we lose touch with what's here because this karuna flows
from the heart through us out into the world and so the sense of well-being
in meditation for example that allows us to connect to the heart is the very well-being or openness the
well-being that allows us compassion to flow outwards and so one of the characteristics of
karuna that I mentioned yesterday is that it does not tied up in sorrow it's
not tied up in distress it doesn't we don't take it on as a burden but actually there's a feeling of
lightness or Sweetness in this even though the heart might be broken it
might be you know there's things my heart gets broken regularly with the
suffering of the world and what people tell me they've experienced in their life or what I read in the news or
anything and uh there have been times when I've sobbed after reading the news because of
what I see there but I don't feel that uh I'm distressed and I don't feel like that I'm upset or
that I feel sorrow exactly I just feel uh deeply like heartbroken and
maybe sad without sorrow or sorrow without sad a kind of feeling of
poignant feeling that has no clinging to it has not it's not self-preoccupation
it's not feeling sorry for myself or feeling distressed in myself I'm quite welcoming and willing to have
my heart broken and feel this kind of poignant kind of I don't know what to call that
sadness in the world but uh but it's not a it has no weight to it and and uh it has no I don't feel
like I'm suffering with it and so uh this compassion this karuna
that is not altruistic but is not self-centered
where we ourselves are as important to care for as anyone else and so there's a
balance then in the compassion with um kind of in self-care and other care
um the Buddhists tend not to like to use the word self-care because it's such a magnet for self-preoccupation and the
idea of self-centeredness is so powerful that even our language we probably should be
a little bit careful with so that we don't kind of it doesn't become a magnet for self-concern
but as we kind of can begin to discover this inner capacity for compassion the
karuna that comes from letting go of distraction clinging the hindrances and
as I keep saying for many of us it starts in meditation then
the very compassion is in a field in a context
of certain degree of Freedom or ease or absence of clinging that itself
supports all kinds of transformations and so compassion with compassion and
this deep letting go of the hindrances and selfishness
resentment can turn to forgiveness uh hostility can turn into friendliness
and anger can turn into kindness that compassion is a force
that prompts or encourages the movement of letting go further clinging why hold
on to anything when we keep hurting ourselves if we hold on to it jealousies
are holding on hostilities are holding on ill will is a whole holding on
and this combination of this connection to this deeper well-being and this
compassion is like a medicine or like a bomb that transforms uh these places
that are tough and hard inside of us and whether that's hostility to ourselves or to others whether it's
being destroyed you know angry with ourselves critical ourselves or others all the different ways we suffer if
we're deeply afraid or deeply hurt to meet that with this softness and
compassion and kindness and non-clinging to meet ourself
suffering with that part of us it's not self-preoccupied to be able to be present in a loving and
careful way and so the um
so one of the things that meditation does for many of us is that
it does help us meet our own suffering and it isn't this and partly really
knowing our own suffering helps us to understand the suffering of others better
but um and so that helps us to have compassion for them but uh it's also that as we understand
ourselves better we understand how we get uh how the complications that might
arise when we're encountering others when we give birth to the near enemies of of uh Compassion or the What's called
the far enemies of compassion which is um the horror or deep distress or even
the Far Far enemy of his cruelty and some people will respond to distress in
the world it's so painful and so unacceptable to be present for it they just want to push it away and sometimes
even in forms of Cruelty so um
so the reference point for karuna this particular kind of compassion
in the teachings of the Buddha is meditation practice and hopefully when we get over time as
we discover the freedom that comes with meditation and how that can give rise to a certain kind of compassion that's very
clean that maybe it's compassion that's kind of like a purified gold that's kind of
uh purified all the dross and all the impurities that can come along with it
then we understand that compassion doesn't diminish us compassion doesn't
is not stressful in and of itself that it's not sharing in the suffering
of others in the sense of feeling their suffering so we feel it the same way but rather it's uh feeling being with
their suffering with a tenderness and a care and a concern and empathy where we
are bringing this soft tender attitude of care and love to meet them and care
for people and support them and be their friends to be with them
and in this way it said that if you want to be happy
in your life be compassionate easier said than done but the reference
point for this little saying is this karuna that we
we discover or evoke or develop in the freedom from clinging the freedom from
the hindrances that the that meditation can lead to if we can really be present
here and if we can't be fully present here
then it's a wonderful thing to be compassionate for that to be caring and
loving for all the challenges we have and because sometimes it's through
compassion that we finally learn how to really be present here for our lived
experience so um I hope that you will
spend some time with uh thinking about exploring reflecting on the relationship
between compassion and the absence of clinging the absence of self-centeredness
but with the presence of self-love so thank you all very much