so good morning and welcome
those of you here to imc thank you for coming and uh
thank you for coming and wearing your masks now that i think uh the two places close closest
to us two counties now i have that one of the fastest surging of covid in maybe in the country
even san francisco and santa cruz i'm going to santa cruz today i think santa cruz has the highest at least in
california so um i'm going down there for the next two
weeks to teach a retreat and the retreat topic is on my mind we
usually are our our
retreats uh have themes that we make up just before the retreat starts to kind
of tie the teachings the practice together and uh
and so i kind of want to do it maybe for me it's my sake a trial run it's kind of what's my mind and so i'm gonna talk a
little bit about this and tell you in a few minutes what the actual theme is
but first i would like to tell a story from my life
when i was a zen student and that'll be illustrative of what i'm going to say more of
the so i lived at a green gulch zen center in marin county for
a while and as a new student there um
so i would go in many times a day into the meditation hall it was a big very big
it used to be a very big barn that they converted high ceiling and big rectangular building
and the way it was laid out you'd kind of go in from kind of from the back back door
and and you would go into the room and down some steps
and you come at the back of the altar and then you'd either go left and right and go
to sit in the main part of the room and and so there was an aisle then behind
the altar and if you were on the left side of the room and you wanted to go to the right side of the room you would
always walk behind the altar the rule was you never walked across the middle of the room in front
of the altar i think the idea that the buddha was in the altar and it was disrespectful to walk in front of the
buddha and so you would always walk all the way around and if you were in the deepest end of the
meditation hall and you wanted to get to the other you know just two to three feet the other side of that
magical invisible line you have to walk all the way around to get there
and as i was there uh sometimes uh there were reasons variety of reasons to
doing things whatever we did there in the room that i would get close to that
that line midline right down in the middle of the buddha's body
you know and i could feel my body would feel
i was approaching like a magnetic field or this force field as i approach that line
and my body with these little micro muscles in my body would be pulling me away or be activated so that inner
it wasn't conscious all this but it was kind of subconscious that was doing this and and so this feelings i had my body's
micro muscles and excite excited energy that would come or something as i approached that line
it kind of contributed to sense that there's a force field here and so i would you know the closer i got
that field more of this force field and then i would pull back
and uh so that went on for a long time but i didn't think about it too much
just what was and uh and then one day i was i knew i think it
was cleaning and back behind the altar was cleaning
and there were some tourists who came there's people who just wandered off off the street and we're just kind of
walking around to see what a zen center was like and they wandered into the meditation hall and
and they just wandered in and walked around and walked right through that line
and nothing happened no lightning struck they didn't get electrocuted and nothing
happened and at that moment i realized that that line was just a figment in my
imagination i mean i was told not to cross the middle line but uh the sense of a force field the
sense of this you know how my whole relationship to this line was just didn't exist
you know it was i mean the line didn't exist and and my relationship was something imaginary
to this it just all was made up by the mind and i'd lived what was made up in my mind as a thing
didn't really exist and but it had an impact on me and i behaved accordingly
so that was kind of fascinating to see you know how the mind can project
onto reality things that are not there and live as if it's there
and to some degree we do that with people we project power sometimes or qualities
onto people that may may not be there sometimes we
up the amplitude maybe of some of these qualities in people and make them bigger than they are and
and it's not uncommon to for people to go spend time with a spiritual teacher
to you know especially if a teacher has if they're really you know elevated
importance in people's minds and then just being in the presence of the teachers like wow i'm in this
wonderful field this force field it was this wonderful field of the teacher and there might be some some few things
coming from the teacher but it's elevated because of the same phenomena the mind is projecting and and imagining
and living as if this is real rather than unders not appreciating how much the mind is contributing to it
and assigning it to the teacher for example it's all kinds of things
so uh so this idea that the mind will contribute
to through its imagination to project onto reality things that are not there
or not there in the way that we're living them is a very important principle to understand buddhist the buddha's
teachings in relationship to ourselves
because we do it to ourselves in different ways and now that's that kind of the theme of
this retreat we're going to do with the buddha talked about five different ways
which we create this these things
these we divide ourselves into five different ways and each of those divisions by dividing
us we're dividing the wholeness of who we are and then we get attached to those
divisions and we put sometimes you put a lot of value or importance into these divisions
some people put more important than one of the divisions or some of the divisions more than other people do
but that projection this idea of this is where it's at this is important this is
where the force field is this is where i am this is my sense of who i am
and sometimes the sense of i am i exist
sometimes is another force field or another
something that's kind of the mind has projected onto reality this case the reality of this being here
and we live in that projection in all kinds of complicated ways and
we like it we don't like it we we don't you know we pull away from it we hold on to it we cling
and so beginning to appreciate how the mind does that is part of the function of mindfulness
practice the simplest way to in the buddhist teachings to understand this is that he
talked about this as being five areas where people cling
they get attached and these things are the word for this in pali the ancient
language is kanda k-h-a-n-d-a which
i think unfortunately the most common english translation is aggregates
so if you aggregates like you know make cement with aggregates and stuff
and um so you know i mean that doesn't sound very appealing you have five aggregates and you get attached to them
you know that for some of you probably as soon as you hear that your mind goes a little bit numb what is what are they talking about here
um the word kanda also means branches of a tree
so these are five branches it also means the trunk has both
meanings the trunk of a tree and the branches of a tree so
which which is really the tree is it the trunk is it the branch that goes off to the
right or the branch that goes off to the left which is the really the tree
and and or is it leaves at the end of the branches
no no really what's the tree is what you can't see it's the roots underneath that's really the tree
what's really the tree if we have five different opinions here but which is the really the tree
you could have a war this is the tree no no not the tree
and then why decide that any one thing is the tree why be attached to this has
to be the tree why not let the tree just be a tree
so we have these branches or we make these branches within the wholeness of who we are
and we can live in relationship to those and we can get attached
so the first one the buddha talks about is our appearance
the word is a rupa rupa in pali which often is translated as
the body or but the word more literally means
appearance it's what the one of the meanings is what the eye sees like so if i look down
at this bell the bell is the root bar because it's the sight object the object of sight
whatever the the what what but the fascinating thing about the word appearance
is that this appears to be a bell
is it really a bell well it's functionally it's a bell
but you know it could also be a begging bowl you know a
buddhist monastery could go around like this in the streets and people would recognize oh that's a begging bull
it could be a spittoon some buddhist teachers in
asia had these things about this size right next to them and it was kind of you know fascinating
to hear the middle of a dharma talk kind of clear their throat their loudest possible way and go
you know and spit into this spittoon
i don't know if could i get away with that here
and so this this is an appearance and so the our our appearance that we
have our physical appearance for example is a big part of it how our body appears to us
and this very important to understand how our body appears to us about instead of how our body actually is
because how it appears to us has a lot to do with the choices the mind makes select
selects about what's important about ourselves what we're focusing on
for some people like when i was a teenager probably one of the most important
appearances that i had that i was attached to was my hair
i had very long hair i had to worry about split ends
and uh and this was like a big thing you know the length of my hair and this and that
and probably probably during the day if i if i was thinking about my appearance that was mostly thinking about my my
hair and uh that's changed over the years and uh
so the so some people get very attached to their
appearance and some people their life is based on their appearance because a lot of their
life energy goes into doing that so i i don't know if this is fair it is but you know for example
bodybuilders some people are professional bodybuilders and that has a lot to do
with appearance there might be other reasons to be a bodybuilder but there are people who are very focused on their
physical appearance some people are more focused on their beauty or lack of beauty
than they are about the words they speak it's been a lot of time preparing you know
going out so that we can be beautiful or nice and going to salons and having the hair made
up or this and that they have beauty contests and some people i think make it their full-time
thing for a while to go to beauty contests some of this thing about the appearance
is very painful because our society makes definitions of what's the right way to be and appearance wise
in all kinds of ways in physical appearance and skin color race
height size all kinds of things and so the preoccupation with appearance
is not just because people have an inner disposition that way but society reinforces it
with a lot of suffering but we're still it's just a we end up with this
you know societally society participating
in creating these force fields in the middle of the meditational force fields
in the middle of our lives that now have heightened importance and value
and all kinds of dysfunctional activity can exist around this kind of thing around
appearance some of this concern with appearance is
a mind's creation sometimes a collective creation of many people in a society
and then people get attached to it and then there's the second thing that
the buddha said that people select out of the whole and they choose to highlight
and that is what in english in buddhist english is called feelings but it's not the emotions it's the
whether things are pleasant or unpleasant and some people are very focused on pleasure very focused on pain
and what's not unpleasant and within reason it's a reasonable thing
for human beings to be concerned with but you know to sit in a chair and be
uncomfortable and adjust it that's that seems fine but to
but to it's possible to select this thing about comfort and pleasure
and make it a primary orientation around how we live our lives some people spend much of their day
pursuing pleasure of all kinds of different types
or much of their day activated around feeling pain in some way pain is an unfortunate part of life
but to what degree is it selected out by the mind given more importance than it actually
is because of all the associations of what pain means and what's going to happen to me and the imagination into
the future and so pleasure and pain become for some people they're orient pri even a primary
orientation in their life and that's what you know what and so that becomes their force field that
becomes their what they cling to and so
and then there's the in the and the third one has to do with our
perceptions of things our recognition of things or ideas of what is
and this is a very the simplest ideas of of things that the mind makes
and some people their opinions their stories their ideas of how things are
becomes uh what's most interesting for them most what they're focusing on
simple ideas of right and wrong simple ideas of of
beauty and ugliness simple ideas of of um
roles we have identities we have and so
having the right ideas being able to recognize what's happening in terms of the world around us and
organizing according to ideas we have is how some people feel safe some people find their way
and so some people are very focused on perceptions and ideas and concepts
because concepts is what kind of you need to have in place to
be safe or get around and so some people that are very attached to ideas to
concepts like a concept of roles concepts of identity the concepts of
you know what should be in society and how other people should be
the fourth fourth area the buddha talked about is the the mental the world
inner mental world that that does all this constructing that
does all this imagining that does all this prioritization so when i was in that meditation hall
there was the mind was imagining this line
the mind was imagining what would happen if i got zapped by walking close to it and so i was living a deliberate life
in relationship to something my mind had created and so the fourth area was this area of
kind of deliberate construction stories ideas intentions plans
memories and stuff that you know complicated inner world that we construct
so the inner constructions that we make spending stories is a nice way of seeing it all the inner stories
we make and live in and some people get attached to that they attach to their memories attached
to ideas of the future and these loom are really big
and for some people that's where they get kind of bogged down or there's kind of the the it gets things get narrowed
into that world and then the fifth one that we have talked about
uh this division of the whole is the consciousness
that is aware of it all all the rest of it that which knows
that this is happening that's what knows this is a this is hearing this is seeing this is
smelling this is tasting this is the tactile sensations this is the mind activity that i see
and for some people that's what they get attached to and people who do a lot of meditation
sometimes that get really attached to consciousness because that everything else falls away
everything else you begin to see is rising and passing coming and going quiets down
and it doesn't seem like something to be so attached to but for some people consciousness seems
to be the ultimate thing the final thing you know i'm not i'm not all these
things i'm not the world i'm not my body i'm not my thoughts i'm not my beliefs
but we'll select consciousness as a thing to be this is who i am and that begins
having the projection that has people orient around that as being important and it's not some people or
their very sense of being existing is invested into consciousness so
consciousness will continue after i die so it's okay i'm safe
and so i need to know who i am and i know that i'm consciousness and it's very comforting because consciousness
is not the world not the things in the world so it's a place of safety and can't be touched
something like that so i'm not saying that all ideas like that are wrong but the point i'm trying to make today
is the way in which the whole of who we are gets divided into these different realms
and that once once that division is made each of these five branches
can be a place of attachment of clinging and for the buddha
it's not that we were supposed to not make these branches
necessarily the buddha was interested in how we overmake them
have too much focus on them and then get attached to them and he's and um and so there was uh
and for the buddha said that the way the way people are identified for the you know the way people are
apprehended the way people are observed is based on
uh where their mind dwells and if it dwells
on any one of these five areas then people are reckoned or measured or understood
by that way so if
if you spend a lot of time with your physical appearance
then you're not you're kind of recognized you're measured by that because i've seen people where wow that person's
really put a lot of work and effort into it day after day workout you know that's you know this is that's the person who's
really puts a lot of care into their appearance so that understood that almost like that
becomes their identity and with each of the other four when there's a really attached to that
then people the buddha said people are reckoned or understood through that category so it's not just
that we understand ourselves that way but that's how other people end up understanding them
as well so then we come to this wonderful little teaching
in relationship to all this and now that i've prepared the ground
the buddha had a friend who was a king king
and one day the king wanted to hear some teachings from some really wise person
and the buddha wasn't around and some of the other monks weren't around and so he was asking her you know who should
i go listen to and one of his advisors said oh there's this very wise nun buddhist nun
named kemah venerable kema
and uh she is really wise you should go visit her and he said great i'll go visit kema
so he did and he asked her a question which uh i think was a big preoccupation
for some other people in ancient india it's a preoccupation that maybe some of
people here in the modern west have as well is what happens when we die
do we get or do we somehow get reborn do we go to heaven is there any kind of content
continue continue continuation of us after we die or is
this life the only thing we have and we know and when we die you know
it's all over it's done what is going on here
and so people would come to the buddha and ask him questions like this and so the buddha came to came this king
came to kemah and she asked this common question you see in the suttas
um [Music] so he starts
does the buddha exist after death will the buddha exist after that
and i think to ask about the buddha because the buddha was kind of one of the most respected spiritual teachers of
his time not just because he had a lot of knowledge but he had
attained something very important attained the highest states of humanity that they knew of back in ancient india
and so what happens to the buddha maybe you know if if the buddha
exists after life that tells me something about what i can expect or something
so does the buddha exist after death and the nun she said
the buddha has not declared this the buddha has not claimed that he exists
after death then reverend lady
does the buddha not exist after death
great king the buddha has not declared this either
then reverent lady does the buddha both exist and not exist after death
great king the buddha has not declared this then remember lady does that the tagatha
neither exist nor not exist after death great king the blessed one has not
declared this and the king is a little bit exasperated like that's all the possibilities that are
so you know what how does this work what's going on here
and so she says to the king well i will ask you a question
about the same matter answer it as you see fit what do you think great king
do you have an accountant or a calculator or a mathematician who can count the grains of sand in the
river ganges thus there are so many grains of sand there's so many hundreds of grains of sand there
are so many hundreds of thousands of grains of sand and the king says no i don't have anyone
who can count all the grains of sand do you have an accountant or calculator
a mathematician who can count the water in the great ocean thus there are so many gallons of water there
are so many hundreds of thousands of gallons of water no
reverend lady for what reason because the great ocean is deep
immeasurable hard to fathom so too grey king
that form that appearance by which one describing the buddha might describe
him has been abandoned by the buddha cut off it cut off at the root
made like a palm stump obliterated so that there's no more subject to
future arising the tathagata great king is liberated from
reckoning in terms of appearance he is deep immeasurable heart a fathom
like the great ocean and then he does the same thing these other five branches
that the people people will measure or see the buddha by
appearance by the feelings by perceptions by these mental constructs constructions and
consciousness but that the buddha has cut off now if we understand that these are
really parts of who we are what do you mean and uh
uh you know cut off appearance cut off feelings cut off perceptions
construct i mean that's who we are isn't it so that just then you don't exist
i think i understand this is the buddha has let go of any clinging
in any constructing of these force fields of these lines in the
meditation hall in relationship to ourselves the buddha is not
creating a sense of self idea through
what we will call appearances is not involved in the world of appearances in an ordinary way
not not involved in creating importance and creating a world around feelings
around perceptions around stories and mental constructions in even around consciousness
there's some dramatic way in which that tendency of human beings have has been let go
put aside and in doing so what is the buddha
and and she's the nun says uh he is deep immeasurable hard to fathom
like the great ocean so maybe that's your who you are
hard to fathom like the deep ocean
like you know as we have climate change and drought here in california and
technology improves and they're learning to harvest electricity from the tides and the waves
at some point we might move underwater that's the only place we'll survive
and then what we'll do is we'll you know we have you know we divide the property here in bay area you know part
b people have you know live in properties and some people live on properties that are
500 square feet some bigger you know so imagine that everyone will divide up the ocean
uh into maybe one acre blocks
square one acre square and we'll all buy squares in the ocean
and we'll have our underwater home in our square and people in the future will say what's the ocean oh the ocean is this place
that's built by all these blocks of properties and all these have these lines in them
and those lines like people fight over the lines and they have to get surveyors to come and get the right line and how
could you have crossed my line and above me there's people below those people you know because i have these blocks right
we've divided up the ocean
is that what the ocean is blocks of property owned
but right now we have this beautiful nearby for us here the pacific
deep immeasurable i go to the ocean sometimes the edge of it and watch and i marvel that it's been there for a long
time humans come and go civilizations come and go and
and those waves been lapping up on the shore kind of the waves have been
crossing the ocean for a billion years billions of years and
the depth of it been there for a long time it's deep it's immeasurable
what a sad thing it'd be if we divide it up into these lines and blocks and think that that's real
and fight over it what if our lives
what if we allow our lives to be immeasurable undivided
not attached to these things for the buddha his freedom
was to no longer live in these branches like with one branch being at the tree
but maybe being just the whole tree or maybe not even the tree
is the tree separate from the soil from the other trees
the birds that come to it the nests that grow in it is it separate from the clouds and the
rain that comes down and the temperature and the sun
is it necessary to divide the world before humans came along
was it divided
certainly functionally it makes sense to divide and i think it's human human
minds will divide to find their food and eat and find the toilet
because if you don't it's a mess but the uh
but uh so it has some usefulness but do we cling to it do we
add more that's needed is there a way of living in an undivided
world where we are undivided with it as well
immeasurable deep where we cannot be reckoned because to
reckon who we are is to make a
invisible constructed line down the middle of something
so is there another way of living a being so one of the functions of this
meditation practice is to help us put to rest at least temporarily
some of the divisions we live under some of the ideas and constructs and prioritizations and choices we make this
is important this is what it's about and to have an experience of
i want to say ourselves but even not even of ourselves just an experience of being alive
that doesn't have to be defined by anything it doesn't have to select anything
from the suchness the fullness the wholeness of whatever that whatever
it's here and what a big difference it is to know that that's possible
to know that this too is a is a refuge
it puts a little question mark behind the way we normally live our lives
so that we don't give too much importance to it it's important our life's important
we care for others through some of these divisions so it's but to not raise them not solidify them
not say it has to be this way but to be fluid and free and to pick up
them pick up some of the divisions some of the ideas pragmatically functionally when they're useful and be ready to drop them
and um when they're not useful to live a life
so this division these five divisions is the is one of the very important teachings
of the buddha because this is for the buddha this is the areas where people cling
and if we want to be free we let go of that clinging
and what and who are you when you've let go of clinging like that
that the buddha doesn't declare he's not going to tell you who you are
isn't that great just like he doesn't tell people who he is
and maybe if you allow me to tell you a little bit who you are maybe then you're whole
and a whole hole with what hole with a hole
what is the whole i don't know
but we find out by not making it into anything
so may you maybe reflect a little bit about this
teaching and and maybe there are ways that you also live with
imagine lines down the middle of your life that
have had some influence on you a force field on you or something that maybe
you know someone will snap the fingers and poof you realize wait a minute
that doesn't really exist and maybe you'll be you can be free
so thank you very much
and one announcement i have is that next week i'm because i'm on retreat for these next two weeks we have a guest
teacher coming a um vanessa able is her name she's a
wonderful uh zen teacher his auntie priest from the local zen center in kanando in
mountain view and she's i've gotten to know her because she's been very much involved with the supporting and
kind of almost a colleague with the trainings that my involvement with buddhist chaplaincy i train people in
buddhist chaplaincy and she's been involved in this world and so she's a wonderful
person that i think you're in for a treat when she comes next week if you're here
so thank you