so hello everyone and welcome
so
humans spend a lot of time thinking and to get
lost in thought absorbed and thought preoccupied with thoughts does not help the process of meditation
of waking up really being present here
and so becoming wise about our thinking world our thinking life
is really essential for becoming a proficient meditator or
if not proficient uh someone who delights in meditation
and and so one thing that can help very much
is to be able to recognize when you're thinking
is thinking stories when you're telling yourself stories
about something or if you're a visual kind of person you have a whole scene in front of you
that's playing itself out with characters and conversations
that uh telling us a story it's a narrative about something
something happened some fantasy and if you could recognize
the narrative thinking the story making mind when it's happening
and simply let go of that letting go of your thing all your
thinking might be too high a bar to quiet the thinking mind entirely
but you simply and maybe lovingly kindly
don't let yourself continue telling you a story and one way to do that
is to recognize clearly this is a story
this is me telling a story this is a narrative of fantasy of memory of planning
anticipation whatever it might be it's a story
and um and stories are are narratives that take time
or involve a certain kind of time and a signing of meaning to events that are happening
so simply recognize story as a way of
not necessarily stopping telling the story but no longer
placing yourself telling the story no longer committed to the story
well that's a story and then return to the breathing
return to the present moment enter the world of the present
over and over again stories take you away from that so learn to so to become proficient in
meditation learn to recognize stories in the mind
when they begin when they're happening and for today make it a particular theme of the
meditation not with stress or strain but
see if you can have a heightened sensitivity to when you start thinking stories
and then recognize that oh that story that story some of you might have to
recognize it every 20 seconds some of you there might be more gaps between the next story when it arises
doesn't really matter what matters for this exercise is that you recognize it
in fact maybe if it happens regularly then um you might actually get better more benefit from this rather than being
discouraged maybe you can be incurs oh yeah story story and then come back to the
breathing and maybe in doing this maybe that
supports the mind for the mind to quiet
become quieter and stiller so
taking a meditation assuming a meditation posture
and gently lowering your gaze
and gently closing your eyes
and in a gentle way not too ambitious take a little deeper breaths than usual
so that you're entering into the experience of breathing
you're participating
and let yourself ride the exhale breathe in deeply
and ride the exhale ride the letting go
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and participate some more with your breathing by feeling your inhale
and as you exhale relax different parts of your body
as you exhale settle in here
and then letting your breathing become the center of your attention
letting your awareness be the companion of your breathing
gently accompanying
breathing in accompanying yourself breathing out
accompanying yourself
when you accompany your breathing
and if you find yourself involved in a story
take the time to recognize oh that's a story that's storytelling
and then begin again with your breathing
maybe as you exhale relaxing the thinking muscle
okay
so
are you thinking and is your thinking
involved with storytelling
so
instead of telling stories accompany your breathing
as if you're accompanying a good friend on a walk
who needs you just to be a silent companion present
but not talking about things
so
there is the mind that's involved in stories in their minds and there's the mind that
doesn't two different ways the mind operates
for meditation stories are not needed
stories are not needed to be with what is
as it is
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
now you can use your storytelling mind
to tell yourself a simple story
of yourself starting your day or continuing your day
and the people you might have some connection with
because you pass them on the street or people with who live with you
that work people you'll communicate with over
email or some other way
people that you read about in the news
there's a story here of you and them and
how would you like to relate to them
perhaps coming out of meditation it's a wonderful time to consider
what it's like to relate to others with friendship with friendliness
to think and consider how wonderful it is to
bring friendliness into the world
and part of this story is that for you to
wish that unto the world
to wish greater friendliness for everyone
may the way that you walk through the world today
may it to known in unknown ways spread
friendliness and safety
may it spread a sense of peace and acceptance
may how we walk through the world be one walking with care
kindness
with wisdom may it be that this practice we do
is for the welfare and happiness of everyone may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
[Music]
um
so continuing this week's topic of the relationship between emotions and
thinking thinking and emotions and
one of the ways that sometimes we live is we tell the story of our day to a friend
that we might see and imagine that the friend sees you and
says tell me how was it at work today
and maybe you know maybe not for you but just imaginary ideas someone said someone says tell me how it
was at work today but tell me about the challenges you had with your boss
and oh that boss of mine oh that boss is always so demanding and so angry and i
can never do enough i can never do it right and there's so much disrespectful and
and and i have some ideas and that the boss takes the ideas and makes it
their own and not you know and i don't get any credit and and um i'm delegated to the back room
and so as we tell this story there's more anger there's more depression or just despair like oh this
is terrible but then imagine that the friend said
tell me about your day at work what did you learn about patience today
how do you learn to be how did your ability be patient improved today
and then you might say oh well i have a difficult boss but
so many times during the day when the boss was demanding or did something i was able to um breathe deeply and just
relax not buy into my tension and my anger and i was able to stay calm with it all
and i was able to manage the situation so much wiser with a calm and i had much more patience and then
when i was working with a colleague who was really slow in doing the tasks
that i needed the colleague to do i found myself more patient and that was really good because later i
found out that my colleague was dealing with a d big really big personal issue
someone in their family had died recently and i was so glad i was able to be patient
so that's a different story and and the emotions of telling that story uh would probably be very different than
the first one if the person said to you for your day
to how was your day and um can you tell me uh i'd love to hear a little bit about uh what uh what
brought you joy today and delight oh yes it was so nice that
you know to watch some of my colleagues uh work together and collaborate and they were
so creative and so supportive each other and so kind and we don't do that much of my job and but to watch it across the
room and and see how respectful they were of each other that
was like a highlight of my day and i if i got a reminder it's possible to be this way with each other
so what i'm trying to convey here is that we can tell the same story more or less
with different themes different purposes different things that we emphasize
and depending what we emphasize will have a different emotional response to it
the tone of voice the body language everything the feelings inside the emotions that come
depending on what we emphasize and what happens to many of us human
beings is that we're telling stories a lot and but we don't we're not so conscious
of the choice we've made for what we're emphasizing in the story
some people are emphasizing how everything is wrong and a lot of their stories have to do with complaining
some people are emphasizing how
how everything impacted me and you know i'm the victim to everything and it's so hard
uh some people are telling the story from the point of view of of um
a lack there's not enough here there's i mean it's so it's an infinite number of ways of stories of a day a situation can
be told and if we tell the same story over and over again or the same
always the same focal point that we're emphasizing in each story then we're going to reinforce
the inner emotional life the inner disposition that we have
and we might not be aware of how much conditioning influence
the stories have on who we are and how we are
and these are stories we say out loud to our friends and people and uh
stories we tell ourselves and often especially when we tell them ourselves but often
we're kind of living the story or the stories are an expression of
of of our emotional life and what we think is important or
how we're feeling anytime so if we're angry if there's aversion
then a lot of the stories can be aversive stories what's wrong what's wrong what's wrong
if we're hurt if we have a deep sadness or hurt it might still be angry because we're kind
of recoiling from the hurt and we want someone to blame and so we're looking the story is a lot of blame
on the victim stories and someone someone has been the perpetuator you know as it has done bad to me
and so some of these stories have aspects of truth to them
and that makes it more complicated because then we think that well it's true and so then it's i'm justified in
telling the story the way it is but truth is varied it you know truth is thematic
how we tell one story depends on the angle we take on it
so if we tell the story from the point of view of what did i learn today
versus how was i hurt today will tell the story differently they're both kind of true
but which is better for you which has a better influence on you
if you tell the story of how you were kind today
that's a different story than if you go home and tell a story oh i was mean
today and i'm always mean and i can never not be mean and this is hopeless for me
but if you tell the story how it was kind today then maybe you'll notice oh yeah there was a moment today where i opened the
door for someone i guess i'm not always mean
so to tell to be sensitive that we're biased
we tell our stories in biased ways and select we select how to tell our stories
and when we re illuminate we tell the same story over and over again or use the same bias to tell the story the same
angle to tell it it can reinforce our inner life and reinforce our dispositions our emotional life and how
we feel what we do it's hard to change the ocean liner make
it go a different way but it is possible to start recognizing what is actually happening
and one of the ways to begin that is to start becoming
skilled at recognizing oh that's the story that's telling a story
there's a story you can do that in meditation but you can do that in daily life as you're going about you can do stories in
your you know see notice your thinking and story making notice how much it's happening
once you notice how much it's happening then spend some time
investigating your stories some of you might actually write them down in a journal tell the story in a
journal and then see it on paper and then look at what is the angle that i'm using
to tell the story what is it what what kind of self am i
in this story am i a self that has agency or am i a self who is a victim
am i a self that uh has rights and needs to demand for my my
rights or myself who has uh can you know has a sense of confidence
oh man i'm just making things up in it i don't want to imply anything here but uh but you know look and see the themes
the what what how your stories tend to go and consider not to make a pollyanna
story but consider are there realistic alternative perspectives to look at the
same thing perspectives it doesn't deny there's been difficulty but perspectives that you become a
better person support you helps you become more free more kind
it helps you become wiser helps you engage in this situation in a way that's better for everyone
and so one perspective that i i like for stories if you're trying to problem-solve and figure out what's
happening or something is ask the question um
what is best here for everyone involved as opposed to what's best for me
what's best for that person what's best for everyone involved and um and then maybe that story
it will help living a life that supports everyone self included
so so stories they're very important part of human
life sometimes i think that we shouldn't be called homo sapiens we should be called
homo historians because probably
stories are such a powerful characteristic of human life maybe animals tell stories but the creativity
and the ways we can do it disassociated from reality um and the impact stories have on our
inspiration our faith our confidence our lack of all these things and and
our sense of purpose and meaning is huge it's huge these things
and um and so to become wise about stories
and in meditation to the degree to which you become really
quiet and still with thinking very still and quiet
one of the values of that is to help us see with greater clarity
the stories that we live by and when we see them
let us become wise about that part of our life so that we are not
unduly our emotional and inner life is not unduly and unhelpfully influenced by
the stories we tell so um
thank you and um i hope that today is an interesting day
and looking at your stories and and
if you have someone to have a conversation with stranger or friend or someone
you might have a conversation about what the role stories have have for you
stories have in your life kind of become wiser about this whole topic of the storytelling mind
thank you