here we are good morning I am cesanga I needed to refresh my own YouTube it's
wonderful to see you all morning
happy to see so many familiar names rolling in and your greetings from all
over the place it's really inspiring to be here with so many people doing this practice
it's a delight so
good morning all the topic for this morning is varia
energy or effort and um
just want to mention that it's part of a five-part series many of you have been
to the other parts of the series this week which is on the bay seeds or
roads to spiritual power and meditative success
so we'll start with a guided meditation invitation is to
enjoy the chat rolling in if you are and while you're doing that to settle into your body maybe weave
back and forth a little like I'm doing feel your weight
forward and back side to side and come to balance
come to balance in the center [Music]
and um can be helpful to start with one or two
intentional breaths a little bit longer a little bit slower
and letting go of any excess gripping or tension
on the out breath
you know if you are ready to close your eyes
and go inward and tune in notice how the body is today
this moment any places of
holding the review vaccination
any vibrancy or energy
softness relaxation
and the other stray and Sensations
noticing this whole body
allowing the breathing to settle into normalcy
end of the breath is a good anchor of attention for you
the invitation is to settle settle your attention there rest there
while very intentionally placing
attention awareness mindfulness at the Forefront
allowing concerns and other experiences anything then and
there to fade off into the background
foreign
making the intention for this time together in meditation
continued to return to this moment
a light touch or firm placing
of the heart and the mind and the body
now
noticing the details of what is arising
maybe ambient sounds Where You Are
the Myriad sensations of breathing and through the aliveness of the whole body
and bringing a sense of Interest
devotion
engagement to the details of each in-breath and out
breath each arising
noticing if the mind is wandering away
and if so with just as much effort as is necessary
returning allowing this moment to be predominant
foreign
from time to time noticing if the mind is drifted away
the attention has become loose and reattuning to the moment
and also noticing if the mind has constricted or gotten too tight
and they're so softening allowing
in the moment
foreign
a little moments of this meditation
reflecting on any calm or peace
any goodness kindness or pleasure
even the smallest moment that may have emerged during this practice
and if it feels right to share it
offer it outwards to the others in your life
so that it may grow in the sharing
casting your mind's eye towards those who share your days
people and creatures
and offering the wish may they be safe
may they be happy
may they be healthy peaceful and free
foreign
[Music]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
foreign
[Music]
thank you
so good morning again sound good I see some notes about refreshing
uh YouTube in the chat and just want to mention that we are
broadcasting via Zoom that may have a little bit to do with it so
if you're a patients with the technology that brings us together and sometimes
cause those little glitches these are all recorded they will be
uploaded most of them will be uploaded on Thursday I think
they are available on YouTube they will be available on audiodarma.org as well
so Sanga the topic for today
is um balanced effort energy perseverance
so just a brief recap effort or energy is one of the key
components of these bases of spiritual power of meditative prowess that the
Buddha practiced before his Awakening and each basis has kind of a tripod of
qualities in it one is samadhi what I've been calling immersion or
collection sometimes known as concentration or stability
padhana engagement and in this case of Veria
effort so three main points this morning first varia of fruit or energy has a range of
intensity second it's helpful to balance
adapt that energy that effort throughout practice and for that matter throughout any activity
and third there's one kind of effort so important to the teaching that it
sometimes taught by the Buddha as a fifth basis and that is perseverance or persistence
so very effort
is a Continuum that's reflected in different translations of it depending
on the context so just want to invite you to feel in your body
how things feel these words feel these different nuances of interpretation
and maybe notice any associations that come up with this word cloud
heroic effort
heroic energy strength
courageous effort vigor
perseverance
balanced effort continuous engagement
gentle persistence light touch
and receiving or allowing
so feeling those in your body feeling those in
your mind your heart and no one is better than the other at
different times in meditation practice each one of them has an appropriate place a helpful place
the key is to take an Adaptive approach fluid flexible to how effort and energy
come up in this practice the Buddha likened this process to
tuning a stringed instrument like a loot it's the example used in in the ancient
Indian texts but these days it might be more like tuning a guitar or violin or
banjo it's worth noting that with these stringed instruments
changes in the weather will change how the tuning needs to
happen the appropriate amount of um turning required to get a good
pressure the same is true for different meditation conditions which are kind of
like the weather right there's a tuning or odd tuning to the appropriate amount of energy that's a
little bit different each time we sit down to meditate and throughout the course of a meditation
there's also in the course of a meditation maybe different phases for many of us
it can be like running or riding a bike on a hill courageous effort vigorous
effort is required to get moving and on the flats once
pedaling has gotten some momentum it's okay to Coast
and then downhill you can just enjoy the momentum
speeding right along cuddling gets easier lighter and lighter
touch sometimes hands off completely just to allow the flow to happen
and this relates to the engagement patana
I want to be lightly touching the handlebars keeping tabs on where we're going
maybe the break to moderate the speed and enjoying the immersion the
intentness the samadhi that flow
so that's one simile or example of how varia energy effort can work with these
two complementary qualities another important way of adapting energy
and effort is to notice what's being cultivated with it and this
goes back to what we talked about yesterday which is noticing
or akusala skillful or unskillful application of effort
the Buddha talks about this in a teaching called the four great efforts which I'm just very briefly going to
mention they're called wise exertions why why is engagement
or padanas that same word in brief it's to prevent the unskillful
the rising in the mind and heart to abandon it if it's arisen to cultivate what's good and skillful
and then to maintain that those are the four sometimes this involves
backing off if we're Tangled Up In aversion or or frustration
grating of the teeth furrowing of the brow that kind of thing other times it can be
a total Act of courageous effort place the attention where it's useful
and move it off of where it's not useful so it's a range right
finally one kind of effort is so important to this teaching on spiritual power that it sometimes caught taught as
a fifth basis and that is the poly is um
Usso L with a DOT under it h i and this translates in many ways
sometimes even as enthusiasm or Vigor but the translation I like the
best is perseverance persistence it's this staying with the meditation
practice over the Long Haul keeping coming back
staying engaged not too caught up in outcomes
it's like keeping on keeping on in a long journey
this kind of perseverance persistence is just vital
to successful powerful meditation practice over the Long Haul
and the Buddha talks about it in different ways in different teachings but it's that stick-to-itiveness
you know any one given meditation session might be beautiful or not but it's the accumulation
all of these sessions over days or months even years or decades that add up
so effort energy is Central to this teaching on the spiritual power
and um so much so that each that the overall
basis of success contain these three related Concepts varia effort or energy
the wholehearted engagement and sometimes this special shout out to
persistence perseverance so it's kind of layered in there in three different ways
so I just want to encourage you to pay a special attention this week to the
tuning of effort the adaptation of energy and what the purpose is that you apply
effort or exertion for
so in the next 24 hours you might notice what kind of effort energy
engagement are helpful in your activities or your meditation you might jot down notes talk with a friend
and explore explore how it comes
so thank you thank you all for your attention thank you for your practice
and look forward to being back with the YouTube online sun god tomorrow
foreign