well so there's what song Go means to me and there's probably what the formal
definition of Sangha is in the formal definition of Sangha from the time of the Buddha it really meant
the community of enlightened monks and nuns who had um sort of gone to the home become
homeless right to that all they do is have their robes and their arms bowl and
they live off of food that's given to them day by day
and they sleep in parks and things where they're they're invited to sleep
um and that was initially the term how what it meant and the word Sangha is one
of um or Sangha is one of what they call the three gems there's three gems in the the Dharma one
is the Buddha the teacher the second is the Dharma the teaching the the teacher
you know what the lessons the practices and the third is the community
the Sangha the community and you know we don't have many monastic
nuns and monks in our day and many of us who are teaching now are not uh where we
live you know lives where we have homes and jobs and so it's life has changed a lot the
community has changed a lot here in the United States um I guess that never really was that way
so it didn't change here but it has evolved and um so now I use the term song God to
represent spiritual friendship and the people who come you know to IMC
when we come together we create a Sangha and it is that Sangha that
um created the space it made it happen so that's what I mean
you want to add anything Diana that was great I just thought I would uh
yeah it's a good one I actually um just last night I had written up a document for submitting on something and
Gil said do you think maybe you should Define the word Sangha
so so it's a theme Gill stole my thought
hi Anne Rose good to see you so are we ready to meditate
great so I thought the way that I would um give instructions is sort of a
combination of telling you and walking you through it
so when we when we when it's time to meditate these are some of the things
I've taught been taught to do or I do and so I'm just going to sort of you
know there's we all find our exact own way so this is not like I'm not telling
you the exact thing that every person does here but I'm telling you things that are taught a lot and you can adapt
in a way that works for you if that makes sense and so also I'll give you instructions but I also want to give you
permission to adjust the instructions so if I say a word that
doesn't land right to you or I invite you to try something and you're like no
please trust what's right for your practice
so the first thing is kind of this decision we're going to meditate
I'm going to be mindful so that's really the very first thing we're going to sort of make this choice
and one posture we can be mindful in is sitting which is what we're all choosing
to do tonight so we're gonna bring awareness into
sitting down and the posture that we take and
you know think about what how you might be sitting right now
if you were about to meet with someone important
how would you show up how would you feel what would your posture be
if this was somebody important you were going to connect with
there's a little bit of extra lift right a little bit of
I don't want to use the word formal but a little bit more upright
in our posture because we're interested and we want to be respectful too
so guess who we're gonna show up for like this ourselves
we're important our our awareness is important
so finding a posture for eating feeling the feet supported by the Earth
the sit bones supported by our cushion or chair our backs are upright
and feel into your body feel it sitting here we want to be comfortable too
and so take a moment to see if you need to adjust your posture in any way
it's great to do that that's right back and forth on the sit
bones you might Lean Forward lean back
you might bring your shoulders up and roll them back to help open the
chest for breath ah
and feeling maybe feeling that there's more a sense
of weight you're more connected to gravity as you bring your awareness inward
and into the seating
the next thing that can be helpful it's like inviting a mindset that will
support us in our practice so I'll mention a couple of qualities
faith and inspiration
so as we show up can we have faith that this is important
that for whatever reason we got ourselves here we wanted to be here
and we don't know exactly what's going to happen in the next hour and a half but can we stay connected to a sense of
inspiration and faith that it's worthwhile
you might if you have a reason for being here you might connect with
that like I want to suffer less
or I want to have more freedom from my thinking
where I want to be able to respond differently to my emotions
or I want freedom I want to be liberated
the next quality I'll invite you to connect with is the quality of being
interested curious or receptive
being curious about how this is going to unfold because no meditation no two
meditations are the same and the journey here
is to stay present awake to what's happening
in our direct experience curious about the next sensation
sound thing that arises
were often taught that it's helpful to have some sort of an anchor
some sort of a way to help ourselves not get lost in thought
an anchor just like an anchor for a boat helps the boat not
drift out to sea or crash up onto the shore an anchor in meditation
helps us to stay as close as we can to the present moment
and it could be sound breath
or Sensations in the body most often
it's the breath but we all find
what's easiest for us to connect with in a way that helps us
stay here
paying attention on purpose
in the present moment
to whatever you can sense into what you can experience
right here right now
and just like the ocean has waves we have thoughts they will come
and sometimes we'll get moved around by them Carried Away by them
that's the nature of a mind that thinks it's not a problem
but is it possible for the period of this practice
to prioritize being with our direct experience
overthinking about
over planning over conceptualizing
can you let thoughts just happen and be an experience
without getting carried away by them
agreeing or disagreeing with them
over and over again we might just invite ourselves
to reconnect with our anchor our breath
we might try what we call a noting practice
that might be something like saying in with the inhale
and out with the exhale
very simple noting
and as you breathe in
out feeling and knowing the sensations of breathing out
you might try noting by just saying the word now
helping your mind Orient to this moment or hear right here
in this In This Moment in this body
or even this is saying what
happens in your own experience experimenting with curiosity a little
bit with these different ways of noting and seeing what happens inside of you
how does your mind respond
this is about learning learning how to be aware and with your
mind not controlled by it
and not wrangling with it either
just here
just now
and if the mind is busy thinking it might be possible
to just sort of breathe through the thinking just letting the thinking happen and
still feeling the breath still knowing now
the mind can have thoughts it's okay
and you can be right here just now just this
breathing right through it right with it
paying attention on purpose
and giving preference to our direct experience
direct experiences the feeling of breathing The Sounds
you're hearing Sensations in your body
the Mind might be just making little thoughts
it can be like little clouds in the sky just
floating around doing their thing
and we can be like the sky
this guy doesn't care if there's clouds
it's wide and open spacious
it's patience
just breathing here
letting the thoughts be thoughts the sensations be Sensations
just letting things be you don't have to try and control them
or change them just breathing with it and through it
Breath by breath maybe three breaths in a row
just three seeing if you can stay intimately connected with the
inhale the paws and the exhale
three breaths in a row
[Music]
thank you so before Diana gives our talk I wanted
to just see how that was for you questions frustrations
Pleasant unpleasant experiences we've got a mic here and
um for the people out on YouTube hello and the other people who listen later on
would you be willing to use the mic and it's just here are a couple of comments
about how that was
Tara thank you
I'm wondering if it's normal to feel like you're falling asleep and you're kind of in and out of this dream state sort of hard to tell if it's sleep or
thoughts is that normal anybody else ever feel
that way yes so we get used to we get we get
exposed in this different way to all these different mind States right and that's one of them
and um you know it can be kind of pleasant did you find it a little bit Pleasant yeah
and um do you feel like you were able to be aware enough of what was happening as it
was happening
it's okay this time not so much it felt pretty sleepy more sleepy yeah so you
know you got lost and you know sloth and torpor right which is a one of the hindrances
can be quite Pleasant and you know um and one of the things we can do if we
find that is we stand up or we open our eyes
or we take off our sweater so we're a little cold you know these are some of the things to help bring energy or more
um yeah a little more kind of energy into the experience not quite so
comfortable thank you Tara thank you
Tara thank you Tara
I kept finding myself uh hunching over and then
I would need to remind myself to sit up and be important because that feels
better it just it's easier and feels more open when you're sitting back
and attentive but if I don't pay attention to that I end up creeping forward and forward and then I
should remind myself to sit back great observation do you want to say anything
about that Diana
[Laughter] I you know I mean you're you have a
habit right of Leaning forward and part of that is
you know the computer and the phone and some of it made us might also just be
part of your habit and so those habits become automatic and
so you it's so wonderful you're noticing it during your meditation and it's just okay
yes important let me just open back up and slowly over time we just keep coming
back and back and yep we get to create a new habit yeah I liked what you said
about important about you know sitting with someone important and then
that person being yourself that helped remind me to sit up straight
Tracy beautiful all right maybe one thing that I will add is um
the manner in which we're sitting like for me I notice when I'm sitting here with my back against that I'm a little
bit more leaning forward and then it makes it easier to do this than if I'm sitting
um probably the reason why I sat on the floor probably is because my feet don't touch the ground and I don't want to put
my bare feet on something so but um when we're sitting with maybe like the pelvis
is just tilted a tiny bit forward then it's easier to be upright because that's
kind of like how our spine is meant to be but chairs these days are they don't
allow that like you're going back or something like this so it can just to work with our anatomy to be if it's
possible for some people you know they need the back support to support their back but to it to be a little bit more
upright and that will also help with sleepiness if I ever feel sleepy meditating it's when I'm leaning using
the backrest that's just for me personally so just something else that might be helpful
yeah and this yeah and you know finding the right posture this is definitely
something that takes practice like we try this oh that didn't work so well try that that doesn't work so well or
something like this so and I just sit on the floor because my legs aren't very long and it's a way for
me to sit upright so I just wanted to maybe build a little
bit on what uh Tanya was talking about here with regard to meditation
and trying to use this word anchor and I like this word so often with mindfulness
meditation like when we're formally in a meditation posture and with our eyes closed that kind of thing we choose an
anchor and what we mean by that and as Tonya said most often teachers will talk about the
breath but it doesn't have to be the breath it can be sounds or bodily
Sensations and what do we mean by anchor so I find myself kind of doing this with my hands so the anchor is here and we
rest our attention on it the experience of breathing like for
example like feeling like that this little stretching that happens around
the chest and then the de-stretching the unstretching you know
so what is the actual experience so we're not thinking about it we're like
feeling what does this feel like so this is our anchor and we've kind of like rested attention on it
Perfectly Natural that the mind is going to wander and start planning or
fantasizing or commenting or something like this and then you'll be oh wait I'm
supposed to be meditating okay and then it comes back and then you know the mind is going to do this again and then oh
right I'm meditating and then you come back so this is kind of what's happening is the anchor is this place where you
always come back while the mind is like going wherever the Mind goes right the
future the past or whatever's happening so choose an anchor meditation teachers
love to talk about the breath but can also be just sounds even though we're
not talking it's very common that there are sounds you know outside of the classroom or just people shuffling their
poster or people doing whatever they're doing you know so the meditation Hall
actually can be quite noisy even though nobody's actually speaking
or Tanya talked about bodily Sensations so an obvious one and an easy I
shouldn't say easy right because this is simple but it's not easy right if you noticed right doing any of this that the
mind is going everywhere except on the anchor but to just be um
with like the feeling of the chair or the cushion against the body so like feeling that pressure that sensation
can be another anchor so it turns out that you can
actually anything can be an anchor we're talking about the breath
because it's always available and because it's changing that makes it a little bit more interesting so it's a
little bit easier for the mind to land there on the breath
so one thing that about mindfulness practice that's different than perhaps some other just general meditation
practices but mindfulness meditation is that in something that we like to say is
that there are no distractions that I believe to say that that doesn't we don't have this word of distraction so
much so what that means is if you have this anchor the breath
and the neighbor's dog is barking or that Ding dog bark bark bark bark oh
it's supposed to be meditating bark bark bark bark you're like oh this dog then you come over here right you may have
other language that you use or something and then bark bark bark this dog like wow I'm never gonna
meditate don't they know this is my only time I have today to meditate and there's a little anger and whatever it
might be and we come back to the breath bark bark bark and then instead of this fighting with
it you just shift the anchor to be barking
oh the dog is barking in groups of three it
feels like this my body maybe every time there's a little bark maybe I feel this really slight little
tightness or something like this or whatever reaction is and we might notice
that there's some emotions that are coming up and maybe a flood of thoughts where we're just paying attention to the
to the working in a relaxed easy way and part of the trick here is the
relaxed easy way because we want to of course we do we want to control our
environment and making it be as best as possible for meditation
that's not possible right we don't get to control the experience so instead we kind of like just fold it into our
meditation practice so you can switch and just bring that into your experience
or maybe you stay with the breath and then just as Tanya was saying make a
little note it could be the note could be sound so you just say quietly in your mind
sound come back to the breath sound come back to the breath
or maybe spark or dog or something but it doesn't matter what the word is
what's really helpful is just like placing a note on it is a way that we
can stop getting tangled up and involved with it with a big story making like that dang dog or I wonder what kind of
dog it is it reminds me of that dog that I had when I was little and right and then off we go right
so that's part of mindfulness meditation is this idea that we can fold anything in
discomfort in the body sounds that are happening whatever it might be we can
turn towards them bring some open-mindedness
[Music] um attention and I kind of like some of the language that you were using Tonya that
uh you started off talking about like inspiration and Faith the faith being
this belief that this is beneficial it doesn't have to be faith in a anything
else so this that kind of maybe uh
warm-heartedness or softness or something like that as opposed to kind
of like okay here's this um the anchor and then there's then we
notice spark bark bark and then oh I'm supposed to be mindful of dang it what am I gonna get Mindful and like holding
on to the breath as much as we can there's a way in which we might like use as type of a sledgehammer or our mind or
kind of come back in a way that has a little bit of aggressiveness or a little bit of
energy a lot of energy to it and we notice this when
if when the bell rings if there's this sense of oh thank gosh
then that means there was a little bit too much energy because you can't sustain that right for very long so and
this is definitely the art of practice is finding the right amount of energy
this is something that it's not like at one time you'll figure out okay not too
much not too little okay perfect I got it dialed in I know how to do this now it's something that we will always have
to be adjusting depending on what the mind's doing how the body feels Etc so this is something that's just integral
and to meditation practice is figuring out the the strength or the amount of energy I
don't even know what the word is exactly in which we pay attention and this is something that perhaps we
never even thought about before but we can explore and
discover as we do this meditation practice
are there any questions about what I've said so far
there was a lot of words and I was speaking kind of quickly but
hello Diana hello Tanya thank you um you know when I first started at IMC
was June June 30th but uh and now it's October 20th and but I've been
meditating you know for six months straight and I
would say that the energy part of it at least the beginning and even now
obviously because I'm no way I'm still like learning and all that stuff but I
find that there are some sittings that I don't wait for the Bell anymore and it's
nice and I'm or you know even with this meditation when Tanya was guiding it I
was having like an imaginary conversation and I'm like oh go back to the breath and it wasn't so much the
dang it why didn't I and I'm like okay just be still it's cool I don't have to
and also if I when I'm breathing sometimes I'm not forcing I'm like oh go
back to the breath but let's don't have to force it or do whatever and I was kind of reverting
back to like just the counting because it's what I was accustomed to so it's just really nice it is like the the
from it just it's working he's like you're the beginning like beginning guide to meditation at IMC and
then establishing the practice and continuing I get it it's like I don't
know if that's the right way to say it but it's I I'm very very excited thank
you thank you for sharing that ah
this because you have a good teacher right because uh Tanya's been here on Thursdays
and sage has a maybe somebody on YouTube I would like to introduce a question from the Beyond
um the Beyond yes thank you something um someone was picking up uh actually
they posed this question before the dog analogy but I thought it would be related and helpful
um this person is asking like how to like is there a way to notice your thoughts while meditating without
judging them one way or the other so instead of judging Sensations how do we
be with our thoughts and not judge though yeah either to be with our thoughts
so um there's a lot of things we could say I'll just say a few things one when
you're lost in thought no problem because you're lost in thought you don't even know that you're
going to be supposed to be meditating right so okay that's there's nothing to be done right you're lost in thought
two if you find that there's uh like there's this real momentum behind the
thinking it's just going on and on and on and or sometimes it's the same thing I gotta remember to do this don't forget to do that okay I gotta remember to do
this or we're rehearsing a conversation we had before planning or whatever it might be whatever it might be there's a
few things we can do one is to kind of to maybe unhook us
from the content is to just generally ask this question oh
are these images or are they sounds like what are thoughts
so we go we kind of let go of the content of the thoughts and look more at
the process of thinking because the process of thinking is happening right here right now so just
this like the gentle inquiry are these images or are they sounds and sometimes
shifting our relationship to thoughts in this way can interrupt the momentum of
the thinking thinking thinking thinking so sometimes that works and sometimes you might have to do it a lot like oh
okay here's this image and then we could ask questions about the images are they
in color are they clear is there a projection screen where is it if there
are sounds what is the sound or whose voice is it rather or you know something like this
and then maybe the third thing I'll say about thoughts and trying to just gonna
probably do a lot of teaching about thoughts when you did the intro class and you will again on November so there's a lot that we can say about it
but maybe I'll just um drop in
is there any motion that's fueling the thoughts I think there's something that's
underneath that's keeping those emotions that those thinking that thoughts going
for example often when there's a lot of planning happening and I know I've experienced
this a lot that oh there's a little bit of like fear or apprehension underneath it
because I'm trying to make sure that I can take care of everything so that I
don't have to because I'm afraid of what might happen if it's not going to go the way I want it to or something like this
so just this gentle inquiry so what I'm describing is in meditation
is a bit different than what we might do with journaling or psychotherapeutic setting with meditation it's more just a
gentle just dropping in of the question is there an emotion that's fueling this
and then we just kind of like open and wait we do not like go and figure it out
this is our mind's habits are of course we want to figure it out because we want that thinking to stop but the power here
isn't asking the question it's not in finding the answer the power
isn't asking the question because there's this way of when we ask the question I go like this
with my hands because it's a way in which there's like being open to learning something open to something new
open to what might happen next so it might be that the answer bubbles up
and it might be that it doesn't and both are fine it's just asking the
question is a way I would again kind of interrupts the momentum of thinking so
those are just a few things that I'll say so thank you for that Sage
on behalf of the internet we're grateful thank you
yes that's right thank you Iris
um I feel like if you go through those steps and you
still feel very maybe like attached or the thought just kind of doesn't let go
how do you work with that I think maybe that causes me more attention and
anxiety when I go through the steps and it's like still there I can't it's not going away yeah
yeah it may not go away right that's the um Tony was talking
about habits of mind right we have habits of mind and there's so much of
invested in our thoughts many of us are in our living thinking right and we've been educated so we get rewarded for
thinking so there's a lot of pressure behind it but it can it can when we can get to
where we um where the Mind settles down and the
thoughts maybe are going to the background and then they might get wispy and blend
soft while we're having like the anchor in the foreground so there might be a little bit of these thoughts floating
around while we're with the anchor but it could also be where there's just a
lot of thinking and then we can talk about well what supports
waking up out of thinking and coming back to the anchor
mindfulness supports mindfulness and maybe that leads me into one of the
last things that I want to say here is that this is a skill I would say is
something that you know and we've all learned how to do things we all learned how to tie our shoes we all learned how to drive we all learned so this is
something that does take a little bit of practice with
but there's a um a way in which if we bring mindfulness more and more into our
experience then it just becomes easier to become mindful the more we do it not surprising just like everything else
right in our life so maybe I'll just say
um this that it's often when we talk about mindfulness meditation we talk about sitting on a
cushion being in a posture but we can be mindful all day long or we can do it in any
posture we we are in doing whatever we are doing eating
maybe we take part of a meal or a whole meal every day and just be really present for the experience putting the
fork and the food feeling the arm moving tasting it something like this
or we um talking about posture in the body maybe the feeling of the body moving as
it walks it could be mindful of that so it doesn't take any extra time but just
bringing our mindfulness to things that we're already doing and then that makes
a giant difference that when you come to sit on the cushion having had those
experiences of mindfulness and in other settings helps when you get to the cushion was that helpful Iris that was
yeah I think so okay I do think maybe I'm trying to force myself to not think
like there's like actually setting causes more tension because of the thinking and like the mindfulness
so yeah so is this okay Tony if I just say it went so then uh maybe one thing that um
I can point to here is so there's I'm just going to make this up you have the
anchor and then you're lost in thought and then you wake up like oh right shoot
I've been I'm thinking I'm not supposed to be thinking and then what can be helpful is to
notice that second beat to like waking up and then notice the attitudes it's
not uncommon to kind of have this little like oh shoot dang it
and just notice what that feels like that's mindfulness too okay and then
begin again in a Gentle Way as as best you can
and so this can be really and this is very common what you're describing I'll say and I certainly had lots of this
absolutely so just notice like Oh waking up out of being lost in thought and then just
notice the attitude or the tone or the word or something that like I should
know how to do this by now everybody else is probably completely enlightened or what am I doing here I shouldn't even
come here you know whatever stories we all make up right crazy stuff sometimes so just notice that like oh that's more
thinking and then come back to the breath so you can notice like the attitude or the tone and maybe there's a
whole little quick little story that happens when you realize that you've been lost in thought yeah that sounds
good thank you thank you Iris thank you Diana you're welcome Tanya
um so the next part would be to do some small group discussions but um you know
this is pretty important what we're doing right now clarifying what to do and what practice is so I just want to
make sure um your questions you feel like you got enough answers to any of your questions
before we move into the breakout groups okay great so why don't we do two groups of well
one Richard you in or out of groups today okay two groups of four
um and um so it's easy enough just as long as you guys I don't think you know
each other so the u4 can come over here and Richard can go with these so you
guys make a you go that way Tara Tara Tara great
okay and um so the first I'm gonna have you do first thing I'm going to have you
do as you sit down in your circle is number one when we're connecting in the
circle we're still practicing mindfulness we're going to still be aware of what's
Happening as it's happening and one of the nice things is to stay aware of your posture
so try and stay upright so not leaning too far back and not
leaning too far forward we want to maintain kind of a balance of staying in
our own bodies even as we're listening to others right staying grounded and
connected to our our experience and and then very is whatever you can be
aware of so talking oh I'm I can feel my vibration of the sound in my mouth you
know I'm aware of that as I'm talking or when I'm listening
um the feeling of hearing or the impact of the words emotionally on my mind or
my body or my heart so just trying to help yourself stay
aware as you're speaking and listening so the first invitation now while
practicing mindfulness is to go around the circle and if you each share your name
where you're living and why what inspires you to practice mindfulness
then just go around the circle and you know maybe take up to a minute half of
30 seconds to 45 seconds let's say per person so not long
um and I'll be watching you to see when both groups are done so whoever has the longest hair maybe they could start in
the group
hi my name is
foreign it
is
a different settings today
to wake up
great and so
I have no idea
they're like in this kind of shift and focus thank you
mostly I think
go ahead and finish your sentence yeah don't finish your sentence yeah make
sure yeah okay so one more question for you
and what I would like to do is invite you to um I'll tell you what the question is
which is what might happen if you practiced mindfulness every day
and then so Ann Rose just answer what comes up for you like one thing that
might happen and then Iris you you say one thing right and then
Mustafa you say one thing and you just kind of keep going around and around spiraling around right makes sense so
you don't have to say everything that might happen just the thing that comes up that feels oh this you know
um and if you have a hard time with that one you could also sit you know just say you could offer what you might want to
do to help yourself practice mindfulness okay and we'll just do this for about
five minutes and so just you know talking sharing an idea letting the next person and letting yourself be inspired
and impacted by what you hear other people say all right
cultures
you know how do you make it fresh
everything
just checking in how was the you feel is this a good time
to shift yeah you guys too sure thank each other and then let's make a
circle so pull your chairs let's make a more intimate Circle here
say do you mind checking also and see if there's any comments in the
yeah great yep beautiful
do you guys mind scooting up a little closer yeah there we go
[Laughter]
nice and is there a mic over there
yeah yeah great
great so um now we get to just share with each other a little bit about what came up for you
um maybe you know I I tend to believe that it's really useful to restate
something that was important to you kind of helps you your mind take it in is
important and helps you remember it and it's also then gets to share with people
who weren't in your group and they get to hear maybe something new
um so is anyone willing to start and then we'll just pass it in a circle the mic
does anyone have something they'd feel inspired to share to start
construction thank you Tracy thank you
so I'm inspired it by Manuel who
was surprised and and I loved it he was surprised that he was able to this is
first time amazing quiet his mind and he was surprised when he when his mind was
still and that was so inspiring to me I just I
I loved that so that supported your practice made you
feel inspired yes great and so why don't you choose to pass the
mic one way or the other okay thank you
and you do have to hold it up to you sure okay uh
no I mean so far it's been a really great experience
it really confirms that I'm in the right track of because I'm in the process of rebuilding my life I guess I've actually
starting a new life I think it's a correct word and uh
paying attention and developing new ways of connecting with people
um compassion tightness and things like that probably are going to help me a lot
in mindfulness you know the give me the opportunity also to slow
down and just pay attention to what I really want or what I don't want so that's
that's what I'm getting from beautiful thank you
what am I supposed to talk about um if there was something that you
connected with that you heard that you felt was inspiring or supportive oh yeah yeah so the fact that you know everybody
here is here showing up and the best they can best we can
and uh I'm inspired by that I mean the fact
that uh you all have busy lives you know and you do uh you know you're out there
every day doing whatever you're doing having families working you know all of that
and you still take the time to come and work on something this significant which
is to learn how to you know create a more
compassionate kind you know world that we can all live in and be in together you know especially in this culture
today where we have some divisiveness that comes up in different places so it's you know just being able
to commit to that in our lives and to make it a priority it feels pretty
inspiring to me very inspiring so and that this place is run by all
volunteers like Diana and and uh Tanya and you know and Richard
yeah and me and other people and Sage you know so the fact that you know this
place can't happen if we don't all decide to help make it happen so
I'm grateful for that so that's inspirational great you can just hand it to Sage leave it on yeah thank you
thank you um I think once stood out to me was a
like you would expect um quite a bit of our discussion centered on ways that we can
Shore up like what I would call like hesitantly like perceived
shortcomings and things like that um but we really like blows me away is
like you know like Richard said like everybody's here and like despite the fact that so much of what we
like do and like think and our lives come
from like seeds that we planted forever ago or seeds that aren't even our responsibility like people are like
committed to like doing the work to make changes
and uh even to get to like resistance like in
choosing to show up when you don't want to like that's right you're impressive
I just forgot the question all right yeah just put the mic up to your mouth and what it what was did you hear or say
connect with anything that inspires you to practice mindfulness here
uh well I mean it seems like we even though it is different between us it
seems like we're all kind of here for the same thing and and that's in itself the most inspiring
thing is just everyone here we're kind of going through the same things but in different ways beautiful thank you
Mustafa
to be reminded of all the different ways it's helped people
recently of kind of I feel like for the first time I've put her right her like lack of motivation with practice
um so these like reasons all kind of help oh that's great I was that's so nice and that's um you know the the
support of Sangha right we really can help each other Inspire each other
remind each other we learn from each other thank you
ah I'm very grateful I think gratitude was the one thing that also came up for the practice and for everyone's just
kindness and receptiveness and being non-judgmental like because I know I can
say things that are kind of well any anyhow so I'm just I I just really like
that I can be who I am and not feel pressured to just say something to impress people I
just need to say something I I don't need to I want to say something just because for the sake of this for my
practice and for my betterment thank you thank you
um I think what resonated with me is just feeling like so much of what I have
felt kind of internally through meditation or mindfulness as being like kind of named or labeled as like the
experience of it and the process and it feels really wonderful just to hear this
commonality that we share as humans and you know just these little experiences
and things that I've had it's like oh that's what that is and you know when you were talking about mindfulness and
just to hear from you Richard that you've been you know doing this for so many years and you have and you have
these little moments or these little epiphanies where you feel a shift and it's like oh yeah I've had that too and just to to fill that you know Collective
sharing of inexperiences I really love that yeah that's nice
full circle yeah and so we have you know little time if
there's um any other questions
that people want you know to ask um or anything else you want to share
about practicing mindfulness I'm not required it's just optional
so um we all tend to drive in California
you know like there are people that I've had come out here for different events
from the east coast and I say to them you know there's no public transformation transportation from where
you're going to be working you know you need to and they just don't quite get it
and so one of the things that can happen here in California is you're going to drive
the driving is one of the best in my experience this is my experience mindfulness
realms to work with because first of all you're going to
make it safer for everybody you know if you're mindful and
it just it's wise to to bring mindfulness into driving and I don't
think we do it quite enough we get caught in you know radio shows or whatever we're
doing we're not paying as much attention as we should be we're you know we're thinking about other things instead of
knowing driving is like this boom now I'm driving
right and I know what I need to do as I'm driving
so it's it's um it's sort of I don't know if it's it's like a little bit of a evangelist about
it to be honest because I'm always scared when I'm driving to be honest
there's a lot of fear I'm experienced I experienced quite a lot of fear as my mindfulness grows like
what's really underneath this fear you know a lot of fear because it's
dangerous you know it's really a dangerous thing and we just take it for
granted so you know like I could go on all night but I don't plan to thanks thanks for listening yeah it's a great
reminder that we can practice doing anything we can be mindful in everything
we do and um
I think that's shift to I'll say one thing that um
when we ring the bell three times just so you know we're ringing the bell for
the Buddha the Dharma and the Sangha so you know that's what it's three Bells
right I thought yeah and at the end of any meditation or
Dharma talk or event or Retreat whatever you do there's something called dedication of
Merit and this is um this comes out of the the whole
philosophy of generosity and the whole Devotion to do our
practice for all beings that we're doing this for the benefit of ourselves
for others and for both and so at the end of a practice period
we dedicate the Merit of our practice and we dedicate it to all beings without
exception right that's the overarching theme and there's lots of
ways to do that but one of the things we've been doing here
is you know I can say let's dedicate the benefit of our practice to all beings everywhere
and there's probably a lot of beings we don't even think about that don't come to mind
and so on Thursday nights we've been doing a communal dedication of Merit
where we pass the microphone around and each person can offer a being a type of
being or a group or a cause an animal just something short that is on their
mind that you would like us to remember and acknowledge and that we want the
benefit of our practice to go to them too and it helps us all bring more beings into our mind so
and we'll do that now and and then at the end of that we'll Diana will ring the bell three times
Richard please start I can't so I'd like to dedicate a practice
tonight to members of the Sangha that are you know quite mature
and one of them is Stephen uh Browning he's an artist and you may if you're
lucky someday see some of his work he's phenomenal Woods uh called wood print
artist and he's going blind and deaf at the same time so
and his partner Pat so that's what I'd like to dedicate to them
I wasn't prepared because he connected me with something that happened with me not long ago I
so I'm dedicating my time here tonight to my mom who unfortunately passed away
oh time ago recently and so that's
beautiful
I'm going to dedicate this to my boss Catherine
who needs a lot of kind thoughts
I'm dedicating my practice tonight to my two sons Liam and James
I would like to dedicate this practice to anyone feeling lonely or isolated
[Music] maybe I'd like to dedicate this to anyone are you feeling
any of the overthinkers nice
um I dedicate this to work honestly that's where I'm lacking the most
um May the benefit of our practice
be for the highest good of incarcerated people living in cages across America
may all beings be free
you say something I can't practice
to the waters and the sky and the Earth
I I was gonna dedicate to spiders partly because I'm afraid of spiders and so
just this uh you know all beans right sometimes we
tend to exclude some but all Beads so may all beings be free of suffering
[Music]
thank you for being here and thank you for your practice thank you for your practice
all beings without exception all beings yep that's right we're all
trying