so good morning everyone can you hear me
all right great it's nice to see you not in your heads
and uh good morning to those of you who are on line on watching on YouTube and
appreciate all the ways in which people attend these Sunday morning sittings
and I appreciate all of you being here um walking down here today I
reflect a little bit on how special it is to have a group of
people arrive together to meditate together and have some kind of shared interest
in meditating perhaps and then
interested in the kind of space the kind of ambiance or Mutual support that comes
when meditating together in a group some people find it hard to meditate alone and being
in a group is really inspiring some people some of you might be here because of the shared values there might
be some kind of values that are shared here that are very different than what you'd find if you go to the mall
you might feel a different set of values that are being operate operating there
maybe someplace and um
and some of you are here because you're interested in hearing some teachings and maybe because they're something
important going on for you in your life you're suffering in some way or a challenge in some way and
you want to address it and you hope that the teachings will somehow touch something that you're trying to you're
struggling with or working with so this is you know kind of in the room
here a lot of different things that I'm reflecting on and many different backgrounds here that
people you all be coming here and and maybe some of you bring particular
things with your background and maybe some of you feel particularly safe
coming into an environment like this different than many other places some people maybe don't feel so safe in
coming here and looking around wondering you know is this okay for me to be here maybe first
time or I'm a little different than what I think other people are like and and you know it's okay and
many years ago there was a woman who came and she was really concerned about coming here
and didn't quite feel like this okay and am I on the right track if I'm here
because so many of the women here have gray gray here Maybe not maybe not today but there's
there's some and uh in her culture you you didn't let your hair go gray and so that was that
was like a big deal for her and uh you know it's just do I have to
be like that and um
so what is here in the room and uh the question for me is speaking
to all of you Dharma teachers I could just kind of read an encyclopedia entry on some
Buddhist topic and then there that's the teaching you got it
but you're not here just to me to read and it's like repeated Gentry on what mindfulness is
um you know there's also things like uh the way we're attuned to each other we
attuned to this did the meditation do something with the Attunement that we share and they're quiet the peacefulness
what's here you've sat being mindful for a period of time and
and so what is the connection that you feel now to the room and the people that was different than when you came in here
and maybe some of you never been in this community before has it changed at all
when I you know when I teach on YouTube and I usually today I don't have a laptop in front of me but I usually have
the screen in front of me and it made such a big difference for me when I started teaching on YouTube I
first time I was gonna like I thought this was weird you know you know before the pandemic I
would have said no way no way that can't be done but it immediately changed because there
were all these chats and not everyone chats but there was a representative those chats and they were
so friendly and so appreciative and and something was conveyed of a connection
to people through those chats that they came alive for me and there was much more than just providing information now
there was an exchange there was a sense of feeling of of a community and a connection
and maybe some of you are doing on YouTube today are already chatting I've chatted to each other and
or you will saying hello for example
and um so to be attuned what is here what are you here for and all the different ways
and sure you hear some people if some of you have heavy things on your hearts some of you have uh you know
incurable diseases that are some people have but we sent losses and griefs some
of you are really troubled by current events of different kinds
the anti-Semitism in this country that's growing seemingly
the the racism in this country which is maybe not growing but becoming more
public and prominent in Sea and the violence that's becoming stronger and stronger and
seemingly the mass shootings of black people and lgbtq and cholera Springs
black people in Buffalo New York and synagogues
so so you know is this in the room at all is this you know kind of in the background or you came here for a
respite from all that you didn't want to have these things named here because like finally this is a place where we don't do that then we can put it all
down so how do I as a Dharma teacher take all this into account
should I take it into account or should I just read this encyclopedia entry of mindfulness
and then you know close the book and we can go home that's that's been done with there's much more going on here than
just the bear teaching there's a connection that we have and um and part of that connection for
me is that I'm conveying something that I find incredibly valuable and I'm delighted and grateful that I have this
opportunity to share it with a group of people and um and I'd like to support you I'd
like to I value you and feel like don't take it for granted that you've chosen to come here you're doing
this practice so I think it's quite a beautiful thing you're doing and have a lot of respect for what you've what
brought you here and all the different ways so thank you and I hope to
that this what I do today here will have some bearing and
and what I want to do today is um partly inspired taking this time the
beginning to establish or to explain all to say all this and that is that um
uh what does it mean to be mindful practice mindfulness
in our relationship with other people and what what is is mindfulness enough
is it enough just to show up and be with people mindfully
it depends that the answer to that depends a lot on what you mean by mindfulness what you think it is
lately I've been thinking the heart of mindfulness practice is non a
non-reactive awareness we might react but the awareness that is
not caught in our own reactivity and so we can bring a kind of attention
that is not being influenced by our reactivity so that we can bring a kind of presence
attention to whatever's happening to ourselves and the challenges we have internally
and the challenges we have externally where we can be present see it clearly but the seeing is non-reactive the
seeing stays clear balanced maybe centered maybe available to see clearly
and say this is what's happening and if that kind of is a one definition
of mindfulness non-reactive awareness some people with or slightly different
definitions some people get the idea and impression that that's enough
it's enough just to be you know just be mindful but it's a little bit passive
non-reactive awareness and uh and in being passive
um what um [Music]
you know is it is it enough just to be passively aware non-reactively and you
know look at someone and be silent just just being mindful with
you once many years ago I many years ago
maybe when I was more foolish as a teacher but I wanted to I wanted to give a good
people the weekend I was teaching on mindful speaking and so I wanted to give them the uh
experience of what it's like all the different communication that goes on between us
that is not words so I asked them to go into dyads and
talk to it and one person talk about something really important in their life I forget what it was
and the other person to just listen and look without any Expressions on their
face without any nodding just kind of be fully present but not you know not and
for anything and and uh you could imagine that how that went you know it was you know it was
kind of it felt pretty strange and so the group got very clear sense very quickly that there's much more going on
in being present than just being non-reactively
aware there's other factors happening in it and what are those other things that
are useful that are important so one of the things is um
uh could be is Attunement to be attuned to the other person
and Attunement means that we have a sense an understanding of who the person
is what's going on with the individual or the group that we're here and um and uh and that how do we become
attuned how do we have a bigger sense a richer sense of who this is person is
and what they're saying what they're feeling what they're expressing what they're hoping for what their life is
about um so that they feel seen not just heard and seeing just kind of
this non-reactive awareness where we don't not but so they really feel like we're with them in some ways
and that takes uh take a little bit of time willing to learn about them find out about them take time to take
them in and understand how they are maybe with if you're just meeting someone maybe with their posture or
maybe with their emotional tone maybe with their demeanor
that we take in and really feel and feel connected to and somehow attune to What's Happening Here with this person
and um many years ago I mean something I was kind of a little turning point in my
social life and and caring being attentive to people was uh I was working at a restaurant and
I was in the changing room and there was a changing of shifts and um and I was
getting ready to leave and a friend of mine walked in and I just uh
um I blurted out something very quick and fun and you know maybe funny or just
kind of made a joke or made a kind of something out of remark that I think was innocent and find enough in and of
itself it was a way of making a connection but what I hadn't done is taken the time
to attune myself to know and recognize what was going on for my friend where where are they at
because I was so spontaneous as soon as I saw my friend and it turned out my friend uh another
friend of his had just died and he was just coming to work just with caring with that with him and I had
missed that and so in some ways I caused distress and harm because I hadn't taken
the time to get a tune to be to understand and see and I probably could
have picked it up quickly if I just kind of taken two seconds to wonder what was going on here for
this person and um so
so to be attuned with someone and so it takes it means an
interest in the person and one of the things I think that is really helpful for a proper Attunement
is to respect others to respect their value their importance
to respect their Humanity to really kind of be attuned to pay attention to listen
to learn I want to find out who this person is with respect your your
important respect means you're valuable I see you as being important enough to get to know
and how many times did we not do that just like me with my friends blurting out
um you know I've been in situations where I was kind of caught up in some concern and I just really wanted to get
my you know my latest opinion out
and um and uh not really finding out whether the person wanted my opinion
about something or wanted to hear it hear a five-minute story about something
that had happened to me you know that day um and so you know I've I've talked to
people sometimes you know just kind of caught up in my own thing and then eventually halfway through or something
kind of noticing the person's eyes have glazed over uh-oh and
um and uh why didn't I notice this earlier did they just glaze over or how long
how long were they glazed over so so you know to talk as if the other person
is not there and I've been on the receiving end of this where people have talked to me they're like a few times
not a lot of times but a few times over the many years I've had people talk to me
um and uh I kind of felt there must be somehow high on something
you know I don't think they were you know any drugs but they were like they were like like I could have gone like
this in front of their eyes and they wouldn't they wouldn't have seen me their eyes were kind of locked into their concern and it was quite so it's
kind of a little bit I don't know possessed it's the right word or but uh you know really kind of in their thing
in such an intensity that I kind of felt like I didn't exist in you know listening to them
so to be attuned to be interested in being attuned so mindfulness in
relationship to other people I like to Repose is more than non-reactive awareness
it's an awareness that searches for an Attunement what is here what's going on
here and that's also true for ourselves the non-reactive awareness that we bring
to ourselves is also an awareness that's doing something deeper to ourselves and
just kind of matter of fact seeing things as they are but it's a vehicle for a deeper Attunement to ourselves to
get to know ourselves in a deeper and Fuller way and then there's
um uh and then with Attunement then there's
also a connection the Rapport that we have with someone what is that connection what is going on
between us is there friendliness is there is there resistance there's a hostility is there
disinterest is there is a person why is this person keep looking at the door
you know you know not looking at me you know there's something going on here What's Happening Here in the connection
but I think I would like to adjust when we when we bring the mindfulness practice if we really want to be mindful
and really use them get the most out of mindfulness that it means we're also being attuned
to how we're connected and being careful with that and perhaps being conscious
conscientious about a connection which is healthy
that is nourishing that's supportive that helps us feel more connected to each other rather than more separate
and one of the one of the reflections that I've I often do uh during and also
after being with someone was did what I say and how we were together do I not
feel more connected with them or do I feel more disconnected and I've said things certainly that uh
at the moment or sometimes afterwards oh I think I could feel that the person
kind of pulled back a little bit or shut down a little bit or that made everyone quiet
and uh and uh and so there was a disconnect so for example some emotional
expressions like anger uh will will sever a connection I mean
some people have been angry very quickly in short notice and the connection to someone has been severed for decades it
doesn't take much sometimes to a real dramatic severing of connections to
happen um but you know you can feel is that is that what you want do you want to kind
of really have that cutting people off or pulling back or do you want to kind of create a
possibility for deeper connection what's a value what what's important for you
is in your Attunement to it all do you recognize in yourself that you're afraid
what happens if your anxiety is there with uh in the relationship and maybe
there's good reason for it but how do you then establish connection or how do you care for that connection with your
anxiety do you tell someone you know I feel anxious right now but I still want to go
for a walk with you and maybe we'll just talk just know that I'm feel anxious that's how how I am or do you somehow adjust the
just the situation so you can feel is more at ease with your anxiety
maybe it's better if you go for a walk maybe it's better if you say let's go get some tea just something to break you
know because it seems a little bit too intense otherwise just having a cup of tea between you that can be a great
protection you know you don't have to because you don't have to be completely connected
you know because you're drinking so this is a little I don't know private thing I'll tell you
that um I don't know how far I wanted to go [Laughter]
on YouTube the world is um so I teach Retreats a lot
and um and you know and I love teaching these Retreats they're wonderful and but the most difficult part of the
retreat for me is when it's finally over we're in this big room at our retreat
center and we're sitting in a circle and it's finally over everyone gets up and they can talk to
each other and everything and that's the hardest part for me because for good reasons you know people
feel grateful or feel like they've really shared something deep during the retreat and I'm the teacher for the retreat some kind of the point person
for what happened maybe and so people come up to me with certain kind of like
it's really important that it has important things they want to say they say it with all this week-long we treat
energy and and I'm you know kind of you know how I am with them I have some a little
bit more value in that context than you know just someone they met at the mall
and so um you know so so if we're standing I learned
I feel like I have to offer a lot of attention to really be there and receive them and acknowledge it and so that's
fine in and of itself but there's a series of people like that and so if I end I'm exhausted
so that's the most tiring part of the whole retreat so what I've learned to do
is um uh you know with the closing Circle I'm sitting in a chair
and uh and everyone gets up and talks what I've learned to do is I don't leave the chair
and by not leaving the chair there's there's a very different way that people like what they expect from me if I'm
sitting in a chair and they come up to me they kind of don't expect me to be fully there
I'm cutting I can be I can be kind of casually there from sitting in a chair
and then um so and so then that's it works really well for me and I appreciate talking to them it's nice you
know and I can be there and and um and it's it's somehow easier the whole thing's more relaxed
and um so so here's you know a connection that didn't work for me
I recognized it and I found another way to be with people in a way that worked
so what is the connection how do we establish the connection what are we doing with that connection are we or how
we're being with it are we losing connection are we severing connection are we
Healing Connection are we making connection are we finding a way to be together that's nice
that's all part of the the art of Being mindful in relationship
so Attunement connection and then there's also a connection where
we do this to something that's other different than just who we are together
as a group uh you know individual one-on-one for example there's also the what else is
here so for example here at the IMC for this today
we're not just meeting at the cafeteria at the mall
and to talk we're here at a meditation center after having meditated together
as a group and there's something about this room with a high ceiling that place people to
be meditating now here for 20 years before those 20 years there was
about almost maybe 40 years where people there
were Christians who were here because there was a Christian church and they were Christian Mystics and they sat in silence here in this
room and part of the reason they wanted us to have it was this church was because we sat and sat in silence they
wanted to have that continue so we have this you know this now you hear this history right of the place and
so there's something here that we're sitting in there's a Dharma we have the Buddha
statue you know so they dar Muslims what does that mean for you what are the associations we have the values the
background some of you might have been born into a Buddhist family and so there's a deep family connection
family history and associations and that with uh with being here and Buddhism
some people it's um other things that you associate with it that maybe maybe
it even touches into onto the sacred coming in a place like this or something maybe some something spiritual here that
you feel and sense what's what's going on here
so what is that that's part of this picture too so what else is going on when you're mindful of being with
another person mindful of being with a group of people is there an Ambiance is there an environment is there a wider
kind of Association of feeling of what's here and how do we take that into account
um the um how do we care for that and so
um what else is present here so uh this question what is present
is kind of the core one of the one way of saying the core question of mindfulness
what is present here but if you ask the question what is present here
opening yourself up to discover something take the time to feel and send
said no what is present here and if you only ask the question once if
you you probably only get one answer if you ask the question 12 times you've got 12 different answers there's so much
here so in any situation but not so much that you have to ask this all the time but mindfulness is
also entering into situations kind of available ready to Let's let yourself be
informed a kind of a way of paying attention that you're available
to feel and discover and learn what else is here what's here in the fullness of things
that you can't if you're completely preoccupied in your concern
and whatever it might be and you know but there's a kind of a dropping of
self-concern enough that you can uh what is present here
and everything I'm talking about how to do this with other people is something we do to ourselves as well
what is present here in me if you're caught up in the thoughts of self-concern Me Myself and mine
ruminating about you know something about yourself it's difficult to be have this kind of
what is present here question what's really here to be attuned to yourself to
discover same thing if you ask yourself that 12 questions in meditation
you might get 12 different answers but you might be living in only one of them
what happens if you open and keep opening what self is here what else is here
so um so one way that in the wider outside the
Buddhist inside world that some people refer to what I'm talking about to hear
is not mindfulness they talk use the word presence
practicing presence practicing presence to the present moment
and so practicing presence means mindful but you're being mindful more than just with the cognitive mind that knows
you're being present with all your faculties you know in your body hearing listening
smelling feeling emoting kind of the resonance all the ways in which we resonate and feel what's going on
presence means so much more than just mindfully you know
non-reactive awareness I think or it feels it fills it it puts you know fullness into what non-reactive
awareness might be but what's fascinating for me about this word presence it can be something we do
but it's also uh what's the what's present here and some people say what's present here is
many things and so there's a presence here of calm there's a present here of
attentiveness there's a presence here of maybe of
certain values many people when they come into a Buddhist Community
have a heightened value in kindness friendliness compassion
and and so you know there's other what's that what's the presence of a Kind
Community or a presence of a space where people there's an openness and attentiveness awareness
so and so you know in some circles you know again you know non-buda circles
people are also practicing mindfulness but they call it the presence of God
or the presence of the Divine or the presence of the sacred
or the presence of in Buddhism people might say the presence of emptiness
or the presence of compassion you know what is it is there something here
some of you might not would prefer not to use these languages this way of talking
but uh in if you want to kind of understand a little bit our practice of mindfulness
to how it overlaps with so many different practices in other religions and other ways you need to kind of
appreciate that they have other language than we have and one of them is presence
and so when you show up what's the presence you bring not just what what awareness do you
bring but what more do you bring to the table to the situation and sometimes I go home and and I feel
you know I bring exhaustion you know after a seven day Retreat sometimes and
after that closing Circle you know I bring exhaustion sometimes I
can come home from Retreat and I bring in a lot of calmness I feel very quiet sometimes I bring all kinds of different
things home sometimes I bring grumpiness home you know and um and you know so what's
that what what kind of presence do we bring in this situation and how do we how do we bring awareness
to how we are and what we're bringing to it where we hold it with this non-reactive
awareness the bottom line for mindfulness practitioners I would like to suggest
suggest were the kind of the first the first
first approach is to really learn well what non-reactive awareness is
that's really key to everything else because without the non-reactive awareness
self-awareness can be bad news for a few of us
you know people discover all kinds of things about themselves which are not necessarily you don't necessarily have it projected onto the walls everyone to
see what's going on in your mind and um or you know where we have we're
grumpy or something you know it's like oh no no not again and and
um or other people are being grumpy and not again you feel like that last time I was this person they were grumpy and I
think I'm gonna recede into the background or shut down a little bit because this is
too much for me or I don't know um you know what exactly I'm saying here
what I'm trying to get across is if we can learn to practice non-reactive awareness if that can be
the bottom line that the kind of fundamental thing we're doing then all the other things we pay
attention to it's a little bit safer it's a little bit wiser a little bit more it kind of works better
because then we don't get caught in our reactivity in the way that we're present
and aware so I might be grumpy but I'm not then afraid or angry with
myself or self-conscious or embarrassed oh I'm just grumpy
that's how it is now and um and uh you know and so
it's very different than if I'm embarrassed or upset with myself and the same thing with other people
occasionally people in the world don't behave very well and it might happen
and um and then if we can have non-reactive awareness of it then maybe
there's a whole different way in which the situation could unfold for example what if the person is
misbehaving and what if you say what else is present here
how what what is it what can I be I attuned to in this person
this person's certainly angry but as I take the time to attune myself to the
person I see the person is also very afraid that seems to be the background for this
anger is their fear and insecurity does that make a difference how you relate to them and then how you connect
then because of it or your nose so this non-reactive awareness
is the foundation so but non-reactive awareness maybe is
not enough maybe the fullness of mindfulness practice has all these different dimensions to it that does
involved is not passive does involve intentionality of some time
for free from you some sense of purpose
let's let's practice non-reactive awareness to become better attuned
better connected better aware of the context and the
atmosphere and the what else is present here let's enter into this world more fully
so that we can be wise and caring for this world in a way that we can't
if we are not really aware or too and connected and
respectful of everyone so mindfulness bring mindfulness into
your life at the end of Retreats people often ask the
this mindfulness is fine how do I bring it into my life and some of you maybe got more than you
wanted to today wow that's a lot of work that's a lot to do
so um maybe we can take a couple of minutes if some of you have a comment or a question
you'd like to make about any of this or what's anything else
we have a few minutes here a little bit like a rock star thank you
hi thank you so much um
with the non-reactive awareness and just being aware of sort of this where other people are at where you're at
I've had situations and I've heard a lot of teachers say the way people behave towards you has more to do with them
than you so I try to bring that into my awareness but sometimes if there's like so much of
someone's anger coming towards you I I just don't know I can't always be
present with that and work with it and it's very upsetting in relationships
because I feel like there's been situations where I I didn't feel like I did anything but I'm bringing up
something in someone else and then it just it wasn't savable even with the
awareness of what's going on in that other person so um I guess in that situation I can only
work with my reactions to it and it's just really it can be very painful yeah
yeah so so there's it's huge the topic but you're raised there's so many variables so many different ways that
this plays itself out so I'll say a few words um one is that um
there is something to be said about being prepared for those those events not to kind of just show up and think
you're supposed to take care of it then and there but if it's a regular thing enough prepare yourself and one of the ways is to meditate
uh meant necessarily just before the event but just a regular practice because it gives you the presence of
mind the calmness the attentiveness so that you're not reactive excessively
that someone's angry with you and then you can kind of be a little bit calm enough to then find your bearings and
know what you should do um that's one the other is in preparing if
it's someone you know well and this happens you know regularly enough wait for a time when it's not happening
and everything is cool and nice and say can we can we have a little conversation it would be helpful for me you know I
get really afraid when or challenging for me when you're angry and it's probably going to happen again
um could we have some understanding of how we navigate that next time it happens like can I just raise my hand
and and wait to pause and breathe deeply for three breaths would that be okay
with you or something you know you know see if you can make some kind of arrangement ahead of time might might
work might not and some sometimes it's helpful in terms of uh I mean in certain certain
circumstances it's helpful to let people know the impact their anger has on you
and um and there are some people if you tell them boy when you're I feel really
afraid right now people can some people are surprised by that and it kind of change in the
context like you know like well what do I do now with my anger if they're afraid do I just keep going or held back and
and so some people that's a powerful thing to say boy I'm really afraid right now
and then it might change the context of the conversation it happened here in this building for me
once where we were doing renovation on the building and there was a lot of noise
and one of the neighbors who had a tendency to complain about any noise that came out of this building I mean
imagine this is what do we do here but occasionally you know you know
there's noise coming out and uh there was a renovation to work and the person came over and was Furious
and and it was I was the recipient of this Fury and I just stood there
receiving all this Fury it was quite something and the person finally paused and I said
this I said oh you know I feel really afraid right now
the person immediately calmed down it was dramatic and and I don't think the
person wanted to have that impact and realizing how big the impact had been then it the person backed down
dramatically from it and the whole thing kind of you know de-escalated or whatever
so I don't know that doesn't always work but it's a whole art I mean this I don't want to suggested it's a simple and easy
thing to do and sometimes certain situations the best thing to do is get out of there
stand behind someone else you know so so it's so many different
you know scenarios that where this plays out but but the study of preparing yourself thinking this you know by just
practicing and developing capacity for mindfulness and calm awareness so that the best
you have maybe maybe the best chance to figure out what to do thank you
so maybe one more all the way in the back if you don't mind taking it there and then we'll stop here
all the way well I noticed in myself that
um I became reactive when I heard that this was being broadcast on YouTube
um and I'm just wondering uh what your thoughts are on how we can mindfully
relate with YouTube and social media because YouTube is uh
you know the the the the the politics the economics the
capitalism the there's so many so many problems with uh YouTube and social
media and all these reasons right things like that yeah I was just wondering what your thoughts were on that
yeah that's a big topic and uh I think it's reasonable to have your concern
and I wish I was as well informed maybe as you are about how all this works so I I
I'm remiss in not being fully educated about the impact and how it all works but um uh what I what I understand is
that we're using the social media or the YouTube that's what it's called YouTube
uh for for a greater good and we're taking something and we're putting a
positive spin in it so it's being used in a good healthy way and one of the evidences that maybe it's
a healthy place on YouTube was at some point someone joined us for the first time on YouTube and they put in the chat
this is the friendliest place I've ever seen on YouTube and
so I you know I don't know if that's true I don't I'm not on YouTube otherwise but but I'm hoping that with
the goodness of what we're doing here is doing greater good for the world and
harm okay thank you thank you
so uh there's a t now let's just say hello to each other some of you are here for
the first time are new what I'd like to ask you if you're willing and you don't have to but uh if you could just uh turn
to someone next to you and say hello and even if it's your first time here welcome them
welcome welcome each other and if you want to say a little bit more you can say it was anything about this talk that
was uh you know it'd be useful for you to hear or interesting that you want to kind of think about more or something
and then it can just be two minutes or so if you'd like it just is just to be friendly and um and then
if those of you want to stay we'll have the tea time and stand outside we can take off The Masks outside and it's blue
skies so it should be good for a few minutes for a little while thank you