hello friends hello good morning good afternoon
whatever time zone you're joining from delighted to be with you delighted to um
practice together in this moment in time and um and as you know uh well as gil
uh announced on friday he's teaching a retreat this week and i'm glad to be
together supporting your practice and practicing together with you in this moment in time feeling your presence and
thank you for the warm welcomes that i see in chat very kind of you so
so for this week um given that you have been practicing
uh the sati patana sutta in a very methodical and slow way
with gil over the past few weeks and weeks also remaining
what i would like to share and support and offer in the support of
your practice our practice is [Music] delving into the refrain of the
satipatana it's not the specific sections about the topics but it's the
refrain that actually years ago as i was studying the satipatana suta blew my
mind how significant the refrain actually is for all of the practices so
and also i'll bring in a little bit of the introduction um phrasing and suggestions for setting the
frame so basically this week these five days it's about how to practice the
satipatana not what to practice gil is very slowly thoroughly going through the
the topics of the establish establishments of the foundations and
the refrain really has to do and the introduction has to do with how to practice how
the way the scope the attitude so that's what i like to bring
in to offer to support your practice maybe of service so and i'll say more about this in
the um darmit afterwards and um
and yeah without further ado let's meditate together and i'll drop in a few
invitations and we'll just simply be with the body the first foundation for
this practice together so so without further ado let us begin
let us begin ah arriving landing
landing in our seat landing in our bodies
arriving arriving each moment
each moment a new arrival
letting go letting go releasing releasing any thoughts
releasing preoccupations
releasing whatever is not necessary or not helpful in this moment
releasing releasing and as thoughts arise not that there's anything wrong
with thinking per se but
for the benefit for the benefit of ourselves for the benefit of others
in service our practice as service
dedicating ourselves in this moment in time
dedicating dedicating ourselves wholeheartedly
to this practice right now
lovingly not with shoulds and i have to but lovingly
giving ourselves over over with love
ah
to this moment to arriving
being aware wholeheartedly
lovingly
even if what we're aware of
are challenging sensations emotions it's okay
ah relaxing softening releasing
with each breath with each in-breath
becoming more present a little more present
a little more aware
bringing in balanced balanced engagement
engaging this beautiful word engaging
with each out breath
letting go of preoccupations of thoughts
of disengagement with this moment
letting go of entanglement
with the world age in breath
engagement with this moment here now heartfully lovingly
each out breath letting go of entanglement
engagement in and then releasing entanglement
letting awareness receive the breath in the abdomen perhaps settled
well rooted grounded
engagement engagement with energy
engaging engaging with balanced
energy not too tight not to lose
tuning the bow of our musical instrument which is our awareness our body
our body fullness
with age in breath brightening brightening this engagement
the atapi
letting the engagement be easeful energetic yet
easeful doesn't have to be tight
with the out breath let there be release
let there be release
as in the introduction of sati patana sutta free from desires and discontent
in regard to the world
vinaya habija domanosa
let it go of discontent entanglement
for this moment desires and discontent entanglement
ah here just here
and clearly knowing clearly knowing what is here the breath in the body
clearly knowing some pajanya clearly knowing
not foggily not half thinking about this or that but clearly
knowing this breath this sensation
this miracle of being alive this body breathing sensing
being
respecting the miracle it is as doorways
to wisdom to clear comprehension
clear comprehension [Music] some virginia
mindfully with sati mindfully
it's like this
without judging wanting it to be different it's like this wow
interesting with curiosity interest
mindfulness and clear comprehension
sati and sampajanya
let's see what is needed more in this moment in time
more engagement energetic engagement with atapi
more release more letting go
with the out breath and of course always with sati with
mindfulness knowing what is needed with clear comprehension
of what is happening what's here right now this miraculous mind body heart
discover how nourishing and delicious
these factors can be
engaged energetic engagement
releasing what's not needed
mindfulness and clear comprehension how delicious
how bright they can feel how soothing how relaxing to the body
and heart and mind without judging yourself if any of them
isn't present no problem no problem release just release
if any judgment arises then begin again with engagement
it's very simple don't throw perfectly good moments
after moments that are gone begin again
clearly knowing some virginia
and as this period of our sitting meditation comes to a close
together
let us bring to mind all of us sitting together
in our minds eye hundreds of us
and hundreds listening later and hundreds of others
other practitioners around the world
and knowing trusting that there is goodness
there is goodness in us practicing
separately together and dedicating offering this goodness
this service our practice as service to love to wisdom
offering our practice no matter how shoddy we might
judge it to be trusting there is goodness we've showed up even if there
was one moment of clear comprehension
or mindfulness dedicating together dedicating
our practice our service our goodness
to the entire world to all beings to all beings
those who are living through
war right now feeling unsafe and challenged
offering our care
for holding witness not turning away with wisdom and compassion offering it
to them and all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere be safe
may all beings everywhere be happy
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you thank you for your practice
greetings greetings again friends wherever in the world you are delighted
that we are coming together in time
even if not space not spatially but temporarily
which actually ties into something i want to talk about today spatial and temporal relationships so
so as i mentioned at the beginning since you've been studying the sati patana
sata with gil systematically thoroughly the different sections
as a way of supporting your practice um i'd like to offer this week
taking more time taking detailed time with the um with the refrain with the
refrain and also today in the meditation i brought in some invitations some teachings from the
introduction so i'd like to say a little bit about
the structure of the satipatana sutta for some of you this might be new for some of you this might be review
and it's always fun even if it's review so and i have one slide and if you have
your eyes closed or if your screen is too small not to
not to worry because i'm going to share with you everything you need to know so
let me bring up let me share my screen
and the joys of zoom here we go okay
all right let's see if it's showing no it's not okay let's try that again
it's not showing i'm not sure let's okay i'm going to try it one more time
oh dear zoom how i love thee okay there we go i think
it's working now okay i think it was working before also anyway okay so
so um the sati patana sutta the sati patana sutta so
this oh i have to give credit so this uh is from the book sati patana the direct
path to realization uh by venerable biku analia
uh whoops you can't see it quite clearly because of the virtual background
so um i'll say more about the book in a moment so so
while i have this this app um
the sati patana sutta the four foundations of mindfulness sutta
is divided to four different sections as you see i you can you can't see my oh yes you can see my cursor that's good so
on the left as you see from the bottom if you look from the bottom you see there's a section called the body right
there are six sections in the body and you've covered them you've studied them with guilt
breathing postures activities anatomical parts
elements and corpse and decay then the second section of the
satipattan the second foundation second establishment
is feelings or vedana or feeling tones which you
practiced with gil last week and next week i trust he will be
covering the third satipatana mind here you see it and then the last foundation is damas
and which again there are five parts hindrances aggregates sense fears
awakening factors noble truths so so right now you're kind of in the
middle here of having covered half of the satipatana sutta with gil and the other half remaining
so this is the structure of the satipatana sutta and um
and what i'd like to bring your attention to is that in between each section
where specific teachings are given about say breathing starting from the
bottom the first teaching is about the breath the second one about body postures etc the way the sutta is
written at the beginning it talks it says you see this box that says direct path
so the suta talks about how this is the direct path
how these teachings are the direct path to awakening
and which i can also read that for use if i'm talking about that so i'll just read it so that we have some so it's a
short paragraph practitioners this is the direct path for the purifications of beings
for the surmounting of sorrow and lamentation for the disappearance of dukkha and discontent for acquiring the
true method for the realization of nibana namely the four satypatanas
so here it's the declaration that this is the direct path this is the direct
path and of course this this is repeated at the end and it's it's actually i love this
because um you know in as an academic as an ex-academic
whenever i gave talks i was told at the beginning say what you're going to say then expose it
give the details and at the end say what you have said so here buddha is doing that the buddha is as supreme academic
is like this is what i'm going to tell you i'm going to tell you about the direct path then he goes all through all
the details lays it out and at the end again on top as you see the direct path
this fret this paragraph is repeated again so it's a beautiful
mirror image in that way so and then there is a definition so this definition
here which i will read for you in a minute is also a way of you know offering how
offering how to practice again gives a definition but what i really want to bring your attention to which we'll go
over this week is the refrain do you see the refrain shows up after every
teaching and it for those of you who have read the suta
sometimes ruta sutras can be repetitive and when you see something repeated sometimes like okay okay i've seen this
before i want to see the the actual you know the new part the teaching and yet and yet
the refrain here is repeated 13 times if it weren't important it wouldn't be
repeated 13 times each teaching is repeated once the
refrain is repeated 13 times wow and years ago when i was studying the
sati patana sutta realizing this through
through actually the pointing out of biku analia so his thesis his
phd thesis he's a venerable monk a respected monk and and
he did his thesis on the sati patana sutra which became a book
called sati patano the direct path to realization and when i read this and noticed wow the
refrain is so important and then he exposed the nuances of the refrain it
it made so much sense given my own practice with uh paak sayadaw and the various things
that he had taught me that had blown my mind yes they were in the refrain they were
in the refrain and i hadn't seen them pointed out clearly by others so the
refrain is so important that i would like to bring that to our attention to your
attention this week so so with that
i'd like to i'll read the definition because i borrowed from it the
intern in the uh guided meditation and then read the refrain then we'll go through it more this week so
so the definition goes so after the direct path it says the
four satipatanas it ended there and then continues what are the four
and here practitioners in regards in regard
to the body a practitioner abides contemplating the body
diligent clearly knowing mindful free from desires and discontent in
regard to the world and then he goes through and points out
the other uh the same phrase repeats in regards to feelings in regards to mental objects
i'm sorry in regards to the feelings mind mental objects a practitioner abides contemplating the
body diligent clearly no or contemplating say mind or
mental feeling mental feelings or or or sorry mental objects or feelings
diligent clearly knowing mindful and free from desires and discontent in
regard to the world so basically the buddha is telling us in the
definition at the very beginning like hey i'm going to tell you about these four i'm going to tell you about the body
feelings mind and the mental objects
and the way i invite you to reflect on them
is this four ways with with diligent with diligence with
the sense of energy balanced but sustained application of energy which is this beautiful word
called atapi which i mentioned before
so atapi clear knowing it's sampana mindful sati free from desires and
discontent in regard to the to the world vinaya abijah
nasa so these four like oh yes have these have these and in the guided
meditation i invited for us to bring this atapi this this
sustained application of energy balanced engagement i call it ener engagement or
energy atapi which i love atapi by the way when i learned about it wow what what a
beautiful concept you can just drop it into your practice now and then atapi atapi let it light light up your energy
and the letting go this letting go this which is also a fact of concentration
free from desire and discontent in regards to the world and then some pagania clearly knowing and mindfulness
which is sati which we've been practicing so so the definition
so i'll just briefly read since i've talked about the refrain i'll just read the
refrain um actually i can stop well i'll read the refrain and of course
we'll go through it more there's so much more about the refrain so here goes the refrain
um actually i have it up on my screen i can read it so so after say breathing has been taught
the buddha says in this way in regard to the body one abides
contemplating the body internally or one abides contemplating the body
externally or one abides contemplating the body both internally and externally
wow okay so we have this internal external concept it's we've just expanded the spatial dimension it's not
just internal okay then he continues one abides
contemplating the nature of arising in the body one abides
contemplating the nature of passing away in the body or one abides contemplating the nature
of both arising and passing away in the body okay so we're not just
contemplating the breath itself anymore it's not the object but we've now added
a temporal temporal aspect time arising
passing arising and passing okay we've just expanded
this teaching of breathing in the satipatana to have both spatial internal
external as well as temporal aspects wow okay what else is there in the refrain a
couple more things mindfulness that there is a body established in him
to the extent necessary for bare knowledge and continuous mindfulness i'll say more about this later we just
want to read it and lastly oh this is this is my favorite line and one abides independent
not clinging to anything in the world one
excuse me and one abides independent not clinging to anything in the world
and the last finishing line and this is how in regard to the body one abides
contemplating the body like okay you get it practitioners this is how in regards to the body
wonderboy it's contemplating the body it's just so beautiful i'm going to stop share
it's just so beautiful this teaching is so beautiful and i can't wait for us to
uh to discuss it and explore it in practice together this week so so thank
you so much for your practice for your care for your kind attention and look forward to practicing
together this week may you be well