foreign so my I offer my warm greetings
and my warm wishes for this meditation session
and uh it's a
very fortunate thing I believe to be able to sit and meditate I don't take it for granted even though
I've been doing it for my adult life to be able to connect with oneself
connect with reality with life with freedom with intimacy with love with
appreciation with gratitude with ease and
and with honesty with an honest uh connection to what's really happening
for us the truthfulness of the moment even if it's difficult
so many things that meditation can do and different settings different uh
ways that it's fortunate to sit here with our experience so in the topic of this week is
equanimity and one of the things that supports Equanimity is concentration
which for the purpose of this meditation I'll Define as a
singleness of purpose or singleness of aim
that or a steadiness of aim and I'd like to the analogy for it
is that of a boat moving through the water and the boat is heading maybe to Harbor
and it's a clear spot there where it's heading towards
and it might be far out at sea but he knows it sees the harbor and it
just heads steadily for that Harbor and as it does so all kinds of waves and water and
Maybe Driftwood or different things small things are floating in the water
and but the boats stay steady on this point and allows the water just
to wash off the side of the hull and and the point of the water just kind
of cuts through the cut of the boat to the bow cuts through the water and with the steadiness and aim for
where it's going and whatever else it encounters with the water just washes off to the side washes off to the side
and it's not uh I don't think of it as being dismissive of the water
the boat needs the water to float and to be able to move
and so the and it's not aversive of the water and
it just kind of steadily not stopping for the water and and is moving ahead
and letting everything just wash by its Hull so in the same thing same way it's
possible to sit with the steadiness of aim on the breathing
and it's not necessarily easy to keep the steadiness but the steadiness of
returning the steadiness of beginning again the steadiness of just resting and
staying and this is the harbor this is the Refuge here with the breathing and all kinds of things might arise
and allow it to just wash right by allows you just to be what it is don't
have to be against it or reactive to it or judge it or get excited by it
just let it wash by and if it is difficult that arises
there's no reason to no need to get involved with it as a difficulty
if it's a joy no no reason to get involved with it as a joy just hold the
steadiness with the breathing and in that way the tendency to get
excited or agitated um activated by the things that Iraq that float by in
the water maybe it won't activate you and the mind will stay steady and equanimous equanimous but all things
that uh wash by that float by
so to take a meditation posture and um
to gently close your eyes
and as you are right now can you allow for a gentling
of your innards gentling of your being your body
perhaps by relaxing the muscles that are tense and
the ways in which you are when we're when the muscles are tense it's kind of like we're holding
ourselves against reality away from it or even away from ourselves
to relax as deeply as is possible for you
whilst sitting upright or without slumping in any way
softening all around the face the face that
works so much at expressing ourselves to others into life
and responding and reacting
giving the face a vacation
letting the muscles of the face release from the skull
to soften and relax the shoulders releasing and
allowing the pull of gravity on the shoulders
and to maybe soften in the chest
maybe something just behind the rib cage can settle back
settle back and down as if what's behind the chest the rib
cage you can also relax and
come to rest
in the muscles that are behind the skin of your belly
deeper than where your skin touches your clothes
to see if the belly muscles can relax soften
so there isn't that pulling away pulling backwards in the belly
in the hands and the arms can soften
in the mind let's see if you can bring a gentleness to the mind
a simple kindness
easy kindness
and a willingness to be here in your body
aware and attentive curious appreciating
the opportunity to be here with your lived experience
and then within your body as part of your body becoming aware of your breathing
become aware of how your body experiences breathing
so you're not so much in the control tower looking the breathing
but you're in your body you're in the boat
feeling the gentle movements
of breathing very slight gentle rocking
the body boat as you breathe
and gently but determinately set your course your aim
on your breathing
experiencing the sensations in the body in the belly the chest or the nose
wherever it's easy for you experiencing those Sensations
almost from the inside of the sensations and intimacy
and as you settled as you sit here settling down into the
experience of breathing every time you exhale
letting go of your thoughts
and re-establish the aim the connection to your breathing
and guiding a boat piloting a boat through water the pilot is constantly making ever
small adjustments always attentive always present
heading for the harbor and be heading for the course
stay with your breathing
mind wanders off come back reminders wonders to the left come back
while I'm under wonders to the right to come back mine wanders up into the head
every time you exhale reset the course every time you inhale reset the course
on the breathing just breathing
relaxing the thinking mind the brain so you can settle in
to the journey of just being with a breath
and allow all our everything else that arises to wash right by
no need to get involved or react to whatever is happening
if you can just stay with a breathing let everything else Washed by
like a boat heading straight through the water letting the water just wash off the
sides of the boat
leaving awake as things are left behind
gently lovingly determinedly
hold your course steadily being with your breathing
every in-breath and out breath hold the course where the breathing
and letting your thoughts that have come up be sure to let them just wash right by
don't be involved in them just be involved with your breathing
give no thought no concern with the mind that wanders off in thought
as soon as you notice Let It wash through as soon as you notice Begin Again with
your breathing steadying yourself
on the breathing in and breathing out
if there are strong emotions that pull you away from the breathing
see if you can let those just wash by forever along they're there wave after
wave hold the course on the breathing
not being bothered by anything
who in the mind is equanimous who are not are not bothered by
all the water that walks washes by it's easier to have a steadiness of
purpose to just hold the course with what's important
not with attachment or aggression
but with an ease and a
unbotheredness
and whatever degree of concentration and equanimity that arises from meditation
it's one of the great things to turn that ability to hold a Steady Aim
and turn it towards having Good Will and care for others
to now arrive arouse the thoughts the intentions
and the wishes for the welfare and happiness of others
as steady gaze of care and kindness
as if you're sitting on a hill and a relaxed easy way under
an oak tree and you can gaze out across the world
and you have the Good Fortune to be able to
gaze with care kindness and
love for all beings
and to consider how today
you might express your steadiness of purpose
for the purpose of supporting others lightening their load
caring for them bringing joy and happiness
how is it that how you experience yourself in meditation
can bring in Equanimity and unbotheredness and ease
to meeting the challenges of this world
may it be that we come into this world that's so challenged
so the steadiness of care and love and generosity
may all beings be happy
may all beings be healthy and safe
may all beings be free
so the topic for today is to continue the discussion from
yesterday so the general topic is equanimity and Equanimity is a form of care or love for
the world for others and um and to not be all bothered by
what's going on with others and people and ourselves and be able to keep a kind of steadiness
of mind calmness or ease of mind so that our love is not agitated by the challenges
of this world the challenges of people and others what goes on and in particular as I've been saying is
the challenges so the mind doesn't get caught up in pursuing engaging doing doing trying to
fix all kinds of things that disturb our love and Equanimity getting too quickly
wanted to fix things and the other is not getting caught up
in repulsion pushing away and and not being able to stay present or
going away from what's going on closing down but to be able to stay open
and and wise without anxiously getting involved unnecessarily
or inappropriately when we can't do anything when it's not appropriate for us to try to be involved
or fix or do something there's many reasons for that uh
why it's not appropriate to actually actively get involved one is that sometimes it's better to let people find
their own way and we can offer our support in terms of our presence and our appreciation and
our encouragement but if we do everything for other people then we don't let them grow strong
there's this beautiful story that went around some years ago and that of a person I don't know if it's
just made up or true but it's a person who comes across a cocoon with a butterfly is about to be
born and come out of and and the Butterfly is struggling to come out of
the Cocoon and the caring person thinks wants to help and so kind of pulls in
some of the threads to loosen up the the space so the butterfly can come out and when the butterfly finally comes out
the butterfly falls to the ground and never flies and dies and what the caring
person doesn't know is that only in the struggle to get free of the Cocoon that
the butterfly lubricates its its wings enough to be able to fly properly
and so the struggle is needed for the butterfly and so one of the reasons not to get too
involved in other people's struggles is when when and only when for example when
it only but when they need to kind of be left alone to let them find their own
way and learn and develop and strengthen and if we do it for them they never grow they never face themselves and is
especially true spiritually um you know if someone fixes all our problems for us we'll never develop the
insight and the capacity and the inner strength to address the problems for ourselves
um and so anyway there's many reasons to develop this and but one of the things that gets in the way
of staying equanimous and loving and and unagitated is for many people is a sense
of responsibility and certainly identify with this is one of my achilles heels has been maybe
still is a little bit the sense of being responsible for too many things responsible for other people how they
feel and needing to somehow get involved and um
and so in terms of uh allowing people the autonomy to choose to make their own
actions and choices and uh and not realizing is not up to us what choices
they make we can support them we can offer guidance and advice but ultimately
people make choices for themselves and to take responsibility for how people feel and how people the outcomes
of people's lives too much is to get agitated as to you could lose the Equanimity and in some ways also lose
the clarity of of Love The Clarity of of
Good Will that can be there when uh responsibility kicks in in kind of a
unhealthy way so in order to have this maintain a kind
of equanimous care and love and Goodwill for some of us it's useful to look at
this topic of responsibility and in this regard I find it interesting
that this word English word responsibility has a wide range of
meanings that as far as I can tell is different in some other countries
I read once that one of the first people to study the Iroquois Erica Iroquois
Nation found out that claimed that there was no word in that language for
responsibility but they seem to have a very successful and Noble civilization
without the word responsibility the if you look in the poly dictionary
poly English dictionary there's a very very there's already a small handful two
three four words that the Englishmen who
made the dictionary over 100 years ago chose to add the word responsibility as
one of its meanings and but those words uh the main meetings meanings are things
like burden and uh and so you know his burden isn't
quite you know I think uh a satisfying definition for the English word responsibility
and so there's almost as if that word responsibility doesn't quite work in the Buddha in the languages of the Buddha
and I speak Norwegian and in Norwegian the word for responsibility is
which means to answer it's like it's a cognitive the English word answer
and it's probably a closer in meaning to maybe the French or Italian words for
response so response I respond responder that then the English word
responsibility to in Norwegian the connotations of unspa means
um uh what you're what you have to answer for what you what you're accountable for
and um whereas the word uh there's a different word for obligation or Duty in the
region it's clicked and so the um the and so these are two different words
whereas in English it seems to me that the idea of obligation Duty and
accountability are all kind of in the range of meanings of responsibility
so much so that responsibility often comes across as something we're obligated to do we have a responsibility
to do something whereas and uh in the Norwegian word
unspa is that we're accountable for what we do we have to answer for what we do
so if we take English word responsibility to mean that we're responsible for our actions
that's a Buddhist that's a kind of goes clearly along with Buddhist ways of
thinking that we're responsible for how we act and what we do the choices we make and
we're responsible for the outcome we're certainly responsible for making the choices and doing the ACT but we're
responsible and we're accountable to the to to the outcome and so what is not in Buddhism is this
idea that we carry with us in an innate obligation and duty to become free to be
loving to be kind to be responsible for other people that responsibility is not
this weight that we carry with us in some ways Buddhist practice frees us from a certain understanding of
responsibility their sense of obligation and Duty as far as I can tell there's no sense no
there's nothing come from Buddhism teachings of the Buddha any sense of obligation in doing the spiritual
practice in life there's no obligation to be loving there's no obligation to be
generous there's no obligation to be caring for other people it's not a duty
it is an opportunity it is a choice it is something we might want to do
but not because we're obligated to do it and the only reason we have obligation
in Buddhism is if we've made a promise about a commitment or if we have a
purpose that we want to fulfill then kind of I don't know if obligation is the right word but certain purposes
require certain things if you want to discover the benefits of
meditation and really dedicate your life to really live out the benefits of meditation
um that requires maybe you could say we're obligated then but maybe I wouldn't but we requires
that we meditate and um so um
but this idea that uh Buddhism very much frees us from this sense of obligation and Duty in favor of being accountable
for the choices we make and uh and the actions we do we're we
have to answer for the consequences of them for ourselves as do other people
and this sense of freedom from this kind of obligatory responsibility
means that we can enter into different situations kind of with a fresh mind with a clear mind ready to respond we
have an ability to respond ready to meet the situation as it is but without
caring with us the kind of ideations and Notions and ideas of what we have to do and should
do that are often a trigger for reactivity for being upset that things
don't go along or that I'm not doing what I'm supposed to do I'm obligated to be a certain way in this situation
but to enter any any situation without obligation and then to respond as is
appropriate to meet it and see what the choices are it can help with this equanimity
it's easier than perhaps to love because then love is not burdened by Duty by
what that we have to be a certain way we have to respond a certain way we have to fix the situation
and so we can just be there and figure out what's needed and so the Equanimity love of equanimity
the Equanimity Brahma viharas is often very valuable to be the first way in
which we meet the person first way in which we meet a situation it's a kind of the first way of
discovering and finding out what's there if we enter into a new situation or meet
a new person and we're just automatically being compassionate for them before we even
know them it's a little bit burdensome for them and certainly we're kind of activated
or if we're already feeling Joy before we know anything about them we might actually do them a disservice if someone
someone they loved just died and we just kind of already just jumping forth with
our appreciation how wonderful they are or if we just have too much good will for them before a chance for there to be
some real connection and knowledge and appreciate to see something and then we can appreciate also is kind of off
so this ability to know what uh the equanimous love or non-reactive love
love that doesn't carry any responsibility and obligation with it but it's just there like an Open Door
that's there ready to meet whatever whoever comes through that door and then
respond accordingly so if some of you can be you know a
little bit like me with an Achilles heel of the responsibility that is obligation
or Duty um to really develop this uh Equanimity by
Mariah's it helps to kind of see that we do this and not be caught by it and and
let it just be water that washes by as you hold yourself steady in your love
and your care for the world don't be tripped up by obligation and
Duty even if other people expect that of you why should they
and why should we believe them that that's that that's that that's how it has to be it's possible to love and be generous
and kind and and um and have very rich and warm relationships without any sense
of Duty and obligation unless you've made promises
so um I hope this is helpful and as I explore this topic of equanimity and
we'll continue tomorrow thank you