good morning everyone can you hear me okay yeah great yes two thumbs up even yay thanks Nancy
good morning good morning it's lovely to be with you all in person wow
three dimensions sweet still surprises me after two and a half
years of of uh Zoom so um let's begin with
sitting together and I'll offer a very lightly guided sit just to help us
settle so
arriving
arriving in this body arriving in this moment in time
and bringing awareness to this body to this body sitting
or maybe at home you are lying down if your body needs to lie down right now
because of pain or self-care the position of this body
and if there is movement needed right now rolling back the shoulders perhaps
ah maybe trying to sit up a little straighter just a tiny bit
just to bring more awareness more uprightness
more sense of integrity and alignment
and feeling feeling the connection of your body
to the Earth
if you're sitting on the cushion feeling your bottom on the cushion your legs
your feet you find a chair the bottom of your feet on the Earth
feeling grounded there might be a lot happening maybe a
lot has happened before you got here physically
figuratively it's okay it's all right
that can be happening still but it's like a globe it's like a snow globe
that's shaken it's still settling still said I it's okay
the snow globe down on the Earth feel grounded feel the connection of it
feel the stability of this body while all the flurries all the flurries settle
the flurries it's okay
but be aware pay attention pay attention
this moment is precious fleeting pay attention
let the breath move Harvard once deep shallow
move through the body not controlled
Let the Body be relaxed soft the mind be soft
and the body is relaxed the mind can relax checking in with the forehead
softening if needed the jaw
neck shoulders eyes in your socket in their socket
let them relax ah moving down arms hands
chest abdomen
sit bones and legs
and feet
really Landing arriving more deeply
every moment
welcoming age and every in-breath and out breath
every in-breath like spring
every out breath like the fall leaves falling you're letting go
appreciating the arrival of each in breath
like a gift
and appreciating and letting go in each out breath
with equanimity
every moment a new arrival and the new letting go
the rising and passing arising and passing
such is the nature of human life
pay attention
and if you find your mind is traveling
to distance places memories plans it's like the snow globe is getting
shaken again it's okay it's all right
notice what has happened and set the snow globe down again and
again and again become embodyed connect with your body
let awareness know that you're sitting and breathing
no judgment
no self-recombination gently set it down again and again
and connect with this passing moment
in this body In this River of experience the body mind and heart
foreign
letting the attention be turned inward
flow of experience in the body
as a way of grounding settling and knowing knowing change
Sensations keep shifting and moving
maybe tingling in your hands
sit bones
temperature shifting
maybe feeling the abdomen expand and contract with each breath
this landscape of shifting changing experience
it keeps changing
stay with the change
feel impermanence intimately for yourself
internally with each moment
foreign
change internally in each moment not as an idea
but as a felt sense experience firsthand
what do you notice
does it stay the same does it keeps shifting
depressed Sensations thoughts keep arising
seemingly uncontrollably
notice what's happening notice pay attention
no change get to know change
ultimately
and if at any point knowing change feels overwhelming too much is changing
internally then feel the stability of the posture
being grounded on the Earth
feel the snow globe resting on the earth stable
ability stability to support seeing change
foreign
can there be a sense of spaciousness stability groundedness
your body your mind
sitting upright grounded rooted with change
with change internally
making space allowing for change
as it is the nature of all things
can we welcome change
with stability groundedness equanimity
and not fight against it
it's all changing all the time can we intimately know this for
ourselves even for a Split Second
and as we bring this
sitting period to a close appreciating yourself
for your practice not judging what happened or did not happen you did
your best
you showed up in aligned your actions as best as you
could with your intentions wonderful
appreciating yourself for having shown up
practiced and trusting there is goodness there's goodness in this
cultivation and offering this goodness to yourself
and all beings everywhere may my actions
my practice my wholeheartedness
without attachment to results may my goodness be of service
to all beings everywhere including myself
may all beings everywhere be happy and free including myself
foreign good morning
so you've been sitting for a while and out of kindness to your body I'm going to suggest you if you'd like you can get
up and stretch for a minute while I get set up with my notes Here
give some love to those bodies okay
okay all right hi
good to see you good to be with you yay how nice just touches my heart to be in the room
with you this is so wild right things we used to take for granted all right used
to take for granted and now it's like wow I'm in a room with people how nice is that
how awesome is that yeah just really yeah actually I want to invite all of us
because I'm really feeling the the poignancy of being in a room with other human
beings and and listening to the Dharma sharing the Dharma supporting each other
in this path it's so poignant and and all of us have
traveled walked or biked or driven miles I know so it's
thank you for for being here really thank you for each other for being here
so so for the topic for today's reflections
I'd like to invite us to reflect on um
unchanged on impermanence you might have already guessed that from
the invitations in the guided meditation yeah you noticed yeah yeah yeah
so the guided meditation just to share what what the intention was was at the
beginning to try to stabilize with the body become stable feel the grounding
because in order to know change it's helpful to have a sense of stability right remember the the metaphor I used
with the snow globe that's shaken and it's like oh everything is twirling all
the little bits and pieces and when we arrive often on the cushion our minds are like that and oh set it down
ah set it down yes feel the body feel the stability feel yourself in the Earth
on the ground and in fact the Earth mudra you see the Buddha is touching the
Earth right groundedness groundedness and the story
of the earth mudra there as as you've seen many Buddha statues actually have the Earth mudra
story is that in the night of his Enlightenment the Buddha uh was was assailed
by Mara the personification of uh of
doubt and and all the other you know the full catastrophe that we have in our
minds I can't do this oh and and it's it's said that the story is that Mara it
comes as doubt and says who are you you think you're gonna wake up and awaken who'd who do you think you are and and
with all of what's going on that is the shaking right the shaking of the all the little
pieces moving the the all the moving pieces in the mind the Buddha touches the Earth as
Earth be my witness I belong here as Earth be my witness I belong here and
studies himself grounds himself hence the Earth mudra so remember at any
time there's no Globe the little pieces are are twirling inside and they do
twirl don't they a lot not just in sitting meditation but throughout the day who do you think you are or this or
that I guess ground ground
so so in our guided meditation I started with inviting you to ground the body
feeling the connection to the Earth feeling the the breath
relaxing relaxing the different parts of the body very briefly because as again
as the body relaxes the mind can relax or so connected they're so connected and
and especially if you're a newer meditator um
sometimes as a newer meditator I remember I would sit and I would come and sit and like okay I'm trying to quiet my mind it took me a while to
realize oh I need to quiet my body first if I really settle my body if I really
stabilize pay attention to my bodies stabilize it around it oh yeah the mind
it's like a little babies like when you call me it's like oh yeah it it falls asleep it becomes not sleep but you know
it calms it becomes calmer when the body is calming so so again coming back to the to the
guided meditation what we did is to settle in the body relax and then I invited you to notice change
I invited you to turn to change internally starting with a breath
each in-breath as a spring a rival new arrival each out breath as
falling as a falling of leaves as like the fall and specially given that in northern hemisphere is the fall as I was
driving to IMC this morning especially down uh Bridge Street wow all the leaves have
fallen it's so beautiful there is a Grace there's a beauty in the letting go in the fall so
change every breath in breath the spring every out breath of fall and noticing
the change noticing every moment Sensations there's
there's um tingling moving shifting all of that all
this change to get to know change intimately because change yeah yeah everything changes we know that concept
yeah yeah everything changes yeah for sure what's new but really getting to know it intimately
is an Insight it's actually a profound inside
in Buddhism it's one what's known as one of the
three characteristics of existence
and the three characteristics
as a review the first one is impermanence in constancy Anita Anita
I'll talk more about that today that's the focus of the reflections today
a ninja the other one is tukka this word that often gets translated as suffering
but it actually that's one translation another translation just as well could
be stress or unsatisfactoriness or just things not quite being right it's like it's never
right do you notice get yourself comfortable and say you're okay for a few minutes it's like oh it's not
it's that sense of dukkha is just that is that is there not quite
right ever even if you get conditions you know perfect
a nature impermanence unsatisfactoriness and anata
impersonality or not self which doesn't mean that you don't exist
and there isn't a self but it means that it's impersonal it's ungovernable and these three
characteristics actually relate to each other they're all different aspects of one another
when something is inconstant keeps changing right Anita when something
isn't constant it's ungovernable it just can't quite fix it get it in one place right hence
anata comes out of that and and also when something keeps changing you can't
quite make it satisfactory and let it stay that way right so these three are
different it's like the light coming through a diamond and just a refraction just going
out different it's the same light but you just see it in different ways in your experience
foreign so impermanent such an important thing to uh to uh
contemplate to to actually become aware of it's really liberating it's a liberating
reflection and it's not bad news it's not
like ah Everything Changes okay might as well that's not the idea here but to
actually appreciate that things change they're not going to stay this way they change
all the time borrowed from
from saido Ray Ranchi from the examined right life
and they say wisdom it's not merely something to be gained with old age
one can be wise in every stage of one's life
to manifest wisdom means simply to step back
and see to reflect in choir be aware
be disciplined and be focused not once in a while but
all the time moment to moment this life is precious and fleeting pay
attention this life is precious and fleeting pay
attention so one aspect of appreciating impermanence is not to have
the delusion of permanence because we have the delusional permanence that's
the modus operandi that as human beings we operate on and it's not our fault
it's just evolutionarily we're designed to think oh yeah things are fixed and you just think about tomorrow and the
day after and the next year and the next decade is going to be fixed and nothing's going to change and things are changing
it's not going to stay this way appreciate it appreciate it especially
this being the Sunday before in in North America in the U.S Being Thanksgiving
next week appreciate giving thanks things are not going to stay the same they're they're shifting and changing
all the time people you appreciate in your life people whom you love and care about
people who annoy you appreciate them all these relationships are impermanent
they are so important we are we're so impermanent we just don't quite connect with it we feel
like maybe we do connect with it intellectually but not um
on an inside level there are different levels of insight and also talk about this a little more in a moment
so the word um Anita again impermanence if you if
you pay it if you notice in many Buddhist teachings impermanence teachings and impermanence keep coming
impermanence impermanence impermanence and impermanence is a doorway really
deep insight into impermanence it's a doorway to nabana to Liberation
to the mind opening up becoming freed up it is a doorway it's
not just some something nice to do or have but this is the way
so pay attention pay attention to change pay attention to how you react to change
say more about that in a minute but um say something about the word so Anita in
Pali this word is spelled a-r-a-n-i
-c-ca and the sea is is pronounced as cha
instead of Anika it's actually Anita a-n-i-c-c-a
and in poly the word literally means inconstant
and it arises from the synthesis of two separate words one being Nicha
and the Primitive ah which negates everything so Nicha means continuous
concept of continuity and permanence and ah means not so not permanent
and Suzuki roshi the author of Zen mind beginner's mind
and the founder of San Francisco Zen Center
the ones they were asked by a student who came to them and said I've been
listening to your lectures for years and I still don't understand can you please can you please express
Buddhism in a nutshell thank you
so he did he replied everything changes
that's Buddhism in a nutshell Everything Changes
Everything Changes Everything Changes
so when we fight that right do you notice in your heart if we fight that
everything changes our when we fight that we suffer
when we make peace with that yeah
this body changes it ages it's Age It's Gonna Age It's Gonna Die
everything everyone I love they'll change they'll be separated from
everything I love thing change
when you make deep peace with change
when you make peace with that your heart is liberated
it's not constantly uh whenever change happens or the thought
of change it relaxes it's freed it can have Equanimity to
hold change it can still grieve it's okay you don't become a robot
it's okay to have emotions and grief it's fine but there is the sense of
ease there's a sea and sense of ease and not fighting not fighting with Things
Are
another quote from Suzuki roshi continuing that so he says everything
changes there is nothing to stick to that is the Buddha's most important
teaching so so today's topic is the Buddha's most
important teaching according to Suzuki Rashi Everything Changes
and change is so around us it's it's within us it's
around us you know on so many different levels geologically
we can see and we can see uh cultures and when we go to historical places
perhaps if we if we travel and we see different
civilizations that have come and gone I remember years ago I went to um
Cambodia to Angkor Wat and seeing the the glamor that is it's a Grandeur the
Grandeur of of the Southeast Asian um
um civilization and wow things how things have changed and made me realize oh this sympathization the western
civilization if there were the Roman and the Greeks and now you know there is the United States in some ways and you're
the hegemony of the US and like oh if it's all impermanent we're just part of
part of this this um this ocean ocean of change ocean of
change so larger levels historical and
then chapters of our lives right you're not the child anymore you're not
a teenager it's all gone who are you
and not just that not just chapters of your lives but of your life but also
every day since you woke up this morning how many thoughts how many emotions how
many Reflections have you had like since you arrived here at IMC or turned
on the YouTube channel like how many thoughts how many Sensations like it keeps changing
he keeps changing all the time
your body your mind your eye just keeps change just this this it's like a waterfall when you actually
start to notice so when when invitation in practice
in meditation is as as I invited you in the guided meditation and then again this was a
short meditation and short time to to contemplate change but say on on Long
Retreats when your mind is really stable and quiet and actually it can happen in
short sits too so not to to um say it can't happen but but
um the mind when the mind can be if the mind is quiet it can happen anytime if
the mind is really present to get to see that they appearance is like a waterfall
appearance is like a waterfall so much changing shifting all the time
all the time
and what's so seeing change so when we see change
our minds can react in many ways and often the first reaction that our
minds have is resistance and that it's natural don't blame yourself this is
just what happens when we see change our minds tend to resist it we don't
want it we want things to stay the same unless unless we want impermanence to be on our side and sometimes impermanence
is on our side right it's like I don't I don't like the situation impermanence change it please
except for that usually we we don't like change
we're scared of it perhaps there's a sense of um unsettledness or or fear that can arise
because even sometimes even if things are uncomfortable
then at least it's what we know it's a devil we know versus the devil we don't or we don't want chains maybe it's a
relationship that's not quite happy but we know it we don't want change right
so being afraid of change
and we often blame ourselves we blame others
there's a sense of blame with the resistance that can come
we don't want our bodies to change our minds
one concept here which which I really like to to
um um it's a it's a when I heard that the
first time something lit up for me like yeah that makes sense of course so
as I was saying earlier if we resist change we suffer and one way to say that
is rope burned right when there is a big when there's a rope and the Rope keeps
going and we're trying to hold on to the Rope really really hard really really tight we get rope burned you know what
rope burn is yeah your hands are so notice when you are new when you're
connected when you don't want things to change so so why is let's turn to why is this
teaching on impermanence why is it one of the most important teachings of the Buddha
so let's contemplate that for a moment why would it be there's so many different teachings right find this one
Well I this one
I'll share a suit to reference
this is from Maji manikaya 37 the shorter discourse on the destruction
of craving and this is translation quoted by Joseph
Goldstein so so pay attention
in seeing impermanence the mind doesn't cling
it's not agitated when it's not agitated it personally
attains Nirvana
I'm going to read this again this is not just poetry so it sounds beautiful but these are actually
instructions to how to practice how to become free
it's very clear step by step by step pay attention
by the way there have been examples where where um where people have given Dharma talks
people have listened and they have suddenly become awakened so pay attention this might just happen [Laughter]
[Music] there's always hoping so here we go 37.
in seeing impermanence the mind doesn't cling
when the mind doesn't cling it's not agitated
when it's not agitated it personally attains Nirvana
yes [Laughter]
it's always hoping
a couple of things to uh to be aware of when is that impermanence is not
suppose this insight into impermanence is not supposed to be used
as a spiritual bypass be very careful about that oh yeah
everything changes whatever no point yeah whatever I'm just gonna go on lie
there and let things change that's not wisdom
so it's not that nothing matters is that actually things are even more precious
life this life is precious pay attention it's impermanent
it actually imbues you know there is when the heart is free and not agitated
then it has more capacity for beauty for goodness for love for
service instead of being threatened by every shift and change
aging lost if it's okay yet these are part of the human experience can we appreciate value value at all and and
live and love fully in the midst of all the change so it frees the heart to
Love More not to not care and say yeah whatever I don't it doesn't matter it's quite the
opposite you see so please don't
use impermanence as a as an impermanent slap as a uh
to slap it on a spiritual Bypass or it doesn't matter quite the opposite truly
as an Insight it allows one to care more and love more deeply
it also allows one to develop to
um drop into different levels of perception
from the content into the process right because we are often stuck with
the content but when we see impermanence we get to
see the process we get to see change itself not the thing but the process we
get to drop down a level from the movie of our life being an actor being and we were still
an actor but we we step out a little bit and see we see the movie on the screen
oh yes we are an actor yes we still love we still care
we still care but it frees us up to actually love and care more freely
not to be so attached to things that are impermanent of course they're
impermanent let's wake up waking up nibana let's wake up to the fact that
things are impermanent and they are beautiful they're precious they're wonderful but not to be
threatened all the time of that
so there's more I can say but I think I would like to pause and maybe what I
like to do is to turn it around and ask you a couple questions
so if you will so one is the meditation earlier is
there anything that came up for you anything that in your first person experience and now the meditation was
gosh a whole what 30 minutes an hour ago so much has happened so much content you
might have forgotten all about it but if there was something that really jumped out
for you when you when the invitation was given to observe change in your first
person experience for the benefit of others for the benefit of others I'd
like to invite you to to share let's open up to that if if there is anyone or
anything that comes out and if not it's okay too
hi there oh okay that's a little bit loud but um so the thing that I noticed is that I have in the past tended to
experience sensation and a kind of like mental map of like where I think the body should be and what it should be
like and then you kept emphasizing like personal experience I was like oh oh
like I'm just like actual like experience like there instead of on leg of the like Mental Math if that makes
sense yeah yeah totally nice great so what I hear happened for you is
usually you experience Sensations as if it's a mental map as it's like it's out there it's like oh yeah there's a leg
there's some emotion whereas today what happened for you it's like oh it's right here there's like look at that it's
moving and changing it's shifting wow beautiful thank you this is great stay
with that because that's how this the the intimacy of this inside arises from
that thank you thank you
thank you Nikki um I recently took a class with Bob Stahl on the 32 parts of the body
and um for me the meditation was um
being aware of your bodily processes and all of the sort of birth and death
that's constantly going on just within your body
yeah great thank you for that Nancy yeah wonderful it's just this awareness of
the constant birth and death and the processes in the body and and the way I
hear you because you've done this practice now with with Bob stahlgrade the third parts of the body it's I'm not
here I'm hearing a sense of oh wow this is what it is it's like ah because again
that sense of fear or disgust or whatever it might be it can arise but after a while when one actually really
stays where the wisdom and Rises oh yeah this is how it is I usually ignore it I
push it under the carpet wow isn't this amazing this body this body that is mine
but yet not quite my like how did this even happen right I've been born as this
body and this keeps changing and moving and and um digesting and like I don't have any
healing and I don't I I don't have any control over this it's just this this
awe this amazement for being human can be born out of this uh a sense of
impermanence thank you and again all of this is about loving living more fully
more being more fully human um it's not about nihilism but it's sort
of if your practice goes into no it doesn't it's all changed don't care like it's gone off the rails
though any other Reflections in a few minutes we have left or any questions from what has been or any Reflections
that might have come up from share today yeah thank you for what you both shared
I really resonate with that um and I just appreciated the metaphor of the snow globe and oftentimes I find
when I said it's like stop stopping snow globes like I just want to like control it to settle it down and just allowing
the allowing things to settle naturally was really helpful so thank you great great thank you for that yeah I love the
snow globe as well yeah it's just such a nice metaphor so gentle right it takes a while for all the flurries to settle and
this sense of groundedness yeah there please
thank you I just had a question about the personal Enlightenment that you
talked about yeah um as opposed to what it when it it's
impersonal Enlightenment or yeah yeah yeah yeah thanks for catching that yeah
yeah this is interesting so so yeah it's um
this is an interesting I'm trying to find in the sutta that I shared yeah and
the part that is translated as when it's not agitated it personally attains Nirvana
so various interpretations about that one is the personal versus the universal
right because these are Universal insights that we
have but it actually it's um
in order to have Universe have insights into the nature
of things as they are the only way to do that isn't to think
about you know we don't start thinking about the how things work you know that's not how this practice works
it's very personal it's you you study you pay attention to your Sensations you
know the doors of the sensations sounds thoughts uh vadana feeling tone liking
disliking all of the you know personal Justice you become the laboratory that's
and through the personal when you study these personal things when you realize oh when I don't cling when I cling wow
it really hurts you really get to see that you really get to feel that and
when the and the when you see that oh and I let go for example ah there is
freedom there is peace there is ease there's more space for love and care for others so it's all of these
Universal insights are through the personal through the personal
studying which seems nitty-gritty like wait I'm becoming really self-centered I'm sitting on the cushion and just you
know noticing my breath and Sensations but it's really through the personal that we get to the
universal otherwise it becomes waxing philosophy so one way to interpret it interpret this this line that personally
attains a Nirvana is this personal through through the door of the personal to the universal I'm sure there are
other interpretations too but I leave you with this one thank you okay
maybe one last reflection if there is one yeah violet
um a few years ago when I was meditating very regularly I put the daily
remembrances on my wall and they were a source of great sort of joy and peace and then
as my meditation sort of comes and goes in regular practice sometimes I look at them and I'm like
gross I should take those down there's like aversion to it and um
I guess something I've experienced in permanence with in the last year is like impermanence in my like belief and faith
in like Dharma teaching and is that kind of impermanence okay like the
impermanence of just like belief that
it's hard to maintain faith that contemplating impermanence actually brings more peace than suffering
yeah yeah yeah so um so thank you for that for bringing
that in multiple various things you've said so when you talked about you know
previously the five Reflections being up and then being a source of joy and
now since like ah this cusp and seems like that is a part of this shift in
your faith and [Music] um about
and it seems like more General about General than is
um contemplating impermanence does it really lead to
Freedom or does it lead to more suffering I mean that's part sounds like that's part of the the
um doubt but it seems like there might be more to it right so I hear more so so
does this bring is it does this path bring more peace or does it bring more
suffering I wonder or am I putting words in your mouth Violet I
I think yeah I think that's true yeah yeah yeah so
that's okay it goes through you know I think that the Crux of your question is does ones
Faith or or trust go does it also shift and change
um you're not the first practitioner I've heard of where the faith comes and goes with this sense of trust becomes
stronger or weaker and I would say actually this is a um it's a natural
part of the process and it might be a maturing
it might be maturing so because sometimes we might have a blind faith maybe this might be the case may
not be but for some there might be a sense of finding say the teachings that
armor and jumping into it so there could be a sense of Blind Faith and then later wondering what he actually does this
work does this piece work for me does this piece not work for me and becoming more Discerning about what pieces work
for you what pieces don't work and then maybe in in that discernment maybe something happens that we throw the baby
out with the bath water so that could be a part of what's happening and that's okay it's natural so we throw the baby
off with right this doesn't work because it's terrible and it's like wait actually I miss it wait that thing did work there were things about that that
really work so we start to bring in pieces and with a verified Faith so you
might be going through that the phase of throw the baby out with the bath water then hang in there
hang in there it's it's part of the path it's part of hanging there so that your
your trust becomes a personal verified trust in what actually works for you
because knowing you now for a while I know that there there are aspects of that that practice you've done
um it's um having heard from you firsthand
um you've grown and you've become wiser Kinder more compassionate and that
and that can't change so so going through this period is okay
hang in there does that does that help things that I feel like that really describes what's been going on
thank you thank you
okay okay all right thank you all
for spending this time together coming to IMC they're physically or virtually
thank you all for your practice may you be well may you be safe may you be kind
to yourself and others and Mayors our practice serve all beings including
ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone