so good morning and a good day
from redwood city inside meditation center so and thank you for being part of this
i appreciate it very much coming here and in a certain way kind of sitting in the
middle in the midst of all of you so um
because buddhism to the degree to which buddhism or meditation mindfulness
is associated with values of peace of non-harming of a certain kind of
modesty and non-greed non-hatred
it's very easy in that process to feel that one should diminish oneself
it's a degree to which there's letting go of attachments and one of the primary attachments is to
self there's a can be the idea that somehow we should
be self-effacing and diminishing ourselves kind of like we don't count or just let go of our own
needs or situations or somehow somehow consider ourselves unimportant
maybe but in fact it's true that buddhism has a lot to do
with letting go of attachment to self letting go of conceit and arrogance is a
big part of it and there's also
a coming into or merging into a kind of personal strength
uh a certain kind of very some people say unshakeable confidence
that we can take our stand we can be here in
a clear upright full way as if we count as if
we are allowed to be strong and in that strength
to uh not be arrogant in that strength to not cause harm or in that strength not
to be you know not to cause harm in the world or or to
hold ourselves in a way that any kind of way that diminishes other
people but still to just be there with strength
and some people might say with power some people might say use the word confidence
some people might use this idea of uh you we're allowed to be here in a very stable
clear upright kind of way here so in this meditation that we do today
i'd like to try to evoke this for you as a support for your meditation
practice and and maybe some of the words that i use
will not work for some of you and one of the arts of guided meditations is if some word that's being
used is not quite right for you you might try rewording it and
see what word might a similar word might work for you or you might consider
that maybe in general circumstances this word doesn't this concept doesn't work
for you but that there might be one or two times in your life where this
it is relevant it is important and so to kind of use that situation as a reference for what the meditation is
about so um
so assuming a posture for meditation in whatever posture it is
probably most of you are sitting a few might be standing if you might be lying down
and there might be some of you also who are maybe doing this walking maybe walking back and forth in
in your room as you listen whatever posture you have to
enter into it with the idea that you're going to
have a posture that has room for your confidence
even if you don't know you're confident yet you create that so maybe sitting up a
little straighter than you normally would maybe rolling your shoulders back
a little bit
maybe letting your chest be a little bit more open and expanded
and then feeling the base wherever your whatever is where your weight of your body touches
your mat your chair your bed the floor
see if you can feel a solid stability there
recently as your weight the body
comes into contact with what is supporting your weight
feeling the support the stability
and perhaps that support or stability for some of you
can be a source of something comparable to confidence
something that's going to hold your confidence or from which confidence can arise
gently close your eyes
and in a moment to take a few long slow deep breaths as we often do
but see if you can let the deeper breaths three quarters full not a strain to breathe just
deeper breath be breathing with confidence
with a kind of intentionality
volition that you're really behind and really
this is breathing confidently
breathing in deeply and then letting go of it all as you exhale
maybe a long exhale softening relaxing the body
breathing in confidently and exhaling letting go into embodied
strength embodied confidence
into and let your breathing return to normal
and take a few moments finding where in your body
what parts what area of your body do you most associate with your strength
personal strength or
confidence if if you are going to do something with some
strength or real confidence dedication
is there some place where you would feel that strength or that confidence
in your chest or your belly hands or the feet
in the spine it could be anywhere
and if you have such a place that you associate with personal strength or confidence
breathe with it let your breathing kind of move through it
accompany it
as if gently calmly breathing is aligning itself with that
confidence
breathing is carrying that strength spreading it through the body
gently
let your inhales arise from your confidence and your
strength
and on the exhale
let go of your thoughts
let go of reactions
let go of self-preoccupation
let go of ways in which you are measuring yourself for
judging yourself
letting there be inner strength confidence
as you breathe in and as you exhale let go
and let go into that confidence
a confidence that reassures the mind
it doesn't need to think about things figure things out
it doesn't need to be involved in self-concern
self-preoccupation
confident to be here now
in this lived experience
and might there be for you a calm confidence
a confident come
where some subtleness or calmness
coexists with strength
a strength which is not asserting anything
as their strength which is not calling attention to itself
but is embodied strength
that offers confidence to being present here and now
may be present through the body
that offers confidence for about the value
of being aware being present to the experience here and now
feeling for a moment or two whatever degree of embodied confidence
or strength that's stability that's here
and staying somehow resting in that
turn your mind's eye outward to the people in your life in your
communities
the world of neighbors and colleagues and
people of your town your city your region
people you know and don't know
and with that confidence that strength gaze upon them kindly
gaze upon the world with good will and friendliness
ready to attend to others
aware of them in their conditions their situation
where your inner strength does not direct you towards
conceit of your own but to care
of self and others
may this practice that we do
free us from conceit
and liberate a confidence that allows us to meet the
world with good will with care
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
do
so the theme this week is binding and unbinding
or being tangled and untangled
and that there are qualities of our inner life qualities of being
that um can look like each other be related to kind of similar
but on either side of that divide and so sometimes in
letting go of how what these two are confused and letting go of
what how we get caught and entangled in attachments because the uh the the wholesome side of
it looks similar we might let go of that too but we want to keep the wholesome that
which is unbinding that which is helps us to become untangled
and so the conceit is one side of that divide for
today buddhism puts a tremendous emphasis on freedom from conceit
and sees that conceit is clearly an attachment and entanglement
and and then together with that is this philosophy this teaching that uh that we
to realize not self to realize how many things everything
but how many things in our life that we take somehow to be me myself and mine
aren't really that way and they're not really who i really am
and so to let go the entanglement with things that we appropriate for our
self-identity for the way we cling to identity and ideas
so these two ideas of not self and overcoming conceit then lends itself to
the idea that you're not supposed to in any kind of way be strong or be confident and show up in
some kind of confident clear way like you're really there you should probably sit in the back of the room you should
probably you know slump in the couch so people you know you're not to really you know
asserting yourself and but in fact buddhist practice
is meant to free the emerging qualities
strength emerging qualities of life that have nothing to do with attachment that
come from uh a the the the
release of deeper responses attitudes
feelings motivations for this world that we live in
and one of these can be a sense of confidence there can be strong confidence
in the dharma in practice of strong confidence in oneself that we've learned how to navigate
through the world wisely one of the ways to have that that's uh i
would like to suggest is easy to understand but maybe not to do so easy
to do is to be um confident
that we'll go through the world and not uh break the precepts
so hopefully all of you are confident you'll go through the world and not uh act on any impulse to
kill any any other human being you have confidence this is not what you're going to do
you're not going to steal from someone and then from there maybe hopefully you're not going to
cause harm through your sexuality misconduct there's where people kind of
that's part of the reason why their sexual misconduct is people start making exceptions
that uh and then that you don't lie and you don't engage in intoxication
but have confidence in your precepts so that we don't
you know we can have that confidence confidence we're not going to intentionally harm anyone
we're not going to purposefully go we'll restrain ourselves if necessary but that's not what we're going to do
and and so and then there's confidence in her ability to
not make things worse um and that's you know this is a powerful
thing whatever situation you're in don't make it worse you might not know what to do
maybe not knowing is important but not it's okay not to know maybe
but don't make the situation worse hold your tongue don't act if you think it's going to
make the situation worse and to have confidence that you know what to do like that
to have confidence in your practice that you can show up and be mindful and find your way with what's going on
and and and that confidence then feeds a kind of inner strength
and buddhist practice makes us a stronger and stronger human being as we go along it's kind of like
we're cultivating and developing muscles spiritual muscles
psychological muscles muscles of mindfulness muscles of concentration and
focus muscles of equanimity muscles of
non-reactivity muscles of understanding and wisdom and discernment
and so these become strong and that's that strength can feel embodied
and and so that when we show up someplace we don't show up with any hesitation we
don't show up in any way to kind of diminish ourselves we might not
we don't assert ourselves but we also don't diminish ourselves and there's a confidence in just being
present and that midpoint between pulling away
and asserting ourselves but just there fully this full
confidence in being present and here as if we count as if we belong here all that
so to navigate between conceit and his confidence and not confuse the two
in uh in buddhist teachings the conceit is said to be a product of
the imagination it is a
a function of its purpose is to advertise oneself the way it's
talked about in the ancient world is to hold up a banner a flag look at me i'm so great
somehow advertise myself is being great it's uh it
comes along with greed greed for a certain for my way and what
i want and who i want to be it
it thrives under it thrives with praise
and the searching for praise is part of the some one of the
functions of conceit it's a contraction it's a form of irritation for the heart
to have conceit oddly enough for many english-speaking people
the word conceit is often associated with arrogance which the buddhists also associated with
but it's also associated with a certain kind of preoccupation with self a contraction and tightness around self
that is a negative what we would call an english may be a negative conceit and that is
uh an attachment to being or a preoccupation or or kind of being entangled with
thinking of oneself as being less than others being less valuable than others or
something like that and um and that's just as much conceit as thinking that we're better than
others uh it still involves the self it involves comparisons
and the and the practice is supposed to free us from
establishing an identity based on comparing ourselves to others either this better
or worse than and and then what what can we do instead of
comparing ourselves is that we learn just to be we learn to be without comparisons
we learn to be without measuring ourselves against other people understand any kind of standards at all
we learn meditation to let go to do that there are some standards that
we might have to deal with the precepts for example the standards of
making amends for some of the harms we've done in the world the standards of learning how to speak
honestly truthfully kindly we might have to kind of clean up our act to some degree
in order so we can really let go and trust this moment trust ourselves
so that there can be an emergence of a non-arrogant
non-conceitful sense of real strength and presence
confidence aliveness and um
and so we do things then uh with without attachment without clinging to
anything but also wholeheartedly maybe
we don't we're not held back by attachments we're not held back by holding on to complacency or resistance
of any kind or ideas it's too hard but there's a freedom in what we do
that we do it wholeheartedly given the conditions of our mind and body the energy that's available and
and all that but there's not a complaining that comes along with doing there's a
just this is what i'm doing to whatever way that i can um this is what's doing so confidence
strength as part of dharma practice in fact uh there's a um
five strengths powers that the the mindfulness tradition that buddha
talks about it's the power of confidence the power of engagement
the power of mindfulness the power of samadhi
and the power of wisdom of discernment and
and and how can those powers flow through us emerge through us
without conceit i'd like to propose that conceit is always a react reactive response to the
world but that dharma confidence dharma strength is not
reacting to anything but is an emergent quality that emerges emerges through our
freedom that we allow for so um
so it may be for these next 24 hours you can look at this you can try to take a look at this
divide between two ways to be in the world one where we're entangled in self-concerns of some form
of other of how what people think of us both that or how we want people to think
of us judgments in ways we measure ourselves that we're entangled and caught in
conceit or or even arrogance or
even kind of self-diminishment that we might uh be caught in
verses and a whole other way to be in the world with confidence with certain strength
and to do this exercise and explore this i'd like to suggest that in whatever way that it is
appropriate for you that you uh
act in the world this day you find ways to behave or to do that
our expressions of confidence expressions of whatever innate strength that you can
tap into it might be as simple as when you're sitting in chairs you might
not slump but sit in some way that also allows you to relax and rest
but but really allows you to be you know it's a posture of confidence and strength
if you're cooking if you're washing dishes if whatever you're doing see if you see this to this day you can
do it with some way that allows something to emerge inside and be expressed
that is strength and confidence without conceit and as you do this
emergent thing of confidence and strength you might it might highlight where conceit is operating
and if you start seeing it don't despair seeing conceit clearly
is one of the great benefits of mindfulness practice and if you see it clearly then there's hope
for not having it to interfere with your life not to bind you and keep you in
entangled so thank you and um and
i hope this this exploration is nice for you