hello everyone and welcome and what I'd like to do today is to also
welcome you to your body welcome you into the
felt sense of being embodied in your body has a variety of different
forms of perception that are activated in different circumstances
and they are ready and available
for you well in a sense inviting you to be here in your body be present through
your body and um and seemingly content enough if you
don't accept the invitation but for today maybe we'll uh
explore this very important form of attention
or aspect of attention component of how we're aware
is awareness through the body
in the teachings of the Buddha the primary one is
to sense the body so that the the through the
sense of touch through all the different nerve endings that are in the body that
um provide you know data to the mind about the
experience of being having a body and um and then the connection between
us and our body is you know the way we experience it is
somewhat um variable just now I said that we have a body
some people might say we are a body uh to be in their body to drop into our
body to inhabit our body to observe our body
to be disconnected from the body there's all these different ways of being in relationship to it
and in a sense the Buddha when he taught
um didn't talk about awareness of body the
sensations of the body the sensing and the body in terms of how we experience those in
relationship to ourselves and uh so we so easily use the language
of self and like having a body being a body but the Buddha just talked about
the awareness that exists with the body through the
body without necessarily a reference point to
the self and perhaps we can understand that to
mean that there's a deeper intimacy that's possible
than if we somehow
take a position about what relationship we we have with the body
but it's closer to the idea that we are our body but even not saying too much
it's a deeper intimacy of allowing the body to reveal itself
to who that question we don't have to answer just let it be revealed
so assuming a meditation posture
and
gently closing the eyes and with the eyes closed so that there
is maybe a greater ability to feel the body to
gently sway back and forth
and then slowly sway less and less finding yourself kind of in the balanced
middle or your weight evenly and maybe on both sitting bones
and maybe there's also be useful to Rock forward and back
as far as you can go back and forward and when you come forward
come back first with the shoulders so there's a little bit of an arch in
your upper back as you come back up and then find yourself again balanced
on your sitting bones the weight of your body
traveling kind of center of gravity Center of the body being directly above
the sitting bones
to take a few long slow deep breaths both to begin
having a heightened awareness of the body especially on the inhale
and to relax this body soften it
because in some ways a relaxed body has a higher
sensitivity to Sensations that we want to stay with
breathing in deeply relaxing exhaling
letting your breaths return to normal
and continue with the normal breath to relax on the exhale
releasing the muscles of the face
including the micro muscles there and heightened sensitivity to the face might
reveal teeny Holdings
around the eyes
forehead
the nose
the cheeks
the lips and the mouth
it might be nice to drop the mouth open relaxed way and then float
the teeth back together or the lips back together teeth don't
have to touch
softening the jaw
and this little tour of the face indicates shows
that we have a global capacity to sense Sensations
in the face it's phenomenal how many nerve endings there are
and so it is in the rest of the body
feeling your shoulders
relaxing the shoulders
feeling the stomach the belly
and the exhale relaxing the belly
we have nerve endings all down the legs
are there any Sensations there that indicate that you can relax your legs
your thighs
we have nerve endings down the arms to the whole hands
any Sensations there give a sense that we can relax or soften
the arms the hands Maybe Maybe by
releasing ourselves to the pull of gravity feeling the weight of the arms
there are nerve endings throughout our body
all of which providing constantly
some sense data to the mind many of it maybe were unconscious of
because of where our attention goes
but it's possible to bring attention to all kinds of areas of our bodies that
we normally in the course of the day don't feel much but feel Sensations there
so much is available and if you sit here
with attention spread go globally around your body
allow your to yourself to feel
the whole body in at whatever way that reveals itself
to you
and then within this Global body
to me breathing
so that breathing sensory experience or breathing the sensations of the body as you breathe
maybe become the center or the animating
Force for being aware of your body
thank you
breathing with the whole body
feeling the breathing in the middle of the body
as you exhale let there be a further letting go in the
body releasing
a quieting of the body
foreign
perhaps at the end of the exhale
letting there'd be a quiet a calm for a moment
as if the end of the exhale is a calming
a settling
and that the inhale arises out of that to come
and becoming aware of where in your body there might be some
manifestation of calm even if much of you is agitated
is there any place that feels calm
as if breathing is a gentle wind a calm wind
breathe with that calm
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps to appreciate
that how we can be present for others is different if we are present just
through our thoughts and ideas
if we are aware through our body we allow ourselves to sense and to feel
the body as we're
in relationship to other people the body that's available to all kinds
of information including information about how we are reacting responding
tensing relaxing
and through being deeply embodied there can be a heightened sensitivity to
the joys and suffering of life and empathy in
to the joys and suffering of others
we can better share this life with others accompany each other
in the depth of Who We Are when we're aware
of the fullness of the body
may we have the patience
and the willingness to be present for others with all our
faculties and in doing so
may we be better a place to bring kindness and friendliness in all
our relationships
may this practice support us in our care of the world care of each
other may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you so hello everyone and
so for this week it turns out that the overall concept tying the week together
is consciousness and in coming down to teach this morning I kind of
Marvel that somehow I managed to choose that as a topic I kind of walked
into it it was not the plan and Sunday evening
uh somehow in the course of by the time Monday morning came around I kind of found myself
almost coming up with that as the theme as we were beginning yesterday morning
and um so maybe in a more cautious moments I
wouldn't have chosen such a maybe a potentially complicated concept
and the one that has a lot of different ideas of what Consciousness is
but here we are and um so the premise that I'm operating under here
is that Consciousness at least in the Buddhist framework uh early Buddhist framework or
how I'm teaching is not a singular thing it's not a it doesn't exist by itself
there's not a pure Consciousness that we can find somewhere deep in our psyche or in our
in our hearts or somewhere there isn't some kind of impersonal Consciousness that continues after death
there isn't some kind of transpersonal uh Consciousness that um
exists Beyond us Beyond us and that we share in or a part of or something
that all these kinds of ideas of making Consciousness into something
is uh in the Buddhist early Buddhist framework there are all kind of recipes
to contribute further to being attached to cling to things
and instead in this early tradition the word Consciousness maybe is not even
used in the texts um uh there's an argument to be made that the word that we translate is
consciousness shouldn't be translated that way so we're left kind of with modern ideas
the English ideas of what this word Consciousness refers to and the premise that I'm working under
is that the Consciousness is not a thing but it's uh the uh in the sense that a
sum can be more than the the gestaltism or the more what's more than just the
sum of the parts the whole is more than the sum of the parts so Consciousness is made up of many parts
that contribute to creating something that has the impression of being more is more than all the individual parts
and um in a sense the parts are all the different mental and perceptual
processes that begin working together and forming each other and um and many of the uh they come
together and and they work together and we can get a sense the mind can create a
sense an image of uh of that whole and
that's partly what we can call consciousness but it doesn't exist apart from the
image we construct or the sense or the idea we construct of the whole that can
seem as some kind of a field of Consciousness or a bubble of
Consciousness or a of some kind of continuous Consciousness Consciousness
that somehow we the self we are the Consciousness and all these things can happen once this thing has been
constructed and um but uh when people some people
get maybe for medical reasons neurological reasons something doesn't
work properly what we can call what with the sense of consciousness of awareness can get very
disorienting disoriented fragmented and you know confused but when it all works
together then it's a little bit like um the uh you know a
um an old uh I mean like a uh clock that's uh with hands and all these gears
that operate to make it all going and all those gears when they work properly
move the hands on the clock but the movement
doesn't exist apart from all the all the movements of the whole clock
so what we call Consciousness is more like the movement than it is any particular part of it
so the component parts which is the kind of the summary what I want to talk about
this week yesterday I talked about our capacity to recognize things and um
the this is important because without recognition then we have no recognition
of Consciousness or of anything but recognition is itself a complicated
mental processing that involves memory and things
but today there at the topic is another
attentional capacity faculty that we have that the Buddha put much emphasis on which is our capacity to sense there's
uh the sensations of the body to we can use the word to feel the body in English
as long as we don't think of it as the uh the second Foundation of mindfulness feeling tones it's the act of feeling or
experiencing the body from the body's point of view itself so this senses of touch all the nerve
endings throughout the body that provide data of what the body is feeling
experiencing how those nerve endings are being stimulated
there might not be there might may be or may not be acts of recognition
when we're sensing it could be sensing or without recognizing what it is
and or sometimes the recognition might be faulty uh I've had uh you know
sitting next to a bush or a little tree and the leaf uh you know brushed my neck
and I thought it was a person that was touching me but it was a leaf so the
first the recognition of what it actually was was not accurate but the
perception of touch was accurate just touch you know that that happened
and and this ability to uh
feel and sense the whole body is something that can be developed and it's
also something that can be lost there are people who for many reasons do not
feel much of their body don't feel much of the body below their neck or below their waist or you know
different parts of the body and part of what meditation mindfulness meditation can do is to reawaken the
body so that the whole body is participating in this being present for our experience
and and some people specialize in being more sensory more
somatic Italy in the world so for them they mediate the world through sensing
and feeling in the body other people mediate the world more through their their cognition and their
mind and their thinking and so recognition is a stronger Factor the cognitive faculties
and it's kind of like left and right-handed people there's different kinds of
perceptual people that's people who are somatic and sense with
their body predominantly can easily live an
imbalanced life because there's not enough knowledge recognition and wisdom about what they're sensing
people who are primarily in their recognition that cognitive parts of their mind do well in becoming dropping
into their body because there's a tremendous amount of information there that can augment and support whatever we
can think about or cognize and one of the things that we support
one of the things the Body Sensations body awareness allows for is it allows us to recognize all the
little ways in which we in big ways in which we tense up in which we are tight in the body
and for the Buddha becoming aware of that is extremely important because when we are aware of that we can
relax it and and carrying unnecessary tension in the body
is one of the functions of beginning of meditation practice is to learn to relax
and settle the body um so that uh the tensions of the body
don't create tensions in the mind or help you know many of the tensions of the body are there because of tensions
in the mind and then as we relax the body the Mind begins to relax as well
and this psychophysical system we have works much better as an instrument of
attention when it's a relaxed and so the movement in Buddhism towards
a heightened attention heightened awareness is dependent on a combination of alertness and relaxation and mental
alertness and a deep relaxation settling of the body deep Tranquility of the body
as the body becomes more relaxed more of uh more information can arise out of the
body and nowadays we know that the body contains a lot more perceptual abilities
than than were known at the time of the Buddha there's a whole sense of
perception that has to do with balance there's a sense of perception that recognizes locations in our body where
different parts of the body are in space there is parts of the body Sensation
that feels gravity and weight all these are included in this
heightened sensitivity to the body but what it but this does a few different things
each of these perceptual ability contributes something to the overall
Gestalt of what Consciousness is and as the body relaxes it contributes
to a sense that Consciousness or awareness is soft is spacious is even
expansive as the body gets more and more relaxed and the tension is not there the hard
and fast boundaries and solidity of the body begins to dissolve and so does any
sense of solidity in the field of Consciousness and awareness
and so part of this mindfulness of the body what it contributes is
um is uh these other data points for constructing
the idea of consciousness and one of them is location part of the this idea that we can feel
and know different locations of the body gives a three-dimensional quality to the
scope of attention which can contribute to the idea that Consciousness can be Broad and wide that
some people have a sense that it's like a field of consciousness and it can feel very real and and kind
of existing in some wonderful way but it's the mind's way of taking in the
data about location and space that where it creates the image
a spatial kind of image that goes into the construction of our idea of consciousness
idea of the totality of all our perceptual abilities
so um so two things about uh
our ability to feel to sense our body is that one is to do it and to awaken
and make it a make it a common part of the day to drop into the body
doing that you'll learn a lot about yourself it's like the early warning
system of tension or fear Joy Delight it's a way of experiencing life more
fully including then having much more information about what's happening with
us and and our responses and reactions and then it also if this deeper feeling
of the body really making it a home for or we can then we have more ability to
relax the body to let go of unnecessary tension that we hold and that in turn supports a calming of
the of the Mind Tranquility of the body leads to Tranquility of mind
which leads to a more harmonious running of the
Clockwork of all our perceptions working together
so uh thank you and we'll continue tomorrow and on this
topic and I hope you find it interesting and um and um
and uh thank you all