so welcome welcome everybody
and happy new year it's uh nice to be starting the year off in this
way the first monday of 2022
with sitting together practicing together thank you thank you for this
so maybe i'll just say i said this at the beginning of the guided meditation
that a good idea to keep an eye on the calendar we may be at the last minute to
be making some changes on whether individuals will be here at
imc for these monday nights for tonight and next week i'm just here by myself
but on the 17th technically right now it'll be open for people to attend but
that might change depending how the covet goes in this omicron variant so
just keep an eye on the calendar okay so back to
the dharma here that we're talking about maybe covet is just as much the dharma as
anything else but just to say a few words about new year's
right it's that time of year when we make new year's resolutions
i didn't know this that there's even a um a technical term for this it's called
the fresh start effect that people tend to
want to make big changes in their lives that have a fresh start at particular times
obvious ones this is the new year but you know i'll start on monday right is kind of a famous thing that we hear
all the times when we have these good habits we want to start we often think okay i'll start on
monday so fresh start at the beginning of the week or beginning of the month or after
our birthday after labor day and for me i there are some things i
like to do and i'm thinking that um the chinese new year which this year is february 1st
i think yeah i'm maybe we'll start some [Music]
new habits i'd like to incorporate or more incorporate embed
more deeply or something into my life but perhaps you've already started with some new year's resolutions
and i'd like to just uh talk a little bit about this and how in some ways some of
the buddhist teachings have things that can support us as well as modern psychology
and how the maybe there's a kind of a meeting of these two
but i'm influenced by this youtube video it's had a tremendous
number of uh views i don't know how many more than 75 million views
and it's about these squirrels who have this real determination this tenacity
this perseverance and it's this video by mark rober a former nasa scientist and apple
employee i think he lives here on the peninsula or in the south bay or something like that
and the story is is that he had a bird feeder and that squirrels found a way
to get to the bird food despite it being squirrel proof bird feeder
and so he decides to have some fun with them i guess and he built a eight-part ninja obstacle
course that these poor little squirrels have to go through um to get to uh food
that they wanted and so this video is about that so we might have this idea that like oh
okay well i'm gonna start something new and i wish i had what i'm calling this
squirrel determination you're like if you've ever seen bird feeders and squirrels trying to get to bird feeders
in your own house in your own yard then you know what i'm talking about
this determination they they find a way and maybe i'll say that um
mark rober isn't the only one that has noticed this but there's um last year at the end of 2020 december
31st 2020 rosemary trauma who's this wonderful beautiful poet
and she publishes a po a poem every day online
and for new year's eve last year she
published this poem that's called again again and it goes like this
on a day when the world asks too much of me and i don't know how to give it
i think of squirrels at the feeder when i was a girl
dad hung the feeder on a squirrel proof wire dad set the feeder on a squirrel-proof
pole squirrels found a way surely there's some squirrel
in me some chattering tenacity some bushy-tailed resolve
if i can't be courageous and brave then let me at least be stubborn
surely inside this aching heart is a scamperer willing to
try again to try again to meet disappointment
and failure and exhaustion and try again
again so rosemary trauma she also is maybe inspired by these squirrels and somehow
we might have this idea that uh if only we could be like that just you have this tenacity or we need it this
will power this determination this stubbornness to make these changes in our lives that we want to make happen
but making changes difficult for example
if you wanted to have a meditation practice have a more regular meditation practice
it's not so easy i'm sure we've all have notices this i don't think there's
i don't know anybody in which it was just easy from the very beginning well maybe i do know one person but
for the vast majority of us it's not so easy and just making changes part of the
reason why it's difficult is because we have to overcome some of our deep rooted
instincts that is our tendency to want instant gratification
this tends to work against our long-term goals and our change objectives that we might have
also humans have this tendency to be forgetful that sometimes we don't remember oh yeah i was supposed to do
that i was gonna meditate every and every morning first thing in the morning and
here it is already lunch time and i'm only now remembering
or it's just natural humans also have this tendency to take the path of least
resistance and it takes energy and effort to
modify our patterns to make changes in our behaviors or make changes in our
thought patterns anything new that we want to do it takes energy
and lastly one other reason why some of the making changes may be difficult is that our
social networks the people that we spend time with in our personal life and our professional
lives may not have been constructed with change in mind that is there might be a certain external pressure for us to stay
the same and not change so there's lots of reasons why change is
difficult and the buddha i believe recognized this and
he pointed to this quality
of determination perseverance tenacity
resolve which in poly is called aritana
and it's this sticking with things even when it is difficult so a certain amount of stick-to-itiveness and
but maybe it's more like this gentle and persistent wind
that keeps blowing and we feel at our back that's encouraging us to
take the next step however small it might be but not to give up but to
take the next step to try again again
and to be sure for some people being steadfast is one of their strengths
and the edge of their practice may be something a little bit different maybe for them it's to not push
doing the same thing this perseverance maybe not push it to the point of drudgery
or to not cut oneself off from others because they're so focused on finishing a task there's a kind of like
go away don't disturb me i'm have something i have to do here
or maybe they to choose the
edge of their practice maybe is to choose those endeavors those changes
those habits that will make the most difference in their lives and the most enriching nourishing and
supportive so resolve aditana is one of the pyramids
and i talked about this i gave a talk about it in november
and so i'm going to talk about something different here but it's the similar
idea this if we want to start a meditation practice for example because it's new
years what are some things that we can do we recognize that we there's this what i'm calling
squirrel determination those girls who want to get the food in the bird feeder they find a way
but humans aren't like that we well let's say that sometimes we are
that way but we're not all that we're not that way every time for everything we want to
do otherwise there wouldn't be this i don't know how big this
diet industry is or the exercise industry is but it's big right how many books and
gyms and youtube videos probably too
apps all these things right it's a huge effort to try to support people
to pursue their habits these changes that they'd like to
make so what can our practice do to support us
what can the buddhist teachings do to support us and also how can we
use what we learned to help support our buddhist practice
so one thing i'd like to point out is aditana is not the same as stubbornness
even in that poem rosemary trauma describes the squirrels as being stubborn
and stubbornness is has this uh quality of this um unyielding
just no matter what just going straight forward even if it might be harmful or
deleterious or not the wise thing to do but doing it anyway so as this really limited view
if i'm just going to do this get out of my way kind of a thing and that's what not
that's not what aritana resolve perseverance determination is about in
the buddhist tradition as a parame it's linked to freedom
it's linked to efforts that have a quality of warmth and care
and nourishing for ourselves and for others and support for ourself and others but
it's like a an integral part of moving towards greater freedom where stubbornness has this way in which
we might feel stuck like no i have to do this even though
it all the pointers might be that um it's not the wise thing to do or the
best thing to do so it's not this type of tunnel vision
nor is aritana this way in which we have to prove ourselves either to ourselves
or to others it's not that we're just striving to become the best just so that we can be
the best we're striving to become the best versions of ourselves
so that our best wisdom can be offered to the world it can be
and play a role in everything we do
and it's also aritana this resolve is also
not about focus on everything that's in our way with the barriers with the difficulties
that we have in our lives the restrictions that we might have in our lives
so it's not about trying to obliterate anything that gets in the way
because that that type of thinking we tend to fall into well if only x didn't happen
or i should have done x it's kind of it's a way in which that type of
thinking can have our will looping quality and doesn't really go forward
and of course takes a lot of our energy so i just wanted to clarify a little bit about what odatana
resolve isn't so what are some ways
in which we can use oritana resolve that recognizes our humanity
that we have limited energy some of us have more
energy than others but we all just have to work with whatever energy we have
and how can we recognize that this how aritana can be a part of
our life instead of something that is a
we feel like has to be the foundation for every change that we make what i mean by this
is often the people who we think of as having the most
self-control or the most willpower maybe those people who
talk about how much they meditate every day or how they haven't missed a day of
meditation for x amount of time or how many retreats they've done or
something like that we might be thinking that they are exercising willpower you know to make
themselves do it or self-control to make themselves do it but actually
will power is overrated that humans we only have so much of it
and it can't sustain us through to help us with some of these really
important qualities to have the best version of our lives
and those people who we think are or appears that they are exercising a lot of
willpower or self-control is most likely that they've built habits they've built
routines they've built systems they've created conditions
to support what these habits for example
meditating every day so they've done this way in which these
good behaviors are more on autopilot than requiring willpower
and that's part of the secret here so to be sure it takes energy to start
to do anything new and different and to have some perseverance so aditana
resolve is an integral part of buddhist practice integral part of any time we want to
make a change but it's not the same as relying on it
because it's not always available sometimes we don't feel well
sometimes we have emotional difficulties we just don't have the energy
towards some of these new behaviors we're trying to develop sometimes we have physical
difficulties we don't have that energy or the result maybe we get disappointed there's
so there's countless reasons why we can't just
believe the commercial the nike commercial which was must have been a pretty successful commercial
that all of us or many of us know it this idea of just do it
i think there's a part of us that thinks that oh yeah i should be able to just do it like everybody else is
but chances are that they have created the conditions
in which these new good behaviors makes it more likely that they will
happen so to change our behavior to do a new
habit to fulfill our new year's resolutions to start a meditation practice
we can focus on maybe systems or processes or conditions
rather than specific goals to be sure it's helpful to have goals
and it's helpful to have specific goals but goals are about the results we want
to achieve for example having a regular meditation practice
whereas systems are about the processes that lead to those results
and when we're stressed not feeling well don't have a lot of energy
these systems these processes can support us
and can help us still make movement towards these outcomes we would like these goals
without relying on willpower without relying on tremendous amount of resolve
so to change our behavior we can focus on conditions
processes systems and the buddha to be sure taught a lot about this too
so when maybe i'll just say this of course there's a big emphasis on cause and effect the consequences of our
actions i recently gave a dharma talk on this topic also and we might say that this is one of the
key teachings of the buddha that everything
is a consequence of something else it's um
it's just causes and conditions unfolding everything is
there isn't anything that arises without a some underlying cause or condition
we know this it's obvious but maybe kind of the
buddhist teachings is just how thorough that is and
how there are no exceptions and it's until we have kind of this deep
insight this deep type of knowing can be really transformative
but can we knowing having this information can we use it to support our
changing our behaviors or starting a meditation practice so one thing that psychologists use this
expression temptation bundling temptation
bundling that is to link something alluring
attractive something that we want with something that
takes a lot of energy maybe we're dreading doing don't really want something we should do
to link these two things together an obvious example
is some people listen to so common now write podcasts or books on
tape with audible to be listening to have this something that's really engaging
and fascinating and interesting really enjoyable for you and uh give yourself the rule
i'm only gonna listen to this while i'm out for a walk while i'm at the gym while i'm
doing cleaning the kitchen or you know some something that we feel like we should do
but we're finding a little bit um resistance to doing it we link it with
something that we want to do and is fun so this idea of temptation bundling
so how can we take this idea of temptation bundling and having to work with our starting a
meditation practice one thing is maybe
to reflect on what does the heart love
what is what is is there a part of practice that makes your heart sing
and is there a way that in a way that makes sense that this can be linked with meditation practice
maybe it's something really small but it's kind of delightful or
meaningful or it touches you in some way and to
have that as part of the meditation practice or the support for
practice or so bundling something that we feel like we should do we want to do but
have some resistance or difficulties can we link that with something that is delightful
here are some examples maybe there's something
in our heart and our mind that wants to
[Music] have uh express appreciation love gratitude
a way to tap into those individuals who
support us or to feel appreciative that we have a practice or
whatever it might be so maybe there's a little bit of we start our meditation practice with just
with gratitude or maybe even if that feels like okay that's a little bit too much work maybe
there's just this devotional aspect that doesn't have words
maybe there's something about i know some people that like to bow before they sit
some people bow um just from the waist some do about on the floor but there's something
about this act of bowing
that can help us get out of our own way or maybe chanting
i know people who chant the meta suta when they first sit down this is their
practice they chant it out loud or they chant it in their minds i certainly have done
this chanted the metasuta i found it uplifting and
also a way of kind of get out of my own way or maybe there's
reading a suita passage maybe there's some passages that are really uplifting and meaningful for you
the dhammapada tariqata terra gata some
passages from the suta napata so maybe to say i'm going to do this
practice reading a suta passages chanting bowie
before i sit and then i'm going to sit for
i don't know how long you know some people say you should sit 15 minutes and some people say
well when you're first starting just get into the meditation posture
just get into the posture for 60 seconds
so temptation bundling maybe there's this part of your
practice that you feel fascinated by or curious by
and there's a part of you that likes to learn so like okay i'm only going to read
these dharma books after i've sat so i have to sit first so that partly so
that the dharma doesn't become just some analytical thing but that it becomes an embodied practice
maybe you could say you know i'm only going to read this book after i've done a set
or maybe there's something about ritual that is
comforting soothing maybe not in a way that you can explain
to anybody else but maybe there's something about um ringing the bell
having a bell especially these days when we're on zoom so often the bells are not satisfying
right zoom with its noise cancellation doesn't feel
as good as especially this like this spell here is really beautiful and imc i think it's
beautiful bringing a bell lighting a candle
lighting incense maybe there's something some gesture
some activity that makes your heart sing
that can be linked to your meditation practice
so this is one way this is one support to start meditation practice
and then maybe i'll mention this this isn't exactly temptation bundling
but it is highlighting the link between having a settled mind having a collected
mind and having the heart sing and that is it's called the gladness
pentad and we see this showing up in all kinds of sutas in so many different ways
and it starts with gladness pented as the name suggests starts with has five elements
and starts with gladness gladness joy tranquility
happiness concentration maybe that last word i could say samadhi so rather than
concentration we can think of it more of a settledness or a collectedness non-distraction
gladness joy tranquil tranquility
happiness samadhi there's a real connection allowing our
heart to sing to have this happiness of this joy this
gladness that allows there to be some settling it could be a
real support for meditation
so psychologists are using this expression temptation bundling as a way to help us
start new habits new year's resolutions and as a support for meditation practice
we can think of this idea of temptation bundling what i just described but also this recognition of the gladness pentad
what is it that supports gladness and in the buddhist teachings this
cascade goes naturally from gladness down to samadhi
so that's one support for our new year's resolution and next week i'll talk about some more supports
for new year's resolutions or anytime we're making resolutions to support our
meditation practice and maybe i will end with just an
appreciation of practicing with others right now i'm alone in this room but i
see some of you on the chat for youtube and just for myself
how wonderful it is to practice together makes me glad
so with a warm-hearted happy new year thank you