good morning can you hear me okay
from where i'm sitting i can see uh outside
it's a uh a cloudy morning here in san francisco
it it brought up the thought for me
as we start to sit to in a very simple way
just notice where am i
you know what's what's the uh
the surround of this moment and then also
what's the interior activity or surround of this moment
any kind of a deliberate maybe even a kind of leisurely way
you know like meditation
is not another thing but it often is another thing on our to-do list
but actually it's also asking us to sort of shift gears
this is a time for simple presence
for noticing what's going on
how is your mind now virgin thoughts
are there a particular
mental dispositions
and your emotions
is there a sense of ease or a sense of dis-ease
is there any particular mood
to your state of consciousness right now
in a way in just that kind of noticing
it's a reminder of the proposition of meditation you
know in mindfulness in awareness that to simply be present and experience
whatever's happening in that moment
in a way that's the wisdom aspect
it is what it is and then for us as humans
it's enormously significant when we open to it
it's a way in which we make more sense of who we are to ourselves
we're noticing and acknowledging what's going on
um this state of mind of these emotions
then as we notice that to let that same
simple attention come into the body
there's something essential primitive fundamental
to our physical being in a way our psychosomatic being
registers the notable experiences that occur for us
and to start to bring attention to the body and notice
how is the body does it feel
settled does it feel spacious and open
are there some points of tension
but then from the wisdom side it is what it is it's beyond
good or bad or as it should be or as it should not be you know
it is what it is
and we take it personally
the continuance of me is in the balance
of what's being experienced right now
it's a two allow
the body to be reflecting
this moment this day's version of me
and when you relate to me as a body
it's a different me from the one that's caught up in
thinking
the thinking it's reconstructing reality
it's judging its own constructions it's having feelings about its
constructions it's drawing conclusions and judgments
and to just remind ourselves that that's not going to stop because we've decided to meditate that will in fact
is a significant attending to that experiencing that the construction the judgment
the memories that the mind creates
these are today's versions of me
and as we embody it can we
invite it to be palpable
the experience of me in this moment
and can we breathe
can breathe in the thoughts the feelings the sounds
and can we notice
how does that register is it pushed aside by thinking
is it imbued with emotion
either pleasant emotions or unpleasant emotions
and however it is can we remind ourselves to hold it tender
in our human existence thrives
when it's related to benevolently
we just let that thought let that disposition
become part of our breath
giving something permission to be itself
can you breathe in in a way that's
inviting the body to be expensive
inviting the body to it's almost like opening downwards
can the chest relax and open
can the mid region the stomach relax
can the abdomen relax
and sometimes it can and sometimes it can't but to invite that in a benign way
it's as if we're very softly saying to ourselves it's okay
it's okay
compassion of practice
and as we start to settle like this then noticing
are there many subtle adjustments
subtle adjustments to our posture
more settled more at ease
are there any adjustments to how we're involving
awareness in our being
can it be invited to be allowing
and accepting
can can there be a softening of doing
and opening the beak
and as you make these subtle adjustments
can you notice what the consequence of it is
it's like noticing is soaking up
what's being experienced
and if the attentiveness of noticing
is starting to dissipate or has wondered
just return the basics of body and breath
physical sensations
it's your posture shifted
some part of your body tightened
it would be helpful to put some emphasis on allowing the
inhale to be deeper
or along we may exhale to be a little longer
so
you
noticing if there are particular thoughts that
keep repeating
or is there an emotional disposition
that's coming into being
and the opening to it it's a teaching about me
it's another interruption to teaching
what is it register in the body
does it affect the breath
[Music]
sometimes it can be very instructive to watch the shift that happens within
us as we shift from meditating
to whatever's next
sometimes it can be a teaching about attention
involvement that affects consciousness
expresses itself for some kind of doing or not doing
so try to notice what happens what's the shift
when the bell rings
um
[Music]
so good morning again
you know the process of meditation of mindfulness
in a in the context of stimulus it offers us an opportunity
to heighten our senses to enhance our capacity
to experience
and so sometimes that's a wonderful gift especially when it's a pleasant experience
yeah something
energizes us says something that is soaked up
as a kind of nourishment something opens up our gratitude
our appreciation for the moment
i think sometimes it's unpleasant that something in us
is agitated distressed
the challenge of practice is to
engage them both
maybe in a human way we could say the engagement of the pleasant
is a kind of encouragement to our practice it's kind of reassurance
maybe we want to tell ourselves oh i'm making some kind of progress
and maybe we are if you want to think of opening to
pleasant as progress and for most of us
it is a beneficial thing
and it helps to create a reassurance and a trust
that the life for living
the being we are can be
validated and embraced for just what it is
and then there's a way in which engaging the unpleasant
can actually have the same qualities yesterday i quoted martin luther king
you know where he said challenging experiences can be both educational and transformative
yesterday afternoon i was at a meeting at the zen center
practice and i'm scheduled to lead a one-day sitting
saturday after next and as we it was a planning meeting
and then in the planning meeting someone said well we haven't advertised
it and i thought
what i haven't advertised it and then i said
well maybe we should cancel it but actually as i attended to my own
experience there was a kind of
frustration that it hadn't been advertised
there's a way in which i took it personally
this impacts me and that statement
even though i said it in a matter-of-fact way you know maybe we should cancel it
you know in an emotional way it was an expression of
my frustration and disappointment
and then that group of us it's about five people
and usually we get along very well
usually the feeling in the room when we're going through these planning things
is kind of fluid cooperative and appreciative
so having that feeling of frustration disappointment
agitation was in contrast
to how i usually feel and so this often happens for us you
know our meditation and our dedication to it
it helps to create a benevolence and a spaciousness
and then that stands in contrast to our moments of contraction or moments of disappointment
our moments of frustration and in a way they become more poignant
it's like we're more open to them and we feel more
so one of the challenges of practice is to uh
despite that despite the the intensity of the unpleasantness
to still find within ourselves the resource
to acknowledge to notice and acknowledge
okay this is how it is and so yesterday when i was noticing and
acknowledging that
what happened to my mind was then
i asked what happened yeah how come
that had turned out the way it turned out that it wasn't advertised
it actually it was a complicated but logical reason
you know it wasn't that someone had done it with
the intention of hurting me it was like there was a miscommunication
of this person puts it on the website and this person connects it to the
online program and they hadn't communicated
and so it hadn't been promoted
but as i listen to that as i took in
what's going on you know so we have an experience
and something in us takes it personally
positive or negative that's our inclination
but there's also a different kind of anchor how come
how come this moment has or this interaction
has come in to be not so much
that our mind gets busy making a story but that we're opening up
to what's going on you know especially when we're relating to other
you know i think opening up to their perspective
because usually there's some variation between their perspective and ours
you know i think there's something for us to learn in the moment
so this way in which our
our emotional response even when it's unpleasant for us
if we can remind ourselves to
knead it with the inquiry
and sometimes the inquiry is
the the interaction between ourselves and others
and then sometimes it's internal
what was i feeling or what am i feeling and what for
what thoughts what perspectives what conclusions am i really re creating
in relationship to that feeling
and then as we relate in that way in that process of discovery
and there's an extraordinary thing can happen for us
we start to see what's happening and we start to see through it
this is this is we start to see it oh okay this is what's happening in this moment
and we start to see and it's just this moment
it's the occurrence of this moment it's not the totality of reality
even though my mind wants to conclude oh this is how it is
judging others oh this is a negligent person
and when we can explore oh and how this come to be
i lose the process in interactively then we listen to
others and then intra intrapersonal
we look at how we had the feeling
what the what the feeling evoked in terms of thoughts and judgments
and how that led to conclusions
we see it and we see through it
the very interesting thing for us as we do that
it it invites us in in a
affirming way to trust our practice
ah when we learn something
about who we are about how we're interacting
it evokes within us a certain kind of trust and confidence
in the practice and as martin luther king said it can
also have a transformative quality because as we see it
and rather than just drop into our habitual way of responding
we see the possibility of a different response
and when we take that different response something in us is relieved
something in us is heartened by the discovery of possibility
but even difficult experiences unpleasant experiences challenging experiences
frustrating experiences offer us something
and and if we can remind ourselves that even though
the the first response can be one of pushing away
you know which is essentially what frustration annoyance agitation is
it's a kind of no i'm not going to
go with this i don't like it somebody's to blame for being wrong
when we can go beyond that we cannot let that be definitive
conclusive end of story
when we can turn towards it and notice it and
experience it it can have
a teaching for us it can create
another story that can create an alternative conclusion
and that's encouraging for us
when we have the difficult experience and we fall into habitual
disappointment discouragement frustration that's discouraging for us
when we evoke this alternative we're encouraged
as martin luther king says we're educated and
it holds the potential for transformation
so maybe today when you feel something disappointment
discouraging you can remind yourself of that and see
what's going on and maybe it's interactive you know
like when i asked the group yesterday what i asked one person in particular
they they explained it to me when they explained it to me i thought oh well that makes sense
this person did that and then they went on vacation and so this other person
um draw a conclusion from what they've done
and didn't advertise it it all made sense
it was something that needed to be mended but
still it made sense
so maybe today you'll be blessed with something that
annoys you you'll be instructed by something that
frustrates frustration or disappoints you
so thank you whatever the day turns out to be may you
enjoy it and be supported by it
okay