so good morning everyone welcome to imc both of those of you here in person
and those of you online and i just say just some brief
comments about meditation before we start and keep it mostly silent during this time
interesting kind of instructions for mindfulness meditation
is to consider that we're
doing two things one of two things one is we're knowing
something in the present moment like knowing the breathing knowing our body just knowing what's happening in the
present moment but in a way where the knowing is clear enough
that you could say to yourself i know that i know
so it isn't just a casual it is just like checking it off i'm kind of aware it's like there's a clarity or
brightness or a fullness in the knowing that's an in-breath
you're not necessarily saying those words to yourself but it's oh it's like i've never had an in-breath
before almost like oh that's what it's like i'm really clear it's really like okay
that's one thing to kind of not really know and to let that knowing be relaxed it
doesn't have to be a strain or just like it's almost like you allow yourself to really know something you make room to
know it all the second thing is to
is uh to know when you're not doing that
to know when you get caught in your thoughts and wander off and go on daydream and
get preoccupied in something and when you know that that's happening
don't make it a problem really know that so you can say
i know that i know there's a clarity there's a brightness and the mind oh that's what's happening
so you're it's okay so in this way you don't have to be concerned with being distracted or
caught up in your thoughts you just fold it into the knowing
so it's a little bit of a trick right it's like you just stay present in the knowing
and then rather than thinking that thinking is a problem
it just becomes the reason to know something clearly oh here i'm thinking
i'm distracted but you're no longer distracted if you say that
you're present with that so you can smile when you say i'm distracted or
because you're not really at that moment you can appreciate it you can love it even
so two things either know the present moment like the breathing
or know that you're not present and if you're not present really know it
so taking a comfortable alert posture
perhaps letting there be a gentleness to your posture
the softness while being alert
closing the eyes
and to relax the body some as you exhale soften
on the exhale and as you inhale a little bit of opening lifting
energizing into the body
a connecting to your body in a fuller way on the inhale
relaxing as you exhale
so
and then perhaps just settling into breathing here
becoming familiar with your body's experience of breathing
and to know breathing with clarity with
it might be more mental it might be physical might be both
a clear feeling sensing of breathing
clear knowing
and whatever occurs in the present moment
is not nothing is a destruction if you take it to be just one more thing
to know clearly
and as we come to the end of this sitting
maybe to appreciate that whatever ability we have to
be more aware
to show up for our life with attention
it's also an ability to show up with care
respect with attentiveness to the situation of
others as much as to ourselves
and may it be that this practice of attention
supports us bringing
kind compassionate caring awareness
to this world of others
in doing so may we better care for the world
may this practice we do be for the welfare and happiness of everyone
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
so
[Music]
so to make a few announcements before the talk
the first is that in a few moments my plan is to take off my mask
the custom is in a number of buddhist centers for the
teacher to take off their mask when they're teaching and then everyone else leaves their mask on
and i think the idea is that with everyone but the teacher wearing masks
it's safe for everyone safe for the teachers because you're wearing masks safe for you because you're wearing masks
and um and we have all these you know air purifiers and fresh air coming in so i
think it's pretty safe and so but if those of you who are sitting close by would not like to move
please do so freely there's no you know it's completely fine but
you don't have to you can sit further away if you don't comfortable with me taking my mask
off and then the other is um
we used to before the pandemic you know in these kinds of events make announcements about things that are happening here at imc that might
interest people coming up and we're kind of out of the habit of it but
one of the foundations of what we do here at imc is the intro to meditation class
and uh we just started on thursday to do it again after almost
two and a half years or more and in person and um
and uh some of you just would like to know that it's on thursdays at 6 30
you'll miss the first one but that's okay you can come to the second one or you can it's on audio dharma the first one you can listen to the ketchup
okay so that was the announcements and then this goes off
and then i'm probably clear too speaking this way not so muffled so
so welcome everyone nice to have you here and be together this way
and uh to be a little bit of a celebration about you know the whole pandemic time
to see so many people coming back to imc this way and
coming sitting in community and i really appreciate the chance to practice together and be this way so
thank you for being here so um
the central feature of this mindfulness practice
is attention and attention is
maybe a number of different faculties we have different capacities we have
that come together under this umbrella term attention and i'm aware of
in this modern kind of technologically centered world that many
of us live in there's a fair amount of conversation now about
how there's a lot of a lot of money and a
lot of effort a lot of intelligence that goes into tricking human beings attention
capturing people's attention the more clicks you can do or the more you'll surf the more you'll
maybe you'll consume or the work all kinds of things that happen and so to get people's attention and
keep it on their monitor on their screen there's a whole industry for it
and many of us participate willingly with that whole enterprise and
maybe spend hours a day sometimes on a monitor and and sometimes even you know
caught by the news caught by the me social media caught by you know the advertisements or you know
searching for something and there's a feeling among some people who are studying this that it's uh it's
a problem for our society that so many people's attentions are captured and being pulled along
and if you go along willingly it can even feel like you're so free i can just go along and just anywhere where
anywhere i want to go i can just go freely into the surfing the web but in fact
it's not that free of the mind in a sense the buddha 2500 years ago was
addressing the same issue but what was capturing the mind was not
social media but monitors but rather was desire desires
in the in the human mind and the desires in one form or other
would hijack our attention take it over or with the tension get pulled into sometimes a black hole of desire of
wanting something or not wanting something kind of flip side
and from a buddhist analysis the we don't want to put the responsibility or the blame
on those people on the other side of the monitor who are dreaming up all the ways to capture our attention
and from buddha's point of view you're responsible for your attention and
and certainly probably there should be a lot of changes in what how social media media and computers are presented to the
world but still in buddhist point of view we're responsible for it and with probably the same problem as it
was time of the buddha and it somehow or other desires or aversions
were caught in the grip of it and pushes our attention but sometimes our attention is hot held hostage or
hijacked by these strong forces of the mind
and as i said earlier it can be feel the same way that if you you can give yourself over to your desires your
aversion so completely that it can feel i'm so free it's like giving and you know an uh
unlimited credit card to spend you know you can feel like so free to go into the shopping mall and just buy buy
buy everything you know and it's too much for you to carry that's okay because you have a credit card you just buy you get sherpas to
carry everything for you or the equivalent by the robots they're going to kind of follow you around and carry everything
back with you so just because you're so free right it's so great to be free when you sit down to meditate
you discover that that kind of mind is not that free you find that the mind sits down you
want to just do the simple thing of sit down and be present in the present moment maybe be present for the
breathing and in fact the mind doesn't want to do that the mind has a mind of its own
and in a certain way it's not your mind anymore it's not the mind that you have some
control over some authority over some choice over you get pulled away pulled away pulled away
and it's a powerful lesson to meditate to see that to see
how not free the mind is whereas we thought we were free the
other way now do you have a choice one choice is to come back to the old
way you know in a sense when we're on the web if you have a monitor to look at and
the web to be connected to it's almost like you have unlimited you know credit card you have unlimited and
no money you can't buy anything necessarily but you just think you have unlimited ability just you know search search search search
and feel free but but hopefully when people meditate or in another kind of ways even just going for
a walk in a park or just having a sabbath day and doing nothing we start reclaiming
our capacity to be be at home in ourselves and not have the mind incessantly searching wanting doing
but the mind becomes some profound meaningful rest and ease and
it's a kind of reclaiming the mind rediscovering the mind or the heart if you prefer
even ourselves and some people are really out of touch with themselves because of
the monitors before you know they work on monitors they spend all their time in monitors and
and it's kind of a way of being disconnected and to reclaim ourselves to reconnect to
ourselves to find ourselves discover what freedom means in some deep inner way
where we feel like the mind has become our friend the mind has become our companion
and and support for the fullness of our life so just so attention then becomes the
medium the means for freedom because it's how we use attention
is a measure of where the freedom and the lack of freedom is and so attention is mindfulness
and so we're developing this capacity to be mindful for the purposes of this freedom
that is a reclaiming of ourselves of coming back to ourselves and being able to breathe easily again freely again and
openly and i don't know maybe i shouldn't say again because some of the ways that we the
deeper ways we discover it's like for the first time that we find this way
so for the cultivation of this attention in our practice we consider that it's an
ecology of the mind or ecology of the heart that's operating meaning there are different faculties
mental faculties that are operating that are cooperating and participating
in this endeavor in this task of setting the awareness free or reclaiming it
and appreciating that this occurs there's an ecology there's all these different pieces of the mind that are support that support attention
and which attention cultivates and develops and um so this what i'm going to talk
about today the ecology is something called the five faculties and the five faculties
are five functionings of the mind five like kind of processes of the mind or
of our inner life if the mental world seems too mental of our inner inner life
that we're all operating in fact they're operating for you right now it isn't like they're strange
mystical kind of states to be listening to me these are operating
and um and you know your capacity to be attentive
is being tested here as i give a talk because you're either
attentive because you want to be or because it's so fascinating what i'm
saying that you're just captivated and caught i mean this this story i'm telling and the drama and the
most you know you you're just waiting at edge of your seat for the resolution of this fantastic talk right and you're
just kind of caught maybe but um
but uh or your mind is drifting off in thought
and your mind is lost or maybe you've decided that you're thinking about really good jeopardy
questions and that's the best use of your time sitting here not listening to me but you know coming up with a jeopardy question
so you made it a choice the very this very thing i'm talking about the ecology of attention
is operating here while you're attentive while you're living here and
you might want to listen just enough to use to then reflect back
how is it operating for you now are any of these factors how are they living in you now
as you're listening so i'll first kind of just name the five faculties
and then i'll kind of talk about them in different ways maybe more creatively than just the classic
language how they're described so most commonly in english they're described as
faith energy or effort
mindfulness concentration and wisdom
and um and what i want to highlight first is that the importance that here
mindfulness is in the middle it's the third factor and the first two factors
faith whatever faith is this energy or effort they're considered to be activating
energizing faith is meant to be inspiring to bring energy
that's the function of faith in this practice the
fourth and fifth and the other side of the middle mindfulness is um
concentration and wisdom both of which are supposed to help with a settling
with a freeing with a relaxing with a de-stressing
and and so they're activating and settling kind of qualities
and it says that mindfulness in the middle helps the bring those into balance
as mindfulness develops these other four qualities can follow in
the wake they get stronger as mindfulness gets stronger
but also it works the other way that the other four are the foundation that we create that we bring in
that supports mindfulness like a scaffolding we build for have a
lighthouse on top so the lighthouse can see and spread light in all directions so these four other four as they become
strong help so support and hold up the awareness so it becomes strong and for
us as well so um it begins
and so on the on the the list begins with the pali word sada
which is most commonly english is translated as faith i like to think of it as
wholeheartedness what you put your heart into
you know what we put our heart what we put our heart into doing what we do wholeheartedly what's what
our heart wants to do in our life is really important
i don't think if you really ask your heart to really what what are you going to put to wholeheartedly put your heart
into because you really love it or it's really meaningful for you it's probably not
going home to your monitor to your device and in search amazon
for the wonderful things you can buy and what's on sale
that's probably you might the desire might want to do that there's energy there for it but it's not the whole if
you really tap into the what you you want to put your heart into it's probably not that
what we put our heart what we do wholeheartedly when would we put our kind of to
you know our whole self into what's really valuable what feeds us and makes the heart sing
what is that and um so that's what i associate with this word sada faith
there's some idea that in the centuries before the buddha the word sada meant hospitality
which also is a very nice idea that what you're willing to be a host for
what you're willing to be present for and invite come here so what you've put yourself into
wholeheartedly with your attention where do you want to put your attention at what's important
for you and and what do you want to be the host for it kind of goes hand in hand because
the idea in meditation at least is to put your your attention
wholeheartedly to reclaim yourself to be here for
yourself with yourself to reclaim this attention this is
important and then in doing that because be the faith to have the faith that it's
appropriate to be the host to be hospitable to all things that
occur faith is kind of since i used the word wholehearted for
it it's the more the emotional most emotional quality of the five faculties
so there's an emotional quality of inspiration it's very that's why it's energizing we're inspired by this
wow i can't do it yet but if this is what's going to
i'm going to find my freedom set my attention free reclaim my attention for myself
that's good i want to do that this is important and then um the next one the effort part
is to what we is to put some energy into this you know not to have a good idea yeah
this is a good idea to be wholeheartedly present but yeah i'm going to do this i'm going to you know really give myself to it
so the engagement the non-conventional idea that i like to associate with this
word is to inhabit to inhabit our aliveness to inhabit what
we're doing and i like this for myself because then it's more than just a mental thing
you know meditation just bring your attention and pay attention and know what's happening but to inhabit for me is to be embodied
to kind of be present in a fully embodied way i'm here with this experience
and there's more faculties of attention than just what goes on in the mind
the part of the faculty of attention it are all the sense endings the nerve
endings that tap for sensations in our body and they're just as important for
embodied fully developed attention as any capacity of the mind to recognize
oh that was a sound there's a sound outside for example
there's also the whole embodied sensory apparatus that takes in that sound
we haven't had it for a while but occasionally it's really great to have these cars
drive down to have the really deep ass boom box because then it really feels like this
is embodied listening you know the whole body is shaking and
even the building shakes sometimes and um so um
the in the ancient language in the of the buddha the i don't think he associated with
this effort or engage with energy with um you know really being inhabited
inhabit your experience he associated with courage
so to do something it was courageously and sometimes this practice requires that there's something kind of a little
courage and then i love the idea that courage comes from the french word heart
so that we're not don't get that we don't feel like we're striving or you know or kind of overriding what's happening
but to really courageously show up for ourselves and feel what's here be with it and that's hard sometimes right our
emotional lives are difficult and challenging and and so to do this practice
so that's what we put energy into then on the other side of mindfulness
there is um concentration and concentration is probably not the
best translation for samadhi samadhi is often associated with
tranquility it's also associated with letting go
a lot of letting go some people with one of the first lessons i had when i went to thailand to do this practice here
like the first evening i was first there to engage in the practice i was in a monastery and there was talking with
some of the monks and and um they were a little bit uh critical of
concentration practice and they were saying oh that's that's just about letting go
as if that's nothing every small thing but the idea was that uh to develop
deeper states of concentration has more to do about letting go than it is about laser focusing your
attention and so this letting go and the word that i liked associated
with concentration that's a translation of an ancient teaching
is to be settled the concentration is to be settled on
your experience and so now you feel how it's the idea of settling letting go relaxing
tranquility how concentration is um is the calming effect of the five
faculties so we inhabit and engage we're inspired
but that can be too much sometimes and then we it comes into balance with
relaxing with settling with letting go and bringing those into proper balance
is the art of mindfulness if we let go and relax too much you fall start falling asleep and the mind
wanders off too much we need the engagement we need the inspiration the clarity
and so we're navigating this ecology in our ecosystem and figuring out which
one to bring forth and then uh the the fifth one is wisdom
which has a lot to do with having insight really seeing in the present moment it's not wisdom that you carry with you it's
like you read a book and now you think you have all the wisdom you need because you have this knowledge the
it's really um i think the word insight probably works better to translate panya
in the sense that it emphasizes what you're seeing and understanding
in the lived experience of the moment so that's where the wisdom is in the lived experience what do i see now
and the one of the primary forms of insight here and now that this is in enterprises about
is to be able to recognize the difference between stress
and not stress the difference between when we are adding stress to our mind to our body to
our heart and to know there's a possibility of not adding that stress
stress is not healthy in the long term stress is not where freedom of attention
is discovered we don't reclaim the fullness and the ease of ourselves
by being stressed and so rather than thinking of wisdom as being
this complex you know you have to get a book on buddhist philosophy to understand the ins and outs the depths
of you know buddhist wisdom it's actually it's always
something very simple what's being discussed here about wisdom something we can see and know for ourselves
and one of the primary ways to say it in modern simplistic terms is to be able to have wisdom inside to
see clearly when what we're doing is stressful and to know
that we don't have to do that we might not be able to stop it
so don't add stress on top of stress but to see that to know that is to start
having wisdom oh i'm striving and pushing i'm resisting
here all that is stressful okay so now i have to be aware of this
be attentive to that i have to know that at least i have wisdom i don't know what to do about it but at least i have
wisdom about it another form of wisdom is to that uh
becomes more and more important as the practice becomes as the capacity for attention becomes stronger
is to have more and more clarity about how moment by moment
and i want to emphasize that moment by moment our experience is constantly changing
and why that is important is then we really see that then we're willing to kind of maybe
uh surf on it as opposed to hold it like it's one way this is the way it has to be
this is the like one of the mice my delusions has been sometimes
i've arrived this is how it's supposed to be you know in meditation for example okay
finally i'm concentrated this is it or finally i feel you know i feel some
sense of calm and relaxed and happy i've got it made don't breathe
you'll mess it up and um but really life is more like
being on a surfboard you're finally caught the wave you don't say this is it
you have to be very attentive to the changing natures of the wave to be able to stay on the board
or in a bicycle maybe that's better example for some of you than a surfboard is you know you you never say like now i got it made
on the bicycle like that don't move you know it's uh you know you're
constantly navigating negotiating and shifting your weight and adjusting the you know everything
it's a so to really start appreciating that the the intimacy of changing nature of
experience here and now then attention this whole enterprise of the five faculties are involved
in not fixating on anything because any fixation is stress
so as if the faith is in the forefront wow this is so i'm so inspired by this or
this is what i realize now what's most important for me and what i'm willing to put my whole-hearted attention in
not necessarily the activities that you do but rather how you do those activities
and that's the secret of buddhist practice i think is not what you do
but how you do it that's where this inner freedom is really found
and that's why when we do mindfulness meditation it's not exactly the meditation that's important like don't think you have to
become a great meditator but rather it's what you're learning about how you use
attention and as you learn how to use your attention and meditation in this simple
laboratory then it'll start spilling out into your life
and then when you go home to wash your dishes or clean the kitchen floor
it isn't about kitchen getting the floor clean as quickly as you possibly can so you can get back on your monitor
it's do you discover that you reclaim yourself your freedom is
found in being fully present for washing the kitchen floor
as if there's nothing else to do in the whole world there's no stress about the next thing
there's no stress about why do i have to do the kitchen floor you know didn't i do it last week
you know which i should someone else should be doing it these are all ways that interfere with just inhabiting
being wholehearted being relaxed and settled
letting go not adding stress
seeing where the non-stress is and washing the kitchen floor being present with attention for this
activity and by the time you finish doing the floor it's like well that was great
not because the floor is great not because the particular activity is like the greatest thing invented by human
beings but because of what you brought to it how you were with it
that's the trick and that's what what happens after a while this the freedom of mindfulness practice
is portable into anything that you do
where what you do is less important than how you do it
and it's absolutely what you do is important and you might love doing some things more than others
but the wholeheartedness the faith the where we inhabit
where we where we are settled is in how we are with our attention
how we are present with our attentiveness for what we're doing
so you might consider how there's a way of being wholehearted
in the attentiveness you bring to what you do that's easier to do
if you don't equate what you're doing with the attentiveness
some things are hard to be inspired to do in and of themselves
but what's inspiring is the attentiveness by which you engage
with them some of you probably have been parents
some of those things we have to do are not inspiring
at all the things i had to do as a parent i never would dreamt that i had to do
i remember one day i should have may tell you maybe shouldn't tell you this but one of the big surprises was um when my kid was really young and he
was still sick and he started throwing up i quite i don't know what to say without any
horror or any disgust i just put my hands together and cup
them to receive the vomit it just seemed like the most natural
thing to do anyway so occasionally
occasionally you know occasionally we have to do things which you know are not necessarily something you would think ahead of time wholeheartedly but it's
the ac it's how we do it that becomes the you know
so to be present for whatever wholeheartedly
to be pre to inhabited the energy factor
to discover to be attentive to really attend to i like the word that the attention kind
of means to attend to to really attend to with our capacity to be present to know
to do it in a way that's easeful i like the word ease and this is almost a synonym of concentration
to do it with relaxing and ease letting go letting go of what
letting go of what we learn with our wisdom letting go wisdom shows us where the
stress that we carry and over time as the practice develops for us
we see more and more where all the stress lives in our body and our eyes and our jaws and our hands
in our belly in our minds and our brains all these different places and we learn
to not give in to that stress we learn to relax it these are five faculties that you have
that whether you know it or not were somehow present here listening to this talk
maybe some of them were in short supply maybe they're all present in a wonderful
way but i hope that it at least gives you some uh
idea of what we're you know the landscape of what mindfulness is about kind of the terrain
the map of the different faculties that were coming into play it might seem like a lot to keep in mind
five different things but you're using them all the time anyway
and and as you become more aware of this and first it might be like riding a
bicycle that's awkward and feels like you're now even more stressed out because you have to keep all these things into my in mind
but as you keep doing this practice you'll see these things become stronger and become more second nature
and it becomes sometimes it becomes like oh this one's weak
or this one's overdone i think i'm trying too hard here or i think i'm you know
i could use a little bit more inspiration here where's what do i what do i feel wholehearted about what's really important for me
and realizing what that is does that bring me some more juice
to
being here attentively finding my freedom in my attentiveness
so that's my talk
may the five faculties be at treasures be five treasures for you
that you've realize are in you
it can be your wealth so um thank you
and um it's we we have a few minutes before the
official ending for the talk uh we can maybe take five minutes or so
if any of you have any comments or questions and then afterwards after that i'll
invite all of you is we'll go out tonight and continue having a discussion if in the in the parking lot outside we
take the folding chairs out and sit in a big circle and we can take off our masks out there if you want
and and we just have an open discussion but before we go out to any questions comments now that any of you would like
to ask here thank you
hi uh thanks for your talk so what i've been thinking was
i feel as my practice deepens i start to notice more things
maybe when talking to people you start to notice patterns of thoughts that they have and
they're not like asking for help or anything but you can tell it seems like a
trap somehow and i still don't know how to navigate that like
they're not asking for advice and is that something that you should like
tell them so they are aware of or oh i see so what you're saying is that
you're as you're becoming more mindful and understanding your inner landscape better you you now understand other people
better and you see for example that there's whatever they're doing now how they're talking or how they're engaging
that they're involved for example in a stressful way and so should you
you know poke them and say hey you [Laughter] not not that way yeah i understand i i
know i know i i apologize i didn't i wasn't at all implying that you were not all by applying it you were you're
that that's what you meant but um so the first thing that occurs to me to
tell you is the story when i was i was first doing this practice regularly
uh i saw how people were so caught up in their
ego games you know and wanted wanted to get some people wanted to be get praised or back then the language was stroked
and um and uh and i didn't want to play the games
anymore so i had a girlfriend and a wonderful woman who
wasn't the practitioner and so i didn't want to you know play those
games and so the relationship ended
and many years later what i realized was that um
i had some wisdom like seeing something how things were operated and there was some wisdom about not participating in
it but what i lacked was compassion and so i didn't i didn't care for her i
didn't understand her suffering and understand how what how i was being was actually
because she wasn't a practitioner and no idea what was happening that it actually probably added suffering to her rather
than took him away so you want to be clear if you see something in others that
they're ready to hear it that they want to hear it that it's welcomed almost invited that it's useful
and you're doing it out of care and it's the right time to do it um
so things like that thank you that sounds kind of the answer i've been found uh i found
like with compassion and it's almost like an art form on yeah when and how to
do it thank you and don't underestimate how valuable it is to be present for
people to listen to people and you know the inner system of human
beings shifts and changes towards health when there's a lot of attention we when
we give attention to ourselves this whole thing i'm talking about today of really bringing attentiveness to our
life tends to shift and move things towards health when we bring a lot of listening and a
lot of attention just just listen and be present for other people it tends to move them towards health too
so don't underestimate how useful that is so even though you might see that person's stressed out
rather than telling them that offer them the kind of caring simple relaxed attention that maybe helps
something in them to relax and then they might learn eventually on their own they'll recognize
it's a very good question but then and i just scratched the surface of all the answers
so there's a question here thank you gil this was an extremely
valuable session for me anyway along the line of the uh
the threat that this gentleman initiated there are times when people
ask for advice but they really don't want the advice so
i think perhaps part of wisdom is recognized when there is a room for advice to be
given and when there is just simply supporting and actively listening and and just being there for them
how do you feel about that i didn't quite follow let me see so
you're talking about when when people ask for advice or when they don't ask for advice well sometimes they actually
dads asked for advice but then you find out later that they really did not want the advice they just said yeah
well in in um there's a in japanese zen
uh there's a little saying or instructions or something um
when someone asks you a question and i think they mean then dharma question like with a teacher but it's maybe good
here too is um only do 30 answer
and um and then see if they ask again and uh like the buddha sometimes
would not answer the first time someone would ask they had to ask three times
and uh and actually in zen monasteries they have that idea it's kind of built into the ritual of the dharma talk you
know no one sees it but before someone gives a talk there's some kind of ritual ringing of bells and bowing that's
offline sometimes where it's kind of meant to replicate the idea that the community is
asking the person three times to give the talk so you know so just offer just enough
that you're responding but not everything you could say and um
and uh and then see if they want more and they'll come back with more and come back with more
thank you thank you great so um is there a question let's do see it
today no question in the chat okay well um
so thank you all very much and uh and those of you would like we can go
outside and there's a cabinet just around the corner there you'll see some people know where it is you can take a folding chair and we'll go out in the
parking lot and we can make a big circle and hover and then chat for a while together thank you