so hello everyone and welcome
i hope all of you who are living in heat waves will
take good care of yourself today and be sure to drink and all the kind of
basic things and it's nice to be able to meditate
so um this week i'm going to follow continue a
little bit with the theme from last week of the dharma and what i'd like to do instead of a
guided meditation is i'd like to read teachings of the buddha
verse poem that he comes from him that was apparently quite popular during
his time because it was recited often and
the monastic followers of the buddha were expected to memorize this and and
and have commentary about it and talk about it and it points i think to
uh it's kind of the essence of some way of understanding the essence of what the dharma is
this particular verse i kind of think of it as the anthem for the inside meditation movement
so i'll read it and then we'll just sit in silence today we've done a lot of guided meditations
over this time and i know some of you really value them a lot
and it's also very valuable to sit in silence and have more more for that and
so i'll read the poem and then we'll sit
so this this poem is called
an auspicious day the buddha said
don't chase the past or long for the future
the past is left behind the future not yet reached
right here where it is have insight
into whatever phenomena that has arisen
not faltering and not agitated by knowing it
one develops the mind ardently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow
there is no bargaining with mortality and his great army
whoever dwells thus ardent active day and night
is says the peaceful sage one who has an auspicious day
don't chase the past or long for the future the past is left behind the future is
not yet reached right here have insight
so with that we'll sit quietly for these minutes
the buddha said don't chase the past
or long for the future the past is left behind
the future is not yet reached
right here where it is have insight
into whatever phenomena has arisen
not faltering and not agitated
by knowing it one develops the mind
ardently do what should be done today who knows
death may come tomorrow there is no bargaining with mortality
and is great harmony whoever dwells thus ardent
active day and night is says the peaceful sage
one who has an auspicious day
[Music]
thank you as you know
that i value a lot doing a dedication of the benefit at the end of the each sitting
and there's a way in which
reading the poem of the buddhas is equivalent and as we do our own practice
i'm confident that we'll be people who will benefit the world
so hello everyone and
here we begin the next five day series
and for this week i'd like to do something a little unusual and that is to repeat the theme from
last week i think there's value in it in that the topic itself we can go further with it
it's so central and important to the practice that we're doing and also um
um sometimes when we keep moving to new themes maybe every week it's uh
the heart the mind the body has less opportunity to let each week's theme sink deeper
so uh that's the plan and so the plan is to
once again go through the five characteristics of the dharma
the dharma of the buddha is well spoken it is
visible here it is now immediate
it invites inspection come and see
it is onward leading and it is to pers it is to be personally
known by the wise so this dhamma in pali dharma in
sanskrit in english now is
you know it means something more than just the buddha's teachings what the buddha was
what his teachings were pointing at the idea is that that the buddha was
pointing to something for us to experience for ourselves that we become a wise person who experiences it
directly immediately here another place the buddha describes the
teaching he the dharma the teaching he gives as being
laid open clear and evident so again this immediacy it's right here
to be seen it's evident it's open nothing hidden and
so we can enter into this present moment more deeply to discover the dharma for
ourselves that's where it is we could also step back a little bit and see more clearly
what the buddha was teaching when he taught and had more confidence that what he was pointing to is what was in that poem i
read which is now here what's evident what's open what is
inviting inspection here and the uh the contrast to this
is in terms of religions and even some ways that people relate to buddhism
is belief looking for a belief to believe a doctrine to believe
and i know some people have come to buddhism and have the idea that if they're going to be good buddhists they have to believe whatever
the buddha said and or they're inclined to believe and
some people have this beautiful thing they say um
for whatever i've experienced for myself it verifies what the buddha teaches so
i'm inclined to believe everything he says now even what i haven't experienced myself
so this orientation around buddhism being a belief and we have to believe
in the ancient teachings of the buddha he was actually not interested in belief and was
actually quite discouraging of people to believe he said that he teaches the dharma
to eradicate belief or speculative views opinions
dogma attachments to the teachings speculation
his teachings was something very different very interesting story is of a man who was a famous debater at the
time of the buddha and religious debates were really a big deal in ancient ancient india
and so he was wanted to really kind of debate the buddha and kind of undermine him and
so he came i guess somewhat assertively to the buddha and say you know what is it that you teach
it was clearly was going to be debate and the buddha answered i teach that
with which one would have no quarrels with anybody in the world
and uh so so the guy didn't know what to do with himself and then he left
in a huff you know he realized it was no way in for the buddha that was his attitude
so this dharma we have that doesn't lead us to quarrel with anyone in the world it's not based on beliefs
opinions it's a very interesting exercise to go through uh the teachings of the buddhism
very many volumes of what survives and and asked the question
you know this when the buddha was going to teach the dharma in brief what did he teach
when he told others when you go out to teach and you want to teach what i teach
this is what you teach that when he talked about what the right view
is what's the right understanding to have when he talked about vika body translated as true knowledge
gnosis vija v i j a
and um what did he what did he point to is this the true understanding or the true
knowledge um buddha talked about the goal of practice
what did he talk about and when he taught the people who were maybe
closest to him and i think of his son he had a son one son who became monastic in time
the story is that he joined the order when he was seven years old and
you know we have records of what the buddha taught his own son you think that that's where he wants to emphasize what is most important
and so what was it he taught his son so all these questions if you take all of them together
and look at the buddha's answers to all of them phenomenally what you find
is he's talking about something that is evident here and now
the first of these characteristics the buddha is san ditiko the buddha
last week i said this the dhamma is sanditko it's dhamma is
here and now the word is visible here now
some people translate this as in this very life and
and the idea here is that it doesn't concern a future life or a past life
it's in this very life that we can realize what the dharma is about you don't have to postpone it you don't have
to hope for it in the future here and now in the immediacy of now
and and so in this very life is a powerful statement
because it it places the domain the locus the nexus
the center of what the buddha was teaching as something independent of past and
future lives which some people often associate past and future lives as a huge part of buddhism
it's certainly an important part of forms of buddhism how buddhism developed and maybe even had a place in the
teachings of the buddha but the concern with past and future lives
was not something the buddha talked about when he went through this is what the dharma is this is what
you should teach this poem i'll read it again that i just read
is a remarkable poem because it's in a group of texts many of them poems which in the most ancient uh
layer of buddhism there's direct there's indication that this is what people were chanting back
then you know we have all these volumes of the teachings of the buddha it's not completely clear what actually
belongs to him was his words and how much was attributed to him later but at this earliest historical layer we
find that the monastics of the time and the lay people as well were memorizing and talked about memorizing particular
verses and texts so this is what they felt was important to remember and to repeat over again
and all of these things together can be summarized in this verse that i
read before which i now read so what the buddha taught what the goal is what the he would teach his son what
um emphasize that people should memorize and remember
and this is the context for what's really considered one expression of what's central in the
dharma don't chase the past
or long for the future the past is left behind
the future is not yet reached right here
where it is have insight into whatever phenomena has arisen
not faltering and not agitated by knowing it
when develops the mind ardently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow
there is no bargaining with mortality and his great army whoever dwells thus ardent active day
and night is says a peaceful stage one who has an auspicious day
and the text is uh translated the title is an auspicious day it's in the middle length discourses
number 131 and um so when the buddha says in the
five descriptions the dhamma that it is visible
last week i said visible here and now and thinking about it it seems like we just say visible here
because the next one is about time immediate so it's visible here now it's in this
very life this is a very important principle very important idea
and what it means is you don't have to go and read a lot of books and
you know hope for you know something far in the future what is it that you can find here in
this very life in this very time here
here here in this poem it says right where it is
right here where things occur where things arise have insight have understanding and this
is a common theme in all the ways that you get to what the buddha with central messages
is here in the present moment see things arise and pass see things
arise and appear the impermanence the inconstancy be in the flow of time see things appear
and go away come and go in particular begin seeing the coming
and going of greed hatred and delusion that they're not always there
and who are you when there is no greed hate and delusion
or say it more buddhistically when there's no in those moments and times when there's no greed hatred
delusion fear
what is left and what is left
if you answer that question with no greed no hatred no delusion
no fear no conceit what is it that's here
so uh to offer you some
assignment that you can do for this day something that i do frequently that find
great value in is just saying the word here
here as a reminder to just be here fully
to not race ahead with your thoughts not linger in the past with your thoughts
but to say the word here as if you're opening a door
into a new room here in this place that you are right here
have insight see clearly see what's visible here and now
not so much what you see in the room or in the space you're in but what do you see in your own mind
and in that own mind and heart of yours might there be
something that is free of greed hatred and delusion
free of fear free of conceit
here so so saying the word here to yourself and
opening a door to here so um
thank you and the dharma is visible
here thank you