you're already recording okay um
so tonight the we'll talk about effort and the first thing I'll say about
effort is um absolutely everything we do requires effort
everything and so I'm going to kind of try and pull some finer detailed attention to how how
we're making that effort um and so the one of the primary ways
I'm going to do that is actually through a guided meditation and um
my invitation is to you know sort of just be curious be
interested in your own effort in the reflections I offer and and then we'll
you know be talking about it together um
afterwards so I think we can just sort of move right
into that um so finding your posture
your meditation posture so a position that you feel like you can
stay in for probably 25 minutes or so
a position that allows the spine to be upright
and allows the the chair and the floor the Earth to hold
your weight so you can give your body to the chair to the Earth
and with your next inhale maybe feeling it rise up through you and
lifting your spine tall toward the sky
and just taking a few deeper breaths
and for a moment just whatever your anchor is if it's not the breath
just connecting with your anchor an anchor is
something that you can use to help your awareness
stay here In This Moment
ever-changing moment so the breath is moving in and out and
can be an anchor to help us keep our mind in the present
with awareness sounds can be an anchor or Sensations in
the body as well
and so just in this we're already making effort
deciding to sit bringing awareness into breathing
and just noticing how easy or difficult it feels to feel your breath at this
moment does stay with the experience of breathing
and just just for experimenting try a little harder for a minute
try a little harder to stay with your breathing
and notice the impact of that effort trying a little harder
and now try a little less not
not intending to follow your breathing
but maybe somehow do it a little more lightly a little more easily
and now maybe try
thinking about a three breath Journey just taking it three breaths at a time
just seeing if you can be intimate and connected and aware
of three inhales and exhales in a row
and then maybe three more breaths three breath turning just three
feeling the rising of the body with inhale
the falling or the letting go with the exhale
now just sort of let go of your effort sit down a little bit more on your sit
bones and I'm going to offer
three similes I just want you to feel into the simile
and see if any of them resonate or if you have your own arise
that somehow captures the energy the effort
that you were putting into being with your anchor or your breath
so the first image I'll call to mind
is of a dancer someone who is really embodied
maybe moving not too quickly imagine how they lift their hand and
their arm and you can feel them
their presence their awareness in every move
even maybe subtle subtle movements
they make they're very committed to embodying
and maybe even you can see how they're aware of the people around them that are moving in your mind's eye
while being connected to their own bodies
they make it easy look easy perhaps
and here's the second simile
imagine a clown how they move
that kind of sloppy moving the way they tend to fall and or slack
in their bodies how they seem to be very focused on one
thing and missing so many things around them
or maybe imagine something entirely different the movement of a wrestler
they're very embodied and they derive their energy into their
movement all of their energy goes into their movement
so those are three different similes
of how effort in our bodies can appear
and there's many many more just taking a moment to see
which one or which one in your own mind feels most like the energy or the effort
you brought to your sitting down here tonight
as you kind of connect with your own effort even now maybe
you can tune into the tone
it can be friendly but it could also be
apathetic or belligerent the tone in your own mind
could be neutral respectful
kind-hearted
what would it feel like to have an internal tone that feels respectful
we can also consider our confidence
we may feel quite confident right now being aware of our breathing
or we could feel extremely insecure uncertain
I'm just seeing if you can find that trusting confidence
to be with your breathing as best you can
to be mindful as best you can without
being forceful
it's just also this quality of commitment commitment to staying
staying aware and noticing if you have a sense of
weak mild commitment or a strong commitment
a dedication or a devotion versus a controlling effort
controlling commitment
another quality to notice is a sense of generosity
is there a sense of generosity with yourself with your mind with your experience with your body
what would it be like to be patient with whatever is happening inside of
yourself right now
creating room
now I want to invite you to imagine you're just sitting down to meditate
again
and as you sit and you come into your posture I want you to reflect on what
is your aspiration for practice
what inspires you what is the reason you're here
what is the reason you meditate
and seeing if you can't just hold that aspiration
lightly with care and try saying
may this practice support me in this way
like a a wish an invitation
that you're dropping into the system the body the mind
trusting it knows how to respond
and then there's this idea of trust faith
belief faith in the practice
faith that it's possible
maybe reflect on the Buddha the Dharma
or the Sangha
what do you have faith in
vited to come into your heart into your mind's eye
invited to sit beside you
maybe imagine your ancestors around you supporting you if that's supportive
or your spiritual friends
maybe imagine being at the time of the Buddha sitting with other monks and nuns
feeling their support
feeling into each other here
in a moment I'm going to invite you to practice again just with your breathing but as you turn back towards your breath
bring this inspiration aspiration or the
what you have faith in with you
bring a sense of curiosity of not knowing
and the sense that something really important is happening right here
in each Breath You Take in your body here in this room
it's important whatever comes up
it's important not that we need to engage with our thinking
we can just let it be it's okay the thoughts can come
witnessing it all being surprised by it all
you're watching your own Karma
that's amazing
though nothing needs to happen nothing needs to be done
just placing value on knowing just the knowing doesn't matter what you know just
knowing your experience with a kind heart
one breath at a time
just knowing
and softening around that knowing
one breath at a time patient
kind-hearted
and when I ring the bell just see if you can't Witness
without moving what happens in your body
your mind [Music]
[Music]
foreign is anybody willing to say a few words
about what they noticed about how
what came up for them what was easy what what they noticed question comment
hold on Ben yeah because we want to hear everybody to hear your beautiful voice and what you have to say
um for for me um it's like every 30 seconds
or maybe a minute I don't know I'm with it and then I'm out of it and then I come back to it it's just a constant
here yeah yeah and did you notice um were you able to play with how hard you
were trying or less hard well the only thing I noticed is that it's a
it's it's always a try it's always trying it's always trying that's heroic
yeah it's heroic if you think about how many times you're saying you keep having to come back that's yeah that is an
incredible devotion then yeah you know
it's a lot of effort it's beautiful commitment thank you for sharing
anybody else willing to share Mitra and Rosa
both Anne Rose and Mitra
good evening everyone hi Tanya uh
um you know the part where you mentioned like the three type like the dancer the
clown and then the wrestler I thought I had all three like the mind was a bit of
like uh the clown in that in some respects because I was all over the place in terms of like
a wrestler very like trying to get at it I felt like I was kind of tense in that
respect up here in the head trying to force things at times but the the dancer
part was just being still and present and kind of at ease and I felt that so
it was there was a contrast you know this up here can be kind of tense but
then other parts so I'm like let me try and focus and there were times as Ben
had noted uh I was daydreaming and I noticed that I was like very much so I'm
like oh why am I thinking about the coke that I bought earlier let me go back to the breath so it's just focusing or just
recognizing it more that sounds I'm just going back to the breath I love that you could tell too
that you know you were having different experiences at the same time too that you could find
the settledness in the body even if the mind was being a clown or a wrestler
yeah that's beautiful thank you thank you
yeah I was the effort um the similes that you mentioned
was interesting to know notice that um I was somewhere between a dancer and a
wrestler and that definitely not as smooth and
continuous as a dancer but um
somewhere in between there um and the thing that was interesting for me is that I
compared it to what I was like before
and I think I was definitely a wrestler I think even a boxer like it was just
very abrupt and yeah I'm just under chain there's a change I see I I
realize a change um yeah and that it got harder
um at the end because I was waiting for it to end yeah and it was harder to be
smooth and I noticed so much even my heartbeat increased thinking that it's gonna end and
that I wanted to end or yeah amazing so that all was there yeah
that's great thank you Mitra Tracy did you have your hand up I'm not sure if you did
I became so the dancer and the clown became one
in the same I would like to think of myself as a very graceful dancer but in reality
probably more like the Clown um so it kind of Teeters back and forth uh
and the the more effort I try and put into it it
seems like things get farther and farther away and the less effort I put into trying to
don't think too hard basically is what I'm trying to say the more effort I put into it the harder it became yep and the
less effort the the easier it became I'm so happy to hear that happy to hear that
yeah yeah and I'm also just so um I'm happy you could each feel into those
different kinds of effort in your own being and see that it can shift and
change and you know maybe there's sometimes you do need to be a wrestler you know but it's certainly not
sustainable to stay in that space and and you're all dancers too you know
I don't know um Sage Nemo or Mustafa if you guys want to
add anything here yep Nemo
thank you my insight had to do with the difference
between the breath as such and breathing through
the similes and usually I would only focus on the
breath in a neutral way and it's almost like a white light
conscious of itself but with the similes I was noticing that
it was less effortful to focus on the breathing
but the quality and Rhythm of the breathing was changing
so as I was breathing through the dancer through the thought it was almost like
two like a color like almost like the awareness
had a different color with each simile and that was affecting the rhythm of my
breath absolutely and I could tell the wrestler was a little agitated and I and
if I was not aware of it I can see how I would stop it like it was I would just
jump out of that oh I can't meditate or too much effort
but because I was aware of it there was still the white light and the color
um and and I it was easier to keep doing it
um because it was almost like it I was not possessed by it yeah
it was a powerful experience oh good I think you know it there's something
about putting and uh finding similes that help us recognize
our experience and recognizing our experience helps us be with our experience and not be
carried away by it right or um you know they're just all of a sudden
there's room or something around it um is the way I would describe it for me as well you know this ability to oh this
is what this is what it feels like yeah Mustafa I know you're new but is
there anything that you would like to add or okay Sage did you want to add anything okay
anything else I mean yeah great Mitra
I also when you said that it's three breaths that we're going to think of it
as three breads I found that very helpful yeah that it's doable for me I can do three Breads and then another
three breaths and it's not as a bigger task yeah so your confidence
level went way up right and when you have confidence so that's one of the qualities we you know I was sort of
suggesting we check in with is that if we feel confident things are a lot easier because we're not anticipating it
to be hard right we have the sense of confidence
and um so how about when I kind of asked you to
think about your aspiration for practice and faith in the practice the Buddha the
Dharma did that change the the experience or the feeling of being present
yeah I think for me I I thought about my aspiration as in in life why I'm doing
this is to find some ease in whatever it is that I'm doing
and I thought that um I also thought again about the changes
that I see during my meditation that there's more ease a little bit more ease in that and I
thought it's I mean on the right path and I felt that the faith and the
yeah and that's that is something that um
you can do when you go to sit you can take a few minutes to reflect on why
you're sitting your aspiration for sitting bringing to mind the Buddha the
Dharma a quote but it can help so initially I didn't give you much to
start right I intentionally didn't give you a lot of instructions to just sort of see what happens if you just kind of
plot down and start sitting you know sometimes I'll give a lot more help kind of okay let go of the day you know
um but I kind of wanted you to experience what would happen if you just start
meditating versus if you take a little bit of time to help arouse a sense of
aspiration confidence patience you know these qualities that
if we have them in our minds they can come with us into the meditation and
support us in our practice yeah and
um Sage did you want to say anything Tracy
the reason so when I'm meditate okay life builds up on itself right so
I I find that my intention for meditation is to kind of re-balance uh
myself try and step out of the Rat Race that is so easy to get wrapped up in and
just spend time with myself being quiet yeah
that that is my intention for meditation yeah Sage is nodding her head over there
two thumbs up she says yeah yeah and
so when you connect with that that that's your aspiration how does it change how you feel about meditating
meditation becomes most important
uh I I have a hard time staying mindful
during everyday life so in order to rebalance myself
re-calibrate things it's very important for me to meditate otherwise it just builds up and builds
up and how does knowing it's important to you in this way support you're doing
it knowing the results that that I'm going
to get uh makes makes me seek it out nice uh just
to quiet the mind it's so hard to get that during everyday life unless you
really know how to do it um it's much easier for me amongst people
here yeah in the quiet where everyone has the same intention it becomes much
more powerful and easier for me to do it here yeah
yeah yeah it's very it's a really powerful thing to have the gift of meditating
with others
thank you Tracy
Roseanne and Rose I I also feel like
oh when I seek something or I put too much effort in whatever it is
it kind of drifts away or but then sometimes I wonder if it's a
what do you call it the thing where it just ends up happening because you will it to but then maybe in this sense
with meditate what I really like about meditation is there is no from what I've
learned I don't have to feel bad if I'm not doing it right if I feel like I'm not or
if I'm doing it wrong or if I had a really bad day today at work which I did
I can still come I can still come here and try to be present and it's okay
because I've made that effort so it's just just all those things and I can go about
my life feeling like a clown one day but the next seeming like a dancer through
this practice and Well on most days like a wrestler or a boxer but I just it's
it's just nice the just being here and experiencing uh Sangha with everyone I
and hearing what everyone has to say I'm like oh I'm not the only one
really powerful really feeling that way so
thank you thank you
yeah Ben please
yeah um in terms of
aspiration um
um years ago when I started to practice
um I know that at some point in the future if you stay
with this you become blocked more aware
my desire was to
be so aware as much as I can that
I can see what's going on I can understand what's going on I can be present to
what's going on and I have all my faculties ready
and awake to absorb and to do what's
needs to be done so and maximize those moments
I mean I can count maybe the instances fleeting instances that something
happens and you all there oh yeah and you all see so
that's those those things those moments are magical yeah as for
the effort um
yes it's hard it's always been hard it's it's still hard it's probably going to remain hard
but gradually slowly
there's a shift that happens very subtle
shift that happens and you stop you thought
sort of cleanses your language cleanses your
um attitude cleanses if there is a but it's a it's
very slow very slow process
yeah anyway that was beautiful then really beautiful what you shared
all of you really beautiful
I think um I just want to stay a little bit with
this um the different kinds of effort for a minute and then I'm going to talk about the the four kinds of effort that
the Buddha taught right um but I think um
one of the things that I'll I'll say when I feel like I have that the energy or the effort of a wrestler
I feel like my my awareness gets really small I don't I can't take in very much and
things get tight um and so I lose connection a lot with the
joy of life and that when I'm in that kind of efforting place and you know I
some I was thinking what are the things that are the hardest you know when do we
have to work the hardest when do we need the wrestler energy effort
and I don't know what what thoughts you have but one of the things I thought about was oh you know I think sometimes
I see people it's that hard when they're trying to go against their conditioning when they're
trying to resist strong strong conditioning that that's almost when the
mo there's no sweat and effort in in that kind of way you know and whether
you're on the cushion or in life that that um resistance of the momentum of a habit
a pattern a conditioning a flow of karma can
really require this courageous intense amount of energy and it's finite how long we can do that
and it becomes to me brittle or um like I said I lose the joy I lose
connection you know um
and you know sometimes we're trying harder and so we're working harder but
I think you know some Tracy I don't know who said it but would like oh actually
if I don't try so hard it's easier right there's it's it becomes easier to
stay and so that's the other thing sometimes we're putting in more effort than we a
lot of times I think we're putting in more effort than we need or maybe we're
trying the wrong kind of effort and so this is the other part of what I was kind of trying to point to in
the practices actually there's effort in getting ourselves to the cushion
there's effort in inspiring our hearts making ourselves feel comfortable and
safe there's effort in making sure we're comfortable enough
right or that we didn't overeat before we came to sit you know like these this
is all effort that happens before can happen before we come to the cushion
and actually the more you practice I think the more the effort is in your
ongoing awareness of your mind and what Ben was talking about slowly this
cleansing of your attitude slowly this cleansing of your word slowly this
cleansing of your your aversive anger that you want to you know
say these things that are harsh those things start to dissipate you know
um but it uh
it's good to know what kind of effort you're making and play with it be curious
and sometimes you'll find your mind is not acting the way it normally does it's different and so it needs a different
kind of effort so it's good to have practices and rituals and routines but it's also
good to keep tuning in about whether or not it's actually working in the moment meaning working to help you be present
with whatever's going on so the four kinds of effort that the
Buddha talked about are essentially in two groups one has to
do with unskillful and the other two have to do with the skillful so with the unskillful if we notice that
we're being unskillful we want to stop it right so if we're being harsh or
critical or we're trying too hard in our meditation we're being a wrestler
we want to try and stop it and then once we stop it we want to
prevent it from happening again those are the two sides of of working with the
unskillful with the the skillful we want to cultivate the skillful
and then maintain the skillful and actually that's all you need to do in my
view mostly it's really about cultivating because
to to stop the unskillful we're not trying to wrestle with the unskillful
if we fight with the unskillful we're feeding the unskillful we're giving it
our life precious awareness and energy and it keeps it going whether it's
because we're angry at ourselves or it or whatever but we're we're still
directing this energy this awareness this is our life energy toward the
unskillful if we're trying to get you know I stop it by suppressing it or stomping it
out now sometimes I have to say when it's something like
really your awareness just goes oh no I'm not going to say that it's so pretty clear like easy stop of the unscaleful
it's like nope not gonna go there you know that's pretty clean
so that's great you know and then like okay how do I want to kind of support
myself and not having that happen again and and reflect on maybe how yeah I
don't really want to go that way I don't really want that in my life so is there something I need to do to support myself
around that but for me a lot of my work is around
the cultivation of skillful and that as it grows the unskillful just
Peters out there's just less and less of it
so it's knowing what do you want to cultivate how do you want to you know how do you
want to direct your energy in a skillful Direction and then maintaining it so how do we maintain what is skillful
for me one of the biggest practices is to appreciate to recognize to have gratitude to
appreciate to respect not take it for granted that these are things that help support
it and maintain it but that can change too our minds get bored
I mean they get distracted they get caught up in other things so we have to keep adjusting what we're doing and this
is another part of effort you know I mean I feel like sometimes
um when I'm on a longer retreat I feel like I'm constantly having to adapt my
effort constantly having to shift what I'm doing to help myself maintain this
balance because I'm you know you the awareness everything gets magnified so you get
more and more sensitive to what's happening it requires more and more refinement I
think so okay one more little thing to share with
you um and then um and then we'll do either a group or
small group discussions whatever you guys want to do so I'm I'm just making this this part up
right the dancer simile that's my making it up right that's not from the Buddha these four efforts those are the
Buddhist teachings okay this part I'm going to add now I'm making it up okay and so this is um just uh I like
acronyms that I find them helpful so and it's not perfect my acronym is
not perfect please enhance it make it better for yourselves but the idea is
Grace with our effort Grace with effort Grace with effort
so if we use the G with the grace like grounding G for grounding right
orienting to Here and Now this is the beginning of a really important
mindfulness practice right grounding here and now the r recognizing right and
respecting the results of the effort of just grounding recognizing what's happening
this is effort right and there's the a acknowledging appreciating
whatever there is to be appreciated see courage courage to turn toward the
suffering instead of doing the habitual trying to get away from it trying to change it
trying to deny it trying to talk ourselves out of it trying to argue
about why it's really the other person's fault and not my fault now it's this courage to go oh okay
it hurts simply purely it hurts and to be with that takes courage and we
need to know our limits how long we can sit with something right sometimes it's gonna be short
but it is there can be it's that moment a magic moment of courage in the mirror
like you know I'm there I see you I can't stay with you but I'm here and I
see you that moment can be enough and respecting our capacity in the
moment to be and stay with the suffering or needing to turn away but doing it with
Choice doing it with wisdom like recognition
gra see courage r remember and recommit
right and receive so whatever our effort is like we try too hard or we didn't
didn't go the way it was remember what you did
recommit to to staying you know intentional receive whatever there is to learn from
it even if it's bad news even if you don't like it
right and recognize the value of whatever was
skillful don't miss that too so remember right remember all these
pieces and the E exhale release the unskillful reactions
exhale don't make a self out of the effort a good meditator a bad meditator
forgive learn right exhale Letting Go letting go
right not creating more
suffering so that's my little acronym Grace with
effort and then I'll read you this quote Gandhi said freedom is not worth having
if it does not include the freedom to make mistakes and Jack cornfield says don't be afraid
of making mistakes step out fly even if you get burned you can fall back to
Earth and start again it's never too late to start over he said zen master Dogan laughingly
called Life One continuous mistake yes
there is the fear of looking bad but later when you review your life will you wish you had held back probably not
Texas all right
so would you guys like to do two groups of three small group just talking and
reflecting in your small group about um effort and Reflections maybe sharing
uh you know what kinds of efforts you bring other ideas you might have other
similes yes okay great so why don't you go ahead and make yes
for oh yeah well actually probably will you participate Richard
are you going to participate you're not going to plan on it okay and
well Sage Sage will participate so yes so we can have one group of four one group of three
um well but but I think the group people might need to migrate some people need
to migrate yes Mustafa you you're not gonna stay
okay are you okay
so Sage will join you guys Ben
foreign
I just want to
I just want to say one one little thing we talked about mindful speaking and listening last week and just how
um we can bring our practice into these little small group discussions
so you know just being kind of staying connected
with your physical experience is really powerful keeping keeping more awareness if you
can internally then externally even when you're listening sort of staying with
your yourself so I think about um if I had a gauge
that would show me how much of my awareness is external versus internal most of the time it's probably mostly
you know a lot of it is out right so maybe just feel in what does it feel like when my awareness is equal in and
out what does it feel like when it's more in you know that's sort of the mindfulness
meditation and when we're listening to others it's very easy to get lost in the out
so trying to just kind of keep that in mind and you know being being aware when you
speak whatever you notice is fine right just we want to invoke a sense of comp
you know confidentiality it's safe to say you're what you share won't be taken
out of here you know shared with others and that there's a general sense of loving kindness you know caring in the
group so I just wanted to to invite you all to connect with that and then I
appreciate your introducing yourselves and do you need more instructions or are you
okay with just talking where you seems like you're okay right I
yeah effort ideas about effort effort you've tried you know yeah yep great
so you guys can talk for like 10 minutes
just taking a pause thanking each other and I made a little circle for us for
this last bit if you don't mind um sitting part of the circle if it's if
it's a problem no problem but if it's okay
and yeah I said you want to pull the camera back okay
does it feel too weird are you too close to each other I
don't know okay great
and Wednesday what's wrong I brought him over already yeah
yay yeah so um
and just the flow I'm thinking of and I'm open but is
um to invite you all to just share your takeaways from your discussion any
questions or Reflections so that we can all benefit from each other's
conversation where the camera's zoomed out so people on Zoom can see the the full group and
the microphones will allow them to hear and for things to be recorded so we're
connecting with our broader Sangha in this way
um so does anybody willing to share
something that came up that they would be willing to
donate to all of us
and then maybe we can just pass the mic in a circle after you start
I want I want to thank sage and Ben for
their kind and careful attention as I was sharing my bad day I tried not to
Tanya I I had the privilege of being a Starbucks barista over the summer but
these past nine years I've also been a middle school teacher oh my goodness and
this year is really challenging and I was just telling them about my day and Ben had said you know humans are like
razor blades in order to have that fine point they must be cooled and sharpened and Sage said well you mentioned should
a lot but remember you said there's no right or wrong and I really liked how how she had
how she and Ben had noted that I I can just be okay and not try so hard but
hit so hard sometimes and I just I think you thank you [Music]
um thank you and Rose [Music]
yeah yeah we're right here and Sage is
getting you some kleenex if you wanted yeah I can't imagine being a middle
school teacher oh my goodness oh my gosh
really really what's that maybe maybe should yeah
I I feel that it's rather heroic to be especially a middle school teacher a
teacher of any grade these days but especially a middle school teacher those
kids are really trying to figure themselves out and
they're not always the nicest about it and as a teacher you have to
be the one in charge and the one that you know is the adult and everything but
sometimes they're just not nice and I'm sure that's hard and I'm
I admire you actually thank you for your service to our world
it's the job you're doing is it's very important job oh my gosh
thank you yeah so Tracy you have the mic is there any
any little tidbits you would like to share so I appreciated finding out that
it's it's not that everybody needs to put in the effort to get here I felt
like I might be the only one who just wants to stay in my bed and you know
cuddle up with the cats and not go out but I found out that I am not the only
one that that feels like that and it it it uh
it makes me feel even more part of a group that I that
other people are having to put in that kind of effort too just he rode his bike
here all the way from Palo Alto for crying out loud and he's caught her right home back in the dark so oh my
goodness that's a lot of effort and and so it just
uh reinforce the importance of of being here and doing this
and what a gift your effort is to each other to me to each other the effort you
made to get here is huge and hugely beneficial for all of
us thank you
I want to jump in but first I need to ask a very critical question of Nemo which is like
do you think you could fit your bike in my car because I'm going back to Stanford as well so
I was actually trying to make it into like a practice I was telling them I was like I want to see the difference uh
maybe I'm I'm not saying no by the way in my mind I was like maybe I'll see the
difference of at first getting here and then this gap of meditating and being
with myself um or groundedness I like that word a
lot like being grounded because I'm in motion coming here yeah and then I'm
grounded and I can share the ground with others that are like me and have that we have a
similar intention and then I was like and then be back but
there's not enough
so uh the running theme for our group I think was um
training or like repeat effort like what does effort look like when you
can't just get it all done in one like solid move and um
Ben was telling us a little bit about his his running and training and how
it's the repeat effort they get to like big differences
um and yeah well I brought this up but like I think it's very common to like know
when you're talking about repeated effort like like loud sound the dodging like talking about these giant
Boulders that have like been in place for like a thousand years two thousand years like there's nothing you could do
to smash them apart like at this time but like a like reveal it like a little stream
like given enough time I'll like cut it so yeah that's I think that's what we're
getting into like how do you do what needs to be done over and over
and over again and I know the struggle about getting out of bed from underneath lots of cats to come
here very very well solution that I found is
the solution that I found is volunteer because then you're like obligated and
then you have to go
that's great you can hand it to Ben
um actually I arrived at the end he mentioned the book she she mentioned a
book you're sorry my apologies I I always mix up this is nothing is my person we don't have he or she isn't
that cool I think that's something we always mix up I mean I'll always mix it up sorry
um yeah so she mentioned the book uh what was it called
oh did you I've never heard of that thing anyway so about the the how
big boulders are shaped by little streams of water makes a lot of sense yeah
uh I I totally believe in that there's always all there is only a small effort
there's never a big effort beautiful a beautiful guy thank you
foreign
to the first many few years of my meditation practice
on high um my effort was the two extremes I was
either and I am still mostly either
um too much effort very intense and very um
um or just the opposite of just too exhausted to make any effort and that
was really um not productive at all and I was thinking
we were talking about how that for me I felt like that I'm that's been the effort that I apply
throughout my life not just on the cushion that I either do
too much or or exhausted to do anything and just now starting to learn that there is
a right effort Grace and effort Grace and effort Grace and effort so I need
to learn that beautiful can you hand to Richard
so I think I'll just chime in a little bit even though I wasn't in the groups um
sort of seeing and being a sort of having a perspective that I'm watching
you guys relate and the things that you've shared tonight and
um
it's very touching to me to see you guys all come here
some of you for a long time Ben and Mitra you know quite a number of years
and other folks sort of just showing up and picking it back up again after a while
in the moment
and Anne you know just steady steady at it you know and so I practiced
a long time in relationship to you guys and but I had to start
you know and I've been at it for close to four decades now and I don't
miss many days of meditation just to say I I'm probably
maybe one or two days in all those years where I've like I didn't meditate you
know like actually sit down and formally meditate and I think it's a kind of a maybe it's
something to share that's important to recognize that these heavy Boulders once you get them
moving right they have a tendency you know I'm sure there's a thermodynamic that explains it
but you know the momentum of practice does occur kind of like what you were
describing Pat that sense of oh yeah it's not as hard
you know that doesn't mean it it's not hard to get up you know and come and get up and
come down but um
it's huge it's really a huge thing like matanya said it's important
it's really important and it's important to recognize how hard it is
it's you know I used to stress this a lot I used to teach basic here years ago and
I used to always tell everybody that just showed up to learn to meditate this
is really really a difficult practice and you have to give yourself a lot of
compassion for doing it you have to recognize hey this isn't
easy right but I'm going to continue and so my advice is to all new
practitioners we're all practitioners don't quit that's the key
just keep doing it and pretty soon you'll be two decades one decade you
know four dick it doesn't matter it becomes you it becomes you as a human
being it's it's not something that you're doing
you're just being this and I just encourage you
just you know no matter what your mood is in that moment it's okay
just be with that mood you know so that's all I'll say thank you for
coming and practicing and supporting me with your practice thank you Richard
Nemo did you want to say anything else that was such a perfect closing note I'm not here okay
so I have a um a new it's a new practice we'll see how it
goes but the practice that is um for the dedication of Merit
what I'd like to do is invite each of you if you want to name
you know the benefit of our practice is for all beings without exception right
and that is the absolute wish and intention and sometimes we forget about some of
the beings that are part of all beings and sometimes we're aware of beings that
are suffering and could really use being named
so uh without you know talking a lot about whatever
animals or beings or causes that are on your hearts that you
would like to name as part of all beings to dedicate the Merit of what we are
sharing here please do so Nemo if you have anyone you could start and just pass the mic around
and and this is just part of helping us remember and connect to all beings everywhere that are suffering
because all beings are suffering and how we hope that our Ben our
practice benefits them I think I would like to dedicate it to
all the drivers I passed coming here all especially in traffic oh it is amazing
it actually is a practice like biking around is
being aware is almost like externalized yeah and just being stuck somewhere
and you can't move and there's a red light and there is also compassion there's so
many times people would let me pass that they didn't have to or would acknowledge
that I am letting them pass and there's even compassion in those moments so I I have compassion for them and I
would I dedicated to the ones that were frustrated at the traffic and the ones
that were kind beautiful Nemo thank you
uh I'd like to dedicate the this Merit
the practice to all middle school students wanting
wanting to feel belonging instead of forcing this whole concept of fitting in
may they know that they are fine as they are
so I want to recognize the teachers
honestly my children are grown very grown adults and so I hardly ever think
about teachers anymore but you have reminded me
how important what you're doing is
and I would just like to include all of the teachers everywhere who are in
charge of you know shaping the Next Generation
thank you
to my brother David
maybe a non-human dedication to my cat and all the cats
for giving us so much joy something that she can only do
I I I just don't do your kids I dedicated to her cat
no but I dedicated to all the Young
middle school girls in Iran who were trying to
grow and have aspirations for a better world
I'd like to dedicate the Merit of our practice to incarcerated people living in cages
across America hell beings be free
this practice benefit each of you may you carry it with you
and share it widely and may all beings everywhere
be free [Music]
thank you