good evening
and welcome to imc it was a pleasure as i
entered this evening to hear one person who's here comment that this was the first time they've been
at imc in person and what a pleasure that is
my name is david david laurie very happy to be here sitting in for gil
tonight and uh
sitting in with you sitting sharing in the dharma together
i had intended to guide the meditation lightly in the beginning
and then as i looked around at people settling into meditation i i i just felt that
that would be superfluous tonight sort of very clear that people were
settling in and finding finding some nice stillness a quiet
evening not too many trains passing not too much traffic or sounds of
sounds of the street supportive evening what the buddha might call an auspicious
and auspicious evening so
gil sometimes comments that in the practice we balance
effort and allowing and if you've heard gil say this you may
have also heard gil uh talk about efforting and allowing just to make
a couple para parallel verbs and i thought that this evening we might
explore a little bit some of the uh some of the nuances of
this balancing effort and allowing in the practice
had i guided the meditation i i might have because i sometimes do
bring attention to how even in the uh even in the initial
entry into the meditative space even in some of the uh most foundational
instructions in our tradition there's a there's this balancing
there's a balancing and there's a rebalancing when we close our eyes for example if we
close our eyes in meditation we we rebalance we sort of re-um
refined our inner life among all the
all the noise and activity of the world we engage in with our eyes open
when we bring our eyes down in the meditation our attention tends to turn come inward
and downward a bit and we find some aspect of what's happening in the inner world in our inner life
when we follow the one of the essential instructions of our
practice when we find that the minds become sort of contracted around something
when we find that the mind has wandered off when we find ourselves in daydream
solving problems searching solutions remembering thinking about other people thinking about
ourselves you know the places the mind goes when it's being a mind
good and useful places um at times
when we bring our attention back gently without hurry to the to here and now
maybe using the breath as our anchor returning our attention
to the here and now we're doing this rebalancing we're sort of you could say adding a
little effort into the mix into a mix that maybe had become a little unfocused or a little
a little tangled a little caught up a little distracted
so what i'd like to do is talk about this just a little bit with a little more detail having sort of set the stage
i'd like to share a suit of one of the buddhist discourses this one from the on guitar
nikaya the collection of discourses ordered by number
and spend a little time thinking about how
when we find ourselves maybe pitched a little far in the direction of effort
a little too overly engaged with various things that come up in our experience
we could bring a little additional ease in or maybe maybe more importantly when we
find ourselves a little settling into the contentment that can come with meditation
settling into the ease getting a little foggy fuzzy a little unclear a little
unfocused how we might bring a little bit of uh um maybe a little bit of edge a little
bit of uh attentive curiosity back into the practice
part of the reason i emphasize that is we emphasize the other a lot frequently we talk about what to do with the mind
that's overly busy sometimes we um i think it's useful to look at what we
do when the mind gets foggy day dreamy or when in the larger picture of our practice we
find ourselves becoming complacent or maybe just sort of going along with what
can be a very pleasant flow of a meditation practice
um
along with this along with this balancing
there's also a momentum of practice and a lot of times the momentum of
practice is is closely related to this balance when we find ourselves in a in a
a time in practice or a place in the meditation where we
feel a strong leaning toward being more awake in our lives
it can be fairly easy to adjust the balance to come back to center to come
back to the place where effort and ease effort and allowing are nicely balanced
and so too this this attention to momentum
uh can be can be beneficial to the practice supportive of the practice
sometimes you'll hear gil and other teachers andrea
the co-guiding teacher here use metaphors to talk about um
balance and practice and very commonly the metaphor of riding a bicycle is used
andrea sometimes uses the metaphor of using a kick scooter
i don't know how many people grew up using kick scooters one thing i found about these metaphors
is that they're a little culturally specific i grew up riding a bike i guess i had a scooter
but not everybody did and some of the communities i teach in bicycle riding and scooter kicking are not actually
part of everybody's experience so i've been trying to find other other metaphors that might be useful
the ones i've come up with tonight for some reason are standing and walking
i recognize that even these aren't universally human experiences and you know don't want to
would like to be as inclusive as possible but let me give an example from each of
these riding a bike we're going to start with but when you're riding a bike
particularly if you've become good at it not maybe when you're first learning we do this we do this rebalancing
extremely um as if it were as
um without real effort or attention because it's become so second nature
we we find that we can tip back to balance really without
thinking about it and similarly with the scooter
um if again and again my memory of the scooter is less distinct than the bicycle
a very similar thing when you're when it when once you've learned it's you could say it's like riding a bike
that is once you've become adept at it maintaining your momentum maintaining
your balance is second nature uh
standing and walking are similar and if you do any standing meditation which i do quite a bit
um you can um just enjoy the body's ability to balance without without thinking
about it if you want to experience it experience that
you can sometimes bring greater attention to it by closing the eyes for a period of time and doing it without a support
noticing the bodies this incredibly complicated little orchestrated uh
second nature maintaining balance maintaining a balance between effort and allowing
the um these two
themes of balance and momentum are can be applied to any scale of the
practice that we that we choose it can be true
in tonight's sit and it can be true in almost any portion of the set
that as we meditate we find the mind moves off into fogginess or gets caught up in something that needs doing before
tomorrow morning or gets distracted by bodily sensation perhaps we're hungry or
overly full or sleepy
we bring it back to greater alertness and um
that's happening at this kind of microscale in the course of a 45 minute sit that's going to happen many times
this is a natural part of the meditation it's important to point out that we don't just establish balance as if it
were autopilot and then it's set for the rest
of the evening or the rest of our practice life but rather it's something we constantly
rebalance just like on a bicycle just like on a scooter just like standing or walking
the balance is constantly being adjusted constantly being reasserted constantly being
refound it also works on the on the scale of the
whole practice where um bringing ourselves back periodically in touch with our
fundamental intentions for the practice balances a tendency to over time
sort of take it for granted maybe not be as focused in it kind of frequently settle into the pleasantness
of it if we find it largely pleasant and lose a little bit of the um
the uh sort of the maybe the growing edge or where the the edge of the practice is where
there's something still to be discovered of interest something that may be
disturbing sometimes when there's a sense of stasis or static-ness in the practice
there's some avoidance something that we maybe have a little aversion to seeing or something that's frightening
so it can work from this very intimate scale a very micro scale of a of a portion of a sit it can work on the
scale of the of the whole practice i said earlier that
one thing uh i think we tend to focus a lot on the busy mind the mind that gets caught up in things
distracted by things lost in things wanders off and sometimes don't
maybe don't look as closely at the mind that that daydreams or that gets fuzzy and
unfocused and this can be particularly something uh in the evening and i
thought of this in particular because this is a rather late time for me to sit
and um i had a little a little uh cup of tea beforehand so that i wouldn't
nod nod off during an evening meditation but i wanted to
share with you a suita that talks about dozing off and
in which the buddha gives one of his principal disciples some advice about what to do
when one finds one's mind becoming unfocused unclear
daydreamy and perhaps dozing off
it's uh it's a suita that provides some tips that we can apply to the micro level to like what to do in meditation
if you find yourself dozing off sometimes which possibly we all have from time to time
or if on the larger scale we find ourselves becoming a little complacent
in our practice again sometimes we focus on over striving in
the practice sometimes we get a little bit i don't know if lazy's the right word
sounds sort of pejorative but a little complacent little a little maybe overly content
this suta tells us i think provides some good good and wise tips
about sort of that work at both these levels so let me read it and i'm going to read
it selectively and then go back and make a couple comments about it so this is uh
this is uh for those following at home this is from the ungutara nikaya from
the book of sevens and it's the 61st suta in the book of seven so i'm going
to turn that kaya 761 and it's called appropriately dozing
and i'm gonna as i read it i'm gonna correct for gender and i typically correct for
some a lot of the discourses as you know are shared with monastic followers of the buddha and sometimes a little
correction for lay practitioners is useful in this case i think it works fine as it is
it begins as so many suttas does with the phrase thus have i heard
on one occasion the blessed one the buddha was dwelling among the bhagas at sum summary era in the deer park at
besakala grove and on this occasion the venerable maha
mogalana was sitting in meditation and dozing off and some of you know may know that
mogallana maha mogulana mogalana the great is one of the buddha's principal
followers um equal to saruputa in his uh
his importance in the early practice community so here we have a senior practitioner
somebody who's practiced a lot sitting and dozing and the buddha
notices this that in the back of the room could be nancy but it's maha maha nancy
who has dozed often the teacher has noticed and uh
approaches and says are you dozing mogallana have you been dozing off sitting in meditation
meditation and mogallana confesses he doesn't confess it doesn't say that he just says yes ponte yes teacher
the buddha says because we're in the book of sevens he gives seven tips
seven ideas seven maybe practice suggestions as a as a teacher might
mogalana you could attend uh you could have
mogulana perhaps you should try not attending or cultivating the object that you were
attending to when you became drowsy perhaps by this means it would be
possible that your drowsiness will be abandoned if this doesn't work
if you're unable to abandon your drowsiness in this way you could ponder examine and mentally
inspect the dhamma as you have heard it and learned it then perhaps by this means your drowsiness will be
abandoned if this doesn't work if you find yourself unable to abandon
your drowsiness with this technique you could recite in detail the dumma as
you have heard it and learned it and perhaps by this means
it is possible that your drowsiness will be abandoned
if this doesn't work you could pull both your ears and rub
your limbs with your hands and perhaps by this means
abandon your drowsiness if this doesn't work
you should get up from your seat rub your eyes with water look around in all directions
look up at the constellations and stars and by this means
it's possible that your drowsiness will be abandoned
if you cannot abandon your drowsiness in this way you should attend to the perception of
light you should undertake the perception of day thus as by day so at night and as
as at night so by day and thus with a mind that is open and uncovered you should develop a mind
imbued with luminosity with light and by this means possibly your
drowsiness will be abandoned if this fails
you can undertake the exercise of walking meditation walking back and forth perceiving what is behind you and
what is in front with your sense faculties drawn in and your mind collected
and by this means possibly your drowsiness will be abandoned
and then finally there's one more and this is the punchline he says but if you cannot abandon your drowsiness in any of
these ways take a nap he doesn't say it quite like that but if
you cannot abound in your drowsiness in these ways you should lie down on your right side in the lion's posture
with one foot overlapping the other mindful clearly comprehending and noting
in your mind the idea of rising when you awaken get up quickly
and think i won't be intent on the pleasure of rest the pleasure of sleep
but rather return to practice it is in this way mogallana that you should train yourself
so there's a lovely set of instructions and tips here presented in
this very supportive way that i think um
provide a sense that that there's nothing unusual or
in this kind of experience nothing wrong has happened nothing's gone wrong in the meditation the
practitioner hasn't done anything wrong but rather that one of the natural aspects of our practice is
this kind of occasional drowsiness if we're thinking about it at that small scale
or complacency or lack of focus in the practice on a maybe on a broader scale
and we can go back and just look at a few of these i want to make sure to leave some time to uh for people to ask
questions or raise uh share reflections or anything else
um but the first one here uh you shouldn't you should not attend to or cultivate
the object that you're attending to when you became drowsy very interesting suggestion
we we tend in our practice to get very um used to a particular object and yet as
we know from for example the sati patana suta the suta in
various ways and various approaches to establishing mindful attention in the here and now that there are a whole host
of practices a whole host of objects a whole host of
ways to cultivate the practice of mindful attention the practice of open
uh awareness and it's an interesting suggestion that
if drowsiness is there perhaps shifting your attention in various ways
can be a useful remedy or useful way to spark a little bit of greater alertness
in the practice
even with drowsiness sometimes there can be a great a great deal of kind of
very sort of small or laser focus on the
breath and it can be useful to broaden the focus
so i think there are many ways that that that this advice could be brought into play
it may also be useful in the broader scale of practice we get caught up in a certain practice
you can do so a practice for years and complacency can set in and
finding with the guidance of a teacher some additional ways to bring support into the practice can be very
beneficial the second one says if you cannot abandon your
drowsiness or your complacency i'm going to sort of add that in in this way you can ponder examine and
mentally inspect the dhamma as you have heard it and understood it
and this is true in a a sit but it's also true in the bigger
practice that it can be very useful if you're starting to find yourself drowsy to bring attention to a teaching
that uh is relevant to whatever's going on in your in your sit or in your larger practice
not sure i can think of an example at the moment but um
it can be useful here's an example two and i think i mentioned something like this a few moments ago
to notice whether the drowsiness has a version in it to notice whether there's something that
doesn't feel comfortable to see or know
or if there's a if there's a attachment to bodily comfort that's
there in the meditation that's kind of part of the drowsiness or daydreaminess if there's ideation in the daydream it
can be very useful to notice where's the how much wanting how much selfing is
happening in the daydreaming as i envision myself in a different position with
different accomplishments different friends different you know
different attributes that uh somehow are puffing me up
so even in the drowsiness there can be aspects of the teaching that if we bring our attention to it can sort of bring us
back to back to the back to the here and now
if this doesn't work this is a slight change we can recite in detail the dhamma as we have heard and learned it
in other words we can ponder examine mentally expect it or we can recite it
and this one is useful to bring forward into our time at that time reciting was the way in a
sense you read or re-read the dhamma you would chant a suta if you were a monk at
any rate and that would be a way of in a sense re-engaging with what we would think of as a text
but this could direct us to a text and in a sit it can be very useful
you're drowsy or just before you sit down to read a paragraph from a book
or a sentence or
a poem but somehow to re-engage with a textual reference or the language of the
teaching obviously this can be true at the sort of larger scale of practice that we can
pick up a book we've read before or listen to a podcast or
you know go on retreat online or offline
and in that way sort of re-engage with formal teaching i think that's the distinction that's
being drawn here in these two the ones that follow
i think we could stretch them to that larger scale but they're mostly i think useful for actual sitting with drowsiness or
unfocus in the mind i have found i have to share that pulling the earlobes is a really good
solution for drowsiness and if particularly if you're in a place where it's not appropriate to just lie down
and take a nap which as we know is recommended by the buddha we'll get to that in a moment
rubbing the earlobes is a really good uh and who knows why this works because the earlobes don't have a lot of you know we
don't really think about them very much but if you spend some time twisting your ears and pulling your earlobes it can
bring quite a bit of alertness into your set if you find yourself nodding off and you're sort of thinking that that's
maybe something you want to you don't want to nod off and fall over
um the following one standing up rubbing your eyes looking around i don't know if
other people have tried this but if you're drowsy in a set standing up for a couple minutes and sitting back down
can really bring some additional energy the following one opening your eyes and
letting some light in can be very useful and we typically even at night
this has this interesting passage about as by day so at night so at night i mean as at night so by day
not sure exactly what that means but the um in our world i'm just looking at those
halogen lights over there there's usually a source of light even at night even in a retreat setting where
we can open our eyes a little bit bring some light in and in that way
bring some alertness back into the meditation
or standing up and walking you know doing doing some walking meditation
there's no rule that says at home if you're drowsy you can't get up and walk around
even here it's um if it's not disruptive to others getting
up and taking a few paces sitting back down can be entirely um
uh can can can wake up the practice and about the nap i would just say and
here here too i i sort of can refer to something gill says
a lot gil let me think how does he put it in the intro class to meditation he
frequently comments that more than mindfulness meditation americans need a nap
something like that and it's very true in our culture with uh you know with artificial light and
self-medicating with caffeine throughout the day you know we extend our days in a quite
unnatural way and i think we think we get away with it but sooner or later we notice it not infrequently in meditation
it's not uncommon as you all maybe remember when you first sat to meditate
that uh along with noticing how incredibly busy the mind is you may have noticed how fatigued both mind and body
are and that can still be there and just being aware of that fatigue and
making sure that it's that it's addressed as a support to practice as
the buddha counsels mogallana the idea is to take a brief nap as a way of supporting
practice so that it it that sort of addressing the natural fatigue
of body and mind can be can be part of practice
so let me leave a few minutes for questions and i would just say this this is a
lovely little suta it's fun to read um it's it shows the buddha in a lighter moment perhaps
or at least uh giving very gentle guidance to a senior practitioner who has
i think in in whom we can in whom and in whose practice we can see ourselves very
easily um and
it's uh in addition to giving these sort of tips and tricks and techniques i
think it does point to some of the deeper aspects of practice the idea as i said earlier in the
evening that the practice is always about not not setting a balance and expecting it
to stay but constantly rebalancing constantly looking for ways to add
additional curiosity inquisitiveness looking being attentive being present
but at the same time doing that in a way where there isn't a lot of for and against where there's ease
noticing as we do when we ride a bicycle or a scooter or when we walk or stand
just noticing when things are slightly out of balance and then coming back into
balancing to the extent that that becomes second nature it's useful even to be aware of
that process happening when it's very very subtle when we follow it
we we keep that momentum going because in that balancing
there is there is directionality that is that is a path that leads toward
awakening toward ease toward contentment of a deep sort
and so this idea of keeping attuned to
the balance of effort and allowing in the practice really is a way to keep
moving toward the direction that frequently we in some sense hold as our fundamental
intention for the practice and perhaps for our the way we take our practice
into the world so let me leave leave it there and then
ask if there are any questions or anything that anybody would like to share we probably have some couple microphones
we can pass around and i can repeat questions if if not
are there any questions any reflections any thoughts nancy
[Applause] hi thank you
um during retreats i have
um usually a difficult time sleeping in the evening and
then in the morning sit usually the six a.m sit i doze off immediately
and i noticed that by the end of the retreat like a week-long retreat
i'll do better at staying awake early but i'll just be exhausted by the end of the
retreat and i'm wondering if you could comment on that phenomena
oh gosh um it's funny because for every
for every nancy with that experience on retreat there's the other you know there's the other half right there's the
uh what would it be the larks right as opposed to the the night owls
um but it would be you could ask the same question from that perspective uh people who find like i quite quite the
opposite you know quite alert in the morning um and it's interesting i've actually i
actually use these approaches a lot um yeah i i didn't read about them all of
them here first you know they were recommended also by teachers but i think
what we find frequently either in the evening or in the morning is that we're sort of fighting that experience instead
of um integrating it into the practice uh
among other things it's okay to nod off we don't usually fall over and hurt ourselves everybody does it so nobody
cares on retreat that is you know people nod off through the course of the day particularly in the first few days
so there's just like the buddha in mogallana there's a i think a sense of supportive environment to the experiences that come
up in the in the retreat um the last advice which is actually eighth
and even though it's in the book of sevens taking a nap there's usually time during the day to
take a nap i always take a nap on retreat after doing the dishes after lunch usually
and so you know you can make that part of your practice but anyway i think the main my main
thing is there's no you haven't described a problem you know
um very much as this is seen the buddha doesn't see this as a problem but he has some ideas for kind of how to keep
alertness there having said that if you were to find and i can say this to you knowing something
of your practice uh just that if you were to find that in that
repeated pattern there's some complacency right or some something that
is not ready to be seen yet that you feel like yeah you want to and i i don't know that i think that's there but
you know that that would be a useful thing to know and that's another reason to look at that drowsiness you know with
some curiosity instead of some judgment like oh instead of this shouldn't be happening oh is there anything else going on here
am i just tired am i just a night owl and if you were to find something like
that you know that's a good thing to bring into your practice too with the support of your teacher
yeah other questions reflections
jim
well thank you david for your talk you know my practice i think a lot about
being sleepy in the morning and actually i kind of find that there's something
that happens in that liminal space between being asleep and being awake
where things do kind of present themselves to me in a way that they don't
if i'm upright and alert and paying attention you know it's kind of like
there might be things that yup you know are kind of in that liminal
space so a lot of my has kind of been in that sort of dream state between
sleep and awake and i was wondering if you've had that experience or might have something to say about it
yeah yeah and what what you point to i think is uh is a is a really productive
way to bring and integrate that into practice which is to notice what's going on in that in that realm
which sometimes when we receive the encouragement to return attention to the
breath uh it's done in such a way that we move we move our attention back to the breath
too quickly and we miss noticing where the mind's gone
and whether the mind's gone you know it's gone all tangled up in some you know compulsive spiral of thought or whether
it's found itself in daydream and i'm i've also found it very useful to be attentive to
i say daydream but i know the liminal space you're talking about that's sort of between it's in a way it's beyond
daydreaming you know toward but but you know maybe there's random things
that happen in mind but i think more likely than not there are
things that happen there that can be usefully noticed
so anyway i think you know the instruction always is to notice what's going on be curious about
what's going on be present for what's going on in a way that can sort of integrate that experience
instead of push it away or hold on to it so
it sounds sounds like good sounds like good practice
yeah other thoughts other questions
it's hard to tell with masks on quite how alert everybody is
and maybe how apt the advice of the buddha to mogallana is
um i'm alert now because i'm you know i'm i'm sitting up here but um
yeah i think i think we can
say again oh that's a good question i don't even know how this works
okay yeah thanks for reminding me nancy that there's a larger audience yeah
any other thoughts reflections
from the youtube audience or the audience here
okay so i can just um trying to think if there's any closing
thought any beyond you know
making sure you get your rest take that nap that the buddha recommends
that mogalana takes it's funny because we we underestimate
the importance of that piece of sage advice from 2500 years ago
uh
i think um i've already sort of summed up these things but let me do it in sort
of the manner of offering uh the merit of the practice this evening
and just um suggesting that we
bring this aspect of our practice this aspect of bringing attention to the balance that gill
has mentioned and that i've just sort of been riffing on this evening between effort and allowing
that that that that's something we we take out into the world with us and make make
that part of balancing our practice something that we we do
in a way and do with the intention of benefiting benefiting others
and there's probably many ways that this could be thought of but i think
being curious about other people being open to other people's experiences you know
being listening with an open heart can be part of that sort of
making that effort and the allowing can be as we look around the world allowing our
hearts to break allowing our minds to be as open as they can
allowing ourselves to ask for help and give help allowing ourselves to care
be cared for so with that in mind may all beings be
safe secure may all beings be healthy in body and mind may all beings
be free from suffering and the roots of suffering may all beings be at ease content
may all beings be free
[Music]
so thank you and thanks for coming whether for the first time the last time
uh 100th time yeah good to see everybody take care