so hello again from irc and site retreat retreat center
and um today i'd like to continue with this
practice of knowing and [Music] it's important to appreciate there's a
range of maybe intensities of knowing or range of
ways we know sometimes it's very intentional and directed
and sometimes it's uh unintentional
and undirected if
sometimes in practice when it begins most people a lot of people find it helpful to have a directed practice just
focusing on their breath for a while and that focusing on the breath kind of allows things to gather and settle
around it and so that um and so that we uh
um um you know and uh so we're not so easily distracted and mind doesn't
wonder so much and when the mind is stable that's when uh that that's when it's be
useful when to lessen less directed knowing and in a certain kind of way less
intentional um uh less not a knowing that has any quality of
work to it or any quality of of um
doing it but rather it's a knowing that just arise just is
and so to give you a little maybe a taste of this i know we just haven't even started meditating
but if you just close your eyes the way you are now
and um and when you make no effort
to be aware but you're awake you're not falling asleep
what do you know
when when awareness is not directed anywhere
what is known what comes into awareness
is it the sound of my voice
are there sensations in your body or in the environments sounds in the
environment
not preferring or directing attention any one direction but in a sense just being open
to the obvious
sensation experience that comes into awareness
in the most simple form
in relationship to simple sensations
the direct sensations of the moment
and the knowing which is no not any work
it's just an openness of mine to let things be known
as they appear in their own way there's no control
over what is being experienced
perhaps the only thing you can do you do is relax
if you notice that you're knowing
has a certain fixation on anything relax
if you're mostly aware of something in particular
maybe a strong sensation chances are other things appear together
with it or in little moments in between
in a sense the knowing follows
the trail of what arises what appears
and if you settle into your body relax into your body
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the belly
relaxing the arms and hands
even the fingers
relaxing the thighs
calves
all the way down to the feet
perhaps relaxing in the face
softening around the eyes the jaws
and with the awareness open now just open and receptive to the
sensations of your body anywhere in the body
what sensations arise which are then known without any work
without any directedness
the knowing might not be verbal
it might be deeper some people might say intuitive knowing
of sensations as they appear
there is a kind of natural knowing of their presence
and no need to linger with any sensation
no need to think about anything simply
each fleeting sensation that appears maybe disappears and
reappears
the coming and going and different sensations
as they arise see if you can notice
almost an almost effortless knowing that knowing
for which you don't need to make any effort
your effort is simply to stay receptive and present in your body
if you're thinking about things or living your preferences or
reacting to your sensations
all that is
different than the sensations themselves
if you live in the preferences reactions thinking
you might miss the dance
of sensations in your body as they appear and disappear
as they appear and then another appears another appears
some don't disappear so easily
but are followed by some different sensation
sometimes a surprise where they appear in the body
not directing attention holding attention anywhere except for the whole body is a organ
of receptivity
and because the breathing is one of the bigger movements when the body is not moving otherwise
chances are that the sensations of breathing
also arise in the field of sensations
see if you can notice the effortless knowing
or a kind of natural knowing
of what is it that arises
settling more perhaps settling into the body breathing
and they're having this receptive awareness
that allows sensations of breathing to appear whatever way they want
whatever way they do
maybe they don't they appear in ways that are not your the common pattern
because you're not directing or expecting
the common experience of breathing just open receptive
allowing the sensations to appear as they do
and allowing the simplest form of knowing of this appearance
when there is a quiet receptivity
a sensitive receptivity to our experience
then when we encounter the suffering of others
we might feel it more acutely
and readily or easily give up the simplicity of knowing
knowing suffering without any without giving birth to effort
directedness responsibility
needing to do something
without taking it in in any personal way
that that suffering somehow
requires something of you the suffering is simply known
experienced as part of the field of things that
appear and disappear
and this doesn't have to be aloof we're disconnected
it's actually more intimate it's staying intimate staying connected
falling back on responsibility or preferences or taking it personally
that's where the kind of disconnect begins
taking in the suffering of the world in this simple way of being present
may allow for a simplicity of compassion
the simplicity of well-wishing of care and love
where our care our kindness can also arise in his almost effortless
way and we know that we care
we see the caring arising
and to know it with this simplicity of knowing
not being quick to make it personal or need to do anything
just care kindness
and perhaps with that as a reference point for
the dedication of merit dedication of our benefits and practice
may these words i speak be your words and may they arise
with ease and effortlessly
out of your being
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we as a community and as individuals
go into the world
to benefit the world to support the welfare of others
may all beings be happy
and with uh as i bow now to end the sitting
perhaps you'll bow and return
so i thought this would be the last talk on the second exercise of satipatana
which is the mindfulness of postures
and as with the first exercise each of the
13 exercises it's followed by the refrain
and the refrain is the same for each and this
implies that this simple pos mindfulness of posture
as it as a as a foundation can lead to the deepening of practice described in
the refrain so it can lead to a
kind of open awareness that's receptive to both what's inside and outside
what's the ways in which we experience our body from the inside out and then the ways we experience our body
from the outside in just it's just an open awareness to know to know what is arising
and um the um
and then as we do this there starts becoming a sensitivity to
how things just appear and um even though there might be some predominant thing that lasts
uh at the same time we notice that new things appear into consciousness into awareness
from the body within the posture the sensations of the body and to receive the comings and going of
sensations and to know it in this simple way can allow kind of a deepening and a
quieting and a settling stilling of the mind until we start tasting something of the
freedom of the radical simplicity where there's no craving
no clinging to anything so that's one direction
in which the this mindfulness of posture can go
i'd like to take it a different direction which is as we become more sensitive and more
attentive to our posture we can become aware of the details of our posture
or the subtle variations in our posture as we go through our lives and we can have develop a tremendous
amount of self-understanding by noticing the shifts in our posture
so there doesn't have to be big shifts so it doesn't have to be mean from going from standing to sitting or sitting to
lying down but if we're standing with someone talking with them or we're sitting with someone
doing some activity what is the posture expressing
are we tense and maybe like we're not happy with what's going on and we're actually in a
chair and we're pushing back into the back rest of the chair or perhaps we're really eager to
understand someone and this desire to understand and we lean forward
maybe they tell you that they have the um they know what you know
what the lottery number will be for the winning some big prize
then we lean forward because of the desire for something uh or maybe we feel uh discouraged
someone says something and and um you know someone says something
personally about ourselves someone says to mel to me that you know
that uh well self-respecting dharma teacher doesn't wear blue shirts and so then
i've noticed that my shoulders sag and the little slumping going on there's a deflation going on the discouragement
the disappointment something so there's all these little movements that the posture varies
and um and if we as we pay attention to the posture and we're sensitive to it and then we
can become aware of the subtle shifts and variations we turn away someone's saying something and we find ourselves
turning away or [Music] the
we're holding ourselves more tensely so the posture
expresses what we're feeling the posture expresses what we're uh
some intention some purpose some uh
all kinds of things are expressed in the posture and we say that we this is a kind of represented in the english
language by the verb posturing
we say someone was posturing it means that they were kind of asserting themselves at their status and
trying to you know take a assume a place in the hierarchy or in the situation or
trying to show them prove themselves or show who they are and relationship to others
and and that can also be expressed in posture confidence can be expressed in posture
care and attentiveness can be expressed in posture
to really be present for someone can be expressed in posture many years ago i've been i haven't
experienced this for now for maybe almost 30 years but there was a series of people over a
course of a year i'm not saying three people maybe who um if i stood listening to them
speak and i was kind of facing them directly maybe i'm a little bit intimidating
perhaps but i directly face someone and listen to them but they would
turn around almost at 90 degrees to talk to me and if i went around kind of to be more
you know directly facing them they would turn around 360 degrees without knowing it
just because they didn't want to have that direct you know looking or direct contact
and so i was quite surprised by this because i was partly because they seemed unconscious to it
though i don't know what was going on now that 30 years later you know maybe it was something about how i was maybe i
was too forthcoming in my attention so it can go both in all kinds
of ways sometimes we pay attention to the postures of other people and it tells us
something about how they're responding to us and reacting to us and this is one of the meanings and one
of the interpretations of the first part of the refrain that
one experiences oneness observes the body
internally and the body externally that some people say it means to pay attention to other people their bodies
and so now with the posture you can also notice people's other people's postures and the
shifts they have and as we speak and as we're doing things as they're doing things we can tell so often a lot about
their emotional state their their attitude about things in their posture
so this uh exercise this mindfulness of posture
can take this more subtle form this variation here as a means of both self-understanding
and a heightened understanding of other people and our psychology our attitudes our
feelings and emotions sometimes can become very clear or first revealed through shifts in our
posture and that happens for me sometimes that the first thing i know that i'm tense is when i'm leaning
forward maybe and sometimes when
when i'm giving dharma talks and i'm a little bit concerned that people are not understanding me or
following me i notice i begin leaning forward and it's that leaning forward that tells
me that i'm a little bit now worried about you know how people are hearing me or
how clear i might be and so i noticed that leaning forward occasionally leading forward doesn't
mean that but sometimes i know that's what it means and and then i notice that and that
you know and then i come back and relax and settle in again
so um mindfulness of posture i hope that these days i've been looking at it
uh has heightened your attention and interest and sensitivity to posture your posture
and the value of how that can be one of the anchors one of the to the present moment to staying
present staying mindful being here and not wondering often thoughts too far
away from the presence so
so thank you very much
and tomorrow i will start on the next uh exercise
which a little bit is a continuation of what i just did now where i where mindfulness a posture can
lead to a wider understanding of of ourselves
so the next exercise also on mindfulness of the body involves a kind of a richer wider
understanding of things in our lives as we go about it so that's for tomorrow and
thank you very much