foreign
thank you
and as this sitting comes to a close
foreign welcoming ourselves here
alert clearly knowing
and mindful
as best we can for the day setting aside our preoccupations
thank you so as to be here
[Music]
I thought if it's okay with everyone just while I welcome you I would take off my mask for a minute and put it back
on good morning
so nice to be with all of you in my estimation it could be a perfect day for mindfulness
sort of settled feeling from the clouds and the light this time
my name is codo conlon this is my friend and colleague Tanya Weiser
and this is Insight Meditation Center and you've come online or in person for
a day long of mindfulness first thing I'd like to do is welcome
all of you welcome everyone and to state that everyone is welcome
whenever your background or history or your location whether that be
geographical or social everyone is welcome here to do the practice
so I welcome you um one of the ways that IMC as a as a
center I think supports the feeling of Welcome is that everything we do is freely given
everything isn't that amazing and we offer the teachings as a in the
spirit of a gift and if at the at the end of the day you feel inspired to support support what we
do here they're ways to give a box there and a kiosk over there
as I was sitting here I was realizing there's some of course I have my plans and my notes
for what I want to say and then there's a way that we make the day of practice together
so as I was sitting here and my heart was sort of settling in and my body was settling in
what came to my mind as what we're doing today is um
one way to understand it we're making peace we're making making peace
with ourselves for ourselves with each other for each other peace with experience
there's something about that that helps me to settle in and feel welcome and safe
here in this space
so today the the [Music] idea will be we will move through the
progressive instructions of mindfulness meditation pretty gently guided
pretty gently guided mostly we're practicing together today sitting and walking practice and then
there are some sign ups for those of you are here there's sign ups for practice discussions that we can do
Tanya is there anything you'd like to add to the beginning
thank you Coda yeah
and don't hesitate to ask for a sign up for a practice discussion kodo and I are
here so it's just the sign up sheet at the end of the stage gives you 5 or 10 to 15
minutes to just ask a couple of questions about your practice
and um I'm just curious a little bit about your experience with practice
um so does anybody here feel pretty new to meditation
okay Joe yeah
yeah great um so anybody feel like um
uncomfortable with not having a lot of instructions during the meditation periods
you do Joe yeah and you do too Tina and you do too okay
so we'll we'll maybe modify a little bit happy to yeah um and try is anybody find
getting you know a little bit more instructions disruptive to your practice
those of you who have more experience is that okay yeah great great great
okay good is there anything else yeah one other
thing is um we'll have Hillary was here to get us started as the manager Sally will be
here at the end of the day part of the practice here is that we clean up the center together afterwards
so um are there some people who are willing to commit to sticking around it takes about 15 minutes after the end of the
day one two three four five great great and anybody else if you want to stick
around the more we can do more if there's more of us but the basics are great so
okay that's what I wanted to add great anything else you want to say
I can say maybe just a just to orient to the space would be a good thing to do
um most important things you're in the meditation home
restrooms are over here there's water hot and cold water and kitchen around
the corner if you need that um where will we be doing practice
discussions outside oh good yeah so um
we'll we'll do we'll set up some chairs in the parking lot okay on that side of
the building
so what I have inside will be pretty much silent unless there's a need to
talk for logistic or for question and answer
you want me to say anything about lunchtime anybody curious about lunch situation Corey that was a yes for you
or no yeah okay great um so we'll keep silence inside we have
tables um and we can put a table over in front of the redwood tree which could be for
silence people who don't want to talk during lunch and then in the parking lot we'll put a
couple of tables where people can talk so um so it's important just to tune into what
feels right for you and maybe you decide to eat it under the redwood tree and then you move to the other tables
because you wanna connect with Sangha right it's not we're not seeing much of each other the way we
used to before covid so we're trying to create whereas normally maybe we'd have a full silent lunch here
we want to support connecting so if you feel like you want to connect
with people and I'll give a little bit more instructions later but we'll have lunch at 12 I'm pretty sure
um oh yeah that's easier 12 30 looks like 12 30. um
there's microwaves in the fridge in the kitchen if you brought your lunch if you did not there's a few places that you
can walk to on Broadway that are pretty fast to get your food so did I answer your questions about
lunch say enough about it we'll have an hour great
okay
so I'm just going to take a breath for a minute invite you to do the same I'm just going to kind of come back into my cell for a
minute here and the first part of the instructions will be mindfulness of breathing
so we'll ready ourselves
and I'll do a little bit of extra talking at the beginning to orient ground toward this practice
So the instructions I'll do this little bit of talking and then I'll kind of do
some more centering to move into like more of a guided meditation just just to
orient you to what to expect the day and the way the practice is
taught here is we start with mindfulness of breathing
and then we move on to mindfulness of body emotions thoughts and open
awareness throughout the day and we start with the breath
because for those of us who are comfortable tuning into the breathing
it's so accessible it's moving and flowing through our
bodies it's a constant rhythm
something that we can tune into that's in the present moment
it's a beautiful support for practice when it works for us and if it doesn't
there are some other things you can focus on I'll talk more about them now
but in whenever I use the word breath if breath doesn't work for you you can substitute it with hearing
sound or Sensations so you have kind of those three options
to help yourself with this morning's practice and
throughout the day it's a focusing on the breathing
helps us stay connected here without getting lost in our thoughts those little mini movies that happen in
our minds all the time and with the breath moving the way it
does changing flowing
we can always bring our attention back again to it over and over again when we
wander away
there's an analogy that we're using the breath like an
anchor so a sailboat comes into the bay and
if they don't want it to float away or get pushed up onto the rocks
we drop an anchor at anchor grounds and holds the boat in
relative steadiness
in the same way our breath can be our anchor helping us
not get carried out to sea or turned over by our emotions
or maybe even abandon the practice altogether getting up and walking doing other things
so when we have an anchor we start to stabilize the mind we give
it something to hold on to in a way
to stay connected to
and we will wander the tide changes the waves change
so do the conditions inside of ourselves our minds and hearts and bodies
you know an anchor on a boat that has a a long
rope or line so you know we the boat does move
and then you know maybe when the boat gets pulled too far
it starts to tug on the anchor in the same way something can happen quite naturally for
us is if we wander at some point we'll wake up we'll
realize it and that's a little like the Rope tugging on the anchor we're right there right there the the
anchor is back
to doing this as gently as we can and
awake and aware with this intention
to stay this day
if you choose the anchor of sound instead of breath
the invitation is to receive sound when it comes your way we don't need to go out and find sound
it will come to you and when we listen when we allow hearing
we can tune into how it feels in our body where it resonates the same way we
do with breathing
if we choose Sensations to be our anchor
it can be helpful to choose something like our feet or our hands
and then you know there's other Sensations that will come in our body but we can have a kind of an anchor of
our hand and hand or our feet on the Earth
so let's take a moment to lift our shoulders
unroll them back and open up the chest [Applause]
might do that a couple of times you might bring your shoulders your elbows toward each other in the back
and naturally then the body can take a deeper breath
so allowing a few longer slower deeper breaths with this opening
and then finding this posture is balance between alertness and
relaxation
it can be useful at the start of the practice to do a brief body scan just sort of
taking your awareness and moving from the top of your head
down through your face and shoulders just touching into the experience in
your body and if you notice areas of holding or tension maybe just pause
breathe into the tension and with the exhale invite invite a sense of letting go of whatever
is not needed just slowly moving down through the
whole body the arms
chest belly
back body side body
with the belly inviting it to relax
to let the breath flow down into the belly and the belly expand with the
inhale
and just continue to scan through the hips pelvis
thighs calves and chins
ankles and feet
and if there are Sensations that remain or holding or tension just let them be
as they are
and let's bring our awareness now back to our anchor
sounds coming sounds going
Sensations coming going
breathing in and breathing out
just tuning in
knowing that we're letting the breath come to the foreground of our awareness
so it's not that other things won't be happening
we don't have to stop thinking you don't have to stop hearing if we're
using the breath just sort of letting the breath move
into the center of our awareness
or our anchor into the center of our awareness
maybe with this sort of a welcoming like an interested
I'm curious I you're welcome Brett how are you breath
let me feel you let me know you
getting to know the breath is not thinking about the breath picturing it but rather
experiencing breathing feeling
sensing
foreign
there's the in-breath feel different than the out breath
where in your body do you feel breathing
getting to know how your body is breathing today
and just resting where you feel it the most strongly
allowing your awareness to rest with the breathing
moment the moment
foreign
[Music]
foreign [Music]
foreign
[Music]
just noticing how you're doing with your breathing
if you're feeling friendly with it
foreign
maybe if it's a little bit hard to get connected you might try just a light note
with the inhale saying in and with the exhale saying out in your
mind silently kind of gently this can be a practice to do that can
help us foreign [Music]
s
breathing out with the sounds
just the way it is
[Music]
thank you [Music]
thank you
[Music]
foreign [Music]
sometimes I find it interesting to notice the system just relaxes when
sound kind of Fades away like that lower
I'm just noticing if there's any tension again in the body
breathing in to it gently
and with the exhale inviting a relaxing
[Music]
foreign [Music]
thank you
[Music]
breathing in I know I'm breathing in breathing out knowing I'm breathing out
foreign
[Music]
foreign [Music]
the whole flow of experience the thoughts that come and go
the sensations that come and go the sounds
the energy in the body
just letting it flow like the water flows
breathing here in and out
in and out
nothing needs to be different
and if you need to move it's okay just
invitation is to be clear in your mind
I think I need to adjust my posture I need to change how I'm sitting
and stay present even connected to the breathing as doing so
it's okay to move to a chair or it's okay to do what the body needs
breathing in and out all the while
thank you
foreign
thing our longest companion in life
the first thing we do when we're born
is to breathe and the last thing to do before we die
is to Exhale
foreign
in the last few minutes of the sitting
foreign breaths at a time
three breath Journeys you'll see if you can connect with the
full inhale and exhale followed by the next and the next
and notice if there's any tension or
irritation or difficulty happening inside yourselves
and if so if you can give it a hug
just a gentle caring
hug
the staying with the breath
a few more breaths at a time
foreign [Music]
just a little short bathroom stretch break we'll come back for
instructions for walking meditation at five till and then we'll have a 30 minute walking
period so just taking a minute to take care of your body we actually were sitting a
long time because we sat half an hour before so I just take care of your bodies go to the
bathroom drink come back we'll be back here at five tail
all right maybe we should all stand up let's give
our bodies we'll do this instruction just standing give ourselves a break
so um you know when we're walking when we're doing walking meditation
um we can make it fairly simple
for ourselves and kind of just focus on our feet
oh the camera that's right I forgot hi YouTube sorry
we can make it pretty simple and just sort of be aware lifting placing lifting
placing you know sort of like that would be lifting placing is sort of like saying in and out with that inhale and
exhale so we're going to notice we're lifting up and we're going to notice we're placing down
so there's two parts know that and feel it right so practice mindfulness is about
experiencing not thinking about using the mind to help us track what's
happening can help us stay with the experience makes sense
so just walking at a pace that's comfortable
for you and you can play with that I encourage you to try different speeds
sometimes when you're on Retreat you'll see people walking like
incredibly slow like this just incredibly slow
feeling just the teeniest tiniest little movements
just staying with it and that can be very supportive for building concentration
but it also can make us tight and tense it's also fine to walk a little faster
you know pay attention to um kind of the impact of the spacing
you might notice um just when you find the right pace it's
like oh okay a little bit of this breath you know
like ease we don't want to try over hard
we want to make it easy to be present for ourselves
if I if we're having a hard time staying with The Walking our mind is doing a lot
of wandering there's more things to start to break down your experience into smaller bits
you can do a lot more of like um really kind of maybe breaking down the
oh heels up toes up you know a foot's off foot's reaching heels down toes down
if you want if you feel like that would be helpful for you maybe a few back and forths I wouldn't
overdo that but it's a little bit like trying to help yourself
get connected to the flow so it can be a little bit more detail can be helpful
the other thing is you can actually kind of just feel your whole body walking
you can just oh like open up more expansively to the experience of the
whole body with the feet so
we'll uh we can walk inside if we walk in the hall
we walk the way Jan's going which is the short Direction and you can also walk outside we tend to
choose a path of walking so like 15 20 feet or something like that long
and you walk come to the end
for me it's very helpful at the end to stop
just pause and kind of let the awareness come back in and feel what it feels like
there's a momentum of moving that when we stop we can feel the settling
and then when you feel that settling that's for me my cue to think about
turning kind of allowing all the energy to settle okay and then I set this
intention okay may I be aware and turn and walk back the other way
it's also okay to walk around the block right if if it's not feeling supportive for
you to do shorter walking go for a longer walk it's okay
be careful of not blocking driveways it's okay to say hi to Neighbors
even though we're in silence right we don't need to not everybody else is doing a mindfulness day-long Retreat so
you know be generous and kind you don't have to shut yourself down in any way
anything you want to add kodo or any questions
okay so we'll do walking practice until 11 30.
we'll see you back here then foreign
so just as we're settling back in after the walking period
before I start talking about this next piece of our practice
just want to mention it always seems apt when we're about to talk about mindfulness of the body that
use my phone also as a medical device so if you see me on it through the day it's part of what I'm up to it's just taking
care of this body
I felt the impulse to say welcome back but it feels more like welcome to continuing
continuing the practice just gently continuing through the day
and with our what we've done so far we've
focused on mindfulness of the breathing and
part of the function is that we've started to awaken this
feeling part of our experience a sensing part of our experience
that is directly Here and Now
um and in some way is direct simple
just right here we've started doing this with the breathing
centering our experience on the breathing
anchoring with the breathing dropping that anchor
into the bay partly so that we can feel when the boat
starts to move oh the attention is tugging here
all my thoughts are asking for my attention here
with this anchor of the breathing we recognize those Tugs
otherwise we might move about and never know
and as we've started relating with the breathing in this way
one thing that may be starting to become clear
is that the the felt sense of the body breathing
is distinct from the commentary on it
the felt sense of the body breathing is different than our stories about experience
comments about experience the breath makes no comments
and so we're prioritizing what's Here and Now and sensed and felt
and so far we've done that through the breathing
in some ways this can highlight how so much of our normal frame of mind at
least for me has so much to do with this fear of thoughts this fear of
thinking the stories and images the fantasies
that pull me into the past and the future my breathing is just here
so the thinking has quite a an outsized influence Maybe
and in the background of this practice a sort of Buddhist way of Reckoning
the mind is one of six since doors
everything that goes on in the realm of thinking just this one cent store
one out of six
and as we begin tuning into the breathing and tuning into this felt sense tuning into the felt sense of the
breathing through the body
or Waking Up waking up to more of our experience than
this one-sixth
the trajectory of the practice is such that we aim to include all of our
experience everything gets to be included
first with the breathing and now we extend to include the body
just a few introductory comments on practicing with the body
and then we can meditate together
as we tune into the body feel into the body know the body sense
the body it too is
not the commentary it is not the thinking
there can be a whole movie going on maybe in the background of experience while we're tuned in to this foreground
of what's being sensed
and there's some Freedom here than the body being distinct from the
commentary one of the ways I first came to see this
was on a Retreat like this one
I was experiencing some physical pain and had a story going along with it
a sensation and some commentary and it occurred to me
for some one reason or another the sensations in my little toe
came to the foreground of experience and I realized
my little toe is not having a problem my little toe is having no problems with
my story right now I've got this whole narrative going in my mind
and my little toe is sitting there quite peacefully having its Sensations
the comments we're not the body
one of the functions of tuning into the body
something we can trust about the body as that is that it is always
experiencing and sensing Here and Now
if what we want to do is stay present
if we're in touch with the body then we know we're doing that
we know that we're here
there's a way that our thinking or commentary can often draw us into
the short films of the past and future in our minds
draw us into memory of fantasy
and in some ways lose touch with what's here and what's now
and through mindfulness practice it's this continuity of Here and Now
it starts to build a momentum
it starts to gain in steadiness
and the flavor the flavor of
groundedness embodiment
the flavor of being here starts to come to the foreground
I have heard Tanya say before that the language of the body is sensation
much is communicated to us through the body
if in this way of Reckoning our thinking is one-sixth of our experience
how much do we perceive through the body
Eyes Ears Nose tongue
felt sense of the body how rich
just as the breathing is a kind of companion I really to the body this way a very good friend
and a sound advisor and what I mean by sound advisor
sometimes I'll do this exercise where I'll uh okay feel free to follow along if you
like I'll open both my eyes
and then I'll close one of them
and you can see how visual experience goes two-dimensional
we lose some of our ability to recognize depth
textures can be challenging to navigate with one eye closed yeah
and then being attentive open the other eye wow
three dimensions light depth
so for me living living uh centered in commentary
is like having just one of my eyes open
maybe challenging to navigate
and when I tune into the body it's like opening another eye
the visual field gets so much more rich textured nuanced
so the body's a trusted advisor because with this extra vantage point of the body then I can find my way
and find my way
it's in this sense that the body enriches our experience enriches our everyday experience
may not necessarily happen every time we sit a retreat but
you may at some point in your practice find yourself marveling at something as
simple as the texture on the painted wall
look at that
such as the enriching power of being present here through the senses through the body
and so it is with our inner life
I find being present with the body allows for the flourishing
allows for the flourishing of what's wholesome and beautiful and wisdom presence
kindness
letting go
there's a maybe thousand-year-old Buddhist teaching
that says throughout the body there are hands and eyes
the whole body sensing I'd like to invoke that as we move more
into the meditation and I'll offer just a little bit of instruction as we sit
so if you haven't done so already I would invite you to make your way back to your meditation
posture and if you already have I invite you to renew that meditation posture
when I say renew I I usually find myself
rocking a bit on my seat finding center again
reconnecting with the ground that's supporting me the seat that's supporting me
I did a fair amount of my meditation lying down so the ground the ground can also be
supporting us if we're meditating that way
so feeling our way through the seat
and then sensing our way up the spine bit by bit
as you feel your way up the spine you may notice oh I can realign here just a
little when I do that I often find myself rolling my shoulders back to come into
balance
the chest opens up
the shoulders wide
that's sensing my way up the spine all the way through the neck
and up the back half of the head
so if you can the ears are in line with the shoulders
because this posture may be a little different than our habitual ones
I find a few deep breaths helps me to settle into it and relax some of the tensions
hmm
you know for you to meditate with your eyes closed if that's comfortable
relaxing the eyes
relaxing the muscles of the face
and for softening the jaw it can be helpful to open the mouth and then let the teeth float back up
and as we did earlier just brief scanning through the body
is there any extra tension here
maybe in the arms elbows
wrists fingers
in the chest
the ribs and the solar plexus
the belly
hips
a seat
any extra tension in the upper legs
to softening
maybe in the knees
lower legs
heels feet
all the way down through the toes
the kind greeting between awareness and the body
and for a minute or two accompanying our anchor breathing
breathing in one knows breathing in
breathing out one knows breathing out
alert and clearly aware
as we accompany the breathing
surely some thoughts will arise
the breathing is not the commentary
and no problem
as best we can I'm not the commentary passed right by
e
now too deliberately incorporate the body
the invitation for the moment is to let go of any effort to direct the
attention to the breathing
and notice in the body
what's the most predominant sensation
if if one is there that's especially uncomfortable you don't have to pick the most uncomfortable sensation
maybe somewhere in the middle
so identifying that sensation turning our mindful awareness
clearly see to clearly know that sensation through the body
as we sustain our awareness in connection with this sensation
what do we notice
what's the quality of the sensation pressure
vibration
coolness Heat
maybe twisting or a pinch or an itch
in the practice of mindfulness that can't be anything
our work is to know it
attending how does that sensation change
as I observe its particulars
does it move fade
change shape
does pressing become tingling
now to bring this all together I'll invite you to return to your anchor
of the breathing
maybe with a big breath
just here with the breathing and steady
and then when I when a sensation arises in the body
that is compelling that is
Sensation that is strong enough
so as to call the attention away from the breathing
then as we just did bring your mindful awareness
to that sensation
than when it's no longer compelling or predominant or it fades away or disappears
come back to the anchor come back to the breathing
all the while with awareness
foreign
staying here with the breathing
until a bodily sensation becomes compelling
bringing our whole mindful awareness to that sensation
noticing any commentary
letting that stay in the background
the body in the foreground
foreign foreign
just a few more words about mindfulness of the body feel free to adjust your
posture wiggle
it's amazing how just a little move can let the pains go
so with mindfulness practice so much starts to open up
when we include awareness of the body one thing in particular comes to mind
right now and that is in mindfulness practice there's both what we know
the objects that we know and there's how we know the quality of that awareness
and I find I find I learned so much about how I am
by what I sense through the body like I can be working on something let's say um sometimes I will sew
the needle and thread and I'll notice through the sensations of my body
especially in my face if I'm do am I doing it with like tension
or am I doing it with relaxation so much information comes through comes
through the body or when the the blower was on earlier
everything gets to be included and I noticed it was almost like my skin had
10 percent more tension in it and then when the sound ended the skin opened back up so there's
actually a there's a physical change that I'm wouldn't be sensitive to just
through the story there's all this information coming through the body
so the primary point of practice with mindfulness of the body
sensing feeling recognizing the difference between the
body and the commentary and really letting the body be in the foreground as much as possible
staying here
wonder if now might be a good time to talk about lunch
foreign
before I talk about lunch we see if there's some Reflections or questions
does that sound okay and so um
maybe just taking a minute to witness your own experience today
just notice you know if there's anything that
maybe is different prizing
or difficult or
surprisingly easy that you experienced in your meditations
today so just just sort of like you know if
you're going into the forest to collect some Treasures witnessing your own experience today so
far collecting
in a beautiful little basket
and is there anything in this little basket
that you would like to share or question that you have for kodo or
myself and I don't know Sage if we have any Live on YouTube folks
but they can certainly type a question or comment into the chat
and we were happy to read those and respond as well
so we do have a microphone to speak into
so that it's recorded and everybody can hear so and it's okay
you know we've been in silence now we're almost three hours
so there may not be a lot that needs to be said and that's okay
and if there's a question or a comment now's a good time
yeah thank you Corey
so one of the great things about today that I noticed is just how sensitive I
was noticing myself my body um
I was noticing uh yeah that that sounds
uh would would reverberate throughout my body and
that sometimes had the nice effect of bringing me back if I had drifted off
so that was really cool and like even certain letters
of the alphabet would reverberate more strongly and I would feel those
I think I felt the S is more than anything else
it was great
thank you Corey
you want to check uh the Stream
see Honda sent three prayer emojis so that's got
to be good beautiful
so let me talk a little bit about um mindfulness of eating and lunch
um if any of you ever done the mindfulness-based stress reduction program designed by John cabotzin are
you familiar with that you you may have heard about the raisin meditation
talk a little bit in case you haven't done that meditation I'm going to talk a little bit about what it's like
and invite you to approach at least the beginning of your lunch in the same way
maybe the first five bites you could treat as a full-on raisin meditation
and then maybe periodically throughout you could pause and you know reconnect but um
you're given about you know one or two or three raisins in your hand to start
sometimes you get really plump raisins sometimes not so much sometimes they're
different colors but all of a sudden right there there's things to notice about raisins that you
might not normally pay attention to the color
shape the sense of plumpness or dried outness
the weight in your hand and you're invited to um
there's a feedback happen in there thanks you're invited to get to know kotose
your mic on okay you're invited to get to know these
raisins like um you've never seen a raisin before
so just being curious oh you might pick them up and you notice that at one end
there's like a belly button a little dried belly button and the opposite end it's just a little
round rump it's very you know doesn't have that
um and then to like smell them did you know raisins have a smell they
do and even to listen to them to put them
near your ear and when you kind of squeeze them a little bit you actually can hear a
little bit of a sound and then
you take a minute here and you hold the raisin before you're going to eat it so imagine having a raisin in your hand
right now picturing it and knowing that you're going to put it
in your mouth in a moment and even as you imagine this notice what's happening
in your body
very often what's happening is you start to salivate your body is anticipating the reason
it's actually already releasing digestive enzymes needed to digest that
reason before we've even put it in our mouth and then we're invited to put it in our
mouths but not to chew it but to let it rest to feel it with our tongues
to let the flavor just sort of you know seep out
and you're gonna feel this sense of wanting to chew the ma the the mouth knows what to do
when we eat and so you when you're doing this practice you start to see everything that's happening before
before you choose it and then you can witness this and not
not just follow don't just start chewing wait a minute
sustain feel the tension feel the wanting you're going to take a bite then
and you may notice your jaw just wants to go
so watching this too watching how the body wants to just move into chewing
chewing swallowing trying to slow it down take a bite pause
chew a couple more times pause oh the body's moving to swallow just okay
can I see that too and then experience the swallowing and follow it
all the way into the belly and then pause for a minute
before starting with your next reason so there's a lot to experience
and if we're just eating a meal we're invited to put our Fork spoon down between bites
to take our time and to feel the greed or the energy the excitement the
anticipation just be aware of it notice it not necessarily just give in
to the automatic patterns of eating so that's you know play with this I
invite you to play with us and like I said maybe you know the first two three
four five bites see if you can't really take your time in this way with your food
maybe even before even if you're sitting at a table where you'll be sharing and
talking maybe maybe just agree to take those few bites together in silence
the momentum you've built up in three hours
you probably have no idea how much more present you are even if it's been hard
it is actually something to protect
it can be tempting to walk outside and just go and just sort of let all your
mindfulness go it's good to relax and enjoy your food
but but maybe pay attention to talking a little less
pausing a little more Maybe eating some at the silent table
just be not rigid and tight at all but but a
little more protective and careful and aware of the continuity of the practice
that you've been building today take care of it for yourselves and for
each other because you will impact each other and the way you move about and talk and
eat and there are some tables it would be
nice to get some help carrying them out everybody maybe can grab a chair there's
these folding chairs over here on the side I'll open the cupboard up so maybe you could each be
responsible for getting your own chair bringing it out and then back in
it's not these you know ones that are out is a different set
and lunch will be over at 1 30.
so we have an hour to set up and disassemble afterwards as
well and I do encourage if you feel
comfortable doing some chatting to commit connect with your Sangha members
you know about practice and how we're doing and you know it's a really precious thing to
be here together I'm I'm I'm getting to know you all just a little bit and it's
very sweet to be here with you thank you for being here thank you for
your presence and if anybody did not bring a lunch
let me know and I'm happy to tell you if you don't know the area a couple of
spots where it's pretty quick and easy to get some good food
okay any questions yes Sage blessed the question that just an
announcement that if anyone asked you actually wants to do the raise of meditation I just so happen to have like
a box of like Grace and stuff oh fun I can distribute them if you want oh
that's sweet that's great
anything else great well let's let's get tables and chairs
and food and there's microwaves in the in the kitchen if you want to heat up your food please feel free to take care
of yourselves