so
sangha
community
it is something that you know as we
start
coming back
or
starting to
engage more
in communal activities
it's a reflection it's a reflection for
me to see how it is that you know in
as conditions change
there are some aspects of the practice
that
that still we can
access that that that are available to
us
and that
yeah the form may change conditions may
change and still sangha community is
possible
sangha is here wherever we go we can
find it
i know you know
the imc community has expanded
to include now so many beings everywhere
wherever you are so happy so happy we're
connected in this way i know you were
there
i knew you were there
but now you know we have a name or we
have more voices sharing or
and so it makes me reflect
how this refuge is one of the refuges in
our tradition
in this tradition in buddhism
one of the three jewels buddha dharma
sangha community
how it has evolved how it has grown how
the significance and importance of it
has unfolded more
more clarity in how important has been
and pivotal has been for me in the
practice
i just even like wow bruno you're
talking about sangha like
in the early 90s it was something
completely
something i will not connect with you
know i will come here i remember
coming here and other centers and other
places to practice where i will go and
i will go just to meditate that was it
and
that was like the the main goal you know
it's just amazing to see how the
practice evolves in a way that
make us realize that there are some
fruits of the practice
that then start showing up for us and
that if we are
aware and mindful and we start seeing
you know how it is that this practice
impact us
and in some ways um
in some ways changes us
yeah in some ways
there are some things that
become more clear
and so
one aspect of sangha one aspect of
community um
that has become more clear
for me has been
something that tina han i started
my the beginning years of the practice
i started practicing in the tignahan
tradition
and
thai would emphasize very much you know
it's like the community how how sangha
is kind of a foundation also for the
cultivation of practice
to a point that
they were moments in which he would say
you know my triage the next buddha would
be the community
and that it is also in community in
sangha where also we can find
[Music]
buddha and dharma
buddha dharma and sangha buddha the
capacity
is like us becoming a word that we have
a capacity to be awakened
that this is not something that is not
accessible to us or
that is like a privileged
way of being or to achieve or but that
is accessible to all of us as human
beings just as
just as the buddha
was able to awaken with
you know the dedication and vision
that he had
that we it is possible it is possible to
be awakened
to be to to see things as they really
are
and so the dharma how it is that many of
us also become the dharma
and that we can see the dharma in each
of us
that we can learn from each other
wow
that we can learn from each other no
matter where we come from no matter who
we are
that we can definitely
support each other in seeing the
teachings in engaging in the teachings
so yes i'm very inspired and very
inspired by sangha by community
just to see throughout the years
you know there is something as
you know
things change the rising and passing of
circumstances and things and
how it is also that there are changes
within
the sangha and
there's also steady and reliable aspect
of it that we can come back to it that
we can
just remember it
there is this aspect also of the sangha
even sometimes even within
other traditions you know
we may
have a practice within buddhism
and we also may have other practices
other traditions other kinds of ways to
to practice
being fully present
and that could be also part of sangha it
doesn't have to be contained also only
within this you know this way of being
here
and so there is something that we can
take with us
to any any community that were part of
us and it's this aspect of
um
creating
you know companionship and camaraderie
and sharing in how it is for us to to
live this life in a way that
that creates assurance and safety for
each of us
asanga that we know like i said even
though i don't know many of you
that there's an acknowledgement that we
are interconnected that we are connected
and that we care that care grows
that care towards each other
and it touches my heart
it touches my heart especially during
these times
you know these times that you know we
are
again re-engaging and not only because
of you know what is what are we as
part of
the
the community that you know is within
the planet
but also at a personal level
just to see the commitment and
dedication
that we
each of us may have in finding
well-being and finding
a sense of
how it is that we can be in this world
and
caring caring for each other at the same
time that we care for others
it doesn't become you
or me but it becomes us
us so it reminds me it reminds me just
arises in the mind and heart
what ananda said to the buddha at some
point
you know like
kaliana meet the friends spiritual
friends on the path
it's half of this holy life and the
buddha said no ananda
is his entire holy life
it's like
his entire holy life
and you know when i heard us like really
you know it's this aspect of
bruni wanting to be in independent but
independent and not connected sometimes
just they have it
you know different habits and patterns
that have arise you know different
aspects of
of this life
and it's true
it is true
you know it is it is the entirety of the
holy life
how
well we support each other and
cultivated
that safety as i'd say cultivating and
creating safety is very powerful for
each other
just offering it
but also in some ways i don't know how
it is for you but you know when i grew
up in
you know within family whatever i would
call family during
those years
we learn we learn from others by just
being in the presence of others
we may learn
many different things the whole range
maybe the whole sum and the wholesome
it may be you know some moments i
remember you know
just seeing myself acting in a way oh my
gosh this is how
one of my siblings used to
behave and i'm protesting over this and
i'm doing it right here right now
it's like okay
okay i apologize i can see it now just
making that call
i'm just being right now
a caretaker
giving care to my parents
all these different shades all these
different levels
of experience within those relationships
start also to unfold in a way that
i can see oh
you know even from here you know we take
we
there's there's aspects here
that i have brought
to communities in how i am
how i've been and i can see the changes
oh yes this is where yeah this is where
this
this was taken so
you know i i learned from or learned
from other you know other moments other
moments in which i've been you know in
groups or different communities
so we cultivate virtue
you know this aspect of
caring about each other
there's there's
a layer there there's some aspects there
that have to do with
with virtue
with integrity
we support each other
we support each other when we
practice
embodied compassion as we
are with each other too
you know just seeing some things that we
may not like about ourselves and other
things that we are like oh this is this
is part of the
you know beautiful qualities of mine
heart
and these other
other qualities it's okay
it's okay
and maybe we'll learn that
when seeing how it is that we are
treated
by others within our communities these
compassion this kindness
the sincerity
the sincerity the presence how each of
us
embody
this practice also
so as we go deeper in the practice and
we realize
we acknowledge we recognize we give
space respect
to all of us including ourselves
what an amazing support and foundation
we have to cultivate the hateful path
the hateful path in community
because there is a
there is an aspect
there is an aspect of the practice that
you know we start with ourselves we
brought
ourselves here right
so we start with ourselves and there's
you know we start seeing what is the
inner community that we have within us
and
then there's this other aspect of what
is the relational when we are out there
how it is that we relate how it is that
these practices becomes alive in other
ways and the hateful paths
support us not only for our inner
community
the inner sangha but also for the
cultivation of the external sangha you
know
i feel very grateful to sangha during
this time
just to remind me
just to remind me oh you're not alone
or just you have your you know we have
your back
or yeah i've been going through what
you're going through
or just to talk about sangha
to talk what do you think of this
teaching
and suddenly you know we're seeing each
other like ah i see it i said and it's
so great to celebrate to celebrate
so this relational aspect of the hateful
path
this fourth novel truth
that there is a path where that we can
cultivate to be free to
to be at peace
a wise view
the understanding that you know our
actions have consequences our actions of
body speech and mind
and the perspective
of these four insights practices
just seeing how it is that we relate to
our lives in different aspects
remembering the wise intention
wise intention of cultivating
kindness and compassion
and letting go
letting go into more freedom
letting go into
wow
this is not to my service
i okay i see it now
and just
okay thank you
and shifting it's like suddenly we just
don't realize that we have let go of
many things
they're not here anymore many many times
happen it's like
they're not here anymore i'm like how
did this happen
and in some ways it may not be at that
point very important to see
when did it happen how did it happen
but there are some things that are very
evident
and is
how it is that we have cultivating this
path who has been on the path
what has been the steady
steady aspects of the path
and one of those
aspects is you
is the sangha
is your intention is your humanity
no matter you know if we see each other
zoom in person once in a while
but just to have that recognition that
we are here that we are connected
that is enough
so
and then we have this relational aspects
with people that are not
directly practicing
you know within the tradition but
but my gosh
in some ways they're practicing with us
and we're practicing with them
why speech
wise action
how it is that we create again this
safety
how it is that we engage in the precepts
and how that changes
as we go deeper in the practice we can
we find we find our way in how what it
means to us
and how it is that it offers it offers
safety and connection and support for
continuing on the path to everyone
and now during these times you know this
aspect of wise livelihood comes more
into play for many people
because we are engaging
so many things have changed and we're
engaging back in so many ways and in
different aspects of our lives how it is
that we appreciate or
value you know different ways
of how we use resources how we
live our lives
and this effort
the effort of dedicating touching base
coming into contact with the practice
coming into contact with what is
important to us
and so how it is that wise mindfulness
includes all these factors all these
aspects of the hateful path
how it is that when we remember oh
there's a body here
it may be a moment oh this is how yeah
this is how we are
this is this is where we're living right
here right now
and mindfulness a feeling tone how it is
that feeling tone can be an entry door
to see how it is that
we relate to what is pleasant and what
is unpleasant
to see how what is pleasant my condition
qualities in the mind that may be
not
beneficial or beneficial
for us
and just you know getting to know our
minds
these sometimes i call it you know this
mind this collective mind
because we are in relation and there is
a you know there's another flavor and
tone to it
mindfulness
and so sangha community
you know for me
in
remembering
remembering sangha or
remembering to be a word to be mindful
when
sangha arises
i can see that it has had
such an impact in how this body and mind
has been able to find some
some some moments of peace some moments
of calm and clarity and discernment
from
the moment in which i started practicing
to now wow
is
a whole different thing
just
being able to sometimes see myself fully
and see you fully
and been here
being here for the benefit of
oneself for others and everyone
so i just want to plant the seed for you
to reflect on what what is sangha for
you community
how it is that we cultivate it how it is
that we um
cultivate sangha in a way that support
us supports the world
and how it is that you know there is
also this
it's almost like a mirror too
that there is an inner sangha that
connects with these external sangha
all the beautiful qualities
of this body-mind heart that we manifest
we manifest through our actions of body
space and mind
so
may you continue you know appreciate it
may you appreciate your dedication and
intention to the practice
and may you know that
we're
all connected in one way or another and
remember
remember that yeah that is okay it's
okay to reach out it's okay to
just remember that aspect of the
teachings and that it could be
manifested in different ways in
different moments in our lives however
supports you trust your practice
trust how you're engaging in it
and see how it unfolds
who comes along
in the path with you
so thank you everyone mucha gracias
and
may the benefits of the practice
the fruits of the practice benefit you
and everyone you come in contact with
everyone
without reception
maybe
take good care
thank you