so hello everyone and special welcome to your bodies
the theme of the week is is uh the different
perspectives by which we can be in our bodies experience our bodies
and how this perspective can change radically depending on the state of the mind
and uh the fact that our body experience the body can be so radically different
uh depending on the mind suggests that um
our experience of it is not stable but any particular experience of
the body we have is um is
conditional is contingent is the coming together of various factors
including the state of the mind meditation qualities of our mind
and that our relationship to this changing shifting
amorphous experience of the body uh can be one of peace
a kind of a radical piece to peaceful about the body not troubled by it
and there is a teaching about the body that
has brought a tremendous level of peace to some people and maybe
it's uh brings that peace when the mind is already quite tranquil and peaceful
so it might require a certain state of mind to hear this teaching so that
it really penetrates or releases something and that's the teaching
that this body is not yours that your hair is not your your face is
not you your body shape is not you your teeth are not
you can go on on the list and um
and in some ways it flies against the convention we have of identifying
with our bodies and that's and it's certainly true to some degree these are part of who we are
but when we mind is quite peaceful we see that the activity of claiming
this body to be me the activity of identifying with the body is this is who i am
is um unnecessary in fact to do so
uh is agitating and to realize this body is not me to
cease to give up to the incest identifications assess and kind of
defining oneself by one body it can be very freeing
so that's a little bit the background for today's meditation
and uh so to begin
and with this body that
you are the caretaker of this body that you've received from all
the elements that from this earth
that have combined to build up this body we are made of parts of the earth and will return to
the earth when we die so this body that we care for
assuming a comfortable alert meditation posture
feeling the weight of the body the substance of the body
feeling how the weight of the body settles on what supports it the chair
your cushion the floor wherever you are
feel how this your weight is received by some
object that's holding you up
lower the gaze of your eyes to 45 degrees down
into
and then gently closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
where our volition our decision to breathe deeply
is directed to the body through inviting the body
to take some deep breaths
and to relax on the exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale relax and release whatever holding that
can be released whatever tension you have is not you you
are not your attention because if you were when your attention
releases where are you
relaxing the face the shoulders the belly the arms the hands
wherever you can relax and as you relax
see if you can the same place that you relax if you can feel like you're relaxing into
peace or tranquility
feeling the in-breath the out breath feeling the bodies
expand and contract as you breathe
in his sense you are not your inhale because if you were then you wouldn't
exist on the exhale you are not the exhale
but the inhale and exhale is where you can relax and focus
ground yourself in the changing nature of the present
moment
as you exhale see if there can be a letting go of the
thinking mind letting go of thinking a calming of the thinking mind
the settling of the mind
it is a gift to the body
to leave it alone not always but
sometimes in meditation just to leave it alone without judgments
without claiming it
as mine and for me
without being at war with it opposed to it
wanting to fix it and change it just leaving the body alone
to have its own experience
and it's to give the body this freedom from our attachments
freedom from our projections and entanglements
that's possible to do in meditation
especially if we can have insight understanding
that this body changing shifting
body is not you
you are not your body
you are not your face
you are not your eyes
you are not your hair
you are not your feet
you are not your legs
you are not your torso
you are not your arms and hands
and as it's not you
to let go of defining yourself by your body
freeze the mind of the body and freeze the body of the
mind
letting go of all identification with the body
so the body can have its own experience
and you not defined by the body
so
one of the things we can learn from meditation
is to give time and space and
to the body to settle to open
to heal we can offer our patients
we can offer our non-identification non-reactivity
learning that meditation is a training for doing that in our life
with other people to give others the gift of
space and time our patience our non-identification
non-reactivity
to make room for others by speaking a little less
being more attentive
being quieter stiller just so we can take in and feel and
sense others in a deeper way and maybe the gift to them is that they
can relax and feel comfortable feel safe
feel heard and feel respected
may it be that will be learned from meditation in many in some way or other in many
ways we can think and reflect how it could
support us in our interpersonal lives
how the benefits of meditation can be shared with others out into the world
rippling out from us wide and far
may our meditation practice of our seven aim community
spread from each of us into the world to
support the happiness of others support others to feel safe
support others to be peaceful support others to be free
may we live for the welfare and happiness of everyone including ourselves
[Music]
so so far we've done we've talked about the karmic body the
joy body the tranquil body tranquil body
and today i want to talk about the insight body and that is the way that their body
is experienced uh under the gaze of mindfulness and
when there's when we start having deep insight when the real ability to be quite very quiet in the mind
very little mental projections discussions going on in the mind so we
can settle back and just observe the body in a deep way to observe the body
unencumbered by our ideas of the body unencumbered by
our preoccupations our fears our judgments of the body
to kind of clear the clear the sight the inner sight the mind's eye
to perceive and sense the body in a
in and of itself and and so it's a it's a careful
sensitivity to the changing fluid quality of the body's experience of
itself our senses the nerve endings that pick up all the different sensations that we
feel in our body are operating kind of all the time
but certain things come into prominence and then are there for a while and then
fade and something else comes into prominence and then fades and and there's a constant shifting of what we
of what comes into experience in our body on top of that the body shifts and
changes uh we uh in the course of a single meditation practice maybe the body is gotten
relaxed maybe occasionally it's gotten more tense it shifted changed changed
maybe over a course of a year or two your body's gotten older and
and certain things have shifted to changes about how you are and you can feel the changes and goes on
part of the inside body is to have a quiet mind
a relatively quiet mind focused mind settled here in the present moment that's observing the changing
nature of the body and and at some point we realize as word sit
down and relax that in fact all the exp the so-called experiences we have the
body all the ways in which we can know and feel the body directly is constantly shifting and changing
it's a kaleidoscope it's a it's a process it's a constant flow it's a stream of
sensations stream of experience that's shifting and changing and moving
and when this first happens in meditation it usually comes when the mind the body
meditation is somewhat concentrated often happening happening in the wake of something like the joy
body there can be a lot of joy and subtleness maybe even some peace
that comes first and that allows the mind the thinking mind to quiet more and more
and the advantage of that is the thinking mind then is not projecting its ideas onto the body
the mind has a lot of ideas some of them which are not so accurate
ideas of permanence like this is always going to be this way you know that
i'll always be this way and and the body won't be unchanging and then the body changes
sometimes suddenly in an accident or something an injury sometimes it's slow and gradual
and um i've known i've been blessed with being able to sit cross-legged into my old age
but i have wonderful colleagues deep meditators wonderful meditation teachers
who started this way when they were young sitting cross-legged and now they sit in chairs
and um it's fine to sit in the chair but it's just an example of the body changes and
so we're kind of there to feel and sense and and adapt
ourselves to the changes but the changing the changing stream of
experience when it's an insight body is not the changes that we see over
extended period of time but rather it's kind of like looking at a river and seeing that the surface of the river the
current is constantly shifting and changing and flowing and so at some point this body of ours
without the projection of thoughts and ideas that we overlay on it begins to reveal itself
in kind of its native capacity native expression
which is all this changing fluid moving field of sensations that the nerve
endings take in and process and with each nerve ending
taking in a particular data point and then we feel the individual data
points coming and going as a sound there's a itch there's a feeling of warmth there's a tightness
and and then we feel into these deeper and deeper and we find that within each one
there's something that's constantly in flux and moving a fascinating place for some people who
do vipassana practice is to do this with pain i've done it with a variety of pains but
with knee pain is most classic for me and to bring my attention very carefully
that non-reactive attention the attention is not afraid or angry reactive to the pain
there's not projecting ideas that oh i'm going to hurt forever or i can't do this or this is terrible i'm probably
going to have to have my leg amputated all these kind of or self-pity was one
that i used to have when i was younger oh poor me that's in pain but to somehow have the mind that kind
of uh projection or or veil between us and the pain be put
aside and just experience the pain in and of itself and find out exactly where it is in the
knee it's fascinating as we get closer to it maybe it's a little square centimeter it
may be it's not always in the same place it's moving around it's pulsing and
sparking and shifting and dancing around and we get closer and closer we see
that's not the solid pain that we might have thought it was from the distance when we were reactive to it
concerned about it it's not a solid unchanging pain in fact
maybe we shouldn't even call it pain because pain is kind of an abstraction
uh an abstract kind of umbrella term because underneath that label there is uh uh
uh pulling and stabbing and burning and
uh and uh and uh you know pressure and tightness and all
these kinds of more particular sensations that are intense the intensity because of the intensity
of it we call it pain but pain is made up of many different kinds of sensations
not every pain but the different kind of pains we have are made up of different sensations that are intense
and so to bring our attention just to that particular sensation and see the dance of it the spark of it and the
movement of it and see that it's not so solid sometimes it's a lot easier to be
present for but it was very difficult to be present for something that we're kind of apart from
and we see it though the pain much easier to feel it in a deeper level
underneath that idea and the pulsing searing burning sparking stabbing
intense you know feelings but it sounds terrible these words but it sometimes it's a lot easier
than just relating to it as the pain even more difficult is when we relate to
the pain as my pain i'm having pain when we add the baggage
the association of me myself and mine to the pain we're adding another
layer of obstruction which is accurate enough but it's not really needed and it does
involve a different order of the mind mental activity which keeps us removed keeps us reactive keeps us
actually increases the level of pain sometimes and you might experiment with feeling
the shifting changing pulsing nature of pain and see the difference between
viewing it as my pain or viewing this thought pain
but it's not just pain that we see the shifting stuff it's just that's an interesting exercise to do it in
but uh even pleasure you could feel a pleasure as a meditative pleasure if you really tune
into what it's like it's a stream it's a flow it's a glow it's a shifting and changing phenomenon
the inside body is when we experience the body but it's all everything is flowing
some people would describe the body as being like um um
sand you know sand you know sand or or rain or snow kind of flowing down all these little
particulates kind of flow of particulate sensations that was flowing and moving
and and and so and when it gets really deep this
kind of inside body there is the boundaries of the body the shape of
the body has no meaning anymore it just uh it's oftentimes the body feels kind
of boundary-less or just it's irrelevant the sense of boundaries of the body and
the shape of the body the all kinds of the ideas of body fall away
uh just settling into the raw data of the senses that senses provide that
are constantly shifting and moving in that raw data that's where
the in this insight body that's where there's a particular unique
flavor to the insight into not-self where we see that in this
the whole body experience is just a flow of these sensations
any one sensation be clear that's not myself that you know if that was the case
when that sensation disappears i would disappear too in a sense but you realize that's not the self
that's not the self and this freeing up of the movement of the mind to this is me this is myself this is mine
is very freeing for the mind very relaxing and peacemaking and
and so to begin recognizing the not-self of this whole field
of the body sensations as it flows is part of the insight body
and part of that inside body also is is then to realize that any clinging to
it is uh is pointless or is painful it's not really necessary
and that's kind of like if you have a put your hand it's the waterfall of water coming down
and you put your hand in the waterfall to grab some water you might get a little bit on your hand but you're done but
but it all gets squeezed out and and um and you can't really grab a whole bunch of you know handful of water
and so you realize this movement of grabbing doesn't work and so this inside body
is um when we're seeing this radical nature of change is a powerful
way of learning not to identify with our experience and beginning to have an experience of life
without the filter or the burden of identification and it's a powerful lesson in the
possibility of non-clinging that the the things we cling to are unreliable
unsatisfactory that it just brings more suffering to cling and to see that for oneself when we're
sitting in the inside body then it's it's uh
obvious it's not a logic it's not rational it's i mean it's not because you've reasoned it out
and not because you read it in a book it's just it's so clear and obvious this is how it is
and and that's the direction that insight meditation is going
someday you know really beginning to taste or feel this insight body
that is again a very different way of experiencing the body than the karmic
body which tends to be the one that solidifies and uh it carries the burden of all these
uh projections and reactions and identifications that we have
so the insight body
so i hope this comes you come to appreciate
and value and care respectfully for these bodies that we
have and by not identifying with being mine
it is also your [Music] your part of this universe
for you to care for care for your body care for yourself thank you