so hello everyone and welcome
and we live in a body human body that has capacity
for pleasure and pain we live in human body has
the ability the potential for beauty and that which is not beauty
for inner beauty we have a world that lives in
has a capacity for suffering and happiness for war and peace
as we're seeing now in
in eastern europe so one of the ways of practicing
mindfulness is to um
be aware of it all have a certain equanimity for pleasure and pain
the beautiful and not so beautiful the difficult and the easy
but to do it from a reference point to do it from a source kind of within
of a kind of a of awareness that is based in or settled
in the place where we have inner beauty or where we have
um yeah so qualify for that for now and it's possible to be aware of
things for example physical pain but to be aware of it at the same time
as being in touch with or being connected to inner pleasure inner beauty in her
well-being and this makes a world of difference
so we're not only identified only rooted in
this sensory sense world where pleasure and pain exists
but we're rooted someplace else that contextualizes the sense world
so i'll do a kind of guided meditation around this and we'll see how
that goes and
and i will hopefully point you first to when you're aware of breathing
there can be more than breathing going on there's also the awareness of breathing and how that is
and that'll be the entry point to this uh teaching on
inner pleasure inner beauty so
to assume a meditation
posture and to
gently close your eyes
and some long slow gentle and inhales and exhales
especially as you exhale to relax and settle into your body
breathing in deeply and relaxing
as you exhale
and then letting the breathing return to normal and then for a few rounds of breathing
to continue to relax the holdings the tension in the body
and if it doesn't relax maybe there can be a softening around it
in the face the shoulders the belly
and then to
breathe normally except the end of the exhale
let there be a comfortable pause just long enough not to be uncomfortable
the pause before you inhale just long enough so that you feel the
gentle pull or desire to inhale and when you feel that desire
allow for it and allow the body to
perform the inhale
let there be a small pause at the end of the exhale when you feel the pull to breathe in
allow it and receive the inhale
so it's not just the inhale you're feeling there's also a context for the inhale
which is a sense feeling for allowing receiving
when you when the exhale begins allow it to
the body to exhale allow for the letting go the
release of the exhale
receiving allowing maybe is close to making space for
something being spacious making a room for it
in whatever feeling you have for allowing and receiving
in breath and out breath
is that does it have a pleasant feeling and nice something nice or comforting about it or
and if it is feel the pleasantness the pleasure of
however small it is of allowing the receiving the inhale
allowing the exhale
and maybe you can feel
this sense of allowing receiving
to feel it in that place within
where inner beauty lives inner well-being
a well-being that is not of the senses not of
the five senses but a non-sensual
inner place
a non-sensual kind of pleasantness pleasure beauty
that informs awareness
which is a kind of a source for awareness the flavor of awareness as you breathe
in and breathe out
if any part of the breathing is uncomfortable it's okay
allow it to be received receive it and allow it
from this other place of within
from this place is not identified with the discomfort
but rather where we are settled
in an inner place of that's of pleasure well-being
warmth glow
with which we're aware of the discomfort
if there's something uncomfortable happening that
preoccupies you grabs your attention
see if you can be mindful of it in a receptive and allowing way
so that your or something like that so you're aware
from that non-sensual place non-physical place within
from a place of inner well-being and not rooted or connected
to the outer senses of the body
but rather to a place of the within maybe of the heart
a place within that is the home for inner beauty
if there's any way you feel a little calmer or settled and you did it beginning
that calmness and subtleness would be considered a non-sensual pleasure
or a pleasure of the inner life
let your awareness radiate from
that inner life an inner place of goodness or beauty
so you're rooted there so you're not identified or rooted in
the challenges or the thoughts or feelings
you're aware of all of those respectfully carefully but you're aware of them from
this place of inner
beauty inner wellness inner calm
can you touch into a place of inner pleasure well-being
it is not a pleasure ordinary pleasure of the senses
in a sense it's an inner well-being that's independent of
what we see and hear and taste smell or touch
maybe an inner pleasure connected to
our inner life of feel inner feelings
and if there is a pleasure there
know it be mindful of it
and what happens when you recognize it and feel it know it
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to whatever degree you know now or other times a place of inner well-being
calmness contentment
pleasure that's independent of what's happening
around you
from that place can you look out across the world
aware of all the suffering and happiness of this world
and wish that you can make a difference to
improve this world of ours to contribute to the welfare and
happiness of others a contribution that wish that begins
with the good will of wanting others the best for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so hello everyone and so the topic this week is the second
foundation of mindfulness which is the mindfulness of vedana
pali word for that i translate as feeling tone often translated as feeling
but then people confuse it sometimes with emotions and what it refers to is the
the tonality the tone of pleasant unpleasant or neither pleasant unpleasant
in which everything happens all experiences are felt through those three feeling tones one or
one of the three maybe occasionally it feels like
they're all there at the same time the um
so this is the the instructions are to be mindful of when there's pleasant
feeling tone that it's pleasant feeling toned when it's painful unpleasant and no it's it's unpleasant
when it's neither pleasant or unpleasant no so it's a clear recognition this is how it is
but then the the text that buddha goes makes a very interesting distinction he goes a little bit further
and this is the uh i see it as a really important pivot in the sativatana suttan the teachings
and a very important pivot in people's mindfulness practice
because then the buddha makes a distinction between
um and they're between the feeling tones
that are uh physical in nature and those which have uh are not
maybe we could call it if you're willing to go along the spiritual in nature or of the heart in nature
but the reason why some people call it worldly and not worldly feelings
some people call it worldly and spiritual feelings different people translate these words differently
the pali word literally means of the flesh
and not of the flesh and that doesn't inspire people that much
and uh so people are finding other ways to sort of say it and how i understand it is that
of the flesh has to do with the of the ordinary senses we have
seeing hearing taste tasting smelling and touching the tactile senses of the
body so if if i feel uh
the coolness against my skin maybe i'm outside and today it was somewhat cold outside and it was cold
and on one hand the cold maybe it was unpleasant but it was invigorating and it kind of
inspiring to be out there and a nice kind of feeling arose of kind of delight and feeling the sharp crispness of the
air and the coolness against my arms and and uh and have a lot of us wonderful
associations and memories of being in the cold and um so there was kind of an inner
smile that happened i just felt delighted to be in the cold little bit even though literally there was a kind of
unpleasantness in the in the skin for that so there's these two different dimensions of our domains of our life
that which is of the physical i call it physical senses and that which is of the inner senses
and many people live in their in their physical senses
and that's a beaut wonderful thing to do it's a physical senses the sensations being in our body is one of the great pleasures of mindfulness
but it's possible to overdo it either by being to identify it with a physical body to attach to it
too reactive to it and but we are in mindfulness learning
to kind of be mindful of it and live in it and the whole first foundation of mindfulness is
learning how to be embodied in this physical body in a a valuable way
and um and so being mindful of the um the feelings of the flesh
feelings of this physical senses one would know that the instructions are
when there is a physical feeling of pleasure physical feeling of
of um unpleasant to physical of neither pleasant or unpleasant no that's the
case there's no value judgment put on it if that's what's predominant then that's
what we pay attention to but then the buddha says also there's another category of feeling
this knot of the flesh which is
i associated with the inner life the quality of our inner being
um the quality of our inner state can be they're independent of what's
happening in the world around us the physical body is very much impacted by
what happens in the world around us cold and hot and you know all kinds of things are
happening and also the physical body is impacted by illness and injury and all
these things that can happen to the flesh itself through the physical body but then there's a there's this
non-physical kind of i mean exactly how to describe this is uh each of you
will probably have a different description that works for you but it's the it's the distinction
that there's a there's a divide here a separation or a distinction between these two
different domains and areas and um and one the second one not of the flesh
belongs more to the the spiritual the mental the psychological the
um the heartful the the um the kind of feeling of the inner life that's there
independent of what happens around us so we can feel contented a very content and peaceful
even though the bus we're waiting for is an hour late and um
some of our thoughts imaginations of oh this is going to be unpleasant later but we're not trapped in those thoughts
we're actually resting and it's happy to stay on the bus bench
just content being there that inner life is very content some people when they meditate
it can um before they meditate there are things that they can look around they're
reactive to and they think they should be different and they want their body to be different way and then after they meditate there's a
kind of ease or peacefulness or calm that
it kind of holds everything much more easily and spaciously so the place of kind of the calm can be
the peace can be maybe the place where love can be a warm hardness can be
the place where inner beauty can reside that's all belongs to the world not of
the flesh and so the buddha here is saying when there's
a pleasant sensation pleasant experience pleasant feeling
not of the flesh know it as a pleasant feeling when you know there's an unpleasant
feeling not of the flesh know it as an unpleasant feeling not of the flesh
and when it's neither pleasant or unpleasant know it as that
so here this distinction between of the flesh and not of the flesh and now that the whole sati patana is pivoting now
to uh you could say you know simplistically maybe to the mind rather than the body
but it's it's um it's pivoting now to the inner life where
happiness and where suffering in a deeper way resides so that can be met and seen
and not to be only limited to the physical body and the physical experience but to not begin opening up
to a deeper and deeper inner dimension of our life and here all we're asked to do to notice
is that pleasant or unpleasant and as people meditate
it's this inner dimension that starts becoming bigger more alive
more reference point as important being embodied in the physical body is and how wonderful it is
for some people there's this other area that's deeper
and some people have that connection to it and because it's kind of in the body anyway uh within the body
they'll often associate it with their body and think this is being embodied and it definitely can be that
but but we're trying to make a distinction here to go along with the instructions
and as we learn as we settle and get calmer and calmer more concentrated and
more connected to ourselves in meditation it's this inner dimension that begins
growing and which this inner dimension then that provides uh a uh
the material for the last two foundations of the of
mindfulness um that of the mind and that of the kind of the inner processes
that lead to suffering or to happiness so it's a very important foundation to
make or switch to go from the physical body to not becoming heightened sensitivity to this
non-physical inner dimension of feeling that can exist and um
and uh in a way those these they can be a little bit more enduring than the physical ones
the buddha like in physical bad enough physical feelings to um
the rain drops on top of a lake a big rain is pouring down on the on the lake
and there's all these little splatters that go on and physical uh pleasure if you're really or physical sensations if you're
really connected carefully to them you'll see that the pleasure and pain and pleasure is uh almost like
little splatters little sparks that come and go and rise and pass
and this inner dimension this knot of the flesh
has usually a feeling a little more enduring it's primarily good feelings there it's
primarily pleasure there can be not of the flesh ways in which we feel
not so good not pleasant and
but in the teachings of the buddha he begins emphasizing the pleasure that's there
and um and that's the orientation is to in meditation as we get deeper and deeper
is to begin appreciating and and and feeling
the pleasant the inner sensations feelings that are there make room for them
and as i did in the guided meditation it's possible that that becomes the
the orientation or becomes the reference point for mindfulness
awareness practice no matter what we're aware of and so it's not we're not just aware of
pain for example but we're aware that of the
of the of the some kind of pleasure beauty some kind of love some kind of care
some kind of spaciousness equanimity that uh allow that supports that
awareness of pain or su suffering so we're not only learn not to only be
identified with the experience of the moment in terms of pleasure and pain
but we're also starting to identify with this inner place of well-being
of calm the economy or something with which we can know what's happening for us
and um so um
so you might if this made sense for you you might spend the day
um reflecting thinking feeling exploring uh what your relationship is
to this non-physical um place within
um that you know you might you know it might be part of you part of your body but not the nonsense nonsense
based that which is not triggered by the ordinary senses but uh is independent of
um the ordinary senses and the inner place where your beauty resides your inner beauty your inner
love your inner goodness your inner subtleness and calm
inner spaciousness inner joy and your happiness
in your calm so exactly what this is uh for any one
of you is variable but what experiences have you had that touch that you have history some
reference points for this in the course of your life and what have been the strongest reference points for this and
and how do you experience it in daily life and what is a useful way to stay more in
touch with it and closer to it and not lose track of it
and maybe talk to some friends and if you can explain this to them and see what their experiences have been about
this i kind of want to spend a day contemplating the nature of this inner beauty
so thank you and we'll continue with this one more day