so hello everyone yesterday i uh used the analogy of
driving uh and when someone is excited they push the gas more
maybe even unconsciously and when they're maybe distracted or
the energy level drops they really pull back a little bit from the gas pedal and the car drives slower
another driving analogy is for mindfulness
is that uh on the freeway when we drive the idea is to for every 10 mile speed
to have 10 feet between you and the car in front of you so at 50 miles an hour 60 miles an hour you have
50 60 feet between you and uh and then you're safe
so with mindfulness we're putting space between the speed of our lives
and some of us are going fast and the faster we're going perhaps the more space we should have
so we don't crash into things and um and how to make space
with mindfulness is um to view mindfulness as especially as
we're getting the hang of mindfulness and developing it to see it as a kind of a stopping
to stop and take a good look to stop and and instead of just going along with
the train of thought with whatever we're feeling whatever going and the best of your ability to stop to look at it
and recognize what it is and then
if once it's been seen or recognized
then pause and now what this pause means to
um to like register what happens in the wake of recognizing it
what what house is is the thing experienced more fully once it's been recognized once it's been
known as it's being seen work fully
and then this relaxed way to stop recognize
pause and take in the experience what's happening then and then do it again
and um and then we're not uh rushing ahead with whatever thoughts and feelings and
things we're doing and we can live a safer life
and this is particularly maybe useful with today's topic which is restlessness
and agitation anxiety to um
to his sense to whatever it means for you to stop
to recognize the restlessness this hyper energy
that can happen hyper arouse state stop and recognize it's happening not to
make it a problem but stop recognize and then
pause for a while to just take in the experience don't just go along with it
feel it in the body feel it in the mind well this is what it's like and also to see if you can pause long
enough to see what difference the recognition makes
the power of recognition is quite something so stop
recognize pause and feel
so um and as meditation gets quieter and more
calm then this seeing of restlessness seeing of agitation also becomes quieter more
subtle restlessness so taking a meditation posture
and maybe rocking back and forth a little
bit forward and backwards maybe in a way that feels delightful to
begin being in your body in this meditative posture
and then gently closing your eyes
and again perhaps as a with some feeling of satisfaction to be starting your
meditation taking some gentle deep breaths
and as you exhale relax
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and feel your body kind of a global awareness of your body
maybe with your attention roaming around your body and as you
exhale relax in your body
soften in your body
relax into your body as if it's a kind of homecoming
then to gently
center yourself on your breathing
as if the comings and goings of in-breath and out-breath
is something you're pausing
everything else so that you can recognize it know it
relaxing on the exhale
receptive to the inhale
feeling maybe the penny pleasure that's in the experience of breathing
maybe it's a particular point in the cycle of breathing
or maybe it's in a particular part of your body where the rhythm of breathing is
pleasant
relaxing as you exhale and feeling the
pleasure of whatever calm or state there is within
maybe a kind of global experience that's not focusing on anything in
particular a global experience of calm or peace
warmth
as you breathe the middle of all things
as you exhale relaxing the mind
exhaling and appreciate whatever pleasant calm or peace
might be in the mind even if it's only hints
and letting there be a gentle calm recognition
of what's happening in the present it can be recognizing the inhale
the exhale recognizing sensations of the body or
sounds feelings or mind states
thoughts
calmly recognize and let there be a pause after
recognizing to feel and sense what happens
to register
and if there's any way that you're restless or agitated
stop for that recognize it
pause and feel their restlessness but feel it calmly
recognize it calmly so that there's a kind of a meeting
meeting between whatever restlessness there is agitation
and the calmness that you bring to it
with a calm recognition a comp pausing to feel and sense
the experience
whatever way you are your offering
is to calmly know it and if you're agitated it's okay
calmly know recognize
pause feel sense what that experience is like
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to calmly recognize
how you are right now where the act of recognition is calm
you might not be will you take your time to recognize and
to feel and to sense
so you're creating a space
so there's the thinking mind the reactive mind
doesn't just go uninterruptedly
there's pauses like there would be a pause or a gap
with the car in front of you in the freeway
and this ability to stop recognize
and feel the spirit experience know the experience
create space and time for more of our life to emerge and show
itself and it creates more of our life
more more opportunities for us to take in and recognize and know others
either when they're in their presence or when we think about them or
we consider them people we don't know that we learn about maybe even in the news
and to take in this world of suffering and challenge
that humans live in
and to offer that loving pause and recognition
that allows us to see this life of ours more clearly even if just for a moment or two
calmly gazing upon the world
and letting that be an occasion for your care
your kindness your good will
may you create calm so you can see the world kindly
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so we come to the fourth of the five hindrances
and these hindrances are you know when they're strong for us
it's kind of like tailgating the car in front of us on the freeway
and we don't have to
stop the hindrances but we want to end their hindering
quality so for example restlessness
agitation can hinder our ability to see to calmly recognize
to calmly consider what's going on it hinders our ability to be wise and be
clear about what's happening we don't have to stop being
restless but the idea is to not have the restlessness interfere anymore
and one way to do that is to practice mindfulness and today i'm referring to
mindfulness as the practice of stopping in order to recognize what's happening
and perhaps if we don't appreciate the stopping the recognition is done kind of quickly
automatically kind of part and parcel of the usual ways of the mind working and
it's not really stepping out of the stream of restlessness agitation to take a look at it
so something inside stops enough to take a good look
and then or a good recognition oh this is what's happening i'm restless i'm agitated
and but let the recognition become and learning how you can have
agency in one particular area and that is the agency to take the time to recognize
what's happening calmly take your time oh restlessness it can be
like that in your mind restlessness restlessness is happening
the mind might be going at 90 miles an hour but the recognition
is kind of like a person maybe who is driving in the slow lane or probably standing on the side of the road and
look at that speed a car going by fast and so to recognize calmly the act of
recognition is where we take some agency and then in the
in the agency in that recognition then to pause afterwards
to register take in that experience and what that can mean is to register
take in the experience of restlessness in a deeper fuller way and make space for it and really feel it
in that space that's been created by the recognition it could also be take in the impact the
effect that recognition has stopping and recognizing has it might create a little more space a
little more calm it might slow down the restlessness and agitation we might
have restless and agitation is part of life
you know even in deep meditation you can feel sometimes and it doesn't it might be a tremendous amount of calm
but the mind kind of gets a little bit excited i mean sometimes it gets excited about
meditation oh look i'm so calm and you can feel the mind getting a little bit agitated or excited
and and so to recognize and relax and let it settle down again
the two words for restlessness and um you know it's two words so
both words imply this hyper arousal this things are a little bit more excited or
wrestle or activated than than
and so one of them is just called restlessness often or agitation
and the other word is sometimes called worry
sometimes it's called regret and i don't know you know it's hard to
know exactly what the pali word is supposed to mean but the principle that this is hyper
aroused state that can happen it can be worry it can be panic it can be
fear that we it can be um regrets
regrets can keep us churning away turning away um uh you know with a lot of energy
it could be um you know anxiety that keeps us activated
and so to recognize what it is anxiety regrets
just kind of ener physical agitation restlessness mental agitation restlessness
and and to calmly
know it calmly recognize it and get to know what it's like
and the more with all these interests the more we learn to be familiar with them
and really know what they are physically emotionally mentally
behaviorally then the more we're able to see it coming
we can recognize oh i'm beginning to go in that direction and when we can
if we can catch something as it begins there's often a little bit more ability
to back off or to pause more or let go of it
so but but in order to do that it takes a lot of familiarity so with restlessness anxiety
remorse agitation
look forward to the day when in meditation you can have a nice belt of it
rather than viewing it as unfortunate then a drag and you have to get figure out some way not to be agitated and this
is proof that you're you know you should never be meditating
take it as an opportunity to study it and get to know it i've had fascinating meditations where i
was a restless and it felt like ping-pong balls kind of bouncing inside my body
and i was just kind of amazed to watch this energy and like where did this come from
and and just sit there quietly and feel the ping-pong balls bouncing off the sides of my body from the inside kind of
feeling feeling the surging energy in their arms
and the legs and or the mind that doesn't seem to want to stop chattering
to be amazed wow as opposed to being
horrified or upset and then take the time to the okay this is the time i was been looking for
a time for me to really take in the experience of restlessness
agitation let me just kind of sit in the middle of it and like sitting in the middle of the
fire sit in the middle of it and just real this is my chance to feel it get to know it become familiar with it let me see if
i can understand to see something new about it something i've never known before
is it in my little finger is it my toes no where is it do you feel any of it in
your along your back um well maybe and maybe not where do you
feel it where is it where it's what's activated um and what are your beliefs around it
what are your second arrows that you have about restlessness agitation having regrets
having um anxiety and um
and maybe it's a second arrows maybe it's the reactivity we have with them which is a fuel for the agitation for
the fear the anxiety whatever it might be and so this thing about
assuming agency assuming that we have some ability
to meet a situation we're in we can't necessarily change it or control it but we have some agency over
our ability to show up for it and and so
to stop okay i'm agitated okay i'm going to stop for my agitation as opposed to kind of
keep doing everything or something i'm going to stop my agitation and if you do that and stop maybe even
close your eyes maybe you find your shoulders relax a little bit and that's the beginning of some
different way of being with it and then the agency of calmly
recognizing so you know if you if you use if you
want to recognize verbally in your mind sometimes that's very helpful and just say to yourself in a calm way
oh this is restlessness
so that you're decoupling the
the mind that does the thinking from the restlessness itself
the mind might be mostly restless but out of you know it's like if you
talk to someone who you know if you talk to someone in the library
you might feel agitated but because it's the library you talk quietly
and so you talk quietly in your mind oh this is restlessness
and then you pause or you take time maybe a luxurious time to feel and know
that experience and in this way we're getting wise about
restlessness anxiety remorse regrets agitation
the whole family of things what happens when we get hyper aroused and
we're finding a different way to be with it
and uh begin to appreciate when you're familiar with agitation
once you're familiar with your agitation also take the time to become equally familiar with the time when you are not
agitated when you feel you feel calm or peaceful or settled
do the same thing there stop recognize pause and really feel it and
here we're being able to recognize calm states or peaceful states
we can also see them coming we can see hints of them and allow them to blossom
because we recognize them and make space for them and also
it makes more room for them to appear to be there and we can somehow let that be a richer part of our
life so restlessness
anxiety i hope that you don't have much
i hope the practice supports you and not having being caught in it but i also do hope that you look for an
opportunity to get to know it better and have a different relationship with it and
practice your agency of being a calm recognition and so maybe today i'm sure that there
will be some occasion for something in the family of agitation restlessness
excitement to occur and and
take a good look at it