give up from quiet cloudy san francisco morning
it has occurred to me over the years of practicing meditation
that we can never remind ourselves too often of just how
the process of mindfulness works
phil did you get those messages that the video is not working
it's enabled now okay okay
so the process of how mindfulness engages our human consciousness
we can't remind ourselves too often just how that is
the the usual way of being it's me
in my world it's so um persistent
that and it's just as an assumption we make
and mindfulness is to bring attention to me
and my world but not to
change it into what it should be that the outrageous proposition of
mindfulness is that just how it is it is the ground of awareness
is is the content of awareness you know there is within us
i think through our deep dedication to practice
a strong impulse to curate it to manage it
to influence it in a way that's more
appropriate of course more appropriate is according
to me whatever our being constructs as appropriate
there's a teaching that persists in many schools of buddhism that say the
awakened are awakened to the workings of karmic mind
so this is our teacher the very karmic conditioning
that constructs me and my world and interacts with it
and approves and disapproves and has the full range of feelings and memories and
associations around it this is
this is what's being offered in the practice of awareness
so with that in mind to simply notice
now liz mind this morning or this afternoon wherever time zone
how is mine now
and as you open in that way can you can you
can you notice a shift from
me constructing something to experiencing me
the shift from the mind that has an agenda
to awareness of that mind
and sometimes we initiate that will be
just by attending to the content
noting acknowledging
and as we do that to notice
is there any impulse to curate
to nudge it over to how it should be
i'd suggest you this morning to let it be the wild and beautiful thing that it is
how amazing that in this moment we are the product of a lifetime
actually through the product of a stream of lifetimes
we're a product of our environment
of the experiences that have shaped us
here is crystallized into me
what is me right now
what's happening in mind what's happening in the realm of
emotions
and can it be drawn into body can it be embodied
can it be noticed as it reverberates through physical beings
and as it happens this mind
conjuring up whatever it conjures up
can we allow it can we breathe it in
can we allow it to be just what it is
and can we notice the disposition of allowance
allowing what is to be experienced
experiencing the experience
me being me
expressing being moment by moment
embodying the experience that's happening
breathing it in and releasing it with the exhale
can mind be allowed to be exactly what it is
can then be held in awareness
embodying in here and now whatever
appears in consciousness
[Music]
um
if i may ask could you hear the reverberation of the bell this morning
no ah someone sent me a message telling me how
to alter the sound but
apparently i didn't register it correctly
i'll try again tomorrow
this radical proposition that's implicit in
the awakened are awakened by karmic consciousness
there's a formulation in buddhism about the nature of consciousness
it has three categories the first one is
discriminative mind the mind that thinks and judges and
concludes and then the second one is
literally the sanskrit word is which means heart
it's like the emotional the feeling the way in which water rises
has we as the phrase i've been using we take it personally you know it becomes
an involvement in me and the world according to me
and then the third my consciousness is
the realm of experience
what is the realm of experiencing well
it's the functioning of chitta and the functioning of pradaya the
functioning of discriminating mind and the functioning
of feeling mind psychological mind however you want to
describe it
and so the very practice of mindfulness is simply
attending to the thinking and the feeling
and coming into contact with the experiential
level of being in the early sutras it says
that this experiential is where the learning
of what is happens that each of us
is a miraculous expression of being
and it's offered to us as a way as a context
to be aware of you know i've been quoting that
statement by martin luther king the challenging experiences
can be instructive educational was the word he used
and they can also be transformative
as we live in this world according to me
and me according to me as we live within its confines
there's a construct of being there's a construct of what is there's
even a construct of what's happening in the moment and the more we invite
the experiencing the more that's illuminated
the more it becomes evident me being me becomes more evident and as it
does it becomes educational
and it invites a a greater be a being beyond just
the be the world according to me maybe to put it a little poetically we
could say it's a shift from the world according to me to me according to the world
and the interface is what's being experienced moment by moment
and this is the great intrigue and challenge of mindfulness
yesterday i offered this illustration of myself in a meeting you know
in watching that impulse the
subtle reactiveness or maybe not so subtle reactiveness
when something when i heard that something was had been
arranged in a way that was disappointing to me
well let's cancel it
it's me and my world would like things to fit more within my
agendas my preferences and then as we see that
we see it and in a way we see through it
oh that's me in my world trying to
corral this vast endless existence
into the way i would like it to be
not to condemn ourselves for such thoughts and feelings
but more to be instructed by the awakened
awakened to karmic consciousness
and can we hold that with benevolence
okay can we let there be within our being in
evolution oh yes
indeed i do have preferences i do have ways of seeing things
and yes they are self-centered however
i can still invite into my way of being
an ever-growing re-calibration
of what it is to be
a burdensome for others if i just go around trying to insist
the world should always be the way i want it
and how human it is that when it's not the way i want it
it disturbs me and that's how it is for everyone
but it's not the way we want it it's disturbing it's challenging
it's upsetting why not
and when we see it it's like we're inviting
a deep sanity into being and a deep compassion
indeed isn't this the way we're made
isn't this how our neurology works how our psychology works
how our somatic being works
isn't this complex organism of being a human subject to these
impulses and can we sit and practice awareness
with a willingness and an attentiveness of being
this this interplay
of all being through
this particular being that i am
as we enter the world can we appreciate and allow
that everybody else is having their version of it too
can we dance together you know can we collaborate can we collude
can we support each other can we offer our patience
and our empathy to others
can we offer them to ourselves
as we experience the moment's version
of this interplay being
can we open to its teaching
and its teaching will be the world according to me
and the me according to me and the preferences and the versions
that are em embedded in both of those
that's the ground of awakening
or whether someone praises us or insults us or delights us or frustrates us
that's the grind of
and then for each of us to discover
how to stay close to that sensibility
how to keep referencing it
and to remind ourselves that complex and amazing as the human
condition is in another way it's fragile
it's asking for a reassurance
it's asking for a wise compassion
so as we open up to the workings of yourself
it's very very helpful if we bring that compassion
that skillfulness and that wisdom and part of the heritage of our practice
our buddhist practices at embodying helps to create stability
there's a teaching that says that when we meditate that would be practice
mindfulness it it offers us a kind of protection
from the excesses that we're capable of it offers us a kind of support
so we offer a kind of benevolence to ourselves
we offer ourselves a support
a reassurance a trust
and it's not that we offer these things just in the level of
thinking although we that's a very helpful way to engage them
but if we can embody it as well
if the core of our being
can find a reassurance and often that's
how the body is contracting in the breath how they're contracting
or expanding
and then there's a way we can do something similar with our attitude and disposition
okay this is how it is
can that statement can it have
a tenderness to it
but when it's pleasant can we soak up appreciation
and when it's unpleasant can we watch
how that ripples through us can we have compassion
in the ways we contract
we have an empathy for others in the ways they contract
so each day this is
for some reason the word that comes to mind is the prayer of our practice
this is the aspiration of
what we carry out into the world to discover
the new day this way of being that's invited to go beyond
me and mine in my world
may this day bring you lots of moments
of awakening thank you