so hello everyone my warm greetings and
my best wishes for all of you for your meditation i hope that
you find your meditation to be settling for you beneficial for you
and that it's inspiring for you to be meditating with uh in community many other people
meditating at the same time today and
there are many ways to benefit from meditation for mindfulness meditation one of the
ways does not require anything to be any different it doesn't require us to come somehow
become more settled or calm doesn't require us to dispel certain states of mind or ways of
being which are unpleasant to have difficult to have
but one way is to begin appreciating the simple act of knowing
that it can be so simple innocent and so such a common
part of everyday life to know there's a door when we see a door and a door handle and opening
the door and we know all these things you know myriad things all the time
that but we seldom find the full fruition or full value of
a of a clear moment of knowing where knowing something anything at all
is a miracle it's an amazing thing that the mind can do that somehow out of the cosmic soup
there evolved living beings that could have concepts ideas
perceptions that can uh then perceptions can be had and
moments of cognition can be experienced where we know oh that is a door
that's an itch that's an inhale that's an exhale and now it's and as i describe this it
might not still seem such a wonderful thing but as knowing
begins to become simplified or purified and the knowing stands out by itself as
its own clarity its own kind of where the knowing is independent of what is known
so if someone has uh something that i want and i'm caught up in wanting and i know
what the object is maybe they have ice cream or something and i want the ice cream and
and so i've recognized this ice cream but the wanting kind of is all over the place my mind is swirling with thoughts
about how i can manage to get it but
and our knowing is often interspersed with or connected with our desires our aversions our confusions all kinds of
things our commentary our history our memory but when knowing it becomes simple
really really simple there's no baggage with it it begins to feel special
there's a kind of peace in it there's a kind of ease in it there's a kind of
freedom to be found in the knowing and this is one of the
kind of inner dimensions of this mindfulness practice that
once we once we can appreciate this the practice opens up in a very different way and so rather than needing to change
anything change ourselves it's uh
appreciating more and more knowing what's happening
and so the cliche or the little saying is that the inside practice is less about
having new experiences as it is about seeing in a new way
so this knowing so i'll do a little exercise
about this kind of knowing maybe help you kind of appreciate how simple and
clear and it can be and then and of course the meditation will apply that to the mind
so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing the eyes
and taking a few moments to settle in
quietly whatever way you like taking in some deep breaths
relaxing whatever way that you want to do it
and then a little exercise in knowing find a sensation in your body
that is pretty neutral it could be sensations of your hand if that's neutral or
maybe there's some contact of your foot to grants against your mat your floor
something that's relatively maybe the temperature of your body
something that's not particularly pleasant particularly unpleasant something where you can kind of
not have too much of a reaction to
and then let yourself become aware of this sensation
notice if there's any attitude of being either for or against it or
questioning and wondering what this exercise is about
resisting it or a little bit irritated to do an exercise
or eager to explore it and figure out what's going on here
and see if you can let go of all that maybe in an exhale
relax all the ideas and attitudes about
and instead see if you can know the sensation
recognize it in the simplest direct way
you don't have to know exactly what it is just approximant is fine
and let there be a clear see if you can find a way to clearly recognize
it could be within with the verbal thoughts in your mind it
could be a brightening of the inner eye
a clear recognition of the sensation where the recognition is its own event
the word door is not the door
it represents the door so for your sensation that you're having
the recognition is not the sensation but it's an amazing
event in the mind that the mind would know recognize
and see if you can recognize or see or understand
that the act of recognition is distinct
from the sensation of course they're related
but the sensation does not need to have the recognition to exist
so stay with the sensation maybe breathe with it if it's there or find another
one and see if the knowing
the seeing of it can be very very simple
it may be a kind of brightness to it clarity
this is what's happening a clarity that doesn't have to have a
before and after ideas of what's going to happen or why
it's happening just the event itself
in this moment
and now calmly become aware of how your mind is
what's your mind state your mood and the mind
what's your inner life like
and in the radical simplicity
recognize in some way what's happening now
for your mind how it is
and recognize it with a kind of independence and clarity
in which you did the sensation
attempt to step back to be free enough that the knowing is
not entangled with the mind state it just knows
in a spectrum from contracted to expansive mind
how is your mind more contracted or more expensive or
right in the middle or not clear none of the above
recognizing how it is
maybe recognizing the miracle of
knowing anything
and when you know your mind state this way with this kind of clear knowing
relaxed and open allowing
what happens through the mind state does anything shift
if it does then know the shift
and then we'll continue in silence
but as you would go along maybe centering yourself on the breathing
from time to time know the state of your mind
and see if you can know it with this simple clear way of knowing
where the knowing itself is not for or against not trying to do anything or understand
anything complicated the knowing is just a recognition
the miracle of recognition
knowing the mind as it is taking refuge in the simplicity of
knowing knowing is a kind of protection
when it protects us from fixing and predicting
wanting and not wanting
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
it can be a gift to others to know them and see them clearly
without any baggage on our parts without any judgments
without any preferences see and know them for who they are as if
they're allowed to be that wave just see
sometimes it allows others to see themselves better
sometimes it frees people very few people have had a have been
seen without the seeing wanting something
turning the attention outwards to the world with the gift of seeing
maybe thinking some about some of the people in your life just let them be there
see them
i'd like to believe that the clarity of our seeing and knowing
is a best channel for our goodwill for our love our care generosity
may our knowing of others be the conduit for our love
our well-wishing may all beings
be happy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings
be safe and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
so the eighth the third foundation
of mindfulness has eight exercises or eight
practices that and they're divided into two halves two
groups of four each of them the verb the activity just to know the
simplicity of knowing these mind states or these ways the minds can be
and the first half has a little bit more to do with the minds that
is either somehow caught in the world of suffering or is not so much it's the unwholesome
mind or in a wholesome mind
in the second so there's a four like that and the last four
have to do with more minds and meditation the mind when it starts becoming free
and matures in the dharma and grows and develops
and that'll be the topic for the next two days tomorrow and friday but for now
so that it begins the first four or knowing a mind that has desire has greed
that's with greed as a mind with greed mind without greed to know it as being
without greed or without desire to know a mind of ill will or aversion
as such and to know a mind without aversion as a mind without aversion
it's now a mind that is with delusion or confusion as such
and to know a mind that without a confusion or delusion as a mind without
confusion delusion those are the first three
the fourth one most translators will understand it to be to know something like to know a
contracted mind as a contracted mind and a scattered mind as a scattered mind
to know a song a shrunken mind a shriveled mind as a
chunk as a shriveled mind and a in a scattered mind as a scattered mind
and sometimes this is associated with the third and fourth of the hindrances
to know a mind that's kind of sinking into sloth and torpor into dullness
as such and to know a mind which is um
kind of scattered and rest from restlessness and anxiety
and it makes some sense because um you know that that's what it means the
other possibility is that it's uh knowing a not a contracted mind but a collected mind
and a scattered mind but whatever it is the art of it is to just simply know
this is how the mind is so contracted and scattered dispersed
mind a mind that's afraid can be either way it can be so afraid that it kind of
shrinks into itself or it can be so scattered because it's so restless and it's kind of running
around and it's we're not really present for ourselves
and this can be very difficult mind states to have but what's happening here is that now
rather than just being part of the mind there's the mind with
greed with aversion with delusion now we're talking about a mind that is
more globally shrunk and contracted or more globally scattered or dispersed
or distracted and jumping around restless and sometimes minds are are that way
and um fear in particular uh can have this kind of effect on the
mind but all the other things you know all the hindrances can have this effect on the mind but but
i find it fascinating to look at my mind and when i get caught up in some mental preoccupation some thought train or
something to then when i notice that's happening to notice what's happened to my state of mind
and for me it's like i guess things have gotten kind of uh obscure kind of
dark kind of they become contracted my world has gotten kind of narrow and small and i'm pulled into my little
concern sometimes if i am
restless or uncertain or anxious about something i could feel that the mind is just
spinning and jumping around and can't sit still very much it's like waters on a sizzling hot frying pan it
just jumps around and and it's hard to arrange the mine in or
to settle the mine because of how jumpy it is so the fascinating thing about this
fourth foundation of mindfulness is it's not giving us advice about what to do when we have minds like
this that can be quite uncomfortable all it says is when the meditator
knows a contracted mind as a contracted mind knows a dispersed mind a scattered mind
has a scattered mind and the fact that it's so radically simple
just to know it's hard to trust that it's hard to have confidence that
this is worthwhile doing of course aren't we supposed to fix it and get away with it make it better and
have a different kind of mind and we're not really meditating if the mind is scattered and so we have to kind
of get advice about how to breathe deeply or to use an antidote or do something so we
fix it there's no fixing it here in this exercise
it's simply recognizing as it is and to know this is how the mind is
at this point and it helps if the mind is somewhat settled
already or has had experiences in practice so we before this so it begins to kind of
appreciate the power of knowing appreciate the simplicity of just kind
of oh this is how it is this is a contracted mind
this is a scattered mind human beings have had contracted and scattered minds for tens of thousands of
years and i'm just one more in a long line of people who had minds like this
and i've had maybe many minds like this and and this is how it is now
and so this is how it is now this is my turn maybe everyone has to have a turn
with scattered and distracted mind and this is my turn okay so now my job is just to know it to see it
and then we fall back on just simplicity of knowing the simplicity of recognition
this is how it is this is how it is and um
over time as we get into the practice we begin appreciating more and more how powerful it is to know this way
how significant it is just no just know this is how it is this is how it is
and uh and we find it becomes it un it helps the free the stickiness of the mind
we're no longer so sticky with caught in it and involved in it and wanting it to be differently
more remarkably as the mind becomes less sticky and we start that itself is settling
that itself is calming that itself that no kind of knowing changes the inner ecology of the inner
landscape and um begins moving us towards freedom
which is the uh this the um the next set the the other half of this
first third foundation of mindfulness is um a set of four
exercises that describes or starts helps us kind of then be on the path to freedom and
liberation these are kind of like this states of mind that begin opening up in meditation
states of mind that can open up and grow out of this radically simple act of
knowing and uh it's kind of phenomenal to watch it happen to be present and just know
something know the mind state know the mind state and then see how the mind changes
in the wake of that clear and simple knowing so um
the primary thing i wanted to emphasize today is this how powerful and significant the
simplest act of knowing can be and i would like to encourage you for the next 24 hours to go about your day
and see if you can experiment with knowing things as they occur in the
simplicity of the moment not impatient for the next moment not needing it to be different not trying to
run away not having a big agenda but see how simple and complete
and free and clarifying and liberating or brightening
it can be to simply know oh this is how it is and it kind of means a little bit you
kind of allow the knowing to sink in allow the knowing to be registered like you make room for the knowing give
yourself time to know and this is my time silly but it's like simple as
coming to a door that's a door driving the light is red
standing in the line in the supermarket knowing i'm standing in a line
and then and then experiment all kinds of places and see how what effect this has on you and how you what impact it
has to practice this radical simplicity that has time for the recognition
and then tomorrow the next day we'll do these more liberating states of mind
that are in this third foundation so thank you very much