good morning IMC Global Sangha good morning can you hear me
good morning nice to see you memes popping up on the chat
and um just checking in to make sure
I can be heard so maybe a sound check
yes great okay thank you we've got a little bit of a lag as I'm sure you figured out from the many mornings with
Bill so it's a delight to be with you again
so nice to see familiar names popping in
seeing in my mind faces of friends and sangamates so good morning Sango welcome
from wherever you are and this morning
as you greet each other I just want to mention that we are in the second of a series of five on
a teaching called the idipada which is factors or Bay seeds or roads to
meditative success and spiritual power and
we are going to today talk about Chanda
which is a form of Desire form of wish a wholesome form in this case
so as you are settling in perhaps even looking at the chat
I just wanna invite you if your eyes are still on the chat feeling the warmth or
Delight or wish for connection and engagement that inspires you to look at it or to
engage with it and just feel that in your body
and then when you're ready take your meditation posture and maybe
close your eyes and turn your attention inward
and feel that wish or connection
that wish to meditate to be with yourself connect
with yourself
[Music] feeling whatever that feels like maybe it's in your heart or your belly
maybe that wish is in your whole body
just feeling into it
and if it feels right maybe silently naming
whatever that wish is that wish for your practice what motivates you
to meditate here together in this virtual Sunday
can name it in words our mental image
maybe even it's just like a felt scent it's almost like a gesture
but tuning in tuning into the wish to be here
to be in connection to practice
meditation
and allowing that wish to clarify into an intention
to include an intention to keep mindfulness awareness
at the Forefront of your attention for these few minutes we meditate
together
perhaps breathing out any excess tension
um settling in
the sense of open interest even devotion
inviting in whatever anchor of attention works best for you
might be a state of your heart mind right now
maybe ambient sounds Wherever You Are
perhaps a sense of your whole body present grounded in the moment
who are for so many of us
Sensations in the body
Sensations of this body breathing it will be the instructions I'll focus
on them story
bringing a sense devotion
interest even love
to the inquiry into what this breath feels like
is it long or short
is it deep more subtle like a sip
because it's smooth and pleasant
whatever way your life's breath is
tuning in allowing the attention to rest
in the gentle waves of your body breathing
you'll meditate in silence for the next while
towards the end of the meditation I'll drop in perhaps a suggestion or
invitation or two bringing that sense
of Interest
love devotion to each moment for each breath
each arising
um this last moment of our meditation together
imitation is to tune in tune in
to the heart to the wish
at the core of your meditation practice
bringing in any sense of appreciation
for the intention there kindness
devotion or love
feeling that feeling bad in your body and your heart
in the mind
allowing it to Ripple through
all the corners of the heart the mind this body
and then sensing into any larger wish or intention
to consider the people in your life
all the ways each life touches so many other lives
and if it feels right to share that wish that goodness that comes from this
practice allowing it to animate you
and trusting trusting that it will Ripple out
through the lives your life touches
and some of that goodness will Ripple out through the lives their lives
but someone
dedicating the benefits of this practice
far and wide
may all beings all people be safe
may they be happy
may they be peaceful and may all of us all beings everywhere
be free of suffering
[Music]
foreign
[Music] good morning Sangha before we start with the little talk
the dormette I have an announcement Gila asked me to announce
that there are two year end sessions for the black identified mindfulness Circle this
December then this is facilitated by Anne Royce and Karen Wilkinson
they are Saturday December 3rd and Saturday December 10th from 9 A.M to 12
p.m Pacific time and it is on Zoom you can register on
imc's website I believe there's a link under what's new and the invitation is if you are back
identified please join join them and hosted by IMC we're delighted to
have any and all black identified practitioners come it's two sessions to reflect on the past
year to embrace the present and to set intentions for the future
and the collective wisdom in the room will allow practitioners to reconnect
and celebrate who they are reaffirm resiliency and vulnerability
amidst impermanence so please feel welcome if you are
identifying that way or if you have friends who you think might benefit from it please invite them
so today's talk is on Chanda c-h-a-n-d-a
the poly word for a desire which has a number of other translations that I'll
talk about but first I just want to get a little context this is
um one of the bay seeds for Spiritual power and meditative prowess or success
that the Buddha used to take good effect before his Awakening and many other
practitioners including myself have found it useful in our Journeys
desire often gets a bad rap in tarabada
Buddhism ancient Buddhism and um
so I want to make a differentiation Chanda this kind of Desire is actually neutral
good or bad but in the context of these teachings it's good it's definitely
differentiated from which is thirst or craving
instead Chanda desire is
healthy or unhealthy because of what's desired and
um we'll give I'll give a couple of examples so if what is being desired runs counter to
interferes with Spiritual Development meditative development then it's considered akusala or
unwholesome unbeneficial one could even say unhealthy perhaps from a spiritual
perspective this is preoccupations with externals that
distract from developing into the best of Who We Are
so that could be things that um just don't lead to our overall
well-being and they can be innocent enough sensual Pleasures that's fine but
um the way we relate to them gets a little bit maybe out of hand or distracting or has
unhealthy consequences the word Dharma and Paulie is Dharma and
Chanda together refers to a kind of virtuous desire a
beneficial skillful sometimes called wholesome desire
kusala in the poly language k-u-s-a-l-a
so wholesome desire is the kind of Desire that is talked about in this teaching
it's onward bleeding it helps to energize the practice
and it fits in as I talked about last time with kind of two other legs on the
tripod beneath this basis for Spiritual success
two that are always there are samadhi often translated as concentration
collectiveness I like to think of it as immersion in this context
amen which is wholehearted engagement
sometimes called exertion so these three things together form the
spaces the desire the wholehearted engagement and the
immersion the samadhi the collective tentness
well some desire has a sweet taste to it or flavor to it and it um
it's kind of a sweet feeling in your heart right maybe some of you tasted
that in the past or in your meditations
there is another distinction to make though even a wholesome desire
can to a lesser extent be co-opted or accompanied by an
unwholesome motivation so it's also about how something is
wished for and I'll give an example here so when I was in um
graduate school for Buddhist studies I had a colleague friend who had come from the activist Community beautiful man did
a lot of good work in the world but he described over years how
him and this small group of others they have these lofty intentions to the world but it was accompanied by a lot of
judgment and anger and diversion and eventually a sense of alienation and he
described remembering seeing the people around him slowly drop off one by one
alienated burned out and how they weren't bringing other people into their
cause because the way the desire was manifesting
had this grasping and judgment and
unwholesome type of constriction to it you can see it in my hand movements those of you who
are watching me so
another facet of skillful desire is that it's open
expansive rather than constricted or obsessive
uh John Shaw a very famous teacher in the kaiforce tradition describes
suffering as root burn clinging too tight to something
so is the desire a grasping hand an open hand or is it more arms thumb
wide in the arms spawn wide hints at a dimension
a virtuous wholesome desire or wish which is that it's aspirational
uplifting so
uplifting open the opposite of fanatical because it is
allowing whatever outcome to be will be but tuning into a wish for goodness
so less expectation less grasping
is more helpful that said if one looks at one's mind or
heart and I have deep in meditation there's usually a little bit of grasping
even in the gamachanda The Virtuous desire it's a holding on to the practice
one translator calls this the one fortunate attachment and that that is the kind of attachment
that leads to the end of attachment right
so it doesn't have to be perfect I can repeat that it really doesn't have to be perfect
we don't need to get snarled up in our own intentions as long as the bulk of the intention for the practice is in the
right direction and we notice notice the parts that aren't helpful
and the beauty of mindfulness practice is that the mindfulness self-corrects
so some ways to cultivate and nourish
this wholesome wish um
to recognize it as it arises and so I'm going to give kind of a word cloud of
meanings all of which are different nuances of translation from the poly
because no poly word really translates perfectly into one English word right there's always a range
so as I explore the meanings feel in your body how it feels
as I speak from the first is that Chanda is close to the
Sanskrit root I'm forgetting what it is I think it's
um that means to jump I like to think of it as to sort of jump or hop with joy that kind of enthusiasm
so feel that in your body maybe imagine a skillful basketball player
totally immersed and engaged in the game jumping to make a perfect Shot Through
The Hoop there's desire there there is
immersion complete Focus collectiveness there's intentness engagement there's
flow it's how these factors pull together
it's enthusiastic participation must play to win
so feeling that wish animating you to practice
Maybe listening for these words excitement
enthusiasm love zeal
eagerness appetite for
delighting in animating impulse intention devotion
so this cluster hints at a continuum a Continuum from excitement and
enthusiasm on one end through a heartfelt wish and all the way
to quiet devotion even contentment on the other end because really this
this is a Continuum to contentment the wish that leads to wishlessness
one really beautiful way I've found to cultivate Donald Chanda which I'll close
with cultivate visible so much and really Turbo Charge the practice
is to appreciate the wish itself appreciate that even that you want to
have the benefit beneficial wish to practice to walk in the world with
more kindness mindfulness whatever it is
that begins to create a positive feedback loop a beautiful feedback loop
that grows that desire and grows enthusiasm for the practice and engagement
and over time is the practice deepens and many of you are already very
experienced even at the very beginning you might notice this that
this meditative development is the process of continually Trading coarser
maybe less hopeful desires for more and more refined ones
one very erudite Teacher Calls this trading candy for gold
so this this Dharma desire is the wish that leads to wishlessness
to letting go and eventually to Freedom
so thank you thank you friends in the next 24 hours I just want to
invite you if it feels right to notice the desire that animates you to do
certain things to practice or maybe engage in other activities and make a distinction for yourself is it
beneficial or unbeneficial does it help with immersion
in what's beneficial if it feels right talk it over with friends I don't know
about it or just notice thank you thank you for your practice
and being back with some of you tomorrow
be well