sake of Audio Dharma here we go okay great so
hello and welcome everyone to happy hour so for today's practice
um I'd like to invite us to consider is
um the theme of this interstitial time how
we fill our interstitial time I love this new word I've just learned
interstitial time which is basically a a time that's in between it's in between
other things it's in between other things when you're walking from place to
place or when you're waiting for someone and it's it's interstitial time it's
it's the sword essentially means that it it fills a space a space in between
other things so interstitial time what an interesting concept so I've become
tuned tuned to how I feel interstitial
time so that's one theme I want to bring in today and really how we how we spend our
interstitial time um is you know it the way we Engage The Way
We engage in their in the interstitial time do we space out are we agitated
waiting for the next thing to happen are we ruminating about what just happened
are we um pulling out our phone and just
vegging out by letting our Consciousness wedge out on social media
wherever it wants to take us like take you know it's as if we we're giving it our the you know as if we're a dog and
we're giving the little leash okay take us anywhere you want to go dear Facebook or our stream you know how do we spend
our interstitial time how do we spend it
and and related to this question of how do we spend our interstitial time
is um is the the idea of of Engagement because
however we engage however we engage
um in our life in these interstitial time that's one example but how how we engage
with um during our time say how we engage
with our breath how we engage with our body how we engage our awareness how we engage our consciousness
it shows up in other places it shows up in other places in our lives
I was talking with a practitioner recently and they were saying that they've noticed as they practice they've
leaned more more into their practice they're more engaged with their practice
of mindfulness of breathing for example that this is what they were doing it's a
sense of Engagement they've noticed they're more engaged at their work with
their life just attitude of Engagement as has really Arisen for them is is
fire it up as they engage in other ways in other areas of life
so these are the two themes I want to bring in of course in in the container
of meta how do we spend our interstitial time how are we engaging because that
engagement during all the time of course but but especially I want to highlight
the inter interstitial time because we all have it we all have it maybe you wake up in the morning you're brushing
your teeth okay what's what's happening in all these interstitial times this time is short time is so short really I
this weekend I was teaching about mindfulness of mortality um and as we really contemplate how how
brief our life is we start to Value these interstitial times again not to
get stressed that's not the idea to stress ourselves I out and feel
pressured sometimes it's quite healthy to let our minds wander it's quite healthy it's
quite wise we make a conscious Choice okay I've really been engaging working
hard all day okay I'm in going to go for a walk and let my mind wander to make a
wise choice so that's a wise choice to make as well I'm not saying that mind
wandering is bad there are there's a value in not trying too hard all the
time and squeezing ourselves and yet to be conscious of how are we engaging how
are we engaging in our lives in these precious moments of being alive
and with the theme of happy hour being dedicated to meta and all the other
Brahma viharas how are we engaging with our hearts how are we engaging
heartfully with every moment um in the west when I say the word mind we
always think about our head but in the east in the in Pali in the
language of the Buddha the word chitta or Consciousness it can
often also be chittag be translated as mind Dash heart mind heart mind heart so
how are we engaging with our mind heart our awareness our Consciousness our chitta how is it
engaging with every moment was it with heart is it with wisdom so
that's the inquiry I'd like to bring in for us and of course we explore that in
the guided meditation that I will guide us and let it be a support for all the
interstitial times so all right let's let's practice together let's sit so
ah so Landing arriving in your seat arriving in this moment
and if your body needs adjusting if you're ah you draw your shoulders back
sit a little differently more upright to bring more energy
or maybe you need to relax and soften the body
maybe both are needed both to sit upright with a sense of integrity
and also also let the body relax often
relaxing softening the sit bones
the legs upper legs lower legs and feet
relaxing the abdomen
the chest softening releasing any tension in the
forehead
the eyes around the eye socket the eyes resting in their socket let
them releasing any tightness in the cheeks in
the jaw letting
your forehead soften your whole face often
letting your neck and shoulders relax your arms
hands the upper body and the lower body and
the trunk ah releasing releasing
releasing and never so gently noticing
the quality of your engagement the way you're engaging with this release
gently gently gently releasing
or ever in the body there is tension or holding
not just releasing body ah
I need tightness and also notice how you're engaging how
you're releasing what's happening
with the release
and right after it
engagement can be so delicious so nourishing
could be such a light touch enlivening
foreign
taking a few moments to release some more any tension or
tightness that you noticed also noticing what happens right before
and after the release what's happening in the body
in the heart and the mind heart mind
and now noticing noticing with every breath
noticing how our heart is engaging
and as if we were to teach the flower its own
loveliness a reminder flower of its own loveliness
reminding our heart our mind heart
that it is lovely it is beautiful there is so much goodness wholesomeness
good will
otherwise we wouldn't be here showing up trying to cultivate kindness for
ourselves for others reminding ourselves
our goodness of our loveliness not this is not a Time
to turn to self-judgment if it arises say thank you very much I
hear you I'm not going to listen to you right now it's okay thank you friend come back later
right now I'm intending I intend to engage
I intentionally engage
with the goodness perhaps
recalling contemplating recollecting
something nice perhaps or kind you've done for someone recently
an act of generosity kindness Goodwill
and again please don't judge oh well he was 50 kind he was 50
selfish okay it's all right Focus choose to focus on the good will
and the kindness and the generosity we have choice in how we incline our
minds use it use your choice use your choice wisely compassionately
you can also if you like recollect
perhaps your values
the goodness of the values you like to cultivate or
you've been cultivating you've been turning towards or perhaps not breaking the precepts not
breaking Sila not lying not stealing so many ways
to remind your own heart of its goodness
see which of these works best for you if one doesn't work try another
trust trust that this is available to all of us
reminding ourselves of our own goodness and if in a small way
lighting up our heart
you can always remind yourself that you are practicing oh oh how beautiful is that yay
the heart that seeks
meditate
to grow beautiful
you can also see that somebody else a dear friend someone
who cares about you Seize Your goodness
and by the virtue of being seen you get to see and appreciate it yourself
as if you're on a swing let this perception
either through a friend or collecting your own goodness it's as if
it's giving you a nice push so that you can soar into the skies
with your own momentum engage
seeing this goodness appreciating this goodness engaging with
it
may this goodness in me in my heart
May It Grow made continued to grow
we have benefit to myself and everyone else
may my heart expand in goodness
grow in Beauty
continue to grow kindness acceptance
patience generosity Goodwill
compassion
taking Delight in what is here already that's how you soar into the skies
this image of the swing
picking Delight the goodness that is here
already
good intentions
engaging with them engaging the goodness in your heart
with each breath
so if you're blowing on fire on Neighbors
of each breath engaging
see my own goodness my own good will
my own intentions for kindness
may they continue to grow
and Grace every thought every word of speech and Every Act
all the time
on the cushion and daily life in the interstitial times
may my heart know its own goodness
may my heart be kind prayed me kindly may I treat myself with
kindness
with wisdom
may I be a good friend to myself
in all moments of my life
now let your body be relaxed released
pension released with each breath
engaging with reflections of kindness
for yourself or others
I treat myself with kindness with wisdom
gnaw moments
or simply may I be kind myself
may I be kind to others
in all moments as much as possible
climbing our hearts with intentions of kindness inside outside
no difference really between the inside and outside kindness all around 360 degrees
Goodwill wisdom generosity
may I engage with kindness especially when I make a mistake
especially when I agitated may I be kind
to myself and others
if there is agitation present fear present sadness
sad challenging emotions grief
to worry may I engage with kindness
to my thoughts to my emotions
may I engage with kindness
when I'm tired
brother's fatigue when there is pain this body is not feeling well
may I be kind
when others are tired but they are in hate
when they are afraid or worried or agitated not their best
just as I'm not in my past may I engage with kindness
inside outside
may I trust that I can engage with kindness and do the best I can
in the moments that I lose
this connection with my own kindness Goodwill
wisdom may I be kind to myself then especially
forgive myself and Begin Again Begin Again just Begin Again
simply Begin Again
especially when I find my thoughts
wandering distracted sleepy may I be kind
to myself kind and wise
especially in the difficult moments
as well as the easy moments all moments
may I always remind myself be remembered be reminded of my own goodness capacity
for kindness it's always here it's always present
even if it's covered by doubt anger restlessness it's
still here trust trust
it's always accessible
may all beings everywhere including myself
know their true nature
kindness and wisdom
may all beings everywhere wake up
be awakened In This Very life may all beings be free
including myself
thank you all thank you so much for your practice it's ah
I don't know where the time went
for me this practice this evening was uh
yeah it went I mean it always goes fast but
like where did the time go wow we just got started five minutes ago it's already 30 minutes anyway
ah so we have time for Reflections for
questions for comments maybe sharing in aha moment in your practice or maybe something
challenging um it's all okay it's all welcome and the invitation is to
offer what has a reason for you as a gift to yourself and to others
and you could uh foreign because there are multiple pages of you
so please use your uh Zoom hand to to raise your hand you can also type in
chat if you type to me in privately I won't read your name just your reflection if you type to everyone I'll
also the tribute your reflection to you so
any any reflection many questions comments
anything that came up for you
hmm maybe I'll break it up a little bit as I'm
waiting so what we did at the beginning of the meditation was to turn well we
started with embodiment with the breath and and feeling the body and then we turned to
um seeing our own goodness seeing our own goodness maybe through a kind act
maybe through not breaking a precept oh I was I almost lied today didn't through
that [Music] um so and the different and also reflection
of your intention your intentionality for example to see the goodness and then to let the goodness really let it grow
to breathe with it to to feel into that intention with intention for engaging
engaging with uh with kindness with wisdom which relates to what I was saying at the beginning with how do we
engage how do we choose to engage not just on the cushion not just uh in daily
life but also especially in those interstitial times those spaces that we
fill how do we engage is it with love and wisdom Susan I see your hand please
oh I accidentally muted you sorry
not there um thank you for giving us permission to
spend time dwelling on our kindness and our goodness you know we don't usually
measure ourselves that way we measure it all sort of other ways
um and it was just so great to go Yes actually there is a lot of kindness and Love in
This Heart and it's just so great to take joy in that
instead of just thinking oh well you know I'm retired and I don't really you know and I'm kind of getting older and
you know I like that I'm not doing that and you know this is like oh yeah actually
um I'm growing a kind heart and being kind in the world and it's it's a good thing
so thank you thank you Susan thank you for that
beautiful reflection exactly it's a good thing and the more we turn towards our
goodness the more it grows the more it grows it's it's just as the Buddha says
whatever you reflect and Ponder upon frequently becomes the inclination of
your mind inclination of your mind heart so whatever you Ponder upon if you Ponder upon your goodness oh you want to
be kind you want to be wise it's like it makes it grow so it is wholesome it's
not just I don't know self uh self-anger and diesman it's not bad
and you I know you get it but I still wanted to say that thank you for that beautiful reflection
and the joy also I could see your joy as you were telling me about it beautiful Claire please
my my reflection is a little remote or mundane but um I still wanted to share
it because it's really been wonderful actually right before covet I got my first dog in New York
and you all are not New Yorkers so you can't totally appreciate this but we
live very focused cold kinds of lives
um and I did not realize that when I got my dog and I knew I would have to walk
her I was walking into one of the kindest most loving communities there is
in New York the dog walker Community is absolutely wonderful we and we all know
each other now and you know we keep track of how we're doing but there's such good people and I'm not kidding and
that's my interstitial time because I love it I love it your interstitial
time is filled with engaging with kindness and care with others that is
very sweet I love that player that's lovely thanks for sharing them
enjoying my heart it's the first time dog owner in New York love it great
any other Reflections in the SE any other questions comments complaints it's
all welcome
Marilyn please
um first of all well thank you I think I heard you say kind of Go Your Own Way try something
different if it doesn't work and
well I found myself saying when you were saying engagement I let the word go by
but it was like I'm not quite sure what that means engagement what does it mean and what I found myself saying was
may I be truthful and may I be kind and may I be wise
and that's all not beautiful beautiful I love that thank
you for sharing that Marilyn Yes you heard me right it was giving a lot of permission to see what works for you to
see what makes sense for you right now and these different ways and and it's beautiful that you took that Liberty and
oh yeah this works for me may I be kind may I be truthful beautiful those values that are important to you to bring
attention to them to your intention uh to bring attention to your intentions a
way of engaging with it right because if you just like oh yeah I'm doing it you
know as as Susan was saying I'm getting old and like you know but there's a different
way you can engage oh yeah may I be kind may I be truthful because these are these values are important to me so
that's what I meant by engagement so you were doing it great I love it Serena please
sir so how am I saying the name right yeah that's yeah that's fine yeah I I
wonder I was experiencing a lot of physical
um you know um unsettledness and squirmishness
and I was just wondering whether you had any um
advice on how to deal with that I mean I tried to be with it as
as best as I could and be as accepting as I could on on the situation but I was
just wondering if there is um yeah there's so many different ways to be with it and for tonight given this
particular theme that we're working with so what I would say is if there is discomfort if there's uh say square
missioness and unsettledness and like ah I would be kind with it I would just be
really in I would engage as I was saying in the guided meditation may I be kind
to myself with my thoughts with my body especially in difficult times so it's engaged with kindness so it's not just
being with it but it's being with it with kindness as if there's a puppy
that's agitated and it's just like oh and you're just oh here puppy hello sweetheart here you are you're just
really holding the puppy and calming the puppy with kindness that bad way of
Engagement that's what I would suggest a way of being with it thank you thank you
welcome a last reflection from
Murray yeah sitting down my mind was full of problems issues and plans it all
fell away during the sitting yes the issue still exists but maybe they don't have to be problems as much now and I'll
be kind with the issues beautiful thank you so much for that reflection that is that's lovely yeah
so so here's the invitation that I have for us engaging in small
um groups together and roughly groups of three and here's the prompt the invitation
and um and of course always in the groups you can show up and share silence
just say you know past just show up with kindness
um and if you do want to say something when your turn comes and we'll go alphabetical order first name you can
share if you like some value that's important to something about some goodness that came up about you and and
you you might see you know and usually you might you might have been taught as
a you know as a child oh you don't don't say good nice things about yourself you
know be humble and don't say oh I did this kind thing but I'm asking you now
to turn your attention to your own goodness or or maybe your your own
goodnesses you know I really intend to um to wake up I really want to wake up
in this life or I really want to be truthful I don't want to lie and this is I really try that every day like that is
beautiful so let your beauty shine just if allow yourself to be witnessed in
your goodness whether it's your intention you're sharing or whether the kind thing you did today yesterday this
past week just let yourself be witnessed by others so socially acceptable to say
something beautiful about yourself to let it be held by other
mirrors beautiful mirrors so celebrating goodness it's a way of celebrating
goodness let us not just celebrate problems and what's wrong let us
celebrate the goodness that every single person has and be inspired oh this
person they they want to do one kind act every every day how nice is that so so
say offer something next person will offer something the next person that'll come back to you and go round and round
that way so celebrating goodness so I'll create the rooms
and um take care of yourselves take care of
each other here we go we'll wait until everybody's back the
rooms will close in about 20 seconds
okay another five seconds [Music] and the rooms are closed everybody's
back welcome back and we have just about a minute of any reflection
especially if you haven't spoken this evening what happened in the groups what did it feel like
be a held witness or hold witness other people's goodness we'd love to hear at least from one person it might be from
one person I think that's all the time we have somebody anybody Reflections what was it
like
I see some smiles
lots of smiles in my group as we thought of our Goodwill says Michelle thank you
Misha and Jesse thank you yeah I'll just briefly say thank you so
much for this practice this was uh deeply uncomfortable for me and that in
itself was uh just a really profound teaching so I really appreciate this practice thank you oh yay beautiful
thank you so much for that and as you said that was deeply uncomfortable and valuable I saw a few other people nod
their heads so yeah yeah great Marie says it's a hard practice to
acknowledge your own goodness yeah and it's so important it is so important otherwise we just think of ourselves as
these whatever the I mean it's a judgmental voice right it's so loud it's so loud whereas the little voice says
it's actually sweetheart you are doing your best it's okay you're growing that is what we need to grow more so so thank
you all thank you so much for your practice for coming to this uh space of
of cultivating goodness turning to our goodness may you all be
safe happy healthy and free may all beings be free
dedicating the Merit here we go
thanks everyone be well