so welcome welcome folks um yeah it's it's lovely to uh see all the
names streaming past and uh i know a lot of them actually and uh
anyway i'm happy to uh happy to be with you
so i'll just uh read a paragraph say a few words before we
sit here so this is uh
quoted from her this book before in different context
this catherine schultz lost and found a book about
losing her father finding her love partner
woman she she married so she writes
even the strongest sentiments are intermittent and inconstant forever
obliged to share the stage with other members of emotions ensemble cast
grief with gratitude anger with boredom happiness with irritation
frustration with amusement and on and on in endless permutations
most of us instinctively resent this intermingling when we're happy we want
to be wholly happy not also missing our father or worried about work or
infuriated by the awful customer service at the phone company
that appetite for contentment makes perfect sense but we often long to experience our
disagreeable feelings uninterrupted as well
in part that's because misery has a kind of inertia to it
there is something about a bad mood that wants perversely
to persist i have felt at various low points in my life that i did not want to venture out
into a social event because i would have to pretend to be happy
for getting the very real possibility that once there i would actually be
happy or perhaps more accurately believing that i did not want to feel
better worse i have sometimes persevered in a
pointless argument simply because i was in a kind of sour mood that would rather fight than be improved
this kind of emotional intransigence is common anger wants only to be angry
levity's deadly to it as is compassion accordingly it resists them both
boredom rejects anything as boring uh rejects as boring everything that
might vanquish it loneliness wants only to be left alone and grief as i noted earlier is so
terrified of betraying itself that it wants only to grieve
she is not a meditation teacher but um that uh
the wisdom of that was um very apparent to me and uh
very dharmic in spirit and
in dharma practice we really [Music]
have no fidelity to the moment that has just passed
we are attending to what's arising and passing but we have no fidelity
to the mood of the past hour or the past day or the past
year yeah mindfulness is neither trying to
engineer the persistence of one state nor engineer the
vanishing of another in other words we're we're wide open to
things continuing and we're wide open to discontinuity
or wide open to discontinuity
and as we sit there's this kind of
sense of of
kind of radical openness to what comes next
and not trying to structure the next moment based on what has happened not assuming
continuity not having fidelity to what has just passed
and so there's this like moment-to-moment openness
and over the course of our practice i i feel like part of what this frees up is
that even really intense experience doesn't leave the same trace that it
used to that we actually are are more flexible
and fluid and begin to kind of find our way into some
homeostatic balance even immediately after real intensity
there's no fidelity to what's just happened even though it's been blessed with awareness
and love and this means that a moment of
grief can be followed by a moment of levity or delight
yeah or peace
let's uh let's sit
just uh landing
letting the the words just uh melt away
just landing in the intimacy of attention
we breathe deeply into the body we're conscious of the whole body
breathing so as to settle there
and it's almost like we breathe deeply into the meditating mind
that might lose touch with the intimacy through its own frenzy and doingness
and doubt trying to get it right
trying to tame thought
don't miss the intimacy right here
okay
no matter how well known or well loved by others you might be
no one can know you and precisely this way
with precisely this level of intimacy
until we listen listen to herself with a wide open heart
with space to let our life unfold
to be open to that which persists
the mind states or moons emotions that persist
but not assume persistence
in other words we're open wide open to discontinuity
to the morphing of experience
we're even intimate with the longings that underlie
our discursive meanderings
and we're practicing not assuming
our life is what we've always assumed it to be
we are not rejecting what just has passed nor
are we maintaining fidelity to it assuming permanence
radically open to the unfolding of
a sensory experience
part of our openness to discontinuity
means we're we're not uh
narrativizing our meditation in complex ways we're not telling
a story about where it's gone and what its trajectory
is
a kind of freshness moment by moment intimacy
who knows what comes next
who knows where insight comes from
just keep offering ourselves up to the moment
so over uh the next uh next four days i'll
highlight um four four mechanisms through which uh dharma practice
gets under our skin into our system
and the the first uh first mechanism wanted to
yeah i said yesterday you see this these are the
kind of um core mechanisms how they're classically framed how the practice transforms us
and um i wanted to lay out a kind of another
framework of this not to replace silva samadhipanya of course but just as a way
of looking and um and so the the first um
first mechanism is dharma as a kind of attention therapy
the dharma is an attention therapy so our attention attention is our most
basic currency and really the sense of directing
directing our attention to what we deem important that's very close to our sense of agency
and sense of self for the core of who we think we are
um william william james said
volition is nothing but attention
volition is nothing but attention and this of course is part of why
um the commodification and extraction and fragmentation of our
attention by modern life technology is actually a profound threat
it's it's like um as ahad akhtar said the bright pliancy
of mind itself attention
is um under assault actually um
and so we as meditators become connoisseurs of attention
and indeed in the scientific uh uh
literature meditation sometimes described as attentional training that's the language that's used
and in the first iteration of what would become mindfulness-based cognitive therapy a
kind of mindfulness-based intervention
it was originally called attentional control training yeah i'm glad they changed the name to
mindfulness-based cognitive therapy but that was originally the name
and um and attention attention
complex relationship with our own well-being and it's notable that um
that attention is fractured when we experience psychiatric
distress so in depression for example there's a
the attention is disrupted there's an intentional bias towards negative information
and disrupted concentration is one of the symptoms of
depression or in post-traumatic stress or some other anxiety disorder
obsessive-compulsive disorder there's intrusive thoughts that disrupt
the flow of attention or generalized anxiety there's kind of a
tension that's being constantly directed to the unknown future and
worrying in an uncontrollable kind of way
and in addiction there's attentional bias towards the drug cue or whatever the cue is
or adhd attention deficit hyperactivity disorder like attention's
right there in the diagnostic name
and um and even when we're not in psychiatric
distress not
in clinical distress or suffering yeah even low-grade suffering often includes
an attention that is pinging all over pinging from memory to future
to emotion and narratives
and so we we train in attention we train in attention
why is it tension where to place the attention
on the four noble truths rather than constantly engaging worrisome scenarios
we practice how to attend steadily patiently
we we train in steadying the attention so that the spotlight the spotlight of
attention isn't shaking and darting around so much anymore
we train the attention to to relinquish uh distractions
yeah like to the movement from
being absorbed in discursive thought to back to the object of focus maybe that's
the breath maybe that's your work maybe that's the person you're listening to but there's less stickiness the
discursive thought is less sticky more flimsy less compelling
we train in attention because life feels uh
very fast to the unconcentrated mind feels kind of overwhelming
and and so we slow it down
yeah and as our attention gathers is less fragmented um
there's a sense of seclusion yeah even though we actually can come into
states where we're noticing more change there's a sense of seclusion and protection from the bombardment of
samsara and
we train we train in the effortlessness of
awareness so when attention can go
anywhere but not stick to anything
yeah when the spotlight of attention can go anywhere in experience but not
stick to anything and there's a kind of
deep poise that happens when we're not
mesmerized by phenomena we're not mesmerized by
our notions of our life our so-called life
and sometimes you hear
kind of divisions between samadhi and insight concentration and
mindfulness but my understanding is that the buddha spoke about these capacities
in tandem not a rigid separation
and a lot of of fanfare about the kind of
bliss of the gathered attention um is understandable um
but as far as i can tell uh the bliss is um it's
maybe most mostly good as faith and encouragement to keep going
um aspects of of samadhi this gathered attention they are uh indeed closely
related to to insight and mindfulness um
when we begin to stabilize the attention we can perceive suffering more clearly
and it's so important to actually perceive suffering with a lot of vividness
and that that entails a stabilizing of the attention
when we we stabilize the attention there's there's no
just some of the buddha's
injunctions become so clear there's no there's just no doubt that clinging
hurts when it's perceived from the stabilized attention
there's no doubt that clinging hurts there's no doubt that hatred
hurts no doubt that greed hurts
and it's through this stabilization of attention that the the kind of fantasy
of the close-hearted happiness ends
that insofar as we will know deep happiness
it will be a function of openheartedness
the training of attention dharma as an attention therapy this is part of what
gives the mind its sense of depth yeah
the the stabilizing the kind of settling of the
mind it gives the mind its sense of depth the matter of life
this matter of life becomes serious
and as our attention becomes stable dharma lessens the insights we have the
seeing we develop those lessons make deeper impressions on
our mind
sometimes we have an insight or understanding or something but what kind of legs does it have
right often often what we once knew
what we learned is overpowered by subsequent learning and lessons and the fragmentation of
life and so we go on retreat maybe and we
know once or for all something we discover something uh this is
this fill in the blank this self-harshness is delusion we know it
deeply but how does that lesson stick how does it get its legs
and my sense is that samadhi allows our understandings this training of the
attention allows our understandings to etch themselves more deeply into our
being yeah our insights
uh stick
and so there are these very interesting interactions between this kind of um
attention this gathering of the attention and the learning aspects of dharma
much more to be said about that of course but um
yeah sometimes sometimes dharma is reduced to
attention training uh but it's it's much more than that
and so we'll keep going tomorrow that's why they're three more days
but uh for today yeah dharma as an attention therapy
all that comes with that so i'll pause here and
wish you all a good uh good day and
um thank you for your your attention and uh i'll hang in the chat for a moment
and um see you see you tomorrow thank you