so hello everyone and welcome to our
practice and discussion of the buddha's teachings on
cultivating cultivating awareness cultivating a strong stable clear
awareness with which to go through our lives
and that's a great pleasure to do this it's a wonderful thing and i find that the path to that every
step along the way is wonderful and then we come to this exercise in the
satipatana sutta which some people skip over some people are
perplexed by and some people don't like and that is that of the
meditating on the parts of the body and um
and i want to uh orient ourselves around this or kind of present some an idea from the early text
that might be helpful uh though at first people often don't like this
so the idea is that um first first time say that uh
the use of the of what we call imagination is uh included as part of maybe a small
part a part of the path of meditation and teachings of the buddha it's very simple acts of imagination but
in doing so he distinguishes distinguishes between uses of the imagination that involve
delusion that are fantasy that are have no real connection to reality
and and for those maybe we can use the word concocting
the word sometimes is translated to english as conceiving
and and so giving birth to concoctions to just imaginary ideas
and manyati and uh and then those which are
understood to be metaphors and uh similes uh and very simple acts of imagination
of visualization of uh reflection that um
point us in the direction of being present support us to let go of our preoccupations let go of those which the
imagination that helps us to let go of imagination the imagination lets us let's let go of being caught
and so imagine maybe you bring to mind some part of your body
maybe something is not too challenging for you that the the body image of it is a concern
for you maybe it's something a simple maybe it's i hope it's simple but
for example um your your fingernails maybe they're too long today there are
times you don't get around to cutting them and they're kind of longer than you think they should be and so you're concerned about the image
of your fingers and your fingernails and what people think about you and and you're going to a very important
meeting and you haven't had a chance to cut your fingernails let alone clean
them and they're still dirt from an ins and them from working in the garden or maybe something a little bit more
challenging and maybe you have concerns about your the length of your fingers
they're too short they're too long or maybe they're too stubby or fat or something
and and you feel embarrassed don't want to show it to people you keep your hands in your pocket so people
don't notice and so it's a concern with body image so something like that
now imagine that you do something really wonderful maybe it's a wonderful
hike in nature maybe it's a wonderful exercise
maybe it's uh you feel really refreshed and kind of wonderful and clean after a shower or
a deep satisfaction maybe after sex or something that maybe you've worked hard
physical work manual work and you feel so contented and a little bit sore but so contented and happy in
your body there's kind of a vitality in the body and imagine yourself sitting down
and maybe closing your eyes in a nice comfortable chair and just feeling the vitality the
surging of energy the the working and tingling of the muscles and
that feels pleasant and nice a deep satisfaction that feels embodied after doing this physical thing
the deep content physical contentment a job well done a situation well
experienced very contented and now with that kind of contentment
think about your fingernails being too long or your fingers being too this or to that
and and notice how it takes you into a world of thoughts ideas concepts concoctions
that um you know it takes you away from the coursing of good
feelings satisfaction contentment in your body and um
so feeling kind of the alienation certain kind of alienation from an embodied
wonderful feeling of oneself in one's embody in one's skin
by going into the world of thoughts and comparative thinking and ideas of what's
ideal and not ideal how things should be and shouldn't be these are two radically different worlds
of weight relating to the body and so this the parts of the body
exercise is one that recognizes that one is not so satisfying one is not so helpful to
be in and if we get caught in the world of concocting and comparisons
then may sometimes we need some help to be able to come back into the lived body
where we fit perfectly inside our skin where we
the experience of the fingers for the fingernails for themselves in and of themselves the fingers don't care if
they're short or long or stubby the fingers just are
in fact if we just settle into the sensations and the fingers unless you have arthritis or something
that the sensations of the fingers just tingles and feels nice and they're totally happy
whatever the fingers are don't mind what's what length or size they are fingernails don't mind if they're
haven't been cut for a while maybe or dirty so there's a different kind of way to
live and so these 31 parts of the body are sometimes called unclean
and the later tradition labels titles this exercise um
the repulsive that they talked about the repulsive the repulsive these parts of the body
but the tradition i'll talk more about later is not making a categorical
judgment about the body it's rather making a judgment about the
way we get into the concocting world of attachments around the body that is what is the ancient world
unclean in our world we might use other language we might use that say it's suffering
it's stressful we might say that it's alienating it takes us away that makes us separate from our
experience from our body we have maybe used different language in the ancients do
but the movement in the same direction away from the secondary
judgments about the body seeing that as a problem that's what's
unclean in a sense and settling in for the body's experience of itself
so assuming a
meditation posture
and close your eyes and just feel your breathing
feel your body feel what's happening in your body
from me talking and listen you listening
what is what energies are coursing through your body what sensations
what tensions are in your body
and are there thoughts ideas concoctions in the mind
that keep you at a distance from feeling the body in and of itself
maybe you can relax the thinking mind calm the thinking a bit
calm your activity to feel and sense the experience of your
body from the inside out
and this difference between what's concocted and what's felt and experienced
applies to the breathing
whether the breathing is comfortable or uncomfortable let the breathing be the breathing
independent of thoughts ideas
judgments expectations
as if each breath is just what it's supposed to be
each inhale each exhale
with a relaxing into your breathing
perhaps as you exhale relaxing the shoulders and belly
and then feel or imagine
yourself physically content
if you felt deeply satisfied and contented in your body
where would that contentment and satisfaction reside
independent of what you think
what is the body's own experience of that contentment and that vitality or
sense of
whatever is happening in the body the body is enough to just write for itself
what what energy tingling vibrations sensations
would you allow yourself to feel
if this embodied experience at this moment
was just right just the thing that's supposed to be happening
whether comfortable or uncomfortable
maybe as you breathe you can feel your skin
over your torso your chest your belly
stretch or move on the inhale
settle back on the exhale
maybe your skin pushes against your clothes
as you breathe feeling your skin
letting the skin have its own experience independent of what you think
just skin feeling
and whatever is inside your skin
fits perfectly within your skin like a good pair of shoes or a good pair of
well-fitting clothes and with inside your skin
there's your flesh
maybe it also moves in the belly or elsewhere in your body as you breathe
breathing with the fleshes like how the flesh the muscles
how it feels itself its own experience sitting here
and then deeper than the flesh is the bones
the structure which holds all the flesh
some of the bones move as you breathe the rib cage
maybe in the shoulders or the spine
we can have thoughts and ideas about our bones
but what would we like to feel or sense or imagine
the bones how the bones experience themselves
or feeling like knowing your bones without those thoughts
judgments fears just bones
and so freeing yourself from body images you might live by
gently breathe with experience of skin
breathe with the experience of flesh breathe with experience of bones
letting each have its own experience free of judgments thoughts ideas
letting each one help free you
from a kind of alienation from the body
that the world of self-image and and bodily perfection
might do for you sitting here content and peaceful
with the body as it is skin flesh bones
as we come to this end of this sitting imagine
that you're comfortable in your skin
imagine that your body is at home in itself
your body is perfect the way it is
and the body has the opportunity he has the capacity
to feel itself be at home in itself independent
of the stories and thoughts and ideas and predictions
you have about your body even if the body is uncomfortable
maybe there's a way in which you can still be at home in your body
at home in your skin in your flesh and your bones
we're at home in some deeper embodied way
and now imagine
that when you look upon other people you don't look upon them
based on their attractiveness or or
your judgments or ideas of how their body appears
but rather you look upon others with kind of an act of imagination
you look upon others how they would be if they were at home
in their own body as if their body is perfect
no problems
if they were at home in their own skin comfortable in their skin and their
flesh and their bones imagine looking upon people that way
how nice it would be if they could be comfortable in their own body
putting aside your ideas of attractiveness or
your orientation towards what might will be unusual about their body
your judgments the stories you make up
and how wonderful would be if everyone could feel comfortable in their own body
if everyone can have some deep acceptance of their body free of
the cultural conditioning ideas and thoughts the social comparisons that are made
all the painful ways in which we relate to people's bodies and skin
objectifying people imagine how great it would be if all the
people you know and all the people you meet could feel at home happy in their body
safe in their body at peace in their body
a freedom embodied freedom
may it be that how we look upon others how we regard
others maybe regard others kindly
caringly may we regard others seeing them
in ways that support them feeling at home in themselves
comfortable in themselves in their own body may all beings live happily
in their bodies may all beings feel safe
in their bodies may all beings
feel peaceful in their own bodies
and may all beings be free
with an embodied freedom
may the way that we regard others support this as possible
[Music]
you
so today's uh this will be the
the last talk on this fourth exercise of the satipatana sutta
and it is um
i think it's as easy to overlook this part it's easy to which i did for many many years
it's easy to be dismissive especially for a western audience because it has such it refers to the
body as parts is unclean and and it's not in the original text but the later editors added added a title
for this exercise that that refers to the repulsiveness of the
body and that's even you know i mean many people in the west even more reactive to that why would you see the body as
repulsive or unclean and perhaps i shouldn't try to
guess at what the ancients were doing and thinking when they had this but i do know
that the buddha sometimes talks about
the the our bodily form our bodily feelings
our bodily our our perceptions are mental activity and concoctions
creations and something that we often call consciousness in the west
that uh he has sometimes very negative language for it and sometimes he says it's impermanent
it's empty it's vain it's a tumor it's an illness it's a fat it's a burden
it's uh you know it's you know it's just kind of it has a long list of things which are very kind of negative
and if you read it out of context it's like wow these buddhists are
completely world negating and you know uh opposed to the body and all this and
and you know treat the body as some kind of you know as a you know a boil a blister
something you know just look sore and um
but the context of teaching these teachings about how uh you know
these things are in sickness and illness or something like that it's it's um
it uses the word as if and it's a particular context to use it
and the context is deep some of the deepest sense of well-being
happiness and joy that can be experienced in meditation the joy of uh deeply being absorbed and
concentrated that comes with deep concentrated meditation and for some people this is the highest
like like the pinnacle of of uh joy and happiness that they've ever experienced in their life
um and in a sustained way is when they're when they drop into these deep concentrated states
and in that context where there's so much well-being and happiness
then be careful then not to be attached to the body
and to perceptions and feelings even consciousness any attachments any preoccupation any
fixation on them in that context
just feels like a drag feels like now why why would i
um uh uh agitate or muddy or lose this deep sense of well-being that
the whole body feels like it's beautiful and glowing and and um and alive and
settled and finally i'm at home in my body and it just like seems like a wellspring of well-being
why would i separate myself into the world of concoctions the world of immense
stories and ideas and shoulds and shouldn'ts even ones any even ones that are
celebrating the body when the celebration of the body is also a separation from it all
and um and uh and so in that context the buddha said uh if all this well-being relate to
these parts of these areas as if they're a drag
so that you can stay connected and i think what you know so you don't get attached to it so you can stay
connected to this well-being that is onward leading and leads to liberation from all attachments
so you know this is uh so in terms of these 31 parts of the
body then the fourth exercise where it talks about being unclean i interpret it in that in that way
that in the it's in a context of developing greater and greater well-being and happiness and being at
home in one's body feeling comfortable in one skin and just settling in and experiencing it
independent of the concoctions the stories the interpretation the opinions we have
and it feels so good to do that that why get involved in the opinions why get involved in all these things
and and so uh and so when is it that it's helpful
to be pre in being present for the body to really see that there are certain
ways of relating to the body that are undesirable
uh maybe unclean if we because it kind of mires or dirties the waters of attention and
our experience and so as we kind of do this 31 as we get into the 31 parts of the body
then more and more we're beginning to free ourselves from the from
the concoctions we're using our imagination a little bit the visualization and inner sense
and focus to focus if you do the practice steadily on 31 you know each systematically going
through each just each body part but you're developing greater and greater embodiment presence in the body
and a greater sensitivity to the way that the mind concocts the mind makes stories and ideas
and how we could let go of that and to stay with the body
and this is phenomenally useful for as the satiputana suta keeps going
deeper and deeper into the the basic practice of just mindfulness of body feelings
mind and damas that we've beginning to help loosen up the grip of stories ideas and some of
them are very connected to the body so this is one of the functions of this 32 parts of the body is to free us from
that grip but also to begin appreciating and being increasing sensitivity
to the concocting nature of the mind the story making of the mind because as we go deeper and deeper in
the satipatana practice we're becoming freer and freer of this concocting
nature of the mind but we'll see though that when we start tomorrow on the four
elements we're still using the imagination to some degree for that
and uh so we're still learning learning these lessons tomorrow we'll do the four elements
start there the fifth exercise and um uh the
the core the original the the pasana instructions the mindful instruction
which much of much of the western uh the pasta movement is based on the inside movement that comes out of
the jack and joseph and sharon and and came from those of us who went to asia
to study something called the a particular form of bipassnam practice called mahasi mahasi practice it's named
after the teacher mahasi mahasi sayadaw and his practice was really centered
on the four elements and he was a for it was from he doesn't he wasn't explicit about it always and
it wasn't conveyed to the western practitioners but the foundation of uh the modern western whole experience of
of mindfulness-based stress reduction and teachings of spirit rock and ims and all
that the fun it was this four elements meditation so it has a the pedigree or the or the
lineage we're in is one that really centers on this and so i'll talk start talking about that
tomorrow and the one thing about the
last thing about the 31 parts of the body meditation there's a wonderful teacher a pasta
teacher in santa cruz named bob stahl and every year he does almost a year-long course
on the 32 parts of the body meditation and it's very popular in people in santa
cruz so i say that not many of you are not close to santa cruz but that
there is a people who do this practice find a great love for it
and maybe you'll try it out memorize the list
and or some of the lists usually people memorize them groups of five or six and then
and then just practice it like the way we did today with the skin flesh bones but using the different
parts um
so a couple of little announcements is that today i posted it in youtube if you're
on youtube um under the the video there's in the description of
the text there's the text for this 31 parts of the body and also there's a
link we'll keep in there to go directly to imc's uh the page on imc's website where we have
my translation of the sati patana suta
and so as we go through this you want to see the kind of
you know the reference point i'm using for this and kind of my understanding of this text in the translation you can
find that translation there and you can also find it under the resource menu
in imc's website as well directly
so thank you and i look forward to starting the four
elements tomorrow