so hello hello and welcome formerly
to happy hour makes me happy to be with you to see you all
this evening afternoon whatever your time zone might be
coming together and practicing so so for today's practice um
i wanted to uh invite us to engage
in the practice of of compassion and care
to explore that as you know as as you might have been uh for those who've been
coming or listening to to happy hour there's so many different aspects of these practices there's just not one way
to explore these practices there's so many angles so many dimensions so many ways our hearts can open
to these practices so um for so for tonight i'd like to invite
us to explore a particular aspect a way of um exploring uh karuna compassion the
practice of compassion which is where care which is where love
warmth meets or holds suffering either for ourselves or for others
and then there is the practice of [Music] this other beautiful word in pali on
kampa often translated as care this basic care
basic care um which we can think of as pervasive just
a sense of caring and both of these practices are beautiful so tonight i wanted to invite
us practically to explore them in our hearts um
in our minds in our mind hearts again in the the pali word is chitta
c-i-t-t-h h often translated just as mind but actually it's mind heart it's the more
appropriate translation so in our mind heart exploring care on kampa
and exploring compassion karuna and um
see how much more do i want to say to frame the topic versus just inviting us to practice
together and explore and see what arises the first person laboratory which is
which is our unique and amazing human mind and heart so
um [Music] yeah let's just dig in maybe i'll i'll
reserve some time at the end to say more let's just explore together fellow
travelers shall we ready yes yes let's okay all right so
so i like to invite you to get into your meditation posture whatever is comfortable for you
you may be sitting or standing or lying down as long as you
don't fall asleep not a problem and if you are sitting
allow there to be a sense of integrity to your body
letting your base your sit bones to release to land into the chair
the cushion in lieu of the earth
ah your base your base well rooted well connected
your legs your feet
well rooted to the earth they can offer their weight
offer their weight the earth
ah releasing releasing releasing some more
and from this
stable [Music] heavy connected
well rooted base a spirit tree
connected to the earth ah
let your body rise up as if a tall branch of a tree
rising upon its own sense of integrity
not needed to be pushed up
bed rise up rise up to the heavens
with your goodness with your aspiration
ah well rooted to the earth and well supported
and feeling expansive expansive in this body taking your rightful place on this
earth taking your rightful seat
as the buddha touched the earth the night of his enlightenment
does earth be my witness i am here i belong here
this earth be my witness we touch the earth with our bodies we
are here here
i let the breath let this life-giving breath
move through your body let it be received received in the abdomen on its own
notice i don't invite you to breathe because the body
knows how to breathe we don't want to make it into a project
simply knowing [Music] that light touch that breathing is happening here it is
being breathed in being breathed out
resting resting
receiving this gift this gift of the breath
is life-giving
enlivening breath this friend
this friend
not to be taken for granted
enjoying the breath appreciating the breath
imagine you i jumped in the lake
in a cool lake the summer day and you jumped a little too deeply
it took a while to come back up to the surface and when you come back up
the surface of the water oh this breath i've been waiting for you delicious
ah let it be enjoyed
natural breath
if thoughts arise not a problem at all thoughts will arrive sounds will
arise it's okay it's all okay
arising and passing
greeting the thought with a smile
maybe for the benefit of this practice period gently
telling the thought thank you and not now
please come back another time i'll be waiting for you but now i'm giving my heart to this
practice to this cultivation
turning turning the awareness
inward internal
calming soothing [Music] breath in the body received
just tilling the soil another few minutes just to settle
before we turn to explore care and compassion
but here this breath
received
releasing tension releasing thoughts
releasing and re-releasing intending
being with cozily
lovingly with this body
knowing feeling that the breath as it's received
it's like stroking petting a cat
our hearts our minds can start to purr with ease and delight
just with this simplicity
now i'd like to invite you is we continue to stay embodied feeling the
body and the earth touching the earth receiving the
breath releasing tightness hoping
continuing to feel the body and invite if you want
this image into your heart for reflection
and the image invite is
an image of care we've often seen interspecies caring for each other
perhaps you might have seen videos on the internet
if you've seen one you can bring pull one up or i'll describe one
little a dog caring for playing with little chicks young chicks
playfully caringly
a dog mothering chicks
or whatever image arises for you
often observing another being caring
caring so much caring protecting keeping safe
another being
it kindles it rekindles a sense of care softness
as we recognize the sense of care
or maybe an image a sense of
and loving protecting its own chicks
or a duck it's ducklings
sweet little furry animals
young ones being cared for protected
in safety by others
witnessing care in your mind's eye
let yourself rest in this and see what it arises in you in
your heart witnessing care
feeling into the sense of care witnessing another being scared
maybe it kindles reminds you of
a being maybe a pet maybe a child
or maybe an older parent that you have cared for
or maybe a friend someone you have cared for deeply cared
for there may be perhaps a tableau
an image of a moment when you cared maybe fed them
kept them safe cleaned them
took them to a doctor
deep care
let yourself appreciate let yourself recognize your own care
your own capacity to have cared this is not a time
to remind yourself of all the ways you haven't cared or you fell short
this is not the time letting go of any self-judgment
that may arise and just feel into the care
let your heart appreciate feel into its own care
expression of its love for another being
i let the sense of care brighten your heart
brighten bright light shining gladdening
and maybe there is a being in your life right now
that you care for you care about
feeling into the sense of care not clingy care
not with attachment or outcome [Music]
but an easy just a sense of care
this being person cause is important to you you care
letting the care be felt let it be bright
let it be nourishing to you care is nourishing
and can we turn this care
the eyes with which we gaze through gaze with
care turn around and piece at ourselves with care
care for this being who is me myself
along with others not separate
not separate
as being who is me just as worthy just as worthy
of protection happiness
health well-being and care to take care
as if you were both the chick and the head the den mother
now transitioning or bringing in the practice of
garuna compassion to bring up
perhaps some mild challenge you've been having recently
i let the sense of care hold this challenge
not self-playing or you should have done this it's your fault no none of that or sweetheart this is hard
this is hard anyone going through this would be having a hard time
this is hard dear it's okay now now holding yourself with care
tenderness compassion meeting meeting the hurt
with love with care
perhaps extending the metaphor
if you see yourself as one of the chicks
maybe you're having a bit of a challenge
maybe you're the one that's running behind doesn't get enough food is the smaller one so the mother hen cares more
oh sweetie sweetie let me care for you
opens the heart more even more to care for this precious
precious being that is you your own care for yourself
now now it's all right dear it's okay sweetie
i care for you i'm here for you
and i acknowledge this is challenging this is hard
and extending extending our care
our compassion to others
perhaps to the being from earlier that in our mind's eye we're feeling our
care for
imagine if they had a challenge our heart would be moved
to a tenderness of compassion needing the hurt meeting the challenge
with even more love
and care
and for the last
minutes of this practice period extending our care
and our compassion our everyday care to all beings everywhere
and all beings who have challenges difficulty suffering which is all of us
no one is immune extending our compassion
may all beings everywhere have ease
may all of us beings everywhere
have grace in the midst of our pain or sorrow or suffering
may we have ease may all beings everywhere including
ourselves be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so care and compassion
so [Music] in this practice we engaged we felt into
a sense of care what i call at the end every day care
just caring caring and then that care can be expressed
as compassion where it meets suffering and there's a
different qualities different nuances to to these flavors
and they're both beautiful they're both lovely and also what i was inviting you to feel
into at the beginning is sometimes when we feel the care of
another being for another being oh that brings up the sense of care in our heart
in in uh yeah it enlivens for us
so there's a lot of invitations in this practice and i am curious
um i'd love to invite you if you wish to share um
reflections questions comments and for the been and this is for the benefit
of both yourself to be held to witness if you'd like
and also for the benefit of the community all questions are important valuable and aha moments
whatever you like to share you can type them in chat also or you can raise your zoom hand
if it's your physical hand i may not see you so friend please
i thank you today i received a
copy of a letter that i wrote 60 years ago to one of my cousins
uh when i was 10. and i could picture myself
at 10 writing that and this is to a cousin who's since been estranged from the family and who i haven't seen in
many years but it it helped me see myself
in the part of the [Music] meditation tonight where we're extending this care to ourselves
which i always find difficulty doing but being able to see myself as that
ten-year-old and seeing the actual handwriting on that letter and actually
recalling the moment 60 years ago when when i did that um
made that much more palpable and accessible to me and um and very sweet
thank you thank you fred so sweet thank you for sharing this how precious to be able to
have access again to this letter um and for it to serve as a way to
access the feeling of turning the sense of care to yourself beautiful thank you
for sharing this and really um bringing the the
um how palpable this is i could feel it in your words so so um i wonder if you have
considered as you practice meta
care compassion all the brahmaviharas for yourself whether
remembering this letter and or put putting it somewhere where you can look at it frequently
the 10 year old's handwriting would be a way in would be a way and
it's it's you know it's as leonard cohen says
uh crack is where the light gets in and this is such a beautiful precious letter
for the light to continue to pour in just a thought
yeah and you're welcome to unmute or not
yeah that's a great idea [Laughter] i'll do that sweet thank you so much fred my
heart is so yeah glad and caring hearing the story exist thank you
yeah any other reflections you can raise your zoom hand you can um
type in chat if you type to everyone i will read your name if you just type
it to me alone i won't read your name but just your the reflection or the question that you sent
anything else that came up for you appreciation coming from
youtube you're welcome thank you for practicing along
our youtube community susan please
yeah well during the meditation i thought of an example of compassion that really touched me then and it did now
and i thought of it and it was watching a video about president carter and habitat for
humanity visiting they were building all these houses for hurricane katrina victims and i remember
it just worn my heart and i felt so good watching that just that them doing this action and then the
reactions of the recipients getting housing again and that they were so
blown away by the kindness of these strangers yeah yeah isn't that
interesting susan yeah someone else's kindness generosity there
their care it just makes us happy right it lights us up we just like your face
was lit up as you were talking about the president carter and habitat for
humanity and i've heard about this i haven't seen the clip but i've heard that even um
as he's been very you know physically aged and and you
know not as young as you but he still continued to do this continuing to care
and serve in this way that's very sweet thanks for bringing that in um jenny
and then we'll have to go we'll go into groups so we'll make this brief yeah
just for that moment i could let go of that moment
now that i didn't have anything else in that moment just that moment and then it wasn't
there and then it was there and then it wasn't and
it's my breath and my desire to be
now in the now that's it
thank you jenny thank you yeah
and jen on youtube says just hearing the worst habitat for humanity and carter lifted my heart ah it's sweet
yeah yeah ah
and here's a reflection coming in today i chose not to drink like i have been doing so happy truly
the pain i have been trying to keep at bay is hard to sit with but you helped me sit gently with it
today thank you for this ah and thank you for bringing yourself for coming to
this container and practicing supporting yourself with this practice the person who sent
me this reflection privately and thank you for being here and supporting others with your
with your practice yeah thank you thanks for being here yeah and and sitting and sitting with
what is hard it's not easy and yet and yet the way
the way towards awakening
to freedom is through the pain is sitting with the pain with kindness and
compassion not around it not it's not gonna go away we all know this yeah
thank you for that so dear ones the time has come
for us to turn to each other and support each other ourselves where the rubber meets
the road in practicing in small groups so i'll make the small groups in a moment
and the invitation is um as always to um
speak from your own experience not managing other people's experience the
group etc but just sharing if you like a couple of words from a few words from your own experience and
if if when your turn comes you want to pass and just hold silent space
[Music] great you can just say pass and hold compassionate caring caring space for
others what a gift your presence as a gift your presence as a gift to others
and let's go with reverse alphabetical order just for the
fun of it and each person will say maybe a word
or two and nugget and then the other person will say nugget and then the third person
and then you'll go around and round maybe a few times and just sharing as
little or as much as you wish about what this was like for you being held witness by others and caring caring
for yourself not not getting in your head like what am i gonna say to be impressive just it's okay
just say little and caring for others so about to open
the rooms with care and kindness here we go okay welcome back everyone everybody's back
the rooms are closed we have just about a minute for any reflections that might have come
up in group so don't be shy
especially especially if you're new
not to put anyone on the spot you can type in chat raise your hand
any insights or we can just close richard
hi i just wondered if you survived the interview with sam harris
if i survived it yes it was intense
[Laughter] i loved it
wasn't wasn't it clear i had a great time we had a great time oh good good i'm glad to hear it
[Laughter] it's sweet yeah
yeah thank you rich um i i was recently interviewed uh by sam harris for his uh app waking up
and uh yeah it's um
sam deeply cares speak speaking of care which is the topic for tonight
um sam deeply deeply cares deeply cares
um both not just for himself and family but for others for their waking up for
humanity for the world he deeply cares and and i really really appreciate that
about him so so thank you all thank you all for
your practice for your care for being here for supporting each other
um supporting yourself may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves