great well hello hello and welcome to happy hour everyone
um I've missed you very much it's so nice to be back in Sangha and practicing
together so so for today's practice
um gosh so many different themes what to um
I think I'd like to explore a theme of simple meta together and maybe not say
so much ahead of time but just practice together take more time to practice and
and explore different themes I have no
doubt different themes from my travel in Southeast Asia especially in the um
uh as I was mentioning earlier Thailand is a Buddhist country and many temples
lots of Buddhist statues and just there's a sense of wholeheartedness there's a sense of kindness Good Will
and interactions that just it drenches it feels like it permeates the the
culture which is so lovely and nourishing so um so I'm sure some of the warmth uh
will come through in the practice so so let's just sit together let's let's begin
foreign arriving in your seat taking your seat
on this Earth on this planet of ours
aching your seat on the Earth here I am
stable grounded here
connected to the seat to this earth
stable and moving even if we're actually hurtling in space on this Earth
rotating around the Sun rotating around this axis but it feels like we're still
ah can we be still here in this moment feel the Stillness
together with all the movement in the space movement in our lives all
the movement that has been is happening right now will be
and in the middle of all the movement open our bodies Our Hearts our minds to
Stillness
holding the duality of movement and Stillness
an opening leaning into the Stillness to the groundedness
relaxing the body softening the body
relaxing the heart relaxing the heart
whatever has happened before up to this moment
perhaps rushing to arrive it's okay it's all right
feeling yourself it's okay dear it's all right sweetheart ah
taking refuge in this moment
letting the breath move through the body
and if the Mind decides to move Wonder
drift rush to a thought memory plan it's okay
it's all right be kind be kind
be kind to yourself to your heart to your mind
address yourself kindly your mind your heart kindly
smilingly Let the Body be at ease relaxed
gently inviting attention awareness to rest again to
take refuge come dear come rest with the breath with the body
it is sweet here it's sweet
we'll get to the plan the memory later it's important though
and we'll come back let go now let's go now dear
taking time taking space no rush
nothing needs to happen no problem solving
so delicious just to be just to Simply Be
this being human foreign
foreign
let the breath be nourishing calming
soothing to the body to the heart
foreign
what a gift to be able to practice
you have met the Dharma in this life
to sit and be breathed by the breath
to realize if the mind is thinking to know that
and cultivate kindness in that moment
I'm not expecting that you will be focused and concentrated and still the
whole time if that happens great but Minds wander it's okay can we be kind no
matter what can we be kind
and if we can't be kind
and we'd be accepting to be accepting be gentle
with lack of kindness that might arise
can we be compassionate to that
and the lack of kindness if any
knowing that we are doing our best
in every moment and cultivating
as best we're able to
foreign
and I like to invite us to explore
receiving kindness and Sharing kindness
so I'll invite or experiment it happened to receiving
kindness which expands the capacity of our heart
not just to receive but to give
so feeling yourself feeling yourself sitting
connections to the Earth through your feet sit bones
your hands touching each other or your lap breath moving through your body
stable now
I'd like to invite you to imagine as you're sitting
you're together with other human circle of people
who are kind endowed with mitta you've been practicing mitta for a long
time
mutiny situation let's say in a foreign country where you don't understand the language
so you can't really communicate but but this human beings other humans
are trying to help you support you maybe you need help you need directions
and you feel you let yourself be supported you feel their meta you let yourself be supported
you can imagine maybe a situation like let's say you're in a store and you've spilled
I'd say some fruit and people come with kindness and help you put it back
or you fall in and they help you get up or whatever it might be there's a sense of kindness and you let
yourself without being embarrassed without any embarrassment
human beings with mitta let yourself be supported
because receiving kindness receiving kindness allowing yourself to
receive kindness it's like receiving a gift graciously
you don't turn the gift around or hurl It to the Ground
it's gracious it's a way of
rewarding The Giver to receive the gift so let
in your mind let the gift of kindness be received
you may be your working with a map and you're confused and somebody unasked comes and supports
you ask you if you're lost and tries to help you find your direction just support
offered this land of beings who've practiced meta
kindness let yourself receive your mind's eye
and maybe you're work here is to receive without an
embarrassment because receiving is giving
so can you give meta by receiving
that's the Crux of this invitation can you gratitude your smile of
appreciation be your gift not shame or embarrassment
we'll come back to the scenario in a moment again but now let's switch
now you are a part of this community maybe you don't communicate with words
you don't understand someone's language but they're lost you want to help them you want
to support someone as an expression of your kindness of your Humanity
it's clear there fumbling with a map they don't know where to go without being asked you ask
them can I help you or with sign language try to figure out where they're going and help them
the act of matter an act of kindness
see yourself giving meta in this way
the sense of satisfaction you've helped one person or helping one human being
was not so different from you you just want to be happy
nor they have spilled say a bag of apples or something
you go and you help them pick them up you comfort them you smile
the random act of kindness
you don't judge them they're doing their best
or maybe you see someone
walking on the street and you're walking too the same direction maybe they have
you can see that they're wearing a splint they have a hand injury and they're trying fumbling with an umbrella
and it's just started to rain
you stop maybe you stop smilingly in this scenario you get the umbrella from them you open
it for them and with a smile you hand it back to them and you keep walking with a smile you're
smiling they're smiling random act of kindness
no judgment just make up random act of kindness
how easy it is the care to notice what's needed
to notice what's needed to take a step to care to share
not questioning not judging yourself or others
random act of matter
maybe in your heart you do say may you be well may you be safe from the elements
may you be happy may you be healthy
may you have ease
how good it feels to give kindness
well now switch again to the other scenario
and again it's so impersonal right you can be the person who needs support
and people stop and support you help you offer kindness
not even needing to speak or exchange words
let yourself receive now be in the receiving end
feel supported let your body relax
seeing others Humanity letting them see your Humanity
maybe imagine the scenario maybe from your own life
maybe in your own City or maybe traveling
let your heart relax let your body relax
let yourself receive in your mind's eye
better random acts of kindness
maybe you imagine again yourself holding a map foreign
carrying bags of groceries puts them down
and comes to support you where are you going are you lost
random act of kindness
now imagine yourself in your hometown or City
supporting helping others whether
they don't speak their language or they do it's random acts of kindness
maybe letting someone who's in a rush seemingly Rush Nina Rush go ahead of you
the line at the grocery store if you're not in a hurry yourself
offering kindness with a smile knowing you've made
one person's day a little better just a little brighter
or say you're maybe sitting on a plane across the aisle there's
a mother with a screaming child she's agitated or embarrassed trying to
quiet the child instead of feeling
upset rolling your eyes you Comfort the mother yes it's hard it is
hard to travel with children it's okay it's all right it's hard
extending kindness so many opportunities
not missing opportunities strangers
colleagues friends family
radiating matter may all beings everywhere including
myself
be safe from inner and outer arm
be happy be healthy have ease
radiating kindness internally to yourself
let it radiate out
60. knowing that this kindness first touches you
first soothes you these rays of kindness
but if we didn't let as business we could
the opportunities that we run into to be kind go by and of course we won't capture all of
them we can't it's okay but turning our heart to receive
kindness and gave kindness
that soothing calming for the heart
enlivening for the mind
and for the last couple minutes just breathing breathing again breaking out
breathing in kindness breathing out kindness
and good will may I be well
may all beings be well
may I be well breathing in May all beings be well breathing out
receiving and giving
as we bring this practice session to close
offering your kindness your meta to yourself and as a gift to all beings everywhere
offering your practice your intention for cultivation spreading it far and wide
in your mind's eye may all beings everywhere
safe happy healthy abids may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
ah well I feel happier and calmer and yeah more more in touch through this
practice with meta how are you doing how how
was it for you any um insights any aha moments any challenges
and you're invited to share your questions comments insights for the benefit of everyone
and all your challenges too so you can raise your Zoom hand
we can also type them in chat if you like
why did you discover how are you how was it
what did you learn Neil
welcome back Ricky um I thought it was um I thought it was interesting um the way
you when you mentioned you know that like accepting thanks and accepting you
know the gifts from the other people is you know kindness in and of itself
you know and there certainly have been plenty of times in my life you know where I'm like no you know and
frequently I have like thought afterwards you know oh you know maybe you know maybe I shouldn't have said no
you know and I you know I think you know I'm hopefully coming up here will you know put me on better footing make me
better prepared the next time that happens yeah yeah thanks Neil thanks so much for
sharing that and and also thanks for highlighting that aspect of of gracious receiving is a
huge gift it's a gift really graciously receiving it gives other people joy to
be able to be kind and to be able to help um and maybe comes up sometimes so we
don't want to trouble them or whatever it is and sometimes it's just yes thank you it's it can be such a breakthrough
moment such a lovely moment of connection and giving and receiving so thanks for highlighting that aspect of
it so important yeah yeah I I'll maybe I'll say one more thing I I've also found myself sometimes
you know somebody wants to offer you know offering a gift some or something whatever it is you're offering something
and I'm like oh oh I'm in trouble you and I realize well actually wait pause yes I accept so it's it's okay in that
moment to to shift and change too but you know as you said it's the practice
that that inclines you to realizing yes what am I doing I'm saying I'm not
giving the opportunity to be kind and generous so so the more we practice meta
the more it gives us that moment of pause like yes yes this is okay let's expand my heart to receive and allow
them to give so yeah it continues to be practice Yeah so
thank you for that yeah yeah any other reflections
questions comments Eileen
hi Nikki welcome back to YouTube and me I have I've been away from here I've been working a lot but um
what what came to my mind is when I'm on a zoom call with people from asanga it's
pretty easy for me to do meta for all the little boxes that I see of all the people or in the breakout room too
um and also when I'm teaching my classes but in a meeting with staff didn't even occur to me today it was very tense and
switching to The Meta practice pivoting like that was really hard because I brought that kind of tense
energy to it so maybe with practice so it'll
get easier no matter what the situation I see yes thank you yes thank you and and Eileen
thanks so much for bringing that up and I want to make an invitation so the invitation is if you notice you know
many times in a stressful situation if you notice right there so so we actually
I'm so glad you you uh pinpointed this particular situation the staff meeting
you know that it's stressful so so so and I trust that you'll have more meetings with your staff so great
perfect this is a great opportunity for practice yay so in the next meeting before you go into you know write your
yourself a note today post it and and put it today so that before that you have set this intention of oh this is an
opportunity that that gets me stressed and it's okay we we each have different occasions uh that that where this
happens and it's and um and and also from the practice you've done you know
that meta actually is an antidote to this kind of this this agitation so in
fact if you bring in metal just choose one person in the meeting just one person do matter for them and then
you'll find yourself oh wow look at this tension shift and change and then the
then it will be easier to do it for others but just start with one person on the screen how does that sound
yeah great thank you so much for raising raising this and so specific this is a
great opportunity for your practice I love it love it yeah uh Paige please
hi thank you for so much for for your for for this evening
um and I was thinking as you're talking about traveling and the kindnesses that people do just automatically and just
how how grateful and just what a wonderful um approach that is what a wonderful way
and um uh and um and I don't know I I guess I can't
really express it in my head but um just to keep doing that all the time you
know just everywhere just being so grateful for for just for the kindnesses that come up and
then and realizing um you don't have to go in with an informed
opinion or knowing anything just being open in trouble it's like everything's fine so it's just actually traveling
around um here for a while for three weeks and that same kind of thing where
just uh he's struggling with a bag or something and somebody you know picks it
up and just realized just how how wonderful it is that there are more people on the planet
welcome back
yeah so much kindness all around right and and we're a part of it we are part
of and we've done that we do that for others but to appreciate to turn our mind to it the more we appreciate it see
it and the more it inclines our mind to see and see it more in others and also
cultivated more in ourselves uh and and be that that support
um or others so yes thank you for that appreciate you sharing your experience also yeah and also I would say um it
would be interesting I I'll take this and say one thing else another point is also to to observe the times that
um we we don't stop to to be kind and that's okay too and and to to observe
you know what are the things that get in the way uh often for many people when they're in their studies when people are
in a hurry when they're in a rush to get somewhere they they they don't stop to
help and support so see that observe that not judge but I get to know really have clear mind ones oh yeah I see that
happening okay so um or if if you don't feel safe or or or
if there's judgment or Rising like and those are things that one can become aware of little by little or maybe this
person doesn't need it or maybe you feel shy about help you know all those things you know those we can study we can have
mindfulness awareness and support them but um it's also I think what I'm trying to say is it's interesting to be aware of
not just when we uh help when we extend our metan and
also the times that we don't and what gets in the way again without judging ourselves but studying it what gets in
the way it's important too so dear ones I'd like to
um invite us all now to engage with each other maybe maybe for tonight the little
conversation we'll have is uh stories stories of random acts of kindness maybe
travel stories if you have any where you've been supported in in the foreign
country or or maybe when you have supported others
um so um and and if not travel stories could
be uh just stories in your own town city just random acts of kindness It's So
uplifting to share these stories so what I'd like to invite in in the breakout groups tonight is on
let's let's go alphabetically and the first person will share you know one
story and the next person will share another little story just not a long 10 minutes but just like a minute or two
it's like this is what happened or maybe 30 seconds depending on how long your story is I I've already shared many
stories tonight weaved them into the the um uh into the guided meditation and
then the next person will share a little nugget of story then the next person they'll come back to you and maybe
you'll be reminded to share another story or or something you've done or you received and and let let us Inspire each
other let us Inspire each other we're sharing these stories of goodness so I've created the breakout rooms and
again as always no um you know no need to uh um you know you're all sharing from your
own experience you're not managing and directing others but um so I think that's enough that's all I
want to say so okay so let me uh hold on let's see here we have the
groups okay I'm going to start the open the rooms okay take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
okay everybody's back the rooms are closed and uh we're at time so I think
what I'd like to do is to to honor people's time and and and close on time
but I'd like to stay a couple of minutes extra after my clothes so if you like to share any
stories or what happened in the rooms I love to hear it's so uplifting so so
let's dedicate the Merit of our practice together may all beings be well may all beings be
free including ourselves
thank you all thank you all see you next week somebody else is teaching this
Friday um uh and I'll see you next week alright take good care