so hello and welcome everyone welcome to this rendition of happy hour lovely to
be with you dear sangha it makes me very happy to see you to see your
faces your square sense of presence was coming together and practicing
so for today's practice um [Music] i'd like to
um bring a
paragraph that i recently read from joan halifax
as an inspiration for us practicing with uh compassion this evening
karuna practice so here is here is the this paragraph from
joan halifax and i'll share it with neil so that he can send it to the google
groups afterwards if you thinking oh i want to hear that again you'll get it later so
so [Music] she says in thinking about trauma and resilience
as i reflect on what is unfolding in our world at this time
from the point of view of systems theory systems that break down have the
potential to reorganize themselves at a higher more robust level of functionality
the experience of breakdown can give one a very deep and optimistic view of the
potential of others to grow from trauma instead of being diminished
this is called post-traumatic growth and refers to the benefit from psychological changes
that can be experienced as a result of the struggle
with challenging life circumstances and can foster greater resilience
we have to remember that people who have survived trauma can come back transformed by the experience
and see that suffering has made them more resilient rather than more fragile
with the ability to thrive in the present rather than being overwhelmed
by the past beyond the ending of the old way of
being there is hope for the emergence of the new
and to imagine a future in which the wounds are still there but
in a form that makes one wiser and humbler
and helps one to thrive
so wiser and humbler and more compassionate i like to add that because
another use of challenge difficulty trauma suffering whatever you want to
call it is us are growing in compassion
not just growing in resilience but also growing in in compassion in wisdom and
compassion for ourselves and for others so i like to use that the as the basis
for our practice tonight it's the use of um
there there is a poem by mary oliver called the uses of sorrow so i think of the uses of sorrow the
uses of challenge the uses of difficulty in our lives to
um refashion us in the more resilient in the more wise
not in a more fragile as she talks about of course but more resilient
pull through post-traumatic growth and growing in compassion
is an important part of the uses of sorrow
the uses of challenges the way that it helps us grow and become more fully human more beautiful more
gracious more kind knowing that all of us have challenges
many lives look perfect perhaps from the outside from
the outside oh yes they don't have problems they have a perfect life they're happy
perfect bodies and minds and jobs and relationships and
knowing what i know and actually our deep wisdom
tells us that suffering
unsatisfactoriness the sword dukkha in pali is part of everybody's life is a mark of
existence as long as you live your human being for
you're an animal your sentient being there is there is there is challenges
there is suffering there is not that everything in the world is dukkha definitely not there are plenty of joys
yes enjoy joy um savor joy
and yes there's also challenges there's tookka which again doesn't necessarily diminish us but helps us
grow in wisdom and resilience and compassion so i've said enough to set the frame
i'd like to invite us to now meditate together so let's settle let's arrive in our sitting
posture so that you can sit or if you need lie
down comfortably for the next 30 minutes
i invite you to close your eyes
if that's comfortable for you
arriving arriving in the body ah
first and foremost embodiment
turning away turning away from thoughts from entanglement
in this moment in time to give our hearts to this practice
to give our hearts this practice
turning the gaze inward the gaze of awareness it is so sweet
the peace within we keep mixing it up
shaking it up no need bowing to all the steering
thank you not now please come back later i'll be waiting for you
and right now ah can we relax can we let go
release into this body into this moment
feeling of the bones
hugging the cushion the chair
you know there is a gecko that has tiny little suction cups
all along its its hands
and feet imagine imagine there were tiny little
suction cups like like the gecko
ah on your bottom on your feet
if you're sitting on a cushion the lower part of your legs wherever there's contact
really really connecting to the earth
connected yes connected stable
stable can release your weight
i let the body release its weight
towards the bones to the feet the legs
rooted well rooted
to the earth and just as we are well rooted
let there be a sense of uplift
uplifting the heart
and uplift through the breath aspiration
the breath being breathed on its own
let it be received in the lower abdomen to calm soothe settle
there's any tension in the next shoulder neck and shoulders your face
your jaw your eyes
anywhere else in the body release with the next out breath
release
one more time taking an in-breath maybe holding for a
few seconds ah
and release landing more deeply and the third time
intentional breathing
holding let's go ah release into the body
now let the breath be natural no controlling holding [Music]
let it be received let the breath breathe
continue like this for a few minutes just to settle before we turn
and as thoughts entanglements her eyes let there be no judgment just clear
seeing smilingly
smilingly let go let go give up
offer up thank you not now dear thought come back
later turning towards the seclusion of the
heart and mind this moment of cultivation
settling peace
and notice if it is possible if it is easy
to allow the breath to to have an image of the breath entering
through the heart center center of the chest to warm up
to prime sense of kindness
associated with the heart center the proverbial heart center
not on the left where the heart is but the center of the chest
maybe if it feels right for you invite you to
put a hand in the center of your chest connecting with yourself
connecting with a sense of kindness
could do well for this being who is you who has the challenges
that you have had or currently have in this life
oh dear oh sweetheart i care for you i wish you ease
holding yourself with care with kindness
now i'd like to invite you to bring to mind something that has been challenging for you
stressful [Music] perhaps not the most traumatic experience
not the 100 pound weight but maybe the 10 or 20 or even 50.
but something that's challenging
and recognizing that this is difficult
this is difficult
this is hard it's not easy anyone
anyone going through the circumstance would
find it challenging
and yet it doesn't diminish you it doesn't make you small
or fragile
it is challenging yes holding it with care with love holding
yourself with care with love
there is strength in compassion as you wish yourself well
of compassion i offer a few
use these or whatever feels appropriate for you may i may i be free
from this challenge is suffering this difficulty
or may i be with it carry it go through it with
grace with ease with as much ease as possible
may i have ease in the midst of this challenge
may i grow in compassion in care and love and wisdom
with respect for respect to myself and others
with this difficulty made open my heart
to care and deeply love myself hold myself tenderly
preciously
to see others caringly compassionately
for their challenge their suffering
holding oneself holding yourself with love and care
as a beloved being as a beloved compassionate being with
no judgment
just as you hold yourself with care with love with tenderness
also realizing your own resilience
your own strength
yes the challenge is here and yet you're not defined by it
there is so much more beauty
goodness mystery to you and just this challenge
this difficulty
yes this is hard this is challenging i love and care for myself and yet and
yet there's so much more to me to this being who is me
now let us invite invite to our
mind's eye others in the world we may know them we may not know them
personally who have suffered or
are suffering or feeling challenged in the same way that we have we are
it's okay to use our imagination imagine other beings other people
we know we're not alone in this
so inviting all the beings hundreds thousands tens of thousands
millions
of beings are challenged in the same way and
sharing our compassion our care may all of us
may all of us have ease with our challenge in the midst of our
challenge may we be free
from the sorrow this pain
may we be with it go through it with grace
with kindness
all dear beings just like me you suffer just like me
i see you in my mind's eye there may be a child
an older person so on another continent
different race different language nationalities
all of us siblings in this way they may not know you
and yet we are connected in this way i wish you well i wish you ease
as i wish it for myself
this is hard friends isn't it this is hard
they understand they know
they feel your pain you feel theirs
if we could make all the suffering be eased suffering for all
all of you all the beings who suffer in this way all of us
i'm expanding the circle of compassion of care
to include not just those who are challenged in the same way you are but in different ways
all beings all beings with their unique challenges
or not so unique challenges similar
tuka you may not know them but everybody has them
friends family loved ones strangers
people you have challenges with everyone
oh dear beings
if i could make it all go away be eased
may we all have ease
and just as we hold everyone all beings
in this practice with kindness with compassion
wishing ease freedom grace with suffering also knowing that
none of us is defined by limited
to or pain or sorrow
there's so much more magnificence to each and every one of us
then our pain
may our suffering our pain open us up
the compassion more compassion for ourselves and others
feeling with feeling our pain their pain
may we all grow in wisdom all of us
and for the last moment of this practice period
holding with kindness whatever arose or did not arise
no need for judgment you showed up and did your best that's
enough we're planting seeds planting seeds
don't know when they will flower all we can do is to plant them
we can't force them to flower under our timetable
offering the seeds you have planted this goodness co-created all of us
together in the sangha offering this goodness may be a cause
for ease for happiness for freedom
for all beings everywhere may all things be happy
may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes
for reflections comments
questions aha moments anything that might have opened up for you
or is challenging it's all welcome i'd like to share reports from the field
for the benefit of yourself being held witness and everyone's benefit
we uh as you already know we benefit from each other's practice
so in that spirit of offering generosity offering your practice to
others anyone would like to share what did you notice what was different
here what came up you can also type in chat if you type to
me privately i will not read your name
and if you type them to everyone then i will read your name also one private reflection i'm grateful for
my compassion toward myself and others beautiful two for one compassion and
gratitude love it being grateful for compassion that is just lovely
for yourself and others get uh oops
um nikki i have a question um can you speak to the role of the
noticing the feeling tone in holding difficult emotions which
i remember during the meditation that it can be a way of simplifying
stories and um bringing things from potentially overwhelm to something
that we can hold because it is feeling tone and not all the interpretations stories and
other narratives that might come with it but i don't remember much more it just occurred to me suddenly and it came in
quite helpful but i might be representing that incorrectly yeah yeah i'm so
uh glad you brought that in guitar yes um that is one way to simplify
especially if the mind sometimes might fall in to sink into the storyline and
if it's a really heavy storyline then one can stay with um
so i would say multiple things there's the feeling tone which is the vedana and that's what you're referring to so it's
just unpleasant just very ever so simply unpleasant
this is unpleasant holding the unpleasantness there's also staying with the feeling
right staying with the feeling so i'm expanding on what you said there's also staying with the feeling and the feeling
then there's the feeling in the body the feeling of maybe heaviness contraction in the heart
sadness you know there could be like these various feelings or emotions well actually they're too
bifurcating more there's the feelings in the body and then there's the emotions in the mind and of course there's interaction
there so so um letting go of the storyline yes very
helpful but there there there are different levels one can attend to
i said oh poor me this is awful this is terrible why me yeah definitely let go of that i'm so glad you brought this up
for everyone's uh benefit and then it could be just like oh this is this is hard this is
hard this is ah sad disappointed whatever the emotion
might be and then another layer of feeling in the body what's happening in the body or even
then going even one level simpler which is the feeling tone so all of these are available
and whatever is skillful to work with yeah thank you guita
um [Music] jamie says thank you for helping me touch the most tender most wonderful
parts of myself and see they can be gifts ah lovely thank you jamie
beautiful yeah
um marianne says it was relaxing to think about how anyone would be challenged by a
stressful circumstance yes another question comes on youtube
how can i have compassion towards home doing mean things and very
egotistic so how can you have compassion towards people who have harmed you
[Music] that for that one needs to separate
the actions from the humanity because they've done actions to harm and you do
not condone the actions and yet they're hurting it's often said
that hurt people hurt people so you feel you open up to their their hurt and you
feel compassion for them and you don't have to condone the actions or even forgive the actions but you can be in
touch with the humanity there fossil says this was a challenging day
at work with your instructions at the end of the meditation though what happened is okay
may the seeds of practice bear fruit in life whenever they may
yeah yeah beautiful thank you for sharing that
appreciate that for everyone yeah it's okay may the seeds of practice bear fruit and life
whenever they may yeah it's all okay
beautiful so dear friends
let's transition at this point let us transition
to um small groups where our practice from the
cushion with our eyes closed compassion for not available
[Music]
this small groups as i was making the breakout groups in a moment remember please speak
just from your own experience um not commenting reflecting managing the group
or other people's experience not asking probing questions just speak from your first person experience
and each person if you have five nuggets you want to share just share one in the first round you'll say something
the next person will go in alphabetical order the next person will say
something and then the third person will say something there are three people then you'll go around and around again speaking just
from your own personal experience and having a sense of meta compassion for
yourself and others these are fellow practitioners in this space
practicing just like you you may not know their challenge but can you and also if it comes to you you
can say pass you don't have to speak you can say pass and you can just hold
uh compassionate space it's perfectly fine if you're feeling quiet or if you want to witness
for a few rounds so so um and remember be kind to yourself be
kind to yourself be kind to others this is such a precious
opportunity to practice kindness and be embodied easiest way to actually
monitor what you're saying is to be embodied see what it feels like in the body if you feel like oh i'm saying this
to impress like oh yeah maybe i don't want to say this i just want to stay with my experience stay humble stay
close to your experience so and again you're speaking for your own benefit not to educate or impress
anyone very important so creating the rooms take care of yourselves
take care of each other here okay everyone's back the rooms are closed so
we have just about a couple of minutes for any insights any last words maybe reports from
um the uh the groups any insights
and type in chat or raise your hand don't be shy especially if you haven't spoken
picky thank you nikki um could you expand a little bit on the
feeling um how to bifurcate feelings and be
authentic with how you're feeling not reactive i i was trying to
process that a bit yeah there are two different questions here okay you're asking so let me help me
understand which there's not being reactive and there is the question about bifurcating the feelings and like
say your question clearly again so when you were speaking before it it
seemed that i understood it but when i started to try to talk about it i realized i hadn't
okay okay so what was i talking about all right that's a clear question okay
maybe the person who asked it could say but it was about staying like i get it i
get it let me say one more time so so so the idea is you know there is the um
storyline right oh actually let me change the settings in the chat i see hold on here we
go the the um the reflections um you know there's there's
with what is happening there is often a storyline like oh i'm sick this is hard it's terrible my back hurts like you're
right there's a storyline right there's a story line and then there's often second arrows why i mean like there's
all that and then there's actually let's say your back hurts there's the physicality of it
and then there is a kind of a sadness oh i really wanted to go play tennis like i can't do that right there's just these
different levels right so letting go of the storyline
and just feeling the physicality of the pain right which is unpleasant has a
unpleasant feeling tone right there
or and also perhaps just the so there's physicality of it and then there's the
emotional uh sense oh there's sadness there's sorrows like oh this is heavy oh and
that also has a feel an unpleasant feeling tone if you wanted to feel that
but whichever way you go which you can choose any of those you can
choose the physicality you can choose the emotion you can choose the feeling tone or all of them together let go of
the story that's the bottom line clear now thank you
you're welcome great so um let's see
ah very quickly i'll read a few reflections lovely lovely lovely chat in my group um
oh daniel apologizes to jerry and bill my mic is not working just sharing that
because the chat was to me not to everyone um thank you for wonderful beautiful groupies oh that's sweet
going to take up the practice of not educating others with speech i'm going to fail a lot so it should be fun oh
that is sweet i appreciate the humility there all right dear ones thank you for
practicing for yourself for others may you all be well made all of us all
beings everywhere may we all be free
[Music] thank you
and