hello everyone and delighted to be here with you and to
greet you all and see many of your greetings in the chat and
thank you there's a
fascinating teaching that
maybe came from the thai meditation teacher ajahn cha i'm not sure the origin of it
but that is the idea that has to do with sound any kind of sound
and the idea is that sounds never bother us
but we bother sounds and how i understand that is that
sounds are just uh sounds that go through
but uh the problem the botheredness where we get bothered has to do a lot
has to do with our reaction to it our reactivity and ideas around it
there are exceptions to this of course people are highly sensitive or people or
sounds that are just so glaringly painful that
that it seems like they hurt our ears or other things but generally
this idea that sounds uh are kind of neutral
and this is particularly true with the words people speak
the meaning of the words might not be neutral but the words as sound
are neutral and somewhere in the
ears that hear the sound between the sound and the ears
there's a there's something that gets involved something happens there a meaning is assigned
memory is about the words and the meaning come into play the relationship we have my behalf to
the person who's speaking them comes into play predictions of the future and what those words might mean and
and then becomes this complicated world in the middle of which there is some place we get knotted we get entangled
we're caught in it we're hanging on to that branch on the edge of the river as we
uh canoe down so um so to learn the art
of not being not being knotted up not being reactive to our senses
is one of the great arts of mindfulness practice it doesn't of course mean that we are
oblivious or indifferent to what happens in the world it means that
we have we can come into kind of a balanced place or a free place
where our response is a response not a reaction uh where we can see clearly
what our inner ideas thoughts impulses are and choose wisely
how to act including not giving in to
nodding up getting entangled with it all so to hear sounds
and so um
so this is true with all our scent stores it's the eyes the ears the nose the
tongue and the body and today i'd like to focus on the body
and in this kind of ability to to discern
the sensations in the body the knowing of the sensation and the entanglement
that um that we might get involved with it so to begin
you might uh just very simply close your eyes
and find a and some of you have done this before but
please do it again so find a neutral place in your body
and uh it could be the hands maybe the hands are touching each other or the hands are touching
your thigh or your knees and
find a neutral spot in your body and
some place where you're not so likely to get entangled or have a lot of opinions or ideas
but that you can feel the sensations are there
and feel the sensations in that part of your body
so if it's in the hand feel the pulsing the tingling the vibration
the warmth the coolness
feel how the sensations might be different in the fingers in the palm
in the back of the hand
and then as you're aware of the sensations in your body in this neutral place
how neutral are you are there judgments ideas
for or against the sensations or the attention with the sensations
is there reactions
now as you exhale
relax your whole body best you can
soften the body
soften the mind as you exhale
settling into just being here putting aside ideas of what you have to
do or should do in favor of the exhale
where you let go relax settle
breathing in and breathing out relaxing and softening
and maybe you can't let go of everything but maybe you can soften
the tensions in the mind soften the places of anxiety
desire [Music]
of ill will
or maybe simply the strong tendency to think on every exhale
relax settle soften
doing it gently even kindly
relaxing and softening on the exhale
and relaxing on the exhale and seeing if you can be
gentle and receptive to the inhale with no ambitions
no standards that you're measuring yourself against and allowing yourself to be aware
of the inhale in whatever way it happens
on the exhale
letting go into the exhale as if you're letting go into the very
end of the exhale to where the things come become quiet and still
before the inhale begins
and as you're with your breathing the sensations of the body breathing
notice if there's any ways in which you're knotted or entangled
reactive caught up in
some idea or preference about the breathing
and appreciate that that is your addition
the extra part to breathing
it's possible to breathe with no entanglement necessary
but if there is
know it as entanglement know it as a knot gently softly
non-judgmentally
but perhaps softening it as you exhale
with the mindfulness the tension hanging out with your breathing
and if there's any reactivity any ways that you are caught or entangled in
breathing bothered by breathing bothered by anything
let that be part of the bigger picture of what you accompany
as you accompany the present moment as you accompany breathing
not being bothered even by being when you're bothered
just knowing it and breathing
[Music]
if you are lost in thinking
chances are that there's some kind of subtle or big ways in which you are caught in it
entangled knotted can you relax the knot
untie it
and if you can't that's okay just know it
just know that you're knotted and caught and continue breathing with it through
it let breathing
be your support
to either freeze you from being caught or gently highlights that you are
and if you are don't be bothered by it
breathe with it gently softly
sooner or later in the practice of meditation
we can become mindful enough
to notice how we get caught up in things entangled
and reactive
to things we see things we hear things we smell things we taste
things we feel in the body things we think
things we emote
and at some point we begin having a new relationship to those entanglements
those attachments the way we're caught up
and that is one that we don't necessarily no longer believe in the value
of being entangled and caught we know there is something better
and we know it doesn't work to get entangled in our entanglements
to be reactive and bothered
by the ways that we are bothered or reactive
and this begins to give us a taste of freedom the freedom of leaving things alone and
not being further entangled just knowing
what's happening
and this ability is invaluable in our social lives
to be able to
not give in or stay caught or behave speak from our reactivity
but to see it and be able to stay balanced relaxed
clear and if we can do that or as we begin
doing this better and better it becomes clearer more obvious
that the practice we're doing is beneficial for others it frees them from our reactivity
and may it be that this practice that you does in fact support and help and
others maybe all beings may it be that this community of ours
with so many people coming here in seven a.m sitting
and collectively we are making a difference in the world
that a known and unknown ways we spread peace
safety happiness and freedom
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may each of us contribute to this
being possible
[Music]
so my friends
there's a delightful for me little teachings in buddhism that
that it's possible to become omniscient but it's not what maybe you think
that it's possible to know something about everything
and what is it that that omniscience is is that
it's not worth clinging to anything
so now we know something about everything but there's certain kind of omniscience
so but but kind of continuing on this theme of some kind of
omniscience and for our human experience
all human experiences we have no matter how sophisticated and complex they are
have comment have a common denominator and that is we know it
through one of the six cent stores the ancient analogy of the time of the
buddha was that if you had a walled city
with only one gate coming into the city then a
guards a guard would stand be at the gate and could watch everyone coming and
going and would decide who can come in and who can go out
if there were six gates then there might be six guards you're doing
the same thing so we have six doors six gates which all experiences that we process
that we take in that we use to understand our life and all that
and we have six doors six gates and that's seeing the gates of the eyes the ears
the nose the tongue the tactile body and then the mind or
that from which we kind of observe or know what's happening in the mind
and so we take in the data from these the sense data the
experiences and then somehow we process it we do something with it
and sometimes we build whole universes with it
there's a story zen chinese story of a painter very realistic painter
who paint very realistic paintings and he was up close painting a tiger
and and involved in the details but at some point he stepped back some feet to look
at it it was so realistic he became frightened and he ran away
so we ourselves our mind is constructing stories ideas memories
predictions of the future meaning um elaborations ideas creativity poems
and songs and all kinds of things our mind creates and we can live in that inner world
but for uh and get lost in it but in buddhist practice what we're
trying to do is live at the doors be mindful of things as they appear and
occur in the present moment at each of the senstors and the reason for that is if you do
that then you know something about everything you know the common denominator everything that's going to happen
is going to be built on those things coming in from those sense doors
and if you can be there and see at that point what the reactivity is the clinging the
resistance how how we relate to it it gives us a tremendously wonderful
vantage point in which to live a wise life to not get caught up in the
entanglements and reactivity and build universes of tigers that frighten
us because we just kind of don't don't not there at the start the beginning point
and in some ways our life is always beginning over and so to bring ourselves into the sense
doors and really be present for it we're there at the start of the life it's always starting in the present starting
over again and over again and and so
to be able to get right there and see it now remember that
uh in this teachings that we're doing now in the sixth sense stores and the entanglement to them
we're coming near the end of a long series of practices of the sati patana sutra
so this is not a beginner's practice this is something that we can begin to do when we've gotten quiet and still
enough or focused mindfulness is strong enough we can really stay there and see it
and the advantage of doing so is like this and
we have a garden with garden beds and
and so i'm kind of responsible for right now because my wife is away she's usually the gardener
and one of the flower beds is overgrown with maybe a foot and a
half tall mostly oat grass and or some kind of tall grass
and all kinds of other weeds and it's packed in the flower bed you know all these must be very fertile the bed because
it's just like bursting forth and over whelming you know how thick it's full of
weeds we have another bed that
where there's some onions and some lettuces and things and
and there there is not so much there's almost no weeds at all
the lettuce and the onions are growing nicely and there's space between them
and there if a weed arises i see the little weed coming up out of the soil
and i'm not overwhelmed by that i come over and pull it out and um and it doesn't grow to be a big
weed to crowd out what we're trying to grow there so um
so the same thing with our mind if we haven't uh weeded our mind
for decades it can be crowded and overgrown with all kinds of weeds and it takes a
while to relax and settle and calm down to the point where we start seeing the
beginning of a weed the beginning of the entanglement and if we see at the beginning of it at
first arising then we could let go of it we can pull it out by the
roots and and put it in the compost pile and
and so this is part of as practice deepens and we have the ability to be much more present
and we trust being present more than we trust the thinking and predicting and
planning and remembering and reviewing and having conversations or having fantasies
we trust being in the present moment things become clear enough our flower
beds become clear enough we see the beginning of a weed arising a beginning of a react
reaction reactivity arising and that is a powerful place to be
because if you see it arise then it's easy to let go of it or not participate or let it be
and it's possible to let it be and let it go and not see it no you're not going to pick it up again
and this is the instructions for this particular part of the satipatana sutta
it is to know the scent store
no no you know like today we're talking about the body no the tactile body
know the sensations of the touch the object of the tactile experience
know the arising of an entanglement
no letting it go and know that you're not going to pick it up again
so that's really the exercise of this this point part part of the satipatthana
sutra is to be able to be present for the sense experience
and to see the beginning of attachment the beginning of clinging react
and to be able to put it down if you can't put it down it's powerful just let it be
don't pick it up don't get involved and then know you're not going to get involved again
you know at least this time around and this keeps us in this beautiful
wonderful place of freedom keeps us in this place where where maybe we're kind of amused or
delighted or relieved when we see an attachment arise a clinging and entanglement rise
because we know we're not going to get entangled to the entanglement we're not going to react to the reactivity
but rather we're going to see the beauty the wonderfulness of being aware of its arising that there
it is and it can be for some people kind of amusing kind of delightful
kind of um faith it can give birth to a lot of faith and confidence
that oh here i got here i got i'm starting to get annoyed
i'm starting to be frustrated or and there it is here's me wanting it to be different
here's me wanting to get to stay forever there's that little clinging going on
and we say oh wow there's the clinging and there's kind of just joy
and knowing we're not going to get involved and knowing that there's freedom and space around it
it's a very different relationship to clinging and reactivity than oh no this is terrible i shouldn't be doing this
so the scent stores and uh so today we talked about i talked
about the technical sense door of things touching our body
and that can be physical things outside things outside but also from the inside out there's
kind of sensate experience the body can reveal
so today i would encourage you to spend more time with mindfulness of your body
and and discover both the delight of being grounded in your body maybe
but more importantly for this exercise today look and see how you're entangled
judgments expectations disappointments with the body how you compare your body
to other bodies or to how you were before how you might be in the future all the
ways you get entangled and see if you can notice the entanglement with such clarity
that maybe you're delighted or amused or maybe you believe that you see it
see if you can find a different way of relating to the bad news
of being reactive and entangled where mindfulness clear mindfulness
brings a different way of relating mindfulness to the body
it's a way of becoming friends with your body when you stop the reactivity