so we'll sit this morning i'll offer you this morning a guided meditation on metta
and the idea is to connect to
whatever way you can to the notion of goodwill it could be that
it's simply the intention the aspiration the well-wishing that
you can formulate it could be a feeling of warmth or
appreciation or love that radiates from you outwards
i'll offer you a simple use of the imagination to
evoke it a little bit more but to begin
it's also helpful to use the mindfulness practice
to drop in deeply into your body
into for a few moments to hold the breathing that holds maybe not the right word to
receive the breathe the breathing
with uh care as if the rest of your body
was receiving with love with kindness
with uh support receiving within a field of safety and
goodwill and warmth and kindness receiving the sensations of
breathing so we'll start there and then we'll do an active imagination and
we'll kind of continue with the simple phrases of loving kindness
so to take a meditation posture
to sit in a way that feels
upright and open
the idea is to assume a posture of a little bit of
embodiment of presence of
as if the posture itself expresses the confidence
that you're really here confidently
here this time at this moment
and to gently close your eyes
and then as you exhale relax and soften the whole body
as you exhale softening around the shoulders relaxing
the shoulders
as you exhale a rather unambitious
relaxation of the belly not trying too hard or
and perhaps there's some softening in the face
in the eyes in the jaws
sometimes the face carries with it our attitude and our drive
to think and to want or to defend
to let the face take take some rest
nothing needs to be expressed through the face right now
and ever so gently allowing the exhale
to relax meaning maybe allow the exhale
to be a fuller release near the end of the exhale
it doesn't have to be much just a fraction
and maybe there's a fuller exhale if gently you take a little bit deeper
inhale it doesn't have to be much
and with a deeper fuller release in the exhale
see also if you can relax your thinking
not necessarily letting go of your thoughts but quieting your thinking
relaxing the muscles associated with being in the control tower of thinking
or for those that fear is an issue relaxing the watchtower of thinking
and then as if the whole body
maybe it's a cozy warm easy chair
or a cozy warm safe cabin
in the midst of this cold weather outside
and in your easy chair resting back or in your
cabin of your body
let the body receive the changing sensations of breathing
maybe as if there's care kindness
that envelops this particular sensations of inhale as inhale begins
and exhale
perhaps an inner softness gentleness that surrounds
the sensations of breathing that receives them holds them
no matter how the breathing is
comfortable or uncomfortable there's a wider field of the body
that is able to receive and hold softly accept
allow maybe even have a quality of
love and compassion the breathing itself
and then within your body see if if it's accessible
see if there's a place that you associate with warmth and goodwill
kindness maybe a tenderness softness
within
and perhaps the breathing
can move through that tenderness
or wash across it
and from a tender place within bring to mind using your imagination
some person that's easy for you to have good will
someone you respect someone you care for and
love or appreciate deeply
it doesn't have to be someone you might most obviously love
it could be someone that you very much appreciate and it's easy to have a kind regard for
them and bring to mind maybe
this person may be imagining when they're there's a smile on their face or they
look happy
they have the potential for happiness and well-being
and then keeping this image or keeping the idea of this person in mind
maybe with the breathing breathing from your tender
place breathing towards the person back and forth
you can repeat these phrases that i say
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be healthy
may you be free
yeah and we'll do it again and the last word of each sentence
let that say it during the exhale
as if you're dropping a pebble in a pond dropping this word into the core of your
being and letting it reverberate outwards
the warmth the glow the goodness that it evokes
it goes in the direction of the person that you're directed you're having your
good goodwill
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be healthy
may you be free
feeling your body feeling whatever softness and tenderness
there is within that can be receptive and open
with tender care tender appreciation
goodwill as we do this practice
have a very low bar for perfection
that whatever way you're doing it can do it is perfect
feeling your body maybe again
the sensations of breathing received in a soft caring
field within the body
relaxing on the exhale
quieting the mind on the exhale
and now bring to mind yourself
maybe at a time in your life when you were happy when you had a smile on your face
or a sparkle in your eye or were any ease
in your being appreciating your potential for
well-being
and now you can say these phrases
keeping yourself in mind wishing yourself well
seeing whatever good will you can have for yourself
so you can repeat may i
be happy
may i be safe
may i be healthy
may i be free
sometimes if you hear second hand that some person has
good will for you appreciation for you it can feel very nice to feel this
to know that there's someone out there who thinks well of you
in the way that you might appreciate that
see if you can allow yourself to appreciate whatever good will you have for yourself
and saying these phrases again with the last word
being dropped in to the core of your being
and letting the associations the feelings associated with these words
reverberate within
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i be safe
may i be free
and to whatever degree you might feel or a sense of good will
well-wishing tender kindness
warmth for your friend person you appreciate or for yourself
breathe with that appreciate that however small it might be
in whatever way it's accessible for you
in the body and the heart and the mind in your thinking or your feeling
and then to open up
to open up this goodwill as if you're
turning on a light bulb or opening all the windows in your home
and have it now spread out to wish goodwill to all beings
everywhere
no limitations no barriers
just an open broad spectrum's broad
feeling sense thought of goodwill for all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be healthy
may all beings be free
and then imagining that firsthand or secondhand or third
hand that your goodwill it becomes known by everyone in the
world so many people out there who could use
support kindness good will
and how encouraging it would be for them to know that they are not forgotten
and as if your good will actually reaches them just acknowledge that you have good will
repeat these phrases again and as you say the last words
let your mind become quiet really still as if in the silence of the mind
the word can radiate outwards
that quality and touch the hearts of all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be healthy
and may all beings be free
and as we come to the end of this sitting
may it be that all beings
can experience your good will and kindness your love and care
while at the same time you make yourself safe for them
you help them be free from you
that your love and care has no strings
no requirements nothing sticky
may it be that you are a safe person
who allows every gives everyone their freedom
freedom from you
and maybe they will give freedom to freedom to you
and you can meet together in freedom
one of the cleanest and clearest ways for people to
love each other in the medium of their freedom
thank you so then we come now to the last talk of
metta the brahmavihara
and when this brahmavihara becomes strong
when this meta becomes strong it's said to be immeasurable or without boundaries limitless
spreading out in all directions and um
so you find we find in the teachings of the buddha that it seems the buddha
held loving kindness up to very important way to live a person's
life that it's a reference point or it's a teacher for us to uh
that to be kind or have good will in our speech
to have it in our actions to other people if we have to have difficult words with
someone that buddha said first make sure that you have good will
in yourself prepare yourself for that and have good will for the conversation
and if there's no good will then that becomes your teacher that becomes the material for
mindfulness and really see what's going on there chances are if there's no good will that
you're not really granting other people their freedom giving them their freedom
and i like to think that the freedom that buddhism is championing the liberation
that buddhism is about is less your liberation
that you become liberated and more that you give liberation to all things that all things
now become free of you and
so freedom so good will cultivating goodwill is a
very helpful it's healing it's developing it's a wonderful way to
develop a kind of a a
non-striving non conceited
approach to doing mindfulness practice to meditation to develop concentration and mindfulness uh in a field of
goodwill and have that as a background and as marvelous as
goodwill is as strong as it become
it is also associated with the buddhist path of liberation
and in a variety of steps along the way as the meta practice deepens
that the liberation is part of it the first that uh
emphasized by the buddha was that when the when one's good will is strong
one is liberated from ill will with when good will is strong there's no ill will
so no hostility and now the wood actually says it's not possible to have any ill will
aversion hostility if there is a meta
so to cultivate and develop meta to get a hang of it and understand it and make it have it accessible
it helps us to be free of ill will and this idea of making it accessible
being familiar with it developing a habit almost a habit or
practicing it developing it thinking about it so that when you need it it's available
you know how to find it in yourself or to evoke it in a genuine way in a way that's really
has integrity to it not something that is uh kind of a just a
surface coating of ourselves and um
as a meta meditation if we do this as a meditation practice as it deepens
then at some point a person that could do with any good meditation practice eventually becomes
liberated freed from the hindrances and this is a really appreciated
tremendously in the tradition so much though it's called a kind of a preliminary liberation
to no longer be caught in the hindrances and it means that when the mind is no longer
under the sway of desires and aversions and sloth and
torpor and restlessness regrets and doubt and to have the mind no longer under its
way no longer under the power of those is a phenomenally wonderful way of being
and it clears the heart it clears the mind and then loving kindness has a
clear feel to develop and now it could develop much more uninterruptedly
and it can deepen and deepen and as a meditation practice it can become boundless as i read yesterday
in all directions and when the lovingkindness becomes quite strong comes kind of all pervading
or fills us or this is not ultimate this is not the end
of the path in buddhism so it's important if you want to do the buddhist path to liberation
to not take experiences of boundless love where
some people have these wonderful feelings of love or good will or kindness that have no object but seems
to radiate in all directions it just seems like everything is touched like midas is touch
everything is touched with our good will our love our kindness and it's sometimes called
in the tradition it's called wet love and moist love and they have kind of everything gets
moistened by our good will and a kindness but to go further
this loving kindness practice when done well and strongly is can be a foundation
for liberation itself and and so to not stop at uh there but go
further there's a story in the ancient texts of a disciple of the buddhist buddha
sariputta visiting a man who was dying and
and taught him the practice of the brahma viharas to practice these
and the man was able to practice him quite deeply and was able to die in this beautiful state of
one of the brahmaghara's goodwill or compassion and
when the buddha heard about this he told sariputta something like a parapher phrase it well
that was nice but actually why didn't you teach him
liberation as well because that man was poised ready to really set his mind free
and so it's possible to do love and kindness and then
go one step further and really do the ultimate act of kindness for oneself or for the world
and that is to really let go and be liberated in a very deep way
and it's a letting go of the every remnant every trace every
foundation within us of the forces within us that lead to suffering
so letting go of clinging makes room
for love more love and the fundamental letting go liberation is letting go of clinging
and without clinging then what is there what's available what sensitivity is
there what receptivity what what feelings and connection do we have to the world
and so to use loving-kindness as a basis for liberation
one of the one of the ins it requires a variety of insights and one of the insights is when the mind
is very very still abiding in love imagine that that everything the mind feels and touches
and experiences is touched with kind of love for everywhere it's like that characterizes the mind
very stable but then to have an insight that
this also is conditioned this also is kind of a kind of a certain way constructed
not to make it the absolute like this is the nature of the universe this is the nature of the cosmos that everything is
love it can feel that way but in the buddhist meditation we don't want to end there
but to see oh this too in some deep way is a construct is a
is a a movement of the mind activity of the mind to
experience this to have it this way and seeing it as being a construct and
seeing it as being impermanent seeing it as being inconstant seeing that it there are there are there
is something beyond it or between it or underneath it that has vast space
where the deep letting go of clinging can happen and so um
or to have in doing that to have some sense that there is something more
as profound and ultimate as great love can be in deep meditation practice very stable
there comes an intuition a sense that there is something else
there is freedom and that freedom
uh you know is not a thing it's the absence of clinging
and and to be there at this tremendously
pleasant enjoyable safe satisfying healing place of love
and then to understand that oh there i can let go further
that whatever sense of self i have who's the one who loves that's not quite the end of the path
there's something beyond that sense if i just put that down and have no self-referencing
if i last little kind of leaning into it and wanting it letting go there's something more beyond
love and in a certain way even love drops away completely the good will this boundless
field drops away in liberation
and this place of radical non-clinging is one of the safest most wonderful and
peaceful places that a person can ever experience it's the culmination of a wish to
be free of suffering and to know that freedom
and to come back without clinging then the good will we've been cultivating and
developing then that good will can feel connected to others can feel
open to others can have love for others compassion and good will and
and there's no need no desire no clinging to need to get something back from
someone else to rely for other people for our safety or our security our
status our admiration our sense of worth
our sense of satisfaction our pleasure that then the love this beautiful thing
we can offer our love to the world and the love is safe
people are free from us in our love and this is a this is a
fantastic thing to be able to love and the love itself carries with it
the gift of freedom where everyone becomes free
of us so it's a deep interconnection
without any need and then people can be as they are
and if they become free then as i said earlier one of the one of the really wonderful things
is when two free people meet in love in good will and kindness
each one either one needing something from the other but each one being able to delight and
enjoy each other and their good will between them
so thank you that's our week on metta and
lovingkindness and then on monday we'll begin with the next brahmavihara
which is karuna compassion and i wish you all well and
may you spend this weekend maybe reflecting thinking talking about
and practicing with loving kindness and goodwill
wherever you go thank you
you