so hello and welcome everyone it's lovely to be with you to feel your
presence different places in the world that we all are
and yet coming together in this heart space together to practice together to cultivate
to share our humanity with each other so
so for tonight's practice um
i would like to bring in a practice that is near and dear to my
heart and many of you know this already it's no news and it's a way that actually this
practice enlivens life enlivens the way we live
enlivens the way we love enlivens the way we interact it awakens us
right here and right now and that practice is the practice of
mindfulness of our mortality being aware not with fear not with trepidation but
yeah of course there's impermanence of course there's impermanence
and bringing that awareness bringing perspectives from
our impermanence that this life of mind this being this precious
being who is me is impermanent this
lovely being who is me with all their gifts with their
aspirations with their challenges with their difficulties in life oh yes this
being this being there's a sense of impermanence to really feel into that
sense of impermanence and let that be an opening and opening
to loving more deeply loving ourselves more deeply this being oh sweetheart yes this
is not forever you're not forever loving ourselves more deeply and loving
others because in the light of impermanence everything can become more precious not
less valuable not oh throw away but actually more precious more sacred
so i'd like to say that tonight's perhaps is um tonight's theme
maybe i would say is love and death love and death
enlivened loving more deeply caring more deeply
through knowing our impermanence so
so i'll be offering a guided meditation tonight um
and in many ways we can think of guided meditations and actually an act of
meditation or any act of actually being in the world is an act of perception act of
perception the way we perceive ourselves the way we perceive the world
this idea of perception is fundamentally important
and we can have perceptions that are helpful we can have perceptions that are not helpful
to happy towards peace happiness service for ourselves and others
so with the guided meditation i will offer tonight
the intention is to bring up to invite to encourage particular ways of
perceiving particular perceptions
particular perspectives that lead to perceptions
and doing this
encouraging these perceptions to arise these helpful perceptions to support us in our life in
our loving in our being i will guide us through
a say as as we often do um
here and happy hour with some invitations with some
um perspectives taking on perspectives
and these perspectives just to say um
as i will guide you will become clear in a moment as i will guide you through this practice but just to say a few
preparatory moments preparatory remarks and then i think what i will do is so
you know i will be locking the zoom room tonight because i want i don't want people to join late tonight this is a
comprehensive meditation and if you happen to drop out it'll be you won't be able to join back so you know this
um so with the invitations that i will make in no way
uh will is there a um an intimation that
they are true that you know that there is life after death there is no life
what we don't know i haven't been there to come and tell you so i don't know so so we take this on as a as exercise the
way you for example if you're an athlete you would imagine hitting the ball just
to bring up a sense of oh what is it like or when you're practicing loving
kindness you see your loved one and you see your connection to them or you see yourself
through their eyes to bring up particular perceptions so in the guided meditation at some
point i will invite you to perhaps see yourself to see yourself as oh
having died from the other side again not to assume there is another
side there maybe there may not be let's be agnostic but these are devices i'm using these
devices in this guided meditation to bring up particular perspectives okay
and particular perceptions that may support us right here right now in
our life right here right now okay we're good with that
yes i've set it up okay great no assumptions no not positing anything
just trying to use skillful means to open up our
perceptions to open up our perceptions
okay so with that i invite you to get settled and i'm
going to lock the room now here we go
okay there so so let's begin
let's land let's land in our seat
arrive let's land in our seat
here we are
as always we arrive with the breath with the body [Music]
arriving landing
and letting go letting go of everything that has come before all the words
all the conceptions conceptualizations just dropping all of it
releasing no need
a beginner's mind beginner's mind
meeting this moment fresh meeting this moment fresh
what's arising in this moment
in the
body the breath
connecting with the soothing breath
the rhythm of the breath the sensations
releasing into the body
with each
out breath relaxing relaxing softening
releasing into the body here
releasing thoughts releasing
contentions entanglements
feeling your feet on the ground
your seat feeling your sit bones
on the cushion on the chair
arriving arriving
keep arriving every moment
and if the mind was distracted it's okay that previous moment is gone arrive
arrive afresh in this body in this moment here this
moment of aliveness
releasing releasing any thoughts
smilingly as if they're flying flying around you
not being entangled in the web
letting there be a sense of connection with the trust
the deep trust in your heart
sense of trust that is there even if it's hard to perhaps really connect to in this moment
in the sense of goodness trust and goodness
yours and others
awakening awakening goodness trusting in goodness
and non-harming
and kindness taking refuge
in benevolence your own benevolence
not causing harm the intentions for not causing harm
and those of others
and now i'd like to invite you
as we feel embodied feeling our bodies
the breath sense of
connection here now not in our head
but in body with the body
let us imagine take on try on
this perspective this perception
that you have died you are no longer living
i am no longer living
and for the purpose of this meditation not making any
assumptions or positing anything about life or death
but what if you take on this perception
of looking through our lives what has been
through the veil through the veil of the beyonds
this person who is me was me
as if you have stepped outside in a zone in an area where there is no
agency no agency
trying on the perception where you can see yourself [Music]
and you can see your loved ones but you no longer have agency anymore
in your life it's it's over
this might bring up sadness it might bring up grief
ah can we breathe with it
appreciating appreciating first this person who is us was us
their challenges their trials their tribulations
all the ways in which they suffered all the ways
they served they were kind
can we see ourselves from this distance as a beloved other
appreciating appreciating ourselves
maybe it brings up a sense of tenderness for
this being who is who is me
they really tried they tried their best
it was not easy for them
is it possible from this perspective to give our heart
to ourselves to this being who is me who was me can we give ourselves completely our
heart completely lovingly oh sweetheart
you thought your struggles your challenges were going to last forever
is there a wish for being more patient more loving
or to have been more patient more loving with this being who is ourselves
who was ourselves playing with
different perceptions
time was short time is short
how could have we loved how can we love support to care for this being who's
ourselves
who was ourselves
again stepping out stepping out of this frame
looking through our own eyes and looking at ourselves from a third person's perspective
through a veil [Music] of lack of agency
no longer possible perhaps
what does that bring up if we feel the opportunity is lost
for many can bring a sense of recognition how precious the opportunity
actually is
to light a fire
before action
not to take it for granted anymore
now also now let's take a moment to recognize also from this third-person perspective
stepping outside through the veil of lack of agency
looking at our loved ones at the world people we care about
or maybe even people we had challenges with
and maybe others in the future people
we don't know but
people who could have benefited from our kindness or action or service
is the heart moved from this perspective
recognizing that opportunity could be lost any moment any time
maybe from this perspective that it has been lost just bring us to more love more care for
our loved ones to give them the best the best of ourselves
not miss any opportunity for generosity for kindness for love
because one day there will be no opportunities
it will be true someday
and stepping back stepping back into ah our first person experience
from our first person experience we're alive gosh
here i am in this body and this mind this life
i can connect with loved ones perhaps resolve
challenges with those i've had difficulty and love myself be here for this person who's me
care for them support them serve the world opportunity is not lost
i have agency time is short time is pressure
precious for loving deeply for serving
forgiving my best
offering my best my wholeheartedness my kindness
the best of me to the world to others
not lose any opportunity for loving for kindness
for generosity don't miss not to miss
enter the last moments of this practice opening our hearts to
our fellow practitioners and this sangha who practice together
with us we are here the gift of our presence
our kindness our care is the highest gift we can give to each other
in our hearts offering our best our care appreciation to one another
thank you friends thank you for being here
and i am here supporting you
with the most precious resource i have my time my presence
my wholeheartedness giving our best to each other
and the world
may all beings everywhere
truly recognize how precious
how sacred this opportunity
to be human this precious human birth really is
to love to wake up for the sake of ourselves and all beings everywhere
do not waste do not waste
may all beings be awake may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so the intention as i mentioned at the beginning with this guided meditation
was to bring a different perspective a sense of
a perception of love of care of
urgency that only
through mindfulness of our impermanence can be enabled so enlivening awakening
to live from that perspective instead of just taking it for granted here we go
yes yet another day etc etc
such profound practice this can be
so i'd like to uh invite you if there are
reflections aha moments questions comments
you can type them in chat type to me alone i won't read your name
if you're typed to the community i will read your name as well as your reflection and
you can raise your hand also if you haven't spoken in a while
for the benefit of all beings offering your practice your insights
and appreciations coming in from youtube thank you you're welcome
and also privately on soon so
any insights any insights that you'd like to share
to be held with this and to support others
any aha moments
wayne i see your hand
you're still muted okay i uh
it it brought me it brings me courage to speak
um but this during it i just thought of
situations where i uh
often don't have good the courage to speak but it brought up for me the feeling of oh you know i i
i it brought up a feeling of courage there's one specific thing related to my
school and a parent a parent that it makes me feel courage
beautiful sense of courage through the sense of uprightness
uprightness and courage beautiful nice yeah thank you for that
it's lovely nancy writes sobering
reflecting on those living in the war zones where every moment brings the certainty
of uncertainty a heightened awareness yes
yeah thank you for bringing that reflection in the certainty of uncertainty
in some ways for all of us there is the certainty of
uncertainty we just don't live according to it we just live
as if the next moment is certain it never is it really isn't
breathing isn't and of course living in a war zone that's quite heightened for
clear reasons and having lived in the war zone myself when i was growing up
in iran during the iran-iraq war there is
an intensity of course to that megan says i am feeling called
to share some dharma humor that came up today on this theme one of the physicians i was working with in
palliative care said life is a sexually transmitted terminal condition
that many people do not realize they have oh that is funny sexually
transmitted terminal condition that's hilarious it is sexually transmitted and it's
terminal well yes exactly birth is terminal birth is absolutely terminal we
we all have a terminal condition you all thank you for that
somebody pointed out that i missed a comment oh yes i've missed a couple of oh my goodness i've missed a lot of lots
of comments here we go uh thank you for that um catherine says this one is hard for me i
live in constant anxiety of wasting my precious life which causes me to suffer and seek
distractions and feel disconnected then i feel guilty for
feeling anxious but it feels like if i truly contact the
reality of mortality versus conceptualizing it it would help
me wake up from this trance yes catherine yes absolutely it's not a
conceptualization you it's so profound what you've just
realized if we conceptualize then it becomes that you know there is terror management
theory and with um if we're afraid of our death then we actually end up wasting time but if we
actually touch into the reality of it um and and
yeah your comment is so insightful then it actually helps not waste time
not distract ourselves yeah thank you for that very insightful
another reflection uh i struggled with the third person perspective and when you mentioned
having no agency it dawned on me that i have and still do spend a lot of
time feeling i have no agency ah what an interesting insight to have
and actually realize that you have the feeling of no agency but actually you do have agency
so it might be helpful to really feel into what really not having agency feels
like in it's like emptying the cup of tea completely emptying the cup and then
when you bring it back it's like oh actually there is some cup there is some tea in here maybe it feels cold or
stale but there is tea in here it's not empty so thank you for that reflection
and continue to work with that um one more reflection i have been doing
five daily reflections for a while but there doesn't seem to be any urgency
even now while we contemplate mindfulness of death um
i recommend the practice of this could be my last breath
um that can bring up a lot of agency and this practice i just brought
up try this because you know in it take your time maybe this 30 minutes was not
long enough really maybe the we as the weekend is coming take some time to just
settle in the body and then bring up um a sense of your debt there's nothing you
can do and then from that perspective look at your life it can be so profound
um it's 6 50 we should turn to small groups scott i do see your hand
uh let i'll come back to you let's let's reserve for
the end at the end i'll come back to you so um so i like to set up the breakout
rooms it's so precious to offer each other our presence
um after after this practice so my invitation
is to um again we're speaking for our own benefit
not for each other speak from from our own experience not commenting not reflecting not managing
not serving as a facilitator just speak from your own experience close to your heart or hold silence
offer your kindness and we'll go around and each person will
say one nugget if you have ten just say one the next person the next person will
come back to you you go around a few times and um
[Music] let's see if there's anything else i want to say to set it up
um [Music] i think that's it
so um so i need to do something to set the rooms here hold on one sec
okay so um be kind to yourself be kind to each other
this is a where the practice meets the cushion meets
live human beings who just like you live and die
okay so here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
and pretty much done but i did promise to come back to scott so scott if your comment is still relevant you're welcome
to share it um
what came up for me during this exercise which i thought was very this exercise is very profound is regret
and the the the piece of it that
i was thinking of was about 10 years ago my wife and i were
deciding whether to have a daughter or not and i didn't want a daughter i didn't want a son i didn't want a child
my wife did and i thought about it and thought about it
and thought about it and one day i thought
when i'm about to take my last breath am i gonna look back and regret
the decision not to have a child and i decided yes i was going to regret
it and i my wife and i decided to have a child who turned out to be a beautiful
daughter and which has turned out to be one of the most profound experiences of my life i think an exercise
that highlights regret or potential regret is
so powerful yeah yeah thank you scott thank you so much for
sharing yes so beautifully indeed indeed and i've gone through
a version of that myself imagining that i'm at my deathbed would i regret
not having taken a particular fork in the road and the answer was yes and that there
was just clarity before was like no i'm not so sure do i do this yep in the light of death there's
clarity it's that it has to be done thank you so much for bringing that in and sharing your experience oh beautiful
may serve others may serve others so thank you all thank you so much for
sharing your presence your practice hmm the cultivation to support
yourselves others and all beings may we all wake up together
may all beings be free
[Music] thank you