so hello folks very happy to be here and
welcome to this meditation session and uh
this will be the last uh morning for a while perhaps to being here at irc the insight retreat center
and [Music] it's been nice to be here in this wonderful meditation hall
some of you have been here and maybe some of you will be here one day and i look forward to the chance to welcome
you welcoming you here in this wonderful place
so
yesterday i discussed um
that one can use posture as a reference point for the state of mind
for the attitudes that we have get expressed in our posture and uh so attending to posture and
having a reference point of a upright posture can indicate when we
lose that and then we can look at why and what's happening inside the other direction works as well
in a sense that we can assume certain postures
and and that can be a reference point for the attitude for the mind
our minds can change to a certain degree by the postures we take
and so the
the image of the buddha meditating like we have here in the altar
is a wonderful example of a balanced posture
that balances of attitude of confidence
and calm confidence and trust perhaps
and and you might find it interesting to
when you meditate to assume a posture of confidence
and maybe a posture that expresses manifests a certain degree of strength
and which is not going to be energetic in a way that's tense
and which will also allow you to become
and i think that confidence sometimes is a underappreciated
quality and that more confidence can be
available to us than we maybe can access through the
mind and one way is to do it physically physical posture of uprightness
of and i suspect every posture
there's possible to find a way of being that somehow feels
like he now this this holds my confidence or expresses confidence
and if i don't feel confident sometimes
the mind is influenced by the body and so if the body takes a
confident posture maybe something begins shifting inside
so assuming taking entering into a posture
for meditation and perhaps for today you can
see if you can take a posture that expresses some physical
strength or confidence
maybe by opening up the chest a bit more
ever so slightly bringing in the spine between the shoulder blades that
also bring opens up expands the chest a little bit
maybe your head can be a little bit more confident
maybe regal straightening out the neck
maybe lifting the head up there's a when i
first started doing meditation the instructions were to imagine a string
from the back top of the head lifting the head up towards the ceiling
and then to gently maybe confidently
close your eyes
and as if you are filling your body with strength
or confidence on the inhale and relaxing on the exhale
take a few long slow deep breaths
taking in some deeper breaths than usual
almost as if you're claiming your right to be here and now
maybe a kind of regal
right or place
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and if you have taken some brought in some confidence to your
posture does that have any influence
on how you're aware of breathing and how you're aware of
the experience of the body breathing
with a normal breath breathing normally on the inhale gently
filling yourself with some degree of confidence and strength
confidence in the value of being present here and now
and then the exhale relax soften
holding tension in your body
as you exhale perhaps letting anxiety melt away
and then simplifying
yourself to settling into the rhythm of the body breathing
breathing
that comes with the support of a confident body
one of the words for confidence in nepali language
is pasada which also means
bright kind of like luminously bright
also means peaceful serene calm
and what kind of confidence strong confidence
even unshakable confidence might you have
that also has qualities of peacefulness and clarity as part of it
a peaceful confidence
and if you imagine yourself having
some form of peaceful confidence
and that that peaceful confidence was the [Music] channel
for your love for your career
for your good will for the world
what would your love be like
radiating from such a confidence
may whatever confidence and strength we've developed through this practice
it be supportive
may it be channeled and used for the welfare and happiness of others
may we live benefiting this world
may all beings be happy
may all beings inhabit their natural strength
may all beings
be safe partly as a
outgrowth of their confidence
may all beings be peaceful
because they walk through the world confidently
may all beings be free confident in the value
of non-clinging may all beings be happy
so thank you
so today we're going to begin discussion of the third exercise
in the satipatana sutta the discourse on the four foundations for mindfulness
for awareness and now one way of reading this text is
that these first four ex first three exercises are kind of progressive
that one can lead to the other and so the first one is
[Music] meditation practice meditation practice centered on breathing
and as we get focused concentrated settled here in our breathing calm settled very present
we bring that calm presence with us into our activities
and the simplest way is to then also know our postures we stand we know we're
standing as we walk we know we're walking and so forth
as uh if we can stay mindful and present kind of inhabiting awareness as we go
through just to begin our activities out after meditation then there's a other things and we do
things only half attention or quarter attention to the activity that we do there's a
delightful kind of calm presence for the activity
maybe in such a degree that it's actually enjoyable to just be there and feel and experience the simplicity of
what we're doing and that uh it's actually more enlivening more rich more beneficial
than the alternative wandering often thought
and concerns with the activities of the day and
then we do our things better when we have that kind of presence and attention
so um i'll read you the passage
the exercise it's a one of the longer ones but uh
a practitioner is one who acts in full awareness
when going forward and returning when looking ahead and looking away
who acts in full awareness when flexing and extending the limbs
who acts in full awareness when wearing their robes
and carrying their outer robe and bowl this is referring to monastics so
it applies to us but not with the same
who acts uh in full awareness when eating drinking consuming food and tasting
who acts in full awareness when defecating and urinating who acts in full awareness when walking
standing sitting falling asleep waking up
talking and keeping silent so these are all ordinary daily
activities that many people do and here it uses the word full awareness
the word is some pajana and it's um
and the and exactly what it means i love this
translation where it says full awareness i love the i'm not completely sure what it means i
have a good sense from my own experience but i just love the feeling of fullness of awareness that as we go through our
lives and what we do the tradition understands it as being
a fuller understanding of what we're doing
so as we you know come out of meditation and start doing the activities we're
doing um we're aware of more
than just the activity itself so if we're doing walking meditation we're
just settling in and doing walking and that's all we're doing but if we're walking to our kitchen
we know we're going to our kitchen as well it's not just walking there's also the knowing of going to the kitchen
if we're reaching for a cup to have tea
we know that we're reaching the cup in order to have tea for the purpose of having tea
if we are uh you know reaching for the faucet to put
water in the tea kettle we have a sense that we're doing this for a purpose for
both to have water come out to fill the kettle to make tea because it's you know
thirsty and it's good to be hydrated so there's so this starts to be it
the in the immediacy there's a number of things that are clear the purpose of why we're doing it the
context in which we do things we walk into some place
and we're going to walk through the room but we know there are other people in the room it's not just walking as if
that's all that's going on we take into account the context of the people maybe we take
we walk around them rather than walking through them or expect them to move
so this full awareness takes in much more in
and and so here we're beginning to use a little bit more of the intelligence of
the mind it's not uh we're not using our intelligence to fantasize
about tomorrow or get lost in fantasy and thoughts about something or other as we do it
as we reaching for the faucet we know we're doing it we have someone asked us about it later
but we're not really present it's not their full awareness of the activity and the context and the
purpose we are um you know already started thinking about
i don't know um can't wait for lunch and i wonder what we should have for lunch and we haven't
even had breakfast so um so
here this is this exercise now is a call to bring our mindfulness into our daily
activities into all our activities and i love it ends with both talking
and remaining silent and putting them both in the same level of importance
um and to have a full awareness to know when we're talking to know that
why we're talking to know the context for why we're talking and the same for silence
to know why we're silent the context for the purpose of silence the context of it the appropriateness of it
the the tradition also says that this full awareness
also means that one knows
in what part of ourselves we stay grounded in as we do the activity
that we stay explicitly says we stay connected to the four foundations for mindfulness
so sometimes we know we enter into the world of the activity very much with our
bodies some of these these activities are physical sometimes we
we're we're present for our mind states the quality of our mind sometimes we're aware of the feeling
tone sometimes they the mental processes involved so these are all kind of the mental the exercises
we'll be talking about as we go through this suta but
but it's uh to really practice mindfulness with all these different aspects of ourselves
mindfulness that keeps us here rooted in the present moment grounded in the present
and capable of taking in this fuller context purpose values of what we're doing the
impact of what we're doing the influence on what's happening influence on us
in what we're doing so it's one thing to walk and be aware that we're walking it's
another thing to feel that we're walking in such a hurry that we're getting tense
and so full awareness would notice that tension or walking in a way that feels
nourishing that feels delightful and feel satisfying to walk
and then we walk with that satisfaction and feel that and um
so the um mindfulness so one way of understanding
this it's mindfulness inactivity it's very common among english
practitioner english speaking practitioners to refer to mindfulness in daily life
which is a great top great concept however it's very abstract daily life just means too much
for the buddha was always kind of more concrete more specific
something more tangible and so here it's mindfulness and action
and and and to infuse our activity
with awareness with attention and and it isn't so much that we have to think
actively about the context think about the purpose but it's one kind of a a
relaxed open awareness that that's taken into account that scene
that's understood that arises as well it's a rich world
so the activities that i just read are generally pretty simple ones uh eating and defecating and urinating
and and extending your arm and doing these different activities
um falling asleep waking up
you might uh in over this weekend look for simple activities
that you do that you can try to do or practice full awareness with
full understanding of what's happening there as you do it and not searching and analyzing for that
but is there some way of being really present for the activity you're doing
that there's a clear knowing of the context of the purpose
of the influence it has on you and because you're so present for it
but your system is taking that in is registering that and knowing that as part of the
full picture of your present moment experience abiding in the present moment
calm and confident available to take in the full picture
of the fuller picture of what the activity is about and how it's going
so to choose a few activities through the day maybe washing dishes or sweeping the floor or
driving or you know different something simple that you can practice and experiment with this
as so that the this mindfulness awareness can begin growing and
expanding and spreading into more of your life so thank you
very much and i'll see you back at imc on monday