sure um
that would have to be on her side yeah she has to do that but I think she was muted whenever she
wasn't talking so it's essentially the same and then I was controlling the um
her mic I had it off when she wasn't talking
and we can't turn the volume off on the laptop because I can't get up and down every
time
sure that's what we'll set it up we'll set it up the first time
yeah yeah
I gotta go thanks brother appreciate it
okay so now you want to test the mics is that the first one is that kill this
is the normal one that's usually plugged in so I can hear myself a little bit and so far it seems that probably is
plenty loud Sage sorry
yeah okay
losers
she has it with her oh okay it's just this
don't you like to be the mic person today if you don't want to listen if you don't
you don't need to for sure
and you can actually it's on you can just butt it right up against almost touch the bike testing one two
testing I'll use my normal speaking voice secret
title oh my God yep is that good oh to me but
yeah oh okay well
uh this is a normal tone but then when I do guided it's a little too loud it's
echoing okay and when I do guided meditations I'm a
little soft Sage [Music]
you're right I do know that so okay so when I do uh guided and I'm soft
you can still hear this yeah right
that people's signal us they can't hear
foreign
so we're just going to have sort of a sitting period between now and about
um just a little before 10. to get settled and to allow people to come in and
so I'll just I don't want to offer too much instructions but I do want to welcome
you I do want to invite you to
bring all of yourself here
and to maybe just sort of start you know if people do wander in
it's an opportunity to practice sort of welcoming the disruptions The Sounds the
energy that's not settled but just to sort of see it and say
welcome it's a nice practice to sort of support
an opening in your mind and heart to what's happening instead of resisting
so so as not to surprise you I will probably if more people come in I'll offer some more instructions at some
point similar ly maybe a little more guidance
and you're welcome to just ignore my voice at any point
welcome
thank you
so one of the first things we invite people to do when we start papasana
practice is to find an upright embodied posture
and to kind of create some sort of an anchor to help your mindfulness stay
present anchor can be the breath flowing in and
out if that breath works well for you
it's a nice one because it has a rhythm but it changes comes and goes
and we can connect with the breathing in a variety of ways
feeling the air flow through the nostrils or in the belly
chest or the whole body
and if the breath doesn't somehow work quite well for you
you might experiment with sort of resting your awareness and the
feelings of your hands or your body sitting on your chair
what we're wanting is a anchor that is easy for you to connect with
another option is sound
and when we do listening meditation really the same with all of them but
we're receiving receiving sounds receiving the breath
receiving Sensations
so just checking in today to notice your body your mind your heart
and what part of your experience is it easiest to connect with
that helps you stay here connected with present moment experience
in vipassana we tend to close our eyes for meditation but it is not required
sometimes it's very useful and helpful to open our eyes to help us Orient or
ground
if you like to just practice with eyes open you can be supportive to
sort of let your eyes gently rest
a little bit ahead of you maybe a little bit down in front of you just a gentle Focus not this sort of
searching or looking but more just a a soft gaze
this morning before we begin the formal welcome it's a great great
opportunity to just check in and notice how your mind and body are this morning
what's easy to connect with that keeps you here practice play a little bit with this
just helping yourself slowly enter into this day of practice
welcoming just as much as you can whatever comes up fear resistance not liking hoping
all of it can just be seen and allowed to come in and move through
this is maybe one of the most important moments of the day establishing
a relationship with your experience establishing an anchor for your
awareness
foreign
just noticing what you're aware of now
may be lost in thought maybe with your anchor or the sound
just as gently as possible
and a sit back metaphorically perhaps energetically in
your body relax a little bit more
nothing has to happen
posture in your mind might be kind of this image of somebody upright but kind of leaning
back a little hands Palms open
sort of receptive receptive stance
being soft with experience patient
maybe just doing a slight gentle body scan
inviting the head the face the forehead
the jaw to relax maybe even opening the mouth a little
bit
inviting the eyes to soften forehead to soften
temples to soften
sort of like warm honey bringing your attention down through the head and neck and face
into the shoulders
just still letting go of anything extra
anything extra that isn't needed
sort of allowing that soft warm attention
to gently flow down through the arms
inviting the muscles even the bones
to soften just a bit
through the chest back body
the heart the lungs the belly
good morning good morning body good morning muscles
welcome may you be at ease may you feel the warmth of my gaze
down into the bottom hips pelvic area
down through the legs
feeling the fronts and the backs and the sides of the legs
maybe noticing the aliveness of the body
into the ankles
and the feet
thank you
foreign
[Music]
good morning everyone my name is Liz Powell and together with
Tanya Weiser we're very happy to be offering this day-long introduction to
mindfulness meditation and this is a good time if you'd like to
stretch you can stand for a minute or do whatever you need to do since we've been sitting for a little while
and I'm going to offer you a little bit of an orientation to the space we're sitting in I also want to welcome and
thank Richard who is our manager today so the three of us have been meditating
for a while this is my 18th year much to my surprise of meditating at uh IMC and
in this community and uh so this if you haven't been here
to before how many haven't been to this space before great welcome
um I want to let you know that there are three bathrooms in the back of the hall you're welcome to get up and use the
bathroom anytime you need there's also a counter in the back there
that has hot water for tea or coffee and there's tea available that you can take
out of the drawers to drink um there is a kitchen with sink and
refrigerator you can store your lunch in the refrigerator if you bought lunch during lunch time you're welcome to
microwave your lunch so feel free to use this as your home
and we have a couple of other things that are very useful for some people if
you have trouble hearing you have a couple of different options one is that on the counter nearest this wall
in the Social Hall there are hearing assistive devices so you can get one of them and turn them
on Richard's showing it hooks over your ear and you can turn it on and adjust
the line thank you Richard will help also if during the meditation sometimes
I know my voice gets really quiet during guided meditation raise your hand or put your thumb up or
just let us know you can even say something out loud because we don't want you to miss it you know you don't have
to be concerned about speaking up another thing that we have available
during the day we're going to do I'm going to orient you to what we'll be doing today but during the day there's a
sign up sheet on the stage and we have a few what are called practice discussions
and you can feel free to sign up for one of those that's just a short opportunity
to talk with Tanya or me and ask questions you might have get acquainted
ask about what's going on for you in the meditation so it's a chance for some
one-on-one support we'll also have a question and answer period later in the day and you can approach US during the
day uh with questions this is one of the wonderful things
about Insight Meditation Center is it's entirely run by volunteers everybody here is a volunteer
and so it's also maintained by volunteers and we ask that at the end of
this day long if there are about six of you five or six who could stay late for
just 15 minutes we you know sweep the floors throw the trash and compost out just simple things
like that so anybody who could do that could stay for 15 minutes thank you very
much wonderful and we'll be joining you during the the chores
so um one thing to know about today that's very important is there's no
there's no mistakes there are no mistakes and there's nothing that can go wrong everything that we're doing today
is an opportunity just to be aware of what's Happening so um I would like you to be able to
relax and enjoy the day
no good that's why there's two of us one is that to support our practice
today we want to invite other than you know in here if there's a specific question about practice silence in the
hall so in the whole Center silence um it helps us keep watching our minds
and not get lost right in interactions during lunch we'll invite people to talk
outside right and also if there's people who want silence outside we can set up two
separate areas for eating so but it just seems like if that's if you know a nice
way to support the continuity because you're going to be building up a lot of practice continuity today so
and one other little thing which is nobody has any liquids in here but
only water into the Hall so tea and stuff just keep it out there
thank you Liz yes we have this lovely light colored
carpet to keep us on our toes as far as mindfulness and keep keep it free of
stains so um I'm just going to stretch my body a
little bit get comfortable here
one of the things about today too is please feel free if you need to to go
out and get more cushions to shift from chair to floor floor to chair you know you don't have to I when I
first came here I had no introduction class and I sat down on the floor right
there just on the floor didn't know anything about cushions and within 15 minutes it was a Sunday
sitting within 15 minutes I was sweating Loosely and I was in so much pain
everybody still I thought I can't move a muscle I don't want it to be like that for you
today you're allowed to move and you're allowed to get yourself comfortable
um I want to start by asking for who is
will this be your first introduction to meditation you've never come to a center
before taking any meditation classes I think Anna said she's not yeah great
wonderful welcome this class is designed for you and who has been taking Tanya and kodo's
intro to mindfulness meditation class Great Sage and Corey and
wonderful welcome who took a prior introductory course somewhere
yeah great so for for you some of what I have to
say may serve as Refresher um and uh then how how many have been
practicing for a little while maybe you've been practicing for a few months if you've been practicing for at least a
few months and about how many have been practicing for a year or
how about more than a year and decades yes decades okay so this day is for
everyone and um what we're going to be doing is called
mindfulness meditation it's also called Insight Meditation which you may have seen on the sign Outdoors
what mindfulness you know there's a lot of teachers who say I can't really Define mindfulness but I'll give it a
attempt paying attention on purpose to what is happening right here and now
moment to moment in the body in the emotions in the mind
in your surroundings but largely you know we're turning Inward and paying attention to what's arising in US
now over time as we notice what's happening now we may also be able to see
some patterns some conditioned habits we have so what comes up routinely may start to
teach us quite a bit about how we've been conditioned or what we've learned over the course of our lifetime
and over the time this practice of mindfulness cultivates a clear
stable non-judgmental awareness awareness is a capacity we all have it's
a natural thing right now I bet if we did a poll we'd probably be able to tell
approximately what the temperature in the room is you know kind of a little
bit about what the weather is the awareness is functioning all the time for a lot of different purposes but
we're going to aim our awareness at specific things
so this mindfulness meditation practice that we do over and over again can
certainly bring calm and Clarity to our
daily life into the pressures that we experience in life and it's also
available as a spiritual path that helps us gradually experience more freedom and
happiness it sort of dissolves barriers to wisdom compassion and other beautiful human
qualities so it's twofold now how we're going to proceed to begin
today is we're going to go through the same sequence that those of you have been going through the intro class have
gone through and we're doing one skill after another and the skills build on one another they
complement one another so we'll start with basics of meditation
and where people often start in this tradition is with mindfulness of
breathing so we'll begin with that then the next segment we'll do a little
bit of walking so we'll start to come into mindfulness of our bodies in that case with with mindfulness of our feet
and legs then we'll come back and we'll do a
sitting where we develop mindfulness of the body and we take in different kinds of Sensations in addition to those of
breathing in the rest of the body we'll move into next into mindfulness of
emotions feeling and then we'll do and by the way we'll
have breaks during this we'll have other walking meditation periods so you won't be uh sitting without a break all day
you'll get plenty of breaks and often the sitting meditations will be
interspersed with walking meditations to help relieve the body and get the circulation going and change it up
we'll move into the mindfulness of thinking something
that goes on quite a bit perhaps and then we'll have a
mindfulness of open awareness and what that is is paying attention to the flow
of what's happening so right now as you experience what's happening as you sit
here there could be thoughts and then there could be a body sensation there could be attention to the breath there
could be emotions and all these things come and go come and go come and go so with open awareness we pay attention to
that changing flow um as we focus on each of what Tanya
called anchors we're going to use each of these things as what we call an anchor so if you think about for example
paying attention or being aware of breathing
the way we use that is let's say a sailor has been sailing all day long and
they've been working hard at the tiller and they've been you know gauging the winds and doing a lot of work and they
decide to come to a rest um they could weigh anchor they could drop an anchor into the water
and the anchors provides a stable point you know so the boat is no longer going
to be blown by the wind or caught by the currents or the tides it's going to stay there so similarly we're using the
breath to stabilize our awareness and our attention and we'll when we're practicing mindfulness of the breath
we'll come back to breathing again and again and it's not that thinking might not happen or a sensation in the body's
noticed other things will come up but then we just gently return the attention when we're aware the mind has gone off
we'll gently return our attention to the breathing so there's many different
types of anchors that the breathing is one then we'll shift to the body the body could be your anchor of attention
you could keep coming back to Sensations in the body again and again
um so that's what's meant by an anchor or some people will call it an object of meditation
please know it's not that we expect that only breathing is going to be happening when we're practicing mindfulness of the
breathing it's simply that we're going to come back to that anchor again and again and in doing that we are training
the mind we're training the awareness to come back to something that will
stabilize it when we start out we have what some people call Monkey mind it's
jumping all around all over the place if you experience that no problem there are
no mistakes there are no problems um you know we'll also offer with these
guided meditations that we'll do on each of these topics we'll offer some time we'll talk about
them briefly we'll do this lightly guided meditation and then we'll offer some time that is just quiet so that you
can notice what happens in your mind and body um have people here have anybody here
been listening to a lot of the morning guided meditations that Gil's been doing at seven o'clock
yeah guided meditations are wonderful and these guided meditations serve to
help give you an idea of what you might pay attention to you know to kind of train your mind in okay here's kind of
how I go about this mindfulness of breathing for example but also guided
meditations are a bit like training wheels and there comes a point where if you want to ride a bike you use the
training wheels to get your balance but then after a while you take them off and similarly it's good to practice
meditation with the guidance off and just see what happens because we learn a
whole lot about how our minds have been conditioned and what's going on for us
so um just briefly I wonder how many people
here are not so familiar with how you use chairs and cushions and things like that
if you haven't really great I'm gonna and maybe some of you are but I'm going to give a little Brief Review of it
it does not matter which and by the way when I talk about postures I want to
include that one of the postures that can be used at any time if you're super
sleepy or you just need a break is standing posture you can stand usually people don't close their eyes when they
do this they keep them resting at a spot on the floor but you can stand while you're meditating
and you can feel your body swaying a little bit or but it's fine to use anything you need
so you'll see I I usually use a chair and I'll show you this kind of from the side so you can see it when you're
sitting on a chair usually what you're trying to do is um
have your feet flat on the floor and parallel or you can have your legs
splayed a little if your feet don't reach the floor there are some cushions and wedges out in the shelves and you
can put you know you can put them under your feet ideally you want your knees slightly lower than your hips or level
but definitely not higher so if you find your feet don't reach the floor you
um or you need some hip height you can put a cushion under yourself like this
free of the back rest with all sitting we're trying to establish a little bit of an independent
posture and this takes time to develop by the way at first our muscles may feel
the new activity and some of us who have
lower back injuries might prop cushions very low behind ourselves like that so
that's that can help but then from there you're going to place your hands
somewhere where they're not pulling you forward they're not pulling your shoulders forward or too far forward
they're comfortably resting on your lap in kind of a symmetrical way or when it
gets hot I do Palms up so that I have one more evaporative cooling Source you
can also rest your hands in your lap like this whatever oops whatever's comfortable for
you then some people prefer to sit on the
floor it's comfortable for them and you have a lot of options there
so I'm not going to sit on one cushion because I know I'm not flexible enough but some people can sit simply on one
cushion the idea with the chair the cushion anything is that you're forming a tripod a sturdy base for yourself so
I'm going to sit on two cushions and what that enables me to do what you want to do is be able to have both knees
forming two corners of the tripod and then the cushion forming the third your
sit bones against the cushion um sitting on the front third is helpful
for stability and we tend to sit Burmese style or tailor style like this with one leg and
foot in front of the other if I were sitting here and one knee was still a little high it just didn't have the
flexibility in my hips I could put a cushion under so that I then have
the stability so use props as you need and then with
each of these things with sitting and on the floor in the chair it's
helpful to have your upper body you know allowing your spine to be alert you want
a balance between alertness awakeness you know that helps you focus
and relaxness relaxation so sometimes what I do to kind of align
myself is I think of additional space between my top vertebra and I I tuck my
chin just a little bit not like this but just tiny bit down instead of you know
our head is really heavy and we can if we're focusing on meditation you can see people start to go like that
so um what I do to help myself is I lift my shoulders and then drop them
back feel that little bit of space in my spine
and feel this balance between alertness and relaxation
it takes time to find these things people who've been doing this for years take their time to settle into this
so feel free to continually you know tiny little adjustments or even big changes
you know if you're sitting here and like if I tried to sit here like this for the whole time I would be very hard on my
arthritis and I wouldn't be able to get up off the floor so another option we have are these
benches I have not frequently used a bench but
theoretically you can sit on it oh boy my knees won't do that but you can sit
on it and balance that way you can also turn one of these cushions
on its end and sit on it like this and I won't go all the way down because my knees won't
tolerate it um those give you a few options
and as I said um experiment with it
try different things until you find what helps you
find that balance between alertness and relaxation
especially if they have physical challenges may use lying down meditation
I'm not going to spend time on that today because that's more challenging it's hard for most of us not to fall
asleep so you can talk to us individually about that
if it's a little bit uncomfortable that's normal as we start doing this
it's unfamiliar and it can be a little bit uncomfortable
but often we'll just hang in with it for a little bit to notice what we can
notice about that but please don't hurt yourself so if
something is uncomfortable after a while a little while you can
intentionally mindfully move so if I've been sitting and I find that I'm getting
uncomfortable I may recognize discomfort recognize I'm going to move and follow
what happens in my body as I make the adjustment
if when you get up from meditation your body hurts still is in pain
especially after five minutes that's a sign that your
possibly starting to injure yourself and you don't need to do that you can find other ways to support yourself
so um just a little bit of an overview
of all of this with any of it with attention to the
posture with attention to any of these anchors we're developing our ability to pay
attention to our immediate experience instead of being preoccupied with the
past or future as you study the monkey mind you'll find
that wow it's pretty frequent that we're thinking about the future of the past and it could be innocent enough we might
need to think a little bit about tomorrow but often our preoccupation with this
contributes to stress suffering fear and other things that
kind of keep us from being free so mindfulness is learning how to
overcome those preoccupations by coming into the lived experience right now what we're living right now
it relies on this natural capacity we have for awareness and awareness by itself doesn't judge it
doesn't resist it doesn't cling it just notices
it doesn't mean that resistance or cleaning my judgment might not come up
they might and then we just notice those too as I said there's no problem it's like okay judging is going on
let me return my attention to what's happening in the breath right now
awareness of what's happening and this can include I'm distracted I feel
disrupted while I'm yesterday I was foggy all day it felt like I was my eyes
weren't focused and I was looking through a layer of fog all day long fine I included it in the mindfulness wow
foggy today thank you there's nothing that isn't supposed to
happen we're not trying to achieve an altered state we're not trying to be different than how we are right now
trying to become somebody in particular we are being with just the way things
are right now with everything that arises whether it's comfortable uncomfortable we like it we don't like
it it's all folded into mindfulness
and the freedom is actually in seeing that you know you're no longer enslaved by something if you
um recognize oh wow I was just thinking for the last 15 minutes okay awareness
thinking let me return to the breathing
there's a lot of um disentangling ourselves that can go on
from these conditioned habits and we can develop a friendlier more compassionate
relationship with the stuff that comes up I've sat down here before and found
that my breathing was just incredibly labored and I was like wow I'm just
working and breathing and instead of thinking oh I'm a bad meditator and that's wrong I got the ability over time
to go okay today for whatever reason the body is really grabbing air
or another time sitting down here thinking like crazy wow and then
recognizing you know what I just had a incredibly stimulating day no wonder the
mind is being pulled into thinking mindfulness of thinking return to whatever anchor I was using
so this is what I mean by we can be compassionate and friendly towards it it's just the way we human beings become
conditioned so mindfulness again just attentively
being present with What's Happening Here and Now on purpose no matter what it is
and it's called to practice in the same way that we practice a piano or a musical instrument
we we come back and we do it again do it again do it again
um we don't we're not trying to get perfect the first time and there is no perfect or imperfect anyway we're just
practicing practicing awareness and it develops uh well if we can just
set aside any expectations any judgments if they come up like okay I've got an
expectation that I'm going to be oh peaceful okay it's an expectation and what's
actually going on is okay there's some calm there's some energy in the body
the breath is coming to support the speaking
the body's pretty tired just you know this is what's happening
so uh with that that's just a little scope of why we're doing this what we
might be able to receive from it and the biggest part of it relax enjoy
the day appreciate anything you're discovering or aware of welcome
thank you
let's check in and notice how you're doing right now it's a lot to take in
we're gonna move into a breathing meditation but I'm wondering if you if
you need a break can you nod your head if you think yeah
yeah five minutes please go ahead and take care of yourselves
also just a reminder the sign up for if you want to practice discussion where
Sage is um near the end of the stage there's a place there to sign up for a practice discussion
foreign foreign
finding your posture finding your body
and giving it to your cushion the Earth your chair
your bones to hold
letting things settle
just in this simple direct way
connecting with your Felts lived present moment
experience your mind will think
seeing if you can play with resting more awareness
kind of on the directness of your experience
start that with the breath this morning
seeing if the breath can be sort of in the center of your
awareness the center of your experience
so it can be helpful to start with some longer
slower Fuller and conscious breaths
with the exhale it can be helpful to invite a Letting Go feeling
maybe with the inhale bringing your shoulders up toward your ears
kind of squeezing in that way and then with exhale
letting the shoulders fall back and down
breathing in I calm my body breathing out I calm my mind
so we'll become a little bit more intimate with our breathing experience
maybe just starting with knowing you're breathing in as you breathe in
on knowing you're breathing out as you breathe out
and you can know this by the sensation and the feeling and the flow
and if it's helpful you can do a quiet noting in your mind of in with
inhale and out with exhale
seeing what's supportive for you what helps you connect more fully
with inhale and the exhale
and if it's helpful
you can also start to include awareness of the breath as it leaves and enters
maybe noticing the temperature of the breath
where it touches your nostrils
how it feels different coming in versus out
you might also notice the feeling of it in your throat
or feeling the chest as it expands with the inhale
and contracts with the exhale
you may feel it in your belly
allowing giving your belly permission to expand with the inhale
for the belly to relax
and just being curious where it's easiest for you
to feel the flow of the breath what part of your experience of breathing
can you rest into more easily
and there's no need to try and stop from thinking or
stop hearing or feeling
it's more about trying to invite the breath to be in the foreground or in the
center of your experience your awareness
just maybe holding a little bit closer to it
a little more intimate with that part of your experience
maybe just three breaths at a time
seeing if you can follow the full flow of the in and the out
for three breaths in a row
being easy with ourselves with our experience
soft and gentle with whatever's happening
foreign
just in case there's some struggle in the mind
maybe just inviting the mind to help you attend
in a simple way to receiving the experience of breathing
and not trying to force it but more like this invitation
Maybe like if you have a puppy
you gently pick it up and invited
to a particular area
not yanking it around and knowing that uh
we need to be gentle and persistent
maybe in the way that we learn to enjoy the puppy
while we're also watching over the puppy
that it needs a certain amount of room
in the same way can we give our own minds a little bit of room
while staying connected to the experience that the body knows how to do
the breathing that is so natural and the first thing we do when we come into this
world and the last thing we do when we leave
this world is to Exhale
a constant companion
foreign
if you're new to meditation you may see us bowing at the end of meditation and
that's just a way of acknowledging um I I've heard it said that uh the light
in me sees the light in you so it's just an acknowledgment you don't have to do
it but I wanted people to know why we do that [Music]
um what we'll do next is have a chance to do a half hour of walking meditation
and when we do walking meditation the anchor is the feeling in the feet and
legs or the just keeping the focus on the feet and legs or returning again and again and generally what's
done is we find a place we can go crosswise in the hall here maybe we can
move some chairs out of the way you can walk crosswise in the hall or you can walk Outdoors
on the front porch in the gravel on the sidewalks of the neighborhood
and you pick a path maybe 15 to 20 steps along and instead of taking a walk what
we're doing is we're walking back and forth and that gives us an opportunity to stay
focused on this the feet and legs returning our attention
and to pick a pace that fits with the pace of mindfulness so this varies by person a lot of people
like to slow down a little bit some people like to slow down a lot but whatever helps you to or supports
you to return your attention to your feet and legs and it's not that other things won't
happen you know you may your eyes may be caught by some bright flower and or you
may pick up a sound of a bird you've never heard anything like that it's fine to pause
notice what the awareness has been drawn to and ah hearing then come back focus
again on the feet and legs and continue with the walking um
so one thing about being out on the sidewalks is just please be considerate
of neighbors who might be walking by and actually taking a walk and you know move out of the way so that they're not
struggling to pass you um I would recommend not walking in the
parking lot we'll be having practice discussions so please don't use this parking lot the
dentist prefers we don't use the parking lot there or the one across the street so instead it's better to find space on
the sidewalk and um just taking your time and seeing what you discover as you walk some
people I'll just demonstrate a little um often what I do is I pause at the
beginning of my walking path and allow my attention to collect and for some people they're just
noticing the movement of their feet and legs
they come okay you know you know I noticed my mind drifted off to a sound outside
back to the feet and legs I come to the end of my path
take a breath and pause and notice the movement of my feet and
legs as I turn around for other people sometimes the way I'd
like to do it is I like to feel the lifting the motion the settling of the
foot against the ground lifting the other foot the motion of the leg forward
settling the foot against the ground so you can do it in a more General way or a
more focused way like that
a couple of people have signed up for practice discussions during that time so
Tanya and I will be in the back parking lot in chairs back there to meet with
you if you signed up so meanwhile please enjoy the meditation
we will come back at 11 35 and if you're somewhere nearby Richard will ring a
bell about five minutes before it's time to come back you may not hear it if you're further
away so just take your watch above all relax and enjoy see what you
discover about what happens in the mind and body as you walk
and we'll see you again at 11 35. foreign
thank you
thank you foreign
foreign
so now we'll have a period of focus on body meditation and I'll start
with a few comments what we're doing today is we're building our ability to notice what's happening
right here and now we're starting with the breath as an anchor or the movement of our feet and
legs and walking meditation as an anchor using those anchors to stabilize the
attention and bring it into the Here and Now we're also noticing when the attention
drifts away from the here and now and when it comes back
so we're going to move in this next meditation from the sensations of breathing
to a broader sense of feeling in the body
the rest of our physical experience
the reason we do this or what's great about it is that the body is always operating in the present moment
breathing in the present moment the hearts beating in the present moment everything's going on in the present
moment in the body and when we bring the mind to those
things that are happening in the body right now they're working in Harmony and this is
different than for example if you sit your body down here and your mind is planning what you'd like to eat for
dinner and thinking about what happened at work yesterday then these two are not
in harmony
so first we'll in this meditation we'll take in sensations of breathing as fully
as possible and then we'll turn to the body I want to make the distinction that the
mindfulness or awareness we're bringing is not in itself commentary or judgment
or evaluation of the breathing or Sensations in the body
and not judging ourselves we're just training ourselves to notice Here and Now how the breathing is
feeling sensing sensations of the breathing sensing Sensations in the body
we could call that knowing the breathing or knowing the body
commentary and judgment may happen anyway if they come up you can just notice ah
I'm judging myself a little bit and then maybe release that
relax and return to the breathing or the body
for some of us we spend so much time thinking
that it may you know sometimes we're not so aware of our body and it may be a
slow Reawakening don't worry if that's the case just allow yourself to notice
what you can and sometimes we can use a word like
here to bring ourselves back to the body Here and Now
so I'll go into a guided meditation now giving yourself a moment to re-establish
your posture in a way that's alert
alert spine and also relaxed and taking time
to make those little adjustments maybe rolling the shoulders
in the out breath
perhaps taking a few longer slower breaths
foreign
letting the breathing return to normal whatever that is in this moment there's
no right or wrong way to breathe
it can be helpful to scan the body from head to foot
noticing Sensations in the head right now
the scalp the forehead
the cheeks and jaw perhaps bringing some ease to them
perhaps letting the jaw drop open a little relaxing it
with a mask on sometimes I find I breathe with my mouth open
with mask off I gently bring the lips back together
and letting the attention flow down the neck to the shoulders
perhaps allowing the shoulders to drop a little letting the weight of the arms
and hands rest comfortably
on your legs or lap
letting attention Glide down the back upper middle lower back
it's there if it's possible to soften
an area you can soften it or if there's activity there that
remains they're simply noticing that it's there it's not a problem
allowing whatever is present
with the next exhale perhaps relaxing the belly
softening the hips if it's possible
letting gravity receive the weight of the legs and feet
against the floor
you may become more broadly aware of the entire body sitting here
you might feel a sense of aliveness
a little bit of vibration or pulsing
some energy or some relaxation
sleepiness or alertness warmth
cool air in some places
it's allowing yourself to take in that broader sense of the body
sitting here in the hall
foreign
just to get a idea or a feeling for what it is to
feel the sensations of the body for a moment turning the attention to
the sensations in the right hand
you might feel a light pressure of where the hand is in
contact with your leg or in contact with your other hand
perhaps there's some warmth in certain areas
perhaps coolness in other areas of the hand
perhaps you can feel a little pulsing or vibration in the fingertips
or somewhere in the hand
foreign taking in whatever Sensations are present in the right hand
and just that's what we mean when we say paying attention to Sensations in the
body sometimes we can be aware of an absence of sensation in a particular area of the
body and that's also fine
to a broader sense of the overall body as it sits here the whole
body
becoming aware of how the body experiences the sensations of breathing
it may be through sensations of the chest
rising and falling
or perhaps you experience the belly expanding
and then releasing
or Sensations flowing in and out of the nose or throat
wherever you feel the physical sensations of breathing
centering on those Sensations
if there's any commentary or evaluation simply noticing it
and gently returning attention centering it on the sensations of
breathing in and breathing out
if it's difficult for you being with the breathing simply acknowledge the difficulty
and be with it as best you can
returning to the sensations of breathing wherever it's most prominently felt in
the body
then letting go of any effort to be with the breathing
and allowing your attention to turn to the strongest or most obvious Sensations in the body
it might be the feeling of your hands resting against your thighs or your feet
against the floor or cushion
maybe something else if it disappears as you are aware of it
allowing your attention to be present
for the next prominent Sensation that arises
the intention could return to the sensations of breathing if that is the
most prominent until something else becomes
the most pronounced in the attention
in sensation in the body
right
if there is discomfort in the body simply noticing that
I need to try to get rid of it or to focus in on it
just included in a global sense of the body sitting here
and allow your attention to take in other Sensations in the body
as well
here
if the attention is drifted away into thinking or somewhere else sounds
simply noting where it went and gently returning to the most
prominent sensation in the body right now
thank you
okay
if there's a need to adjust your posture remembering to be mindful
as you feel the need as you begin the movement and during the movement just feeling the
sensations of moving
all right if a sensation in the body is getting very strong
it's possible to be with it from a greater distance
imagining being a bird high above the building
and taking in the strong sensation
from a distance
foreign
if it's getting to be too much
if something is very strong firstly be hanging out with it for a few
minutes and then if it's wearing the mind or
exhausting the body then mindfully moving to a more
comfortable posture staying with the sensations of the
movement and noticing what changes after the movement
different
foreign
the attention to what the most prominent sensation is now
foreign 's entering the sensation more fully
feeling whether it varies or is steady
seeing if it stays or dissolves
foreign
everything
here
thank you
foreign
foreign [Music]
just a few comments afterwards it's usual in our tradition that
breathing is placed at the center the grounding anchor at the beginning and
there are some people for whom the breath is useful and some For Whom the
breath is not so useful or there can be periods of time where it's not so when I first began practicing
I wasn't so able to use breathing so I use the body as my anchor until I
became my attention became stable enough over a period of time for breathing for
me to turn to breathing um so often breathing is used or the body
may be used until another experience becomes more compelling or prominent in the attention and then we turn our
attention to that and then perhaps return to the Anchor now sometimes what comes
up is Pleasant sometimes it's not so pleasant and as I mentioned there can be discomfort in the body
it may not use bees to this posture it can take a while to become stronger more
flexible or can just be conditions of that particular day or that particular
phase of life
There's No Agenda again for what you pay attention to whatever is coming up
arthritis Sensations in the knee mindful of that
returning to the breathing and mindful of that
just using whatever anchor you're using is a way to come back and stabilize the
attention there's no hurry with any of this it's sometimes called a purification process
which means that we're becoming aware of all the ways we've been conditioned and
sometimes things are coming up like poison coming out of a wound and we're experiencing that
so we're just noticing whatever is prominent allowing it getting to know it better
being present with it and as I mentioned if it's sometimes too
much it's okay to take a different view like move out to a distance in our attention or not not try to hammer into
it or get rid of it I'm just feeling it and if necessary
mindfully Shifting the posture and noticing how it felt during and
after so you're encouraged when discomfort comes up to hang in there with it for a
little bit or even for a long while but not to injure yourself
so being present with these Sensations in the body again and again practicing
like we're practicing an instrument um can begin to help the body relax over
time I went through many Retreats at the beginning years of my practice where it
felt like the whole retreat was working with discomfort in the body and then
over time that became not the case my body was more relaxed
so this idea of staying unified with mind and body being present here and now as the body is here
and now we start to become aware of Habitual
preferences Cravings aversions judgments all the stuff that comes up
that is being purified and we get a chance to understand it
more deeply so thank you very much for your practice of
mindfulness and body
so just checking in with yourself right now noticing what you need Maybe
and where you're at we're going to have a lunch break at 12 35 so if you're
feeling hungry just you know orienting we have a period
of time now for some questions
reflections but I want to just sort of let you know
that that's what's going to happen so if you feel like you need to stand up and go to the bathroom or maybe it's better
for you to stay in silence so you want to go and do some walking during this period
please take care of your practice right track track what is needed for you
one of the things that can happen is we get more and more sensitive to
the talking as we're quiet
does anyone have um any questions or Reflections they'd like to share
during the walking meditation one of the things I noticed uh
was that when I was putting my attention on my feet and my legs I noticed
just all the little tiny adjustments things were were happening just to maintain balance
so I was noticing how wobbly I felt and then I or how wobbly I was and then
I started putting attention on just the act of willing myself to move forward
uh more gracefully so to speak and when I
put my intention on that intention of doing that my body just naturally did it
and I thought that was really interesting that's great great to observe sort of
essentially one you know we're bringing our awareness more intimately to something
we maybe don't usually pay attention to right and then you start to see all that
goes into walking and how it can feel quite wobbly
um and then it was it sounds like it was uh your mind responded well
to the kind of in the invocation or the intention the you know
to film Marty's or more smooth in the walking
and that was interesting for you to see just how it happened you put in an intention
and something happened and you got to witness it it wasn't like you were in there doing all these little things
right so is that uh a fair summary yeah it's like the body
had a intelligence of its own that was just sort of carrying out my wishes of
more naturalness and it just it was interesting
body does have an intelligence of its own it's a wonderful thing to witness
for sure thank you
over here Richard if you want to say your name before you
speak feel free hello everyone my name is Abhishek I was
able to actually write happy but I see you know therapy sitting there side I'll write the full name okay yeah I'm happy
to be here it's I haven't been here in a long time and just to add to what you
said Corey I was diagnosed with gout more than two months ago it's been tough but
I'm trying like this walk just a simple walk kind of made me realize where it hurts like this
deep realization I've I've had it for two months but I didn't have that realization so I would push myself to walk more but
you know just kind of figuring out how the leg balances things out and varied hurts and
where it doesn't hurt was insightful yeah yeah
foreign about walking in the hall
is it's okay to wear shoes in the hall if you need them for support okay
and it is so interesting as our bodies change over time which they do with this
and that to notice the different Sensations and the different compensations that happen and
pretty amazing the tiny little adjustments that the body's sensitive to like ah walking on
the inside of my foot the outside
I'm wondering how it is when there's a prolonged period of silence for you
during the meditation periods what are you noticing Corey thumbs up
okay Jan thumbs up
anybody struggling more when there's a longer period of quiet or is it okay just getting some feedback here about
how much guidance we're providing right yeah what
oh thank you I think my thoughts tend to wander when there's more silence
yeah but then like when um you say something else then I can bring my attention back yes
what have you noticed in your own you know have you you you're brand new yeah
did you notice anything else that you did that helped or when you noticed on your own you were thinking
um how was that for you when I noticed that I was thinking I
like thought that I'm thinking and then I would remember like what it what it
was that I was focusing on before I would try to bring myself back to that beautiful and
um so sometimes we can have that in a very simple way
or sometimes there can be added judgments to the fact that we were thinking
yeah yeah I think that would come up like I would feel like a little bad
a few times felt like I was drifting away from what I was focusing
on so one thing that has helped me is um
kind of just to know that the moment we wake up to thinking we're aware already
and that it's an opportunity to then sort of oh just appreciate oh
it happened awareness came back I mean I'm aware and and sort of choose to rest into that
and that sort of reinforces it um it is tempting to get critical but I
think that reinforces being critical as opposed to reinforcing just the
Gratitude or receptivity the appreciation that we could become
aware again um yeah so there's just just like wow
what's that's cool that's cool all of a sudden I'm aware
again sort of like and then like oh like
okay yeah this is gonna this is
that's what the Mind does it thinks So yeah thank you thank you
uh very experienced teachers have been teaching for decades say wow you know and that meditation my
mind was just thinking and thinking and they keep coming back keep coming back keep coming back so it's not a problem
which is great to discover and even when we go oh judging not a problem
um my name is Noel and this is more of a meta observation about my experience
today um because of covid and the center shutting down
after I was very very involved here it was a great loss for me and now that
it's reopening I'm very anxious that it be successful and it's reopening and
um I I experience personal disappointment when I saw that not a lot of people were here
and I began to feel like perhaps you as Leaders felt like this is a lot of
effort for 10 people and I know this is just me and I began to gallop into a
sense of um what if we can't restore its figure here and that I didn't ever have that
fear of this collapsing before covid and
this is new for me to feel this want of of
success and um and so uh you don't need to address this
because I know this is just me but this is what I sit with now
um and it does it does
um um bruise a little bit of my pleasure just
being here because of my anxiety that this um
uh Sangha be restored
and its Vitality be restored and that's what I sit with now when I'm
here so thank you so Noel I just want to thank you for sharing you know that's a
lot of mindful awareness of what is actually going on and you may not be the only person who's experiencing some you
know responses to covet and noticing what the emotions are sitting here with
the hall looking like this and also I just want to share that for
me even if one person shows up I'm delighted to be with that one person
and this song is very healthy very healthy so
thank you
yeah there's a lot of tenderness there Noel so maybe just
um really holding yourself dear you know holding the care that you're
expressing dearly the preciousness of the practice and the
Sangha yeah and then you know
great thank you
hi my name is Nena and I um wonder if
you have any additional ideas in terms of this particular
process I go through after sitting So eventually
when I said to meditate a pressure or a
pain comes to my heart and this is like I can sit for hours
with pain in my heart and I am there is the um
because of like somatic experience in training and so on
I stay there and I say to it
not that I want to disregard but I'm gonna go to other places in my
body that are comfortable right now all right and
um and so I go maybe to the back or to the hips or to the feet places where are
more quiet and um
there is so perhaps there is not perhaps there is
a kind of impatience happening within me that this is something that that this is
what it has come to be after sitting for for a long time
and and so
my question is sometimes
coming back to the breath I think has caused a certain amount of
um maybe disregarding maybe a certain amount of
like lack of a deeper relationship to that which is coming up which is
challenging and and I eventually thought that I had
created a spiritual bypass
and I this is probably you know and I just wonder
um in terms of how does if you have any any suggestions
any kind that take on this and how
do I said and lightly people who might have experiences like me said
in a way that will not create that spiritual bypass
yeah or perhaps you know redirecting but at the same time
creating a kind of deeper relationship with with what's happening
so what I'm hearing you say I'm just going to State it back to you a little to make sure that I'm clear so you've
sat for some time with a pain in your heart and you can sit for a long time
with it and then as a result of somatic experiencing training you became aware
that sometimes it's useful to turn the attention towards other areas of the
body that might be not as heavy a pain and that's a way to titrate an intense
experience that can be useful but it sounds like over time you became concerned that that could become a kind
of spiritual bypass getting around what this is trying to tell you and you were wondering whether there's a
way to be with this more fully and understand it come to be with it is am I
understanding correctly very much so except sometimes my concern
is that the instructions in their mindfulness Community might be what could also has has this spiritual bypass
yeah just like coming back to their breath coming back to the breath yeah
you know in in not creating a deeper relationship to that which is coming up
and as a result we are in a layer of okayness and underneath all of this pain
right that that I come with yes so your point into something very
important that it may be unfamiliar to people who are newer to practice but
this idea of spiritual bypass is when you you know take something that's part
of a spiritual tradition as a way to escape some of the deeper issues in your life
your body your heart so you know I could think that I'm just a really great
Buddhist sitting here with my breath and ignoring that a relationship's falling
apart or something and I could just it could feel very soothing to come back to the breath however and so you're right
that this training has that sometimes that could happen to people
don't be afraid of coming to the breath coming to the breath but as you get into
it more deeply as Nina has for many years you this is that other layer we were
talking about conditioned experience habits things in our lives that have happened trauma all kinds of experiences
may present themselves to awareness and we over time can become aware of oh boy
I keep skipping around this but maybe I need to be with it maybe I need to understand it
so because you're so alert to the possibility I have this feeling that
you're not going to fall into spiritual bypass for too long you're raising it right now it's like I wonder if I'm
doing that so I just encourage you to continue to to deepen with it if it feels like for
you I'm not going to just keep kind of stepping around it by feeling sensation
in the body or breathing I need to be with this thing and be patient with how
much it hurts and maybe occasionally not as a demand or an agenda but
occasionally drop in what is this
you know and let it reveal itself to you over time so I noticed over a long
period of time sitting here every time I would sit here I would gradually end up in this
position where one shoulder was this shoulder was tight
and I was in pain and over and I'd be like what the heck
I thought I could relax at the end of a sitting I'd be like that
again and over many years it took a long time to become aware
that this is sometimes called guarding the heart that the musculature kind of
is protecting that little heart that's been hurt so much or been through so
much in life and over many years just being aware guarding the heart what's in that heart
what's going on with that heart uh the body began to relax so that now that doesn't happen so much 18 years in
that doesn't happen very often so it's this slow peeling back and you
know I really am appreciating your awareness of this issue of when is it appropriate to
stay with it so am I understanding you and is is this helpful yeah exactly how
much attention what is appropriate to give attention to something that is challenging in in the neurology a bit
that it said becoming Amplified or you know how how to I don't
understand this is kind of a complex situation but but it is you know how to
find that balance between the neurology the amplification of an experience
and and how to kind of work with it yeah yeah I think um one of the will shift here
after I say this but um I think one thing to really pay
attention to Naina is the results of however you practice
so try practicing differently with the heart and notice
what happens like thinking about this is a feedback you're getting feedback
so you keep tuning in you know if it's um you're clear that right now you've been practicing this other way and
well it's not changing so let me try something a little different and
um and stay tuned in listening listening to what happens inside of you
and paying attention to one thing you said which was maybe there's at times some a mind or
perspective that comes up that thinks has some judgment or impatience about it
so that too don't let that slip without being seen yeah so beautiful
as Tanya said we're gonna shift gears here we're in five minutes one last Quick
comment yeah a couple of the YouTube participants which are many hundreds by the way oh
thank you YouTube are also accommodating that it's not just 10 people uh thank
you thank you we forget we have all of our companions in cyberspace so welcome to the YouTube
participants and we'll this afternoon will be attentive to questions or comments that you may have
um we're going to turn to lunch in a few minutes here and
are you surprised to learn that it's another opportunity for mindfulness so
there's a beautiful practice of mindfulness of eating that can begin
here right now as you think about oh we're about to eat lunch what comes up in you do you feel sensations of hunger
in the stomach or not hungry at all bored with lunch thinking like oh I
brought that or wow I can't wait and then as you get up and walk to lunch and
sit down and start to eat you can have a practice of noticing the sight the sound
the smell of the food you can feel the Body Sensations of
lifting it to your mouth placing it in your mouth and tasting chewing noticing the difference between
the beginning of the tasting and the end swallowing feeling the sensations of
swallowing sometimes people put their spoon or Fork down between bites and
take a breath then begin the practice again feeling the sensation of picking up the fork so it can be that detailed
or can be generally noticing what's happening to the heart and mind around eating
um budget this is an opportunity and we're going to set up tables inside and outside inside I think just outside oh
just outside okay so yeah thank you one table will be in silence if people want
silence maybe let's say to the right silence to the left we can put we could
see does anybody want to eat in silence just raise your hand great so let's put
a table on this side by the redwood tree in the gravel for silence and then there can be a couple of tables
in the parking lot perfect thank you she's been here a lot more often lately
than I have so and then there's mindfulness of
speaking and listening so if you're speaking you can pause
take a breath notice what's arising in you in terms of wanting to speak and then just being is it keeping one hand
in touch with what's going on in you as you speak when other people are speaking
mindfulness of listening am I really taking in what they're saying is is my
urgency building up oh oh I want to tell you this so there's a lot to notice
um so with that enjoy your lunch enjoy this mindfulness of eating and speaking
and please come back at 1 30.
great and then um as is the case with everything at IMC
we do it all together so Richard is grabbing tables right now we'll need to
bring chairs out so the more hands the better so please thank you enjoy yes and
in coming back you might start five or ten minutes before to help put things away and everything comes back indoors
and then come back to sitting thank you
Richard will you check the YouTube feed to see if there's any comments or questions from
okay
let me say oh look I'm looking at the schedule because maybe you could post
that we will have another question and area
well you have the schedule in front of you right can you look and and post it
okay foreign
that sounds right so just posting so people know
the information kiosk over there oh it's not huh
okay huh
okay you know how I don't know how to adjust that but you can make donations on the
website I'm not even sure who how that gets
done so but thank you I can I can find out at some point
so let's um find ourselves back and
maybe our friends will slowly return from the lunch
and we've been um sort of talking about the way of apasana is taught at least at
the center is can be thought of sort of like eccentric circles that
um we start with the breath right that that's our main sort of focus and then
we expand to include breath and body and then we go from breath body to
breath body and emotions and so that's what I'll be uh providing
guidance on in the sit is mindfulness of our emotions
um it's worth saying a few words about emotions
you know their um a pretty dynamic
part of our lives may be connected to some of our
best experiences and most difficult experiences yeah
and part of being alive is having emotions
and uh it's not possible to try and prevent having
negative emotions without also blocking positive emotions
so in this practice the aim the instructions are to learn how to be with emotions and
allow them to flow through move through without kind of trying to cling to them
or push them away the word emotion
to emote means you knows referencing this idea of letting things move through
move through us when we run into trouble with emotions
it's often because couple of metaphors come up one is we
try and block and prevent feeling certain things and then we kind of move into a frozen emotional numb space
and that frozenness is you know that kind of trying Contracting that binding
shuts us off from like I said all the aspects of Life connecting more fully
with them experiencing the small Joys even and can create distance between
ourselves and ourselves ourselves and others another uh kind of simile that describes
what can happen is a sense of trying to repress or push down certain feelings
and um it can be thought of like a spring we're pushing a spring and pushing and
pushing and pushing the spring down and at some point the spring winds and then we get flooded
with an overwhelming kind of rebound of emotions
so how do we let feelings arise and pass away and not in a
dismissive way not in a bypassing way
but um more inspirationally like allowing ourselves to be moved by experience
the Dalai Lama as kind of famous for being described as somebody who when
talking with him will just like if somebody says something he might start
just sobbing he might just allow that emotion to just come in and be expressed
and then kind of it recedes and he moves on and then the next minute he's joyful and laughing
so just sort of understanding this is part of our Human Experience
and it's we don't have to be um
like unfeeling or unbothered or unimpacted
sometimes with this practice I think some people start to feel like they should always be fine
you know it's really more about our relationship to our experience that we
want to be fine with not that we can't be moved by
the other part though is that we also don't want our emotions to carry us down
the stream emotions come with energy they they
they're like a motivational system they want us to do something they want expression
sometimes when it's you know intense feelings those expressions aren't
helpful they're harmful to ourselves or to others
so another way to think about being with emotions is to think about rivers
and emotions are like the water and the bed is like what we can learn to do and
be which is to hold the space for the flow of the water
the flow of the emotion
and sometimes we might feel like a very small River and sometimes we might feel open and
wide and expansive and like just really able to allow it all to come through
and sometimes it's actually skillful to be with emotions for a short period of
time and then to take a break the idea is yeah to let them move
through but sometimes we can't without getting carried Downstream by them so in those situations we need to keep
Discerning wisdom on board what can I manage what am I able to open
up to right now
another thing that's I think very helpful to kind of uh some science about
this that I think helps me there's the book my stroke of insight by
Jill bolt Taylor I don't know if you're familiar with it it's a great book but one of the things
she says in this book is the natural lifespan of an emotion
meaning the average time it takes for it to move through the nervous system and body
is a minute and a half a minute and a half
so sometimes if we just sort of hold that in mind it can help us turn
toward and be willing tricky part is it really doesn't matter
how we are with those emotions because we all know we don't just fill things for a minute and a half all the time
and what happens then is that we're retriggering our thoughts our reactions you know feed
that emotional so it just keeps getting triggered and triggered and triggered and triggered and triggered
but each time we trigger hypothetically it's another minute and a half so at any time we can pull back
stop the reactivity stop the in the Buddha's simile he talks about
getting hit with an arrow and how that causes pain or
you know pain to us and then he says
now imagine getting struck with another arrow and another arrow
do they keep hurting and does the pain grow over time yeah yes I would say yes
and so the Buddha is essentially saying in the simile when he talks about it that those extra arrows are the optional
arrows that's the re-triggering and retriggering of emotional states and the
self-criticism and the other kind of discursive mental formations and
thoughts and stories and and emotional reactions to our reactions that keep
causing deeper and deeper pain suffering
so can we just let the one Arrow come in and be with it without adding
more Gil gives an example and so such a silly simple example his his examples usually
are which speaks to their Brilliance I think of being a meditation teacher he talks
about walking outside and tripping so he hurts his toe because he trips
and then that's the first Arrow that's the like that's the pain of
stubbing one's toe and then he wonders
oh did somebody see me do I look like a fool
oh my God I'm a meditation teacher I wasn't being mindful or I wouldn't have
tripped right and on and on the Mind goes
just on and on just Adam I so stupid how could I have not been what was I lost
and thought about you know and we're just it's Arrow after Arrow after Arrow
so when we when we notice this happening maybe just go okay enough I don't want
to keep shooting arrows at myself here enough it's enough this hurts
and this hurts I care
so feeling into your posture finding your body here taking the time
to roll the shoulders up and back
inviting some deeper press in so we habitually Lean Forward
over our phones and computers and then it closes the chest
which shuts the lungs down from breathing fully so rolling those shoulders up and back
can really help just let the lungs do what they know how to do breathe
ah
so we'll start finding our posture again
and if your anchor is the breath connecting with that anchor to help
ourselves ground in this moment come back into direct contact
with what's happening Sensations the feeling the receptive feeling of
sound we don't have to know what's making a sound we can just know the experience of
hearing we don't know have don't have to know what's causing a sensation in the body
we can just receive the experience
being with our experience directly and simply
hmm yeah breathing in and breathing out
breathing in I know I'm breathing in
breathing out knowing breathing out
giving space for things to settle in the body heart
and mind being generous
with our experience
sometimes the settling is really about more our response
to what's arising then to what is arising so if a thought a Feeling
a sensation comes up if we can be with it really simply
sort of like water and a pond
we might be able to toss some little rocks little pebbles in and
they create a little wave pattern on the surface
and then things settle and slow smooth
but if we toss a little Pebble in and then we follow that petal into the water
walk on the bottom of the Little Pond try and find that Pebble again
that whole process stirs up so much more activity
so if we can let a thought or a feeling come up and just sort of Ripple across the water and be simple with it it'll
settle on its own
but if we feel we need to argue with it comment on it
try and get rid of it we might just be stirring things up
so because emotions can be complicated for us
I'm gonna offer a very structured practice a guided practice
with the acronym of raft with two T's r-a-f-t-t
it's one way to practice with emotions
so I want to invite you to notice what emotions are present for
you right now
it's maybe simply noting naming them this is the r of rafter recognizing
kind of a simple acknowledgment I see you sadness I see you anxiety I
see you whatever is there
and of the things that are present
is there something small and manageable
an emotion that you can turn toward that's a small little thing
a small Ripple tolerable
and if so the next part of the practice is the a
which is just allowing the truth of this emotion to be seen and felt acknowledged
can we allow knowing and connecting with this emotion In This
Moment
and if there is a simple sort of yes
find and feel where that emotion resides in the body
maybe leaving the story connected to it behind
and simply finding and feeling if there's a no I can't really allow or
feel it's not tolerable then maybe you can turn toward the
resistance that feeling of not okay
too much and practice with that welcome that
maybe it's your friend maybe it's wise
and can you find and feel where that resides in the body how it
feels in the body
not resisting and not succumbing
not resisting and not so coming being the banks of the river
allowing the emotional energy to flow through
and that may be all you need to do with this emotion it may be over a minute and a half come
and gone
if so enjoy relax
and maybe when another emotion comes up that you feel you can practice with you
might name it recognize it create an atmosphere of allowing
if it's tolerable and finding it feeling it in the body
sort of leaving the story behind
if you're still working with an emotion the next part of the practice
the T is to tease apart the different pieces
that are here meaning there might be a memory
an image a story
a belief an expectation
or all of the above present as well
so I'd like to imagine for myself a big spacious room
maybe even like a cathedral it's just very large
and maybe there's a big table or maybe there are chairs spread around
and inviting each thing that you notice that comes up that's connected to this
emotion to have its own space its own seat
as many chairs as much space as needed there's enough room
sometimes maybe something needs to go in another room
watch out for thoughts like yeah why did I do that again because that that is yet
another part to tease apart giving that space
there might be a feeling of bracing that might need space
sort of untangling all the things that get put together in
the mind to create one experience that's really a combination of many
different things
maybe imagining all these pieces sitting around the table
but you get to sit at the head of the table your awareness your choice
just taking it in with some distance perspective
and whatever has occurred has occurred without expectations
to end the practice we add a second t and that tea is Trust
finding and connecting with what we can trust in this situation
can we trust awareness mindfulness
can we trust the idea that emotions come and go
that things change
can you trust that you no
something important here and rest rest in whatever you can
take refuge in what you can trust the Dharma
the Buddha the Sangha
and see if you can linger here and what you can trust for the last few
minutes of the practice
I'm gonna drop in a reflection for the last two minutes of practice
my emotions can be thought of in lots of different ways
Helen Keller said the best and most beautiful things in
the world cannot be seen or even touched
they must be felt with a heart
[Music] foreign
[Music]
so staying in silence we have a 15 minute stretch or walking break
before we come back for instructions on mindfulness of thinking so we will begin
at 2 20 with the next meditation
so we'll be doing a guided mindfulness of thinking meditation
giving yourself time to settle into a meditative posture
that's comfortable for you perhaps gently closing your eyes
and giving some attention to your spine
perhaps sitting up a little straighter than usual at this time in the afternoon
to bring some energy into the body
perhaps emphasizing the in-breath a little bit to bring in that energy
and creating a strong core around which you can relax
perhaps taking a few long slow full breath
as you breathe in
feeling energy enter the body as you breathe out
some ease
perhaps as you breathe in feeling the rib cage expand
the front of the rib cage in the back of the rib cage
and softening them as you breathe out
breathing in and breathing out perhaps softening the muscles of the
face
releasing the shoulders
softening the belly thank you
letting your breath return to normal however that is right now
seeing if there's a way the breathing can support the uprightness of the spine
in the sense of ease
and then as we've done before Beginning by entering into the world of breathing
into the way your body experiences breathing
for now letting go of any thoughts or concerns
so you can better feel and sense the physical experience of breathing
noticing how the inhalation differs from the exhalation
if any thoughts arise either letting go of them or perhaps
letting them recede into the background
so that in the foreground you're with your breathing
feeling the full breath in from start to finish
feeling the top of the breath where it switches to breathing out
feeling the full breath out
giving yourself over to your breathing
so that breathing has a chance to settle you and calm you
ground the attention Center the attention in yourself around the
breathing
foreign
natural simply notice it
and gently re-center yourself around the breathing
thank you for the next several minutes
gently letting go of any thinking that arises after noticing it
and re-establishing yourself in feeling the breathing
and now with calm and deliberateless deliberateness
letting go of your breathing of paying attention to your breathing
and simply notice when you're thinking
you're welcome to think no need to stop thinking now
but as you're thinking being clearly aware that thinking is happening
rather than letting go of thinking looking at thinking directly
head on
your thoughts disappear or fade away as you watch them
quite natural just waiting until they come back or
going back to mindfulness of breathing until you notice thinking begins again
when thinking begins again clearly knowing it
being aware that it's happening
perhaps when you notice thinking arising
Whispering very very softly in the mind thinking
thinking very Softly
foreign
what you are thinking is not so important
but as you're paying attention to thinking and meditation perhaps noticing other aspects of it
besides the content
you might notice if you're thinking in images
or it's like a movie
perhaps you're thinking in words
or conversation
foreign
what's the quality of the images are they
fuzzy or clear
if you're thinking in words what's the tone of those words
is there an inner voice that thinks
is it harsh or is it soft and gentle
thank you
are your thoughts pushing you or critical
or are they supportive accepting
just allowing yourself to explore the process the quality
the texture of the thoughts
is there a lot of energy in the thinking or is the thinking very subtle
or almost elusive
you might notice if there are any emotions connected to what you're
thinking about
the thinking might be coming out of a particular emotion
or connected with it and if that's so
quietly note the emotion
as well as the thinking
if thinking goes away as you're mindful of it allowing the space that's left behind
enjoying the spaciousness of a quiet mind
perhaps noticing if there's a physical side to any thinking
is there any pressure or tension connected to thinking
somewhere in the body tightness or even pressure in the brain
that feels activated with thinking as part of it
any tightening of the forehead or around the eyes
and possibly releasing softening any tension you find
or pressure perhaps
as you exhale releasing the tension the way you might
relax a muscle relaxing the thinking muscle
foreign
and now letting go of thinking enough to re-enter
breathing re-centering yourself on breathing
gently letting go of any thoughts perhaps letting them recede into the
background
in re-entering into the world of your breathing
thank you hanging in there with the breathing
perhaps seeing if you can stay connected through a whole series of breaths
full experience of breathing in and breathing out
foreign
perhaps taking a couple of deep breaths
sitting and when you're ready opening your eyes
foreign
like life on planet Earth can be likened to living here with all
kinds of variations in the weather we have periods in meditation when it's
like a calm day with blue skies and no wind just peaceful
other times it's like a storm has arisen and suddenly we're in the middle of
thunder clouds of emotion or a blizzard of thoughts or it's a very very hot
day and the body is very uncomfortable
sometimes the analogy is used that the mind is like a clear blue sky and
thoughts are like the clouds passing by we establish mindfulness of the breath
of breath relaxed and tented
and sooner or later a thought Cloud floats by
or a whole storm of thoughts come by we may not even see it coming we just
suddenly aware that we've been caught on those thought clouds for some time
a really common one is planning that were tomorrow bubbles up in your
mind or later today bubbles up in your mind and you're thinking of what you're going to say or do
a thought comes along about the past and you start living in the world of
regrets or beautiful memories how wonderful the past was
you've still gotten on a cloud the mind is caught Maybe by these
passing clouds and storms and some are beautiful you know thinking is totally
healthy and appropriate at different times and they can carry us away into areas
where we lose our stability or our groundedness and we lose our independence from what's
what we're thinking about we're really caught in it so one of the things we're doing with
mindfulness and meditation practice is we're returning again and again to the
groundedness of awareness we use awareness of the breathing awareness of
the body awareness of motions awareness of thinking itself thinking thinking and learning not to
get totally lost in the weather whatever the weather is
so you can you can't stop thinking from arising and you need not try
but you don't necessarily have to pick it up maybe you had a little bit of an experience with this meditation then
instead of picking up the content you could look at oh I'm noticing how my face and head tense
up when I'm thinking or noticing the tone of The Voice or the kinds of images
that arise or simply noticing the fact of thinking
it's a huge and important part of human life so we're not anti-thinking in the scene
and when we learned to clearly see it we have a choice with it we have a
choice of how to relate to it instead of being dragged around by our thinking
and wherever it wants to go we start to become a little less identified with it we we are not our thoughts during the
class that Tanya and Koto have been teaching they read this lovely book you are not your thoughts a child's book but
could be an adult book it's a great book um and a lot of times we we tend to
believe for a while that we are our thoughts that's who we are but actually if we you
know it's kind of like if I stop thinking then who am I where am I so it
can be challenging to let go of all the stories we create about ourselves the interpretations we
have of events past present future so an important really important part of
mindfulness is learning to see this phenomenon of thinking
we're not at war with it we're not trying to push it away or say it's bad
but we can notice some thinking's painful some is pleasant we get to be
more grounded with it and um start to notice things we haven't
noticed before about our thinking you know are we ruminating a lot stirring up
a lot of anxiety trying to rework the past until it works out just right I used to rework the past all the time
like trying to make a more perfect past in my thinking guess what it never
worked um or to control okay if I just can figure this out I can control the chaos
that is life so by learning to be mindful of thinking
we can start to notice those patterns oh look at that I'm planning again look at
that I'm ruminating look at that I'm fantasizing and drifting off into this Pleasant
feeling um just noticing the emotional quality that
it can have sometimes the tone of voice you hear all these aspects are really
giving you information about how you've been conditioned and it's valuable every time you step
back from thinking and just notice that it's happening you're no longer enmeshed
in it and this is actually a huge movement of mind
and it takes time it takes time because we've developed a lifetime of being enmeshed and engaged in our thinking
so it's not always easy I for a while I had to deliberately think thoughts to be
mindful while thinking those thoughts in order to catch the feeling of what this was like
I'm sometimes thinking just evaporates when you're all ready to work with it poof it's gone
or it can be quite clear but when just this is an invitation when
it arises in meditation and it's easy to let go of
Let It Go and come back to the breathing come back to the body when it's difficult
you know sooner or later it's going to be difficult and you're going to be caught and you're going to think oh my
gosh I was just gone for the last half hour thinking
and you when you come back that's always a great Moment Like Tanya was saying I'm back
I was aware that thinking was just happening um and you can think oh I was caught in
thinking it's not a huge problem we're just developing the awareness of coming back and then noticing as much of it as
we can things were strengthening our ability to
be aware in the here and now which leads to more freedom
so thank you for that and we're now you know let's give 15
minutes I agree so we're going to take a 15 minute break you can walk you can
stretch so enjoy the 15 minutes and come back at 3 10 please
okay
as you come in and take your seats just kind of notice
notice how you are now live allow yourself some space to
receive and connect your own experience right now
after this day of practice
feeling tired
feeling energized
just caring just meeting what shows up with a sense
of receptivity [Music] welcoming
allowing
inviting the inside Space to be like the meditation Hall
there's a lot more space than there are things
in the same way can we open up inside expand our
awareness the way we're holding and create the sense of spaciousness
and just taking these first few minutes to just Witness what's coming up in our own minds hearts
and bodies foreign
maybe there were moments today of surprise
I remember during a walking period the wind was blowing and
the redwood tree you know it was like rain it sounded
like rain and every little dried little thing that
came down made me smile I felt joyful it was like I was so present for this
delight the surprise the warm air but with wind and the sound
of rain but knowing it wasn't water just like maybe there were some moments
like that to you that happened to you today a different way of relating to a thought
or a Feeling just giving it some space right now
to be held in this maybe wide Riverbank
and maybe some of the things that arise right now they might need a little
more snuggly energy they might need the riverbank to be a little
closer and so playing with that too
opening a little bit again and then feeling what needs a little
more tension touching a little more connection [Music]
and then resting back again
and just like the sky is incredibly spacious so generous
does this guy care that planes fly through
does it care that there's a weather storm or that it's clear now the sky is fine
with it all it knows it's the sky
nothing offends it there's room for it all
and this is the the type of practice we'll invite now
spacious open awareness
and when you find that you have a hard time being spacious
it's okay to find your anchor and breathe a little bit
grounding centering and then when it feels okay to relax and
open up again no problems can't do anything wrong no
mistakes just being as easy as you can with
whatever arises and using the skills and tools we covered today as you need them trusting
yourself paying attention to the results of how you meet your
experience so maybe putting your hand on your heart
just a sense of okay I can feel myself I'm here
I'm gonna bear loving Witness just setting an intention really
inviting the mind a heart the body to be open
and for awareness to witness [Music]
it all
can we be the knowing be with the knowing
allowing experience thoughts emotions to move through and watch
but we don't have to be them I'm Not My Thoughts I'm not my feelings
it's a part of my experience and I could know it
can be with it
foreign
to notice things
we come into a space and we notice the chairs or the decorations or the
people how someone's dressed or what we're trained to do
so in this practice the invitation is actually to do the opposite
to notice the space in between things
to look up around to broaden expand
to invite the mind to be open spacious
to connect with awareness knowing at all
and noticing the space
the emptiness
the allowing
the mind can be boundless
it might be really helpful to notice the gaps
the end of a sound
it's fading away
new sounds will come and then noticing when they fade
it's very natural for the mind to
move from one thing to the next
what we can do is hold our attention
on the gaps endings
sort of sinking into it
letting it soak in those moments of quiet or
is
noticing receiving
the space
if it feels appropriate for you you might
I'll tell you this and you can decide if you want to try this
but you might actually very gently and slowly open your eyes
and just notice where the eyes go what they take in
and then see if you can't
shift your gaze something that is space
a gap the openness the light
and just try and hold your attention on that emptiness
that space
the objects are still there
but we're shifting our awareness
to what we're taking in
in the same way you may close your eyes again and just see how that helps you
practice in the last five minutes with connecting with the spaciousness
the sky Within
I'm going to ring the bell slowly
and allow silence between the bells to allow you space and time
before you come out of the meditation to stay with
[Music]
foreign taking some time to stand and stretch or
to shift the position of the body as you need
noticing how the body is right now
foreign
thank you
we now have another period for Reflections questions
anything that you'd like to share and I'd like to include the YouTube
folks so thanks Richard for noticing anything
that they have to share but just could be anything about the meditation you just or the
meditations you just went through the day a general question
or a reflection on what you've been noticing and how that is for you
yes please
all right um okay so I've been meditating for a
few months and I've noticed that it does help with like the I guess like the strength of
thoughts and emotions but as you kind of dig deeper into some of like the
thoughts and emotions they tend to be triggered by specific like strong negative core beliefs so all meditation
seems to help like mitigate the symptoms of these core beliefs it doesn't really feel like it helps
really address the issue at hand which is like these strong negative core beliefs so I'm curious how you work with
that well first of all it's great that you notice that they're coming out of these
core beliefs you know we all get conditioned into beliefs views about ourself about others
and about how the world works over a lifetime so the fact that you've
identified that is great and I would say allowing time for yourself to see the
manifestations of that is much more valuable than you might imagine because
sometimes these play out in how we hold our body
how we think what emotions come up how we interact it's a huge world
so taking time to notice that world and the core and
then over time there may be something evident about what's underneath the core
beliefs or what all is in there I mean gradually kind of unfold for you
and ultimately it's just a process that I think requires a lot of patience
great great question great observation I think I just I I want to offer
something just to see because you know some people are more or less connected with this idea of core beliefs
um maybe a way to think about a core belief is sort of like um
the Earth is round it's like kind of a fact
right for most of us not all of us but it's just it within your own being
it's so just unquestionable it's just there it's like almost you don't even
know it's there because it's so just accepted
and a view might be more like um or a general belief might you might notice it
sounds like something in your head it's more like a
you know it's really impolite to do X
you're supposed to stop at the stop sign all the way not roll like that's like
more of like um more of a kind of a belief that's just sort of you know something that you
if there's more narration around it narrative right so just to try and get a
feel for how core beliefs exist within us they're very they're kind of
structural foreign they're kind of structural so they can be hard to notice
and um so you know when we and they are very influential in terms of like uh
very influential in in some ways that are it's a kind of I don't know out of
sight almost but just holding that just sort of
seeing Oh there's a core belief and like sort of maybe doing some of
this opening around it with this curiosity like is the Earth
really round how do I know that it's round you know kind of idea and
what happens if I believe the Earth is round what would it be like if I believe the Earth was flat instead
sort of just loosening it up a little bit and exploring it in that way can
might be helpful thank you one of the things I really
appreciate the way Tanya opened that up just now and some examples this is where
practice often leads us we we may be going along noticing our
thoughts noticing the patterns of our emotions and what happens in suddenly discover that we have a core belief
I'm not good enough or a core belief other people do stuff wrong and that's
what makes me unhappy so there there are very many of these
but that is actually what often what this meditation peels back to reveal
that helpful great other Reflections comments or questions
things you notice today that you'd like to share with others as a gift
um I would just like to say that I'm just kind of Blown Away with how moved I
am just to be in the space again after covid and and the Buddha statue so unperturbed
and the redwood tree you know that um it's just
I don't know just a lot of feelings have come up and I want to say thank you Liz
and Tanya I feel very nurtured
you Jan maybe I'll say to this moment that um
I also feel very nurtured by the YouTube people it really helps me to know that there's
this worldwide net of people connected to IMC and practicing with us supporting
us and how important each of you are here to help
you know you're helping create the space that holds what we're all sharing
together so thank you Jan and every one of you and all of you out there
all right Naina yeah to your question about the gift um to give it's mostly
really appreciation for for both of you for the
effort you have put into coming and making this space available for us
and I too have felt the care that you have put into it and so so thank you I'm
so touched
thank you So speaking of YouTube great Diane is
your last name working with emotions I sometimes tend to go down the rabbit hole of looking for why that emotion
came up yeah that's a really good observation
and there's so there are many different ways to work with emotions one thing
that's interesting about mindfulness is oftentimes we can let go of the why and
notice that something is happening anger is arising
Palm is arising Joy is arising disappointment is arising just that we
notice that's Rising we notice how it affects the body we notice how thoughts
May spin out of it so that's one very uh amazing advantage of mindfulness that
sometimes we don't have to know why and things can transform just by noticing
them and that they arise and that they're Rising of course it can be very
helpful to understand the origin of motions as well so sometimes
meditators may spend time journaling or reflecting on the the background of
their emotional life what you were taught to accept as common emotions growing up
with the people you grew up with what emotions surface most frequently so
this this is also a very worthy area of of study so there's no one way but there
are many ways to work with it thank you Liz um Diane is that what her name was Diane
um one thing I want to say to Diane is you describe something so for me
visceral which is the rabbit hole going down the rabbit hole which
um it describes actually to me it says you have an awareness of what it feels like to get
entangled and caught in the emotion that's sort of how it feels in in my
body so that is a huge gift that you can describe it that way
and so again sort of the opposite of
that might be the riverbed allowing things to flow through the opening up
around the experience even if you find yourself in the rabbit hole it's like this and then okay so I feel like this
and then you know is it possible to open up around it
is it possible to kind of create a little bit of space because
emotion is an experience it's an experience we're having but
again it's not Who We Are and if we're over involved in it we're
um we don't have the space to let it move through and we tend to be re-igniting reigniting and then the
teasing apart idea of that the raft practice where we tease it apart here is
a memory here's a view here's a core belief you know here's an image just trying to
again it's like everything gets knotted up and tied up together
and it's pretty hard to deal with things when they're like that so relaxing
opening and then sort of helping sift through can be helpful so I'll ask Diane
if she feels that that was helpful if she has any further questions she can
well she's responded a little bit so great uh because she's typing and I'm
speaking for her so she says thank you and then yes as you describe the rabbit
hole process and then she says the rabbit hole to me seems more like the thinking process around the emotion
and then Diane says the why of it sort of thinking about the emotion the why of
it which is reminding me true too yeah um really good points that she's raising
that and that tiny just alluded to that there's such a thing as fuel that we
throw on the Fire we're in the rabbit hole and we throw more thoughts in and we're down further
in the rabbit hole or we can have this thought of is there any way I can open out of this
so um this is a huge area practice and I'd encourage patients
infinite patience for allowing Discovery over time
about emotions I have a great quote I want to share if
I can find it um it's by Rick rorden
you can't think your way out of your emotions you can't think your way out of emotions
doesn't work yeah they're already here for one thing
they and they are a record perhaps of our conditioning because they show us in a moment in a
Flash how we've been conditioned you know around
oops around the thoughts that have FedEd the
experiences that have had it they're kind of a flash reaction summarizing the past
all right Diane says thank you great great
almonds great Iris
uh there Naina has it thank you Naina
okay um I guess the question before kind of brought up so if you like or with an
emotion and maybe you don't really understand why it was triggered do you just kind of let that be and be okay
with it in summary like as you're trying to tease it apart maybe you don't understand like what
specifically caused it um that's part of that you recognize
what you can about it you allow what it is even if it's kind of unknown it's
kind of murky allow it feel it however it feels notice where it
is in the body and even if you can't tease it apart that kind of accept allow feel will
serve you trust that it's there for a reason it's you know it's coming up for
in response to something and you can be with the fact that it's there
hmm yeah that's you know one thing to know it helps me sometimes to look at
neuroscience and what we know from that about studying the brain and one way
they describe the brain in Neuroscience is that it is an organ and its job is to
predict and it predicts based on past experience or associations
and so sometimes emotions can be triggered before we're even conscious of what's going on because the the brain is
predicting something and it doesn't come to be but the emotion still got triggered or we don't notice that it
didn't come to be whatever we were expecting because we get so caught up in our our predicting or anticipating you
know mind so it's a tricky thing
thank you and also thank you for taking the data set this is very helpful
great
I think one of the um the gifts of mindfulness
is it gives us choice having the capacity to sit back a bit
to observe to pause gives us so much more freedom in our
life so much more choice without it without the mindfulness
without the capacity to kind of let go or sit back
here's a quote a different quote about emotions I feel like this is what can happen to us it's not it's Elizabeth
Gilbert says this and it I don't think it's a fact the way it is but without mindfulness I think it's what happens
your emotions are the slaves to your thoughts
and you are the slave to your emotions and that's what happens without
the capacity to witness to observe to know to let go to pause to breathe to choose
pointing to something really valuable about mindfulness meditation practice
and where this leads because you'll come to a point after you've done this for a
while where you can see the rabbit hole you can go I'm not going down that
rabbit hole it's not worth it I could worry and worry about this thing that's never happened
most of the horrible experiences in my life have never happened it's just the mind has created these and
so you can see the choice after a time after observing these things for a while
or the horrible experience happened once but I've relived it a hundred times
and I didn't have to yeah
any last comments
things that have happened that you're sitting with
so I'd like to invite everybody to take a moment to recognize how much you've
been through today you've actually been through a
significant amount of practice and training a whole day devoted to
mindfulness to seeing what's coming up
and how that's been for you maybe some things you really found
helpful you could use them it was really great and some things were challenging
or maybe it was all challenging or it was all helpful so just appreciating that whatever you
put into today every moment of mindfulness matters is
what that's what I've noticed in the years of practice that every moment every
sitting it may not the fruits of it may not be apparent right away
in fact it often isn't but later something has subtly shifted something
shows up it's like wow it really was useful it really was useful to sit
and maybe reflecting for a moment are you do you feel different in some ways
than when you came in this morning
and then how what's your relationship with how it was today
meaning do you have an attitude towards it like yeah that felt that felt
really good and wonderful or while I'm worried I'm not sure I can get this thing or it could be anything but just
taking a moment to notice what your relationship is with what has happened
today is just information about conditioning
we could look at today as a day full of experimentation and play and just
learning new things
one of the things that can be helpful is um reflecting on any wholesome or helpful
or good feeling that has come up for you today or is present with you right knee
now even if you're just a little bit calmer than you were when you came in
this morning that landing on and feeling
beneficial feelings or body States or states of
mind or even the spaciousness that Tanya just invited us into just that quality
of spaciousness when we take the time out to appreciate those
feel them that reinforces those beautiful qualities and the
can realize again
and if today showed you some difficulties some areas
that were challenging I'd like to say that's also excellent that you saw that and to keep in mind
that this is called the gradual path it slowly unfolds us
in our own time allow that allow it to unfold
there's a a kind of story I'm going to paraphrase maybe not quite accurately
but a story in one of the books that Gil francon has written called the monastery
within that's about you know a monastic who's living in the monastery who's on
fire to be totally free and asks the abbess so how long will it take me if I
really really focus on this and the Abba says you know something maybe seven years and
the the monastic says yeah but what if I really work on it harder oh it'll take a
lot longer so I love that story because
you know we can we can move at a more natural pace and let ourselves
unfold and show us what we need to look at and know
we don't need to rush ourselves another thing Gill says that I really
love is that if this practice leads us to full
Liberation in this lifetime wonderful but if it doesn't we've lived a way
better life in the process and I'll attest that the last 18 years of my life
have been happier and happier and happier and more
smooth and free of Affliction so what's not to love about that
one of the things you can do taking this practice back into your life
is use some of these tools even during the middle of the day I've known parents that have trained
their young children to we're both going to stop right now and we're just going to take three breaths
I've had a practice for a long time of whenever I get up from my chair
at work or at home I tune into the body and how it feels to walk to the restroom
to the kitchen wherever I'm going I just feel that walking so there's these mini mindfulness breaks
throughout the day and as you pay attention taking breaks
out to breathe paying attention to the body catching yourself in the middle of
thinking or a Feeling you could say You're Building more
steadiness more collectedness more sometimes it's called concentration
but by noticing these things in some of the questions we can notice
what we're feeding there's this story about um the wolf you feed and the Wolf you feed
grows stronger and the Wolf you don't feed grows weaker so we can watch what
we're feeding you know as we watch our thoughts as we watch our
emotions and as we watch our attitudes we can understand what have I been
feeding am I feeding things that are helping me or am I
feeding things that are making things harder for me these are just some of the things that may come up for you
so as we leave today um this is you know a wonderful Center that
has a lot of programs that can help you continue this practice Tanya's going to have a class
in building a practice that's coming up so I'd encourage you to attend that and
about a month from now I think there will be another day long with kodo and Tanya
so that's a resource there are sittings on Sundays Monday nights there's a half
day on Wednesday that's wonderful to attend if your schedule has that flexibility and there are all kinds of
programs Tuesday Morning Thursday evening so there's a a lot of ways here
to continue to cultivate your practice it's valuable to continue to to build a
daily practice of finding a time of day that you can do this sitting practice
that works for you and sometimes it takes some experimentation you know first thing in the morning is better or
the evening or do I do it during my lunch break but even if you start small
you know start with a 20-minute meditation do that for a while then
maybe 25 or even if it's 20 21 22 you
can build a practice but the the daily quality of it can really help to
reinforce what you've been learning today and um it's very interesting but often the day
goes better no matter what kind of sitting you have quite an interesting phenomenon
we have a library here with lots of different books on Buddhism that can be checked out and brought back
there's as you know there are these online offerings gills morning sitting
and Dharma talk so there are tons of tools and
opportunities here at IMC and online the YouTube folks I'm I'm usually one of
you I don't live here so I'm normally out there in cyberspace with the rest of
you so I wonder if there are any questions
about what's available here or about Tanya's class maybe you could say a little bit
about when that's going to be it started last week oh great Thursday
but pretty much every Thursday night assuming people show up I'll be teaching
a class one class after another so right now the plan is establishing a practice
is the focus for the month of September October will be let's talk about
practice November we'll be living the practice
December will be the four noble truths so each month will sort of be a class
format where there's a combination of teachings practice guided practices and
small group discussions and Q a so would love to see any of you there at any time
thank you and it will be on YouTube yes
I forgot to mention one of my favorites that happens here every night every week
night at six o'clock uh Pacific time is called happy hour
and happy hour is dedicated to some practices that uh
we work with qualities of loving kindness or we could just call it
kindness compassion equanimity sympathetic Joy so the qualities of the
heart that are that really feel good and actually that's the way we're going to end today so some of you may never have
heard of this practice before but we'll just do a couple of minutes of it
and so you may find a comfortable posture this time
and allow yourself to take some breaths
sometimes this kindness practice or loving kindness practice
which is also called meta practice is done in the form of phrases
so we'll do just a little bit of that right now bring to mind
the effort that you've put in today the way you
've come back to the breath come back to the body and worked with what we've presented
today really bringing that fully into your mind and heart seeing
that really wonderful effort on your part
and seeing that part of yourself that would really like to be more free in the world be more
peaceful in the world happier in the world and sing to that part of yourself
may I be healthy
may I be happy sincerely wishing that for yourself
may I be safe and free from all harm
may I be peaceful
we've been taking the part of yourself that may have had some difficult moments
today or found some things challenging bringing that to mind as a dear friend
thinking of your dear friend and wishing
may I be happy
even in the face of difficulty may I be healthy
may I be safe and free from all harm
may I be peaceful
[Applause] days like this are possible because you've all come together
in in YouTube and here in the room we've supported one another to do this
practice looking around and seeing each other sincerely working with this
so we can extend these same wishes to one another may you be healthy
may you be happy
may you be safe and free from all harm
may you be peaceful
and taking all the benefit that we've experienced from today that
we know of and the benefits we don't yet know of we can wish them for the world around us
may this practice that we've done today
Ripple out and benefit those close to us in our lives
and to strangers whom we don't know
by dedicating the benefit of this practice whatever it might be
to all the people and creatures around us may you all be healthy
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe and free from harm
may all beings be peaceful and free
foreign [Music]
[Music]
here and for those who are here in this room
and that offered to stay for 15 minutes to do some cleaning thank you so much
and um Richard are you able to um you know what Nana you have managed
so much would you mind organizing the cleaning so he can address the the recording
so everybody who is willing to help clean up
Nina will organize you all and Liz thank you so much for being here today oh it
was so fun thank you oh my gosh what a delight it's a treat to teach with one
another we haven't had that opportunity in years and a big thank you and from
our hearts to you on YouTube look forward to being with you again
so we're transitioning to cleaning and I will be mentioning a few a few things
so just wait