so so hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour this rendition of it
wherever you're joining from from this planet of ours also whether
you're joining on zoom or on youtube we have friends joining on youtube also or joining later
on audio dharma lovely to be practicing together so
so for our practice together i wanted to invite us to consider um
[Music] maybe the the phrase that comes to my
mind and captures the invitation for the way um to to relate to meta to
kindness to care um tonight for ourselves and for others
is by the phrase you matter you matter
you matter ah just feeling the power of the strength
of that and maybe sometimes it's easier to see yourselves
say that to others either literally or through our actions people
who really matter for us in our lives they matter we're grateful that they're
in our lives they're alive um either human beings or
or or pets children well children are human beings too but pets
you matter you matter there's a sense of of course you matter of course you matter and can we have that
same sense of yes i matter the same way that
other people other beings are instrumental i feel they're instrumental
in my happiness in my in in the the difference that they make
for me their existence in the world they it they have and they continue to be
that i matter too i matter so taking shifting perspectives
and and and extending the same care the same importance the same acceptance the
same love same meta to ourselves so that's the invitation instead of
invitations i will make tonight to work with this this idea this this
way of relating to others and ourselves um is it different it's it's a um
different way of of thinking about meta of care
of um [Music] of warm-heartedness of friendliness
there's this sense of yes you matter let me embrace you let me care for you you
matter so different images might come up anyway
let me see if there's anything else i want to say to set the stage um yeah and if you're new to happy hour
whatever you need will be shared with you [Music] relax and enjoy the ride and whatever
arises is the right thing that it needs to arise and if
if the opposite say arises for you like oh i feel like i don't matter
can you bring kindness can you bring compassion can you breathe bring care
to whatever arises to whatever arises work with that
with kindness um and let that thought actually yes you
matter oh the thought of thoughts of sadness yeah you matter too i'm not gonna
dismiss you you matter you play you play a role in my life too
so let's let's play around and see what might open up with with an attitude of
care um yeah and mental so yeah that's all i want to
say to set it up tonight so so let's begin
let's begin by landing in our
seats starting our meditation [Music]
landing in our seats if you need to shift or move your body so that you can
sit comfortably for the next 30 minutes this is a good time to roll your shoulders maybe move
left and right front and back or maybe you need to stand up to standing meditation for the next 30
minutes or maybe you need to lie down that's okay too see what your body needs
lying down as long as you won't fall asleep and for most of you sitting
landing landing in your seat
in your sit bones
ah can we take this attitude of you matter with our bodies with our sit
bones with our bum contacting the cushion the chair
and resting relaxing releasing [Music] interested bones
letting the upper body be heavy
forehead soft
the jaw released
the tongue resting your eyes also resting
in their socket
let the chest relax release
the upper chest the lower chest the end of the diaphragm
ah the abdomen be at ease
releasing the upper leg the lower leg
and feet
letting them rest on the earth
their weight offered to theirs
my thoughts are rising it's okay
this mind thinks just like
puppies run around mind thinks
any sense of ease smilingly releasing
taking refuge a few minutes just spending the time
with the breath with the body
just calming settling soothing the heart the mind
this moment matters what we do in this moment matters
so releasing rejoicing
the breath in the presence here
you are able to be together and practice
letting go of all the previous moments whatever they were
five minutes ago today especially if you had a challenging day
it's gone it's in the past this moment matters
afresh inhabiting this moment afresh
arriving like the spring
how we incline this how we incline our mind in this moment
matters release release relax
receive
spaciously
letting the breath be soothing calming
maybe child breath releases more deeply arriving in this moment
and as we bring our hearts our minds
together collecting gathering settling
with the breath with the body here
consider that every breath matters matters to you
matters to your body to millions billions of cells
of your body
to all the friendly microbes in your biome that call you home
each breath matters to them
each heartbeat matters
each part of your body matters
and just connecting with the breath in breath out breath
each life-giving breath
to settle
and now as we feel our feed on the earth our sid bones
our hands age breath settling calming
feeling embodied so i make these following invitations
not getting into our head thinking so much but staying in body
bringing to mind to your heart space actually bringing to your heart space
inviting someone who matters to you
some being [Music] who matters welcoming them wholeheartedly into your heart's face
as if you're embracing them
if you have a party in your heart with banners you matter
with balloons streamers
celebrating celebrating this being
you have a little loving parade in your heart for them with joy
very quiet one
a parade in their honor you matter
we'll invite others later but right now just stay with this one being
it's okay to have fun relishing this image this parade this meta parade for this
being an expression of your joy of your
gladness your appreciation your meta for them it's okay to have fun with it
maybe you give him a little crown real sash you matter
giving them flowers
celebrating them in your heart
maybe you have a cheerleading squad celebrating
them their name the fact that they exist they've been
part of your life they matter you matter
you sing to them in your heart
and in your mind's eye they completely fully receive it no shyness no deferring
let them receive let it be satisfying for you it's not so satisfying when people defer
and deflect it be satisfying they receive the accolades the recognition
that they matter to you
now if you like can thank this being maybe invite someone else
someone else to your heart space
someone else maybe who's been an unsung hero in your
life how celebrating them this friend this relative this
mentor teacher was pat you matter you matter
you matter you have mattered you matter to me your beingness your existence in the
world you matter so much
maybe there's a parade in your heart for them
you matter
letting your heart your body feel full
of light of appreciation of meta you matter it's a different flavor of mitta
you matter
you matter to me you matter to me
so much thank you
and now
imagine your friends your relatives your
family colleagues people who are related to you and have been related to you
see them around you all around you
they're throwing a parade a parade for you
and the banner reads you matter
you matter you matter you matter to them you have matter to
them you continue to matter to so many people
maybe they put you on a stage give you a little crown little sash
you matter you're looking at the audience all the people you know
[Music] in the audience people in your life
who are looking at you appreciatively holding up signs you matter to me
you matter to me
let yourself take it in
wherever you look these appreciative eyes
people from your present from your past
even from your future people you don't know you haven't met yet
people you have touched directly and indirectly
you matter you continue to matter
in ways you don't even know yourself you matter
let yourself receive let yourself receive
even if it may be overwhelming it's okay don't get in your own way
you matter in more ways than you ever realized
continuing to appreciate to enjoy the parade taking it in as much as
possible the appreciative eyes
the hugs the gifts maybe even the tears of appreciation you
matter you matter
you have been a source of joy for so many people without perhaps even
knowing a source of support comfort
inspiration by just being
you matter
seeing the appreciative eyes
a felt sense of this journey that is yours only you
and you can take the world would have been so different
for these beings without you
you matter
and for the last moments of this guided sit together
knowing that we all matter every single one of us matters
every single one of us matters
may all of us all beings everywhere know that we matter
cherish ourselves cherish each other
with appreciation with kindness with menta
may all beings everywhere known wake up
to their inner goodness inner buddha
inner magnificence to their awakening may all beings everywhere including
ourselves be happy be awakened
be free
thank you all thank you
thank you for your practice [Music]
so we have time for some reflections i changed the chat settings you can type
them in chat if you like it's privately to me i want to read your name if it's typed to everyone i'll read
your name as well as your reflection you can also raise your hand
and um and sean and youtube has this reflection
actually it's a funny play on words i like it he says they say
i like that matter we are matter yes it's so true we both matter and we are
better both so we are matter and we matter so what
did you discover what did you discover
mark says fantastic thank you nikki you are so welcome mark thank you for practicing
together on youtube any reflections anything that opened up
for you it was surprising or or was challenging
or anything at all and again the invitation is to share your reflections as a gift
to the sangha your reflections are a gift that can help and support
other people's reflections opening up experience even if it's like
this didn't work for me or was confusing whatever it's all okay it's all okay everything is welcome
and remember your reflections matter you matter
you matter as a member of the sangha you matter
lisa please hi nikki hi
um yeah this was not the not the easiest um
guidance for me but i found that the way in for me was like
connecting with uh visual imagery of communities that i'm in and also just
imagining like a comforting touch like a hand on the shoulder
or like on the back and kind of imagining that
sensation uh with the other like images really helped
me to um to experience that so thank you very much
beautiful don't don't unmute don't mute just yet lisa this is beautiful lisa this is fantastic thank you for sharing
how these different modalities of touch actually i primarily was bringing the visual and
and how the sensory really the sense of support and touch work for you beautiful
beautiful and of course there could be the sound through the um so there could be
um you know there's so many different ways and and one question i wanted to ask you was as you were saying was uh
challenging to get in was it more to to see it for others the they matter or
when you turn to yourself for myself for yourself yeah when when it took that turn it was like
oh resist yeah it was like oh i can't and then it was oh resistance
you know and then it was um the tools that have helped me in the
past with the gut the visual imagery like guidance and that it's okay to be imaginative and
then also with doing um a lot of like self compassion recently
with uh touch yeah like just learning more about that and um then that kind of came
in and i could kind of imagine imagine that other people would just like a hand on them oh yeah other people
would touch the human hole and support you physically oh beautiful that's lovely that's great that was just
like okay i got it yeah oh yay yeah yeah that makes me very great this
is just these are paths that you've explored and know in this way like oh yeah this is hard to turn this around but oh wait these paths i know work for
me the sense of touching and holding and other people beautiful thank you lisa that's lovely
yeah maybe maybe your reflection also support others who might have trouble with turning it around and maybe a sense of
touch can be supportive for them great thank you um
nicolas says the thought of a parade for me was somewhat difficult i cried a little
as i needed oh beautiful yeah thank you for sharing that nicholas um
yeah it it um as as i turned it around i have to
say i had the same feeling it was very touching to imagine oh my goodness there's a parade for me like all the
people in my life who who know i matter to them and yet to actually bring that into into awareness or i was quite teary
myself sense of oh this connection this different way of seeing them and it was easy to have a parade for the people i
cared about and to really celebrate them yay very joyous and then um
turning it around was very touching and and also soothing and calm it's needed it's
needed for us to be seen in the way that other people see us we don't see that
it's there's resistance there's challenges one private
reflection i had difficulty reconciling knowing everything everything passes away with knowing
everything matters i was wondering if you could talk a little bit about this yes yes that's great
so glad you brought that in um so yes you know it's teaching of of
emptiness emptiness and impermanence those teachings are related so let's just talk
about impermanence which you've brought it in but it's also a bigger teaching of emptiness it doesn't impermanence doesn't mean that things
don't matter in fact things matter even more similar to how when people know they're
dying say the last year of their life if people have terminal illness they become kinder they appreciate people in their
lives more they appreciate every moment of life force things become more
important more so so impermanence or even emptiness
doesn't mean that things are just blah and they don't matter in fact there is a beauty there is a goodness that comes
because things are impermanent says you know this cup that i drink out
of to me it's already broken knowing that it's already broken hence impermanence knowing that it's already
broken i actually appreciate it even more knowing that's already broken so i
offer that to the person who asked that question please sit with it and but there's a lot more this can be an
hour-long dharma talk but i'm just giving it a little
little part um another reflection private i had zero equanimity the first person
uh let's see the first person was a blast so much fun the second person was where
it where it became emotional yeah it's okay it's this one was actually was supposed to be very joyous it's okay not
to have much equanimity um you know you know the first one was a blast great it's more of a joyous it's
more of a like joy great have fun this is yes let your heart sing with
appreciation for others and the second person became emotional that's okay too it opens up the channels
of appreciation bittersweetness it's it's it's okay
it's okay we don't always have to just be completely quantum yes i appreciate you
you matter like it's okay let yourself have the range of emotions
oh gosh there are many more reflections that i can get to now uh and also some sadness with the loss of
others yes and that's okay too that's all right there's a much longer one that i can't quite get through right now i'm
going to read it later this is a private one i'll get to that uh
and also more reflections on youtube okay so tell you what let's it's it's uh 10 minutes to the hour so let's turn
our attention at this time to practicing in small groups otherwise we won't have time for that and that's very
important part of happier and then at the end we'll come back
for for the reflection so dear ones the invitation for for practicing together in small groups
speaking from your own experience only not managing not facilitating the group just
offering what you like to offer and if you want to offer silence meta just holding the space that's okay
too each person will say one nugget and they'll come back to you another nugget you'll go round and round maybe a couple
of times two or three times depending on how much time there might be and i'm going to create the breakout
rooms right now take care of yourselves take care of each other remember kindness kindness kindness
okay here we go opening the rooms now okay everybody's back the rooms are
closed welcome back everyone we have just about a minute
gosh and there are lots of reflections i'll say something very quick about them
folks had appreciated also the invitation that each breath matters every cell
and um uh lynnea had wrought about wrote about that to everyone that um
there's a sense of really appreciating every every moment every breath of reaction and how we how we manifest how
we show up in every moment that's something i wanted to bring up and they're also story beautiful from berlin
on youtube um how he had showed up to a volunteering father's day event today
and uh today with this practice thinking that his presence had uplifted
others just felt made him feel really emotional and he was grateful for that it's really oh a
touching beautiful story so jerry i see your hand please
uh very quickly thank you i don't know for the first time i experienced more bitter sweetness than
i've ever felt but it was saying to the group it just came from that it was offset by
at least the existential loneliness that we all felt by being with this small group it was like an anecdote but the
the the meditation seemed to highlight the fleetingness as well as the benefit
of being connected but then you were left oh it it will come as fast as it
goes and vice versa so uh the small group was an antidote to that so yeah
yeah yeah i'm glad that that connecting the antidote was i mean with the small
groups felt like an antidote and also someone else very quickly had mentioned a private comment that that some bitter
sweetness some sadness came up for them because of the pandemic feeling that they're connected and appreciated but fewer
people than they were before and it's okay to have compassion for oneself and the circumstances of life and to also
still appreciate that wow we have matter to people and we still matter to people so there's so many ways we can play
around with with the with the griefs that also come up not to dismiss them
but to appreciate them but also see the the the the golden light or the the
um they pray the the gifts within within the things that we grieve there are gifts within them
also so so we're a couple of minutes over time so i'm going to bring to a close i'll stay a couple of minutes i'll
see another question i want to address um so but i'll stay over time uh to address that so but let's bring it to a
close and thank you all for your practice thank you for cultivating
your heart to your mind for your own sake for the sake of all beings everywhere and you matter may all beings
be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thank you all