hello everyone warm greetings from redwood city at imc
and um where
everyone we are ex discussing the
discourse on the four foundations for awareness and developing awareness on different
areas of our life and the topic for today is developing
awareness on the feeling tones of our experience the ways in which
things can be experienced as pleasant unpleasant or neither pleasant or unpleasant
and at this point this is in the satipatthana this point in the text we're following
the emphasis is not the
the pleasure or the pain of pleasant and unpleasant but rather the inconstant nature in
which these sensations appear how they come they persist they go they appear
they disappear and it's not just the sensations but also
the dance of this inconstancy also has to do with how we are
how we perceive them our perception is not constant we're aware of
the pain the knee and then we hear a sound outside and our attention for a moment is not
with the pain or reduced with the pain and then we have a thought of something
and then we're back to the pain and it might seem like whenever we're paying attention to it the pain is there in the
knee um but in fact it's uh the perception of it is varied and
changing and if if the attention is very close to the pain we might see that it's a
it itself is made up of component sensations that are dancing it may be
intense same thing with joy so it isn't that we have to understand
them these pleasant and unpleasant experiences we have as only being
inconstant but it's the inconstant nature of them the way in which they come and go that
becomes a foundation for being in the present moment
awakening awareness in the present moment as an alternative to being reactive to
them or caught in them or distracted and away from them or whatever it might be
so maybe that can be a little bit the meditation this morning so to assume a
upright alert meditation posture
and lowering your gaze of your eyes
45 degrees to the floor and relaxing the gaze
looking at nothing in particular loose focus
and then gently if it's nice close the eyes
and then having the attention in your torso and your chest
rib cage taking a few long slow deep breaths
deep in-breaths and extended relaxation as you exhale
relaxation where you settle in to your body and your seat
maybe breathe deeply if couple of more times and as you exhale
relax into the contact of your body against the chair your cushion your bed
wherever you are
letting the breathing return to normal
and maybe also to relax further in the exhale
the normal exhale softening in the body relaxing into your body more
and then centering yourself from the body breathing
wherever you're it's easiest or nicest for you to be aware of the breathing in the body
enter into that part of your body to feel and sense the experience of breathing
and if there's any experience any feeling sense of peace
or calm as you breathe
let that register in your body
maybe there's a part of the exhale that feels peaceful or calm
or the end of the exhale or maybe it's the beginning of the
inhale
relaxing the thinking muscle relaxing the thinking mind
so the thinking mind moves towards greater peace or calm
tapping into the mind's ability to be at ease
and as you feel your breathing the body breathing
notice if there's any pleasant or unpleasant sensations
maybe a different parts of the cycle of breathing
allow those sensations be felt and known peacefully
seeing their coming and going as you breathe in and as you breathe out
and it might be the pleasantness might be very mild
the unpleasantness might be very mild
maybe it's a feeling of comfort and discomfort in the breathing
see if you can be untroubled by pleasant and unpleasant
and rather [Music] breathe with it feel in the breathing
ride along
with the rising and passing of
strengthening and weakening of pleasant and unpleasant as you breathe
the ancient analogy for the sensations of pleasant and
unpleasant pleasure and discomfort
is a vast peaceful lake
imagine being at a lake that's peaceful
calm relaxed very still surface
and a gentle rain begins and little drops on the surface of the
lake those are likened to the sensations that
come and go
rippling briefly in the calmness of the mind
and as we come to the end of the sitting
may it be that whatever degree of calm or
peace or whatever degree of
heightened awareness or clarity or other benefits we received from this
meditation may it be a medium maybe a vehicle
for good will into the world may it help us connect to our
well-wishing or our capacity for kindness and care and
compassion
and may our peace our well-being
carry out into the world these wishes
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and may these wishes spread out to lands across the world where there's war
hunger
people struggling with climate change and environmental deterioration
people who are sick may our kindness our good will
spread out with our peace out into the world for the welfare and the benefit of the
whole world and as we live our life today
maybe we can think of practical ways maybe small ways
that we can enact that goodwill
in order to be friendly and kind to the people we encounter
may all beings share in bringing forth
happiness peace
[Music]
i'll be right back i have to push a button
um
so this week we're doing the second exercises and exercise in the
fourth foundation for awareness and
the first second and third exercises five total is
the first three have to do with ways in which we
select out of our environment things to cling to or react to or get
caught in there's a vast sea of sensations perceptions
experiences in any given moment and the human being
when we're born slowly starts to make a
process of selection to zero in and and um and pick up what's important to
emphasize or it's important to uh gather together and and construct into the
different things that we experience and we know that the brain is a constructing
apparatus that it takes in sense data and it
reconstructs it into reality to how we experience and know it
and mostly there's a very good relationship between uh kind of a
good enough relationship with what we see and what the mind constructs so we can find our way in the world
and but it is a construction process and sometimes you can see it go a little bit
awry you know it happens probably a couple of times a year when i go hiking on the
trails in the mountains near here that for a moment i see a little some it was
a stake or a little root of a tree that's half out of the ground snaking along
and i think of the root or this or the stick for a moment i think it's a snake
and so my mind has kind of somehow constructed the snake out of it
or there's a particular tree that i go by where there's a gnarly kind of
side growth on the trunk and and it looks like a cutest little dog
dog head sticking out and i said i always see that dog and the smile
and so it's no dog there but my mind somehow reconstructs it from the pieces it looks like a dog
and so the mind constructs and and it's partly also a selection process
we select out of the out of our environment the things that we want to prioritize things are important for us
as i like to said many years ago i was looking for a futon couch
futon bed couch and so i started looking as i was driving around or
attentive to that and back then so many years ago i was surprised how many futon shops there were i had no
idea they just kept popping up i was never really paying attention to it but now i was prioritizing that it
was on my mind and i was noticing it so we tend to notice the things that interest us
and i go down the shopping store you know the supermarket aisles
and a tremendous amount of stuff that just a blur that i have no interest in and i don't really take in i can't tell
you later what what i passed by and i'm looking for things that i particularly want
and so then you know when i know where i'm in the aisle where it is then i start looking
and searching for it and oh there it is and so there's a selection process
so this is all very normal but then the selection process also then becomes places we cling to
and so for the areas in which we cling to self or cling
to our own experience or a sense of who we are the buddha says that we
he emphasizes five areas that we prioritize or that we preferentially pick up on or that we
select or we project we kind of the part of the construction process we
give emphasis on this and he talks ab and these are the five
heaps the five groupings the five divisions the five ways in which we group our experience
into you know heaps of things and then we might prioritize these over
others and the buddha sometimes called this a burden
he also referred to it very explicitly as a construction constructing process
of the mind that minds
constructs the or some degree our experience of each of these five domains
groups groupings then the first one is appearances it's usually translated into english as
form and kind of the appearance of the body the physicality of the body the way it
appears to us the second one which is today is vedana the feeling tones of experience
whether they're pleasant unpleasant or neither pleasant or unpleasant and that was a whole exercise
a big exercise that near the beginning of this text the second foundation of mindfulness is
on this as well and and then it was just to know it
to know pleasant as pleasant to know unpleasant as unpleasant in the fifth foundation
the instructions are to know the inconstancy of the experience to know that the unpleasantness arise
that um and that it's arising it appears it uh if it persists that persists but
then as it uh passes away the rising and passing of um
of this feeling tones and um and as i said in the meditation
the analogy for this is a peaceful lake surface and a gentle rain it comes along
and uh and drops fall in the lake and makes little little uh ripples little concentric waves that
goes out a little splashes and um and those little splashes are there for a moment
and then they're gone the after effect might be the ripples that go out and so
these sensations are like the splash and then and then there might be a ripple through
us the after effect of that if there's if the rain is
uh falling hard it might just seem like it's a constant uh you know
uh there's a constant experience but if we look very carefully we see
that actually in fact it's still just a moment of splash and another one another one just a lot of them are happening all
around so um so in terms of the construction or
selection process some of us will prioritize whether we're comfortable uncomfortable
we navigate the world looking for what's pleasant and what's unpleasant avoiding the unpleasant wanting the pleasant
and um and that's kind of how we uh you know has give some priority to an
essential world and sensuality and is uh comfort and
being comforted by by experience and so we don't care that much maybe
how our appearances are the appearance of other people we're just interested in whether it's physically comfortable or
pleasant we don't care so much about
you know our ideas our opinions our stories of things we just want to be comfortable and pleasant
and of course it's a matter of degree but this is part of the grouping of our experiences some people prioritize and
select out of and and for the buddha this is one of the areas of clinging
so these are the five groupings of clinging and one of the groupings of clinging
is clinging to the feeling tones of experience
and and the antidote to that is uh is not to feel
um is to avoid feeling but rather the antidote is to see
that uh these sensations that were that are the basis for the construction
basis of the grouping and the clinging they are constantly
arising and passing away rising and passing away it's not necessarily easy to see that
but when we're now in the fourth foundation so if these four foundations of mindfulness our path it implies that
as we settle down and get concentrated and focus in this mindfulness practice at some point we're settled enough
that in the subtleness we become the calm we kind of become the calm surface of the lake
it becomes obvious that these sensations of pleasant and unpleasantness are appearing and disappearing
and then in that seeing that it's obvious that we are trying to hold on or cling to it
it's fascinating how clinging gets highlighted when things are coming and going
appearing and disappearing it's almost as if clinging is not quite successful
when things pass away in in deep meditation it's possible to feel the mind go towards an object like
i want that and by the time the mind gets there in that fraction of a moment the experience
has gone away that there's a pleasant experience so that's nice i want that by the time we
get there with you know it's gone because it arises and passes so quickly
and and so in that process uh not only are we beginning to let go
of clinging but we're also beginning to appreciate hopefully
the mind's clarity to see that clearly to see something
very simply in and of itself to see pleasant unpleasant and neither unpleasant in such a simple way
that it's not connected to stories not connected to the past and the future not not connected to the preferences we have
uh not connect to our fears of where it's going that uh that there's a kind of clarity and
simplicity it's just pleasant it's just unpleasant it's coming and going it appears and go appears and disappears
there's a rhythm to it it pulses into existence and pulses out the awareness of it the perception of it
the perceiving of it is moving and shifting around a little bit and one way or the other
we begin loosening up the grip of of clinging to it and selecting that out
of the wider field of experience that we have and at some point that as we do that the
attention becomes more much more spacious allowing and um more choiceless or more available
to whatever is happening without us that selection process operating
so
so it's great to learn not to cling so much and this is one of the ways that the
buddha is talking about and the benefit of this is that as we let cling less we can love
more as we cling less we can have more good will we can our hearts
care for the world can exist more we care for ourselves more
and and that's kind of the reward or the benefit from learning how not to cling
and for today it's clinging to pleasant and unpleasant so you might over these next 24 hours
see how much you prioritize or select out of your environment
and how important it is for you to kind of how you orient yourself and how your choices you make
uh whether whether things are pleasant or unpleasant
is this a neutral thing an interesting thing for you is this particularly strong for you
and if you can see if how important this is then can you also kind of see the ways
in which pleasant and unpleasant come and go through the day and what shifts for you
when you see it's coming and going and you realize oh this is the way it is for now just for now
it'll pass so thank you and um
i look forward to being here with you tomorrow