so good morning
and i find myself
unexpectedly kind of quiet and without
easy access to words but they don't they're they're here so
so one of the very interesting
things to realize about oneself is that
we're not in any fixed way who we are
that who we are is changeable and changing in context and situations
and also who we are as a question mark you know who are we do we really know who we are
from day to day minute to minute year to year
to begin and one of the things about some of us
is that we might have a place within maybe our thinking
that or feeling or some somatic experience that we most associate with who we are
and when that is thinking or when that is emotions but especially
thinking that we might limit ourselves by identifying with ourselves in a
particular way like this is who i am and so for example
i think i said this a couple of days ago that i find that how i think privately to myself
is differently than how i would talk out loud to myself it's like a different part of the brain
almost that's working and so i'm accessing different things i speak different languages
and and i'm a little different personality uh or a little different
connection to different parts of myself depending on the languages i speak it's almost like a little different self
and i've known people who spoke two different languages and
their personality to me was dramatically different in each one
and so i'm saying this as we look at our thinking or mindful our
thinking that we have to be very sensitive that we don't overly identify
with the thinker with the way that we're thinking because then we might overly believe in
or participate in or be burdened by the particular thoughts that
the thinker has or the particular attitudes that come along with our thinking
or the particular emotions that the thinking is part of
the ecology that it's part of so um
so what i'd like to suggest today is uh for those of you who are willing
you can ignore it if you'd like but to spend this meditation period more as an exercise
than as a meditation and it's an exercise which maybe won't help you be as calm and centered as
maybe can be in meditation but uh you'll learn something about yourself
that will support your ability to be mindful to be to meditate much better in the future i hope so it's
kind of a little stepping aside for a moment to do an exercise for the ongoing
growth here and that is to begin noticing
aspects of your thinking that the thinking phenomena the thinking
process that normally you don't notice and in particular
to notice um the mood the emotional
emotionality of the thinking what emotions do thinking come with what emotions they come out of
and if you pay careful attention to your thinking what is the attitude that's behind the
words or the images you have the ideas you're thinking about what is the mood what is the emotional
quality of it is it apprehensive and afraid is it harsh judgmental is it kind and supportive
compassionate how is it but then the more difficult part of the
exercise may be whatever you notice it to be
if it's not particularly supportive for you doesn't maybe particularly supportive
for meditation call upon a different part of your thinking mind
and think in ways that are supportive for meditation
and there's two ways to do it either think
kind generous thoughts be compassionate
the other is to offer yourself meditation instruction
think instructions think about okay now do this not do that but do it in a gentle non
harsh way with a very different attitude than the unhelpful attitude you've noticed at
your that's part of your thinking process there's not necessarily meaning that
you're jettison how you're thinking or pushing it away the attitude but you're bringing in
something else into the ecology of the mind and maybe you're disidentifying
with the usual thinking mind that you have that doesn't have to be you
the authority of how it feels and its attitudes are just an attitude and a and a feeling and uh
emotion it's not like this is the truth this is really what's happening
so so we'll see how it goes so taking a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and it's still valuable to settle in for this exercise so taking a few long slow deep breaths
as you exhale relax and settle
breathing in relaxing
breathing in and feeling your whole body
letting your breathing return to normal and spend a couple of minutes
gently relaxing the body the face the shoulders the chest
the heart center the belly
and then another couple of minutes of just being simple and
centering yourself on the breathing allowing more things to just settle and
quiet being here
and now if you would like to do this exercise
allow yourself to think rather than letting go of thoughts
as they occur just let them be and let yourself that let the mind think
and notice some of the qualities of that thinking
is it fast or slow
is there a lot of energy to think or is it kind of calm thinking
are you thinking more in words or thinking more in images or a combination
and as you're thinking are you strongly pulled into the world
of thinking or can you
track yourself thinking can you be aware of
the momentum of thinking
aware of what you're thinking about
aware of how you're thinking
does your thinking have a location is it centered somewhere in the head or
the heart in the forehead and the brain
back of the brain front of the brain
the eyes if it's imagery
are the images centered in front of you
hmm
and then as you're sitting here become aware of
any emotion connected to your thinking
maybe there's a mood or emotional attitude with which it's expressed or in the
middle of it or maybe it's propelled by an emotion
what emotion or emotions are connected to your thinking
sometimes the emotion can be identified by feeling the pressure to think
is there any pressure to think and if there is is there an emotion connected to that
sometimes the emotionality might be like the atmosphere or the weather that
surrounds a person walking on the countryside
you're thinking might be surrounded by an atmosphere of an emotion
mood attitude
the emotion might be subtle just a hint
or might be quite loud even predominating
sometimes the fuel or pressure to think comes from the emotions
associated with thinking
and if the emotions connected to your thinking
doesn't feel supportive for meditation
or feels like it's the emote their thinking is and the emotions are
you identify with it more than necessary
see if you can now think in a different way
almost like you're calling upon a different person to speak
leaving the other one alone but gently
maybe kindly
lovingly say words about yourself and for yourself here that are
supportive and
kind
say supportive words that
direct the mind the attention to do the meditation practice
of mindfulness if you want to be mindful of the emotions
it's like you're stepping back and with a soft supportive voice
encouraging yourself with the words or ideas of
just just feel the emotions where are the emotions felt in the body
are the emotions somehow dynamic and processes
are they vibrating or changing or shifting in any way
where in your body do you feel your emotions
so without that kind of instructions those kinds of thoughts direct your mindfulness
to be present for this other part of you that's doing the thinking
the automatic thinking and the conscious intentional thinking
that you do let that be relaxed easeful
no pressure
but an alternative to being identified with your old way of
thinking
and now as we come to the end of the sitting
call upon a voice the inner way of thinking or imagining
that taps into your capacity for goodwill
well-wishing of others perhaps your kindness perhaps your
generosity perhaps your love and compassion
and imagine that your attention now goes out into the world and concentric
circles from where you're sitting the people near you people in neighborhoods and counties
provinces outwards across the
the continent you're in and around the globe
and think some thoughts with an inner voice
say words of well-wishing
speak from your heart quietly silently
your care your
well-wishing for others
and experiment with a voice with an inner thinking inner way of being
that brings forth some of the best qualities that might be
available right now
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
and while i'm um drinking some water here transitioning for the talk
if some of you'd like to put a few words in the chat about if there's if that exercise was useful
for you if you discovered or learned something about yourself in that process
be kind of nice to read a little bit of that before i give the talk
thank you
yes if i talk and no one's there am i really talking
it's a question for our minds when we talk to ourselves who's there
so thank you very much for those of you who wrote comments in the chat and
about what this was like to do that exercise we just did and [Music]
not surprisingly i think there was a fair number of people who had mentioned anxiety and fear
it's very common to have fear or anxiety apprehension be the drive for thinking
especially if thinking is a lot to do about planning and spend a lot of time planning planning
tends to be fear based not always sometimes it's sometimes it's delight based
so you know if people if meditators get the message that all they're supposed to do
is let go of their thoughts and go back to their breathing that can be a very nice instructions and
very helpful sometimes to keep it that simple but it also is a way of dismissing thinking
and not really bringing a lot of mindfulness to this whole process of thinking
ideally in this mindfulness practice we're doing we're learning how to bring a kind of a
clear clarity of attention and care and respect to all aspects of
our lives and to keep letting go of something and not really take time to really get to
know it is a kind of disrespect it isn't we're not inspecting it and again and again
and um so there comes a time when we want to really turn our attention to the
thinking mind itself and be mindful of that and maybe it where maybe even the meditation becomes
not thinking meditation the sense of actively thinking and contemplating something but thinking meditation in the sense
that um the thinking is the object of the quiet attentive mindfulness we're
doing just like we would bring quiet attentive mindfulness to breathing
and then it's not about breathing exactly but it's about being present and for it
so being present for thinking but maybe without participating in the
thoughts and there's a lot to discover in that world of thinking
and without discovering it about seeing the how it works our thinking what drives it
what how we're pulled into it the energy in it the how we identify with it
the thinking well those things will operate in thinking anyway and some people get confused about
why do i keep thinking same thing or why do i always feeling the same way or
some people won't understand the teachings about not self in buddhism
because they're so strongly identified with our thinking i think therefore i am
and who am i if i'm not thinking it says that's the locus that's the center of it all but to be able to step back
and watch it and see it and realize that the watcher is not the
thinker and and if we're able to step back far enough if that the watcher can be do
more quietly silently or doing it from a different place
and um so one of the things to discover is that
certain emotions are the fuel for our thinking they're the they provide the pressure to keep
thinking the same thing over and over again and if that's the case
then it's really valuable to do a mindfulness of emotions to respect
the emotions get to know it more deeply practice with it and some people know how to practice
mindfulness of emotions when emotions are kind of their own thing but when emotions are kind of embedded
in our thinking uh it's more subtle or or we don't really take time to look at
it and one reason not to look at it is that if we think we are
the thoughts we are the thinker and who we are is observing say
with the world it doesn't occur to us to turn around and look at the observer look at the
thinker because the thinker is the one that's looking not the one that's being looked at
and so we might miss a whole bunch of aspects of our inner life because of the
of not having that ability to look back on what we think is the self you know who we are
over time we start being much more relaxed about having the central locus a
central coagulated center this is who i am
we are something of course but we don't have to have any stress and contraction compaction
around that self often has to do with our thinking sometimes it has to do with some people
are more emotionally based and some people are more somatically based but
all these places are valuable but we don't have to be based in them we don't have to be
centered in them as if that's who we are the idea is to be more fluid and inclusive holistic
include it all so if we're not blinded
by our thinking so we can't look at thinking if we could turn around and look at it
and if we see the emotions there the moods then we could do mindfulness of the
emotion so say for example there's a lot of future thinking that's driven by anxiety the anxiety
comes with some authority some power some sense of alarm that we have to do
something we have something has to go on and so we get pulled in seduced in in a
sense to have those thoughts problem solving fixing imagining all the possibilities so maybe we can
become safer or something but it can be so repetitive over and over and over again
but if you turn around and feel the anxiety and for some people that never taken
time never felt it was you know possible or of interest to turn
around and feel the anxiety in the body to help the anxiety feel
safe help give space for the anxiety to be there so that it's almost as if the thinking
is the signpost for the anxiety it's the messenger and we stay with the
messenger and we don't read the message and the message is the emotions that are
there and so we might practice with the emotions the other thing that we might notice
when he starts noticing the emotions of the thinking is that
having the thoughts is one thing the thing the thoughts we have influence us in one way
but the emotions might influence us in different way sometimes the primary influence on the
ongoing mood and concerns we have might be the underlying emotion
not the content of the thoughts itself
then but then certain certain emotions they influence the kind of thoughts we
have so fear thoughts might produce thoughts of
danger if they all the possible dangers we might run into anger thoughts
and a mood of anger move of aversion might predispose us
to have thoughts about all the things that are wrong and and what we don't like
if the underlying mood is one of desire we might be thinking
fantasies of desire looking for things we want and can have so the underlying mood can affect the
kind of thoughts we have and motivations we have and um and so
and then when we have those thoughts that are you know shaped by the emotion they in
return will feed back on those emotions there's a feedback loop that goes on feedback circle
and um and so we can get caught in these circles and spend all day sometimes if
they're not very powerful and you know not too much suffering in them
they can just continue all day especially if we identify with it if we take it oh this is who i am
if we've done this for so long that this is normal
it's become the normal thing so normal becomes invisible to us isn't that's how everything is and how it's
supposed to be this is the order of the universe is to have you know these kinds of thoughts or have
these kinds of mood and this is you know so normal um
maybe there's no normal for this mind of ours it's a dynamic fluid
uh process that the more free we are the more we can kind of surf and
navigate it all and not be unduly influenced or caused by any of it
but respectful for all of it and and so this ability
to look at the underlying mood emotion tone
of how of our thinking is eye-opening for some people it's kind of revolutionary
it's like the missing link for some people it can be quite disturbing for some people because it upsets what's normal
it reveals things sometimes that you know we haven't admitted before
but in the short term it could be a little bit disorienting but in the long term
this is the way to find some real inner stability some real ability to be creative and
present and let the best of who we are give it a chance to surface and come
in a way it can't if we're over over identified
with a particular mood attitude of thinking that
we don't even know is there sometimes or or we so strongly think this is normal
that we're kind of caught in its grip with enough care with mindfulness
practice all the grips relax not automatically but i want to
encourage you to to have confidence that this practice leads to the
de-gripping the relaxing the clinging that
goes on in the mind and
so and perhaps today
you can spend the day kind of looking at this through the day what are the emotions
that seem to be behind your thoughts that you have and see if you can
almost like you're speaking in a different language see if you can call upon a different part of the mind
and start thinking a different way not pushing away or denying the fact
that you maybe are thinking with a lot of fear anxiety or whatever it might be for you
but simply see if you can find on the side of that somewhere else a place of confidence or generosity or
kindness or maybe even humor
playfulness all kinds of possibilities but uh see today whether you can kind of
shift and change and pay attention to your mind and find if there's different ways of
thinking and and in the process begin to de-identify
with one particular way and as you de-identify
you might become a greater observer of it all
so thank you very much and um
i look forward to continuing tomorrow