i said my name is marilyn johnson i am from the netherlands and i live in
the u.s that's where the accent and the weird name is from
very happy to be here with some of you here in person and
some online to youtube and for those who celebrate happy
valentine's day
um i want to thank also the volunteers who make it possible for us to be here in person at imc
and to make it possible for the recording and the youtube
stream so yeah big bow over for the volunteers thank you
and today i'd like to talk about for
ways for helpful supportive ways that that we can use in our practice
both on and off the cushion and i came up with those supports a
while ago when i was doing a retreat and they were very helpful reminders for
me to stay balanced and stay on course on the
path towards a more easeful more wholesome a more free life
and i still use them regularly in my practice and so i thought i'd share them and hope
that they are also of use to uh you or at least maybe
one of them so i'll briefly mention them first before i dive deeper into each of them
and the first might be familiar which is mindfulness
and mindfulness is of course the ability to be aware of what is happening while it is happening
and then the second support i'd like to talk about is relaxation
because if we can relax a little bit in our often stressful lives this can be very
helpful and i will give some tips and tools on on how to do that
and then the third support is kindness and i'd like to specifically focus on
kindness towards ourselves because i think that's something that in our society is
often difficult while it is vital for our well-being
and then the fourth support will be returned to the present moment
so we all recognize when we are meditation we just go off lost in thoughts of
past or future and just a simple reminder to be in the present moment can be very helpful
so mindfulness relaxation kindness and returning to the present
moment so first mindfulness
the buddha says mindfulness is always useful
so we can never go wrong by being mindful it's a very special quality of mind if
you think about it because it really helps us to be aware of things
we see what is happening while it is happening there's not really another
aspect of our mind that can do that and mostly most people
live in their lives without really knowing without really being present for
what is here right now what is happening in our body and and we live
mostly out of old patterns and conditionings and tendencies that we cultivated
through our life in our childhood and later on in life without really
knowing that we're doing that another simple example in my own life is
that um i used to like be super aversive towards cleaning
like if i had to clean my house i was like oh i have to go clean again and it's really really
needed again and i really don't want to do it and i was like days and days would build up like oh i
really need to clean and i really don't want to and then when i was actually cleaning i was still aversive towards
the cleaning i said i really want to do something else i really don't like this and through mindfulness practice i
started recognizing that better enough aversion towards cleaning
and i became aware of like oh maybe this is actually not so useful
maybe this is actually painful to be aversive the whole time and i had to see it maybe like 100 times
before it started to shift a little bit towards like letting it go and
being more present and just uh finding it a bit more neutral to to clean
and sometimes i now even like it sometimes it's even just a pleasant way of
being mindful of the body so it can actually change
so mindfulness can really help us to see all these old patterns these conditionings that we tend to live
from and we might find very unhelpful
unwholesome patterns and tendencies that are based on greed or aversion or delusion
delusion sometimes also called confusion so it's very useful to keep an eye out
for like oh is there any greed or wanting in the mind is there any aversion
is there any confusion present but we can also find very helpful and
wholesome states of mind when we start being mindful um
like patterns that are based on generosity and compassion and wisdom
so if we find those kind of veterans that is very useful to see because
if we say for them if we acknowledge them then they strengthen and they become more
so it's a very good thing to to really acknowledge those kind of patterns and
and tendencies as well
so as you understand probably this mindfulness sati in pali
can really help us gain insight into our own minds insight into what is governing our lives
those patterns and tendencies and maybe another super simple example
is when we just start meditating then we find out like oh the mind thinks a
lot i didn't know that like how much the mind is thinking um
so that's just there's these tiny little simple things that we can notice
and seeing these patterns is of course not always pleasant
we we often see things that are not so pleasant but sylvia borstein is a meditation
teacher she says mindfulness meditation doesn't change life
life remains as fragile and unpredictable as ever mindfulness meditation changes the
heart's capacity to accept life as it is end code
so mindfulness can help us to grow this heart's capacity
to be with both the pleasant and the unpleasant to really
have the capacity to be with what is
mindfulness itself is a non-judgmental presence for life for mindfulness it doesn't really matter
what happens mindfulness itself doesn't have a judgment or doesn't need anything to be different than it is
it's just seeing life as it is in this present moment
so in a way we can learn to be not so reactive anymore
and not necessarily want want things to change not necessarily want to want to push it
away or pull it towards us but just to be there with it just to open to whatever it is however
difficult it might be i do have to say that is it's a training
it's not something that's like in an instant like we can do that
sometimes we just need some time in this process so it can be useful to practice with
easy things first and we don't start with the biggest thing in our life too open
to that but to start with maybe something small like if someone cuts you on the
highway and you feel anger coming up that you start with that anger
or when you have an itch during your meditation you you don't want to move so
you feel the irritation of the itch that kind of thing
might be useful and then slowly we will build some resilience
and bit by bit we have more and more capacity to be with
difficult things so patience is really important in this
process really see it as a gradual learning process
and i do want to say that we sometimes need to back off sometimes it's just overwhelming when what we
experience and it's just too much and then it can be just really skillful to turn away
from what we experience to to turn the attention away can be also very skillful
and wholesome at times that's an important side note to what i'm saying
but in the cases that it's not overwhelming and super difficult then when we do open to difficulty then
to help us get a little bit motivated we could ask ourselves like
do we want to live in ignorance or do we want to know what's happening even if it's maybe not so pleasant
because only when we know what is happening can we change it
and can we work towards a more wholesome way of living with a bit less reactivity maybe
so when we know we can start to learn from it and gain wisdom
and we can practice this knowing of what is happening both in formal meditation as well as in
our daily lives and especially in daily life we can see those patterns and conditionings
that that govern our our life and our activities and we can see simple things maybe like
craving for coffee in the morning or that we see that when we say hello to
our neighbor and that it's actually coming from our kind heart uh or we see the change of mood during
the day from energized to down to at ease to stressed
we can see all sorts of interesting things
so when we start to see more and more know more and more about our own minds and hearts
then we start to develop more and more wisdom and skillfulness in our lives
and one of my teachers said otisha talks about that there's this wisdom part in the
mind the wisdom is like this separate part in the mind just like like anger and and
love they're all like little entities in itself in the mind and then
those can grow or weakened hopefully with anger for example and then when we start to see things
with mindfulness then the wisdom part of our minds can start to learn from that
and one way of learning would be that what we see
uh and what we're gonna see is that what leads to happiness
and freedom and peace and what leads to suffering
and that's a very important thing to start seeing like what i realized with the cleaning
that my response of being super aversive towards cleaning was actually not leading to happiness
but was contributing to more and more suffering in my life
so we start to see the painful habits and then start to let go of it because wisdom starts to
start to let go of his wisdom is the part of the mind that can let go it's not us that let's go let's go
so we don't necessarily meditate to get rid of a problem
but a more helpful way to see is that we meditate to start to understand and
to learn and to gain wisdom
so and this way you can make mindfulness
your whole your whole path your your whole life becomes your path because it becomes
this fertile ground for wisdom
that's what i wanted to say about mindfulness and then the second
second support i'd like to talk about is relaxation maybe you recognize that sometimes you
sit down for relaxation for for mindfulness or for meditation and you just sit there and you do your
thing but you don't really start anywhere you just sit there
so what often is very helpful is when we have a little bit of a beginning
when we start our meditation and one of the things we can do to start would be to relax
because when we deliberately relax then
it will condition the next moment and next moment so every moment conditions the next moment
so if we deliberately relax then that helps us in our meditation
so we can also relax during daily life we don't have to wait till we sit down for meditation
um anytime you think about it you can relax
like when you drive to work or when you're in the bathroom or when
you're eating whenever you think about it but how do we do that
how do we relax like the first easy thing to do is to
relax the body because the body and mind are connected
so if you consciously relax your body then it will affect your mind as well
and one way to relax the body is to do a body scan um
so you just go through the body and um just touch on with your with your attention on each
part of the body and often there's a little bit of attention for the body
already relaxes the body and sometimes a direct invitation to the
body um helps the body to relax so you can say may the body relax
or if we have certain tensions in certain parts of the body we can we can invite those parts to relax
like the shoulders maybe the forehead or the little muscles around the eyes
sometimes get get tense and sometimes just breathing in and out
a bit deeper a few times can really relax as well
and we can also [Music] work with the mind to relax
and the simplest way is again an invitation you can say oh may the mind relax and
see if that does anything sometimes it will sometimes it won't
[Music] because what relaxation is actually what it actually is
is an absence of unwholesome mind states so when we
experience those unwholesome uh
roots for example greed wanting aversion delusion
um confusion that i was talking about earlier these cause all sorts of unwholesome
mind states to arise like wanting attachment
frustration despair sadness fear anger whatever it is that we experience if we
experience any of those kind of mind states then relaxation becomes a bit harder
because when these mind states subside then relaxation will automatically follow
so relaxation is about the absence of desire or aversion or confusion
so anytime you find yourself being not relaxed you could ask yourself like oh is there
maybe desire aversion or confusion present right now
is is there anything i want different right now because if we're in contention with reality it's really hard to relax
so when i was uh feeling tense about the cleaning
um i i couldn't relax you know i was feeling tense i
was a versatile or you know you you feel your whole body contracting uh
and then when that lets go then there can be relaxation and there
can be an ease in the cleaning and that's a whole process of course it's not that uh when once we recognize
oh oh i'm aversive or uh or i'm stressful that it lets go
immediately sometimes it does sometimes just a simple recognition is enough
but sometimes it doesn't sometimes we need to see those patterns like over and over again
just the recognizing of it is is the first step
and this of course ties back into the mindfulness and recognizing of what's happening um
is mindfulness so mindfulness is the basis for the relaxation in a way you can say
so with mindfulness we can start to recognize like uh
we can also start to see like oh i am not relaxed right now and indeed there is a version or wanting
maybe in the mind or you can see oh i'm actually really relaxed and the mind is pretty wholesome
right now you can see start to see that those things are related
connected so that's what i wanted to say about relaxation
and then the third support is kindness
so as i said i'd like to talk about kindness towards ourselves even though
kindness towards others is very useful and wholesome of course so [Music]
fantastic also to practice kindness towards others
but i think for a lot of people here in the west um [Music]
yeah kindness for ourselves is a bit underdeveloped like
many of us are you know somewhat unkind towards ourselves we experience
self-judgement or self-hatred or or self-loathing [Music]
these can be pretty strong patterns of the mind
and the buddha says hatred never ends with hatred by love
alone it ends this is an ancient truth
so sometimes we try to [Music]
overcome these patterns of self-judgment or self-hatred with hatred like oh i don't
want this better i it needs to go away um
but it doesn't really work because then we're trying to end our hatred with hatred
and hatred is a little bit of a strong word aversion is kind of a milder form of
hatred you could say so these patterns we can actually
overcome by kindness kindness towards ourselves
i would say that developing this this kindness for ourselves is actually
for westerners often a fast track to more ease and more peace in our lives
and i do admit it's not easy to develop this
it can be it can be quite a challenge as this especially because these
patterns can be of for example self judgment can be very strong but
we all are somewhere in our practice and we all have to start somewhere
so even if it's not easy and a lot of those kind of patterns come up it's
still worth it to incrementally try to practice this
i think that trying to cultivate the kindness will be beneficial
for almost anyone even if you already feel kind to your towards yourself you can always practice
a little bit more
if you imagine being kind to yourself how that influence like every aspect of your life
and there are several ways to do this to practice this kindness towards
ourselves and the first one is very simple that it would be
just a simple intention so we can have the intention
to be kind just the intention to cultivate kindness
because intention shapes
shapes our mind and shapes the next moment in the next one with what i said with the conditionings of
the moments so it's a very powerful tool i can use that in all sorts of settings
not only with kindness but it can be very strong a strong way to cultivate it because the
mind will start to direct us in that direction even though we might be miles away from kindness
right now it will give us just the dire interaction it's like trying to advance those big big tinker
ships trying to uh to change the course you know you might
not might not notice it much in the beginning but every tiny bit that you pull on the wheel is going to uh going
to have an effect in the long run
so intention we can use intention and then the second way we can develop kindness is
through using what is called meta meditation and metta is one of the brahma viharas
the heavenly abodes that's translated as loving kindness meditation
and i think most of you are probably familiar with meta meditation
but just to sum it up it's it's a buddhist meditation form
that uses phrases to generate this hard quality of loving kindness
so we would express phrases it's not out loud but just in the mind
like a wish for ourselves for example may i be happy or may i live with ease
or may i be healthy and what i said about relaxation we can
start with relaxation if we do our meditation we could also start with kindness
that's a choice i mean you don't have to know all everything but sometimes you can maybe start with like
relaxation sometimes she can start with some meta practice with some wishes for yourself
and you can even try this in your daily life like also whenever you think about it
use a phrase may i be happy i mean i live with ease
um i use it a lot during my daily life just when i feel a little bit down or
something i just realized oh i can do a little bit of meta for myself just a few phrases
and it sometimes just lightens the heart up right away it's not like an instant
an instant cure for everything but it can sometimes just give us a little bit more light in the hearts whenever we
need it and then the the third way to cultivate
kindness would be to pay attention to
when we are kind to ourselves and when we are not kind to ourselves
so this also would require some mindfulness so being mindful of body and mind state
of mind and also this
is a learning process we can learn and grow from those moments that
we are not kind to ourselves and we can see those moments over and
over and over again and we start to recognize the better and static that it comes from
and the mind might start to realize at some point that it's not that great to experience
unkindness towards ourselves the mind starts to realize that it's painful and unpleasant
and that's what what i said about gaining wisdom [Music] this
the mind recognizing that it's painful is wisdom at work
and if wisdom wisdom starts to grow then it might at some point steadily
slowly let go of these patterns or just a little bit here and there
so wisdom can really work in the background it's not something that we would
uh easily see for like it's like with that big
big tanker ship uh like only when we are way down
down the road down the road not really a road but our way down our path we see at some point oh we've actually
steered so much in the in the wholesome direction now i start to see that
my part actually changed compared to where i came from it is something that
that can be a very slow process but at some point we might see some effects
can be weeks can be months can be years
so an example that sharon salzberg gives she's a meta
meta meta teacher fei pasana teacher as well but she does a lot with meta
and she describes in her book on love and kindness that [Music] she once was on a retreat long retreats
and she was doing only meta only meta for herself and
during that retreat after some weeks or a month or so i don't remember she she got a message that something was
wrong at home so she needed to leave the retreat early and she didn't feel any
meta she had like set all these weeks for for nothing she thought because she didn't feel anything
and just this meta practice was just not working for her she was thinking so she was packing her stuff
and she dropped a bottle and it just shattered all over the floor and her thought was something like
it's okay dear and she realized wow metta meta just came up for myself
um and she just like before her retreat she would never have thought anything like that but now
the meta even that she didn't notice anything during the practice it had worked somehow
so we never know what happens in the background when we practice this kindness for ourselves maybe at
some point we have a kind thought too
and of course we can be aware of those moments that we're unkind or towards ourselves but it's
also very important to see those moments that we are kind towards ourselves
and really take those moments in really savor the moments
because if we savor it at any wholesome state also with kindness we really
reinforce that state of mind when we really really enjoy it and feel it um
then it can can grow more and that's not an ego trip at all
it's actually the building of a healthy self and we kind of need a healthy sense of
self uh before we can let go of ourselves like in buddhism we talk about all the
not self aspect of life but yeah it's we need an unhealthy sense of
self before we kind of can let go of ourselves so
this kindness towards ourselves is actually contributing to
uh through this aspect as well of not self it's very beneficial for a wholesome
and free life
so that was what i wanted to say about kindness and then we get to the last
support for our practice for today which is to return to the present moment
i'll quote the buddha again don't chase the past or long for the
future the past is left behind the future is not yet reached
right where it is have insight into whatever experience appears
end quote
like how much of our lives do we spend not in the present moment how much of our lives are we
off into daydreaming about the future or worrying about the future planning
or we're ruminating about the past thinking about this fun vacation that we had some years
ago or this difficult conversation we had yesterday or whatever it is
and of course we do need to think about the future we do need to make plans
like else we wouldn't all be here or we wouldn't have turned the computer on to look at the dharma talk
um so there is some use in you know thinking
about the future or the past but often
like a big chunk of the time that we are lost in future or past
it's just this habit pattern of thinking thinking thinking but it doesn't really contribute much to
our lives so being in a present moment and really
experiencing this moment like what's happening right now in the
body what's happening right now in the mind can be very skillful
um and can be very grounding and stabilizing
and if you think about it like is there anything
do you ever get anything else than this present moment
not really right we always get only this moment and this one and this one
our lives is just this flow of present moments everlasting present moments
so even if we plan for the future or if we think about the past or um
or worry or want something or have aversion towards something in the past or in the future
and the only thing we have is is those worries or wants or feelings or thoughts in the present moment
and it's even if you think like oh i want like let's say i want a pizza right now
like you're never gonna get that pizza um in this present moment it's always
wanting to get something in the future once you get it it's not this one thing anymore of this
moment if that makes sense
so it's important to recognize that we can't really escape this present
moment even though we're off in thoughts and about future of past
and this returning to the present moment is also
a simple recognition like oh i was gone i was lost in the thoughts about the future or the past
so it also involves mindfulness again and often when we recognize that we are
already back in the present moment and and next to that we just see oh i
was gone and now i'm back we can also more actively tune back into this
present moment like uh we can check into what the body is like now like oh
it's like this right now there's maybe some tension here or there's some softness there or some bar
end or whatever it is and we can tune actively into what's
happening in the mind and it doesn't have to be like this big
elaborate investigation it can just be a tiny moment in our daily lives or
if we're meditating then we might do it a little bit more elaborately tune back in the present moment and try
to stay there but in our daily lives it might be just a moment like oh yeah the body is like this right now or the mind
is like this you could try it even right now when i'm
talking tune into the body tune into the mind the present moment sensations
recognizing it's like this right now
so that's what i wanted to say about the
returning to the present moment and like what you can see throughout
all these supports is that mindfulness is actually the basis for the other three supports
so we need mindfulness to recognize is there any stress
present is there an unwholesome mind state present or do i need to relax a little bit more
the first the first support to relax or mindfulness can recognize are we kind
towards ourselves or is there some harsh harshness or judgments in our minds
and mindfulness can help us to learn from these patterns and tendencies of harshness or judgment
and maybe eventually let go and and cultivate some kindness
and mindfulness can recognize if we're off into future or past
it can help us remember to return to this present moment
and so if you have bandwidth for only one of those four supports then you can pick mindfulness because then you cover
all of them basically and mindfulness is always useful as the
buddha says so but you can also
pick and choose or see which one resonates most with you right now or which one you feel like would be
beneficial right now or what i do is i've written them down i use a digital
notebook and they're there when every time i open that notebook they're they're clearly
there and i see them like several times a day and then i remind then it reminds me
like oh yeah right i was supposed to be mindful or i take this conscious moment to relax
the body and relax the mind i fight the body and the mind to relax or check in is there any aversion or
detention present or then i see the kindness
reminder and like oh yeah i'm supposed to be kind to hurt myself let's cultivate a little bit of kindness
and sometimes i'm really stressed out and you know my to-do list is right there and i'm like oh i need to do all these things and like oh yeah kindness
oh yeah i can be kind towards myself
or i uh consciously return to the present moment seeing that reminder like oh yeah i only
have to take care of this moment and then this moment i don't have to think about like four
weeks from now just this moment
and of course there are many other supports that we can use
for our lives and our meditation practice these are just four that i came up with
that were very helpful and useful for me
and some other supports that you can think of might be like the other brand of harass compassion
joy equanimity maybe
support like acceptance or patience or
impermanence might be useful and so we all have different
conditionings different habits patterns and tendencies and we all need different types of
supports in different times so we don't have to be attached to the four
that i talked about today
yeah i just wanted to share that they've been helpful for me and how
they can be helpful for you maybe as well so the invitation is to discover
for yourself what is supportive for you in your practice in your life
and that might change over time as well
i'd like to end with a poem it's by the poet and teacher
kaveri patel and a poem is called dear you
dear you you who always have so many things to do
so many places to be your mind spinning like fan blades at
high speed each moment always a blur because you're never still
i know you're tired i also know it's not your fault the constant brain bus is like a swarm
of bees threatening to sting if you close your eyes you've forgotten something again
you need to prepare for that or else you should have done that differently
what if you closed your eyes would the world fall apart without you
or would your mind become the open sky flock of thoughts flying across the
sunrise as you just watched and smiled
thank you for your kind attention