okay hi welcome to happy hour everyone
so for today's practice together um
i thought we would do some simple meta together some exploration of simple meta together
and uh see what arises see what arises so
so um let's see if there's anything i want to say to
frame this maybe maybe what i would say is um meta loving kindness
practicing kindness acceptance care
arose by any name is just as sweet so
so many different nuances different ways for
this quality of meta-friendliness warmth to be to be expressed
and today what i'd like to do is actually to start with our bodies to turn
and share some spacious care some spacious care
for this body that is ours that is ours and not ours
um so yeah i think that's where i would like to start today and see where we
where we go so so let's let's begin let's begin our practice
together our formal practice of meditation i'd like to invite you to sit
or lie down or even stand comfortably whatever
is supportive nourishing to your body in this moment in time maybe even moving a little bit before
you become still see what this body needs
and then landing landing arriving
in your seat
arriving in your seat
inviting
your sit bones
your bottom on the cushion or the chair
to soften [Music] to feel
the sensations of contact
inviting your upper body
your neck your shoulders your head
your face to relax to release their weight
onto your sit bones
inviting the chest to release its weight
the arms the hands to release their weight
your abdomen to release
releasing releasing releasing
you might notice their sense of buzzing in your limbs your body
where there is a sense of release of tightening of holding when it's
released
releasing your legs upper legs lower legs
your knees your feet releasing the weight
onto the earth
let the breath as it moves through the abdomen
help you release more i'm pushing but just
gently opening up your fist as if the tightness in the body and the
muscles were a tight fist the opening the releasing letting go
[Music]
and as thoughts arise as they will inevitably arise not a problem
see if we can open our hands and release
nothing wrong with thinking per se but as we take refuge together in this moment
for the sake of this practice this training together
let us open our hands and not be entangled in this moment
trusting if the thought is important enough we'll
come back later
releasing releasing releasing the tightness tension in the body some
more as an act of care towards this body an act of love
inviting the breath to be soothing calming
to the limbs of our body moving wherever it needs to go
wherever there is tightness or tension
their feet tense abdomen neck shoulders face
or our heart our heart center where the emotions are
the proverbial heart center seed of the emotions
let the breath move through
it's an act of care act of self-care
my
trusting that being here with the breath with the body
with care is more nourishing and healing than being entangled in thought
sweeter more nourishing right here right here
right here close very close
if there are any areas of the body
that are hurting or tender or tired creaky achy
let the breath move through them [Music] with even more care tenderness
like a mother holding a child
see if this care towards the body towards the heart
is the medicine that is just right in this moment
and if the phrases of mitta are helpful for you
feel free to bring them in if you wish or stay with the breath
just a sense of care i'll offer a few phrases feel free to
use your own
may i be safe from inner and outer arms
may i be happy and joyous
may i be healthy and strong
may my life flow with ease
may i be safe may this being who is me
may i be sick fully knowing that complete safety is
not possible in this world and yet i offer this wish to
myself it's an act of care as a gift
may this being whose may be safe the gift of good
will or simply may i be safe
may this being who's me be happy may i be happy
as much as possible
may this being who's me be healthy as much as possible
embody may my body be strong may i be healthy
may i take care of myself happily with ease
may my life flow with ease
you can repeat the phrases simply or they could become words
synchronized with the breath safe
happy healthy
ease or simply be silent the sense of care
for this body for yourself
see what is needed for you right now
you can play around with synchronizing these wishes with your breath
either the sentences or the words or just
simply the breath
breath soothing blessing [Music]
the heart the body the mind
breath moving inside and outside there is internal and the
external aspect of the breath
a gift
a gift in every moment
safe
happy
healthy
bees
or may i be saved
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease see if the whole body can be included in
these blessings these gifts of kindness to
yourself from your toes
up to your head
if any tension anywhere release release and receive
the goodwill
and let us expand [Music]
the goodwill from ourselves our bodies this being who
is me and bring in someone who's dear to you
with whom we have an uncomplicated relationship
and include them too may both of us
may both of us have safety
happiness health and ease
bringing them to your mind's eye [Music] as vividly as possible
as if they are sitting with you
if it feels better to just direct it to them alone that's okay too
may you be safe happy
healthy [Music] now these dear ones
expanding opening the doors of the heart wide
letting whoever wants to step in into the space be welcome to step in
whoever steps in may all of us
have ease be well
your heart can be relaxed feeling boundless
just keeping the frequency of goodwill and friendliness
whoever comes in contact enters this heart space
can be quite joyous actually perhaps with even random people coming
in across your mind come to your mind
becoming the object of your meta your goodwill
wishing whoever comes to your mind to your heart space well
friends family [Music] maybe even random strangers you run into
as they show up in your heart space wishing them well
they're human just like me just like me
and see how joyous this might feel might feel like a meta party everybody's invited
whoever wants to show up
maybe even a smile shows up in your heart and on your face
expensive
and this meta party is expansiveness of the heart make sure you're included
360. may all of us
all of us have well-being and ease
sharing good will care kindness with everyone everyone
no one left out
as we bring this practice period to close together
offering kindness to ourselves for whatever arose or did not arise
during this meditation period it's all okay we've showed up we've done
our best it's the best we can hope for planting seeds
no attachment to outcome and offering the goodness
the seeds of kindness we've planted offering this goodness
generously to all beings everywhere may all things everywhere
including ourselves be safe happy [Music]
healthy and have ease may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone
ah
so i changed the settings if you like to
share reflections in chat
you can [Music] raise your hand your your zoom hand
because if it's your physical and i won't see you there too many of us
to fit on one screen and you can also
type your reflection if you wish in chad either to me privately or to everyone
as a gift to others any aha moments or questions or
challenges it's all welcome as i
invite your reflections i'll share that um as i was leading the meditation at the
beginning especially with inviting us to release to release to release
any tightness tension holding in the body and to allow
the breath to be soothing i realized that my body was quite tight so it was
quite lovely to have this release just really settling settling with the sense
of meta so that's my nugget
there's more but i'd love to hear from you if there's anything you'd like to share
barbara [Music]
thank you for this this meditation nikki
um i've just gotten back from a a
trip and i'm going to be leaving in a few days on another one so
to really settle and be here was wonderful and at first my thought
went to um [Music] well what am i going to do about
meditating on my trip hmm should i take my computer and then i
thought no i i'm taking this trip to reconnect with
my sisters that i haven't seen through the pandemic and the most important
thing is to show up be there for them and not have my mind thinking of how can
i do everything no just show up
oh that touches my heart barbara that is so sweet such a a wisdom answer that came on what do i
do oh just show up just just offer your presents beautiful oh i'm loving that
voice of wisdom thanks for sharing it with all of us it's lovely yes just show up
yeah yeah practice yeah here as as your voice of wisdom has has
already brought forth just practice meta with them
with whatever challenges whatever goodness
maybe the meta will become compassion if their difficulty maybe will become mudita if there is joy
maybe it becomes gratitude or if it becomes equanimity yay i'm happy for your practice in the
next few days barbara it's lovely
it's lovely
mary says i really appreciated all of it and may i care for this body with ease
yes indeed may i care for this body with these yeah
yeah it's interesting as barbara was talking about having just come from a trip and
going on a trip as as many of you might know since i think i might have i mentioned it that i was
on a trip myself and i was in new york um and attending a conference and uh
just got back very late last night and my body is creaky and achy and you know that's what happens after you sit on the
airplane for a while so yeah just nice to bring meta to the body especially
when it's not feeling its best may i care for this
body with ease as mary has put it beautifully
so dear one since i don't see any other hands reflections we'll have time at the
end for more reflections if any let's turn to hold space
for ourselves and each other in small groups and it could be silent
holding space if you don't want to talk it's okay if your turn comes you can say pass and just hold silent presents
for each other uh for yourself and if you're moved to share anything
about your practice about what's coming up you share one nugget
from your personal experience and then the next person will share
something and then the next person then they'll come to you so instead of a long monologue you just share one nugget
and so if you have five thoughts to share just share one then the next person and the next person
and again from your own experience not asking questions of others managing
their experience not facilitating the group just each person is like a stone soup of meta
stone soup of meta bringing your own kindness and care and holding space holding space
especially if you're going to be spending time with relatives and family this can be
a great practice session to hold space with people who are freshly meditated so
so with that i'm going to create the rooms
it will take me a moment here we go [Music] um
[Music] let's see a little slow today
okay the rooms are created take care of yourselves take care of
each other here we go okay welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed so we have a few minutes for any reflections
excuse me if there might be anything that has come up especially from from speaking together in groups so
please don't be shy you can and if you raise your physical hand i may not see you so please raise
your um zoom hand or you can type in chat any questions
it's a good time for questions also if there's something was challenging or confusing or didn't
know how to work with it
i think i see your hand esther yes there i don't see too many people but i
just did happen to see it there okay i was i was looking for my zoom hand i got
confused i couldn't find it um yeah i had something challenging come
up um there's so much chatter you know about
violence and i don't need to describe it
but i noticed i have a lot of fear um
just carrying a lot of fear in my body this is not new but it seems like it's really heightened for me right now
so you know it was it was good just to take a beat take a
breath and you know try to be in my body
yeah yeah yeah so i i hear that in
what you shared actually more as a comment than a question what i'm hearing
is that actually given what is going on and also you know what's going in the zeitgeist
in this country as well as um also as you shared a pattern that you know fear has been coming up for you
before but you realize that today actually taking a beat and just
calming calming the body calming the heart with meta
trying to remember the exact words used but it was good or something you said it was just something something good
about just take just taking a pause taking a pause and resting from that
yeah you know that energy of being vigilant and you know worried
just taking a pause yeah yeah and breathing
beautiful beautiful yeah i hear that more as a as a
reflection like yes this is what's going on and actually this was really nourishing so
um what what i would invite you to consider is that as that agitated energy comes
because that agitated energy of fear is is really uncomfortable because in
some ways we cannot control i mean we have some control over our environment but not completely right we know this and
yet we can control our hearts we can control our body we can control our minds not to live
in fear um because the fear of fear is
is worse than i mean well anyway that can be a much longer
dharma talk which i don't want to go into it but but you know this if you have been having a pattern
i fear you know that you know the future may or may not turn out what we fear it to be anyway but living with that
vigilance and fear is so destructive and in fact the buddha supposedly
gave the instructions to the monks to practice meta
originally because of fear because they were living in a state of fear
and there's there's a story about it's seven o'clock so i won't repeat it
maybe next time but but that is the antidote meta is the antidote to fear esther so
perfect thank you thank you thank you so much for your reflection yeah that's beautiful
so thank you all thank you so much for your practice for your sincerity for your
care for yourselves for each other and may all of us everywhere
keep cultivating our hearts with meta care for ourselves for everyone
everywhere may all beings be free may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you