so tonight I'd like to like to talk a little bit about practicing mindfulness
maybe that's not too surprising at a place called the inside Meditation Center
but why do we practice like for us as individuals like why do we have this
mindfulness practice what are we expecting are the benefits or the purpose or why
would we do this is there a way that we have a sense of
we would measure there how our meditation goes or how our
meditation practice over time progresses like what are the
the values or the qualities that we're expecting to arise or shift or change as
a consequence of meditation and for some of us we're meditating
because we want to reduce stress why not nobody wants to be completely
stressed out all the time so this that we want to reduce physical
difficulties or emotional difficulties or a combination of them or
just a number of ways in which stress shows up or maybe we want to make changes in our
Behavior we have this idea that 'd be really great if I were more loving
and compassionate in the world to other people and to myself
to my annoying co-workers or to whomever it might be
or maybe for example we have this idea that we want to lessen procrastination
or are we maybe want to work with some some activity that feels like a
compulsion or an addiction maybe we do have an addiction and we're hoping that
mindfulness can help so
there's a way in which maybe we want to to change our behavior in some way
or maybe we're practicing mindfulness because we want to understand ourselves better
what makes ourselves tick what what's going what's our in our life
maybe get in contact with that or what are our habits of mind that
which ones that are supporting us and which ones are not supporting us these
patterns that uh we've inherited and patterns that we've
that have been created whether we intended to create them or not
and I'll say for me personally I came to the Dharma to practice partly because I
just didn't know what to do with my life this kind of angst like I have all these things that
I thought I wanted and yet my life just doesn't seem right
but I couldn't didn't really know what to do I'd been chasing after so many
things and for so long and I've just had this sense there's got to be something different
when I stumbled upon it the Dharma by accident during a yoga class
each of us as ours and own our own story of how we came to the Dharma and why we
came initially and chances are it hasn't been constant or the same the whole time
every your whole duration of practicing
but I would say in general like this is a gross generalization
that people do not want their meditation practice their mindfulness practice to
be about everything that's unpleasant that isn't Our intention when we start
this practice I just want to hang out with everything that's
uncomfortable or difficult instead like some people
have this idea I just want to meditate I want it to be some kind of like a chill out session where I can just be a little
bit quiet and settle down and feel good for a little bit or feel better or something like this sure why not I mean
right we all want this nobody wants to be with the difficulty all the time and
and to be sure for some people that's exclusively what they expect from meditation I'm using this word
meditation in general here it's a opportunity to
chill out but
I would say that mindfulness meditation in particular as opposed to like maybe
just this kind of global idea of meditation and recognizing that there's so many different practices other than
just mindfulness but I would say specifically mindfulness practice can help us with all these things right
reducing stress changing our Behavior having greater understanding in fact I
would say that those arise whether that's your intention or not but
one thing that's maybe I don't know if it's Unique but it's something that I would like to emphasize is that
mindfulness meditation is a way to increase the freedom in our lives
and I like this word freedom in a way because it's kind of a vague way and we
can understand it in lots of different ways and there's room for all of us to
interpret that in a way that makes makes sense to us but one way we might
understand freedom it is not being pushed around
by our experiences like oh I have to avoid this situation
because it might cause some uncomfortable emotions and I don't want those to arise so I have to avoid this
person I have to avoid this situation I have to avoid some of these uh
being alone with myself for too long or whatever it is
or maybe we have this sense that we're spending our
all of our time engineering manufacturing creating during whatever we can
to control our environment so that we can feel okay so that nothing
unpleasant and toward difficult arises
and that's not Freedom either if we're just always trying to control everything
control other people control ourselves wrestle ourselves into
being a particular way behaving in a particular way
if we only feel free or relaxed when under certain conditions when we've got
them just straight and that's not real freedom
and what the Buddha is pointing to and what this practice is pointing to is the freedom of not being pushed around by
our experiences the capacity to be with whatever arises
and the confidence to be with whatever Rises
that's where the freedom is
so I want to read a little excerpt from a poem
and I'll talk a little bit more about the poem I'll tell who the poet is and the name of the poem a little bit later
but I'd like to start by just reading this excerpt I found this poem really powerful
and just like to share little bits about it and talk about it
so this poem starts like this it's a it's a well-known poem maybe some of you know this
there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out
but I'm too tough for him I say stay in
there I'm not going to let anybody see you
there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too tough for
him I say stay in there I'm not going to let
anybody see you
so in some ways I appreciate very much what the poet is pointing to here
that he's like he's recognizing so many different things and expressing it I
think in a in a way that I appreciate but might say that expressing a an
emotional experience and using metaphorical language as a way to express it sometimes it's not clear
what an emotional experience is and if this person's a poet he's using metaphor
in this kind of language but there's a blue bird in my heart that wants to get out
okay there's something fluttering and maybe we're not even clear what it
is and so not only does this poet pointing to his emotional experience but he's
also having some awareness of his relationship to that experience
he's saying stay in there I'm not going to let anybody see you
maybe this is a sense of shame or maybe a sense of you know this shouldn't be
here or something's wrong if it's here but clearly a sense of this is not something that's welcome
so the poet knows about this emotional experience and his relationship to this emotional experience and maybe he also
has this view of himself I'm too tough for him the poet says
so so this mindfulness we might say of this view of himself or maybe even a
wish that he has for himself to be tough so that this little bluebird can't get
out and mindfulness is points to all of this
though our experience including our emotional experiences our relationship
to our experiences and sometimes things that aren't so clear or obvious to see
and that is a view that we have about ourselves and a view about we have about
what how things should be and how they shouldn't be
and with this like learning to be with the experience or we begin with
just by recognizing what's happening and then with recognition we can increase
our capacity not only to be with experiences but to even acknowledge them
and be able to tease apart like for example an emotional experience and our
relationship to them sometimes they get all tangled up and we can't quite tell them apart
it can be really helpful to tease them apart what's happening
and our relationship to what's happening
so poet he's not expressing Freedom though
right he's having some mindfulness there but right this there's a bluebird that
wants to get out and the bluebird isn't free
and he's trying to control his experience he's not going to let anybody see this blue bird and we have a sense
that his heart is closed and or he has this fear of intimacy he doesn't want anybody to know that there's this
Bluebird in his heart but perhaps he's on his way to more
freedom because he is recognizing these different elements he is being mindful
and this is the way forward like if we want to have some freedom
it's really helpful to notice what is it that we are tangled
up with what is it that is inhibiting this freedom
so helps to have some understanding some awareness some intimacy with this
with whatever it is that's arising I like to read a little bit further
along in this poem I'm not I'm skipping some parts in the middle
and then I felt like I should preface this that um and then I'd like to talk a little bit about some of these other uh verses
but I I feel obliged to say you know I was thinking to myself I'm trained as a
research scientist and as a Dharma teacher like I have no business looking at the American literature and trying to
unpack it and look at it so I just want to recognize that there's lots of ways
we can interpret poems and I'm just using this in one particular lens
so I kind of want to honor the poet and I want to honor those people who study English literature which may say Diana I
don't know what you're talking about but that is a disclaimer Maybe
here's a further along in the poem
there's a blue bird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too clever
I only let him out at night sometimes when everybody's asleep
I say I know that you're there so don't be sad
that I put him back but he's singing a little in there I
haven't quite let him die and we sleep together like that with our
secret Pact and it's nice enough to make a man weep
I don't weep do you
I find this poem really touching
and there's a number of ways that as I said we can interpret it but his emotions are shifting
in the beginning he's talking to this uh blue bird and he's saying stay in there
as this tone of harshness and then he at the end of the poem he's saying it's
enough to make a man weep so first I think this is
I could speak for myself this is often the way it is when we discover like uncomfortable experiences or like we
have some emotions for me I had a lot of fear and I wasn't even sure what I was afraid
of like I couldn't say I'm afraid of this or that but with some of these long
meditation Retreats I was doing there would just be this fear this not a fear and
I couldn't point to exactly what it was or but first I just was trying to like shove it down like oh I don't want to be
with that but then you know things were shift and
at the end of the poem he's saying it's nice nice enough to make a man weep he's
pointing to maybe the poignancy and the tenderness of just
being with our experiences being mindful of them as best we can
as best we can it's not he didn't he's saying that he didn't let
the this Bluebird die right he's not like getting rid of it
he's not trying to excise a part of himself but instead he's starting to engage with the experience
and I would say that relationship with his emotions is also shifting
starts with saying I'm too tough for him and saying I'm too clever for him I go
okay now I see you but now I gotta figure this out I don't have to experience this and at the end of the
poem he's saying we sleep together so in a way you know like maybe making friends
often this is kind of how our emotional life is to I would say with the practice
we learned to make friends with all these parts of ourselves that we were trying to ignore or somehow excise from
our experience or trying to shape our inner life in some way that they weren't there
and lastly I would say this is of course my interpretation his relationships with
others is shifting in the beginning there's this sense of
isolation and the be I'm not going to let anyone see you
right and maybe I for me I had the sense he's not even going to let himself see this little bluebird
and then in the middle of that poem is this maybe a sense of uh acceptance I
only let him out at night sometimes when everybody's asleep so
maybe like okay you're there but not only when the conditions are right I'm
going to be with this and then at the end
maybe the sense of connection and conversation even
he ends with it's nice enough to make a man weep but I don't weep
do you so all of a sudden there's this connection to somebody else before there's this real isolation and then
there's this openness
so this poem is called bluebird by Charles Bukowski
it's a it's a powerful poem I left out a few as stanzas there in the middle but
this um way in which you know we meet our emotional life and as we meet it
things start to shift towards more opening more acceptance more being in
dialogue with ourselves and with others
and we do this by and we find greater Freedom by bringing awareness to all
aspects of our experience It's Perfectly Natural that as I was
mentioning earlier that there's these parts that we don't really want to be aware of and we're just wishing they
would go away but with this practice is about
meeting all of it including some things that we might consider distractions sounds that the
neighbor's dog that keeps on barking or whatever it might be whatever the sounds
might be we just fold them in like this too we can be mindful of that we can be mindful
of a dog barking and then be mindful of the
annoyance and then be mindful maybe there's even a a sense of our self like don't our
neighbors know that I'm trying to meditate here and why do they have a dog they should let the dog do whatever or
something and in ways that we kind of like create this strong sense of self when our
preferences aren't getting met and maybe to just be mindful of that oh yeah
here's uh the experience of Me versus the world
and the uncomfortableness of that
so this idea of you know we can bring mindfulness to everything
and as we do we start to find more and more freedom there's things that we don't have to avoid so much we know that
we can practice with them and in some ways I kind of like this poem because it doesn't have a neat and
tidy and they lived happily ever after and rainbows and unicorns and hearts and all that kind of stuff
because I kind of wanted to show that this is you know this is a person
expressing some time in his life
and sometimes our life isn't filled with hearts and unicorns and rainbows and
this kind of things it has difficulties of course it does
and so we start Where We Are this practice isn't asking us to be
somebody else it's not asking us to pretend things are different
we start where we are and sometimes where we are there's a lot of difficulties
suffering sometimes not too sometimes we feel like we have a little
bit more ease in our life in particular I'd like to talk just a
little bit about mindfulness of emotions
this idea that if we're being mindful of like our inner life and emotions here I
don't know what the blue bird in the heart wants out but right we can think of all kinds of things in there
I appreciate this poet pointing to that but mindfulness of
emotions is a way in which by if we're just able to be with them recognize them have
awareness of them without insisting that they be different without trying to shove them away
we can allow these emotions to flow through us to arise
and pass away I think I think I heard this from Gil
Gil franstal e motion like this idea that they there's a movement motion
and that if we don't get all tangled up with them that they will move through
and part of mindfulness practice is discovering how we are Tangled Up and how we get tangled up and how might we
disentangle ourselves I just want to say a little bit about
emotions and then I'll talk a little bit about how we can be mindful of them there's a lot to be said here so I'm
just going to touch the surface here maybe I'll do some more talks on this
but one way to think about it emotions is that they're a form of communication from ourselves to ourselves
some kind of way like oh I'm feeling angry well then there's maybe a
way we feel like a boundaries been crossed or we're seeing some injustice
something that feels like this this shouldn't be happening maybe we feel sad maybe there's been
some loss and It's Perfectly Natural that we have some sadness or maybe there's a loss of something that we're
not even quite clear that we're mourning something that we don't even have some quite clarity about
but it's a communication from ourselves to ourselves but we can
only really kind of like learn what this communication is trying to tell us if we allow that emotion to exist
instead of trying to shove it down or extract ourselves
or if you don't try to immediately push it away in whatever way
it's the habit I think for most humans and these days right there's Industries
billions of dollars are getting spent to make it easy as possible for you to
distract yourself and to avoid your inner life
so there are forms of communication and I'll say that they are also Composites
Composites have both physical Sensations as well as mental Sensations because we
can kind of like divide our experience into those two ways physical and mental
there's different ways we could talk about emotions this is one way I'm doing it now
physical fear in the god in the gut anger is
hotness sadness sometimes feels like really heavy and maybe like pressure behind the
eyes so there's a bodily experience that goes with emotions and sometimes we're not so
aware of them or connected to them but they're there but generally and most
often they're like in the trunk or in the face or some something like this not always but
and then there's these thoughts these uh mental events that go with them stories
of who did what to whom and the next time that happens I'm going to make sure they did this or maybe we're rehashing a
conversation and thinking that trying to make it go differently you know something that already happened and
we're trying to make it go differently or maybe we have this sense of trying to
make things or a story about how things should be
and how we're going to make it be that way and maybe in this poem that poet says I'm not going to let anyone see you
you know right I'm going to control it that nobody can see and these things shouldn't be seen this type
of an idea and sometimes it's hard to maybe understand exactly like what's a thought
what's an emotion so we we don't have to get too tangled up in that I'd like to
kind of simplify and say there's a bodily aspect and a mental aspect to our emotional life
and maybe I'll start with this uh little this quote which I think
is a kind of a playful way to think about this this uh some time ago there was this article in the New York Times
about uh mindfulness being taught in schools
And the reporter asked this young kid who had was participating in a
mindfulness program and as this little kid to describe it mindfulness
and here's the kid's response mindfulness is not hitting someone in
the mouth and I kind of appreciate this right you
know this recognition you know what this kid is pointing to probably is like oh
yeah okay here's anger here and I don't have to act out on it you know some
awareness of this so and I'm imagining this is like a way to be with difficult emotions instead of lashing out
so how do we work with difficult emotions
there's a few few ways I'll just give some highlights here
one is can be really helpful is notice that there's a mixture of things
happening at that moment maybe there's this heat of anger
and there's this perfectly neutral sensation of your feet on the ground
and there's a perfectly neutral sensation of the furnace going or the refrigerator
humming or something like this and maybe you feel hungry
and you're noticing that the person is
wearing a particular type of shirt or something like this so just to kind of
like open up the experience sometimes we like collapse into the emotion the anger
or whatever it is it's not always easy to do but to open up the experience and
notice anything else really and often the easiest is feeling that
the pressure on the feet touching the ground and there's something in particular
about that that can kind of help us feel grounded and settled and the awareness might go to the feet
and then go back to the anger and then we can go to the feet and then go back to the anger and then go back to the feet but there's something about coming
back to the feet that interrupts the momentum of the anger getting bigger and bigger and bigger and right we have all
noticed this and there's something that you know we might think about that the amount of
harm we can cause our relationships
if we're angry for a full day as opposed to if we're just angry for a
couple of hours right we might not send that email we might not make that phone call if
we're you know the anger it's still there but just isn't for the same duration so this one thing we can do
just notice there is mixture so we could ask ourselves what else is here anger is
here sadness is here this terrible sadness what else is here and allow the
attention to rest on something neutral or Pleasant
if there's something pleasant maybe you're wearing some soft clothing
maybe you're sitting in a comfy chair so something like that that's one thing to do with difficult emotions or strong
emotions maybe I should use that word strong emotions
and then can we transform this emotion from this abstract concept sadness anger
love whatever emotion it might be anxiety
transform it from this abstract concept into something that's a little bit more tangible
and this is where being aware of the bodily experience of emotions can really
help oh I'm afraid and I have this knot in my
stomach and this notch
feels like it's in this region and it's
seems like it's a little bit Dynamic it's moving around it's not it has maybe
a little bit of a throbbing quality so this way of kind of like bringing the awareness to a bodily experience
something tangible that's happening in this moment is another way we can interrupt the momentum of whatever the
emotion is we're not trying to get rid of the emotion we're not trying to shame
ourselves or anything like this we're just trying to not dip into overwhelm where we lose all our wisdom
so to notice the bodily experience the bodily part of the emotion
and if we are finding that we're just really stuck in this emotion
for a for a long time and maybe that the power of it or the intensity of it is
waxing and waning but we find that we're really um
yeah that's where it has a recurring feeling to it or this
going over and over and over again maybe we can just drop in the question
that's a gentle inquiry not that we have to find the answer we don't have to
figure it out the power here is in asking the question the power is not and
getting the answer and the question is
there something underneath this that is fueling this anger
or or whatever the emotion is what is underneath this
and as I said we don't have to do this archaeological interior dig to figure it
out it's more just being open to whatever is
fueling it because there is something that's feeling it otherwise the emotion would just arise you'd be mindful of it
and it would pass away right all the neurologists and physiologists and
mindfulness teacher said notice this right that things arise and pass away but if it has this way in which it's
just there for a long time then there's something that's fueling it
and just having this kind of curiosity about what are the what is underneath
this having that Curiosity bringing this kind of investigation and this openness that
itself is a way which might create that creates the conditions and when some new understanding might arise and that might
help with a new relationship to it or or a new understanding or something like
that so many of the times we practice
mindfulness and to have some reduce stress or reduce anxiety or to
change some of our habits or maybe to gain some better understanding and I'd
like to maybe offer just this language of some more freedom and part of the way to have more freedom
is to recognize where do we not have freedom where are we I I'm using this expression getting pushed around but
this way in which we're trying to navigate Our Lives spending so much energy trying to avoid this and only
have that and if of course we do right of course humans do this and we need to
do this it's wise to do this but there's a way in which it can also feel exhausting and oppressive so can we
have some discernment about what's helpful to
what's helpful to avoid and what's maybe we don't need to avoid
what's helpful to support greater freedom and what is like
maybe some tanglements or something that's uh are not allowing for greater freedom
and part of that what maybe being with emotions is
something that can support this freedom as well as reducing stress and greater
awareness and changing our behaviors
so I think I'll stop there and open it up to see if there's some questions or
comments
maybe I'll say well Jim is walking the my friend it's not uncommon for uh maybe
people later when they hear it to say what was the name of that poem again I'll just say it's Bluebird by Charles
Bukowski um thanks for sharing um
how do you when you're getting curious about what's underneath an emotion that's arising how do you sort of draw
the distinction between unhealthy or like ruminating digging
into it versus it's helpful and curious um
because you could just feel the emotion and and that would be it and try not to put a narrative to it but
how do you kind of go through that process yeah I think this is a a great
question and I think part of the answer is uh and how you described it if you
find that there's a lot of ruminating and going going around and around and around and around we could sometimes it
can be as simple as to ask ourselves is this helpful I thought this thought you know 500
bazillion quadrillion times I don't this isn't so helpful so that sometimes it
could be just you know having that question um
and so maybe I'm do you want to is that how was that answer was that like oh
okay but no that's not yeah so yeah so definitely the rumination when you're cycling right so I like that question is
it helpful but
sometimes the asking the question and like the creating the narrative around it is
the unhelpful part of it of the emotion right you're investigating it you create
a story that's not helpful I see thank you around the emotion how do you know whether it's like oh I'm out I'm trying to understand what's
you know your mind can spin like well maybe it's this but then from that and like
helpful analyzing versus just the emotion is what it is and not
trying to put a narrative or understanding yeah so when you're asking the question
you're using the word analyzing and I'm I'm you know kind of like shy a little bit
shy that word of analyzing I'm just saying a gentle inquiry is
there something underneath that's fueling this so less about figuring it out and analyzing and I I I appreciate
what you're pointing to that sometimes we can create a narrative a whole story that um I'm having this emotion because
I'm a person who acts or because of this or that and then we get all tangled up with that story and that's isn't so
helpful
maybe if we find ourselves stuck in that we can do these other things we can feel
our feet on the ground feeling into the body these types of things to kind of help interrupt the
momentum of those things thank you
I may also have a question yes for you
good evening Diana thank you um I have a question regarding the
like the mindfulness aspect like I know I'm very grateful for
this practice because I I am gaining more awareness of my emotions and what's
overwhelming me I just feel like sometimes am I am I just being passive about it
like okay I know the dog is barking and I'm gonna ignore it because it I
don't want to make a big deal out of it but in in doing so I feel frustrated or
I feel like it's still bothering me or I mean the dog barking is figurative for
yeah live but I I just sometimes feel like it's not
where like I this practice is very has been very life-changing for me I
just with all of this the presence of where I'm like where I'm
at and how I'm feeling and just sitting with all the things that I'm I think I'm
aware of or maybe I'm just they're just so much more illuminated I just don't
know if it's like how to be okay with it yeah
right yeah this is a great costume so maybe I'll say a few things
I'll just well I'm just gonna go with this dog barking uh sure we can try to create the perfect
environment and uh which we feel comfortable all the time
I kind of feel like how's that that project hasn't worked for me
trying to make everything just be right so something like the dog barking is a
place where we can practice like okay here's annoyance and this is what annoyance feels like frustration
this is what frustration feels like anger because there will be times in your life where you cannot control it
and it will be really hard we're all going to get sick
people that we love are going to get sick and we won't be able to change it but if we are practicing for other
things in the simpler things like the dog barking sure you could pick up the phone and go to the neighbor's house or
I don't know all these types of things but it also could be a place to practice and so that because there will be plenty
of things in our lives that are really difficult that we can't change so like there's just nothing we can do
there's lots of stuff about that so that's maybe no like thank you so much
thank you