so hello and
uh at the moment I'm imagining that all of you who
are present here for our YouTube
meditation is welcoming each other we're all welcoming each other we're all
greeting each other and appreciating the
shared companionship to the degree to the degree to which doing the same thing at
the same time um and
uh and sharing the same Focus here so thank you for being
here so um
one way or the other when we come to do meditation we are uh ascribing or
assigning some meaning to what we're doing some uh sense of purpose some
sense of uh values of what it's for some sense of um the um
uh context of it in our wider life some way in which it serves kind of maybe
ultimate values we have religious values spiritual values all kinds of ways in which are there on the edges or at the
center of doing meditation and one of them is
um our values and some people clearly bring along
values when they meditate maybe they that they've inherited from their society their family and some of them
are deeply unconscious as just matter of fact and some of them evolve and develop
in the course of meditation practice engagement with Buddhism that we acquire
new values so whether it's an old value or a new value one of the central values for
Buddhism and I would propose for people who mature in this practice of meditation
is non-harming that uh there's a very
thoroughgoing uh devotion interest sensitivity to living a life of not
harming at all and often that idea is attributed to
is assigned to the idea of not harming anything outside of ourselves other people the world
and um and that's true but in
meditation the primary care around not harming is not
harming oneself and what we learn about not
harming ourselves uh through meditation um is um
directly applicable to how we live that life in the world around us that uh the
very things that we do that cause harm to ourselves are one way or the other a
a uh support for uh that spilling out onto others in the
world so to sit and meditate where there's care
given that we don't harm ourselves and that takes the form of not
criticizing ourselves not being upset or angry with ourselves but of course we will be
sometimes the uh very significant part of this
practice is to appreciate the degree to which you don't have to take
responsibility for the particular impulses thoughts feelings when they first
appear what we take responsibility for is how then we
respond to them react to them so if there is
a hostile thought that arises in the mind maybe hostile towards
oneself the teachings of not taking it personally just that's what the mind is doing don't Define ourselves by
it but in the wake of it what is a non-harming thing to
do not be hostile towards hostility not to hostile to ourselves not to pull away
and shut down and give up and all kinds of things that we
do what is the non-harming thing that can be done in this practice is simply
to see it clearly with kindness and if kindness is too much
just to see it clearly so
for whatever arises in this meditation when it first
arises let it be known and in that knowing practice
nonharming radical non-harming as you sit here and
practice so to begin with a upright
or maybe say it differently for those of you who don't sit upright uh a dignified
posture something about how you dispose your body the posture of
your body is to
um kind of embodies your dignity your value
your
importance maybe in a way that lets your chest avoid collapsing
or crunching
up a way in which your neck is a little bit straightened and
and gently close the
eyes and
feeling the contact with
whatever supports your
weight and almost as if the inhale begins there taking a few long slow deep
breaths
if you want to get a little more benefit from taking these initial deep breaths calmly count to five on the
inhale count to five on the
exhale to have your inhale be that long
and then letting your breathing return to normal letting go of
counting and sitting here
quietly devotedly to being present with your
mindfulness present with the breathing and devoted towards to
nonharming not responding to anything
in ways that cause harm an
attitude motivation
belief and if you do let
go the best you can
and perhaps your
mindfulness is a nonharming
wind that blows gently on whatever it is you're aware
of
for
e
e for
for
e
e for
somewhat like a pebble being dropped into a quiet
Lake and the Ripple spread out throughout the lake so I drop the concept of
nonharming into you and let the ripples of
nonharming spread out to touch all of Who You
Are
e
e e
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to turn our attention to how we will be living our
life the next day or so and independent of all the things or
the few things that we'll be doing if all we
do is to live a life dedicated to
nonharming that would be enough you don't have to be kind you
don't have to be compassionate and loving
you don't have to wish everyone
well but a radical non-harming to become for someone
everyone else become someone who is safe someone who for whom no one needs
to fear no one
feels aggression or or assertion dominance no one receives
judgments
Prejudice everyone is seen through eyes rooted in not causing any
harm inwardly and outwardly just this
is one of the greatest ways of living a
life may it be that on this next
day whatever benefit we receive from this meditation from our practice from
being mindful may it serve
to support being in this world in a nonharming
way may all beings benefit from
our harmlessness
[Music]
thank you so the topic for this week has to do
with the meaning that meditation has for
us and I know some people like myself at one point were
a little bit allergic to the idea of meaning but as I've come to understand
the word that uh it's really a broad word that covers a lot of ways in which we
assign purpose assign roles assign functions
assign value assign um all these things to the
activities of of Our Lives to the events of Our Lives that uh how we understand it in or
interpret it in the context of our life story context of our society context of
our beliefs and um and there there's you
kind of no shortage of the many many ways in which we one way or the other
assign some interpretation to the meditation we're doing so this week we're try to bring
some of that out and have you be more reflective about it in a way that would help your meditation both in that it would help
you uh not get caught up in assigned meanings that are not useful for you get
in the way and but also to recognize the useful ones are there to support to to give uh
buoyancy to give momentum to give strength to meditation as
well uh to help you stay focused in what you're doing so uh today the topic is uh the
values that we live by and the role connection that meditation might have
with those values and it's hard to imagine that there's people who have no values at all
no ethical values no sense of uh uh prioritizing certain attitudes to how
to be in the world and um the uh some of them might
be healthy and supportive of self and others and some of them might be harmful for self and
others and but how does meditation fit into it um it would be unfortunate for
someone who's a thief who feels that it's fine to steal that's they have no problem with it and and in fact they
feel proud of their ability to steal uh and they assign the value
importance of meditation has for them is it centers them calms them down so that they can do their profession effectively
that would be quite sad because of the harm that that does but someone who um is a uh
caregiver for example and the value is to give the best care to someone in a
medical setting or any kind of setting and for them meditation has the value of
doing the same of grounding them centering them um preparing them for the
best so that the best of them can be present with wisdom and Clarity for caring for the their people in their
care and so here where the values we have how we want to live are brought to
bear on meditation and meditation is used to serve that
purpose uh one of the uh one of things that really inspired me is people who
want to live honestly to really live you know without any lies any deceit any
just really want to have the truth be the Forefront and um and with that as a
value mindfulness can be really a support for that mindfulness is a is a
truthtaco
is that it's truth making someone else the values could be
harmlessness and so the function the meaning the purpose of meditation is to live a more harmless
life someone else their value is Enlightenment full complete total
Enlightenment and um and uh so for them the the value the purpose the functions
assigned to meditation is that this is going to support them to find a way to that enlight
M there can be multiple functions happening at the same time there can be you know meditation can be has uh can be
the same meditation can be done for different purposes it can be both for many purposes it can be for
truth-telling for de-stressing for coming with more groundedness to work
that we do to being on a path to Awakening so there's a these it's not like you're choosing one over the other
but to have some clarity about what's important maybe what's most important around the values we have and U and
maybe even picking and choosing between that things that are important for us uh to give so we can give emphasis uh
to one thing to do really well if we have too many values too many purposes
um everything gets watered down nothing really kind of takes root and and uh
flowers and sometimes in order to really do well we have to kind of choose this is what meditation is about this is what
I'm developing and doing here and have some clarity with it and what the benefit of that is that
no matter what the purpose is and the Really sense of getting behind it and having some dedication to it as
meditation deepens it kind of blossoms out into all these different dimensions
of our life so you might put aside certain things as the purpose value and
later data you you find that if it's a healthy purpose it returns in a whole
different way um it maybe be a little bit like someone who um uh you know moves to a
foreign country where they have a different language and really wants to be friends with everyone on the street
and uh goes around trying to be friends but can't speak the language at all and
um so they get dedicate themselves to learning the language and once it's learned they find that walking down the
street that um it's really easy to make these connections now because of shared
language so regardless of what the purpose is for meditation learning to meditate well uh opens up in such a
wonderful way to so many different things so um what are the values some
people live uh Center their life on the values that they have more than the
goals that they have the work that they have the the what they're trying to do in their life and um it's some people
how they live is more important than what they do and I think that in Buddhist practice I think that uh we
emphasize much more the how than the what that whatever what meditation is is
for the way to it is by caring really carefully for the how we
are uh that we're not living a harmful way that we're doing what's beneficial
that we're learning to be at peace and relaxed nonattached learning to be kind and
supportive learning to have be have care to what we do learning to be honest in
all ways learning to um let go so so
many different things that so that we can be at ease have equinity be at peace
here and now some people uh lives is the value
they have is to be of service to live a life of generosity and
support and so then meditation serves that purpose for them for some people
it's to live a life of uh of um of really practicing Dharma for its own
sake and the result of that they want to live a life of service so all these things kind
shifting and changing in fact over a lifetime time of practice um that uh it's fascinating to
see how the uh what the interfaces between meditation and the way we live our lives
the purpose the values we have um what we emphasize as being important the
assign assigning of meaning assigning of importance of functions uh to meditation
into our life and back and forth and it shifts and changes in a dynamic way and
um and to hold on to any one way any one purpose any one meaning for what
meditation is um uh sooner or later we'll get all bottled up get kind of
limited and come to a dead end and um but rather they keep opening up keep
kind of uh looking and feeling and sensing all the different ways and
functions and meanings and purposes that um evolve evve over the years of
practicing more and more and and it's like it's like a dynamic stuff that happens it's
like um I don't know it's like
um um having a good friend and over the
years the Friendship shifts and changes as the the friend the the two of you
change and shift and um but somehow you stay connected and involved and things
flow back and forth and change and unfold and and U but because of the commitment to stay present and stay
connected that uh it's um it uh you all
change together so the same thing with meditation so to understand some of the
values that you live by and that come into bear on meditation uh and some of them you know
are you know and then see how they shift and change and one of the way they change is they
move sometimes we discover through meditation that some of the values some of the assigned purposes some of the
attitudes we have about meditation don't work that they're actually harmful for
us straining uh in meditation being attached to states of mind that we're
going to attain uh holding on to calm holding on to Bliss that might be there
the these are all these these kind of holding on and wanting and overvaluing particular states of Mind are kind of a
dead end they're not really that helpful and uh so if value is it's all
about attaining a state it's all about having you know some wonderful experience so that I can just add it to
my repertoire of wonderful experiences um that doesn't that's kind
of a dead end to go to attain to experience the full potential of medit
ation can be about if there's a lot of conceit involved in meditation and the assigned
meaning is that is has to do with I'm going to be the you know the best
meditator on my block and everyone will like me and accolades so how wonderful I am because I'm such a wonderful
meditator or if I meditate well then my meditation teacher will praise me and
put me up on a pedestal and will be happy ever after so so those kinds of
assigning of meaning assigning of purpose assigning of function um uh are
dead ends and they'll just you know end up kind of knocking your head against
that dead end until you know you go find a different way so to look deeply what
is the meaning of meditation what's the function what's its purpose for me so
here's an exercise I'd recommend that you do for these next 24 hours until we
meet again and that is uh you know uh with a
paper or with a computer um uh write the the
words meditation means for for me meditation
means and then fill in the rest of it and do that 100
times and every time write something different and U so I know I would have
some years ago many years ago I would have um May I would have written down
meditation means nothing you know was kind of would have dismissed the whole
exercise but then because it's a hundred different times you have to kind of keep
going um and uh meditation means means that
um I I sit on my cushion meditation means that I sit early in the morning
you can say kind of physical things like that but does that really get to your heart does it really get to some deeper
thing and just kind of keep writing keep writing 100 times for me meditation
means and after a while you can drop there for me but that's the idea behind it and see what you discover and um and
uh stretch yourself it doesn't have to be all at one sitting to do all 10 in one time but maybe over the 24 hours you
can write down a 100 uh fill in that sentence 100
times so thank you very much and um I hope that um the exercise is enjoyable
and and useful for you and then we'll finish the series tomorrow thank you