so hello and welcome everyone glad to be with you
practicing together whatever the shape of your body
um might be at this point feeling well or unwell
um so I realize
excuse me um yeah there's there is one topic I had in
mind but I am I'm so touched with Mario Christine coming and and having been
unwell and still you know not so well so I want to actually talk about
um self-compassion especially when you're not feeling well so that's what I want to talk about and maybe may be
supportive to to everyone because self-compassion we can never have enough
self-compassion and um and whether you are physically right now
there's some something maybe the whole body is not feeling well maybe there's there is a part of the body that's this
this back ache is just keeps you know bugging you or maybe there's a pain in
your heart maybe there's something that ailing your heart because physical
pain and emotional pain are not so different really they're not so
different we think they are but the way to work with them
um with care with compassion um it's it's very similar in fact physical
pain working with it skillfully is a way to practice how to be with emotional pain
so so with that
I'll say a few words maybe the first the first thing if there
is some challenge right now it's not a challenge or difficulty in your body and you're in
your heart is to uh to relax around it it's just to
relax around it it's here it's here it's a truth of this moment
it's what's happening because of causes and conditions
so many of them beyond your control this is what's here this is what's
present right now in this moment and
number two ah
as you relax as you open up to it to treat
to treat yourself and treat whatever is showing up with kindness
practicing kindness practicing kindness
practicing kindness holding with kindness
so the practice really is simple keep relaxing
opening to ah and being kind
being kind to whatever Rises
whatever pain challenge difficulty
as if you're holding holding a beloved child or or a pet
a dear being [Music]
I guess we'll just slip into our meditation because my
setup really has been the words of settling into
the way of being so ah if you often transition from a chair
to a cushion or to a different postures this is a good time
we can transition right now to a posture let's relax
maybe you need to lie down right now
and how can you how can I make this
practice period
in nourishing one How can I
see this as a resource not as something that I should do
because I want to be better or this or that but something that
ah I want I want to be a way I want to be not even in something I want to do
ah how can I be how do I want to be
with ease with care with love
to be here for myself
to be here for myself and therefore for others
if we fill our own cup with kindness with love with care
we become more available for others when the time is right
no use running ragged trying to serve
others take care take care of this heart
just Landing in the body sitting and
breathing
and keeping watch keeping presents for ourselves
sweetheart I'm here for you I'm not abandoning you your body your heart and your mind
calling yourself dear darling sweetheart try it on for size
there there darling you're tired yeah it's okay
I was breathing with breathing with the ache with the fatigue if there
is any present with the physical ache or heartache or
anything that's metaphorically aching in this Human Condition In This Moment
holding it with care
breathing breathing breathing
with it around it lovingly gently
no more is needed
teaching ourselves the lessening gentleness with this
breath
this breath a teacher in gentleness
tend to it well learn its ways
and if thoughts arise stories plans memories preoccupations it's okay
be kind to all of you
can you thank the thoughts thank you
and set them free ah later later set them free let them
fly away like birds doves
or swallows Little Birds
set them free set your heart free
and let the breath teach you a gentle lesson in tenderness
as if each breath is stroking your hair
stroking the ache in your body the ache in your heart if
there is one each breath stroking
lovingly tenderly
relax relax relax the body
with each breath
as much as available
and as if you open your heart your Embrace far and wide
as if you're embracing the Beloved a dear dear being
in your mind's eye embracing your own aching body aching heart
lovingly oh sweetheart this is challenging this is hard
acknowledging this is hard
and it's okay no need to fall into
grief why me so you'll never end no need for any of that
no need for second arrows to further injure ourselves just meeting
what's happening right now with care that's all
I'm meeting whatever is alive present
with care
when we left when we hold something
the amount of energy or left in our hands
is equal to the weight
if we don't meet if we don't meet what we're holding
with something heavy we hold it up there's more energy in
holy if it's light very little
our hands don't sink into the Earth and they don't push up
we meet we meet the appropriate response
appropriate uplift energy in our hands
in the same way the level of care and love
attention meets whatever is here right now
meets it holds it it doesn't sink down
under the heaviness it meets
it's appropriate the appropriate amount appropriate response
doesn't sink into despair it meets with kindness and it doesn't push up or throw away
it meets at hopes
and in this meeting in this appropriate response not pushing the way not falling
sinking this meeting a sense of delight can
arise with meeting our challenge meeting the paying meeting
a physical or heart pain a sense of delight can arise in this
mastery of meeting
with care meeting with kindness
with acceptance this is how things are right now
which is very different from resignation resignation is listless it's hopeless
acceptance is upright it meets the moment
it meets what is with care
explore for yourself with each breath
foreign
relax the body relax the heart
here here with each breath soothing calming
meeting what's here there's tightness holding relaxing
caring
even if it's something you don't like and you be kind [Music]
this is born of causes and conditions
it's here for a reason
acceptance means acknowledging what is
every moment
we learn we teach ourselves
to treat ourselves our bodies Our Hearts
with kindness with acceptance self-acceptance
instead of aversion resistance I hate this
every seed every seed of kindness we plant
in this practice in this moment
is onward leading leads to Future moments of kindness
for ourselves and for others
so practice with yourself on yourself
the art of gentleness
soothing practice on your body practice on your
own heart
who had better opportunity to practice on yourself
to learn kindness care love
so we don't go around essentially
begging others to care for us to love us love me love me love me
tell me I'm wonderful we secretly Shout
silently shocked to others
no need I practice I learn how
to be kind how to love myself In This Moment
their being here here
now now it's okay it's all okay
that's happening your body and your heart
there there
kindness
good well with each breath I wish myself well
I hold myself with care
nor may I be well may this body have ease
May This Heart have peace
may my body and heart be happy and well
whatever phrases of care you like
and are appropriate In This Moment wrap yourself in them like a blanket of
metal
may I be well may my body have ease
may my mind my heart thank you
have joy and ease float
and gladness
may my body be free from pain
may it feel light
made feel loved
allowing this feeling of care meta warm-heartedness let it expand
expand expand expand
outward engulfing you
cremating all of you every cell
spending Beyond expanding radiating
expansively spent expand expand
expanding on its own let it go let it expand
rest
as if it permeates your body the space around you
the space of your heart space of your life a space of your mind
and let this expansiveness of
gentleness kindness
care for hurting bodies hurting body
your body others bodies or hurting hearts
this care be radiated every hurting body or heart it meets
this light radiating line of care bring
sucker brings soothing in peace
to all the beings who just like me have been hurting
all of us all of us
wishing us all well
as we're bringing this practice to her clothes may all beings everywhere
have ease and well-being
be free from sorrow and difficulty in their bodies and their
hearts and their minds including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have some time for any Reflections questions shares
aha moments what worked what didn't
um complaints it's all welcome
and you can raise your Zoom hand if you like
or type in chat Jesse [Music]
thank you for this practice today I love the phrase of
you know whatever phrases to use them as a warm blanket of meta and wrap wrap up
in them and um last week you know you had recommended once a while back of just the importance
of safety and I've been using the phrase may I be safe for a while and then I love how phrases
sometimes just naturally Arise My Mind a couple weeks ago you know I was just saying my may I be
safe over and over for months and then a couple weeks ago it changed
to um I am profoundly safe and all is well
and uh that's just so that's my new phrase I know not for I don't know how it got
there but it's been really helping me and it really does feel that uh feel like a warm blanket of meta so thank you
for this um thank you so much for sharing your your
practice your your um my goodness it's so beautiful Jesse what you just shared
for for the benefit of everyone and also to be held Witnesses is so profound
that the practices you practice something for a while naturally not pushing it yes may I be safe may I be
safe the heart at some point says okay sweetie I'm I'm full okay I
feel safe and then the phrase changes to what you said I feel profoundly safe wow
I am so touched and delighted and and moved uh and celebrate your your
practice um the it's this is how it happens right
it it shifts it changes we graduate quote unquote from one stage to the next
and it's so gentle it's so sweet um
yay thanks for sharing this Jesse anything else you want to say I'm just taking so much delayed in your practice
report yeah thank you oh it's been it's been great it just felt very natural and very
organic and I still feel fear on quite a few occasions but but I feel like I have
this extra strength medicine you know for any task that feels
challenging and uh so it's been a fruit of the practice so we appreciate the
Sangha and your your guidance thank you yeah thanks so much for sharing that yay
yeah it's beautiful I miss you says thank you Jesse what you said is
strength strengthening yay Jesse thanks for sharing your practice and supporting others oh Claire says what just what I
needed at the end of a difficult day oh Jesse I'm just loving how your practice report is supporting others there's this
goodness in the Sangha it touches me deeply yeah thank you all
thank you thanks for sharing thanks for practicing yay
any other Reflections questions comments complaints
maybe as I uh wait for anything else to come in I'll share with you that
um I uh I feel so much lighter actually I
um myself this practice I mean it just practice still it it I mean it's clear to you how
excited I am and thrilled I am about practice otherwise I wouldn't be teaching and practicing and it continues
to profoundly amaze me not that I don't know the power of it but it's so fresh
it's so amazing before actually leading this guided meditation there was a lot of pain in my body and and inspired by
inspired to support um I'm Murray Christine as I as I led
this practice there was this there was there's so much more ease in my own body now and towards the end the body and now
it feels fluffy and light and easy and all the pain and hardness and tension
just feels through the the healing power of meta at least for this body has has
been eased so that's my practice report there you go okay Deborah you're on
okay uh I haven't been here for a while and I wanted to say that it's really
great to be here because it sort of bolsters uh
well it just bolsters but but I wanted to say that a lot of times I have to not listen to the side
of me that says oh these these sayings that you say to yourself are silly you know I wake up in the morning and I say
to myself I'm safe I'm what do I say I'm safe I'm loved
I'm included you know these three things I say most mornings and sometimes I think it's hokey but the
truth is it makes a difference to hear your words
and speak these kind
statements to myself really does make a difference so
indeed exactly it it picks the difference I mean there's so many you know just I I
just can't listen just can't listen to the cynical it's the cynical voice right right it's the story of of uh you know
the the uh this the story of the two wolves um the the
uh the indigenous story of uh two wolves which the the unwholesome
one and the wholesome one which one is going to survive well which one is going to win inside you there are two wolves
inside you I'm telling the story kind of how how you know piecemeal because I'm
guessing that all of you has heard it have heard it but but the answer is that the wisdom is the the wolf that you feed
that's the one inside that's going to to to win and so every morning you are
feeding the wholesome the kind wolf of yes I'm I am safe I am kind I am
included yes you're you're feeding that instead of I'm I'm excluded I poor me
like oh my it's it's that simple and yeah then then there's so many research
studies in Psychology blah blah blah like yeah of course makes a difference and here you have this amazing lab
to experiment on your own so we know we know it makes a difference we know it works so
thanks for that reflection Deborah thanks for sharing your practice I love your practice maybe it inspires others
to to do that every morning when they wake up to to feed this wholesome aspect
of of uh themselves oneself so so dear ones
let's turn to practicing in small groups together
and um and the prompt I'd like to invite you to consider for
for reflection and to be held witness is um
yeah what actually inspired by the reflections shared what are the helpful
phrases or self-talk but but you're nourish or you would like
to nourish what will have you been nourishing or you would like to nourish
um so let's let's share that with each other and if you haven't had one yet and today's your first day at happier what
would you like to nourish at this point at this point is the deposit the feeding of the the wholesome wolf so
so I will create the uh rooms it will take me a moment and also what I want to
say um is uh yes so we'll go
um uh alphabetical order according to first name please share something if you wish
from your own practice uh you can also offer silence if you want
um and then the next person will offer a nugget the next person will offer a
nugget it'll come back to you and you'll go around and round a few times not asking questions or directing the group
or just sharing just honestly as as little or as much as you
like to share um from your own practice so
so here we go it's gonna take me a moment to do
this and okay I have the rooms no I don't have
the rooms it's taking a minute oh wait okay here we go I'm gonna create the
rooms and let's see [Music] um
give me one moment here I'm going to
there we go okay all right rooms are ready oh no they're not okay hold on
it's like people keep moving so all right I think the rooms are ready now is
that right hold on one second yeah they're ready okay here we go I'm gonna open them up enjoy each other
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back and we have just about a minute how
was it what did you discover from this practice I see a lot of smiles coming out of the rooms so especially if you
haven't commented tonight or in a while love to hear from you go go go
oh Neil says that was so sweet oh that's nice you want to say more Neil or does
anybody want to say anything about what happened what you discovered
Murray Murray am I saying your name right yes that's fine thanks
um we're like we had a nice conversation it actually reminded me of something that I hadn't connected with this but um
I was saying that I just came back from a holiday in Indonesia and we noticed on all the beds in hotels in Indonesia that
they have the long bolster pillow and so I got sort of Googling about that and
they were saying yeah look most most Indonesians in southeast Asians sleep with a bolster pillow and they they hug
it at night you know like it's a very common thing to you know and often and
then people I've posted on my group and people were commenting back from Southeast Asia saying oh yeah I can't sleep without a bolster you know we have
to have one and and so I'm shopping now for a bolster for my bed
and anyway just it just made me think about this about loving kindness and looking after yourself and you know kind
words kind actions sweet sweet so if bolsterers is is a kind of a reminder or
is it there's a connection to care self-care and loving cake oh nice nice thanks for sharing that well that's a
lovely note to end on tonight so self-care loving kindness and and taking
care of oneself so thank you all for taking care of yourselves your hearts your bodies and each other by practicing
thank you so much may you all be safe happy well may all beings everywhere be
free including ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone take care