okay great so so dear ones welcome welcome
so for tonight's practice um I'd like to invite us to engage with
um with self-compassion both Beth this soft
gentle nurturing type of style of self-compassion as well as as what
actually feels like Fierce self-compassion there's a sense of um strength a brightness and and it's
very loving and it's also powerful at the same time so for us to engage in
both of those ways so so
um especially I think especially as as we are in the holidays in in the US
um it it can be both a joyous time for for
for many and it can be a stressful time for many um in fact
a very stressful time for many for a variety of reasons and
um of course not not assume that everybody else's experiences like us or
who are getting together with family and and um it's great to to for us perhaps to to
acknowledge and and and perhaps um consider that for some people maybe
if they've experienced loss this might be a difficult time especially this stressful time so
let's end and of course the two can coexist together joy and sorrow can
exist together so one does not negate the other we can hold joy and delight
and happiness and gratitude um and we can also our heart can also hold
challenge difficulty perhaps sadness Melancholy at the same time it's our
heart is so expansive that that um they can both be present and it's
okay in fact the state of equanimity state of equanimity equipoise allow us
to be with everything that arises um as a part of this Human Condition
so so um
self-compassion can be a healing a healing wand both for us and as we have
it for ourselves it can support others so and the very first
um step towards self-compassion is acknowledging actually realizing
that we're hurting that seems kind of simple and straightforward but actually
that first step of realizing and knowing that we're hurting we often miss we often kick ourselves in
The Shins okay get going get why are you being XYZ calling ourselves name and not
names and not realizing that actually oh maybe oh this being who is me is having
a hard time right now oh I'm having a hard time this is difficult
this is difficult if anyone else was in my shoes right now with this
background with these jeans with this upbringing with these set of experiences
um life experiences Etc they would be having the same the same challenge same
difficulty so so it could just be as simple as if this is hard right now this is hard right now and that recognition
that simple recognition can help transform us
from kicking ourselves and adding more insult to injury
um versus cutting ourselves a little bit of slack bringing more kindness bringing
more compassion ah finding our balance through
gentleness and kindness and then maybe some fierceness some some
ability some some uh compassionate power and accountability
for ourselves that we did we couldn't have before because it hurts too much can then show up but then together with
kindness together with kindness compassionate accountability can come in
as a sense of fierce compassion so I'll try to invite us to to play with
these Concepts if it just seems like too heady right now what is she talking about don't worry about it I'm just
introducing some ideas and I'll guide us I'll guide us in the guided meditation
for us to explore and um for each person the exploration might
be might lead you in different places and that's perfectly okay trust trust your
own wisdom trust what is appropriate for you right now so so with that let's transition into
our sitting practice so inviting you to
arrive in your body
as always we're going to start with settling in the body
arriving settling with the breath with the sensations of the body
foreign
taking Refuge ah in this moment and the Simplicity of
this moment of just sitting and being breathed
letting go of the busyness that might have come before
just resting resting with the breath so sweet so nourishing to just be here
just here that's it nowhere to go nothing to do in this
moment and if thoughts arise I want to take you away
nothing wrong with thinking per se but right now tell them not now thank you come back later
with ease with a smile tell him you're giving your heart to this practice right now
you want to stay you want to stay
later and let's stay
the breath releasing into the body
one breath at a time
here just here letting go of thought balloons
ah feeling lighter as you let go feeling lighter as you let go
well feeling lighter your heart lighter feeling more grounded
are grounded heavy connected to the Earth to this body
holding dichotomies
foreign
here just here settling arriving
connecting connecting with the entirety of the in-breath
with kindness receive in the entire in-breath
in the abdomen receiving the entire out breath
allowing them to ground you support you
in Stillness and with each out breath letting go
your neck and shoulders the stress the holding tightness the eyes and their socket let them rest
hands let them relax your feet ah give their weight off to the Earth
does this in-breath as if it were your first breath as if
you're first and last in breath
same with the out breath
foreign
breath the entire out breath it as a gift
there are distracting thoughts or our plan the memories it's okay
be kind to yourselves they arise part of being human part of
the monkey mind be kind be gentle
bow to them smile thank you not now
release them with ease ah letting go
connecting with the breath with the body here I'm here I am here
In This Moment letting yourself be breathed
gently gently
continuing to be breathed connecting with the breath in breath out
breath
foreign
so you continue to feel embodied feeling the breath in the Body Sensations of the
breath sensations of your sit Bones the cushion
on the chair your hands on your lap
your feet on the Earth
invite sense a feeling of yourself as being who's you
as if a beloved other
a dear friend someone you care about dearly
you want this person you want this being to be safe and happy
just as you would want that for a dear friend or a child
or a pet
if it might be helpful you can even take the perspective of
a fully compassionate being say the Buddha or foreign
example Paragon of compassion just
accepting you completely
seeing you with kind eyes
holding you with care that you're fully deserving of love
compassion goodness just as you are just as you are
you don't have to earn it to deserve it just as you are
just because you are a human and being human is hard enough hard enough
hard enough you're held
by the Buddha by kuanian or any other
compassionate being
that they like to conjure up
this being knows your ups and downs all the challenges of your life
understands accepts you just As You Are your body can feel safe relax
feel seen and held
If instead of an archetype archetypal figure someone from your life connects better
for you who's held you with love and care
feel free to conjure them up and their sense of acceptance see what works for you
or it could even be a pet that's offered you a complete sense of acceptance and
love
with your body
feel at ease receiving the sense of acceptance
is unconditional compassion
that your heart put its weight down
and now if you would if you would like
in the space of being held bring to mind bring to your heart maybe
something that has been hard for you recently not the
most difficult thing but something that's been a little difficult
just a little bit maybe a pain in the body
something challenging that happened let yourself acknowledge
and yeah this is hard this was hard this is hard
just as this loving presence would know this loving compassionate being
who knows you yeah this was challenging for you this is challenging and it's okay
they see that let yourself acknowledge
without falling into grief or sadness but just acknowledging yeah this is hard
and it's okay I can hold it I can hold it with care
not self-criticism but yeah this is hard ah let your body soften at your heart
soften
let this acknowledgment of the challenge be held with kindness
anyone in my situation would have felt the same would have felt
challenged may I have ease I wish myself ease
and freedom from this challenge may I hold myself with kindness
and acceptance may I offer myself safety
and generosity of spirit
with respect to this challenge especially
just as this compassionate being hold to you with care compassion holding yourself with care compassion
and maybe as you hold yourself
with the recognition of the difficulty and with compassion
a brightness a brightness awakens the brightness the power of compassion
as compassion together with its soothing nature also empowers you from within
your heart foreign
feeling soothed feels more ready to take on
to be with what's difficult what's challenging for
you so compassion
maybe it feels you can feel that it's both soothing calming
nurturing and empowering at the same time
and if the empowering aspect of it isn't clear lean into the soothing
calming nourishing healing
and when enough healing has happened
the heart will feel more whole and more empowered in its own healing
see and explore for yourself
and as we begin this begin to bring this seated
practice to an end together
offering kindness to yourself for whatever Rosen did not arise and
letting your sense of goodness and
kindness however much you were in touch with it let it shine Let It Shine internally
and externally for the benefit of yourself and others
equally it's a gift to ourselves or practice it's a gift to others
same same
and may our practice be a support for our Awakening and
Awakening of all beings everywhere may all brings be free may all beings be
happy
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
ah and I certainly feel happier and happier and calmer and
practice is sweet it's so sweet lovely to share it with you in community
in Sangha so we have time for reflections
uh questions comments and I invite you if you wish
for the benefit of with yourself to Sharon be witnessed and for the benefit
of others what came up what did you discover
Stephanie so it's funny uh I had a meeting with a
meditation teacher I worked with today and she was talking to me about self-compassion so when I showed up on
this call was funny that that's what we're talking about so I really got a lot out of the practice as I always do
your practices Nikki and um really appreciate it it will definitely have to listen to this one again
hmm thanks Stephanie thanks for sharing the the Serendipity synchrony that has
happened for you and and I'm delighted that these offerings are supportive to you yay thank you
thank you for being part of the Sangha Stephanie Dan
hi thanks Nikki um I I I don't quite know my difficulty maybe
you might have some comments or insights I have no trouble whatsoever
being compassionate to the first seven you know fifth seventh eighth level of
compassion for you but I can never make it past two for myself
it seems self-centered it seems selfish uh give me some perspective here please
ah thank you Dad this is such an important question
um and it's it's important to bring this up as you as you well articulated it and
first to say it is very common it is so common for for many many people to have
this sense that it's easier to give compassion for others and for ourselves
it's a little more challenging it feels uh and and you named a couple of things that come up
a couple of blocks that you mentioned it feels uh self-centered you said selfish
um trying to remember what else you said there's there are many of them there are many blocks to compassion uh one is oh
if you become compassionate then or especially self-compassionate then um you will not get anything done
because you're just you'll lie on the couch and eat bon bons all day so it's it I mean there are lots of fears of
compassion lots of fears of compassion and the one that you named is one of them that it just feels like oh it's not
appropriate um somehow that um yeah I'm being selfish and there's so much need in the
world here I am trying to uh be kind to myself
um and so so and there might be more there and and I'm going to ask you to unmute if there's more there if you want
to share so that we get to the Croc server or is that is that it basically that's that's short of it I come or I've
spent most I've done both Buddhist Meditation and sort of non-denominational meditation on and off
for a number of years I come from a classic Christian background with lot lots of optional Theology and stuff yeah
I think uh I'm old enough to to you know go back to the Latin mass and stuff like
that so I've got a lot of time on the meter so
to speak um and it despite your kind words I'm going
to have to reflect on this and oh we're not finished yet we're not finished I wanted to ask you that we're not
friendship I just wanted to give you a chance to reflect some more so before I I I was just hype I was just formulating
the problem before getting into it so so good so excellent so let me take it if I
may um so so and thank you thank you for more um more background so
so here's a couple of things to consider then one is that this this challenge could be a sense of perspective so
consider the perspective what are the thoughts that are creating the block and
and actually catalog them I I invite that you Journal you write down okay maybe there's a sense I'm not deserving
maybe a sense that it's a waste of my time other people are needed more or I need to to earn it and or whatever the
perspective is it's just you know there could be a dime a dozen whatever person and then try to catalog them it's like
okay well is that really true really is that really really true and and and and
with kindness like okay I don't deserve the you know the thought might come I don't deserve like I don't know if
that's the case or not but I'm just giving an example say well actually is that really true and then reflect on
that and and given that you have a rich background and with different theologies well every human being and and uh maybe
I'll use the Christian language for a moment ever God loves everyone I'm as deserving as
everybody else why wouldn't I be deserving of love and my own compassion
so so examine all these unseen unseen assumptions
um that there might be that when you're in meditation they just come up and the mind believes them and it just blocks
and that's it just so take time with kindness to examine all these hidden
perspectives and and also one holds someone to add is that um
um there's that that if you know if we really fill our own cup with our own
compassion with our own kindness first if we do that first
then then we don't go around basically through the whole world saying love me
love me love me love me take care of me it it because we might be doing that subconsciously but if we their sense of
acceptance and love for this being who is me as as if it's the third person
then there's a sense of contentment as a base for uh compassion for others
actually and as you mentioned you know you can have level seven or eight for me and two for yourself right now and
that'll become oh 10 for yourself and ten for me it will just open up that other extra you know that the blocks
that there are so so offering that for your reflection Dad yeah thanks thanks for being here beautiful Serena I see
your hand up and we'll let this be the last reflection before we transition to
um the groups thank you so much for this opportunity
and much appreciated um yes so
um I have a really difficult time
well one of the things that happens to me during meditation was that
um I was at a meeting before I came on and I stood up very strongly to somebody
to someone of a certain point of view and I could really see I could really
feel at one hand I was feeling a lot of strength um
uh Within Myself which I haven't been feeling at all as a matter of fact I've been quite
depressed um for a few months and
um and um
I'm just kind of wondering how to be with with that kind of strength
and you know standing up kind of energy uh and having compassion for it yeah
yeah I get I did get the gist of the question thanks Serena um and for the for um given that the
time is short I I like to respond in this way so so how to balance that so so
actually fears compassion is loving so you can have you can as you said stand
up to someone but not from hatred and not from um well I'm gonna show you but if
actually loving them and loving yourself and out of love for the community are
out of love for the cause out of love for what it is you're doing instead of instead of resentment or anger so that's
how you bring these two together um and it's it might sound like a tall
order but it isn't it it's it's um it's something that I do trust every
single one of us can do if we practice if we and that's why we come but that's why we practice so that this practice
becomes becomes the natural tendency so that's what I like to offer for for your
reflection Serena thank you thank you so much okay let's transition now it's uh 10
minutes till the hour let's transition to small groups and the um small the The
Prompt or so the groups will be size of roughly three and each person is invited
to just share something from their experience or say pass and hold a compassionate space for others and the
prompt is simply um how does um how does self-compassion
um when you experience self-compassion um do you notice that it'll there's
there is some gentleness some kindness some ease with suffering do you notice how self-compassion actually can hold
the suffering and can you see how it actually brings more resilience how self-compassion can bring more
resilience so that exploration your answer might be no I haven't really thought about this connection at all
it's like oh yeah no actually I say that when I was kind to myself oh there was some resources or strength that I had
realized so so that's the exploration exploration each person will say maybe one minute and then the next person will
say them uh another minute and the next person another minute then you go round and round and make sure everybody gets
the chance to speak so so hold back from the full story just just give it a little bit and and he'll come back to
you be kind take care of yourselves take care of each other
um yeah so I'm going to create the rooms now and here we go
okay all the rooms are closed everybody is back and
um we're at time so just to honor the timeliness I'm going to
um yeah close and um dedicate the Merit of our practice together I hope and trust that the small
groups were nourishing and you're welcome to share any um Reflections or shares in chat if you
like while I thank you all for your practice both for your own sake and the
sake of everyone whose lives of yours touches may all being beings be well may
all beings be free and happy including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone
bye