so hello and welcome to happy hour wherever
you're joining from whatever time zone i see some folks it's morning or afternoon for them in
japan i see you high and and others on the east coast 9 p.m 6 p.m here in
california etc and everywhere in the middle too so welcome welcome welcome warm welcome
so for today's practice um i wanted to invite us to turn our
attention to um the brahmavihara
of of joy of mutita vicarious joy or just joy
turning to joy to gladness to happiness and
this practice of turning to gladness happiness is so happy making
can be so happy making the dalai lama has said that if you're just happy for
your own happiness you have just one chance of being happy if you're happy for other people's happiness your
odds include increase to what seven billion are we at eight billion no i don't know what the it keeps going up
every time i hear the statistics of the number of people in this beautiful earth so so
happiness gladness turning our heart to gladness whether it's ours
or others gladden our gladness and gladness of others and letting our heart rest rest in joy
to be nourished to be nourished in gladness in its own good fortune and our own good fortune
that we often take for granted we often the mind turns to challenges and
difficulties and what's hard instead of realizing that there's so
many things that are going okay so many things that are going okay
so so with that what i'd like to invite us
um tonight in this practice is as we engage with other people's happiness
to to engage with gladness for them and of course the near
enemy which is envy could arise and that's okay you're not a bad meditator you're not a bad
person if any of that arises we'll work with that and also when we turn to our own
gladness to our own happiness it can be expressed as
um gratitude when we're happy for our own
happiness happy for our own happiness it becomes gratitude it feels like
gratitude so so [Music]
these are some um invitations and of course we'll fill it
uh fill in all the details uh practically not just talking about a
blah blah blah there's only so much that talking can do with these topics but actually
feeling into them and experiencing them firsthand for ourselves so
so with that yeah i think that's all i want to say to set the the frame we're just going to
turn towards joy tonight yay happy hour turning to joy why not let's turn to joy
oh i guess there's only one last thing i want to say um yeah um to frame the topic and that
is if if if what's coming up in your heart and your mind is like oh i've had a hard day i'm not in the mood for joy i
am just having a really hard time it's okay it's okay
joy is not forced joy is nurtured when we gently gently
turn the mind to what is good even if you're having a
hard day a difficult time in your body and your your mind
turning just inviting gently like like a little kitty that's under the bed kitty
kitty kitty kitty just inviting it shy kitty turning to what is good is there
something that's going okay well i have a roof over my head yay [Music]
yay hmm i had i had a nourishing meal yay so just gently gently don't have to
go whole hog all the way to yay joy if that doesn't feel appropriate
and yet and yet in praise of joy in praise of joy
the more joy you can contain
the more space there is for suffering to be with suffering with resilience for
yourself and for others so turning to joy is not
the selfish thing of oh i'm turning away from suffering oh i'm just going to like la de da la da pauliana
that's not the idea that's not the idea the more joy we can contain the more
resilience the more resilience there can be in our hearts our bodies
our minds to be with adversity without
falling into it without drowning in it for it to be balanced with goodness
for service for the benefit of ourselves and others so it's
it's for ourselves others and the world all right i think i'm now done with the
frame i wanted to set okay let's begin the meditation before i add more frames
just kidding all right let's let's land let's arrive together
let's arrive let's arrive in our bodies
as always we start we start by landing landing in this body in this moment
tilling the soil before we turn to any gratitude or
vicarious joy just arrive with the breath with the body
just arrive here
here
maybe letting the word here be dropped and for you
in your own pace next few minutes just arrive here
i am here
letting your body be here
sensing sensing the sensations
of the feet the hands
and your bottom of the cushion or the chair
here
here their thoughts arising
gently kindly release them
as if you're letting a birdie fly
and then here oh this precious body here
this
here simply here with the body with the
breath amazing to be here
present can feel more expensive
more expensive being here
just here
now as we continue to feel
our bodies being here here
here
connected rooted to the earth our feet
our bottom of the cushion our hands entire body
here notice if there is a sense of nourishing
calming healing soothing
just simply sitting in silence with the breath
gives rise to brings to the heart
deliciously here
opening up opening up your heart your awareness further
to any goodness in the body
with the breath any area of the body that just feels comfortable
may be warm maybe soothed
letting that in opening up to it
letting in what's good
what's calming soothing peaceful ease
maybe you notice the breath oh it's moving
smoothly on its own or then my hands feel warm or they feel
nicely cool my cheeks
maybe my feet feel relaxed and heavy my legs
are shading any parts of this body
where there is ease
now opening up a little wider opening the heart a little wider
so this ease to this goodness
ah drinking it in let it nourish you
doesn't have to be huge however it's showing up
however shyly it's showing up to welcome it open the door
let it in fully
now opening wider as you stay embody
what is good what else is good in this moment
maybe the temperature where you're sitting in your room
is comfortable you have a roof over your head dwelling
appreciate appreciating the goodness of this
this gift is blessing
glad for your own good fortune
this person knows me
maybe feelings of care love for supportive friends and family around
happy glad for the good fortune
of this person who's me
stay embodied don't get in to your head
to think about these just let them arise in the body and resonate
and be appreciated
opening up to the good in your life the gladness that brings up
maybe even joy ever so shyly
keep breathing keeping your body
stay stay with goodness with appreciation with what is good
challenges sorrows fear arises say thank you not now
i'm inviting joy and fighting gladness right now
for the benefit of myself and all beings
simply release you know you can
simply release
now if you wish bring to mind someone who is dear for you
someone for whom it's easy to feel warmth care meant to
consent or something that's going well in their life may not be
everything they might they might have challenges and difficulties that's okay
but is there one area one blessing in their life that is good
let your heart open to being happy being glad
celebrating this good fortune this blessing
this new year being has
breathing feeling embodied and maybe adding phrases
i am happy i'm happy for your happiness
may this blessing of yours
may it continue made increase
may never end what is giving you gladness and
happiness made increase
i share in your happiness as if it were mine it is mine
imagining them really appreciating this blessing and you being glad with them for them
vicarious joy can feel bright in our heart
if at any point envy arises it's okay you're not a bad meditator or bad person
simply turning turning to the pain to the hurt
of one tank wanting this yourself and holding it with mental with care
it's okay sweetie it's okay and see if
care for yourself meta for yourself can coexist is it possible
for it to coexist with gladness for the good fortune of another
if not then just attend to your own heart
with love and care and goodness
maybe you can be happy for them and hold yourself with tenderness and one
for wanting this in your life this blessing could it be at both end
maybe you discover your heart is more generous than you realized
you can stay with this dear being if you wish their blessing
or blessings or invite someone else another being into your heart heart
space bring their blessing to mind and feel happy for them
as if it were your own happiness your own joy
see what's needed right now
maybe for the last few minutes if it feels appropriate for you
including yourself together with these other beings
opening up feeling blessings in all your lives
may our happiness make all our happiness
our blessings may they continue
may they increase may they never wait
simply i'm glad i'm happy i celebrate
i delight this goodness in our goodness
and our gladness
this
may i appreciate i celebrate all the goodness all the blessings in my life with an open heart
with joy may all beings everywhere
no joy know the goodness of their blessings
may all beings everywhere be happy and free
thank you all thank you for your practice
[Music] so
we have a few minutes for
reflection questions comments for
whatever you might have observed what came up for you the spirit of service and the spirit of
service to the sangha like wow this was an aha moment or this was a challenge
it's all okay so you are invited
you can also type in chat if you like and if you typed in me alone
privately i won't read your name only the share and if it's public to everyone i'll read
your name and i see rich's hand that has been raised
yes rich can you hear me yes
well i just wondered if it's okay to experiencing experience sympathetic joy
watching youtube videos of little babies and puppies
of course it is
oh i see the hearts and the thumbs up are being shared in the zoom spade looks
like other peoples or other people are joining in yeah sure
of course absolutely yeah okay even though it's not serious
oh it doesn't have joy is joy joy is joy
um yeah and um cats and dogs too
someone that's great cats and dogs
absolutely yes he see the the um um [Music]
the spirit the the spirit of vicarious joy happiness for other people's
blessings for other beings blessings oh it gives you joy you know it's it's when
little children are being um being happy you know little children are
well taken care of or they're sweet it just brings up brings up joy brings up joy so yeah
yeah yeah
and i appreciate also the comments that are coming in both privately and also
publicly and on youtube and as we started at the beginning of the
hour acknowledging um take not hans passing today
what a beautiful amazing precious precious gift
ties get teachings and presence in this world has been to so many
and he also taught so much about peace about joy about gladness such
tenderness a gentleness in his teaching so bringing him in
[Music] again both at the beginning and now so claire i see your hand please
thank you i loved your topic tonight it happens to be very appropriate
because i had a one beautiful day but in any event i wanted to share a practice that i've had for a number of
years because others might find it helpful i have two friends in different parts of
the world once in switzerland and one's different part of the u.s
and we exchange every day gratitude list by email of three things that we're grateful for
every day and it's really just been such a rewarding experience for me and i think
for the other two women also um it's really changed our lives
so wow beautiful yeah thanks for sharing that uh claire
remember you had mentioned it before once and and i think what we tried actually that evening was to have folks
connect together uh if they wanted in the uh in the room
yeah yeah yeah in the room so maybe we'll do that again now that you brought it up again and see if people would want
to do that and i wonder if anyone did actually last time um if you did would you raise your hand
or or um or um type in chat if you did connect
yes okay i see fred yeah
yep you're unmuted fred oh okay well i i just raised my hand because um
because i did do it yeah great and with with two other folks in the
in the sangha and we've been doing it nightly
since whenever that was i don't know what a month two months maybe yeah
and it's and it's been a great thing to do so thank you claire oh beautiful lovely
thank you for sharing fred it's great that you've been doing it the entire month a couple of other people from
happy hour it's lovely yeah beautiful and i see
other reflections i think um oh earlier i hadn't seen charlie's hello charles lee thank you for the hello yes
and um let's see moving up and down yes that the
the next buddha will be the sangha maybe us maybe so nam says sometimes your joy is the
source of your smile but sometimes your smile can be the source of your joy thai oh
great thank you na for bringing this this quote from tiknot han as a way for us to honor him
tonight with the topic that we have beautiful thank you sometimes your joy
is the source of your smile but sometimes your smile can be the source of your joy
beautiful take that on lovely eileen says i felt joy to see that
people worldwide are pausing in their day to reflect on tiknot han's
life and to pay tribute to him what an amazing influence yes i agree how how inspiring really how inspiring
that one human being this gift of this human being this simplicity some simple
way of being in the world you know in some ways he was a quote unquote simple monk as the dalai lama often says and
what an impact what an impact that he had
and [Music] let's see seems like there is also memorial ah
wayne shared this information i'll read it out loud for those who are joining on youtube we invite you to join our global
community online as we commemorate ty's life and legacy with five days of
practice and ceremonies broadcast live from hugh vietnam and plot plum village
friends starting on saturday january 22nd please see our website for
more and the website is plumvillage.org memorial beautiful thanks for sharing
that yeah yeah
yeah and and uh i like that you change your your name whoever you are
take not on 22 22. what a beautiful coincidence that
we have been celebrating mlk as well they were friends yes
true yeah beautiful thank you for bringing that up i'm so appreciative i'm so
touched by the wealth of of so much
such beautiful sharing tonight on the chat that's beautiful yeah and nancy also shares at 7 p.m
tonight as well apparently there's a program on um
palm village oh the plum dave says the plum village website may have crashed it's presently unavailable wow maybe
they were not expecting so many people from around the world so
so dear ones so um you know tell you what this is what
we can let's honor let's take
our let's take uh opportunity tonight to honor ty in our small groups with the
theme of joy how has knowing him one of his teachings something about him
um inspired you how has it supported you maybe something comes up for you maybe
just the fact that he's been a human being in the world or maybe you read a book of his or one of these instructions
that have stayed with you um so that is the invitation um that is the invitation for tonight's
breakout rooms and um and if you can stay please stay i
think it's so lovely to take this opportunity to honor tai in this way together as a community in small groups
so i'm creating the rooms now and um
and yeah please please take care here we go i'm going to open the rooms
take care of yourselves take care of each other and we'll come back with more time for reflections okay here we go
and the rooms will close in about three seconds okay
the rooms are closed everyone is back welcome back we have a couple of minutes if any
reflections if anything came up you'd like to share you can raise your hand
as i wait for you to raise your hand i'll read this reflection from sharon on youtube
that ties meditation instructions on in breath i am arriving on out breath i am
home are an anchor for me how beautiful how beautiful
yeah such beautiful instructions actually years ago he was giving a
teaching in oakland and i had the privilege to to be in his presence just what an amazing
being yeah ah
i actually found out only through you guys tonight i've been sequestered
working all afternoon so i didn't hear the news until you shared it through chat so
we get to we get to honor him together any reflections please we have a minute
any thoughts that came up in your small group discussion
fred please [Music] well i'm gonna say this because i think it runs so counter to everything tonight
um but i as i was saying in the in small group maybe it was the this time in oakland
that you were at nikki i remember it as being in berkeley but i i went with some
friends to hear him i had no idea who he was it was uh you know 25 30 years ago
and i just wasn't ready you know that
i know people were bowled over my friends were my wife was and
i thought well there's something there but i just wasn't ready for it and
you know ripeness is all um so i just wanted to say that
yeah thank you so much for sharing that fred ah
thank you yeah it's that beautiful yeah
there is there is readiness whenever one is ready whenever there is a time then the teacher shows up and
yeah thanks so much for sharing that and i see your hand
very quick uh just because fred said this i had a very similar experience
fred um which was that i was 19 and i went to see him at spirit rock and i wasn't ready and i
thought it was all a little strange there was all this singing and my friend and i snuck off into the woods
and like because we weren't supposed to talk we snuck off in the woods so we could talk
uh somehow it got in you know i think the seeds got planted somehow yeah yeah
exactly yeah yeah it's sweet i'm so appreciating these stories and actually
the the um the um [Music] i i love jerry saying i like your
courage right yay and also i'll share with you that the time it wasn't 25 30 years ago maybe i saw him maybe 10 15
years ago in oakland it was another very large teaching and he was older at that point and
slower and and in some way you know i really appreciate what he was talking about and yet there was a lot of pomp
and circumstance that just the evening went on and on and on and on so that
that i'll share that too and i've i've loved reading his books just the simplicity being at peace has
been a go-to for me uh just each page is so simple just so lovely so
all right i see more hands raised but we're 702 so let's bring this formally to close so
that people want to leave but i'll stay a few couple of minutes extra if people want to stay and say and i mark i see
you answer your hand i'll stay extra uh and and invite others to do the same so
so thank you all thank you for showing up for practicing supporting yourselves
each other and this cultivation for all beings everywhere may all beings be well may
all beings be free [Music]
thank you all