so so hello hello and welcome again to happy hour
wonderful to be with you and practicing together
so so for today's practice um [Music]
there are two themes i like to bring in and invite us to work with one is that it's friday it's kind of the end of the
week and also for some it's saturday those joining from uh from different time zones i
acknowledge that but it's kind of the end of the week perhaps so this way of um
bringing in some silence some quiet some rest some
some nourishment and that theme together with another theme that actually they can really go
together and that is um the theme that i've been sitting with and
exploring because um some of you know and actually you signed up i'm teaching a course
starting in less than two weeks called befriending mortality befriending
mortality um and actually i might as well tell you where that is
for those who might be curiosity might be peaked it's um could be fined on insight
inside as an insight meditation in sight practice so it's
insight.podiapodia.com and there's all kinds of information there about it anyway so insight that podia is sorry
the the um i meant to say is the befriending mortality so so befriending mortality
this perspective of of the arc of our life the arc of our life looking and this is
a theme we worked with um last week also which is a world
meta from this perspective from this perspective of looking at their our
lives for this being who is us
this being who has done their best um
hopefully with no regrets at that point maybe there are some but but the sense of meta the sense of
love the sense of acceptance of all there is goodness challenges
of regrets difficulty just the sense of complete acceptance and love as if
our inner buddha our inner compassion itself is getting supercharged and really is
taking on we're taking on that perspective of looking at our lives
with with sense of freedom sense of peace sense of
letting go and sense of ultimate love complete love and acceptance for
ourselves for all the mistakes we made for all the shortcomings all the quirks
we had and all the goodness also all the goodness we brought as well as all the
interactions all the interactions
all the interactions so um
so [Music] that is the theme that is the theme for
our um [Music] practice tonight and
you think about if there is more i want to say about it
um yeah i see there is a question about the course coming i'll answer that later
uh marianne i see that coming through but in terms of our practice in this moment
to stay with to stay with to stay with the sense of meta this perspective
um whether you're new to happy hour or your experience whatever you need to
know whatever you need for this practice for this guided meditation
i will share with you i will share with you so relax
let go enjoy the ride and whatever arises it's the right thing that needs to rise
if sadness grief arises if joy arises if freedom arises
whatever rises trust that that's the right thing that needs to arise right now
as long as you hold it with compassion as long as you hold it with love it's okay it's okay it's okay as long as
you don't push it away as a mistake as long as you love it you may not like it
but as long as you love it you're doing the practice perfectly right there's no wrong here there's no
wrong okay so so with those invitations like to
invite you to settle settle in your body
ah arrive arrive here in this moment
this life this being
here
this body landing landing in this body
is always we arrive we connect
with ourselves letting the body be seated or lying down [Music]
feeling your feet on the floor grounded rooted to the earth
your sit bones hugging the earth
landing on the cushion your hands relaxed soft spread
on your lap or touching each other your neck and shoulders ah letting go of
any tightness or tension
i'm noticing this breath
this amazing lovely breath
morning breeze
fresh with possibility giving life
moving through your body through your lungs
in the lower abdomen
this
letting go this moment releasing of course there are thoughts
memories plans agitations it's okay it's okay
that's what this mind does no judgment
no judgment
releasing releasing
here so delicious just to be here taking a moment of refuge quiet silence
on this friday saturday whatever moment in time
this precious moment in time has never been and would never repeat
i am here i am i am
i am here i am
so simple yet so profound
i am
i am here
i am here now
this may not always be true but it is in this moment
this
you
i am here i am here now
in this moment this will not always be true
but at this moment i am can i deeply connect and appreciate
with gratitude
taking refuge the just presence
the magnificence the mystery of presence
and i am i am i am
here right now i am
wow
thoughts arise planning let that go release just be here simple just be here
i am in this moment not complicated not what if i'm not bob of just i am
simple see the magnificence and the simplicity
of not thinking just being connecting with i am
here
really incredible to just be
to exist to be conscious and aware
i am
not i am sad i am good i am bad i am worthy i just i am just amazing
amazingness of i am here now
now i'd like to invite us
from this perspective connecting
with the amazingness of just being being here now
existing
at this moment
what if this were the last moment of our lives
i'm taking the perspective of oh this precious
beautiful amazing being who did his or her their best
letting there be sense of love tenderness even heartbreak
for this being who was you is you
without any judgment
from the perspective of your inner buddha nature
your inner buddha your inner quantity
just loving
this being walked this
earth at times jumped with joy
with love with care sometimes crawled with sadness
with pain sometimes was alone and lonely
sometimes was connected interconnected with loved ones friends
family was touched and touched many lives
of course every one of us has everyone
loving loving this being who is me it was me
unconditionally
i as much forgiveness as possible they did their best if they could have
done better given all the causes and conditions they would
can we just open up to love
from the perspective
of a compassionate compassionate inner buddha
in your divinity just love just held in
love and if there are areas in life that perhaps call for
more love more care more forgiveness see what's needed right now
both for yourself and other beings you are entangled with
you can also just choose the time of this being who is you
had a vulnerable time it's a challenging time to just love i
just love this being
and recognize the courage the goodness
of having hung in there
so recognizing the goodness the beauty and offering love
now acknowledging that you are here i am i am i am here
this has not been the last moment of your life the time will come you will for all of
us humans it's inevitable and yet you are
you're here you have time to love
to forgive yourself and others to love yourself and others
see what kind of energy that might bring in to your practice
i can i can love i can't forgive
i have a chance i have time limited
but it's still possible
how do i want to love myself others
to show up
my heart and my mind
time is short
there's only [Music] one of you in the world there's ever been and will ever be
you're unique
this is unique being with its particularities
wants to express
it's amazing the potential to care to love
and for wisdom
you still can you still can
time is short and you have time
may all beings everywhere wake up no
capacity the magnificence of their goodness their buddha nature
may all beings including ourselves know how precious and limited our time
our precious human birth is and may we use it wild wisely and
compassionately
thank you thank you dear sangha for your practice
for showing up mark i see your hand shut up please
many times i'm completely out of sync with what you're talking about
and sometimes like tonight i'm totally in sync with it
early this week i was watching a tv program and there was a song
playing in the background for just a couple minutes about a little girl in her
made up little world with a little house where she fed her guests bark and leaves
and went on and i was intrigued and so i looked up the song afterwards
and i found it on youtube and i played about half a dozen
versions of it and um went to bed and i woke up the next
morning this is a few days ago just feeling that i had lived
i was satisfied with my life i had done all that that i needed to do i was ready i died
this afternoon that was absolutely fine there was no problem i
you know i certainly had made loads of mistakes and it all wasn't
perfect perfection but it was i was happy with his life
and it was enough i was satisfied and i was ready
to go and um in case anyone else
would [Music]
thank you mark thank you so much for sharing that beautiful reflection
part of your practice thank you thank you for the benefit of all
sanghan beings and yes please do share it in chat actually i need to change the
settings so everyone can see it and also
please share it if you like in in the google groups thank you mark
yeah claire please
thank you nikki um i raised my hand because this is such a beautiful coincidence i was on the
phone about two hours ago with a friend who had had a serious accent we were
talking about her medical needs and so forth and then somehow we got on to the subject of death
and you know if she had how seriously she had injured herself
uh and the thing that i she and you know so this was you know just to follow on to that
conversation but what i shared with her at the time is that i have had a near-death
experience um and it was it was really uh
it changed me forever in terms of the way i live my life the way i see myself
and the gratitude i feel for having had the life that i've had
you know i as i lay on the stretcher i thought you know it doesn't really matter now i'm
i i has the previous speaker just said i haven't done everything i wanted to do i haven't
done it all very well but i've had a chance and i've tried hard uh and i will you know always be
grateful and i'm no longer afraid of death because i was able to look at it and say
it's okay whatever happens is just fine um with me
and so there you go thank you claire thank
you also for sharing your sense of ease and freedom with the inevitable it's just
part of life death and and also the um the profound shift that your near-death
experience has had in fact i was looking at um some studies on it's called
post-traumatic growth and and um one thing that
happens after some such traumatic experiences um
the post-traumatic growth is one's um priorities shift the way one shows up
once actually lives more fully and more completely and yeah there's a lot of
research on post-traumatic growth so thank you claire for sharing your insights your
experience life really firsthand yeah thank you
yeah any other reflections you can share oh yes and now i can come back um so you
can share your reflections if they're privately sent to me i won't see you read your name if they're to everyone
i'll read your reflections and your name and uh and there was a question about the
course that i had mentioned [Music] befriending mortality and one person had
asked but they have too many conflicts and work conflicts on wednesdays for the
four wednesdays or in their courses starting january 26th
whether it's possible appropriate to sign up and listen to the sessions after they're recorded that is okay we're
allowing that option because it's not just listening to the recordings but
they're also homeworks and the reflections and the participation in that way with the sangha online
through writings and reflections and sharing that you're more than welcome to participate
and even if it's not possible to be in all of the live sessions in real time
jerry says sometimes ego gets in the way of accepting death and then one gets lost absolutely of course that is so
natural and and normal of course it is if it wasn't if it were easy it wouldn't be a
practice it would just it would be perfect we would just have it all we would all have it whereas there was so
much about ego it's so hard for the ego to contemplate its own demise
hence terror management theory and psychology anyway there's so much i can say about
this but i'll save all of that for the course anyway the other reflections from the their
meditation tonight before we turn to small groups any that you like to share
um one private chair very powerful happy hour
thank you sangha and thank you to you thank you for your practice yeah
yeah it was a powerful one for me also really powerful ones so many different aspects to to the
guidance tonight and especially at the end when i invited you to realize oh i still have time i still can show up with
love with forgiveness for me i felt this burst of energy and
and um [Music] and determination gumption brightness
like yes i'm still here i won't always be and yet what
what precious star agency how precious
so dear ones how about we turn how bad we turn
our attention at this point to um [Music]
to uh practicing in small groups in
in size of roughly three and um and the invitation is to start
with about 15 seconds of silence and then here we are these beautiful amazing impermanent
beings and whatever you like to share to support
others practice your own practice as little or as much as you'd like to share you are welcome so
be kind to yourself be kind to each other this is where the practice really
the rubber meets the road in these small groups so so okay so i'm going to open the rooms
and here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed so and we have a
couple minutes for any reflections that might have come up from the practice from speaking with
each other that can be of benefit uh to yourself to be held witness or for
the sangha any questions confusions um aha moments it's all good
so this is your sangha what would be helpful to bring up to share
very close
greg please i was just sharing with the other folks
that um i had the curious experience of finding myself in an er
and being a young black trying to sort of get up
and then being told by the attending physicians that they may not be able to save me
um as in don't move don't be a don't be a young buck we don't know if you're going to survive
so don't try and make any movement at all and it was just curious how
absolutely sort of average no trumpets were playing no angels descended there was just this sort of
averageness of this existence and i have to say it inspired a real curiosity about
whether that was like a normal an average or a desirable reaction to
the core existential challenge to me as a little old person
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah thank you thanks for bringing that
up and i so appreciate how you are sitting with that not taking it as good or bad but as oh
interesting this is one experience that showed up out of so many different experiences that could have possibly
showed up in that moment well this is the one that showed up and i'm curious oh what how
feeling into that what does that feel like what does that say what is just exploring it a little more and and being
curious for it to continue perhaps to continue to open up thank you greg
yeah and rachel i see your hand please
hi nikki it's good to see you too i was in your marana sati retreat a
few years ago um and i just signed up for your course also
so i'm looking forward to that um i i'm not sure if it's a question or
just an observation but do you know how there's this concept of
worse almost practicing for our death in a sense right where we're working with
being comfortable in the moment and and being able to tolerate you know uncertainty and all of that
and lately i've been i've been doing a lot of meta practice a lot
and a lot towards myself and others and i've been thinking backwards in time and i don't
know if there's a is there sort of a parallel teaching in buddhism that we're not just practicing
for our death but we can actually send meta back to our younger selves because that's what i've started doing
and it seems like it's really helping yeah yeah yeah beautiful that's that's
great keep doing that it's what what what lights me up is when i hear that ah
i'm doing that and it's helping it's helping like wow this is working this is
helping so yes trust even even before i turn into the buddhist
you know the buddha said on his deathbed which again talking about death and your clear
important message be a light unto yourself be a light unto yourself and what i'm hearing rachel
is that when you're light unto yourself like yes this is working this is helping this is
opening something up for my humanity for my being the way i'm loving and showing up
so absolutely yes keep this is beautiful please keep practicing in this way
and yes i can you know talk about you know practices etc etc so i think i'll
just leave it at that so yes keep doing this is great all right thanks so much for sharing that lovely
yeah and we close with this last um reflection in
chat from uh soy min i was thinking about the experience of moments
uh fear i've had the habit of being kind to others and ourselves i feel it would
help in being kind and calming ourselves in those moments yes absolutely very
much so the meta is an antidote to fear especially in those moments of
of challenge being afraid and being kind to ourselves and others yeah another
beautiful insight so thank you all thank you for showing up
thank you for your practice thank you thank you thank you deep bowels to each
and every one of you for your beautiful practice may all beings be free
including ourselves [Music]
thank you