so good morning my friends and happy to be here with you again
and i've been on retreat for the last week and
i'm surprised to find myself sitting here with not feeling that there are many words
for the moment so um but feeling peaceful feeling
content happy so
we can begin and to
then i'll say something once we're settled some a little bit i'll i'll uh offer uh orientation a question for the
practice
so to allow yourself
to become quiet
to let your body become quiet
or if quiet is not possible let your body become quieter than it is
the quieting of the body
in a quieting of your eyes maybe if your eyes are open
let them gaze down or whatever direction the eyes are most
relaxed soft eyes
and to maybe gently close your eyes
and to gently quiet your mind
a quieting
maybe a reminder that now not much is needed
but to sit here quietly peacefully
and if the breath breathing is a refuge for you
become aware of your breathing aware of
the movements in your body as you breathe
then quietly slowly
comfortably take a deeper breath
not too deep just so it's nice
take a few deep breaths and as you exhale
a settling in your body releasing into your body
and letting your breathing return to normal
and a quiet gentle scanning of your body
to find the places of holding and tension
that as you exhale you can soften and quiet
as you exhale maybe quieting the thinking mind
maybe first by letting your thinking become slower
a bit more relaxed
and gently if you're going to be thinking think about your breathing
your body think about the here and now your direct
experience think about it in very simple
manner just wrecking thoughts of recognition this is an in-breath
this is an itch this is a sound
and might there be some even small hints
of being peaceful a peacefulness that
is underneath or outside of whatever agitation there might be
a peace which is not opposed to anything a piece which you can hold everything
and then as we continue this meditation you might ask yourself the following
question maybe ask yourself this question three or four times in the time we have here
what is happening right now
that if you recognize
you can be more peaceful about
what needs to be recognized here and now
so that you could be more peaceful about it
maybe more accepting of it
maybe more accepting of yourself as you are
what needs to be recognized
so it can be held in the context of peace
non-conflict
so
for sitting here meditating
what needs to be accepted so you can sit more calmly peacefully
so some degree of peace
provides the atmosphere for whatever is happening
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
tapping into whatever calm or peace there might be here might be
around any agitation there is
and see if in your mind's eye you can gaze upon the world peacefully kindly
gaze upon the world with a vision with an eyesight that
can see the world peacefully calmly
there are places in the world where there is peace there is calmness
okay say be gazing upon the world kindly
love everyone
what might you learn from meditation practice
in holding everything peacefully
that might help you to love everyone
or to love a vast expanse of human beings
looking upon them kindly
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be happy
may all beings
live in peaceful circumstances
may all beings have a peaceful heart
may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
[Music]
so
so good morning everyone and welcome to this monday morning and
nice to be back and and thank you meg for
teaching last week appreciate it very much and
so what i thought of doing this week
is to make and to have emotions be the theme
and to emotions are an important part of human life sometimes for ourselves and sometimes
for others and to be aware and wise about emotions
is one of the potentials of this mindfulness practice
because we can learn to be mindful of emotions and see them in new ways and
deeper ways fuller ways and
so today i want to say some introductory words about this and that is to start off that
many of you know that i'm fond of the latin roots for the word emotion
that means out and the motion means motion
and here and so the um the
that which moves out and why i like this interpretation or this kind of etymological
playing with the word is that i like to think of
whatever emotions are they're changing they're in flux they're
they're moving and if we leave them alone
they move out they move out they settle out they they don't stay for too long
and so understanding the conditions that keep the emotions going
that fuel them that trigger them that perpetuate them is one of the things we can use the
mindfulness practice to do it seems that more literally the word
emotion comes not from first from latin but from french where it
in i think which i think in french means more to be excited by something
uh to be a certain kind of excitement agitation be to be stirred up by something
and was so you know it has this a little bit interesting is history but
even more interesting i i think is that um the the we take this word emotion many
of us speaking english take this english word emotion for granted or as if it's you know
describe something real or essential or
and important and certainly it does in certain ways but i find it fascinating that um
the english as an english word the word emotion wasn't was not coined
until around the early 1800s so it's uh only been around for
um [Music] you know a couple of hundred years in the english
language and there's a book on emotions and history of emotions
where the author says that kind of kind of maybe tongue-in-cheek a little bit
that until 1830 it wasn't until 1830 that the word emotion started to get currency or
it was actively adopted into popular speech in english i guess in england
and and so he says the author of this book says that until 1830 or so english-speaking people
didn't have emotions what they would refer to as they refer to having sentiments
or having he calls it accidents of the soul or passions
they had other words that they used for something that was in the domain in the range of
the world of emotions but they had kind of a different uh overlapped with different meanings it
doesn't mean exactly the same as what most many people here in english think of as emotions
and the um
and then i've looked it up in dictionaries for different definitions of what this word emotion is
and most of the definitions i see don't really tell me much
they don't not i don't feel like they're very helpful for providing a clear definition and this is one of the wonderful things
about this word emotion in english is that um there's no real agreement for what this
word means even in among psychologists there's different definitions different ideas of
what it is and so not having a clear precise definition
can also be seen as a gives us some freedom around it that we don't have to have some kind of
um fixed idea of what emotions are fixed ideas of
their role in our lives fixed ideas of their impact on us personally fixed
ideas of where they're going and what what's happening what they mean and
all that one of the things we can learn to do is to
whatever each of us individually refer to as an emotion
and we're allowed we're allowed to have our own definition and we're allowed to kind of use the
word to apply to what we're experiencing and as we see fit to use that word
but what we whatever whatever we were using that word to refer to
the practice of mindfulness can help us to discover freedom in a relationship to what we're
experiencing and so to experience freedom in relationship to emotions
and this is uh i'd like to propose for some of us it's a radical idea because it's not an idea that we need to
do anything about emotions we need to get rid of them the ones that are not we don't like
do we need to bring on the ones that we want
it isn't changing our emotions to be free of our free
with our emotions is to change our way of relating to them
to change the way we hold them or the way we think about them and this uh radical idea of discovering
discovering freedom in relationships to emotions to not be defined by them
not be pushed around by them not to
assume that emotions have meaning
that the emotions have a purpose emotions have
uh uh tell us who we are
or who we're not or all kinds of things all those things might exist together
with emotions but to be to discover freedom in relationship to them
to discover a peacefulness that can hold what
whatever emotion we have or to discover a wakefulness
to be awake to emotions as opposed to be overwhelmed by them
to be awake to emotions rather than being pushed by them or defined by them or
or or to without or to have emotions without assigning
meaning to them and
and so this ability then to give freedom to our emotions
is a tremendous gift to ourselves and the place where that gift i think is
safest to give and and the most productive is in meditation whether it's sitting
meditation or walking meditation and but in a context where
what we're doing is not acting out the emotion not acting because of the emotion
um not criticizing the motion not needing to not express the emotion because maybe
socially it's unacceptable in some way whatever we're feeling
but in meditation we're kind of we look peaceful the body's still quiet
but internally we can allow whatever the energies are the feelings are the
sensations might be the moods the states of mind that might be
associated with all this and the motivations that are associated with some emotions
that all these can flow through us to be present for us uh with permission we give permission to
it to be there we're not fighting emotions we're not feeling ashamed because of having
emotions we're not justifying some emotions we're not indulging in some emotions
and and we are just there's a ability to be
still to be quiet certain parts of us um and let make space create lots of
space for whatever the emotional expression is at the time and to be awake to it to be at peace
with it to allow it but don't and we're not going to act on it so if we're angry with someone we want to
punch them out we don't in meditation because we're not going to move and we just feel the energy that's there
if we have a strong desire for something we don't act on the desire
we just sit there and let the desire be there in that space of freedom just allow it
to be there without making a story or meaning or purpose out of it
if there's a wonderful emotional thing it really feels wonderful and delightful and this is where some people now will
protest uh we don't indulge in it we don't lean into it and they don't we don't
fuel it or or encourage it and some people say why not it's a good thing
it's true there are times when it's good to lean into and allow ourselves to really feel a lot of good emotions
when we're trying to discover how to be free with emotions we want to uh the freedom of something
has to be equally granted in all directions to what the good emotions are and the
difficult emotions and so certainly we're allowed to feel the good emotions but we don't indulge
in it we don't lean into it or savor it or actively enjoy it we just allow the
enjoyment to be there because we want to be able to do the same with the difficult emotions
allow them to be there maybe we don't lean into them always with those but we don't pull where we pull away
or we shut down or we attack or something so to learn how to be free
with our emotions is a huge gift from this mindfulness practice
and it begins by recognizing what our emotions are
and and you're allowed to have it your way in this recognition things
different cultures different places in the world different languages have a somewhat different relationship with
what we might think of as emotions and maybe different families different
all kinds of things so here in this practice is freedom practice you're allowed it for it to be
your way and your associations with it with the with the idea
that a clear mindfulness of your emotional life clear recognition of what's there
i can support you to hold it peacefully
to be aware of it without being pushed around by it and
so what i'd like to suggest that as we start this week is that um
you reflect some on your emotional life and two things one is you you kind of uh reflect on
what are the different emotions that move through you through the day
you might at the end of the day write down a list of all the emotions you can identify that you've had for
that day from the subtle to the big and once you have that long list of all
the emotions you see there look and see what are there any patterns
certain emotions appear more often or more predominant and then reflect a little bit about what
you've learned about emotions um what you have um
what your culture your family your religion your society your language your
languages if you speak different languages how what what have you learned about this emotional life of yours and how you
identify it and what you think they are so um that'll be the beginning of our
reflections for this week and um happy to be back and happy to
to to be sharing this with you thank you