so lovely to practice with you all welcome
welcome so
for today's practice I wanted to invite us to
[Music] um to engage with [Music] um
with the practice of equanimity Equanimity equipoise
which is the fourth Brahma vihara the fourth Heavenly abode
practice the the four of the four heart practices the first one being meta
loving kindness second one being Compassion or karuna the third one the
yes the third one being vicarious Joy uh or sympathetic joy muddita and the
fourth one is equanimity and it's it's holds all the other ones
and it's also in some ways could be thought of as the Perfection of the other one so Equanimity is um
[Music] um this sense of balance equipoise and it
has warmth has care about it so it's not aloof it's not
uncaring it's not uh whatever I'm just being a Quantum is that's not Equanimity
that's aloofness that's the nearest neighbor nearest neighbor or near enemy
not nears tonight somehow the words are different words are coming in anyways this is interesting uh lots of anata
here in the way this mind is working tonight but it's the near enemy uh it's a near enemy
um of mudita so um the aloofness or is a near enemy
somehow nearest neighbor from well my years of doing mathematics and computer science is coming in but anyway just
laughing at this mind wasn't it fun sometimes to laugh at the impersonality of how our mind works right it's
ungovernable sometimes you want to do something or think something and something else happens just anata not
self right there anyway but tonight we're not going to practice not self we're going to practice
um Equanimity so so Equanimity so so many different ways to get into this
practice of equanimity and and it's a crown jewel really Equanimity
is a crown jewel of um Buddhist practice
it supports us not just on the cushion in our practice the formal practice but
throughout our life as the vicissitudes challenges difficulties
um our Diamond a dozen in this Human Condition so can we be with them with
Equanimity with equipoise not bearing down but just
in the middle of the storm and the eye of the storm having an expanse of
spacious view so so I think that's all I want to say to
set up the framework for tonight and we'll just practice together and find our ways our
a unique way into it tonight so so I'd like to invite you
to get into your meditation posture whatever that might be
if you need to shift move from
your cushion to a chair or from a chair to a cushion
the posture that will be comfortable for the next 30 minutes of meditation
and letting there be a sense of Integrity in your body
sense of a brightness
letting the spine be upright be held
not pushed up but as if there is a thread
the top of your head Invisible Thread holding you up
nor a powerful magnet ah that opens your
upper body your torso your chest all opened up with the breath
sitting upright
and letting your lower body
be well grounded well rooted to the Earth
the upper body opened up
a bright sense of foreign spaciousness opening to the
heavens and the lower body connected well rooted to the Earth
your feet your sit bones
so that you feel like you have both Roots you're well rooted
into the Earth in this moment
and also you have wings like an angel expansive you're heart expansive
you have roots and wings
I let the breath move through soothing comforting
your abdomen your chest expanding with each breath
feeling more present
and whatever is arising in the body the heart and the mind
and be welcomed
and be welcomed and can be here just as it is
no need to get rid of it
push it away
or even attend to it perhaps but just opening to
it all you can be here there's so much space space spaciousness
ease that this can be here along with everything else for us
and if they're fatigue restlessness all of that can be present
too doesn't have to take Center Stage
as if you're expanding it's imagining imagining that you're expanding your
stretching your heart you're stretching your awareness
first you're stretching it and then it stretches on its own it keeps going
expanding expanding just like the universe keeps expanding
your heart keeps expanding stretching
stretching on its own including everything everything
and there's still more space
there can be so much ease in this expansion and yeah pain difficulties emotions can
be there sleepiness agitation can all be there
cannot be here there's enough space
for everything to be present
your heart so expensive spacious
when your thoughts are rising plans memories
it's okay it's all right
letting the expansiveness spaciousness hold everything
or letting it drop everything doesn't have to hold
if it feels like an effort
okay ah I can also drop just drop
release
not with aversion
but with the wisdom that doesn't need to be held can be released
so if you're opening up your hand ah
letting it Fly Away
and this gesture of the Open Hand Helping Hands
being felt in your heart too not just in your hands maybe actually might be helpful to open your hands
as they're resting on your lap I feel into the energy of the open
relaxed resting hands
not grasping not pushing away
no pin relaxed
kneel into the spaciousness of this gesture of the Open Hand
how much is release ah
you can feel with in this gesture
now imagine your heart
also has the gesture of the Open Hands
relaxed not grasping or pushing away
things can be Landing resting in the hand and then
leaving arising passing away it's like this
it's like this and this human realm comings and goings
all the comings and goings
interesting maybe even delightful
expansive a sense of care your hand is
turned upward so we can hold your heart can hold
yet it doesn't grasp hold on to
also as the hand has this gesture of openness
the fingers there's space between the fingers pings pour through
thoughts memories
there's a lightness and the feeling
and letting them pour through fall through it's okay
your hand is open for new experiences new knowings
new gifts
new blessings and new Sorrows that serve as teachers
this gesture of the Open Hand
a heart that has an open hand
it's also just a gesture of generosity
generosity with life
experiencing knowing giving
not grasping can we relate
to Equanimity in this practice today as the gesture of an open hand open
heart in this way
maybe just to get a sense of it close your hands feel the fist forming
on your lap feeling to how that is different let
your heart feel how this is different different stance
in life a closed fist
and open whenever you're ready you've got a sense of it
Open Hands resting on your lap
your heart
with the gesture of the open Heads
see what new perceptions this brings about
new realizations no insights for you tonight
In This Moment In Time this Open Hand of the heart
gesture of the Open Hand
here with the breath with the body With This Heart
feel feel the embodiment
of the Open Hands in your heart with each breath
the gesture of equanimity sitting grounded
upright like a mountain stable
chest heart open present
hands open heart open stable open present
feel it in your body the mind will follow
feel the stability of your posture
your brightness the well-rootedness
the Open Hands feel feel into it
feel the embodiment
it's not an idea of equanimity
it's an embodied experience
be equanimity
trust that your body knows Trust
Equanimity not falling into
not grasping not being reduced to
not sinking into and not pushing away
with the version fear dislike
but upright well rooted with an open hand open heart
all experiences can be just as they are arise pass away
spacious heart spacious mind and your body knows
Even If you experience it for a moment with respect to something here
something opens up in your mind in your heart a possibility
for different relationship to life
your thoughts stories
emotions
again feeling to the embodiment
fake it until you become it sitting
feeling your body on the earth connected
rooted upright open heart open hands
expansive spacious the breath inside outside all around
you might even visualize stories like a little bird like a butterfly
Landing in your hand open hand and then flying away
not reacting comes and goes
you sit you are breathed spacious stable
nowhere kind here
and as we bring this practice period to a close
may we embody Equanimity for ourselves
for others the benefit all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
be stable no true
equipoise with presence and care not turning away
not closing the hand may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
[Music] it's everyone
thanks for your practice
so we have some time for Reflections for questions comments
about this practice Equanimity in this particular way of feeling into it and
and today I was inviting us to feel into the embodiment of equanimity with the
gesture of sitting connected to the Earth really feeling or stability sitting tall like a mountain it's a
gesture of equanimity with open hands open your hands and open heart really
feeling into that it's not a closed fist it's not the one that grasps objects uh
it's not one that pushes away or throws away it's one that's open it can land it
can go pour through there's a sense of openness of the heart and stability
so that's the invitation I was making for us to feel into Equanimity not at
night not like an idea like what is equanimity this word I can never get like what do they even mean
feel into it what does it feel like what does it feel like
that was the invitation I was hoping that maybe even for a split second something connected in a different way
than that maybe opens something up for your possibility in your life in your practice so
that was my hope intention and would love to hear how it was for you
many insights experiences what worked what didn't work for the benefit of yourself
benefit of the Sangha you can raise your Zoom hand you can type in chat puzzle
please hi just uh when you said to the Equanimity that just kind of hit that
was pretty neat it's like oh wait just wait it changed a little bit it was it was
neat thank you nice thank you for reflecting them back to be equivalent I
love it great thanks for highlighting that puzzle I'm glad something shifted for you yay and try that try that
since it hits in a particular way it you can
drop that in right you can drop that in in your daily life practice I'll be Equanimity oh yeah I
know what that feels like my body knows like it's not so much a heady thing be Equanimity beautiful thanks muzzle
any other Reflections you can also type in chat red
thanks Nikki the contrast between the open hand and
the clenched fist was really striking to me I if I was less aware of equanimous
feelings throughout the meditation I could tell from the uh the sharp contrast of being
in the defensive position with fists closed that this was not Equanimity and
better better to return to the open hand beautiful great thank you so much for
reflecting that yeah that's great thank you for the reflection Fred this this um
contrast because like yeah it feels different in in our bodies
um this and this and and um
it's there's a lot of science too um our mind States
and um and our physical States in fact a lot of metaphors and a lot of our mind
States the words that we use in language come from our physical gestures so so
it's important to to um yeah to to take advantage of what we
already have to make these knowings more more
clear distinct by using these uh these gestures and some um Michelle I think
you're trying to raise your hand yes and and Dan will go to you afterwards Michelle please
um as I open to this tremendous fear that I was feeling
um the more I open to the fear the more Equanimity I felt
does that make sense absolutely it makes sense Michelle yeah
yeah how interesting right now interesting the more you open to
fear the more Equanimity you felt yeah feel into the profundity of that
that's a profound insight because the more we close up to fear the
more we're afraid of fear uh the more the bigger it feels and the more we open
up to it okay I'm not scared here come oh wow there's more Equanimity look at
that it's so counterintuitive and yet that's it
beautiful thanks for sharing that Michelle
beautiful ah
Jerry says it felt like a brief moment of openness to a blend of the loving
kindness compassion and joy yep great Dan I see you please
yes um um I I thought I had the explanation
damn very well as you gave it and it was a very good session
but just for the heck of my life I'm I'm got this on my phone but I have my computer here so I typed in equity
and I looked at that and was talking a calmness composure even the September
especially in a difficult situation and I was thinking and you talked about
you know uh disturbances or or being upset and things which was very useful
as a bit of a contrast but there's no threat while sitting here
and a couple hours ago I was crossing the street here in New York City and
years ago it used to be worth your life crossing a street in New York the traffic was very aggressive especially
the cab drivers they would come right through an intersection and it was almost worth your life crossing the
street so almost through without exception if you're in a crosswalk even a quarter of
the way across the street someone coming the other way will stop they'll let you go okay and come so I'm crossing the
street and I'm about here for your cross and the guy is coming quite quickly into
the intersection and I can tell by his speed and the Kangal it was real he's
just gonna go he's not gonna stop and it occurred to me to slow my Pace to
be sure he had a left enough room I didn't I just kept walking I'm a big
guy I have a very big mouth good commit command voice and I got really close to
the car not to endanger myself and that I was I knew I was going to yell at him
even though in a sense I knew it was a bad idea and I wished not to do it and
the phrase no good can come of this went through went through my mind right and I
thought how the heck with it I'm just going to yell got it okay oh I didn't curse I didn't do anything or but he had
his window all the way down and I was grateful for that I think I'm getting I think I'm getting the picture then yeah
and for the benefit of time I think I get the picture and your question is okay that's a stressful situation oh no
all I did was yell hey and as soon as I did that I read I
regretted it and wish I had said nothing at all yeah so so here's what I would say I
appreciate you bringing that in and and here's so the the question basically is you're asking okay here I'm sitting I'm
practicing there's no threat uh I'm feeling pretty calm and I'm practicing
this Equanimity thing and yet there on the street is where I really wanted it
uh well that's where I wish I had it great fantastic I'm so glad you're bringing this up like what does this
have to do with the price of tomatoes because that's what I wanted I'm here I'm doing nothing well this is the
practice we practice it it's like going to the gym with small weights so that
and it's it's the same thing with the loving kindness we we cultivate it so
that when when the 100 pound weight is present like oh I know how to do this I've been
practicing I've been practicing my heart I've been practicing in my mind for those States When the Thought comes like
okay there's no good to come out of this yes I could be equanimous etc etc so this is exactly why we do this practice
this it's what that's why it's called practice we're practicing because there
are a lot of performances in the world when we're crossing the street um
etc etc etc when somebody I don't sends us a text message or calls us Etc so so yeah
so thank you for those Reflections everyone so I'd like to invite us to engage in uh
small groups small practice groups I'm going to create them now and uh the
breakout groups are roughly size three and the invitation is to share a little
bit um anything you'd like to share about tonight's practice about the sense of
embodiment if there's something new for you something that arose and you can also hold uh presence uh quiet silence
off of you silence they pass off for one nugget from your own experience allow
the next person to offer their nugget or experience and the next person again
speak from your ex personal experience not from your head but embodiment let's
really bring in embodiment not advising or directing other people's experience
be kind take care of yourself take care of each other and
um yeah it's it's beautiful to be able to share and spend time in Sangha so so I'm
going to create the rooms take care of yourselves and let's go uh reverse alphabetical order according
to face to first name okay so I'm going to open the room uh one more second and
here we go okay their rooms are closed everybody is back hope you had a
wonderful connection and it's uh seven o'clock so um don't have time for
any Reflections from the practice uh from the breakout groups but tell you
what let's uh dedicate the Merit and close and I'll stay for an extra couple minutes on Zoom afterwards if there's
anything you'd like to share um so thank you all thank you for practicing together and uh and being
Equanimity yes practicing on the cushions though that in the world we can show off for ourselves and for the
benefit of Others May all beings be well may all beings be happy including
ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone take care