all right so formally hello and welcome to happy hour lovely to be with you to practice
together very much looking forward to our practice together dear sangha so
so for today's practice um [Music] i'd like to invite us to consider
the cultivation of metta the planting seeds of kindness
good will [Music] for ourselves for others
basically planting these seeds as
as the biggest gift perhaps that we can give to the world maybe not
the biggest maybe i don't want to set it up so big but as has
a uh as a gift of our presence as a gift you know we are passing we're passing
through this earth our lifetime is is a flash relative
to the cosmic time scale so of course for many of us our work in the
world is important maybe children maybe relatives etc we all have different ways
that we engage and and give our gifts to the world what if we also consider
planting the seeds of meta offering offering kindness in whatever shape or
form it shows up both for ourselves this person who is me
as well as for others other beings as as an expression
of our gift as as a big gift that we can give
not just say the work we do maybe the books we write the companies we create
whatever it might be but but how we do it how these things are done how we
interact with people how we interact with ourselves with this person who is
us um whom we are the guardian of the only guardian of
really the care of this person who is me has been entrusted
to me so so not just what we do
but how we do it and actually the how the how
in the world being the bigger gift being leaving a lasting impression
on people on loved ones on people we know and people we don't we don't know
so so that how that that gift of generosity of kindness towards ourselves
and others to consider that so
i offer that for our reflection and
for guided meditation i will invite us with
some invitations for planting seeds and can whatever happens if you find that
this mind this body is achy is sleepy is distracted
different thoughts arise the opposite of meta arises as long as you have kindness
as long as you show kindness towards what is arising you are planting seeds
of metta so even if even if
say self-judgment arises if you're kind of sweetheart you're being
you're being very judgmental you're having a hard time right now you're having a hard day hard evening
you turn towards that even self-judgment even if you turn towards it with kindness you are
planting the seeds of meta this how that i'm talking about this way
of being in the world this big gift that this legacy
that we create these reverberations that we create for ourselves and for others
through each act of mind and in buddhism
thoughts are considered actions of the mind the sixth sense doors the sixth one
the five are the regular five that we know and the sixth one being the mind door
thinking recreating all the other senses in the mind
so i think i've said enough to set the stage for our practice tonight so
so with that i'd like to invite us now to
arrive and settle in our bodies you may need to move the shift to sit up
straight or to lie down to stand see what your body needs
see what your body needs to be able to
be still and rest comfortably for the next 30 minutes of this guided
meditation together so arriving
arriving in this body
however the body is in this moment
embracing welcoming appreciating
that there is enough health enough stability to show up in this
moment the body might be achy
tired it's okay thank you body
thank you for supporting supporting this mind this heart
this awareness inviting the body to relax
to soften
to let go of tightness tension
releasing releasing the forehead
lighting it to be soft
releasing the jaw
the face let the eyes rest
in their socket
wide your neck your shoulders
to release the weight the proverbial weight they've been carrying all day
it's okay it's okay now it's all right sweetheart it's okay
putting down thoughts concerns
in this moment taking refuge
taking refuge in your heart
in your intentions your kind intentions
for goodness for gladness happiness for yourself and others
releasing your back
ah your chest your abdomen
let the breath
be received in the lower abdomen
filling this cavity
let it feel spacious let it feel
expansive your abdomen
the breaths moving
and releasing the tension in your sit bones
and your upper legs releasing
the weight onto the earth
the knees the lower legs and feet
as if any holding is offered to the earth as a
weight dropping dropping the weight of your
legs or your sit bones
let the breath move through notice i'm not saying
to breathe because the breath breathes you
you've been breathing all this time
no need to make it complicated into a project
just let it happen as it has been happening simply notice that the breathing
is occurring
any thoughts arise it's okay no problem
they will arise
noticing thoughts smilingly oh dear thoughts i release you
with a smile as if i'm letting a little birdie fly
taking refuge in my heart and not now please come back later
you may need to release thoughts smilingly a hundred times
do it with kindness to yourself and the thoughts
planting scenes of kindness one bird at a time
and for the sake of our practice tonight today
let there be an extra dose of kindness
for whatever the mind notices if it's the breath
the abdomen can it be received with kindness with appreciation
graciously
if your awareness is holding turns to
the body sensation maybe an ache or pain
can it massage with your thought
with your mind can the sensation be massaged with kindness
with care
if a thought or entanglement arises
maybe you think of a person [Music]
or a project or something can there be extra kindness
maybe a smile maybe a little blessing of meta
friendliness before you release the bird
bird by bird whatever arises
kindness towards all these birds that arise that land
in your sphere of awareness
awareness spacious like the sky
birds of sensation birds of thought
maybe even the breath as a bird
smilingly offering seeds of kindness to the birds
especially if there are any challenges in your heart and your mind
extra kindness care soothing
[Music]
offered
you were doing your best
all the birds are doing their best
if anything could have been different it would have been
and the causes and conditions are like this
can we be kind to what is to whatever is showing up
just as it is yourself included
kindness it's also an empowerment
see if you can notice feel the empowerment
the strength of kindness in your heart
as a gift
and then sharing kindness care good will
not only is there an empowerment that we feel in our heart
but it's a gift that in giving [Music]
we receive ourselves
the goodness of it
radiating radiating kindness
goodness to whatever rises this fear of awareness
and as we offer kindness radiate kindness
opening our heart
to whomever arises whoever shows up as a guest
friends family neutral people people we have challenges
with
there are human beings just like me who want to be happy they don't want to
suffer
offering friendliness maybe a smile
neighborliness
may you be well may all of us be well
see what's easy whatever comes easy
to your body to your heart to your mind let your body be relaxed at ease
and i like to make another invitation feel free to explore this if it works
for you
if kindness were
like light shimmering light
as you offered it to the world to others to yourself
shimmering light that brings goodness brings sucker brings care
whomever it touches whatever it touches
whatever it shines upon whoever whomever it shines upon
brings gladness goodness it's an offering as a gift
again not attached to outcomes it's just an offering
it's a cultivation of our heart
now what if you imagined your whole body
drenched in kindness
shining with this light
this shimmering light and you offer yourself to the world
if your judgmental mind gets in the way oh i'm not that good i'm not that kind
it's okay let that go for now we're just exploring
imagine imagine for just a moment that you are the light you are the gift
of kindness you offer yourself up
wherever you are needed wherever this body this heart this mind
is needed you offer yourself up without hesitation
offer your skills your goodness your time
your heart you are the gift
let yourself be the gift you are the good
in ways you we
cannot fathom of ourselves
making ourselves the gift of kindness
of goodness onto the world
the light that shines
without preference
unconditionally
as we bring this practice period or close
whatever rose or did not arise during this practice period
if there was sleepiness distractedness present not a problem
offer kindness to whatever rose offer kindness to yourself
trusting that even if there was there is one moment of kindness
goodness that's good enough
offering seeds planting seeds
and collectively [Music] we share we offer to the world our goodness
from this practice may all beings everywhere all beings
may they know [Music] their own goodness
that they are a gift unto the world
may we all cultivate goodness wisdom kindness
and give ourselves and others
the best gift of all wisdom and kindness
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone
[Applause]
so we have time for reflections
questions comments for a few minutes and you're invited
to share what came up for you if there was an aha moment
or a challenge as a way of giving a gift offering the gift of your practice
to the sangha
often the ways in the ways in which we open up
can be helpful for others dawn please
um nikki yeah thanks so much that was um yeah i had a really rough day
and it was nice to um uh be encouraged to uh
be kind to myself and like and also to sort of whatever came up was okay anyway
so i wanted to really thank you
thank you don i want to thank you for coming here practicing
and also speaking up and sharing your practice having had a hard day a rough
day which many of us probably can can identify with and
bringing kindness to whatever role especially with yourself beautiful thank
you thank you dot [Music]
any other reflections you can raise your zoom hand i won't see your physical hand because
there are too many of us or you can type in chat if you type to me privately i will not
read your name it will be private if it's typed to everyone i will read your name
other reflections what what was this like for you
did you try did anyone try the invitation towards the end to see
yourself as a gift onto the world how did that go was there a moment that actually
that practice lit up for you or was there a lot of lot of judgment oh no
not me curious what happened you're willing to share
it's all good
silence is fine too i see claire's hand claire
thank you nikki that was actually the part of the meditation that i appreciated the most
um it's a practice that i've been observing for a number of years
and it was interesting i i was approached this week by a woman who's roughly in my age range very
accomplished but not as accomplished as her friends in her eyes
and i was trying to explain to her that the joy of living came from giving my skills away
not taking and i couldn't get through to her i felt so bad because she's very lonely and
very unhappy because she sees herself as a failure
and we're not failures if we give what we've got yeah well
you know it changes the whole dynamic yeah absolutely well said claire well said
it's it's not about getting it's about giving yes and we're all we have so much to
give every single one of us yeah our time our attention our resources
thank you claire beautifully said thank you lovely mark please
to my surprise i was able to get into that final
image of of just being light and goodness
towards everything and towards everything that that i might touch i've been
sitting with a meditation of jack cornfields for the last couple of months where
he ends up saying you can send out compassion
love and blessings in every direction now and that's how i've been starting my
day every day for about the last 90 days and your
your image and someone was able to to really connect that to me i'm i was
i am surprised it's great thank you so much
beautiful thank you mark i'm just delighted to hear you've been doing this practice with jack for the past 90 days
and something about tonight's guidance really connected for you and lit you up
you know uh it was the it was a prepared mind right you've been preparing your mind for 90
days and something happened tonight like oh things lit up that's just beautiful it's lovely yay makes me so happy lights
me up with joy for you that's lovely thank you thank you yeah it's so sweet
and i see someone who's clapping and it keeps appearing and disappearing if
you're trying to raise your hand please try again uh the raised hand function is
um could be under reactions again i see that i think it's hugh
hugh are you trying to raise your hand but clap doing the clap instead
yes [Laughter] what's up you
uh uh thank you thank you thank you the um
i had a really good uh experience and we're with the meditation
tonight and when you spoke about that um
we are the uh a light that shines a gift to the world you know it uh it reminded me of
a couple of times i think it reminded me of you know a biological uh
thing called bioluminescence right i think i've seen a couple of people who
were just overflowing with compassion and kindness and it seemed to my eyes
like they were glowing yeah yeah yeah that's exactly right yeah
it's beautiful image we appreciate you bringing that in yeah that's sweet by you luminescence exactly yeah maybe
i'll suggest that next time the guided meditation for those who have seen that that's lovely thank you
yeah it's great so so the time has come for the invitation as we've been
spreading as we've been shining um kindness in our heart space in our quiet
heart space what if we actually open our eyes and be in relationship with others
with a couple of other human beings who also are here to cultivate their hearts and kindness
and so in small groups will be roughly of size three the invitation is to share
just one nugget if you have five things to say from say the guided meditation just share one nugget from your
experience again speaking just from your experience and then the next person will offer a
nugget or will be silent they can say pass just holding kind space for the
community that's perfectly fine and then the next page this is the next person
will say something or we'll share or we'll pass and then you go round and
round a few times until the time the groups which is about eight
minutes would be over seven eight minutes um and please speak from your own
experience not guiding asking questions or or trying to
facilitate the group just holding close with kindness to yourself kindness to
others see what happens having practice now to show up and share with these
amazing sangha this is such a beautiful sangha really such a beautiful sangha
to show up in this way together so so with that
i'm going to open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go okay
the rooms are closed everybody is back welcome back everyone
and we've got just about a minute for any reflections that might have come up
uh from [Music] connecting in groups so
anyone last words i see smiles
as usual coming back from the room
okay i don't see any hands i do see deborah's um
words in chat the song lyrics lyrics came to me during the meditation this little light of mine i'm gonna let it
shine great may you all let your light shine unto the world yeah thank you all thank
you for your practice for coming together for cultivating this
this practice for your own sake for the sake of others
and may we all let our light of kindness shine onto the world
may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thank you