so good day everyone happy to be here
and um this being the could be could mark the
so uh end of our second year
of doing these youtube uh sittings and teachings together
thank you for these two years i appreciate it very much and um
i'll say a little bit more about that later for now i would like to uh for this
meditation um imagine that you're a passenger in a car
and the driver you notice after a while that when the driver gets excited about
the conversation you're having the driver pushes more on the gas pedal
and you go fast maybe someone's faster more maybe faster you and then you're comfortable
but when the conversation's not going in a good way and the driver feels challenged and
or feels discouraged about something or feels overwhelmed or feels like you know this is just
you know maybe maybe getting bad news or something
that uh the the driver pulls the pedal off the gas a
little bit a foot off the gas pedal a bit and the car slows down and maybe slower than you're comfortable on the freeway
and you see that in your trip constantly depending on the mood the attitude the beliefs that
how how the driver is reacting to the conversation
the pedal goes up and down and this car goes slower or faster
so we're this way as well that uh there are
forces within us they get us to put up put the gas pedal on our energy
and that we suddenly were energized and excited and and there's lots of energy and other
times when things happen to us that we we
remove the energy we don't apply or give energy to our life and we go slower we the energy sinks there's
a sinking feeling the classic this language of this is sinking mind
and an excited mind and so in meditation it's possible to be
aware of this movement from from the mind being somehow uh
not being not having a vital alive uh energy that keeps it kind of going in
a nice way the mind feels drained or subdued or
numb or you know sluggish or
you know closed down or the mind gets hyper aroused
and gets maybe from fear and anxiety regrets maybe some kind of
restlessness that goes on agitation and and so we can watch this in meditation
we could be the passenger in our own car and mindfulness allows us it gives a
chance to see this what's happening and to become sensitive to that movement of energy
that um from a kind of balanced energy to over energized and under energized
and sometimes it can be dramatic some some thought or feeling arises something that
goes on memory arises and it can go one way or the other quite strongly
i've had anger arise in meditation and boy suddenly i was like on fire with energy just thinking about something
that happened long ago and and so
and so it can be quite subtle as well little movements it could be that the mind wanders off a
little bit too much for your liking and so there's a little bit discouragement i can't do this this is
too hard and with that attitude you can feel the sinking of energy
and a little bit more less energy available to engage and so as we practice
we want to it's nice to become sensitive to the swings of the energy that go on
and maybe there's always a little bit of swings and and a little bit we can adjust for
it and simply being mindful of it is already an adjustment
so in this meditation perhaps you can do this
so taking an alert posture sitting upright
or literally and maybe lower your gaze to about 45
degrees to the floor and let your eyes becomes
relaxed let your eyes become soft without
looking anything in particular and then
if it's comfortable gently close your eyes
and become aware of your energy level become aware of how you're feeling
how much vitality there is does it feel like overenergized
under-energized just right
and whatever way it is for these moments it's okay let yourself be the way you are
just recognize it
and then gently take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe deep breaths and almost like expanding of the body expands into your
energy level
you feel into the energized body and as you exhale you relax
the body
letting your breathing return to normal and continue
relaxing the body there is a way of relaxing the body
that simultaneously gives a kind of a
good energy to the mind an energy which i
associated with clarity a relaxation that brings clarity
relaxing the face
relaxing the shoulders
softening the belly
and then letting your breathing return to normal and notice now
how is your energy level your vitality or
the ability to engage here and now
and is there some quality or some way you are
about sitting here to meditate
that limits your the energy that's available an attitude this is work and you don't
like to work attitude that is difficult
the idea that life has been hard and so you're
overwhelmed coming here so there's kind of giving up or letting go or
unwillingness it could be very subtle
or is it more the other side excited restless
over eager
racing ahead that energy of wanting or
energy of aversion that keeps us charged up
and if you're under energized
can you bring in some more energy to the practice
that helps bring clarity to the present moment clarity of seeing
and if you're over energized can you soften relax
and when it feels just right or close enough to write
allow yourself to then just be with meditation
be with the coming and going of the breath
what's happening now with your energy
and coming near the end of this meditation what is your energy like now
the energy of your engaging in mindfulness
what if any forces within you that tend to be deflating of your energy
and what forces within you brings too much energy
and to simply see it know it without needing to judge it or react to
it just for a moment here just see it clearly
and then this ability to see clearly what is is not a small thing
it's one of the great gifts that we can give the world so we see without the filter of our
attitudes beliefs without our reactions to what's
happening so we learned to have this clarity of
seeing of ourselves and then we learn to do it with others
to the world and may it be that our ability to
see clearly allows us also to seek kindly
to see generously to see with care and compassion
being attuned to what brings welfare and happiness
it may it be that this practice that we do
it's always encouraging us to apply it to this world
so some way or other we're making a better world for all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and in particular may we spread this kindness and care and wish
to all the people suffering in the ukraine
certainly the ukrainians but i imagine it's for me it's
heartbreaking
what this situation must be like for many of the russians and soldiers
may they be safe and go home may they be happy
may they be free and find some way to not participate
in this violence that they've been sent to
they all beings live together
in friendship
[Music]
thank you
so i think we had no um
glitches with uh broadcast today so that's good and maybe things have
been taken care of
so um a few things before we start here
one is that i want to celebrate with you and appreciate you
this now this second year anniversary for doing these youtube broadcasts
and um it's been wonderful to feel part of this extended
wide global community of people interested in this practice and practicing meditating together and
it's been a real uh it's been a delight for me to have this opportunity this
privilege to be able to teach this way and to have an audience so thank you for all of this
and it's been a while since we had a community community meeting
and um the um
and uh i thought maybe on friday we could do that i think that i didn't actually check but i think friday i'm
free for this purpose and um
yeah friday friday should work so friday i thought maybe would i'll post a zoom
link and we can those of you would like we can meet and maybe partly a celebration for two years
and also just check in with each other it's been a while
the fundraising drive we're doing for the ukraine
uh for the refugees there uh has now as of uh yesterday was raised 62
thousand dollars it's a lot of money and uh thank you for those of you contributed and partly because of our
treasure who processes this won't be able to be to do it until sunday is away
we decided to just keep the donation page open we said it would be until monday of this cost monday
but we'll keep it up open through sunday when he returns and and then we'll tally up the amount and send it to save the
children so so thank you for this and i hope that our small contribution will
make a difference in the world
and so so
where the topic is now the third of the five hindrances
and in english it's often called sloth and torpor and i suspect that a good percentage of you
don't use those words it's not in your kind of active vocabulary especially the word sloth
maybe it is maybe especially if you've been around this insight scene for a while and maybe you've picked it up
and it's not it's not so clear this is the best words for what the pali is
the the original buddhist idea where sloth and torpor came as
translations i don't as translations of these terms i don't know but it's been around for a long time so
it might have been the 18th century english translators who
chose a word that maybe had particular meaning for them
the word for um
sloth the pali word literally means rigid
or stiff and in a mind that becomes stiff or rigid or
not soft and pliable and the word for torpor
that maybe works but i like the word sluggish it's the tradition says that the second
one has more to do with physical the body and the first one more with the mind so the mind becomes rigid the mind
becomes um stiff or the or there's a sluggishness in the
body but you know where exactly where this stiffness and sluggishness is whether
it's mind or body or both um it doesn't really matter in practice we're just paying attention to how it is
and this is a movement of the mind when the energy level energy is not
alive and engaged in a nice healthy flowing way and so it's often considered associated
with a sinking mind a sinking of energy sinking of vitality
in the mind the next hindrance to forth uh is the act the arousal over arouse arousing of
the mind so what we're noticing here is the energy level the activity the engagement
level of the mind and that can be either it can sink or it can be over aroused
and there's many reasons for that in life in following
desire and aversion the first two hindrances uh if we're able success successfully to
kind of not be caught in the grip of greeds and and hatred and ill will
then some people's minds don't have the usual entertainment don't have the usual
fire that kept it going sometimes people are exhausted
from too much wanting too much anxiety too much um
aversion they're angry all the time and when we finally stop the greed or
the fear or the anxiety or the or the anger
sometimes we crash sometimes the energy level drops down and and some of it has to do with just kind of finally getting
to rest but some of it has to do with the confusion a little bit
maybe depression a little bit and not knowing where where to put the mind what to do and a little bit lost
and there's no good cause to be engaged in and want to have or want to make go away
and the person's never discovered maybe the natural vitality of awareness of
attention because the vitality of attention was always being fueled by greed and
aversion or sometimes by fear and so there's a huge adjustment
that can happen when those those caffeines of the soul i call them are not operating and we go through
withdrawals a little bit sometimes a sinking mind the mind gets rigid or or closed tight
or gets we get sluggish in some way or other is a response or a reaction
to our circumstances we might feel overwhelmed we might have too much stimuli
too much emotional difficulties and it's just so hard for our heart our mind to
manage and i know we believe we can't manage we have ideas that should be different and
we feel discouraged and we feel maybe that a lot of self-pity or a lot of self
doubt because i should have done better i made a mistake or something and um and so all these different
attitudes come into play around the difficulty of our lives and sometimes our lives are extremely
difficult they don't want to dismiss diminish or pretend it's not difficult
but one of the ways the mind responds to that is to get rigid is to get to numb
is to get closed down another way that we
we can get sluggish as a sometimes sluggish is resistance to what we don't
to do what we don't want to do sometimes it's just a sense of being deeply deeply worried and tired
and so like we kind of give up a little bit and um and so uh
this is part this this is part of the you know one of the ways in which the mind responds to difficulties and
challenges and it can be dramatic and very big it can
be very subtle as meditation gets clearer and more and more clear as meditation practice gets
stronger we can get sensitive to the more subtle shifts in this direction of
of um uh stiffness or rigidity of mind and
sluggishness and um and it can be very subtle it can be like
you know just just a little feeling that it's just too much to stay with a full
in-breath you know just like you know i've i did that before and and so there's the mind kind of doesn't
want to do it anymore there's a kind of a little bit resistance and so something shuts down
or it starts feeling that meditations become a duty we've done it for a long time it's just in the sense of duty and
one more time i have to do it and something inside gets rigid or tight or closed
or we've had meditations and they've been you know three days of difficult meditations and something inside feels so
discouraged that the energy level drops or tops away and there's a sluggishness and unwillingness of the mind to operate
and so uh this is all we could the hindrances can all be considered normal human
uh mental activities we're born with hindrances they come with human life
and it's not a personal failing to have them but it is a personal field of
mindfulness it's a personal place to discover and what's happening with us get become wise
about what's happening with us and so one of the tasks of mindfulness
is to start becoming sensitive to the movements of energy and for this
third hindrance how energy sinks the sinking mind or
energy gets frozen or tight or the mind gets rigid the heart gets rigid
and and then become wise with it practice with it wisely and one of the ways to be wise about it
is to make this 180 degree turn to really feel and sense this
more really kind of care for oneself by feeling well what this is rather than being
discouraged by our discouragement rather than being overwhelmed by our overwhelm or how we're shutting down and how we're
not practicing just right or something care for ourselves by turning attention just oh this is how it is now and feel
it and be with it and it's invaluable to feel and be with an experience
and partly because that's one of what one of the things we're trying to develop in this
practice is the ability to have clarity of seeing clear knowing clear feeling of
what actually is so we're developing it with the things that are difficult
we might also discover that some of the attitudes underlying this third hindrance
attitudes of shoulds or it's too much or it's been too long or it's been
uh you know i can't manage um i'm supposed to be better so there's
all these attitudes that kind of can uh can drain be draining for us to live by
and so we see those attitudes and to see them as attitudes this can be quite powerful
when the time comes when the meditation is a very clear and peaceful and settled
then it might be very subtle the movements of the third hindrance
but we can see it arise see it be born and because we're familiar with it from
all that kind of practicing with it for a long time then we see it just come arise the first
inklings of it the hints of it and then it might be possible to let go of it to abandon it
and this is really a good thing to do when the abandoning of it feels like uh it moves us to greater
health great moves us to a greater clarity and a good way of being and so
in this practice of the hindrances we want to be able to see clearly
and then if it's easy enough to let go and then appreciate the absence
and the helpfulness of the absence of this rigid mind or the sluggishness that
might arise so
the hindrances and so tomorrow we'll do
um we'll do
restlessness they will over energize the hindrance
and so forth we'll do doubt on friday and then doubt today afterwards we'll do a community meeting on zoom and
i look forward to meeting those of you who come to that
so thank you all very much