so hello everyone and welcome
i have there's a tendency for me when i approach my meditation
meditation time and sitting down to become quiet in my mind
so it's a little strange sit down to meditate every morning with you this way and start with words
and um this idea of quiet it's like there are
times like in this uh vacation i had last week where
we're in the mountains hiking and and there'd be these places we'd come to
the beautiful mountain lakes and groves of trees
and it seemed that the way to approach it was to be quiet not to talk so much
and also to kind of have silence in the mind a receptivity
as if the place that we're in is to be respected and
attended to and heard and seen and listened to on its own terms
not on what i think what i think should be happening or what
i think i want or what my thoughts are spinning stories about
and perhaps there are some times in you know ordinary life where that
happens that maybe we go
to a temple or a church and entering into it there's a kind of
irreverence and a silence like okay this is a place to open attention up and and
take in the ambiance take in the presence that they're quiet and not come barreling ahead with all
our thoughts and concerns going to a funeral can be like this
going to a a preschool class when all the children are napping
it's so peaceful and quiet and it's the time to become quiet oneself
and so meditation is a time like this where we're trying to
where the receptivity the availa that there's a presence not a presence
but there's a something we're attending to that
we're quieting the mind we're not living in the world of our thoughts and thinking and
what we how we're interpreting and things the stories we make about things the meaning
we have about what's happening and the expectations of what should be happening or what shouldn't be happening and
the mind can be spinning and sometimes it spins fast
there's fast food and now slow food there's fast thinking and there's slow
thinking and quiet thinking there's thinking that is more receptive
to the moment to be present and not asserting itself and its desires and
wants and wishes and fears on top of the moment
so we come to meditation and certainly to recognize how is it for us
are we bringing a truckload of thoughts ideas stories
memories plans concerns to churn and to think about
and if so then that's what should be listened to and attended to
in a quiet way as if something needs to be heard and
you're the hearer you're the one who will listen
and sometimes it's clear that coming into meditation we're allowing ourselves
to the thinking mind to take a backstage it's not that important what we think
what's important is what we're feeling or what's happening or the presence the attentiveness to the situation
allowing the situation to speak to us rather than us
being the speaker and the talker and so to sit in meditation with a
quietude a receptivity a listening
to whatever is there so to
assume a meditation posture a posture in which to be receptive
a posture in which to listen better
a posture which doesn't doesn't yes
which uses the body
to attend to be here with our experience
it means being many people sitting a little bit more upright or a little bit more intentional
and then gently sending uh gently closing your eyes
and noticing
how this moment is for you as if your body your heart your mind is
the temple that you step into maybe something become quieter
as you listen sense feel
what is here
and within with what's here gently gently and maybe slowly
taking a few long breaths
as if with each breath
you're gently touching your full experience
gently feeling attending
and as you exhale relax soften this body
letting your breathing return to normal
and as we you continue meditating today and you notice that you might be
thinking and lost in thought involved in thought
remind yourself there's a different way of being it does not depend on thinking
letting your thoughts get quiet softer
the thinking recede to the background so you're not living in your thoughts
so you're not seeing everything through the lens
of thinking and stories and meaning
let your experience of the moment
be known quietly without thinking
a reverence a respect for everything
which calls on invites a quieting of the mind
as you enter into a sacred place
of your direct immediate experience breathing here
so
okay
for this meditation don't center yourself on your thinking
let the thinking recede so you could center yourself on your
direct experience as if your thinking mind gets quiet
so you can feel better or hear better
there can be a receptivity
to the specialness of the moment
so as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps it's possible to feel recognize the difference
between being with other people and asserting
our desires our needs our agendas
versus being present with others and
listening receiving the other being available for the other to be
to barrel ahead with your own wishes and needs and desires
or to relax and open up and to get to know the other person
to feel to sense to really know who you're with
and love in the family of love compassion
care good will kindness
arises most easily in the second mode it doesn't have much space
when we are asserting ourselves and asserting our needs and our wants and
our agendas but love has much more time and space
and availability when we take the time to be quiet and
reset receptive to know the person we're with
so perhaps you can imagine
meeting someone today stranger or someone you know
from the peacefulness or receptivity or calmness of meditation
or the way whatever way in meditation self-assertion has taken a backs
a back back step in the background
and you can just be with someone without a need or a want or an assertion of self
and from this place to let there be kindness good will
well well-wishing may others
be happy may others
be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and may you tap into your kindness and love
with which to meet others
may we meet in friendliness and kindness today
as we learn not to fill the space with our stories our genders
our needs our wants so there's more space to know and to
feel and to love
me
so
[Music]
so hello and welcome to this second talk on
grief a
topic and a state of being that can be very difficult
and also can be very deeply connected to our love
and the depths of who we are and what we think is important in this life
so it's a very important topic to be able to learn how to be present for and recognize and then get under the surface
of to see more clearly and grief is not an enemy or grief is
not a illness or a problem grief is a part and parcel of a human
life and becoming wise about it and knowing how to
be with grief is one of the great benefits of mindfulness
practice so i'm defining grief as the
pain is see
the pain arising in the emptiness born from loss
the pain that arises in the emptiness born from loss
and this definition i'm hoping will span all the different ways in which
griefs are experienced because there's an infinite number of ways that
grief is sometimes it's more emotional sometimes it's more physical sometimes it's more
relational in nature and there's all kinds of very different cultures grieve in different
ways different ways different different cultures experience the pain not lost in different ways
but because it involves a loss that loss means there's now an emptiness an absence of something
and that absence that emptiness can be huge and some people feel it's so huge that
it you know nothing will ever fill it again and we'll always be in this great vacuum or great
place of meaningless or loneliness or loss
but the bigger that emptiness is the bigger that
absence is it actually the more it gets filled and it gets filled with many many things
and part of mindfulness practice is to begin to enter into this world of this emptiness
to be able to see clearly what is it that fills the emptiness that we're in
what is it that characterizes this pain this discomfort that comes with loss
and and so rather than taking it as being a singular thing
my grief now we can put a little question mark after it what is this
maybe we don't really know the grief so what is this grief
and to sit with it to be with it not so much to investigate and think about it
but rather to enter into grief as if it's a temple or sacred
spot or place where we enter into quietly peacefully non-assertively
without our needs without our demands and our wants but to really be
present in the middle of this emptiness to make space and room for what's there
and then to see all the different elements of it and one of the key things to think about
or that i think i find helpful is to not give a lot of
preferential treatment to the world of thinking to thoughts and stories and memories and
meanings that we assign to the situation but rather to be entering into this
emptiness and start seeing there is stories there are meanings there are
thoughts ideas associations there those are there a part of the big picture including the emotions and the feelings
and to begin seeing making space for all the component parts grief is a composite
of many different pieces and parts some of them come are very personal
some of them are cultural some of them are come from our life experience
some of them come from our hopes and aspirations that we have that have been
maybe been the rug has been pulled away from them and so to begin to see the different be
pre enter into this carefully and make space and quietude to really
recognize oh this is what's happening make space for it and to
become quiet the thinking mind can become quiet in the relationship to grief
and this is not easy but it's probably one of the most respectful things to do
to really make room for the natural or inner process that
our body has for being with grief and allowing grief its space and its time
so to be able to kind of begin understanding the component parts of grief
i want to talk a little bit about what these might be and one of them is to appreciate
the kind of grief it is or the source of the grief
so some grief is very relational in nature it has to do with the relationship that
has been severed and lost like there's been a death death of a parent or a child or a spouse
a sibling or a friend and that relationship was so important
and so there's a lot of a lot about that relationship that comes into play with the grief
there might be a divorce and a lot about that relationship comes into play with the grief
and uh and that relationship is what is the emptiness is the loss of the of um
the you know the laws that has created the absence and so to understand that the quality of
the relatedness that's no longer there or is lost or is it been
other kinds of grief are more functional that isn't so much a relationship with
another person but we're losing our abilities so there's a grief about aging when we
get older some of many of our abilities become less and less and there's a grief from an accident that
some abilities we have functions we have no longer work and we've lost uh
maybe been paralyzed by something and and we'll never be able to do things we
did before because our body doesn't function the same way and
so the loss of functioning of abilities that we've had
there's uh the loss of roles that sometimes people retire they've lost
their role that it was so important for who they were children leave home and the role of
being a parent is no longer there and it's that's the grief is not being able to care or take care of someone or have
breakfast ready for someone you know that and um there's a
someone dies and part of the grief is not the loss of the relationship or is it a loss of the relationship but
another part of it is um now we can't have that role of the caregiver or the lover or
or the friend of someone which was so valuable for us such an important part of our our identity who
we were and then there's more clearly the identity itself
that um being some person is you can't be that person anymore
when this kind of loss has gone away and not the way that you experienced it before the loss of identity loss of
who you thought you were and who you thought you were going to become
that you know spouse dies and you expected that you'd be in retirement together or traveling around the world
or playing bridge or something something with yours but now this spouse is gone and
the anticipated futures are not no longer there
some people are grieving lost futures lost anticipated ideas of what was going
to come but also lost identities of who we were going to be
we lost we lose material goods we might lose all our money in a stock market crash
and our identity as someone who is financially stable or secure or even
wealthy is gone or our identity as someone who can do certain things that requires money goes
away and and so it's a loss of grieving the identity grieving loss
and then there's a loss of material goods uh all kinds of you know losting of
wealth like i said money but losing um valuable piece of property that we have
or losing our financial security or losing our home
that we've had for many times of divorce and we lose something that was so important for us
so these are all different kinds of losses that come into play when people can experience grief around these things
and some of these griefs are very personal in nature and some of them are more social and interpersonal in nature
there's a personal and interpersonal quality to it some of them so for example the personal
is an individualistic culture like maybe the united states
many people are not living in a rich dynamic social
sphere of family or clan or tribe or different things and so there's a loss maybe a couple has
been living together alone and they're old and and maybe
you know there's no one who's taking care of them particularly and so one person dies
and it isn't that now they're part of a rich network of family and a clan
tribe and so the grief is very individualistic very alone and so grief can be very lonely
other popular people who might be living in a extended family in a compound or a town
or village or a tribe and um the elder of the tribe dies
the grief is very social it's collective it's something that everyone shares and the social dynamic of the village has
changed with this death and and people that the whole so social
world begin shifting and changing and so grief takes a very different form
than when it's not it's not so lonely it's uh it's collective when it's collective it's more cultural
and there's cultural aspects that come into play with how we grieve
and so um there's so grief is a composite it's
made up of many different things grief is not a singular thing though each powerful grief that we experience
might seem like this is the end of the world this is it that you know this is the thing you know that is so huge and how could anything
ever be the same again
but to enter into the world of our grief maybe in meditation
and let the mind become quiet this is one of the gifts
or the approaches of the meditation world life and that is to enter into what's
difficult be present for it but don't let thinking get the upper hand
but to feel and sense and begin allowing the pieces of it to show itself and to
be recognized and be known some very different things can happen
in with grief when we're not churning and thinking and spinning
and living in the thoughts and the ideas and the histories and the memories and the and the ideas
but they become quiet quieting the stories
the stories are important but there's another way
so in these few words i have in this 15 minutes i hope that this has
given you something to consider that
in the emptiness of grief we fill it with many many things and to sit quietly in the middle of it
so all the different component parts can be recognized and that which is extra
those pieces of the component parts of grief which are not needed can quiet and
settle and some of that has to do with the stories we tell ourselves and the
meanings we assign to grief and that'll be the topic for tomorrow
so um thank you and
care for yourself well and think of mindfulness of however you are
as mindfulness as a powerful way of protecting yourself caring for
yourself loving yourself by not asserting your desires and needs on top of
yourself but rather to listen deeply to respect here
so thank you