incredible hello and good morning good day
and to um
say a few introductory words for the meditation
there's a fascinating the use of attention awareness
in meditation especially and I say meditation by the time when we
can kind of give ourselves over to the exercise the experiment the discovery
process of what we can what happens when we're really aware and that is to be aware of some
psychological thing Within thinking some emotion
and um and hold it gently carefully fully
in the Gaze of awareness and if you do that
what you what you're doing is um if it's really ju only aware of it
uh what we're doing in that and being aware of it we're in itself awareness
does not interfere or doesn't judge or doesn't react React to what we're aware
of and so if we're fully invested and
caught up in something being aware is a process of beginning to step away from it to know it to see it without being
caught in it without fueling it without adding to it participating in it but
just knowing it as we know it more and more that way we start seeings
eventually we might see how we're participating how we're fueling it how we're repeating the same thought pattern
ideas Desires in order to keep certain things going and um and so we keep kind of opening or
developing that awareness to non-reactive non-judgmental just to see it we see what we contribute
and or we stop feeding it we stop you know this
kind of re-newing it all the time and then we see it begin to fade
baby fade and and fade away it becomes less intense it weakens
more often than not it's hard to see sometimes if they are participation in it our reactivity to it
is subconscious it's deeply embodied and habit made or something
so we have to be careful with making too many conclusions around this but uh but
this idea of just gazing upon something long enough
to watch it begin to fade to weaken this is a fascinating process
and and a lot of things will fade quicker than we realize surprisingly
fast there's some studies about how quickly an emotion will last by itself and it's
you know at a minute or 90 seconds or something that's how long emotions last unless
there's something in our psychophysical system that's renewing it feeding it building it up
so to be with a breathing also the
breathing if the if the breathing is a neutral place where we're not controlling
reacting to this is another way in which we are shifting the direction of our
the mental fuel mental renewal process so that we're renewing and fueling
attention to breathing not to our thinking not to our reactivity not to certain emotions
reactive emotions so
um taking a meditation posture assuming a posture entering into a
posture and
and slowing down
slowing down and maybe twisting and swaying your body in a slow
way to kind of begin process of mindfulness of the body
aware from the body's point of view how we can find a balanced aligned
posture
maybe twisting a little bit from side to side the upper torso around the
shoulders is a way of maybe helping the shoulders kind of
come alive and maybe settle a little bit
lowering the Gaze
gently closing your eyes
taking a moment to Simply know how you are in the most obvious way
no it didn't the most non-reactive way that you know how
just know how you are in some simple General way
where what's important is not what you not how you are
but the way you know it
and then on the exhale relaxing your body
a kind of relaxation is not forced or expecting much
almost allowing the body space and room
to release itself
shoulders
the belly
and then connecting more fully to your breathing taking three breaths
just three breaths three breath Journey of settling in being here just with your
breathing three times
and then once you've done three four three breaths ordinary simple breaths
that you attend to carefully
you're very quite aware of the count the breath the really connected it
then do it again and again
give yourself over to three breaths at a time
a relatively small goal to stay present for three breaths
and then to renew that practice
remembering to do the three breaths just fully present for three breaths
the inhales the exhales the transition between
inhaling exhaling exhaling inhaling
coming back to doing three full breaths remembering
to stay with three breaths again and again
thank you
all right
foreign
if you're able to stay with the repetition of three breaths at a time
great and if you can't
what is it that's pulling you away
not the content of your thoughts but is it thinking is it feeling
emotions recognize clearly
what it is that grabs your attention so you forget
to be with your breathing
and now let go of breathing focusing on breathing
bring your attention to the process of thinking
or to some
emotion that is difficult or
engage upon it carefully non-reactively just watch and see
step back let it be what it is but live in The Knowing of it
not in it
you might even use the name the note thinking
feeling
allow whatever is there to be there but don't participate in it
just step back and gaze upon it non-reactively
and if there is desires or aversion wanting or not wanting
gaze upon that with non-reactive awareness
recognizing it as wanting not wanting and see what happens under that gaze
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
there is a way to gaze upon the world non-reactively
that is at the same time kindly
kindness friendliness love
is not necessarily A reactive way of being but rather is the
closer to just flows from the Open Heart
and to gaze upon the world with kind eyes
without wanting anything or not wanting just kind eyes
a kind of kindness that carries with it
the the wish and the Delights and the appreciation of others
wishing them well
May from these eyes of mine
May there flow well-wishing
wishing for the welfare and happiness of others
May flowing for me May there come
the wishes carried in these words
May others be happy
May others be safe
May others be peaceful
May others be free
and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
thank you
foreign foreign
so this is the third talk on the Insight pen pad
which is um the five qualities of practice five
aspects of how we change and grow that has a flow to it there's a kind of
evolution there's a kind of a natural growth from one to the other of course it doesn't always work in this
linear way but uh another way of understanding this is that there's a five qualities that
work together they support each other and guide each other and feed into each other
and sometimes maybe it goes in reverse order and but the classic way is this order which
I'm presenting them to you so it begins with having insight
described as seeing things as they are and then from that comes disenchantment
breaking the spell of our desires and our projections onto things that
are not so helpful and then today we'll talk about
something called fading away sometimes translated as dispassion and
I'll talk about the two choices and then there's Liberation and then there's this interesting we'll talk on
Friday the knowledge of Liberation the and um but today the topic is uh B Raga
fading away and um and this is uh as we uh see things as
they are as we really well let me back up a little bit further uh this Insight
pentad Builds on the gladness pentatonin and one of the great Treasures maybe the
phenomenal forms of wealth that we can have is uh inner well-being some sense of
inner contentment Happiness gladness joy some kind of feeling of well-being
Within it's not easy to come to necessarily but I think it's fair to say that most
people live a life without availing themselves of what is available
that if we slow down or take the time to really allow the inner life to settle and open
chances are there's more well-being there than most people allow for
but it's a treasure we want to stay close to and and build and know how to
support and and protect because what this does when we sit down
to meditate with this inner sense of well-being then we have a reference point
for what takes us away from that and what keeps Us close to it
and so when we then are settled enough then to begin seeing things as they are
um we can see that the ways that we are caught in them Enchanted in them
preoccupied with them is takes us away from that well-being diminishes it
and um and so of course it doesn't feel good to do it and that seeing that
distinction that this one feels like it's I feel more contracted I feel more
tight I feel more caught up in my my
despair depression upset resentments whatever that doesn't really feel good it takes it's a it's a diminishment of
some modicum of well-being that's just being here can feel like
then it begins to be easier to question the value of the projections the
interpretations the ideas the desires that keeps us hooked and fixated and
caught up in something and so there starts to be a process of disenchantment
these things are changing constantly moving constantly impermanent arising and passing these things are you know
they're suffering that them caught in there's it's cause causing more pain to be caught up in things
and there's something about being these things that I'm caught in that are not useful to Define Myself by
to measure Myself by and so a process of disenchantment as I
talked about yesterday as we get disenchanted in the projections we have
then the the strength of the projection the strength of the desires
the wanting and not wanting that's behind those projections that enchantment
um is begins to diminish and it begins to fade away and this fading away is supported by
non-reactive awareness as we become non-reactively aware of
what's Happening Here and Now that's a for many people it's a very
different way of being than business as usual business as usual as you go about our life is to have a reaction and to be
living in the reaction and living in response to the reaction participating in a little bit
or a lot or a lot in a way that feeds it and keeps it going and keeps the fire going but we can keep putting
logs into the fire it keeps burning and so our anger will not persist as
long as it does unless we are putting more fuel in it maybe repeating the
story and to ourselves over and over again and um and so the non-reactive awareness is
doing something very different it's uh ceasing putting logs on the fire it's leaving
things alone and we can watch the fire whatever it might be but a watched fire
which we don't put logs back onto it uh you know in a little log little uh
fireplace fire or something a campfire will fade away by its would just die out
and you can if you have enough time one evening watching a campfire not being
fed you can watch the whole process kind of until it fades away and and the
Flames disappear the hot coals cool down and so they can do the same thing within
that as we become we see things as they are as we become disenchanted with them
disenchanted with their promise and then how they're going they're going to bring us happiness which is a future happiness
that's unreliable compared to the inner happiness we know for develop through
meditation then the interest in those Fades away the the desires and the aversions that
go into those projections begin to fade away and um and that fading away is stronger
in the non-reactive awareness that doesn't put fuel in the fire and it's fascinating to watch that
process of fading away and some things will fade away quite quickly under the Gaze of non-reactive
awareness so I'm thinking you know people sometimes struggle with thoughts and let
go the thoughts come back to the breath let go of their thoughts go back okay keep getting caught up until they are
told just let yourself think but bring careful gaze look carefully on
the fact that you're thinking really see it and some people are so surprised by this new exercise because their thinking
stops some something under the Gaze of attention thinking doesn't have the fuel
that it needs which is often done uh kind of out of sight
but to re to have the main fuel be seeing which is no fuel at all for some
of these fires things fade away sometimes his fading away is very slow
maybe days weeks months maybe years for some things that are quite powerful habits Within
and some things can fade remarkably fast at the the speed by which things fade
has a lot to do with how much concentration we have together with the
non-reactive awareness it's almost as if the more more concentrated we are to
some degree um the more open space we have for things to kind of unwind and and
dissipate under that gaze of non-reactive awareness
and so part of this process of insight inside practice
is to allow recognize and allow for the disenchantment
they they're no longer enchanted with the things we used to kind of want and
think was all about what we had to fix or get and to allow for this fading away this
fading away is very important whether it's fading away or the tensions in our bodies
and some of the tensions we can relax but someone takes a long time it's just a it's a remarkable what a deep Body
Work Can Happen by regular meditation and sitting in a good posture and things
begin to relax and relax in a deeper and deeper way and um
and then uh things reactive emotions fade away reactive thinking Fades away
and I use the word reactive because some emotional states moods that we have are
not reactive and and those don't necessarily fade away the same way they
sometimes actually get bigger and stronger because there's more room for them to flow into they don't come from
reactivity they don't they're not states that are being fed by the fuels by the by the logs and the fire
um it's more like um rather than the light of the fires lights up the darkness uh there's some
emotional states Like Loving kindness and that is more like um the dawn where
the sun rises and it fills everything and um and it'll be there for the day it's
not going to fade away quickly so um
so this enchantment what are so what are you disenchanted
with what projections what investment of belief and value have you put in things
consciously or unconsciously a lot of this is uh you know happened subconsciously
um that we think somehow it's so important what do you invest yourself in that
doesn't really serve you that takes you away from this place of well-being
trust the inner well-being and then allow for the fading away
and so the homework if you'd like for this next day is to spend some time some high quality
minutes during the day through the day maybe having tea maybe looking out the window maybe going for a very nice
stroll maybe meditating a second time or a third time today
and and see if you can uh in the forgiving room and space a little bit to
you know some minutes of a Sabbath some minutes of sacred pauses and see if you do that what fades away
if you give time that allows for fading away what fades away from you if you're
relaxed and taking a break from the usual being caught upness and engagement
take breaks through the day and observe what's happening in you
to see if you can see what fades away and how is that good what's the goodness
what's the value what's the benefit you get you get from this fading away
so thank you for going along here in this Insight journey and we'll continue tomorrow
thank you