hi welcome nice to see you here tonight
and uh hello out there on youtube
thank you for being here as well
so this last week i've been um
thinking more about and noticing continuing to notice this
this idea of receiving moments of gladness or joy
faith as they come up and um
you know it's interesting i was also noticing kind of where i don't
connect where i don't allow myself to take in the goodness
and even you know this we really do have to stay present
to receive to receive the gladness and the joy that come up in
our lives even the simple ways
yeah i am so helpful to you know
really truly try and notice these moments and take them in it's very easy to skip over
the little the little gifts of the day
this week one of the things that i um
noticed was you know there can be things that happen in life
can you turn the volume down just a little bit um
that are kind of in that space of like this could be
seen as good by the mind or it could be seen as difficult or not good by the
mind depending on how the mind engages with
it so for example my
i had said something to my daughter that
was i was trying i was being joking in the moment but it really hurt her feelings and so she told me
didn't come out exactly directly that way but she told me that you know what i had said had hurt her feelings
and there was a lot of gladness that she could tell me right that we could talk
about what what happened and i could apologize and
and there was this appreciation so my daughter is 25 so the
mature maturation of our relationship our ability to um
to talk things through right and and not just have a lot of reactivity which we used to have a lot
more reactivity with each other
and uh you know we got to a really good place it was good it was a really good thing
and i noticed that the you know i went to bed happy and the
next day i got up and i felt happy but then i noticed
uh starting to like well i wonder i wonder if you know she's still okay she
feels okay this morning when she wakes up if she feels good about the talk
so i sent her a text just to check in and i didn't hear back
and so you know i'm sort of a little later halfway through the day i'm like oh i didn't hear back and i'm like
what does that mean right so i sent another little text and i still didn't hear back and
so during the day i could feel myself um kind of having a hard time staying
with the fact that we had this really good conversation that the there was this energy of worry
or just you know yeah worry that maybe there was more
more conflict to be managed i could be
really clear in my mind that i was really glad that we had the
conversation it was really healthy i knew these things and i could feel the energy pulling kind of
i'll call it right here the sense of anxiety or tension in the core of my
body and
i was thinking about sort of um are you guys familiar with the hindrances
the five hindrances jim you know you know them they're good friends of yours
there's these five hindrances that um are discussed by the buddha as being pretty
significant interferences in our meditation and i'll say in our daily lives and our
lives in general and so i was like really like naming okay the hindrance of
restlessness and worry right this is one of the five restlessness and worry just
kind of keeps keeps coming in and while i have this clarity
like a mental clarity of this is a good thing there's this other energy that's kind of
keeps stirring things up and so you know as the day went on i was like
okay it's like just pull over
the metaphor of a driving or a car you know the mind when it gets going it feels like you're
driving and when you're restless and worried it almost feels like um
you keep trying to find your way somewhere and getting lost right you're just like
this relentless searching feeling and so it's like the opposite of that was just pull over and
stop and breathe in to the gratitude for the
the contact the event the sharing that happened between my daughter and myself
and uh keeping myself there right so last week i was talking about
savoring right that the brain needs our help to savor or take in the
good stuff especially when we've got a hindrance going on in our minds we need to help it
settle and to help it take in and recognize and attend
it's like a fork right we can keep a fork in a road we can get caught and pulled off right into the
mental kind of hindrances or worries or we can
nope just stay stay here just take in what's going on
here so this week i found gratitude was a
really helpful way to help myself work to
take an entrance to gladness right to a sense of gladness and that
gladness supported a light lightning of the heart right a lightning of the being
so um we we pretty much all know right that
our minds are different things are happening it's not always just peaceful and common here
and uh sayadaw uttajania do you guys know who he is
he's a a monk burmese monk and he um he has a lot of very pithy
little direct sayings that have to do with mindfulness and daily life and
one of the things his quotes is it's inevitable to make some wrong turns in daily life
but you have to learn to profit from these experiences learn to profit from them these wrong turns don't allow
um just the difficulties to keep running the show but but learn from them
so these uh hindrances and i'll list them in a moment
it's good to get to know them it's good to recognize when when they're present
one of the yeah one of the simplest things to do is
kind of to do what the in the suit is some of the pursuit does it when the buddha is um
facing some challenge some difficulty um
he will reference mara mar as the representation embodiment like of
the temptress all the the ill ill will and the desire and the aversion and
and that you know he'll say mara i see you
when those qualities are coming up in the moment sort of this turning toward you know i
see you i see you that you're you know restlessness and worry i see you i see you i see you here it's a
really important way to help us start to to benefit to learn from these visitors
so what are these five let me just list them for you
typically they're listed in the following order one is sensual desire so a lot of desire for
pleasantness for objects for you know feeling good
the second one is ill will so anger hatred
wanting to strike out the third one is
restlessness no sloth and torpor actually there's a yeah sloth and torpor so a sense of
tiredness fatigue that can be both mind or body or
mind and body or or one or the other and then there's restlessness and worry
which i was sort of alluding to and the last one is um doubt
and this is like a um a doubt in the practice or down ourselves right that's kind of a
not not a very helpful doubt
so
shiloh catherine says that just as an oyster transforms the
irritating presence of a grain of sand into a pearl meditators convert irritants into wisdom
so this goes back to that statement by dao tejania you know like let's take
advantage of it when these things come up in our lives learn from them you know let them become
the pearl the wisdom that guides us
they're um these hindrances are you know energetic
they affect our body like uh just think about the experience of of
having a strong desire for something what does that feel like in your body
there's like generally just even just thinking about maybe even imagining something you know you really
really want and as i'm even just imagining it you see my
body is leaning forward right do you notice that that tends to be what happens
energetically with our bodies is we we lean toward it and there's a feeling of a pull
now contrast that to ill will when you really don't like someone when
you have aversion just kind of bring that to mind something
some event some person some food just as you imagine that what how what
do you notice in your body how's that energy feel different
you want to lean toward it probably not right there's more of a sitting back or
a pull back in general so i'm pointing to this because um this
is partly how we start to recognize that the forces are present of the hindrances
is we can start to see it in our the the body will start to give us clues
in terms of sloth and torpor well
when we feel really tired there's a sinking right there's a sinking energy which can be felt literally in our
bodies like just a sleepiness heaviness but sometimes the torpor and the mind
can actually get really drifty and dreamy and quite pleasant
so it's also important to recognize because we can kind of be losing touch with the present
moment in meditation and not really recognizing it because it feels it can
feel somewhat pleasant so in that energetic state when we're
you know feeling slothful there's usually a heaviness a sinking feeling right
um with restlessness and worry
for me that uh there's this kind of habitual pattern that feels a little
like like this i'm doing you know like a settling okay okay and then a stirring
up and a settling and a stirring up there's a difficulty
settling period right with restlessness and worry and it can manifest you know very much in the
body and you can see it just in the mind just sort of the
circular thinking that we tend to get involved in when we're caught and then with doubt
what does that feel like when you have a lot of doubt what do you notice in your body when you're really
really questioning doubting if this is the right thing to be doing
for me what comes up is there's this a way in which it feels it's almost like there's a frozen
feeling in a way of the energy like a little set resonate for you
um any other words feel free to speak up you guys to describe what it feels like for you
when you you're feeling a lot of doubt uncertainty stuckness
comes to mind you have anything else you want to say what's that
back and forth okay okay yeah
like not the that speaks to that energy of do i want to do i not want to kind of like is
this right is this good is this bad kind of yeah and some freezing
yeah yeah yeah so it's it's said that these
hindrances weaken our wisdom they're like a sieve because they drain the mind
there's a lot of pretty strong language used to describe them um obstructing hindering blocking
enveloping i think it's um they're all it's really really
helpful to think about them in strong ways but it's also like they're this is
part of being human these are all experiences every human being has
and uh you know it's
better to i think to uh to get to know them to understand them
just sort of normalize them than to vilify them
in my view gil franzdal talks about
having a hindrance is like wandering through a maze staring at the ground
where you're never looking up right like that and he says in contrast being mindful is
like standing above the maze to get an overview right without eliminating a hindrance
mindfulness gives us a better perspective of what's happening so when we notice when we recognize oh look at
me i'm i'm experiencing restlessness and worry it is like having that above view of oh
look what i'm doing i can see it now right before you maybe are just feeling it and getting drawn
and driven by it but when we can start to have that
awareness recognition of its influence we have a opportunity to kind of get more free
so you know last week i was sort of emphasizing um
that you know when suffering happens in our lives
it is an opportunity to recognize it there's an opportunity to notice the pain
the difficulty of it and in doing so we can do that thing like we see the
maze and when when we see the maze we have freedom we have this opportunity
and that can be like it can help us see that that suffering that was happening
that was going on was actually an invitation you know to to freedom if we listen to
it if we listen to its call and we we recognize it
so um maybe i'll talk a little bit more about
the the five hindrances just uh there's some really cool similes
in the sutas um so with central pleasure
it's it's compared to the experience of being in debt
so having a huge financial burden versus um being free from it like the
difference between like i don't owe anybody anything like that feeling of freedom
and then there's other similes that are related to water and this one is
with with central pleasure it's related to a colored pool of water
so here's the suta from um that i'll read if there is water in a
pot mixed with red yellow blue or orange color a person with normal facility of sight
looking into it could not proper properly recognize and see the image of
their own face right the water is discolored might be pretty but
in the same way when one's mind is possessed by central desire
overpowered by it right it's really driving us one cannot properly see
you know see the escape see the clarity
it's not available and then when we we don't
kind of see and see the way out we don't understand right we don't
really understand what's happening it's like being in that maze and looking down at the ground
so i think i'll just kind of go through with the similes and then we can see where we want to go from there but um
with uh ill will it's compared to
illness or disease a sense of you know feeling really sick
right when we feel really angry and hostile there's a great sense of discomfort disease in
the body there's a often it's talked about as like wanting
to strike out or push push something away
and so with the simile of the water and if there's a pot of water heated on
the fire [Music] the water is seething and boiling
and a person with a normal faculty of sight looking into it cannot properly recognize or see the
image of their own face their own mind they can't really see what's going on in there
so when we're possessed by ill will
and we don't recognize it's there we don't know our way through the maze right we don't know our way out
with sloth and torpor
it's equated with imprisonment or being
locked in a cage that feeling of not being able to move
and the simile for it is uh if there's a pot of water covered with
moss and water plants this is you know it's it's full of that
sludge so we really don't even see hardly the any reflection at all not even a
distorted reflection
with restlessness and worry
i like to think about it as being very very caught like in a tide pool
and with the simile it describes if there's a water and a
pot stirred by the wind agitated swaying or producing waves
that that's the way it distorts the surface of the water and makes it
impossible again to see clearly to sleep into our own minds
and for skeptical doubt it's equated with the dangers of a
desert journey no water no no relief from the heat of the sun no
no safe space to rest we just can't maybe that goes back to what you were
saying like we just there's no settling right and then with the water simile
it's described as water that's turbid stirred up and muddy
um in a dark place [Music] right
do you connect with those those images do they resonate for you
yeah yeah
can you imagine which of these hindrances are the most
often visitors in your lives
what would you say if you feel comfortable saying which ones are the most common for you
sensual desire yeah yeah
doubt yeah yeah
what's that i still didn't it will and it will and you say that so
yeah like almost like embarrassed right yeah they're so it's just this is uh
[Music] so much just a part of our psychological makeup and our evolution really if i if
i step back from all of these forces i think well of course we need to have sensual desire right that's sort of what
propagates humanity and you know and at this point we're living
in such a capitalistic society right so much about sort of
you know so much greed in our society right so that's just wow really fed and then the
hostility and ill will right well we do need to uh or we used to need
to maybe we we shouldn't need to now to to have that sort of hostility with
other beings um but if you know at some point uh if you just
watch animals right it's just it's an instinct you know it's an instinct
um and uh sloth and torpor right you know it's
sort of a natural response in some ways to if we're feeling um overwhelmed or bored or
disengaged it's a natural thing we're not connecting with our lives
we're not connecting with our experience often a lot of times when people talk about being bored i feel like
they're leaving themselves in a way they're leaving their experience they're not interested in it
and with um
doubt again you know it's important actually it's important to have doubt
right if we didn't have doubt we might just believe a commercial and do whatever
you know we're told to do right the beautiful thing about
working with doubt in the practice and the buddhist teachings was
so you know just this encouragement to to listen to what works
to trust your experience not so much your ideas about what's
supposed to be happening but just to trust your experience to really and then we need to commit ourselves to
it too right if we've got too much doubt it's hard to commit to a practice it's hard to commit to sitting
right but but if we can really help ourselves commit to the practice
then we can stop afterwards and reflect on our actual experience and trust it
it's also without really helpful to talk to a teacher or read
read the teachings or you know seek wisdom to
help you that can be very helpful
so do you have any kind of any direction
you'd like me to go with this talk do you want me to go back to this idea of you know joy and
gladness or would you like to hear more about any one of the hindrances or tips
for working on them in daily life what would be helpful and people in youtube feel free to write
in the chat if there's anything for you as well
great let me just uh think about that yeah take your time
when do you when do you see these five hindrances as something as maybe like these are
indications that i need to work on in my life and maybe use them to your own benefits
or at the same time compared to just like i need to fix
or maybe versus i need to fix my mindset so i'm not having these hendersons come up like how
do you compare and contrast contra compare and contrast maybe like maybe the doubt you're having is
beneficial for you yeah but versus like maybe i shouldn't be having this doubt i need to be confident in myself same
thing with desires and ill will because sometimes they are beneficial for you to have them versus i need to fix myself i
need to be more aware so that i don't have them how do you compare and contrast that's a great question i don't know how
succinctly i can answer it but it's a beautiful beautiful right on point
question and i would say number one is trust your
experience study your experience notice the impact of the hindrances when
they show up and notice one thing that can be really helpful is notice when they're absent
right so when we're not in the grip of them it's hard to have full understanding of their impact or when
they're useful or potentially you know more useful
when you're under their spell because you can't see clearly
and then what's really amazing is to have experiences of their absence
because it is pretty blissful it's pretty surprising how
um these things that we're so familiar with how much they actually do block our joy
and block our capacity to be really present but this is not something to know
intellectually this is something to know directly through your experience
when i'm trying to recognize for myself
like i'm trying to think about you know
desire right kind of one of the other thing you can look at is what is it you're desiring
and you can use some discernment right around like am i desiring
peace and freedom and so i'm motivated to get to the insight meditation center and sit on my cushion and there's very
there can be very wholesome things that that desire supports us
in but if the desire isn't wholesome right
it's not leading toward a beneficial outcome
that's a very clear indicator for us that we're the hindrance itself is
keeping us connected to something that's not helpful for us in our practice does that make sense
jim or richard do you want to take a stab at responding in any way add to what i've said or
yeah okay so i'm going to look here at the chant or not the chant the chat
um says i definitely find that i can be drawn into the hindrances much easier
when i have not fully appreciated their absence yeah i i really agree with that graham
thank you that when when we're it goes back to in that simile really pointing out to
we can't see clearly when the mind is under the influence of the hindrance
we were in the maze looking at the floor we we aren't seeing the conditions
so the evaluation of what is useful and not useful
is much more clearly seen when we're free from it
and it is helpful to notice those moments of freedom what what is that like to have
a moment free from wanting things wanting things
right or in the case of ill maybe not wanting things
right or what is it like when you don't feel doubt
when you feel confident right what's it like to have a moment of
contentment free of that like wanting like oh it's just everything's okay
what does that feel like it's it's so much more peaceful really
yeah yeah to mentioning how maybe let's focus on
what the absence of these hendersons are like so are there some exercises that we can do is it maybe just so more like
reflection every day writing something and how can mindfulness help us because
a lot of times yeah when we're meditating these hendersons are coming up yeah so what can we do to actively
work on and maybe in terms of exercises or mindfulness that yeah will help us like avoid these
interests and secondly be more aware of the absence of them at the same time great great question
yeah you kind of had something yeah please it's sort of related but um
so i think what tonya is pointing to with the you know practicing with hindrances is really understanding first
of all being cognizant or recognize the hindrance so that's a really great
reflection like you're going through the day if you're completely absorbed in a
story in your mind about a conversation that you had earlier in the day and it didn't go the way you would like to it
had gone or all the stuff that goes on the mental activity you recognize at
that moment oh this is restlessness and worry this is some clinging to wanting a different
this is greed this is wanting this is aversion if you're really angry about it
so yeah so seeing that is working with the hindrance and so over
time if you continually bring your mindfulness to that process eventually you'll notice
oh i don't i'm not experiencing that hindrance in a sense you may even be
kind of looking around for it you know i don't know if that makes sense
yeah work that muscle is a great way to put it
so i'll just go through a list of things i wrote and i'll keep and before i actually uh read them i'll
say there i there have been many times i've taught
and other people have taught a five-week series on the five hindrances here
and so those recordings are all on audio dharma and if you go to the website the imc
website you can actually find the handouts and the handouts have um
exit suggestions tips for practicing for the week really fabulous ones
so under documents on the
yeah and you can even if you you know have trouble you can search um there's a little search feature five
hindrances and a lot of stuff will come up um so that's that's written stuff and
then there's also the recorded stuff so so i want to share that resource and
then gil wrote a book um that's on amazon
and unhindered it's called unhindered
and he has a tremendous number of reflection practices in there just really
a lot of lovely material yeah and in fact
most of the handouts and stuff are you know evolved into this book
so the book is just a great it's a few bucks on amazon yeah
so um one of the things i think about is uh just going back to this idea of we
you know wanting to have moments of gladness you know and joy in our lives
it's helpful to actually believe that we deserve to have these experiences
just starting with this like it's natural and it's a good thing and it's good for me and i
i believe i you know i'm deserving and i want to have moments of ease
i think if we orient our mind toward this idea that this is natural and
beautiful and a good thing it helps us to recognize that when it happens
and this again is kind of um helping
reorient the mind away from just the negative right the mind has a negativity bias a
threat by us and so by creating this other thing that we value we help the mind orient toward
it it's helpful to know and recognize
the absence of the hindrances because then we also get to consciously mindfully experience the joy that arises
when we're free from them and the more we're aware with that and allowing that the more it strengthens
our kind of the value that we can place on them on that freedom
um it is
the more quickly we recognize them the better not in some sort of evil way
but you know if the water's not totally boiling yet it's easier to deal with the pot right
than it is if it's been roiling for a long time the energy builds with all of these hindrances
so you know being like yeah i want to notice i want to notice what's happening
in my body i want to notice what's on you know my mind it's not that it's bad news it's like no it's really good to start
to get to know these things it's good to notice
which ones are your frequent visitors get to know them maybe name them
give them a color you know shape size help those those kinds of things all
help help us sort of oh that's familiar that's oh yeah that's what that is right
um it's also helpful to notice
um not just the the pleasantness of their absence but the
way that they negatively impact you they end up so
maybe it's not the beginning of the little desire that's a problem but that it it leads to then overspending or over
you know gaming or whatever it is for us that
then leaves us exhausted or depleted and we're not doing the other things that we wanted to do with our time or spending
time with the people we wanted to spend time with so helping us consciously connect
like if i go ahead with a greed or go ahead with this hating energy
initially there might be some thoughts of pleasure around this or satisfaction
but then it feels like this and then this happens and then this happens and i'm more likely to do this and then i'm
more likely to do that so uh kind of playing the tape out
letting helping your mind think all the way through if we just get caught in these
energies where they're gonna lead potentially
um and what that does is grows your wisdom right it helps you not just get enamored
in the moment it's good to make changes in your daily
life to help protect yourself from the things that you know trigger the hindrances
right for you what are the things that tend to trigger your endurances
media right can be a big trigger
um shopping or overeating and these various things that we can do that we
indulge in can can kind of be food for the hindrances
can support their rising the other thing that really helps is
to actively cultivate alternative mind states like contentment
like really practicing with the idea that it's good enough i don't have to make it go away i don't
have to make it better it's good enough literally just really inviting yourself
to just sort of notice the niggling and go you know what it's good enough it's okay
um [Music] it's also you know yeah i think the brahma vaharas in general so that's
loving kindness practice are you familiar with that yeah so it's another practice and it's
another talk and it's 8 59 but there are other qualities that are
considered very noble and sort of uh
what is the word i'm not thinking of the word but heavenly almost right and they're feeling and generating a loving
kindness their compassion their sympathetic joy and its equanimity those
are the four brahmapaharas so there's practices that support arousing those kinds of mind states and
those are all protected mind states where we are pretty much free from the hindrances
when we're fully engaged so there it is
thank you so much for your comments and questions it helped help me
find some energy to respond to you and focus so i appreciate it
yeah thank you both you guys yeah and everybody out there
have a good night and may you be free from the hindrances
and uh may it be a benefit to you and everyone in your life
[Music]
thank you