there's a particular teaching of the Buddha that for
ever since I learned about it maybe some 30 years ago or so I've ignored it
and and even though it has a very central place the Buddha got organized
his practices in the mind and the mind states that develop as your practice were organized into a list called the 37
wings of Awakening so the four foundations of mindfulness of five faculties some factors of
Awakening the Eightfold Path there's like these list of lists they add up to 37.
and um and there's a list of four called the four sometimes it's translated into
English as the four roads to spiritual power or psychic power the word is Idi uh I
think maybe in Sanskrit it's a city but Nepali it's IDI and um and it's a little bit strange the
formulation of it and it's never clear what and there's never there's no discussion about it and so what does
this mean and it has this word IDI which means psychic power and and I just kind of like this is too much
to handle for me and then uh last week I read an article
by wonderful uh colleague of mine wonderful teacher in our tradition named Ruth King and this uh this article she
explained it in a very ordinary she did she denatured it or demythologized it or
made it ordinary made it accessible he said wow this is fantastic I loved it and um and uh and she did
what the Buddha did with things in at his own time he would take these uh
wonderfully Supernatural or psychic power ideas that existed back in those
times and he would regularly say oh yes we do that too but let me tell you how
we do it and inevitably what he did was he uh kind of made it ordinary
into this you know something that was ordinary that human beings can do rather than some of the more kind of
Supernatural Dimensions that that uh sometimes they these existed in his time
and so he he already had a customer doing that and so when I saw with King do it I said oh
so I was a little bit inspired by her a little bit borrowing from her way of doing it I'm going to offer my take
on these four and one uh one time sometimes they're called four uh practices or four roads
to success any kind of success in any Endeavor that you want to do in life no matter what it is
um to think to include these four approaches to doing them what can help
you be successful in what you do and I apply to Dharma practice I think
it's particularly significant as its support as an aid as a as the offer kind
of uh some power or some some some strength to your success as a as a
meditation practitioner or a Dharma practitioner and these four roads to power are or
some people call power to success whatever it might be and um our um the desire
um effort thinking about things thought
and investigation it's kind of a very rough translation of these
and so the first one is desire and what's nice about these four is that
it's very easy to listen to Derma teachers like me and uh and here somehow the opposite
idea that you know like you're not supposed to have desire in Buddhism
that uh you're not supposed to make kind of strong effort you know you're supposed to be kind of chill and relaxed
and you're not supposed to be thinking in meditations or thinking is out that thinking is bad
and that uh I don't know about investigation maybe but but um
but here here the Buddha puts kind of its center of the stage the idea of
Desire that and I like to think of it as Dharma desire mic desire
and the word for desire is Chanda this is important because the
problematic forms of Desire the Buddha has different words for it
for example it literally means thirst this is a part this is the kind of
desire that's considered to be a source of suffering that is suffering to be kind of the compulsive desire
that you know it really it's it's thirst it's not any old desire and so the word Chun does an umbrella
term for all forms of Desire but in this list it's kind of dharmic Desire desires
that um that have equality what makes them dharmic one of the things is that
there's no clinging involved with them clinging is a source of suffering can there be desires without the Eddie
clinging and can there be desires that are for the Dharma for practice for Liberation
for compassion yes the answer is of course
and nebula talks about marshalling that kind of Desire standing behind it Gathering it together and having it be
strong for you and so if you want to have a success in what you do
become clear about your desire and sometimes people emphasize having
really clear about intention but intention and desire you know well I
think are overlapped quite a bit just intention seems I don't know uh more inspiring it's probably more
sophisticated maybe or intention is um you know it doesn't quite feel like
desire which you're not supposed to have um but um
but we're resurrecting the word desire and here in a useful way an important
way you have to want something and if you don't want something why would you do it why would you pursue it
why would you engage you have to want to come to IMC you know I don't think any of you probably none
of you just happen to be walking down the sidewalk and someone pushed you in
um you know you have to want to be you have to want to be here you know something something has to bring you and
um meditate sit down to meditate you know to on a regular basis there has to be a desire for it
how to have that desire be without clinging is the art how to have the desire without
compulsion without expectation without being attached to results and is part of
the art of learning how to hold desire but still to be clear about the desire
to be clear about the intention I spent a good part of my Dharma life
reflecting on intention and I would ask the question regularly to myself what's my deepest intention
here someone else would my teacher might ask what's your practitioner might ask
what's the heart's deepest wish what does your heart most want
and this idea of the mo what the hearts most wants so what's the deepest wish it means to go through the layers
underneath the conceit underneath our fear underneath our greed underneath our
you know all these layers of places that are not really at the heart but the question kind of presupposes
that there's something very significant beautiful wonderful a
treasure to be found you know and you can get deep enough to go to the hearts you know the deepest place within
that there's something really to honor and respect and to maybe be guided by
so this idea of you know once you look at like you know bring desire to the table
means reflect on desire think about it be clear about it don't just take the
first desire that comes along but uh you know drop down and what is what is it you really want
and a fascinating exercise is if what you most want is something which is
stated in the negative you know I Want to Be Free of fear that's wonderful but if it's in the
negative it's something what you don't want then um ask the question if I could have
that what do I want then so if if there was no fear
what then is my heart's deepest wish and that might kind of bring you to a
deeper level underneath it and that might also change your relationship with the the fear for example when you
realize there's a bit deeper thing that's your your hearts call your the calling of your heart
the second of these four practices for success
is the poly word is virya b-i-r-i-y-a
and uh it uh is a word that uh uh implies a lot of strength that's
associated with the word Vera which means hero so some people like to translate it as
courageous effort thank you so there's a kind of oomph so like it isn't like you know easy going
it isn't like again here it's not all about being chilled you know these Buddhists are supposed to be calm and
easy going and relaxed and I think that's nice maybe it's true kind
of but it doesn't mean that we also don't make a lot of effort you know and serious effort and you know
this is important um in this world of ours for many of us not everyone in the world but in many
people in our kind of neck of the woods there's a lot of great things to do
there's so much we also unless we have like too much too many wonderful things to do too many good causes to be
involved in too many Recreation opportunities too many Netflix movies too much you know and um
and then there's a kind of neurosis of trying to have it all or if you're not up to speed then you go to the block
party and you're kind of like you know not holding your own in the conversations you're supposed to have to
know something about everything and and um but a wise life
that really kind of looks carefully at desires what's what you most want
is going to start whittling away the things that get in the way of going deep
going seriously with what's most important uh if you if you want to live your life
skimming the surface of all all these things that's maybe a little bit unfortunate when you want to go deep
and that's what Dharma practice is possible is to really if this is important for you really do it put effort into it make
energy to it don't expect it just kind of like you know you know
there's something called uh bookstand Buddhists the people who just you know you know
you know read little Dharma books in the evening before going to sleep or something and I don't want to knock the importance of that that's a wonderful
thing by itself but if that's all you do then it's like reading the menu all the
time you go to the restaurant this is a great restaurant didn't I you know and
all you do is ever ever do is read the menu and they never order the food so
you know so if you just read Dharma books you know it's like them just it's just a menu kind of
so you have to engage in the meal you have to eat it so you have to make effort and then this this word very such
a strong word it kind of means courageous effort and um and so what does that mean for
you I just love the word courage in French comes from the word heart so what's the heart's deepest wish
number one now what's the hearts kind of wholehearted
engagement in what you're doing to be wholehearted
and don't be afraid of making effort don't be afraid of being wholehearted
the art of it though is what is dharmic effort dharmic effort is effort which is
done without conceit conceit is where we bring ourselves along measure ourselves I'm failing and
I have to do better I have to get a badge for what I do and you know be able to show the block party you know how
great I am in my effort and how I succeeded and um mostly Dharma practice is kind of
like baseball we're you know baseball batters mostly fail
I think you know how many times do you does your mind fall off the breathing
when you can meditation and go off into thinking about it I mean probably baseball players have better success
than we do you know but but uh but you know this
Dharma effort has nothing nothing we don't don't measure it the conceit of success and failure and
get caught in the kind of what's important is the engagement how we
engage how we engage wholeheartedly without strain without measuring
ourselves without kind of the ordinary kind of conceits of being successful and
being a failure these these don't really apply here but rather what really
applies is the wholehearted application then you're doing the best we can that's
what carries the day the third of these four is uh the word
is chitta c-i-t-t-a that are usually translated as
mind but cheetah in in in the ancient Pali language can also mean uh thought
Thinking by itself sometimes people Scholars of study I think that's that that she tells the
thinking mind as opposed to the whole mind but any case to hear think of it as
thinking and that is have desire make the effort but think about it
spend time being could do this in a considered way don't just be blind and Thoughtless and
just I'm supposed to do it because I'm supposed to do it reflect and contemplate and think and
have conversations with friends and stretch your mind to kind of uh so you
can do it in a way that's more intelligent better informed better considered
they sometimes people get the impression that with meditation that he has to not think at all and therefore I'm not
supposed to think in my life um I think that the thinking learning how to think well
is an art that we all should learn ing how to spend time you know even taking even going to the Community
College and taking a class in critical thinking skills that's a good idea
and just really learn how we make mistakes in our you know in our
cognitive um understanding of things because we we
make leaps we make assumptions we believe things that shouldn't be
believed automatically we don't learn to question and look and what's going on here so learning the art of thinking so if
you want to do something well really consider your desire make the
effort and think about it well and then the fourth one is and one of
one of the ways to think about it well a kind of a guideline for it is as you
think about things think about it in a way that makes you more peaceful
a big guy you know it's a track how you're thinking and if thinking is stirring you up
making you anxious or making you whatever then um it's not so much not only what you think but how you think
that's important and so see if you can adjust how you're thinking
so that the thinking itself starts to kind of encourage a calmness a
peacefulness and ease rather than the opposite
the fourth of these roads to success is um
I called in before investigation and um
and now this goes along with this uh and how I understand it is that when you
engage in doing a thoughtful way you want to learn from what you're doing
so this is called in some circles it's called action reflection
you act and then you reflect about what you just did and from a Dharma point of view it's
often reflecting on what are the consequences of what I do did this work out what was the impact of this am I
better off because I did this or am I worth worse off that I asked am I more attention tense
now or I feel more alive and vital and and relaxed now
so we want to track ourselves and monitor ourselves and learn from our
mistakes learn from our successes learn from what what works and doesn't work
and that takes time to reflect and to investigate to consider to evaluate how
it's going as we're doing it and um so this idea of having a sense of
the consequences is Central to the teachings of the Buddha he was a consequentialist
he was regularly and constantly looking at describing uh what we do from the
point of view of the consequences it has so consequences means that you have to
think about a little bit you have to reflect you have to investigate you have to track what's Happening Here
and um so you know why this is quite unfortunate and why it's a drag to hear it for some
of you is that it's work you have to give yourself time for it
and you have important things to do right like I won't go through the list
and um and then and it is work but it's a work that leads to rest work
that leads to the mind being being de-stressed we have to engage something
and it's a work that maybe becomes rejuvenating vital welcoming and uh
until we can reclaim the word work be
wonderful as opposed to work being discouraging I'll have to do more work
again more work I think some people in English the word work is not a welcomed
word but I I think if we learn how to do it all this well
it's I think becomes more and more welcome because we feel the benefits it feels inviting invite and invigorating
or revitalizing and we start discovering through Dharma practice this whole process of Desire
engagement reflection and and evaluation
it feels more and more like second nature it's almost as if it's almost as if um it's kind of what the heart does
if we get out of the way well enough if we have a clear sense of a desire
that is healthy and maybe it almost feels natural to have then the rest can follow almost as if
it's natural and it doesn't feel like work after a while just feels like this is what life
is this is what we do for some people what seems like natural
and what we who we are and what we do is be neurotic because that's the habits that we formed
and created and all that and fear and anxiety and all kinds of things become second nature because we repeated it so
much and it's inconceivable that it can be different it can be different
we can transform ourselves and change we can develop other skills and ways of
being that become second nature and these the and the and the one of the
one of the perspectives for understanding how to do that through this is these poor
roads practices for success and which you can apply to almost
anything you want to do in life but in Dharma practice we do we apply it
to our practice so you might try it this week you might try to maybe you know you could do take
one of the four One A Day for four days and just kind of let it write it down a
piece of paper or the word and put it on your I don't know sticky notes a few sticky notes put it
on your wheel of your driver your your steering wheel of your car or your mirror or someplace where you are next
on your phone that that's the place
yeah and so a day on desire Dharma desire
a day on effort to darn my effort curvature's effort a day on consideration reflection
thinking about it Dharma thinking and today an evaluation looking at the
consequences considering it and um spend time with us and see if it you
know get a hang of it to get a sense of it learn how to develop it learn how to
you know make it make it an art form or a skill or a craft that you've developed
it so it becomes easy it doesn't become like you know it doesn't become this like heavy work it becomes and you know
vitalizing work if you call it work so um
what are your thoughts about this any questions anything you want to be clarified or do you have any protests
anything
um so it feels like almost when I think about this I need to start with the
fourth one first because that kind of leads to you know
the investigation feels like the to uncover the things first fantastic I
think that's great because um what that means is you're going to be looking at the consequences of how
you're living your life now and what you might discover might inform how you go forward and what desires you
want to have yeah yeah I love that thank you starting with the last one
I just may want to make a simple observation the comment that lady made there reminds me of the circle that you
have you investigate you form a desire you you put a very uh sincere effort into
the into the work I had to improve and then you basically evaluate and reflect
and then Circle goes around there very nice yeah it's a circle like a spiral come around and around and it keeps
developing and growing yes that's very nice idea yes in the other hole
that's okay there we go it's a race
that's not very dharmic it's the effort
oh uh I really appreciated the
Clarity around desire around uh cultivating wholesome desire
because uh for me I've always been very driven
and I think for a long time in my practice I kept thinking that that was something I kind of needed to get rid of
or not be so involved with
so when you described a desire without clinging
or greed or aversion
that really landed for me wholesome desire agree horse and desire
yes and uh and it can be uh strong it can be something we put a lot of effort
into and you know it makes you know that really dedicated so some someone might think wow that person's putting a lot of
effort I wonder if that person's too attached and they ask you and you say no
I just have a strong desire and I have a lot of energy for this and I'm I've
given myself over to it and so that's a it's a beautiful thing to do
sometimes I I have sometimes the aspiration to I say that some I'm a
wannabe obsessive because I really like engaging and doing
and I just want to have sometimes more time to just give myself over to what you know one thing for a while
so it's a beautiful thing just to do one thing and sometimes I feel nourished by just doing one thing for a while and
just you know just really get myself over and there's a kind of Harmony that sets in in my system when I just really
spend time with one activity so yeah
I appreciate very much your your wisdom today thank you thank you
and it made me think about my own practice in the practice of
living in that fashion which is for me mindfulness for the most most part um and what came to mind was Tara
Brock's reign rain do you know that yes acronym okay so I'm going to speak it
just because I think it's so applicable and Rain stands oh look at that rain stands for recognize allow
investigate and nurture which the essence of that is compassion self-compassion
and I bring it up because if I stopped with the four roads that you just shared
and I I have so very much to learn I'm a beginner um the question I sat with was well as I
investigate what do I do with all the emotions because here I am in my human body facing my habitual ways of being
that may be problematic or may not be and what what do we do with that and that's what made me think of Tara
because the only thing I can think of to do with that is when they arise
to let them be there and love myself through it right because inevitably there are things that come up that take
me away from that that space that you just described which I do know and
experience but I certainly must practice to be there as much as possible so thank
you for the great the validation thank you love it
that was easy earlier in your talk Gail you talked
about how you have to the Buddha talked about clearing the path before you can see
more deeply for me that took about 15 years of meditation retreats
and the dedicated practitioners program that gave me the Forum in which to do
what you're talking about what I know about myself is without a
lot of support I I just don't
have the discipline I I don't I I can't I I have the idea that I want to do
these things but in daily life I unless I put myself in some kind of a
program I I don't stay with it that's fantastic so you you just in some ways
we can we can kind of evaluate to what you just said from this point of view of the teachings you certainly have a desire
as you reflect and look at yourself and you find it's difficult to do it alone
and so then you know so you see it doing alone the consequence of doing alone is you don't do it
and so but you still have this desire so what's the right effort what what how how to go forward with this and so for
you maybe it's to do it in community to make sure you have Community then you do it in the community and you find oh
yeah that works I'll do more of it so that's that would be an exact a
simple example of using these four to um you know to to to to address what
you're addressing but you're already doing this I think you just didn't have to have these categories to put them
into and um and then you might do it for another 15 years or something probably
take that for me and then at some point you might discover you know this is nice but I think I should uh uh you know I
see the consequence has been good and something might occur to you and say you know maybe I should try
an experiment because a lot of the Dharma practices good think of it as an experiment let me try an experiment
let me see what it's like now to practice alone let me do a self retreat
let me go off someplace for four days by myself and see if I can do a retreat without
any support from anybody else and and because I've been practicing for so long
and uh and then you find oh this is hard but maybe I have to find the discipline
inside now and not to rely on the group to support me and that's the I think this is the next
step for my growth and that's what happened to me that they're that very thing I wasn't
planning on it that kind of stumbled into it um I'd done all my Retreats and all my practice in Zen where you it's all group
practice and then I was introduced to this vipassana practice in Thailand and the
Abbott the monastery said oh go out there at that little Hut to the end of the monastery uh overlooking the rice
fields and stay there by yourself and practice all day and then come see me tomorrow so I went out there to do it and I
realized wait a minute I've never practiced all day alone and I said oh
uh this is this is I have I have to call on uh something inside of me I never called
on before I call the discipline then but this is you know an inner motivation that's and so that that became a growing
Edge for me so so this I'm not I'm agreeing with you I'm just I just wanted to say at some
point you might also find as you do as you do what you most supportive for you you might find that the the question
will come should I experimentally differently am I ready for an experiment that's that's so helpful I I really
don't have a group in which to practice now I probably need that uh the idea of
doing something alone scares me but it intrigues me too fantastic so then uh apply these four
steps to practicing alone you know what's desires what's desire
really fuse it or animates it in a good way would it be a good desire what's the importance of it what's the what are you
trying to really trying to do in a deep way and then what's the right effort
and then think about it for a while to really kind of get clear about what's
all it involves and then when you do it start doing the feedback loop of action reflection
thank you thank you thank you very much
being a discussion um I was looking for peace and safety
and I you know I didn't have it for a little bit so I've actually decided to
go into self-retrieve for three weeks prior to going into one week retreat with you in
person so I did it two like two days straights Friday and Saturday about six
hours straight and the way I kind of handled it was having darmi the day I woke up and as I
was approaching it I was reading choosing the emotion or topics or
dharmic idea that calls to me and listening to your talk and then having a
meditation and listening your talk and meditation and I was able to go through that five to six hours
and I found incredible safety and peace just within me knowing that you know I
have some sensitive issue that I'm dealing with and emotion and what would
you think because for me this is how I'm approaching I'm in a private retreat with you where I who I'm whom I feel
safe and I'm gonna go find myself the safety that I can create because ultimately the
fears or the anxiety or the strong emotion that I have
really I really do need to take care with myself and have defined I think I need to find it within me yes to develop
that so um what would you recommend and then the way I was thinking about it is when I
didn't want to get out of my home I could reframe it I need to take care of my mind I need to
take care of my body the body they need to relax so I'm doing this for me
so what would you do to prepare I don't think I'm just gonna I'm just gonna keep
this whale until I get to the in-person retreat without too much expectation
yeah but what would you is there any other thing you could recommend within
it a couple of things occurred to me one is it's wonderful what you described that the part of the action reflection
thinking about what you've done is that uh you might as you reflect the way you
did in seeing the benefits of what you've done let it let it support or nourish your con your confidence
your self-confidence that oh I can do this so that your I can do this in certain lit in ways and and
um so you have so that's one and the other is when you come to the retreat center uh you have a variety of
options of how to practice there and if you you found that it was beneficial to
explore the edges of practicing alone you might try it even at the retreat to
do some of the meditations in your room okay well you're alone and see if that some of what you've been learning the
last few days benefits you and and you can carry it with you there and and uh
and see you know and then and you evaluate how is this working in the context of practicing in Silence with
other people is this making me feel less safe or more safe to have spent some time alone
okay and then during the next three weeks I'm going in the Intensive continuously doing maybe not six hours a
day maybe three to four hours just go into deeper and deeper and deeper I'm kind of doing the same thing that I had
done in the past when I go into one week Retreat where I did this intensive Retreat and it became intensive sessions
for myself it became much more meaningful when I get there so so this
is wonderful but keep reflecting on how it's going okay learn from how it's going evaluate study yourself carefully
and some days it might work really well but you know we are we have all these emotional ups and downs in our life
right so you're tracking yourself and you might say oh today is a day to really do something different because I
don't feel I woke up kind of feeling pretty vulnerable so I think I better you know just read a
book [Laughter] okay so thank you all for being here and
coming uh and I invite any of you who want to meet me in the parking lot if you want
to pull a chair out from the folding chair out from the cabinet so it's around the corner there we can bring
them out to the parking lot take off our masks and uh and just to continue this discussion if you'd like
too thank you