hello everyone and happy to be here and
wonderful to have this to have this clear sense of
meditating together with the in community with others
even though i'm looking mostly at the camera as i speak
i have a very rich sense of um those of you who are at the other end of
this and seeing that chats helps tremendously with that and and um both the names that i recognize
and those that are new and so thank you all for being here
one of the attitudes with which to meditate
is an attitude of curiosity or interest
of wanting to really know what is happening here in the moment in our experience
and to have that kind of interest in knowing
what is here while at the same time not trying to understand
and the reason not to try to understand is then we will be not meditating we'll be thinking
reflecting probing so the art of this is to have that
interest where the eyes the perception the attention
is has a nice alertness to it
as if we're trying to discover the message that's available here
as if we're trying to understand it we're available for it and so rather than trying to figure
anything out there is heightened availability as if there is a profound message to be
discovered here but only a message that only can be discovered
if we don't actively try to discover it but rather be available to it so that
kind of interest and and it might be
and some of this has to do with beginning to understand the deeper conditionality deeper
conditions that are coming into play that are operating in the moment as we're living our lives
and the message that we can receive is that see the deeper structures of what's happening the deeper
motivations and emotions and the other thing that the message
might be is something about the potential of what's possible
and it becomes really clear that it's not just of the moment but
what future we create for ourselves maybe in the next moment the next minute by how we are here
and so this availability to wisdom availability to understanding
um an interest to understand to see
while not trying to so available but not figuring it out as if it's going to be
arise it's going to be it's going to appear if we have this attentiveness
so to sit in a meditation posture
and maybe to think of the alert posture as a
that's alert to
just to be available to sense and to feel if you're going to go into the woods to
listen to the hear a sound of a faint bird
there might be a physical uprightness lifting up of the body
kind of to hear and listen
and so this alert posture and then closing the eyes
to also begin a process of settling into the body
maybe settling around the alertness
so the unnecessary tensions and holdings are released
taking a few long slow deep breaths and savoring each breath taking your
time really sensing feeling the body
expand filled with air stretch as you breathe in
and maybe relaxing into a longer exhale
maybe with a sense of ah relaxation
settling
a deep long inhale in a long exhale
relaxing the thinking mind quieting the thinking
letting your breathing return to normal
taking a few moments to be attuned to the rhythm of breathing
in your body
breathing is connected to so many different parts of our being
it's at the crossroads if you be available
for the message of breathing for the deeper experience of what's
happening as you breathe what is revealed
and then for the next few exhales relaxing whatever energy agitation
there is of in thinking
the thinking mind quieter as you exhale
settling more deeply
on the exhale as if the thinking mind can rest
can let its weariness settle down
and if you're present for your mind in some quiet open available way
as if there's a message or a deeper understanding deeper insight
does anything arise when you quietly make yourself available
to sense and feel the thinking mind
and taking one deeper breath and exhaling
returning to natural breathing
your normal way of breathing
available to the experience of breathing
and continuing with the rhythm of breathing
maybe within the breathing itself
if you what a message what emotional message
what emotional understanding comes if you're available
to see or feel your emotional life as you breathe
is there a unique message or understanding that appears
when you take into account when you feel both your breathing
you're connected to your breathing and you feel your mood or emotional state
what what does mindfulness or breathing contribute
to a better understanding
and then continuing now in silence with your breathing
but perhaps with an openness that's available
for a deeper experience
so
you
one way of understanding mindfulness
is that it involves an availability
to experience we're available
we don't assert ourselves we don't pull away
we don't project our ideas we don't
shut down or avoid
but we're available for experience
we get distracted and then we return to that availability
and in this way we're not asserting ourselves
not protecting ourselves
and as we come to the end of this meditation imagine that in a safe way
safe situation you're simply attentive present
mindful innocent feeling of it with availability you're
available
to be mindful to be attentive to the social situation
not asserting yourself not pulling away just available
available to feel and sense know the humanity of someone else
available to sense and feel what animates them
more fully who they are and how they are
and through this availability good will and kindness
every very different life then if we assert our goodwill assert
our kindness we're available to our kindness our
goodwill
we're available for love to arise
in the space of not knowing
the space of possibility
in the space of knowing others more fully
and in this way our meditation practice
can benefit our wider life
and others in our life may it be that this meditation practice
we do serves for the welfare and happiness of others
may it bring others safety happiness peace
and maybe even freedom at least the freedom
from our assertive assertiveness our neediness
our projections unto them
may we be safe for other people may all beings be happy
[Music]
so
so continuing the discussion about emotions
people have many attitudes towards their emotional
life some people are shy of their emotions or
troubled by their emotions some people don't pay much attention to them
certain emotions are considered wrong or inappropriate to have or we have an
aversive relationship to them or were ashamed of having them or
and some were happy to have some were delighted and hold on to there's a wide range
of ways to relate to it in the dharma
in practicing with emotions it's useful to respect all emotions
to all emotions in a sense that all emotions have a place and that
buddhism buddhist practice is not meant to negate or squash or
push away any emotion but in that more respect and openness to
experience the full range of emotions that we have to come to healthy emotions to come to a
healthy relationship to emotions and a healthy source for emotions
and one way to relate to emotions for this purpose is to
see all emotions as maybe all you know provisionally at least all emotions
to be a message all emotions are pointing to something
and so right we don't want to kill the messenger before we've seen the message we don't
even after we see the message but to think of emotions as pointing to something
that's deeper some emotions are
arise out of other emotions some emotions come together with other
emotions sometimes if the predominant emotion might be grief
but there might be mixed in there there might be a sense of guilt
there might be some shame there might be anger and it's the in in in part of the whole
complex of how we're feeling at a particular time but maybe we focus mostly on the grief
or we feel we might sense the other ones are there but we feel somehow it's wrong to have those
but they're part of the complex and maybe they're needed part of the complex they're they all point to
something and if we see them all these emotions as being
messages messengers that are pointing to something then we can easier to respect them
and take time to get to know them more if we take emotion some emotions like anger as
being anger in and of itself
without being connected to something deeper then we can have an aversive relationship to anger we can feel
ashamed for having it or upset for about ourselves or something but if we see anger to be a message
and then we ask what is going on here what's it pointing to more deeply
and in the broadest terms um the uh some emotions
uh uh arise out of attachment they rise out of something we're holding
on to and clinging and um and so the message might be the pointer is
is to discover what are we attached to here and
so rather than cutting caught up in the anger by itself
and relating only to the anger if we do that then we're missing the deeper message a deeper understanding
but if we look and see the anger represents something it's a manifestation of something that deeper
what might that be so in terms of other emotions it might be that we're hurt
and that the being hurt is the primary um more primary than the anger which is
secondary and so the anger is pointing allowing the anger to point back to the hurt that
might is what might might be what really needs our attention what we want to practice with
that's because it's more primary that's somehow the source that's prompting the anger
it might be that anger what underlies anger is fear and so
if we just stay with the anger and blame someone and get angry with someone we
won't feel the fear we won't know the recognize that we're afraid as well and recognizing the fear doesn't make us
weak the anger make us strong well recognizing the fear can actually
give us a lot of strength if we learn how to be with fear in a useful productive way
but then we're more connected to what's primary we're coming home to a deeper way and now we know what needs to be taken
care of we know better what needs to happen but uh both hurt and fear
may be related something even deeper those are kind of messages too and what's more deeply what's going on
that's more deep here and that's where there might be attachments and there might not be
attachments if there are attachments clinging then that's what we want to see in this
practice that is really the the heart of moving towards freedom
is to see where we're caught if we're not uh attached and
caught then below the the fear and the hurt there might be some something that's
really precious something that's tender or loving or or
appreciative or grateful about this life what's going on here
there might be some deeper place of being at home that maybe makes us feel more vulnerable
and rather than avoiding the vulnerability or the tenderness or the love
the task is the dharma task is to discover how to find strength in that
how to find ease with that how to be wise about that so we can stay in touch with that as we go through our lives
so whatever the emotion might be it should be respected
and what respect means is kind of how i understand the etymology of the word the etymology game
is that it's to look again to inspect again to respect to take a
second look or a third look and really spend time getting to know this experience what is this
and then be available to feel or sense what else is happening here what is it what might it be pointing to what might
it become be coming out of not so much by to analyze what it is
but this is why mindfulness is so helpful we're kind of like available to notice
what's going on in the cracks of it what's going on underneath it if we open up the attention more widely
and look beyond the the secondary emotion or the thing that's strongest
at what it's pointing to then we might start seeing deeper and deeper
sources and processes that are going on so in this way we're respectful
and um and so what's the message
as i've said now a few times even the most you know
even i'll say this differently even the most difficult challenging maybe painful
maybe even uh inappropriate or emotions that we might feel
the more strong they are stronger they are the more they represent that there
is something important for us to delve into and see what's going on there probably is some strong attachment
some strong clinging to something and and the stronger the reaction the
stronger the despair the stronger the grief the stronger the anger the stronger the whatever it might be
the more it actually is a messenger it's hard to take this idea in sometimes
when the strength of our reaction strength of our emotions has a lot to do with the terrible things that are being
done to us are happening in the world and and uh
i don't want us in any kind of way say that we're responsible for our emotions and because
you know there's terrible things that happen to us but the stronger the reaction we have
the more uh the richer opportunity more important opportunity there is
uh to see where like the bigger the reaction the deeper
in our psyche and our mind and our hearts is where the attachments might be
and so the stronger the reaction the more it can it it's a doorway into understanding the depth of what's going
on i've seen this a lot of times on retreats uh the classic example on a meditation
retreat is we try to make these safe places for everyone
but occasionally something happens that you know that is not so safe not you know what the
very thing they were trying to protect people from happens i remember once there was a um
we were at renting facilities in a kind of a university
and there was a fire in a distant building in university and um
and uh there were helicopter firefighting helicopters that came flying over really close to us and there
was a lot of noise and maybe some smoke
and uh there was a woman at their treat this is many years ago now who has still had
a legacy traumatic legacy from growing up uh with the bombings in europe during
world war ii and uh the sounds of the helicopters and the noise and everything seemed so much
like what she was familiar with that had been so troublesome she got
really frightened and um but because she was on a meditation retreat she kept practicing with it
and going deeper and deeper and discovering where the knot was where she was still knotted up holding herself
in fear and protecting yourself unnecessarily and it behaved it was able to let go
so on retreat it's a very special environment to to kind of really
the stronger the reactivity the more it points to conspiring something really really deep
uh sometimes and um and sometimes perceiving the message of uh
is um there's respecting emotions is we're respecting our love our
kindness our compassion to give it time and when we connect to that and use that
as a message to what's more deeply or deeper maybe we connect that to our freedom
we feel we see ah this this good will i have this compassion i have
it's arising out of freedom and the freedom is maybe the greatest gift we can give
to connect to that sense of freedom that we've discovered and to let that be the vehicle
for our care of the world so you might try this
to whatever your emotions you have today um if it's safe if it's appropriate maybe
to step away a little bit be on your own and reflect more deeply
what is this a message of what is this pointing to if this is a messenger
what's uh more intimate deeper more important here what can i discover
and maybe all the emotions are pointing to something deeper than
themselves so thank you and i'll continue tomorrow