hmm hello everyone and
I feel a little slow to speak I think I'm a little bit um
just happy to be here with you and this way and somehow more
focused on that happiness then speaking
but speak I will
there's a difference between being mindful
and having the desire to be mindful
and and many people who learn about Buddhism and it may be in a
simplistic way will believe that there's something wrong with having desires
and this is not the teachings of the Buddha
he said that there's to paraphrase him there's something wrong
something painful about craving
about thirsting grasping
certain kinds of desire which carry with them inherent in them is pain
stress and um
but desire doesn't have to have that desires can flow through the Mind
through the heart like a small Cloud floating in the sky
not with no pressure no just kind of floating through desires
can be quite easy to have and there are desires that arise out of
our goodness out of wisdom out of care compassion out of compassion itself
is a kind of a desire and um
and so in the difference between being Mindful and Desiring to be mindful
is a useful distinction if it helps us to appreciate our desire
to be mindful the wish the aspiration the
the wanting to be mindful and to find a way to want to be mindful
that is this is my language which I maybe you translated for yourself
but which is delightful to have delightful desire
and maybe inspired desire maybe a loving desire
that has no expectation in it no pressure in it
no requirement no should no admonition it just kind of like
of course this is a good thing and so if we can find that kind of
Desire someone asks Chanda yes that's the Pali word c-h-a-n-d-a
and if if we can find that kind of Desire
maybe it can support being mindful
it can be a a
gentle like the that used to be water Mills water wheels
that as the current of the river passes through the wheel it turns the wheel for
the mill to grind flower and and maybe the Chanda maybe the
desire can be the current
that keeps the mindfulness engaged or present to Turning flowing
moving active so in this sitting
maybe after settling in I'll ask you to explore the nature of a desire to be
mindful and see if that can support the practice
so
establishing a posture for meditation
and then allowing the eyes to close themselves
if they want to
whether the eyes are open or closed see if you can relax The Gaze of the
eyes any engagement with the eyes to see
tension
into take a few long gentle deep breaths
with the inhale to get a full embodied connection
to yourself the connection to your as much of your body as
the deep in-breath that reaches
and maybe as you exhale long exhale let it be like all the weight of your
body Settles into the bottom of your belly
and from there is supported
and letting your breathing return to normal
and for the next three or four breaths to feel wherever there might be tension
in your body tightness into the exhale soften around it
relax
and then take a couple of breaths to relax the thinking muscle
any tension tightness associated with thinking
and then take a few moments to feel your whole body
or a wide experience of your body
in whatever way is easy for you
feeling your body so it can be a reference point
or a deeper connection to your inner life
and then see if you can find within you
a relaxed desire maybe one that is
Wells up from within rather than
a thought that carries with it you should
the desire which is maybe kind of an inspiration from within
of the goodness of a possibility of being present
aware and mindful Here and Now
maybe a desire to be aware
of the aliveness of this moment
knowing that whatever is occurring in the present whether it's Pleasant or unpleasant
is a manifestation of you you're alive right now being alive right
now and Desiring to be present for it to be
mindful
because mindfulness itself
being conscious is a primary characteristic of being
alive and awake
it's a wondrous thing to be aware
and a gentle loving inspired desire yes
to awareness desire that is so simple that it's just
a simple yes this is good this is what I'd like
letting there be a gentle on going desire
that is like the wind pushing a sailboat
through the water where mindfulness is the bow
that meets the water Moment by moment
as the boat moves Through Time
if you find yourself Swept Away in thinking
because of the wonderful desire to be mindful
when you come back there can be a delight
in following through on that desire
that coming back to mindfulness
is a happy fulfillment of his simple desire
and you can enjoy that fulfillment however
week it might be
and as we come to the end of this sitting to appreciate there's an art
to having desires
many people don't study the art of Desire Desiring
desires can come from a place of within of creativity
of
non-craving desires that have no need
within them just a simple open
goodness so this would be a nice idea this would be good
a desire which can be an Inspire action can Inspire change
but doesn't assert itself doesn't push for change
and there can be then a desire
for the well-being of others
that come from this place of creativity and simplicity
that is a form of art perhaps it comes from a kind of Grace and
non-neediness non-obligation from a place within where it just seems
like this is a really good idea that others would be well
it's a desire which feels good to have it's nourishing supportive to you to
have this desire there's so little pressure or
sense of lack or sense of inadequacy that goes with it it's the opposite
it's a desire that comes from a sense of
being content here settled
and from such a desire
wishing expressing the wish in simple words in your
in the quiet of your own mind you might repeat to repeat these words
that I say may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may the and may your peaceful desire for the welfare of others
be nourishing for you
[Music]
thank you
so this week we're doing the Buddhist teachings on right effort
sixth factor of the eighthful path and in the classic description of each of
the factors of the path eight volt factors
this has the longest description and has a lot of repetition in it
so there's four right efforts and a lot of the way it's worded each one is the
same just some variation for it and there's a lot of repetition of some words
and uh so the repetition has an impact as we read it or listen to it
and um that kind of emphasis and each each and just the right effort each of
them has a series of words that um that uh describe the kind of effort that
to be made but with all these um uh and and uh
and so we'll talk about these different kinds of efforts that the text says
but each of these four right efforts is supposed to be done with desire
the poly word is Chanda c-h-a-n-d-a rather innocent word for desire
that sometimes is used for appropriate desires sometimes for inappropriate
desires or painful ones it's kind of a broad word desires
without any ethical or other kind of valence implied except in the context in
which it's used but it's used for wholesome things and one of the wholesome
engagements is this right effort to engage to to how to practice
and and so learning how to have Chanda to have desire which is itself right
effort which is itself without any afflictive Tendencies the unwholesome
and which has wholesomeness as part of it uh which is skillful which is nourishing
which is supportive for us and so the art of discovering of investigating having how we have desires
so they come from a place within That's Not Afraid which is not
greedy which is not angry or hostile aversive
that's not uh related to conceit you know I have to be I have to make the
effort here so I can be the you know the most you know perfect effortful person and
all my Buddhist Community or something so um but to really kind of begin taking
desire seriously enough that it deserves attention it deserves let's look at this desire
what does it mean to have desire and rather than maybe a kind of a
simplistic understanding of Buddhism I'm just supposed to let go I'm just supposed to let go of everything let go
of desires let go of everything there is a time and place for that kind of approach but to have that be the the
broad swath what we do with our life it's not really what the Buddha was
teaching um but to go along with his emphasis he
talked about having desire for the practice for the path of liberation
and so to discover how do you hold the desire in a way that is inspiring for you that
it comes from a place of goodness and rightness and doesn't add stress to your life but if it may be if anything
reduces the stress and you're just happy to have this desire rather than having oh one more
desire one more thing to do and you know I have those long to-do list and now I'm supposed to do this too
um you know but not not like that but something like oh I'm so lucky I'm so
fortunate to have this this is a great thing and um in a sense one of the great
aspects of these four right efforts it's taking it's an application it's a way of
being a way of being with everything we can possibly do
no matter what we're doing we're looking at it from the point of view is how I'm
doing it and what's motivating it is it wholesome or unwholesome is it helpful or unhelpful
and um and then to uh does desire to not be involved with the unhealthy ways of
doing things and to desire the healthy ones and then how is that desire am I in a
hurry with desire I have so many to do things to do I'm in a hurry if you are in a hurry and trying to fill
your life or can you tap into the healthy form of Desire
is healthy for my desire come from some other place one of the paradoxes of of really strong
desire of you know neediness or craving or thirsting of wanting to do things even if we do it
out of fear you know fear of missing out or something is that it diminishes the wholesome
and sometimes the wholesome within us gets eclipsed entirely by all the
desires we have but if we find how to have wholesome Desires in a place where there's time
and space then the wholesome can well up the ways in which we do things can be
fulfilling in and of itself and we don't need to find fulfillment from accomplishing a lot of things we find
our fulfillment in the moment of doing something much more so
um so each of these four right efforts talks about taking up taking hold of the Mind
and with desire so the way that this the right effort is
often written translated it's a little bit
you know I think I often felt it was just I was tired by the time I read it so here's a common
translation of the it's also part of the each of the four right efforts that's similar for each one about
it's a it says um one makes effort
arouses energy exerts the mind and strives
um so that seems like a lot of uh work
but I want to read you a different translation that the one that I've made that uh some of some of the what the
original poly is left out in the English Trend this English translation so
um one takes up and takes hold of the Mind
so here one begins by being present for one's own mind one's
own inner life one takes hold and takes up
um so so you know our inner life let's say inner life everyone's inner life the mind this is important to engage and be
attentive to um so one takes up and takes hold of the
Mind and generates desire so one arouses one gives birth to desire
so there's a conscious intention here to look for that desire that is appropriate that's healthy
that's um you know so uh beautifully done like a piece of
art that you like to look on this desire one takes up it takes hold of the mind
and generates desire initiates
initiates courageous effort so the word initiates is there in the original
and the word for courageous effort is Viria
which is a very powerful word sometimes it
means power or strength and it's um sometimes it's correct translated I think maybe into Tibetan Buddhism is
courageous effort um someone who's a uh a warrior is
sometimes called a you know a word that's related to a very uh so courageous but I like the word
courageous effort that sometimes uh we have to have some courage to be present and for ourselves
and hear so it's a little bit has it's it's it's bringing some strength to it
um um so one takes up and takes hold of the
Mind and generates desire initiates courageous effort
for the non-arising of unwholesome states of mind
so that's the first right effort for today I want to introduce now the second one
and uh and this one goes takes up when takes up and takes hold of the Mind
and generates desire initiates courageous effort
for abandoning unwholesome states of mind
and this word uh pahana abandoned is a powerful word it's
different than just letting go Letting Go has more of more a sense of
letting go of it for the moment abandoning is Letting Go done with
wisdom and commitment and Clarity and a fullness this I'm going to put down this
I'm not going to be involved in anymore of course mostly they come back but there's a kind of a definite in this or
fullness or seriousness this I will abandon this I won't do anymore
and here again we have this kind of idea of living in a conscious mindful way that comes when you take hold of the
mind if take hold up take hold of your attention take hold of you know being here in the present moment
take it up be here so that when you're doing something you
do it wholeheartedly and here this right effort is
generate the desire to wholeheartedly abandon
whatever you're doing that's afflictive that harms you maybe it harms others as
well it's not necessarily it's not at all easy to abandon and let it go so just
say it so simply is uh you know can be confusing or even you know even
stressful but this we're talking about having the desire for this the healthy desire
taking the time to find that the definitiveness of clearness that you know I think I want to be
finished with this I've been critical of others in an aversive annoying way
and I'm done with this I've done this for so long it's not good for them it's not good for me I want to abandon this
aversive nature that I have this criticalness this cynicism
the resentment I have I've been caught in addiction which is
very difficult I want to undermine or under understate the difficulty of it
but still I've had enough and I want to now just you know I would
I want to have the desires here to abandon it and once that clear desire is there to
abandon it then we can engage engage in the process of
doing so so it might not just be snap our fingers and then we just do it it's um it's uh
you know then we practice the rest of the hateful path so that we can find a way to do that
so um um the second of the right efforts
is to arouse give birth to generate the desire
find the desire find the way to desire that you enjoy
it does require you to take some time to get to know what that kind of Desire
might be maybe it's a desire you arouse
when you're relaxed at ease having cup of tea looking out the window for something or
or maybe you can be in touch with that kind of healthy desire at the end of a sitting of meditation
so this is not an obligation to let go of unwholesome desires or a statement
having unwholesome mind States it's not a statement you're a terrible person if you have unwholesome states of mind
it's rather discovering something wonderful inside a wonderful desire
that cares for yourself that wants to engage in a process
of bringing these to an end so they can be abandoned put down once
and for all and maybe it's done in small pieces small steps
maybe it's done gradually over time maybe for today if you know you have
some afflictive unhealthy mind States and desires
that you don't want to kind of live by but you're caught in often maybe the goal for today is not to abandon them
entirely but to discover a desire to abandon them
so whenever they arise take the time to find a healthy desire one that you like
that you enjoy having in relationship to the things that you would like to abandon
and then rather than abandoning them entirely maybe you can less lessen the frequency
or their intensity today by 10 percent
and um and what would that look like just going to turn down the volume a little bit
as opposed to being caught up in the idea it should be all or nothing
so I hope you enjoy your desires take time today to look at them and explore
them and maybe enjoy the desire to
be done with some of the unhealthy unsupportive states of mind that you
might live with and maybe you'll enjoy
doing them 10 letters less so um thank you
very much and tomorrow we'll start the discussion about um
the third right effort which is the related to
um wholesome mind States thank you