so good morning everyone and welcome to IMC and those of you here and those of
you who might be With Us online
and a few announcements before we start the first is that um
yesterday I put out on the table the counter where the by the exit a whole
stack of the end of the year fundraising letters I don't know how how delighted you are
about receiving fundraising letters but if you're delighted enough but receiving it from IMC there's one there
you can you can pick up and I realized this morning that we've
been doing fundraising letters for 25 years end of the year
and the first time we did it was so we could be in the circumstance to buy a
place like this building here many years later it was so that we could have a retreat center and take care of
it and so all the kind of building and the kind of growing of imc's
a lot is attributed to those end of the year fundraising letters
anyway so if you want to read what I wrote I wrote the letter you're welcome to take one whether you
donate or not and then uh on um
I won't be here next week Max erstein will be here and the next time I'm teaching here at
IMC but also you know also online will be a Saturday December 10th now
that I guess I'm teaching the 7 A.M that week but um uh I'm here alone then
but uh on December 10th I'm doing a day long that's uh offered through Insight
Retreat Center there's information for it it's online it's on zoom and it's information is on
it about it on the what's new section of the home page of IMC if you're interested in doing a day-long
from home or someplace
so to give a talk
so imagine that you finally able to bring a friend along to
hear a Dharma talk someplace they've been resisting not wanting to come but you feel like they should
really you know learn about the Buddhism or something and so they finally agree to come
and the Dharma teachers hits that and starts talking and announces today I'm going to give a talk about
suffering and how important it is to address
suffering and in your mind you're going oh no I
finally got my friend here and this is going to be like this they're they're going to be turned off by this
and or imagine another time you bring another friend who finally would link to come but they're kind of cynical about
things skeptical and the Dharma teacher starts off by saying today
I'm going to talk about happiness and
oh no my friend is skeptical about all things
about this you know South Sacrament Buddhism can be or spirituality and you know and probably they're going to talk
about loving kindness and my poor friend is not going to never going to come back
so I don't know if any of you brought friends today but today I'm going to talk about
suffering and happiness
and then some of you go oh no my friend
so um but I want to emphasize how important happiness is for the path of
Buddhism Buddhist practice I think that it's underappreciated that it's a path of happiness and that
orienting oneself on this path to Buddhism to see what you can do
to become a happier person are there reasonable ways that you could Orient yourself and
navigate this world so that you're a little bit happier and delighted with
life with yourself and there are other ways that you can do the opposite
so I know some people might feel that it's very important to become Wealthy by
the time you're 29. and so you say well I'll be happy later
but this is not the time to be happy well that's you know maybe I don't know
what that is about but uh but then you're not really cultivating the factors for this path of Liberation that
Buddhism champions which has a lot to do with developing a
very significant useful supportive strategic
sense of well-being and then with that
addressing suffering this isn't this is well known since the
time of the Buddha in fact there's a there's a council of the Buddha giving Dharma talks
where the first thing he did is he elated and inspired the audience
and then he taught them about suffering so both right not one or the other so I
wanted to read the description of how the Buddha prepared people
so he could talk about suffering when the audience was ready
receptive free from the hindrances elated and confident
he expounded to them the teaching special to the Buddhas
suffering it's a little bit more but that's what you said for now
so you know I don't know if I can manage to do that today to all in one Dharma talk
to make you ready receptive free of hindrances elated and confident
but just the idea that that's kind of what the Buddha did I think that when I was younger in life
especially when I came out of Zen practice where it was mostly just about a direct penetration to the truth to
emptiness or something I would have thought this was manipulative you know they're kind of playing with
people's emotions getting them elated and all that we just want to we want the truth let's just deal with suffering directly
or something but I think that it can be helpful and useful and ethical
to promote being happy without it being necessarily
um you know manipulative or something saccharine
and it's important part of the path so why not talk about it and emphasize its importance
so then there's also a teaching about meditation practice where at some point in meditation also
to address suffering I mean that's kind of the specialty of Buddhism
however in meditation there also there's a description letting the meditation practice develop
and prepare you for encountering your suffering by going through stages of Happiness of
well-being and there's a series of them and it begins by doing something which evokes
or having something which evokes your gladness
your Delight your kind of a joy and uh and what is it that can be
evocative of that one of the things one of the primary one the Buddha talks about is something
called sadash Radha in Sanskrit uh usually translated as faith it could
also be confidence some people come to Buddhism and they hear about not they hear about suffering
and the importance of it but what they hear more importantly is there's a
practice and a path that leads to the end of suffering and they go wow
finally I meet someone who's really talking about suffering as it is without kind of painting it over or talking
about something else and and they have a pet they have a
practice for it this is inspiring I'm so glad to have found it finally
it's kind of a gladness Wells up other people have a gladness or
inspiration kind of I think of as gladness and inspiration being closely related they're inspired
I remember meeting people when I was a newer practitioner and seeing as people who had been
practicing for a long time and being so inspired by them so wow I've never met
someone like this they're seem ordinary enough they don't seem like they're putting on the errors
or being you know spiritually high in the clouds but there's something about them that really inspired a kind of
peacefulness and Joy or something in myself there's all kinds of ways you know to be
inspired one of the things that creates this gladness and joy that perplexed me when
I first came across it in Buddhism was the idea that your own ethics could be a
source of joy you know because I you know I didn't grow up with much I wasn't particularly
unethical but it wasn't like a place you know and it you know I was just a hippie and
you know we were kind of antinomian back then you know not not into
the hypocrisy of a lot of The Commandments and rules and all that
and um and so what I heard about people who were joyful about their ethics I thought
well I thought I kind of found mistrustful and I'd heard that in when I went to
Thailand that that's what taravad and Buddhists could have they were so delighted in their following the
precepts gave me misatisfaction and all that
and um and then I went to Thailand and I did a long retreat there 10 weeks long
and to my surprise about seven weeks into it I felt a kind of
strange feeling inside what is this strange feeling
and the best I could come up words to describe it I felt a kind of ethical
purity wow what is this and it felt kind of delightful to have
it there was a joy to it and I thought oh maybe that's what the joy is to feel you know it's not like an
evaluation or going through the checklist say well I don't do that I don't do that therefore I should be happy it was the source inside for ethics that
was just inspiring to me so um
so the so the Buddha talks about this that the idea of something that inspires
us inspires gladness and gladness is evaluative in nature you
have it's a conceptual oh yeah I have this experience I have this knowledge I've touched into something this is
really good and I'm so happy so glad that I've so inspired by this this thing that I've
come into contact with foreign then as we're inspired through gladness
that's said to create a momentum to practice and when we practice the excitement they
add the little bit agitation of gladness begins to dissipate
but the engagement finally now I'm doing it myself it's not just an idea
and as we do it there's something about the engagement in meditation at some
point that brings something called pity p-i-t-t-i
and uh I like to translate it as Joy some people say Gil that's too
sedated or too you know dampening it down it's rapture
and then I I like sometimes I just like to call it well-being there's something kind of inner sense of some people call
it a thrill it's a little bit energetic because it comes partly from or very
much from starting to get concentrated as we practice and as we get concentrated there's something maybe it releases you know
serotonin or something in in our system but the point being that something when when things become harmonized in the
mind and a Harmony between the mind and the body and things are kind of working together
without any stress so the mind or the heart begins
evoking or bringing forth something very different than it can evoke when it's
caught up in stressful thoughts and preoccupations and lost in thought
it's a kind of a joy it's kind of a miracle that happens this way
then as we practice further The Joy being content with it happy with
it being able to kind of put aside so many of the preoccupations we have because we're feeling this Joy
something in the body has a chance to relax a lot of the relaxation of the body has
to do with finally being present for your experience the body just wants to relax
if you just give the body half a chance it'll relax and some of us don't do that
and sometimes the tension in the body is unconscious we don't even know we're carrying it
I was so surprised when I started to meditate to discover that I could feel I
would feel more rested and more relaxed after I meditated first thing in the
morning that when I woke up from sleep I thought sleep was supposed to be the
premiere rest but in fact meditation that allows
something to rest deeper and a lot of that had to do with just being present the body wants to
relax to become and so the body relaxes
as the body relaxes that joy that we have gets quieter
settles the energy or the excitement around goes away and it gets replaced with happiness
well-being and that is usually not translated in
energetic terms like Rapture it's it's more Sublime some people actually translate this word the Pali word sukkah
as pleasure because it's a very deep embodied sense of well-being that just
feels so such Sublime pleasure everywhere
and then the Buddha says goes on and says with that sense of happiness
that's the condition that allows for some very deep concentration
if you're content already if you're happy if your body is happy
it's just nice to be here some people talk about it and I feel like I'm home finally
this is safe this is you know satisfying this is better than watching Netflix
this is good and um and uh and so there's a deep
satisfaction that allows something to settle more to unify to come together which is a lot
of what samadhi is concentration just deep willing to settle here
and that deep settleness here in the present moment with the mind at rest the
body at rest provides a new vantage point A New
Perspective just like the Buddha when he gave his Dharma talks people became ready
receptive free of the hindrances elated and confident though that that state of being that he
evoked in people prepared them they were ready right receptive prepared them to see and
understand something in a new way in fact when he starts teaching about suffering to that audience
it isn't that they then believe something new what happens when they listen to his
teachings about suffering the description is their Dharma eye opens some ability to perceive
is available we open we have New Perspective arises in the meditation path going through
gladness Joy relaxation happiness and samadhi also
gives the meditator A New Perspective to see and what is that
so imagine yourself really as contented and happy and satisfied as you've ever
been without being sleepy so here's the Earth and present maybe
you woke up and up from a wonderful nap and nothing has to happen nothing you
have to do anything and you do have thoughts that come through but the thoughts are like wispy
clouds that come through you so there's a thought that goes through and passes and he's looking at the dust I've done
nothing laying in bed after a nap and the sunlight comes in wow there's a lot of dust and just watching the dance of
dust through the sunlight you know or the Speckles on the ceiling yeah just
you know my thoughts come and they go and nothing is sticky nothing is grabby
it's just kind of just really nice to be there and then a thought arises
about some really big challenge at work that's really distressing for me and
anxiety producing for me or something and I see that thought work challenge
coming up but I'm so settled so quiet and so
peaceful they say oh look
there's thinking about that that work challenge and then we feel a little compulsion
arise somewhere maybe in the chest like
ought to get involved with this anxiety we've got to get and you say wait a minute
I don't have to be involved I don't have to pick this up this thought up
I can just let it go let you know pass through and there's a such a subtle place that
you actually have some choice oh I don't have to get involved in this though
and then it passes and then you're back to the Dust Dancing In The Light which feels so good
just nothing to do and peaceful and content and then you think about then certainly
it's been 50 years or something and suddenly there's thoughts about your
high school sweetheart comes up who who spurred you or whatever what's the
word you know it's kind of left you suddenly or something or and and um and like suddenly the anger
starts coming 50 years ago right but you're in this very nice state did
you see oh look at that it's fascinating that after 50 years I should feel this
compulsion towards anger let's not get involved with that I have better things to do today
and you have enough Choice there to not get involved and it passes and you watch all this stuff come and go
come and go wow this is something
and then you wonder you have this thought how can I live with this kind of peace
how can I just go through my life this way so I don't get caught in these things
that I always just get caught in in fact not I think about it I spend most of my days caught in
something I never realized that until I was had this deep peace that to watch things
come and go watch the tendency to get involved I want you to begin and watch it end I
had no idea that I was so and most of my day caught in things no wonder I wake up
in the morning still tense and so he's like how can I live in such
a way that I stay close to this piece so you think about it what would it take and first thing you occurs to you well
I think keeping this perspective active for me keeping the perspective where I see how
things arise see when they first appear so that I can see them as an appearing
phenomena with no more reality no more substantiality than just as a thought an
idea compulsion arising and so I have a chance to see it pass to Let It Go
seeing that all things come and go that's a good perspective okay
what else do I should I do well I've noticed that when I do get in really entangled
and Rich juicy good painful suffering ways
it's because I have a meat being mean
I'm being greedy wanting to send more sensual pleasures of all kinds
I'm a little bit cruel even I mean those those are cognitively complex
complicated activities of the mind to have those motivations
let's not do those okay that's the second thing let's let's avoid certain kinds of behavior and
motivations and then you think what else well
I've also seen that it's cognitively complex and involves entanglement takes me away
from this kind of peace if I lie a lot
how about if I not lie what else
I bet I've never you know it's never been an issue for me but I bet that if I
spend a lot of time killing people stealing from people
and running around doing sexual misconduct I think that that also puts me into this
more complicated cognitive world of of you know that I have to kind of plan
and hide and run around and escape and justify
that's complicated so
let's not do that what else
well I've been involved in work that harmed people that didn't do any good for this world
and that was so stressful for my mind and I've been involved it didn't do
things that were felt wrong to do in the world and that felt so much better
let's avoid work that causes harm
is anything else I should do well you should really take a good look at myself
and I see this from this New Perspective I have I see that when these compulsions
arise in the mind like if greed arises or hatred arises
or the kind of spinning spinning around in confusion and delusion and perplexity
that that actually doesn't feel good then I'm kind of caught again I've left
that kind of relaxed Place watching things come and go
let's not do those things I never noticed actually the opposite
there are certain ways that the Mind operates and thinks about things and where it's generous or it's kind
who it's wise that it comes so naturally it seems to
actually be part and parcel of this peaceful satisfying relaxed place
that I discovered at the end of this path of gladness Joy Tranquility
happiness and concentration so let's stay close to those good things
what else should I do I think I better stay attentive enough
to track all this I think I need to be mindful
stay mindful what else well it seems that a lot of this new
perspective is supported by being really settled concentrated still
let me live a life in such a way that I have access to a quiet concentrated
still mind great
what I just went through is the Eightfold Path
this is their apparently what the Buddha did when he was enlightened he went did
exactly the same analysis what keeps me close to this freedom I discovered penny
so when the Buddha gave this talk where he made people's minds
receptive ready receptive free of the hindrances
elated and confident he was putting their minds in a state
that now was ready for a new perspective and what was that news perspective
it was suffering that the arising of suffering the appearance of
suffering the cessation of suffering remember this
is what happened after the nap that you saw states of Mind thoughts
ideas arise and pass and you saw compulsions to be involved
in them come and you chose not to be involved let it all come trust the simple mind relax don't get caught in
anything see the arising and passing because if you get caught in it and
involved you won't see things come and go there's Freedom there almost like
between the ending of one thing in the beginning of the next there's peace there's space there's something
wonderful almost like that and then he taught them the path
sometimes called the path leading to the end of suffering and uh and this is the eighthful path
I like to think of it with the Buddha thought about it this way as well that it wasn't so much leading to to the end
of suffering it is but it also is how to live
from that place where is that freedom that ease
so happiness has a role in Buddhist
practice happiness prepares us to be able to see the world and ourselves in a new way
that's actually hard to do for suffering a lot Buddhist practice can help people who
suffer a lot can give us practices and perspectives and compassion and all
kinds of things that support the lessening with suffering coming to
having better relationship to our suffering finding our way with suffering but at some point this practice of
Buddhism is also about Awakening or staying close to developing our capacity for a
significant kind of well-being happiness
how often in your day do you allow yourself to be happy
how often in the day are you so involved in serious things
that you don't take the time to be delighted at what your circumstances are
the weather the sky the trees the people around you
maybe you have such important things to do that you can't really take the time to appreciate anything that's around you
or with you so I don't want if that your life is that important
I don't want to interfere but maybe for some of you it's not some
of the things you get involved in are not that important if an anthropologist from Mars
came to study you and looked at what you actually did through the day
what conclusion would they make about what human beings are all about
would it be like the best news in the universe or would be well maybe you should have
chosen someone else because the way my mind works I'm always
caught up in this and that and involved in this or that and being resentful or
so when they report back to Mars this person mostly spends their time thinking
about the past or they could write back to Mars and say this person
is mostly planning because they're always anxious that's what's that maybe that's what
human life is on the planet Earth is all about being anxious a lot of those people are anxious so
they must have I think it's a religion of anxiety they must worship it you should see what
they do and they had this special altar the sacrament they go to regularly in
which to kind of increase their level of anxiety they're really good at it it's a monitor
and uh so I think at first not for anyone here of course but there are people for whom
what we do in daily life regularly and repeatedly would not be the best representation for
what human beings are capable of if the anthropologists from Mars reported about us
I would propose that some of us don't have to be don't have such
important things to do all the time that we can take more time
to feel happy do you feel joyful to feel appreciation
to find things that are inspiring is that pollyanish is that saccharine
life is that a life then it doesn't realize that this is a serious World we're in there's a
lot of people suffering and we have to get Grim quickly or we are serious about the degree of
suffering that is in this world there's a lot it's heartbreaking what goes on in this world
but maybe just maybe we are better off with a new perspective about it all
in addressing it than the old perspective to have the Dharma eye open
and that's what the Buddhism is about and to have this Dharma eye open to be able to see in a new way
to see from the perspective of how things are coming and going Moment by moment
to see from a place of well-being subtleness happiness
and then from there let us address the suffering of this world
let's not ignore it let's not just be happy and then
forget everyone else so so the importance of happiness
and that the a full path is a recipe for
that happiness staying close to it the happiness of this New Perspective
and it's kind of a a kind of a cycle
that if you feel the happiness of this New Perspective
that strengthens the gladness The Joy the tranquility
the happiness and the ability to see things as they are better
which can produce more happiness more feeling of this is being inspired
and so it grows and grows so
today's talk was about happiness and suffering
and the point I wanted to make was the importance of happiness
I don't say it's easy to be happy but it might be
more available to you than you allow yourself to take advantage of or to touch into
and if you allow yourself to have more happiness perhaps it'll allow your meditation
to become more settled more contented more concentrated so that
it isn't just dust dancing and in in sunlight that you
that you see coming and going but there's a profound way of seeing this world
as coming and going and you
free in the midst of it
so those are my thoughts for today and um
we have a few minutes here we can take maybe a couple of questions if someone would like to ask or comments about this
or anything and then afterwards we can take some time and go outside in the parking lot those of you would like to
join join me out there we'll put chairs in a circle and
and uh we can have continue our discussion and out there you can also take off your mask if you want
Gail early in the talk you mentioned I think serotonin which
leads which he mentions
houses not so good do you have the other one mark
okay it's better Gill early in the talk you mentioned
serotonin and I think and that leads to a body chemistry kind of question
um I have this idea but that I'm not sure about that that
um that any any kind of getting what we
want kind of activity stimulates some body chemistry uh
serotonin or adrenaline or hormones that feels a lot like happiness
but maybe they have the seeds of some stress maybe these maybe these maybe this body
chemistry that gets stimulated has the seeds of stress
underlying them and that the greatest happiness the kind of
a dharmic happiness would be the kind of happiness that that Taps down
our body chemistry so that there's not strong emotions
happening instead there's just kind of like pure awareness and and a letting go
does that does that bringing body chemistry into
the Dharma like I'm doing now does that make sense to you
I'm not qualified to answer I mean I shouldn't have brought up serotonin I hardly know what it is
that's what I was asking you because I don't know and so you know to answer questions about body chemistry is
something I'm not really capable of doing but I think that the when Buddhist
classic Buddhist point of view there's a difference between the mental emotional
physical activity that we're engaged in which leaves traces and those it doesn't
leave traces and so the traces of
of uh you know what those traces are that there are not that are not helpful
for us not useful for us uh the negative karma in a sense uh is uh that's what
Buddhism talks about Karma being left behind and so maybe it's maybe just chemicals
that are you know stuck in our system but there are good chemicals too there's good states of mind that can get quite
strong and persist and create very different conditions that persist and whether this practice makes us kind of
kind of emotionally neutral dampens down our emotions um I think it's a it's a
it depends on the person there are people who whose emotions
swing between very dramatic states of well-being and very dramatic states of suffering emotions of
suffering Despair and all kinds of things that are directly connected to what they're clinging to
write the clinic directly connected to their attachment to self-identity
and so for those people as their clinging reduces the swings won't be as much
the other people who cling the and the way they cling Narrows the range which they have
they're not going to budge they're going to be frozen kind of like and just maybe they'll smile you know and and so they're damping down
and for them as they relax they're clinging they begin having a much wider
range what the right range is for and for people is a very individual
and there shouldn't be any comparison to others what the only thing is get out of the way and don't add clinging to make
it worse this helps thank you yeah or maybe one more if you have any
so a build button in the quarter
thank you for the talk uh so nice to be here this is my first time back since
since it's the shutdown um so I just got through watching a global
Joy Summit it was a multiple day thing it had speakers from
all sorts of you know from contemplative sciences and you know neuroscience and
different spiritual leaders and it was really amazing and it started with
um a documentary that is available to everybody uh where Desmond Tutu and
Dalai Lama it's a if you look for them and and joy it
comes up and it's it's just really timely what you're talking about also with the Eightfold Path well on its way
here um but one of the biggest things because both of them have gone through such
tremendous suffering their countries have and they have but to see the two of
them together was really remarkable they were like lovers because they couldn't keep their hands off of each other
and and it was I guess what what I took away from that and and today
um it's not about denying suffering at all absolutely not these people these two
leaders absolutely faced it but it's almost like a choice to
purposely make space for joy and to and to to see it to see the opportunities for
it to claim it in a sense when it's available I I guess that's what I took
away from it it's in no way is it meant to deny the suffering at all it's more
of a purposeful claiming of joy is that about
in line with with what you're saying I think it's close enough uh I think I
like what you're saying right so I feel a little hesitant about claiming it seems a bit strong but I think that
uh there are all kinds of ways in which people
are there are people out in the world who are trying to make you miserable I mean terrorists for example and
politicians and all kinds of people and it's a revolutionary act to not buy into it
and it's a revolutionary and Powerful act not to give into fear not to give into anger when there's a lot of people
coming at you with with giving you a reason or ordinary motivation to be that
way so to appreciate how how radical it is to stay happy
but how to do it so it's genuine is the art there's so many people who do it in
a fake way who do it as a veneer and that doesn't help either
so I think meditation is one of the means by which to keep it sincere or
authentic for ourselves because you if you're really practicing mindfulness and
being present you'll feel that the veneer doesn't work
the pretending doesn't work and or the insistence
but I think that I believe that the examples you give are fantastic examples
of people who have stood up against the suffering and the evil of this world and
demonstrated an alternative in such a way that inspired people to live a
different way so yes so um please
if you want to change this world in a very good way be happy
please and it's not easy for those of you who
struggle with this topic I don't want to pretend that it's easy but it's really worthwhile to be on this
path and there is a path that you can take and sometimes the path is slow but it's
really worthwhile and to knowing you're on a path is one of the recipes for at least gladness if
not for joy so thank you very much and those of you
would like to stay we'll go uh there's folding chairs in the little cabinet just around the corner there in the
other room take one with you outside and then we'll we can meet outside and continue our discussion thank you