so a good monday to all of you
warm welcome and um
i hope that at the beginning of this week finds you well and if not i hope that the unfolding of the
week goes well for you
our companion for this day this morning for this sitting
is uh the statue on the imc altar statue of the buddha
and it's more than just a statue it is a depiction
of a particular event in the life of the buddha or to say it more accurately perhaps not
just an event but in the story of the buddha and there's a custom sometimes in
different rooms in a buddhist monastery the buddha will have a different
will depict a different story in uh some rooms where mostly the dharma is
taught the buddha is hands are in a teaching gesture
in a place where meditation is emphasized he's often in this posture here
where it's a meditation posture and it depicts the moment of his
awakening or just before his awakening and uh his right
hand is reaching over his right knee to touch the earth and i'm literally blocking it
the um and
um it's a story that is inspiring for many people it's meant to be here to
uh represent a story that becomes our own story it's a story of
sitting in the middle of our life the buddha sits very stable strong and the uprightness of the buddha
is not an uprightness that turns away from anything but sits in the middle and the depiction
if is an occasion where the chaos and temptations and
and worldly challenges of life are all around the buddha
and he doesn't he has an equanimity he has a balance in the midst of all all the challenges
that are coming in the story that is depicted in the statue and then he's challenged in some deep
way about his right to be awakened and he reaches and touches the earth
calls upon the goddess of the earth as a witness that to his right to his the
appropriateness the naturalness of him becoming awakened
and this reference to the earth can can evoke many different things for
different people for some of us for me it evokes the naturalness of it all or
the way in which our are
that we are part of the earth part of this nature and that any movement to
deny that pull away from it separate ourselves from that
with greed hatred and delusion is a loss and we can come back
to that place of home of freedom which is kind of our place in nature
so that's a story and the statue depicts a story and in a sense when we sit down to
meditate we are participating in a story and a story of
finding peace a story of waking up a story of compassion
of discovering engaging in this world not to fix it
not to run away from it not to return to some pristine
way in which things used to be but rather to wait to
to find our equanimity or calm our peace it's a journey in a sense it's a story
in a sense every time we meditate we could tell the story of that meditation of how it unfolded and what the
challenges were and sometimes this idea of that that it's a journey
a story that a journey that we can narrate
can be a distraction for sure but it also can be an inspiration
it can give us a sense of possibility and encouragement inspiration to
yes here i am on this journey let me stay in the journey let me stay in the story
as opposed to slipping away into other stories of uh
that maybe are depressing or just not to the point or worse
so in this story we are here to be present
to begin with establishing our presence with our body
and everyone will find everyone has a little different body so the posture we take will be different
from each other some will sit cross-legged some in a chair some lying down some of you might
actually be standing or doing walking meditation during this time
but to enter into your posture whatever your posture is
with a dignity and a metaphorical uprightness
here is the place to be established to be rooted
here in the middle of this world
of our your world to sit with a posture
expressing some level of stability
calmness rootedness here
and then to gently close your eyes
and to
appreciate this body that we have whatever the challenges of the body
might be and it sends this body
is our companion
this body has to sit with respect and dignity for this body
to feel it and sense it as it is
and with appreciation with love with compassion
to take a few long slow deep breaths three quarters full
and long exhale releasing relaxing as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and with a normal breath to continue this entering into your body
may be similar to lowering your body into a
warm or refreshing pool of water entering into your body
from the top down with the relaxing of the face
the relaxing of the shoulders
with the relaxing of the chest
the softening of the belly
and within this body
to become attuned to the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and there is a kind of communion or companionship with the buddha and
breathing and that he too meditated mindful of his breathing
and so that some of the sensations your experience of breathing
are the same as his
and as we sit here we're engaged in a journey a story
of relaxing the mind enough and focusing the mind enough
so that we allow ourselves to just be here in this moment's experience breathing
touching the earth that's within that we are
so
if you find yourself distracted re-enter
the story of waking up here
of being present here rooted grounded in your lived experience
see it as a journey a process of entering the present more
and more fully
breath by breath moment by moment
give yourself to the journey
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to appreciate anything that we can be appreciated
about this journey of meditation
to appreciate maybe how you are right now
the relief of coming to the end the ways in which you are now maybe a
little bit calmer or centered than you were before
particular 30-minute story is coming close to an end
and it is what it is the journey
and there's a tradition in buddhism to never end a journey of practice
without dedicating the value of the practice
for the benefit of others that in whatever ways that can
this can work seen and unseen intentionally and unintentionally
we aspire we wish that the story doesn't end here with us
but that rather the story continues into the world
benefiting the world from our efforts here may it be that
spreading from us the hundreds of us that are meditating
together this morning may there be irradiating glow or
radiating momentum
of benefiting the world may the world be better
safer [Music] happier more peaceful
because we've meditated here today and may we contribute to that
possibility in the people we encounter the places we go
the things that we do today
and may this journey story of benefiting the world continue
for a long time [Music]
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this monday morning
dharma talk beginning of the week and as usual there will be a five part
series and today i'm inspired to
have the week be about story and to um
have a five-part talk um using the word story as a
kind of a um um
each letter to stand for some aspect of story
so today it'll be source source story
and then trapping stories stories that trap us
opening stories the stories that release us from the trap
and then is re uh releasing the stories
and then there is uh for why i'd like you to use the word yes
and what that means we'll have to wait until friday to understand the yes in relationship to this theme of stories
and the buddhism this insight vipassana tradition
historically has put a lot of emphasis on the fourth
theme of the week releasing stories letting go of stories learning how not to live in stories as
we meditate not to live in the storytelling mind discursive mind that's
talking to itself and thinking and and um and learning to release
and that's certainly a very important part of this path of mindfulness practice and
something that we learn but sometimes it gets overdone and such a way that we overlook
really understanding deeply the nature of
how stories work in our lives and their centrality and their importance
that not a few people have pointed out that stories are
really crucial to human society and human beings it's how we understand ourselves how we form
identities the stories we tell our children are not just stories they're often
passing values and understanding of self and understanding of the cultural self how we fit into
society and how we are and the stories are what conveys
all kinds of cultural values and
identities of how we fit into this world and
and religions have been pointed out that as much as we might focus on religions as being a set of doctrines
that for most people what is most animating and engaging with people around religion is the stories of
a religion that somehow we identify with the stories there's there's a narrative
there in which maybe people feel they can participate in or they enter into or
inspires them for how they live their lives because life is a narrative life is uh
in a sense could be something we explain through a story of what happened you know if a friend asks you how did it
go today and you tell them the story of parts of the day and um and they have a bit better sense
of how you are perhaps it's much clearer
so stories are quite important and um the um
and some of the stories that we carry inside of ourselves that influence us are somewhat
subconscious we don't always know think of it in terms of a story and so i call this a source story
and and maybe it's a bit dramatic to use as an example but it
speaks i think to how central stories can be or events narratives that really shape a person
is that um
for many years i've been going to san clinton state prison and haven't done it now the next last
few years because of the pandemic but i'll visit a particular program a
year-long kind of mindfulness-based program um
anti-violence program that helping some certain prisoners deal with their
violent past deal with their own past and their difficulties and really confront
themselves in a very deep way and the group of prisoners about 30 who do the program every year are really are
become each other's challengers and each other's best friends supporting each other to really
take a deep look at their lives at the origins the source of the violent
life that they lived and most of the men in the group of 30 have
killed someone so it's pretty bad what they've done but what's remarkable is to be there and
discover that each of them had a sore story an original
event that happened that became the primary pain that they carried with them
that became was the was the um
the pain from which they they acted violently in the world
unresolved festering pain from some event in their life a story
often having to do with a parent often having for these men having to do with a father who
was violent at home who was violent to them violent to their mother or a father who was killed
and then just you know the trauma that a young child that they went through
it was so difficult no one then supported them no one helped them they were left with their pain and started
acting out and to get away from the pain to somehow
try to feel better in this very dysfunctional way and without these prisoners taking a deep look at the
source story the source event and really coming to terms with it
the transformation out of their violent life can't really happen
and it's remarkable to go there and watch to see them grapple and struggle with this and and come out to the other end and
some of these men that i've met you know that they become deeply transformed and
changed it's inspiring to see so each of us probably have some source
story maybe it's maybe a series of stories that have created an a a attitude
an orientation a belief about this world that we live in
and and those stories it's kind of a story that led that conditioned us and we carry that with us
so the source story is something like um
we when we see the world and go outside we might see that everyone is dangerous
there's danger everywhere and no matter who we meet the first instinct is to be afraid of them
to be mistrustful of them certainly it's wise to have some mistrust of some people and be afraid of
some people but to have that as the policy the de facto orientation
pro probably was something that happened in our youth that uh some event that conditioned us
that led us to believe that something may be dangerous happened to us
other people might have a story of hope that they've somehow taken in a story
that's been told over and over again and they have idea that there's a hope of getting somewhere of attaining
something sometimes the hope is unrealistic the hope of becoming rich the hope of
becoming famous um the hope of becoming a movie star
and um so the um um
so what's the story we've been told so what's the source story of your life
what have you what kind of orientation story attitude policy do you carry with you
about other people about yourself are those stories
happy stories are they debilitating stories and people who investigate
the narratives that people live their lives by sometimes have
divided narratives into three types the narrative that there's some kind of
normal life to come back to that's been disrupted and the story is how do we get back to
what we had the other story is that the world is dangerous and chaotic and
it's not going to get any better and it's just going to get worse and so we have to do the best we can to
protect ourselves and to keep the world at bay or keep others at bay or
and that's all about our own protection a third story is that of the quest
uh that uh yes the world is maybe dangerous it's chaotic it's things change all the time and there's no
normal to to go back to but there is a possibility of of engaging
in a journey to freedom to peace to transformation to
wisdom to make the best out of the situation and be personally transformed
to become a better person that's independent of the situation that we're in
and so the quest is the one that i think is most empowering
and the most realistic the idea of returning to some pristine state
is never going to happen when life is always changing the idea that um
uh it's all gonna downhill from here that it's a world is chaotic in a terrible place we just have to do our best to
protect ourselves or or be afraid or be angry or that everything
um is also not necessary so it's very debilitating
um the idea that i'm chaotic that i'm a mess that i'm somehow incapable or terrible
person that's a story that uh that has no hope and no possibility in
it and um and then there's the quest
and that uh we don't get bogged down by the stories but where it's a story beyond
stories a story out of the debilitating stories it's a story to
discover how to be free so the source story
this brief words that i've met i've said today i don't know if they you know speak well enough for your
particular situation but you might spend some time thinking about uh what is the source story what's the what what
stories what events narratives situations in your life um either a particular one or
some kind of pervasive kind of ongoing way of how you were raised something
what kind of uh world viewed as i provided you
what kind of philosophy what kind of story about what this life is about
have you learned and is there something that is deeper than maybe you're fully conscious of
and it might not be a big story it might just be an attitude or a belief
an approach to how we are emotionally as we go through the world
but to see the source or story and maybe there's a sore story that um
that is the the origin for so much of how you live your life understand yourself who you
are and um
so story i'm doing this uh theme partly i think inspired by
um a continuation over the last little while talking about emotions and anger and grief
and it's maybe a continuation this emotion theme because uh the chronic emotions of our
life most likely are connected to some story what is that story
and how do you tell that story and is it the right story does the story
change over time what's the source story
for the story you tell of your life so thank you
and um tomorrow we'll do um
trapping stories how some stories trap us in their in their grip in their
their in their web thank you