okay so so hello and welcome everyone to happy
hour so lovely to see you to be with you at this time wherever you are joining
from um this world and whatever the weather might be externally and internally wherever you
are so so for tonight's practice um
i'd like to invite our attention um to
to the joy of generosity joy of generosity in a particular way to actually treat
not just generosity because when i say generosity maybe what is conjured up in many people's minds is giving giving
money giving resources giving gifts i'm not just talking about that yes that
of course is one aspect of generosity but generosity includes so much more really it's
generosity of spirit generosity of our hearts and the way that we can give others the
benefit of the doubt in the way that say when we see
someone else's success we can feel happy for them even if it's
something that we would want we we don't say oh well i wish my name was there you
actually have this sense of generosity oh yay yay
feeling happy so mudita vicarious joy as an act of generosity of spirit
as if it were your own goodness as if it were your own
well-being your own happiness your own success because really
on the ultimate level there is no separation between you and
the other there is no self and the other or the given or the
gift or the receiver or the giver it's we we are so
intricately amazingly interconnected
that again through through our limited sense of this human life we see
our separation me you mine yours etc but and
and on an ultimate level it's all us
it's all this goodness this beauty of
of divinity of buddha nature whatever word you want to call it by that it
expresses itself through these actions of kindness generosity goodness good will
so one way again that could be seen is that we do in in our limited perception until our
perception opens up or there might be many moments that actually our perception opens up and
maybe closes down again um that
we do we practice we keep practicing we incline our minds
as a way of expressing as a way of expressing this goodness this ultimate
goodness and beauty in all of us and
another way also to see that is that
generosity goodness beauty um
all these beautiful um
goodnesses in the world need to be expressed through us beings
so so in some ways it is said that divinity needs us to express itself
divinity buddha nature goodness god whatever words you want to put it needs
us humans to express love to express goodness to express
generosity to express giving others the benefit of the doubt so
so it is actually through our being and through are these seemingly small actions of every day
that goodness is co-created it is expressed in the world
so i'll pause there are so many ideas there these are some things i've been sitting
with um in my own practice so so
i'd like to invite you to let the words drop away now so much
and let's just practice let's just practice with some of these themes let's
practice with some of these themes that i will invite us and if you're new
great whatever you need to know will be shared with you during the guided meditation so
so landing arriving arriving in your seat
ah arriving in your body
letting go letting go of all the words letting go of thoughts
arriving arriving here in this moment
in this body this human body
breathing sitting
just here wonderfully here connecting with each in an out
breath in the abdomen just to settle and arrive some more
to tell the soil of presence here
here
now now
this breath this breath coursing through
your lungs your body filling it with oxygen
both yours and not yours
a gift
can you receive this gift in this moment with appreciation
gift of this breath
each moment a fresh gift and new
arrival each breath
first breath is in breath
this outbreak
receiving generosity offered to us
is just as important of having a generous heart
of generosity that gives both receiving and giving
receiving opening up her senses to receive
the good that's offered in this moment not making pain suffering challenges the
only measure of our attention opening up our senses
yes there might be challenges difficulty heartbreak
heartache that too that too and
and goodness
the gifts of this moment
a body that works well enough a mind that is clear enough
enough safety to be sitting and practicing
safety from the elements in this moment enough sustenance
to feel this body and the gift of this breath
this air
this life is being alive
relaxing the body receiving opening the heart to receive
appreciatively the goodness in this moment
now as we fill we feel our lungs
our lungs are filled on their own we're there
our bodies nourished by oxygen by the gifts of this moment
fighting fighting our heart to open and share
its goodness as an expression as a reflection
perhaps even as a wholesome
duty
to our inner goodness
by the nature or the divine whatever words we call it
tell our hearts to express co-create
goodness kindness generosity
by bringing to mind someone
who has some good fortune
perhaps starting with someone easy they don't have to have good fortune in
every aspect of their life but some aspect that's going well
and as if it were ours as if it were our happiness our goodness
celebrating
it is ours others happinesses are our happiness
for a moment what if we just dropped just simply dropped
the sense of separation it is our goodness it is our happiness to celebrate
it is our joy i am happy for you i am so happy for you
as if it were my own happiness it is my own happiness
i wish you i wish your happiness to increase
i wish this happiness not yours or mine i wish this goodness to increase
i wish this goodness happiness to never end
may it continue made never cease
may grow
now if you wish maybe moving to someone was just a little more
challenging
still bringing to mind their good fortune [Music]
their gladness as if it were your own no separation this human family
and again if this relationship you're about to bring up there's been some hurt
not to condone
see perhaps unskillful and hurtful behavior
and can we still relate is it possible maybe not
this relationship in which case it's okay don't judge yourself but is it okay to still
relate to this person's humanity feel happy for their happiness good
fortune knowing that there might be some repair some forgiveness
it still needs work that isn't just swept under the carpet
it's acknowledged but we can still have spaciousness in heart i feel happy
for this being
you might be surprised
i'm happy for this happiness
for this good fortune
in the world made increase
may never end
i'm happy for your happiness
taking your place as if it were my own
we are not so different you and i after all us human beings
we have so much more in common
in our humanity
having bodies that hurt that age that die
hopes aspirations challenges pain sorrow
i can be happy for your happiness for your goodness
may there be more of it for you
is it possible to see yourself in the shoes of the other person living
their life with their hopes and dreams their challenges their physicality
because life is so random you could have been born as them they could have been born as you
you could have had the same perspective on life as they do
opinions behavior
we are such a product of our environment
our culture or family upbringing
or genes
it is all dependently arisen dependent on
so many causes and conditions
can you take their perspective
even if so different from yours
from this perspective letting there be generosity of spirit of
heart as much as is available right now
for the last minute of this practice period
being generous towards yourself for whatever this practice period was or
wasn't distracted sleepy it's okay it's okay
you did your best you did your best you've planted seeds
and that's more than good enough
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes for reflections
for questions comments and in the spirit of offering
your reflections for the benefit of sangha community
if there was an aha moment or if there was even something challenging or difficult it's
richard see your hand please am i unmuted yes you are unmuted
oh one of my teachers uh who loves to teach the perimeters
is always telling us that gratitude considers she considers gratitude the 11th paramate
and and when you were talking about receiving generosity it sort of it rang a bell for me as because she's
really getting it she really is having us get into gratitude practice all the time
yeah yeah great yeah it's it's so interesting because um
yes there's so many places that gratitude fits
in the practices i mean one one place is as you said this teacher who was putting it
as the 11th parame for those who may not be familiar with that terms
is 10 teachings the 10 perfections 10 qualities of the heart and also
so it's a perfection it's a beautiful quality of the heart also another couple of places and one
place that actually i usually put it is in the brahma viharas in the four brahma viharas with mudita with vicarious joy
when you feel happy for the happiness for the good fortune of others
when you turn it to yourself when you're happy for the good fortune of yourself
oh that's gratitude it becomes gratitude you become grateful there's no other way
to be happy for your own good fortune without it being expressed or felt as gratitude so so given that this is
happier and we covered brahma vihara's gratitude is definitely part of the brahma be heard so that's something else
for you to to bring in also to further further um plant
in your practice richard thank you bella i see your hand please and
there um i i was able to think of the first
person that they have joyful media for
the second person i wasn't able to come up with a distinct person that i knew was doing better or i knew how they were
doing and who i had difficulties with and i ended up cycling through a number
of people that i you know where i had maybe not the best relations
the odd thing was it actually came much easier than i i thought it would be possible so i don't know i followed instructions
but it actually went okay i love that bill that's fantastic that
is so great yay you know as
as you know by now these practices take um some creativity and i just love
that you didn't give up like well i don't have a person okay i'm done this is hard i can't you know like oh yeah
well let me let me try it in this other way let me kind of cycle through these people like great fantastic
inc creativity is absolutely uh encouraged and what i love about your
practice report is that it was easier than you thought like yes you could feel happy for this pers
for these persons that you had some you know a little bit of unresolved something with
beautiful what a lovely report thank you bill thank you
and debra i see your hand please well similarly
i but i found it sad that i couldn't find a lot of people in my
kind of in my close circle that are really thriving right now it's quite the opposite and
but what was helpful was toward the end you talked about just finding generosity for people and there
had been today a few people that really irked me just really
let me down you know and so then i realized oh i can use the generosity there too so
that was helpful nice but i had to search for people like way outside of my
people i don't even know you know like successful whatevers yeah and and i know
that if i knew them i would realize there probably wasn't anything to
to practice with because i think a lot of people you know having challenges so so this is what
i'll say actually deborah i appreciate that you brought this in and this is a line of invitation or instruction i fit
but it might have been just once and it might have gone unnoticed which was the person may not be happy in every
aspect of their life there could be just one aspect of their life that they're happy about so so that's what actually
makes this practice um work otherwise you're right if you
you know people well you love them and you know everybody has sorrows everybody has challenges it's there's not a single
person especially the time of the pandemic right and i was like oh yeah this is great and like me
your happiness in every aspect of your life increase so don't try to do the practice that way
don't because as you said that's the problem you would run into like yeah yeah
maybe slump some i don't know figures out there whose lives i don't really know yeah maybe they're happy but but
find someone for the first part of the practices that you know and and there's an aspect of
their life that's going well so yes maybe they're having financial trouble maybe
you know their health is not great but oh they're in this really loving relationship that really supports
them may your happiness continue may it never end so you see that that modification
there yeah and so may that help that work better for you yeah
great uh yeah so you you say you're if you want to add more you're welcome
to you found that you were happy for them yeah yeah i found that i couldn't find the
the places where i wasn't feeling happy for their happiness like yeah i would think of people that have
you know success in some area that i'm still working on but i do feel happy for them so it was really a stretch to like
say oh but i i mean i'm kind of thinking of it as jealousy i see i see i
understand now what you what what you're saying and the distinction i see it wasn't every aspect of their life it was that well
yeah even the things you would like in your life when they have them you're still happy for them beautiful
what a beautiful you know how beautiful to to to know and you already know it but also rediscover
reconnect with that generosity of your own heart wow even i even though i want this for myself i have hap you know i
can be generous with this i don't have to get jealous or envious or tight beautiful that's like it
happens though but it just didn't happen tonight i'm sure it happens i'm not you know perfect none of us are are perfectly enlightened
and and yet it's let's celebrate the areas let's celebrate the areas of our
heart that are generous yeah thank you for i know you're trying to bring in humility yes and and also let's help
celebrate beauty where there's melanie i see your hand we'll make this last comment before we go into groups
i'm amazed please everyone here is how you sort of generous and autonomous everyone is meanwhile i was like
struggling a bit um but i kind of had two examples and i noticed the difference in that one of them was like
the person i talked to um and it's very future looking like the thing that she has that was making her
happy i hope to like one day having the future and so then it was like really easy to
like feel very warm and comforted and it felt very like not zero-sum and then i noticed the contrast
with another question i was thinking of where i was like this should be easy i should be happy i felt stuck i was like
oh but i'm kind of annoyed because i used to have that thing and now i don't have it anymore and like should back
prevent me um there might be something there like it's
easier to you know like the difference of how it feels to
have to feel something that's gratitude but it's truly doesn't feel like a zero-sum game versus
you know when you do have those feelings it goes and it's interesting for me to see the contrast in myself
yeah interesting so thank you for sharing that so what i'm hearing says i went was future oriented there was a
sense of aspiration like oh yes i'm happy for what you have that inspires me whereas you notice like how interesting
when it's past oriented there's a sense of loss almost loss and
and um it's inviting you what i'm hearing and and correct me if there's more that you're saying that i'm missing
but but there's a sense of oh this is interesting you know it's not a zero-sum game i know that oh sweetheart what's
going on here like there's some curiosity is that what i'm hearing you say yeah yeah yeah beautiful yeah beautiful
investigation lovely thank you for sharing that yeah may you discover more
that in this non-zero sum game of of goodness in the
world so dear ones let's uh transition to
small group practice groups of roughly size three or so
and the invitation is to uh just uh we'll start with about
15 seconds of silence meta for one another and then you can share as little
or as as much as you like about your practice with each other really with generosity of spirit
generosity practicing we've been practicing with our eyes closed and silently but can you actually not do it
with a couple of other human beings practice generosity with a couple of
other human beings such a precious sandbox uh to be able to to do these
little groups so here we go i'm going to open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we have just about a minute
so if there are any uh reflections that came up burning reflections you'd like to share you can type them in chat raise
your okay kneel i see your hand shut up go so how do you deal with someone who you
are in direct competition with right right where they're winning could
you know in some ways mean you're losing yeah yeah i i trust it's it's more
challenging right it feels more challenging so um [Music]
yeah it's um [Music]
i think it's it's a case where a different framing because if we enter
it as a zero-sum game of winners and loses you know if we enter it as a
finite game versus an infinite game are you familiar with the concept of finite versus infinite games yeah so if you
enter it as an as a finite game and set it up as winners and loses then that's a
that's a frame that is stuck for it's a particular perspective that is is valid
too and yet what i invite is actually shifting shifting and looking at it
slightly different there are ways to look at it differently also not to say
saying it the way of winning and losing is wrong is just one way what are some other ways
so look at it that way too i yes not not to negate it but are there other ways
that this could be seen as and this whole practice and not actually
practice in general is about ways of seeing the ways we see something so
i'm not going to give you a recipe but i'm going to invite creativity what are some other ways this could be seen and
this is a longer conversation and it's already 701 so so i'll just leave you with this invitation
not to negate this is one way yes valid worldly there
are many other ways that it could be seen so i'm going to invite your creativity and and perspective shifting so maybe
we'll pick this up another time neil is that okay that's great thank you yeah thank you so
much so so dear ones we have come to the end of
yet another happy hour thank you so much for practicing with sango for cultivating
your heart for your own sake and the sake of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves [Music]