there ah so hello
good to see you good to be with you this uh in the U.S the eve of
this holiday we call Thanksgiving giving thanks giving thanks and there's
so much to say about this holiday and of course it's complicated and and
um challenging history um
just give a nod to that acknowledge that and uh
what I'd like to perhaps um
bring in tonight for our reflection is this practice of
of appreciating appreciating appreciating
giving thanks gratitude
um or affirming goodness affirming goodness that's one way we can think of
the practice of appreciation gratitude affirming goodness
are appreciating and and we can also appreciate
um what you know we we often we often um tend to like or appreciate or be
grateful for what is good what is Pleasant but it may not necessarily always be
that way can we also be can we open up and appreciate what is
even if it's not pleasant if it's not [Music] um
if it doesn't feel good in the moment so so just to give you an example I just
recently been sick with the flu as I shared earlier and still recovering still you might hear it in my voice a
bit and um and I want to relate also another practice in this story so let me just
bring in another yeah so so I want to bring in the theme of of appreciation
given that in the US at least this is the week of Thanksgiving so this holiday
of giving thanks appreciation turning our mindset so I want to bring another theme in and
um this is um uh thanks to Christine one of the
regulars at happy hour who sent me an email and I think she also sent an email
similar email to to happy hour with a local
singer songwriter that she likes and the name of the songwriter is Leah and
her Channel on YouTube because I am Leah and and Leah has a lot of songs on on
gratitude and on love and and uh her song so many of them are like mini
Dharma talks so so um so one of them that Christine sent and you can look at your mailbox later
please don't do it now oh is this song that inspired Christine and I did watch
it too and it's quite lovely so this this singer-songwriter as this song about
um that's the what's called three three magic words and uh
um in many ways we talk about this theme we teach this thing we practice it
together and these three magic words not surprisingly are I love you I love you
foreign and and the idea here with this practice which I want to bring in actually and
weave in and we've practiced this actually um here um but the idea when you say I love you
isn't so much oh I I have romantic love for you and and I want you and an
attachment and I expect you to love me back no that the idea of these three magic words is is when you open yourself
up um to appreciating and you can say we can say I love you to the sun I love
you or or the leaves I love you or the Blue Sky I love you or or or
um anything else that's in your life your neighbor I love you you know we may not even know that the person who's challenging for you I love you yeah you
you keep expanding my my edges you I love you because I can be more human
through you instead of thinking oh you know I'm enlightened perhaps or or or whatever my heart gets to expand I love
you so so hearing the song This I love you
song as she sings it you can check it out later it's just very sweet I love you this I love you that I love you this
guy I love you the earth I love you the tree I love you person who's walking by
I love you this sense oh opening up opening up opening your heart up so I
was uh this was in my mind today and I was um I was trying it on for size and and what
I invite you to to to to to play around with it as we'll explore in a moment is
I'll see what happens in your mind see what happens in your mind when you try
it on so and some reactions might be actually humorous might be funny when you try it on and see what the reaction
is so as I was trying it on today or I was outside I always love you Blue Sky yeah I made my heart actually open up
more to really appreciate that wow it's it's the fall and it's sunny today wow
or the fact that I can be out today I'm not so sick like the past few days I love you Skye I love you body I love you
and then and then my mind turned to oh the flu virus I love you virus I'm like
oh that's funny that's a funny thing to say I love you virus so humor came out
this sense of this this stance of of holding this relationship ship oh huh do
I love this virus well I don't exactly love it but but you know it's been a part of me it's been hanging out with my
body for a few days so so it it opens up different perspectives it opens up
different perspectives not to always be fixed in a particular way we see things
so for me this particular you know the three magic words I love you brought up a sense of uh humor appreciation kind of
releasing the way perhaps I usually relate so so so joining this these three magic
words practice with the theme of appreciation and gratitude uh this being
the week of quote-unquote Thanksgiving is let's try it on for size and see what
happens let's see what arises um is it more appreciation of something
that is might it be a different perspective it might be humor maybe it's resistance and if it's resistance it's
fine too like no no this thing I I I don't want to open up to it but maybe
these three magic words open our hearts a little more to something and
especially with respect to ourselves what if I what if you say I love you to yourself and you really mean it and if
resistance arises you you hang in there with the resistance anyway I've said a
lot already lots of themes but let's just ah leave all the words and
practice together and see what happens
now let's arrive let's arrive in our seats
ah let's get into our meditation posture sitting
up with as much integrity respecting the form
letting our hands be on our lap
and if you need to lie down the body needs care in that way that's okay too but I'm going to assume for the most
part that you're sitting up you're on a cushion or a chair
and that your feet your legs are
well rooted on the Earth your spine is straight upright
letting go of judgments letting go of thoughts plans
not needed right now not needed whatever has happened before you get got
to this point Let It Go let it go take refuge in the Simplicity of this moment
you don't have to figure it out you don't have to be a good soldier
marching on just be just be
do nothing for a moment be humble be simple
be an earthworm simple just simple
feel the softness of your body
let your heart relax your body relax
nothing to do to think to figure out to be
be an earthworm ah
release release
feeling the connection of your body to the Earth your feet your legs your sit bones your
hands with your lap
ring the center of gravity of your awareness down down from your head
down to your body let it be in your lower abdomen
receiving the breath there just settling
for a few breaths
receiving the breath receiving the sensations of the body
let the breath be calming soothing nurturing
receiving the breath receiving the breath in the abdomen
this breath just this breath gratefully appreciatively this life-giving breath
entirety of the in-breath the entirety of the Opera intimate
intimate
so sweet to be intimate with the breath knowing it knowing it
closely
serves as an antidote to destruction
scatteredness Which is less satisfying
so the breath this gift this anchor grounding in the
body thank you brother
thank you for your companion trip
say with the breath with your awareness
thank you
letting your heart be solved
appreciating what we may often take for granted maybe not if you're
having the flu or a cold and you're congested and breaths are hard but
you appreciate when there is this breath
maybe even when it's hard that it's still here thank you I love you thank you
and now like to invite you to bring someone for whom your meta your care
flows with ease maybe a child a pet so with whom you have an uncomplicated
relationship invite them to your mind's eye to the
space of your heart
and as you are sitting with them you're seeing them being with them in this moment see how
their presence impacts you
maybe it brings a sense of ease relaxation to your body to your heart
are you just appreciating them
maybe softly Whispering thank you thank you for being in my life
thank you thank you I love you
and again I love you not so much as romantic love or expectation for
reciprocation but as a way of saying yes
to this being is your heart opening up its doors and saying yes to them
appreciating them caring for them sharing Metta
accepting them appreciating their lovely qualities thank you I love
you try it on for size
if you feel silly doing it saying it whispering it do it anyway be silly be
childlike be simple what do you have to lose
try it on for size
foreign
with this particular being you lean more into thank you or lean more into
I love you or or both balance of both
dare to be silly dare to experiment be bold
yourself stretch your heart a bit
thanks for being in my life you're a gift thank you I love you
foreign
your heart can love in so many ways can be so expensive
be so magnanimous it really can be
loved so many beings and so many nuanced different ways
foreign
and expand the door open the door of your heart
and invite someone else
maybe someone who's a neutral person for you maybe you've worked with them as
a neutral person a neighbor someone who works at a grocery store
when you've interacted and never appreciated for a moment
thank you I love you
try it on for size
can your heart be undefended unprotected
sharing its goodness sharing its medites
it's well wishing it's care it's kindness with strangers
I don't precise don't have to push it
and maybe now inviting someone you've had challenges
with but you really know deep in your heart they've
helped you expand your heart your capacity
you've been your teacher can you invite them and thank them for the role they've
played in your life thank you thank you I love you
let's try it on for size it's an experiment
and yourself inviting yourself
the being who's both your dear being sometimes neutral sometimes
person you have challenges with
this being who is me who does their best
thank you and breath out breath
keeping yourself in my thanking yourself thank you
I love you
and if resistance arises stints judgment
feeling silly thank you I love you
see what happens is it disarming is it funny
is it a movement of acceptance
experiment on your own see what works
for you
maybe as you sit on the earth thank you thank you hers
your heart is resisting to be stretched
the resistance thank you I love you
maybe I love you in this case is an acknowledgment is a softening into
not the usual ways we think of it experiment on your own
can you love your challenges thank you I love you
as well as what's good
foreign
as we bring this practice to a close
appreciating yourself or having showed up having done your best have you practiced thank you I love
you
and let's offer goodness the goodness of our practice the Merit our practice to all beings
everywhere may all beings everywhere
no the Limitless Ness of their hearts
including ourselves may all beings be happy may all things be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice foreign
s if any questions comments complaints
and raise your Zoom hand or type in chat
Lisa
hello hi so special to be with you before Thanksgiving
um um they gave out last year too when we were and so with this
towards the end it was something like about impersonality because suddenly it
was like I love you heartbreak I love you pain I I love you lonely like like
hard emotions and then it was just like oh they're like visitors
to show me what this is this Human Experience is like like it was
um not super personal there was some kind of like space
there um maybe because I'm not like in the throes and caught by one of those now
but yeah that was what came up for me
um that's profound Lisa thank you for sharing that yeah so appreciate this
this both opening going there your your mind inviting you to to love
your challenges that become the challenges of The Human Condition and
this this um really an insight into anata in personality not self-rises yeah
thank you challenges whatever name or face you have
um thank you for sharing that wonderful beautiful hmm wow
any other reflections
Missy please
thanks Nikki yeah uh this is brilliant I you know just never ceases to amaze me
that just like sitting silently in a chair here on Zoom with my eyes closed you know some of these practices my what
I discovered was that this can require courage you know to the
invitation was there and I didn't need to take the invitation but I did and I
did it to the neutral person and scrolling through these different people and I was like wow that uh yeah it was
an amazing practice thank you thank you Jesse I love how you talk
about um courage I completely agree it takes courage this practice takes courage a
lot of Courage the invitations are there and and yet you know sometimes our mind
goes oh this is too too dangerous or maybe the mind doesn't say that it says
oh this is so silly this is too stupid I don't want to do like or whatever it just comes up with with the reasons why
not to do it and it takes courage to say okay thank you I hear you but I'm gonna try this on for size and and expand and
and as as you were sharing sounds like it was quite impactful for you in different ways like this experiment
um with these five magic words not just three but through five magic words um
showed up for you yeah anything else you want to add or does it feel complete
yeah no exactly as you said you know just um those voices are like oh this is
silly this doesn't make any sense but uh choosing to Step Beyond that exactly
thank you yeah yeah thank you thanks Jesse age please
please um hello um I'm thinking that um uh I have the
um the experience of last week um I'm I'm away from my house
and travel I'm not troubling but I lived down in Honduras half the year and my
house in Portland was burglarized and so I have the opposite of bounty usually or
celebrating Bounty and and um and being thankful for the for I was
going to say the things but thankful for things for lack of a better word in our
life and um and this was a devastating I have um a lot of had a lot of artwork
sculptures and um pretty much totally cleaned it out and broke whatever's there so I'm so sorry
yeah it's it's um and luckily I had just been on a on a
passionate the passenger retreat in Mexico um a few weeks prior and so I guess I was
kind of like in in shape to be able to receive such a blow and just say it is what it is and not um
and not do that but it was um you know considerable amount of um
of possession I I hear and I appreciate that and and this might be
I um since there this is the theme of tonight too
um and it might be too soon so so this may not be the practice right now for you Paige but but when the time comes
when they're the stability and the Equanimity comes um of seeing that there is stuff in this
world and the stuff there's goodness Beauty and also they weigh us down is
there a way to be grateful for is there a way to see the good not right
now this might be too soon whether ouch might still be too strong but there always is a way to to find Liberation to
find Freedom to find more ease especially when things are let go of um even if it's not what we would have
chosen so I'll just offer that for for a reflection for you to sit with me I think I can understand that in theory
and think you know sometimes people are a great point if they have a if they have a house burned down and then and
then say Oh start over but thank you thank you Paige thank you yeah
ah oh Rose asks um what are the five magic words the Five magic words is what I kept
repeating through the um the uh guided meditation thank you I love
you thank you I love you five magic words thank you I love you
so so um with that I'd like to invite us to to
uh engage to together in small groups and offering our ears for listening our
hearts um in appreciation of each other and there might be words there may not
be any words in are coming together and um the prompt or tonight is is there
something challenging something challenging perhaps I mean you can choose something good actually
something good and something challenging let's do it both something good and you can say thank you I love you something
challenging that you can say thank you I love you and and we do a couple of
rounds starting um first a person who uh alphabetical
order first person will offer something good they can say um thank you I love you next person next
person then the second round would be something challenging you can expand your heart to to have that relationship
with and um and
um what else do I want to say um and then the future rounds could just
be um just open conversation so so with
that uh I'm going to create the rooms and again as always
please only speak from your own experience not uh uh you know managing
the group just just offering a little bit from your own experience and letting other people have their space and if you
want to say pass that's perfectly fine you can pass and be kind to each other
be kind to each other so here we go the rooms are created
and uh enjoy oh and we've got about just a
minute for any Reflections that might have come from either the practice silent practice or the practicing
Community this reflection these two uh questions
any Reflections what did you notice Kim please
I noticed that um with with the group with us going
around and and saying I love you
um it normalized it or I was uh struggling a little bit with it during
the meditation I could kind of get there but to have the three of us saying it
um really normalized it was like yeah this is great this works
awesome very nice thank you so much Kim for for verbalizing that for acknowledging that
because I that's exactly it I think when you hear it out loud other people saying
it and being held witness and that that um yeah that in that community that Norm
that normalizing feels like yeah or one's heart can land into and sort of sort of in the meditation like I don't
know what does that exactly mean I love you I don't know it feels wild it feels weird but oh yeah thank you so much for
that and and um for those of you who are on the mailing
actually if you're not on the main language get on the mailing list because uh uh Christine already sent pointer to
this um uh person doing the the I Love You
song and and the way they do it is a little different than when when how we did it tonight is they do and you know I
love you Skye I love you the chair I love you this I love you that's what that can become part of what you
practice too I love you this and might feel silly but it's like oh I love you chair I love you computer you let me
communicate with my Sangha you know I look so there's a sense of naturalness that can come here but but tonight we
did thank you I love you which is the Five magic words practice instead of the three magic words of just I love you
anyway all these practices are so profound and can really shake you out of
your usual way of uh habitual way of going about the world with with more
meta with more care with touching into our Humanity anyway thank you so much
for practicing for showing up for um yeah for
or being part of the Sangha may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone