okay okay well hello and welcome welcome to happy
hour everyone it's lovely to see you it's lovely to be with you
ah so so for today this fresh new day
whatever day it is whatever time zone for today the topic i'd like to invite
us to engage with [Music] is
patience for ourselves patience for ourselves and patience for others
patience such a beautiful quality of the heart and mind
ah so patience
in praise of patience and praise of patience
such a useful parame parami is is the name of
what's called ten perfections in buddhism there are ten beautiful qualities of the heart and patience
kanti kanti is one of them patients
so patience as as an expression of meta as an expression of kindness for
ourselves let's consider you know this mind this body we take it
to be ours we take it to be we take it so personally especially when
when um maybe it doesn't feel well or it's
sluggish or it forgets something or or
it it gets agitated or gets upset angry this heart this mind this body
what if we treated this being as
as we would treat a an elderly beloved parent just it's okay
sweetheart it's okay it's all right i'll have patience with you i'll have patience with you instead of
being short-tempered with ourselves like ah you forgot this again or
ah gosh you you lost it or whatever it might be whatever it might be or you're
sleeping again oh my goodness you're distracted again fill your favorite
habitual pattern in there the one that you you lose your patience with what if
what if we had patience so so you might wonder oh wait a minute if i have too much patience with myself then
i'll never improve i'll always be distracted and
sleepy and forgetful and angry not exactly so not exactly the idea of
patience is not acquiescence it's not to accept and and um
and resign ourselves that's not the idea here it's actually it's like a very wise
uh [Music] aikido move and the aikido move aikido
for those who may not be familiar with this martial arts the idea is you use the
energy of the opponent you use the energy and you redirect it in a very
skillful way you don't oppose it you redirect it you redirect the energy so
the idea of the redirection here is say with the pattern that
um is troublesome or for one thing it may not even be our fault anyway if it's with the body or the mind or we're not
feeling well and we feel betrayed by the body um and then with the other patterns with
with the anger and loss of temper etc um
having patience with ourselves actually that that moment of acceptance is like re
it's like shifting the energy like okay you're here i see that you're here i
accept that you're here ah instead of fighting you now how now
that you're here now that you're here okay how can i work
with you that is in that moment wisdom can come in how can i work with you
and again i've named a range of different patterns um in the mind and in the body and some
of them might be realized the body is just tired or sleepy or
angry or having a hard time like okay rest patience patience patients
and then with some of the patterns um maybe another skillful means is helpful
but patience patience taking our time taking our time with heartfulness all right
there's more i can say but i think that's enough let's just practice together and see what arises
in our reflections in our hearts and our minds and our bodies in the areas that we can have just a
little more patience for ourselves and of course patience for
others so all right let's let's practice
land in our seats let's arrive
calling forth the power of patience in this moment
can we have patience as this body settles relaxes
let's go or maybe it doesn't let go just yet maybe it's too agitated to let go
right now can we be patient with that
with whatever the conditions are
whatever is arising in this moment and this body and this mind
space of the emotions can i can we have patience with it
as we gently invite the body to settle
it's just an invitation it's not
meant to be forceful
like a hammer it's just an invitation
and can equality of patience inhabit the body especially the lower
part of the body sense of stability groundedness receiving the breath
can patience be intertwined with awareness right now
to receive the breath all the time in the world for just this breath
as if this in breath is the most important awaited breath in the world
to take its time
not waiting for the next in breath chest this one
just this out breath
deliciously enjoying with patience
it's arising in this moment
receiving receiving this breath
just the sensation of the breath in the body
not going after the past or into the future
resting resting moment of refuge
spending another few minutes just settling with the breath
with patience
and if there is lack of patience right now
with anything sense of irritability lack of patience
can you be patient with that can you be patient
can you be patient with lack of patience or the judgmental mind or whatever is
coming up it's something challenging
to be patient with the lack of patience
see how that might feel like an aikido move to be patient with lack of patience
does your heart relax a little bit more is there more ease
and i feel like i'd like to invite you to ah a little
experiment staying grounded [Music] with the body feeling the breath
bring to your heart bring to your body memory
not to get too heady but bring the memory into your body to the felt sense
of your body the memory of maybe today or yesterday
maybe an occasion where something happened
some mishap
maybe you were a little less patient and normal with yourself
maybe you're impatient
maybe judgmental mind arose or any other version of it for you
gently ever so gently without getting off kilter if you get off kilter let it go
keeping keeping a sense of calm bringing this memory to your body
the felt sense of it
maybe you're berating yourself chastising
yourself your body your memory your emotions
ever ever so slightly it doesn't have to be a big huge emotion but just a little bit
of just
that flavor which can feel like a tightness in the
heart
feeling the contraction maybe in the body the heart
and now having a felt sense of this memory
while feeling embodied
lift redo do a redo in your body in your heart the felt sense
well this feeling this memory comes up or maybe there was the aikido move of
patience with yourself an extra dose of patience
maybe you joked with yourself oh sweetheart it's okay
you're getting the hang of this being a human thing it's okay yeah
it's challenging it's okay given all the causes and conditions
this is the best outcome for this moment for your body for your heart for your
mind it's okay it's all right
whatever the situation was
the sense of could have should have would have feel the tightness and then see what
arises this feelings aikido move redirecting the energy
of patience it's okay
patience with this body it's doing the best it can
but this mind that is doing the best it can
and see what might arise in your heart and your body
notice
is there more settling more peace more ease
more energy available
more kindness available
and is there more uprightness more aspiration available
yes sweetheart it's okay patience patience
more energy for a different outcome next time
more kind more wise
more wholesome i would come next time
now if you wish can stay with this feeling
or spaciousness or if you like again feeling your body on the cushion
or the chair your breath feeling embodied
and opening up the heart the body again maybe this time inviting a memory of a time
the recent times you were a little bit impatient
not as patient as you would have wished with someone else
maybe it wasn't even so overt maybe you didn't even lose your temper
but in your own mind you knew that you were a little patient like okay
wanting them to see the point or get it or do something or not do something
aware of this internal impatience
and feel really a little bit if it's okay it's not overwhelming
let yourself feel that contraction a bit in the body just
contraction of impatience lack of patience doesn't
feel so good does it it feels like it sucks the air out of the room
sucks the air out of your lungs
now relax and let's do a redo in our minds and our hearts
our memory this thing is happening in our memory
ah we're being patient fully patient they're doing the best
they can this being with the causes and conditions of the
background their upbringing [Music] their experience their genetics
who they are they're getting a hang of this being
human thing just like i am i can give them space
to figure it out in their own time
and give them the gift of patience give myself the gift of patience
and see how your heart might feel
is the contraction loosened ah melt
is there more ease
offering yourself this other being the gift of patience
and if there's impatience present like it's not working can you be patient with
the lack of patience it's okay i'm getting
the hang of this human being human thing too
offering them patience maybe yourself too
see how soothing calming healing
the self can feel
and notice how with more patience towards others can be more supportive
more wise in our actions towards them
more kind
it frees up energy for wisdom patience frees up energy
for kindness and wisdom
can there be patience with whatever is arising in this moment border agitation distraction
not acquiescence but patience patience has an uprightness to it
immorality that acquiescence doesn't
see for yourself
and as we bring this practice period to an end together
can we offer patience to our hearts
in our aspirations to awaken to be wiser and kinder
patience paves the path
offering ourselves patience as a gift of kindness
to enable wisdom
and may our patience may our cultivation our goodness
be a cause and condition for kindness
awakening goodness all around the world all beings everywhere
may they be patient with themselves patient with others
all around for those who are like them or those who are different
patience patience patience may all beings everywhere
be free including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
in praise of patience so
so time for reflections what might have come up for
you if you are like if you would like to share
for the benefit of others your aha moments maybe your questions
your challenges um we offer these as gifts to others
so any reflections any questions comments in praise of patience
or maybe more specific and oh you can always type in chat if you type to me
privately i will read your reflection but not your name so it will be private
if you type to everyone it will be a both um
i'll read your name and your reflection you can also raise your zoom hand
and richard
hi i i i wondered if patience extends to like giving yourself
time enough to do some let's say practice you know that you want to sit for 45 minutes instead of
five minutes rather than get antsy and cut it short
yeah exactly yes tell them tell me more
yes and i'm curious what where it's coming no because it's sort of easy
to say oh i i know i'm progressing slowly
but you know i'm easily distracted not in the sense of
thinking of something but wanting to do something else and
i need to do one thing for long enough
before i drop and do something else well said that's exactly right there's
this it's um you know given that you have the aspiration just as you said to to awaken
to wake up and and you sit and after five minutes there's like okay i've got to do this
other thing like oh yeah that's more important like wait a minute dear what's what's your highest aspiration
what's what's really important to you right so could be can can you and bringing patients there
this is a beautiful way this beautiful quality or can i be patient with this agitation because maybe what's really
underneath of wanting to get up and do something else is a sense of agitation um can i be patient with myself or maybe
they're different framing as you were saying like a sense of patience okay i'm just gonna be patient with me walking this path
i'm going to be patient and i actually give it time not just give it five minutes so there's so many different but
it's also fully engaged with whatever that thing is yeah yeah
exactly yeah patience is fully engaged yeah
yeah patience is fully engaged resignation is not engaged that's another thing you have to explore
patience is fully engaged yeah thank you richard
you are the reflections here bill says it seems to me that patience and love
are closely related yes indeed exactly thank you for that
you says thank you nikki you're welcome you mary says i love the reminder patience
paves the path yes you're welcome yes patience paves
the path it is engaged it is engaged
active engagement with ourselves with others um yeah
patience pays the path
any other reflections before we share patience
pepper says patience and acceptance are also related yes yeah definitely yeah
they're both related and and a little different the same way that patience and love are
related and it's like i think of these as venn diagrams right you know you're familiar with venn diagrams these
circles like you have these circles that define a particular entity so patience and acceptance have areas
that are in common but of course there are other aspects to them
and so so in many ways patience uh needs needs acceptance patience
um patience requires a level of acceptance that yes this is how things
are right now this is how things are right now and and how can i hold it how can i hold this with with both
uprightness with spaciousness with good will and with steadiness there's a steadiness
also uh in patients that's part of it it's it's really fun to explore
these qualities in the body and the mind like oh yeah and i'm so loving how all
of you have been and how the comments are coming like oh yeah these are related oh those are
related kind of feeling them in the in your in your body and mind yeah
so [Music] there are no other further reflections
maybe i'll pause for one more moment
so okay so i'll invite you now to
the small to small rooms so the invitation
for um the practice together
is um first of all showing up with patients showing up with the quality of
patients for yourselves equality of patience for others which again
has both love and acceptance in it as observed
and each person will say one nugget just one thing could be about this practice
today or it could be about your relationship with patients
relationship with your patients in general um does it come easily does it seem like a challenge or what nuance you've
explored you observed today as you were playing around with it
and um and so each person one person will say one nugget and then the other person
will say another nugget um and then the next person will say one more nugget
and it will come back to you so you'll go around a few times and
let's go in alphabetical order according to the first name and
um what else yeah so each person just sharing from your own experience if you
wish you can also offer silence and say past and just hold presence
patience compassionate presence that's perfectly okay it's fine
so um yeah i think that's uh i think that's
all so i'm going to open the rooms now
and uh take care of yourselves take care of each other
be kind here we go okay welcome back everyone
the rooms are closed and we have a couple minutes if any reflections came up
from your conversations in the rooms together you're welcome to raise your hand if you
would or type in chat
questions reflections how is it to be in room and discuss
patience with one another what did you discover such a juicy topic
i see some smiles
i'll be patient with you i am patient take your time
fred please
well we discussed among other things being on the phone to a t
[Laughter] and i thought that was just to me that was just the the perfect uh
the perfect obstacle the perfect task perfect learning uh situation
uh how to hang in there and maybe get what you want but not make it
worse yeah yeah yeah that's that's exactly right
yeah thank you fred that's a great example yeah and we all go through
examples like that yeah appreciate that barbara please
oops please you're still uh you're still muted ah there i have a similar example i live
on an island that has a drawbridge and for the first time in the year and a
half i've lived on the island i went to leave and and there that there
was no the traffic wasn't moving we were backed up for blocks this way and that
way and you could see people that were unaware of it were getting really worked
up and those that know that the drawbridge is up we're just sort of relaxing
and you know none of us were going to get across the bridge any faster for getting all worked up so that's exactly
right opportunity for patients yeah for exercising practicing thank you
thank you for that and there's one reflection privately that it's hard when someone takes up the
whole time seems to be happening a lot lately so so i appreciate that maybe in the groups also you know even though
with the invitation that each person will just say a nugget and then the next person will say nugget and the next
person will come back to it may not always happen that way even there's always the invitation to be mindful and
yet especially with the topic tonight i think that is the perfect if that happened in your group
it's okay it's a perfect opportunity to be patient with one another it's like
it's okay if i don't say something tonight i can exercise patience that was
the invitation anyway can you show up with patience for each other and yourself so
if you did that yeah you just succeeded even if you didn't get a word in edgewise yay then you've practiced
perfectly with with uh meta and patience so anyway so thank you all it's it's
lovely to practice with you and whatever we do as long as we bring kindness to it
it's it's part of this practice it's part of this practice so i appreciate you showing up you're cultivating your
heart for the purpose of serving yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be safe
may all beings be free including ourselves
great thank you all thank you oh and i will be traveling um
uh this next week so you'll have some wonderful
other supportive teachers who will be supporting the sangha in the coming days