foreign
good morning everyone and have a good day good evening for some of you maybe
good afternoon so
lately I've been thinking about the Town Square of a small square the
the and I wonder sometimes if this you know
YouTube It's kind of open to the world to come by and a little bit of a Town Square that
people come and visit and come through and everyone's invited
and I'm thinking about this meditation session with the metaphor of town square
imagine you're a traveler and you come to a small town looks like
a welcoming Town looks like people are happy to have visitors come through and
and so you come and make your way to the town square and and there have very comfortable benches
on that town square and you're happy to sit on the edge of the square and
and watch the comings and goings the Town Square
and it Marvels you all the different people and maybe animals and
activities that somehow come through show up in the town square stay for a
while leave and it seems like every Everything everyone has ability to use the Town Square as a
public space and there's no sense that anyone shouldn't be there that everyone feels looks like
they feel like they're quite happy to be there and comfortable and they belong and they can be themselves and
and um and it's lovely to watch the young the old the children
the lovers the you know people argue and
even maybe the people on political soap stands soapboxes so all this comes through it's all of
life comes through and um
and then at some point it Dawns on you as you look at everyone something seems unusual
you can't quite put your finger on it Until you realize
that all the people who come into the square they're all visitors
like you some of them might stay for a few days some of them are for a few weeks maybe
some of them a little bit longer but in fact everyone in the town everyone coming through are just
visitors and you realize you're a visitor
everything here is a visitor so in the same way
it might be useful to think of your capacity to be aware your mindfulness
as the Town Square that you keep open 24 hours a day kind
of kind of to keep it open and everything is welcome in into the town square into the
mindfulness your job is to make sure that you are sitting on that bench that
comfortable bench that allows you to be present and gaze upon all that
comes and maybe if you have a responsibility in that town square
as all visitors do perhaps is to be accepting
kind to all the visitors that come
so to think of mindfulness as a Town Square in which everything everything is
allowed to be to come through everything that comes through is allowed to be there everything's just a visitor
something stays longer than others
and um and your job is to know it to see it to be present and to keep
the Town Square available to everyone to keep keep this
town square as a place where all things could be
without you being for or against without being involved or interfering
with anything just aware just present
and perhaps this will give you a profound sense
of being at ease and at peace
because you know you're in the Town Square and you can just allow things to come
and go yourself all things all the ways that you are
so to assume a meditation posture
that is upright
literally or metaphorically
and to gently close your eyes
and to settle into your bench in the Town Square so you can relax and be present
taking a few long slow deep breaths
as you exhale it's settling in
relaxing
and letting your breathing return to normal perhaps you've actually come to the Town
Square early early in the morning before anyone else and you they find a broom to sweep it
clean to make it nice for people who come in the same way
relaxing your body is to sweep
and make it nice for all that's going to be there for you on the exhale relaxing the face
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the chest
relaxing the belly
maybe relaxing the whole body
releasing holding
tightening
and then the comings and goings in this town square
include to include the comings and going of each inhale in each exhale
maybe their breathing can be like the pigeons
lying around and as you stay here
sooner or later all kinds of things will come to your awareness
Let It Come Let It Go Let It Be
but don't leave your bench don't leave and get involved
with anything just watch it just see it
from the vantage point of your bench as if
your attitude of acceptance of all of it is the very recipe
of providing a sense of freedom and homecoming
to whatever arises
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe to take a few moments with the perspective
that you're a visitor here in this world
and everything else everyone else is a visitor everything is a visitor
we all have this in common in the comings and goings of all things
just visitors
and with that perspective perhaps sitting on your bench watching in the
Town Square it might be a little easier
to gaze upon all the visitors kindly
caringly respectfully
maybe even reverently
men may be wishing aspiring
that your heart and your eyes
can look upon all people and all beings
with kindness that you can look upon all beings
with eyes that convey safety
that you can be with all beings with a heart that radiates peace
that you can be present for others in a way they feel free to be themselves
May It Be that your gift to the world that you
Aspire that you give to this world were all visitors
that you contribute kindness good will
safety Peace and Freedom
and may this meditation practice we've done today may it be that one way or another
it supports this aspiration to be this kind of person
in this world of that we live in
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone I'm starting a new week with a new theme
and um I think maybe the title of the theme
that one word for the theme this week perhaps it can be the word meaning
and now too we'll want to spend this this week exploring the topic of meaning
in relationship to meditation what's the meaning of meditation
and I think in years past I would have been very hesitant to take up a topic like this
partly because coming out of my zen training the idea of assigning meaning or finding meaning was often presented
as being besides the point there was something very significant just showing up and being present
without inserting or meaning on top of our
experience in our life and I love this idea it was a radical Simplicity of
so much Falls away but I think we cannot get away from human life
human Minds somehow one way or the other whether it's conscious or unconsciously
being involved in the questions of meaning of purpose why are we here what's the
most important thing for us to do and so religions provide often sense of
meaning and purpose and interpretation of what it what's important what priorities are
what we do with suffering what's up what's the meaning of suffering what's the purpose in our life in relationship
to suffering and so what I thought I would like to do this week is that with the hope that
this topic gives a kind of depth to uh your involvement with meditation that it
gives kind of um uh it lets your meditation be fueled or
or founded on based on supported by
some of the deeper values deeper understandings you have maybe that you're not even conscious of that gives
me meditation more motivation more strength more value more like grubby
toss in a sense and um and so we'll do that by looking at the
connection of meditation Association meditation can have to a variety of
different things in our life today I want to talk about suffering and I don't quite remember the sequence that I have
but I think neck tomorrow was the important values we have and then the connection to values the connection to
ourself the connection to others and the connection to what is might consider to
be sacred um so what's the meaning of meditation in
relationship to these important areas of life there was a tendency when this
mindfulness meditation that I'm teaching when it was brought to the United States
there was a very strong Wish by the teachers to make it very available to as
many people as possible without the hindrance or the this that
it might be there if it was the whole Buddhist religious package was brought
with it there was a idea that this mindfulness practice is a simple raw basic practice
is doesn't have to belong to any particular religion doesn't have to
belong to any particular philosophy maybe and wanting to make it this
practice available broadly and widely so it could benefit so many people
and in fact they succeeded in many ways because they inspired those first Buddhist teachers inspired Generations
now of people who offer mindfulness completely separated from Buddhism you know sometimes call it secular
mindfulness in clinical settings and all kinds of places and it's I think it's
been overall a wonderful contribution to society
and um and uh and I think there's some real
value in offering kind of a Buddhist Buddhism light where we don't kind of Pile in a lot of the Buddhist meaning
the Buddhist sense of purpose Buddhist religiosity that surrounds it and just
make it accessible to people easily and that's still the case but uh I'm but
I'm hoping that this the discussion this week will prompt you to not feel like
you have to adopt or adapt uh you know some Buddhist idea that might come
through here but rather it becomes a mirror the teaching for you to reflect
and think more deeply about your life maybe more deeply than you ever ever have for some of you about uh maybe the place of meaning and
what what meanings do you bring what purposes do you bring what is your understanding what it means to be a
human being in this world so perhaps this can be an example for or
a kind of a for the value that can be found is that um
someone might go to the doctor and the doctor says you know you're about to
have a heart attack and you're living with so much stress that I think you need to go and learn
some meditation so mindfulness is very helpful and there's a mindfulness center
nearby why don't you go there and learn to meditate because you know you're without stressing I don't think I don't
see that you're going to live more than a couple of months so that motivates the person and the person shows up at a meditation center
and learns mindfulness and and maybe the teacher there asks why are you here what's the purpose what's the meaning of
you being here and so you or this person might say um well my doctor sent me
and uh therefore if it says a prescription end of story
and uh and then um the
the um but then you press for further you ask
the person the person you could ask or something the question further what um
what um but you know is that why the doctor send
you and um and that the um
the doctors and so because uh you know the doctor said that if I don't do it I'll die and I want you know
you know I don't want to die and the meaning of the meditation is not dying but then you go person you start
thinking about more or you're asked more questions and and so the question becomes um oh why do you want to live
oh because I want to be able to see my grandchildren I want to be able to finish the work that I do I I love life
and I just want to be able to live it fully I'm afraid of death and I'm trying to put it off as much as I can
I um I feel like I haven't really dealt with my big issues in my life and I
really before I die I want to finish and deal with those issues is um so there's all kinds of so this thing
I didn't have the doctor says you have to go and meditate because otherwise you'll die it begins being connected to
other values other important ideas about why you should stay alive
and um and those can are animating forces there's a reasons
some people don't know why they're alive or the people don't have a meaning or purpose that they have
um and some people might do it because they've discovered that they can live much more peacefully if they don't have
live searching or questioning or or getting all
wrapped up around issues of meaning purpose and they just you're happy just
to kind of Roll Along with whatever's happening then that becomes the meaning that
becomes the purpose just Roll Along just be present and the meaning is that the
meaning is a is a hindrance and it's just nicer just to roll along with things
um so to there's many so what's the meaning
what's the purpose what's their interpretation we have and so it just might be interesting for
some of you to know that um uh in in kind of classic or
quite uh there's a kind of standard terravan Buddhism that this tradition
comes out of I consider myself a taroten Buddhist and this role as teaching but I don't really uh have much place in
my heart or my mind for some of the core teachings that give meaning give a
purpose to teravan Buddhism some people will say this is the foundation of it some people say that without believing
in this there's no Buddhism even but I take exception of that in my sense
of meaning is very buddhistic I have some kind of an ultimate sense of meaning and purpose that comes from this
practice but I don't share some of the core things that some of the tradition has
so the I'm not motivated so the example would be I'm not motivated with idea
that the purpose of this practice is so that we can we will no longer get Reborn
that doesn't speak to me doesn't inspire me doesn't have a place for me it's completely appropriate and fine for
someone else to have that view I don't have a issue with that but it's just not what animates me
um and um and uh and the idea of you know that I would the purpose is to no longer be
reborn it doesn't really do much for me and so but but do I have something else
that's comparable um I um if anything I feel
uh that it's enough for me the idea that to have a radical freedom
from suffering they really let go of suffering in some deep way and then live this life free of
the attachments the clinging that's motivating for me it's almost fundamental
but in the background of that there is some kind of idea that I don't hold very
tightly but some sense that of trusting life a feeling at home in this universe
and so this letting go of suffering letting go of clinging is also a homecoming into this universe where I'm
no longer standing in opposition to it or or or making some problem with it so
these are all ways of making meaning a purpose of uh contextualizing interpreting what we're doing
so I want to just end here now with one of the things to find that people find
meaning in or purpose is in relationship to suffering and some people will inherit some
meaning of what suffering means what the purpose of suffering is from the religions they grew up with and there
are some religions that have a very important idea that's suffering is Redemptive that you're supposed to
suffer it's good to experience suffering because It prepares you for the hereafter
some people say that suffering is testing our religious faith and so we
have to kind of you know somehow hold on to our faith when we suffer that's the key thing about what we have to do and
we'll get rewarded if we hold on to our faith um and um and you know there's all kinds
of ideas people have um and um and in Buddhism the kind of
the meaning of suffering is that it's unnecessary and that it's motivating
in order to come to the other side of suffering to be free of suffering to radical Liberation from suffering
uh if there's a famous quote from the Buddha where he says I teach suffering and the end of suffering
um and why and suffering you might say there's no need to ask why just like you
take your hand off a hot stove uh you don't have to ask why you do it it's your body will do it immediately
so it could be that simple uh like it's almost like a biological imperative to
be free of suffering but there might be other things there might be the idea that yes I Want to Be
Free of suffering so I can be a better support for the world around me I wanted
I Want to Be Free of my clinging so that I can act with uh act from a place of
compassion and care for this world take care of my family I want to become free of the kind of
sources great hate and delusion that bring about the suffering so that I can live a certain way or be a
certain way or do this and that um the um so what is your meaning
in terms of your meditation practice what's the purpose what's the role what's the meaning of suffering
uh how does suffering fit into it and how does that fit into a wider uh
Circles of meaning or deeper Circles of meaning in your life is simply just to
be free of suffering and that's enough or is there some deeper purpose that that serves some deeper value is it just
to kind of be free of stress so you don't have a heart attack or you know
what do you if you're free of suffering what what do you hope that will do for you
what is your aspiration what is your sense of purpose if you can become radically free of
suffering or is suffering just kind of a free freedom from suffering and coping with
suffering kind of a little bit of a sideshow that you do reluctantly so you can get
on to what's most important what is most important what is the most important kind of uh
way in which you understand your life what your life's about what it means to be a human being
what is and what is suffering and freeing suffering how does that fit into that in your life
so I hope that this makes some sense for you and I'm hoping this as a catalyst for you to do some reflection
and I would encourage you if you have anyone friends family total strangers
that maybe you engage in this topic of meaning and purpose and what is the most
fundamental meaning and purpose that you have that you associate that you live by
um and how does meditation connect to that once they can meditate connection meditation might have to support that
so thank you and um and um
we'll continue these reflections over this week