so hello everyone good to be with you on this
[Music] sunday um
we'll do a meditation offer some
light guidance for us to begin and then followed by a silent sit
together let's enjoy each other's company
and practicing together
arriving
arriving arriving here and now
taking a few generous moments to arrive
not rushing through this arriving process
coming to your meditation cushions cheers
maybe just take a few moments to allow your feet to really settle on the ground
maybe the bodies still need to move
riding with the movements of arriving
so
when you're ready allow the contact of the body with
wherever you're sitting
to be in the forefront of your awareness
noticing that you have arrived here
and you have arrived now
feeling and sensing into the contact of the body with a floor and earth underneath of you
grounded supported
by earth
what's the felt sense of a grounded here and now
in this body with this breath
maybe the bubbly energy that you came with
settles down ever so slightly
maybe the movements of the breath become more visible
let yourself savor in the sense of groundedness
centered
from this grounded place
open the awareness to receive
whatever is present right here and right now
movements of the breath
sensations in the body
wavy emotions
lingering
thoughts nothing excluded
being with the ever-changing experiences
if the breath is prominent
resting grounding in the movements of the breath
being with the breath
nothing to do nowhere to go
just to hear was the movements of the breath
strong sensations in the body arise
no problem
open the space of awareness to be with the sensations in the body
just as they are
are learning to be
to be with what is here
whatever is here
we're learning to be with
[Music]
yeah so good to be here with you all
very delighted i'm aware that day you're probably all
sitting for a while for those who are online or in person
if you need to move uh feel free to do so just allow the body to shift and change a
little as we shift and change in a different mode of
practicing and learning learning dharma
so what's on my mind on today is a couple of words that i like to
share my reflections upon and these are the words
grounding or groundedness
i have introduced this couple of words in our meditation
and just slightly and so those two words um grounding
groundedness may evoke something in you
and even now as you're sitting or lying down standing
and just checking to see what is the felt sense of grounding or
grounded being grounded
for me there is a immediate sense of resting down
settling down be a sense of a safety
sense of a trust feeling secure here
not worried that somehow the ground will disappear
underneath of me so you may have
words and phrases images of your own
in this sense of grounding or being grounded
and so for me what i'd like to share today is
a reflective question where do we ground ourselves
where do we ground ourselves as human beings and one way or another
we're always finding ground to settle in
consciously unconsciously ever since we were born and when we were babies
the parents arms are the nice comfy grounds to be in
and they're resting there as we grow up on lots of different grounds open up for
us relationships with the friends family
relationships in communities maybe coming together here
feels a sense of a grounding and their sense of trust and safety
as we are in specific kinds of communities and our heart and mind and body can rest
feel some sense of settling in in those kind of grounds
and there are also other kind of grounds and some must find
grounds in jobs work we do the careers
and they offer certain kind of a fulfillment excitement
certain sense of security in different ways maybe
and grounds of hobby and grounds of
entertainment that's where we are kind of feeling
okay you know a sense of okayness may come in a sense of resting and coming when we're engaged in
those activities and the list can go on you know lots of
these grounds can open up as we go about living our lives
and some of these grounds [Music] as we begin to get a sense of kind of
them emerging we may also notice
many of those grounds involve a pattern of activities and doing
in relationships we have to find relationships maintain them
jobs and careers that offer our fulfillment had to really work at it and
and be in it and uh
for me i remember when i first came to this country more than 30 years ago
and as a college student i immediately realized that
that there was absolutely no security in any form
no financial security no relationships and i just immediately got very busy
doing trying to get a degree as fast as
possible and just so that i could feel a little comfort in achieving that and
and um getting a part-time job while doing that
i remember days when i would have spent all night in the computer graphics lab working on my
project and this um
this is all okay i think we all do this in our lives from time to time
and um and little did i know though
as i engage in this pattern and this can become
a habit a habit of doing achieving more
accomplishing more acquiring more and uh so
you know they uh i got a degree and got a job
and in the in my job i could do this or i could climb the
corporate ladder and so it doesn't stop
and so we all know that as individual engaging this way
and if many people engage in the same way
before we know it there is a culture began to evolve around all of us
there's a culture of a doing culture of busy doing endless doing
accomplishing achieving and once the culture is emerging
all around us that can become a norm we don't even know other
possibilities exist and so we just keep engaging in this
and sometimes um i recognize that even even
when a retirement comes the doing doesn't stop
because we just shift from one kind of a doing to another i remember at my
work and there was someone who retired uh i think a close to 80 years old but
after retirement uh he still shows up in the lab
and i was wondering wow this really goes on and on
and um we can begin to kind of uh
let this habit force kind of take over us continue in this mode
i want to offer an image and well before i do that i want to
point out maybe that on
it's not to say that all of this is our problems
well what i wanted to point out is as we began to um
reinforce this pattern in our lives
we began to engage in a unconscious in unconscious
dynamic and often and this is driven by the
forces of wanting desires and greed hatred delusion
but as we kind of continue to engage in this pattern we lose sight what is
driving underneath of us the image that i have
in this mode of operation is that of constant dancing on tippy toes
that's kind of before one foot landed completely on the ground the next foot had to move and i guess um
that the next foot the next landing is where we can finally
stabilize and ground and rest but as we know when this pattern began to engage on it
on its own kind of have his own life we just typical dance
not knowing the resting is even possible
and so we can begin to find the difficult um
to know what's possible to really ground
i remember that my teacher gail fransto sometimes
pointed out that maybe human beings it should be called human doings
because we really do we do a lot and is very fortunate for me it's not
until i encountered a dharma practice and dharma teachings
that i realized that there is a different kind of grounding that we can rest in
the ground of being being with what is happening here and
now unlike putting the two feet on the ground really solid on the ground
and even for all of us right now just you know as you settle in your chairs and the floor and
just allow yourself to feel the feet on the ground
sitting on the cushion not on the tears lying down wherever you are standing
what is that felt sense of a being being with what is happening here and
now being with listening
being with the breath moving crossing through us
being with the seeing
being with the sound inside and outside thoughts
nothing to do nowhere to go
for me that sense of a being often immediately evoked a sense of
resting down that sense of groundedness that we were speaking about and practicing with
opening and receiving receiving what is happening here now
being contented with what is here
not wishing it to be any other way we don't have to be towed to the next
step but here here is enough
maybe the pain unpleasant sensations are here
unpleasant emotions are here but it's okay to be
to be with to be with this is enough
for me there is a sense of a contentment coming along
and maybe also sense of a centeredness all right here rooted right here right
now
being grounded in the way things are not what i wanted it to be
but the way things are and the pali term
that gets translated as the way things are is that of a dharma
grounded in dhamma
and this is not to say that somehow we'll just have a magic way of simply stopping not together and
stopping the doing stopping the momentum stopping the wanting doesn't happen there's no magical button
to push right we all know that
and yet as we engage in the dharma practice from
time to time we may discover the moments where we can be
with what is happening
and it offers an opportunity to know and to see
that there is a different possibility for us
and as we engage in the dharma practice we may also learn oh there is a different kind of a doing
that allow the being to come about
to be in our experience and this is the kind of a doing
and that i um [Music] that in our dharma
world referred to as walking the dharma path it involves certain kind of doing
and you all come here today and practice meditation together
learning the dharma learning the dharma together there is a form of doing engaged
and yet to this kind of a doing are conducive to settling
and resting conducive to an establishment of a sense
of a well-being i love the term well-being it's kind of
a being that has a goodness to it
kind of a being that we can trust
that's very fortunate and that this is possible this is available to us
and walking the dharma path is a form of doing that one can engage
in that allow a different ground to emerge
i uh pointed out early on the kind of activities that we're engaging the kind
of doing that we engage in involves involves maybe sometimes a lot of physical activities
and i also want to point out that there is a kind of a doing that happen
in our mind and so we discover this as we begin to sit on the cushion
and oftentimes when we began our meditative practice
even though our bodies settled down immediately would discover how much we
think right and boy they're loud and
persistent and knowing that this is also a
long-term conditioning that happened maybe from very early on i'm aware that
my teenager is on and you know needs to figure things out a lot
you know i'm fond of these terms and figure things out sorting things out in our
mind because we never read out we always keep figuring continue to figure but never really kind
of out of it maybe out of it momentarily the next one will come pretty quickly
we're kind of aware of this kind of uh doing as well internally
internal chatter for me i never realized how much i talked to myself
in meditation constant yeah we have inner inner chatter going on
and our culture and there is a culture norm and that supports this conditions this right and
the more knowledge we have and the more information we accumulate somehow
we will be okay you know we'll be able to figure things out and and so we get to stimulate stimulated by
constant feeds into our being and
social media emails and internet and what have you
and our this thinking machine is constantly fed
with lots of resources
and so figuring things out sometimes can be become a belief an idea that we have we
hold so even if our physical bodies are settled down
and that belief may still continue to feel kind of feel the momentum
in our patterns of thinking patterns patterns of planning
yet walking the dharma path we begin to learn
what is a different possibility what is a different possibility here
that's great you know we are offered with
mindfulness practices allow us to begin to see the patterns
exist in us allow offer tools
for us to begin to settle into our
experiences the mindfulness of the body of our breath
invite us to begin to settle in the experience that's happening here
and now
and sometimes maybe sometimes you may have this experience yourself
as you settle into the rhythm of the breath sensations in the body
our beliefs about having to think through everything may soften
we may have momentary experience of
silence even the silence in between my words
space some momentary stillness
however small it may feel like and this might be the pointers for us to
say oh there may be a different ground
that's possible here
again i want to invite you to just chucking in your body however it is
maybe in the midst of the movements in the body there can be a sense of silence
kind of a stillness that's not rejecting
all the things that are happening but just being with
just being with listening to the sound
and yet the silence can be in the backdrop of it all
i'm fond of this story of mother teresa
from the book uh civility this is an interview with the mother
teresa there is interviewer asked the mother teresa what she says to god when she prays
i don't say anything she replies just listen
and so the interviewer asked her what god says to her
he doesn't say anything said mother teresa he just listens
and before the astonished interviewer could press her further she added
and if you don't understand that i can't explain it to you
so quietly listen listen to the vibrations within us
vibrations outside quiet still
when we're more and more grounded ourselves in the way things are
not wishing it to be in any other way grounded in being
actions can arise spontaneously out of wisdom compassion
and so this form of a being is not some form of idols and simply kind of giving
up doing nothing but rather it's a deep trust
of the inner wisdom and compassion that's available to us
and the kind of trust that allows the kind of doing that emerges
not based on the wanting and the aversion or the
delusion but based on the big field of compassion and wisdom
and so this form of being is a rich
and potent field and not a barren field
i want to offer a poem from
and which is written by a chinese philosopher laos
and translated by stephen mitchell
and it says this is the chapter 15.
the ancient masters were profound and the subtle their wisdom was unfathomable
there is no way to describe it all we can describe is their appearance
they were careful as someone crossing an ice-covered stream alert as a warrior in enemy
territory courteous as a guest fluid as melting eyes
shapeable as the block of wood receptive
as a valley clear as a glass of water
do you have the patience to wait till your mud settles
and the water is clear can you remain unmoving
till the right action arises by itself
the master doesn't seek fulfillment not seeking
not expecting she is present and can welcome all things
so there is a kind of doing that's a field by
wanting delusion that leads to more doing
tipito dancing [Music] and there is a form of a doing that
leads to being well-being
and this being [Music] is a rich potent flexible
as being as shapeable as a block of a wood
can be a stick for someone who needs a stick to walk around
can be a pillar holding the structure of the building
and so there is this a form of a being that offers the potential of doing
for the benefit of all beings for the well-being of all beings
but this happens when we have the patience to wait
for the mud to settle and the water to be clear
and so this practice we're engaging in [Music] is to learn to be
to settle to allow the mud to settle and so our heart and mind become clear
and the right actions arise by itself
and so may we all trust um trust the holes i'm doing that allow the
well-being to emerge and trusting the doing that arise out of
a deep sense of well-being and may all beings be benefited by this
so thank you everybody
so we have a few minutes maybe anyone who have comments and
protest questions welcome yeah
are your own reflections
being that must have been a good dharma talk because during it i realized how
unsettled and antsy and restless my body was
yeah yeah that's noticing it it has a lot of power
yeah yeah thank you it wasn't pleasant to notice it but it was kind of wonderful in a way because
oh yes you know i've got this body and i'm alive yes yes that's right yeah
yeah so that there's one behind you
thank you ying that was so beautiful um i have i have a request and then a
question my request is if you could read the poem one more time
and then my question is about that um you know waiting for the
what was it the mud if you could talk about
how that process might unfold that would be great yeah beautiful thank
you thank you for the question um let me read the dev poem one more
time and then maybe we'll unpack a little see how we get the mud to settle
the ancient masters were profound and subtle their wisdom was unfathomable
there is no way to describe it all we can describe is their appearance
they were careful as someone crossing an ice-covered stream
alert as a warrior in enemy territory courteous as a guest
fluid as melting ice shapeable as a block of wood
receptive as a valley clear as a glass of water
do you have the patience to wait till your mud settles
and the water is clear can you remain unmoving
until the right action arises by itself the master doesn't seek fulfillment
not seeking not expecting she is present
and can welcome all things
yeah so and here it offers the words and patient
patients have the patience to wait till the mud settles
image evoked in me is that of sitting right here
being in the midst of what's happening here and now as
bill was pointing out sitting here noticing
the unease that may be in the body in the mind
do we have the patience to be with this
is so often when unpleasant uh experiences happen we immediately
wanted to tip it over to the next step you know i gotta get rid of this one and
and what this invites us is to be with this
i'll allow this experience to unfold on its own terms
not based on what i believe it should be or um
i would rather that's not happening to me you know there are lots of agendas that that our
habitual mind can have and wanted to wiggle out of where we are
and we've offered um in the dharma practice lots of tools to establish that kind of
a sense of centeredness being with and for example
mindfulness of the breath being with the breath
as the breath unfolds on its own being with the body
in the body of the body not us of my belief of what the body is
supposed to to be and so a lot of those
things that you've been practicing is pointing to this direction
and part of it this is and the trick is to begin to notice the various patterns
that emerge in us that wanting to wiggle this way or that way
and so when we cultivate mindfulness we begin to see those momentum
and we just look at them and smile can i be with this
and let the flow so the mud will settle
but if you know we can try if we you know want to get rid of this and want to hold on that
um we can see what impact that has
and does that lead to settledness or does it lead to more spinning around
and so this you know as as long as we begin to open our awareness
to see this we will begin to see and
kind of inner functions of this and i want begin to see the
i don't like to use the word logic because it doesn't feel logical sometimes they're pretty chaotic
but we will begin to see certain patterns and we'll begin to know
what will actually support a sense of well-being and what doesn't
does that seem to land yeah okay thank you
maybe the last one if there is one
otherwise
well then we can stop right here thank you so much everyone for your practice
and um may you continue take good care