good morning Sangha good morning nice to see you all
and um chat form lovely to see the greetings from all
over the place really beautiful the weather reports the
warmth that you all share with each other it's really meaningful it's really meaningful
to be here so we're right at the top of the hour so I'm gonna go ahead and start Us in the
meditation just
introducing some playfulness experimentation this
morning so to notice whatever feelings are happening whatever mood whatever
excitement or emotions are happening from engaging with each other or if you've
just arrived and you're not seeing chap noticing where you're at just noticing
the internal weather
the sense of familiarity being here or of newness if it's new for you
and finding a comfortable posture a balance of
relaxation and alertness
adjusting anything that needs to adjust for your comfort you'd be rocking back and forth in your
seats wherever you're sitting and finding balance
an internal balance
[Music] and allowing any excess tension
just to fade away on the out breath
and attuning to an overall sense of your body
your body immersed in this moment immersed in whatever weather is outside
contact of skin on air air on skin
and from the inside the contact of breath
gently soothingly stretching a diaphragm the belly
perhaps movements moving the rib cage
or chest ever so slightly
perhaps Sensations in the nostrils or at the top of the lip
feeling the warmth the warmth of the breath Within
and perhaps coolness as air becomes breath
from the outside
taking a moment to scan through the whole body
acknowledging in a friendly way possible whatever's there today
perhaps areas of heaviness or lightness
movement or Stillness
foreign go
and inviting to sweep through your whole body
inviting a softening the balance of relaxation and alertness
settling the attention on whatever
object or anchor of attention is most comfortable for you
my instructions will be on breathing mindfulness and breathing
for the most part and the invitation is to use what works for
you playing with it experiment
bringing awareness to the Forefront of experience
allowing other concerns then and there
to fade to the background
noticing any soothing qualities or pleasure
even just a sense of aliveness on the in-breath
and out breath
resting
experimenting
experimenting with how it feels to place the attention
more firmly or more lightly on the sensations of breathing
which brings more satisfaction
noticing the differences between the beginning of the inhale
and the fullness of the lungs at the top of the inhale
noticing the release the beginning of the exhale
the feeling all the way through the exhale
to that letting go that moment of Stillness
at the end of the exhale prior to the next natural allowing
of an in-breath
encouraging continuous contact
of attention and breathing
in an open allowing spaceships kind of way
foreign
most of the remainder of this meditation will be in silence
the encouragement is to play with
how you engage with the breath the moment Sensations
lightly to maximize a sense of immersion in this
meditation
and when that sense if that sense of immersion emerges
to rest allow ride the wave until it makes sense
to bring a little bit of experimentation in again
foreign
and for the last few minutes of this meditation
opening opening the awareness up to the overall flow of experience
perhaps still maintaining contacts
with breathing the body
allowing the flow of Sensations
moved our atmospherics of the heart and mind
arising flowing and passing away and
mental phenomena sound
opening up and allowing a global sense the overall
inner processes
stepping back
foreign
taking a moment to notice again the overall internal weather
sense of heart mind especially observing any
corners of experience
that are Pleasant peaceful
any good qualities that may have been cultivated
perhaps patient or awareness the touch of immersion their stability
and tuning into your heart
setting the intention to share these benefits this goodness
with those this life touches
perhaps with an internal gesture of offering
wishing others well as close and near or far and wide
as it feels right to send those missions
we have the benefits of our practice here together be shared with all beings
may all beings be saved may all beings be happy
may all beings be healing or healthy
may they be peaceful and may they be free
foreign
thank you for the sincerity of your practice [Music]
so good morning again Sangha
today the topic is interest and experimentation in practice
this is the fifth in a five part series on a teaching the Buddha talk the basis
the steps or fundamentals to develop spiritual power and
meditative success a list of known as the idipada
and the poly for interest and experimentation is the Mansa
v i m a m s a
and today I'll cover two main points about this and then kind of briefly
review how this quality of Interest exploration investigation that's sometimes called
fits in with the other bases or enthusiasm or desire
um Veria energy or effort or mind and of course the two tripod
legs that have been with each species all along which is wholehearted engagement
and collectiveness immersion concentration
so the two main points are to be a
naturalist of the inner Ecology of your body heart
and mind In This Moment and second that there's an art and the science
and the encouragement is to be curious kind of Applied curiosity to be
experimental and to notice action and results
inputs and outputs but before I get into those points
first let's explore the range of meanings of this Factor
kind of a word cloud as I've been doing so some of the translations
or vimansa are experimentation
consideration and as I see these consider feel into
how they land in your body your heart your mind what associations they bring
considering that investigation
discernment close examination
active intelligence empirical inquiry
applied curiosity creative exploration
and receptive interest
so as with the sort of ingredients of all the other bases
practicing with this interest experimentation is on a Continuum it
depends on the other conditions in the practice in our lives in any
given session in any given day we there's an active end which is kind of
like the experimentation and the close investigation all the way through sort of a gentle
creative exploration or applied curiosity
to a more receptive end does this open allowing interest
any and all of these can be appropriate in a given meditation session and as the practice gains momentum at
different points whether it's over the course of years or on a long retreat it tends to be wiser to move towards the
more open and receptive end at a certain point the practice kind of does us you might have noticed this
occasionally where there's just this sense of coasting right
so in experimenting with experimentation
it's helped helpful as I mentioned earlier earlier to observe your
experience like a naturalist like a scientist and I'm remembering an anecdote someone
um said in a Dharma talk in the past year I can't remember who
they were walking hiking and on the hiking trail they ran across
someone who was just I think they were actually lying down on the earth and just closely examining this plant
and as they encountered each other on the path the um the hiker said hello and the
scientists the naturalist just looked up with this expression of lit up Joy about
the discovery they were making so that's part of the potential of this
close observation that that in itself can build a sense of
enthusiasm interest engagement immersion
so the key is to observe in this moment
it's not so helpful to and for the purposes of meditation it can be very
helpful in daily life but the purposes of meditation it's helpful to watch the cause and effect or the inputs and
outputs actions and results as we're meditating not so much to think
about the stories of the past or planning for the future but to look at those interactions as they're happening
it involves observing the details of the object of attention like we talked about
I've led us through this morning with the meditation and breathing
in that sense it's like that scientist looking at the details of the foliage of this plant on the ground right
or like a bird watcher watching the plumage
or the shape flight and song of a particular bird species
particular bird there's also this
benefit to looking at the overall biosphere or ecosystem
how the body and mind are relating to each other in the moment how the whole
system is interacting oh when I take this longer breath
my my back relaxes or when I exhale in this way
there's a subtle sense of pleasure in the chest
so to notice notice these relationships
there's an art and a science to this this is the second point and so
to be creative be playful be experimental at times I think of it as running these little testable
experiments or like an artist mixing different colors on the palette and just seeing how they
work seeing how the brush stroke works so in the moment this can be like
fiddling with a recipe adding a touch of seasoning while cooking or turning up or down the heat
and tasting noticing the effects many results though as all of you know
by now I'm sure unfold over time so patience is really really helpful
it's um more like that simile of the garden
changing the conditions a little plowing in a bit more mulch or fertilizer changing the watering regimen and
noticing the shifts over the days in the plant and then noticing at the end of
the season the difference in the fruits the yield
so um meditation many of the true benefits take
a season or more right to ripen there is though
a big place for this more closely related feedback I guess I'll say and
this is more feedback in the sense of instantaneous or close
noticing of results it's like the action reflection action model of learning and this is used in
many fields including in spiritual counseling field I do which is to do something
to reflect on it and then tweak what you do the next time
and notice the results reflect on it again
there's also a real benefit every now and then just stepping back
and looking at the big picture whether it's how the practice is affecting the overall mood or tone and mind heart and
body in the moment in one session at the end of a session but also every now and then to look at
how focusing meditation is affecting my life your life
and adjust a just course appropriately I had the great benefit the first year I
practiced I think it was I didn't know any better I didn't know anything was supposed to happen when sitting
so what kept me going was the difference in how I was showing up and experiencing the rest of my life
with huge changes but they were changes they felt good
more relaxed a little happier and more aware
so in some ways this quality of overall
observation curiosity interest experimentation
Loops back to apply to all of the other bases that we've talked about this week
right noticing the overall
way these species are developing and how each one is showing up that is a
kind of Investigation or interest
the Buddha made two other overall suggestions he made a number but I'm going to focus on two
who are relating to these species for Spiritual power one is with each quality desire or
Chanda varia or effort s subjective sense of Mind heart and
investigation itself to notice to Slack
or two tense like tuning that guitar
it should be neither two sac and we're too tense a tunic to tune it
and then the other is to have it neither be internally contracted
or externally distracted so those are two kind of shortcuts you
can bring to any quality in meditation really two tenths two Slack
too constricted or obsessive to distracted and Scattered
or is it just right or even in the range of just right
so each meditation each process in this
journey you step in this journey of cultivating heart and mind invites us
to learn receive adapt I just want to invite you to enjoy it
when possible be playful or hold it lightly and to be with it with patience sense of
connection so this is the idipada
the basis for Spiritual power and I just also want to acknowledge in
closing that these teachings tend to emphasize more doing than a lot of mindfulness teachings
so please keep in mind thank God that these doings these
explorations tend to unfold best in a field of
relaxation and ease and Trust in the process
so may these bases of spiritual power invite you Empower you to deepen and enjoy your
practice thank you so much it's been a joy to be with you