so good day everyone and i'm happy to be back i don't know how many of you noticed that
the tuesday and wednesday recordings were the broadcasts were pre-recorded
i i had to go away for a couple of days fun
i had to go off a couple of days to accompany my wife on her
that trip and now i'm back and now it's literally live
so continuing on this
theme of sati patana there's a paradigm shift that happens as
we do this practice especially the the third
foundation and that is that we go from a fragmented mind
to a mind that becomes whole inclusive
that a fragmented mind is a mind that uh well one of the things that fragments the mind is excessive preoccupation with
desire beginning with any preoccupation any singular focus kind of being caught up
in desire the mind is limited by the desire
preoccupation with ill will or aversion and the mind is limited by that and is
narrowed and the scope has become smaller and same thing with delusion
with mindfulness we're beginning to expand the scope of the mind of awareness to become not absorbed in
in great hatred and delusion absorbed in the hindrances but rather becoming broader wider
stronger bigger to be able to include all those but not
be limited by them and then at some point the paradigm shift is when we have a sense of the
mind as a whole the wholeness and how good that feels how satisfying it is and
how comforting or at home it is to be at home in the in the kind of the
wide broad inclusive mind and it's a it's a
kind of a it's a kind of a big shift because there can be so much authority
so much pull into the world of desires and aversions
and the hindrances and they can feel so compelling i feel like that's the right place to be that's
appropriate it's justified and and
and so and to pull ourselves out of that world is quite difficult
because the the habit of it the pull of it is so strong the insistence of it
but as the sati patana deepens we are able to no longer be limited or caught
up in that limited world and start becoming aware of a shift to something that's more holistic
sometimes called the expanded mind or a big mind and that can include everything
in its scope so so we'll sit a little bit with this
to assume a meditation posture
where the posture is the beginning of a shift away from the
preoccupations of the mind
to something broad or wider more inclusive
kind of like going from uh cooped up in a small little room
beginning to go outdoors wide open
so the body can be beginning of that shift assuming a upright posture
sitting strong and present
and to take some care to awaken awareness in your body
beginning by taking some long slow deep breaths feeling the rib cage stretch and expand
the belly expand as you inhale
and relax
relaxing your body as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and allowing your awareness to roam around your body
feeling the different parts of your body
in a way to awaken them or to welcome them into the wholeness
of being here and now
and perhaps as you exhale
to relax more in your body
and as you relax to feel the effect of the relaxing
and then breathing normally and
settling into the experience of breathing
just enough that it highlights any ways in which you are
being pulled into the world of thought
and perhaps you can notice if you pulled into thoughts and ideas stories and memories
commentary that your attention might become limited
by those concerns
and there's a way that if you let go of them relax a thinking mind
you become aware of more than your preoccupation
aware of your body
aware of the state of your mind
is the mind contracted or expanded is it scattered or settled
is it possible too is the mind
tight or is it loose and open
is it receptive
or closed
okay
and settling into your breathing
every exhale relax relaxing the mind and letting go
of your thoughts
every exhale relaxing every inhale receiving
the experience of breathing
if you're involved in your thoughts see if you can
realize and even feel maybe
what is beyond the edges of your thinking
if your thinking has a lot of desire or aversion in it
the desire and aversion doesn't fill the universe it's in you
in the mind awareness can be expand beyond the edges of desire
the edges of aversion
and as you breathe let the breathing expand inhale expand
outward in this into this wider world
massaging an awareness that's larger
more inclusive than any particular thing
in a sense your mind or your awareness
can feel like it's as
extends as far away as the furthest sound that you hear
if all the sounds for the sound
occurs within the sphere
of perception
on the exhale relax any tension or contraction in the mind
in the brain
the mind becomes broad and still
like the broad and still morning lake
in the windless quiet dawn
if you're involved in any thoughts right now see if you can shift your allegiance
from thinking to awareness
maybe a broad wide awareness that is able to and willing
to be aware of whatever is happening in the senses hearing
smelling tasting touching
seeing even with the inner eye
an awareness that's open and wide and receptive
to the degree that you're you are relaxed now calm or
peaceful does the relaxed state or the peaceful
state calm state
is it contracted more contracted or more expanded
is it more a very small little thing or does it have a feeling of being
large or not without strong boundaries
edges
and if you're aware of some more expanded state of being
might you recognize that it is more inclusive or expanded
than preoccupation with any kinds of thinking
more expansive and open than any fixation on desire or aversion
and that there's more room for all of who you are
in the relaxed expanded awareness
and then to whatever degree that you're calm
see if you can now expand the scope of your knowing your awareness
your consideration for the people in your lives
your life
the people that you will read about in the news the people you'll see in your neighborhoods
in your communities and see if they can be included
in relaxed awareness relax consideration
and in this open relaxed state
to have thoughts of goodwill well-wishing for others
thoughts about how it would be quite wonderful if others could be happy and safe
peaceful and free
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and to the degree to which we have an open relaxed awareness
may we have that as the medium through which we contribute to the
welfare and happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
[Music]
so hello everyone and
so we're now continue continuing to talk about the third foundation of mindfulness
but i would like to point out that in the second third and fourth each of them
as the as a description of the practice unfolds there is a shift
and i like to think of each of these three as being progressive or describing a
little journey that meditator takes and the second foundation
one begins by just becoming aware of the feeling tone of experience pleasant
unpleasant or neutral as we settle in and become more familiar with it more sensitive
we're able then to distinguish between those things which are pleasant of the flesh and those which are not of the
flesh that which is um in the part of the sensual world of mind
and body and those which are more spiritual in nature and so we're making a shift this journey
from one into the other as we deepen the practice in the second foundation and the third
foundation uh we begin by becoming aware of a mind that's accompanied with great hate and
delusion and then there's a a journey from that state of mind into
what can be called more meditative or spiritual states of mind and
and that's what the last four pairs of mind states are
but if this journey through uh from these uh mind states that are characterized by great hatred and
delusion um have an intermediate kind of a stepping stone to it
and that is this uh the fourth one uh fourth of the of the eight pairs
the fourth one is that um is um
um a scattered mind or a contracted mind
when the mind is not caught up in greed hatred and delusion anymore it's sometimes a little bit lost to have
great hit and delusion is always to have some focus of attention some concern something that we want
something we don't want something we're confused about and and the degree to which we're
focused on this object of thought this object of concern it limits the mind
the language of the buddha is it's a limitation for awareness of the mind the mind becomes smaller contracted its
scope becomes very sometimes very very narrow we can feel the mind gets kind of tight and narrow and just preoccupied
with one thing and and it can even feel pleasant a lot of
good energy or strong energy compelling energy habit energy around desires and around aversions and
around the illusion and the mind just kind of goes into it like because it's like like a black hole
where a strong gravitational pull pulls us into this and it can feel so natural so normal
that we don't realize how the impact it has on us and how we don't realize so easily that there's another
whole option when the mind is no longer focused on
objects these objects in this kind of narrow constricted or forceful way
um then it's there's a mind goes through a transition sometimes where it's a little bit confused not quite sure
what what to focus on or what to do it's kind of like if if
desires and aversions and delusions are kind of like caffeine it keeps us energized
when we stop taking the caffeine the mind goes through a period of adjustment
and that period of adjustment is the mind can either doesn't have a particular object that is particularly
concerned with but the mind hasn't developed its capacity for subtle concentrated presence
and so the mind then can get scattered just jumps around kind of looking for something to be concerned with but not
enough focus to really settle on anything the mind becomes scattered
or the mind just comes shrunken it just sinks in on itself sloth and torpor sets in kind of
giving up or kind of like deflation that could happen
and so without greed hidden delusion sometimes it's deflation sometimes there's scatteredness of mind
restlessness of the mind that can happen but we keep practicing we keep
you know it can feel like things are going backwards because where mind is all scattered jumping around or more deflated and and
shrunken but it's actually a transition time sometimes we have to go through it be patient with it and just be willing to
breathe with it and be aware of it and then at some point the some of the
fruits of practice come into play in the first one it says in this third foundation
one knows an expanded mind as an expanded mind and one knows a
non-expanded mind is a non-expanded mind mahachita could also mean big mind one
knows a big mind so here mind
in the in the earlier exercises one knows a mind accompanied by desire as a mind accompanied by desire accompanied
by a version as accompanied by a version that the mindfulness shows us or creates a
wider context of the mind to be aware of desires and aversions so the desired version doesn't kind of take over fully
um and so desiring a version just part of the mind it's big influence on every
part in the in this transition after this this contracted or restless
mind there comes this time when the mind starts be feeling expensive
open wide large because the mind and awareness
become more and more closely linked rather than or overlap or coterminous
and and now we can almost talk as synonyms that awareness and mind become almost
the same that awareness becomes broad and expensive that can be include
everything and this idea of an inclusive awareness
an open mind open set of perceptions that everything
that happens is allowed to appear in its own time in the field of perception in the world
of what we perceive and there's not a for or against our experience is there's not a preference
for one thing over another the preference is to not for the object of attention not
for the thing that we're aware of but the preference is to rest in this wide or calm awareness
the awareness that can receive things in a relaxed way
it can know things in a relaxed acts do i perceive and
and so in the language of the buddha when we're too concerned with some
purpose then the mind is limited by that purpose if the if we're not constricted by a
purpose or if the purpose in a sense is to just relax and open up
then the mind is not limited anymore it's not bounded it's not con contracted
it's not tight and narrow and it becomes broader and wider kind of
like the feeling maybe that if you're inside a small teen little cabin for a long time and all claustrophobic
and you go out into the wide open fields open space you know maybe high in the
mountains with a great vista there's something an expansive feeling that
arises certainly that the vista is expensive but something like uh opens up in the
mind in the heart that makes it also kind of like a breath of fresh air it's kind of expansiveness that it takes as
well so you don't have to sit go out to a great vista point to see
a great view to feel the mind become expensive even with the eyes closed the mind
becomes quite expensive quite large because
it's its nature to be that way it's uh it's how it is
awareness is consciousness is when um it's not being channeled into particular
direction it's not being held and contracted or being used to focus on a
particular thought a particular concern a particular desire or aversion
and so to be able to drop the limitations in the mind the contractions of the mind
and that's why a calm meditative state for many people the mind begins to feel
kind of expensive or large or peaceful broad
and and so here we begin this journey now into more spiritual states or dharma
states whereas greed hate and delusion those mind states
are not particularly not particularly dharmic not dharmic at all
the awareness that can include everything and be broad enough is dharmic
and kind of paired up paradoxically or ironically it can also include
the presence of greed hate and delusion nothing is but the difference is that the mind is
not contracted or focused on greed hate and delusion it just knows it's there but in this
wide field just one thing about many we're not identified with it we're not prioritizing it we're not
bothered by it caught a continent in its grip and uh and this idea the mind that's not
caught by anything does not doesn't stop for anything doesn't get involved with
anything entangled with anything is abe the mind that's just able to allow things to arise
and pass to be there when they're there but without being for or against
and that begins that begins a feeling of a mind that's whole a holistic mind
and this is one of the great delights and pleasures of meditation starting to feel more and more whole
that we feel whole our whole sense of beingness feels more holistic and we come into our wholeness
rather than the contractedness or the or the narrowness of particular
preoccupations and concerns and how to make that transition
from desire and aversion to this expanded state
it really helps if we no longer
are convinced or not us but maybe our mind convinced that what's important is to
pursue desires what's important is to be involved in aversion that or even get what's important is to
kind of be constantly preoccupied with our delusions our thoughts our confusions
about things all those who can feel how that limits us
and to begin relaxing and softening and opening is until we feel like
everything is included all of who we are has a place all of who we are has a respected place
in awareness and consciousness this is a game changer for people who do
meditation and over time it begins realizing we're actually much better off
in this peaceful state than in the desire state in the wanting state or the aversive state
and so if you have um you know if you have a half an hour free in the evening
and you have uh you know there's a common desire you get
pulled into but instead of that you go and meditate or go for a walk and do something that
allows you to kind of tap into this expanded state you might find that it's
much more pleasant much more satisfying in the long run
so um we'll continue tomorrow on this third foundation
this these dharma states that opened up in the last four exercises
and i want to make an announcement so
imc now has started a fundraising drive to support refugees who are fleeing ukraine now
they're supposed to be close to 2 million or so and and the organization that we're
supporting is save the children for a number of reasons one is there's a there's a little bit of a personal
connection to that they're one of the highest rated charities i think in the world they've been around for a hundred years
and they're involved in the ground in some of the refugee camps and some of the reception centers um
on the borders uh ukraine offering care for some of the most vulnerable people the children and the
um and families and so um if you'd like to donate to
this fund all the money you you'll give to imc for this purpose will go to the save the children
and the way to do it is that on the what's new page on the home page of imc's website
there's a there's a section in the bottom right called what's new and there there's notice about
fundraising for the ukraine and the button there the donate button there
is specif specific for imc to know it's for the ukraine so um
maybe tomorrow i'll post it here on the youtube chat as well so we're doing this we're raising money until
through monday we did this for haiti after the earthquake last august and we raised
thirty thousand dollars which was quite impressive and maybe we can do something similar maybe even more
to support this provides support for this tremendous need
there in eastern europe so thank you all and
i look forward to our time to get tomorrow