[Music]
so i want to begin this talk
by
uh recounting um
a famous uh
psychology experiment some of you have
probably heard of it
and
so
being told again is maybe not so
interesting you know it but the
implications of it are interesting and i
think important to consider
and this was an experiment done at the
princeton theological seminary in 1970.
with
and the subjects who are going to go
through unwittingly go through this uh
experiment
were theology students of chris
christian being trained to be christian
ministers
and um
and who supposedly were quite familiar
with their scriptures and stories in
their scriptures
and uh
the experiment was at one of these these
different different times the theology
student was
told that
they were late but they would you know
they really need to go across campus
to give a talk on the story of the good
samaritan
the good samaritan story if you don't
know had to do with a man who was sick
on the side of the road i think he'd
been robbed and beaten up and was very
sick and
you know and maybe in the danger of
dying
and
a variety of people coming down the road
just ignored him
until this man who was a belonged to the
people of the called submit
cemetery and samaritans
stopped and helped him and then
supported him took him to it in
left and and so made it possible for the
person to
um
not die to save the person's life so the
good samaritan was a stranger who stops
to care for someone
and um
so i told my wife this morning that i
was going to give this talk on this kind
of story and
and
she says well if
on the way to imc if someone needs you
you better stop
[Laughter]
and then i thought
i better have i better i should have
left earlier then
so
so they did this experiment so the
theology students were they had to go
give this talk about the good samaritan
but they were given very little time
they're like late for giving the talk so
they were told to go across campus to
give the talk
on the way there unbeknownst to them
an actor was there uh disheveled and
dirty and
you know and
sitting propped up against the wall kind
of slumped over kind of hidden their
hands or something in their knees
and as the person who walked by this per
this actor was moaning and groaning
and uh and the study was to see who
would stop
and after all the what was the subject
of their talk was that very thing
and a great majority of the seminary
students did not stop
but just kept going
and the idea being that somehow
in being in a hurry
uh people don't have time to help
the h the hurried mindset maybe you
don't even notice maybe what's there
because you're so in a hurry to get
something and
maybe it's high pressure maybe they're
being graded on the giving this talk may
be and so the pressure all kinds of
things contributed to
you know not
stopping to take care of someone
and um so it's kind of heartbreaking
that's how
how it works
but
so
the implications of this story for us
is that um certainly one simple one is
that maybe is that
if we want to be live in the world
in a way to help people to help society
help this world of ours
don't be in a hurry
don't even be a hurry to help maybe
don't be in a hurry give yourself time
live a different life
then um
because there's certain ways of living
life
where
you're not you don't in in the mindset
and the heart set
to be able to notice and stop and care
and come from that caring place for the
world
this world of ours for some of us has so
many temptations so many things to do so
many demands
the more there's been
time saving devices kind of invented
over the last 150 years or so
the more it gives us a chance to do more
more things and more things and more
things and so it's kind of epidemic in
our kind of circles for some of us
how much little time there is to do all
the things that we can do and fill our
time with
how does that affect us how does it i
think one of the ways is that it
makes it bring make it causes us
sometimes to be out of touch
with important healthy valuable places
within us
because we're so distracted we're so
caught up in a hurry we're preoccupied
we're doing things
rather than feeling things and being
present
so in uh in buddhism there's discussion
of a lot of discussion and uh of um
kind of opposites
like there's uh there's greed and
there's generosity there's hatred and
there's love
there's delusion and there's wisdom and
this idea that we've talked about the
unwholesome and the wholesome
and
when we presented that kind of simple
way
this kind of divide
between these two
it could almost seem like they're kind
of not exactly of equal value
but have some equality to them it's like
a like a seesaw or something or a
spectrum and it's one side and the other
side and they kind of have equal weight
or in that spectrum or something
but they're radically different
the wholesome and the unwholesome the
the um
this healthy place we can come from
where we can maybe the place that might
help others
and the other place which is unwholesome
the place where we're not just simply
not helpful but maybe worse or maybe
even cruel or unkind to people
uh they're
they are um they're they're kind of very
different in a number of ways
it's not either or
first of all
the wholesome side has a different
source inside of us than the unwholesome
side
and this different source is different
place the origin for where they're born
is so different
that if we're interested in one more
than the other
live in that source live in that place
where they arise from
the other is it's not either or
it's in some ways possible to have both
coexisting
and this is actually very important for
our healing it's very important for the
path of practice that's trying to
in a healthy way
find freedom from some of the
unwholesome motivations and
and uh ways of being in the world that
we have
so the the idea of this having different
sources within
um
the um
so
uh the preoccupied mind
the mind that's spinning and
ruminating caught up in its concerns its
worries its conceits
its problems all kinds of things that's
kind of we can get lost in the labyrinth
of our concerns and preoccupations
that there's so much energy there and so
many kind of certain kind of emotions
that go into it
anxiety is a common one
uh desires wanting wanting is another
one
the
you know ill will aversion not wanting
is another one there's a lot of kind of
energy that goes into that kind of
preoccupied caught up mind state
that comes with insistence sometimes it
comes with
a
despair comes with undermining us comes
with kind of um
uh keeping us in touch with a part of
ourselves with if we're if we are in
touch with ourselves that hurts it's
difficult
and in the the pain of it all
it tends to we can recoil from it
in such a way that we put more energy
into that kind of mindset
and we're more spinning out and more
angry and there's anger and hate that
just
just cultivates more of the same there's
greed that cultivates more of the same
there's fear
that cultivates more of the same
if we stay in this kind of reactive kind
of i think of it as kind of a
uh i think of it as
especially as kind of higher up in the
head
in where we are in the head
spinning
there's another source
and there's a source that i i think
spatially is deeper within us maybe in
the heart or maybe in the belly
when we're settled on ourselves
when we're not caught in the rumination
and preoccupations of our lives
when we're not caught in this spinning
of emotions that are pushing us and
driving us and
and being like
reinforcing it themselves in us
if those can become quiet enough and
still enough
soft and you know and more in the
background or not even there
and we can become settled
here
then there's a places of love
of care
there's a places of generosity
there's places of wisdom and
of patience
that
really they need time to exist
they need space to exist
i like to think of these parts these
really healthy parts of ourselves
often in ways people live their lives i
like to think of them as shy
and so uh
you know they're shy they they need to
be given time and space and
to feel safe to come forward and be
there
and
if we have a loss in self-criticism and
self-hate lost in
in um you know blaming the world for all
our problems lost in our fear and
preoccupations
the healthy parts of us
are kind of they're shy right they're
maybe a little
tender and tentative about
showing up
but if we could
give time and quiet and openness and
enough time to let these shy places come
forward
enough time to give ourselves
a real real opportunity to feel or sense
the generosity
the love the care
the
the generosity
all these healthy parts that exist in us
then those can condition us those can
affect us
they have an impact to live in those
close to those
if we are just kind of and they also are
self-reinforcing
and so but we have to give time for them
to be able to
be self-reinforcing support and change
us and open us and develop us
and
you know it's not like you check it off
generous done that
you know
and
now let's go out and get the ice cream
and you know i deserve it and we need to
rush around the time in either town
trying all the different ice creams
until we find the right one is going to
do it for us
because checked off the generosity thing
because you smiled at someone
and that's done
you know the idea is you know to live a
different way
to come from this place to make time to
feel the generosity to feel this
different source
and that's one of the possibilities that
come from something like meditation it's
not the only way to do this
but it's one of the purposes of
meditation
is to give time
to settle
and feel and open
and start feeling what's this deeper
place
and let and live in that source let that
be the source
in case you're
you know
interested in the pursuit of wealth
over everything else
the buddha had a response to that
he said what comes from this source
is the greatest wealth
greatest wealth is not money and goods
and material things it's really your
loving kindness your compassion
that comes that lives within you there
your integrity
and so that's how you become wealthy
and it's a wonderful wealth because it
fills you from the inside out
that
external wealth can never do
it's not uncommon for me to hear stories
about people who are phenomenally
wealthy
who are empty inside who are you know
don't don't have any not in touch with
his inner wealth
and
some years ago i had there was a person
my circle of friends people i knew who
was probably the poorest person i knew
and the way that he lived his life
i saw him as the wealthiest
you know material he was poor but
in terms of how he lived his life not
just how he felt his life was but just
like the feeling of abundance and
it was quite inspiring to me
so this uh to it takes so to really
appreciate this different source
of what motivates our life what animates
our life
and i would like to suggest
that there's no one but you
who take can take responsibility
for that where you come from we're what
motivates you deep down inside
um there's no pill that can do it for
you i think
i hope not
um you know there's no one else who can
do it for you
it isn't that you wait until you find
the person who's gonna you can be around
that's then you can do it
it's for you to do
and it's really a choice matter it's a
choice a choice point
and don't think it's so all or nothing
it's like i have to not have to choose
to be all good
and choose to avoid all bad it's not
it's not like that kind of all or
nothing
but it's a choice about where you lean
choice of where you want to come back to
what you want to be reminded of
what you want to inspire you
what you want to try to do that come
from the best you can
and this brings it to the topic a second
topic around this in that these things
can co-exist
luckily they can co-exist
and they can co-exist in a variety of
ways
but the most important way for a
practitioner
is that that part of us that's a healthy
part
can hold
and care for the part that is unhealthy
that part which is
full of greed hatred delusion fear
we don't want to dismiss it
because then it'll come back and bite us
i think
but rather
um we don't want to then kind of think
oh that i can't do that i have to now i
have to feel good
and then have set up a a
a resistance or a
wall between these parts of ourselves
but rather this as we get more and more
aware of this deeper place to come from
then we want to
have that deeper place hold or be
present for
the part that's difficult
because otherwise the that part is
difficult if it's ignored or repressed
will fester and come back in all kinds
of unhealthy ways
so pretending you're good doesn't work
and one of the simplest ways i don't
know simple maybe i should be careful
with the language i use
but i'll say it again but maybe i can
you can
reinterpret it for yourself
the simplest way of doing this
is
not to come from places of generosity
and love and wisdom that they like like
as easy to find
but
bring mindfulness attention
to what's happening
there's mindfulness is considered to be
healthy part of the healthy part of who
we are
and so if we can bring the attention
attentiveness
and hold the difficult parts of
ourselves and learn how to hold it
without
adding more
hatred to our hate
without adding more greed wanting
something so desperately
you know if only i can get rid of my
greed then i can really have that good
stuff
you know or feel like i'm a bad person
because i have delusion i'm supposed to
be wise i better get more books and read
you know then i can practice
but rather
these parts are rather difficult almost
like you it's useful to think of them
they need to be healed
they're parts of us that are kind of
wounded or broken or
hurt or
or undeveloped
and so
to hold them in awareness to hold them
in our good will to hold them in
friendliness
to be present for the make room for them
not so they can motivate us
not so that they drive us anymore
the driving force hopefully is this more
healthy place
as as whatever degree that you can
access it whatever small degree
and from that place
to hold what is an unhealthy earth that
needs to be resolved or settled or
healed
and some of us have a lot of pain
tremendous amount of psychological
emotional even physical pain sometimes
that comes from that's associated one
way or the other
with how we live
from this different source
and some of it is because the deeper
source the deeper parts the tender parts
the shy parts
have been hurt have been betrayed
welcome to society people do all kinds
of terrible things to each other
and uh and so all kinds of things make
it difficult even to be
in that deeper place because of the pain
and so part of this be we can do both
means we learn how to be present for the
pain
difficulty
we don't dismiss anything
but we allow to settle to open
and slowly we begin to more and more at
home
in this place of a deeper source
this deeper wellspring
for
the emotions the motivations
that according to this uh psychology
experiment i discussed
are were considered i think they were
considered more the helping dispositions
the helping
and the world needs more helpers doesn't
it
i think that there's not enough
but there's a lot there's plenty
so i some of you probably heard the
famous story that
mr rogers
told of his childhood
when he was young a kid and there was
some catastrophe in the world terrible
things happen in the world i think he
grew up during probably world war ii
and
and his mother would say
remember the helpers in many situations
there are more people helping than the
people who did the terrible things
remember that remember the helpers
so what about
the helper in you
what about you living from place of care
in of this world not because it's an
obligation
not because you should do it
because
you will do that
in your own personal way
if you can find that deeper source
within
if you can rest there come from there
and learn to be very careful
to recognize the difference between
these two different sources for
your behavior your speech and even how
you think
the source from which you that life
comes is a crucial to who you are
and many people don't don't know that
there's these two sources
most people think that the spinning
ruminating difficult challenging
preoccupied
reactive kind of mind
is what there is it's all they've ever
known
and it's a radical thing
to begin
discovering slowly maybe at first as
just trusting as possible
to begin
finding your way to this other source
within
and
thinking that it's shy
that if you want to receive the benefits
of it you have to spend time there close
to it
so for example when you maybe if you get
in touch with this little bit at the end
during something like meditation or
other things you do in your life
when the meditation or whatever thing is
over
don't live the checklist approach to
life okay done that
and pop out of your meditation and rush
off to the
you know
you know to kind of figure out what the
best netflix is to watch
you know
for you to be watching on your commute
to work
while you're checking emails and
and the news has to be you know you know
it's like
don't do that right after meditation
because
i mean you could but
but you but then you're not giving it
opportunity a chance
for this deeper source
to condition you to affect you to
to benefit you to reinforce something
really great
we have to live a different life
if you want to be have a different life
if you want to have a different life but
not change anything
it can't be a different life
so um
and maybe just maybe
you're more likely today to be the good
samaritan
if the need arises
that would be nice
or this week
this year
this life
so thank you all
very much
and as i said earlier
those of you who would like to come and
now and
meet outside
uh we need to have the folding chairs
which they're in the cabinet some people
know where they are
just the other hall
and we'll carry them out there and i'll
come out as soon as i can and join you
and we'll spend about half an hour
together just chatting about this
thank you