hello everyone and welcome to our monday beginning of the
week meditation and um i'm very happy to be back here
and sitting here in my very familiar meditation posture which
i've done so often enough that it is a kind of homecoming
to sit here to sit in this posture and immediately when i take this posture
usually i feel very content this deep sense of contentment
and so i'd like to suggest that a theme that you keep for this
meditation is contentment
and there's many ways of feeling contentment many reasons for feeling contentment
and and maybe there doesn't have to be many reasons just it's okay to just be
content with the moment content with being alive right now
even though there might be all kinds of things elsewhere outside of this posture outside of your meditation which
there's good cause to be discontent but maybe they don't have to be imported
maybe they don't have to be evoked maybe we can just let go of it for a few
minutes and experience contentment for no reason just to be here
or one of the great kind of pieces of
um i don't know spiritual spiritual wisdom or maybe pop
spirituality wisdom that i'm fond of is um
the idea of being content with what you have
rather than focusing on what you don't have sometimes the contentment can come with what you do have
and so in meditation um
uh you might want to uh think that what you have
that allows you to have actually a very deep contentment not to be troubled
not to be
overwhelmed by life and what's happening no need to be critical of the situation
and that is to be content that you have a practice content that you have a meditation practice a mindfulness
practice a kindness practice content
this is good and even if this practice we do is so valuable
it's even valuable when we do it imperfectly when we do it
you know a little bit so to be content that you have this
practice and maybe this contentment can uh save you from
the discontent that takes your mind away spins off in thoughts and desires and
aversions that can be for later but for now
here content just to be here practicing
so to begin with
sitting upright in an alert relaxed posture
and lower your gaze
and gently close your eyes
and regardless of how you're feeling in your body sitting meditating
whether it's comfortable or uncomfortable take a few long slow deep breaths
that somehow feels like it moves through the comfort of discomfort
to something larger sense of presence larger sense of body here
as you breathe in and fill your lungs with air and as you exhale
a fuller experience of just letting go of everything
including concern with comfort and discomfort
breathing in deeply and letting yourself become larger than anything
that's troubling you
exhaling and letting go maybe deeper inside than anything that
troubles you
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and letting yourself be content with whatever way your body is breathing
there's no right way to breathe in doing mindfulness let it be what it is
content that you get to breathe however imperfectly
and as you exhale to
relax and let go of the places in your body that hold
discontent maybe there's
some of the tensions of your face could be interpreted as a discontent
with how things are and as you exhale relax the face
and the exhale relaxing the shoulders
maybe there's a resistance resistance or holding back
in the shoulders that you can relax into a deeper contentment
less resistance
softening in the chest
softening discontent in the heart area
letting it soft soften melt
fade away on the exhale
and then softening in the belly
perhaps the belly can be content in some deep place within
in the depths of the belly
hmm
and then sitting here not with the idea that something has to be done or accomplished
that you need to succeed anything but sitting here close to
whatever feeling of contentment
just content with being alive just being alive is enough
and out of that contentment
let there be present moment awareness awareness of breathing
and out of present moment awareness let there arise contentment
that these two come hand in hand oh mindfulness and contentment content
to be mindful mindful to be content
one breath at a time
content you have a practice no matter how imperfect it might seem
one inhale at a time one exhale at a time
so
um
then
so
whatever is happening for you maybe you can be content
to breathe with it breathe through it
content that you can keep the breathing at the center
of your attention
instead of your concerns at the center of your attention
me
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider how contentment being content
might make you available for the world
discontent is a barrier to being connected to others to the world
to listening deeply and contentment is not a walling off or
a barrier contentment can be a state of being
available being available for what the needs are
of others being available for the sufferings of the world the joys of the world
to cry with others to laugh with them
may it be that this practice that we do makes us available for others
available to care for others
to be attuned to others
to be friends to others may
this practice that we do our availability to the world
be for the welfare and happiness of everyone
may this practice spread happiness into the world
may it spread safety where there is no safety
may it spread peace where there is no peace and may it spread freedom
where there is no freedom may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
yep
so monday morning and we start a new series
of in this general topic of emotions that covering the last weeks
and uh now it's uh this week it's going to be states that we have emotional states
perhaps that are kind of the opposites of each other
but that live in relationship to each other sometimes a pendulum swings one side to the other
and sometimes we react to one and the other arises and vice versa
uh or that they uh both sides of this of this range
um have a place in our lives and so to appreciate that there's these two sides
that live in dynamic relationship to each other and and to appreciate understand them deeper
and so for today i want to talk about contentment and discontent
there is healthy contentment healthy discontent
and there is unhealthy contentment and unhealthy um
discontent and so to really look and see more deeply what is this world of contentment
discontent that we live in the um
to live in a world of discontent is often a world of suffering
to continue living a world of stress of greed of hatred is stressful
and it can arise out of our discontent with how things are
is to pile more discontent on top of it we can out of the discontent the
difficulties of our life we can get caught up in greed and hatred and fear
and there's a healthy discontent
with suffering buddhist practice that does involve a discontentment and intolerance even
in a certain particular way to our suffering not intolerance where tolerance
associated with hostility and bias and prejudice but rather intolerance and say you know
i'm not going to be content with a life of suffering i'm not going to be content with a life that i'm
miserable and live in constant fear or constant
um discouragement or stress and so that inspires practice a certain
discontent that inspires practice but then at some point there is
um so that to be content with things as they are sometimes means being content with
things which you know are to our detriment
so but to be content
with is a very important valuable state
for people who are doing buddhist practice and doing mindfulness to learn to be content with
through having few wishes when we want all the time we want and
what we want then um you know there can be a strong discontent
and and but to have fewness of wishes and just be happy and content with what we
have can provide a very satisfying state of
being it also can provide a very positive state to be available for the wonderful
things in our life if we're discontented and always wanting more and more different things we might
not be available to really appreciate what we do have and what is good here
the um um there's this wonderful story that i
that's told many different ways recently i read the version by pablo uh
kohilo and um so it goes something like this that uh
there was a fisherman who would go out to sea every morning get up early in the morning go out to fish and
and catch enough fish for the day to take to bring back for the family to
eat and sell a few of them for some of the things they needed and would come back in the you know in
mid morning and then would play with his children on the beach and a delightful time playing
and then he would go home and spend a good part of the afternoon with his wife and maybe siesta hang with her
and then uh would go into the evening and spend a good number of hours
in the village square with his friends and talking and chatting and having a nice time
and he would do this he did this for a long time and then one day a um
a very successful businessman came by and noticed how he was living his life
and he said you know it'd be pretty easy for you to take out a loan and get a boat and
there's a lot more fish out there for you to fish you can spend a few more hours of the day fishing and
you'd be able to pay back the loan quickly and then buy a bigger boat and um and why should i do that says a
fisherman well then you would have more money you can actually then buy a fleet of boats
and hire people to work and pretty soon you'd have enough money to
start a whole company and you could have the international headquarters near your village and
and run this huge conglomerate of of
fishing and selling fish and and um and then when you're uh
you know after many years of doing this you'll be able to retire and then you can
just get it then when you're retired you can enjoy yourself you can just get up in the morning and go into the sea go
fish for a few fish and come back and enough for the day and then play with your children at the
beach and and um hang out with your wife in the afternoon and your friends in the
evening and the fisherman said well that's what i'm doing now already
why should i wait until you know i retire and so uh to be content with what we
have is partly the story of that this i think the theme of that story
and um and when do we do that in such a way that um
it allows for something uh profound to happen for us
when we when do we when does contentment open the doors to the practice
to see ourselves deeply and to move through layers and deeper and deeper contentment and joy and peace
and happiness move through layers of letting go
of this layers of discontent layers of suffering of greed and desires
um you know one of the advantages of meditation one of the really important aspects of it
is that as we settle and get quieter and more concentrated we start seeing aspects of our inner
life that are not available running around everyday life running around discontent
taking care of things doing things and so we start seeing the deeper levels
of healthy and unhealthy discontent the deeper layers of places of holding of clinging of fear
that we're living by and and then we let go
and so then as we do so we start feeling deeper and deeper layers of of
freedom of happiness of contentment of peace
so um so this whole world of contentment
and discontent has a lot to do with the world of desires and the classic language in
buddhism is that people who practice should have few
should be content by having few desires some desires desires for practice ours
to be free desire just to help the world but maybe not it desires for
expensive cars and expensive homes and expensive you know all kinds of things it's possible so many desires
and this modern world for some of us it's uh there's so many
things to do and to acquire it's astounding and it can be
stressful to live in a world of so much temptation
and so fewness of wishes desires but then there's a whole other layer
and um and the this world of contentment and discontent as it gets settled and
more and more settled and peaceful and quiet it all comes like a funnel down through the spout of the funnel to
a whole other world of being available being available to what the world is
about being available to the uh the you know the
cool breeze against our cheek being available to notice the colors of green in the trees
around the property around the town being available to sip tea and enjoy oneself being
available for meditation being available for honesty about what's really happening here for us as we
become more mindful being available to truth-telling oh this
is what's happening to have enough contentment to be quiet enough to be subtle enough
to start being more and more honest about what is here being available for the truth
being available to see what is not true so
as we navigate and find our way in this world of contentment and discontent
as we begin seeing where this where there's possibilities of healthy contentment
and where we might get caught in unhealthy contentment
when we start seeing where healthy discontent is and where unhealthy discontent is and we
start maneuvering and finding our way and finding some freedom from the incessant desires that can keep us
discontented in unuseful ways then there can be a settling and a
quieting a contentment with just things as content with how things are
imagine standing in a long line at a government agency to get something like
your driver's license and there's nowhere to go because you have to stand in the line
imagine being content because being discontented there is just
a waste of time it serves no purpose
it doesn't make things go faster it doesn't help you feel more healthy and happy
to be available for contentment with what is
when that's the best alternative to know how to let go of desires
wanting things to be different when that's not really what's possible
to learn how to be content with what is when what is is actually quite wonderful
maybe what is is more wonderful than what you're striving for if you're striving for
wealth and fame and all kinds of things
so i'd encourage you to spend the day
looking at your relationship to contentment and discontent
and and perhaps you can begin to appreciate the greater range of ways that
contentment can be healthy and also the healthy ways of being
discontent and
and in the process of doing that find yourself more settled and available
for this world available for your practice
available for yourself so thank you
and so this will be kind of the theme for this this week these i'll do this pairing of two different kind of states
and just uh explore them a little bit with you
and tomorrow will be gladness and sadness so thank you