testing oh that's maybe too loud yeah testing testing
how's that sound is that still a little bit loud yeah a little bit not too much lower there
because i get so quiet sometimes okay thank you
[Music]
did you all see the handouts on the stage when you came in right on the end of the stage and then
there's also a small little handout for a day long it's coming up september 9th
it's an introduction to mindfulness day long here on a saturday so there's a handout for today's class
plus the the flyer yeah
and for people on youtube the handouts are going to be attached to the recordings
so when you go to audio dharma and you look up the recording you can
find the attachment the handout that we're giving
great so welcome welcome welcome back welcome for the
first time nice to see you again
this is the fourth
fourth night uh out of five an introduction to mindfulness meditation my name is kodo this is tanya
it's a real pleasure to share in this i'm noticing as i say that it's a pleasure to share in this
in a way that is it's a it's a sense of pleasure that is more like well-being or more like
a deeper sort of happiness than the pleasures of chasing after and getting what we want
so settled so nice
so these last weeks just to situate us these last weeks we've been giving a
sort of progressive instruction in mindfulness meditation and the way we've been doing it is um
beginning in a sense at the center of our experience with our breathing
using this very simple faculty of attention to direct direct to the breathing settle
in with the breathing find a home or a companion with the breathing and then gradually with that basis
including more and more of our experience in this in this mindfulness meditation
nothing is left out everything is included so we've extended from
breathing then we included the body it emphasized with the body
this feeling sensing awake aware through the body
sensing that kind of sensibility this body alive it's wondrous
so including including the body and our and our wise attention and
then opening the circle even a little wider to include emotions
wise relationship to emotion such a rich territory gives so much
color and shape and beauty to our lives and part of our task is to learn to train
how to relate wisely to our emotions so one of our instructions last week
with regard to mindfulness of emotions was a sort of guideline to
to aim toward a very simple relationship with one's emotions
the idea here is that the emotions will come part and parcel of our human life
if they're uncomfortable if they're uncomfortable that may be like
uh getting pricked with a dart or the metaphor is an arrow the emotion itself if it's uncomfortable
that's like the first arrow and then how we go about complicating it
with our interpretations our reactions our responses identification just layer after layer
making what was one arrow into two two arrows into three into four
and on and on and on so as best we can to use our wise attention to recognize oh i'm adding i'm
adding difficulty to this direct experience of emotion
and return as best we can to a simple relationship
and tanya introduced some of the ways that we can do that using this acronym raft
one r one a one f and two t's raft
each could be thought of as different ways to relate wisely to emotion and they all kind of work
together so the r was to recognize simply to recognize oh there's an
emotion here maybe to recognize what it is a is to allow or accept
and i like to think of allow or accept as not having any conflict
with the fact that this emotion is going on not being in confl conflict it is indeed
true this emotion has arisen and then f feel
just what we were practicing with mindfulness of the body
how is it that this emotion is showing up in and through the body through the language of the body what's
being said so recognize
allow feel and then the
tease apart i love this image that tonya used of a tapestry
a tapestry made up of many many threads and as we as we hold or attend to this emotion with care even if you rub it
between your fingers maybe these threads start to loosen up and show themselves the different colors
you can see green for green and red for red so on
and this whole process is supported by the last t trust trust
one of the things we can trust is that the body is always experiencing in the present
moment if we can be in contact with the body we know we're right here
and we're receiving the resource of right here and right now
so recognize accept feel tease apart
and trust some of the some of the guidance we talked about last week and i'm really interested to hear how it
went for you anyone who was practicing over the week
anything you might have done with this raft practice or anything you want to report in your sitting
questions you have or if you had an experience of what we talked about writing out an emotion
if you felt an emotion arise set yourself down and be still and just say i'm going to sit here and ride this out
so anything you'd like to share please
do you want me to pass um so i wanted to share that
it's very useful for me and i've been trying the techniques i learned in the first three classes
and i already had familiarity with trying to feel my emotions from other practices
and um it's just really liberating because for example one of the things
that's been a long time in the background it's been different types of fear like
social anxiety or dreading things and um today i did my meditation
practice and it was just really amazing to feel the fear
feel my heart beating fast and just sitting with it and then afterwards i just felt so
liberated even like um 10 minutes later and for the rest of the day i was able to be just more
present to other things and enjoy things and um yeah just even doing my work i was
enjoying that as well so yeah thank you for teaching us wow wow i feel i feel so
much a joy for how that's happened for you thank you so much for sharing thank you i don't know
if anyone else feels that but it's like it puts encouragement in the room to hear a story like that thanks yeah great
observations
maybe there were other things that came up maybe questions or even challenges
um i find that i have if i look really closely i have a lot of
aversion especially to any kind of discomfort
so it's almost like it's an automatic thing for me to um
think of something else or so
and it's mostly with um subtle things
if it's a strong feeling in my body i usually will try to
um let it go through my body but it's it's those subtle things that happen more
often where i just find there's a lot of conditioned
mind habit aversion [Music] it's uh
it's so fortunate that you're you're seeing you're seeing a process is what i hear and and discerning
um yeah what i'm what i'm hearing is that there's this experience of discomfort
and aversion and it seems like you're getting closer to it and seeing that there there's a there's
a variety of aversion that you can stick with pretty easily in another where
it's almost like because it's subtle uh it it doesn't register that oh
there's a version here and i'm going to slip away yeah yeah
but i hear you feeling it in your body and returning returning to your body and that's exactly the practice
it's it feels it registers for me as akin to the way we train with the breathing
where frequently there's a part a place in the breathing cycle where we tend to lose contact
often at the very end it gets really subtle and soft so the instruction there just as the instruction i'm i'm thinking
about for this a version that you're working with when you when you notice
you're in that field where the slip usually happens what's a way you can give just like a
half a notch tiny little bit of deliberate energy to hang in there just a little longer and
that intention will sort of work itself through the practice
thank you thank you sounds like it's going great
i have a little question um i noticed that um
quite often when there's a lot of thinking going on
um [Music] and i i ask myself so what's is there an
emotion is this something on the line and
usually like 90 90 of the time i don't feel anything
there's this resistance no we're not gonna go there or i don't know i would call this we're not gonna go there but i
don't know what it is actually like we're staying here in the thinking realm
and and then i feel like it's like a war i feel and so what i do is i'm
i'll shift to my body and i feel this i would i would call it resistance at
the body level it's not pain which is in some specific place but it's kind of
like this tension everywhere and so
but one thing that i tried deliberately recently what if i just
kind of generate a thought like i voluntarily think about something
like i know what things i what topics i usually you know my mind goes to so what if i just seed something
that i know is emotional for me and
it's kind of intense so i just recently yesterday i just kind of
thought about i was not home and i thought about the stove did i turn up
i i knew i turned off the stuff i made a mental note but i just kind of thought about it
and i felt this wave of fear through my body like
it was pretty intense yeah but the interesting thing is that
it's not it's not easy to you know to go there or like to even
you know just thinking and thinking is wants to be there and i feel like i'm emotionless
very often do you have a comment
thank you for describing your process feta
so one just drop in the bucket thought is
the resistance is worth spending time with itself so
when when the time is right and you have a thought come up and you're
sort of oh what's the emotion or is there emotion what do i even just starting with
if i have this thought can i feel where it lands in my body so um maybe even
getting rid of the what am i feeling but just go thought oh okay
when i have this thought what do i notice anything attention oh a little bit here that's
you know and you might not notice where you feel it until the next thought comes because then you you know so but just
so that's one thing just starting to track how a thought impacts your body
the other is when you feel like because you felt that resistance is very clear that you felt
by trying to turn toward the emotion something was saying no so ju that right there you can just that
is an emotional response and so just giving that some space like
oh being with the resistance feeling the resistance where do you feel it you know like because it's it has a purpose it
has it's in trying to protect you or it's you know trying to defend from something
we're afraid of so maybe getting to know that and why you know like being curious oh wow this is
so quick to come up i can't even feel what i'm feeling oh
so that that is uh maybe the emotion that's the most immediate actually
there might be other emotions but they're not activated at the moment the motion that's activated is the is behind
the resistance great
great a lot of times i think
resistance is really important to pay attention to sometimes we're trying to practice
with something and you know we know we're sad or upset or
we know that this thought isn't good for us but there's resistance to anything
going deeper or changing it and so just being with that resistance can reveal a
lot so we don't need to run away from resistance it's actually also can be
thought of as how we're clinging how we're wanting things to be different than the way they are
and there's a lot that's a beautiful place to hang out it's really working with the first noble
truth and then it can help us kind of recognize the second noble truth or the cause of
our clinging what is it we're resisting which is we want different right
so where are we for time
a couple more minutes okay i was just going to invite even if you haven't been in the class you know
haven't been attending maybe you've watched on youtube youtube or not but if you had a question
about working with emotions now is a great time to ask it otherwise we can move
maybe i can swap eggs with you
thank you thank you
so tonight's topic is mindfulness of thinking
and i just want to invite you to do an imaginary exercise
to start i'd like to imagine yourself as a young
child like really little two three
and i'd like to imagine story time with whoever you feel felt
safe with and cozy with as a child
imagine that one of your favorite books was brought out and the name of thought the book is you are not your thoughts
imagine being read this book from the time you were two or three
years old you are not your thoughts
you open up and you see this beautiful little baby
in this picture and it says thoughts come and go
they never last long one minute they're here the next they're gone
imagine learning that that little
right and then and then you read the next page and it says
when you look up at the clouds in the skies of blue try to see the whole sky
as the clouds pass through the clouds are like
thoughts the sky is like you
can you imagine if you've been taught this
and you knew this your whole life that you are not your thoughts
that thoughts come and go that they move through and that
awareness itself is like the sky and knowing we can know the thoughts the
clouds can move through our sky move through our awareness
what if you really knew that now because somebody's been reading you this book for all those years
be pretty cool here's another book i'm going to read
you a little bit from it's called can't stop thinking
it's by nancy collier and the subtitle is how to let go of anxiety
and free yourself from obsessive rumination she's clearly a meditation practitioner
she's endorsed by sharon salzberg and tara brock and others
and so she she didn't get she wasn't read this
story either she was a kid but she writes about some an experience
that i'll share with you i'll read you a couple of paragraphs from the beginning of her book
and the title of this introduction is addicted to thinking
she said it was a magnificent let me do this actually i think it will
help
it was a magnificent spring morning and i was walking in the park near my home
well that's not really true i was walking yes but not exactly in the park
i was oblivious to the colorful flowers blooming the warm sunshine
the smell of cut grass i was missing all of it having disappeared inside my own head
into my own personal prison thinking no matter how delicious that may day may
have been i wasn't experiencing it
i was trapped inside my mind obsessing about what was not working in
my life replaying and rethinking the same problems
i've been replaying and rethinking for years
and then something remarkable happened my inner lens spun on its axis instead
of being inside my thoughts i was now the one looking and listening to my thoughts
instead of being inside my thoughts i was now the one looking
at and listening to my thoughts and you see the shift
yeah can you feel into experiences where you've gone from being
inside the thought to being able to witness great
great so that's that's what we want to support
in our practice with mindfulness of thinking is the connection with awareness
being aware of thinking as it's occurring or
is it starting sometimes we get lost and then as it's ending or later we start to become more aware because we it's a
little perm it's like there's not a firm boundary between
the thinking and being aware of it we can absorb into it and we can come out
of it right there's no fixed line that helps us keep that
boundary or other awareness aware aware aware right
another way um to think about this that's often talked about is foreground
versus background so you know when the the
letting the thoughts be more in the background right when we're when we have a little more awareness the
thoughts can be a little bit more sort of in the background that can help us not get so merged with them
i think another really important thing to start
to pay attention to when we're working with thinking is
there's there's two things that i find people tend to do i do we do
one is to try and change the thinking
another is looking at our relationship to the thoughts
so sometimes it feels like there's more we can do it's a little easier in a way to like
i mean i'm gonna get really busy trying to change the way i'm thinking i want to be
have more kind thoughts or be more supportive be less critical and that all helps
that all helps and we're still kind of merging with
thinking often in that way so another way
to try and relate to thoughts is actually to look at our relationship to the thinking to notice
we like this thought we don't like that thought
i am this thought this is me this thinking is who i am
this is all a reflection of our relationship to our thoughts this is how
it should go right these are all ways that we relate to our
thoughts and many of those ways i just described lead
to emerging and agreeing and a building with the thinking
right so there's another thing to think about is there's thoughts
which are like the clouds and then there's the thinking which is like a chain
little engine that can you know i'm thinking i'm thinking i'm thinking i'm thinking i'm thinking i'm thinking
there's this energy of of keeping it going
so it's a lot easier to be mindful of thoughts than it is to be mindful of the thinking
make sense but to be mindful of the thinking well that's you know we're usually
starting to get in it become it to merge with it so
but noticing this noticing when you feel like the little engine that could you know that's that's climbing up the
hill with those thoughts pumping them out oh i'm actively thinking pretty much
means i'm bought in i'm biden i'm buying in it's me i'm i'm agreeing i'm working
on it and so uh then we can sort of in that moment there's a way to shift oh okay
how do we like let it ourselves open up a little bit around the thinking
oh there's this thought oh there's agreement more like watching
like the clouds and then what happens is when we're not so engaged with them they
start to lose their momentum they peter out they dissolve they
transform guess what a new more tempting thought will come up
you know it's it's sort of a wonderful thought-making machine in here and its intention is to engage us
the work is in learning how to witness
and you know when we're sitting on the cushion as much as possible
to watch and not become the engine that powers it
so some of the you know one of the things that's um easy and nice to say is i'm not my
thoughts remind ourselves you know we all we have so many thoughts
every day and many of them are repetitive but there's no one thought that is going
to capture who you are sometimes you have thoughts you don't even agree
with yeah so how is it you are a thought how can i
be that thought right so it's helpful to kind of work on
seeing thinking as part of my experience but it's not who i am i'm not my
thoughts in this book uh
the woman has a question that i really liked she said ask yourself
what if i am not my thoughts what if i am what hears and sees the
thoughts the awareness within which the thoughts are appearing
like that sky metaphor i'm like the sky and the thoughts are the clouds that move
through the sky
so one of the things that can be really helpful when we're
trying to recognize we're thinking which is not always so easy to do because of that
you know permeability and the merging that happens with our thinking
is to kind of recognize um there are different kinds of thinking
and we all think in different ways actually so
who hears who here thinks in images you see images in your mind
not everybody right some people sometimes some people like this
like okay maybe like this who thinks an image is not very much a little bit a lot all the time
right right there you go right okay so that's one way we think
who hears words being spoken
ah okay so some people are peer and other people who were up here before are now
here or down here right so there's that's the auditory the hearing
of the speaking is one way we think not the only way
there's also kind of can be a subtle layer of thinking that's kind of almost
like this is one i've been working with lately it's it's almost like an opaque
feeling or image in the background that just is enough to generate an emotional
response in the body it's sort of like it's like
for me uh what i've noticed the best way i can describe it is like knowing there's a
yellow light flashing caution caution you know just like so then there's this
feeling in the body of like oh you know and what do i need to be paying attention to you know oh oh oh like
and that's you know there's not um when i look in my mind and i watch in my
mind it's not like i'm sitting around talking there's no conversation happening
maybe every once in a while a word or two or a sentence might string together but it's just more of this like
holding of this perspective
right a sense
what what else have you noticed about thinking have you noticed any other ways that you think
imagining myself doing things in the future and then i can catch myself and like oh
i'm not here i'm trying on different scenarios yeah great so i like uh the movie-making
mind it's how i tend to and i'm the star of the show you know like i'm trying on
things and i'm imagining them and how it's gonna go and how i'm gonna respond to this or that so rehearsing or
or visualizing and it's going to be very powerful actually it can be really really helpful it also can be really
harmful right we can get lost and almost sometimes i feel like i'm working
with people and it's almost like they're living in that instead of in the real world
yeah i see it's nutting yeah i feel like just even having more spaciousness from
that yeah is useful so maybe when i want to be there i can but
being aware and if i choose to not being there yes yes beautiful
okay you want to say something yeah so um
it was very interesting to hear this third like as you said third way
uh that you mentioned like holding on to something a little bit like i i often find myself like i have a
combination i maybe have an image and a couple of keywords yeah it's like a little cluster yeah
and it represents a topic for me and i don't really hear sentences or see like
a sequence of images i just have this cluster yeah and it comes to my mind and
and it's kind of the air yeah and i don't even know what exactly is happening but i can recognize the
cluster of yeah you know these data points yeah a mix of words and that's
right absolutely so this is what um [Music] you know thinking is different for us
it's also when we have memories versus when we're imagining can be different
when we hear somebody else's voice versus our own voice sometimes we don't even notice our own narrator because
it's so normal to us it's just like we don't even recognize or
meditating and talking to ourselves okay just keep breathing keep reading you know which is a you know we're trying to
keep we're trying to help ourselves but we're actively thinking and narrating right so that's another form of it and
sometimes we need it right so but but still being able to recognize that that's what's happening is thinking
can be very very helpful liberating um too you know
so let's do a little bit of practice yeah
so finding a meditation posture that supports you being in in your body
in your body here in this space in this time and
you know taking your time to get comfortable to adjust your posture
right and to find maybe something like lifting the shoulders up rolling them back to help counter the
forward and closing habits we have
oh and just let the breath come in
so feeling that sense of uprightness but relaxed
in a position and posture that you feel you can hold for 15 minutes
and seeing if you can't start to connect more deeply with
whatever your anchor is and we've been using referencing in general the breath is the anchor
so taking a a few minutes to help ourselves settle like
when we come into the harbor in our boat we find the right spot
and then we lower an anchor into the water and it takes a while to lower it down
and then we've got to kind of pull on it a bit and make sure it's nice and firmly caught
and then you can feel the tension pulling on the anchor holding the boat in place
and so as we cultivate that our connection to the breathing if that's our anchor
it starts to feel like that anchor the tug the rope that's connected to the anchor and the
bottom of the ocean that's holding us here
the water is moving things are happening sounds and there's that feeling of connection
to right here right here
and it's just happens one breath at a time one sensation at a time
and maybe like if you were a sailor on this boat and you put your anchor down
and you tug on the rope and you know you've got the anchor kind of settled
there's a feeling of trust that can come up
a feeling of like okay okay
okay so inviting this sense of
okayness the sense of i've taken care of my body
my presence i'm orienting myself to the practice
and then noticing the attitude and the way you're speaking to yourself might be a form of thinking
and see if there's some kindness invite some kindness in there
some kind orienting kind thinking
invitational
let me just be here breath by breath
at some point you will find yourself thinking
yay mindfulness of thinking yeah here i am seeing a thought yay i
see a thought
it's okay thoughts happen we don't have to stop them
let them be those clouds moving through the sky
some of the things that can help us with that or to distinguish
the kind of thinking that's happening so maybe just oh talking
or seeing or movies
so just first oh subtle background thinking just sort of first noticing what kind of thinking
it is kind of the process of thinking that's happening in this mind at this moment
a second thing that we can be aware of that's different than the process of
thinking is the content
so you might just say a story or remembering or
planning or just just somehow noting the content it might need to be
named lightly labeled
[Music]
and sometimes the thoughts just kind of keep moving and slipping through and sometimes they kind of stick around they
feel sticky and so sometimes if that's happening you
might say is there an emotion connected
here with this thought is there a physical sensation
in the body connected to this thought
and if it feels really really sticky in your little engine that could and your power and those thinking thoughts
and can be helpful to consider dropping the anchor back into the ocean and reconnecting with a breath
re-establishing that anchor breathing here right here
and then once we reconnect to the breathing when we're ready
we can more just sort of open up again a little bit more
gently just watching for that next little puff of a
cloud how is it showing up
what's the process of thinking that's happening
maybe noting the content maybe noting planning
remembering imagining
and see if you can just breathe right into it and through it
being gentle and kind patient
maybe thinking's not me it's not who i am thinking is happening
thinking is here thought is here
my mind's job is to think thinking just is something that happens
it's natural
so
maybe just dropping in the question when am i aware of now
[Music]
so
so what did you what did you experience what did you
learn about the mind and how it's thinking or engaging with
thinking tonight in the last 15 minutes
okay hello good evening sorry i was late um i noticed that i was noticing that i was
thinking a lot um apart from that too just with the meditation practice i
found that i can if guided or not guided i'm having
it's nicer to it's easier for me to be able to just sit with it and not try to
resist or force anything but still when thoughts or emotions arise i
can still find myself in the midst of this in the midst of it rather than being the observer of my thoughts so i
i'm still trying to practice it practice that but meditation has helped me with awareness
sweet sweet how does it feel different
to be more aware and less less entangled i would say i remember in one of the
talks the sessions i had attended with you on a sunday like holding on to things like whether it be enemies or
something it's if by letting go of that how does it make
you feel and this week at work at one point i could just almost imagine myself
like seeing what would happen if i reacted in a way that was more so reactive rather than responsive
and i'm like oh that was the first time i'd ever had a chance to do that and it was good but and it would not have
happened had i not had i not been doing this had i not been meditating but
it's still a practice that i had every day and you know yesterday i was still pretty
upset about something and i just had but i also had to
let myself like be in in that emotion and not resist it too because
if i kept fighting it i'm like okay i know i'm upset right now and i'm frustrated but
what can i do with it and as guilt in the handout from gill like you you kind
of just have to be with that emotion i think or be with it and
not force anything thank you it reminds me of talking about the river
being the riverbed right letting the emotions move through yeah beautiful
what i noticed is when the resistance comes up
the more you pay attention to it
uh or the more you try to avoid it the stronger it gets yes that's what
happened for me it's the more i tried to tell myself you know
stop resisting stop stop paying attention to that don't look at the elephant in the room
the more i wanted to stare at the elephant in the room and about halfway through
when i remembered what you said about the foreground and the background yeah
all of a sudden the observer
came to the foreground and the thoughts went into the background and i felt more
relaxed immediately i felt like when i
stopped resisting things got easier but i also feel like
it we're trained our whole lives to think to you know to do something to be doing
something to be thinking about something to it is very difficult to to tell yourself
not to think about things and i also want to know about that
children's book is that a book that i can buy for my someday grandchildren or
is that a made-up book no this is a real book um i think i bought it at spirit rock but um
i'm sure you can you can find it online it was done by mila and john kabat-zinn
so you're welcome to come up and look at take a picture of the cover and yeah absolutely please do
everybody should be reading this together i don't think so too i think so too thank you
one thing i noticed as i was noting each of these different thoughts um
[Music] at first there seemed to me so many
different thoughts and
eventually i realized they were all variations
on a core thought which would be sort of a core belief i
suppose but i i had never thought of that before that a that a belief
is sort of a core thought um that your keeps repeating itself
you know looking in a million different ways so now i felt like i can see
that thought disguised as all of these other manifestations
oh that's so wonderful it's like it's like all these variations are like
the leaves and somehow there was a recognition that they were all pointing back down the
branches to the something in the trunk of the tree what was that like for you when uh or
what what happened
it it made it much easier not to um
hop on the thought train of this or the thought train of that
and it it helped me stay
more centered and i i started hearing that one
thought rather than 50 60 different thoughts
i could hear it more clearly yeah oh wonderful wonderful thank you so
much
um i wanted to share something too um so i noticed that at one point i was
i was lost and probably not for a long but it was very obvious okay
and and i immediately and i why i noticed i don't know how like what
basically i noticed that because i felt shame i felt shame
and okay that's because i was lost and then i i something interesting
happened i noticed how my mind was like ready to jump on the shame thing and
then go there and like oh that's because well i'm not supposed to be lost it's a
short-guided meditation and tiny is guiding us right and i'm a good meditator i'm not
supposed to be lost like that and and what is interesting i noticed
this you know i'm kind of prepared my mind prepared me for this new
you know cycle around the shame and i just kind of okay that's what's
happening and it i felt really amused it was it was actually quite amusing
that i noticed that so it was actually a very pleasant experience to see how these things
happened in a sequence yeah yeah i just want to appreciate the
the clarity of observation of process and you hanging in there
the place you ended up was a friendly relationship with what could have been a really
juicy captivating thought train to get onto
yeah nice nice thank you
shall we go ahead yeah i'll just add it's very obvious what i'm going to say super super
obvious but the main thing that you know one of the main things that i heard that for me would have
helped me was you there was disbelief there was
that space of like i'm not just believing this thought this thought doesn't have to be a fact
it does it's a thought that's being produced and oh i can see where it's going to take me
but i don't have to go there which is so empowering right so freeing
the cover of the book says it all you are not your thoughts
oh yeah for us meditators too the identity of good meditator
so the experience of thinking
and our relationship to thinking little engine that could driving up the hill we're in the thought
other options for relationship to thinking i get to introduce one of the classic
imc analogies now i'd like you to imagine
maybe you're out taking a walk it's the end of the end of the week or taking a walk somewhere in the
say on a trail brought a little snack with you you have everything you need
and um you're feeling quite happy and you find yourself
under a tree by riverside you decide to sit down just uh
you can feel the air on your skin the light is just right the temperature is comfortable
you want for nothing just perfectly content right there as you are watching the river go by
how pleasant so there you are seated and before you
know it up the stream comes one of these
party boats yeah the music the decor
the dancing maybe they have a jazz band on board or something
and before you know it you're on the boat how did that happen
you're dancing away you're dressed differently
having a great time and then you realize oh i'm a little tired from dancing oh wait
i was sitting under that tree that was so lovely okay i'm gonna
make my way back so somehow or another you make your way off the boat back uh
back up the trail sit down in your tree so nice
so nice just there just right here not carried along just watching the flow go by
and then comes a battleship and before you know it you're on
the fighting boat little surprise you're the you're the
hero you're the star of this show or alternately you're hiding in the hall
but you're on this battleship and you're on it for months
maybe then you realize oh where was i where am i
i have lost i've lost the riverbank i'm gonna get off this boat go back sit down
ah here i am so glad to not be dancing any dancing on this party boat i'm so glad not to be fighting i'm just
here just here here for a while and then comes this
meager barely a raft it's like like sticks tied together with a little
grass it's hardly holding up and before you know it you're on the raft and you're like oh i can barely float
how did that happen how did that happen before we know it before we know it we're on the raft
then we recognize and make our way back just to here just to hear again
such an apt analogy for the varieties of really juicy thoughts
that can captivate us some of our favorites right and the relationship that we can have
with them before we even realize we've hopped right on the boat and we're
riding right along we're going for the ride we're the little engine that could going up the hill
but there's another option another option we can exercise with the practice and that is
just sitting under the tree just being content here just here
we see a boat coming down we can have the intention oh there's a
boat i know that i could get on it but how many boats have i gotten on this one time i'm gonna try just watching it go
by and you know what you got to stay right here stay right here
so some little bit of wise relationship to thinking
we don't necessarily get taken over
to develop these ideas about thinking something i really want to make sure we talk about meditation gets kind of a bad
rap in meditation circles thinking it's a bad rap in meditation circles don't you find that's true
or maybe some of you have heard that being around meditation communities for
the years that i have been so many so many times i've heard
oh you know meditation is not for me i can never get my mind to stop thinking there's this understanding that like
meditation is only when there's no thinking going on or meditation gets uh
uh seen as the problem or i keep saying meditation when i mean thinking
excuse me thinking thinking gets seen as the problem
nothing gets left out mindfulness meditation thinking is such an important part of
our experience so i wanted to give a little time to recognize and respect thinking and it's
it's a actually fruitful and really powerful influence in our lives
i was i was taking a walk just this afternoon and i noticed a block over there's one of these um
like give and take a book you know what i mean
and i thought how much how much joy
how much how much depth and profundity in our life
has been has come to us through books every shakespeare play
thoughts every poem you've ever read that's touched you those are thoughts
they get documented and they represent something they've had an influence in our lives every speech by martin luther king
thoughts what an important part of our lives this too gets to be included our whole
life gets to be here
i think something this is closely connected with is that of course thoughts
they have their they have their place in meditation they have their difficulties but often
they're pointing at something else really valuable in our experience oftentimes a thought as we've been
exploring might be connected to an emotion underneath or a thought might point us
back to some core belief or an identity that we have
maybe a thought connects us to something in our body or it arises based on something in our body
all these different connections in our lives that thoughts may be pointing back to so in some ways a thought might be a
signpost
when i was a when i was a boy i was um i grew up in a place where it was very warm and i was learning how to water ski
if anyone's learned how to water ski you pretty much hold on to a rope and you have these two boards on your
feet and the boat goes and if everything goes according to plan you go up on the water and you stand and
ski now it's lovely i was i was quite young and i was learning
so i got my rope i got my little skis the boat starts to take off and i
stumble and i hang on to the rope i didn't want to let go and before i
knew it i was under the water i was still tenacious i was like i'm not letting go
it's just like that we're thinking sometimes just like that
sometimes we think the thoughts and sometimes the thoughts really think us
sometimes the thoughts take us for a ride and that um that can contribute to
all sorts of difficulties and complications in our lives so again this wise relationship to
thinking being able to have some some wise space from our thinking
or even to pick up the boat analogy again say we wanted to engage some thought say the the party
boat comes down and we're like okay i'm deliberately going to pick up this thought and i'm going to dance on this
i'm going to i'm going to artfully dance with this thought and then when the time comes i'm going to get off the boat
but doing it with some choice some choice
i was talking to someone recently who has been i think she's been practicing for maybe
40 years practicing mindfulness practice and she said the thing that she has
gotten from the practice that she appreciates the most
is that now she has an affectionate relationship with her mind
an affectionate relationship with her mind and that that opens up some some
possibilities in uh i don't know about you but in me and my my heart and mind for
this practice with mindfulness of thinking how we can get wrapped up in our identities and really suffer our
thinking or there can be the possibility
friendship with our thinking kindness with our thinking goodwill toward our thinking
and freedom with it freedom with it
maybe one last comment
we've talked about a lot of different aspects of mindfulness of thinking
an important thing tanya said that i want to highlight it's not about
getting busy around our thinking it's still about simple awareness
awareness with what's right here so say we're practicing with the anchor of the breathing
and the thinking can just be there in the background and we can stay with the breathing let's
continue with that if a thought is
persistent uh or compelling maybe then turn toward it and investigate its process
what's its beginning and ending what's its quality what's the tone of voice like
if it's really repetitive is there something physical going on is there an emotion underneath
is there something fueling the thinking you might turn toward that all the while just a simple relationship
with thinking so why don't we do a little more
practice together
can take a moment to renew your posture
finding yourself upright with an alert spine a relaxed body maybe
opening the chest
feeling your way into alignment through the body with the support of the breathing
allowing the earth allowing the seat to hold your weight
to invite a little relaxation into the limbs
having a minute to connect with your anchor perhaps the breathing
a breath comes in a breath goes out
a thought comes in
the thought goes out
baby
let's thoughts begin to blow through like clouds
if they can stay in the background
just to allow them to pass by
if you find that there is a thought that's persistent
perhaps giving it a name planning
planning
replaying replaying
if you recognize
a thought has visited you many times before
repeat repeat may be giving it a name
and perhaps something in us can trust that it's okay
to not pick up this thought this time
as we bring this sitting to a close
a moment to notice just now what is my relationship
to this present thought to this present thinking
as you hear the bell when you're ready you can open your eyes
[Music]
so an affectionate relationship to the mind
maybe so maybe so how was the practice for you
are any uh questions coming up
are any comments you'd like to share
hello well i was having a coughing fit but i at the at the same time i realized oh my
gosh i'm i'm finally getting comfortable sitting on the you know meditating on the floor and i've been practicing like
sometimes i do a mix of on sitting on the chair and on the floor and i'm like okay in the midst of all this this these
coughing spasms i'm like i can still find myself anchored to the fact that i'm breathing
in and breathing out and so i'm like it's okay it'll i can still steal my i
thought it was kind of representative or symbolic of the mind too and you know
kodo as you said getting on or finding yourself on that ship you know i
i i do get on the ship a lot or whatever the rafter a sinking ship sometimes but
but it's i do want to stay under the tree under the bodhi tree i
really do but sometimes it's a free ride and it is very it is very seductive to just
but i don't but then i i before that before meditation i know i i
would just easily hop on but i know now there's a bit of hesitation but in a good way like you
know like and rose if you get on that it's you know what's going to happen so
pause pause for a bit or just breathe and i really like in this practice i've
been able to extend it to others or the whole loving kindness put your hand over your heart and just like you know i'm
you know i have everything i need and it's it's really cool so i'm very grateful for this and for you and for
tonya and for you for helping me with that
so thank you thank you so much for your practice so much um
so much to appreciate there and one one thing that's standing out to
me is that there's such a variety of experiences happening and all of it gets to be included
all of it gets to be included in the awareness practice it seems really skillful
some of the ways you're relating to of having a bodily experience in the foreground and the background
even bodily experience can be related to that way not just thoughts in the background
so thank you for revealing that thank you
um what i find sometimes is when i am sitting like this to meditate i'm actually
more still than in my regular life my my thoughts are really going through my
mind really fast and sometimes they can feel disturbing if they're
upsetting thoughts and i notice that i notice it in my body first
i may not even realize that i'm thinking um thoughts that
don't serve me but then i start to have like almost like a pain here in the solar plexus area
but for whatever reason when i sit um and i have done meditation before i
just wanted to come tonight but when i sit i um
sometimes i'm in a a quieter space so i almost feel like i need to like
stop and meditate when i'm getting in that whirlwind that's not
serving me but a lot of times that whirlwind is not happening when i'm sitting
so you know obviously if you go to like a retreat where you're sitting all day
you're gonna get the whirlwind but i just i just thought it was an interesting observation on my part that
i'm like oh you know like i'm sitting here now i feel really comfortable and at ease and
nothing disturbing is coming into my mind and i was like okay
i don't know i mean what do you think of that and how to work with that
it sounds like it's restful it sounds like it's nourishing
and so when we're offered good food eat it enjoy it
let yourself be aware that that's your experience right but i was just thinking of when
it's the opposite yeah and i'm not meditating how to deal with that yeah
well um are you familiar with any of andrea fellas teachings
no so she if you're interested in her in this she does a lot of teaching about being
mindful of the mind in daily life so you might look at um sort of simply
first of all are you aware of what the five hindrances are yes okay so when you have a lot going on your
mind in your mind you might just stop and go okay what hindrances are at work here
kind of or what emotions are because they're the fuel right they're the
they're the um the lighter fluid right that's really catching
and burning things keeping it going and so then you can start to like uh
hopefully have a little more awareness in the midst of it a little more awareness oh there's a lot of aversion
and then you know you you said you were aware of your body so just like you said it i loved what you said about i'm often
become aware of my thinking through my body yes and that it to me is
really powerful practice mindfulness of the body you could even cultivate that during your daily life
being more tuned in more consciously active uh mindfulness of the body practice and then
as you notice tension you might start to notice things sooner is that helpful yeah okay
maybe maybe time to bring it to a yeah a close already yeah
so there is a few people came in late there is a handout on the end of the stage
that has um some a good overview and some
homework suggestions so this week we're encouraging you to
bump up your practice to 30 minutes did we do that last week actually i think we did okay
so 30 minutes and if you can sit that out one time great if you need to break
it up great you know just if you can make that amount of practice it's helpful um
and and then during the practice and even just during your daily life just
kind of noticing more your thoughts and your beliefs just getting a little bit more familiar and
what's repetitive and what comes up what tends to fuel a lot more energy or upset
there's um a suggestion to do a two-hour period of
tracking different kinds of thoughts just sort of taking a couple of hours to keep no
thinking is still happening with imagining visualizing movie making
words talking you know just sort of keep kind of oh type of thinking right tracking that
and then there's a suggestion to do two hour period of tracking of intentions and we didn't really talk about
intentions tonight so i didn't read the hand without do did
you re-read the handout before before today so i'm not sure what it says in there about intention so if it's not
clear don't worry about it and we can talk more another time um
and then i'll just repeat i really like this question just dropping it in if i'm not my thoughts
what if i'm what hears and sees the thoughts just kind of playing with that a little bit
sort of dropping that question in what if i'm what hears and sees the thoughts
just seeing how that lands
and may this time together be of benefit to you
and of benefit to all the people you come in contact with and then the people they come in contact with and
so on and so forth and uh thank you thank you for being here and cody and i will be here if you
have any questions afterwards or you want to take a picture of the book all right thank you
thanks so much
you