so hello everyone and um I'm going to uh
try to talk about the topic of right relationships
and um and how I'm using this term is in the
same way that the word right is used for in the Eightfold Path so right
view right intention right speech right action right way of life right effort right
mindfulness and right concentration and um
the and in fact one way of looking at the
Eightfold Path all eight of those factors are defining or bringing forth right
relationships that's what the April path is about and and the word right is some people
have problematic with it in English because it just seems like maybe it's righteous or if it's you know
some kind of moralistic right that you have to be a certain way the word summer in the ancient language
samyak in in Sanskrit is um
the first definition in the dictionary in probably English dictionary is thorough
and in Sanskrit it's uh first But it includes the definition of being full or
complete so the intention the view the relationships that are complete or full
is part of the meaning and so what would it like for a relationship to be complete to be whole
his uh part of this question and being part of the Eightfold Path
um it also the word some also has the apparently the etymology of it that goes
back maybe before maybe for the Buddhist time has also the meaning of doing client
words to move towards like a be directed towards a particular direction
and so the the the complete in the kind of completely involved in a
particular direction and the direction is towards Liberation
towards freedom and this Freedom that Buddhism talks about is very relational in a certain
way and a certain way is is a transrelational maybe or you know free
of relatedness and and this wonderful kind of richness of the combination of both as part of this fascinating way in
which the Dharma practice deepens so the way that the Eightfold Path can
be seen as being relational is that the first right view has to do with seeing
suffering and seeing what the how suffering comes to be sometimes just seeing the cause sometimes seeing the
Dynamics of how it appears and and suffering is always relational
the suffering that we're looking looking about it has to do with the way that we relate to things in the world and to
others and sometimes that when suffering is we've caused harms been caused to us is
because someone's in relation to us or the world's in relationship to us in such a way that there's harm caused
but in a strict sense in Buddhism and they use the word suffering they uh there's a very personal
contribution that goes into that that um that uh
that we want to take into account and one of the contributions is that there's
clinging there's attachment to that and so uh and it be attached to anything
is to be in relationship to that thing to be attached to anything you're not free of it
you're kind of entangled or caught in it and if you can become free of it
that gives the opportunity for us to be related to it to have a relationship it's very different
and uh so there's no there might be no intentional relationship to it in terms
of wanting something or intending something but when a person's free then
they're good will their love their compassion can flow and that contributes to whatever they relate to whatever it
might be and um and when you're free you're not
being defined by the relationship when you're not free we tend to be
defined or shaped or limited by the relationship because of the attachments of what we
want or what we don't want or what we're resisting and all these things So Right View has to do with
understanding that right intention the second factor of the April path is clearly relational
it's uh the right view is one way of understanding it is that it is to relate
to things with compassion to relate to things with kindness and relate to things with with very
dangerous word in English concept with pronunciation
so it's nice to be challenged by these big words but uh but the simple way of
saying it is to relate to things without projecting or Clinging On It our
attachment on it and the pronunciation the Buddha always focuses on is not pronunciation of things but when it
relationship to our clinging attachment to things so it's a different relationship with or
without clinging right speech is completely relational right usually we speak to ourselves and
we're relating to ourselves perhaps but but uh you know when we speak out loud
it's usually to other people and so we're in relationship with them and what comes through the speech how we're
relating what's being created there what's being done there and right speech is speech which is kind
of timely truthful beneficial so really if you're looking at the relationship and what's kind
what's beneficial for What's Happening Here right action is uh usually understood to
be able to avoid three actions which you'll understand are very relational
one is killing someone the other is stealing from someone and
the third is engaging in sexual misconduct with someone so that's very relational right and so
as we as we developed the Eightfold Path that those areas of our relatedness to others begins to shift and perhaps
rather than having those three awful things happen it's the opposite that begins happening there's a reverence for
life there's a tremendous generosity and not taking but giving and there's a deep
respect for people and and their sexual well-being and all that that entails
and um and there's right livelihood or like right living which tends to be for most people is very related to something
if not to other people if you're a subsistence farmer living by yourself you're still relating to the world
into the Land There some of the most beautiful relatedness to the world sometimes it's for people
who are farming and some kind of harmony with the natural world
uh I write a wonderful New York Times article this last week about
um um maybe it was titled some like a truce in
the war and it was the war that farmers I think it might have been in Colorado
or in some place Arizona that they had with uh beavers Ranchers with beavers
and they in order to because they felt that these beavers are causing too much problems they would blow up the beaver
dams and then this man inherited his father's farm and he thought there's another way
and he started to allow the Beavers to build their lead gems and then he kind of worked with him a little bit
sometimes he needed to help drain the water and he put pipes in but didn't destroy the dams and what happened was
that his farm his Ranch became much more resilient in times of drought and at
times of flooding the the dams turns out protected the land tremendously and protected the moisture in the land
tremendously and so now there's Ohio movement to to for renters to work with
the Beavers rather than getting rid of them so this idea of you know being in real
how we live our life in relationship to the world what kind of relationship are we living there
and then right effort that that could be seen as relate a relationship right effort is mostly very personal
uh though it has it has a has a relational effect but it has a lot to do
with your relationship to yourself and so um to really understand in
yourself what motivates what engages you with activity in the world and yourself
and so to have a mind mental activity that avoids what is unhealthy mental
actions and mental activities and do those things which are healthy and so it means tracking yourself being
mindful of what's going on right mindfulness is is uh you know
maybe a little bit harder to find exactly the rich way but it's the foundation for allows us to be in
relationship to the world in a good way and right concentration is a
phenomenally beautiful way to be related to oneself it's probably one of the kind of one of the most beautiful ways to
relate to yourself to set up this kind of inner life to be really settled and
deeply concentrated relaxed and allowing the natural kind of um a flow of energy
within us to kind of flow in a harmonious way it's a beautiful thing
so NATO passed to the totality of the output Old a12 Pad maybe we can call
right relation relationship and what is the relationship and some of
you know that there's sometimes there's a category that's they say there's three things there's you
there's you there's others and so we that exists between them me you and we
but we as little bit of a maybe abstract idea and so I like to say but there's me
you and the relationship between us and sometimes we need to take care of
that relationship more than we need to take care of the other person more than we need to take care of oneself
I saw this very clearly as I started to have children
and I have two sons and when they were young it became clear at some point the way I
had known before that um because I think because my my wife maybe myself especially
um uh I done I've done a lot of Letting Go letting go and said you have compassion and caring and so it was like
just let's take care of this kid you know at all costs whatever you know
whatever is needed and um and my mother would tell me you're careful you don't
spoil him and that didn't mean anything for me I just ignored her
and later I understood if she only used maybe a different word she actually was good advice
but um but what happened I realized after a while that it didn't really make sense as a as a child when the child was
you know a month old of course you sacrificed everything for the kid that can't do anything for it for himself
but as they get older and older you have to pull back and let them kind of more autonomy and but also became clear as my
son got and the sons got older there was a we there was a family unit
and unless we took care of the family unit we were going to create a skewed relationship in the family
and my son wasn't going to learn how to live in harmony with the family unit it
wasn't all about his welfare and what he wanted right that's the recipe for disaster but he had to also learn that other
people had need and the family had need and so I think just in time we got some
sense of that and um and so that we became very
important to family units and so that's true you know for for when there's two
people involved or a family involved it's true when there's a song got involved a community involved a town a
city a nation a world that there's also the way of the of everyone everyone and
and how does that what what's the relationship of that and what's happening there and what are we contributing to that relationship
and to focus a little bit on the relationship is is unusual for some people
there are some people for whom what they focus on is Me Myself and mine
everything is seen through the filter of how this affects me what I want what I don't want how this is impacting me
and how I'm being hurt by this how I'm a victim for this and now I'm afraid of everything or something it's all about
me and there's powerful conditioning forces in our
society that really inculcate this kind of view it's not something we create by
ourselves this whole focus on me me me that can exist is something that's been
some people have been kind of trained by our society I mean like I said in my family I could see if we weren't careful
at some point that's what we were creating in our sun and our society with so many different
forces is reinforcing um self-preoccupation self-concern in it
for yourself all kinds of things and um and so that's some people's
default and it's so strongly in our culture that people don't even know they're doing it and they're so strong
in our culture that it's like second nature for people to be self-concerned and it's about me and
don't even know they don't even recognize their thinking that way it's just obvious and and um and it's obvious
you're supposed to share yourself you know in some way that me is about me in a way
um and um and then some people are the opposite it's all about the others
like if it can be for young parents like me who are kind of naive not knowing and
just kind of give everything uh and it's all about that person that person
and um and and some people have religious
and family kind of World Views that really reinforce it's about others but
others about others taking care of them but what is about that third thing that
in the relationship and what happens in that relationship how do we study it how do we see it
and it's not something we see physically and this is now we're kind of entering into
you know a little bit The Invisible world and not the not not like a mystical
invisible world or something at the other but it's something we don't obviously see you have to be attuned to
you have to pay attention you have to pick up the cues you have to understand yourself better in order to really
understand what's happening here in the relationship to this but that also makes it kind of fun
and it's a very different way of navigating in the world nervous surfing along the relatedness
rather than engaging This World by asserting oneself or or
denying oneself and the example that I have for you that
you know no it's not going to work for many of you because many of you probably haven't gone surfing
I think it's possible I haven't been a really start surfing more than once
so I don't know what I'm talking about maybe so but maybe you'll forgive me and I'll
just just use as an example and hopefully I can um uh when you're on if you're on a
surfboard and you're able to catch that wave
though it's you you don't catch it and on this on the wave and that's okay I've
done it now I can just freeze and just kind of ride the wave out and not do
anything anymore but the wave is dynamic and you're a dynamic and everything is
dynamic and so you have to you have to be totally and kind of in Harmony in
relationship to all the different factors in at Play and and uh and shifting and adjusting
accordingly the whole time and probably one of the reasons is so fun to be on a surfboard is that uh
self-concern drops away self-preoccupation self-consciousness drops are because you have to be so
fully engaged to be right in the present moment to track all the different things going on
and it's not just the wave but it's everything that's involved
including you and uh you know and so for if there's
two different people writing exactly the same wave and one
person is really petite and one person is humongous the size whatever they're
probably going to ride the wave very differently and they might follow the wave just as
far the same distance so both of them are managing to do the wave perfectly
but it's going to look very different for these two people and so the perfect way to ride that wave
it's going to be different for those two people it has to do with the relatedness between what the factors that the
individual brings and the factors of the board you know they have different size boards and
depends what board you have probably the same person writing the same wave on different boards
switching boards every time perfect white riding the wave is different because it all depends on the
board too so the person's writing the doing the perfect ride is in constant conversation
relatedness with that contributing that relationship so to stay on the board but also
recognizing what the wave is contributing what the what the board is contributing the whole thing
and so it's a dynamic thing and it's the combination of all the relatedness all the things coming
together that allows us to do the perfect Rock to perfect ride so for you living your life
what's the perfect life what's the perfect way to do things what's the perfect way to be in a conversation with
someone what's the perfect way of caring for someone or what's the perfect way of doing anything
if you carry an external standard of what that is I'm supposed to be like someone else
that's the way they do it it's not going to be it the perfect way to be or in the language
of samma right the complete way to be the whole way of being in relationship
to this situation has to do with your contributions as and
who you are and all kinds of things about you as much as it has to do with the
situation so um if you're a
if you're offering I train people to do spiritual caregiving as chaplains and I said tell
that these people being trained sometimes said if you're a
um maybe I usually say unrepentant extrovert but maybe that's not a good way of saying it
and then I followed that by unrepented introverts but but what I mean by that
is you're completely at home with being who you are you're not you're not to apologize you don't have to you know
it's not a crime yourself anyway so um so someone who's a very strong
extrovert shows up to for someone who they're offering spiritual care to like in a hospital
the right spiritual care relationship is found in the in that relationship
between them and so the person doing spiritual care has to be attuned to not the other not
only the other person but to themselves to know where that right way of being is
and I knew one spiritual caregivers Joplin who showed up to very difficult situation
and um and uh couldn't really not really communicate this person who was conscious but but it
was you know it was header face to the wall wouldn't communicate to anyone was pretty upset
and so the spiritual caregiver started singing uh Amazing Grace
if I sang Amazing Grace I just would sing to my kids sometimes
when they were little and they'd tell me to stop
so you know that wouldn't be my way but that was that person's way and uh and if someone is in this
unrepented introvert what their their perfect spiritual caregiving conversation
is going to be very different maybe for them who they are and what's
right that is maybe they should sit down quietly and hold someone's hand and that's the Avenue with which some
the perfect spiritual caregiving thing happens so it's in the relationship between all
the factors not in some abstract idea that we have perfection so this is very respectful of yourself
you get to be yourself imagine just be to be yourself but you have to be you know yourself well enough
to know what you're contributing and to know the situation well enough to know that you're contributing the right
thing and you're creating the right relationship in that interaction between them
and if what you're contributing is clinging grasping attachment it's
probably not going to be a good outcome if what you're committing
bringing into it is cruciality and unkindness meanness it's probably not a
good relationship it's not one that you you're going to thrive in or is healthy for you and others
if it's wrong speech if there's a lot of complaining and a lot of bit you know you're doing kind of verbal verbal
stabbing of people verbal knives about you know just kind of get back and get them and and that's not that's that
you're establishing a certain relationship there but if your words are kind supportive
not mean not cynical or complaining about something
or blaming a very different relationship gets formed and the sad thing is sometimes people
want to have an unhealthy relationship now sometimes because they think they
think they get some benefit from it or something so to be careful with this relatedness
the right relationship where do we how do we what do we contribute to it
and one of the principles you find sometimes in Buddhism is the idea that um to assert the self
is delusion but to allow all things to inform you
is Awakening so to take you you know the self your
self-assess that it is the key word is assertion pushing yourself asserting yourself aggressively putting yourself
up into the world want you know with clinging attachment and that can be done forcefully
but it could also oddly enough in Buddhism Buddhist terms we assert ourselves in the world when we are
really shy that's just as much even though it looks like we're pulling back and not doing
something there's still a strong sense of self that we're contributing to the situation
and um and so what we're learning in Buddhist practice is how to soften and relax
um all attachment all clinging so there'll be the opportunity to come forward in different way
and one of those attachments is this excessive preoccupation with self that has been the case since the time of
the Buddha otherwise he wouldn't have been teaching this and not sell for non-selfishness that he taught but in
probably every generation thinks it's gotten the worse now so maybe that's you know but uh you know
it seems to me it's pretty bad and um it was still an issue so to
really understand that Me Myself and mine and how much were self-preoccupied and measuring
things by the impact it has on us of course we want to respect ourselves that's we're part of the we're
definitely part of the writing the wave right but uh are are you contributing a
healthy relationship to yourself and maybe we should not even use the
language healthy relationship to yourself because as soon as you see the word to itself it's a magnet for all these cultural
familial religious ideas of what it means to be a self that we're way down under
so another way of saying it may be a healthy relationship to all that lives within us
free it from this idea of being the self that we have to prove or defend or do anything with
to be awakened is to be informed by all things and so to be informed by what's within
us it's all to be respected every thought every impulse every feeling every
emotion in this practice is respected we're in a healthy relationship to it we
don't condemn it we don't and we don't hold on to it and oddly enough we don't celebrate it
maybe you don't get you if you nothing gets kind of overly evaluated overly
valued everything is respected which allows for this the birth of this
healthy relatedness this freedom in which things can flow and the idea that things can flow within
us without it being appropriated by self
made into self measured by self is a fascinating and delightful and
empowering empowering kind of situation to be in and so to begin exploring this world of
self the self thing we do the attachment to it not in any blame nothing now
you're a bad Buddhist uh you don't become a bad Buddhist by anything that you do and how you are
and maybe you're never a bad Buddhist but uh where Buddhism is found and where
the health is found is in the relationship we have with all things
including your relationship to yourself and some of the relationships that people have with themselves what's been
going on here is very difficult there's a lot of criticism sometimes
despising of oneself there's a lot of difficulty here and so and it's painful
very deep and so trying to come to a new relationship finding your relationship
where there's compassion and care and kindness It's a slow process
but it's helpful to know that this is what we're doing we're trying to come to a new relatedness
where we're freeing ourselves from the fixed ideas of who we are fixed ideas of
this is what perfect is or this is what imperfect is there's no actually there's no
imperfular perfect or if there is perfection in writing the wave
the perfect riding the wave you know how long that lasts
it lasts probably less than a second so congratulations but you don't have
any time to congratulate yourself because you're on to the next half seconds when you have to kind of make the adjustments for the next perfection
and so with this kind of idea you know how long you're imperfect a few of us are occasionally imperfect
right a little bit you know but you know how long it really lasts it's like the wave
it's like it might be true for half a second unless we're caught in the idea of it
we're projecting the idea we're living the idea I'm imperfect but the idea is just an idea
the idea of the wave is just the idea but the wave is always changing you're always changing everything is fluid
and one of the the one of the things we're coming to in this practice of mindfulness is appreciating deeper and deeper the
fluidity of the moment to moment we're always on a wave
we're always finding our way and if you're not finding your way you'll probably fall off
The Wave in some ways if you get involved in too much retrospective thinking about what I did
you probably fall off the wave so to ride the wave of the present moment and what is the right relationship
what is the way what's the relationship that rises when it's informed by everything
within and without and as we become Freer what we discover
is that we don't have to be so self-concerned about how we respond
the sense of the right response it's just it becomes more and more it
feels almost natural obvious of course you're going to be kind
of course or say differently maybe you'll automatically be kind
but you'll automatically not be unkind you won't be mean
you're automatically be succumb someone this is very clear in Buddhism they say that once you reach a certain maturity
in this practice you become someone who will never kill intentionally never steal never engage
in sexual misconduct that harms people so there's all these ways in which
you don't do all this stuff that's as harmful because that takes work and effort
and with the absence of that what is left
and what I love is this tradition that was Buddhist tradition that we're in it doesn't specify what's left
it's very reluctant to say that what's left is your basic human goodness
what's left is wonderful what's left is love and delight and all
that because I think because as soon as you say that
you fall off the wave as soon as you'd say that you're kind of locked on into something and you this is
how it has to be but rather there's a deep Trust
in with this maturity of just allowing
something to flow through us now that you know is not going to be unhealthy not going to be harmful
so that's taken out of the picture and then what the response is from the inside
might not look like the ideal might not look what you think it's supposed to be
but maybe it's the right thing in the combination the relatedness of
you and everything else who knows what that's supposed to be you don't even know what it's going to be
sometimes to come with preconceived ideas
limits of what might arise so to assert the self
is delusion to allow all things to inform you
or allow all things to inform
allows for health to unfold the healthy wave
so I'd encourage you if this talk had some meaning for you
that um I'm not I'm not assuming that what I was saying about the relationship between
you and the world you and others is an obvious category to understand
maybe because it's always shifting I'm not saying it's easy like now you can just kind
but there is this relatedness there is something that happens in relationship and it takes a while to begin to become
sensitive to it and attune to it and appreciate it and with some people it's easier and
some people it's not so easy there might be good friends that you can say I there's a new thing I want to understand
better maybe you can help me there's not you and there's me and that's what there's what happens between
us let's explore that and having some friend to help you might
be make it kind of come alive more and interesting and and make it uh help you
with this new kind of world and uh and maybe you'll understand some
point very personally to assert the self is delusion
and to a lot of allow everything to inform you is Awakening
thank you