hello everyone welcome
and to begin
there's a variety of turns of phrases or
expressions that convey something very important about dharma practice
and one of them is that um
maybe we're not focusing on changing our experience as much as increasing our capacity
for experience expanding our capacity
for being with discomfort expanding our capacity to be with
comfort with pleasure with joy
increasing our capacity to be with challenging emotions
increasing our capacity to be with beautiful emotions this idea of
being able to have to hold or to
make space for our emotional experience
if we have very little capacity then we become easily reactive or shut down
or try to run away or collapse all kinds of things
and if we have a capacity to hold anger without
acting on the anger hold sadness hold
despair hold emotional pain it's a radically different thing to make
room for to hold it and what this means is not to be defined by it not to be
constricted by it not to be pushed around by it
not to be necessarily before or against it you're not kind of caught in its
in its in its grip or caught in its you know making it into something but
rather allowing it to be there and and even very intense
and sorrows to just kind of keep opening keep relaxing well i can relax with this too
this too even though there might be tension as part of it sometimes there's a greater capacity of awareness of the
heart of the body to hold it to make room for it to expand
beyond it to allow it to be there
so with that in mind maybe we'll sit today meditate today
with the uh not with changing anything not with
probing anything but rather opening to
everything opening our capacity to hold to be present to make a room for
so to begin
to have a posture that for you and your way
the posture that is stable strong open enough
so that you can bring a capacity to be with challenges and joys
the body is a great help for this capacity building
and gently closing your eyes
and to check in with yourself sitting here right now
respectfully respecting yourself as you are
what is your capacity right now some people are
stressed some people have difficult life situations going on some people
have illnesses all kinds of things can happen that might limit our capacity
to be with new challenges or even new joys which are energetic or
challenging demanding and to recognize that's the case
to do that with respect with care with love this is how it is now
maybe your capacity feels bigger maybe it's a time in your life where
things are settled and peaceful and you've had lots of rest and so you feel
like you're now you have lots of room and respect that
and then to take a few long slow deep gentle breaths
as if you're breathing through it all breathing through your capacity to hold
your experience
as the body as your breathing exhales to relax
soften
to let your breathing return to normal
and gently without ambition
as you breathe see if you can
spread waves of calming calmness
through your body
see if you could also let there be a calming of the mind as
you maybe as you exhale
the quieting of your thinking
settling into your breathing
and as you inhale
be present for the full length of the inhale
as if deep as you breathe in and the lungs
fill with air the chest expands
as if you're expanding
the boundaries of your body is if you're opening up and becoming
larger
whatever you're experiencing as you sit here
rather than changing anything open up more fully to experience it make
room for it
whatever is happening recognize it's happening
and allow it to be there as if it has a lot of room
whatever is happening physically in the body
emotionally mentally in the mind
allow yourself to become bigger than the experience
whatever is happening whatever way you get distracted or involved in thoughts
or feelings body sensations you can gently say
this too you're open to
this too you will allow and breathe
breathe with it making room for it
so
and as we come to the end of this sitting
is there some way that silence supports a greater capacity
to be with all experience
a certain kind of silence of mind silence of heart
the silence of the space around us
and is there some way that a healthy inner silence or stillness
can give you a greater capacity for being with the joys and sorrows of
others
a capacity to accompany others
in their challenges and their celebrations
and in that greater capacity to be with people to share with people
their joys and sorrows
maybe it's easier to tap into
feelings of care and good will love
kindness
may it be that our capacity to be present for all experience
makes room for our love and kindness and our friendliness
everyone that we encounter may it be that our practice
this morning is for the welfare and happiness of others
and our own may all
beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you so on this fifth uh talk
on becoming wise with emotion towards emotions
i want to talk a little bit about uh attention to the source of our emotions
now where they the emotions arise from and now certainly there are layers of
sources from within and a little bit i talked about that yesterday
is that certain emotions might have other emotions that are the source for it or that immediate
predecessor for it anger might be hurt or fear
joy might be vary the source within it within us
it might be uh praise to our conceit and we're so energized joyfully about that
or it might be this delightful sense of freedom or ease
that comes when conceit disappears
and um when it's not there and um
and so but the in the teachings of the buddha there's a
distinction between two sources or two kinds of
emotional lives and one is
i like to call dharmic and the other we call
non-dharmic some people might call it spiritual and worldly some people call it um
yeah you know there's a variety of things they call this but at the heart of the buddhist teachings on mindfulness
is this distinction between that which belongs to the sensual world
and that which belongs something deeper that is the non-sensual world
and spiritual and non-spiritual it's not it's not a a criticism or a denigrating
of the what's maybe non-spiritual or that which is essential
but there is a distinction between uh that which um uh
emotions to get they get triggered by our reactivity
and those emotions that um are not
not arising reactively to something but rather emerge flow through us
arise out of us almost almost independent of the conditions
around us so if i am in a hurry to get somewhere driving
somewhere and someone is driving really slow
my eagerness my strong desire to get someplace is frustrated
and i might then get angry or get afraid reacting to the person who's driving
slow another situation same situation i might be trying to go somewhere maybe i need
to get there on time but i'm driving in a relaxed open way
someone's driving slow and and i see it and i say oh someone's
driving slow and looks like someone who maybe is old and and uh is you know just trying to
drive carefully and so i let it be and i use it in this occasion just to
relax and in that relaxation that just be the being of the situation there's
now room more deeply that i'm not reacting to anything but there's a feeling of contentment or
feeling of gratitude for the day and the sky and
and things like that there might be a sense of uh care and
love for the person in the driving slow and um and i don't uh i'm not
it's not being triggered by what's out there it's just kind of a of a natural kind of upwelling
of warmth for someone who's driving carefully and caring for them
um there we sit and meditate and we might feel
like we're you know very ambitious to get really deeply concentrated right away
and and that ambition to get you know and maybe we have a bad feeling for ourselves we feel like we've somehow
um don't succeed very well in things in our lives and meditation is supposed to help us
and it's supposed to be an alternative to the challenges of life but i have to be successful in meditation and then
we're not we're not getting concentrated and so that already there's a built up tension
behind doing the meditation and so when meditation is not going successfully we react to that we get
angry at meditation angry at ourselves angry at buddhism you know angry at the world
reacting there there's on the surface more i think of more the surface level of who
we are um we're carrying the tensions and stresses emotional physical mental
and those stresses when they're touched by by the world
they get triggered when when we have a great capacity
and lots of space and ability to be open to be relaxed to be present and
without those surface tensions stresses then uh
in for someone who's really mature in this practice there are no triggers
the things occur and they don't so when if we hold up our my in buddhism this
idea of holding up conceit and something comes along that threatens that conceit there's like a collision
and then there's a reaction to it if there's no conceit something comes along and criticizes us and you know
normally maybe it doesn't hit our conceit it just goes right through
but that's going right through that capacity to not be caught not be reactive not have
something up there that inside that the world hits um makes room
for the upwelling of a lot of wonderful emotions there's
an upwelling of healing upwelling of movement towards harmony movement
towards unification there's an upwelling of contentment or peace
sometimes joy and happiness and these are these there's this that
which is up that wells up uh is not reactive
that is what's dharmic dharmic emotions dharmic feelings are those that arise in the space
uh where kind of an empty space in a certain kind of way empty of
of tension and empty of holding on to certain emotions
empty and having certain kinds of demands on the situation or expectations
or cravings or ambitions or oh a strong sense of self that we're
protecting or hiding or something and so uh the dharmic
emotions are those that they're kind of non-dharmic are the ones that arise when there's a collision with
something hard inside of us the the non
the the that's the non-dharmic the dharmic is when there's nothing in there
and there's space and things can go right through but more importantly there's space for
things to well up and the classic analogy for this similarly for it
is that of a mountain lake where there's no rivers or rain that fills the lake
it's getting completely refreshed from an underground uh fount underground spring that's
welling up from the bottom of the lake spreading this fresh water throughout the lake so in the same way this uh
we're not getting um we're not depending on input from the world around us
uh the rivers coming into the lake and we're not depending on the rain all
the thoughts and ideas we have in the mind in order to
have this upwelling but rather there's more like a subtleness
a relaxation a real sense of presence attention to
here and then an upwelling of
of uh has a chance to arise we have within us a tremendous capacity
dharma capacity for a flow for a naturalness
of positive emotions things like love and care and joy and
contentment gratitude um delight glad
compassion [Music] beautiful beautiful states
and but they're not states that we make happen reactively
they are almost like a gift that comes when we our capacity
to be present is expansive and open and we're patient and available
without the is stirring up or the agitation
of reactivity of a lot of desires that are pushing us around a lot of aversion pushing us
around there's a subtleness happening so this distinction between those
emotions that are born out of our reactivity and those that emotions that arise from
a deeper upwelling that's n is not a react reaction
but it is more like the um the innate capacity of our systems
psychophysical system to express itself to manifest something
that is responsive and in harmony with our environment and with what's happening
so i don't know how well i i've articulated this but i think maybe well enough this distinction
to maybe give you something to reflect on this weekend
to think a little bit about the source of the different emotions that come through over the next few days
are the emotions more reactive emotions even the joyful ones are they reacting
to something um that's happening in the world so that uh it's you know it's touching some
hitting something inside there that then just um reacts
or is there an upwelling is there a naturalness is there a kind of a
almost as if you're getting out of the way and something wells up
dharmic joy dharmic happiness that
doesn't depend on the conditions of the world
reactive emotions depend on the conditions of the world and
and the world being ourselves as well the dharmic are those which are
independent non-dependent in a certain kind of way
so um
so then uh one announcement that some of you might be interested at in a
few weeks a couple weeks at july 9th
through insight retreat center we're going to have a day-long retreat
online on zoom and that i'll be teaching and if some of you would like to kind of
continue this in a deeper way then
you know for a day long you can go probably to the uh insightretreatcenter.org website
or at some point in the next while it'll probably be announcement about this on the imc website too on the what's new
so um thank you all and
and i was thinking that maybe on next monday next week maybe to continue with this theme of emotions but maybe to go
through and choose five different emotions to consider and reflect on how to practice
with and what we've been talking about this week might apply to particular situations
so thank you