so hello everyone and
and we come to the end of this week the end of this five part series on
i'm calling it finding our way and
these days have been somewhat progressive um with the pointing towards
first to contentment then to gladness
then to joy then to happiness and today the topic will be peace
peace and agitation finding our way with that
and um and so this week uh the idea in my mind
or in my heart my body is that uh with the practice
we begin settling into ourselves settling in to these uh
places that inside the states inside which are available to us
but are often eclipsed by agitation by
preoccupations by busyness of life and to become quiet
to be able to let go relax enough to be able to touch into
our capacity for contentment and gladness joy happiness and now peace
so today the topic is peace and
i think it's really really important to understand that how peace can begin with ourselves
and then in buddhist practice that's where we tend to start if we want peace we start with ourselves
and we start by being peaceful so that seems a little hard
to start with to want what we don't have and then start with it the idea is that
two things around this one is
bring into the meditation whatever sense of peace peacefulness that's available
to you and one of the important areas of that is
in the knowing in the attention you bring to whatever is happening here and now
if you're bringing attention to your breathing to your posture your body if you're bringing attention to your
emotions or your your inner mental life your thoughts can you let that
attention can you bring that attention or evoke that attention
engage that attention in a way that has some kind of peacefulness to it
it doesn't have to be dramatic but that's where it begins
and then the second thing which is uh different than the first but the two can go together
is rather than
being too active and be making yourself peaceful
avoid agitating yourself avoid agitation
rather than become peaceful don't participate in the agitation don't
go along with it and one way not to go along with it is
to be aware of it peacefully there it is my agitation my old friend
peace begins with oneself so taking a assuming a meditation posture
and giving some care to the posture in a
peaceful way so that the attention to the posture and getting things lined up and settled
is done not in a hurry and not ambitiously
but peacefully
and then to gently close your eyes
taking a few long slow deep breaths
letting your breathing return to normal in an
unhurried way go through your body and as you exhale
relax and soften in your body
and then if it's appropriate you can center
yourself on your breathing
and as you exhale
to quiet the mind
maybe you can't stop thinking but can you quiet
your thinking
and in the times in your life where you felt peaceful
where in your body that sense of peacefulness reside
might there be a place in your body that you associate with peacefulness
a place that feels quiet or calm
feel settled or content
feels unagitated
calm tranquil
and to maybe breathe
with this place
maybe the memory or the sense of this place being peaceful
can help the awareness your attention to be peaceful too
so
whatever degree of peacefulness you have right now no matter how small a little peace there
is notice the peacefulness
and then see if you can avoid becoming more agitated
and if that's all you do that will be a great meditation
so
so then as we come to the end of the sitting
to [Music] consider
how healthy and helpful it is for this world for there to be more peace
that the people we run into in our lives today chances are
they could use a little bit more peacefulness maybe being agitated being afraid being
angry confused
so to um consider how is it that whatever peace
that you have whatever way you live your life
can you in some gentle way
bring peacefulness to this world a sense of peace
and probably best that it's not too noticeable
just that you're calm or centered or available in a nice way
may it be that this practice that we do serves for the welfare and happiness of
others and for this world may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe may all beings
be free
[Music]
thank you
so in buddhism is often associated with peace
and in fact the emotional
um manifestations of awakening of freedom that the buddha
points to is most commonly associated with happiness and peace
peace and happiness and
and the opposite of peace is maybe agitation conflict
and and that's part of our world we navigate a world where we get agitated
we get we're calm and then we're not so calm we're maybe somewhat peaceful but then
we're not peaceful we're agitated and then we're less agitated
and and so how do we fall how do we find our way in this world of navigating in all
this when do we emphasize peaceful peace
appreciate it value it cultivate it when do we um
allow ourselves to become agitated or less peaceful or
allow there to be energized in a dynamic way that doesn't feel very peaceful
and there are times for both and as we're living in this world there are times when it's appropriate to put
aside our peace and let ourselves kind of enter into the world of doing and activity
and not being so concerned about whether we're agitated or not or lost our calm or not
so there's times for peace and there's times where peace is not
really the name of the game not really appropriate and and there are times when there's
agitation which is inappropriate and really a challenge and it makes our life much more difficult
and there's a time to allow ourselves to become agitated or lose some of our calm
if you're you know they're you know it's easy to argue that it's maybe always good to be calm
but realistically i don't know if that's really going to happen unless we're living
you know a solitary quiet lifestyle if you're living in someplace in your
neighbor comes knocking at your door with a i don't know with a big injury and asks
you to take them to the emergency that's not the time to
be excessively concerned about your calm and as you get to the emergency and your maybe your
neighbor can't talk much at this point and so you're having to explain and
and be engaged in the activity and and i think that chances are is that that's going to be
you're not going to keep your calm you're going to be activated in some strong way and enough so that when your
friend is finally being taken care of and you can sit quietly you see how much activation there is you're spun up
and but that's not wrong to have that happen in the circumstances in fact to be holding on to the calm and
the peace and let's let's kind of make our way to the car slowly and peacefully and
you know and count our steps and every step say peace that's not really the name of the game
it's uh we have to let go of any emphasis on peace and just engage in what's needed
being in the world with what's needed is part of what dharma practice is about
and so certainly it's possible to be attached to peace and hold on to it it's possible to kind
of pretend we're peaceful or kind of hold ourselves kind of hold ourselves kind of contain ourselves
in certain kind of ways so it's kind of like we're not agitated physically we're not moving around a lot or
we're kind of staying close to something that looks like peace but it's more attachment and
manufactured and not really real the the ability to navigate between kind
of activated states and peaceful states it's a lot easier if we're fluid to go
between them and this fluidity if we can't if we resist one or hold on to one
then we're not fluid and then it's not easy to go back and forth between them in fact one of the
principles of dharma practice that i value a lot is not that we have any we attain any
particular state as if that's the state that we're supposed to be in there's all kinds of
mental states embodied states that we can experience and to be free
is to have fluidity to be able to move between them and back and forth
uh and if we have that fluidity then we can kind of navigate this world
of all the differences much quicker and more easy if we don't have that fluidity we become
fragile we're holding on we're resisting we are threatenable and because what
we're holding on to is threatened or what we're afraid is going to happen will come and overwhelm us
but if we kind of can kind of surf with it kind of navigate and and um
with fluidity with ease with relaxation not holding on to anything and not resisting much in at least in the
inner life it's much easier to let go it's much easier to not be troubled by things
so there's activated states in life and there's peaceful states calm states
and sometimes it's healthy just to move between them with fluidity and it's okay
to be activated it's okay to kind of lose our calm sometimes and sometimes it's not
sometimes we lose our calm and we make mistakes and we make the whole thing worse agitation can create a lot of stress and
exhaustion and so navigating between this
is part of this and and uh it's a the uh it's much harder if
we're as i'm saying we're clinging clinging grasping holding on resisting
all those create more agitation and less peace
non-clinging non-attachment create more fluidity
less attachment more appropriate peace and a greater capacity to
flow out of that piece when something else is needed and was no longer needed flowing back to a calm state or be centered
so so finding our way with peace and activation peace and agitation
some of this has to do with becoming connoisseurs of both not just become experts on peace but
become experts on agitation itself that mindfulness is really to see and
understand how our life works what's really like these things we go through
and so spend time and when you're agitated what and with the question what is this agitation
how am i experiencing it what's being triggered where does it live in me what's my relationship to this agitation
do i believe it do i go headlong into it am i resisting it am i judging it am i
um critical of myself for being agitated there's all these things to study and
become much more aware of and we can study it we can bring a
peaceful mindfulness to that a non-conflictive mindfulness so this is
how it is this is how it is and equally well we want to study peace
we want to get to understand and become connoisseurs and recognize it even the small hints of it even when it's a very
minor piece be able to recognize when it's available
peace is much more available than most people realize most situations we're in
have more peace somehow somewhere in the center of them in the corner of them than the busy activated mind allows
ourselves to tune into so to study these things get to know them more
and that brings us into the capacity to recognize when we cling when we resist
where our attachments are and as the practice deepens
there's a process of letting go or relaxing or softening our
attachments it goes deeper and deeper and deeper more and more to the core of who we are
and we start letting go of small things that's a training to let go of the
deeper attachments and the deeper attachments and and then we don't want to
become attached to letting go we don't want to be attached to these deeper states of well-being and
peace that might be there that is a recipe for agitation again unhealthy agitation
and then and then to drop down deeper and deeper
to to some of the deepest places we can let go
to and so the deepest piece is what's called release
release is peace the deepest peace comes from a profound
release where we're no longer in the world of polarities between peace and agitation
where we're centered in such a way that the kind of a peace goes with us a comp
goes with us even when we're busy and activated and doing things it's not far away
that the deeper the letting go can be the more thorough it can be it's like it
creates a space of absence a space where there's kind of a spaciousness
in our minds and our hearts and our bodies someplace and that spaciousness can feel calm can
feel open and that kind of because it's like more like space
things can happen to us and they go right through that space if they're if we're peaceful but
peaceful is kind of like we're holding ourselves peaceful or it's very palpable a kind of state of
peace that is a kind of feeling that's wonderful
but that also is not an empty space of freedom where things can just go through or
there's space to hold everything and so this letting go is what creates
this inner space which provides a qualitatively different kind of piece
different kind of calm different kind of well-being and
and room for all of ourselves so
to navigate this world of ours with the
idea that we want to make room for all of who we are
in this way this particular wave where there's no attachments no clinging
and on the way there we have to make room for our attachments and get to know them as well
so it's a wonderful journey finding our way and i'd like to end this little series
on finding your way with these different states that
one of the lessons i'm trying to get across is don't have a categorical
right and wrong for almost any state that you have any way that you are
take time to look at it and sometimes almost this part almost a time for everything
and um and certainly a time to study it and get to know it and that finding our way navigating this
world of ours when we're a mindfulness practitioner has a lot to do
with bringing mindfulness and space mindfulness and room
to how we are so we can learn to find the most
the wisest way and the freest way to navigate this life of ours
so thank you for
participating in this and maybe for this weekend it can be a theme for your your
homework home practice to study your relationship to agitation and
peace agitation and calm or tranquilly whatever you like and to see how you uh if there's a
pendulum that swings between them do you prefer them do you hold on to them what can you
what happens if you spend time with each studying them or getting to know them becoming more familiar with them
become the connoisseur of your agitation and of your peace
thank you