it's a pleasure to be here with you my name is May Elliott and I will be leading these 7 A.M sittings each day
so um over the next five days I'll be going over the foundational vapassana
meditation instructions as they're typically taught in the West so uh we'll start with breath today talk
about mindfulness of breathing then we'll talk about tomorrow the body Wednesday
emotions Thursday we'll talk about thinking and then Friday open awareness
practice so I'll say more about this series once we finish the meditation once we're in the darmet
and give you some context for this um as I mentioned the focus of today's
meditation will be the brat and that's going to be our primary anchor for the
meditation so um for some people the breath doesn't work very well as their primary anchor
and if you're one of those people that's totally fine Some people prefer a sense of the bodily posture like a
global sense of the body some people take the sense of Sound hearing for
their anchor that's all fine and just for the sake of simplifying the
instructions I'll be offering directions specifically on the breath as a primary anchor so
that's what I'll be I'll be talking most about and do what works for you so let's start our meditation with a
stable upright posture I can gently close the eyes
have your hands on your lap or your knees it's fine to be sitting standing or
lying down whatever posture works best for your meditation
so as we start let's take three deep breaths together
inhaling and exhaling
and again
now allowing the breath to take up a normal rhythm in this practice we're not
tampering with the breath or trying to change it in any way just being with it as it is
and allow it to happen naturally
and as we settle into the body it can help to have some uprightness in
the posture if you're sitting to have a straight spine
we can think of lengthening the spine as though we're putting just a little bit
of extra space between each vertebrae
making the neck a little bit longer
and then from that upright stable posture it's allowing everything else to
relax allowing
the skin flesh the muscles to drape on the scaffolding
of the bones
softening the forehead and the temples
relaxing the jaw
softening the shoulders
releasing the belly
loosening the hips
and allowing any extra tension to flow out through the legs and the feet
arriving here
as we start this sitting together I invite you to connect with the breath
where you feel it most predominantly
for some people the sensation is clearest at the nostrils
for some it's in the rise and fall of the chest
and for others it's in the expansion of the belly it's in the belly
so go ahead and take a moment and connect with where you feel the breath most predominantly
foreign
the mind to settle on that sensation
allowing that area where you feel the breath most predominantly to be your primary anchor
so you are collecting the mind around that sensation into that sensation
and when you find that the mind has wandered
just gently and kindly slide right back to the breath right back to this
predominant sensation
it's no problem if the Mind thinks you just don't follow its content we don't
actually engage in the narrative it's telling us we just
come right back to the breath no need to judge ourselves for thinking
or reject the thinking or just releasing it with a really light
touch
fonts fall to the background and the breath is in the foreground
as soon as you notice that you've been thinking
you're actually back in the present so there's no need for reprimand
already back here
breathing in and breathing out
releasing any preoccupations to come into the breath
entering the breath and not just the idea of the breath but
the felt experience of the breath feeling it through the language of
sensation
and I'll offer some ways to be curious about the breath to get to know it
okay kind of like we are welcoming an old friend that we haven't seen for a long
time sitting down with great curiosity to get to know them to get to know who they are
now so can we
get to know the breath with that Curiosity and friendliness
can we sense whether the breath is textured what's
the texture of the breath is it smooth
or silky
is it staccato or rough
sensing the texture of the breath
foreign
what's the shape of the breath
does it Billow widely with a big inhale
or is it thin and narrow
feeling into the shape of the breath
maybe the breath starts thin and narrow and then it widens as the chest expands
what's the temperature of the breath
is it warm or cool
and does the temperature change when shifting from an inhale to an exhale
maybe the inhale is cool and the exhale is warm
and how do you know how do you know it's warm or cool
what's the sensation telling you that
maybe getting to know temperature with a little more interest
foreign
attention now to the length of the breath
our breath short or long
and is the inhale longer than the exhale or the other way around
foreign
are you feeling the breath most predominantly in the right lung or the
left lung
or do you both fill evenly
foreign
as we explore the breath remember that we're not tampering with it in any way
not trying to make it deeper or longer or a smoother or warmer or cooler
just noticing what's happening
no need to make the present moment any different than it is
many of us tend to notice the breath in the front of our body maybe in the rise
and fall of the chest or the belly or through the sensations on our face by
our nose
we can also tune into the way the breath affects our back body
Can You Feel the rise and fall of the breath in the back
foreign
be sensed in the rise and fall of the shoulders
maybe there's a subtle lift and release as you breathe
can you notice the moment an in-breath starts
staying connected to the breath from the moment it starts through the length of
the inhale
and can you notice the top of the inhale when the breath is finished
bringing air in noticing that moment and the turn the
pivot to the exhale
feeling the complete release of the exhale
noticing the moment the exact moment the exhale stops
and then again the moment the inhale starts
this can be a great way to stay with the breath
ensuring we notice the point the breath starts the inhale starts
and the point that the inhale turns to an exhale
the complete exhale the end of the exhale
ensuring we notice these transition moments shifting from inhale to Exhale
again
often the mind wanders in the paws between breaths
so can we catch those moments those transition moments then bring our
curiosity to the breath in between
and on your own now allow yourself to see what your mind is interested in with the breath
maybe noticing the texture maybe the shape or the temperature
maybe the length
continuing with the breath in whatever way works for you
foreign
to make a mental note very light mental label
when breathing in you might note in
when breathing out or you might try
Rising falling as your notes
and the note can help us keep connected help us stay connected to the present
gives the Mind something to do naming the experience as it happens
if you do note the breath make sure that the note is light
the majority of the attention is in the body's sensing and the the note is very
light and faint
foreign
oh
as we come to the end of our sitting together
taking a moment to feel the goodness of this practice
some gratitude for having this time
to take care of the heart and the mind
may all beings be happy
healthy safe and free from suffering
foreign
I hope you enjoyed your meditation my name is May Elliott and uh I will be
leading the 7ams this week so welcome if you're just arriving
at the beginning I shared that over the next five days I'll be going over the foundational
vipassana meditation instructions as they are typically taught in the West
so there if you haven't noticed there are so many different styles of practice in vipassana there's the Brahma vihara
heart practices and the five elements meditation and 32 parts of the body
um maranasati uh yeah contemplation there's so many different
ones and so my hope is just to simplify and lay out the basics of a passionate practice
um so if you attended a silent retreat at a Western papasana Center like
site Retreat Center or Spirit Rock these are the meditation instructions that you would typically receive over
the course of the retreat and the instructions I'll offer are the ones most typically suggested for those who
are building an at-home practice so um and for me personally I'm always
returning to this instruction for myself for my own practice so I hope that
similarly whether you're a new practitioner or a very experienced practitioner that these are beneficial
for you so we'll be going over today Brett day two the body mindfulness of
body day three emotions day four mindfulness of thinking and then the
last day bringing that all together bringing all four days of teaching together into open awareness practice
sometimes called choiceless attention so these these instructions are most
influenced by the Burmese teacher mahasi sayadam and he's really the biggest
influence for our Insight scene in the West um however though mahasi did emphasize
the breath often feeling it in the abdomen um I don't know that he emphasized it quite as much as we do in Western
teachings and this this emphasis on the breath uh came largely from the Burmese
teacher upandita so he he had a strong influence in our scene as well
and of course at the heart of this teaching is mindfulness that's what holds together each each day of teaching
um so where we pay attention to the present moment experience learning to be
intimate with our life so we're engaging in the direct experience of the moment rather than
being lost in our narratives our stories our judgments fears Etc
and in doing so we can start to have insight into the changing and the selfless nature of experience
and mindfulness it has a uh the successful function of mindfulness
depends on a particular characteristic awareness doesn't judge it doesn't
reject and it doesn't cling to anything so by practicing mind mindfulness by
simply being aware of our experience that can allow us to disentangle from
our preoccupations and that that can allow us to touch in with the wisdom and the compassion
that's already within us so uh so the basic teaching is that when
the mind is really active and there's a lot of thinking this is a great time to simplify
this is when we want to choose a really simple object to attend to a really simple thing to focus on for our
meditation so that's why we're starting with the breath we're moving from the complexity of our stories our problems
our confusions to something very simple uh just this just
just the breath there's a book that came out a few years
ago called Caesar's Last Breath the Epic story of
the air around us and in it the author Sam Keane makes quite the claim he says that of the
sextillions of molecules entering and leaving your lungs at this moment quite literally there might be molecules
from Cleopatra's perfumes particles exhaled
by dinosaurs or those emitted from atomic bombs
um and it sounds very unlikely but apparently Keane crunched the numbers and estimates that
across all that distance of time and space a few of the molecules that were
inside Caesar's lungs during his last breath are actually dancing inside your
lungs right now for many of us who are lost in our inner
fantasies the breath might not seem as interesting as the fantasies
and I think that's in part because we forget what a miracle it is
that when I breathe in I'm breathing in the the air that the
Buddha exhaled 2500 years ago
like how extraordinary that from the moment I was born to the moment of my death that I'll have
a companion I have a promised friend that will be loyal to me for each moment of my life
and that companion is the breath
so with this in mind can we pay attention to the breath with gratitude with friendliness with wonder you know
what could be more important than paying attention to this this tiny spindle of air that miraculously Keeps Us Alive
can we be curious about it if you haven't noticed in your practice curiosity is like slight glue for the
present moment it keeps us here so if you can find ways to be curious about the breath you'll find ways to be with
it and that's why we explored all these different Sensations in the meditation practice this morning you know getting
to know the texture of the breath the shape the temperature Etc
so as we as we continue returning to the breath
it collects the Mind into the present moment almost like harvesting vegetables from a field and
collecting them into a basket the mind that's scattered becomes collected and
unified so often people associate this practice of collecting the mind of
focusing on the breath with the practice of concentration
with the word concentration often specifically in the west is that it can
lead to this image of a narrow um like a tight narrow laser laser beam
like where really cultivating striving in our meditations you know really
focusing really hard concentrating but that's not actually what we're trying to do with breath Focus
um so if you notice that you're heavily straining or you're tightening up to
concentrate then then you're cultivating straining and that's not what we want to
cultivate so um so this practice is of collecting the mind so I often like the word collecting
rather than concentrating because it's relaxed we're just collecting the Mind into the breath
so traditionally there are five factors of concentration and I'll only talk about the two today the first two today
um and uh and specifically I want to talk about those two because they can be supportive in learning to stay with the
breath so the first is vitaka and the second is vichara vitaka is application so we're
applying our attention to the breath applying and then the second is vichara
sustaining so sometimes we talk in Vitara are referred to as aim and
sustain or practicing aiming and sustaining
so um recently I was on Retreat and while on Retreat I had a yogi job about
a half hour job doing a little work meditation and my job was to scrub the vegetables
and so one day I was I was scrubbing the potatoes and I was thinking about this
teaching of yitaka and vichara and I took the scrubber and I I applied I
aimed the scrubber at the potato um and then I sustained contact with the
potato as I scrubbed it right so if you talk in Vitara aiming and sustaining and I realized if I just aim at the potato
and I place the scrubber on the potato potato but then my hand kind of floats
off with the scrub brush uh I'm not sustaining contact with it you know I
can't actually I'm not actually scrubbing the potato if my hand floats off right so I have to aim and sustain and the same thing happens with the
breath often actually well aim at the breath oh I'm supposed to be paying attention to breath right okay I'm going to feel the breath and we place the
attention on the breath and then it slips right off uh kind of like sliding on a banana peel we just slip right off
into thought so sometimes it can help to remember that we want to aim and sustain
maintain contact with the breath so touching it and staying connected
through the whole inhale the potato won't get clean if you don't aim and
sustain the mind won't get collected if you don't aim and sustain with the breath
so um this quote from w s Merwin
little breath Breathe Me Gently Romy
for I am a river I am learning to cross
little breath Breathe Me Gently roll Me Gently for I am a river I am learning to cross
so the breath is our raft and it's taking us from delusion to Awakening
it's our it's our trusty companion that supports Us in traversing samsara
so I hope that you take good care of the breath that you get to know it and that
you maybe even fall in love with the breath and ultimately this practice of
returning to the breath again and again regardless of how many times we're
distracted this builds concentration the mind is collected again and again and
this brings forth calmness and Tranquility so this calming force allows
us to develop enough stability to have insight into the nature of things
um as we return to the breath and continue to collect ourselves into the present
it's kind of like stabilizing a tripod that holds a telescope so if we don't have a stable tripod it's
really hard to be still enough to see the stars and in meditation we're really wanting
to to clearly see the true nature of things we really want to see the stars right
um and what I mean by that is we want to clearly see the three characteristics
um we want to see um understand the source of suffering we
want to see the true nature of impermanence and the selfless nature of
all things I want to see suffering impermanence in that self but in order to do that we need to have
a stable tripod so the breath practice can stabilize us sufficiently to have insight into the
way things really are and when we can do that we can be free
so I think I will I will offer you a practice for the day
so if you would like to take this up your invitation is to spend uh two
minutes three three different times a day spend two minutes paying attention to your breath
just doing your best to let go of concerns and preoccupations maybe it's a moment to be grateful for
the breath or curious about the breath you might even set a timer now for three
different times today that you'll pause and do the practice practice and I've found that it's very rare in life that I
don't actually have time to sit for two minutes or to stand in meditation for two minutes
and I also I always know that if um if I think that I don't have time to sit for
two minutes that's often exactly when I really need to sit for two minutes so you can
explore that uh that practice as it's supportive for you
okay and I'll I'll close with a poem for you
this is called wage Peace by Judith Hill
wage peace with your breath breathe in firemen and Rubble
breathe out whole buildings and flocks of Red Wing blackbirds
breathe in terrorists and breathe out sleeping children and freshly moaned
feet moan fields breathe in confusion and breathe out maple trees
breathe in the fallen and bring it breathe out lifelong friendships intact
wage peace with your listening hearing Sirens pray loud remember your tools flower seeds
clothespins clean rivers make soup play music
memorize the words for thank you in three languages
learn to knit and make a hat think of chaos as dancing raspberries
imagine grief as the out breath of beauty
or the gesture of fish swim for the other side
wage peace never has the world seemed so fresh and
precious have a cup of tea and rejoice
act as if Armistice has already arrived celebrate today
that's Judith Hill wage peace so thank you everyone for your kind
attention this morning I hope to see you tomorrow for our focus on mindfulness of
body take care everyone enjoy your day