foreign hello everyone
and now contentment
is a little Maybe
problematic when a person is broadcasting to hundreds of
people in that for a few moments here I was just content to sit here and kind of
was not thinking about that I'm supposed to speak
so um it's nice to be here
and I want to begin with just a story
that uh hopefully you're generous with going along with the interpretation
because that's the point is the moral of the tail not the how well it fits the moral
and um so there because there's a spiritual Seeker
it's very sincere dedicated to the spiritual path wants to find but has
been doing it for a long time and and hasn't had any success
whatever that might mean and goes to find
one of the most senior Elder wise people in that spiritual tradition and
and explains the difficulty and you know been practicing for a long time
and searching for a long long time to no avail
and the teacher says oh okay um it's not far away for you what you're
seeking but you have to uh seek search look
practice wholeheartedly and um
the person what do you mean wholeheartedly I've been sincere and dedicated no no you have to practice wholeheartedly
do that for a year and come back
so the person does does that that's not quite sure what wholehearted means and tries all kinds of things sometimes
strains too much and learns that that can't be wholehearted and sometimes practice whole wholehearted relaxation
but that doesn't seem to be quite it and sometimes kind of evokes all the faith
the person has lots of faith in the spiritual path and but that doesn't seem
to quite do it but keeps trying it keeps engaging keeps
finding out trying to what is wholehearted what is wholehearted a year later goes back to the teacher
and says well now I've been doing this for a year and described what had been the
practices of wholeheartedness the efforts and the teacher said very good
you're been seeking so now
realize or now turn the attention around 180
degrees and realize
that what you're seeking what you're searching for is in the seeking
and with that the person was set free
so the story of kind of searching for something or what out there
that we're going to attain but maybe there's something very profound to be discovered not in the
what not in some realization not in some understanding not in some experience
but rather in the our capacity to be aware
the capacity in which we know anything which we gaze upon and see
and sometimes we're blinded and don't see the seeing because we're looking for something
we're involved in something thinking about something
and to take that backward step that 180 degree turn and to appreciate and find maybe even
freedom in the seeing in The Knowing in the
awaring is a radical paradigm shift
from how people many people live their lives and how they find meaning in their
life so to assume a meditation posture
that will be the support
for a wholehearted
awareness practice wholehearted just being here with the experience now
I like to interpret wholeheartedness not as straining or pushing or trying a lot
but a complete willingness
to enter into this moment of experience
a wholehearted means to enter wholly into the experience of now
gently closing the eyes
taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing with the long extended exhale
continuing with some longer deeper breaths hopefully in a comfortable way
and then at the next exhale the end of the exhale the
hold your breath for as long as it's comfortable and while you do so
feel your body and let your body relax more
till you feel the strong pull strong urge to breathe in
and then gently breathe in deeply
the end of the exhale hold your breath for just long enough that you start feeling the body relax
and maybe holding your breath the top of the inhale
that pause before exhaling there's a heightened attention to the
body to the urge to in exhale but also maybe a heightened sensitivity
to the body that allows you to the body to relax more
holding your breath for most people puts them more fully in
the present moment
and then returning to a normal breathing without holding anything
and on the exhale continue this process of softening relaxing your body
and then is there a way that you can be aware of the present
without trying to be aware
to be aware and allow yourself to be aware
where wholeheartedness is not trying harder
but rather allowing for fully
holistically globally
for awareness to be here and now
not trying
but allowing the present moment awareness
and in a sense allowing breathing at the center of it all
to come to you to come to awareness
rather than you directing the attention
the attention receives the experience of breathing
and then wholeness wholehearted awareness
whole awareness of the moment let that include
honesty and honest recognition of what is happening
within you
thinking feeling wanting not wanting
and honesty that needs nothing wants something nothing
honesty that's not judging just an honest recognition of what's
Happening Now
and then the to turn the attention around 180 degrees
to find Freedom in the searching
rather than being aware of freedom
as something external from awareness
to be aware of the to know the freedom of awareness
is there a sense of freedom and non-attachment
in the simplest acts of knowing sensing
seeing with the Mind's Eye
even if it's just a hint
rest back in the freedom found
in awareness in being aware
foreign
to imagine yourself sitting back in an easy chair
maybe you are even
nothing's required of you nothing you have to do or say
but just be present Here and Now
and the people of your lives start coming in
and they sit down around you with you Neighbors come in
strangers come in the whole town the whole County the
whole state everyone
comes in as the walls of your house expand bigger and
bigger nothing's required of you but to be present
nothing you have to say or do
and maybe it's possible to be aware of them all
with the freedom of awareness the awareness that
doesn't get stuck anywhere or attached to anything
kind of like looking out across the ocean just not fixating on anything seeing the
ocean relax that ease
gazing upon all these people that have come to you
and perhaps to
bring forth Good Will and friendliness
a good will that simply is wishing them well
may it be that they have lots of benefits lots of Happiness
lots of safety
lots of Peace may they be well may they be safe
gazing upon all beings kindly while staying calm
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe they all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and here we are at the third talk and this
here five part series on meaning and um
that the meetings we have for ourselves meanings we have for life can come to bear on our meditation
there's a connection with it and sometimes we um that the sense of meaning we have
animates and activates our meditation like search for meaning
staying close to it sometimes it agitates it sometimes it's you know you
get caught up in these topics of meaning meaning uh the important important
meanings we have can influence how we meditate and why we meditate and
and so to begin looking at the meaning making aspects of the mind and
meaning making aspects of how we live our lives is important all around but
it's also important to really kind of clarify what we're doing in meditation what meditation is about for us
both so that we can maybe have a little bit wholehearted engagement we know why
we're doing something but also be so that sometimes the meetings we assign to meditation or
connect to it are not helpful they actually get in the way of the
depth and full potential of meditation um the
so the um so there's this idea of meaning
sometimes connected to the big questions of life that people are sometimes very strongly motivated to find or to live by
or or to establish for themselves so something as big as what's the
meaning of life or what's the meaning of my life that I want to have there's these big questions about uh
death you know what what happens when we die what happens to us after we die
and um and so people are you know trying to understand that then that affects
their relationship to meditation meditation for some people is a strategy
in order to deal with death and for some people it's uh it's
understood that mindfulness meditation is one of the best preparations for dying and so wanting to die well or die freely
and not be die you know with difficulty but some people it's meditation is not
about dying well but about being reborn well or not not being reborn in future and there's a
strong momentum or approaching Buddhism about practicing in
order to become free of rebirth so some people that's really important for what they do and that's kind of
informs and animates their whole dedication to meditation
some people mistrust meaning making
and uh and don't see a need for it and for them meditation is not about
um you know the big questions of life but have to do with the Simplicity of the moment just living this moment in a
nice way but that also is connected to meaning somehow the idea that just living fully
for this moment in a simple clear free way that that's meaningful that's important that's a valuable way of
living a living this precious life that we have that some and so you know this
idea of what interpretation what understanding do we have about what this life is about
so um so these are things to reflect on and
and partly reflecting on what's most important for us and um and the value of really spending
time with that and looking at it then we can ask the question um how does my meditation support what's
most important for me and it's possible that if meditation
doesn't support what's most important maybe you shouldn't meditate maybe there's better things to do maybe it's
to do things that actually support what's most important but if meditation in fact does support
what's most important then maybe then there's a more easier to do it or more
motivated to do it or and we see the connection and and you know it it really
you know and encourage us to be more fully involved with it all
also to realize that maybe they're consciously or unconsciously that we
have these large existential questions or our large extential answers some of us live by
uh engagements as part of all this then it's possible to investigate more deeply
um kind of to turn the attention around 180 degrees to really look deeply inside
where do these existential beliefs where do these ideas
what is uh fueling them where they arise out of what's the source of them inside
of ourselves and and rather than accepting it as a
given uh not questioning the philosophy or the beliefs that are there necessarily
but rather questioning maybe or looking deeply what is motivating that what animates
them what is their fuel for thinking this way or being this way
and what I mean for this they'll give you some examples that um
some people will ask you know what's the meaning of life some big question like that
and I might ask what's the emotion that is fueling that question
and some people will say it's fear fear of missing out fear not doing it
right fear of of failing this life or fear of you know not really
understanding what's the purpose of my life and and if fear is motivating it
then the practice of mindfulness is to turn the attention around to really attend to
the fear before we attend to the big questions and really go deeply into it and be
present until that fear dissolves and when the fear dissolves then what
has happened to those questions if those questions are big questions or the big kind of meanings of Life are not
fueled by fear what fuels them
or if they're not fueled what happens to them is our relationships does our relationship to them change the beliefs
might still be there but if they don't have the uh the strength that comes with the power that
comes from the fear what happens to it then the same thing with death
concerns with death might have to do with fear and to look at the fear deeply
sometimes what fuels these things is conceit somehow it's about me and myself
and I have to prove myself I have to do what's right I have to account for
myself I have to show that I'm a good person I have to prove something
and um and so these big existential questions are very tightly connected to ideas of identity
of conceit of um that we attachments to self uh all right now I'm using all of
these in the context of how they involve attachment and um and uh
um and so we investigate that we bring our attention to that and so this idea of turning around 180
degrees and really is looking deeper and deeper rather than letting the big questions of Life the big existential
conclusions and ideas of life a hover there in our life and as if they're like
a fixed thing to stay with and we live by uh mindfulness meditation involves a
looking deeper and deeper what what animates it where does the source inside
where these kinds of beliefs understandings come from
what what fuels them and um and so it's a paradigm shift in a
sense from being concerned with something that's and
um you know um that we can be aware of we can think about we can believe about
to something that's deeper than what we think about or what we believe about or
that kind of focus and returning around and what what is it like to be believing
what is it like to be searching what's it like to be holding on to these
ideas that it has to be this way uh or this you know if I don't kind of
believe this or hold on to this kind of thing everything will fall apart and these beliefs keep me safe Maybe
so these big existential questions in in this mindfulness tradition are important to see
the big existential conclusions we've come to they're important to see and then but then
look more deeply what's going on under the surface what is the source for them inside what
is the feelings the emotions the fears the conceits the you know what's what's
the complex it's all about and how this all connects to meditation
is that um it turns out that these existential
questions these big answers we have to the big questions of life
more often than not will interfere
with the full potential of meditation being a full releasing
of all attachment and when all our attachments have been
released what happens to our relationship to these big existential questions big
existential big you know answers that we might be trying to live
by or living by him they don't necessarily go away and the answer still might be relevant for us
but it's a kind of a whole different world to live in with them
if that we've been able to take meditation all the way to its potential
to a full release so what is your relationship
to the big questions of life to questions of meaning questions about life and death and what
is it questions of what's most ultimate
questions of God and Heaven and rebirth and and um
purpose and do you have something that you believe believe is Ultimate
or you're searching for that and to respect that you whatever it is you're doing like this respect it deeply
but then turn the attention around and look more deeply at what's
underneath that what's fueling it uh what's the what's it what's animating
those beliefs so that involvement and see if uh what you see there and
and find and and see if that might help you uh to become quieter Stiller
more at ease more
centered Here and Now in that place where there can be no attachments
so thank you very much and uh continue
this idea of meaning um tomorrow