so hello and i some of you uh probably miss the
meadow the hillside and spirit rock where i was this last few days and i miss it as well
and i would love to do this
broadcasting and meditation and teaching in the natural world and
i haven't figured out how i can do it with the urban life that i live here
and um but this is uh it was a nice taste for those three days
so um
there's a whole class of mental states and mental
practices in buddhism that fit underneath the
is in the family of tranquility peace tranquility calm
subtleness stability all kinds of things where things get
still stillness quiet peaceful that come along with a deep sense of
reassurance and confidence and trust and
sense of at-homeness the famous story of the buddha touching
the earth and i think today is
john muir's birthday but touching the earth
and and you know to feel our
belonging here that's so intimate that isn't that we ever don't belong we're
just we are part of the earth and um
the um so the subtleness has come in this process of uh
of the factors of awakening there is at some point there's joy
and a very important movement is how joy is a bridge
to happiness where happiness is more more
simpler more refined more embodied more
associated with a very deep contentment whereas joy has more to do is more
associated with the bubble bubbling and excitement of something
and so in this process of the satyabatana the process of
seven factors awakening we're going through uh this phase of um
of tranquil of tranquility of relaxing and uh calming
uh our whole system but in particular uh the texts talk about calming the body
so i'll do i will do a i'll do offer a guided meditation
through the first five
factors of awakening and coming to tranquility and and that kind
of happiness maybe and if you don't follow don't worry about it
maybe imagine use your imagination to participate as if
you can feel or imagine these things and then someday you might
recognize them
so assuming a upright alert posture
and even though later there will be a process of relaxing
relaxing can begin right at the beginning
and to take a few deep breaths
on the exhale let your body settle in to the spot in which you're sitting
taking a deep breath and relaxing releasing the
whole body as if there's a big ah
as you exhale here now
and then let your breathing return to normal
and part of the function of relaxing at the beginning is to
awaken a certain kind of
healthy awareness in your body
healthy sensitivity that works best when the body is relaxed
and so to relax and feel if there's a shift in
sensitivity sense of awareness
in the parts of the body that you relax
so the exhale softening the muscles of the face
and as they soften different sensations are there than if
this face is tense and different receptivity
as you exhale softening relaxing
the shoulders
and feeling with whatever softening relaxing releasing of the shoulders you can have
if there's now a little bit more awareness in your shoulders
more ability to sense and feel in a certain way
perhaps on the exhale you can soften the chest
and awaken a certain kind of attentiveness awareness
sensitivity to certain kinds of feelings that come with the relaxation
and then the same thing with the belly relaxing
softening
and even if the relaxation brings
sensations that are not so comfortable maybe
appreciate the heightened sensitivity
and then using the same process in the mind
as you exhale relaxing the mind the thinking
energy
and if you're thinking quiet and the mind
settles a bit
is there some kind of shift in how the sensitivity the awareness of the
mind is present for you
and then now for a little while connecting to your breathing
maybe relaxing on the exhale
and with whatever heightened sensitivity that that relaxation provides
receive the sensations of breathing in
breathing in and breathing out
on the exhale letting go of your thoughts
as if your thoughts can drift away
and with whatever degree of calm you have
let your awareness be sensitive to
the contrast of any tension that your whole body mind system might
have and almost like there's a conversation between the calm and the tension
the subtleness and the agitation
and to whatever degree you can choose the part the calm
way of going choose being quiet and peaceful
non-reactive
instead of letting your mind choose agitated thoughts or
stress tension follow the trail
of peace relaxation
and if you can see the difference between being caught in thoughts and not caught
between following a path of stress and agitation
versus following a path of calm instability peace
you see that difference
that can be a source of joy
of delight that you just see the possibility of
following a trail towards peace
the joy that you know an alternative
to being stressed or preoccupied caught up
and while it's not always easy to follow the alternative path of peace
it's a inspiration to know it exists that you can see the difference
and if you do feel some inspiration some joy
at this difference maybe allow yourself to have a little
quarter smile with the corners of your lips
move up a little bit to share in the delight and the joy
of having this practice to practice
and then see if you can know relax your body even more
as if before you're relaxing the surface parts now something deeper
deeper in the face relaxing and softening
deeper in the shoulders
deeper in the chest
he deep in the belly
the relaxing of the whole body that is also letting go
into a kind of contentment
simply being here present connected
with a sensitivity that comes from being
relaxed
with each exhale
letting the body and mind become more tranquil
even if it's infinitesimal movements
we're in the inhale you're present for
any of the non-tranquil ways you are in the body
and mind however subtle
on the exhale you relax soften
let go into whatever piece that's here
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to feel or imagine
any degree of peace that's present for you
or with imagining remembering
a feeling of peace that you've had sometime in your life
deep tranquility
and imagine that your calm and your peacefulness
can be felt by others
that it is a gift that spreads from you into the world
and may it be that in known and unknown ways
your experience of peace
supports others to also know peace or to feel less anxious
may it be that our peace and our contact with peace and deep
tranquility is shared with the whole world
may it be that it spreads from us for the welfare and happiness of others
may we be a source of peace for this world
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings experience freedom
and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
so today i will
cover the tranquility factor of awakening and the
concentration factor of awakening so that um
six the fifth and sixth factors and these
factors of awakening the way that the instructions are in
that satipatana sutta it does not say evoke these
make them come forth or it says recognize when they're present
and then when they're present support them and maintain them
and uh and i think the reason why it says that is that this the seven factors awakening
are a byproduct of doing mindfulness practice and as the practice begins to have some
momentum it it brings forth within us
a clear and clear capacity for awareness so mindfulness practice
is bringing forth a an abiding a living in
a state of awareness a way of being aware that's
maybe very individual how different people recognize that they are aware some
people may be more with thought some people more with other perception perceptive
ways of being some people feel awareness is more like consciousness it's just a
broad feel the state of attention there's a heightened sensitivity
that comes naturally it's like whatever for you that is awareness that if you relax deeply
you can't turn it off uh in a relaxed quiet state that's not distracted in thoughts
the awareness will be there just uh no way not to have it
and so this natural state somewhat natural state becomes strong becomes pervasive
it's kind of like if someone um
you know it's like now it's gotten light outside so or light in this room if you i come
in here and it's dark i don't see anything and then slowly the light
the sun comes up and slowly gets more more light until finally
maybe you don't say it this way but the natural state of the room when the sun is up is to be able to is
to have light and be able to see it the whole room is then in awareness in a kind of effortless way
so the sun of awareness dawns and grows within us
until awareness becomes stronger and there's heightened clarity of what's happening in the present
moment and that heightened clarity lets us distinguish between
the trail that leads to suffering the trail leads to stress and reactivity and
the trail that leads to peace to wisdom to to
happiness and and to be able to see that distinction
then it can bring a lot of joy because then there's we know
where the path is we know the trail to take we know what trail to avoid
um and so it might not be easy to avoid the old habits
but at least we know there's a difference some people don't even know and then slowly we break the old habits
and we begin following a healthy way of being the trail to happiness into peace and
this brings a lot of joy into so very much associated with the joy of being
able to practice finally i have meditation and i know meditation is a good thing
and and the way i was living my life didn't work or there's there's no peace or no
freedom and the preoccupations being lost in my life meditation seems to be
a path of of happiness of following a trail
towards something that's really good i feel so much calmer and subtle when i meditate and it affects the rest of my
life most of my day so a certain delight and happiness can arise
of knowing this possibility to practice as we really start coursing in this
practice more and more there's a way in which that joy that the light gets stronger and stronger
and and it's almost as if it's the
it becomes not just an evaluative joy like oh i'm so glad i have this practice but there's a kind of a joy that comes
from being absorbed in the practice just just kind of coursing
cruising in the practice and it's almost like uh as an analogy are
given of petting the cat as we stay with the practice day with the practice the cat within us begins to
purr that kind of wonderful delight and joy comes up and that's uh
some people then describe surprised by this strong feeling of joy that wells up as they meditate
sometimes it can be somewhat intense and some people call it rapture or something
at some point the movement of this factors of awakening is that um
we're following the path of tranquility and so things calm down
the whole body mind system begins to calm and so the excitement the the enthusiasm
the inspiration of joy quiets down and the joy becomes kind of a happiness
that's more embodied that's more like a deep contentment a
sense of being cozy and connected in some soft embodied way
and um it's uh that hap and that happiness
is then the foundation for the sixth factor of awakening which is
concentration or samadhi and and uh
and this is important to realize because some people think that they're going to develop samadhi concentration by huffing
and puffing by straining and trying and and uh but rather the the dharmic way of
developing concentration is to have in place the conditions that support the mind
wanting to get settled wanting to become unified and absorbed and focused on something
and that's a mind that is in body that's tranquil and has a certain kind of happiness in
it and and that happiness is the foundation for deep concentration
and so we're just happy to be here there's not a question about being present here now because it's the better
alternative than wandering off in thoughts and thinking about our daily concerns or the past and the
present being connected here this body this mind this heart
feels so rich so satisfying that of course we want to
settle in of course we kind of then almost natural to settle in to relax to
give ourselves over to this process of meditation for example
and there's that happiness that comes with this factors this path to the factors of
awakening then you know
unifies brings together all the fragmented parts of ourselves so that
the unfragmented way of being is samadhi
and because they were absorbed we're all unified connected collected
and and then we have the the samadhi factor of awakening
so what's remarkable about this we've been doing this sati patana now for i know this is like the almost a 60th
maybe 60th talk on it that are given gone through all these exercises
and um and i've said this before but it's worth saying again i believe that we're we're
building on the momentum of having done the practice all along even if you go back to the very
beginning of it and just do the first exercise with the breathing it's powerful thing to do and if you do
it consistently it just keeps showing up and taking your meditation posture and
engaging over and over again there's a natural process
that can begin kind of opening up and moving through you
you move through that eventually can be recognized as being the factors of awakening
when practice is really strong and for me it's been mostly been on
retreat that i feel this the meditation retreats sometimes that the the predominant
experience of the present moment by far the predominant is the seven factors of awakening
and what a cool wonderful thing to do to not be anxious about
what's happening tomorrow or what happened yesterday or be angry with anything it just be really
peaceful and settled and all your all the the focus of the mind is on this
beautiful qualities of of uh mind and body the seven factors of awakening
and so this is natural process that unfolds but it requires practice practicing well
sincerely practicing subtlety
learning how to practice mindfulness how to bring attention how to recognize what's
happening learning how to relax deeply how to
get concentrated to some degree learning all this all this kind of the
path the world of meditation so that more and more you can trust that
there's this natural process that's emerging this unfolding that can happen
that we allow for if we feel like we're the agent responsible for everything that happens
in meditation we're actually shortchanging the process of meditation a lot of meditation is letting go of
thoughts enough being subtle enough that we can trust and open up and allow for
something to move through us and these seven factors awakening is one
way of discussing this so i did talk about tranquility being a
bridge between joy and happiness and which it is
and then i went from tranquility to concentration factor of awakening so where is the happiness
so there are other lists that go from joy tranquility happiness concentration
the same factor of awakening leaves the happiness out not because it doesn't happen on the process but for some
reason it doesn't need to be there or maybe or maybe the number seven was a special number they wanted
to so that shows the most important parts but um so it goes so
what we've done so far there's the awareness that's often called mindfulness
the ability to differentiate between what's healthy and
not healthy in our practice skillful and not skillful there is joy in being able to do that
there is no there's the energy the effort then to choose the healthy path there's a joy of
being able to do that then there's tranquility and then there's a concentration
so then tomorrow we'll do the last factor of awakening
which is equanimity and tomorrow also um
we'll do a quick q a question and response session after the
this youtube we'll do it on zoom and i'll post the zoom link
here on the chat but also post it on the imc calendar
for 7 45 well it says youtube community meeting
and and also on imc's what's new section both the calendar and the what's new are
found on the home page for imc and you can find the link there and there'll be a password required and the
password will be meta m-e-t-t-a and that'll be clear also
so thank you and i look forward to our time together