so good morning again
ah
how wonderful it is to be with you
my name is kodo
and we are on the second day
of five
on the topic of the five precepts
our practice with the five presets
Sila virtue restraint
[Music]
taking a moment again to appreciate the
all the comments that come through as I
can't see any of you this is my this is
my connection with you
see how you're doing
so in this uh development of our
discussion around the precepts
um yesterday I discussed some some of
the general principles of relating to
the precepts and I will continue to do
this throughout the week and then just
touch on
each of the five
five presets
um
of course in these short times we we
will only just be able to scratch the
surface with these so
I hope
that some further reflection unfolds for
you
to begin I would like to um
I'd like to note that today is the full
moon day
yeah full moon day so
um
[Music]
last night in San Francisco this bright
Moon behind just a
behaves of some collecting clouds
and I was reminded how auspicious it is
that we're discussing the precepts at
the full moon time uh you see because as
many of you know this is a this is a
very traditional time
to
in
practice to visit temples and to renew
your commitment to the precepts take the
precepts again and to
um
spend a day
committed to meticulous observation of
the precepts
and to meditation practice
sort of immersing oneself as best one
can in the Dharma
so I'm wondering about how that can make
its way through each of our days today
so as I discussed yesterday one of these
key principles with all of the precepts
in practicing with all the precepts is
that of non-harming
and it's it's definitely been said more
than once that one concise summary of
the path of practice
is
um
to grow ever and ever more skillful
in the path of non-harming
ever and ever more skillful in not
harming others and not harming ourselves
and I think this can provide a basic
orientation to how we relate to the five
presets
um
five presets again
or just these this is a reminder for
ourselves
and
I'll Circle back to the first one in a
moment right there just like this
for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept to abstain from
harming living beings
for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept
to abstain from taking what is not given
for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept
to abstain from sexual misconduct
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
false speech
for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept to abstain from
intoxicants that are a cause for
heathlessness
thing I thought we could do
is
um
you know with a few minutes that we have
to reflect a little bit on these first
and second precepts together
and I use the word reflect I'm actually
thinking of holding them in a kind of
contemplative way
with you
and to pause and really take them in
almost like a meditation object
and to move along phrase by phrase and
and see what it is that comes forward in
your
your heart of meditation and
contemplation as we move phrase by
phrase
so you may even want to jot down a note
or two or you may want to offer some
phrases to the the YouTube chat as they
as they come up
but to slowly and contemplatively
reflect
how does it resonate for you what does
it call forward
just to begin with the first
for the sake of our training together
what does that call forth
to me it puts me in contact with the
community
and all of a sudden I have these
memories of
um
various temples or training centers or
monasteries and I have the felt sense of
being with people
and that these presets
both support my development and freedom
and they support this connection
the community and safety
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept
that's evocative for me there's
something about effort involved in
undertaking there's a resolve or a
an intention
which is to say I'm making an effort
to conduct myself in in such and such a
way
I'm making this effort
it also that also touches on the fact
that the precepts are a practice
the
something about them as we we don't
complete the practice of the precepts by
making an effort once
we undertake them and then we undertake
them again
and we undertake them again
and as far as I understand it the the
purpose of these precepts is not to
solidify a self
for further solidify a self
through unwholesome forms of shame or
self-harm
but rather
one of the purposes one of the functions
of the precepts and practicing them is
to more and more free our hearts
so we can show up in skillful ways for
others
and in a sense consummate this path of
non-harming within ourselves
so for the sake of our training together
I undertake I make this effort
if I undertake the precept
thank you
to refrain from taking life
in some of the original
it's uh to refrain from harming
breathing beings
and I think that latter image to me is
just a bit more evocative
just a bit a bit more evocative to
refrain from harming breathing beings
because I sense into the effect that
that not abiding in this way not
conducting myself in this way would
cause harm
to someone who breathes
it's another breathing being
the freezing of not taking life also
is evocative it edges into the second
precept because it shares it shares the
word take
for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept not to take what
isn't given
and there's something right there in the
word take that's so clear so clearly
about
to me so clearly grasping
you can you can feel sense and to take
and how that's that's quite a different
physical mental
uh posture
from our practice of giving
the practice of open-handedness
and the virtues that that brings along
so
kind of slowly reflect and slowly
contemplate on these on these presets
particularly on the full moon day
um
as I mentioned yesterday one of the
closest analogs to the precepts in the
early literature is called the 10 whole
10 wholesome actions
you can find these in the the
numerical discourses the book of tens
for those of you you would like to read
along
laughs I came across something
interesting so
um
with the 10 wholesome actions
it uh the Buddha teaches them in
contrast to ten unwholesome actions and
you could well guess the first one would
be
um
taking to take life
is unwholesome and it goes through the
rest of the ten to refrain from taking
life to abandon taking life to give up
taking life
is wholesome
and he does something really interesting
and he presents this idea of their roots
of the wholesome
what's underneath
what's underneath the wholesome
and I was reminded when I came across
this teaching um you know some some
years ago I was living at tasahara
Monastery I was the gardener for some
time and
one of my fellow gardeners was inspired
to um
plant
something new so there's this lawn
across from the meditation hall there's
a one lane dirt drive that comes into
the monastery
and across that drive from from the
zendo is this little yard
a little yard that we call the moon lawn
um I'm not sure exactly why it got its
name but it was beautifully illuminated
whenever the moon was full
and my fellow Gardener was inspired to
um sort of dig up this uh disused area
and plant Something Beautiful
she wanted to plant a yarrow lawn
and yarrow when they're mature they have
these broad soft leaves
that when you rub them they're quite
fragrant and then these tall stems with
clusters of beautiful flowers
I thought yeah this is something
beautiful we can do
something beautiful we can do for that
would nourish us
and nourish
the other monks and the monastery the
other monastics and the monastery
this comes to mind for me this morning
as we're meditating and we're nourishing
what's beautiful in US
nourishing what's wholesome
foreign
[Music]
maybe in some way
as we're as we nourish what's beautiful
in US these these uh soft leaves can
come to sprout
these soft leaves can come unfurl in us
and ourselves and
something fragrant
can come forward
it's said in the dhamapada that the
scent of virtue the scent of Sila for us
the scent of the precepts
travels Against the Wind
even in the way that the scent of
lavender and rosemary Jasmine don't
travel Against the Wind
so may we have a
reflective contemplative
dharmic day
keeping ourselves safely on the path
in touch with these precepts on the
auspicious full moon day
and right now
for anyone who would like to stay just a
moment
I'm going to put a link so we can all
see the precepts together and then if
you'd like We Can chant them together
this may take a moment to load for you
so this is um this tends to be done in
column response so this can be our
closing
and we'll say
farewell
for the sake of our training together
they undertake the precept to abstain
from harming living beings
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
taking what is not given
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
sexual misconduct
for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept to abstain from
false speech
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
intoxicants that are a cause for
heedlessness
may you be well
may you be well served by the practice
of the presets
please take good care today
until tomorrow