so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be with you
so many different time zones of joining us in this moment in time
so so for today's practice i'd like to invite us to um to consider
this quote that i heard um earlier um and i don't know who's attributed to
actually i didn't get the chance to search but uh um here it is
comparison is the enemy of contentment
so it's such a profound statement and i want to unpack it a little bit
and and also maybe add some more to it
there's so many different ways that perhaps comparison shows up can show up
in our lives and um and
i just as i said that i just i remembered um gail has this um teaching
where where he comes with artificial flower or something holds it up and says
you know there's a flower and then um oh yes here's here's a similar one
that just came through um theodore roosevelt comparison is the enemy of joy
i like that too that's a good one comparison is the enemy of joy yeah joy
and contentment both so i'll talk about both how's that this is great thanks for sending that to me uh steve great
so so gail has this teaching where he shows up with an um
or the flower sometimes and and uh and the sense of oh yeah the flower the
flower is perfect in and of itself the flower is perfect enough itself and then
brings up another one like a taller one or you know and then a shorter one then then there's a sense of like the mind
wants to compare or this is bigger smaller not good enough whereas in and of itself it's perfectness of itself
given the causes and conditions of of this flower so so
comparison can show up in different ways sometimes we compare experiences like oh this
soup i'm having right now no the soup this this restaurant you know this route i'm having at this restaurant this other
soup was better and you're always seeking in your mind the perfect soup the best tasting soup so you're never
satisfied because oh yeah the one that you had which actually you're misremembering the taste of it maybe
you're remembering to be better than it actually was because i don't know you were hungry or you were with the i don't
know with the group of friends so the soup tasted really good but that's what's the best
soup this just not good enough the one i'm having right now or at the restaurant or making
it at home like oh it's just like not good enough not good enough so there's a sense of depletion there's a
sense of lack of contentment or lack of joy lack of appreciation instead of
appreciating what is appreciating what is here what is right now all the
possibilities in this soup in this moment in this amazing
soup that this is showing up just as it is um and sometimes that soup is us
in terms of comparison we compare ourselves oh that other person who is
i don't know taller and more famous or more successful or has more friends or more
likes on facebook i don't know just i'm being silly but but use your own uh imagination you know has published
more or written more i don't know is more this xx
comparing ourselves to some other hypothetical person so some other person
whereas um each and one of each one of us
has um unique occasions and unique opportunities
unique obstacles unique challenges i mean buddhism unique causes and conditions we
all have unique causes and conditions so to say oh
well i wasn't born as this other person i mean they are who they are and i am what i am so how can i
how can i be inspired so instead of comparison i want to
bring in the concept of inspiration how can i be inspired
to be the most ethical most kind most giving
person i can be to to fulfill my potential and to remember that life
isn't about getting we think it's about getting life really is it isn't about getting
it's about giving it's about giving to others our life
the best way we can live and satisfy to to the best way we can um
fulfill our potential is to become a gift it become a gift
not just to ourselves but to become a gift unto the world so let that be
your measure of of contentment measure of joy or measure
of aspiration is what i want to bring in tonight so comparison is the enemy of joy as
theodore roosevelt roosevelt said or as i misremembered it comparison is
the enemy of contentment and again so many different dimensions of this both in our experiences and also
with with things with events with friends with just experiences in life if we're
comparing always and the other dimension is whether we're comparing ourselves this person who is me to some idealized
version the wrong way of really framing it
if we are bringing comparison maybe it's a way of aspiration oh how can i be how can i be the the best
the kindest i don't know just the sense of values really thinking of the values
not in the way of again getting but giving so that's the frame
i want to set up tonight for our practice and um
with the guided meditation um as always we'll start by setting
settling in the body with the breath and then i'll bring some invitations
some invitations and settling in the moment and just a set of can settle
settling into contentment and joy in the present moment um some gentle invitations so that's the
plan for tonight all right let's let's sit together friends
so so arriving arriving in our seat
arriving here in this moment in time
in this moment that has never been and will never be like this experienced
through this mind through this heart of ours unique mind and heart
ah landing landing embracing as if we're opening our arms wide
wide wide opening the arms of our hearts wide wide
wide
to embrace fully embrace the world as it shows up right now in this body in
this moment this justice
not comparing just relishing even if there is discomfort
present and the body or mind can we
open up to this evanescent
impermanent
moment in time
and then letting the body relax letting the body land
knees release here
releasing thoughts that arise it's okay thoughts will arise
smilingly releasing them in this moment just returning [Music]
to the awareness of the breath the body this moment in time expansively
letting the body feet to feel
to appreciate being connected to the ground to the earth
just this breath not comparing this breath to the previous one
or vying for the next one just this breath this perfection of this breath right here
this moment fresh amazing miraculous never left before
such an odd to even have awareness to be alive
so amazing just to be alive have consciousness
of this breath these sensations
uh
do just this breath the amazing miracle of
this breath in this moment the entirety of the breath
breathed in breathed out
the miracle of this breath reverberating through the whole body
softening relaxing very outbreath every in-breath
enlightening enlivening enlivening
bringing more energy and more lightness
now is it possible as we're sitting being breathed
to open up the gentle appreciation gentle appreciation
for whatever is arising in the sphere of experience right now
most prominently the breath sensations
of the body
sense of aliveness
maybe any pleasantness in the body
maybe there's pleasantness associated with the breath being breathed
gently swaying
maybe the mind realizes wow this moment is actually pretty good
maybe there's more contentment available in this moment more joy than i realized
if i just open up ever so gently not pushing
just opening up to the possibility appreciating
the joys the delights pleasantness
comforts even if coexisting with discomfort
there's an overall spaciousness that's here
the mind here not in the past or future just here
just gently enjoying the breath
and if there's a part of your mind your heart
that's negating that's fighting against this moment it's okay include that part
include that part don't throw it away shut it out exile it that part is
included also if there is any no part left out
no part left out
and as we expand opening up to appreciation in this moment whatever is arising
pleasant or unpleasant included appreciating it just as it is
can we open up also
expanding from this moment in time
expanding temporarily
not with our thoughts not thinking but the possibility of all the causes and
conditions that have brought us to this moment
in our lives so many of them gifts
good fortune we consider
in our earthly terms some of them challenges
all of which uniquely all these occasions so many that perhaps are neutral just
the zeitgeist we're born in paris upbringing culture
random coincidences just all these causes and conditions so
many events that have made this a unique being that
is me possible in this moment
product of so many causes and conditions
not independent of them how unlikely how
unlikely was it is it that we're even born
that this being was us should even be here
we appreciate the
mystery the intertwined the inter-being
interconnected mystery of our existence
and let there not be a comparison with other amazing mysteries of existence as
other beings with their causes and conditions
appreciating them wow all these miracles all these points of light
and this is mine this light this line of mine
how can i be the brightest i can be
not comparing to others but aspiring [Music] to shine brightly for the sake of myself
and the sake of others to give to give my light
my warmth my goodness
and this brief flash of lightning that is
my life and the cosmic scale
to aspire aspire not compare but aspire
to shine brightly according to whatever [Music] my values
the goodness of my values my north star is
let that be the measure
of the brightness of my light my goodness
shining in the world
just being embodied not thinking just being embodied letting yourself be
breathed letting these reflections be breathed in
and out without so much thought but dropped into the body
resonating
maybe only a residue remains just being breathed
the buddha said be a light unto yourself
can we be a light can we be a light unto ourselves and others
making measure of giving
making giving the measure of our success not getting
shining our light shining our light of goodness
maybe meta gladness good will for others
generosity
kindness
compassion
gladness joy letting our joy shine brightly
for the sake of ourselves and the world what a beautiful gift to give to
ourselves and others our joy
our contentment
and for the last moments of this practice period
honoring appreciating ourselves for having showed up
if any judgments are arising for what happened or did not happen
can we be kind can we be generous to ourselves or having done our best
given all the causes and conditions it's like this it had to be like this
or it would have been different appreciating ourselves
and the gift of causes and conditions for being here now together practicing
in sangha and offering the light of our goodness
to all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere including
ourselves be safe be happy
have health and ease may all beings
be free
thank you everyone thank you for your practice [Music]
so we have some time for any reflections that might have come up any questions
comments aha moments complaints it's all welcome
what did you notice this this practice tonight and around the
theme of comparison is the enemy of joy slash contentment
both internally and externally radha please
hi hi um so i'm outside and i was um
there's a lot of wildlife where i am um there's a lot of bad life
um and i was kind of feeling into um like i could hear the bees and the birds
and um yeah just kind of feeling how like
they each have their own kind of unique song and call when they don't
you know it's like the bee knows what it needs to do it knows what its work is and it doesn't
you know i saw a meme once where that was like um it was like a bunch of animals and it
was like you know an elephant doesn't try to be a dolphin or something like that
um yeah so like there's kind of the sense of relief that
comes with that kind of self-acceptance is what i was
feeling lovely beautiful thank you so much for sharing that it's it's oh it
touches me so deeply your experience and and the metaphors that have come to you
why did you say an elephant doesn't try to be a i forget the animal's ears but one animal doesn't try to be another an
elephant doesn't try to be a bird it's just that radical self-acceptance absolutely and
appreciating the the bird you are or the frog you are or
whatever lovely or the puppy you just it's so that the radical sex self-acceptance of yeah beautiful thank
you radha lovely lovely thank you lovely yeah claire
please thank you
i think they're two things claire there's a lot of noise in the background
that's strange um
i'm not hearing it because i've got a headset on maybe if i if i take the headset off does that help
yeah there's a lot of echo
[Laughter]
i haven't loved uh like a lot of church music
are you hearing something another voice yeah i don't have anything else going on here
so [Music]
okay all right thanks claire yeah so any other reflections any other
before we go to groups and practice together
you can also type in chat if you type only to me i won't read your name so it
will be private just read your reflection if you type it to everyone i'll read your name and your reflection
yeah such beautiful reflection so far love that
yeah beautiful here's another one after a particularly mindless incident
yesterday mortifying and very upsetting the idea that given causes and conditions it
could not have been otherwise is soothing it's difficult to accept such a self if
one doesn't feel deserving of it but i'm working on that as well yeah
thank you for that reflection yeah yeah
yeah so many causes and conditions and it's such a combination right we
it's um and this is the i think the beauty of of
this the dependent origination which is one way to see the causes and conditions
actually causing conditions is is the superset of dependent origination teaching
which is so many cause and conditions coming together giving rise
um and and accepting that if things could have been different they would have been just brings freedom and of course one of
those and then usually actually people ask at this time well well so how about volition well yes volition is one of
those causes and conditions that we put in place and we make it more likely that
we behave more mindfully or more kindly you know
it's all of those are set into place it's not like everything is on on our shoulders i will behave this way it's
all causes and conditions another reflection may we all have
people in our lives to acknowledge and celebrate our special gifts and skills along with us yes may it be so
so i'd like to invite us now to turn to practice together and and
started to give more invitation more instructions as to how to be in small groups as people have said
it brings more of a sense of safety so so let me just say a couple of words
about groups before i set them up so so you'll be in about in groups of
roughly size three depending on where the chips fall could be two to four and the invitation is
that what you have practiced now silently with your eyes closed
here are these wayfarers like you these travelers now you get to
connect if you wish it's a very sacred beautiful opportunity to connect it's
not just oh go talk amongst yourselves peoples oh yes honoring honoring
yourself honoring each other just for a few minutes and sharing as little or as much as you
wish about your practice and holding witness that's a big part of it it's about giving it's not about impressing
not about educating it's about offering if you wish um what has come up for you
as to support you and others as a gift and to hold present to hold presents
for them also witness them see their beauty just as one reflections that see
their special gifts special cause and conditions to see that so this is really the opportunity
of the groups and please speak from your own experience not comment or manage or
other people's experience asking questions
but yeah and not serving as a facilitator either just staying with your own
experience and honoring others maybe they offer their silence maybe that's what they need to offer
tonight and that's okay too and um you can start with alphabetically if
you wish um and uh maybe we'll do spiral so each
person will say in nugget instead of doing a long monologue which is sometimes we do just share one nugget
one thought of what came up if you have like five nuggets just share one the other person next person in the alphabet
first name will share another nugget if they wish or they say pass and then the next person and they will come to you
i'm just gonna go around a few times this way just call creating going around
to see what happens so so i will create the breakout rooms
now with um here we go
okay so in aim here we go okay i'm going to open them take care of yourselves
and each other in kindness okay welcome back everyone
uh the rooms are closed everybody's back we've got just a couple of minutes for any
reflections like see two hands just shut up okay richard what's up
i i understand what you say by comparison and sense of like i used to
be better or other people have more than me that kind of thing but there's also the kind of reframing
of there are a lot people have a lot of people have it a lot worse than me
and and uh or there are a lot of people in my both right now which is a really
powerful there's a lot of people in my what right now in my boat i mean who who share the
same whatever that service is you know that really sort of like depersonalizes things right right
yeah yeah so so your question is what about that yeah yeah
so it really depends it depends how the spirit in which that is taken because sometimes if we just get
into the um comparison game it if you go like oh gosh
like wow lucky me i'm not i'm not them right
sometimes it can be pity sometimes it can be like not very helpful you just
just don't go there but what you're saying is slightly different the sense of common humanity oh it's kind of
opening the heart so i'm not quite sure if that's comparison it's just a little bit of appreciating
the challenges that other people have so maybe that's how i would put it a little bit
yeah thanks richard excellent question neil please
so how do you like enjoy physical pain right which yeah
right i mean you know be grateful for the current moment if it is dominated by physical pain yeah yeah yeah yeah
that's a very good question so i think the crux of it is this it's the
domin dominated or perceiving it to be dominated i think
pain can sometimes limit our minds and having had plenty of pain can limit our mind to think that that's
the only thing there is that the experience is dominated by pain so what i'm inviting you and i
was inviting you gently um to open up to and a little bit here
this again this meditation isn't quite focused on it primarily but that there is so much more present the pain can be
here also but there could be so much more presence so appreciating the panoply of
everything there is so that's what i'm going to invite you when there is pain present in the body back pain like
intense pain see if there's more there's more spaciousness around it that can hold it
all so that the mind doesn't get tight around just just that that's my invitation for you to explore neil
thank you thank you and this is our last oh i think we're out of time okay quick
if you can make this quick
just just curious about how to work things out with comparison
lines because i think that i i'm just like so many comparison mind
about instead of appreciating the process where i am at my in this time
and i'm just comparing the other person oh he will be here and here and here it just
makes me suffer yeah so i so it's good that you see that comparison is making you suffer and your
the question is like how do i work with it i think part of what i've shared all evening or if not all any but this hour
is about ways to just not not go there bring the mind back bring the mind back
and if your mind is really used to comparison getting into that game it's going to be like mindfulness like come
back sweetie come back mind just don't go there sweetie consider the perspective cause of condition so it
just has to be reoriented reoriented reoriented until it becomes the the proclivity of your mind so not even
in the meditation just in real life in real life exactly but yeah exactly
yeah okay yeah thank you thank you thank you so dear all thank you so much for your
practice for cultivating your heart your mind for your own sake and the sake of
all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music] thank you
and now