morning everyone happy to see you
or not see you happy to be here
just want to check in and see can you hear me
good morning IMC community
hi
fantastic it's lovely to see greetings coming in from
different parts of the country probably different parts of the world any minute here
nice to see some familiar faces and promote your names that I'm imagining to
be faces so for those of you who don't know me my
name is Dawn Neil and I'm really happy to be here covering for Gill this week he'll be back next week
warm greetings to all of you it's a delight to be here from Redwood
City California and really lovely to see so many
regulars greeting each other
San Jose and Bellingham Washington Sausalito Mountain View Scotland
Nevada City San Francisco
so um just gonna give it a moment or two before we get started
and um just name how much I appreciate the
dedication the regularity of this Sangha it's really quite something
going for a couple of years now
so thank you all everyone who gave me a sound check that's great
and um let's see we'll get started here all
these greetings
it makes me so happy to see people greeting each other many of you have gotten to know each
other over these couple years right and all over the world
so this morning the topic is
um in the week the topic is these series of steps or bases
roads sometimes that the Buddha talked about many times in the ancient
discourses that are supports for our meditation
progress prowess success and for a kind of a spiritual power
and [Music] um there are a couple of these that appear
in many different lists or appear multiple times in this
list the idipata and they are um
sense of immersion in practice and a sense of Engagement with meditation
so the invitation is to sit back find a
comfortable meditation posture and um
balance relaxation and alertness
I'm going to start with an image a couple of images
maybe close your eyes if that feels right and
imagine being in a vast field very relaxed
and as you're in this field a very soft
comfortable warm rain almost like a mist starts to come down
soaking the ground maybe some
hitting a roof above you or maybe you enjoy the sensations of it on your skin
but either way there's a sense of being soaked saturated
settled
as you look across the field any dust or Haze that was there has been
washed away there's clarity
and in this way the invitation is to set a kind intention
an intention that your body your heart your mind
be saturated with filled immersed with awareness in the moment
and to support that it's helpful to relax often
perhaps softening your eyes behind your eyelids
foreign
your face and forehead
and even imagining rule of relaxation behind the eyes
spreading spreading through your whole body
allowing your neck shoulders torso to soften
your weight to be fully supported deeply supported on whatever surface
you're sitting on or lying held
save
noticing the weight of your body where it contacts the floor
perhaps the hip points the buttocks feet
rooted rooted Here and Now
and then a tuning attuning to a sense of this whole body
noticing the contact of air or cough on skin
all the sensations of aliveness vibrancy
allowing a sense of being immersed In This Moment
and then tuning in to the deeper Sensations in the body
movement we'll see
tingling perhaps warmth of the body's core
and especially tuning in to the sensations
of this body breathing
settling
resting the attention wherever the breath feels most
pleasurable compelling
perhaps the movement of the belly diaphragm
gentle wave-like up and down
perhaps the expansion and relaxation of the ribcage or chest
or the refined Sensations of the breath of the nostrils
tip of the nose or top of the lip
noticing the distinct qualities
of breathing in breathing out
noticing the difference between the sensations
but the fullness the top of the in-breath
and how they shift in the Letting Go the relaxation of the
out breath
noticing too if it feels natural
the whole body of the breath in the very beginning to the very end
inviting awareness of all the little Sensations
aliveness through this whole body
of transpiration the whole body breathing
foreign
from time to time checking in
refreshing the awareness of the moment
acknowledging any mental processes kindly
noticing appreciating foreign
sensation of aliveness in the moment
in this body this breath
softening in to the moment
and from time to time checking in
what's this moment like
foreign
from time to time rededicating yourself
to close devoted attention to the sensations of this body
the arisings of this moment
allowing decent some connection
pleasure to be there
and allowing being with anything else
that's there with kindness
foreign
and as we approach the last moments of this meditation
invitation is to gather gather the attention the energy
in the mind and the Heart around the heart
perhaps even breathing as if you could breathe directly in and out of the heart
Gathering any goodness any sense of peace
sincerity from this meditation
and soaking in that for a minute breathing with it
and then as you open your mind to your inner eye
out to the other people creatures beings in your life
that you cross paths with
dedicating some part of this goodness
to them
May those in our lives benefit from this practice
breathing this beautiful intention outwards
May others in our lives be happy
May others be safe may they be peaceful
and may they be free May others be safe may this practice be
occasion for that freedom may they be peaceful
and may they be free foreign
[Music]
May others be safe may this practice be occasion for that freedom may they be
peaceful [Music] and may they be free
thank you for your prayers others be safe may this practice the occasion of
that freedom may they be peaceful [Music]
may they be free thank you very much others be safe may
this practice the occasion for that freedom may they be peaceful
[Music]
sorry about that time so I didn't realize I could ring an actual Bell I couldn't ring an actual Bell
so the sound should have stopped looping by now
I'm diving at a moment
[Music]
thank you so
thank you all for the dedication of your practice the sincerity of your practice and for the technical troubleshooting
I did not realize I was going to be experimenting with sound effects in this meditation
so the topic you'd like to talk about for the next few minutes is um
relationship between immersion and engagement
and just a quick overview this is part of the theme of the week
which is a series of bases or steps that the Buddha taught that were particularly
supportive for him before he was awakened and they are
wholesome desire energy or effort
investigation and quality of mind
and these bases these steps are sometimes called the roads to spiritual power
or the um bases for Spiritual power
bases for meditative success those are all valid translations
I hadn't paid a whole lot of attention to them over the years because of one of the translations that appears which is
the um bases for psychic power
and so I found that title a little off-putting and uninteresting but um
I'm seeing the list again recently I was struck how helpful for my own practice each of
these qualities were so these four or sometimes five faces
steps um
are conditioned for deepening practice for improving the efficacy of practice
and they can be kind of considered in tongue-in-cheek modern Parliament
superpowers for meditation when the Buddha's teachings include them
as psychic powers it's just important to notice the cultural context
to be aware of it spiritual power psychic power was a
currency for a lot of the ancient teachers in India as um in that very old
culture and it was kind of part of what was talked about it was very subjective kind of way of seeing the world and
understanding the world based on experience in the mind and um
the Buddha does bring them in but the only
power he recommends over and over again and is the power of insight
the power to free the heart permanently from greed hatred and delusion
and it's almost like rhetorically as a teacher he's setting up how important that is by naming all of
these other capabilities so we can supposedly books developed in those
times as serious meditators the Buddha also discouraged his
followers from cultivating these other powers
and really focused in on insight and he went as far as to say that in
cultivating all of these attributes in the meditation a practitioner could expect full
Awakening in this lifetime or something very close so
each of these faces I'm going to call them is a bit of like a tripod stool
and each has three attributes the immersion and the practice or samadhi which is cultivated through a
wholehearted kind of Engagement a word in poly that's padhana
and then one of four things desire
energy or effort quality of mind or investigation investigation In This
Moment and these qualities all of them unfold a lot more fruitfully in a Marine
field relaxed content field
of contentment in the practice itself contentment just be immersed engaged
fully in the moment so an image will focus on these two legs
of the stool that are there in every base the immersion and the engagement
and imagine a Potter an artisan at a potter's wheel
and that their wheel is spinning looping the theme for today
we The Potter's Wheel is spinning the pot is spinning and their hands are gently on the pot shaping it
they're very engaged with the act of shaping that pot right
and they're also immersed in settled and concentrated on the process
so that's a little bit like the trade-off between the symbiosis between
the reciprocity between engagement and relaxation relaxation into this
immersion of samadhi wholehearted engagement
can be it can be helpful to understand it in terms of its opposite which for me
is boredom or disinterest a sense of kind of a separation from the process
and engagement is supported instead by
getting interested getting interested in the details of the process
the materials of the moment and how they weave together to create now
it's kind of by play in a way whether it's playing a sport or playing with
kids and it's an engagement that yes there's
maybe an outcome in the back of your mind but it's not outcome focused
its engagement play for its own sake
so for me one of the most powerful lessons in this in my life was in many
many figure drawing sessions I went to back when I was more focused on being a visual artist
and a couple of times a week we would go to the studio and a group of us would get together and draw
and in a way we're kind of doing the same thing every week
just like we're doing the same thing with meditation every week but there's this engagement in the difference of the
materials how they worked together noticing different facets of what could
be seen and finding each day each drawing each meditation
a different way in a different way to connect the process be fresh with it embodied
with it each of you probably has an example of
this in your own life something that continually
I is rewarded by finding new details in it
skillful samadhi immersion is a softening into
softening into this kind of collectedness born out of the contentment of being engaged in the
process itself and earlier in the process it can be
a very active kind of Engagement and later in the process as a sense of
flow takes hold chicks and Molly's flow concept takes
hold then there's it has its own momentum and then the engagement is more
relaxed settled back right
skillful samadhi has qualities of calm and relaxation just woven right into it
it's not a bearing down or squinting a huffing and puffing instead it can be like that soft rain
softening field or a desert quiet can be softening
that very clay that ends up on the potter's wheel
and that is kind of a good simile we are the clay
and we are also the Artisan shaping our own mind
there's a malleability and a reciprocity that happened because
these two qualities continue to support each other
so when brought together with the other
four qualities we'll talk about this week Dharma desire or wholesome desire
energy balanced effort quality of mind and heart and thought
and investigation these can become really powerful ways to cultivate both
of these foundational meditation qualities so look forward to covering that with
many of you in the coming days and tomorrow we will talk about desire
dharmic desire and falling in love with the practice
look forward to being back with you then thank you for the sincerity of your
practice and for being here