hello everyone welcome
so entering into your body
with your awareness and assuming a meditation posture
a posture for being alert and present a posture that
affirms that you are here now
and to gently close closing your eyes
and again affirming that you're here present
taking a few long slow deep breaths
maybe on the long inhale the feeling of fullness that comes in
the torso as you breathe in take it as an affirmation that you are
here nowhere else and in the long exhale
releasing into here just here now
letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale relaxing your body
heats relaxation embodied
affirmation that you are here
here in this body at this time
on the exhale softening in the face
relaxing any intenseness forward looking and
that's carried in the face the eyes settle back in their sockets
on the exhale softening in the shoulders
to the degree to which the shoulders can relax
it's an affirmation of their trusting relaxed ability
to trust the moment not tense against it
on the exhale softening in the heart relaxing and trusting
a subtleness
the relaxation in the heart
and softening in the belly
and relaxing anywhere else where you might be holding tight or stiff
the arms and the fingers
in your hip joint and down your legs
uh
perhaps relaxing softening in the spine
then settling into the body's experience of breathing
maybe letting the inhale be a kind of gentle
affirmation of being here
and the exhale to be relaxed letting go
into here just here
here is where awareness can be established
and can blossom
blossoming of open relaxed awareness
supported by breathing in and breathing out
with your whole body affirming that you are here
feeling the weight of your body maybe against your seat
the substantiality of your body
clearly recognize and affirming you are here nowhere else
and within this here this affirmed presence
breathing
as the primary physical activity
that's occurring as you sit quietly
so
whatever is happening for you that's present moment happening
is a thing to accept in direct experience
and in accepting it to affirm that you are simply here
here simply aware
but maybe not troubled just aware
breathing with what is
and as we come to the end of the sitting perhaps to recognize
that when we are at odds with what is in our direct experience
if we're tensing against it judging it
we have less affirmed presence
less fullness of being to offer the world
to affirm oneself being here in the present moment
as if you have a right to be here means there's more of you here
to be friendly to have good will to be generous
or to simply listen better to others to offer your presence
may it be that as we practice
mindfulness
it gives us the ability to be more present for others
more caring for this world
may it be that this practice that we do this large community at the seven a.m
sitting that we collectively
aspire to contribute to the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
often in the teachings of the buddha
he lists our experience in terms of body speech
and mind or our activities as being activities of body activities
of speech and activities of mind and it's usually [Music]
the body which is activities which are you mentioned first in this uh these kinds of lists
and part of the reason for that is the physical like physical activities we do walking talking
eating is not only the most obvious to notice there's can be seen by other people we
can they're you know they're much more obvious than uh sometimes then we are aware of our
speech and certainly uh can be more obvious than how we're aware of our mind and
mental activities and in being more aware of them we also have more choice more ability to
do something about our activities than maybe our speech sometimes and also especially our minds
that seems sometimes to be an automatic pilot and so
uh the training in buddhism begins classically with
attending to our actions and because that's where it's easiest in a
sense to bring mindfulness to and to see clearly and it's the easiest to have some choice
about what we do within our actions so um here in this this discourse we're
going through the teachings of the buddha and the four foundations for awareness
the first foundation is the body and in the beginning of the body
exercises has to do with activities so the first one breathing
is um a physical activity when we sit still it's the you know the usually the largest
activity biggest activity of the body and then with experiencing this the
breathing uh experiencing the whole body just taking in the body in whatever way it comes
and then relaxing it calming this body and so this body we might not be able to
calm our mind but we might be able to calm relax this body to some degree it's
more accessible sometimes and then and then we're aware of our postures
that we're in and then this third exercise is aware of the activities that we're doing
and uh these are activities that are mostly most of most of them are you know
activities that involve the whole body and much of the body and we can observe we can watch we can train
ourselves to be attentive to these activities we do setting the ground setting uh
warming up the mind strengthening the mind so at some point it can be aware of
something which is much more fickle much more slippery
and that is the mind itself and um
so in a sense mindfulness activity is preparing the ground for a fuller experience of mindfulness
but mindfulness of the activities physical activities that we do has another very important role
and that is that our activities are a mirror for what's happening for us
mere to see ourselves better and this idea of our activities being a mirror
that goes back to the buddha's teachings to his own son when the son was relatively young and
encouraged him to use his activities of body speech and mind as a mirror to understand himself
but he offered particular criteria of what to see in this mirror and
part of the what we want to see is whether what we're doing is causing harm to oneself or to others
to really see that this ethical component of mindfulness is really important and we want to see whether what we're
doing is wholesome or not wholesome whether it's nourishing whether it brings a
sense of goodness and warmth or nourishment to ourselves or it does the opposite
and then also we want to know if it also brings suffering or whether it brings happiness
and so these kind of reflections of what's the impact what's the result
of the activities we're doing is part of the the role of seeing activities as mirror
mirrors so it's not simply being aware of the activity in and of itself
which can be quite delicious just to be there fully for it but as
we kind of develop this capacity from mindfulness it's also taking in the impact the
influence the effect of these activities we have and so when the buddha talks about full
awareness of activities this kind of using activities as a
mirror is important and then as it's a mirror we see what we have choice about
so if we're hurrying to do something and we see is this nourishing us or not
then we see actually we're not being nourished we're not taking in the full experience and being present in a way that um
offers some deep support for our being
and but rather we're kind of draining ourselves or shortchanging ourselves
and this can be for example with eating food to take your time to eat food to take in
not only the food the food properly but to enjoy it to take in the nourishment
of it to feel and sense the goodness of caring and maybe someone is cooked for you and
and what it's like for the body to process that food and to take it in
yesterday i had this delicious soup for lunch that i was hungry
and it just felt so wonderful to take it in just feel it feel it kind
of it felt like it was like almost like medicine for my myself and just felt good to be there present for it as
opposed to you know reading emails while i'm eating for and
and not really taking it in so this ability to then make a choice i'm not going to do emails i'm going to
be there with a soup and just be with that rushing
rushing anywhere you know if you're driving your car you're rushing
is that the way it be nourished is that the way to be benefited to feel somehow the growth of attention and kind
of a feeling good about being in your own skin probably not probably rushing takes you
out of your skin or disconnects you to some way so to use uh
the activities as a mirror of something deeper and important for us
as we go through life sometimes in the teachings of mindfulness
the emphasis seems to be so much on certain schools of mindfulness on just being present for things as they are to
just feel the immediacy of it and and then there's no emphasis on taking
in the bigger picture the impact the influence it has on us as we take in this bigger impact then we
can make choices about what to do and what not to do learning to do this with our physical
activities is also preparing the ground for later when we do it for speech
later we start doing it for more importantly for the mind the mind is really the origin the source
for our physical activities our speech activities
and so to get a sense and feeling for what it's like to shift gears to move into a wholesome
direction to move away from that which debilitates us or
drains us in the mental activities as well that's coming it's much more difficult
but to learn to do that in terms of physical activities prepares the ground gives us a sense of how to do
it and if we do it in a relaxed way and but it builds and becomes stronger over
time it's like we're developing a muscle and that muscle at the right time can be
applied to the mind but if we live a mindless
mindlessly in activities of our life then we're not developing that capacity
that's going to be eventually in buddhism directed to the mind itself and mental activities
and uh what we'll see as we get into this is the mental activities are quite um
um you know get more and more subtle what we see but the subtlety of it
is not inconsequential that's where there comes from the core operating principles are for our lives
and so to be able to touch into those and be able to use them as a mirror and have some
choice about them what to let go of and what to encourage is a very important part of this
practice so the message for today is that um in training
mindfulness developing awareness and physical activities it's phenomenally important for
uh what we're gonna do you know as this mindfulness practice develops and goes on and you can you can try this in your
daily life is be present for the activities you do but uh not just not just the activity in
and of itself but being present as a mirror so you can in the fuller picture you're
opening up more and fuller picture you see uh what impact does this activity have or what is impact does the
way you do the activity have on yourself is it uh healthy for you is it wholesome is it
beneficial the way you do it and if not can you find a way to do it
that feels good and kind of to repeat what i said a few
days ago one of the guidelines for what is
maybe wholesome and beneficial is that which is beautiful
to live in beauty to act in beauty to to uh see how to be in the world
with beautiful activities and um how would you walk down the sidewalk in a way that
not for other people but for yourself it was beautiful or how would you clean your dishes how would you clean your
your home what would you how would you go about if if the activities you do
have the capacity to really really nourish you support you develop something beautiful and wonderful
inside so i'll read uh one more time this
passage um oh no i don't have it here now
so we'll have to do it another time and
and i hope that you
will stay my closely mindful attentive
to the activities of your day and see if uh how that supports
something wonderful wonderful possibilities for you and for what you can offer other people
so thank you and we'll do one more day on these activities
mindfulness of activities and that's tomorrow and and then monday we'll start with a whole
new orientation on the fifth the fourth exercise of satay patana so thank you