good evening welcome welcome
nice to see you all
maybe before i turn on the recording i'll just make a note there was
for those people that are on youtube there's a little bit of technical difficulty but that just
i know somehow when i was sitting it was kind of funny it just popped in my mind oh
this is probably what the problem is so if you saw me kind of get off here and
go play with something like what is she doing just
fixing that so okay
so again i'll say a really warm welcome to everybody
so nice to practice together makes it makes a difference
so a few weeks ago i gave a talk um about some of these poems that were inspiring
and i wanted to build on one of the poems there that um i don't know for some
reason really touches me and i kind of wanted to flush it out a little bit
and bring in some other teachings around it
so i'll start with this poem it's by maddie weingast
who is somebody who was inspired by some of the poems in the early literature
and then wrote his own poems so it goes like this
while walking along the river after a long day meditating on vulture
peak i watched an elephant splashing its way out of the water and
up the bank hello my friend
a person waiting there said scratching the elephant behind its ear
did you have a good bath the elephant stretched out its leg
the person climbed up and the two rode off like that
together seeing what had once been so
wild now a friend and companion to this good
person i took a seat under the nearest tree
and reached out a gentle hand to my own mind
truly i thought this is why i came to the woods
i like this poem it's very evocative this idea of this elephant and this person scratching behind the ears hello
did you have a good bath i know it seems like very sweet and you know certain intimacy there too
and then how to seeing this this perhaps i don't know how commonplace it was in
ancient india but maybe not extraordinary
this little just this you know mundane event inspires somebody
and partly why it inspires this person is because there's this line
um seeing what had once been so wild
so the meditator right had this idea that in this case it's a woman the meditator
that her mind used to be so wild isn't this true right when we start
meditating it it seems like it's this wild thing
a little bit out of control but then this uh this this shift in this
relationship in the poem the person has befriended the elephant and now the meditator realizes oh yeah
befriending the mind is the practice
rather than somehow thinking that we have to get rid of the thoughts we have to
make the mind be completely different we have to be completely different
instead just this idea of befriending the experience
reaching out a hand it's kind of just this gesture
so it says maybe this uh person has now kind of like is maybe a little bit more maturity and practice i think this i
suspect it's universal that when you first start meditating you're like oh my goodness i
had no idea my mind was like that but then our relationship we start to be
more accepting more allowing more relaxing and just allowing things to
unfold so
at the time of the buddha there were questions about
training just in the same way that maybe there are some ideas like okay
well how did this elephant get from this wild elephant to something that
steps out its leg and allows the person to climb on board like how does that happen this process
so there's a suta that's from mogallana the accountant
ganaka mogalana he's talking to the buddha
in the palace of megara's mother i'll just
because i'm a woman i'll make this tiny little statement right this is not so common
that some a place is named after a woman but this is megara's mother's palace
another suit as we learn her name but so this
woman who was a donor donated this palace i'm sorry mogallana the accountant is
talking to the buddha so he's not a monk
and he asks there's they're standing there in the midst of this um
[Music] palace which was donated to the buddha and some of his other monastics would be
there and they were practicing together and i can imagine that it was recently
completed in its construction because mogallana asks
do his followers do the buddha's followers have this progressive training do they
have training just like other people do just like other professions do
we can imagine that at that time they were the kind of the question was like are you magical can you just zap people
when they become awakened or do people have to work at it
because mogallana he's when he asks the question he also is drawing from his present moment experience exactly what
he is seeing right then and he asks them
this is a quote from the suta now master gotama that's how the buddha is
addressed by somebody who is not a follower master gautama in this palace of
megara's mother we can see gradual or progressive
gradual progress down to the last step of this staircase highlighting that when you're making a
staircase you make them one step at a time right you can't like start at the top and have the bottom right you have
to just do them sequentially so they're standing in this palace he points to you notice how there's these
uh steps is your training like that
and then he goes uh on and he says among the brahmana priests we can see
gradual progress in learning the scriptures among archers we see gradual progress in
archery among us accountants we see gradual progress in mathematics
for when we get an apprentice we first make them count one one two twos three threes
all the way up to a hundred we make them count is it possible to similarly describe a
gradual training for you and your what you're teaching
so ganaka mogalona is just recognizes that there's a natural way in which people learn
and that there's a way in which there's also uh different people in
different professions also have the results of their efforts right
they the people who are counting they can become accountants the
people who are practicing archery can become archers the brahmana priests become priests
during their training so in my mind mogalona is also looking
around and saying okay well there's all these people sitting but
do they get anything is there any purpose of this
so mogallana asks is it possible to describe a gradual training gradual
progress and gradual practice in your teachings
and the buddha says yes it is possible and then he gives a little simile
suppose a horse trainer were to obtain a fine thoroughbred horse
first the trainer would make it get used to wearing the bit
i don't know anything about horses so i'm just assuming that this is what uh happened
and then they would train it further so in the same way when the tattogata
when the buddha gets a person for training so that is
when somebody ordains underneath him first he guides him in one way and when
they have learned that he guides them further
so first one way and then further
maybe in some ways it feels really obvious to us but maybe in some ways when we think
about our practice it sometimes just feels like a mumbo jum or a whole jumble
of things i know certainly from me in the beginning it did partly because i would go to dharma
talks and then the dharma talks you know that not always started you know start here's
the the first dharma talk you hear isn't where you should start and then the sex second dermatogen the second one you
start right it takes took me quite a while to figure it out that oh there's a progressive practice here
and it wasn't until actually you know i heard gil give a talk about a suta that i realized oh
that's like this happens before that and this and something like this so
so you can imagine that maybe this person moghalana sees these people sitting around
he knows how he was trained and he's heard some things and maybe he's a little bit confused
so the buddha does give him this progressive this gradual training
i'm going to talk a little bit about that but before i do i also want to say because mokelana he
asks this other question so
when your followers are instructed and advised like this by you the buddha
do all of them achieve the ultimate goal nabana
or do some of them not like what good are instructions if nobody can follow them or achieve with
your want to i think this is a great question
it's a legitimate question it's a fair question and then the buddha responds well
some accomplish the ultimate goal nibbana while others do not
and then he asks the next i think a great question why
why do some reach it and some don't
and then the buddha responds and includes a simile in his response
he says well mogulana suppose a person were to come along who
wanted to go to raja gaha he'd approach you and say
i wish to go to rajagaha town not too far away
i wish to go to raja gahap please point out the road to rajakaha then you'd say
to him here this road goes to raja gaho go along for a while and then you'll see a certain
village go a little further and then you'll see a town and then go a little further and then
you'll see raja gaha with the delightful parks woods meadows and lotus ponds so you'll know
when you get there because it's really beautiful and you see these lotus ponds and these lakes and things
and then the buddha continues talking to this uh to mogola instructed that like this by you
they might still take the wrong road heading west
but then a second person comes along with the same question you give the same example the same instructions and
instructed by you they do safely arrive at raja gaha and why is that because raja gaha's
present the path leading to raja gaha is present and you are there to give them the
instructions and one person takes the wrong path and heads west while another arrives safely
at rajakaha and then mogallana responds well what can i do about that
i am the one who just shows the way i just give the instructions
he's not physically carrying them there or something like this just gives them the instructions
and then of course the buddha says in the same way although nabana is present and the path
leading to nabana is present and i am present to encourage them
some of my disciples instructed and advised like me the chief the ultimate goal nabana while
some of them do not and what can i do about that the tatakata is the one who shows the
way kind of highlighting his role as a
person the buddha's role is to guide others we can't
make it happen for them can't make it happen for us
so what is this path what is this uh
this gradual training sometimes it's called or progressive training
many of you will be familiar with this maybe in the um less obvious ways
or the more um uh and in a certain form and it shows up in
lots of different forms at the bird's eye view is sila samari
panya ethics mental development and wisdom probably we've many of you have heard
this and certainly we talk about the eightfold path this way but the gradual training has some other
details in there that often we don't talk about in dermatox so i thought i would uh pull
out a few of them and uh talk about them a little bit
but this idea that uh it's progressive you know certainly in the west we don't us don't necessarily
teach about okay ethics first get that down and then when you're ready
go on to the next step when you're ready go on to the next step
for some people that works perfectly fine to have it not be progressive not to wait until you're
ready to receive the next instruction until you do but for some other people maybe it's
helpful to especially if you're feeling stuck or things don't quite make sense
or you're feeling lost and confused or overwhelmed or some of these things
one potential thing to do is to kind of go back to some of the earlier steps quote
unquote okay so what are these steps
i'm not first one is sila ethical behavior
moral restraint following the five precepts for a lay person if you're a monastic to follow the
patamoka i'm not going to talk about ethics today
but in this suta maybe i'll back up and say the gradual training this shows up i don't know how many
times in the suit does 20 or 30 different times and each time it's a little bit
different there aren't any that are exactly the same so we might imagine maybe with the
buddha was speaking to different people and had a sense that this person maybe needed
something a little bit different or i don't know exactly why
and there are some scholars and some practitioners who love to do this who love to compare all the different
versions of this and postulate why they're a little bit different
so i'm going to focus on the on three
supportive practices that are in here that often we don't hear about so much and
i'm going to talk about them in terms of if then statements
because they're presented not exactly that way but often um i find practice is feels
a little more like an invitation a little bit more like okay here's something you can do
you can try you can work with as opposed to that you better do this
you know we don't i think many of us don't respond so well i know i don't i don't like it when
people tell me what to do sometimes this gets me into trouble but i think there's also this uh
that comes in the flu in flavor more of an invitation if it's an if then statement so what do i mean by this
if you would like a particular experience or outcome then
do a particular thing to help create the conditions if you're not so interested in that
outcome then there's no need to do it okay
so if you don't want unhelpful states to
overwhelm you then guard the scent stores
so if you don't want unhelpful states to overwhelm you
so what are what's being pointed to here is and here and i'll read the exactly
how it is in the suta but these unhelpful states
a kusala dhamma some of you may know this word kusala unhelpful and skillful and wholesome
the specific ones that are being pointed to are greed and aversion
so often right this just this even subtle or not so subtle i i want more
i want less get that away from me these are the first of the hindrances
the first two hindrances so these are things that definitely get in the way of our
settling down and having some peace and ease
and a short this also kind of greed and aversion is sometimes also a shorthand
way of saying everything that's not equanimity like any kind of like response we're having that isn't
equanimous if you don't want unhelpful states to
overwhelm you then guard the sense doors well what does this mean to guard the
scent stores scent stores of course are the
senses taste hearing feeling
seeing there's probably one i'm missing the mind is one i don't know if i have
them all but the six senses and maybe i'll just say a classic
example of not guarding the scent stores is when you see somebody attractive and
you just start watching them or they're going like this and you're kind of going around to look at this
right this is a typical thing we see in the movies right how somebody catches somebody else's eye and they look at
them and watch them and then usually their partner is angry right or something like this in the movies
so that's not guardian ascent stores so garden the scent stores is about
it's not that we have to close down and always avert our gaze
but it's that we're not like prolonging if there's like a peak of interest we're
not grabbing onto and like watching to
have that uh experience of attraction desire just grow and grow and grow
there might be oh yep that's an attractive person and just allow them to come into view
and out of you in the same way that uh you might be
standing on the sidewalk and there's cars that are going by like okay there's thoughts that are going by there are
sense there are physical experiences there's visual stimulus going by
so you know they're going by but and you also know when it's safe to step
out and what it's safe not to but something like this is guarding the
scent stores it's a way of taking stimuli
as they are without pushing or pulling
but instead just allowing us to have experiences and allowing the experience
to arise and pass away so it's not a shutting down it's not a
shunning it's not a locking oneself up into a cave or a
closet when we're on retreat we do we do kind of guard the sun stores and a little bit
more legitimate or not legitimate a little bit more
i don't know what the word is i'm looking for but in a way that it's uh really
exaggerated necessary than how we are in daily life right we have kind of are isolated from so many of these
things that might impinge our senses just as a support but that's not the expectation that
we're doing that with our daily life so here's how the suta goes so here's
the quote here's the instruction here's the buddha's words
guard your scent stores when you see a site for example with your eyes don't get
caught up in the features and details if the faculty of sight were left
unrestrained bad unskillful qualities of desire and aversion would become overwhelming
for this reason practice restraint protect the faculty of sight and achieve
restraint over it and he goes on with the other five senses
so just this recognition that if it's unrestrained the translator here is
saying desire and aversion would become overwhelming maybe not overwhelming in terms of
uncomfortable but overwhelming in terms of we would lose our mindfulness we would get lost in the desire and
aversion so then the next uh
step in this gradual training i'll state it as an if then statement
if you want to be healthy and live blamelessly and in comfort
than be moderate in eating sometimes we don't talk about this so
much about being moderate and eating but just pointing to consuming just enough
to end our hunger and to eat enough
that's not starving right the buddha we know in his life story he had both when
he was younger in the palace we were imagining that he was a overeating and then
when later as a practitioner he was starving himself so this recognition that moderate and
eating is part of taking care of ourselves
is part of having a healthy body as well as a healthy mind
guarding the scent stores is to help sort of protect the mind and eating in a healthy way
is to protect the body for me it's a little bit interesting to
note that thousands of years ago as well as today there is a lot of concern about food
and of course religious traditions often have restrictions on eating or there's
or and certainly monastics for example in this tradition don't eat after them uh
then when the sun is up at so 12 o'clock or depending on daylight savings
whenever this soon the moon is sorry whenever the sun is straight overhead
so and there's a way of i mean today there are people of course they're
identified by what they eat and what they don't eat
and when we think about how much mental energy and how much even like
commerce and is concerned with food like how many
websites how many advertisements how many apps
how many you know what people talk about and stuff is food and there's nothing wrong with that
except that when it's a way that you get a little distorted view
that it becomes not so much about taking care of yourself
but some how it becomes more about the meaning of the food or
what it means for you in such a way that's not supportive for practice
i don't want to say that we shouldn't ever have uh you know there's
food that maybe our is our family or our traditions
have but just this to notice that this is such a rich place
where we often don't even want to look at it or consider it
how we might be using food in terms of stress or when we're feeling a little bit out of sorts or boredom or something like this
this is certainly a rich place for me to practice i have this thing with cookies
that sometimes you know when i'm feeling stressed or out of sorts or something that
i don't know i like to have cookies so
reflecting on the role that food has in our lives and allowing it to have a role
that is supportive and this is not easy because there is so much
because societal pressure about meaning of food or
what it should mean and what you shouldn't eat and something like this
so here's some how it's worded in the suta eat in moderation
reflect properly on the food that you eat not for fun or indulgence or adornment
or decoration but to sustain the body
to avoid harm and to support spiritual practice
and reflect that in this way so like eating eating this way i shall put an end to
old discomfort and not give rise to new discomfort and i will live healthy blameless and at
ease so to put an end to the feeling of being hungry
but not eating so much that then you feel sick from overeating
and in this way to live healthy blameless and at ease i appreciate very much right the buddha
is encouraging us to have some comfort and ease
sometimes when we think about these practitioners we are not thinking about comfort and ease we're thinking about
you know striving and working really hard or really
abstaining or restraining you know these uh asceticism and hardships
but the buddha is talking about eat in moderation in a way that supports you
so then having created favorable conditions to meditate one was
behaving ethically which i didn't go into any detail the second was to guard the sun store so
that the mind is not flooded with desire and aversion and just chasing after them
taking care of the body that's getting expressed in the way that and eating
so then the buddha sources talk about meditation practice
and he talks about by first by having a commitment to practice
so the the way it stated is to be committed to wakefulness
and wakefulness interestingly is used both ways that we might use it in english to be
awake that is to not be asleep and to be awake is also to be aware of
what's happening so this
the buddha he had this emphasis you know to be committed to practice to be committed to
wakefulness it means that you're not sleeping your life away you're not sleeping your days away
and maybe we i would consider or invite you to consider like well what
are there's ways in which we are maybe not literally sleeping but figuratively like that we're kind of
numbing ourselves and no longer aware of what's happening around us and
disconnected from ourselves and others
for example watching too much tv there's a way right in which the mind just
kind of gets into a a stupor or something i know this having done this recently
visiting someone who had a tv like watching tv and just noticing like how just watching
it it just kind of i don't want to say that old tv watching is bad but
right we're not going to become awakened if we're watching tv all hours of the day so
here's how the buddha expresses it he expresses it in terms of
what to do with yourself in the evenings be committed to
wakefulness practice walking and sitting meditation by day purifying your mind from obstacles
we're here for obstacles are the hindrances again so when the hindrances arise you know work with them
in the evening continue to practice walking and sitting meditation
in the middle of the night lie down in the lion's posture on the right side placing one foot on
top of the other mindful and aware and focused on the time of getting up
right of course they don't have alarm clocks so this idea of setting the intention okay i'm going to wake up at a
certain time and then in the last part of the night
get up and continue to practice walking and sitting meditation purifying your mind from obstacles so
this idea of before you sleep and when you first wake up to be practicing
with sitting and walking meditation
and then and this gradual training goes on to a description of mindfulness and
then concentration and then some of the wisdom things so i just wanted to highlight these
three different practices that are in there that sometimes we don't hear about but there can be a real
support and i like the way that it's these if then statements are about if you want to have some comfort
if you want to not be overwhelmed if you want to be healthy and take care of yourself so
it's not only for meditation but it's just to enable us to have our best lives
so that we can bring the or the best version of ourselves to our
practice and allow the wisdom and to arise and allow meditation to arise
creating the conditions for that
so maybe these are some ways and i don't know how many
different steps there are to train an elephant to go from a wild one so that they can then
put their leg out and allow a person to step up on on them
but i imagine there's a lot and it takes time but maybe some of them are mundane and
not so glamorous or even fun
but in the same way this practice too has
these steps and some that are maybe supportive that
we might overlook or we might consider if we haven't really engaged in them before as a support for our practice
on the way to nirvana the buddha says he's the one that shows the way
and if we would like to be able to follow the way that he is giving
so may our practice be a support for finding more freedom
more ease more comfort and maybe
support for not only ourselves but for all beings everywhere
thank you