greetings everyone it's lovely to be here with you on this
dharmic path so again we'll begin our meditation by
making the conscious choice to first of all
leave all of our concerns preoccupations agendas worries
and responsibilities outside the door
of our meditation area for the duration of the sit
so take a moment to carefully put all your concerns in a safe place
on the other side of the door with the commitment to leave them there
during the meditation you wouldn't come back to them afterwards
no need for them now and as we have done over the last two
days we will continue to breathe in open
non-reactive receptive awareness
and we have a good friend who can help us with this
her name is sati which is the pali word for
mindfulness awareness many of you have participated in guild
series this year on the satipattana and in the final talk of the series
he spoke about living in awareness with sati patana
and if we can do that we know that we have a clear place
to abide in it's a home that we take with us
wherever we go maybe it's like
living in a messy house that has a clean living room so when messy challenges
fears desires attachments arise we know that with sati this lucid
awareness we have a clear place where we can abide
sati is the treasure the magic of vipassana practice
and we can call on her whenever we need help
so as we would do when sati patana practice let's begin our meditation
by bringing awareness to the fore we know that when awareness is strong
it opens the door to seeing when unskillful states arise
and then we can make the choice to not pick them up
so now bring this strong clear awareness to your posture
balancing and aligning the whole body
feel your physical and energetic connection to the earth
and now imagine your energetic connection to space
via the invisible thread through the small opening in the top of the head
sitting here between heaven and earth
now with a long deep breath invite your awareness to the experience
and sensations of the body breathing
breathing naturally now on the exhale relaxing
and letting go of the muscles of the face the eyes
around the eyes forehead
cheeks the lips the tongue
the jaw
and moving downwards relaxing the neck the shoulders
letting go in the arms and the hands in the torso
the heart center and softening the belly
relaxing the legs and the feet
breathing in lucid awareness
breathing out letting go
on the in-breath lucid awareness of this body breathing
and on the exhale letting go again
relaxing
sitting with the stillness and tranquility
of a mountain no matter what the weather is like
the mountain does not react
and as the body becomes still the mind has a quiet place to abide in
this is the piece of simply being
as agitation and craving are left behind we are soothed
nourished
with the body calm anchored in the earth
the mind and heart open softly becoming spacious
limitless and connecting to the vastness
of space
in his calm spaciousness of resting in awareness
our knots our places of holding can begin to untangle
breathing in receptive awareness
reading out calm letting go
the tranquility of calmly letting go
naturally gives way to contentment
we are in the safe space not needing anything
so now the invitation is breathing in calm receptivity
and breathing out well-being and contentment
nothing is needed we feel satisfied
by the simplicity of being here
breathing in [Music] calm receptivity
breathing out the well-being of contentment
if the mind becomes agitated we can be calm
about being agitated we hold ourselves kindly
when agitation is present but since we know that feeding our
thoughts does not bring relief we choose instead the dharmic path
of resting in spacious awareness
breathing in calm receptivity
breathing out well-being contentment
not needing anything we breathe in calm receptivity
now on the exhale we radiate out ease
and contentment to all beings everywhere including ourselves
and for this practice of radiating
the invitation is to bring to the corners of the mouth
the buddha's gentle half smile of contentment
breathing in calm receptivity
radiating out ease and contentment
on the exhale
as we come to the end of the sitting we bring to mind the people we will come
in to contact with today strangers
as well as people we know and we make the aspiration
of offering them through our own example the ease
of calm contentment one of the fruits
of cultivating a mind of peace with things as they are
may all beings ourselves included first of all
be safe
being safe may all beings be peaceful
with safety and peace may all beings be contented
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
welcome everyone it's good to be here with you all
today is the third day in our theme this week of cultivating peace
and the flavor of the day in the spectrum of peace is contentment
in pali the word is sukkah which can also be translated as
happiness and i'll use these two translations interchangeably
sukha is the opposite of dukkha
and in the scheme of liberative dependent arising contentment
is born of tranquility which in turn is associated with joy
joy always contains happiness but contentment can arise in the absence
of joy this may be counterintuitive
but this kind of happiness can also arise
from the depth of grief when we allow
the grief to be as it is known and embraced
those of you who have heard me speak before may
know that i lost my youngest sister
to als motor neuron disease um i was the
uh eldest of four and she was the youngest with an eight year difference and she was my baby
and i adored her and um she grew up to be a
a wonderful wonderful wonderful person
and uh did so many good things in her life
and when she was 59 she
was diagnosed with als which is a death sentence
and it's a particularly challenging some may say cruel
illness in the sense that the body becomes progressively more and more paralyzed
and you know first you lose the use of your limbs and
then you can't swallow and eat so my sister got a feeding tube in her stomach
and then you can't use your hands anymore and so to be able to communicate
using a computer she had to learn to type with her eyes
every week for over five years there were
increasing challenges and when she got this diagnosis i was
i was just distraught it seemed so um
it seemed so not right why wasn't it me i'm i'm older i mean you know
she there was she was a model of kindness and generosity and
community support and she saved a rare plant species in maine
and so i was railing against the injustice
that this illness was happening to her
and a few months later i went on a
long retreat and um and i was still just
um this this pain was with me day and night
but um thanks to the practice and the beautiful instruction
the mind began to settle
and quite early on into the retreat
somehow i don't know how but i seem to dive into
this ocean of tears
and doing that was followed by
a feeling of happiness
and peace i had i had come to peace with the way
things are and i wasn't fighting against reality
anymore and so um
this was a tremendous help for me in my um uh
my desire to be uh of as much help as possible as like as i could be to her
during her five years of illness and it was essential because
when i was able to live with the reality of her suffering
with a calm useful mind i could bring that
to all my interactions with her and with her husband who provided her tremendous support
so um not expecting things to be different
than they are and
the mind becomes more peaceful when delusion is dispelled
and in the meditation we just practiced we
um explored how tranquility
can naturally give rise to the ease of contentment
our nervous system is soothed when the body becomes still
and the mind the heart can abide in the tranquility of lucid
receptive awareness many of you have participated in guild
series this year on the sachipatana and in his final talk
there he talked about living in awareness with sati patana
how knowing that we can be present in lucid awareness can make a world of difference
with strong awareness we have a peaceful abode when fears desires attachments and
challenges arise and this awareness
is a place of freedom that allows us to be present with our shortcomings
and our challenging mind states in a healthy way we see them arise
and we don't pick them up so in this
wholesome abode of strong awareness we know that there is the possibility of ease
when suffering and agitation arise we can be at ease with what is
we don't need to change reality to be okay
it's normal to want relief from agitation and the karmic samsaric path offers us a
wealth of unwholesome solutions to escape
and here again is a fork in the road we know that there is an alternative
dharmic path where we can find true relief from suffering and agitation
when we step into clear awareness we can be fully present
for whatever arises sati
mindfulness or awareness the first and most important
of the factors of awakening satya is our best friend
on this path to awakening because
once the mind is free of obstacles and established in awareness
then gladness joy tranquility
contentment and samadhi arise without personal effort
the only effort that may be required is maintaining our mindfulness and not picking up the mental obstacles
so you may have had experiences of this when the mind is
clear and calm ordinary things become wonderful
simple things become beautiful and the mind settles more and more
and we experience this as a relief
knowing that this simple moment is enough
that we don't need anything except to be established in awareness
and then sweet easeful contentment arises from knowing
that this moment is enough
so i'd like to read you from
89 12 the story of king pasanati coming to visit the buddha
and the king was surprised when he arrived and he said to the buddha
here i see monastics smiling and cheerful sincerely joyful plainly delighted
their faculties fresh living at ease unruffled
subsisting on what others give abiding
with the mind free as a wild deers
and what he saw was the sangha of monks and nuns radiating contentment
and this was from the happiness that arose naturally from their practice
this kind of happiness does not depend on external conditions
it doesn't depend on getting our needs met
and the possibility of being content
may be much closer than you realize
by recognizing suffering and agitation directly there is the chance
to direct the attention to the alternative
of dwelling in the possibility of ease and the ease that we seek
comes from within
so for the next 24 hours
maybe you can um
practice noticing moments when
you don't really need anything except to be present
and with that calm contented presence
you can radiate that same useful contented mind
to everyone you come in contact with thank you for your attention thank you
for your practice
hey thank you meg uh so everyone if you want to come off mute and as you sign off
i'm more than welcome to do so thank you meg
yeah thank you thank you so much