there so hello and welcome everyone welcome to
happy hour it's lovely to be with you ah lovely to practice together with dear
sangha so so for today's practice
um the theme i'd like to offer for us to
consider is how taking care of ourselves
really caring and modulating how much
we we perhaps engage how much energy we
pour out a sense of care sense of awareness of our own energy
our own engagement our how tired we are are we tired are we pushing ourselves
are we out of resources but still that level of awareness
and caring for ourselves is an act of meta to
how this care not only is an act of meta for ourselves but it's also a way of
sustaining ourselves so that we can care for others we can care for the world
so how caring for ourselves really being both mindful
of our moods our attention our our body our resources and caring caring for this
being after all this this person who is me
consider that this person we are um entrusted we are entrusted
to care for this being who is me as if you were your own
child you know your children if you've had children or you have children or you will have and with children you
have them they grow up you know you care for them and then you they also care for themselves whereas you're the only one
you you care for this being in this body in all ways so
so and also bringing in mindfulness mindfulness what what does this body
need what does this heart need what does this mind need so in a way bringing awareness together with meta
for oneself and in that way when we can care for ourselves we can be
more available to care for others to take care of others we don't become resentful like oh
i've given you everything i've got and now you ask more like oh no it's okay i've been actually been
monitoring what i have and what how much i can give and how much i need to care for myself
so there is a discernment that can come in that can
support us not falling into say resentment or over giving or also undergiving too so
so awareness together with metta
for ourselves is is the basic theme or practice tonight so
and it might be a quieter night because it's nice to tune in and take care
see what's needed and pay attention so so that's the theme so let's practice
together let's land let's land in our bodies
let's arrive let's arrive fully let's arrive fully in
our bodies
letting the breath be soothing calming nourishing
all that is needed just the breath
in the body
receiving each breath in the abdomen
letting it be nourishing soothing like a lullaby simple
very simple
receiving is an act of care
this
and as the breath is received
in the abdomen with care
with awareness settling
let the body settle
into receiving care
feeling cared for
letting there be the settling
settling of the body settling of the heart
whatever is present is okay can be here just as it is
after thoughts entanglements it's okay
can we bow to them and let them go can we bow to them and let them go for
right now they can come back later
dropping in the question with awareness
their heart their body to your mind what do you need in this moment what is
needed in this moment what is your level of energy
[Music] fatigue anxiety
whatever is present resources
as if you're reading the meter what is needed right now
let yourself know in your body not in your head what is needed but in the body let it be
known sensed in your heart
i know that this questioning this snowing is an act of care
if you're asking yourself how are you dear how are things
it's an act of care to ask
you want to know
and whatever arises is the answer what is needed
here ah can you open to it with care with love
with kindness as if this body this heart this you
as tender as a newborn needing support care
holding nursing rocking
this being that is yourself
and if it feels okay in your mind's eye as you're perhaps seeing this younger version of
yourself this this baby
being held rocked
a newborn vulnerable
completely open
it feels appropriate in your heart to feel
i care for you i care for you i love you
i will protect you or whatever words are appropriate or
feelings it's friendliness meta for yourself
this baby doesn't have to do anything anything to do anything right or perfect
to deserve to earn to scare this love just because
they are just because they are this miracle
of life this tender miracle of life
to be protected to be appreciated
to be tended to be tended
with matter
and if it feels appropriate you can stay with this image of
a younger version of yourself a baby being held rocked and stay with that
it's nourishing
supporting or if you like you can sense
this being who is you now [Music] in this body and drop in the reflection
in what ways
have you given too much or exhausted yourself
in what ways can you be more mindful of your
resources with care
for yourself
how can i care how can i care for myself better
how can i care for this body this heartless mind let yourself just drop in the questions
it's not a heady thing don't start thinking about it
let yourself breathe the question let yourself live the question
breathe the question
in what ways am i not exactly skillful and pushing
exhausting so that i don't care for myself with meta and
then wisdom does not arise maybe unskillfulness arises
i get resentful tired angry drained
haggard how can i care
how can i love care for this being who is me
in this moment and in general
just loving
being kind being kind
and if the metaphases are supportive you're welcome to say them silently
may i be safe happy healthy
and have ease
as we bring this practice period to a close together
trusting that caring for ourselves filling our own cup is the first step of caring for others
being more available skillfully to care for others in the world
now offering our goodness offering our care [Music]
our cultivation our metta to all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere be safe happy healthy and have ease
may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you thank you all thank you for your practice dear sangha coming
together supporting each other yourselves
so we have a few minutes if any reflections you like to share you can raise your
zoom hand if it's your physical hand i will not
see you so i only see just very few of you you can also type in chat if you type to
everyone i'll read your name if it's just type to me it'll be private reflection
jerry can you hear me okay
i hear you great okay so i haven't been in the
uh sangha a lot in the last few months but that came to me and maybe i need more
work and self-compassion but um i uh when i was thinking about this and
i'm sorry i joined a bit late but i thought of myself as a small child that was a nice place to be
and uh so i thought you know uh we all have a difficult couple of
years collectively in the world and of course it doesn't seem to be getting easier as things continue to turn
um uh even events today but one of the things that came to me is
i said you know i i need a brief
weekend vacation from it all and i thought uh
uh of going away and uh
to a place that i've gone before that i've associated with which i haven't gone to because of covert
it involves taking a plane for five hours to an island and coming back and then i thought oh i
should really save that money for renovations in the house you know so that i thought oh my god i'm
being selfish what am i doing and uh i'm giving myself i i joined this
thing and i'm now giving myself a trip and i maybe i shouldn't what am i doing like this is like i thought oh yeah yeah
maybe i should have some self-compassion so i was in a a bit of a mess at the end of all that
oh jerry jerry jerry how human right how
human what you just described what are you how human
what do you describe you know we have it's like i'm tired you need to have more self-compassion and then like oh
okay a triple yeah that would be great oh no this is like oh and then punch you're like wait i'm practicing here i'm
in the middle of a meditation you're like oh my god oh dear heart or dear
dear human being part of this this collective humanity right it's it's
so human so human so yes so having self-compassion for yourself who's
having this this papancha you know the word papancha in polly is like oh your proliferation
like should i do this or go to this island oh no about that oh sweetheart oh sweetheart
you know this papancha is painful let's start here let's start with a
moment of just rest here just here yeah yeah thank you for
sharing that just the humanity of it we go through so much of that every day every moment yeah
thank you thank you very much thanks jerry thank you
[Music] any other reflections questions comments
for the benefit of the sangha yourself i see someone is clapping if you're trying to raise your hand
that's a clap is that mary mary are you trying to raise your hand and the clap
is happening or were you really clapping for uh no jerry
i i would like to um go on from jerry can you say more what is papancha i've
never heard that word before oh yeah yeah yeah and i'm always in it
is one of these wonderful pali words pali being the language of the buddha
which is related to sanskrit but it's it's more um vernacular the vernacular
language that which the the bullet buddha taught in
and this word papancha papancha it's actually kind of sounds like what it is like punches like the pug
the burst of like activity and the mind it's like oh you know maybe i should you
know you're sitting you're meditating like oh gosh i'll give another oh i'm so calm oh
this column is so sweet oh maybe maybe i should like oh i remember that lake i
sat next to like oh that was a great like oh maybe i should buy a lit you know a houseboat and go boating or oh
but but house boots are exposed like you know it's just like one thing after another right it's just like fun you're
just stuck in this proliferation proliferation of thought and maybe
emotion and just being tossed around right tossed about with thoughts and emotions and this and past and future
and planning and you're just gone right papancha it's just proliferation so that's a great word
so papanja when we're caught in that so so it's actually a great word to have in
your vocabulary so that when it comes up you know you don't go bad bad bad meditator you'll get oh sweetheart oh
sweetheart papancha you're just you know papancha part of the human condition
right it happens for all of us papancha oh that's cute um
uh pat on youtube says papancha sounds like popcorn mind yeah kind of
but but not very yummy it's kind of stuck it's burnt popcorn mind [Laughter]
great thanks for that question mary that's great that's great
and and next time you want to raise your hand the the the race hand is under the clap but you'll find it
so any other questions reflections before we turn into ah rada i see you
i see your hand i don't see you your camera is turned off
there you are hi ryda hi um
that's like lastly i just want to say thank you um this is a really timely um topic for me
um and i was wondering in the beginning you said something about undergiving and
over giving yeah um and i feel like i kind of
have worked a lot more on the over giving um side of things um [Music]
and i guess yeah i'm just over giving your undergraduate sorry i'm thinking
yeah um i guess i was just wondering if you could say a little bit
yeah i guess i was just reflecting on um the idea of giving from a place of kind
of being where we can still be kind of embodied and in touch with
actually how much resource we have to give um and also without attachment to kind
of any outcome or result um and i guess on the undergiving side i
was just reflecting that i think like in a specific situation
that i have um with a family member who is sick who has been sick for a really long time um
and it's sort of an ongoing thing um [Music] and i think recently
you know having been through like my own healing journey in the past couple of years like
coming to terms with how that's impacted my health um and being really aware now of over
giving um i think sometimes there's actually a tendency to kind of
undergive in a sense of like disengaging because of like fear of
you know of the situation and everything that it brings up so um
yeah that i guess that's a lot i mean i was just wondering if you could speak
a little bit about that yeah yeah thank you ryder thank you for um
about that and and your question and your reflection and and in what you said i actually hear a lot of awareness and a
lot of wisdom that you already have about the conditions were over-giving
and under-giving in your case and it's so hard to be a caregiver it's so important in the the case of being a
caregiver to be resourced otherwise it can lead to burnout so
easily and resentment and and and disengagement and and just it's hard all
around but but really realizing that caring for someone you really have to
care for yourself you really have to take time for yourself you have to ask
for support and figure out what this heart this body
this mind needs does it need eating sleep exercise just taking some time out go for a walk
or a movie or whatever it might be you're just like taking care taking care
of this so that you can be available so they can give um with joy
not as a way of i have to get like ah here it is again like not so it doesn't become a grim duty so that there is
enough water in your own cup there's tea in your own cup right there's um
so so to know that it is of the nature of
being a caregiver that's that is challenging and you have to be extra
aware so maybe the last thing i would say because again you have a lot of wisdom yourself
bring awareness bring a lot of awareness to the body
what's what's happening right now am i leaning in too much and i'm leaning out what's sweetheart what's happening here
and not to beat yourself up but sweetheart are you okay is this is so care are you
disengaging is it too much for you because when you care for yourself you're caring for the other it's caring
for for the relationship also so it's caring for yourself
there's more i can say but that might be enough for now is that okay yeah thank you thank you great thank you
so dear ones the time has come let us let us turn
to each other in small groups and and the invitation
um as we engage in small groups of roughly size three or
four or two or three we'll see what how it ends up the count
um so first and foremost
be kind to yourself be kind to each other to the other people in the group
and also consider it it it just offer one thing it's not
appropriate to go on a long monologue that take the entire time and share your entire life history even though that
might be tempting and cathartic for you but it may not be appropriate for others
so please be wise and kind share kindness this is an
opportunity to be kind to everyone in the group okay so share one nugget just a short nugget
about what it is that maybe by your practice or anything
just but kindness share kindness with others for the benefit of others so you
say one nugget the other person says another nugget another person comes back
to you if anyone at any point wants to say i pass i just want to be silent and hold
presence that's perfectly fine this is enough small groups are an opportunity to be kind
please don't manage the um the invitation is to go in alphabetical
order in terms of your first name say one one just one minute nugget maybe
shorter okay and you go around and round um okay to be silent and again be kind
be kind be kind i cannot emphasize that enough be kind be kind be kind
all right so
so so give me one moment to arrange the rooms here
uh i think i think they're arranged oh
something i gotta shift and move hold on one second be patient with me
and um [Music] okay i think i have it here we go i'm
opening the rooms be kind be kind be
kind okay all the rooms are closed everybody is back
thank you all for your practice and sorry the rooms the breakout
sessions were shorter tonight because we had so many wonderful questions and went
a little over time with the reflections which is always lovely but there was just a little less time so maybe next
time there will be more so it's just so that we don't and too much past 7 p.m i kind of
shorter so thanks for your understanding anyway let's dedicate the merit of our practice
may maybe goodness trusting there is goodness um cultivated goodness arising from
the cultivation of hearts of our hearts for the benefit of ourselves and all beings everywhere
may be a cause and condition for gladness and freedom of all beings
everywhere including ourselves may all beings be well may all beings be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice and i'll stay afterward well i'm gonna
stop