hello everyone and welcome to imc
and we'll just start with a meditation directly
so to prepare yourself
by sitting here with respect
for yourself with a kindness and care
for your own welfare perhaps so that later
you might be able to offer respect and kindness and care to others
and to think of meditation as a act of
self-respect self-care self-kindness
in such a way that it feels welcoming for you
to be present to be here at this time at this place with your
attention that your attention is the vehicle
for which care kindness
respect can be present
gently closing the eyes
and perhaps with some long slow deep breaths it's a way of
both connecting to yourself and as you exhale clearing away
whatever it is that might interfere
with present moment awareness
so and letting your breathing return to
normal
relaxing in your body [Music]
softening
perhaps with the health help of your breathing softening whatever is hard in
you
meeting with care and kindness whatever is difficult in you
um
at the end of the exhale as the inhale believe begins
perhaps you can evoke the kind of awareness attention which
has a quality of clarity just
clear awareness here
with the beginning of each inhale
so
um
uh
so
this
okay
so
you
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
where would you connect to inside of yourself
if you were going to gaze out on the world
with respect with care
with kindness where would that come from in you
from the heart from deep
in your torso
below the layers of fear anger despair
is there a home for compassion
for care for respect of others
and if there is to now at the end of the sitting to gaze
out metaphorically gaze out upon the world
and evoke a good will for this world of ours
wishing well to others
may all beings be free of suffering
may others be free of oppression violence
maybe they may they be free of hate
disrespect may all beings
live in safety in mutual respect
may all beings be happy and free
and may it be that we can contribute to that being possible
[Music]
okay
so hello everyone who's here at time c welcome and to those of you who are
online welcome as well and um
i'm thinking about how there are two sources within us
for how we act in the world
how we react in the world respond in the world
and one is more what i can consider more on the surface and one is from our depths some place
deep inside and the surface i i associate with
responding reacting to the world when the events of the world
come to us and it meets our fear
or our anger or despair or hopelessness
our greed and all those things i think of more surface
partly because they usually involved a lot of thinking imagination of ideas and desires
and they also are more activated state
the depth within us is to allow something deeper inside of us to respond to be touched by the world
that's that is deeper than whatever fear and despair anger he might have
maybe when those things their the fear and anger despair
have settled and quieted greed has settled away
enough so that we feel a sense of satisfaction and and warmth and
pleasure and happiness in life in a deeper way without needing
the world to be a certain way where we feel at ease and feel
at home in a deep way and so there's a different sensitivity is that
we in which we receive the world the difficulties
that other things that are i think deeper inside and maybe easily eclipsed by the
surface can emerge and rather than
reacting we respond rather than reacting
we we something emerges from the heart
merges from deeper deeper inside that where we can we feel our shared
humanity where we can feel and see other people for their humanity
that's very hard to see if we're reacting from the surface if we're
seeing through the fear through hate through greed through despair
through a sense of hopelessness helplessness and so to
be able to kind of tap into some deeper place within is a hugely important part of meditation
buddhist practice and some of the guidelines for how to
live like a life that the buddha gives make a lot of sense or there's a lot of
there's a they they resonates much deeper inside of us
if uh uh if we're in the touch to this in touch with this depth inside of us
so one of the guidelines one of the kind of precepts of buddhism or maybe the first precept is not to kill
and and the kind of the primary principle
they're associated to that and the principle that underlies all the buddhism i believe is
not to harm the principle of non-harming living a life of non-harming
and i want to talk about this a little bit today because of recent events you
know it seems like two uh you know two weeks ago we had this
horrific shooting in in buffalo and a market called tom's friendly
market and 10 black americans were shot just
shopping and that was the motivation for the talk
last week on on hate it was a hate crime
and uh and then just five days ago we had this uh horrendous
another horrendous shooting of children 19 children and others were killed
in texas and uh
and you know we've had a lot of shootings school shootings in this country
and so what happens when these kinds of events are allowed to
touch something deep inside is there a place that's deeper than anger
deeper than fear deeper than despair deeper than
then is there someplace deeper not to dismiss those reactions and those
responses because they're so human so
you know so so much of how people respond to things but what happens do we have access to
some place deeper and i think that's the call one of the
calls of buddhist practice because of the first precept in this first principle of not killing and not harming
to the the call of buddhists is to see how can we come from that place
how can we be dedicated and committed to non-harming in a radical way in a
thorough way how could we be champions of not killing not just not
killing ourselves because the buddha also taught
that or encouraged more than just
not harming not killing but advocating
for others not to kill as well or inspiring others not to kill
to cultivate maybe a culture of not killing
and so how do we you know change this human tremendous
momentum of a culture that has so much you know has so much momentum in
violence in killing after the killings in texas there was in
the news reports of uh that the manufacturer of the gun that
was used the company called uh daniel defense
that they had a uh advertisement which i then found on their website
uh the but you can't see the face but uh clearly a young child is my guess is uh
four or five years old with a semi-automatic rifle
on his lap and uh
and uh you know just resting there and he has a t-shirt that says a rascal on it
that seems to diminish or kind of make light of or kind of suggest something very different about
what it means to own or possess a and a semi-automatic rifle but then even
more remarkable is the statement that goes along with that you know together with the advertisement
train up a child in the way he should go train up a child in the way he should go
and when he is old he will not depart from it
start them early with semi-automatic rifles
so here's a company a business trying to promote the
sale of their rifles so this is not neces i don't know if
they're operating out of some kind of strange idea of compassion for our society
but it seems to me like they're operating under wanting to make business wanting to sell
and trying to hook people in and so the momentum of some of the
economic forces in the society that's advertising
a culture of violence
how do we do something different where does that come from
so in the in the description of the first precept the kind of the little bit longer description of it
one abstains from killing
one lays down weapons and swords
a modest compassionate
dwelling with care for the welfare of all beings
so it isn't just killing there's more that's involved with much more that's involved and these are
beautiful qualities i'm inspired by some people who put down their weapons
throw them away for me
that creates a different culture a culture of people who are not going to
succumb to fear greed or conceit or arrogance
and one of the worst ways of i think of responding to the violence in
the world is to allow the fear that it elicits to get the
upper hand in such a way that we go out and buy another gun
then we just kind of perpetuate more there is a
story from japan or a historical event maybe it's slightly interpretive the way
i'm going to present it to you but uh in the somewhere i don't know when in
this the fifth sixth century in in japan
uh there were in the in the val in the valley that's surrounded by mountains
that's now kyoto they were building buddhist temples and there was a capital
and uh and there was this um idea that evil spirits forces
would be coming out of the northeast corner of that valley down the mountains and somehow come and harm
the capital so to protect the capital
they built a buddhist a temple up there in the northeast kind of like
and they would do rituals and practices and somehow have the dharmic protection
and that monastery grew and developed to be one of the biggest monasteries in japan
over the centuries at some point they became so big it became like i think it was probably also
like a landlord you know like a big estate and
and uh they had uh some kind of monks i don't know exactly what kind of monks they were
who were soldiers and at some point
that was the evil force that came out of the northeast down to kyoto
to attack kyoto to take over so it was a it was a self-fulfilling
prophecy that there's danger let's protect us with the
let's have monks up there who can harm themselves and be soldiers and and it became so powerful
that that came around so it's a kind of a
you know i don't know if we want to take too much of a lesson from that but certainly an example
of uh sometimes living with fear and
uh off you know in kind of in a reactive mode
can elicit the very thing that we're trying to avoid
a more contemporary statement of this is uh
saying what i'm trying to say here today is from martin luther king
the ultimate weakness of violence is that it is a descending spiral
begetting the very thing it seeks to destroy instead of diminishing evil it
multiplies it through violence you murder the hater
but you do not murder hate in fact violence merely increases hate
returning violence for violence multiplies violence adding deeper darkness to a night
already devoid of stars darkness cannot drive out darkness
only light can do that hate cannot drive out hate only love can
do that
so i don't know you know there's all kinds of things being said now and
and almost every time there's some mass shooting like [Applause]
many of the same things get said about what should happen and
analysis of our culture and our society and that's
it's it's kind of a kind of this is very sad to kind of think that here we're
saying the same thing over the repetition of this is kind of phenomenal so i don't want to repeat some of the
cultural ideas societal ideas that are so common they said
but i i do feel inspired to evoke
the importance of non-harming and not killing in a buddhist life
and that learning how to do this in a wise way
learning how to do this so that we can protect ourselves better that way
than we can through violence
it's not an obvious and easy thing to naively say you know we should be non-violent
when there are dangers in this world it doesn't work but are there ways resources
that we can do to prepare ourselves and have other responses that come out of our
compassion that help us be safe help us live well
help us not perpetuate fear not perpetuate fear despair
or sense of hopelessness with all this and one of the reasons why
to do this is to
is to radiate from ourselves hopefully a cultural change
so much of what's this uh you know the the roots of violence
in this country as we see some of it comes from hate
some of it like with this uh last one in the school shooting in texas
this 18 year old who committed this horrendous
killings he was bullied apparently he had a stutter and a lisp
and other things and he had a mother who was a drug addict and and it probably had a very difficult
life you know and bullying is horrible especially if you're already at home
have a difficult life and no place of refuge
so the movements of bullying is not that something to be taken lightly
i've had parents who tell me that they went to the school to try to deal with the bullying of their
child at school and and the principals were not that interested in doing anything
but look you know we have to respond but how do we respond kindly
what happens we've had correctional systems
that you know put people in jail and they become worse in jail than they were when
they before they went in because of how terribly and disrespectfully they're treated we don't
call it bullying by the guards but the guards can treat people horrendously
i met a man when i was in san quentin who had spent 24 years in solitary confinement
can you believe that that's possible in this in california in a state prison 24
years and uh and so you know to perhaps perpetuate
and and the very system that's supposed to be a correctional system doesn't correct it makes things worse
so to um but what do we do and what we do as buddhists
among the many things you can do but is to really appreciate and find a
way to love certainly others but love non-violence
love not causing harm love it because
it protects you it protects the best that's in you that protects something that's wonderful
and beautiful and rich and and satisfying and and worth worth
coming from a way that provides a meaningful life that doesn't depend
on things which are relatively superficial but comes in like from a heart that's
full and and satisfied or delighted and
rich to do this practice not just to restrain
from love restraint from killing but as the rest of the
teaching goes uh to be certain kind of modesty i'm not clear
exactly what that is but what got some kind of modesty compassion
and care for the welfare of everyone
the uh it's interesting that the the buddhas presented kind of an analysis of
how rulers can care for people
it's an ancient myth that the buddha kind of maybe he
invented it he just he composed it but it involved
the decay of society when the rulers do not care for everyone equally
and this is such an important idea that everyone should be get treated equally everyone should be given
the same opportunities and it's the role of the government to make sure that happens
and the way that this myth goes is that there were a whole series of kings
hereditary kings who were born and ruled for many years and
and the custom was they would always go when they first became king and get advice from
wise people from wise religious people and others
and their and the teachings that they received was was to live
to live by the dharma and and one of the ways that the dharma means outside of buddhism which is the
meaning here it means just justice to live
or to live to to rule justly to rule fairly which i interpret to mean
um treating everyone equally giving everyone equal opportunities
which uh is still not the case in this country
and uh the passage goes like this
so these wise people will tell the king yourself depending on the dhamma
honoring it revering it cherishing it and doing homage to it and venerating it
have dhamma as your badge and banner acknowledging the dhamma as your master
you should establish guard award and protect
everyone your household your troops your people
everyone's on long list including animals and birds the first task of uh the rulers is to
protect everyone but this thing about the dhamma dharma
is uh it's not this doesn't this in this context doesn't mean buddhism
but it means kind of a natural law it means justice it means fear affairs in the fairness
um it's uh uh and so they
the king is supposed to rule based on dhamma not on their own wishes their own
desires you'll see this becomes important later uh let no
uh non-dharma prevail in your kingdom non-dharma means
injustice here in all the different ways that can mean let no injustice prevail in your kingdom
and to those who have nothing provide them
for those who don't have anything provide provide for them provide for them property probably so
that they can take care of themselves and whatever religious people there are
in your kingdom who have renounced the life of sensual
infatuation and are devoted to forbearance and
gentleness each one taming themselves
each one calming themselves and each one striving to the end of craving
if from time to time they should come to you and consult you as to
at the time they should come to you and consult you as to what is wholesome and what is
unwholesome in other words take advice from some of
the people who do a lot of practice and have a whole different set of values uh
don't consult with the people who manufacture assault rifles
consult with the dalai lama
and uh and and who can teach you those things
that will will in the long run uh
lead to welfare and happiness not to harm and sorrow you should listen
to them so this is the advice that king got and so for many generations that's what they
did until one king kind of forgot to do that forgot to
consult with when he first became king but finally the ministers came and got
him and said you have to listen to this so he heard this this advice
and so he did set up to guard and protect others
however he did not care for the people who are in need
the people who had no property and to hit the way of taking care of themselves he didn't provide them with property so
they could and uh and as a result
became rife with the spread of poverty a person took what was not given thus
committing what was called theft the king arrested them the person
and after a little short trial the person admitted to having stolen
the king gave him some property here take care of yourself and your
family this way but the other people who are poor
but wow that's all i have to do is steal and then i'll get so there's stealing began
and that and the king very quickly said wait a minute this doesn't work the people keep
stealing so instead he um he killed them
and punished them and with punishment like that then
the people took up weapons themselves
and with weapons themselves they started killing each other and other people and so violence spread through the realm and
things society deteriorated dramatically so this is a kind of a mythic story of
origin but the origin here the mythic story begins the decay of society
begins when those who are ruling
are not treating everyone equally not giving everyone equal opportunity through property and
something to to live and have a successful life and so people become
poor and of course when they're starving they steal and when they steal then i said of
course that you it sounds like it began with a good idea to give them something
but it was already too late it set up a very strange dynamic where
people other people started not to steal and then violence and all that
so this spiral of violence violence begets violence as martha the king said
non-violence does it beget non-violence not harming does it get non-harming
i'm sure you could find ex situations where that's not the case
i'm sure you can find examples of where violence does not not beget violence
but the tendency is that non-violence begets non-violence
that non-violence comes from this deeper place inside can come from this deeper place inside not from
fear and non-violence out of fear doesn't really work either but can we find a place within
can we clarify our hearts enough
so that we're in touch with something that's an inner wealth
an inner place of peace and satisfaction and inspiration
when we feel we've resolved our wounds resolved our
conflicts resolved our our fears and despairs
it's possible to resolve them it's possible to settle we should not succumb to the belief
that how we see the world through fear how we see the world through despair and anger
how we see the world through greed or hatred
gives us an accurate view of what the world is like it doesn't
so if we think that it's accurate then we will
only perpetuate that very view it supports that view
strengthens it but it's not accurate the view of the world
through love and compassion is that a more accurate view
it doesn't have to be that has its own problems sometimes
especially if it's enforced like a surface thing like i'm supposed to do this
where i think really makes a huge difference is doing something like meditation
that allows all the shoulds and all the kind of even like a lot of the
structures of our thinking to get quiet and peaceful
to resolve the challenges of our hearts to get quiet in the heart or peaceful in
the heart so that when we when we encounter the world
we're encountering it from this place inside where something resonates something different can happen
i don't know what i don't know all the different ways we'll respond from the heart
but it'll be much healthier than responding from the surface the
reactive way and so this this to be inspired
by the horrendous things that go on in our society to change society to find ways to
promote non-harming in our society is one of the great tasks of a life
but before we could do that i think to really do the work in ourselves
to find a way to be an exemplar
of a life that's motivated by non-fear by non-hatred
by non-despair and non-greed
so that the most the most the most wondrous qualities of our heart
have a chance to be shared in the world that we live in
it's heartbreaking to have
all this hatred and despair and anger and violence that goes on in this
country but in that heartbreak don't despair
use it as as a powerful catalyst encouragement
to do your work to do your practice to resolve the issues of your heart
so that your heart can come forth in beautiful response
to what this world needs and a response that's clearly and obviously one
that never will harm anyone let's live in a world where non-harming
is understood to be one of the greatest gifts we can we can
give so thank you
and if some of you would like to have some
discussion about this or with anything else i invite you to come and pick up a folding chair from the cafta just
outside there and we'll meet in a few minutes in the parking lot and we can maybe take off
our masks and and have a little sit in the circle and have a little conversation if you're like for maybe 20
30 minutes or something so thank you