good to see everyone why don't we go ahead and get started
together on the meditation welcome if you're just joining and
welcome also if you've been here for a few minutes it's nice to see you in the chat
but now settling in and if you're comfortable doing so you can
close your eyes just allow the body and the mind to
settle into each other bringing the Mind into the present
moment this location this time
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
maybe even feeling the body settle back slightly I know I have a way of Leaning forward a
little bit when I'm on the computer sometimes
so just settling back letting the body be upright and stable
and softening the muscles of the face the eyes the jaw
inviting some Eaves through the neck the shoulders
arms and hands
down into the Torso the chest area
heart area releasing the diaphragm
and letting the belly area be softer
often a fair amount of Habitual holding throughout the Torso and just inviting
some ease
down through the hip joints feeling the contact with whatever we're sitting on
letting the body release into that and be supportive
and softening the legs and the feet
and then again broadening the attention to be aware of the whole body in the
sitting posture or whatever posture you're in you could be lying down or even standing
feeling the body as it is
and being at ease with how the body is maybe it's tired or has some pain
that's okay just invite ease in the mind about how
the body is
and then also sensing how the mind is
is there uh dominant emotion right now
or mood
how's the energy level was the mind a little dull or tired
or is it a little agitated from a lot of thinking
foreign
noticing that as we do in this practice we are aware of
what's happening in body and mind so there's mindfulness a simple knowing of what's Happening as
it's happening and sensing in the mind
what mindfulness feels like right now
and in this meditation we will gradually
praying more and more into our awareness
there's always a lot happening at the scent stores but we only
pay attention to part of it so it will be
exploring the whole range of what we can know
so beginning simply with sound
can hear the sound of my voice
maybe there's birds or the sound of other people in the
house
sound of cars
just opening to the field of sound
a sound without needing to have opinions about each sound that we
hear
one quality of sound is that we don't know what sound is going to
come next we don't have much control that can be useful
to just sit and be receptive
foreign
now also opening attention to the sensations of the breath
breathing in and out as the body becomes more
still even a little bit often the breath is the largest movement
that we feel I'm just tuning into
a simple sensations of in and out breathing
and if you also hear sounds that's fine but it's it's also fine just to turn the
attention to the breath
we can notice how the breath is a whole series of Sensations
almost like a kaleidoscope
cascading through the body
slightly different each time the way snowflakes are different
so like sound there's kind of a varied landscape of the sensations of breathing
foreign and opening the awareness further
to include all the little Sensations throughout the body
we might first notice that the breath isn't just in the physical lungs
that may feel like the breath energy spreads throughout the body
all through the Torso and even into the arms and legs and head
or if that isn't quite evident we also have the touch sensations of the contact
points the seed against the cushion the legs or feet on the floor
perhaps the hands are touching each other or the legs
there are a number of other physical Body Sensations
that we can include in our growing range of awareness
and as we tune in with a generally
receptive even curious awareness there can be a sense of ease
for just exploring the territory of Sensations
nothing needs to be changed
you know as we continue to open the awareness
we can bring in the field of emotions we're now moving into their mind
you can sense if there's a mood overall
sadness or appreciation or interest
or there may not be a dominant mood may just be kind of neutral
and you can sew we can also have short-term emotions passing through
a tickle of amusement adhering something
or a little bit of annoyance at persistent pain
the emotions too or like a landscape varied
changing they're actually likened in the
teachings to wins
flowing through
and as with the other experiences we just include them as something else to
be noticed in mindfulness foreign
and further Opening Our awareness we can include the whole field of
thoughts and volitions very related to emotions
but still a broadening so we're allowing even thought to arise
and pass if it's there and just be noticed as thought
not so much the content of the thoughts but the process of thinking
if it's there maybe it isn't
one more thing to notice in the field of experience it's part of Being Human
can help to imagine the mind as a big broad space
or sky in which all these different experiences
can be seen The Sounds coming and going
various Body Sensations emotions thoughts
all of them can arise shift and change
and pass away in this broad space of the Mind
and we don't have any preference for one thing over another whatever wants to come and whatever
wants to go
if we find ourselves wishing for something to come or wishing or something to go
than the wish is what we notice oh there's there's a volition or a wishing in the
mind one more thing to notice
and then one more thing that we can notice is the quality of knowing in the mind
there are all these things that we know experiences
and there is also the knowing
can we notice even the knowing part of the Mind
so there's all the things that come and go in the sky and there's the sky also
the sky itself
that is the whole Space of Human Experience
if it's not so easy to see the knowing it's possible to ask the question what
knows this we don't exactly get an answer but there
may be kind of a shift in experience how was this
and then we can rest with that shift
so let go of directing your practice it's all just happening
there's a saying in Zen the great way is not difficult for those who have no
preferences [Music]
foreign
[Music]
thank you
a few minutes the meditation will be over
and the conditions will shift
and yet it will be the same set of experiences
sounds various other sensations of the body
including seeing various movements in the mind emotions
thoughts volitions to do things and the knowing of those things
because the mind has awareness just the proportion is going to change
and it's interesting to consider could we carry this sense of
inclusiveness of wholeness into
the changed conditions of being more in the world
and what benefit might that offer if we came with a sense of open
receptiveness we'll still take actions volitions will
happen things may come about but somehow that's determined by the
needs of the moment
sometimes it's said that it's not that we're going to become free
it's that the world is going to become free of us and so our experience goes on
but there's not so much interference or obstruction from
me needing for things to happen a certain way me needing my preferences to be taken
care of it's a whole different way of being
one that serves everyone ourself included but the whole situation that
we're in becomes what we serve
foreign
[Music]
desire and letting go and I've been asked to spell the poly
words so here they are the one that I used for sense desire
comma is K long a so that's an a with a
bar over it m a comma different from the word for this the
poly word for the Sanskrit Karma which is k-a-m-m-a with two M's and no long a so K long a m
a and then the word for renunciation is Nick comma
n e k k h a m m a
so there you go you can see they look slightly different but they are somewhat related
Okay so we've seen that there are different kinds of Desire some rather coarse and generally
unwholesome and some that are more refined and and that the associated
happiness with getting various things is also coarser or more
refined so we know that material Pleasures are not as deep or as elevated
anyhow you Orient the scale as the well-being that comes from ethics
Goodwill and states of meditative calm but most importantly wholesome desires
are onward leading they help develop the path and so the Buddha encouraged us to
move along the path by asking us to notice how the mind can become more more refined through letting
go of for this coarser however we have to be careful not to get
the idea that this is a linear progression and Liberation is simply the
upper limit of loftiness or maybe even some Transcendent realm
that's far loftier than what we can imagine here on Earth
um this kind of view is easy to develop actually but it it isn't helpful in the
end I tend to allow ideas of Superior and inferior and it allows there to be a
certain ego identification with refinement So today we're going to talk about what
is the movement toward freedom it's natural at some point to Aspire to
spiritual Freedom you know what if we decide that we want to let go of all forms of suffering and we want to take
the happiness of letting go all the way but then we encounter a seeming paradox
what if what if we want to stop wanting can we wish for Freedom From Desire does
that make sense so we'll get to that and we'll get to that in a moment
I just want to mention a couple of other quotes from the sutas because it's good to know up front that renunciation
prepares the mind for awakening it does actually say that in the teachings
so for example here's one um desire and greed for the eye ear nose
tongue body or mind so all six senses is a Corruption of the mind when a
practitioner has given up this corruption in these six cases their mind inclines to renunciation a mind imbued
with renunciation is declared to be capable of directly knowing anything
that can be realized and then when a practitioner has four
things their practice is guaranteed and they have laid the groundwork for ending
the defilements which means Awakening what for thoughts of renunciation Good
Will and harmlessness and Right View when a practitioner has these four
things their practice is guaranteed and they have laid the groundwork for ending the defilements
so we can feel assured that renunciation in those texts it was in a comma
poises the mind for deeper wisdom and realization
in fact the attitude of renunciation even persists after Awakening so um
here's another one when a monk is an arahond who has reached fulfillment which means that
they're fully awakened they are dedicated to renunciation it is because
of the ending of greed the ending of hatred and the ending of delusion that
they are dedicated to renunciation okay so we're convinced that what we're
talking about here really is integral to Freedom but if we want to take letting go all
the way we're going to have to look a little bit more carefully at what's actually going on with letting go
so as we mature on the path we start to experience that there is a distinction
between volitional letting go and some kind of letting go that's not
volitional so there are many times in the practice where we see some reactivity in the mind
and we consciously that is volitionally steer in some other direction in fact
just recently I was fatigued at the end of a long day and I felt my mind inclining toward
irritation with some sound that was going on outside and I brought up the
reminder that the sound is impermanent you know this irritating sound is not
going to last even though it was trying to irritate me while I was fatigued so that's choosing wisdom in order to
counter aversion and it was easy to let go of the irritation and kind of elevate the Mind
by remembering impermanence but I did feel like I was doing that and
so I can you know at times I can carry in my mind the idea that I'm reshaping my mind by making choices like this and
that these choices become available because I'm practicing mindfulness you know that's that's a common way to think
and it's true to a certain degree but there's also we can also begin to
experience that there's release that simply comes about when the conditions
are there and the mind is seen clearly it's fairly common for mindfulness
practitioners to suddenly realize that they're behaving differently without trying
so you know maybe for the last two decades you've been habitually tense
when talking to certain relative you knew that maybe you were tense even before that but you didn't know it but
you feel physically tense when you're talking to someone um and then one day you become aware
that you're talking with them and your body feels relaxed you know you didn't consciously practice
with body awareness with this relative you didn't attend workshops on social
anxiety or cultivating Equanimity but when you examine your mind you realize
that some defensiveness is simply gone you don't feel any threat from this
relative as you used to they're just as they are and you can be with that how did that happen you know
don't you have to actively work on the issues that you want to let go of actually no not all of them
and we can only go so far on the path if we want to be the ones doing it
so as we let go of the unhelpful forms of Desire grasping and holding on and
even pursuing some of the normal sense pleasures of human life we can tap into a powerful movement of
release that is not done by us it is a movement toward and that was the general
term that I'm calling desire this week this tendency of the human mind to be able to move toward things we feel that
but we realize that we're not the ones doing it and so we begin to suspect and
to actually see that those beautiful qualities that we were wanting or
practicing toward there seemed to come about naturally in the wake of releasing the unwholesome
habits so I meta emerges when ill will is
released and maybe at first we can cultivate meta a little bit we can breathe some life
into it we can bolster it a little bit but if we look carefully we start to see this deeper
process at work where when we release ill will it's actually just that meta is there
so sometimes it feels like the Heart Is by itself dropping painful habits and
sometimes it feels like the heart is moving toward the Deep peace of not
grasping they're kind of like the front and back of the hand whether we're moving away from suffering or toward the
end of suffering but either way there's a growing sense that it's not a willful
creation that we're doing I once told Gil at the near the
beginning of my practice that I had had heard that desire was the cause of suffering but I still had the desire for
freedom this is actually a very common question among Dharma students and Gill
said what most Dharma teachers say in some version he said oh you can have
that desire Kim until it's the last one so it's fine to want the more elevated
aspects of life like ethics and compassion and wisdom but bit by bit we
have to drop even those lofty Desires in order to move move fully into those
States so take compassion for example I would say that we become fully
compassionate when we're no longer striving to let go of Cruelty when we're
no longer aiming to generate compassion and when we don't view ourselves as
being a compassionate person we can have some degree of compassion with all of those things but it becomes full when
compassion is just natural and unself-conscious so gradually along this path and it is
gradual we gradually concede our volitional desires to this more
non-relational movement of the Dharma and then maybe the last aspirate the
last thing to go is this aspiration of the heart for complete freedom
that we can sort of incline the mind in that direction but then it's no longer up to us
so I'm I want to read a quote from Aya Kemah who was a wonderful
um bikuni Western bikuni she was German and she was born yesterday on August 25th in
1923 so she would have been 99. this is from her
trying to achieve something in the spiritual world is just as foolish as
trying to achieve something in the material world there is nothing to achieve there's only letting go as we
let go more and more of ego identification desires and support
systems Bliss will arise
so it's interesting um you know what do we do practically with these teachings on renunciation I
want to kind of Bring It Back Down To What We can each work with
I would say that please only let go of what makes sense
for you to let go that will be fine the volitional renunciation of various
material things that we realize we don't need and various unwholesome mental
habits if we work on those that will gradually help build momentum toward
this non-volitional letting go and that is what carries the heart beyond even the wholesome even the
Beautiful to what is free so in a sense the deepest happiness comes when we no longer want even
happiness but we don't have to worry about that and we just we just let go of the next
thing that feels like it's limiting us and the process will go on I have so
much faith in it so to kind of tie things up
desire which is this movement toward that we have naturally in the mind that
can help us walk the path only one part of this broad space of
Desire is harmful and then there are these more elevated desires that lead to
deeper forms of happiness and that makes them onward leading because the mind is motivated to keep moving toward refined
happiness but to continue deepening we'll have to let go of volition and ideas of
achievement like I have came and said so true Letting Go comes about without
our help in a sense eventually we get squeezed into releasing all of our
desires so it's a process that makes sense I would say as you do it there's no need
to manufacture it or to push ahead or to try to let go of something that we don't
understand why we have to let go of it each Insight that we have and each little thing that we release
helps us go on to the next thing so it's actually kind of a path of trust of
trusting that desire and letting go do form an onward leading process that will
eventually take the mind all the way and every little bit that we're working
on whatever we're doing right now in that process is beautiful and is helping
us to feel more free in this moment and is helping others around us as we grow
and develop in the Dharma so this is kind of one lens that we can
put onto the path of Awakening it's about desire and letting go and I hope the journey this week has has been good
and that you know may it continue for all of us so thank you very much