greetings friends greetings and good morning from mountain view
california where it's cool and cloudy um
mountain view california and seated olonyland and greetings um to all of you
whatever time zone you're in lovely to be joining
[Music] you each other in this moment in time to practice
meditation and and share the dharma so
it's always lovely to hear the greetings on chat as they're going
as they're being added one by one so so this week we're exploring today we're
exploring the mind's body and um
we continue the exploration today noticing how
the uh perception of our body can [Music]
be different there's a different sense of the energy body not just that the perception of the body is different but
but some shifts can happen energetically too um as we pay attention differently so
different ways of paying attention in the body not just places uh
to pay attention to the breath as we discussed uh on tuesday that was but also the way
the way we pay attention or what quality we choose to attend to
with our mind can have impacts about um
on how we perceive and also what arises maybe also what's called energy channels
in the body shifting and changing and the perceptions so
so without further ado let's practice together
inviting you to arrive to arrive in your body
in this moment in time however the body is right now
whether the body is feeling good tired agitated peaceful
greeting reading the body with your mind just as it is
with openness with kindness
and as we land and arrive
turning turning the attention inviting the attention
to receive the sensations of
the body contacting the vision the cushion and the floor
the lower part of the body the sense of groundedness
contact with the earth
i'm releasing [Music] any tension or tightness in the upper
body
forehead jaw
face
neck shoulders
arms and hands let them be heavy and rest
chest upper back lower back abdomen
with the next out breath releasing any tension holding
but awareness be curled up in the breath in the abdomen
comfortable soothed nowhere to go nothing to do
right now
then just sit and be breathed
receiving the breath awareness receiving the breath of the abdomen
now as we're paying attention to the breath in the abdomen in this moment
feeling grounded in the body
feet said bones
connected to the earth
see yourself see the sense of a brightness that you're sitting with
it's not that you have to create it it's already there just bringing attention to it
as if there was a vertical axis
or rather bringing the tension to the vertical axis
connecting your your head
to the middle of your chest to your heart center
your abdomen [Music] groin area
all the way down down and up
from the inside
the sense of verticality uplift both uplift energetically
and also downwards direction connection connected
to the earth while rootedness
as if you both have roots into the earth through this verticality
and connected to the heavens
or the sky proverbial heavens the sky
so that you can relax into the verticality
it holds you it grounds you
there's a structure so thoughts aren't fleeting here and
there and everywhere like getting whiplash there's a sense of a brightness connection
to the earth and up to the sky
through your heart through your heart center
now letting sensation
or awareness of sensations fill your body
not just that the breath is moving up and down
but filling your whole body
on its own don't let it be effortful
as if your feet are breathing your legs
your abdomen your hands
your back your chest
your cheeks the back of your head
sense of fullness of the body
sitting and being breathed
receiving the breath
the whole body bellowing with the breath
in and out like a sphere a round sphere
expanding contracting [Music] bellowing
and what if the boundary of your body wasn't at your skin didn't end there
but a few inches beyond your skin
it's porous more space more space
imagining this breath being breathed received by the body
bellowing further out into the space sense of
expansiveness
you don't have to push it out make sure you're not pushing it out
effortfully just perceiving oh yeah
there's more expansiveness than i realized look at that
expensiveness all around
and then a few more inches
further out
the breath and the mind's body expansive
received pervading into space
let yourself relax into the spaciousness
relax into it spacious easeful
all around the breath
bellowing and maybe at some point even the edges
completely disappear
the edges of this orb
or above the body
the breath
pervading expansively
into space
space all around
and along with the breath being breathed in
breathed out expansively
the edges of the orb disappearing of the sphere disappearing
can there be
your kindness your good will accompanying
this expansive breath
just shining naturally for yourself and all around
relaxing into an expansive sphere of the breath intertwined with metal
and as we bring this sit to close together
letting there be a spreading expansive boundless
expressing of our good will our kindness our meta
for all beings everywhere including ourselves
intertwined with each breath
so that each breath each moment of our life is intertwined
with goodness kindness service
to benefit ourselves and the world
as best as we can offer
trusting that we're doing our best
may all beings everywhere
know their own goodness
wake up to the goodness within and all around
them expansively may all beings everywhere including
ourselves be free
hello friends greetings once again
so [Music] so we are exploring this week
the mind's body together and this
sense of um
this this and this as i mentioned especially on the first day
the way we pay attention the way we perceive we attend to and where we
bring not just how but where we bring attention to we touch with our awareness with our
knowing places in the body not just the places but how we do it in
the body it can make shifts
in our perception in our body perception in our body mind perception arise
and it's actually quite um
flexible there's there's a lot of flexibility and it's important as practitioners
to know where we bring attention to how things can shift and move and the results that
they can have in our perception in our my physical perception and in our
mind's perception of the body and the perception of our mind
[Music] and connecting this a little bit perhaps to
maybe chinese and other energy medicine uh traditions
um [Music] either physically touching or bringing
energy bringing minds attention to a point can have impact can have impact
and a lot of times these arise in meditation and we may not actually know um
well that's interesting how did that come up so it's good to know that yes these are there are some laws in the
body in the mind even if we don't fully understand them
so though um so exploring exploring the mind's body
or the energetic sense of the body this week and and today the exploration that we
did we did uh two different explorations and and let me spell them out for you
the first invitation the first exploration i invited you and again these are very quick brief
just you know two different instructions fit into 30 minutes that's that's very brief so i i suggest that you actually
explore these on your own time
later now more expansive sits um so the first one the first invitation was to um
explore what i'm calling or what it's called a sense of verticality
so this sense of uh being connected
to the earth through your sit bones and your abdomen your heart center your head there's a
sense of sitting in verticality the sounds of uprightness as if there was a vertical pull
the energetic pole going through your hole this cylinder going through your whole body and connected
ah there's sense of spaciousness and there's a sense of well-rootedness and and feeling the breath feeling your body
around this upright vertical cylinder and
of course you can see what um impact that has for you and for many
for some or to say can and so so that you continue to become curious and see what impact it has for
you but it can have the sense of both grounding feeling grounded and also
feeling upright being awake and yet grounded at the same time there's just some
beautiful energetic feeling to it and the mind can actually be quiet
the thoughts thoughts can be quite um still quieted there's a sense of
spaciousness and grounding at the same time emphasizes verticality and sense of
uprightness which also sense of um maybe ethical uprightness it can come
with this sense of verticality it just it's a lovely way to sit a lovely way to go through the world and explore
both being grounded and and uplifted so that was the sense
of verticality but we uh that i invited you to explore
and then we switched to another way of exploring the body and that is and the
the energy body and the breath in the body and that was imagining that the breath
filling out the whole body first we start there and this sense of ordnance the sense of roundedness so the breath
filling out the whole body and then and then i invited you to
imagine that the border of your skin the border of your body was a few inches uh
further than your skin so the sense of expansiveness the sense of spaciousness of the breath bellowing and
then spaciousness and more spaciousness and more spaciousness and at some time
again through practice the sense of border can completely dissolve and there's just the sense of
complete spaciousness um in in the mind's body and the energy body
that the breath is moving through and and what this can bring for many is a sense
of peace and just expansive peacefulness that can arise and and um
[Music] and spaciousness a lot of spaciousness you know the space element part of the
four elements the space element can be quite present here sense of spaciousness and peace
and this also for some people who practice open awareness this can be
also a good support a good support for open awareness or actually open awareness can lead to
this sometimes and um and similarly as i invited you at
the very end to add some meta just not not to push it out but just
imagine that your this spaciousness of expansiveness of the breath
has some good will um some good will some kindness that's just like a light that's intertwined
with this expansiveness and and similarly this um just as it can be in the nice support for open awareness
practice can be a great support this way of seeing the body and perceiving
the mind's body great support for meta practice if you're doing um radiating
meta this can be really lovely support for that as well
just really getting to the practice in a very expansive way where also the self
can disappear so all these practices are connected so
and of course it can be very expensive and beautiful just in its own right to really settle especially if there's
a lot of anxiety or or fear present just giving it a lot of space a lot of
no boundaries it's often when we have anxiety it feels like
a um a wild horse or a wild ram running
around like in our chest so and if we try to contain it and really put up the barn doors like
it can can even it feels like it wants to kick against the barn doors and it's just
the sense of anxiety can become worse so in this way taking the doors down all the
all the boundaries down and just giving space giving space to the breath giving
space to the sensations to be expansive expansive expansive
ah a sense of relief and expansiveness can come from that
so these are two different ways you can explore the energy body and
delighted to to read for some of you this even in this short period
never felt so light before etc etc
yeah wonderful tingling wellness
yeah just very different ways of
yeah so so thank you all thank you for your
practice and and again i'm trusting there are many more comments here but that's uh
yeah it's it's hard to both teach and and and attend to to all the moving comments at the same time so
so thank you so much for your practice for your dedication for
being here supporting yourself supporting each other
and [Music] may our practice
be cause and conditioning for for awakening for ourselves and all
things everywhere take good care and see you tomorrow to conclude the series
take care