so good morning uh good afternoon welcome uh to to all of you
i see there's a watermark on the uh
the video um where i'm i'm running the youtube and so using my zoom account and
uh david geffen gave i think a quarter billion dollars to
ucla and so you get your name on imc's zoom feed uh for that kind of sum
uh anyway um happy to be uh to be with you
to be sitting together and um um
yeah maybe i'll just say say a word before we sit um
a mentor of mine we'll do some some we'll settle in do some
meta practice loving kindness practice mentor of mine um
said matthew there's a difference between
kindness and niceness and you're being nice
so um yeah meta is not
niceness you know it's a deeper kindness and it's not pretending
it's not pretending we have to be very careful about
pretending to feel one thing when we're feeling another in our practice
because um when we pretend it erodes some confidence in
our path in ourselves our heart is very sensitive to the
misalignment of of pretending
and so we're never asked to pretend yeah we're never asked to pretend
um this is about um
an authentic encounter with our own heart and there's some way to connect with
what's actually here in an authentic way there was some one
of the brahmaviharas is here for you yeah one of them is always here for you
and so there's never a need to pretend to turn kindness into niceness or
something like this so um
let's uh let's sit together
it's a spirit of kindness towards your own body
the astounding number of things it's doing right
in this moment even if our attention goes
to uh what feels like it's doing wrong
one of my teachers said the your body your body
is done
generosity some kind of gift
your body is donna
maybe this begins to open your heart
as we settle breathe as we do his first couple minutes
um that is love in the face of goodness
so we can attune
to our own our own goodness
it's not grandiose or something the goodness
is we might detect is nothing we would want to brag about it's a goodness that
softens our heart maybe it's a goodness that you overlook
always in yourself
i promise this is not a self-indulgent
kind of uh affirmation
the more deeply we sense in and appreciate and abide in our
own goodness more obvious that becomes in the eyes of
others
so we consider our goodness
maybe rest in the kind of heart center your chest
and pulsating feeling life
of maybe a little bit of warmth
a little softening
a little bit of love
and just stay with the signs of love and care and softening
so when we silently whisper to ourselves
we would be happy
it's really not a prayer about some future that may come
it is a way of touching into the heart right now
of ringing a bell and then listening to the reverberations in your body
softening your body making your
body more porous
we are moved by our own goodness
moved by the innocence of our own longing to be happy
foreign
maybe it's useful to use a words
images
maybe happy
i be safe protected
man live with ease
we start to drop some of the vigilance
the vigilance of patrolling ourself the vigilance
of arrogance the vigilance of self-hatred
we drop all of that
maybe right now it's safe enough
to be moved by your own goodness
to abide in this kind of quiet love
you don't offer yourself this meta because of something
you just offer that
foreign
so um it's nice too nice to practice with you
you know i i know i said ever pretend in your practice something
like that but then you know what i thought of i thought of carol wilson saying
fake meta is better than real aversion any day
yeah that stuck with me that's true yeah
but um kind of kidding aside uh i do
feel like we want to be careful about pretending and sometimes the brahmavahara realm
feels like a zone where we're being enlisted to pretend something
and the heart rebels against that sense of in authenticity
and so the encouragement is to find find our own
ways like how can we have this really intimate encounter with the moment
and find ways of practicing that um that feel real alive true
so um the
the buddha said that um
suggested that that fear and wanting are two sides of the same coin
the coin of uh of clinging yeah and uh sometimes i don't i don't
like to kind of trot out neuroscience so often but sometimes i
read something that reminds me a lot of dharma
so the point is not to get the science exactly but to hear the resonance with
what this tradition offers is uh shelley warlow and um
her colleague ken barrage so motivational salience can occur with
either positive valence as incentive or negative valence as fear
and it's possible to flip the valence between the two forms under some
conditions despite being affectively opposite the
two may still share some neural and psychological features
normally both may engage mesolimbic systems including dopamine
signals in the nucleus accumbens consistent with an amygdala role in
bivalent positive and negative motivational salients
some neurons can respond to both aversive outcomes or rewarding outcomes or to their
predictive cues rather than strictly encoding only reward or fear per se some neurons might
integrate sensory information context and motivational state
to assign motivational salience with positive or negative valence
to particular targets making them either wanted or feared
wanting and fear they seem about as far apart as possible
but maybe they're closer siblings than they might
appear
um scientist k tai she says uh fear has an authoritarian
command over the rest of the brain [Music] and tiknot han said
fearlessness is the ultimate joy
and so meta practices heart practice is really um
about stepping out of wanting and stepping out of fear
and sometimes we step out of that and there's just love
but um but sometimes meta practice of course is um
we step out of wanting and fear by getting really close to it
so anxiety depends
uh on avoidance to some measure the medicine
around anxiety is actually to approach the feared experience we drain
the affective emotional charge from our anxiety and avoidance
by doing the opposite by moving towards and mindfulness
is one way of moving towards it's an approach
orientation all of mindfulness is an approach orientation
we permit our pain into awareness
but in a sense love is like the fullest approach we can
make with our pain with our love we get we get so
close to what is unresolved in our heart that we begin
to habituate to it and that pain loses some of its
electrical charge we start to uh
the the met uh actually starts to be a way of of digesting
digesting fear this was you know one of the the classical ways that that uh meta is
prescribed for fear
we're stepping out of of of fear and and out of uh
wanting or controlling right because we know there is attached
love you know a love that includes some measure of possessiveness
and and there's a love that is a pure giving
no controlling yeah and attach love that sounds bad in
buddhist spheres right but it's okay like we're gonna have to pick our spots i feel
as humans maybe especially as lay people people with with partners or children
parents and commitments some measure of
attachment is i think
inevitable i i saw a friend um i've known for
for many years now and i've known his daughter who's now 13 since since her birth
and um and i asked asked him you know how how are you
and he quoted i think it's susan orlean uh the writer
um he said um a parent is only as happy as their least
happy child and i don't even have kids but i know
enough to just be touched by that sentiment you
know okay yeah only as happy as a
least happy child you know some measure of uh
i don't know what we want to call that the complexities of these bonds these
karmically rich bonds with people that i don't think can be
purified of all clinging or something like that can we consent to that can we
bear that with grace
and and we cultivate
the love that is without conditions uh
that is um a warmth without control or possession
the warmth the kindness of of metta
which is a kind of simple friendliness and kindness while wishing
the proximate cause being seeing the goodness seeing goodness love in the
face of goodness
this is an image of a mother cow
gazing at her calf and
sometimes we're the mother cow sometimes with a cow
but we we sense goodness yeah there is well wishing
and just for me amidst this this kind of cycle of um
of grieving you know i've become so sensitive to
goodness like
just just little bits of it that i see in others you know
uh if i'm gonna cry that's what's gonna make me do it goodness is gonna make me
cry and um a phenomena in
in uh psychology known as moral elevation where witnessing
good witness and goodness yeah witnessing acts of moral beauty
inspires and elevates us and we become more devoted to goodness in seeing it we
become the kind of wholesome pro-social
um movement of our own heart is drawn out by witnessing it right we become very
this practice makes us very sensitive to goodness
and lovingkindness is being moved by your own goodness
it's being moved by it it's not the goodness we put on
our resume or something yeah and as i said in the the sid it's not
even like well i'll offer this love like because of yeah you get into the because
of and then there's always the contradictory whatever you know you get
into debates about worthiness and deserving and all this and it's like no no no not because of i'm just offering
care yeah being moved moved by your own goodness
and to abide in this is um very healing very healing and
not self-indulgent it will connect us more deeply with all beings
and a sense of of warmth of
radiating from our heart there's sometimes just so we get quiet there's
nothing but warmth there's nothing on the other side of our love and emerging from that emerging from
that it really dramatizes the pain of
hatred of divisiveness of separation of aversion
hatred becomes less and less tenable less and less terrible
and so sometimes metta is abiding in love and
sometimes it is lowering our our resistance bringing
love to what needs love because um the truth of dukkha
that needs to be mourned for a long time and that takes love
it really is um often
almost unbelievable that the young human is like this
being human is like this it's gonna take some love to open to
and and the meta practice it helps kind of
um sometimes we just cannot feel something until the love thaws out something in
our heart and so in these ways meta is is both a
it's a purification practice and it's a practice of cultivation
many many blessings of meta
so stop and um
yeah i wish you all um much uh much goodness today yeah
let us let us be attuned to the signs of goodness in ourselves and others
open our heart to that today okay thank you