so welcome welcome everyone and welcome anyone online watching
very happy to be here today my name is dawn neal and i'm a long time practitioner in this
i've been teaching for about 10 years and we're just going to sit together so
the invitation is to settle back
into a comfortable yet alert posture
it can be helpful to start with two or three intentional breaths
perhaps a bit deeper than normal
allowing any excess tension to flow outwards on the out breath
letting go on the out breathe
and allowing the breathing to return to normal whatever that is for you today
taking a moment to establish awareness establish mindfulness
in this body noticing the details of your posture
noticing sensations
warmth or cool
tension or relaxation
perhaps allowing acknowledgments of sound
and acknowledging any energy left over from what it took
to get to your meditation spot
and allowing the heart the mind to rest
to settle into whatever meditation anchor primary
object
feels most hospitable
perhaps the sensations of the body
especially the sensations of breathing
allowing thoughts of then were there to fade to the periphery
and settling into here into this
this moment
allowing your awareness to become intimate
with the felt sense at this moment
allowing sounds to come and go
sensations to come and go
creating each arising
what's this breath like this moment
inviting awareness to suffuse through the entire body
inviting the body to soften relax
if a sensation or sound or thought pulls the attention
away the suggestion is to gently
kindly acknowledge it
and allow the attention to settle back
riding waves of breath or sensation
or the general felt sense of being here
now
from time to time refreshing the awareness
noticing mindfulness perhaps re-emerging
or perhaps continuous and steady
either way appreciating the awareness of this moment
uh
for the last five minutes or so of this meditation
the invitation if the mindfulness awareness feels steady
is to take an internal step back
allowing everything to come and go
in a broad skylike awareness opening up
noticing whatever appears and goes away again
and in the last moment or two of this meditation
noticing any calm softness
perhaps a touch more attention or clarity or mindfulness
appreciating any benefits of this meditation
noticing taking it in
and then with that in your heart and mind calling to mind
the other people and other beings in your life
here in this room near your home
your neighborhood anyone get your own contact with
and see perhaps if it's possible to
generate the intention the resolve
to meet them with kind receptive appreciative awareness
to share the goodness of this practice
as you move through your life
[Music]
so welcome everyone morning
so i'm gonna start this talk with a story this is from the kind of fables um
the myths of early buddhism called the jataka tales
and it is the story it's sort of a story within a story
there's the buddha who is in a retreat with
several very senior monks and during the retreat
four or five of them experience full awakening and
before he comes to speak with them after they break the silence they're talking
and each of them was doing a different practice so some were meditating on the four
elements that some of you have heard about others are
practicing with breathing or different aspects of their experience like their senses eyes ears
nose taste and their experiences of awakening are
different and they're confused by this and they ask him when he comes
and he tells them this story that
in the distant past the king of varanasi had four princes
and in conversation with these princes
a certain sort of very unusual tree came up
and it was like a king sukka tree in pali but that would
roughly translate as a what do you call it tree right okay so it's kind of goofy whatever it
is and um he describes it a little bit to them and
they're all fascinated by the idea of seeing this tree
but you know princes are busy and you know even though they didn't have iphones they had full schedules so one
at a time at different times the charioteer took them to this distant forest
to see this tree and eventually maybe six months later a year
later they're in conversation again and this tree comes up and each of them describe how they saw
the tree and one says well it was kind of like a charred stump with just these
little green specks on it little buds and the other goes no no no we saw something different we saw
a tree with flame-like leaves all over it and yet another one said well
no i saw a brown tree with big whumpy fruit and then the last one was like no this
was like a shrub with these gorgeous flowers all over it and the
king just sort of looks at the princes and said why didn't any of you ask the charioteer
about what kind of conditions were at play around this tree that's the same tree
it's in different seasons with different amounts of water
and i like this story because what the buddha is pointing to by telling it to his monks is there are all these
different kinds of ways that awakening can show up and that practice shows up
and the experience can look different depending on how we're practicing
of the big awakening but also the little awakenings of awareness too right
so tonight i'm going to talk about one of these methods one of these practices or today this
morning i'm going to talk about one of these methods which is recognizing the many many different
forms that mindfulness mindful awareness or awareness can take i'm using those
terms synonymously so this is what the buddha calls the third
foundation of mindfulness and kind of shading into the fourth if that's not familiar to you you don't
have to track it but it's quality of our minds and quality of how we relate to what's in them basically
and just like the whatchamacallit tree awareness can show up very differently
depending on the different conditions and depending on what's being observed
whether it's breath or sound or emotion
can feel different it's kind of like um old landscape
painters understood this very well like the quality of light happening in a day
you don't notice it as much if it's just a cloud this sky right but if there's clouds
trees rocks houses fields the quality of light becomes apparent
through what it strikes the same is true of awareness and what we're aware of
so part of broadening and maturing
awareness practice mindfulness practice is recognizing all of these different forms that awareness can take
and i'm going to describe them as different experiences but but in
reality they all shade into each other they all overlap they're like a continuum even
and they're all good i'm going to go through them progressively but there's no need to
rank them because any complete moment of mindfulness is an opening
and a possibility into waking up
so broadly in the next few minutes i'm going to describe mindful awareness as
the tree with the buds with the weebs with the flowers and with the fruit and then i'm going to talk for
a few minutes about the forest so
moment-to-moment mindfulness is like those little buds on that tree
one breath at a time one sensation at a time
noticing each one in its particularity as it comes up and as it goes away
most of us begin to notice this process when we first start sitting meditation
and it can feel a little bit like labor to bring the mind back to it right
we can also notice another example of this is sensations which broadly might be
you know back pain for example like a spot in my back but when i really look closely it's all
these scintillating little star-like sensations coming and going and there's not actually a border around it
but just moving in and out coming and going
sometimes with moment-to-moment mindfulness little bursts of many moments in a row
will happen this sometimes happens when sitting right it feels like it's going easily
flowing that's a certain kind of momentum and there's another kind of momentum too
which you may have noticed which is throughout your day or maybe innocent
a little bit of awareness will just pop in without you doing anything at all
it just arises
another form of this like simple level of mindfulness
is something i call wholehearted presence or open-hearted presence and this is where
everything is more of a wash it's the completeness it's just the sense of being present here and now
so there's not any particular object of attention rather there is um
just a sense of being here and
in daily life this can manifest as
a tuning mindfulness when there's more going on to rather than trying to track for
example i'm not going to try to track my breathing when i'm driving right i'm focused on driving
it can also mean noticing like for example
when i am walking with a friend just oh here i am walking with my friend
it's being present at the very simplest level it's
also the capacity to simply be with whatever is going on
right so if intense emotion is arising for me
being with that just being with it
so um there's a way of
lensing in and out between these two different forms of moment-to-moment
awareness i remember like i sat a long long
retreat actually two long retreats one at ims in massachusetts and the second one in
burma and when i got back my awareness was attuned
to all the little changes in each moment very subtle well shortly after that i started
volunteering as a hospital chaplain i felt like i'd been
i was a violin that had been thrown into a frenzy dance floor it was just like
and it's because i hadn't yet learned to pull back open the lens of awareness
and just take in the whole wash of what was happening and as soon as that happened it felt
quite easily so there's this focusing in and pulling outwards
sometimes this um simple meeting of mindfulness as it is
can just be like a brightening or perhaps like a gong striking
just richer flavors and food right
and moments of clarity can arise inside of this kind of like shooting stars when we get those meteor showers
i went up to a local bihara a few years ago this was pre-coveted and was hanging out with some of my
friends there and we were lying in this field at night looking up at the stars
and every once in a while a meteor would go by right
but then just like when mindfulness momentum builds we started getting more
and more and more of these one after another one after another
showering through so when continuity of mindfulness builds
these shooting stars can happen more and more often and every now and then no matter how often they happen
a bigger star might come through a bigger meteor oh
insight can happen at any minute
so second level of attention if you want to imagine the tree again
perhaps the tree leafing out this is the step back
in awareness so there's this massive difference
when there's even the slightest difference between an experience and the knowing of it
i was walking with a dear friend recently and she had started a mindfulness practice
kind of recently and i asked her what have you noticed what's different and she said
it's so huge when i'm stressed i can just notice that i'm stressed
right that distance no longer being hooked into the story that the stress is making but just like
oh stress okay or oh relaxation great
stephen covey has been known to describe victor frankel's understanding
as in this quote that he found in a library stack somewhere roughly it states
between stimulus and response as a space and within that space there's a choice
and therein lies freedom right
one of the things that can really help make space is a sense of humor and the practice playfulness
and i used to think i was kind of cheating by doing this um on long retreats i would sort of invent
these things so i'll tell you one like there was this one retreat that i was just really caught up in resentment
about something for the life of me i have no idea what it was anymore but that grudge was just kind of
weighing on the mind and pulling it in and eventually the mind made it into
this little troll like this little squat you know with ears and hair coming out
the ears and just really hammed it up and made it silly and imagine the trolls stomping back and forth as being the
grudge and that created enough distance from
the experience to be able to hold it lightly and eventually it just went away right
like i said i kind of thought i was cheating about this until um
i heard joseph goldstein talk about playing kind of atari with his thoughts
and like shooting and letting them kind of explode and disappear
so there's all these different ways of being playful that can help create this
second level of attention the knowing we're aware the knowing that we're in an emotional state
right holding it lightly
we get to the flowering of awareness what in
the satipatana sutra the four foundations for awareness the four establishments of mindfulness
that's called full awareness and it talks about how a practitioner or a monk knows when
they're moving when they're reaching when they're eating when they're using the bathroom all these different daily
activities it's um for us maybe
walking i know i'm walking reaching for the refrigerator door i know i'm reaching
right that's at the body level but this full awareness this mindfulness
of context applies also to other things like what kind of
practice is helpful in this moment for example
what's helpful now
then there's um the awareness of conditions
also foot phil fits into this this full awareness i'm describing nepali is
of satisfying the bigger picture so
what kind of practice is helpful when i'm driving maybe it's just driving maybe it's seeing
right or having a tough day maybe it's loving kindness
mindfulness of conditions is part of this as well and that could
be as knowing the effects of what my mind or heart is doing on my
body softening in the chest
relaxation or a quenching in the neck tension
but noticing the relationship between these things
noticing our kind of internal ecosystem the internal
system of interactions that's happening
then we get to sort of the the tree bearing fruit
which is another level of satisfaction mindfulness and full awareness lucid
awareness as it starts to shade towards wisdom or discernment
and this is discernment one level of this discernment it's the quality of the heart and mind at the
moment right it can be um the quality of awareness how spacious is
it or how contracted is it is there distraction or concentration
is there greed or contentment just as simple as that
sometimes too there's almost a spatial component to it for some people i know
where it's like the awareness can feel close in and intimate
or it can feel like surfing the sensations of the
changes in the body and the mind can be kind of floating
or very grounded vast like the sky or as tiny as a little
pinhole sometimes it even feels like
being immersed in reality like that fish swimming through water
suddenly realizing there's water there wow yeah
it can even feel like being steeped like there's no separation awareness inward
and outward so there's another kind of discernment
too which is perhaps more helpful even which is
discernment of what's helpful and unhelpful in our minds and hearts
what's helpful is that which leads to greater benefit for ourselves and others what's
unhelpful leads to greater affliction there's a few teachings in in the
ancient texts the pali canon where the buddha talks about this he teaches his son and
one of them and he just talks about a wise person and another a wise person is one who
acts for benefit for themselves for others for themselves and others and all
concerned an unwise person
builds affliction and then themselves affliction in others affliction in both and for all concerned
and he the buddha suggests dividing thought and meditation
kind of along these lines on one side are the afflictive thoughts and on the other side are the beneficial
thoughts and he suggests keeping very close watch when there are
afflictive thoughts happening because there can be a cascade effect right
it talks about it being like a cow herd who keeps the cows away from the neighbor's crops very carefully
there's also when things are good noticing that too but appreciating it
allowing it to grow to extend
mindfulness in these contexts is sometimes described as a gatekeeper who is guarding a walled city
and the buddha was alive in the bronze age so there were more like i think individual
towns or cities with protection around them and the gatekeeper
knows the way for the important messengers to go straight to the king he also
has discernment in recognizing who's coming in that the king's guards might
want to keep a closer eye on or in extreme circumstances
who's trying to enter that he shouldn't let enter at all and our minds can be like that too the
mindfulness the discerning quality of our minds can just be as simple as not now
or i'm just not going to go there right
helpful qualities of the mind are also balanced by awareness
kind of like a chariot tear keeps horses in sync that's how it's described in the ancient
teachings
there's a quote that jack cornfield i believe has said i believe quoting annie lamont the writer
saying my mind is like a bad neighborhood i try not to go there alone
right so these
helpful qualities of minds are sometimes considered to be like seven friends
this is a poem based on the early teachings of the first
ordained monastic women in the buddhist order and this book is poems based on that by
maddie weingast called the first free women
and in it this awakened woman because of these or their awakening poems
is saying i was forever getting lost until one day the buddha told me
to walk this path you will need seven friends mindfulness
curiosity courage joy
stillness calm and perspective
for many years these friends and i have traveled together sometimes wandering in circles
sometimes taking a long way around
oh my heart you don't have to go it alone train yourself
to train just a little more gently
those seven friends are the seven factors of awakening that translation's a little bit different than the normal one
so gentle gentle attention helps in recognizing
all these different forms of awareness
so there's another broadening of this sakti sampanchanda this full
awareness which is to notice the forest around the tree
venerable annalio highlights how important it is to balance internal awareness which we talk about a lot here
with external awareness awareness of other people living beings or life forms
awareness of our environment and he says the one of the reasons it's so important to balance internal and
external is that there can be an over focus on the self an over self
absorption that happens if it all becomes about my experience
that can be balanced quite beautifully if we start noticing and practicing external mindfulness of others and their
experience so
while it can be helpful for to notice one thing at a time in this body that
tree that i keep mentioning it it's also helpful
to have the entire surrounding ecosystem in mind
in the hidden life of trees wallabong author talks about how trees actually
communicate through their roots with each other they send out signals
sometimes they're helped by the fungi beneath the forest floor they send each other nutrients warnings
they even help prop each other up quite literally when they're in this kind of symbiotic relationship
noticing others being present for others is another way
of building a symbiotic relationship a mutually helpful relationship
and this kind of awareness really draws on awareness of ourselves right
so i might notice a person's posture or expression and be able to infer a certain kind of
you know with humility with not lack of certainty a certain kind of perhaps awareness or emotional state or
gosh they look like they might be going through something maybe i should check on them like just so noticing with humility with the
possibility that you know i'm seeing this am i off here right i could be wrong
that is one way to start noticing external noticing people's body
movements is a much easier way like how they're walking if they're walking sitting
close or far but all of this can draw on the wisdom
the mindfulness that has been learned inside our bodies right
and that is tracking also internal and
external awareness those of you who are healthcare professionals or work
with people maybe therapists coaches whatnot we use this all the time checking in
with our own experience to get a sense of how to read the room it's like
a stringed instrument when a really heavy truck drives by and
the building shakes the stringed instrument might hum in resonance right we're also humming in resonance
with everyone around us our nervous systems are the instrument our hearts are the instrument
noticing this provides space for something known as a non-complementary response
so this means for example i don't have to meet anger with anger
and my day job one of my my jobs as a hospital chaplain
and there are times where there might be a visiting family member that's very upset really angry
or grieving and there there's something so powerful
about being able to be with that person and feel that resonance without getting pulled into it
it enables a sense of compassionate calm in meeting them and it can transform things
and help someone get further through their process or if they're upset it can help them
calm down very quickly because my instrument isn't caught in their instruments tuned i'm aware of it i'm
responding to it but i'm able to be with and each of this each of us has this
capacity um
also times when one's impact on others maybe isn't so
clear maybe i'm caught up in my head or i'm busy or i'm in a rush or something like that
and then we can notice how people are showing up in relationship to us
as a mirror to our own behavior lily tomlin talks about how
this famous quote people will forget what you said they will forget what you did but they
will never ever forget how you made them feel right
and we can often see it on people's faces in their bodies if something was a little off
it's important to say here too that this internal external awareness this
perceptions of other people is also precisely where bias can come in our own
filters so those can distort
the mirrors and they can also filter our perceptions including what we are even able to see
what's even able to be seen at all
and to how we see it like a number of you i sat a lot of home
retreat in the last two and a half plus years of this coveted pandemic
and i just remember on this one retreat it was during an informal time between sittings and i was like
walking through my apartment and the back wall of the apartment has a lot of windows on it and one of them
looks out onto a porch that my neighbor also has access to
and my eyes lit on a form on the porch
you know kind of brilliantly lit by the sunlight and almost before i could perceive what it
was there was a version and i could just because my mind was
quiet i could just watch the mind cascade through this story of oh my neighbor left that
stuff on the porch and then it like filtered the view of the neighbor too and it definitely filtered the view
of the object the really humbling thing about this is with the second look the object wasn't
what i thought it was at all it was conditioned by these attitudes in my mind they literally distorted what i
saw there are also people who
have described receiving an email when in an agitated state
and being convinced it says something not good
having the presence of mind not to respond to it going back to it later and realizing it actually said something
different the text was different than they read it to be the emotional state filtered the
information that much it distorted it that much
so one benefit of starting to notice awareness is notice when noticing when
there might be a little distortion at play oh i'm maybe i'm not in the best frame
of mind to be taking this in right now maybe i'll set it aside take it in later
so um internal and external awareness is where
we exercise some of our most important choices this includes what voices and
sources we amplify in our own hearts and minds that allow our own hearts and minds to move
in certain directions and it can also be
in noticing what we say or amplify and move on to others
right so um
the choices we make can be the difference between sort of cultivating trust
kindness honesty
awareness cultivating our sort of cultural and relational comments
as opposed to putting
agitation anger judgment fear
even untruths we run across without checking
we have the power to emit things that are more
wholesome versus things that cause more problems and agitation than the people we know or
don't even know
another gatekeeper story and then i'll be done here so
i don't remember if the story is in the sutas i think it may be sort of in the literature around the discourses
it's another gatekeeper and this gatekeeper is a friendly sort and
people ask him all kinds of questions and so one day one group
kind of comes by and they're doing what they need to do to get them in the city and they ask say what are the people like here
the gatekeeper looks at them and goes well how did you find people in the town you left
oh they were awful greedy conniving couldn't trust them
always putting people down he just nods and he said i think you'll find people like that
here too next group comes by a few groups later
he gets the same question he gets this question a lot what are the people like here
oh they're kind trustworthy generous i feel blessed
to have them as neighbors back where i left i'm gonna miss him oh okay i think you'll find people here
much like that too right
what we put out has a large impact on what we receive
so to recap the takeaway is that awareness can take
all of these different forms with different breadth and depth and
scope any of which all of which can be useful whether it's moment to moment
more of a general gestalt if it is more of a full awareness an encompassing
awareness or a discernment like that whatchamacallit tree and all
the fruits and blossoms and buds eventually mindfulness awareness
blossoms into that greater discernment and wisdom now this is not a project it's just
something to keep in mind you can trust the process as long as awareness mindfulness is
practiced as part of the path it will mature
into discernment and wisdom
so may we all awaken into healthy relationship with the way things are
and to the capacity to show up in ways that make this life and the lives around us
better in all different kinds of ways
so thank you for your kind attention we have just um two or three minutes if
anyone here has questions that you would like to offer thank you
comments are also welcome
john i just want to thank you um for all your words and all the of
planning and thought that went into them but also the way you manage things this morning
that's that's a very powerful teacher so thank you thank you martha
i just want to point out how much i appreciate the difference between the stimulus to
the stress there's that space and with that space a lot of times we get caught up with the stimulus and
ruminate and not knowing the space is there and that's why mindfulness is kicking in and
knowing the space creates the expansion that's when we can have a different response
and so that really resonates with me so thank you thank you thank you for
putting it so well i can tell you it really went in you haven't made it thanks
anyone else we have just a moment or two
behind you i loved
uh the gatekeeper at the end that you were talking about when people show up and
what they show up with and precise perspectives and perceptions that they take with them and project
into into their environment and just it's really important to remember that
and to be aware of that you know just to let go of those that are not
beneficial and so thank you for that i love the story
thank you hillary thank you
so thank you friends for your kind attention
may all beings benefit from our practice here together
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
may all beings know the highest safety freedom
[Music]
[Music] okay thank you for your kind attention