so hello everyone welcome
and as an introduction to today's meditation
it's as if we have two bodies two physical
bodies that we one that's the body we have when we're not
mindful the other when we are mindful of the body
we have two minds two thinking minds
one when we are not mindful not aware of what we're thinking
and one that is when we're aware when we're mindful
we have two emotional bodies when we're not aware of our emotions and
when we're aware of emotions we have two
faculties of intentionality of motivation of purpose
of desire and there's one that when we're aware
and one when we're not aware it's a world of difference it's
almost as if we live in two worlds we live in a world when we're not aware of the world
it's lost in our thoughts and we live in a different world when we're aware
and this idea that we live in there's there's two there's these these uh being aware and not being aware
is so radically different it's like two different worlds
different causes and conditions come into play when we're not aware
than when we are aware it's almost as if we have two selves that which we who we are and how we
behave and exist when we're not aware and when we are aware
and so a huge part of buddhist practice of sativatana the main part of it
is to live a life that is aware as we do this meditation
see if you can you can see the difference between what's happening
when you're not aware maybe you realize it afterwards and when you are aware
and let the awareness be and not be something that you have to work at
maybe you have to work at remembering to be aware maybe you have to work to come back
to awareness maybe you have to work at at um
hanging in there with it letting go of the distractions
but don't let awareness be work let awareness be something you
allow to be there and sometimes you're aware of the body
sometimes the feelings sometimes mind states emotions
sometimes the mental processes and purposes desires aversions
aspirations sometimes sounds
all kinds of things so you see if you can see the difference
between when you're aware in a relaxed way almost effortless way
and when you're not aware at all and in between that is the practice of
coming back of waking up of letting go but you're waking up and letting go into
something which is easy effortless just to know what's happening in the
simplest possible way
so we'll sit quietly and i hope you enjoy
the world of awareness
so
um
when you come into awareness
how do things change that's different
if they don't come into awareness
thinking when it comes into awareness emotions
body experiences
so
and as we come to the end of the sitting
there's a world of difference
when we're with other people and we're
aware clearly openly a sense of presence really present for
someone versus not being aware
or not being aware of how we're abiding in our thoughts our
judgments our anxieties our expectations
all kinds of ways in which simple awareness is complicated when we're with other people
and there is the world a difference between having all these complications in our
relationship to other people present as we're with them
and being away and not know it
and then being aware of it wearing being aware of how we are and
the unnecessary complications we make not to judge it but
simply to be aware to know that that's happening
it's a different world when we trust awareness
the awareness that protects us from rushing ahead and
believing and doing the things that maybe are not so healthy
and to what we learn in meditation mindfulness meditation
may be something we bring with us into the world of other people
so that we know how to be present for others with real awareness
uncomplicated awareness
so that when the people we're with are distressed
we are not distressed but we're there present understanding how they are
empathic when others are
grieving let us be present aware kindly openly understandingly
and not be caught in the web of sadness and grief
to remember to be aware when the people with are dying
to have learned the ability to be present aware an uncomplicated way fully there
is a gift may it be that this practice that
sativatana that we do may we bring it into the world
so that we can love the world care for the world you see wisely the world
and be protected from the
inner tendencies we have that make things more difficult and
harmful may we through practice of awareness
be a source of welfare and happiness for the world
so
thank you so hello and
we come to the final talk now over 70 talks on
the sati patana and it's a practice
this is the practice of mindfulness by which we're cultivating and developing a heightened capacity for awareness
i like i like myself the language of lucid awareness clear awareness
that's available and present for us as we go through our life
the in this text there are 13 exercises
that we've gone through bit by bit and and the relationship between the
exercises and the awareness that's being developed is similar to
the idea of running if someone says i run
i'm running or something oh it doesn't tell you much about what what that's about
it's possible they're running for exercise
it's possible they're running to catch the bus
it's possible they're running from the police just telling them they're running doesn't say much
but if you tell them if they tell you that they're training they're running
in training as their training program and running then you get a clear sense of the
running now it's an exercise it's a protocol they're following
they're probably doing sprints and long distance and exercising strengthening and uh you know all kinds of things you
might be doing if you're training to run like trying to run for a race or something
and so there's a lot of things you do but what you're learning is developing your capacity for running
until the running becomes you know i mean we it feel can feel effortless at some point if you're
really in the flow of running even though a lot of energy is being expended
and we can feel like you're abiding in the running and running just kind of like looks like we're being carried
along with it whereas in the beginning of training it was hard and you had to apply yourself
and there was resistance to it so the same thing the 13 exercises is
the training in awareness and they involve other kinds of
you know other things training exercises we do and
areas of practicing and a lot of that training has to do with knowing recognition of
what's there and and as the recognition grows
then awareness develops and that awareness can be stay with you for a while
sometimes it might stay for a few seconds sometimes it might stay for a few minutes sometimes a few hours sometimes
longer you really feel like now there's the awareness is kind of for a while
ever present or continuously present for a period of time and
and that awareness makes a world of difference you might still be
have all kinds of inner challenges and you might have fear and desire and anger and
attachments of all kinds but the art of awareness is like a now we have a like a separate
place to abide in it's like your whole house is is dirty
but the living room is clean and from living room you can see all the rooms
but you're not disturbed by it because you've learned that you can clean the living room and there's no need to dirty
the living room by being upset by what's in the other rooms but with time you'll
go there and and clean them up and take care of it you know how to do it now so we have this awareness and there's
actually a kind of a of um of a relaxed feeling
about our shortcomings uh it doesn't mean we indulge in them it doesn't mean that we
celebrate them and just kind of barrel ahead with them but it means that we don't criticize
ourselves or upset over ourselves or um are burdened by our shortcomings of
course we have shortcomings court their desires and attachments that's what we're working with that's
where we're training and developing more and more this capacity for awareness
but as the awareness gets stronger at some point this point it becomes clear
that that is the best alternative that's the better place to be in awareness
and being aware of everything else that tends to shift everything else towards health
that tends to shift things in a skillful healthy way it makes room for healthy mind states
and motivations and wisdom to occur when awareness begins to be present in
an open relaxed way we know how to be aware of what's happening
and um at some point that oh satypation doing the practice doing the practice at
some point doing this satipatana practice the awareness becomes so
um clear that we say it's kind of like an aha moment oh
now i know what this practice is about now i know kind of something about freedom
now i know about not getting caught in anything including my shortcomings i don't have to be
drowned by them or upset with them it just that's what the mind is doing
and now i know there's and there's this place of freedom this place of open awareness this place of lucid awareness
that uh we know that it really makes an impression for me for the first time like wow
this is fantastic the um and then
that's a confirmation of the practice of sati patana that said oh this practice kind of
brought this about this clear lucid awareness this freedom of awareness
and now that's what sati patana is about is to cultivate and develop
this strong sense of awareness the strong awareness and and then
after that clarity um tendency is that a person is more
ethical but there's no guarantee but the tendency is because this field of awareness is so wholesome it lets us
see and feel the impact that our inner behavior has and our external behavior what we do and
we can feel how we're diminished by unethical behavior
and how we're kind of enhanced by ethical behavior so the tendency to start being more interested in being
ethical and not causing harm in the world or any kind of eventually any kind at all
once this kind of clarity this aha moment happens and now i know what the practice is about now i know something
about it then the practice of satipattana doesn't
change it becomes the same practice we do the same thing again and again
though now there's a reference point for it this little this clarity of awareness
it becomes easier to do we can fall back into awareness more clearly or some qualities
characteristics of this lucid awareness might be with us all the time even though it's not always there strongly
and then the practice develops and then at some point this experience of aha and freedom of awareness
comes to full maturation and in this tradition you talk about full
awakening full enlightenment and um and
you know the i don't i've never met anyone i know that had that full awakening full
enlightenment i've been a lot around a lot of wonderful buddhist teachers
but i know that that's a possibility that's a direction we can go once you have enough practice and enough aha this
works this is what it's about then you can you have a clear sense it's just other rooms in the house
and it's possible to clean it all out someone can do that for themselves no doubt about it
and whether but it's a big task and so whether
there are people in the modern world that you can meet who've done that it's an open question it's hard to know
but but doesn't matter so much for oneself because one knows this is the direction we're going there's no other
thing to do the buddha said that once you become fully awakened
then the practice of satina becomes the same
for the buddha that's a person who practice who is fully awakened continues to practice satipatana
maybe it isn't so much exercise anymore but rather it's a kind of a way of being
but he's still exactly the same instructions are given for people who are fully awakened
so whether we're new to practice and you're developing the practice in
satipatana whether we know what the practice is about
which is the when a person becomes called a trainee
sometimes it's referred to as stream entry um then after that it's the same practice
and if you become fully awakened it's the same practice jack cornfield has this title of a book
called you know after the ex after the ecstasy the laundry um
the uh another way another thing that from this what i'm teaching here today from the from the buddha he said he
would you know his title of his book would be um
before awakening after partial awakening
sati patana after a full awakening satipatana and that
this is the practice for a lifetime there's no end to it it's always we're doing it and it's not a burden it's not
a doesn't feel like a work it just becomes more and more natural becomes who we are
and it becomes trusting living an awareness more than anything else living and being
present for experience and and the alternative to not be aware
is clearly not as good not as wonderful not as enjoyable and not as helpful for the
world because to know something about freedom from attachments and clinging
then uh we know what other people are uh what's up what's possible for other
people what their potential is and then we can somehow support that
and and just like uh so if you follow this path
to the freedom freedom from clinging to lucid awareness
you're being supported fully that's the most wonderful thing you can do for yourself and
you become a model you become a exemplar and you become someone who can
recognize and support that possibility for other people that other people too can
attain more and more freedom in a deep way rather than having to accommodate
suffering put up with suffering assuage suffering with
compassion and self-care which is a wonderful thing to do but to limit be limited by that
is to be limited to open up into this world of freedom a full awareness
everybody has that potential and it's a game changer
but it doesn't change sati patana sati patana sutta satibata practice the
training of it before awakening and after awakening
after sati patana more sativatana
so thank you for this and i hope that
the joy of awareness the joy of mindfulness becomes
your joy and that it's contagious
and thank you for being part of this series and and i'll be back here in about two weeks
next two weeks we have guest teachers i'm going off to teach a retreat at the insight retreat
center and with andrea fella and so for next week
matthew brent silver will be back and the following week nikki murgafore will be here
the wonderful teachers i've taught here before very much appreciated by by
here the youtube uh sangha community and um so you'll be in good hands
and i'll be back somewhere around the 22nd monday around
and look forward to being together again