here we go okay so hello again and welcome to happy hour
everyone so for the theme for today
um I'd like to invite us to consider consider
wise speech [Music] um truthfulness there are many aspects to
why speech but today specifically um truthfulness as as an expression of
matter not just for others but really for ourselves as an expression of care
as an expression of love for ourselves so I want to bring those two to Concepts
together for us to sit with and to practice with with the guided meditation and
the consideration um is you know we often don't connect the
teachings on on Silo and ethical conduct um truthfulness as a subcategory of why
speech or being one of this we don't usually connect it with with the Brahma
viharas with the heart practices but they are intertwined they aren't they are I mean all of the Dharma is
interconnected to me the more I get into the Dharma all aspects of it
um it's like a cloth and you take one you take one thread and you pull it like
oh yes this thread is the whole cloth it's it's so there are all these aspects
of these teachings really they they come together so so the the relationship between
um truthfulness honesty um as an expression of love so so how
are they related many ways but it's formulation consider this um not only is it an act of care and
love to to be truthful to others um
and to care for them not to deceive them not to be deceitful to offer safety to
offer care in that way but even more so even more so it's for ourselves really
and I want to emphasize that um because and made me seem counter-intuitive
um this teaching on the Bliss of blamelessness the Bliss of blamelessness
it's such a beautiful heart space to have because when we have
done something when something just a little you know we've told uh a lie or
we've been untruthful in other ways um it's it's a niggling feeling it
doesn't sit right it doesn't feel right and it can lead to all kinds of other problems and issues and not sleeping
well and and and and and just the the heart being riled up the heart being
riled up so as a way to really love ourselves and
care for this being who is me offering themselves offering ourselves offering
ourselves this gift of honesty ah what a relief what a relief and you
might actually remember or as I'm telling as I'm sharing this briefed our
met consider times that maybe there was a niggling feeling or something that you're not quite truthful about or or or
kind of sitting with should I do it this way or that way and and maybe
in maybe in in reality it it caused a lot of trouble Pro for you and others
and also maybe you can remember a case where there was a sense of clearing a
Clarity a clearing of of um resolution that there was this maybe
um say something untruthful or unethical
and then when you actually did the right thing there was a sense of release there was a sense of release for you and
relief for yourself and someone as an act of care for yourself gosh this was so easy why didn't I do this earlier
this was would have been so easy to to tell the truth and and and and act
ethically so so in Praise of honesty and praise of truthfulness
as an act of matter it's an act of care as an act of offering safety offering
um love and care for ourselves especially for ourselves as well as others because it's interesting whenever
we think of honesty we usually think oh yeah honest for the sake of others yes true absolutely but I'm trying to
bring in different aspect of it here which we usually don't consider how important it is for
our benefit really um there's also another thing I want to
briefly connect with it is with the five Daily Reflections the
fifth one having to do with Karma excuse me I'm gonna cough
where the fifth reflection is that I'm the heir to my actions born of my
actions um and I have my actions as my arbitrator and protection whatever I do
for good or bad of these I shall become the heir and this sense of
of our actions really impact ourselves first and foremost so do we want to care
for ourselves do we want to love ourselves not rile ourselves up and cause problems for
ourselves in in our future selves um so for our consideration for our
consideration and again the invitation is not to feel tight about
honesty truthfulness why speech but actually see it as a gift see it as a
gift of love to see it as a gift of protection we give ourselves first and foremost yes others too but forget about
them for a moment really the the sense of filling our own cup with care with our own care with our own truthfulness
honesty um why speech so
so offered for your reflection and now let's uh let's sit together let's
meditate together so lighting right us to sit in our
meditation posture whether sitting lying down
standing
and if you're sitting to feel ah to feel your body releasing onto the
chair in the cushion oh what a gift
but a gift to just sit and be breathed
foreign
let awareness connect with the breath and breath out breath
the sensations not the thought of the in-breath out breath but the sensations in the body very simple
nourishing foreign
foreign
your heart to settle ready your mind to settle a picking
Refuge the Simplicity of this moment and if thoughts arise thank you thank you dear
thoughts nothing wrong with you but not right now giving my heart to this practice
so good so delicious to be just here right here
and again if thoughts come to take you away Dancing Away say thank you my dance
card is full right now with heartfulness with mindfulness
later later the most beautiful dance with the breath
is right here the breath and the body don't miss it
most beautiful walls of the breath
in out
foreign
he Refuge
the Simplicity of this moment
foreign
dancing with the body
soothing calming
be present for the dance this precious dance that doesn't last
forever
foreign
connected to the Earth the sense of integrity
sitting upright a brightness of the spine
a sense of Integrity of the heart both physical uprightness taking your
seat really taking your seed on this Earth feeling connected and rooted
feeling the seed of your agency you're alive have agency
power of agency being the seed of your power and your sit bones
connected well rooted
alive and from this seed from the seed of your
power your agency feeling your
spine upright rising up
feeling your heart expand your shoulders relaxed
Integrity integrity
from this place you'll feel your brightness and rootedness
maybe maybe let your heart conjure up a memory of a
time that it was so easy to not be truthful
but you were a sense of a brightness could be something very small
could have been a white lie you avoided this is not the time to think of all the
times you were not truthful but just think of the time turn your awareness to the time that
maybe it would have been so easy to say the equivalent of the dog ate my homework but you actually
you're upright your truthful
maybe instead of saying I but there was a lot of traffic you said I actually left later
than I anticipated I'm sorry you were truthful or any other
simple Act of truthfulness and if a memory doesn't come up imagine
yourself actually doing that saying that a sense of goodness uprightness Clarity
the gift of truthfulness ah how soothing that is
to your heart how aligned you feel
ah the heart feels good
recognizing seeing its own goodness
Conjuring up imagining said telling the truth see how that
feels in your heart your whole body
may be coming clean or whatever it might be
clearing Clearing Your Karma
setting in motion truthfulness for the future Clearing Your Karma making your karma wholesome
so that future actions are more truthful
putting it in motion right now in your heart and your imagination in your mind
and feeling this goodness how good it feels
Letting Go releasing
recognizing this goodness within you within your heart
such a gift such a gift to yourself This recognition
your own goodness maybe a smile arises
there is goodness here yes there's goodness seeds
more of them being planted right now yes
let yourself feel the wholesomeness of this goodness kindness to yourself for yourself
holding yourself with benevolence with appreciation
I am capable of kindness of of truthfulness of course of course of
wholesome is of course I appreciate and cherish
being who's me
may my goodness increase
may my truthfulness continue and grow
as a gift to myself it's a gift of Bliss of blamelessness as a gift to
others
appreciating all the times you've been truthful past so many times oh my
goodness
and honoring the intention the beauty of this intention
moving forward as a gift to yourself
may my goodness grow may my goodness continue
may my truthfulness be a gift to myself and others in all aspects of life
bringing e-safety relief
healing less of blamelessness
I wish myself well I see the goodness
may I be well
then maybe just for the joy of it maybe imagine if
you wish all the truthful statements
that you've made through your life as as a chorus of angels
that are singing back to you you're wholesome karma for truthfulness
we're going to bring the good to our mind to our heart emphasize the
good so that it grows
there's another practice for remorse not right now emphasize and see the good
all these truthfulness all these even especially when it was hard to be truthful
all these Devas these angels Celestial beings
singing your Praises yes well done well done
seeing your own goodness
and inspired being inspired sense of aspiration for more good
as a gift to yourself as a gift to others
is there any clearing that needs to happen
it's so easy easier than we think
allowing yourself to sit with a sense of meta kindness for yourself wholeheartedness
having say and recognized your own goodness
may I be well may my goodness be a gift to myself and
to others
may my goodness increase May It Grow
I wish myself well and more goodness
foreign
spreading the kindness foreign
[Music] truthfulness
around you
people who've supported you cared for you you care about
yes maybe they have not been perfect
yes but appreciating the times that truthfulness really supported you seeing
the goodness an offering appreciation and offering your goodness
your truthfulness as a gift of safety and kindness to those around
you radiating out
radiating kindness radiating safety and care truthfulness
making ourselves safe for others foreign
truthfulness
foreign
[Music]
appreciating your goodness again that you showed up and you practiced
with these invitations as best as you were able to letting go of the outcome you did the best you could
yay for that yay and offering this wholeheartedness
is showing up his goodness as a gift to all beings everywhere including yourself
we'd be a cause and conditions for all beings waking up may all beings
be free may all beings be happy including
ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
ah so as always no there's so many different aspects and
dimensions too to practice of the Brahma viharos and it
really as I mentioned it ties into the rest of the teachings including truthfulness as an offering
safety to ourselves and others and I wonder whether as you were doing this
practice what came up for you this really recognizing the the goodness and
truthfulness and and how a pride actually how good it feels that when it's so easy to to say a white light but
just to say tell the truth how easy how good it feels how it's a reaffirmation
of goodness it's a gift to ourselves and also if it's ever been the case when
when in your life maybe there's been a reckoning and actually that maybe that was a a
relief oh yes oh yeah I was holding this I was holding this heaviness this rock on on truthfulness for a long time and
now gosh it's so ah what how Blissful will that have to carry this anymore
so I invite your Reflections I'm changing the chat settings you can send
um chats to the to everyone or if you send it to me it'll be private I won't read your name you can also raise your
Zoom hand not your physical hand because I cannot see you there are too many of
you I do see Richard's Zoom head Richard please
oh you're doing can you hear me uh this practice you know I'm very happy
about it it's been it's really allowed me led me to be much more myself I speak
much more freely much more naturally on occasion I'll Express
happiness over some good news that I've had and I'll I'll make somebody in my
audience will feel bad that you know they haven't had the same good luck the
same good fortune and you know it's almost like to be truly wise you have to
shut up all the time and and I I don't quite know how to make that
bounce yeah yeah thank you Richard it's a great question
and and multiple things it's it's in also about how we share and with whom we
share right so truthfulness um it's as we talked about it tonight you
know if there is a piece of good news and say um [Music] but I'm gonna make an extreme case but
say you just start you know you you're falling in love and it's a new relationship and you're so excited about
it and and yet maybe there is a friend you have who's just had who's whose
partner has just left them or or has died right so gushing it's it's maybe it
means it's not very wise right it's so wisdom comes in there so it's not very wise to I mean it's truthful to say oh
yes but it's not very wise it's not very caring it's not very compassionate to
gaussians how awesome it is and uh so so I think wisdom here uh when you in this
special specific case that you're talking about so wisdom when it's not appropriate to be gushing and and of
course that can bring up grief and sadness and not mudita not vicarious joy for the other person
and then also there are cases with with folks maybe with some people in your
life where um it's it's part of their work it's part of their practice of of
um of Envy or jealousy that so that's something in general they're working with so it may not be a bad timing
because with why speech there are five different aspects through one is it has to be not just truthful but it has to be
timely so in this case that I laid out may not be Timely
and in the case of and also with with Y speech there's also um kindness so it may not be actually
kind for you to gosh when you know this person has a tendency to get into go
into envy and and self recommendation that they don't so knowing all those it
may not be kind right so all those aspects of why speech are not satisfied
so you have to be wise it's not it's different it's it's not just truthful but it's like sharing your good news and
boasting about it or or it's it's a special case does that make sense the
distinction yeah great thanks for that question the other questions are reflections more
generally about truthfulness about the theme of the the uh practice that we just did together
with sense of safety sense of e seeing our own goodness
what came up for you Jamie please
um well I I need to leave a little early tonight Nikki and I just wanted to say thank you before I leave
um now I I was adopted and I think as a child I was a bit of a square peg in the round
hole of my adopted family even though they were loving and did their best for me um I didn't and I didn't really want to
see uh the ways in which you know my family and I were not a
perfect fit and so truthfulness didn't it's actually come easily as a result of that and
somehow this this set just allowed me to see that and that it's okay to be honest now
well thank you thank you Jamie thank you so much for sharing that so beautiful
yeah it's it's yeah so it's okay not only okay but it feels good in your in
your voice I was hearing the sense of fullness yes it's okay to be truthful now it's the fullness of your heart is
coming through through the line thank you so much Amy yeah I see yeah thanks
for the thumbs up beautiful other Reflections you can type him in
chat you can raise your hand we still have another couple minutes
so it's a big topic anything else anything that didn't work
for you but that's okay too
brag please I really appreciated that the second
piece you added there about other aspects of white speech a friend
of mine once said to me Brock you wield the truth like a hammer so what are the other other ones you said it was timely
kind yeah truthful yeah so so I have I have an acronym for myself let's see if
I can remember all of it TT ttb GK timely truthful uh beneficial
beneficial uh gentle okay kind
thank you those are the five aspects of it yeah aspects and all all five are
important thanks Brad great
Reflections all thank you for the reflections and questions so
so now here's the invitation for our small Sangha practice this evening is
um the here is the um the question is appropriate somebody
sent in it that's not one of the five because I think basically if you do all the five appropriate becomes it becomes
appropriate it becomes part of why speech so so the question so the reflection for
the small groups tonight is regarding you know the sense of as
you feel your body as you feel your sense of integrity as you feel
into the sense of Integrity of taking your seat feel how that feels different uh how
that feels different in in leaning into the truth or not leaning into
forthrightness into honesty into into why speech so so it's an exploration of
embodied the embodiment of this uh this why speech with care with kindness
towards yourself so just each person will have a minute to have a monologue
of of [Music] um um us speaking out loud exploring and being
held witnessed I'm going to set up the groups and someone asked what do you mean by
beneficial beneficial means but of the benefit of beneficial for the other
person so when you're saying something yourself is of benefit it's a benefit for the other person's benefit for
others it's not to make your ego uh bigger that that's what beneficial means
okay so so let's uh let's turn to the breakout
so so again take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind uh only speak
from your own experience and um yeah not leading Joy just speaking from
your own experience and then if you want to pass you can pass and hold uh
compassionate silent space for others you can just say pass and it's an interesting exploration the embodiment
with care and the theme that we've been exploring tonight so uh and then next
person will talk and next person will talk and if there is time we'll come back to you so so I'm creating the rooms
now take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind and and enjoy this
exploration here we go
close everybody's back so I would love to maybe um hear one or two Reflections if we
have time maybe one reflection what did you discover if you haven't spoken yet please
Serena hi thank you for letting me ask this
question um I've had a very difficult relationship with my sister
and um I really have been working on this forever
and I sent her loving kindness I wish her
well when we
uh however when there are situa family situations
where we're both present and she takes over
and whatever Dynamics happened I always wind up leaving the place
feeling uh wounded feeling yeah like I somehow
a lot of the time I don't leave the place feeling okay
so I really
don't know what you know what else to do besides saying from her yeah yeah it
sounds it's it's it's it's a um thank you for asking that question it also does seem like you've done the
complicated Dynamics and and for the given that it's already actually 701 to go into detail but this is one thing
that I can say Serena um and that is you know there's still what I'm hearing is yes you are doing
meta for her compassion for her and and and and please do it for yourself I didn't hear that you're doing it for
yourself because you're the one who's who's feeling hurt and leaving wounded so it's important for meta and
compassion to be uh 360 degrees but also to do meta and compassion for the two of
you who are entangled in this way in this life to to do Mets and compassion for the relationship and then let go of
the outcome let go of the outcome I think you're still attached like that's the sense I have attached to things
going particular way maybe they won't in this lifetime but still so release your
heart but continue to do release your heart from expectations and and continue
to have compassion for her for yourself and for the two of you entangled in the relationship
thank you thank you so much so thank you all for your practice with
this topic tonight quite uh yeah quiet intense and related to meta and care for
ourselves and others so thank you all for your practice mayor practice be of
benefit may it be of benefit to ourselves benefit to all beings everywhere may all beings be well may
all beings be free [Music]
thanks everyone take good care be