so good morning uh good morning to to uh some
afternoon and evening uh lovely to see where everyone's calling in from
um it's raining here in berkeley which is very unusual
um for this time of year and it feels whenever it rains even in the rainy
season feels very good these days in california
so um i'll uh share a few thoughts and we'll sit and have uh our usual uh form
so this is from um a book um from kieran kieran sataya
who's a philosopher talking about goals the goal directed
life the value of goals and then the limits of goals
says um what gives purpose to your life is having
goals yet in pursuing them you either fail not good or in succeeding
bring them to a close if what you care about is achievement earning a promotion having a child
writing a book saving a life the completion of your project may bring may be of value
but it means that the project can no longer be your guide sure you have other goals and you can
formulate new ones the problem is not the risk of running out
it is that your engagement with value is self-destructive
the way in which you relate to the activities that matter most to you
is by trying to complete them and so expel them from your life
your days are devoted to ending one by one the activities
that give them meaning
for me that captures something important important really about what
the buddha said of of dukkha of uh
unsatisfactoriness that if we live exclusively in this goal
directed life our relationship to those projects is
self-destructive we complete things and expel them from our life and then have to look for more
and there's something fatiguing for the heart in that
now is meditation like that too i think in some ways you can say yeah meditation
is a goal-oriented activity to heal to wake up
but if it's not just a goal-oriented
activity some of meditation practice
is about stepping out of goal orientation entirely
and resting with nowhere to go
and no goals to achieve and nothing to do other than
be present and so it's confusing i think for us
practitioners to sense the goal directed dimension of practice
but then also the [Music] the language and philosophy like atylic
not goal directed and atylic activities are
only ever done in the present moment that's where it happens
and so this morning or just try to guide us in that that atylic
side of practice of like really stepping out of the realm of
goal orientation where we strive and achieve and expel our goals from our
life something in the heart is restored when we
take a walk with nowhere to go or listen to a loved one
with nothing to achieve or sit in meditation
with nowhere to go nothing that needs to happen
whatsoever
so please uh find your posture
just uh arriving right here
maybe using using the your body breathing as a way of arriving
maybe there is something that
just gently put down
but from here on out and this said
we're not trying to go anywhere
we're not trying to engineer
concentration
not seeking insight
or even tranquility
just a little bit fed up with the relentlessness of our goal
seeking
and so we put it down all at once
so deep is the habit of goal making
striving and expelling
goals from our life
that we turn our meditation into it too
and we turn ourselves into self-improvement project
but for now we surrender
all notions of progress of regress of moving
somewhere anywhere no
refuge outside this moment
and the anchor if you have one the breath at the
nostrils or belly the whole body
sound the whole sphere of sensory experience
whatever the anchor is
it's only a way of reminding you
to surrender striving
to be here
thinking is uh can be
a powerful tool for solving
for achieving goals strategizing
but we're practicing non-achievement
and so our thinking strategizing simulating futures
problem solving it's not wrong it's just beside the
point
it's just a way that our goal making creeps in the side door
so we keep relaxing [Music] into all that's already here
keep relaxing into non-achievement
everything that strives in us finally gets to rest
and everything that evaluates and contests our enoughness
also gets to rest
because the only refuge
is the imperfection of this moment
and its beauty and brokenness
this is the only point
foreign [Music]
[Music]
okay thank you it's good to uh
good to sit with you um i tried to uh
ring the bell more loudly my little electronic bell
hope you heard that this morning um
okay well more to be said about those kinds of instructions
so um let's keep going
um [Music]
i i am uh often amazed that um
kind of short low-dose mindfulness interventions uh eight-week
interventions that have a lot of wisdom in them but they that's a there's a low
dose yeah they seem to develo actually deliver
positive benefits results and my sense is that if if
mindfulness and these kinds of mindfulness-based
interventions were merely attention therapy
i don't think we'd see benefits after eight weeks it's too short too small a
dose but this path of practice is many things
yeah it's not merely an attention therapy even in an eight-week mbsr program for
example mindfulness-based stress reduction there's social support and a
lot of new views that are introduced
religions are really a kind of attempt at a cognitive therapy
in part yeah and yesterday i spoke about
the dharma as an attention therapy
and today the the second mechanism dharma has a cognitive therapy
and so cognitive therapy is um [Music] this approach suggests that maladaptive
thoughts about self and world and future lead to emotional pain psychiatric
symptoms and so uh classically this is um beck
says schemas which are central to information
processing reflect various beliefs expectancies evaluations and
attributions and serve to order everyday experience
when information processing becomes distorted other systems affective
motivational behavioral begin to function in a maladaptive
manner schemas can be modified in response to
potent new information adaptively modified schemas deactivate
dysfunctional schemas which leads to a reduction in symptoms
so we're living our life in a situation something happens it elicits
schemas which elicits emotions and motivations and behaviors
and so the treatment is that maladaptive thoughts are explored and challenged and
self and world and future are reappraised
reappraised we we reconstrue self and world
and classic kind of distortions of over generalizing or catastrophizing
or dichotomous black white thinking
these distortions are corrected
and those corrections are said to lead to more adaptive appraisals of the world
more adaptive functional schemas
it's the structure of cognitive therapy cognitive behavioral therapy
uh a blend and um
practice is a cognitive therapy too
in part it begins with wise view right with understanding
right understanding right view
the buddha says with wrong view wrong everything follows
yeah with wrong view wrong effort wrong action wrong speech
all the stuff that gets us into trouble this follows on the heels of wrong view
so we pick up wise view right and the dharma introduces so many
views yeah so many views so many ways of perceiving
experience that are adaptive functional a functional schema
this is how you divide up experience not good and evil
but suffering and freedom from suffering that's the distinction to attend to
it invites the view that clinging hurts always trying to
control experience hurts
the view that suffering can be redeemed this is a path of purification
and suffering is not a brute fact in the way we imagine
it can be redeemed it can be transmuted into
wisdom love
the view that everything you are is a facet of nature
and that the story of me is forever at least
a little wrong and so the buddha invites a view of the
self that is fresh the self as a kind of to use
some philosophical language from gilbert ryall the self as a
category mistake so this is ryle
foreigner visiting oxford or cambridge for the first time has shown a number of colleges libraries playing fields
museums scientific departments and administrative offices
he then asks but where is the university
it has then to be explained to him that the university is not another collateral
institution some ulterior counterpart to the college's laboratories and
offices which he has seen the university is just the way in which
all that he has already seen is organized
the buddha introduces a view of the self like this
now part of what we're doing is uh in our practice is beginning to detect
the s stories and schemas we live by
some of which are quite obvious and some are very subtle but all the things we believe without knowing we have fidelity
to them these kind of wild absurd
beliefs that if we actually said them out loud they would seem utterly ridiculous
but there's a part of us that has fidelity to them i should be
perfect yeah should be loved by everyone
the next possession is going to
make me finally happy
i shouldn't experience physical and emotional discomfort i
shouldn't get sick maybe should never die
we're much more suggestible than we believe if
we feel so autonomous these are my views but they're
conditioned by a million factors right so
we are all of our time in a way
and so many cultural inheritances and stories about our bodies and about
our affective life stories about strength and weakness about the nature of
happiness and the good life
and um and we just take these things on we take these things on we're more permeable
than we recognize and so we look we look we investigate what are
the stories we live by and our stories about ourselves are so
often charged with a kind of moralism yeah kind of infantile
toddler-ish moralism our egos are a kind of tangle of moralism
and so we start to see i have a lot of maladaptive beliefs
about happiness we basically assume the opposite of the
three characteristics
suffering unreliability impermanence not self
fantasy that some some pleasure will end all seeking
fantasy that the more choice we have the better we are
the researcher about choice yeah how could five choices possibly be
worse than two but yeah sometimes the proliferation of options can have a
variety of negative effects on well-being as options are added within a domain of choice three problems
materialize first there is the problem of gaining adequate information about the options
to make a choice second there's the problem that as options expand
people's standards for what's acceptable rises and third
there is the problem that options expand people may come to believe that any
unacceptable result is their fault because with so many options they should have been able to find a satisfactory
one in dharma
a lot of our happiness comes in narrowing choice narrowing the menu
in all spheres
we have the sense that if we worry in just the right way we'll be able to game out aneesha
to manage uh uncertainty
and anxiety is is um is the intolerance of uncertainty
we have the sense that um if i accomplish this or that become this or that i'll finally feel
like a grown-up yeah finally land in a kind of identity and
feel at home and
that moment never comes as far as i can tell
and so we look what are our organizing assumptions and how is the cognitive
therapy of dharma relevant
yesterday i spoke about the attentional dharma as a kind of attentional therapy
and these two interact the cognitive therapy and the attentional therapy because
as i was alluding to yesterday when the mind is steady stable concentrated it's
very valuable very elastic
and the cognitive changes the new views we introduce
has um more staying power the learning induced
has more staying power makes deeper
marks in our being
so i offer this for consideration and
yeah happy to be with you and look forward to
tomorrow okay uh thank you uh thank you all i wish you a good
good day