so good morning or day or evening
it's nice to see everyone coming on it's a good time to start uh sitting
together so just settling in
once again and finding your meditation posture for today
bringing the attention gently into the body
maybe just taking a moment to check in internally how are you right now
how's the body how's the mind
just knowing that you're here letting go of whatever you were doing
before or whatever activities were needed before getting to the screen
and just knowing that you're taking this time for meditation
so inviting some ease throughout the body
maybe softening some of the usual tight places
maybe the face letting that soften
the jaw letting the shoulders release
just soften
softening the belly
and the arms and legs
shifting the body slightly if needed in order to have a balanced and natural
posture
encouraging a sense of aliveness in the body
alertness and also relaxation
and then similarly in the mind inviting some ease
so there may be thoughts or feelings
which is all fine and normal but can we find some part of the mind
that can be at ease with that
somehow by knowing that by just being aware of what's going on
often the mind can relax
and to help the mind orient we can feel the sensations of the
breath
the in and out rhythm of however the breath is right now
and then expanding the awareness to include the whole sense of the body
so not necessarily the details of each little sensation
but the general sense of the sitting posture
or if you're lying down the lying down posture
even if the breath remains the primary object it's very helpful to have
a general sense of the body sitting
so in today's sit i would like to offer [Music]
three ways that the scent of the body
is useful in
being with the changes that happen in the mind being
with the thoughts and emotions that can distract the mind
so the ways that the body can support the mind
and they're only if you're interested if you prefer to just stay with your meditation that is fine
so these are supports that we can bring in [Music] at a time when we notice that the mind
is easily getting caught up
so as you're sitting resting with
the breath of the body if the mind is getting going down rabbit holes shall we say
we can firm up our sense of the body
so instead of getting drawn down into anxiety or sadness
or envy one of the heavy emotions
we can rest in the sense of substantiality in the body
somehow that strength of the material body can sometimes
keep the mind from getting overwhelmed by an emotion
so it's useful to get familiar with feeling that
substantiality of the body
another way that the body can support the mind
is to tune in to the stillness
of the body to emphasize the non-moving
part of the posture and to imagine that as a
a calming or a dampening effect so this is useful when the mind is
engaged with the flames of irritation or discontent
the various ways that the mind can flare up
and then we can have a sense of the stillness of the body like a calm lake
cooling down the tirade of the mind
the contrast between the still body and the movement of the mind is obvious
so we can help to reel the mind back in
and then the third option [Music] for how the body can support the mind
works particularly well with the meditation on the breath
simply to increase the continuity of the mindfulness
the extent of it so we can allow mindfulness to pervade more of the
body really feeling the fullness of the breath in the body
and also extend the continuity in time
to feel the full duration of the breath
committing to stay with all the little sensations throughout the body throughout the
length of the breath
and we may find that there's something satisfying about that in a certain way
because it's simple just to be with these various breath sensations
and then there's no room for long thoughts or complex emotions
there's some satisfaction with that
so we can imagine that the mind gains strength through its association
with the body together they can
prevent various thoughts and emotions from taking hold and dragging the mind and heart around
and it's not that we don't need to attend to those things but it's often helpful in meditation to
to say not now we will think about these things but but
later
so we have the substantiality of the body
and the sense of stillness it can cool the mind down
and the continuity the close connection between mind and body
so noticing how the mind and the body work together
even in meditation which may seem like it's mostly about the mind
there's this interaction going on
they support each other
oh
perhaps there are ways during your day today
when you could find ways to benefit from this support
between the body and the mind
the body is always in the present moment
so we can always drop into our awareness of the body
throughout the day whether we're on the computer or talking with someone
or shopping whatever we need to do
maybe there's a way to connect with the material substance of the body its
robustness its strength even if we're not physically strong the
sense of substantiality
to help the mind be more grounded
or maybe we can use the relative
slowness of the body to slow the mind down
to dampen down any flames that arise in the mind
or maybe just deliberately tying the mind to the body for a
stretch of time will provide less opportunity for the
mind to wander off or to get caught up
the body is so available to us and there are many ways that it can
support our mind throughout the day and then that supports our relationships
and our ability to be present and to do what we can to serve this
world that so much needs our presence
[Music] uh
[Music]
so we're talking this week about mindfulness as a protection
and different dimensions of that image and we talked earlier about
mindfulness as safety and non-mindfulness is danger
and kind of along similar lines but with a different facet of that
sometimes the buddha talked about mindfulness as a strength and lack of mindfulness as weakness
so today we'll talk about protection in the form of
strength and there are a whole [Music]
bouquet of wonderful similes about this in the discourse that is on mindfulness of
the body that's matching uh 119 for those of you who
want to look it up and i just want to um read a little bit
about some of these images are really great so
um okay so when someone
has not developed and cultivated mindfulness of the body
mara that is the forces of distraction mara finds an opportunity and a support
in that person suppose someone were to throw a heavy stone ball upon a mound of wet clay
and then he asks what do you think would that heavy ball find entry into that mound of wet clay and the monks say oh
yes yes venerable sir and so if someone has not cultivated
mindfulness of the body mara can get in
and then later he's and then he says the opposite of that you know suppose that
someone has developed and cultivated mindfulness of the body
in that case mara cannot find an opportunity or support
and the image is suppose a person were to throw a light ball of string at a
door panel made entirely of heartwood what do you think would that light ball
of string find entry through the door panel of heartwood and of course the monks say no
no it wouldn't so we have this these two powerful contrasting images of a heavy
stone ball thrown into wet clay and a light ball of string thrown against a
door of heartwood and so as i reflect on this um
i know that there are times when you know when the emotional state is kind of one of collapse
right and so you know the mind is just kind of collapsed and so it's it's easy
for even small things to push their way into our psyche at times like that
and so this image of a stone ball kind of points toward heaviness and burden
and then in in contrast a door that's made of heartwood feels
upright and strong and solid it has a clear shape and clear
boundaries so i think that's the contrast being made
here i know i've had sittings where my mind was repeatedly overrun by certain
emotions or thought trains and then when i look back after regaining mindfulness
it's as if i had no firmness along that dimension where the thought or emotion was coming in
and even if i was vaguely aware that those thoughts were starting to emerge i had no real resistance to their just
pushing into my whole consciousness like the wet clay doesn't resist an entry of
a stone ball so then you know what's the remedy for this when we realize
you know sometimes it can help to just be a bit firmer in our resolution to sit in meditation
or we can use as i mentioned in the guided meditation this feeling of
substantiality and body to bolster the strength of the mind
so the door image nicely conveys that we're kind of closing the door on certain inputs that they don't gain
entry into the mind and just say no thank you this is not the time for that and we
in that way we kind of bolster our healthy boundaries in mind if you will
so then there's a second image we're going to do three images all from
this suta today the second image says
again suppose that somebody were not to cultivate mindfulness of the
body and so he says suppose there were a dry sapless piece of wood
and a person came with an upper fire stick thinking i shall light a fire i
shall produce heat what do you think monks could that person light a fire and produce heat by
rubbing the dry sapless piece of wood with an upper fire stick and they say oh yes that would work well
and similarly he says mara can find an opportunity or support in someone who hasn't cultivated
mindfulness of the body and then the opposite image is
suppose there were a wet sappy piece of wood and a person came along with an
upper fire stick and wanted to light a fire but they would not be able to do that
you know because of the wet sappy piece of wood that they were striking it against and so you know similarly
we have this image then of this image i think relates especially to
irritation or aversion but it could also i think apply to greedy or deluded thoughts but when the
mind is is weak and it's not connected well to the body the mind can easily pick up a
small input like a pain in the body or a subtle thought of frustration or dislike
and then keep rubbing away at it until it catches fire it becomes a huge
conflagration in the mind but with mindfulness of the body that repeated irritation
can't build up and cause the fire have you ever had sittings like this i
certainly have so i remember one time having a conversation with a nun who was talking about how her mind
sometimes felt like it was on fire and she was struggling to put it out during meditation
and she said that often when she would investigate more carefully around the edges of that fire
maybe the parts that weren't so much in the foreground of her consciousness she would discover that some part of her
own mind was throwing kindling on the flames you know kind of in the side where she wasn't looking so carefully
and this is really the case you know we so maybe the image from the suta would be that over on the side we we're
rubbing the fire stick and just generating more and more sparks to build up the flame
so um you know we think that what we need to do to deal with is our irritation and our frustrating our
frustration because that thing is so irritating and i have to manage my irritation of it and it's so irritating
but in fact there are many supports in our own mind that inflame irritation or frustration
the image of the two fire sticks is pretty apt in that we're supplying half
of the stimulus right which maybe we're supplying both haves
so [Applause] often we have views and beliefs that we aren't quite aware of or expectations that's
very common so the mind is getting riled up and if the mind is getting riled up repeatedly
it can be worth investigating to see what ideas or expectations in our own
mind are contributing and then bringing mindfulness to those and one
support can be to feel the stillness and the relative coolness of
the body so to imagine the body is kind of a um a lake and at least the awareness of
the body as a calm lake and then this conflagration in the mind is kind of on
top of that and contrasts with it so we should be able to use that to investigate and see
how it is that we're riling ourselves up
okay and then the third image in the suta is of a water jug so
in the case of non-mindfulness of the body suppose there were a hollow empty water
jug set out on a stand and a person came with a supply of water
what do you think could the person pour water into the jug oh yes yes of course
and so similarly someone who has not developed and cultivated mindfulness of the body
mara finds an opportunity and a support and then the contrast is that if there
were a water jug that were full right up to the brim with water and a person were to come along could they pour water into
that jug and the monks say no no of course not and so if we've cultivated mindfulness
of the body then it's like trying to pour water into a full drug
we can't do it and so in this image there's a sense of fullness as a strength and
in my own practice i see this as relating to continuity of mindfulness
so there are kind of two dimensions of continuity in relation to mindfulness of the body
and my use of the breath as an example in the meditation so we can be aware of the full
spatial extent of the breath it's not just in the lungs but it kind of pervades the whole body
as energy and actually even if we try to look for the boundaries of the body sometimes they're
not so clear so it might be that the breath extends even out into space a bit
and when we're full to the brim we haven't left out any aspect of the breath
in the bodily experience there's a fullness to how we're experiencing that
and then there's also the second dimension of continuity and time so we can be aware from the very
beginning of the in-breath to the end of the in-breath the little gap and the start of the out breath and then all the
way to the very end even as it gets very subtle before the next in-breath
and when mindfulness has this kind of fullness then there's no opportunity for some
distraction to slip in any more than we could pour water into an already full pitcher
so if we pay attention in our own mind we can check where in the cycle of the breath
does mindfulness tend to be weak you know that's where the thoughts can find entry or are there parts or regions of the
body that we're not really aware of and so you know if we have thoughts or
emotions that are related to that part of the body they would easily get into the mind and start growing
so then so there are interesting images right about mindfulness as a strength and not succumbing to the
weakness of being overpowered by these various things in the mind and then the buddha after that
lists a bunch of benefits of mindfulness of the body we don't have time for all
the benefits but i want to just mention a few of them
so one of them is that and again it uses this image of you'll
hear the strength metaphor one becomes a conqueror of discontent
and delight and discontent does not conquer oneself one abides overcoming
discontent whenever it arises one becomes a conqueror of fear and
dread and fear and dread do not conquer oneself one abides overcoming fear and dread
whenever they arise so there's a sense of [Music]
strength in being able to overcome various issues in the mind
and then it goes on there's another one about overcoming one bears well with cold and heat hunger
and thirst contacts with various physical things wind the sun creeping things
and also one endures ill-spoken unwelcome words and painful bodily
feelings so there's a way in which this mindfulness of the body gives strength for unpleasant physical and mental
experiences and our willingness to be present in our
form helps us to overcome those things to conquer those things and then i'll skip to the end of the
list which is where one realizes for oneself with direct
knowledge and abides here and now in deliverance of mind and deliverance
by wisdom the destruction of the taints so all of that is code for one reaches full
awakening so mindfulness of the body can take one all the way to freedom
from great hatred and delusion so all of this power or strength i want
to emphasize is not the kind of power that is oppressive or dictatorial or
aggressive instead i will suggest that it comes from compassion
it's the strength of really caring about our own mind and heart
and also caring about other people so um you know when we're strong and mindful
we are protecting our own well-being from the various inputs that we've said
many times we're not going to be able to not have inputs we're going to have to learn somehow to meet them with
mindfulness and this strength that's being pointed to here comes from caring about our well-being
caring that we are able to meet things well in life everything from the irritation in our
need to ill-spoken unwelcome words to discontent because life is
challenging and we can't get things the way we want it all the way up to the moment of death
so when we're strong and mindful we can protect not only our well-being
but we can i'm now going to say extend that protection outward to care for others
and that's tomorrow's topic is mindfulness as protection for both our self
and others so i hope you'll appreciate these images of strength and be inspired is um
that mindfulness is really a powerful force in our lives and it may bring you a lot of benefit today
and also spread to those around you all right see you tomorrow