so
good morning everyone and good day
I'm quite happy to be back here after these three weeks of being on Retreat
and
okay I kind of feel I feel very content to be here with all of you too and maybe a little bit too content since
all that occurs to me to say is um is that but we will uh get I'll get into the
swing of it of teaching here in the morning and
so um um a little bit uh kind of
dipping into some of the teachings from this three-week Retreat I taught
I want to start with um this simple idea that sometimes floats
around different places and physics and other places that um you can't observe something without
changing it and so you don't necessarily see exactly what is there but you see somehow you
see what's kind of core arising with How You observe it
and that could well be but what I'd like to suggest today is
that you can't observe something you can't be aware of something you can't know something
without changing the Observer changing you
and that the act of seeing something recognizing something knowing something that's happening in the moment
that something can also happen to the Observer to the meditator
an ordinary life things go so quickly we hardly notice that but in meditation we're allowing for
that to really build a change within us that creates
um a a context or can take it creates a
container for holding our experience
so uh maybe it'll be a little more interesting for you to stay present
if you also are aware that this is also bringing about the beneficial change in
you maybe not the change you want to see happen if your knees hurt you want the paint go to go away
if you're somehow agitated you want the agitation to go away
but some in a different way the act of mindfulness begins to change
the Observer change you and that can be uh
guided or be augmented in a very nice way
if in the knowing of the experience whatever thing we know we know it in a
calm way we know it peacefully and that is and what we can bring to the
cut for the bring to the practice is not just our mindfulness but we can also bring a mindfulness
which is calm or peaceful that is not agitated
and the wonderfulness of that is that it's then possible to calmly know
agitation calmly know what is troubling
how we're troubled and as we use this calm knowing
this changes the observer in a nice way
so to take a meditation posture
and whatever posture works for you to um
to meditate in but ideally a posture
that Expresses in and of itself a bit of alertness
some part of your body is made alert with the chest is more open
the back is a little straighter a little bit more vertical
for some people having their head tipped down and back a bit
is a useful thing to do
in lowering the Gaze and if your eyes are still open to let
your gaze be soft almost like the hero being a you're
gazing with your peripheral vision
now that anything in particular
gently closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow breaths
as the deep in breath grows to feel
more fully your torso the expansion of your chest
and as you exhale to relax
let go
into and let your breathing return to normal
and other further places in your body you can now relax
release
and also as you exhale to relax the thinking mind
any tension or pressure associated with thinking
let it relax and settle
any agitation of the Mind
can you allow it to become calmer
like a stormy sea that becomes still
quiet
and then become aware of some sensation in your body
that's neutral or easy to be aware of
sensation which you can be aware of calmly
peaceful awareness a peaceful knowing
a gentle and peaceful recognition of the sensation
staying with a sensation for maybe three or four more breaths
or another one if it goes away and with every exhale
see if their awareness or the knowing
of the sensation can be calmer
Maybe by recognizing it a few times each time a little bit more calmly
and the more you can be aware the more you could recognize
whatever is happening in a calm way
their recognition will change you
so then now centering your attention on the breathing
and calmly bring forth a calm knowing of breathing
a calm recognition of inhale
a peaceful recognition of exhale
and if there are other things to be aware of during this meditation
experiment with being aware in a calm fashion
no hurry
no worry about what your experience is
for there to be a beneficial change in you
simply through your calm knowing
calm recognition of what's Happening
it's helpful to be continuous
in that knowing in that awareness
continually renewing it when it fades away
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn your gaze out into the world Minds gaze
calmly imagining or bringing to mind
people of your life your neighbors colleagues
people you see on the streets or in the stores
in them imagine gazing upon them kindly gazing upon them calmly
peacefully
and to wish them well to wish them a peaceful time
and to offer them a little taste little
peace in how you know them how you look upon them
looking upon them peacefully
may they be peaceful may they be happy
may they be safe
may they be free
and may we find a way to be peaceful together
and in doing so change the way that we relate to each
other for the better
[Music]
thank you foreign
good day everyone whether it's morning or afternoon or evening for you
and um and as most of you that are on right now
no I mean wait for three weeks and um happily teaching a three-week
retreat the second one we've done at our Retreat Center in Santa Cruz California
and I imagine that some of you who are watching today we're at that
Retreat I think there were some 140 or so people on it
um 130 140 uh about 40 in person and
another 80 90 or so doing it online
and um so it's since it just ended two days ago on Saturday I feel kind of very much
still in the momentum of the retreat
and in without with the teachings there still in my mind
I want to say something about uh
the consciousness awareness I see Consciousness and
awareness is being uh synonyms of each other
and in fact in uh in one dictionary that I have you look
up the definition for Consciousness it says awareness and look up definition for awareness it has consciousness
I'm sure that there are people who will parse apart more better distinctions between them
but uh and maybe in a simple person's English that it's very easy to to to
treat these as being the same and um
but the question is you know what is it what is consciousness what is awareness
and I don't really know exactly but I have a theory and it's a working Theory and that it's
a theory with which I work the theory the kind of understanding with which I
follow them I find my way with I'm in awe by the capacity to be aware
to be conscious and I see it kind of as a metaphor is kind of like a spark
in a vast Universe kind of like a little candle that's burning
then we have seven billion of these candles burning in of Consciousness or brightness of of
and Clarity that uh that we all all humans share and
to the degree to which we share it with animals and other sentient beings is um
you know it's not so clear but there's a lot of different ideas about it
and uh so I'd like to kind of relate this idea of Consciousness to the basic
tools of mindfulness that Consciousness is not a thing
it's not a static thing but rather it's a
it's uh the image
or the sense that the Mind constructs for the Gestalt of all the different
past cities we have for attention and all the different kind of mental
influences that might impact on our attention
and so Gestalt means something that's uh kind of a hole that's larger than its uh
some of its parts and um and so the mind has this capacity
to construct to take and that's the mind is a constructing organ it can it takes in a lot of the
data from outside and inside from all the different scent stores we have and
the inner from the mind and the minds memories and thoughts and projections of
the future and it's an amazing uh the mind is an amazing organ of processing data
information that comes in and then reconstructing in such a way that we can
find our way in the world one of the ways that I Marvel at is that
um you can um someone can throw you a ball
in the air and you your mind will calculate the physics
of when and how and where you will catch the bow
if it's a beach ball you'll calculate it very differently than if it's a baseball thrown at you as
a festival um you know so there's a very different kind of calculation that goes on and
that includes the height of the right to throw and the weight of the ball the the
size of it all kinds of things come into play and uh and your mind doesn't calculate
the physics of it in a conscious way but somehow it knows it takes all the data
in maybe the memory of different balls being thrown in before and understands
the the particularities of this time so this is the mind's ability to
construct and to make things and we know that sometimes it's does so
creatively that um or or sees things dynamically that are
not really dynamic in a certain way and so the old uh movie films eight
millimeter films where there's all these uh individual frames
that are still shots but when they pass through the eyes quickly the brain reconstruction as
motion there's no motion on the on the screen there's a lot of
quick still shots put on there and um and so the Mind constructs
something so the mind has a constructive organ and it takes all the different capacities
for perception and awareness and knowing and recognition
and together forms kind of a whole sense of what that
is that can feel like it's the marvelous sense of consciousness of awareness open
broad spectrum awareness but the way people experience
consciousness and being aware varies very much from person to person and from an individual
from day to day depending on all kinds of mental factors that come into play
that um that's a that the influence that sense of awareness and consciousness
so for example if we spend a lot of time being distracted then we hardly even know that we're
conscious and aware uh you know we know it in the abstract but we don't live in
the in the in the intimate awareness of awareness the Intimates knowing of wow
this is amazing whereas other times when we're not distracted and may be in some beautiful
natural setting or looking at the sky and clouds we might kind of Marvel at
the fact that here we are on this planet aware of the planet and
um and how you know special that is and and
um and it's you know quite something to be with someone as they die and see that
there's Consciousness and then seemingly in that body there's no more consciousness
you know it's kind of that'll happen to us at some day
so Consciousness sense of it all can uh can depend on whether we're distracted
or not distracted calm or not calm um and um so the sense of Consciousness
is influence in different ways by different ways in which we know things
and in mindfulness practice there are different attentional faculties that
come into play and um and different people who use will specialize in different ones of these
attentional faculties as they're grounding into mindfulness
mindfulness itself is not a particular function of a particular organ of
perception but rather is also a little bit of a Gestalt of different things
coming together to help us to be mindful that maybe is narrower or a smaller
sphere of it things than what it constructs the idea of consciousness
um uh so um
so today I want to talk uh today and tomorrow I think a little bit about uh
in the rest of the week some of these different attentional fact of facilities
capacities we have and um and what they are so we can recognize them the more we recognize the
more we can use them at different times in ways and I'll talk about the other ones that the Buddha emphasized when he
taught mindfulness practice and there's about four different things that he ways of paying attention that he
emphasized and with a with a principle that we are changed as we use them
The Observers when we observe The Observer something The Observer can
be changed by the observation and and that's a principle that we're
using in Buddhist practice we're observing we're being mindful in such a way that we are changed in the observing
the simplest way of seeing it saying it is that as we OBS we observe in a calm
way we become calmer and calmer if we observe our experience in an agitated
way it's easy to become more and more agitated so
um so how we're aware is crucial for this Enterprise of mindfulness and
allowing it to change us for the better and so uh what I'll talk about today and
tomorrow now it's almost time to stop is what I call knowing
which I see as a synonym for recognition a moment of recognition just a simplest
recognition of something looking at a at a cup and recognizing
that's a cup that can be verbal you know recognition or it can be kind
of non-verbal cognitive recognition of a cup we have a lot of non-verbal cognition that goes on all the all day
long and um and uh
but if you take the time to let your knowing of something
to really know it to really kind of in a sense let yourself stop for a moment or more and to really know the experience
you're having or know the thing that you're with know the cup that you're with and um
and then see if you can know it in a calm way begin experimenting with calm knowing of
things and that could be the homework for the next 24 hours if you're inclined is to um
is to go you know during the course of the day
see uh uh the manner by which you know the world you're in your Pursuit where
you're perceiving it but especially how you recognize what's going on is that in a hurry is it agitated is it
tense is it contracted is it pulling away what happens if to you to you if you
know if you recognize something in their recognition itself has time to be done
calmly and then I'll pick up on this tomorrow so I hope that makes sense and
um and uh I hope that as we go through this week you'll start appreciating both
the different faculties for attention but also how those faculties then might
help shape our sense our construction of Consciousness itself
so um thank you very much and um look forward to being here tomorrow