so hello and welcome to happier everyone yeah it's lovely to be with you it's
happy making to be with you in this moment in time wherever you are in the world so
ah so for today's practice i'd like to invite us to explore
a couple of themes one is um yeah i want to bring two themes together
the the theme of meta kindness
together with the theme of peace peace
especially given that it's a friday or saturday depending on your time zone so a sense of bringing in a sense of peace
and peacefulness this this um you know meta can show up in so many
different ways meta kindness this practice can be very energetic and warm
and it can also be very quiet very gentle very comforting soothing very stilling
very stilling so that's one aspect that i want to
bring in and and invite us to really rest to relax into it there's not so
much doing that needs to be done but to rest but really to rest
and um the other theme i want to weave in today is um
is one of impermanence is one of
of brevity of time brevity of our time and the best
way to be with the brevity of our time um
that actually we are all dying we are dying every
moment and the best way to really appreciate that and open our heart to that is with
peace is with stillness with presence being fully present with care with love
with appreciation for whatever is in this moment in time
for ourselves for others i want to weave those in and even though maybe for some
it feels like wow awareness of our brevity of time awareness of mortality is not peaceful
but it can be you know that it can be and actually the appropriate response is peace
the appropriate response is peace so and and the invitation is
if um leaning into brevity of time really brings in more
sense of letting go peace love kindness lean into it but if it
brings um [Music] more agitation then don't lean into it
it's an invitation you don't have to lean into it at all you can stay with the yes
yes saying yes to the peace to the calm to the presence of the groundedness
in this moment so see what is more helpful for you
as i bring up the invitations and um yeah and
lean more or less into these invitations so
see what might work for you so okay well let's get formally started with our
with our practice so so moving your body perhaps
if you need to move shift find a comfortable position
where you can be sitting or lying down or even standing whatever
this body needs whatever this body needs
appropriate response to what is needed in this moment what does your heart need
your body need at this moment
ah letting go releasing
with the out breath
ah letting the in-breath be received in the abdomen
the in-breath received
the out-breath released released letting go
feeling sensing sensations of the feet
and the earth the hands on your lap
your sit bones on the cushion on the chair these contact points
releasing your weight onto these contact points
releasing releasing doesn't mean pushing away if
there is their emotions present might be sadness grief joy
disappointment whatever there might be it's okay
instead of holding them tight
as if you were carrying a load of bricks in your chest to release it's okay
let them gently drop on the floor proverbially
with you ah don't have to hold them so tight
all them contained let them release
let the sack open ah no longer heavy being carried
i let the breath be spacious
through the body the whole body
around the body
and if your body was
the breathing breathing ball
maybe the edges are a little blurry
a little elastic the breath
being breathed inside outside including breathing through
the bricks that have fallen on the floor about you maybe softening maybe the
bricks as they're breathed into maybe they become a little softer
a little lighter
not effortful just happens on its own
maybe nothing more is needed in this moment but to just
be breathed let everything be breathed your joy your
sorrow your lightness your heaviness
your gladness your grief your gratitude your disappointment
your hopes and dreams for the future your fears all of them breathed
right here all of them okay to be here
uh
any thoughts arise preoccupation let them be breathed
through not so heavy
the grace of the breath touching everything
this breath this thread this thread that keeps
you alive breathing through everything all these
moments
of awakeness of sleep
of being alive this thread
this precious thread
runs through everything can be aware
of the grace of this breath threads through everything
let run through everything
holding this magic thread let it lead you
comfort you calm you
lighten the weight
inspire you
inviting the breath receiving the breath
it's also an expression of care for yourself
meta kindness distilling the mind and heart
listening to the breath
this caring lullaby
these precious days these precious moments
spent with yourself but this being who is you
this being who is me
expressing my care my love
simply by being present the precious breaths
here
intimate so intimate with oneself
this beloved we may have ignored all day
intimately attending listening feeling each breath each
precious breath
and if the mind wonders if there is distraction sleepiness
it's okay can it be greeted
and breathed through let the breath
the ease of the body let the breath breathe ease through the body and
thoughts in your heart your mind
in this moment and now in this moment
and now again this fresh moment of now-ness
keeps fleeting keeps fleeting
king's fleeting
even more precious as it slips comes and goes through our fingers
it's like this
spacious spacious
can the sense of care kindness be imbued in the breath
just being present for ourselves in this moment
this precious breath is an act of meta it doesn't have to become complicated
no phrase is needed just being present
holding spacious presence through ourselves
an act of care
i'm here for you sweetheart
just being being breathed
and whatever is present it's boredom sleepiness sadness
joy peace is welcome
breathed into breathed with body relaxed
with kindness
if your heart were smiling at all the comings and
goings in this impermanent moment
this practice this being present in this moment for myself
is both for me and so much bigger greater than me
seemingly holding witness space with the breath from myself
opens up to more dimensionality of what who
this person is a service
for all beings all beings our lives
each breath is an offering [Music]
to others to those we love
those we're connected to directly and everyone indirectly
may not understand all the dimensions all the meanings
but trusting that our breathing or being in the world
our actions
for good or bad
impact ourselves and so much beyond ourselves
to dedicate the goodness the grace of our practice
the beauty trusting in the goodness that has been created co-created
to all beings everywhere with gratitude with appreciation
that we live on this earth we're here to breathe to hold witness
together with all the joys and all the sorrows in these precious days
while we're alive may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thank you thank you friends for your practice thank you
so good to sit with you so good to sit with you
my sitting is lovely i love sitting alone and yet sitting together with you in sangha as you are
in various places in the world just makes my heart happy so happy
yes i see a heart there yes other hearts are happy too sweet sweet so
so so
so we have some time if there are reflections
if you'd like to share and
i'm going to change you're welcome to raise your hand
uh anthony i see you here we go
there
nikki uh i wanted to thank you so much for this uh uh guiding guided meditation
i was very powerful um it was um
very easy for me to comprehend uh i always over overthink it
to where you know what i'm doing and just uh the simplicity of receive
and uh release you know i really i really felt that and it was very very uh
felt very very good so i wanted to thank you for that i've never uh
felt it that simple you know that simple so thank you thank you thank you anthony thank you so
much release release yeah yeah the simplicity
of that beautiful thank you for sharing that yeah
and see see simone i trust it's okay to say your
name because i think it's sent to everyone let's see it's a long so i'm
going to summarize and start reading the whole thing so let's see um [Music]
yeah let's see
right right right yeah great yeah so so i appreciate i think that
what i'm reading is that you appreciated the guided meditation my voice is calm and soothing and yet mentioning death
and dying is triggering for you especially as you're dealing with cancer at this time and it really deals really
hits home so how to i think the question that you have asked but i'm going to paraphrase it actually
what you've asked is how to continue to come because you want to come to happier and you want to do the practices and yet
the mention of death brings stress and anxiety so
keeping triggering so so uh i appreciate you saying that and
and also to um and to take care of yourself i mean the
invitation that i had at the beginning was to see what is helpful for you to lean into
what is helpful what is not helpful and and i would venture actually to say and
and you you may not know this but i love teaching about meta and love and i also
really appreciate teaching it's one of the other things that i teach a lot about which is mindfulness of mortality
um so that really it's so that we work
with the with the anxiety because the solution is not to avoid
um to to to turn away when any mention of
death arises because we're all dying and and yes i appreciate that
there's something that you're working with right now given the cancer and it's very um
uh present for you and um what i'm trying to say is that you know
and i can stay and we can have a conversation short conversation at the end can reach out to me and to say
it's actually let me share the intention the intention
that i do have with combining the mentioning of death and mortality with
a meditation that is about release letting go and calming
is actually to help us work with that anxiety death anxiety because you might
have heard of systematic desensitization which is a method in psychology so there are many
methods also in in in buddhist practice which is slowly slowly pairing this gentle letting go
calming soothing and bringing a little bit of the mention of what might be triggering or might be
challenging or anxiety producing for some to pair it so that it can be held
in in ease we can lose our fear we can lose our
trepidation because it's the human condition of course we're all gonna die we all have a terminal condition we
don't know when with having a terminal illness perhaps and it may not be terminal so sorry i don't want to
be saying that but having illnesses uh as i do have a chronic illness myself
makes it more challenging to deal with these conditions but anyway i'm happy to
stay but there is a reason to this there is a there is actually um
quite a deliberate way of bringing these in and pairing and supporting with death
phobia especially in our culture so so um [Music]
that's what i would like to say about that and again i'm happy to stay later if you want to stay and and i can
talk with you one on one about this any other reflections
questions
yeah so
we are approaching the time to
um yeah so it's actually both it's it's
the bringing mortality makes meta more more palpable there's so many ways in
there are so many ways in so i'd like to invite us all to practice
with uh in small groups and [Music]
as always the invitation is to only share from your own experience not
managing not handling not not [Music] probing into other people's
experience and [Music]
the each person is invited to share one nugget from their own experience
and then the next person and the next person then you go around and round so
take care of yourselves take care of each other and if it comes to you your turn and you want to stay silent
silent and just say pass that's perfectly okay here we go great so we have just about a minute if
there are any reflections and questions comments
you can type in chat you can raise your hand please take it away what's up
thank you for the heart what's up
any reflections anything that came up in the groups maybe just quickly i see it's
actually it's seven o'clock so tell you what we're going to formally bring it to a close just to respect the time and
i'll stay a few minutes extra and happy to uh to have
reflections afterwards so thank you all thank you for your practice thank you
for coming and supporting each other supporting yourselves all beings everywhere
may may you be safe happy healthy and have ease
[Music] take good care be well