so hello so today i want to talk about
perfection and imperfection in relationship to this practice that we do
and um one of the little take-homes i hope to take with you because little slogan
is the idea that it's better to be righted than it is to be right
and this is a nautical reference sailboats maybe maybe most of you know that all of
you know it may be but sailboats that have a keel
a strong tempest a wind can come and push this elbow over towards the side tip it or tip it
quite far but because the keel is quite heavy the more it gets tipped the more the
keel kind of is heavy in a sense and counters um
the the force of the wind or the waves and then the boat and the keel rights the boat
uh and both comes to standing a righted boat who understands more or less the mast is vertical again
and uh and boats are being tossed around in the sea sailboats and they're constantly being you know righted
and uh and therefore they don't capsize usually and
so this wonderful expression to be righted is to come back into balance to come back and to be upright
so the this little slogan is it's better to be righted than to be right
where being right means that you know that you you are right with your opinions you're right with what you
do you kind of justified you defend yourself you have an opinion that you feel is the
true opinion and everyone else should know it or you're going to defend it at all costs
and so one has to do with a the second one has to do with a kind of a some idea
and ideas come and go and the for the first has to do with your your disposition how you actually
are as opposed to what you believe and what you think so it's better to be righted
than to be right and so the practice is to help write us
practice provides a keel a ballast that can help keeps us come back up
and we'll get tossed around by the waves of life all the time and but if we have a keel
something like that we'll get will become righted and that's part of the function of mindfulness
is that it's partly functions as a keel just to know the clarity of knowing what's happening
begins that movement to be righted to be come back up straight straight upright or something
so that's kind of a little bit the one of the takeaways i'm hoping you'll understand by this talk
so but the theme perfection and imperfection is that
the buddhist tradition if you listen to teachers and read about it and the ancient texts
is that it lends itself or has a kind of a shadow side or lends itself to this idea of
perfection and that there's some you're trying to attain something perfectly
and i think it's most represented by the by the
idea that someone is fully enlightened here we have the word fully enlightened
there's partially on there's a fully enlightened or perfectly enlightened the buddha was said to be perfectly
enlightened that if someone gets fully enlightened they have
overcome all suffering they freed themselves from all suffering
you know there's no room for suffering then that's perfect perfectly free of suffering
they've someone has perfectly freed themselves from all their defilements
all their attachments and then well short of this kind of idea of perfection
is the idea that there's like perfect meditation experiences for mindfulness practitioners you can be
completely in the present moment without the mind wavering whatsoever perfectly
present or people who do concentration practice you can enter into a deep state of
concentration where the mind does not waver does not get distracted into any
kind of distraction and you can be perfectly there
all these things i believe are true it's possible to attain all these things
but it sets up a big shadow side or downside where people then are measuring
themselves against the perfect standard and you know i'm supposed to be perfect
i'm supposed to manage just you know not have to any problems here and i'm not supposed to waver i'm not supposed to be
distracted i'm not supposed to have any attachment and heaven forbid that i come to buddhist center and show anger
because anger is like one of our you know like that's not being kind and so the shadow side of buddhist
organizations like ours is that people sometimes are kind of hold and check their anger because
you're not you're supposed to be kind here and so people don't you know like admit that they're
angry or they hold it back or they do something and so the shadow side is we have this
imperfect side that then we deny we hide we push away
and we're trying to hold it up perfectly when i was a zen student there was this idea that that
there was something to some way of being there was an it that was never defined
but if you knew it then everything was good and some people knew it
and some people did you know but you know i never knew it so and so there was this there was this
kind of strange kind of mythic thing going on that was kind of being held in the
community that i don't know how many people even the teachers understood how much this mythic idea which was
undefined was kind of people are measuring themselves again and hope against and
holding themselves but this is supposed to attain some people have felt the same thing with the pasta tradition that we're in
that there's this mythic idea of nirvana this great attainment and um but they don't never quite understand what is
this what do they keep talking about but you know i don't have it and so i'm not you know really up to snuff
you know somehow i'm kind of lesser than and then there's the projection when there's perf ideal of perfection
then there's a projection of perfection on others there's certainly that person that
teacher that practitioner must have it all together and you know that's the perfect example of
how it's supposed to be and or maybe close to perfect or something
and uh so yeah that teacher picks his nose but you know mostly it's like you know
pretty good and and so this whole perfection thing can be a
headache can be a problem it can also be inspiring and people some people are motivated
as a kind of north star or this is possible and this is the direction i'm going
the um so it's part of a part and parcel of this buddhist tradition that we're part
of this ideal of perfection we can't get around it and the buddha was
in the centuries after he lived his perfection kept growing
and if you watch the growth uh you know the historical literature that was produced in ancient india
relating to describing the buddha you see how he began more or less as a human being
and he slowly became more and more something was closer to a deified being a perfect being and with greater and
greater powers and abilities and part of my interpretation of it of this is that
in that culture of ancient india where he was at it was kind of required that a spiritual
leader spiritual founder that no one could be he couldn't be it
was usually he right uh he couldn't be no one could be second best to him
so if there was another teacher who had some ability that was greater than the buddha then the buddha wasn't so great
and so whenever there was some new person in town who had some ability the buddhist texts would always describe how
the buddha was even better and so it just grew and grew this grandiosity of the buddha you know like
until you know he would visit heavens and fly through the air and you know all
kinds of the one my favorite little story that from a thousand years after the buddha
is written in a famous text called the path of purification
is there are ancient ancient texts that talk about the buddha
going into the river debate well this is a big problem
because a buddha by the nature of being a buddha never gets dirty
it's always clean it's impossible for a buddha to be dirty so why is the buddha going into the bathing that explain it
now and um and so they're explaining well it's just for the sake of other people
to understand that it's useful to bathe something like that
and uh so you know the buddha wasn't even allowed to be human you know dusty india walking around in hot season and getting
dirty because that's that just doesn't happen to someone as perfect as a buddha
so so we have that idea also that's at play and going on
and then on the other end of the spectrum i guess or the other we have imperfection
which is kind of um us
it's a few of us and i don't want to speak for all of you
um but you know there's a little bit of you know you know um oh there's a famous story of suzuki
roshi the teacher of the founder of san francisco who said when i he told talked to his students
well when i look upon you i see all of you as perfect but there's room for improvement
and so that was you know very generous kind of way of looking at people then there's room for improvement
so um and so we have ways in which we're wounded psychologically in our hearts
the ways in which we have attachments and fears and desires that catch us
we're caught in resentments there's ways in which our minds function in many diverse ways
and and now we call people some people neurodiverse rather than calling them
have an illness or some kind of deficiency we now recognize people are neurodiverse they have all these
different ways of operating which is a much more generous than how it used to be when people are seen as
being somehow deficient because of their ways their brain was constructed and
and i really saw this wonderfully in my kids elementary school classes and
so i got to see all these diverse kids in a way i'd never seen human beings before they kind of stood out in their
differences and their sensitivities and their uniquenesses and and how luckily in that school they all
had a place and we were kind of well cared for when i was growing up they would have
been sent to detention or i don't know been expelled from the school or something because people had
no idea what what was going on 40 50 years ago
so so rather than seeing so that you know we used to be things where people were imperfect now we see there's more
perfection is more different ways of being a human being which is kind of wonderful
and maybe you're more perfect than you realize maybe you're kind of unique in your ways
and how things operate for you and what are the ways of rather than thinking of yourself as being imperfect
against an external standard you get to just be yourself
and um and isn't wouldn't that be nice the um
so the practice we have these but we have still we have shortcomings
and that was my favorite word when i was a new practitioner you know i have these shortcomings
and and one of the challenges when i was a zen student for me personally
was that the practice was being presented as a practice of just being present in
the moment radical acceptance of this moment without um
trying to attain anything or any goal or anything you're trying to do except be here
and in some ways it was a wonderful practice i loved it at the same time i saw i had these shortcomings
and at some point i became the gardener of the monastery and i would welcome i would as a
gardener i would pull out weeds so that's other things could grow and i looked at i thought wait a minute
if i do this for the garden isn't it natural to do that from my mind as well
don't i have weeds in my mind and isn't it a normal natural thing to take those weeds out
and and so i struggled with that because of the zen teaching seemed to not make room for that
until i came to kind of the understanding that um it uh removing weeds was not really
uh wasn't a natural thing to do it wasn't like be i was so focused on goals or
attainments which is like if it's a weed you take it out kind of more if you have a weed in the mind it's fine to take it
out and for me the primary one that was a big issue was anger and so i would have to be no work with
you know i saw there's that anger and do i just let it simmer and be there or do i find a way to work with it and
practice with it and um and so what i came to was to appreciate
that i had actually a lot of shortcomings and i got to see that all every time my
eyes noticed a shortcoming i would be happy not because i had it
but because i had a practice to meet it this was just part of this was the the
compost this was the fertilizer for doing the practice
if i had been perfect with no shortcomings i wouldn't have had any fertilizer for
the practice and so i started i learned to be happy kind of to recognize
i wasn't content it wasn't happiness okay now i'm just gonna have a shortcoming it's gonna
the world has to deal with it now because you know i'm just gonna accept myself and
you know go out into the world and do my funny things my mind wants to do
it wasn't it it was rather this emphasis on practice and this idea that i take a refuge in
the practice sometimes my shortcomings were difficult my attachments my fears whatever it was
but i had i knew i had this practice and i took refuge from the practice okay
i don't know how to do it i know how i'm going to get through this but i have a practice i trust this practice
and so this idea of of appreciating shortcomings
rather than being embarrassed by them or shamed by them and many people are shamed many people
are embarrassed many people hide them even from themselves because somehow you're not perfect you're not
like living up to some ideal the ideal that i would like us to live
in which maybe is dangerous to say because maybe there shouldn't be ideals like this
but the idea is that it's okay to have a shortcoming
if you practice with it and it's okay to admit you have a
shortcoming if you practice with it and now that was one of the wonderful
experiences i had in this outer hall here many years ago we had a meeting here of the most senior
zen teachers here in the san francisco area some of them have been practicing for 40 years or something
and it was just kind of a personal time together i don't know how many were 15 of them or so sitting in a circle
and and so they went around at some point the question was um what are your
challenges these days and they went around and they had all these ordinary challenges that
beginner beginning meditators would have like you know you can probably guess what they were you know some of them had
fear they talked about being nervous and afraid or anxious about certain things and they just went they you know had all
they all had their thing but what was remarkable that i'd never seen in such a collection of people they
were completely at ease and relaxed about having their shortcoming it was it was clear that they were
practicing with it and being sincere with it and trying to do their best but they were so at ease at least with you
know oh you know when i give dharma talks i'm so anxious
you know you know like they were smiling no you know whatever so
so the buddha partly the inspiration for this talk was that i read recently a suta discourse ancient discord of the
buddha where he has this teaching he distinguishes two kinds of people
the awful people and uh excellent people
and exactly how these two poly words supposed to be translated is um is controversial but um one translator
does uh inferior and superior people but that doesn't work very well for
me or much of the modern audience i think but the word kind of means more awful
and excellent that's more closer to the literal meaning so um
and then it is it's going to describe how that works who are the awful people who are the excellent people
and um it has to do with whether or not they have a blemish a shortcoming
a fault of some kind so you might think that it would be that the people who have the fault
the blemish they're the awful people and the people have no blemish they're the excellent
people but that's not what the buddha says instead he says
it's the people who have a blemish and don't know it
they're the awful people the people who have a blemish and know they have it
are the excellent people and he goes on to say and the people who
don't have a blemish and don't know it are awful
and the people who don't have a blemish and know it they're wonderful they're excellent
so probably each of you should re-translate those two words into words that work better for you than awful at
excellence so don't take them too serious but there's a distinction here
and clearly the ideal is not to be free of blemish
but rather to know how it is how you are that's what's excellent
and so here you're allowed to have a blemish by the buddha if you know it
and because if you know it then you can practice
if you don't have a blemish and don't know it then you can easily slip off into delusion into attachments
again but if you know you don't have a blemish then you can little bit appreciate that
state and practice with that and grow in it and develop it
so i was i'm just delighted by this idea of knowing that you have blemishes knowing that you're imperfect
knowing perhaps in some ways that you failed and now we come to one of the
central pieces of the culture of the united states that
some of you maybe can appreciate and that's baseball
at the center of american culture is a sport
that mostly involves failure
someone who who fails only two-thirds of the time when they're at bat
is an excellent player and they're mostly failing
and they just come up to bat again and again and again so
failure blemishes maybe we don't have to take them so seriously maybe it's okay to have
shortcomings and faults and if we practice with it
if we engage in it and one of the ways to practice with it is to know
that it's present to know our shortcomings
and the knowing is mindfulness and the knowing is how we right the ship
how the ship writes itself whether you think about a sailboat is that
the sailor doesn't do usually doesn't do the riding it's a you know a big sailboat can tip
over but then say you know everyone holds on and then the boat writes itself
usually and and so the so the knowing
so what is it about knowing that helps right our ship and one of the things is that the
clarity of knowing means that in the clear time of knowing
we're not participating in the shortcoming we have it but we're not engaged in it
we're not identified with it we're not barreling ahead with it so if we're angry and say oh wow i am
angry right now there's anger here right now that's very different than continuing
ruminating about all the reasons you're angry with some situation and planning revenge
then you're really kind of even if you kind of know that you're angry but you're really kind of sunk into it
versus kind of stepping back and say oh this is anger
it's kind of like now you're making space for something else to operate
that rights the ship you're making space that there's more more of you there there's breathing room
there's there's you know space to expand into to relax into
oh it's like this for me as soon as you then say well
i guess i'm imperfect and i gotta get perfect quickly this is wrong i'm a bad person because i'm angry
then we're adding piling uh winds upon winds upon the sails keep
we keep pushing it over we're adding second arrows or third arrows as we say in buddhism
we are just adding more suffering the way to not add suffering
is to appreciate and learn the simplicity of knowing just be mindful clear
oh this is how it is and then to have a practice that works
with it it could be as simply as now that i know it's there let me know
it again let me feel it let me really see how it's like let me kind of name it and
and so that there's an honesty self-honesty oh it's like this
it's a lot of people are not honest with themselves about what's going on and we're trying buddhism we're trying
to be honest oh that's how it is maybe we practice relaxation maybe it's
time to practice breath meditation so we're not so caught in the grip of something but it's not with the idea that we're
doing something wrong exactly that we're bad
there's no bad people there might be bad thoughts bad impulses you know they're harmful
but we don't have to bury ourselves in shame or regrets or
upset criticism of ourselves we because we have a practice oh i see
it this is how it is let me practice with this now let me find my way with it
let me see if there's another way of holding this then holding it with resentment
or shame can i hold it with kindness can i kind of a generous attitude
towards this challenge that i have can i
just see it as this is this is part of me but it's not who i am
it's a part of me that i certainly i'd like to address and work with and find some freedom from
but i'm not going to give it the
i'm not going to be held hostage by it i'm not going to be trapped by it
but i'm going to be untrapped myself through the my practice of mindfulness
some of these shortcomings we have might remain but with time they don't hinder us they
don't grab us they don't take over they don't possess us
so there might be fear there might be strong desires there might be anger that kind of accompanies us
oh there's very there you are of anger i know you're there that but you're not gonna
i'm not gonna say anything i'm not gonna do anything based on it i'm free enough to not live my life
unhindered by it but i know it's there
the attitude that immediately sees a shortcoming a fault that we have as being terrible wrong to identify i'm
that terrible person because i'm angry means that we've kind of put that
anger center stage and become beset possessed by it
the mindfulness practice can put it in its right place which is just piece of the whole picture
and just a piece of it means that it we don't have to be maybe caught by it or limited by it
so the very fact that we have a shortcoming doesn't have to be a big deal
it becomes oftentimes a bigger deal than it actually is because we're reacting to it or judging ourselves because of it
instead of judging ourselves or defining ourselves by the shortcoming just smile and say hey
today i have a shortcoming isn't that great
[Laughter] someone asked you why are you happy you're smiling a lot today
oh because i'm so anxious [Laughter]
what you're anxious and you're smiling oh yes because i know i'm anxious and i have
this practice it's not easy to be with anxiety but i'm so glad i have this practice
isn't this crazy yeah somebody nodding
it's a kind of a a shift of perspective how we hold ourselves and see ourselves
so the last thing i'll say is that this practice that we do the practice of mindfulness
is so valuable it's even valuable
when we just do it partially it's so valuable
it's even valuable when we do it imperfectly and i suspect that a few of us
occasionally will do it imperfectly
the i mean i had this this is a family joke that i had saying that it's kind of like an ancient family we used to go skiing
when i was a kid and some point my father used to joke and he said um
like well i almost felt today on the ski slopes of course he fell but
he was like oh my you you know so you know you almost had a shortcoming
but um so to practice with it to admit it to see it to not be weighed down by all
these uniqueness and the foibles that we have
so you might consider if you if you understand what i'm saying here you might consider
what nice word you have for your own oddities
for me when i was younger i called it my shortcomings you might call it foibles
you might call it um oddities
you might call it your friends what do you want to call it that
that is a little bit kinder and more supportive for you then call it a fault or a
problem you have a word i do mistake
mistakes mistakes okay so call it a mistake rather than calling it wrong
idiosyncrasies you have some of those many
what other good words are there illusion or delusion
delusion some people like that great just delusion yeah
my way
yes habits my habits
[Laughter] [Music]
wabi-sabi
eccentricities all of the above
life and this is life the full catastrophe
so um it's a wonderful thing to have a practice
and it allows us to have a whole different perspective on the challenges of our life
and there are other challenges in life besides our foibles or shortcomings
life itself is a challenge the tragedies of life those the losses of life that we all live with
life is not perfect some of you some of us are aging some of
you aren't haven't gotten around to it yet but at least to recognize it
but aging is not an accident
you know it's just this is how we're we're built to age that's what's how human beings are created
it's not a mistake so we have these tragedies we have these challenges we have all kinds of things
that come besides our shortcomings and we have our practice
and we meet everything with practice and take refuge in the practice is to find your freedom
in the midst of everything it's a fantastic thing to have
and if you have a refuge you have that kind of refuge there's no need to complain about
anything because you can just practice with it
instead so may you
take refuge in the practice if that's too high a bar
maybe for some of you is to take refuge in your sincerity your sincere your
sincere effort to practice because maybe your practice can't be perfect
but maybe your sincerity can be sincere do your best
so thank you everyone for today and for some of you if you'd like we can
go now and meet in the parking lots and sit in a certain you want to have a little discussion about it this or
anything at all and take off our masks out in the parking lot if you'd like you don't have to
if you'd like to do that there's the folding chairs that are out in the cabinet there just outside in the other room
bring a folding chair if you can or someone else will bring couple and we'll make a circle out there in the parking
lot in a few minutes and have a little discussion and i look forward to being with any of you
that just start this day thank you