[Music]
you
so hello everyone and i feel uh
particularly heartfelt to greet you on this weekend of martin
luther king's birthday and um
i think at the foundation of his message and therefore foundation of his life that influenced
this country to such an extent that there's a holiday after him the foundation is
his dedication to love and um at its best or what it can grow
into mindfulness becomes love or mindfulness is
inseparable from love when it's strong when it's well developed there's something about the nature of
awareness that is unrestricted awareness which is
uh un
uh has no unveiled unclouded
that allows the heart's capacity for love
to shine and i suspect that each person for each person love is something a little
different it's not like a uni a single absolute same phenomenon
but it's the human capacity to care for others
with generosity with friendliness with
valuing of others respecting others
and now kind of the beautiful thing that can happen with mindfulness is that when mindfulness and love seem
inseparable maybe become the same that
it also doesn't require having an object it doesn't require having someone
that is the object of love it's just love just care just warmth
just tenderness or gentleness or compassion
in this huge family love is like a family of different emotions
and so i don't want to narrow it down to one thing for any of us but to
sit quietly openly in awareness
and allowing making space for the possibility
for the many flavors of love
to be born to show themselves
and so to value this awareness this mindfulness enough that or to value evaluate more
than our distractions so that when we are distracted or caught
up in concerns and feelings we don't dismiss those but we
are we center ourselves in the awareness of them
maybe with the idea that awareness is kindness
awareness is free enough from our concerns and our challenges
that there's room for the heart's capacity for love
for everything including our challenges and including our distracted mind
so assuming a meditation posture
taking a posture itself that maybe
expresses your care your good will
towards yourself
maybe one that allows the chest and the heart center to
begin to open to all that's here for us
the difficult and the wonderful
and to gently close the eyes
not to shut out the world but rather so there's more room to open
to a different way of sensing this world knowing this world from
deep inside
the place in which there may be love exists compassion kindness
to take a few long slow deep breaths
as a way of awakening a heightened
sensitivity to our body
which is not just our physical body but as our physical capacity
for sensing the physical
awareness embodiment
breathing in deeply and exhaling and settling into the body's capacity
for to be aware to sense to feel
and then gently letting your breathing return to normal
and with a relatively normal breath on the inhale
feel whatever tension or holding there might be in the body
wherever it appears on the exhale
kindly without ambition
soften and relax around that with that tightness
it might be around the face
the chest might be around the belly
or in the arms and hands
in the hips or the legs
and what kind of receptivity or opening or
what kind of sensing would you need to feel
your capacity to love
what would you where in your body would you open feel
rest your attention if you were going to be available
for love kindness
the generosity of spirit
and if it's comfortable for you on the inhale
fill your love with awareness
with sensing and feeling maybe breathing into the place where
love is found in your body
on the exhale continue to soften and relax into that place
where awareness and love are closely connected
either touching them touching each other as you breathe
moving to become almost the same
lovingly aware
mindfully loving
one breath at a time
perhaps turning your corners of your lips up a little bit
just enough to feel a smile
and with that little smile
is it a little easier
for mindfulness to be accompanied
by kindness
for whatever you're mindful of
for whatever mindfulness knows
what happens if you use the quiet soft mental note
yes just yes
without agreeing or proving just a yes for
awareness yes
this too i can be aware of and will that yes
make room for kindness
love as you are aware
[Music]
as we come to the end of this sitting
to dedicate the benefit whatever benefit has come
whatever goodness known and unknown that
has been part of this meditation
we dedicate it so that it might spread from us out into the world
for the welfare and happiness of everyone
may whatever goodness and benefit that has come from this sitting
may it somehow influence our actions in the world
so we act from love the act from our goodness
and so whatever ways in which goodness love lives in us
may it spread out so that those whose sorrow
may be happy those who fear may be safe
for those who are threatened with violence
that they may experience peace [Music]
that those who are oppressed they have the oppression lifted
so they can breathe freely and live freely
find their way in the world successfully
may we be a source of goodness for this world
may all beings be happy
so warm greetings on this sunday and this is the weekend that here in the
united states we celebrate martin luther king
and i love this holiday because it's the holiday that
i associate most closely with love
martin luther king based his life on a love that was
inclusive that was not compromised
for the conflicts he was in but sought
to stay present with love in these conflicts to search for
cooperation to search for mutual kind regard
and this dedication to love which was at the foundation of his life can be celebrated on this day
i'd like to celebrate more than his great accomplishments like with civil rights and voting rights
that were really the outcome of his dedication to love
the um i suppose the other holidays that the united
states celebrates we could infuse them with love
labor day and our love and care and good good will and gratitude for
the people who work and all the different ways which sustain our lives
memorial day and veterans day maybe it can be a
evoke a certain kind of love that uh
maybe even love for our enemies in conflict
and the dedication of people's lives
to protect what they love
and so so forth maybe it's possible to infuse everything with love to that to be the foundation
and of course it's very common for us to say but but what about
what if not that how could i do it how can i love that
and martin luther king's message i believe is that
if you don't love you harm yourself certainly he said that hate
harms the hater and so he was dedicated to not hate
and perhaps against tremendous challenges he dedicated himself to love
and it's inspiring and what's possible
martin luther king was inspired in turn by mahatma gandhi and he said that
one of the gandhi's great contribution was to
uh show how love can be evoked
for social action love can be evoked for
civil rights for freedom for overcoming oppression
government oppression national impression of all kinds
and and so martin luther king kind of took that message from gandhi
and dedicated his life to to love the force of love the power of love
the it said that he was first inspired to non-violence by henry thoreau
who had an essay on uh disobedience and a civil disobedience
and um and from thoreau he learned he kind of was inspired
that you could stand up against the government against the state
with in non-violent ways and and
and so he and he spent a lot of time studying this and thinking about non-violence and in college and graduate school
and seminary and uh was influenced he was apparently a big reader of the philosophy of
non-violence and social change and it got him more and more centered in this idea of
non-violence but when he was introduced to mahatma gandhi that's where he understood that this
dedication to non-violent change could be centered on love
and he was dedicated to an all-inclusive love that no one no one was left out
and um
he wrote he said for oh he dedicated himself for a worldwide fellowship
that lifts neighborly concern beyond one's tribe race class and nation
and all embracing an unconditional love for everyone
and so it
is this possible is it interesting is it valuable is it valuable enough that we can dedicate ourselves to it
perhaps on this holiday at least for this one to emphasize love
this weekend i read a short story that was came out of thailand published in a news
journal a new news site there of a
in bangkok they have these uh neighborhoods small corner stores that are money exchangers
money places to transfer money and send money to and thais will use it to send money to
the relatives in the countryside from bangkok and for a long time there was a woman who came
once a month end of the month and would send 20 000 baht 20 000 the currency of thailand
to her relatives in the countryside and there was no real discussion about
it just matter of fact transaction but one day she came and she wanted to transfer 15 000
instead of 20. and so the owner of the shop asked her you
know what's happening and she said well uh times are difficult and i this is all i can do
and um and uh and uh she said he asked her oh i'm
sorry to hear that and somehow in the conversation he learned that even when she sent 20 000 baht to her
son so he can go to school in the countryside and her sister take care of their elderly
parents and that she had very little money for herself and it seemed like she worked a little
bit as a masseuse and a little bit overlapped with the sex industry there and
something that she really detested doing but felt that she had to
and so the next time she came back next month
she came with 20 000 baht and wanted to have a center sent to the countryside
uh so he took the money and he did a money transfer and she returned a while later and said
there's been a mistake you didn't transfer 20 000 but you transferred 200 000 baht
and he said to her it was no mistake i thought i would try to support you and
help you and what your life that's so challenging for you she cried and thanked him
and then some months later she didn't come back anymore to transfer money but then he got a
facebook message from her that she had opened a noodle shop back in her
home village a hometown and that it was already thriving people loved her noodles and food and
she'd taken that money and started a business and gotten out of the massage trade and
was now running a business that maybe was sustaining her more than her
massage trait could do and she thanked him deeply
the title of this article that i read was um
love without action is a four-letter word
so that was kind of powerful title i thought that's why i read the article i said what what are they going
to say here love without action is a four level letter word
there's a bunch of buddhist teachers a few of them who started the non-profit
that's called meta in action is a word for love or loving kindness
so loving kindness and action and they raise money to support uh
mostly schools and medical facilities in burma and then they've built school houses and
supported teachers to teach in the schools and and that's kind of been their mission
for many years now so love and action
is without action is love love what is love without action
and what is it to act on love and live with love
and um and certainly we find in buddhism a lot of emphasis on the value of love
uh and kindness and good will and we the oh kind of or the
opening kind of you know if buddhism has a you know a
sacred body of texts and technically it has no official opening passages but because of the the
fame of the dhammapada this book of verses um sometimes that's seen as the opening
kind of teachings of buddhism of early buddhism
and the text begins in the first chapter
with not the very first two verses but the third verse
quoting someone who's exclaiming he abused me
attacked me defeated me robbed me
and then for those carrying ill will such as this
hatred does not end for those who say she abused me
attacked me defeated me robbed me for those carrying ill will such as this
for those not carrying ill will such as this hatred ends
so when hatred takes the form of attacking and criticizing other people and being angry with them in
in a mean-spirited way hatred doesn't end hatred never ends through hatred
by love alone does it end this is the eternal truth the literal meaning is by non-hatred
alone does it end this is eternal truth but it's often understood that it's the word non-hatred
means love in this context and then there's a very interesting next
verse and maybe this is kind of punctuates this many do not realize
we here must die for those who realize this
quarrels end
so there's something about realizing that our life is limited on this planet
that maybe we don't want to waste time wasting it with hatred
wasting it with greed wasting it with closing in on ourselves or closing in
tight on one particular clan one particular tribe or race
but rather to have some love that's all embracing
so martin luther king was this way and he's i think i think he's most
famous for the work he did for civil rights and the need for it was so great in his
time he when he grew up as a young man in the south he saw
tremendous injustice happening injustice and voting and justice in the courts and justice by the police and
justice by the society around him that his african-american neighbors
and friends and and struggle under
and so he wanted to change that and work for that and
and so he's famous for his civil rights work and it was phenomenal
what had what happened in among the civil rights people that he was part one of the leaders for
in terms of changing a whole country where they did not give up
their non-violent dedication under their onslaught of violence and
most of you have maybe seen some of the videos of the tremendous violence that was done in montgomery and
against children and teenagers and high school students
and the violence uh in the bridge in selma where
a lot of the civil rights leaders and others were brutally attacked by the police
people who were killed and shot and lynched coming to the south to try to make a difference
and even in these horrendous conditions martin luther king refused to give up
love it's hard to believe that anyone could do this
but this is a message that he said all religions taught and for him he was just trying to live
out the message of love that he received or he found in the teachings of
jesus and christianity and he made i think a very powerful statement
about about the love and from a christian
point of view he said at one point let us love
one another love is god
love is god so to not
worship love to not to to
destroy love you know for him is kind of a destruction of god
the he also wrote when i speak of love
i'm not speaking of some sentimental and weak response i'm speaking of that force
which all the great religions have seen as the supreme unifying principle of
life all great religions have seen as a supreme unifying principle of life
love is somehow the key that unlocks the door which leads to ultimate reality
so is love at the heart of buddhism love and action in buddhism is
is um described by the word anu kampa a quivering of the heart the vibrance
vibrancy of the heart that has translated to action and care and kindness and support of others the
buddha dedicated his life to this anu kampa i think was the organizing principle for
his life he was dedicated to metta to loving-kindness
and when people came to him with uh to attack him both verbally with anger and hostility
and and in one story where it came with hostility to actually actually try to kill him
uh his response was to radiate the power of his love his power
of his meta towards the people and to the in one case an animal that was coming to kill
him an elephant and uh the stories say that his power of love was enough to stop
the attacks that he was receiving is it realistic
to do that in the threat of violence the buddha made a tremendously powerful
statement about this that uh it's easy to dismiss because it's so maybe it's
hyperbole maybe it is uh so unrealistic that how could we ever
make this true but it's uh you know martin luther king says that
love is the unifying principle of life and this dedication to love
and so the buddha said that even if um bandits
come and capture you and start cutting off your arms
do not succumb to love but radiate your kindness through them
and i think we have to understand this uh story this this instruction from the buddha partly is hyperbole like in all
cases but i think also literally because the buddha succumbing to love was such a bad thing to do for oneself
it's one of the worst things we can do in terms of harming ourselves to succumb to love
someone who really understands and sees the self-harm from hate understand never give up love always
always work hard not to succumb to hate and
and it's not a message to not defend yourself i think the conditions for this powerful
statement is if you have no other choice and you have can't escape
because the buddha said that if if he did condone
not actually acts of violence maybe not but acts of self-defense
to escape from the harm others are doing to us and he said that a monastic can a monk
can strike out to defend themselves for the purpose of escaping
provided they do it without any hate provided they can do it with goodwill
towards the people they're escaping from so i think what's striking back then though you know
what striking out meant maybe to lift up your hand and block a block a blow or push someone away
there's an example of someone who protected their own life by pushing someone off a cliff from the time of the buddha
and the buddha kind of understood that matter of factly that that was somehow
not an act of hatred or an act of self-defense so how far this idea of self-defense
goes and how far we can go in our lives to do it
that kind of act the buddha was not just saying stay you know passive and allow yourself
to be you know taken advantage of
and that there's nowhere in the buddha that he says that you know somehow just accept violence being done to you
if anything my interpretation of the buddha is that you should always look
hostility in the eye be strong and forceful and look at in the eye and don't
don't don't you know kind of sense hold your ground even if you have to step away and walk
away but there's no idea that you're supposed to cower or be less than or be somehow
meek in buddhism the example of the buddha is one that kind of the way he's talked about in the
with language of the texts is a language of power strength
sometimes modern people when they read some of the this language of power and strength in buddhism
interpret as being kind of certain kind of machoism or a certain kind of
overemphasis on strength but i think it's uh when i read the text i
interpret at least to be the nice combination of love with strength love strength with
love and this dedication and so
that's what martin luther king says in this quote i'm not speaking of some sentimental and
weak response i'm speaking of that force
the force of unifying love um
i see the shadow you miss speaking about love and hate and like what i said i think yeah i got a little bit jumbled in my
love and hate where i i don't remember well enough to go back and correct it so
if you listened hopefully you understood my jumble
the
so here's a quote from what i was saying from gandhi from martin luther king of what i was saying about gandhi
gandhi was probably the first person in history to lift the love ethic of jesus above more interaction between
individuals to a powerful and effective social force on a large scale
love for gandhi was a potent instrument for social and collective transformation
it was in this gandhian emphasis on love and non-violence that is i discovered
the method for social reform that i have been asking
one of my first zen teachers said that the buddhist contribution contribution
to humanity was the importance of meditating
gandhi's contribution to humanity was important to decide where you're going
to meditate and i think what he had in mind was these non-violent protests that
where you marched where you stood where you sat you can sit in such a way that you're
there to offer a counter to offer an alternative to oppression to violence
that exists in this world and so they had in this in the south in the 1960s 50s and 60s these satins
and you know us buddhists will often call meditation sitting i'm going to sit
and um and so where do we sit and now the possibility of sit-ins is
non-violent protests we've seen this over and over again and
you know it's easy to say they don't work but i think the genius of gandhi and perhaps of martin luther king
was to not do this naively but to really choose very carefully
where we show up to sit to walk to march to the actions of non-violence
to have to really change the other people and to search for cooperation
to not live a life of competition but one of cooperation to see seek to change the heart of the other
um not by force one of the
important parts of martin luther king's life was that he realized at some point
that the civil rights movement as important as it was and voting rights important as
it was was not enough to liberate the african-american population in this country because of the tremendous
poverty that existed and and so he became a champion anti-poverty
champion he saw that the two uh the civil rights for african-americans and
for all people were intimately connected to uh economic change into
improved economic position of african americans in this country
and he worked with uh in conversation with martin luther king with
president lyndon johnson around this and lyndon johnson began this great movement
to eradicate poverty in this country but then martin luther king saw what happened
when president johnson escalated the war in vietnam
that the money for working doing poverty programs in the country
was taken away from those programs and used to
to fuel to pay for the american war in vietnam
and so martin luther king started to see all these three as being unified
necessary to be addressed civil rights poverty and militarism
war and he became a ch anti-vietnam he started actively fighting against the
vietnam war uh actually supporting anti-poverty programs and
fighting for working for that and civil rights and he lost a lot of his popularity because of this
um he was seen as some even by many of the people who supported him earlier as somehow uh becoming an enemy
of the state in a way he hadn't before or of the country but he saw these as being unified as
being connected and he talked about the importance of restitution for
african americans he said i'm not talking about getting them paid
back all the money that they deserve from all their work they did in slavery but there has has to be enough
focus and financial support to bring them out of poverty as to repair the damages of slavery
but the interesting thing he said about this because his love was so all-inclusive is um
was he said that
so he proposed um
he did not seek full restitution of wages lost to slavery which he believed impossible
but proposed a government compen compensatory program of 50 billion dollars over 10 years to all
disadvantaged groups so 50 billion dollars now seems like a
drop in the bucket compared to what this last year the spending programs the federal government is doing
now there's 65 billion dollars just available for broadband
across the country martin luther king posited quote
the money spent would be more than amply justified by the benefits that would accrue to the nation
through a spectacular decline in school dropouts family breakups crime rates
illegitimacy swollen relief rolls rioting and other social evils
unquote he said he didn't want to be only for
african-americans he wanted the money spent for all people
who were poor he said quote that this effort should benefit the disadvantaged of all races
so seeing the evils or the problems of suffer of poverty
in the times when the buddha gave social teachings for the kind of for teachings
that addressed governments and how they should care for everyone he saw that one of the one of the most
back in the time of his time 2500 years ago one of the important most important role
for governments back then it was the king was anti-poverty programs
was to provide the means for people to be able to pull themselves out of poverty
and provide them with land and other means and you know this idea that uh
that poverty and well-being and lack of well-being and overcoming poverty
is essential for people uh to work for you know to to help them
out of poverty how without that how can people thrive and develop
and so this dedication to love in action
would take the form of not allowing people to live in poverty to
support anti-poverty programs support those who are poor in our country support people who are disadvantaged
and that's why i was so touched by this one man in thailand who
used his own savings to to provide enough money to this woman a gift to
this woman so she could break out of her cycles of poverty and and um
and the sex trade and then open up a shop in her home country home town
to make a difference so love so i would like to suggest that
that we think of martin luther king's holiday as a holiday of love
and the argument or the rationale for that is that love was what martin luther king based
his life on and all all the all the good work he did for our society that we celebrate and then they did so much good
was um you know was really based on his foundation for love
and when this country went astray and went into war with vietnam
he knew that that war in vietnam was going to damage this country he thought called it a poison for the united states
and one analysis for the consequence of the vietnam war is that
we're still suffering from the divisions in this country that that war opened up
and and if it's true what martin luther king said that the focus on overcoming poverty that
started just before their rise this this uh escalation of the american war
in vietnam that that was that that came to an end or
was to somehow impoverished war and poverty was impoverished
that this has a lasting effect on this country that we've never really come back to
really address poverty in the same all-encompassing way
and we've ended up a country that the poison of hate is uh
exists in our society in such a huge way and so let's be careful
remember hate it does not end with hate let's be phenomenally careful that
to use our practice to use our care and our
love to not succumb to hate ourselves
and it that's all we do fantastic but maybe when we don't succumb to love
to hate maybe we too can celebrate love and can open up to love and
let love kindness good will generosity respect
uh compassion be the operating principles for how we
live this life because if we do that then that is the world that we're
contributing to make with every action that we do that's influenced by
love we are contributing to a world where love has a place
may we love on this weekend and perhaps on every day
thank you
you