so welcome welcome folks uh it's nice to see your names and chats over there
um yeah
okay so um yesterday i i began with that that
formulation that um
a certain kind of um
the complications of goals yeah that we we have goals they give our life
meaning we don't achieve them it's not great we do achieve them we
lose the meaning giving function of the goal
itself there's a different way of characterizing maybe
unsatisfactoriness that um
wanting something is always different than getting it
and so the response to that
is to turn meditation not into a goal-directed pursuit we see this in whole lineages you know
just embody the buddha or something like this
and that's real that's real to sit without any
sense of going or getting somewhere it's it's an atylic activity meditation
but meditation is also a telic activity to use that the
language from kieran sataya that i mentioned yesterday
it's also structured by goals the goal of
being free or more free but the interesting thing about the way
we make our way to that goal is we do we we make our way to that goal
in an atylic kind of way yeah we're not pretending not to have goals
exactly but there's a sense of actually surrendering the goal-making mind the striving
the sense of being sandwiched in time between the past and the future
we make progress towards goals by giving up
that orientation yeah and so we're aware we're
cultivating lots of spiritual faculties and
cultivating the steadiness of mind samadhi cultivating
uh a million things yeah
but um we do it all one moment at a time and that moment is
free of grasping and engineering and
uh the desperation that we usually have around striving and goal making
and uh so let's uh that's it see what happens
in the most general sense our goals are
wisdom compassion and to use technohands language
understanding and love
whatever progress we make towards the actualization of those goals
we can be happy with
so we just begin with a sense of the depth of aspiration
the reverence for those who
have manifested understanding and love
in the sense of ourselves finding
finding ourselves here in this stream this lineage
of understanding and love
and so there's an aspiration
but no urgency
we let go of our need to get anywhere
and in this way we get somewhere
just pouring your awareness into your body
and blessing your whole body with awareness
blooming and buzzing the constellation of sensations
all infused with the intimacy of awareness
all phenomena have liberation as their core
just the buddha
every phenomena every sensation and thought
sound
are a kind of invitation to know everything
but grasping [Music] striving
towards goals makes things solid
gives everything a solid core
not a core of liberation
and so we relax everything
clinging always experiences a kind of friction
tension we relax everything
we practice being a monastic
in the sense that finally
we're privileging awareness
over our life
over the relentless struggle
to get our ducks in a row
me
thank you it's good to good to sit with you
so on tuesday said um
that a core core mechanism of action
uh in dharma is attention attention therapy
and um and yesterday said uh the the dharma is a kind of
cognitive therapy and they interact attentional stability
makes the learnings sink in deeper
and today the characterizing the dharma as an exposure
therapy moving towards that which we
habitually avoid and
virtually every therapy psychotherapy
group approaches no matter what its name has exposure
as a core component and that is a function of the pervasiveness of
experiential avoidance defined as the unwillingness to remain
in contact with unpleasant thoughts memories emotions other private internal
experiences and taking steps to alter aversive experience or the event that
elicited that experience
and experiential avoidance is is known as a
a trans diagnostic risk factor it's across a wide range of
psychological distress um there's experiential avoidance
so this is um hey is 1996.
many forms of psychopathology are not merely bad problems
they are also bad solutions based on a dangerous and ineffective use
of experiential avoidance strategies instead of encouraging people to use
more clever ways to fight and win this war with their own thoughts feelings and bodily sensations
the ubiquity of problems associated with experiential avoidance
suggests that it might be safer to help people step out of this war
altogether
experiential avoidance we often talk about it implicitly in the dharma world but it
manifests in different ways been characterized and is not a
definitive list but been operationalized as
procrastination distraction behavioral avoidance
difficulty enduring distress aversion to distress
and repression denial and so
exposure therapy in the psychotherapeutic world involves the deliberate approach of anxiety provoking
stimuli people activities places other internal experiences
with um the ultimate goal of changing emotional and behavioral responses to
to life's experiences and
we do this to habituate become desensitized to the
fear to disconfirm catastrophic beliefs around the feared
outcomes if i feel this if i do that if i encounter
to to de-catastrophize and to develop new learning to actually
form associations between the feared experience or object
and the experience of safety
and in clinical situations you kind of create a hierarchy of
exposures so in like a snake phobia just to be very simple as the example i
usually give give a kind of rationale for the treatment and develop some access to
tranquility to ease and then gradually introduce more and more anxiety provoking experiences so
first you're writing the word snake and then seeing a picture of a snake and then
walking past a pet store and then you know getting close to the snake and holding the snake and then then you kind
of graduation day is the boa constrictor kind of wrapped around your shoulders or
whatever and you're at ease yeah it's called systematic
desensitization and
the dharma is unsystematic exposure therapy
the dharma is exposure therapy
for samsara for this realm
exposure therapy for samsara because we know as practitioners that um
anything that can disrupt our peace will yeah
that is the logic of the dharma anything that can disrupt our peace will
and that means that this is the path of purification
and freedom is the uprooting often characterized
enlightenment as the uprooting of greed hate and delusion but that entails a deep intimate contact
with those forces we cannot live in fear and obedience to the forces
of greed hate and delusion but that means we're going to have to feel our way through them
and so every time i get hungry i can't eat every time i'm angry i can't yell
every time i'm anxious i can't ruminate we practice
new strategies we have these familiar ways we neutralize aversive experience
and in dharma we expand
with relinquishing the usual ways we neutralize and soothe aversive
experience and so purification
is its own kind of unpleasantness but it's wholesome unpleasantness yeah you
can taste taste the relief in it
yeah the unpleasantness is it's there the unpleasantness of
purification for sure is is dominant but you can also sense things getting
lighter one of my teachers shinzo young says we
develop a taste for purification
university college london survey published a
prominent journal 1200 meditators researchers were
assessing un unpleasant experience in meditators
and in this survey they found that 26 of meditation practitioners reported
particularly unpleasant experience associated with meditation
and they found strong evidence for an association between particularly unpleasant meditation related
experiences and retreat yeah um that's funny
that's funny to me 26 yeah unpleasant experience and the very obvious question
is what on earth are the other 74 doing
as our attention stabilizes um
we get bigger and bigger doses of
of suffering or suffering and
samadhi the attentional decide the samadhi lubricates the mind
and so where it goes it really goes we see this very clearly in retreat
where it goes it really goes and our peace
at some point gives way to purification yeah whatever happiness or ease tranquility
that gives away and we move from the mode of abiding in some peace
to purification and in purification we're called to make
peace with primal forces that disrupt peace
and sometimes really intense high affect states of rage or
terror helplessness
and we just keep making peace with our conditioning
we just keep making peace with our conditioning
this is the exposure therapy dimension of dharma
and in that exposure we change our conditioning
we develop new understandings more degrees of freedom
michelle mcdonald who speaks so beautifully about all of this says
we develop a relationship with everything so that we're not afraid of
anything
read a um a story story about a mathematician
a kind of kind of very major impact on the field and then kind of vanished and
vanished into some some loops of isolation pain
not totally clear but um something from one of his his journals
yeah reminded me of this theme today
i know that there is nourishing substance in everything that happens to me whether
the seeds are by my own hand or by others
it is up to me to eat it and watch it transform into knowledge
i've learned that in the harvest however bitter there is substantial flesh
which is up to us to nourish ourselves with when this substance is eaten and has
become part of our flesh the bitterness which was only the sign
of our resistance to the food intended for us has disappeared
it's a dharma dharma as a exposure therapy for samsara
offer this for consideration and pick up what's useful
leave behind what is not so thank you uh thank you all happy to
uh be be with you and um we'll keep going
tomorrow yeah have a lovely lovely day whatever that means
whatever lovely is supposed to look like today may be lovely