so good morning or good day everyone and um
coming here from having finished the being at a retreat teaching you the
retreat for the last week and and so perhaps The Retreat practice
that is still with me and maybe I can share a bit of it with you and this
meditation and I'll do it with um
a simile the
Buddha taught a lot with similes and he had one he had many having to do with meditation
and one that fond of is that that you know adapt it
for the kind of a modern example that um
you take dry flour and you sprinkle the water in it to make bread to make dough
and as the water gets into the flour uh
the idea is to begin kneading the flower first mixing first so that all the flour
can become moist and and then to really spread it out and
and kind of line up the structure of the wheat proteins so that it can can really
receive well the the the yeast and the I guess the carbon
dioxide the yeast make so it spreads and expands and so this is kneading the bread to get
the moisture needing the flour to get the moisture throughout evenly throughout
the Buddha used something almost the same idea that kneading and kneading some powder and dry powder until no part
of the dough is not moist saturated so fused with
moisture um but also not oozing
not the dripping with the moisture either just enough to hold it all together
and this idea of keep keep kneading so that the structure of the flower gets
a line and gets well established for the rising of the bread
and in this analogy the the body
is the flower and a body which is
not saturated with awareness with attention is considered kind of dry
and not held together in a unified hole but as we take our awareness
and we're kind of like awareness is the water more or less and
we are massaging or needing the water the awareness into the body
and the rhythm of it the kneading is the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and um and for different people maybe different halves of breathing is the
pushing the the dough down and then the other half is kind of
squeezing it together and um for me that what works well is the
in-breath is the kind of gathering together the dough into a ball and then the and then the exhale is spreading it
out and kneading in and spreading out other people is the opposite that somehow the exhale as they're kind of
gathering together and the inhale with the expansion of the Torso is the
spreading uh is the spreading out the exhales the Gathering
in bunching up and as we do this there's a kind of
Rhythm that goes with the breathing and some of that rhythm is inherent in
the breathing and very gently it's possible to just like with the dough
we don't uh try to knead the dough as fast as we can there's a speed
that seems to be proper appropriate for the dough
and so to not necessarily breathe in whatever way you happen to be breathing
but to be attuned to what is the kind of breathing the
speed of breathing the the extent of exhaling the extent of
inhaling that seems appropriate to the task of
moving spreading awareness throughout the body
so that's assembly and uh it gives a very different sense of what
to do in meditation than just you know follow your breath be with your breathing if your mind gets
distracted come back there's a kind of embodiment or fullness and the imagination is a little bit
engaged so assuming a
meditation posture and one that allows your chest to be
more open have posture where the front part of
your body doesn't get scrunched up but rather the front of your body is a
little bit open and your belly can also a little bit
not be bunched up not be squeezed or
bit more open
maybe even allow it to relax and extend forward
gently closing your eyes
and maybe the dove is already starting to get moist
in the first few needs that you do
are large large long extended deep
really to kind of get started on the kneading of the dough
breathing in deeply
exhaling and relaxing into the body
breathing in deeply and exhaling so that the chest and the belly stay open
maybe even open a little bit more
by letting the muscles of your back
settle relax
and letting your breathing return to normal
and the body is malleable workable like a ball of dough maybe still not
completely moist everywhere parts of the body are not saturated with
awareness embodied awareness
breathing normally
maybe gently exhaling a little bit longer than usual
partly to so the Mind becomes more interested in
the body we're interested in breathing
or another deep instincts of the body is to breathe
the natural instinct to breathe in and breathe out
feeling breathing in your body how the body the Torso moves and
sensation shift
for this meditation in there
lovingly putting aside concerns with whatever you're thinking and also
whatever you're feeling emotionally not out of disrespect or
for these minutes it's all right to let those be on the side
to give yourself to the simple task of needing the body with breathing
and maybe as you exhale a gentle spreading
of attention awareness more broadly into the body
bit by bit wider and wider awareness
maybe on the inhale pulling in breathing in gathering together
his sense of preparing
to spread the awareness a bit more through the body
perhaps gently a little bit longer exhales
in that extra longer period of exhaling this may be an occasion to feel more the
body
letting the thinking mind become quiet in favor of feeling the body
foreign
yourself over to the rhythm of kneading
the rhythm of breathing
if you don't feel your body is so well inhale a little bit more so that the
chest expands the belly expands
if you still don't feel your body much gently hold your breath
at the top of the inhale the top of the exhale until the sensations of the body
ask you for to breathe
the kneading of dough doesn't make the bread
the kneading of the dough prepares the dough for the oven
prepares it to rise and
needing your body with the breathing
done don't try to make your meditation into something
let it be the preparation loving gently
massaging the body with the breathing with awareness
that spreads as you breathe
when you stay close to the breathing the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out the rhythm of movements in the body
there's less attention given to
our reactivity our preoccupations or distractions or judgments
we're less likely to get lost in those
and it's possible when the rhythm of breathing in the body
to let breathing be connected to your care your love your
generosity your friendliness you might have for
others that those can coexist
and breathing can be like a gentle Bellows that blows
onto your good will for others
the exhale can be the gentle Bellows that blows your Good Will on others
as we breathe we are needing like kneading dough we're kneading
basic friendliness Goodwill
kindness to the world
by breathing staying in touch with ourselves
and letting her friendliness
radiate outward to the world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may my respect and care and kindness
for others
live closely in my heart carried on the Winds of breathing
out into the world
[Music]
thank you
so warm hello on this Monday beginning of our week
and the theme for this week will be the Buddha's use of similes
for teaching meditation and um
it's possible to give very simple basic technical instructions on meditation
but that leaves a lot to be filled in by the meditator
that Buddha did this he gave very simple instructions for breathing
and some people gloss over this instructions because they seemed too simple or
or seemed kind of yeah kind of besides
the point almost the most basic instructions that he gave in a lot of different times
is one knows
when one is having a long inhale one knows one's having a long inhale
when one is having a long exhale one knows one's having a long exhale
when one is having a short inhale one knows it's a shortened nail
when one is having a short exhale one knows this
and um so this doesn't really it's not very
inspiring or evocative it doesn't really indicate you know the
richness and the possibility of meditating in this way in fact some people it seems actually
maybe even discouraging or uninteresting uninspiring and and doesn't quite come alive
but the um and so in a sense the that
simple instructions is just a a stand-in that represents a whole universe of what
can happen in meditation and it's kind of like a pointer or it's like a title
of a chapter that kind of gives you a sense of what the chapter is about but you know the
subject but that doesn't fill in the details that's what reading the chapter will do
and um and so meditation is something organic in a sense it's something that's
holistic something that can can or with time includes all of who we are is
included in the practice of meditation it's not a simple
um you know certainly it's not a disembodied experience it's not only about becoming calm and centered
it's about gathering together all of who we are and having all of who we are
somehow held in a field of attention of awareness and
and um and so it's uh multi-faceted it's
you know in a sense it's all of who we are not just a simple kind of mechanistic uh attention to how long and
short the breathing is and so to convey uh you know so so when
the Buddha gave instructions in meditation uh he sometimes would include
similes and the similes are actually part of the instructions they actually
give more life to the instructions they provide examples illustrations for how
to do the practice or how to a sense or feeling of what can happen as
we do them they provide kind of a somatic or kinesthetic feeling or sense
of what what's going on when we do this these instructions what can happen
and so this week I'd like to talk about these similes for meditation that the
Buddha gave and in particular we're going to focus on breathing in this guided meditation I just did I
felt that I talked quite a bit and those of you who are experienced meditators and
prefer to have silence I can sympathize with you and maybe for this week as we go through
this you would meditate a second time each day in the
silence admit and what I'm trying to do in the in the teachings here today is to
let some part of meditation become more alive and full for you um and so that when you do meditate uh
silently to you with yourself that that's with you kind of supporting you and guiding you and so if I speak a lot
uh with the instructions here this week think of them as laying the foundation
for what you'll do maybe later in the day on your own and uh and to get the full benefit and
of what we're talking about and um
so um um the it's kind of fascinating all the ways
the Buddha uses water in his similes especially similes for meditation
and sometimes I think water represents awareness and it's what happens to
awareness as we meditate that shifts and changes and and sometimes it seems more that
he's using water for it is using water to represent related things in meditation not to awareness
and how that works together is part of the richness that we kind of live into
so one of the um so this breathing in and breathing out
and being aware of long and short the the metaphor the assembly that I
compared it to in this last sitting is that of needing flour
I'm mixing water into flour and then kneading it massaging it until the water
is evenly spread throughout the flower you make a ball where with the ball everything all the flowers held together
into the one hole and um and this is I think marvelous uh
metaphor for the Rhythm and massage of breathing and coming and going coming
and going and um and if if that's the kneading and
the awareness is the is the moisture then
um we're moving and developing that moisture of awareness so it spreads throughout the body and so the body gets uh uh gathered
together part of meditation in in the Buddhist teaching is a process of unification of
gathering together bringing all of who we are in the same place at the same time
so there's a holistic feeling of being here connected in our lived experience
so this massaging that goes on and and so uh
so he gives us metaphor back in his time not of flower but of a certain kind of
soap powder that they had in the ancient world and that they would put the soap
powder into a metal Bowl basin and uh and then sprinkle water into it
and then start kneading massaging uh that fly that until the all the flour is
saturated with water the whole ball is saturated so if they go on with these wonderful uh words or kind of synonyms
so the moisture pervades saturates suffuses fills uh the ball of soap
powder so that the water suffuses pervades fills the the flower
as we're making the dough the bread dough and um and this repetition of these
words is just kind of a delightful and you know the ancient world they weren't reading the text they were chanting it
and so to chant this over and over again you know this suffuse pervade saturate
fill it must have had kind of an embodied kind of reference point like when you chant it you just feel that
this is what we're doing and um
and so the Buddha goes onto says uh the same way as uh the person who's stopped
making this ball of soap powder that the whole thing is suffused so in the same
way the whole body is suffused uh uh with not no part of the body not touched
so it's clear that you know it's a really kind of a openness to the whole body
and uh and the way that this kneading of the flower uh wide works is a good
metaphor is that it's um it's kind of it represents the rhythm of breathing
breathing in and breathing out and um so here we take this as part of
the instructions that it's not just being aware of the long and the short but it's uh it's taking the whatever
like the the breathing every length of breathe that breathing is and entering
into it as if it's a massage it's as if we're supposed to get into the rhythm of it and kind of ride the Rhythm and kind
of let the awareness kind of gently not forcefully not with the expectations gently softly
um kind of kind of opened a wider and wider field of awareness in the body
and so we might start with awareness at a particular Point some people are aware
of the breathing and the nostril some people in the middle of the chest some people in the belly and really stay with
that be with that and then as we're doing it gently kind of a sense that
that sense of awareness and opening to the body kind of begins to spread and
spread and spread and um and then we're saturating the body with
awareness Technically when the Buddha gives us instructions it's not only awareness
but it's a certain kind of um satisfaction Delight
joy that comes when we can give our attention over to the meditation rather
than giving the attention to distractions to preoccupations
and this ability to appreciate attention to Value it and value attention which is
not compromised by being pulled into these strong preoccupations we might
have it's also spreading that Delight that Joy with the awareness or feeling that
satisfaction of of awareness freed from distractions even if it's just for one
exhale feeling the goodness of that the joy of that the satisfaction of UN
compromised awareness for a few moments that that satisfaction is what we're
spreading with the awareness through the body so there's a lightness there's a joy
there's a pleasure that of some kind that goes along with
the breathing maybe it's a subtle pleasure and but it's a pleasure of attention that's not
compromised or held hostage or something um in other metaphor that the Buddha
uses for water that has a very different reference for the moisture is
is taking to back the ancient world they didn't have matches the way we'd have or
lighters or to light fires they would take Fire Sticks and rub the fire sticks together and if you rub it long enough
they get hot then the spark gets created the and um but if the Fire Sticks even just
one of them is saturated with water and is moist the Fire won't get lit
and so here the water the the this the Soggy uh the stick the Soggy log that
you're um is uh the Mind saturated with
preoccupations with the hindrances with desires sensual desires and ill will and
uh rigidity and stuckness and restlessness and all kinds of things
where they that grab the awareness and when we're saturated with that
um the Fire won't light up but so as we empty ourselves as
attention is not caught in those things and getting all kind of and then
awareness is kind of drier and can light up in the ancient world I think of Fire
that we relate even a small one like a candle was much more associated with
making light than it is for us because we have lots of light and electricity most of us
and but in the ancient world the fires one more form or other was a oil lamp a
candle the fire was how things were laid up
so so the uh um so to light up
with awareness which is not compromised by distractions to light up the body
not necessarily put it on fire but to light it up and spread the awareness through the
body so these are the similes that Buddha uses and I think for many years I
ignored the similes because I don't know I just thought they were just kind of cute or something but
they're actually part of the instructions they fill in the details in certain kind of way
and with the similes the Imagine our imagination is is uh employed for the purposes of
meditation and so maybe uh for this next day you
could try meditating and engage your imagination with these similes
and see if having those these similes kind of present to your imagination a
little bit can gives you a richer deeper sense of to get you connected and involved in your meditation maybe even
absorbed in your meditation as you free your awareness from preoccupations
where you get all soggy and there's no light nothing lights up
to this lighting up of attention that moves and fills the body
so um so that's I'll talk more about similes and Imagination as we go through
the week and different similes the Buddha gave and I'm hoping this will kind of give you a richer sense of
what's possible in your meditation so thank you