so good morning everyone and
um so i'm here in the fog
at spirit rock spirit rock meditation center in northern california
i'm teaching a retreat currently and and uh
this is uh i'm sitting outdoors just outdoors outdoors from the little
room where i'm i'm sleeping uh living well during the retreat and uh
behind me it wasn't as foggy when i first set up here the morning fog is coming in
it is um you see behind you the rolling foothills of marin county
and maybe in the course of the 45 minutes maybe the the fog will clear and maybe you'll get
to see the the the hills occasionally there'll be turkeys walking
by
so so happy to be here happy to be with you
and this week we are doing um the getting to the end of this satipatana
sutta and we're doing the what's called the seven factors of awakening and i'll say more about them
later but if you can think of them as the culmination of
the of this uh close to the culmination
of this long practice of satipatana meaning practicing for a long time not just
sitting down and being introduced to mindfulness and expecting that the seven factors of awakening will
arise but that these arise through
practicing and developing and settling in and so for this meditation
uh imagine that um all the best moments of these
weeks that we've been doing sattvatana if you've been following along all the best moments of your meditation
are bundled together and you feel a tremendous trust
in the practice in your ability to practice and um and that you're settling down
here not so much to practice mindfulness
as to allow for mindfulness to allow for
a kind of natural awareness to appear to float up
to arise and your job is mostly to get out of the way if you let go of thoughts and
distractions it's mostly in order to allow
for the kind of love the form of awareness which is always here
and and then to be aware of to recognize what the mind is aware of in those
circumstances so some of this can still be directed towards the breathing
but the but the breathing now is uh not something that we're working
or that we're intentionally focusing on
but it's more that we're opening to it to allow the naturalness
of the sensations of breathing to enter into awareness or to say it differently
we're noticing what sensations of anything what experiences of anything
including breathing arise effortlessly in the mind
in relationship to the breathing it's kind of like the door
doors of awareness are open to the experience of breathing and
rather than bearing down is what noticing what is effortlessly arising
in relationship to breathing into awareness so to
take a meditation posture and to
settle down by now first taking a few
long slow deep breaths
some breaths that as you breathe in
you're gathering together all the momentum or the associations best associations of
sitting down to meditate and then as you exhale
you're letting go into
the practice that arises from your body you're letting go into
the natural capacity we have to be aware that does not require
intention it requires allowing it
noticing that you are aware
then letting your breathing return to normal and we'll begin with a little exercise
here and that is
of all the present moment experiences that are occurring
what arises obviously easily effortlessly
into awareness for you
what arises maybe it's not even planned maybe you can't even expect it that an
itch or an ache or a pressure particular thought or feeling
and before there's any reaction on your part to it notice the effortless way in which it
arises in awareness just there
and if you notice any holding and tension in your body
rather than relaxing see what happens if you just effortlessly are aware of it meaning
you're not trying to do anything or fix anything or make anything happen
and maybe you're not even holding your attention on the tent on the tension
but you recognize it's there when it arises effortlessly
and your awareness little bit maybe floats
between different experiences
man
and then not so much as you're directing your attention to the breathing
as you are opening the door or the window
and then you become aware breathing comes into awareness
and becoming aware of what is obvious about breathing
or and what comes effortlessly what parts of breathing the experience
come effortlessly to awareness
and if your mind floats between different things the sounds of the birds my voice
anything else that's happening in the present just allow yourself to know that
now the mind is aware of that
you might be confused by these instructions and if you are
then no simply no confusion allow that to be there effortlessly
in awareness
so
when the mind becomes aware of anything [Music]
maybe there's a little movement of relaxing you can do
relaxing trying
letting go of the mindfulness which is a trying or work
in favor of just keeping the doors of awareness open
to receiving the experiences that float through
so
if you're able to be aware of what arises effortlessly
sometimes it's the more pronounced strongest
experiences of the moment and sometimes it's the more subtle ones
or the quieter ones sometimes the louder experiences recede
to the background and the quieter ones are what come
sometimes the other way not having any choice not choosing what
to be aware of so much is noticing
that quality of the mind that aspect of attention
that seems to operate effortlessly
the quality of awareness
that you could not turn off
if you stayed relaxed and present for the
present moment you couldn't you could can't not be
aware
so
if you're trying to do anything trying effortfully
see what happens if you let go of the trying and just let awareness mindfulness
know what is obvious rather than trying to overcome a
distracted mind relax
and simply know
simply let there be in awareness the fact that you know the mind is thinking
keep returning to being aware of
how awareness how knowing can operate effortlessly
by noticing the new things that come into awareness unplanned
for a moment they're there they arise
before you try to do anything with it try to be mindful
there's a simple knowing simple awareness
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
is there anything about being aware that you can recognize that you
recognize is peaceful
that you recognize is
safe for something you appreciate
maybe even joyful
and then think of the people in your life or the animals in your life or
the world around you
and perhaps you can wish for them to have some of the same peace
some of the same well-being or
appreciation
and perhaps with your simple awareness
taking in and being aware of others you can wish them well
you can wish that your ability to be attentive
can be a support for them
may it be through this practice that we do
that we're able to bring greater safety and peace happiness
and freedom to this world may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
so i didn't bring a bell with me here outside so um
maybe with this saying thank you for being part of this we end this sitting
thank you
uh
i saw a comment about the volume being low i just increased the volume uh
output for the mic on this computer i wonder if that made a difference
okay so
so good morning everyone and so this is the beginning of the week on
the second to last exercise in the buddha's discourse on the establi uh on
establishing awareness and um
it is the seven factors of awakening and there's nothing in this uh exercise
that talks about
making these factors arise it's more recognizing they're there
and then maintaining them so the seven are
mindfulness usually the second one is called the investigation and tomorrow we'll talk
about it some so mindfulness investigation
effort joy tranquility
concentration and equanimity and these are considered to be
the crown jewel of buddhist practice sometimes because they come
when practice begins to mature and develop when there starts to become kind of an inner momentum or naturalness of the
qualities of the practice living in us and coming forth and
and flowing through us in a certain way this is not an easy thing to experience
for beginners it's not so easy sometimes it takes a long time of practice
begin to these things get awakened and as they become awake they're present
and they support us the um but when they so this remember this is the
second to last exercise of that it's a 12th exercise of 13 exercises in the
this discourse we have and i'd like to understand that the others provide the foundation we're kind
of building momentum developing learning how to be mindful in the body and feelings in the mind
and as that learning happens and as the muscle of attention becomes stronger
much muscle of being in the present moment become stronger
then we find ourselves that these things begin to arise
and the first one that arises or the first one is talked about is sati or mindfulness itself
and as i said the text doesn't say you know now practice mindfulness now
apply yourself more to being mindful but it says basically it says notice that there is
mindfulness there and so the question is what is mindfulness here
and i prefer to translate the word sati as awareness
and what we're doing is we're establishing awareness uh we're abiding in it we're dwelling in
it we are not doing awareness nowhere in the buddha's teachings does
the buddha say do awareness awareness itself is not a verb of
something that we actively do but something that we establish or allow for we abide in
and um so the um and that's kind of in the very beginning of the text if you remember along this
at the start it talks about um abiding observing
uh the four foundations it's the city of abiding in something
um knowing it's there in this very simple way so to um
um uh so so in that nas meditation i talked
about the effortless quality of attention there's certainly attention that can
take effort and sometimes that's useful to apply and and there's but sometimes there's a
kind of effort that is effortless if you are just kind of minding your own
business and suddenly a loud bird nearby uh whistles
uh the first hearing of that bird just appears without any effort on your part
if um i'm sitting outside and just as i was saying this i felt cold going through my
thighs and that cold was effortless that it appeared that knowing of it it just
there it called attention to itself and my mind knew it and and um pretty equanimous and content to
be here and it was not a problem to just know it and um
and so then um and so what would uh so begin appreciating as practice deepens as
certain moments of practice of meditation practice or other times
as it continues and matures there'll be times when
we can tune into this effortless quality of attention and it might take some little gentle
effort to let go enough to allow that to be there but
with time it becomes kind of maybe the backdrop or it becomes a foundation it
becomes the support for how we go through our lives because there's a kind of a constant
awareness of present moment experience as we live it we don't get lost in our thoughts we
don't get lost in conversations we don't get lost in the work we're doing we can do it wholeheartedly but there's
a sense of feeling a knowing that seems almost like effortless that
oh i'm here this is where i'm present for it's almost like being present for or the
feeling of presence some people might say ever-present presence
ever-present kind of awareness attention and
and why this is uh useful as we develop awareness is that
it's an awareness that doesn't um automatically
come with attachment with greed or clinging with ill will with diversion with
pushing things away things are just allowed to be there um without us being for or against them
we don't have to accept them and we don't have to condone them we don't have to
um criticize them the awareness is not awareness in in and
of itself is not involved in being for or against is not involved with needing to accept
it or needing to reject it it's just there with the experience
to practice acceptance is an extra step
this allowing things to appear in the in the mind effortlessly might might be evaluated thought as a kind of
acceptance practice but there's no acceptance being done
it's just things arise in awareness and here we are
to do that with the breathing um at the same time
is part of the art of this that's possible to do and i'd like to give you if i can on on
this format of the video here i'd like to try to show you something
um if um if this finger of mine
is my breathing breathing in and breathing out and
and then one way of being aware of it if my other hand is my mind and so the idea of focusing on the
breathing really being there with it and the mind comes and is really
close down focuses and it gets kind of tight and it bears down it focuses on it all
together this way now that's fine it can be done and it's possible to get very focused and concentrated this way
that is very kind of nice another way is not to make any effort in the mind like that
keep the mind relaxed and open soft and and just kind of available
and now i'm sitting outside so i feel when i do that i start feeling the wind and the palm of my hand the back of my
hand the cold in different places it's kind of nice and
then gently i bring these two together this is the breathing
and this is the um you know this is this the hand open hand
is the awareness and i bring the them together so that the breathing and
the softest part of the hand most sensitive part of the hand are in touch with each other and now i'm really
feeling intimately the breathing and the world around me begins to fall away disappear recede
because the the breathing becomes the only thing i'm aware of but the breathing is known effortlessly
the coming and going the rhythm the different sensations are known effortlessly
there might be a tendency to want to do something again to stay there to stay not not lose it
and the mind begins to tighten up again and hold on but the idea here in the when you come
to this part of the seventh seven factors of awakening is to
for sati to be awareness to be less and less work
and more and more arresting and abiding in awareness
and then in that abiding letting things be known effortlessly
and um and then and the uh if there is any work at this
stage of practice it's to um remember to do this
remember to do this because it's not easy to be this way there has to be some momentum in the
mind um don't try to do it if it's not easy
rather be very content even to go back to the very beginning of satiptana
go back just the simplicity of practicing breath meditation and the first four steps of this whole
enterprise of sati patana is to really know experience no know
your breathing you recognize the experiences of breathing and that takes a little bit more effort
then as you know it know and recognize your whole body
and then relax your body and that's how it begins so you always go back to do that that's a fantastic
practice in his own right and it leads to where we're going here with the seven factors of awakening so if you're not
there yet in the seven factors don't worry about it it's um it's not important for you then
but as the momentum builds then you'll see that you can
that there'll be a kind of an effortless awareness that arises that can hold things peacefully
hold things openly and clearly
and this is a gift this is one of the great gifts of practice and it sets the stage for the other
seven factors of awakening and tomorrow i'll talk about
investigation and which sounds like a lot of work but
is also meant to have an effortless quality to it and how does that work is what i'll talk about
so thank you and i delight in being here outdoors and at spirit rock doing this
with all of you and um and i see there's a note there a chat
about having an interactive session uh end of this week um
yeah it's possible we can do that i'll i'll look at my calendar and see
i'm here at spirit rock through wednesday so so
tomorrow and the next day we'll do it this way in these rolling hills of marin county
and then thursday and friday i'll be back at imc and
so thank you all very very much and i look forward to being here with you
tomorrow
you