so welcome um you know you know the drill here
uh let's let's sit together
just let there be space in your heart
for all the joys and sorrows being human
when the heart begins to give permission
something drops in the body something settles down
no one has a perfect shiny mind or a perfect shiny life
some loose ends in every human life
we develop the confidence that
we can take our seat amidst it all
when we stop trying to control our experience
the necessity of love becomes more and more apparent
just breathe and relax into
the condition of your life this moment
you're not responsible for solving the predicament
the human condition
you're simply being asked to
uh bless the intensity of the human condition the intensity of a moment
of an urge or a feeling to bless
this with wisdom and love
every moment is practicable in one way or another
in the wake of letting go
there's something like a quiet love that remains
and turning now more explicitly
to compassion
just bringing into your heart mind
someone you care about who's suffering
when we first fill out the landscape of their pain
to actually take that into our heart
to consider their inner life the life of their body
and develop a kind of vivid sense
of their suffering this is only one part of our practice
but this is the first part
and to understand their pain of course we naturally draw
on our own pain
from memory or from life right now
we make vivid the suffering of
this person we love we care about
and so in compassion one dimension is a willingness to
grieve
but we do not stay here grief is not the last word
as the vision of their pain this dramatized made clearer and clearer
our heart makes another move
and we pour all of our love
into them
as if we fill their mind and body
their care or wishes that their suffering be alleviated
that they be at peace
of course there are traces of the grief but it's mostly
displaced by the warmth
love of compassion
kind of compassion that doesn't fatigue our own heart
what feels good to dwell in
we're not insisting that someone stop suffering where
offering our love and our blessings that it might be so
we just rest our mind abiding not care
warm
and then maybe these last few minutes we let go
orienting to one person
of orienting self and other
instead we practice just dwelling in the openness
of compassion
distinctionless compassion
it's good to sit with you
so it took uh suffering
is both everywhere
and super obvious
but it's also kind of shocking that there is suffering there's
something shocking startling about that at least startling to our nervous system
and when there's some hard moment
i find there's a part of me that can like barely believe it you know like of course i know i've
contemplated dukkha a lot right but there's a little part of some naive part of my mind is like how is this happening
you know and we can have that sense of like how did the the universe conspire to do
this to me this moment and it might be just like some small ache you know
holla allian poet um psychologist and poet
wrote a kind of grief poem this is i think it was published in september or
october of 2020 so pandemic
george floyd election uh
staggering amount of dukkha and uh one of the lines in that poem was
the patients who come to me swarmed with misery and astonishment their hearts
like newborns after the first needle
or it's like newborns after the first needle dukkha
can feel like that
the buddha asks that we we comprehend suffering that we comprehend suffering
i somehow like that translation comprehend suffering
and the the act really of comprehending suffering
highlights the necessity of love
yeah sometimes i feel like yeah the first noble truth
that there is dukkha contains the next three in a way to really
compreh comprehend suffering that is to uh
to know the necessity of love of compassion
otherwise we just kind of armor up and try to make the first noble
truth vanish or we crumble collapse
so the the alternatives when when i think about it the alternatives to love really
are something like hate and apathy those are the alternatives
and so while we we have some details to work out no
doubt the path is actually pretty clear
compassion is is love in the face of dukkha the wish that it be uh
let it be alleviated and
part of compassion is coming to a more nuanced understanding of our own
of our own suffering we first comprehend our own suffering
and so often we we kind of you know without training [Music]
we basically misdiagnose our own suffering
you know it's just like people are trained a doctor whatever trained in differential diagnosis or something
and we have to train in diagnosing our own suffering too
because our habit is to embrace monocausal models yeah like
single cause this is what's doing it yeah
this is the source of my suffering and
the buddhist psychology invites us into a much more
complex map of causality it's
it's almost never just just this yeah our mind gets seduced into that
but as we practice more we start to appreciate the complexity of causality
so we're not highlighting just this you know
we have that fantasy if i could just pull that one thread the whole thing unravels but
our dukkha is a testament not to one thing but kind of to
everything and if we have the wrong diagnosis
we can issue the wrong treatment
so often um we want to
control our suffering rather than understand it
and compassion makes us patient in our understanding
makes us patient in our understanding of suffering
the the compassion the love of which i'm speaking it's not a kind of enmeshed
love it's not emotional contagion in that first phase of taking in the
suffering of another kind of the willingness to grieve with them
um we're not we're it's it's not this pure emotional con
kind of contagion and my my conditioning around love is a
kind of enmeshed model or something it's like
your pain is my pain is your pain and love and space
are somehow intention rather than space
affording room for love and so i've found that um the the
suffering the suffering of loved ones spins me
spins me in particular ways and
my words maybe some you know might masquerade as compassion
but what they really testify to is the intolerance of their pain
yeah and so it's somehow wanting to quickly manage dukkha
and makes sense that you know as as children like the suffering of a parent
or caretaker or someone it's like an existential threat you know
and um at some level growing up all of us
all of us want the adult to be
fully enlightened you know to be free of suffering to be a kind of
master of samsara and that is not so
and and so maybe maybe some of that sense of
threat the the threat of the suffering of the other encodes some fear
as we grow up of our own families the commitments loved ones
that the suffering of the other spins us but compassion is not
a kind of insistence that someone change it's not even an insistence that someone
stops suffering it can feel that way
but then we just need to issue our own heart love it this compassion is love
in the face of suffering
the monk uh matchy ricard and brain scientist tanya singer they were doing
some you know kind of uh
study where where he was in the the scanner doing compassion practice and
um she's sort of uh you know this kind of exceptional being she's interested okay
what's this person's brain like and um and she saw she saw that kind of brain
activity and she asked him afterwards like what were you doing you know because
the brain activations you know looked quite different to what she
she had expected the kind of some of the familiar nodes
that light up with when when people are in a state of empathy yeah
the kind of brain regions that you would see activated when you
experimentally you know a loved one is getting an electric shock or something like that
and in empathy where we're feeling the grief of the other's pain and that's
hard but compassion might use that as a seed for generating
our commitment but that's not the last word
but and then this kind of turning of the heart to love to actually
enjoying act in a subtle way enjoying
take that han said um true love never makes you suffer
compassion is a form of true love
and uh love doesn't hurt
clinging for sure hurts controlling for sure hurts
but love doesn't this kind of love
so we
recognize without without compassion the path can feel
almost sometimes like greed more and more
happiness ease peace for me
and so we we center this commitment to the welfare of others
and we develop our own compassionate motivations by knowing
suffering intimately in awareness in every day we can do this the pain
of pain the pain of change the pain of the disjointedness of
samsara and as we
start to release our own pain
to comprehend dukkha to become more and more free
the pain of the world doesn't so much resonate with our wounds but
with our heart and um
our compassion is is vitalized our own healing
um energizes this kind of care
makes it more urgent because we know suffering so vividly
so intimately start to
wish more and more naturally that it be alleviated in others
and body speech and mind follows
figure concrete said um secretly you have to fall in love
with sentient beings
uh for this for consideration and please um
pick up whatever is useful and leave the rest behind yeah i would never say the same thing to each
of you and so you it's your job to decode
the beneficial from what what can be left behind
so uh every once in a while i have this moment
with my webcam knowing
you're uh behind it having one of those now
okay