well good morning and welcome back my name is May Elliott and here we are in
our week-long study of the foundations of vipassana meditation these are the
basics that you would be taught if you went to most Insight or vapassana centers in the west so today we will be
focusing on thinking the first day it was on breath then on body then yesterday emotions and today the
thinking mind so um so let's get started with our meditation
foreign a posture that is both
upright and energetic as well as relaxed
connecting with a felt sense of the body
and touching in with the breath or your primary anchor
settling into the Here and Now
befriending the breath giving a powerful attention as we drop
into this moment as it is
as we begin this meditation together we'll be rooting our attention with the
breath and when thoughts arise we'll simply let them go to start
we're allowing the breath to steady the mind to stabilize the mind
foreign
and sustaining our attention on the full length of an inhale
and the full length of an outhale and exhale
feeling the complete release of an out breath
foreign
thank you
shift in our attention moving our awareness away from the
breath and instead we'll imagine
we'll we'll open the awareness in front of us
open the awareness in a way where
it's as though you might be looking at a blank screen in the Mind's Eye
and soon a thought will arise and unfold through that space in that space
so I invite you to just notice
the first thought that comes into the mind after I finish this sentence
foreign
stay for a moment and pass away if not that's fine too
and if you did this is mindfulness of thinking in the present moment
thoughts occur as present moment phenomena
the content of the thought often is not in the present but the thought itself is
opening again now to that open space in front of you maybe tapping
into the sense of a blank screen in the mind
and go ahead and see if you can notice the first two thoughts that enter the mind after I
finish this sentence
foreign
and then returning the attention to be with your anchor again
space this sense of a blank screen
and see if you can pay attention to every thought that comes up after I
finish this sentence see if you can maintain the awareness for a little while
foreign
to your primary anchor maybe the breath
you may have found that you were able to be with the thoughts and uh you might
have gotten lost in thought and that's okay mindfulness of thinking is a very
slippery object as we're so apt to get lost in the content
so for the rest of this meditation so you're allowed to think
see if you can look straight at thinking being aware ah this is thinking
foreign
that you are watching a group of people standing around and having a
conversation with each other but that you're standing maybe 15 feet away so you're not lost in
the content of what they're talking about just see the process of them speaking to each other
we can relate to the mind in that way watching this process of thinking from a
little bit of a distance
and at any point if you find yourself getting too lost in thought or if
you need to just ground in the breathing or if the thoughts subside you can
return to the breath
foreign
as you do this you might take a look to see
do you think in images or in words
to your thoughts have a tone of voice
foreign
is harsh or soft
judgmental or gentle
foreign
do you notice any physical Sensations associated with thinking
maybe contraction in the forehead in the jaw or the Torso
foreign
foreign [Music]
s that go along with the thinking
foreign
hook are they very compelling
do they pull you in
foreign
to find yourself with the desire to keep thinking
wanting to continue with the content
foreign
just observing whatever happens no need to judge or reprimand
just doing our best
no right or wrong
if it's helpful for you you can use a soft mental note with thinking
when a thought arises you might just know thinking
thinking
and then if you return to the breath you might note in I'm going to inhale
and out on an exhale
very light note
and if you notice a repetitive thought and that seems to keep coming back you
might choose a specific label for it so that you're not as easily caught in
its gravity this might be
rehearsing or planning
Maybe judging
and When the Thought moves on you see what happens next
foreign
as we come to the end of our sitting together
you can dedicate the Merit we can dedicate the positive energy of our time
spent together to all beings everywhere
so they may be happy healthy safe and free
foreign
welcome back so here we are mindfulness of thinking
so at the beginning of the meditation I mentioned how
up to this point the meditation instruction has been to just stay with
the anchor of the breath and if a thought takes us away we don't
give it our attention we let it go and we come right back to the breath and because of this really standard
meditation instruction let go thinking uh you know don't get engaged in it uh
many meditators think that meditation is about getting rid of thoughts
when really that's actually not the goal of meditation
so the goal of meditation is to be free from suffering to be liberated and in order to be free we need to learn
to have a skillful relationship to our thoughts part of this skillful relationship
is in knowing that our mind produces thoughts and that's okay
the Mind produces thoughts in the way the mouth produces saliva it's just the
function of that organ it's nothing that we need to beat ourselves up about and this doesn't mean that we're
complacent with thoughts we don't let them run wild it just means that we don't need to be aversive to them that
we don't need to get rid of them so our skillful relationship to thoughts
we'll also include letting go of them at times but we don't need to reject them there's
a distinction there between letting go of thoughts and pushing away
thoughts Koto Conlin uses this image of we let go
of thoughts just like releasing a balloon a really light touch there's no
rejection there and one thing that can be helpful to
remember as we learn that our thoughts are not the enemy in meditation
is to remember that thoughts can do wonderful things we can have Loving Thoughts generous thoughts wise thoughts
like all of the Buddhist teachings the four noble truths these can all be
transmitted because of thinking and we can have very onward leading thoughts
so another interesting aspect of thinking is that thoughts themselves occur in the present moment and this is
what we were exploring in the meditation right so their their content is often in
the past or the future the content of the thoughts is taking us into ancient
history and planning what we'll do next but thinking itself regardless of the
content takes place in the now so knowing this we can learn to be mindful of thinking in the same way that
we can be mindful of sights smell sounds Etc
as our practice with thinking matures and we stabilize in the present moment
we learn how to see our thoughts simply as additional phenomena arising in the present
and being able to incorporate our body emotions and thoughts in meditation one
of the impacts is that of this is that we're able to meet everything as worthy of our attention and that's something
that's so beautiful about vapassana is nothing's left out as we learn to
include everything in mindfulness nothing's excluded
everything is included everything can be folded into our meditation practice
because of this there's no such thing as a bad meditator because of too much thinking thoughts
are just another phenomena phenomenon to be mindful of
now the trick is it's hard to be mindful of thoughts
because mindfulness of thoughts isn't getting not lost in the narrative isn't getting lost in the storyline that
the thought is weaving it's being present knowing that thinking is occurring
now if the mind is really active and the thoughts have a lot of gravitational force likely to kind of suck us up into
their content this is a good time to just practice letting go of thoughts
because if we don't let them go we're going to disappear into them so this might be a time if the thoughts
really have a ton of gravity that you might just do breath practice maybe not the best time to practice mindfulness of
thinking if as soon as you look at it you get sucked into it Once the mind is more stabilized though
we can begin to see thoughts more clearly so on Monday I spoke about mindfulness of breathing and I use this
analogy of a tripod when we practice focusing on the breath and uh and letting go of thoughts this
stabilizes the Mind much like a steady tripod so when a tripod is steady we can
put a telescope on it and see the stars much more clearly than we ever could before if the tripod isn't steady we're not
going to see much of anything so in the same way when we focus on the breath and let go of our thoughts our mind becomes
steady and we can see the Mind much more clearly and from that place we can begin begin
to see more clearly how our thoughts function as process rather than as
content so um we begin to be able to see more clear clearly whether we think more in images
or in words whether the thoughts have a tone of
voice like you might discover that a certain thought patterns might have a critical voice of a parent or the loving
voice of a sibling and some some thoughts may not have a distinctive tone at all but uh we kind
of we can get to see um how our thoughts are speaking to us
um can be incredibly helpful to notice the physical Sensations associated with
thinking that even often pleasant thoughts will have some level of contraction in the
body it can begin to investigate our the way our emotions go along with our thoughts
uh and we can see how um how compelling they are we can see how they they pull
us into their gravity so these are all great things to investigate
because these observations over time they begin to show us how flimsy thoughts are some teachers talk about
thoughts as being like little Holograms or energy wisps
and yet as Joseph Goldstein said if we're not aware thoughts are little
dictators saying get married get divorced so when we can see them for what they are we learn that we don't
have to believe them they don't have to be the dictators of our life
and this is one of the most freeing experiences to realize
that we don't have to live by limiting fears that we don't have to believe our
judgments that we don't need to be enticed by our addictions
we don't have to take our thoughts so personally or believe them
I have a refrain that I often say to myself the thought is not the thing
the thought is not the thing we so often mistake our concepts of
things our thoughts about them as the actual thing but our thought is not the thing the concept is not the actual
experience that's the great teacher Moon indraji said
your thought of your mother is not your mother
so as we begin to see this we start to like to let go of our obsession with
thoughts um when we realize how often their false prophets that the news is
not always good and the the news is not always true
so another aspect to consider regarding thoughts is that they're not ours nor
did we deliberately choose to put them there
I sing the line we all live in a yellow
I bet a certain word popped into your head it might have been submarine so if you
grew up listening to The Beatles or familiar with them that conditioned what happened in your mind
you didn't intentionally put that there we didn't put that thought there did you it was conditioned so there's a way that
we think uh that our thoughts feel so personal and like if we think something
that does that seems unwholesome or unethical that we're a bad person for
thinking that that it's all conditioned uh thoughts are impersonal and important
uh impermanent not sorry impersonal and impermanent but we give them so much
weight and it can be helpful to remember that we don't need to be bothered by our
thinking I often relate to my own thinking as off-gassing the pancreas produces
insulin and the mind produces thoughts no big deal it's just how that organ
functions and when we begin to question the
stories of suffering that we tell ourselves so much room can open up
we still think thinking is an incredibly helpful thing that we do but the thinking is lighter less believable
that no longer Reigns over the castle
the quote by Guy Armstrong
the per the deeper purpose of meditation is not simply to enjoy moments of calm
as rewarding and meaningful as they are but to understand deeply how our minds
lead us into unhappiness so that we can stop the activities that lead to those
States to reach this understanding we have to
learn to observe Thoughts with as much presence and discernment as we bring to
the seeing of breath
another way that we can do this is by getting to know the patterns of thoughts
I mentioned this in the meditation often will have repeating tracks and it
can help to name them kind of like the top top 10 hits of your thinking mind if you have a repeating track you might
name it planning or wedding thought or judgment or football game thought
and remember don't follow the content if you want to get to your destination you need to stay on the freeway don't
get off at an exit if you get caught in the content of your thinking it's like
getting off at the exit stay on the freeway
I lived for a number of years at tasahara Zen Monastery in the Ventana
wilderness and each month the community would have a full moon ceremony where we
would renew our vows and perhaps the most Central vow in the Zen tradition is
the bodhisattva Val I vow to save all beings and one of my teachers at tasahara
Leslie James put a playful Twist on The bodhisattva Vow by altering it to say I
vow to save all beings from what I think of them hmm
so while this is a little cheeky it's also right on target our thoughts about others can cause a
lot of harm the acts of killing stealing lying all
begin with thoughts so if we can get to know the mind and
see the insubstantial insubstantial and the selfless nature of thinking
you have much greater agency in choosing what thoughts we want to act on
I thought about killing stealing and lying red light don't do that thoughts about
shaming blaming or othering red light don't act on that
thoughts based in kindness uh compassion renunciation green light
yeah that's a good one to act on so our level of agency
is equal to our level of awareness our level of agency is equal to our level of
awareness so if we are aware of our thoughts we have greater agency we have
greater choice in what we do in our life and we can make skillful choices to
um to move towards Awakening and to reduce
harm in the world so I will close by reminding you that the thought
is not the thing don't mistake your ideas of others for
who they really are if you want to help others
practice mindfulness of thinking if you want to help yourself
practice mindfulness of thinking so may all beings be free
from what we think of them thank you very much I hope you all have a wonderful day and
I'll go ahead and I'll put that uh the quote that I read from guy Armstrong in
the chat I saw that somebody was interested in that