okay so so hello and welcome everyone welcome to this rendition of happy hours
lovely to be with you to feel your presence from so many different time zones
joining these different mediums different media
so so for today's happy hour practice session together
i'd like to invite us to engage
with the practice of of um
of mudita in the form of appreciation so what is mutita for those of you
uh who may not be familiar with the term um
the polyword for vicarious joy so basically turning
towards joy whether it's joy for our own
goodness and blessings or or um the gifts of other people so it's um
it's a way to really just relax relax and savor goodness
relax and savor goodness and the gift of this practice
is especially important because our minds tend to gravitate towards
challenges towards dukkha towards trauma towards what's hard it's difficult
ouch and in order to knee in order to feel resourced to remember yes there is
goodness here there is so much goodness here this practice allows us to open up to
goodness in our lives the goodness in our lives in the lives of others
especially when there is difficulty especially when there is difficulty in our lives
and when there's difficulty in the world it's not a way to
to put our heads in the sand not at all it's not escapism
but the way to open the heart to really fill up our sphere of experience
with with the fullness of life with the fullness of life
so so we've practiced joy opening to joy gratitude
in different ways and tonight i want to get into it actually slightly differently differently than i usually guide it
because as you know but i always like to to invite explore in
different ways and invite you to explore your heart your mind these these spaces
through different entry ways because as we enter through different doors we end
up in different chambers of the heart like oh wow i didn't know this was possible as many of you have shared and reported
as we try different doors different windows not always the same thing but just
creativity this practice of the brahma viharas the
the heavenly abodes which meta loving kindness and would dicta vicarious joy and gratitude are a part
of our creative practices are really creative practices to to plant seeds and
and if you happen to be new to this practice what i like to say is whatever
arises is okay don't feel like you're a failure
just because you cannot generate joy or you cannot connect with gratitude and
in order to be successful at the practice it doesn't work like that it does not
as long as you turn towards whatever arises with kindness even towards difficulty with
appreciation i'll talk more about this because it's like what is she talking about towards difficulty with appreciation but it can
become available then you're doing the practice right then practice you're planting seeds it doesn't have to look a
particular way in fact this this practice amazes us it surprises us
in ways that opens us to the dimensionality of our humanity in ways
we don't quite know ourselves we take ourselves to be this limited
little two-dimensional being and then these practices open up our heart to so
much possibility so let yourself be surprised so
so i won't say more about how we're going to enter so that you just
enter through a different path today maybe
and whatever arises again turn towards it with times it's all okay
so i think i have said enough to set the stage so i would like to invite us all now to
enter into our meditation posture landing
landing in this body and if you need to lie down or stand
the different postures the buddha has taught that's perfectly fine
if you're sitting for a moment maybe move your shoulders move back and forth
reconnect with this body see what this body needs
and land in your sit bones
land with your feet
land with your breath breath in the abdomen
breath in the abdomen let it be received
and breath and the outwards
and just spending a few minutes
being settled connecting letting your awareness connect with your
body your feet on the ground
as if your breath is moving through your feet
into the earth connecting deeply rooting
feeling the sensations of your hands on your lap
releasing relaxing
your bottom on the cushion
releasing the weight of your upper body
ah unto your sid bones
and as thoughts arise as they will
inevitably arise it's okay
see if you can
attend to them know them not with judgment but appreciatively all
this mind this brain works thinking is happening oh
thinking about this and then with kindness with a smile
saying thank you and not now
i appreciate you please come back later
let's just settle settle in the body and relax
nothing to do nothing to accomplish in this moment nothing at all
nothing no doing [Music]
just let the body the heart relax
just be breathed taking refuge into simplicity
by doing nothing
and can you enjoy just really enjoy having no agenda right now
no agenda
and just to enjoy being
in its mysterious simplicity
just opening your awareness to joy delight
what's nourishing in the body in the heart maybe you feel some buzzing
in your body
maybe with each out breath there is more letting go and settling
nourishing contentment
sometimes we forget what it's like to just sit contentedly
always need to do to accomplish to be
even when it comes to the dharma to the practice
radical radical simplicity of letting go
it's like a free fall where there is nothing to fall onto
it's safe just enjoy
enjoy the release
and if thoughts arise i don't know what i'm doing ah is this right
simply smile and release
no need to believe all the thoughts you are doing it right
whatever doing there is in this non-doing
release and open your heart to enjoy
inviting all the flowers the birds
the deer to come [Music] to the watering hole wait wait long
enough they will show up
the bird song of the breath maybe you notice it's enjoyable
for the sense of heaviness in your body after a while wow
how nice be patient release and enjoy
so we wait long enough our attention becomes more subtle
it can take a while be patient
release and enjoy there is so much
it will become clear
at the beginning we put more emphasis on their release
there are more thoughts more doing wanting release and enjoy
and when you notice your heart has settled into refuge in this moment
and open wider to enjoy
when we look when we perceive [Music]
through the lens of enjoyment we notice more
joy that we hadn't noticed before
maybe the sensations of the breath a particular way particular place
becomes source of joy enjoyment
or sensations in the body or sound or maybe there is nothing and that
nothingness becomes a source of contentment
and joy and ease
your mind your heart can enjoy
what is subtle more than you give yourself credit
open up to that possibility
relax and receive the joy of the present moment
relax re release and receive the joy of the present
moment
you can stay in this subtle
present moment embodied presence
appreciating the subtle contentment with the subtle
what is
and if you like you may drop in [Music] still in the subtlety but like a dropper
that picks up a drop of color drop in one goodness one blessing in your life
and let it reverberate
maybe it's friends family health
roof over your head something it's personal
to you drop it in this reflection
not to think about it drop it into your body
and let yourself savor enjoy
take delight in with your heart fully open in this
goodness and this blessing
and now you can drop another dropper full of something else another drop
of another blessing let it be appreciated enjoyed
not thinking about it feeling in body just relishing this
goodness
maybe now another dropper another drop of something else
another goodness in your life drop it into your body
and now as we've been taking this dropper
taking a drop of our own life's blessings and now take a drop
it's the drop of color from someone you care about the blessing in their life
something good in their life and drop that
drop of color into your
sphere of experience let yourself savor appreciate be happy for
enjoy
their blessing their cause for happiness
as if it were your own
let yourself feel it in your body in your heart
your body relaxed released just enjoying
your heart savoring this deliciousness of this goodness
as if it were your own
and that every aspect of their life may be happy or blessed but this one drop
now another drop same person or another
person in your life drop it into your heart this blessing
let your self relish it an embodied way
maybe for example this person is enjoying sports and it's very athletic
as you drop the joy of the sports in your body your heart ah as if
as if it's your joy your body feels a light with gladness appreciation
happiness energized
as if it were your own
as we bring this practice period to a close
let there be appreciation in your heart in your body contentment for whatever arose
it did not arise and if there was one moment of goodness
and appreciation yea planting wholesome seeds
with gratitude appreciation offering our goodness offering our gladness as a gift of
generosity to all beings everywhere
may all things everywhere
no to savor to appreciate to delight in the goodness in their lives and those of
others may all beings everywhere be happy
and free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your goodness
for your practice
so we have some time if you like to share reflections
you like to um [Music] raise your hand to share reflection what
came up for you maybe something new you're welcome to you can type it in
chat if you type it to me privately i won't read your name if you type it to everyone
i'll read your name and [Music]
yeah what was this like for you what um
any aha moments any challenges any any gifts don i see your hand please
yeah nikki uh thanks so much it was uh
really interesting i was pondering enjoying i'll call it suffering or
pain and um and i was just that's a slippery one for me
and every once in a while i sort of go oh that's really interesting that's really cool to sort of just seeing a
pure or feeling pure sensation but it's tough and i'm just curious kind
of hear your reflections on you know observing difficulty
yeah yeah so i appreciate you bringing that up and don't mute yourself just yet don let me ask you something here i'll
say more about what i mean and yet i think there's something very important here that you're raising from your own
experience it feels like something opens up for you in the way of oh actually there's some
maybe there's gratitude or or or openness to dukkas of to suffering
seen a different way and then it's like whoa whoa whoa this is slippery slope this is not safe this is not okay is that how it's showing up or actually let
me hear it from your words oh it the slippery part is it just reverts to suffering the uh sort of the
sort of excuse me sort of i'm not i'm not sure if it makes any sense
but just sort of observing the pure sensation and is is sort of
yeah i can enjoy that and and and sometimes it's suffering or it could be pleasure
but in the case of suffering oftentimes it just reversed you oh wow this is really painful
and um and and so there isn't that that joy and uh
and i heard at one point you mentioned that it would sort of be patient
and uh and yeah that's the part that's like oh okay how patient do i need to be
yeah right right right yeah so so very interesting so what i'm hearing in your
own experience it seems like maybe and also sounds like you're talking about physical pain because there's so many different types of suffering but you
talk about physical pain it sounds like both men physically mentally
and maybe there is a moment of opening up to oh just seeing perhaps a different perspective and suffering and then
reverts back so so so um i think what i mean by that again this is not it's not meant to be
it's not at all a masochistic way of enjoying pain it's it's not that at all
for its furthest from that so i just want to say that at the very beginning
but what what it is is that our perspective can shift our perspective
um to what what we take to be
reality or experience what's good what's bad it can shift
and and sometimes it can be surprising um and there can even be the sense of
and and maybe one way that's easier to see that sometimes not enjoying suffering but maybe the word gratitude
for suffering i think that might be more present for people that might be the way to enter that's not so much enjoying it
so i'll drop that for now because that that's a little it could be more obtuse or weird but
let's let's work with with appreciation for suffering and that i think that can be more
uh accessible because sometimes you can actually see the goodness you can we can see the
bright the silver lining in the suffering that's that's inter intertwined with it so
there's a sense of gratitude for it because of this there is that and yet sometimes
this perspective shifts so much that it's not just the silver lining but it's like
wow even suffering this is grace to be human to have the joys to even have the
sorrows this is this is amazing this is grace the mind the heart can open to
that perspective and and yet don't push it just knowing that that can be available like that can be possibility
does that does that help don yeah thank you great thank you so much for bringing that in
any other reflections before we turn to practicing community
anything else that opened up for you today in this way of getting into this practice of mudita from a very
different way i'm really curious about that if you notice the
they're just relaxing releasing and enjoying and then just dropper full of your own enjoyment then drop her full of
somebody else's enjoyment into your life like wow this is another
way to feel feel joy for others joys so
merry christine oh my goodness i see you and booty booty
boys all of a sudden very loving joyously [Laughter]
is it that the suffering gives us are we gradual because the suffering opens an opportunity to
explore is that what you're saying or i've misunderstood yeah i think that's the first stage of
it i think that's what i'm that's the first stage that can be more accessible for people that it's it's through the
suffering that a lot of growth uh and there's so many studies about post-traumatic growth etc that we
wouldn't be the people we are if it wasn't for the challenges we have in our life so so that's an easier accessible
so yes i'm saying that and i'm saying another level to that which is above and
beyond that okay thank you from birdie and i ah thanks to both you and bodhi oh so sweet
oh my god so cute
in the other reflections a quick one perhaps um
again how this different way might have affected you impacted you entering this
this metaphor of the dropper full of appreciation for your own or somebody else's
maybe i'll share since i don't see any hands or written reflections i mean for me again this is another way to get into
it and it's instead of going into like imagine somebody else's happiness and feel happy for them this really brings
it home this really brings it in this embodiment of happiness joy for ourselves delight
appreciation and then for them it's just such a physical and and what i was sharing at the end for
example imagining what came up in my mind or someone that i know who's very physically active with sports and
and just imagine taking a dropper full of their uh energy and their joy to all these
sports and dropping and you're like oh yes it's as if it's my own there's a such a sense of embodied
appreciation embodied mudita via carious joy which is different from a heady appreciation that's what i was
hoping you would you would tap into that's my hope however much that was
possible anyway so dear ones let's turn to
to holding each other with mudita with appreciation with with with joy and i will um
create the practice discussion rooms with another couple of people
invitation always is to just share from your own experience and the next person we share from theirs
will say past just hold space if you don't want to speak that's fine holding kind space for each other
and then the next person then comes back to you you'll go around around a few times so we'll be sure to monologue each
person not into no interruptions asking questions just sharing from your own
experience and not facilitating the group either just showing up and letting other people show
up in whichever way is safe and comfortable for them and holding each other with kindness
so tonight you're invited to say if you like something about how this practice was for you or maybe
something that you're grateful for just the dropper full for of your life or somebody else's
life that brought you the sense of gladness so opening the rooms take care of
yourselves take care of each other here we go
okay all the rooms are closed everybody's back um
and any final fast quick reflections before we close
the urgent anything that you like to say to feel complete
okay going once mario christine make it quick thank you could we explore
this topic a bit further next time please um possible yeah yes i think it'll be explored at
some point yes it may not be next time but yes we might yeah appreciate it merry christmas take good care
well thank you all thank you so much for your practice for showing up for
cultivating your own witness for your own sake and the sake of all those whose lives you touch may all
beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone [Music]