so hello everyone and welcome
and uh
when my children were young we had this children's book
that had drawings that um were magnifications of 10
and these these books would start with um I think they went different
directions maybe they'd start but one common one was would start like far out in space and
maybe see the world in the middle of our
our solar system Maybe or a Galaxy
and then each page would take a power of 10 closer in until just the world
then just that particular maybe continent and then get closer and it'd be just a
city and closer or just be the park in the city and then the lawn and the city and then
the grass and the few you know pieces of grass in the city and then going closer it would be
somehow a close-up of the cells and they go into the cells and
see pieces of the cells and maybe DNA and then go closer still and there would be molecules and atoms and
closer still and just the electrons and protons and in vast space and it was quite a
remarkable thing to kind of change the perspectives and see things in so many
different ways and meditation is can be a little bit the same way
and which direction we go varies and sometimes it's going inward
and to our vast space of just a few electrons and sometimes it's outwards
into a vast empty space in a galactic systems or
something and um and sometimes it's nice to have the idea
of going back and forth between these two different perspectives vast and you know large and very small and close
in and and but I think
starting where we're at as human beings and then nothing oftentimes meditation
is more like starting where we're at and learning to be fully present for where
we're at regardless where we are in the powers of ten
but then as we relax and settle and quiet it's kind of like moving inwards
and now it's becoming kind of closer and more intimate in here and until we're kind of powers of 10 and
just go in and end to come to a place we're the most intimate the most expansive the most freeing
is kind of like this vast space and and it feels like we're home in some
ways and then we return and come back to this human
perspective and and hopefully bring with us the freedom
so to take a alert upright posture
and lowering your gaze gently
letting your gaze be relaxed
and then to gently close your eyes and to begin here
at this human Realm
of your life here and in the place where you live maybe
surrounded by your neighborhood of maybe other Homes apartment buildings
Maybe you live early surrounded by fields or forests
mountains just kind of where you are
and the environment around you
maybe as far as you can walk for five minutes as if this too is part of your world
part of who you are in a sense
so here in the middle of this neighborhood this land under the sky
here you are in a sense sitting on the Earth
here
and then bring your attention in closer and if you're sitting in a room
be aware of sitting in a room this is the power of 10 maybe coming inward
or if you're sitting outside it just not what you can walk five minutes in any
direction to but here what you can see what you can feel around you
in Buddhism we have this idea that any of the location where someone
meditates is kind of like the Center of Your World
your experiential world the world of your perceptions
and if you come closer in to just hear in this body
feeling how this body connects to this place
the weight of the body full of gravity and where those meet in
the your cushion surfaces your body touches
here definitely hear this spot
the center of your universe
in this body that breathes and maybe as you breathe you feel the movements of
your chest and torso against your clothes
maybe you feel like whatever your hands are contacting your thighs your knees each other
hear this body that has been your companion one way or the
other for years now centering yourself in this body they
can give you long slow deep breaths relaxing into the body on the exhale
breathing normally and as you exhale with a normal breath
perhaps there can be a quieting a gentling of your thinking mind
maybe not dramatically but a little bit of a quieting
calming of the thinking mind
with a lot of thinking it's kind of easy to feel removed from
oneself one's body once lived experience
letting go of your thoughts they go into this living body
feeling it from the inside out
and maybe coming in closer power of 10 kind of movement
feeling the particular location in your body where you feel most you
most feel your sense of aliveness
the place in your body that most represents or is associated with
to living here in this moment
and perhaps if it's easy allow this location in your body
to be gently massaged rocked by the breathing
for the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out by the rhythm of the body moving as you
breathe
as you exhale can you settle in let go into
deeper Within like a power of 10.
it's entering yourself
either at the center of where you're most alive
or centering yourself where the breathing begins
where the breathing ends place in your body the ending and
beginning of breathing
like you're entering into a beautiful Grove of trees leaving the World Behind
enter into your depth of your body
leaving your thoughts behind
letting go of thoughts and letting go into
the quietest deepest place within
foreign
going inwards beneath your thoughts beneath your feelings
beneath it all is there some place of calm or peace
that you can touch into at the center of it all
maybe it's a just a pinhead
in size someplace the powers are ten going in
of calm or peace
maybe of your breathing the rhythm of breathing move through that place
through the calm the peace
and as you inhale let that calm
become larger through your body as you inhale that your awareness spread
through your body
bringing with it to calm or the sense of spaciousness
expanding to the whole body
letting you be your awareness your
conceiving spread out to include this room where the place you're sitting
maybe the inhale spreads the calm or the or the spaciousness out into the room
and then letting your awareness expand outward as if it can
reach out across the land around you the territory the neighborhood
bringing away that a sense of expanding calm
and visualizing or considering
The Wider land in which you are at out
as far as you can walk on a five minute walk maybe just out and expanding outwards
as if you're calm or your spaciousness
spans ever outwards
and powers of tan outwards across the the city the county the province
the state that you're in
and all the people that inhabit this area
in you as one of a multitude of people
but from your point of view you sit in the middle of the multitude
from your calm spaciousness
imagine your gaze upon all beings with kindness and friendliness
you wish them well
and taking powers of ten more broadly your powers of a hundred and
out into space looking back on this world
Planet floating in space
this Blue Marble with so many people on it
so many beings who have this precious opportunity to be
alive and to be breathing and
okay is a component all kindly and friendly
wishing may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to the second talk
on a series of talks on the topic of meaning the meaning meaning making and
relationship to meditation and one of the areas of that we
so first I want to say is Introduction that um there's a cliche that everyone is a
philosopher but they don't know it many people don't know it and what that
means I think is that everyone has um a set of interpretations meaning
understanding of what it means to be alive what's important what this life is
about that they operate from though sometimes it's not reflective
sometimes reflect they don't haven't thought about it haven't realized they're doing this and part of a path of mindfulness is
both to be reflective about this to be clear and conscious but also to discover what are some of the underlying
assumptions belief systems interpretations that we are basing our life on
and as we said quietly in meditation it's possible to see these operate
and then also to question them some of them aren't really that helpful or
healthy for us and some of them are and be able to distinguish between which is useful and
not which seem accurate or not is part of the wonderful power of meditation of
mindfulness so one area that we can connect one area of meaning
making in connection to meditation is the our understanding
of what it means to be a self and what it means to have other people in relationship to a self
that there's a lot of philosophy a lot of ideas that come along with our
Notions of Who We Are and who who others are and what that connection is
I think a wonderful story around this was some years ago there was someone who
did a study of different
um meditation centers I think they're all in the United States but some of them were primarily
um the participants the meditators were
primarily um born and raised in the United States
I call acculturated in the United and then as local United States Yen's culture
and some were were acculturated in an Asian
culture that had a much stronger collectivist culture much strong sense
of communal sense of identity in who they are whereas the United States many
people who grew up in this culture have a much stronger sense of individuality in the individual
so researchers studied these two different meditation centers and asked
that the participants how was the retreat you did I think they both did you know set week-long Retreats or
something well how was the retreat and and uh and what did you gain or what was the benefits from the retreat
and um and both groups loved the retreat that it was fantastic it was life-changing so that they had in common
but when they discussed uh what they benefited from them and what way it was so great
um in one way or the other the people who have been raised in this local
culture in the United States they
emphasize that they discovered who they are they got a sense of real
Independence and freedom and all the reference points were very individualistic
and um and those people who came from the Asian culture uh they said oh I realized how much
gratitude I have for my Society my family how deeply
connected we are and and um and I've you know I've appreciated so
much more all the benefits I've received from you know my Society my family my
everyone and and the sense of connection and gratitude and being part of
something was you know so powerful for me and I and so in many ways maybe they're having
similar you could say similar experience of settling getting concentrated
becoming still letting go of hindrances but the meaning or the value that they
took out of the experience what they selected out of their experiences this is what is important
it was so very different one was very individualistic one was more about how they are in the collective
and so this speaks to how uh and often that's invisible that we make this
selection just seems like this is natural of course this is like isn't this what it's all about or
because the view we have about what's important is not just taken for granted
it's built into the fabric of the universe that self is important than discovering the self
similar thing happened to me many years ago where I was on a panel and um with a Christian minister and I
was kind of like the Buddhist teacher minister and uh and they're also the person that
I was uh the panel that the person I was with was uh Asian Asian American and I
was you know you know represented people from the United States I guess
or Europe what kind of this individualist Norway where I'm from is very individualistic because maybe even
more so sometimes than the way we are in the United States and um
and we were asked you know what when you what brought you into Buddhism what were you or into your religion she was
Christian and um and uh I for me I was kind of Happily matter of factly as if there was
the most natural thing in the world back then um it was talked about how um you know
finding myself or finding this inner freedom and and she talked about how her Christian
faith how much it put her into a community of fellow fellow people in
relationship to a society and people and that was what was so meaningful for and found a sense of belonging and home
and there again we see this you know people enter into religion have very different orientation of what they're looking for and what they want
so and we also become with a lot of ideas not just simple like that but what
it means to be an individual what it means to be a self what's important and so when we sit down to meditate it's
part of what our motivation can be is about that self um it could be that uh we're you know
we're looking for how to be a better you know get a career advancements and so
we've been told that if we're too anxious and so you need to meditate they get calmer and quieter because that's
how you're going to you know be more respected at work and so so it's all about me
attaining something getting something it could be that um
uh it could be this you know it's another person has been told that you know you really don't fit into the
community here uh very well and um you might try meditating because then
you'll relax and start feeling more connected to the people around you and so the meditation can have a
different function for different people depending on what seems important for them
and um and then um so then also the locus of uh of what
what's valued the most around the self is the self as an autonomous independent
person what's most important and we have to realize that and and find it or as a
self as someone embedded in a system of relationships with other people and somehow finding ourselves kind of
connected to that embedment and embedded Nation nature of society or social
connections that meditation is going to help us to really feel connected to that
and and feel much more part of it in a deeper and deeper way
um the uh I've seen you know my early years when I was first coming to Buddhism and was kind of peer with a lot
of new people coming to Buddhism how many peace on people were really coming to find themselves
and um and what they found was instead of finding themselves that or maybe they
did because they found themselves then at some point they found themselves back into the deeper connection to the
religion they grew up with and so they will go back into a church or synagogue or something and um and uh in a way that
they then participated more in the collective life of it other people I've seen it goes into
Buddhism and and um and it also finds a sense of community there and that's what's kind of more important than the
meditation because that's what they're culturally or personally their philosophy what they
think is important and some people
um I've you know just for some whatever reason find that their engagement of
Buddhism is always very personal and they're happy to go off and be Hermits and long periods of meditation without much
connection to to others is one better or worse than the other
I'd rather not think that way there are all ways of organizing meaning purpose
in this world of ours and maybe they all have a place they all have a role there's a time and season
for all things and there's a and there's a place in society for maybe all the
different ways that we can construct our sense of self our sense of meaning our sense of being connected to others
and um and and this is an adventure it's kind of like a discovery it's kind of like
the and as I said in the meditation kind of like the powers of ten that meditation takes you into some deep
deep place quiet still Letting Go place and then how do we interpret that around
the sense of how we understand this self and what's important around the self and what the self is in relationship to
needs and motivations and purposes and our place in this world
um in that deep place or what's that connection from that deep place of Freedom as we come back to
powers of 10 back into the world back into society and not a few people have found
themselves transformed so that their relationship and their understanding of what it means to be in
relationship to other people is radically changed a simple way where understanding would
be that many people are codependent very deep sense of neediness and need and and
really measuring their success and their well-being in relationship to other people and comparing themselves to other
people and to really delve deep into this kind of varied powers of tend to go within
going within within and letting go the social world for a while can be transformative so that when we
come back into the social world that the sense of neediness is not there anymore
this sense of comparing ourselves and measuring ourselves with other people and then the
social world can have a very different meaning than it had before how much meaning it has how important it
is depends in part by the meaning making understandings that we have about our
place in the world and who we are and who we are in relationship to other people and we shouldn't assume that two
meditators share the same understanding of in that range or in that of what's most
important where are they most Center their life and I said more in community or more is in
the individual and and what other kind of secondary understandings come from that
so without saying any of us are right and wrong I think that's very important
what I'd like to say is that it's important to become reflective about it think deeply about to realize what we're
operating under what are the assumptions what are the beliefs we have around self around others and to dismiss this whole
investigation of self because Buddhism says there's no self kind over not to focus on self
um is it there's uh it's easy that we think I almost Miss or not notice that we actually haven't
almost subconsciously unconsciously deeply embedded Notions and operating
principles around what it means to be a self and what's important and what this
kind of selective process attention uh is used for to pick out and
recognize and know in this world what's important so I offer this uh with the hope that
you will uh maybe spend some time today maybe
talking with friends and others about you kind of your you know your your own
Central focus on understanding of what it means to be a self an individual and
the uh what that mean what what what beliefs and ideas come along with your
sense of personhood and what is it to be in a person in
society and what are the beliefs and ideas and their standings that come along with how you are embedded in
society are you embedded or are you really removed what's the connection there
and um and I hope that if you reflect deeply on these things and think about them that when you come to do your
meditation some of those things can be put can be put down it could be put to rest
temporarily and they won't be operating and churning away in some maybe quiet
deep way and allow something some power of 10 to open up for you
whether it's power of 10 deeper and deeper in or power 10 further and
further out that's for you to discover
so thank you very much and um