so hello hello and welcome everyone to
uh to happy hour so so for today's practice um
i thought it might be nice to turn our attention to the third brahma vihara the
third of the hard practices of the heavenly abodes
which um we sometimes practice but not as often as
meta so the first one being metta second one being meta translated as loving kindness
second one being karuna compassion the third one being joy vicarious joy
joy for ourselves and for others and the fourth one being equanimity so
so let's turn our hearts towards joy
and the word in pali is mudita mudita and
it's really the expression of loving-kindness kindness that
comes across gladness in the world whether it's somebody else's good fortune or whether
it's our own good fortune and there's always good fortune even if
somebody's having a hard time having difficulty suffering there's some other areas of their life where there is
goodness there's good fortune or blessings similarly for ours because we
usually just turn our attention to what is difficult
we get to see we tend to see what is difficult what's challenging and
lose sight of what is good what is beautiful what is
magnificent actually that so many things are going right and yes maybe a few things are not
going right with us with others with the world so turning turning attention and
intentionally looking at relishing what is good
about others fortune our fortune so that the heart can rest in joy and
again not as a way to to turn into la la land but as a way
to empower nourish the heart
the states of joy are really important on the path to liberation the states of
joy and contentment and bliss are very important this practice this buddhist practice
mindfulness insight to the pasana different ways to translate it it's not about hard work and engagement
yet there is plenty of engaging being noticing with with
awareness what is happening internally externally but the heart needs a lot of
joy bliss contentment to
be settled on the path in fact there are many steps uh practical the steps in the
step-by-step instructions and what the buddha taught towards the path of liberation that end in nibbana in
awakening but they go through bliss and joy actually
gladness joy and bliss and concentration so those steps
are one after another anyway so so the practice of joy
modita gladdening our heart is not escapism
but it's a way of enriching enriching our capacity to hold more we can become
more available for ourselves and for others [Music]
to relish the beauty the the mystery the mystery that this life
is this world is so so without further ado let's practice
together as i've set the frame so so
arriving landing in your body
landing in this moment notice what the body needs if the body
needs to maybe shift or move or lie down or stand up it's all okay
turning the intention
towards the body first and foremost the body
[Music] the feed the legs the sit bones connected to the
earth
inviting awareness to rest
to lower to lower the center of gravity [Music]
of our awareness from our head with habitual thinking move it down down down from our chest
to our abdomen belly lower abdomen somewhere between the
belly and the sit bones receiving the breath there very low in
the abdomen
ah let the breath be received in breath the out breath released the whole body
releasing
and as thoughts arise can we release thoughts that there's anything wrong with
thinking but the benefit of
this cultivation this moment of taking refuge
can we release
letting awareness be intertwined
with the breath appreciating the gift of the breath
it is a goodness not to be taken for granted
to tune into enjoying appreciating
being calmly perhaps contentedly collected in the
breath
same way often pets collect themselves cozily in their bed
wrapped in a ball comfy cozy
can the breath be that bad for us cozily
collecting ourselves in it
with ease relaxing the body resting resting
and now like to invite us as we continue to stay embodied
relaxing receiving the breath
collecting ourselves enjoying the gift of the breath
let's bring to mind someone who is dear to us
well we like to be happy we wish for them to be happy
we want the best for them ideally someone with whom we have an uncomplicated relationship
bringing this person this being to mind could be a pet
it could be a human a child
conjuring them up as well as possible in this moment
as if they were sitting in front of you
hold hold their presence with yours see what happens in your heart
being in the presence of someone you care about in your mind's eye and your heart
and now this person this being you have brought to your attention
there might be areas of their life which is challenging that's okay
but there's probably something in their life that is going well
that's a blessing something that's a blessing
so choosing choosing wisely choosing in
this practice of mutita vicarious joy
we intend we choose we select
to open our hearts
to what is going well in their life what's a blessing
what they're grateful for what we see is a blessing for them for
anyone they have it they enjoy that
just one thing can we feel happy for them
happy that they have this blessing this good fortune
feeling glad for their gladness for their fortune good fortune
feel like you can say the phrases of modita vicarious joy
i offer a few different alternatives choose what you like
i'm happy for your happiness
my delight and your good fortune
or
may this blessing this good fortune
made increase may it continue made increase
may it never stop may it continue
may it increase for you may it never wane
offering with generosity generosity
it's not a zero-sum game this is life this happiness
the happier they are the happier you can be for them
offering generosity
may your happiness may your happiness continue
made increase may it never wait
and notice how your heart can feel more generous more
glad more happy this is the surest way the fastest way
to become happy if your mood is
flat getting caught up in
challenges
feeling happy for others happiness
may your good fortune increase may continue dear one
may it continue made increase made never wayne dear one
keep in contact with this being in your mind's eye it's important to keep the heart connection
in this practice
feel like you can stay with this being or you can let them go if you wish
and invite now someone comes to mind to your heart
a being that has some good fortune you're really happy about
just so happy maybe they just got married or something
they have a job that they love
something that just brings brightness gladness to your heart
for this person this being maybe they had a hard time for a while
see what works for you whatever it needs a sense of gladness
for someone
maybe they're getting to travel or whatever it might be even if it's
something that you wish for yourself can you be happy for them offer generosity
i'm happy for you i'm happy for your happiness may it continue
made increase may it never way
taking delight in somebody else's good fortune
is so beautiful so beautiful nourishing
a selfless act of generosity
so many ways to be generous
some of this practice at any moment happens to bring up envy it's okay you're not doing it wrong
it's a purification practice it can come up it's okay
don't berate yourself that should happen you can't let go of that being
you can turn to yourself with compassion oh sweetheart you really
want this thing too don't you this is hard it's okay
holding yourself with metta with compassion not with self-judgment
appreciating your own blessings
you can stay with yourself or go back out to another being
you're staying with a being for whom you're happy
i delight in your happiness may your happiness continue
made increase may it never end
may not be every aspect of their life but just one aspect
that they're really happy about and you're happy for them
and at any point you can also turn if you want
and make yourself this beloved other bring to your heart
the blessings that this being who is you has in their life that you often take for granted
they often take for granted become happy for your own happiness
maybe for a moment we'll take the external perspective as if you're stepping out of yourself
oh sweetheart i'm happy for your happiness these blessings in your life what good
fortune i'm happy for your happiness
may they continue may they increase may they never wait
if stepping out of your stuff seems complicated you can do it from your own perspective
may my happiness my good fortune continue
increase never wane or i'm happy for these gifts these
blessings in my life
you have a roof over your head what a blessing
you have found your way to the dharma what a blessing
you have a mind that works
well enough to be here to be practicing what a blessing
you've had food to eat
what a blessing
for people you care about
those who care about you
even if our
if you like inviting now the other beings earlier you hide in your mind's
eye a dear being and the being who's happy invite them may
all of our blessings all the ways
we're blessed with goodness in our lives
maybe continue
may it may there never way [Music] or a delight in our
happiness in our shared happiness
common humanity happy in different ways in this human condition
letting my heart rejoice for all of us expanding the circle if you wish
including more beings all the ways different beings are happy
maybe their grandmothers who adore and love their grandchildren and vice versa
ah let me be happy for them
or wherever else your imagination takes you let your heart
bleep with joy for people having joy
on this planet
and as we bring this practice period to a close
letting your joy spread
offering it as a gift to the entire world our joy is a gift
think brightly our happiness can make others happy
can be infectious so offering our joy as blessing
the wholesomeness of it all may be the support
of all beings everywhere being happy
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your joyful practice or however
however it was thank you for your practice ah so
we have time and i'm told my internet connection is stable unstable so
hopefully you can hear me even if my image seems to be freezing
um audio is fine great thanks yes the video is going to be choppy it
is what it is we work with the conditions of this digital
zoom room so so we have time for uh reflections
questions gifts whatever came up for you like to offer to the um
any insights any aha moments any challenges it's all okay
mima all right thank you nikki thanks
um i really enjoyed this i've never done just joy
and it felt so good it was so uplifting for um
to do it for others that had been struggling and some that have it like really comfortable
and then for myself i noticed the small things that bring me joy like my husband
put a hammock up for me and i work from home and so in between i get to go and sit out in the hammock for
15 minutes whenever i want and i hadn't noticed how much joy that was
bringing me and so doing this i was like looking at all the good things that and it did
bring joy to my heart it lightened liked it so sweet so sweet thanks so much for
sharing mima i'm having joy for you and your hammock and all the ways this is so
sweet and i see other people smiling and delighting very sweet very sweet
ah thank you for letting me mom bernadette please
it has been um i actually went on a one-week spring inside meditation retreat at um
spit rock for one week from 14th through 21st with my um long time meditation teacher
matthew bren silver so i when i was there i actually experienced
the most wonderful relaxation and calming
joyous moment and i was able to kind of reach it and i
would be able to brought it out and matthew and i had a discussion
don't be surprised if you maybe go back in some way in other way and i just sent
him an email over the week i've been able to maintain it and
they're and i wonder if because because i've been practicing with the spirit rock and then now i
started with the gills morning climates yeah and then sunday and then this this uh loving kindness
and also spear rocks as well as uh i'm a jew a lot of continuity so yeah and yeah
yeah and then also i've been also practicing with the mic synagogue group which is
meditations the combination and everything is literally still making me
in state of a calmness and relaxation right as i left
that was 21st and despite all the bad news that was happening
i was able to send loving-kindness to myself and others
and the persons the people that i know who are losing their jobs yeah yeah so so that becomes compassion
yeah so so so what i'm hearing is that this is lovely bernadette you have a lot of continuity you decide to retreat
beautiful and and now you're having a lot of continuity and really supporting yourself with these different conditions
so there's a sense of continuity beautiful fantastic lovely and don't get
attached because when conditions change state of mind changes too and not you
know i'm not saying this to to to burst your bubble but you know this it's it's enjoy it's made up of conditions which
is great so so you get to enjoy it while elastic yes and know that yeah there
might be some challenges but can i also have equanimity and ease and joy in the midst of challenges because you know
you're coming from retreat but there might be other people today joining from a really hard day and they're tired and
yet there's a sense of oh this is nourishing this is refreshing this is
gosh i can dip into this even though i haven't just sat a retreat and there haven't been sitting all so so
it's all good thanks for sharing that and welcome again now i see your hand please
i'd love to share um a friend of mine who i met yesterday
who's um having stage four cancer she's a psychologist by training
and she spent a lot of her volunteer time trying to support students and teachers
in vietnam with practices of well-being and um and in speaking to her yesterday knowing
that her life is in a way kind of coming to an end uh she was full of joy that um
people are finally listening to her at a much deeper level so she was expressing how you know um her mission of her life was
to spread these ideas and that you know in this time with this situation it's given her this
beautiful opportunity to really share it at a deeper level so i was thinking of her a lot uh in this
practice thank you thank you enough thank you so much for
sharing wow what a beautiful what a beautiful being what a beautiful shining heart to to see the brightness and the
beauty of how her message is now being
listened to and taking joy in that because of that her time is short oh yeah how beautiful is that how beautiful
inspiring that's lovely thank you know thanks for sharing that that brings me joy yay so when you it brings me joy for
you also that you have someone in your life you know that you know and and you connect with this way and you worked
with this is beautiful yeah it's lovely so
dear ones so today in the group i have a particular request actually in the group the question that you ask or you'll
answer which is really a practice of joy making is what brings you joy what brings you
joy so each person will share about what brings them joy could be your hammock could be a friend who is inspiring in
your life a teacher a grandchild
a partner you know anything your cup of tea so it's it's you'll go around and around
just sharing something that brings you joy and let yourself really relish really share with with uprightness with
with um with courage like yes taking your seat
really taking your seat on this earth this brings me joy this brings me joy
and it could be something small something big anything strawberries bring me joy apples bring
me joy right anything just brings makes you happy so and each person will say some will so
you'll say something another person another person you'll go you'll go around and round and um
and and when people are listening they just hold space so you hold space for
joy you let you practice mudita it becomes it becomes easier practice of mudita because people are talking about
what brings them joy and you hold space for them so it's a it's a very joyous practice so
so again um just sharing from your own experience not managing not asking
questions not probing just sharing whatever you feel like sharing
uh from your own experience so i'm going to open the rooms enjoy
here we go open all rooms okay
the rooms are closed everybody is back and we have just about a minute for any final
reflections if anybody wants to share anything what was it like to be in the
room sharing your joy today anybody wants to say a quick word who hasn't spoken yet before quick quick
i see hearts that's sweet any final reflections
lots of hearts oh sweet very sweet
yeah wow i'm trusting that it was a joyous experience to to hold
people's joy yeah and to share your joy so maybe you will end on that note so
thank you all thank you for sharing your joy thank you for holding space for
others joy may our joy spread throughout the world may all beings be happy may all beings
be free [Music]
thanks again take care see you on wednesday