so hello everyone and
it's always special when people gather to practice the dharma to practice
awareness showing up for this life of ours in a fuller way or deeper way than maybe we
can do in ordinary life maybe in a way that we connect to more
of ourselves more of this experience of life
so that but the topic these days in sati patana is contemplation of the corpse
and i think it's significant to recognize that the corpse contemplation
occurs right after the four elements the four elemental properties
meditation that just before we're doing these the
sensations the living sensations which are a manifestation of being alive it's what
animates us it what fills us in with life
and uh when we're no longer alive
then there's no more sensations the body might still exist as a corpse
but it's not animated with the sensations it's also not animated with awareness
and it's not animated with the depths of our feelings
so there's something about
for me at least that the contemplation of a corpse that's not animated consciousness is not in it
anymore highlights awareness highlights consciousness
highlights our sensations our animated life right now
it's kind of like absence often highlights things better
silence can help us hear sound
a blank piece of paper can highlight a dot that's
a pen puts on the middle of the paper in a way that you wouldn't be highlighted if it was a
piece of paper that was scribbled all over
so the contemplation of the corpse the way it goes is this too
my body also one day will become a corpse
one day will decay or be cremated or
it will change to something else the elements of it the pieces of it
and perhaps this idea that your body one day
will be sensation free absent of sensation
for now we have
sensations and that can be the place where we center our attention
perhaps highlighted and appreciated or valued more
knowing
not only is it temporary just for this lived life we have
but this live life we have through our sensations the way we directly experience ourselves
is a river of change a river of unfolding
coming and going you hear a sound
like i hear the train right now train whistle i can't grab it or hold on to it it'll
be gone now it's gone
comes and goes
many of the sensations you have they appear and disappear maybe repeatedly
like the sensations of breathing
one day your body will not have these sensations
this day you have sensations
but they're fleeting and passing perhaps you can settle back
marvel at this animated life of sensations
while they're occurring one day they won't
so taking a meditation posture oh
let's see my
okay so there we go sorry about this my laptop froze
and i thought maybe i'd lost you but that i muted and then i forgot to unmute i think
we're back on
so yes back on so it's part of this theme of today's
meditation absence the end of things
everything will be gone someday and on this day
the deep experience of
sensation or sensate life is meant to help us not cling to any of
it just aware
so settling into your body and your breathing
following the sensations in your body noticing when they appear
noticing when they disappear
following the appearance and disappearance of sensations
the appearance of sensations indicate you're alive
the disappearance of sensations is a reminder it won't always be here
and then we'll sit quietly
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to not only appreciate that the living animated life we have
is found in our sensations and our senses
it's also found in our capacity to love
to have a tender warmth and care for others
it's found in our ability to care for ourselves
a gentle valuing of our own life as well
and to go deeper into the heart to places where we can love
either because we can do it or because
we're making ourselves available for the day when we can
and to end the sitting maybe expressing that love or
inviting that love if it has not yet come
to consider the welfare and happiness of others that others just like you
have the capacity for happiness for being alive in a peaceful
happy way
and maybe this be our wish that all of us self and others the whole
world move towards greater and greater happiness and
peacefulness freedom may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may our love or our aspiration to love
be expressed in action
may we care for this world in how we live
[Music] thank you
so to continue with something i said at the beginning of the meditation this
sixth exercise of the 13 exercises that make up the practice
of the four foundations for awareness
this sixth one is the contemplation of the corpse
sits between the mindfulness of sensations
and mindfulness of feelings and so
we're preparing the ground to go deeper in this practice of sati in becoming sensitive and aware of the
sensate life the lit the sensations that come and go
but those sensations have a characteristic qualities
of being pleasant unpleasant or neutral and this ability to feel
the pleasure of things to feel the pain of things is part of this deeper animated life
that we have and the pleasure and pain is in some ways we can think of it as something
deeper and more in within us because it's not only physical
when we feel the sun of the war the the warmth of the sun against our skin
the that's a physical pure physical sensation the pleasure we get from that
is mixture of physical pleasure and mental pleasure the mental evaluation of it and so it
something deeper more connected to our lived life and
and so between these two between sensations and feelings
there's this contemplation of a human body that has neither
has neither feelings sensations or feelings and
to spend some time contemplating that there will be a day for each of us because this this contemplation of the
corpse there's nine different states of decay that
the practice talks about and um and to imagine for each one of
those i will be like this too and then um my body also will
but all the things of our body that we cherish we love we're identified with we may be attached to
preoccupied with they will slowly go and
now this contemplation of the corpse involves uh
what happened to corpses in the old day bef uh when many people did not cremate
their bodies but rather they were just put on top of the charnel grounds
where wild animals just were left there to rot and decay and
decompose and so you could go to the charlotte ground and see this process
a friend of mine wasn't up in the himalayas where they still have charnel
grounds and came across walked through the charnel grounds
and came across a recently dead body that was just laying there
and been left and so and this uh i mentioned yesterday the teacher buddha dasa who had the skeleton
hanging of miss thailand 1936 his instructions for when he died
was to simply be put in the forest a place for his followers his monks nuns
could come and just contemplate his body decaying
he didn't get his wish because he was one of the most famous monks in thailand and so
other authorities had other ideas but
so our skin that we put a lot of attention to perhaps
our hair will all decay and pass away
may be eaten by worms and other things mushrooms and fungi and
the muscles that maybe some of us might be exercising working out
the muscles fade and decay they won't be here some point
the tendons will no longer be here the bones will no longer be held
together the bones will begin to decay and eventually just become dust
so you know it's orient and orientated feeling knowing that not only the sensations go but all this
ways in which we're attached or we orient ourselves around the body will also go
um the absence of it the highlights that we're alive
and the and some of the core elements of that aliveness is are the sensations and the feelings
so to maybe we appreciate these sensations deeper in contemplating their absence through the image of a corpse
that we will be like a corpse too and maybe it's a way of taking a little
more seriously this moment the only place that you can be alive
is in the present moment and now there's a a
a very powerful verse in the dhammapada in chapter 2 the
first verse that says it goes something like
negligence is the path of death vigilance path to the deathless
those who are negligent are as if already dead
those who are vigilant never die
and i don't know you know what the figurative meaning this would never die but the sense of
to be vigilant to be hateful to be careful to be present
in a full way and the only place where that can happen which is now in the present moment
and to feel that to be pray to feel and pray present for that the flow of sensations of flow of
experience the flow of feelings to let go of everything else
when you die in your corpse you'll have letting go you will have let go of everything
it's possible to do this before you die
and why not why not when that gives us freedom why not that lives us gives us
an experience to really be alive and present and free
in a way that that is fantastic and wonderful
so to spend time contemplating
a corpse you might
that you might not have a place to go anatomy lab to go visit a corpse it's probably pretty easy to find some
photographs but the photographs of
people who are peacefully dead maybe photographs of bodies which are
decaying not to make it gruesome not to
upset your stomach but is there a way of contemplating corpses the body that has no animated
sensations that brings you into the present moment i'll tell you a story which i've
something i do which i've told many times but it's related to this
i'm fond of looking at old photographs old enough that the people in it are no
longer alive like from 100 120 years ago 130 40 years ago
and i like it when the people in it when the photograph has a really good resolution
and and you see portraits of people see people and i'll go up and look at their eyes
get close or their expression in their face and occasionally you see you see in the
old photographs a gleam in their eyes like the spark of life that was there for that moment
other times you see the expression of their faces that are kind of stand out like expression of the moment
and now when i see these i i contemplate this was their moment to be alive
and this is my moment for me to be alive somehow appreciating that that was their
moment i don't want to miss my moment this is my moment my
my glimmer of spark of life life is short and
and so kind of looking at for old photographs puts me into my own life in a fuller nicer way
so um i think that's what i'll say today and
i'm unsure what we'll do tomorrow i kind of would like to do one more day on the corpse
i haven't really introduced you to the full text of it
and um but um maybe maybe we'll see or we'll move over
to feelings and so
thank you and i'll be here tomorrow