they're recording on for audio dharma's sake there
so hello hello warm hello and welcome everyone
it's good to be with you in this moment in time whatever the time zone might be for you
so i'd like to i'd like to invite us to explore
um the theme which is actually the title of a book
and it's a theme that we have explored in different ways and yet
it's so rich so let me share the title and the title of this book is happiness
is a choice you make and i might have mentioned it before uh
happy hour some time ago happiness is a choice you make and the sub title of the book i think is
lessons from the oldest old the title of the book is quite
provocative happiness is a choice it's a choice you make it's not something that
happens to you when when circumstances are perfect when you have perfect health when you have
just the right amount of money or the right job or the right relationship or the
right house um all of these come and go and yet
happiness can be can be a fountain within a choice that we make
that is not dependent on the conditions you can be sick you can have limited
mobility and still have a sense of well-being contentment happiness
and these are lessons that we explore in our spiritual practice of course we do and
and this book which i do highly recommend is is quite remarkable so this um journalist i think new york
times uh journalist i believe um and
john leland i think his name maybe i should quickly find just so that i'm i'm
referring to him correctly so he um spent a year
with the oldest old with with seven um uh
people who were over 85 and they became his teachers basically in that year yes
john leland l-e-l-a-n-d is his name and it was a time when his life had
fallen apart after a long marriage and and um and he learned so much and he shares
that with humility in the book about how the people who became
his teachers had lost so much had lost so much mobility and and you know with old age
what happens and friends relatives with some of them not being able to live
where they wanted to live being transferred losing their friends etc and and actually there is research
that suggests that um when we get older even though we lose
so much we lose so much but the level of happiness actually increases
which is quite surprising but it's because of how
how people become wiser in learning in learning to to be with to appreciate
what there is instead of pining after the past or or thinking about a future that's actually quite limited at that
point you know because lifespan we know it's short so so this art this this this both
science this art of turning inward and there are beautiful examples in the book how
how john neeland's teachers these people over 80 85
for example when one person is not able to go out to you know
uh to have an outing and then he decides he's actually happy in his apartment
turning on the tv and having ice cream which is not he's not supposed to have but there's a sense of contentment
instead of thinking oh they didn't pick me up they fell through like there was a sense of happiness there was a sense of
peace their sense of peace with with the simple pleasures with the
simple joys with the simple actually miracles of life so so hence the title happiness is a
choice you make happiness is a choice we make um [Music]
and it's a training we train ourselves with us as the buddha invites us we
train ourselves we train our attention we train our attention here right now
right here the mystery the miracle of this moment instead of the past the future we have
choice yes of course we can decide oh this is a terrible moment i wish i was in
somewhere else i had a different body different relationship different whatever but and yet the wisdom is and
recognizing the beauty the miracle the grace
so many gifts in this moment not to be taken for granted
so i think i have said enough so that is the
frame that's the frame for the invitations tonight as i lead us in the
practice of of meta and exploration so
so i'd like to invite you to
ah land in your body arrive in your
practice body you could be sitting upright you
could be lying down it's perfectly okay see what this body needs in this moment
and landing in this body ah
hello and even if the body there is discomfort and pain
ah hello body hello this miracle of being i'll share with you that
my body is having pain right now not feeling well and yet wow what a miracle i choose to turn
my attention to open up to what is
amazing the breath the sensations being aware of what is
instead of what isn't i'll invite you to do the same with me
releasing releasing any tightness or tension into the earth
and also releasing letting go of
of thoughts of memories or plans of the busyness of the mind
not that there's anything wrong with thinking but in this moment
offering it up thank you not now please come back later
i'm giving my heart my full heart attention awareness to
this practice in this moment ah
feeling [Music] the sit bones contacting the cushion or the chair
ah the contact points releasing release i guess if you're letting a
ball internally drop drop internally
ah released unto the earth
in lieu of the chair the cushion dropped dropped internally unto the
earth
allowing awareness awareness to to receive the breath in the lower
abdomen the in-breath and the out-breath soothing comforting slow slow it down it
helps to slow down the mind to arrive more fully
slowly and slowly out for a few breaths not for the entire practice but just to
encourage us to settle
slowly in the in-breath
the abdomen slowly and more slowly out
the out breath
this breath is enough can it be enough notice
this is enough this breath right here
not just enough but amazing
sweet
surprising full of miracles every breath different
like a snowflake
can we meet each snowflake of the breath
with with all with appreciation
of contentment
here's an experiment to try on for size
after this period you can go back to
choosing to be any way you want but for now what if what if
for a moment here in this practice in this meditation session
we practice we practice
releasing letting go of the thoughts of the past what has come into now until now
preoccupations and thoughts of the future i need this
do this do that i'm worried about this what is good what's going to happen to that just
right now let's let's release ah
release like letting go of these helium balloons
let them float
and what if in this moment just for trying it on as an experiment see what
happens again we can bring back all the thoughts later
and right now experiment with a radical radical perception perspective
which all of us can the
perception the perspective that this moment
is a contented it's a contentful moment
that you can feel contented contentment in this moment
if your mind goes but but but say thank you i'm just trying it out for size
release release the butts let yourself taste
let your body relax and soften as much contentment as there is in this
moment just with a simple breath moving in and out
to lullaby
the privilege of just sitting and being briefed how awesome is that
the mind may want to turn to what's not right what's unpleasant what's hot what's cold
can you tune into as if you're tuning a radio and there are lots of channels so
much here so much information it's a deluge really every moment so
much stimuli the body outside inside
tune the radio of your mind
to what's wholesome what's nourishing what's good
the body and the mind and just to give it some support
let's bring in some meta
some kindness some loving kindness so care some warmth
for this being who is you struggles who tries their best
ah releasing into kindness as if you're held with kindness
it's okay no need to struggle
as if you're an old person practice as if you're a very old person
ah let it go
not so much to do to accomplish but just to be here
is enough
and if judgments are arising you're not doing this right this is not enough let it go
this is enough whatever is happening whatever is here
whatever is here
tuning the radio of the mind to the goodness perhaps of some actions in the past
maybe kindness or acts of generosity ah
let yourself sit in the ripples nothing else to be done right now this
is enough to sitting in ripples of goodness
trusting tuning the radio of the mind to goodness
you can do this
train yourself less
knowing that you are doing your best this is enough whatever is arising is enough
don't struggle don't try so hard releasing letting go is a part of this
practice
release let go it's enough
so
this is enough release lego
you're doing your best this is enough
you
release relax let go the body
now it is if there is any more priests present peace
ease contentment the buddha said peace is the highest
bliss it's a different flavor of happiness
the highest flavor of happiness
see how much of it might be present right now
this is enough let it go
notice if there is desire to continue with this state
with this enoughness whatever it is for it not to end for me not to ring the
bell notice acknowledge if it's present
honor it
this here is enough when we let go [Music]
pining after one thing and thinking
of what is not going well etc etc
may all beings everywhere including us
find the freedom no peace
deep peace of contentment
what is here what is enough
thank you all thank you for your practice
i wanted to share a couple of reflections before i invite you to share yours
and that and one is that the the sense of
contentment the sense of um [Music] oh enoughness this is enough this
contentment sense of peace that can arise which might never risen
for you even just a little bit to taste it this meditation i was tasting it i don't want to bring the bells like oh
this is enough this is yes the body's in pain but this is great this is this is
plenty so and and that is not so much
you know when i was inviting you to tune into the radio of your mind to what is
enough it also means really it's more about i think it's more about letting go
letting go of what is not helpless just letting go is releasing this releasing
again coming back to this book happiness is the choice you make is the releasing of the pining after the
wanting the this to that so that it's oh this right here and again
not to say that this is the state that you may want to have every moment of
your life i'm not suggesting that you give ever give up every intention or
desire that's not the idea here but it's a training it's a training that we take
on on the question and it comes to us in daily life when there is a sense of our mind is turning
to this that finding fault with everything it's like oh wait i know a different way to be so yes we can
continue to plan to be in the world to serve to to make plans all of that it's
nothing wrong with thinking and planning in the world but it can show us a different way of being
so i've said enough and i would love to hear your reflections what came up for
you what did you notice what worked what didn't again
sharing for the benefit of the sangha
your insights your aha moments and also for the benefit of yourself to be held witness
and if you've shared recently to pull back if not please pull forward and you can also
type in chat if you type to everyone i'll read your name if it's just to me privately i will only read
your reflection not your name so take it away what happened
what did you notice was there any peace
was this moment enough for anyone did you notice the bliss of
peace
or not
oh this one or maybe you're just too quiet to talk i see thumbs up somebody's giving a thumbs up yay beautiful whoever
is giving the thumbs up would you like to raise your hand and and say something oh it went away the thumbs up so that's
great that's alright here we go aurora please
there hi hi
i i really appreciated um the opening frame
and i felt like there was this like
my my meditation was like releasing grasping releasing
grasping um and then when you said the bit about
you said something like imagine that you're very very old
i got like a long moment of like oh right like
i don't have any other time but this time and it just like it like washed over me in this really helpful way
and so i then i kept coming back to that like remember you're you're you you could die tomorrow
and and it was really helpful
beautiful thank you so much er for for saying for sharing your insight and
the practice yes this this this reflection of
i could die tomorrow i could die tomorrow practicing as if you're really really old what a great
way to practice in the past i've given the instruction to people to practice as if you're sick as if you're ill because
when you're sick you don't try so hard it's more easeful and now i think i'm going to give the new instruction to
people practice as if you're you're 90 years old like yeah oh wow
something happens in our bodies right this in our minds beautiful thank you so much for sharing that
a couple of reflections in chat bill says pleased to see that slowing the breath did slow my mind yay
bill wonderful at the same time there was a slight physical strain in the breathing and
breathing so slowly yeah yeah so so it's there's lots of research about breathing
and the effect of slow breath especially slow out breath how it calms the mind and the physiology
there's plenty of physiological research and actually the book breath it's a lovely book i'm giving you lots
of book recommendations tonight it's a great book so and and it's good to do that for a while but then if
it becomes strange then let it go and my recommendation was just to bring that in at the beginning to kind of slow down
and then to let it go let it be normal and then deborah says i'm still
in the gooey peaceful state and didn't want to use words now to shift out of it
yes yes thanks for sharing that debra i appreciate it that's how i felt myself
after the meditations like i don't really want to talk i don't want to ring the bell but it times up
yeah yeah and one more reflections when private my
practice is not regular yet and when i allow myself to relax to the deepest
i still feel this background rumbling of jangling nerves
like a quarter rattling on top of a washing machine on the spin style yeah
yeah thank you for sharing that and it's okay it's been cycle right spin cycle right
oh came the correction um that is okay it's it's it's often like
you know we're like running you know we're like a car that's driving at 100
miles per hour through our lives again going to get this done and that done and this side is like and then we sit to
meditate and the car is still like kind of moving shifting and and and i love your description of
yeah jangling nerds the quarter rattling on top of washing machine it's okay it's
really okay make space for that that's what needs to happen that's what needs to be
present given everything that has come before and if you hate it if you say okay i've sat
down i want everything to be quiet stop you quarters but by pushing it away and
hating it actually you give it more energy so my recommendation is make space for
the jangling nerves for the rattling quarters like oh yeah it's like this
and notice that how actually there could be peace there could be contentment
even if there's rattling and jingling the same way that there could be contentment peace and ease with physical
pain with things not being right the two can coexist and the moment you
see that there's a person who wrote whose practice is not regular yet the moment you see that yeah jingling and jangling
can be together coexistent with ah peace and contentment
the peace can be spacious enough to hold it then wow then your practice would open to the next level so
so dear ones with that i would like to invite us to to
share to engage to reflect uh whoever shows up in the room tonight is
the right person is this person that you're supposed to be talking listening
to to these special individuals they're supposed to teach you something
tonight and you're supposed to teach them something again not fatigued like preach but but you're it's you're meant
to leave each other with a gift let yourself be surprised and the gift may not reveal itself so don't start
like stressing out like okay i gotta say something smart no no no just just be yourself and your gift might just be
silently holding present just silently holding presents maybe
that's the gift that you give to the other person tonight the gift of compassion the gift of care
so so see what happens see what happens i am
going to uh create the rooms now and
um here we go let me see yes i'm going to
so open them so take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
okay the rooms are closed everyone is back welcome back
we have just about a minute if any insights have arisen especially from
sharing and discussing in group and sangha and especially if you're new
you're welcome if you wish not to put anyone on the spot but you can raise your hand if you want or type in chat or
not it's all good whatever makes you feel complete
how was it to be in group tonight oh i see the heart showing up ah sweet
neil please
you get the last word neil go for it um so i mean this was just a lovely
practice right and it just carried over into group you know i mean it was just
you know it just felt you know especially warm and supportive it was it was very nice
thank you thank you so much for sharing that oh it's
beautiful how that mindset that the heart set carries over
to the interaction right and it gives us hope all of us hope that this is this
can carry to our other interactions in the world from the sandbox of the sangha
to other sand boxes so thank you neil for sharing that reflection yeah
beautiful thank you and jerry says contentment yes yes yeah
may you all be content thank you all thank you so much for your practice
thank you for ah cultivating for your own benefit and the benefit of
others may we all be free may we all know deep and true contentment
thank you all
and now i stopped