okay so let's go ahead with the the meditation together
i see folks arriving and more will come and join us
so just settling in arriving
and allowing yourself to have a sense of
slowing down becoming present for your experience
you can let the eyes close
i just feel the body in the sitting posture
feeling the straightness of the spine
feeling the connection to where you're sitting
contact points of the seat and the legs or the feet
we might imagine that the body rises off the cushion or the chair
the way a sea plant rises off the sea floor it's anchored at the bottom
and just floats in the water lead upward
the arms float the head floats on the spine
it can help to imagine a little space between the top vertebra and the base of the skull
to soften the neck
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
releasing the chest the belly
so inviting some ease or expansion in the torso
so the invitation today is to take body sensations as the focus of
mindfulness
this includes sounds and the breath
often one of the more prominent body sensations
and also all the various pulsings and
tinglings heat and vibrations that
course around in the body
some of these are related to being in the sitting posture or whatever
posture you're in some relate to
digestion or breathing [Music]
and some are just there because because the body is alive
so we have these different sensations
and we put those into the foreground
while letting thoughts or emotions be more
more in the background for now
those things are fine but they're not the main focus for now
so just resting with the various body sensations
opening to that or being willing to listen to the body
whether the sensations are pleasant or unpleasant
as well as all the many many neutral sensations
the body has a way of opening up when we turn our
gentle mindful attention toward it
perhaps the way a flower opens when the sun begins to shine on it
perks up a bit it shows more of itself
when there's a genuine non-judgmental interest
there are a lot of options with the body so if a given part is feeling
painful it may draw the attention but there's no need
for us to continue with that if it feels like it's getting stronger we can just move the
attention elsewhere
or we can open to sounds or even open the eyes
you can find what works
is simply to be to be simple
okay
me
as we stay with this realm of the body and breath and
sounds
it's easy to see that many of these sensations are changing
some are very quick just to rise and pass
others feel like they're there ongoing but if we look carefully they're they're
probably shifting fluttering a bit
there are different ways to be with changing
experience like this we might
kind of feel each one as an event
noting it
or we can also have a sense of mindfulness as a field or
an expanse like a lake or like the sky in various
experiences come in and out of that happen within that
in either of those ways is fine
but just being aware of this changing
flux of experience
[Music]
and from time to time we might again just scan through the body
and invite ease in case any parts have tightened up
sometimes the eyes get tight if we are literally trying to look
at experience
or sometimes the changing nature of experience brings up some tension
so it can help to imagine softening
just letting the experience be changing as it
so we have a sense of resting in the normal flow
of sounds and sensations and breath
resting
when we are noticing impermanence or inconstancy
it becomes clearer to see when the mind hangs up or gets
fixed on something which is very normal
and when we notice that the mind has grasped onto the
bank of the river we can just gently get back into the
flow
[Music] again seeing if we can rest [Music]
and soften with this changing experience
noticing the changing nature of experience
gradually helps the heart learn to let go
there's no point in grasping this flow
there's hardly anything to grasp as it changes so much
it even seems to run by itself
so as we move toward the ending of this sit
we might consider how might it be to
flow a bit more today
we may find that it's easier to be present for other people
when we are not stopping the flow of an interaction
in our mind by grasping on to our own thoughts or views
thinking about what we're going to say next but instead just staying present
for this other person
our own willingness to be with how things are changing
makes us more available for other people and more resilient
more flexible more responsive
so cultivating this understanding of change is our friend
and it's a an important rather deep aspect of practice
and it evolves over a long time
so
[Music]
so first i just have one little announcement which is that on friday
we will have after this session a community meeting on zoom
and the link for that will appear on the imc website in the what's new
section and it'll be on the calendar also and i'll i'll be there for
any questions you might have and and we'll have time for some breakout groups also
so that's friday if you're interested
one time gill was on a long retreat during his time in asia
and he had an insight about mindfulness
sometimes these things don't sound maybe as profound when spoken out of context
but his insight was that we can be mindful of anything
there's nothing that can't be known in awareness and this is really good news
it's really good news so we talked yesterday about practicing to extend our mindfulness
into broader realms of our life and the focus was about how
mindfulness counteracts what are called the five chords of sensual pleasure
which also includes a version so today we're going to go deeper into this
territory that mindfulness can penetrate so even beyond
the kind of more everyday situations where we have tempting sense pleasures
or more challenging emotions there is the great challenge that all
humans face of aging and illness and death
and this too is a realm for mindfulness so the buddha gave some brilliant
teachings on mindfulness in relation in particular to death or or terminal
illness and i hope you're not reaching for the off button at this moment please stay if
you can i'll be sharing some some stories around this
including something that the buddha said as his own death was approaching
so many many suites talk about mindfulness at the time of death as well
as mindfulness being a refuge in general in times of challenge
so both of those are today's theme mindfulness at the time of death and mindfulness as a genuine refuge for us
when the buddha was giving meditation instructions to his son rahula
one thing that he taught him was mindfulness of breathing and in the discourse where he does that
he says to rahula when mindfulness of breathing is developed and cultivated
even the final in-breaths and out-breaths are known as they cease
not unknown so it's quite powerful he's saying that in other words you know we can die
mindfully just through the basic practice of mindfulness of breathing
which i know many of us have have done at least to some degree so continuing with that
goes all the way to being mindful up to the last moments the last breaths
so mindfulness is a reliable practice for us in ways that
some other practices may not be the monk um osagie became agitated
around the time of death because he was a practitioner mostly of concentration
and he found that he could not concentrate his mind when he was enduring
a terminal illness and so he expressed this concern to the buddha he said i think i'm slipping back because
i can't get concentrated and the buddha pointed him toward letting go of attachment even to meditative states
and he said just be mindful he didn't quite say it that way but
he um he pointed out the reliability of simply knowing we can be aware of how we are
mindfulness is always possible um being aware is very simple
as ajahn sumeto says and this is very practical advice for any time
right now it's like this i've practiced that myself sometimes
just um realize right now it's like this and it brings the mind right back right
to a simple place and we could do that all the way up all the way up to the moment of death
so then another story
one time the buddha visited the sikh ward according to the discourse
place where the monastics who were sick were staying and he said to the monks there
a person should await their time mindful and clearly comprehending
this is our instruction to you and how is a person mindful
and then he goes on to name the four establishments of mindfulness
exactly using the same language that they're stated in the santi patana
here a person is mindful of the body in the body ardent clearly comprehending and mindful
and so forth so it's interesting that he
he points out that this is what should come to mind as we are even when we're
sick even when we're in the hospital essentially so then which aspects of satipatana
might be particularly relevant for someone who's in a state like that
and in one teaching the buddha points particularly toward the contemplation of
feeling tongue so you might remember gil has been going through all the
satipatanas and when he spoke earlier in the series feeling tone is the second foundation of
mindfulness and it's about whether experience is pleasant or unpleasant
or neither pleasant nor unpleasant so it's a very kind of basic response that we have to
experience and so that means it can be done without much mental effort
to just know whether something is pleasant or unpleasant or neither is
something the mind can know every moment and it's a powerful practice because it
directly prevents the mind from or at least reduces the chances that the mind
will move into craving or aversion so if we just know something with the label this is pleasant we're much less
likely to mindlessly go on into thinking how can i get more of this i really need
this etc or if it's unpleasant we can just stop
there and not get into a long thought trail about how horrible it is and how we wish it would end
which the mind would otherwise naturally do so this is definitely relevant for for
dying we don't want to keep our mind in a prolonged state of aversion
and then the uh the suit does also very much encourage the wisdom reflection that all feeling tones are impermanent
that was what we looked at in the meditation that was more just impermanence of
sensations so that means it's not fruitful to grasp onto them or push them away
so reflection on impermanence is a major theme in the as you might guess in the teachings
about death so again even just the simple practice of sitting and
noticing changing sounds changing body sensations
in our current state is something that will fortify the mind
and prepare it for something that's coming later
so all of our current practice is actually building up strength in the mind
i volunteered in a hospice for a while and i noticed that there was a big
difference between the people who became overwhelmed by regret or pain worthy
general indignity of dying compared with those who could stay present and could
somehow keep their mind in a more wholesome place
i guess to be clear i'll say that there is not just one perfect way to die the proverbial
good death however you die is going to be fine but it is good to at least aim the mind
toward mindfulness and it can help in particular to keep feeling tongue in mind
so having this method of avoiding falling into craving an aversion
really serves as a refuge for the mind and the heart so there's again this sense like we
talked about yesterday that when the mind is mindful we're safe we're we're
protected in a sense so i wanted to look now at some
passages from the sutta that deals with the death of the buddha
so that's the mahaparinibana suta and it
chronicles the last few months of the buddha's life it's a very long suta that kind of
goes through everything he was doing in his travels and his teachings all the way up to
to the time of his death and it includes these um famous lines that some of you have
probably heard so he says monks you should live as islands unto
yourselves being your own refuge with no other refuge you should live with the dhamma as an
island with the dhamma as your refuge with no other refuge
and many people have only heard that much and that alone is good advice for
dying which we will be doing alone even if there are people with us of course no
one is coming along with us in that transition but i want to highlight today because of
this series what comes after those famous lines so
the buddha continues and how does a person live as an island unto themselves being their own refuge
and with the dhamma as an island as a refuge here a person abides contemplating the body
as a body ardent fully aware and mindful having set aside covetousness and grief
for the world a person abides contemplating feeling as feeling
and so on you may recognize the lines again straight from the satipatana suta
saying language so the buddha says that cultivating the four establishments of mindfulness is
how we can be a refuge for ourselves and how we can also take the dharma as our
refuge and he thought that was important enough that he conveyed it clearly and strongly
quite close to the time of his own death he was taught he was thinking about what to pass on
uh to people so one more story this one modern
and this is um about uh this is something i heard from a friend of mine who trained as a monk in asia
and he tells the story of an abbot about an asian monastery who was dying so this
is recently during the 20th century and the abbott summoned his senior monk
saying that he wants to give him a final gift and the monk was wondering what's that
going to be and so he came to the abbott and the abbott took the monk's hand and
he folded down four of his fingers and he just held his hand like that
among sand and he said the four foundations of mindfulness are my gift
to you as i pass on
so these are um some lines from vikku anaglio's book on on mindfully facing disease and death
suppose one has suddenly become seriously ill and is in pain
physically unable to sit in formal meditation or just be quietly by oneself perhaps
even being close to passing away what to do the one thing to rely on in such a
situation is mindfulness from early buddhist meditation to modern
day clinical pain relief mindfulness is what empowers one to face
disease and death after all we might say what's the alternative
so mindfulness is valuable even as we approach death the great challenge for humans
and so it might be that at this point you're starting to get a sense of the real strength and power of mindfulness it's
very powerful so we started just a couple days ago by talking about
an almost passive guarding of the scent stores but mindfulness has a different
dimension also where it can step forward and meet very difficult situations
so that's the direction that we're going to go next tomorrow i'll talk about the
strength of mindfulness and some of the wonderful images that go with that it can be can be quite inspiring
so thank you