so good morning again
um
how wonderful too
start the day
in Stillness with this
community
this Sangha
as it's my first time here with you I'd
like to introduce myself briefly
yeah
um
Gail very kindly introduced
introduced to me at the end of the week
let you know I would be here
uh Koto kotlin is my name and
um
I'm a teacher trainee in the IMC teacher
training I'm a teacher training
along with a cohort of just lovely
people
and in addition
live and
work can serve as a priest at San
Francisco's and Center
so the Dharma is all around
so the theme for this week
uh comes from a
well it is inspired by a custom
of this group going back I understand to
the time of
Palo Alto sitting group
that gill would teach
the introduction to meditation class
once heard twice a year
and
immediately before that he would teach
the precepts
the ethical Foundation
of of our practice
so the theme from so the the plan for
these next two weeks will be this week
to discuss the five precepts
and then next week
May Elliott will teach the introduction
to mindfulness meditation
of course and about
12 minutes we won't be able to cover all
of the subtleties of
precept so uh
um I hope we can we can say enough
to encourage a reflection
uh to touch something in you
to consider
how it is that the ethical practice of
the precepts encourages
your sitting practice and your growth in
the Dharma
so
first uh to locate the five precepts
within the tradition
closest analog we can really find
to the to the five precepts which are
the the
precepts of training for Lay followers
for Lay practitioners closest analog we
can find in the early teachings is the
10 skillful actions
discussed a lot in the on gutura nikaya
and then also there are some there are
some
sprinklings
I say sprinklings but it's really
everywhere this distinction between
wholesome and unwholesome action
skillful and unskillful action
and I'd like to talk about the precepts
over these next five days
in terms of a slogan
and that is keeping us safely on the
path
keeping us safely on the path
um
as well as we might sometimes hear if we
go to a retreat at IRC
at Insight Retreat Center within the
context of the Dharma there's no Us in
them
there's just us
so keeping us safely on the path means
there's no one and nothing
outside of our Circle of Care
no one and nothing outside of our Circle
of Care
and keeping us safely on the path
when the Buddha was teaching about
precepts it was often teaching to
monastics
but still I take some inspiration about
how it was done
one important teaching that inspires my
own reflection is that there's a list of
reasons in the vinya that the Buddha
um
lays down a training rule
why the Buddha puts forth a precept for
practice
and three of them I'd like to select and
talk about are the fact that uh he lays
down to training world one for the
comfort and ease
I love this of well behaved monastics
the comfort and ease of well-behaved
monastics
the second is that
um behaving in line with this training
rule
inspires faith
it inspires faith in those who don't
have faith in the Dharma the Buddha the
Sangha and it inspires faith and um
and those who already have faith in the
Buddha Dharma and Sangha
and then the third reason that I want to
highlight is that they support
the ending
of greed hatred and delusion
they support liberation
letting go
and in our colloquial terms they support
happiness
so ease and comfort faith
and Liberation as reasons that the
Buddha may put forth a precept for a
training put forth a standard of conduct
by which we walk the path and keep
ourselves safely
on the path
so in this in this insect tradition
one of the places we most commonly
encounter the precepts is at the
beginning of a retreat
there could actually be some long while
that someone's been meditating before
they ever hear anything about the
precepts
but if they make their way to a retreat
of course
um
on the opening night
as we settle in have the first formal
session
in this in this Opening space
where the Stillness is beginning to fall
the tone has begun to shift the concerns
of our everyday are starting to
starting to subside some little bit
and we undergo a short ceremony where we
take refuge in the Buddha and then we
commit ourselves to these five precepts
um
and more or less they're said in this
way
for the sake of our training together
I undertake
the precept
to refrain from harming
living beings
second for the sake
of our training together
I undertake the precept
not to take what is not given
third for the sake of our training
together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
sexual misconduct
and in the context of a retreat that
means celibacy
fourth for the sake of our training
together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
false speech
and fifth for the sake of our training
together
I undertake the precept
to abstain from intoxicants that are a
cause for heedlessness
five seemingly simple in some ways maybe
maybe obvious
but powerful ways to keep ourselves
safely on the path
and keep others safely on the path
you know something I've noticed when
whenever I make these commitments or
renew these commitments
I actually feel a palpable settling in
the body
it's like um
oh what is it it's touching in or it's
it's being reoriented to
the these parameters of the path
reminders saying oh yes this is how
safety is Manifest in my conduct
this is such a simple way that I can
benefit myself in a simple way that I
can benefit other beings
a simple way I can keep us safely on the
path
and there's a principle behind the
precepts
and one of the most one of the most uh
common and basic that I mentioned
already
is this action wholesome is it
unwholesome
is it skillful is it unskillful
I appreciate the word wholesomeness
because it it points to
it points for me first internally
how we're nourished we're nourished by
our conduct
when it's in line with the precepts when
it's ethical
and how we may be denourished or
depleted when our conduct is not in line
with the precepts
so wholesome to me points inward
and then the word skillfulness
points to the interpersonal aspect of
the precepts
is my conduct skillful in such a way
that it's supporting me and it's
supporting someone else
is it skillful skillful for our
Liberation for our comfort
and for the faith of others
one of my very favorite teachings
associated with all this is from the
maju malikaya 61. I have a I have a
special fondness for them
those sets of teachings when the Buddha
is teaching his son
of a venerable after he ordained as a
monastic
foreign
and in this uh in this scenario
venerable rahula has already committed
to the parimoka he's already committed
to the monastic precepts which are many
more than these five
and so he has that as a background of
restraint for this conversation
and Buddha gives this beautiful teaching
he holds up a mirror and he says
what is a mirror for
reflection Dante reflection sir
just so says the Buddha to his son
we should act with our body with our
speech and with our mind
with our body our speech in our mind
only with repeated reflection
and he goes on to explain that he means
before we do an action
think reflect is this action
going to cause harm going to cause
Affliction and I might say all the
discomforts of agitation
that come along with harm
is it going to cause this if so don't do
it
but if you reflect and you discern this
action that I'm about to do
it won't cause Affliction but it will
cause well-being
support calm goodness
non-affliction non-harming
then go ahead
while you're doing the action reflect
again is this action causing harm
affliction
disease discomfort
if not
continue and then after the action
reflect again did this action cause harm
was it unskillful was it unwholesome
or did this action cause
skillful results Pleasant results
supports for the path
it's a comprehensive
high standard for the examination of
conduct
I think one that inspires me
and I think when we look at the content
of these five precepts
we can see or we can reflect for
ourselves
in what ways do they cause agitation
Affliction and harm for others and what
ways do they cause harm agitation or in
what ways do they not cause
harm agitation Affliction what ways do
they cause well-being
in what ways do they keep us safely on
the path
foreign
so I would like to propose
that uh when we finish each of these
sessions for the next five days anyone
who would like to can take up this
practice with me of reciting the five
presets
um
and
perhaps thinking of them
thinking of them as
um
guideposts or
um and encouragements of the Buddha in
wholesome conduct
noticing they're not copying very well
I'll do this after we close and anyone
who like would like to stay on we can do
that
keeping us safely on the path
[Music]
I hope that it can be that
many of us who gather here for these
for these morning meetings can in
whatever small way
help keep each other safely on the path
with our conduct with our sitting with
our encouragement
wishing you a fruitful week of practice
until tomorrow
please take care