uh my name is Jim Podolski and I'm going to give a talk tonight
about what I call everyday mindfulness
so the word mindfulness gets used more and more these days certainly more
than um back when I first started this practice and
she's in a lot of different ways so when I use the word kind of a very
simple and probably incomplete definition would be it's
knowing what's happening as it's happening so it's a present moment awareness
practice I'm curious how many you of you have
taken some kind of mindfulness meditation class whether it's an hour
long or uh day long or a couple weeks okay looks
like most everyone has um of course I don't know about people who
are online so I thought I'd give a very very brief description of mindfulness meditation as
we teach it here at IMC there's basically four postures that you
can take for meditating sitting standing walking or lying down
we teach primarily sitting meditation since it's the
works the best for a group and it really just consists of
sitting down taking an alert an upright posture
bringing some relaxation to the body gently closing the eyes if you'd like
and then bringing the awareness to the breath just noticing the sensation of
the breath wherever in the body it's most um it's most accessible for you where it's
most noticeable and and so that's
really um the beginning of it is just
bringing the awareness to the breath and noticing it noticing when the awareness wanders off
and just gently bringing it back over time other uh
experiences may arise you may have bodily Sensations that arise and those
for the most part you might just leave in the background and stay with the breath if they become
compelling much more compelling than the breath than you can bring your your
awareness to those bodily Sensations and when they're no longer compelling
come back to the breath um the other experiences that might
arise are emotions noticing when emotions arise and again
if they're the most um a dominant experience then you'd bring
your awareness for a while to the emotion wow watch it as it arises and passes
and then likewise thoughts all of the activities of them all the mental activities
the planning for the future the remembering the past
stories fantasies beliefs opinions
um letting your awareness go to them in a in a very conscious way in a very
intentional way and then when they're no longer dominant
coming back to the breath so in this
21st century Western
Insight way we let the awareness
rest on one of those four categories the breath the body
the emotions or the thoughts
and the other characteristic is that we often decide ahead of time how long
we're going to meditate we usually set some kind of a timer for maybe 15 or 20
or 30 minutes 45 minutes maybe even an hour
and then just set the intention to to just sit still and be with whatever
arises until the timer goes off
and that's I think are very wonderful practice it's very helpful to to do it
every day you know set aside you know find some time to to sit and meditate
on retreats uh it's much more intense than that rather
than just doing one sitting a day you do an alternate between sitting meditation
and walking and sitting and walking and then there's some meals in there
but again mostly they're kind of fixed length and of course the Retreats fix length at the end of The Retreat you go
back to your your everyday life the effects of of either a daily sit or
a a longer retreat usually can last for some time and eventually
um are no longer as noticeable
enduring retreats there's often an instruction after the first maybe three or four or five days
to bring some more continuity to your practice so rather than just sit
and then stop meditating get up go back to your normal
state of of awareness and then doing walking
meditation and taking breaks between every each one of those activities the instruction is
often to um see if you can bring some continuity of
practice between the sits and the walks and the sits at least maybe for a couple
hours and see what that what that's like
um I've had the opportunity to do that a
number of times and I often wish that I could do it differently but
um my life was such a I was working I had was working to
earn a living and pay my mortgage and everything else so I couldn't go on a
retreat uh continuously so I started to think how how can I
develop this mindfulness um in everyday life
off the cushion off retreat
on the Retreats they they sometimes say well when you go back
into your daily life you might find a few uh cues a few things that might
um help you remember to pay attention so for example turning on and off light
switches might be a cue to you to like really notice what's what that's like or
going through doors um things ordinary things that we do
every day that we could use as cues to to just um
you know uh amp up the the awareness
at least for momentarily
in the last few years certainly since the pandemic I've
I live alone and I've been doing a lot of my work remotely so I actually do
have a lot of I'm so I'm seldom really rushed or
constrained in time so I've started developing more and more ways of
cultivating mindfulness throughout my day so I thought I would walk you through
um a day in the life of Jim and point out some of the potential
places where I can practice mindfulness I I'm not going to say that I do it all of the time and you know like I never
miss a beat uh there there's plenty of uh gaps
but um there's also many many parts of my life where
that don't require a lot of interpersonal interaction or a lot of
cognitive activity to try to figure out what I'm going to do
so my day starts with my waking up and often waking up isn't just one I
don't just wake up and then that's it I sometimes fall back to sleep and uh
but eventually there's one time that I wake up and it's okay this is It's Time
and I tend to dream a lot and so the very first thing I do is notice
was I just dreaming you know what was going on in my mind just before I
moved from unconscious to conscious and oftentimes
um I can remember something you know like I I
can be aware that there were thoughts and images going on even though I wasn't
um wide awake for them
some psychotherapists think that there's a lot of meaning in dreams and they encourage people to journal their dreams
and I used to do that in the 80s now for me I use it more as a
kind of a mindfulness tool that that when I wake up my first
intention is to pay attention to what what was just in my mind
and I find that by doing that it there is a little bit more energy that
immediately comes up a little bit more awareness
a little bit more Focus you know if I don't then my mind is often or my
awareness is kind of floating around um not quite sure where to land
so if I let it land on on dreams that
immediately um
bring some some Focus to awareness
the next thing that I do after or is not every morning but most mornings
I do a short period of loving kindness so even before I get out of bed
I just let whatever being or beings or people
that come to mind I say some phrases of well-wishing for
them you know may they be safe may they be happy may they be healthy
may they be tranquil and I repeat those phrases you know a
number of times for for one person and then maybe someone else will come to mind and I'll I'll do that
and I don't set a timer for that usually I do at least five minutes of loving
kindness but sometimes it could be 30 minutes
and the value of that practice for me number one is um
it helps set an intention for the day
that I've noticed over the years that this this mind is is fairly prone to aversion
you know kind of finding what's wrong with this picture so by doing loving kindness when I first
wake up there's um it kind of shifts things so that that
the old uh patterns of thinking
um yeah I get challenged a little bit you know and notice oh yeah well
it there's a certain happiness from wishing well for others
um so that not only helps wake up the mind and the
awareness but it helps wake up the heart and it brings some energy
to the body and it it sets an intention
and these are easy this is pretty easy practice um I'm not sitting in some
uh on some cushion on a hard floor I'm
still in the warm nice warm bed until I decide to get up and then when I
get up these days the house is kind of cold I leave the temperature at about 56 so
so there's all sorts of sensation of the body you know going from lying to sitting to standing
feeling the coolness of the air
um and then
from there I I go and now that
I'm woke up I wake up my computer I turn it on and you know it it takes a
while to connect to the internet and do VPN and
single sign-on and certificates and all sorts of things to get my work computer
ready to talk to the world and then I go in the kitchen to have
breakfast and
um that's quite an enjoyable experience
so um let's see I forgot one part I was going
to say the um when I talked about mindfulness meditation
the uh categories that we that I use for experience are you know the the breath
the body um emotions and
thoughts what the Buddha taught is the foundation the four foundations for mindfulness are
also the body um but also feeling tone
is the experience you're having is it Pleasant is it unpleasant or is it neither Pleasant or unpleasant
and then the third one was mine States
kind of the mood of the Mind is the Mind contracted or expanded
you know is it irritable or is it happy
you know is it um is it kind of fuzzy or is it clear
and you can probably think of your own labels for the states of your mind that
you find but it's it's helpful to to be able to recognize what what what's the mood in
the mind right now and then the fourth one is
um is mental activities thoughts
mental formations um much like the the first list that I
that I gave so those are the four that the Buddha gave us and
so going back into the kitchen and and back uh preparing my my breakfast I
always have oatmeal with blueberries and raspberries pomegranate arrows uh
walnuts a banana and a dollop of Greek yogurt on the top
so it doesn't you know it's kind of the same every day so it's it doesn't take a lot of thought and planning
so I can just just let that time be a time when I can
notice you know kind of notice what's it really like to hold a bowl of hot
oatmeal what's it like to um you know slice the banana
and then sitting and eating eating meditation is one of the formal
practices on Retreat you know they really encourage you to to s that when
you eat just eat just just notice all of the sensations
you know the The Taste the texture uh the smell
you know the the visual of it even the sounds like the the spoon hitting the
Corel Bowl it's quite a sense experience
um and if you just decide that
um you want to do this you can just you know kind of let
everything else um be in the background you know all of the thoughts that my computer may have
generated from looking at email you know all my plans for the day are still there but they don't they
don't have to be um what I'm attending to what I can attend to is just this this process of
eating um
I go back to the computer uh
look at email some more and also notice how am I sitting you know like what's what's my
posture like as I'm sitting at the computer I I find often that my my shoulders tend to move forward and I
hunch over so uh I might make a decision to sit a
little bit more upright and then the next
uh activity of the day is um going to the bathroom and getting clean
you know so I use a water pick floss brush gargle
shave with a safety razor you know a lot of a lot of sense
experience going on there and to the extent that I can just let
the rest of my my thoughts and my um
plans um relax a bit then I can just notice what
what's it what's it like is it is it Pleasant when I'm shaving is it pleasant when I'm
brushing my teeth
you know just like you know kind of letting whatever that simple activity is
be the focus of of awareness
really makes a difference and then of course
taking a shower is kind of a almost a body scan
type mindfulness practice you know starting from the head and shampooing my
hair you know all the way down to my feet the warm water
that I use sparingly the cold air when the warm water stops
um and drying off you know taking the towel it's it's another whole body scan from
uh the top of my head to the bottom of my feet
you know it doesn't it's very easy to do all of these things automatically and with
um and kind of tuned out you know like doing them and not really knowing that
you're doing them so I uh many mornings use the sh you know
kind of do shower meditation then get dressed
you know and you know feeling the
feeling the cloth as it as it covers my my upper body and lower body and putting
on my socks and then going off for the day you know
going to work there's several categories
I mean one one of the areas that I think is very important for mindfulness and
it's so important that I'm not going to try to cover it tonight which is
mindfulness of speech uh or more generally mindfulness of
speech and mindfulness of listening and more generally than that is
mindfulness of communication like like really paying attention when
you're talking to somebody when you're listening to somebody when you're reading an email or writing
one or a text or a letter um those those in some ways are sort of
advanced mindfulness practice in in my view
there's been a lot of talks given about that kind of thing just yesterday afternoon the there's an Eightfold Path
class that was all on right speech um there's a teacher named Greg Gregory
Kramer who often holds workshops on Insight dialogue
which is um a way to to really help bring more
awareness to the way that we communicate with each other
so I won't say more than that about my mindfulness of communication but
that's a that's a a very important
daily practice but the simple practices the ones that
don't that um don't take quite so much um practice
um the other ones for me are
my office is at one end of the building and the both the men's room and the
break room are at the other end of the building so when I get up to either
go use the restroom or go to the break room to refill my water bottle
that's an opportunity to do sort of a mini walking meditation to just allow myself to say well for
this next couple of minutes that I'm walking down and back I don't have to figure anything out I
don't I don't need I'm not I don't have to compose an email or understand some
obscure concept or figure out how I'm going to
solve a some problem that I can just for that few minutes I
can just take a break and notice what's it like to be walking
the feeling in my feet in my lower legs maybe the breeze on my hands as I walk
you know just getting in touch you know getting in touch and staying in touch with the body
uh the other the other place that I practice mindfulness at least at least
some of the time is driving I'm kind of in an age now where
my reflexes are slower than they used to be so
so it's really uh it's really crucial that when I'm driving I'm just driving
I'm just paying attention to the road to the car to other drivers
I don't play music I don't listen to talks I don't have a hands-free telephone to
to talk to other people um
I just drive you know I just I just uh
let the awareness you know stay um
partly in the body and partly on the road ahead
I I don't go on any really long drives it's probably most most everything that
I do is within about an hour of where I live so being mindful driving for an hour is
um is not that challenging I mean
as much as there's some desire
for the mind to be entertained you know entertained with music or
I'm not a big fan of talk radio but you know Dharma talks or things like that
um you know for however much time I'm in the car I
can just forego that and just and just let that be a mindfulness practice
and then at the end of the day it's you know the same thing you uh brush my teeth
get into my the pajamas that I wear and then
go to bed so that's that's kind of a
a day in the life for me of of the simple ways that mindfulness is accessible
when I decided to give this talk I also happened to ask a number of friends
of mine people in um kalyanamita groups like
so how do you how do you cultivate everyday mindfulness what you know what
are your practices or what are your cues to uh
kick it up a notch and one friend of mine one person in the
group had talked about when they go out to the mailbox each day to get their mail you know they
you know just um do that as sort of a mini air micro
walking meditation now the person didn't tell me whether once they get the mail whether they
start to read it on the way back or whether they just stay stay with the walking I I suspect that it's the latter
or taking out the garbage thing take it to a dumpster so again it's it's
it's one of those everyday things where you can just
bring your awareness to the body and and also
primarily to the body but also to the feeling tone is this Pleasant or
unpleasant or neutral um you may also notice
um the mood of the Mind or the thoughts in the mind
for many years when I would drive up here on Monday nights to
to manage the traffic on 101 would often be bad
and it never it almost never failed that I noticed that when I left work to head here
I was irritable there then the mind was irritable
and by the time I left here it was completely different it was it was much
more energetic much more uh relaxed much more uh tranquil
I'd often wondered why couldn't my why couldn't my mind State have been
different when I got in the car to come here and I I don't know it could have
been I hadn't eaten it couldn't just I was kind of tired
but in any case that um
those are some of the things that I've come up with um
other people told me something that I thought I was kind of surprised that at
first and then I realized that this made perfect sense which was
their cue for kicking up mindfulness was when they were suffering
when there was Duca um it could be anything from
as mild as just feeling like something is kind of off
uh you know feeling kind of awkward
uh I'm uncomfortable dissatisfied
uh irritable all the way to fairly intense pain
and they said when they noticed that
they realized ah the response is to um shift into a higher gear
awareness wise you know to bring to bring more mindfulness to bring more attention
to what's going on for me it's not just the tension it's
a particular kind which is and the tension which has kindness and
curiosity so that it's it's
greeting the experience with a certain um openness
and also some curiosity to want to know what you know is is there something going on
here that I'm not missing that I'm missing so that that sense of
um openness of welcoming and of wanting to be curious and
investigate [Music] I think are also important parts of
a mindfulness that will help when things get tough you
know when things are challenging when when you're having not a nice
pleasant bowl of oatmeal but when
you're having an experience you just don't want to have like no not this I don't want to be I don't want things to
be this way um
and for many many years and still to this day although not as
much my instinct
when unwelcome experience showed up was to
try to somehow Escape how can I get out of this you know can I
just physically get up and leave or can I just zone out
uh can I be can I ignore it can I distract myself can I distract
others is there some delusion or some fan you know is there some other
uh place in the imagination I can go so that I don't have to see what's
happening and after
all the years that I've been alive um that never works
I mean it might kind of work a little bit but a long term it never works so
developing an ability to be present in those times of
challenge in those times of uh suffering in those times of uh
experiencing The Unwanted
um paying attention is and meeting it
can often be a much better approach
than trying to make something go away I have a friend that I talked to just
recently who's subject to having migraine headaches
and they said that that when the pain is real intense the
only thing that really helps is mindfulness it is just paying
attention to the experience because what they told me was
when they really paid careful attention they found that it wasn't constant solid
pain that you know that there were moments of relative ease
that were interspersed with moments of of
intense unpleasant and they found that that there was
actually sort of almost a wave nature to the pain that would kind of come and go
and come and go and by seeing that it became
easier to work with that the Mind wasn't trying to push it away wasn't trying to
escape that it was actually possible to stay with that experience
and that over time it dissipated when I was told
this story last night um there was no migraine operating
so
so cultivating mindfulness in everyday simple experience can
give us a capacity to deal to to be able to be present when those much more
challenging experiences arise so it isn't you know
cultivating mindfulness in itself isn't um the ultimate goal it's really
developing mindfulness so that we can see more clearly what's going on
and respond to our experience in a more wise and beneficial way
you know so so there's a way that um
I think practicing mindfulness can be beneficial in the moment
and it can be beneficial as the light as the challenges in life
um present themselves to us which
they always will I don't know that I've ever met anybody who hasn't hasn't uh face challenges
so uh thank you all for listening um if anyone has any questions or might
want to share their experience of mindfulness Sally could you give him the
thanks Jim you mentioned that there's times of course where you're not mindful do you find that happens by accident out
of weakness or do you find that you make a decision you know now I am going to opt for
entertainment rather than mindfulness and how do you make that decision
yeah that's a that's a great question um
I'm not sure that I ever consciously decide not to be mindful
if there's certain but it happens I'd say mindlessness happens
uh and I don't think there's anything wrong with
uh entertaining the mind I I don't have a television my television broke during the the pandemic and I just decided not
to get a new one but I have the internet and so I listen to music from my youth
you know from the 50 from the 60s and 70s and some of those songs are just I mean
they just bring up a lot of memories a lot of um
emotion and I think that those are fine to enjoy you
know I I don't think that the practice is about some real strict asceticism of
you know sitting in a cave and all your life
I'd say there's still some mindfulness operating when I when I do those things
like uh listen to old music or watch old movies
which is seeing that they can't be clung to
you know I can listen to a song that I really like and then I might listen to it again
and again and after a while it's like well song's end
you know and often they end in just a few minutes um
so being able to enjoy and not cling is is maybe the practice
to do in in those situations um
yeah I don't know have you had an experience of of
um consciously consciously
dropping awareness if I have a long drive sometimes I will drive mindfully and try to pay attention
to my hands on the wheel and sometimes I'll listen to a podcast or if
I've had a maybe a difficult experience like a hard day at work or something I feel like
I don't have capacity for mindfulness at that time yeah
yeah well I don't I don't want this any of the practices that I that I described to
be um presented as this is what you should be doing
these are just opportunities you know this is a something that you might want to try
um yeah so thank you
okay well it's nine o'clock so um thank you all for coming I hope
if any of this is is helpful for you please um take it with you and if it's not helpful
just let it go