welcome and uh
at the moment my wish in welcoming you is certainly welcome you to this
meditation and in a sense to imc online but i would like really to welcome you
to yourself that when we sit down to meditate ideally there's a we welcome ourselves
we offer a welcome to however we are at the moment
sometimes you're astray we're a stranger to ourselves sometimes we're know ourselves all too well
sometimes we come in all kinds of moods it's like a stranger or a neighbor who
you never know to come knocking on your door and they have a need and you welcome them in
and um so so are you meditation is a time to welcome yourself
in and when we meditate
there is a healthy and unhealthy fear
there is helpful and unhelpful fear there's fear that pulls us away from the
present moment there's fear that in which we freeze or get lost
there's fear which keeps us apart from our experience of the moment
there's also the fear that keeps us in the present there's a fear that keeps us close to a
sense of peace non-conflict ease or calm
and that is the fear of losing that the fear of losing our balance losing
our peace losing our well-being
because it's that's a worthwhile fear to have because in two ways
when we lose our well-being our balance then we're much more likely to
create more problems for ourselves more stress
when we protect our peace if there's if there's some fear like
that like don't don't lose that this is dangerous to lose this peace danger still lose myself
dangerous to lose my welcome to myself and really be present here
that fear might encourage us to let go of the other fears
that take us away that fear leads us maybe motivates us
to protect our mindfulness our presence our being here
and in doing that this secondary is protecting our practice protecting their inner well-being
if if there's fear connected to that a protective fear that hopefully won't be stressful
because it's pointing you back to that place of the absence of stress
it's the protection it's the safeguard it's the fear
that points us back where there is no fear because we know it's dangerous to lose
it so here we are welcome
and to gently close your eyes
and what do you welcome
what is happening with you right now that you're gonna open your door and
welcome in and this is what's happening
and you are the welcomer if you're distressed you're not the
distress you welcome the distress
if you're calm you are not the calm you welcome it whatever there is
welcome it here in this body this mind
feeling and sensing how you are
and then within this body
allowing yourself to take a few deeper breaths
as you inhale feel a fuller maybe a stronger connection
to what is here for you how you are what you're feeling
in a longer exhale than usual let go relax
soften the body
here the inhale is almost like a welcome here
let me feel you let me recognize what's happening
and exhaling settling in relaxing into the middle of it
letting your breathing become normal
and still on the exhale soften relax wherever you can in your
body even if it's micro muscles
let there be a gentle movement of relaxation throughout the body
sometimes in particular spots sometimes the whole body
almost as if you're relaxing into how you are
relaxing into what you welcome here now
and then continue as you exhale to relax a bit
but let the welcomer relax that part of you that knows that feels
that's recognizes what's happening let that relax
so that your awareness your mindfulness has no fear in it
no hesitation relax the witnesser the welcomer the
the awareness of it all
and then sitting here so far is there something about how you are
some inner sense of balance or calm or peace
in your sense of openness and welcoming something
that's appropriate to protect
it's appropriate there's a healthy concern maybe fear
of drifting away from being connected to yourself being present here
there's a danger in drifting away from whatever
whatever degree of calm or presence
here there is
maybe there's a way of being motivated by that fear that concern
to love and stay close to
that place within where there's a sense of well-being
or the place within where there could be a sense of well-being
close
stay close to the place that's safe inside
and through these minutes of meditation
have you come to a time a place where you have a clear sense that there's
something here to protect to nourish to support
to safegarden some sense of well-being or clarity or
calm
and maybe there's a healthy concern of fear
that motivates you to stay close to that well-being
not to lose it
so
and as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps you can consider whether there's a healthy fear
that is the fear of losing our respect and love and care for others
even losing it temporarily or having it be eclipsed by other feelings
the fear of losing a kind regard
of others and maybe this is worth protecting
maybe there's never an occasion to be mean or hostile
or unfriendly and so to fear
going in those directions and that for that fear to be motivating
to stay close to your kindness your friendliness
or maybe it's meaningful for you
to wish well in others may may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you so we come to
the last and fifth talk on fear and i hope that thing during this week
i've been able to offer you some new perspectives on
practicing with fear living with fear understanding fear and
i'll continue with that today and
i thought of maybe that the subject for today would be the wisdom of fear
and part of the wisdom of fear is that or how to understand that the wisdom that fear can
be wise is when we think that one of the functions of fear
is to is protection it's an attempt to protect something
and then what are we protecting what is being threatened
and and some things are worth protecting
some things are not worth protecting and so there is this notion in buddhism
that there is healthy fear and unhealthy fear helpful fear and
unhelpful fear so to have a categorical attitude towards fears being wrong or bad
is not so useful what's useful is to practice with fear to normalize
fear to not identify with fear to learn to hold fear
with kindness to hold it [Music] gently so you can really see it and know
it and and it's helpful to have it you know
sit on your shoulder and accompany you rather than be you
all things that i've talked about this week and um
but then it's also important to be able to look deeply at fear and is this
healthy this fear is this helpful this fear is it this really protecting me in an
important way is it really a protection or is it is that is it the opposite am i
actually more in danger by having this fear because some fears and anxiety
especially anxieties that are quite strong probably put us in greater danger
than if we don't have it we're more likely to make mistakes we're more likely to act impulsively
we're more likely to some some anxieties are self-fulfilling
that if we're anxious something's going to happen that very anxiety makes it more likely to happen
sometimes it's the analogy that sometimes is used around dogs if you're afraid of a dog the dog is
more likely to attack you and so the more anxiety there's around the dog we want to protect ourselves but
the very movement of anxiety is the thing that that
keeps us from being protected and um so we have to kind of look at what is
what are we afraid of here and is it a healthy or not healthy and if it's a healthy fear we're
protecting something worthwhile then the fear has a function
of being motivating there's energy in fear and that energy can be motivated to do something
to actually do something that protects what needs to be protected and sometimes that's to do things in the
world and maybe put a lock on your door for example if
that's what's going to keep you safe and sometimes it's um to really
practice the careful self-monitoring
so that you don't succumb to unhelpful states of mind you don't succumb to
anxiety or anger or hostility or greed
and you don't succumb to attachments that are maybe even the source of the fear
itself and so the fear a healthy fear protects what's
needs should can be protected it's helpful to protect
and so what are some of the things that are helpful and healthy to protect
certainly our integrity our ethical integrity because one of the sources of fear
is when we live unethically and afraid of being caught or or
afraid of our own conscience it's also uh um
uh you know there's a fear of wrongdoing so there's fear so that if there's a
healthy fear of no i don't want to do that i don't want to lie i don't want to to get in that kind of situation and
that keeps us from doing it keeps us even getting into those situations and
the deeper and more peaceful meditators tend to become the more likely they're going to have a
fear for somehow harming themselves with their ethics
or harming anybody with their ethics the fear of causing harm
that's a healthy fear and it can be an anxious fear it can be a
neurotic fear not to harm others and that that maybe won't be so helpful
but if there is a healthy not wanting to cause harm it's like the heart's the heart sings when it doesn't cause
harm their hearts stop singing when you think about causing harm or i think we have
caused harm and so that's worth protecting being close to
and and then there's a sense of well-being we get whatever that is i use that word very vaguely
that as we practice as we go through our lives there are times when we feel a degree of peace happiness
connectedness that is nourishing supportive for us
brings us joy and delight and that's worth protecting
it's remarkable how easy it is to give it up how easy it is to get distracted and cut up and sometimes very petty
concerns that that to really wipe away
the sense of balance the sense of inner strength or peace that we might have
and that's so it's worth protecting that so how do we protect that maybe we protect it by being careful
with what we watch on tv you know maybe we're careful what we uh
who we spend time with or how much time we spend with people maybe we're careful about where we go or
what the activities we do because some activities like like uh you know watching at a shopping channel or
looking at catalogs maybe stimulates um unhealthy desires and attachment and
that the stairs stirs up and causes us to lose the fact that we were pretty content before we looked at the catalog
and so to um to be
so fear the wisdom of fear is to understand that fear is trying to protect something and is what it's
protecting worthwhile is it appropriate is it helpful for us
so there's this uh used to be read quite a bit this quote by krishna murthy
there is fear as long as you want to be secure
secure in your marriage secure in your job secure in your position
secure in your responsibility secure in your ideas
in your beliefs secure in your relationships to the world and in your relationship to god
at the moment the mind seeks security or gratification in any form
at any level there is bound to be fear
so there can be attachment to a security to a certainty
in a world that has much more uncertainty than we often will admit
and so our is all these things we try to search for try to hold on to for our security
and then is that really the right place to feel secure
for the buddha the ultimate security ultimate safety
is found in letting go is found in peace isn't found in non-attachment non-clinging
and that can make us feel very vulnerable very challenged but to find strength courage
stability in that place of non-clinging non-attachment
and realize that that is portable and learn how to take that with us in all the insecure situations in life all
the uncertain places in life life is uncertain there is dangers in life
but the biggest danger is that of what we do to ourselves through our
attachments through our karma the actions we do through the dispositions of the mind to
hate or to be greedy or be caught up in something so that
we get we lose ourselves we lose ourselves in anxiety
there is a place of security within that it's worth protecting is worth finding
getting close to and and the place where
it's a place within that is cannot be threatened no matter what happens in the world
that place is not touched and to be centered there to know that
is the ability to go through the world with out fear
but until we get to that place that point any hints or sense of that possibility of
that inner well-being that that moves in that direction that should that can be protected
that we want to be careful for that is worthwhile protecting um because we're moving
towards freedom we're moving to the place where we're really bringing ourselves bring the healthiest
the greatest health to ourselves the greatest spiritual health the greatest freedom to our hearts
so fear is an all-too-human experience it's a
there's healthy and it's a it's it's there's it wants to protect us it's a kind of in and of itself a healthy
movement of protecting something so we don't want to dismiss fear
we want to be able to be friends with fear and connect to fear see it deeply
because as we see it deeply in our present for it all fear all movements of protection
probably at the very root of what they're about is
is this place of ultimate safety this or this desire for ultimate safety
and many fears are mis understandings many fears is misunderstanding what's
really important meditation like meditation
hopefully will connect us to what is most important so that we remember that as we go into
the world and we don't fear things which are not that important
that doesn't matter so much there's plenty of things that we might fear that we don't have to worry about
so um i'd like to end with a quote from martin luther king
that brings this topic of fear into our social domain
martin luther king jr wrote people fail to get along
because they fear each other they fear each other because they don't
know each other they don't know each other because they have not communicated with
each other so to the degree to which we are afraid of others
maybe we haven't really gotten to know them and maybe we really haven't let them
know us maybe to develop real communication between people
is one of the benefits of becoming wise with fear because then fear does not interfere
with our ability to communicate connect and and
have real friendship with other people
so thank you for all this and uh
may you now take a time to really
become wise about your fear maybe even courageous around it
so i'm going away again next week for another week of vacation this summer
and happy that the nikki nikki murgafore will come back she's come often to be my substitute and
a wonderful teacher she teaches happy hour at imc
which is a time for an hour's time for loving-kindness practice in the
afternoon so she'll be here next week and i'll be back the following
thank you