so good morning good day just a quick reminder that we'll have a
community meeting after this session today and i'll say a little bit more about that later
but for now let's go ahead and meditate together so finding
your comfortable spot for meditation
and if you're comfortable doing so closing your eyes
bringing the attention inward to the sense of the body sitting
or maybe you're lying down or standing
not just sensing your meditation posture
and feeling into the balance and groundedness
and support of where you're sitting so actually sensing the
contact point with your seed against the cushion or the chair
and letting yourself be supported by that
and sometimes it's helpful to even explicitly check into the balance of where you're
sitting so you can even rock side to side slightly or forward and back to
just really find a middle point where the body feels the most
balanced i find that looking at a computer screen
sometimes i get a little bit pushed forward
so you might check if just settling back a little bit feels more
aligned and upright
if we're going to be sitting for a while that makes a difference
just to use as few muscles as possible
and then softening into that upright posture
softening the face the head
letting the head float on the spine
softening the shoulders
softening through the chest area [Music]
around the heart
and letting the belly be very soft and round
and letting go of any bracing in the arms or legs
so we're inviting a very useful bodily position
and then also the mindfulness in the mind
in a simple easeful way just to know how it is right now
sensing the sensations of the breathing which become more evident as the
body and mind settle a bit
and the invitation is to continue with the breath as an anchor
but allowing the mind to open to or turn toward
any object that becomes more compelling than the breath
so if a body sensation becomes strong or a sound
there doesn't need to be any conflict between that and wanting to stay with the breath just open to
what feels more compelling and then when that reduces in intensity
just naturally going back to the breath
and the same is true if there's a strong emotion or thought train that
comes up maybe at first we even get pulled into
it but then when we realize that's what it was just allowing that to be the object of
mindfulness until it's again not as compelling and
it's easy to return to the sensations of the breath
and to support this we could deliberately invoke
a sense of care care for your own heart
care for your mind states
it doesn't mean that we're going to block anything out and decide we're not going to have that mind
state it's still okay for anything to rise in
awareness but the care is in intending to meet it
well to meet it clearly with mindfulness
that itself is an act of care
and this quality of mindfulness that we've been exploring
for a while now is inherently balancing
that's actually one of its qualities
so if the mind is feeling sleepy or dull
it's mindfulness that knows that and often
just seeing that we're dull brings in a bit more energy
and when the mind is irritated [Music]
it's mindfulness that knows that and that can feel the pain of that
and so that will naturally soften the mind
if our mindfulness is clear and equanimous
it will balance the mind
so the sit today will be largely silent
and the suggestion is that when the mind is somehow off balance
getting distracted or pulled into things
instead of trying to do anything about that
see if mindfulness alone will rebalance it just by knowing really clearly
what's going on in the mind
so exploring this inherently balancing nature of mindfulness
you
so practicing in this simple way
where mindfulness is helping to balance our mind
we can really see that this
act of noticing our experience is an act of care
sometimes it goes so far as to say seeing is loving
[Music]
there's so much in our experience that isn't seen clearly
and wants to be seen clearly and when it is it somehow gets
incorporated somehow gets balanced
so meditation is quite compassionate
and then this these qualities also move outward to
protect others sometimes directly sometimes more
indirectly
and certainly this sense of care that gets evoked through mindfulness
translates into treating others with harmlessness with
meta
there's really no way to only practice for ourselves
so you could reflect for a moment
how does your practice of mindfulness affect other people in your life
and also how might the way that you practice mindfulness
serve to promote qualities that explicitly benefit others
things like patience or harmlessness loving kindness and sympathy
how does your practice of mindfulness help generate those qualities
[Music]
[Music] um
okay so first um as noted there will be a community meeting today after the talk
and it will just start around 7 45 a.m pacific when we're done here
and that will be on zoom so you'll have to switch over to that
and the the link is on imc's homepage under
what's new and it's also on the imc calendar
and i tried to put it in the chat but it turns out it's i i can't do that easily
from the way i connect so i hope you can find it in one of those two places
and there's a password for it that i'll mention at the end
okay so this week we've explored a broad range
of how mindfulness can function as a protection it might be a simple
guarding of the scent stores and but it also has the potential to be very strong
and powerful such that one conquers that's what the texts say conquers states like fear and pain
and one becomes able to endure harsh words from others
so today we'll talk about how mindfulness serves as a protection
of oneself and others so both of those
together there's a suta called the sadaka suta that's about
an acrobat and his apprentice who do their stunts on a bamboo pole
and they're talking together about how to be protected while doing their work together
and it's a short suta so i'm actually just going to read it
on one occasion the blessed one was dwelling among the sumbas and there was
a town of the sumbas named sadaka there the blessed one addressed the
monks thus monks once in the past acrobat set up his bamboo pole and
addressed his apprentice made a catalica thus come dear apprentice
climb the bamboo pole and stand on my shoulders having replied yes teacher
the apprentice climbed up the bamboo pole and stood on the teacher's shoulders
the acrobat then said to the apprentice you protect me and all protect you. thus guarded by one
another protected by one another we'll display our skills collect our fee
and get down safely from the bamboo pole and when this was said
the apprentice replied that's not the way to do it teacher you protect yourself and i'll protect
myself thus each self-guarded and self-protected
will display our skills collect our fee and get down safely from the bamboo pole
that is the method there said the buddha it's just as the apprentice said to the teacher
i will protect myself thus should the establishments of mindfulness be
practiced i will protect others thus should the establishments of
mindfulness be practiced protecting oneself one protects others
protecting others one protects oneself and how is it monks that by protecting
oneself one protects others by the pursuit development and
cultivation of meditation it is in such a way that by protecting
oneself one protects others and how is it that by protecting others
one protects oneself by patience harmlessness loving kindness
and sympathy it is in such a way that by protecting others one protects oneself
i will protect myself thus should the establishments of mindfulness be practiced
i will protect others thus should the establishments of mindfulness be practiced
protecting oneself one protects others protecting others one protects oneself
it's a pretty interesting suta so i thought we would unpack this a bit
today so mindfulness brings protection for ourselves and for others
and i'll even add that it brings protection for the whole world in certain ways
so let's talk about sort of a number of main ways that can happen
so certainly mindfulness protects us from unmindful actions that are coming
from unwholesome motivations so at the kind of at the gross blunt end of the
spectrum this would include things like breaking precepts others are certainly affected by actions
like that and when we're mindless we we might do that or just more broadly
unskillful responses in general so if we're if our mind is caught up at
a certain time in sensual desire or lust for power or
anger or fear then we harm our relationships and we also harm
the social atmosphere of safety that can be created and so if the mind is caught up in these
things and we're not aware of that we might act on them and
do some harm and then maybe a little bit more subtly when we get
swept up by our views we might then impose those views on
others or act out our views unskillfully and that also goes in this
category of you know unmindful behavior
and of course i've been sort of implying that this is for the people that are affected directly
but in this media saturated world it's not only the people that we
directly relate to who are affected if we have misguided views or harmful
speech they can spread rapidly to a lot of other people certainly
even before this media saturated world history shows that even a small group of people who have a
particularly strong misguided view can sway a large number of people
inducing them also to do harmful actions
so that leads to the second main area of protection which is that mindfulness paves the way
for wisdom so um you know in a sort of a personal sense
we can clearly see and feel the harm that comes from unwholesomeness and when we can then it becomes natural to choose
the wholesome that's this balancing function that i talked about is that when we see actually the pain that's
caused say by being irritated then the mind will naturally want to
move into more balance but then also mindfulness makes our mind
more resilient and wise such that we are less influenced by harmful messages
coming in when we're mindful we are actually less likely to believe misinformation
and also though um sort of rumors that come that come in and so we become
clearer and more more capable of functioning as community
members as citizens and then in addition
we come to know through mindfulness we come to know our own mind and heart well
so that we can work skillfully with our own tendencies we start to know what our
particular little patterns are and and then how to counterbalance those so that they don't
bring harm to the world i went for a walk one time with a longtime practitioner
who i otherwise didn't know very well [Music] but we got into kind of an animated conversation about
the dharma and at one point uh he paused to say
my tone of voice can sound kind of authoritative when i get interested in a topic like i am right now so please know
that i'm not making strong declarative statements i'm actually quite open to inquiry and exploration
and i i was impressed that he said that so he knew himself well enough to know that his manner of expressing
deep engagement in a topic might come across to others as being a
little bit assertive or even sound close-minded so he was taking care to say that that's
not how he feels inside so he was showing good relational skill
and that kind of skill comes from close mindfulness from knowing ourselves
knowing our tendencies and then also in the realm of wisdom
as we come to see the universal truths of impermanence of
unsatisfactoriness of not self we're less inclined to grasp so tightly
onto one way of doing things and this flexibility makes us better
community members and leaders there's another pseudo where the buddha talks about qualities of a
good community members and one of them is wisdom
knowing the wisdom in particular of impermanence so as we see that everything changes and
it just becomes less important to grasp onto our particular way that we want to
do things and that makes things go better in a group
and then also through mindfulness we become stable for
others and i'm reminded here of a story that take not han tells about the
the vietnamese vote people of course there were many many other terrible conditions surrounding that
situation but what he was focusing in on in this story is that when there was
one person on the boat who was expressing uh calm and presence
um everybody on the boat would also feel calmer and that could make the
difference between really between life and death for those people if everybody panicked
the boat was likely to go over but if one person could could stay calm
then they had a chance so this is um you know another function of mindfulness
another great value that it offers the world and the buddha was clear that we you
know remember he favored what the apprentice said not what the teacher said so the apprentice said i'll look
out for myself you look out for yourself and in that way things you know will be able to stay
balanced so we take care of ourselves first in a sense like they say on the airplane you put on your own oxygen mask
before assisting others so um yeah this is this is how it can work how
it can work in a more broad way than just our own internal practice
so in in many different ways the benefits of mindfulness kind of spill out to support others also we can't help
it we're going to help others also and the the cultivation of mindfulness naturally brings forth
qualities that we might associate with protecting others so as the suta said patience harmlessness loving kindness
and sympathy and these qualities come about
actually kind of naturally through the development of meditation that's the game changer because we see in ourselves
we see our suffering we see our patterns we have to soften up and work with that
and care about that and love that and then that translates into
treating others the same way when we see those qualities in them it's not that much difference between internal and
external as practice goes along so but we do need to meditate to create
enough depth and stability that we can protect both ourselves and others
so i want to um quote now from nyanaponakatera
who has done a nice analysis of this suta about the acrobats
and he comes to the conclusion that it relates to what are called the wings of
awakening so he says self-protection and protection of others correspond to the
great twin virtues of buddhism wisdom and compassion i shall protect myself
thus should we establish our mindfulness and guided by it devote ourselves to the
practice of meditation for the sake of our own liberation i shall protect others
thus should we establish our mindfulness and guided by it regulate our conduct by patience
harmlessness loving-kindness and compassion for the welfare and happiness
of many so it's quite beautiful what we're doing
we kind of can't help ending up benefiting the world and if we make that explicit in our way of being
through the balance of wisdom and compassion we can really
discover the potential of the human heart the great potential that we have the potential of this practice
for bringing about so much benefit in this world that it so much needs it
so thank you thank you for your practice and it's inspiring to me
to been here this whole week with you so um
so thus ends our exploration of the images of mindfulness and some of the
i think the kind of broader context in which this practice situates
itself and with that you can dive back in next week with gil and looking at the four
fourth foundation of mindfulness he'll be going through some of the other qualities and practices that are in that
final final foundation of mindfulness so thank you
so we're moving now into the community meeting and as i said the zoom
link is on the imc home page under what's new and it's also on the calendar
um i connect into youtube a different way than gil does so i first of all i can't put the link into
the chat but second of all when i switch over to zoom this youtube session will end
it has to end so just so you know and you're welcome to join if you're
both available and interested and the password in case it's not listed there or maybe it's listed as the the
buddhist word for love is uh m-e-t-t-a meta
and um yeah so very good and
i will see you there in a few minutes