uh well welcome back and good morning my name is May Elliott and here we are on
our last day of a week-long study on the foundations of vipassana meditation
so today's instructions are on open awareness up to now this week we've
covered a couple of different areas of our experience to pay attention to breathing Body Sensations emotions and
thoughts and today is when we bring these four different aspects of meditation into a seamless whole
so this is the culmination of the work we've done so far so far we've seen we've seen that we can
be mindful of any of these parts of experience and today we see how they can be unified together
so um so let's begin our meditation
go ahead and connect your meditation posture
posture that invites ease and well-being
that's both energetic ready to meet the moment and relaxed
sitting with a soft forehead relaxed temples
or released the jaw
relaxed shoulders and a softened belly
as we begin to sit we can connect with our primary anchor
that might be the breath The Sound State or maybe a global sense of the bodily
posture for the sake of Simplicity we'll focus
on the breath
for this first part of the meditation just being loyal to the breath
connecting with where you feel it predominantly and staying connected to it
so I'm using all preoccupation
foreign
foreign [Music]
starts
[Music]
feeling it for its full length noticing the moment the inhale ends
and the shift to Exhale
noticing the whole length of the exhale and the moment the
exhale stops
making contact with each transition or inhale to Exhale and Back Again
thank you
foreign
begins to settle on the breath foreign
at any given moment there are lots of things happening sounds
Sensations emotions
moves thoughts
so the way that will include these so begin to openly awareness is it
rather than focusing solely on the breath if one of these other aspects of
experience becomes predominant will allow the attention to go to that new
experience and to heal it fully to get to know what
it feels like in the body in the heart and mind in the present moment
[Music] so you still have a
my preference for the breath and that that's where our our home is we keep
coming back to the breath in between the objects that we notice
that will venture out to different Sensations feel them for a bit if they're predominant then come back to
the breath an emotion arises
you go feel that emotion connect with it explore feel it when it's no longer
predominant come back to the breath foreign
[Music]
capacity for attention functions a little like a spotlight It Shines on one
thing at a time [Music]
so with this practice we're allowing whatever is predominant to be in the spotlight
foreign [Music]
foreign practice can be particularly supportive
for this style of meditation [Music]
making a soft note in the mind and
inhale exhale
hero here
[Music] inhale exhale
tingling
contentment inhale
exhale inhale exhale
foreign
we're taking note of anything that arises
and then returning to the breath
foreign
[Music]
foreign meditation [Music]
so let go of our preference for the breath let go of
the practice of continuing to return to the breath in between phenomena
the math will sit with a full open awareness
so in this style of practice we're meeting whatever it is the
spotlight of awareness Falls on
maybe it's pressure cleaning the chest
we feel that for a few moments and then
the sensations of relaxation in the belly become predominant foreign
then tingling in the neck in the legs
then a hot you might not thinking
even an emotion
in this way we keep meeting whatever arises the breath might be something that comes
into predominance and we note it but we're not intentionally returning to the breath as our primary
anchor you could think of this as an anchorless
practice
we're allowing the attention to move from one object to another to another
not trying to control an environment just enjoying receptive attention
receiving whatever appears in awareness
[Music] foreign
foreign
wanders off you can try we only went into the practice by asking
what's happening now
turning Tomatoes we're changing objects
foreign
thank you period
thank you that's in the spotlight now
thank you
foreign
[Music]
[Music] foreign
foreign
as we come to the quotes of our meditation you can take a moment to connect with
the goodness of this practice
regardless of how we think our meditation went
just the intention to sit down and make an effort
to have the body be still so wholesome so onward feeding
may all beings receive the benefits of this Peaceful Practice
foreign
[Music] I feel so blessed to get to have another
day with this this super sweet songa that's really
been a joy getting to sit with you um so uh here we are uh the focus of
today's instruction our last day covering the foundations of opposana
these basics and uh we're looking at open awareness we're practicing open awareness
sometimes called choiceless attention because we're not intentionally choosing
our object of meditation we're choiceless in that we're allowing
whatever is most predominant to be the next object the next object of attention and this practice of open awareness or
choiceless attention is what's at the heart of mahasi sayadas meditation
instruction the Burmese master who had so much influence over Insight in the
West uh so today I'd like to review what we've done so far this week as it
pertains to this open awareness practice and then we'll shift to talk about styles of practice and when when do we
focus just on the breadth versus when do we sit with open awareness and how to
discern when to do what so hopefully by the end of this morning you'll have a better sense of what practice is best
for whatever mind you happen to have at a given moment that you sit down to meditate
so let's start with a review of Where we've been and how this comes together into open awareness practice
so the way this works is we start by developing my photos of breathing
the breath becomes our primary anchor the anchor is where we've been directing
our attention back to bringing our attention back from the mind wanders at
that time in the practice if something else drew our attention we would return to the breath right away we wouldn't
focus on it just just go back to the bottom and that's what we did on Monday day one of the instruction focusing on
breath then the next day we added more objects to our meditation we added physical Association
Sensations and we learned that if a physical sensation one is more predominant than the bread we could
shift our attention to that new sensation we actually were to hang out with it we would feel it we give it our
full attention until it leaves it uh no longer was predominant and then we'd
return to the breath and in that way we learned the symptoms of the language of the body and we're
going to feel the many different types of Sensations that can be helped
then we focused on how to integrate emotions and thoughts into our
meditation learning that if an emotion became predominant we could turn our attention
away from the breath to the emotion recognizing it allowing it feeling it
teasing apart what we were noticing and then when the emotion faded we could
return to the breath I'm studying thoughts if a thought
became predominant we could turn our attention to the process of thinking not the content of the thinking not not
getting lost in The Narrative of the thinking that seeing the process noticing our thoughts as present moment
phenomena and then returning to the breath come on
so today as I mentioned we're learning to integrate them into a seamless hole
so rather than directing attention to the breath or to any specific object on
the last day hear me practice with receptive attention receptive as opposed
to directed attention we open up our awareness and allow anything that arises physical Sensations
emotions thoughts to be known and we're doing that without preference
um in a way learning how to be mindful of each of these parts of experience black
body emotions and thoughts it's a little like learning to make a suit
each day we've learned how to chop one kind of vegetable right like day one we chopped onions stay tuned we chopped
carrots day three we chopped zucchini Etc but today we put it all together in a
pot and we made and when we dip the spoon in our soup we pay attention to whatever
vegetable floats onto our spoon we taste that vegetable and then we see
what floats onto the spoon next we don't go fishing for a particular vegetable we just pay attention to
whatever vegetable floats onto the spoon next [Music]
in essence I whole body and mind is the soup and the vegetables are the different
experiences of breath body emotions and thoughts our awareness is the spirit
whatever whatever experience appears in our awareness whatever floats on the
spoon is what we're giving our attention to so in doing this we're not controlling
we're receptive we're relaxed we're not choosing a specific object
just allowing what's in the foreground to be experienced
as I as I explained in the guided meditation in this practice and this was at the end
of The Meditation we dropped our preference for the breath we're equally
interested in taking any predominant experience as our object of mindfulness in the open awareness practice
um and at any given moment there are lots of things happening Sensations bodies Body Sensations sounds Etc
um and as I shared in the meditation our capacity for attention functions a
little like a spotlight you know it shines at one uh on one thing at a time so choiceless attention we allow
whatever is the most dominant sensation to be in the spotlight and as soon as something else becomes predominant we
allow that to be in the spot of my arm and the challenge with this practice is
is staying attentive enough
and then the Mind needs to be pretty pretty settled in order to stay with changing objects I'd say that's the
primary challenge of the open awareness practice um if the mind isn't settled when it
makes contact with an object say a sound an emotion a body sensation it will
provide commentary so when a bird chirps if we if the attention isn't consistent
or it isn't grounded enough uh rather than just being the sound of
the bird chirping the Mind might say like oh that sounds a hummingbird or oh
I love hummingbirds I should get a hummingbird feeder oh but that might attract squirrels and do what the Mind
does but so the mind has to be relatively stable in order to stay with each object and not get lost in the
commentary about each object one thing that can be supportive with
staying with the object as we've mentioned each day this week is using noting practice so it's making that
light mental note in the mind where ninety percent of the attention is on
the sensation or the sound or the emotion um and maybe just a 10 there's just a
little attention denoting what's happening um and when we're sufficiently present
when we notice a bird chirping outside rather than falling into commentary
about it we might just know hearing and the way this open awareness practice
might look as we note hearing and we hear it for a while noticing what
it sounds like and then we might notice a tightness in the neck and note tightness
feeling the tightness and then a thought comes in oh I hope my neck spasms don't start up
again then you might know thinking at which point you notice an emotion and
note anxiety then you might notice an intention to
relax and intended then relaxation happens in the shoulders
and so you know relax it and maybe it stays for a long time and so you note a
few times relaxing relaxing
relaxing calm
and then a thought arrives wow this meditation thing is really working and
we might know surprise you might think then I'm getting pretty
good at this and then we might note Pride
then an emotion comes in and you note embarrassment
then some warmth in the face and you might know warmth
etc etc so this this is one way that it might
look and notice we're not taking anything that we notice we're not taking it personally it's like oh just a clean
clear awareness now this is embarrassment this is pride
and uh you may have noticed that those were some pretty uh specific
ways of knowing experience
Pride embarrassment [Music] um intending
Etc so it's okay if you don't have the perfect note for what it is that you're
experiencing so if you're not sure that it's I don't know if it doesn't stand out oh this is an intention or this is
um this is planning you might guess not thinking or you might just note emotion
you don't have to strain to to try to find the right name for what it is that you're experiencing
for a long time when I was growing up I would sometimes say or do something
and then I would have this feeling afterwards and I wouldn't know what it
was all that I could do to describe it was to say I feel bad
I feel bad because how it felt inside and it took me a long time to realize
that that feeling was called guilt um but for the sake of this practice it
would have been sufficient just to note healing back
going back [Music] um and so having that
um you know if if the recognition for the name isn't there that's fine the
main thing is just being present and noticing what's happening
um even if you don't have the name for it the way that the noting functions is
it really just gives the Mind something to do to stay engaged so we're just giving it something that's present
centered to pay attention to [Music] and if you make a note every few seconds
that will be enough to help you stay connected the pacing is hit
relaxed and gentle and spacious you don't have to make a note every
millisecond so this might sound something like hearing
inhale
Etc [Music]
so that's a summary of open awareness practice
and how loading can support us in it um I'd like to shift now to a question
um when do we do this open awareness practice is this what I should be doing
all the time in my meditation well it depends on the person but for a
lot of people the answer is no this practice is best instead for when the
mind is somewhat stable and steady not when there's a lot of dispersive thought a lot of of uh
so if the mind is really slippery and unwilling to stay with an object and you notice yourself getting really lost and
thought just go back to breath practice this open awareness practice might be too wide of a pasture for the mind to
play in at that given moment so instead just let the Mind focus on
the breath the breath is is a smaller playing field where it can be put on a
leash so when the mind is dispersive we just have it focused on a simple object go
back to the breath only go back to the primary answer so this is directed attention and the simple object of
breathing as this stabilizes OAS it settles the
mind Once the mind is a little more steady
and present then you might start allowing in other objects and try this open awareness
practice when the mind is more stable that's when you can allow it to go off leash and
have a wider pasture again that's when you can most effectively practice with the open awareness
so another way we can think about these two ways of practicing is through the analogy of a camera aperture so when we
focus on the breath the awareness has a small narrow aperture we're just looking
at the breath when we sit with open awareness we're allowing anything to come into our field
and this is like having a very wide aperture open awareness
so if the mind is wild and there's lots of the Concha we go to the primary anchor we hang out with the breath
smaller aperture and then when we stabilize the mind is more quiet
we have a wide open app and shirt aperture open awareness I'd like to think about this as as two ends of a
spectrum narrow to wide on breath only to open awareness
now I'd like to provide a middle ground for you in between these two practices
on either end of the spectrum and this is what we did in the middle of the meditation today
um and what an adaptation share is what I often do in my personal practice as it's both stabilizing and it's inclusive
of all experience and this is a lot like what we've done each day in our meditation so here's
here's what I do I start my meditation by spending some time with just the breath to stabilize and collect the mind
then as the Mind settles a bit if something else becomes more predominant I allow the attention to move to that
new object I contacted we get to know it and that can be any of the things that we've covered this week's Body
Sensations emotions thoughts Etc and then when it's no longer compelling I come back to the breath and
that's the key piece here is the breath is the home so in this way we're still
being with the breathing so it's stabilizing the mind
um only difference is that open awareness doesn't have any preference for a particular anchor so with full
open awareness it doesn't favor the breath as the landing path but I'm sharing now this kind of middle ground
in between um the narrow aperture of breath and the wide aperture of open awareness in this
Middle Ground we still have a preference for the breath we're still coming back to it so that stabilizes us and at the
same time we're being inclusive of anything that arises because we're allowing ourselves to venture out to
feeling so so I'll uh just give you an example I'm
saying uh the analogy of a hand here so we can imagine that the if the breath is
our home that's the Palm here and then each finger is negative Body Sensations
emotions thoughts um so we're focusing on the breath when
a body sensation becomes predominant if you go and feel the body sensation then we come back to the breath
then we come back to the bed not getting caught in the content of the thought just noticing the process and we're back
with the breath an emotion breath body sensation breath Etc
um so hope so hopefully that gives you a sense of something that you can do when
the mind is starting to settle but full open awareness practice where there's no preference for an anchor might be a
little too um a little too expansive the mind's too
likely to get lost in things it's not quite stabilizing enough
so um maybe just a few last words about open awareness practice
remember that it's sitting with a receptive mind it's uh it should be easy it should be
kind of again unnaturalness to it and I'm just receiving
and one of the impacts of it is that it allows us to see a knee chat and permanence the inconsistency of things
and we get to see kata's practice of just seeing what arises next next we get
to see the arising and passing of all phenomena and when we sit in this way it's as if
the whole world comes to us so I will close with a quote
the type for its Master ajan cha he says
just go into the room and put one chair in the center
take the seat in the center of the room open the doors and windows and see who
comes to visit you will witness all kinds of scenes and actors
all kinds of Temptation and stories imaginable your job is to stay in your seat
you will see it all arise and pass and out of this wisdom and understanding
will come as I see it the mind is like a single point the center of the universe
and mental states are like visitors who come to stay at this point for short or long periods of time get to know these
visitors well become familiar with the vivid pictures they paint the alluring stories they
tell to entice you to follow them but do not give up your seat it is the
only chair around if you continue to occupy it unceasingly
greeting each guest as it comes firmly establishing your yourself and awareness
transforming your mind into the one who knows the one who is awake the visitors
will eventually stop coming back if you give them real attention how many
times can these visitors return speak with them here and you will know
every one of them well then your mind will at last be at peace
so may you all experience this great Peace and Freedom of knowing the many
visitors that can come to see us and not taking any of them personally
thank you all so much for such a lovely week I look forward to hopefully seeing you again soon take care
[Music]