good morning everyone how's the sound
can you hear me okay great all right so we'll begin this morning with a 25
minute 35 minute meditation together we can start by finding a stable
comfortable relaxed yet energetic posture
so this can be a sitting posture a standing posture or a lying down
posture all of these are suitable for meditation
we might start by taking three deep breaths together inhaling
and exhaling inhaling again
exhaling and a last time
[Applause] and allowing the breath to resume a normal rhythm
as we begin our meditation we might consider setting an intention
for practice this morning
maybe to meet the moment with patience and kindness
maybe just to recognize what's happening at any given moment
and to feel it to feel it fully in the body
at this time you might connect with an anchor for your meditation
that might be the breath the soundscape
or the bodily posture
allowing the mind to rest and settle on the anchor
on our object of meditation
as we begin to settle together
it can be helpful to notice if there's any extra tension in the body
you can intentionally relax the body
softening the scalp releasing the temples
softening the jaw
perhaps allowing the mat the mouth to open for a moment and float clothes
closed so the jaw is relaxed
softening the shoulders
allowing the belly to drop down and forward
and releasing any extra tension in the legs
the ankles and the feet
and if there's any tension in the body that won't relax that's no problem at
all just relax around the tension
no need to ask this moment to be any different than it is
so
reconnecting with your anchor now
feeling a full breath cycle
inviting the mind to rest on the simplicity
of what's present
so
if you've noticed that the mind has wandered
can you gently and kindly return your attention to the present
moment bringing yourself back to the anchor
just sliding back to the anchor no need to contract
or judge yourself if the mind has gone missing
just sliding back to the present moment as many times as is needed
as we continue staying connected to our primary anchor
of attention the breath
the soundscape
if something else calls your attention maybe a strong sensation elsewhere in
the body
an emotion or mood
a sound allow the mind to recognize that
such that mindfulness knows what's happening
sensations in the knee
contraction in the shoulder blade
a sense of peacefulness
or dis-ease just allowing the mind to recognize
what's present if it draws your attention away from the anchor
and you can take a few moments to get to know that experience
that which is recognized which is identified
feeling the sensations in the knee getting to know them
getting to know whatever draws your attention for a few moments
before returning to your anchor
so
so [Music]
may the beneficial energy of our practice benefit all beings everywhere
so they may be free from suffering
[Applause]
[Applause] good morning everyone
welcome if you're just arriving my name is may elliott
i'm coming today from san francisco zen center where i live and work
and it's a delight to be with you today today is a special day for those that don't know
it is gay pride day with the pride parade in san francisco
an opportunity to celebrate all forms of lgbtiqa
diversity and identities um and something for me that feels so
special about pride is it really feels like an opportunity to
um celebrate and honor all parts of oneself
and so learning to love ourselves just as we
are is such an important thing so i hope that this talk today inspires some of that
same sentiment for you so that we can learn to be present with
ourselves present with whatever is arising for us without judgment
no part left out
i'd like to begin the talk this morning with a memory
i was just reflecting on how when i was a teenager one of my favorite things to
do was to go backpacking and we'd pack up our our backpacks with
everything we'd need and take off into the back country and go out to remote lakes and mountains
and one of the aspects of this is we needed to be self-sufficient and we
could only carry about two liters of water on us at any given time so we needed to hike from
water source to water source and so this might be finding
mountain streams or creeks or um finding lakes
and on occasion we would travel for miles and miles through the
heat and get to a water source and it would be murky or filled with silt or
overgrown with moss and that was not good news
we'd have these little plastic water filters with us that we'd pump the water with and though
they did a pretty good job they were no match for a really funky lake so
um what we needed was for our water to be somewhat clear in order to sustain us
and to continue surviving on these on our journey
and i remembered this experience when i was thinking about the mind
so our mind is a little like the water in these in these lakes and creeks
when the mind is clear it can be life-giving it can sustain and support
us and we can become more free of suffering we can become more loving and joyful in
our lives but if the mind is too agitated to murky
to overgrown we're not able to see clearly the qualities of love and wisdom
are obscured by the silt of the mind and we're not able to move forward towards greater freedom in our life
the buddha named five specific states of mind that create a lack of clarity
these are called the five hindrances i'm just curious who here has heard of the
five hindrances people familiar wonderful great so this will be a review
for some of you and for me what i find is uh the more i hear about the hindrances the
more i'm able to recognize them in myself and to not be fooled by them
so the hindrances are known for covering over and obscuring our wisdom
and typically if we're having a difficult time probably one of the hindrances is at work
so the five hindrances for those that could use a review are
sense desire the wanting mind ill will or aversion
the mind that doesn't want what it has so these first two are two sides of the same coin wanting and not wanting
the next is restlessness so this can be a higher energy state a
mental or physical agitation the next sloth intorper which is
sleepiness and those two are energetic states and
then the last is doubt so the buddha compared the mind to a
bowl of water in one of the early buddhist sutas he talks about the hindrances
as though they were a bowl of water
so the doubtful mind is like a bowl of water that's murky the
restless mind is stirred up or agitated water the sleepy mind is like a bowl of water
overgrown the aversive mind is boiling as though
hot with anger and the desirous mind is like water filled with colorful dyes
dyes that can entrance us and distract us in the way that sense desire is so
apt to do so in all cases the mind is not clear
so lucky for us the buddha offered some wonderful teachings on how to work with
these states and in this talk i'll share a singular practice that you can use to
apply to any of the hindrances so we could think of this as a one-size-fits-all teaching
and then i'll go through each hindrance individually and share some of the specific practices that you might apply
to each individual hindrance including the antidotes
and something i find quite helpful to remember is that almost anything i'm struggling with not everything but many
things can in large part be distilled down to simply being a manifestation of one of
the hindrances so simple just one of these five things pretty easy right so if i can learn to
meet these hindrances skillfully then there's gonna be a lot more freedom in my life so i find that pretty
incentivizing for learning how to work with these so to begin here is the one size fits
all practice and if this is the only thing that you remember from this talk
it will serve you well and it's really simple just two steps to this the first is recognize and the
second is feel so recognize that's just recognizing what's
present present identifying what is present in this moment
so that might be oh this is wanting this is wanting that's present or oh
this is sleepiness and it's really helpful to know a hindrance as a hindrance oh this is just
one of the hindrances we're so often transfixed by the storyline of what we want or what we
want to get rid of that we don't even really know that desire or aversion or are present for us
and that those are actually what's fueling the show
and sometimes just the act of naming something is enough to help it lose its power over us
sometimes there can be something in us that's asking for attention and piping up in our mind over and over
again and when we can turn towards it and identify it recognize it it's as though we're giving it the
attention that it's been seeking and that can sometimes be enough to help
it release
some time ago i decided to embark on trying a new
meditation technique and this was taught by a teacher that i really admired
so naturally i wanted to impress the teacher with my
meditative prowess and of course as one could suspect i
found myself sometime later worrying about well am i any good at this practice i really want
to be good at this am i doing it right and so it's no surprise that there was
some suffering there associated with that experience
so one day i was sitting kind of mulling over my sense of insufficiency
when the mind stopped and a phrase came into the mind
and it said this is doubt
this is doubt that's it this is just one of the hindrances and i know that i don't need to take the
hindrances personally and it was upon the arising
of seeing the recognition this is doubt that the whole package fell away
that whole narrative the whole storyline just evaporated and in its place
it was replaced by joy so
sometimes just the naming of something can be enough to have it release
and you'll notice when that happened i didn't make the doubt go away i didn't
get rid of the doubt i didn't even let go of the doubt inner wisdom released the doubt in that
moment and that's what can become possible as we we begin to practice with the hindrances more
and often for us simple recognition does not cause the hindrance to evaporate
and so what what then so then we have our second step so we recognize and then we feel
we feel the hindrance in the body we get to know it we bring curiosity to it we
investigate it and this is an opportunity to
to shift our fixation so often when we're entranced by hindrance
there's typically an object that we're fixated on especially this happens with desire and ill will or aversion
we're fixated on wanting a new haircut or getting our roommate to take out the
trash and so we're so wrapped up in the object
the trash the roommate the haircut that we don't really know what's happening
so instead in this way of working with the hindrance we let go of obsessing with the object
and we turn 180 degrees and look inward and identify what's happening and this
begins to pull us out of our trance it pulls us out of our daydream so rather than trying to get rid of our
hindrance we turn and look at it we feel it
and just to say a little bit more about what i mean when i say feel um we can
when we feel it in the body and we get curious about it we're actually feeling into the sensations
we're not exploring it with a mental narrative we're feeling it in the present moment moment so that might be
experiencing tightness in the chest or a dull ache at the pit of the stomach
or heat in the forehead tingling pressure we're feeling it from that lens
and we might notice what um uh what the the hindrance feels like in the mind also how is it coloring the
mind maybe there's an emotional tone or a mood that goes with it
you might even notice what sorts of thoughts are occurring without getting caught up in the narrative
but just seeing like oh wow there's a lot of thought production around this or the thoughts are kind of yelling or
they're maybe really quiet just seeing what's happening from the present moment view
so that's it recognize and feel and it's through this experience of
recognizing and feeling what's happening in the present when we're not transfixed by the object
that the mind is obsessing over that the mind and heart can register
oh this is suffering it actually hurts when i'm caught up in
this pattern of these hindrances and in the same way that the mind knows
if the hand touches a hot stove ouch that burns and we don't have to convince ourselves
to not touch a hot stove we just know that hurts i'm not going to touch a hot stove
the mind heart begins to learn that with the hindrances because it really feels the hindrances
fully it begins to learn ouch this hurts i'm not going to do that anymore
and we can see this in the way that the mind let go of doubt right it's like oh yeah i remember that one that hurts i'm
not going to touch that stove anymore i'm not going to do this doubt thing anymore and the system can learn to
release it and that's a really powerful and inspiring thing when the mind begins to
do this when the mind begins to let go of these patterns these hindrance patterns
okay so now i'll go through the hindrances individually to say a little bit more about each
and provide the antidotes so traditionally an antidote is a
medicine to counteract a point a poison and in this case with the hindrances the
antidotes are no different they are designed to counteract the the hindrance
and to say something about when we would use an antidote i remember learning about
all the antidotes and kind of being confused about how to practice with these things and when do i do one and
when do i just feel it and too much stuff so uh
what i would suggest is start with recognizing and feeling antidotes
are what can be applied when we're being overwhelmed by the hindrance and we can't just be mindful of it so we
start with being mindful of it and staying with it with feeling it getting to know it and it's only when we become
overwhelmed feels like too much that we can try something different that it's a good idea to change the channel and try
something new
so let's go into sense desire let's talk a little bit about that so other ways we might refer to this hindrance include
craving wanting the wish to acquire things longing
grasping sense desire is at work when we are longing for a cup of coffee
or when we are trying to make ourselves more physical physically beautiful or seeking
to go to uh gallery to have some visual pleasure
it's at work when there's fantasy about sexual or romantic desire
all different areas that can come up it's even comes up when we are craving for uh trying to repeat a blissful
meditation experience so as you know we have the five senses
hearing seeing touching tasting smelling in buddhism we have a sixth the mind so
there's these six senses so with sense desire
it's just that we're craving for pleasant experience at one of the six
senses so that's what's happening and it can happen at any of those senses it's the craving
for what's pleasant and agreeable to take place at any one of the given sense stores
if not all of them and often when we have free time in our life
say maybe a sunday afternoon we're often trying to fill that free
time with back-to-back pleasant sense experience there can be the illusion in our culture
that a happy life is one where we've been able to string and up string together back-to-back pleasant sense
experiences and avoid anything unpleasant
and generally what's at the heart of sense desire is a feeling that something could make
this moment better that this moment is insufficient and that happiness resides out at the next
pleasure the next pleasant experience and i i do want to note as i say this
because desire can get a pretty bad rap in buddhist circles that not all desires are problems
so there's the desire to be free from suffering the desire to be compassionate or
patient these are all wholesome desires then we can also have
what i might call innocuous desires like the desire to go for a walk outside or
to put on a sweater um these typically don't manifest as
hindrances and what shifts an innocuous desire into being a hindrance
is when we're gripped by it when we're preoccupied by it when it runs the show
so often desire it's it's as though it gets in the driver's seat and we're
in the passenger seat and it's taking us for a ride so kind of we're subject to the wishes of desire
but it is possible to hold sense desire lightly the dalai lama was
uh in germany and getting a tour of an abbey there and this was an abbey that was known for
producing cheese and fruit cake so the dalai lama is getting toured around to the different sites and
seeing all of the things and that night the dalai lama got to sit
down with the monks that toured him around and he was recounting his experience of
the tour and he shared that you know it was great but you know i kept being offered cheese
here's try this cheese try that cheese cheese cheese cheese but the whole time all i wanted was fruit cake
and of course upon saying that he threw his head back and laughed and laughed
and he held his his sense desire so lightly not owned by it in any way
really really at peace with it so how can we do that for ourselves how
can we meet our sense desire without distress or disappointment
[Applause] so we can do this practice of
recognizing that desire is present and feeling it in the body and when i
want to say something about feeling it in the body because something that's interesting about sense desire is it
often feels pleasant in the body when we think about it so for me if i think of something
enjoyable that i want often it has a sort of sparkle in the mind and that's a
indicator for me that sense desire is at work if i have that little sparkle of feeling enticed
by something
under the surface though what i've discovered as the mind has become more settled and
more peaceful is that the state of sense desire even though it's exciting there's an
excitement to it it's unsettled it's based in this feeling of lack or
insufficiency and that there's actually something much more peaceful the mind that is content
is much more peaceful and satisfying than the mind that is excited by sense
desire
so if you're having a hard time staying mindful of sense desire this is when you might consider an
antidote one of the antidotes for sense desire is
impermanence or in constancy so remembering that whatever it is that
we're reaching after will fade away in time and for me it can be helpful to remember
that even if i'm i get that object and i can keep it for a long time my enchantment with it will probably fade
away pretty quickly you may have had the experience of having something that you really want
and you finally get the new purchase and you're so excited and you have to have it and you it's finally here
and then a month later you hardly remember that you own it anymore the enchantment has disappeared
so remembering impermanence can be useful and in states of meditation actually
observing in constancy observing impermanence the arising and passing of things
in the present moment helps train the mind in the truth of inconstancy
and when we understand at a deeper level how everything is falling away and changing it's hard to be fooled by sense
desire so both reflecting on and observing impermanence
in real time is an excellent antidote for sense desire
and lastly this applies with all the hindrances
don't miss recognizing when they're absent so really let the mind register when
sense desire isn't present really enjoy the satisfaction there the
the lack of seeking so out on the backpacking trips
we didn't just fixate on the pools of water that were cloudy and covered over
but we really enjoyed the pools that were clear so let yourself be nourished by those
the second of our hindrances is ill will or aversion
this can manifest as anger disliking grief fear
resentment boredom etc the zen teacher leanne shut
talks about this hindrance as the terrible twos spelled t-o-o-s
so we can know aversion is happening when the mind is saying too messy too cold too many bugs too
itchy too ugly so if you if you notice that's happening a version might be happening inside
and then when we have the terrible twos that can turn into the terrible use
so uh you're too loud you're too distant you're too unprofessional so it can shift to
judging others right so these are all common ways that aversion can manifest
and just as with desire we can recognize oh this is a version
dropping the fixa and drop the fixation turning and looking inside and feeling
it and i think that a version holds a special place amongst the hindrances
so much so that i have a specific nickname for it i call it the tagalong
hindrance and that's because typically if any of the other hindrances are present
chances are aversion may be tagging along too and that's because the other the other
hindrances often not always but often manifest manifest as unpleasant in our system
and so naturally something unpleasant is there we want to get rid of it so there's the primary
hindrance of say restlessness and then an add-on a tag-along of a version with
it so just watch for this in your hindrance practice often when we can
see the aversion we can begin to reorient and learn to relate to the initial hindrance with more patience and
kindness so if the mind can't be mindful with
aversion then we go to our our antidote the classic antidote for aversion
is meta or lovingkindness and for me
if i'm feeling angry if i'm feeling aversion towards someone it's often not so accessible to send them loving
kindness so what i do is i send it to myself because if i'm angry chances are i'm
suffering i'm the one that needs that loving kindness in that moment so that's one
way you can bring you can replace the mind of anger with
well wishing
so the third hindrance is sloth and torpor and before going into this i want
to remind you that these next two are energetic states sloth interpret and restlessness one low energy one high
energy so sloth and torpor can manifest as fatigue drowsiness sleepiness dullness
and sloth typically refers to a mental sleepiness and torpor to a physical tiredness
i usually just think of them under the category of sleepiness
and that usually does the trick to be able to note sleepiness in one's practice
and this can come about for a variety of reasons sloth and torpor can come forth because we're genuinely tired we're
genuinely under stress or underslept stressed overworked and our body really
actually just needs to rest and there are other forms of sloth interpreter that can arise in meditation
such as as the mind tries to focus on something simple like
the breath we're not used to being
we're not used to having an experience where we're not entertained by our inner fantasies and aversions
by our exciting romance films or horror films
that play in the mind so as those start to dissipate sometimes the mind gets a little bored and falls asleep
there's yet a third type of sloth interpreter and it's defensive
sleepiness so this is when there's something difficult that's being experienced and the mind
does not want to feel it and so sometimes when that's in the system the mind puts
up this shroud so that we can dip out and not have to feel that difficult feeling
in my early retreats i had a lot of sleepiness i had a lot of the
the head jerking bucking bronco experience
and this was really unpleasant for me there was a lot of fighting and i remember this sort of kind of clenched
the teeth sort of energy trying to fight against my sleepiness
and what i learned after suffering significantly over my sleepiness
was that the difficulty of it was my resistance to it it was the tagalong hindrance of
aversion that was making sleepiness difficult and that sleepiness itself is
actually karmically neutral there's nothing bad about sleepiness
so the key with sleepiness is befriending it
and particularly if we can can continue to just be with the breath from a tired
place there's no problem it might not be the sharpest mindfulness you've ever had but that's okay
if it's a sleepy period of meditation we can just be sleepy buddha
no problem there and when we look at this basic instruction of recognizing and feeling
something i want to emphasize with the feeling part is that that aspect can have a little
curiosity or investigation in it and for sleepiness can be really helpful just to
turn up the volume a bit on the investigation turn up the volume a bit on the curiosity because those factors
of mind are energizing and that's actually the antidote to sleepiness is energy
so in this case when we're just feeling and kind of checking it out bringing this
this curiosity can be just enough energy to see what's happening and of course if
the mind is really really tired it's hard to investigate anything um
but if there can be just a bit of energy it can be really interesting and this
totally revolutionized my sleepiness practice so some of the things that i got curious
about which you might explore in your own sleepiness practice is
where is the epicenter of sleepiness in the body
and what i mean by that is where in the body is the most sleepy
so what i would do is i'd go looking to find the sleepiest spot and for me it was often behind one of my eyes
typically not both but behind one of my eyes would be the sleepiest spot and if i brought the attention there i'd fall
asleep but if i kind of hung out around it i could stay awake
or we might explore uh are we if we're falling asleep in meditation can we catch if we fall
asleep on an in-breath or an out breath or if we are somebody who's counting
breaths in our meditation one to ten what number are you falling asleep on
for me it was often like around somewhere in the six to eight range i'd go down
pretty repeatedly each time through so you can check these out in your own
practice and if there's enough brightness in the mind um you might be able to see some interesting things or see if you can
notice the moment the mind falls asleep this can all be really fun to explore
so as i mentioned the antidote to energy so perhaps a more
direct intervention or a little more extreme intervention if the mind's too sleepy for all that
is open the eyes stand up go for a brisk walk splash water on the
face the buddha all recommended these for people working with sloth and torpor
for me cooling down my body temperature if i'm warm and cozy in the hall in the
meditation hall i'll probably fall asleep so even if i'm a little on the uncomfortable cool side if i'm wearing
short sleeves in a cool haul i usually don't have sloth and torpor so
these are things you can play with oh and lastly i had mentioned that
defensive sleep if you're sitting a lot and there's
and you're falling asleep a lot and particularly on retreat if you're past the first several days of retreat and
you're still getting sleepy a lot and you're getting enough sleep you might just drop in the question
is there something underneath this is there something underneath this
and that has the potential to expose if there's something else going on
that sleepiness is shrouding trying to protect you from
okay the next is restlessness fourth hindrance
so with restlessness there can be an over abundance of energy
it's sometimes referred to as worry and flurry
and can come forth in a mental or physical manifestation
so mental restlessness can manifest in an agitated mind racing thoughts anxious thoughts
worrying and in the body it can be that sort of
can't sit still fidgety itching moving adjusting that can be
physical restlessness where i've experienced it getting home from a really busy day of work and the
momentum of the day makes it so i can i i can't stop almost like it's it's hard
to slow down because there's so much movement in the body
with restlessness it can be helpful to remember that this is a natural part of
being human the zen teacher and author mark lesser likes
to remind us that we are the descendants of the nervous apes
so all of the chilled out apes got eaten
and it was the nervous apes that made baby nervous apes
etc and here we are so don't be too hard on yourself
if uh if you have restlessness if you have anxiety in your life and practice
this is so normal
so the antidote the antidote for restlessness is calm or tranquility
so if you feel restless you can return to your meditation anchor if you're
meditating can return to your anchor say the breath or the soundscape but do so in a gentle way
in a way that invites the mind to rest what we're doing here is allowing the
mind to gravitate around a simple object
and this can be a refuge for the mind that's tangled up in what can be a high-energy agitated storyline so we're
moving from a complex object to a simple object and sometimes that can be very relieving
for some people bringing the attention to an anchor
can increase the energy though and if that happens can try giving the
mind a really wide pasture so that might be rather than focusing on
a small point in the body opening up to the soundscape so that there's a lot of room
for the energy in the body
and then another way is to if if there's restlessness is to connect with any calm
that may already be present so sometimes if i'm restlessness if the energy is really
wrapped up in the mind in a story line or maybe there's tightness in the chest
i might notice if there's calmness anywhere else in the body like maybe the feet feel pretty relaxed
or i might tune into any tranquility that's in the space around me
if i'm in a natural setting or a quiet room or a peaceful meditation hall
i might allow the mind to be soothed by the tranquility that's already here
and then as with all the hindrances when the mind is free of restlessness
when calm is present let yourself be nourished by that don't miss that
okay our last hindrance the fifth hindrance is doubt
this can manifest as doubt in the buddhist teachings does this really work
maybe i should have tried hinduism doubt in your teachers
doubt in the teachings doubt in yourself
can i really do this practice i'm not really any good at this
when doubt arises for the inside teacher greg scharf he says he feels like he's in the i'm
not very good at this club you may relate and as i shared in my story earlier of
self-doubt it can be a powerful visitor self-doubt can be a powerful visitor
something that can help with this is remembering that you don't need to
judge or assess your progress on the path
that's actually extra and not necessary
if we go to a guitar lesson for the first time
we don't expect to be a grammy-winning musician the next day
and yet somehow when we sit down in meditation we can have the feeling like oh
i'm supposed to be peaceful and calm and tranquil all the time so re readjusting our expectations can
be quite helpful the antidote to doubt is faith
another other words for faith are trust or confidence so faith doesn't resonate
for you these other words also work so can we trust that whatever
is arising is arising right on time
we are right on track can we trust the dharma can we trust the practice can we
have confidence in it if you struggle with doubt
build a daily faith practice this might involve reflecting on times
that the dharma has supported you remembering times that you've felt
that the dharma has benefited you in some way reflect on times that you've had
confidence in yourself and in these ways it can bolster the mind
for some it's taking refuge in buddha dharma and sangha and connecting with faith in the triple
gem that can bring faith so there's a lot of ways to do this you can borrow the faith of your
teachers if there's a teacher that you particularly admire and trust and maybe
you don't have a lot of faith but you can see that the practice is working in them you can borrow their faith
so have confidence in the practice by seeing how it's working in others
i saw a sign a while ago that said proceed as though success were
inevitable and i don't think people proceed in that way very often
so what would it be like in our practice to proceed as though success were
inevitable so those are the five hindrances
and i'll review the antidotes for you so of course we start with recognizing
what's happening and feeling it exploring it in the body and then if that is
isn't accessible then we turn to these these antidotes so for sense desire
it's reflecting on and observing impermanence it's one of the antidotes
aversion or ill will it's meta loving kindness practice
for sloth intorper it's energy for restlessness it's calm or
tranquility and for doubt it's faith so those are our antidotes
and as i come to a close here i want to say
how important it is that we have a friendly attitude to the hindrances
as we do this practice it's so easy to judge ourselves when hindrances are a
present so remember that it doesn't say anything
about you as a person or as a meditator if the hindrances come for a visit
it can help to remember that the buddha was visited with the hindrances
up through his night of awakening so these are going to be around for a
while so if they're going to be around for a while you know if we can think of these as roommates that we may be living with
forever that come and go from our house it could help to make friends with them to learn how
to be with them in a skillful way
i like to think of the hindrances as a valuable messenger that's come to teach
us can we respect our hindrances as teachers teaching us how to love our
life our role is just to meet them
not as a diversion from our path but as the next stepping stone on the path
itself and when we meet a hindrance with
recognition curiosity patience kindness we're simultaneously
growing a wholesome state so it doesn't matter that a hindrance is present if
we're bringing wholesome states to it that's what we're cultivating if we're bringing mindfulness to it then we're cultivating
mindfulness so we can simultaneously work with the hindrance
and cult cultivate these really beautiful qualities so they're really an opportunity to grow the heart
the hindrances are ultimately the medium by which we wake up
so in a way learning to be with the hindrances without rejection
is a radical act of inclusion it's a way we can make ourselves whole
so there's no part excluded everything here is allowed and welcome
so i'd like to close with a poem by izumi shikibu a female japanese poet
from the 10th century it's a short poem it goes like this
watching the moon at dawn solitary mid sky
i knew myself completely no part left out
so let's sit together for a moment
watching the moon at dawn solitary
mid sky i knew myself completely
no part left out
[Music] thank you for your kind attention
as it's a little after 10 45 we won't have time for questions this morning
but if you have any questions for me after the program ends i'll be outside
and i'm happy to chat with you for a few moments so thank you so much for your practice
this morning i appreciate you being here thanks so much