good morning everybody my name is Nancy yamahiro
I was your check-in person today I'm also a board member here at IMC
I'm warm welcome to all of you thank you for your practice
thank you for being here and a warm welcome to Our Guest today
um for those of you that don't know um
they're all from a group called grip an acronym for guiding rage into power
which is an intensive year-long trauma healing and accountability program
serving about 500 incarcerated people each year in California state prisons many folks serving life
sentences for serious or violent crimes
it is a model for restorative justice in the state and I would argue around
the country in the last 10 years more than 1200
students have graduated from grip of those 525 or 528 sorry have been
released and come home to their communities there were
recidivism rate is less than one percent in other words a success rate of 99
percent I'd like to introduce Kim gross Moore
who is a student of IMC and the Sati
Center chaplaincy Program she subsequently trained as a group
facilitator and then became the executive director in 2019.
with the support of IMC she led the expansion of grip to the correctional
training facility in Soledad where she continues to
facilitate today a strong believer in the principle the first Revolution is internal
she considers meditation and the Dharma as the foundation of her work for
justice in the community and I'll turn it over to Kim and let her
introduce our other guests and welcome
it's okay to take off my mask is that right to speak that we can okay thank you
thank you Nancy for the introduction and good morning
I'm going to introduce my colleagues briefly and then say a few words so I'm so happy to be here uh with a team of
folks from grip my actually my boss
PJ BluRay I is on the board of directors of grip and he's here with us today he's
been here before Bernard Moss is a senior facilitator with grip on our staff
and uh chewy Cortes is a facilitator as
well facilitated for several years inside Avenal State Prison and now lives in San Francisco
and they'll have a chance to share more of their stories in a minute but I'm
just so happy to be back here I as I was driving up this morning my
so my daughter just started high school and last night was the homecoming dance
and all the anticipation and flurry and nervous excitement of that as I was
driving up her I realized oh this is feels like a homecoming for me to be here it's uh it's been
about four three at least three maybe four years since grip was here at IMC
and we really do feel like this is a home for us and so I first just really
want to thank you all and express the gratitude that is in my heart and that
we feel when we come here because Gil and the IMC community so many of you who
have come up to visit grip at San Quentin or down at Soledad or elsewhere or have just been supporters over the
years is really just wonderful and I don't think grip would be where it is today
without the support of this community so much gratitude and thank you
and I feel that sort of nervous energy and excitement of homecoming as well so just being here and uh when I I actually
first met grip learned about grip when Jacques verdant the founder brought some
folks to sit up here and I was sitting there and that was my first introduction
to grip and it was a transformative experience for me and I was in the
chaplaincy training program and got the chance to go up and visit the program in San Quentin and then
train as a facilitator and then help to bring grip into CTF Soledad where I
still facilitate so as as Nancy said she said everything
that I was going to say about what we are and the stats if you're interested in the data of impact that we we have
been quite successful in supporting folks inside the state prisons to turn
their lives around and and then become peace makers in the community and we're going to share some stories today that's
what we do best is share stories that's the real impact that we have so I'm going to turn it over in a minute to my
colleagues really to take it from here and then we're hoping that we'll have a little bit of time after after some
story sharing to actually share an activity that we do inside the prisons
that builds a sense of common humanity and empathy it's called struggles in a
hat and so we we might ask for a few volunteers to participate with us to do
a little activity so I think maybe I'll just one other thing I'll say before inviting my
colleagues to speak is that our curriculum is grounded in a course book
that Jacques Verdan the founder wrote and it's called leaving prison before you get out
I think that's really kind of the common cause we have here with IMC that there's
an understanding that we're on a common Journey we're on a we're engaged in a
common practice of freeing ourselves from whatever that prison is between our
ears right and whether you're incarcerated or whether you're in you know free
ostensibly geographically and able to come to a place like IMC there is still
the kind of practice that we all are doing to learn how to free ourselves
from suffering and be able to be of service be able to open our hearts and
uh and experience true compassion and love and connection in the world
so much of what I do as a facilitator in grip is really about that shared Journey
my own practice my own healing work that I do and accountability work that I do
in tribe in community inside the prison with others who are
engaged in that same practice so we consider it very much a shared and common Journey we
it it is a program that's mindfulness based we bring tools and practices into
the prisons but really what I hope today will be about is an
understanding and an experience of how much of the Dharma is coming out from
the prisons as well the wisdom and the experience and the the uh the living
examples of transformation that we can learn from folks that have been
incarcerated so with that I'm going to invite I think I'm going to start from that end and
invite Chewie to start and then make our way this way
good morning I want to share with you guys
how grip has impacted me but before that I'll briefly share where
I was before group before grip I was 15 years incarcerated at the time
and I was in the shoe what is known as isolation in
prison not knowing why I was angry not knowing why
I was so prone to be reactive and when I got introduced to grip
I did so by a commissioner of the parole board she says you might want to look into
some programs she directed me on where to find these resources and
the first program I participated in in 2016 I learned about anger
but it was still leaving a lot of gray areas with educating myself about myself
and in 2017 I came across grip
and I remember getting interviewed by the founder jocks and he asked me why do
you want to want to be part of grip and I said well I've done some work but
there are still gray areas and and I don't understand why I'm so angry all the time
why I'm so reactive I spent 10 years in isolation you don't
spend 10 years in isolation because you're a good person right and for me
what grip allowed me through the curriculum it's not just curriculum it's
it's a guide in in helping us educate ourselves about ourselves through the
curriculum and what I was able to learn I was able to learn about the trauma
and understand how the trauma was manifesting itself in my life
which was in a dysfunctional it was a dysfunctional expression
and the work through the exercises that I was able to do I was able to learn of how powerful
this trauma was just learning about the amygdala a part
of the brain that is always on alert and it's like a security guard
you know Vigilant paranoid so when I started learning about that I
started seeing myself and that that's me I'm very reactive
and when I started understanding where these triggers were were coming from
what trauma was uh connected to then it allowed me to actually
acknowledge it make peace with it start to make peace
with it heal and have compassion for myself
then it opened up the door for me to have compassion for my father for my mother
and what it did is it replaced the anger the resentment that I had for them with
empathy and compassion because I was able to have empathy and compassion for myself
so the work that I've been able to do in grip alongside other men
has been very rewarding has been something that uh it's been life-changing
and uh it's not only for me it's I I'm witnessing these men in there have uh
those realization moments those realization moments that
it's like a light turning on right and and when that light turns on there's accountability
there's complete ownership and there's transformation I'm an example of that
so I'm just so grateful and honored to be here thank you guys I know I have to
share the mic here otherwise I'd I'd like to be speaking in the full time but I can't
so with that I thank you guys
I need this I think I'm out here I can talk in this okay okay
uh hello everybody my name is Bernard Moss um so uh this is my third time here so uh
thank you for welcoming me back here um so my journey
um I spent 28 years in prison California State Prison uh was convicted in 1988 of
of crime of attempted murder um in 2002
I arrived at San Quentin and I met Jacques for then and I participated in his first program
called catargio which was that San Quentin and I just thought it was the
most silly thing in the world to sit in a room and to meditate and to just talk
about your feelings and and your emotions and I would not bite in I I
wasn't a buy-in for for the group and but I stuck with it because he stuck with me and uh some years later 2011
we transformed over to grip and I was chosen to be one of the first
participants to participate in the grip program and I sat in and I went through the
program and I graduated and uh after graduation they came to me
and they asked me to come back and facilitate and I said me you know like really yeah and then and they like yeah
so I was like yeah sure I'll try it so I came back and I started facilitating
grip but the tools that I learned from the grip program are invaluable
we talk about when our tools is called Ceta practicing our Sensations emotions
our thoughts and our actions and being able to connect and recognize those things and it was something I never was
able to do before I was sitting here this morning and when I was asked to guide the meditation I immediately
realized how nervous I was right I'm like I'm gonna guide a meditation with people
who meditate all the time and I'm nervous so once I started got into
meditation and and we got silent I said oh I forgot so many things right and I'm
sitting here and I'm like well this is a sign of meditation but I really want to say some more things but I'm not going
to say anything I'm just going to sit here and go with it right but yeah but uh thank you all for just bearing with
me with that I appreciate that but um yeah um yeah the the this has taught me how to
reconnect with me right and and to be my true authentic self
we sit in a room for 52 weeks right meet
once a week for two hours for 52 weeks and we really get to cover four areas of
stopping our violence developing emotional intelligence cultivating mindfulness and really
understanding how our violence affects our community our victims and
the survivors of our violence and it's so so powerful right and just meditating
and just sitting is so it's so is this one of the main
tools that help us connect with our inner self and our inner being
and it brings so much peace and harmony to people who are inside of violent
environment right so you have all of the people from different gangs and
different cultures and you know different races who sit in this room but
it's a room full of peace and Harmony right and we sit there with each other for some of my class I facilitate here
on the outside now and one of my classes is two hours long and then I do a weekend class that's eight hours long
and this just peace and Harmony throughout that day with each and every person that sits in that room and it's
powerful and I I I can't stop doing this work because I sit in that room and at
the end of the course I have men who have sat on death row for 20 years and
are now on the main line of the prisons who tell me
after doing this work I feel again I honestly have feelings and emotions
again and I can never hurt another human being and that is so powerful I can never see
myself not doing this work and I can never see myself ever doing harm or
hurting anyone ever again so I I just attribute that to grip right and and
being a part of this program it's it's it's life-changing and and I think
people like Kim and jock that come into the institutions and they provide programs like this and IMC for
supporting uh people like myself and PJ and Chewie who who
who made bad decisions in our life when we were young and now we got an opportunity to participate in a program
like this to help us go back to being our true authentic selves the people we were truly intended to be before our
lives in prison and and it's it's it's it's yeah it's it's just something to be
so grateful for and now I get an opportunity to be a grandfather and a
husband and a father and an uncle and you know it's something that I never
never imagined you know and I get to make all these new friends people that we used to sit on the yard and we used
to look at each other and want to kill each other and now we get to be best friends and you know today me and two we
met each other for the first time personally and we've been on Zoom calls before but today we first met each other
personally for the first time we drove over today from San Francisco and we were just talking in our stories are
just so similar and you know but we wouldn't have realized that on a prison yard before grip right because we
probably would have been pinned against one another or you know we wouldn't have that opportunity to just sit down and
get to know each other on a personal one-on-one basis and like we're both humans right so programs like grip help
unite people and to realizing their Humanity before they're released from
the belly of the Beast right so uh which I just want to thank all of you just who
support efforts like this and programs like this yes so thank you Edward
Airlines yeah and uh yeah it's just powerful and I appreciate you all so with that I'm going to shut up also and
I'm just going to pass the mic over to uh PJ thank you Bernard
I'm not sure what I'm going to talk about actually no I think about it
um I guess I have a lot of like it's a lot of stuff like just flies
through my mind doing a meditation a lot of stuff comes up um I want to say thank you all for a lot of gratitude
to be back here again I was here four years ago I think it was my first few months out
for my IC Attention Center after serving 19 years in prison I was detained by ice
and I was there fighting my case they were trying to deport me to a country I've never been to before where
I have no relative where I have no ties and um it was a very scary time and I think I found a lot of comfort and
support when I got here in balance so my life has changed a lot since then and covet happened and just the world
has changed in this really you know like brought me to a different direction and
I'm so happy that I'm at least at this point to be able to do this work again I
have to actually live it right I think I guess what I want to say is um one day I want to share is some
this thing that I always it's in the group curriculum that I've always been part of my life and I was born into it by this um called
amorphity which is love your faith and um as a as a Buddhist practice
practitioner I grew up into Buddhism so my mom all Buddhists my dad are Buddhists a whole culture is Buddhist
I'm Cambodian and so Buddhism is just not a practice that we do but it's a way of our life I've been born into it
what's in a culture it's in the language it's in a mannerism even in some of the food that we eat and um my mom always told me you know
like she always shared a story about how she survived the genocide with the Khmer Rouge and the committing Master
genocide she shared about the hardship she grew up what it was like for her as a farmer's daughter and then um
you know crawled through landmines from for hundreds of miles getting to the border of Thailand so that
so that I can live and so my brother can live and so she can live I was born in
Thailand so I wasn't born yet at the time but um
yeah and I think like coming to the United States resettling you know feeling the hardship of living
the polished community a lot of violence a lot of gangs experiences school shootings and school
you know just bullying that led me to a joining gangs myself and then
getting to incarceration as one of the youngest juvenile lifers in the correctional system I was 14 at the time
and um and I've like gone through all this hardship and I've always had this thing in my my heart it's like
my mom always say like you know you cannot like when I say more for tea I love your face he said it always sticks
to me she said um like you can always make things worse for yourself you know
like you could make things better for yourself now um make the best of what you got no matter what it is
or you can make it worse and then I think about her I think about her like in the refugee camp
you know looking from sun up to sundown starving and then getting beaten at the
same time and having to witness the people you love get tortured and killed in front of you I'm like
how do I love that kind of Faith you know is this it's a really hard thing to swallow until you actually live through
it and I remember you know sitting in prison um I was in the shoe at one point and um
I was really hot and I was like I feel like I was dying because there's no air conditioning it was like summertime and
I was for concrete wall and it was so miserable I couldn't sleep you couldn't like I was I think it was
too sleep deprived for some for some point and my my soulmate my best friend
um was in the top bunk and he was like dude just so let's stay on the floor you know and
we try to float the cell but they fix the um the water so you can't really
you know one other thing we used to do when they get those so hot you flood the cell and it cools the cell down but then
they they um some people will float to sell and made a mess and so they would shut the water off so then you can't
really get cool right so and I remember like that's in in my head
and I um when I went to ice I had the exact same experience I was you know after 19 years
of incarceration so my journey with grip was that I I um was I had an opportunity
I was a young young man you know like trying to prove myself I was really afraid you know in prison because I was
one of the youngest person there right I I knew it I knew I was young I knew people you know look at me a certain
ways and I don't have like same kind of status I don't want no one else have so I would always try to
assert myself more than the next person in front of me and I'll try to make myself bigger scarier you know like
um that was my mentality and it's because I ideally I think that if people are afraid of me and people think that
I'm not a easy person to victimize they're going to leave me alone right and they're going to show me some
respect and so I lived that lifestyle for many years in prison and um one of the elders actually told me man
you need like that's not you like we can see it like it's not even with you you
know I think I think it shows in my um upbringing from I guess part of my um
being with my mom has early made me a better good person and I never see that and I never thought myself to be a good
person until I went to a program um it's called the red World program and
actually I was a Chapel I was talking to chap at the time and um one of the Native American
practitioner who invited me to a ceremony and so he said like man we started
talking he said man Cambodian your guy says like indigenous way is similar to ours
you know like I really wanted you to come to a ceremony and it changed my life forever because I sat in the ceremony
and it was dark I was in a nippy it's called the lodge and um you can't really see nothing right and it's between you
and the Creator between you and Mother Earth between you and yourself you know like um no one dares to judge you no one
there to see you and they will sing this really cultural spiritual song and it just like really Echoes it through your
whole body you can feel yourself and the the hot rocks and the steam you know
it's almost like a sauna but the steam which is really like it represents the breath of Grandfather which is supposed
to cleanse you right and so I was I was felt cleansed I felt the hardship of the heat was over 100 you know 140 easy and
um coming out of the lodge out there like maybe a couple hours of being in there
and I felt I suppose I felt tired I'm supposed to have felt drained and exhausted but I
came out of there like a new person I felt I was Reborn and and everything everything that that
I in my life that didn't make no sense all started like crashing in on me and and all the teaching my mom had taught
me all the stories you told me about her experience about where our people come from and I struggled all came back to me
which I have forgotten all those years because I was so deep in my own pain that I never really looked at no one
else and uh and so when I was coming for this renewal this moment of
my life I just I was really open now I was really open to anything like because then I was so close I had a big old wall
in front of me I was hurt so many times I was abandoned so many times that I didn't
accept anything right any any like opportunity and so I didn't really love my experience like I never made it better I
made it worse the whole time and so when I was invited to do this
program um from through through the the split Lodge they were like hey we have a red World program we want you to attend with
us you know and we'll just do some healing and so I joined the program and it was
strange because I was youngest I sat there on a circle with eight men been in
prison more than three decades have done everything in their life um the manageable and they were like so
vulnerable you know they were sharing so deeply about their experience and everything that they have said I have lived through and I feel like
like accumulate in so many ways it's almost like a cycle you know this is cycle of how can you be so much older than me
and still live the same cycle I have gone through and I think what I connect at that time is not the experience but
our emotion our feelings you know like I felt what you felt you know and I think I could relate to you and I remember my
facilitator and just a moment that just totally changed my life forever and made who I am today
um my facilities shared how he lost his daughter to crime he lost both of his daughter
and he was crying he was shaking he was reliving the moment and I connected with his pain and the thing I
connected with his pain because I was so open and I've clicked with his pain and I started connected with other people in
my life's pain and I connected to the person of harm and she's asking her family
and um I was ashamed you know first time I felt like I did the sexy and pain to someone
else's that I did you know to my facilitator my friend Martin at the time who was sharing this
and it rocked me to the core and I just was so guilty I was so ashamed and I was
at that moment I think I pledged my life to like never allow anyone in my life to ever experience that again and so I
dedicated my life at that moment to the change and I walked away from the prison job pretty much walked away from the
prison yard almost started started a full-scale riot because people were like you're not person politic you're not you can't go
by yourself you can't do what you want to do but um I had a lot of Elders who thought that if I was sincere and they cared for
me enough to give me a chance and they told me like we'll give you a chance and you want to try to harm you in this yard we will
respond accordingly and and I was allowed you know to practice continue practicing the Native American spiritual
circle on ways and then their their ways were so related to mind that it allows
me to find like horror again my who I am as a person and I started to see myself I remember I'm a good person like what
happened and that Journey you know led me to restorative justice
I went back to school I became a counselor and I started doing a lot of work in the prison and then my counselor
was like man you should go to San Quentin because there's so much opportunity like you could grow more and
and at the time they were doing like a prison realignment they were changed in the facility we changed the process of
how things are working and I ended up going to go to San Quentin and that's when I met job you know my first first month and
actually I was I was in the program but because I just got off the bus running and I was
I was like I wanted to learn I would have to say she would desire to learn to grow because I found myself for the
first time I knew who I am I knew where I wanted to do I knew where I wanted to go and I just want to do it
and I want to get involved in everything so I can learn I feel like if I have more knowledge I have more tools I can
provide more services and I can do more right because I didn't not I didn't know and um and and I think one of the
facility Kevin Penn at the time he was um he was the violent prevention facilitator who was working with Jacques
before this was before we would call it grip and um Ken was like dude
like you have a great spirit man I can feel it when I'm around you he's like you should come to class with me to to
you know to sit with me in a class and say why would I want to do that he said well because we teaching people how to
be Peacemaker you know and and we're teaching people you know it's related with domestic
violence but we also want to teach people how not to do violence and how to like prevent violence so he said I think
you would be good for to be one of the facilitators so I invite you to come and just sit with me and find out so I came
through class and I see Jacques with his hat I thought it I'd kind of laughed inside
of my my mind because he reminded me of the guy crocodile Gundy and I was like
what is this guy have to offer right he's this white guy come over and he's you know like gonna offer me some
knowledge about um being be a peacemaker and it was so strange because I talked
to him he talked to me it was like the first time like this dude is so calming
you know I was like nervous but I was like excited and I was like just curious but he just like talking to me and you
know just he just calmed my nerve right away he's like so welcoming and then I sat in the circle and I was really quiet
and I just watched shop the whole time and the way he taught the classes and I
at that moment I realized this is what I want to do and that's the person I need to follow
that I need to take note from and so Jacques started talking about the curriculum we started teaching about
grip and about the ways and a lot of the stuff that when I think about grip I think about a way of life you know a lot
of stuff that came back to me you know about the more fatigue you know like I remember you know just sitting there and just
meditating and just thinking about man I can't believe my life has gone from you
know from a kid who was bullied who was spit on who was pushed around who was shot at on multiple occasion first for
being Asian and then they're being different and to a prison yard and now I'm in the
class and I'm teaching and there was a it's just so so real I'm like this is this can't be right and and
then I started to really think about that more in depth and I started to meditate on it and I just
realized it was my energy I willed it to happen you know like my mom said like love your faith you know make the best
of what you got and put that out in the world because you can always make it worse or you can make it better and I think your energy my energy was was
creating this environment for me and and I was able to do the work you know and I'm able to
touch people's heart and able to make so many friends and naturally you know minus minus the the harm I've created if
someone asked me would you go back to prison and live your life all over again I would say yes the reason why is because I've met so
many beautiful people through that Journey I will not be here with Bernard or with Kim and I would not have met Chewie I would
not have like met jock and I would not have met a lot of people that I loved today that called my friends and my
brothers who have gone through and I think I think my life was forged through the fire and hardship
and I think it was forage before me
my mom my people
so I became very proud who I am where become
and I'm proud that I could sit with you all
be vulnerable share deeply and just appreciate the moment you know
I can never do that before in my life so I think like when I look back in my
life and I think about my journey I mean I'm still stuck in Immigration I'm still dealing with the court process
but despite all that I think this beauty you know I think there's Beauty and growth and beauty and and going through
like they said that the lotus flower grows were very beautiful but it goes from very dark muddy place
so a big grip our work is beautiful I think
I mean we build leaders and teachers so so far everyone I know who graduated from grip who's out now it's doing great
thing in the world and I think they're they're doing great things because not just the tools that they got from grip but because
they grow some of the transformation and I think they have changed transformed their own Journey their own life so
I just love your faith I think that's kind of
my teaching today I'm worth a tea thank you
maybe we can just take a minute one of the things we do in grip is we put one hand on the heart and one hand on the
belly and it's a way that we hold the emotion in the room together
because we know when one person is doing the work we all are doing the work so
thank you PJ for sharing your journey that we all are holding with you
and thank you Bernard and Chewie also for sharing your stories
do we have time to do um how much more time do we have ten
seven minutes Bernard can we do a yeah a very quick version okay all right so I'm
gonna pass up so um can I ask for maybe four volunteers there's one
and this will be real quick
and one more thank you so uh
so this exercise is called struggles in a hat anybody else need a pen okay and what we do is so we get people
together in the room and they don't know each other they don't trust each other oh Abraham okay
and they don't know each other they don't they don't they don't trust each other they don't know each other but we
have to find a common Bond so do an exercise called struggle and a hat so we ask people to write down
something that they're struggling with currently and they write it on a piece of paper so
if you can write down something in your life that you're struggling with and it can be anything
and just think for a second and write it on the piece of paper and then just ball up that piece of
paper I mean my my head under your chair all right
okay thank you and don't put your name on it anything
so what we're going to do we're going to drop them in the Hat and and we're going to go back around and you're going to pull it out and you're gonna read it
and we're going to ask you if you ever struggled with that how you
dealt with that if you've never dealt with that situation how would you
personally deal with it by not giving advice but just talking
about how you as an individual would deal with that situation and uh and just using I statement if I
had if I had was encountered with this situation I would and that's as simple as this uh
this exercise is so so you're going to put your you're going to put your struggle in the Hat
and then you're gonna pick out somebody else you're going to pick somebody else and speak as if it's yours right
so just ball it up you can ball it up or fold it yeah there you go and just drop it in thank you and then we'll come back
around and you'll pull somebody else's out if you pull your own out drop it back in
and we'll do it real quick and this is a way that we kind of build
a bond in our circles to let people know that we're alike
right we're not as much we're not so much different than we think we are we've been sitting on this prison yard
looking at each other pinning each other against one another wanting to harm each
other kill each other stab each other but you're just like me you go through
the same things I go through oh I can trust you right our our cultures are
somewhat the same we we you know we come from the same place right we're all human and this is a a real way of
building a bond within our tribes and this is what we call our circles we call our circles tribes and this is one of
the first steps to building that tribe and building that Bond within that tribe
all right and you could uh whoever like to go
first can just say your name and and read the struggle that you pulled out of the Hat
okay thank you yes [Laughter] and that's how much I appreciate you all
I'm missing the Raider game right now
so whoever would like to go first you can read the struggle
will I go first okay there you go it used to say your name and read it out my name's Alan
and the card says worrying about my health conditions
um yeah I'm getting I'm getting older so there seems to be a lot of
a lot of little things that come up and I can imagine that they're a lot worse
than they might be and it's not only is it worrisome that uh
they uh um will affect my the way I live
and and be painful and but also financially I often I really
get afraid that you know something if something's really bad enough it could ruin me you know because you know it's
very it's very difficult to pay for medical care so I actually avoid
going to the doctors and I try to manage most of what I can on my own and uh
and not worry about it too much but it's not always easy thank you and I I also struggle with
that thank you thank you someone would like to read the next one
yeah okay all right
yeah mine says saying goodbye to someone I love
so I when I saw it I wasn't really sure what it meant does it mean that
someone broke up with you and you're ending your relationship with them or someone you love is dying
or moving away and I guess my response would be different for whatever the
situation is but if someone I loved was dying I would just want to let them know how much they
meant to me and make sure that I told them how much I love them and what they've added to my
life because I think it's really important to be real with people
if it was someone that was dumping me I guess
um I would just it would be done internally I might tell them the truth
depending on how safe it felt but otherwise I would just appreciate them
in my head and maybe even I'm taking this course called a year to
live and one of the things you do is people that you have unfinished business with you meet them in your head
they may not be alive or they maybe you may not be able to talk to them and you tell them what they meant to you so to
me that was like a really amazing process because you're able to do the healing around it without actually
having to talk to the person if they're not available for you so I guess that's what I would do all right thank you
beautiful I will read the next one yeah right right behind you
I just retired I'm struggling how to live the rest of my life in a way that
is true to to my beliefs to make peace
EFI if this was something that I am facing
I would drop the question to my mind
and wait for it to come to me and so I would say to myself
how can I live a life that reflects truth and integrity about
my beliefs how can I make peace
and then the last one foreign
a yearning for mothers to have a voice to make herself known to
people who care about her and there's one word I couldn't read but
I think that's the gist of it um I think for me the key to
helping people have a voice
is to is to listen um which I've learned
over the years is is not as easy as it seems
you know to become a good listener but I think that if
um you can listen deeply to somebody and respond in a way that makes them
feel heard that will give them voice and uh
and strength yes so that's that's my thought yeah thank
you and I appreciate that yeah just being hurt and and appreciated is so powerful so thank you all Just for
participating I know we're running short on time and I want to let everyone get to where they need to go so just thank
you for participating in that and that's just one of the ways that we build a
community in our tribes and just show how people that we all go through some of the same struggles in life and
hopefully some of you all can relate to those struggles and see how it relates to our lives thank
you I just wanted to thank you all for being
here today and for sharing and being so open with us we really appreciate it
um Abraham runs a group here that supports grip and so I wanted to give
him a chance to yes just see me after all of this if you
want to do some volunteer work around the grip program
thank you we'll also be having a tea out in the parking lot set up some chairs if
you'd like to sit around I don't know what your time frame is if you're available but
um there we can get hot tea and take it outside and there's chairs out here in
the hall that we can take out and put in a parking lot
so thank you everybody thank you for your practice
[Applause]