hello everyone and it's a
auspicious and wonderful occasion to come together both to a group of people
meditating meditating together is always uh suspicious to
reflect on the dharma is auspicious to spend a week appreciating
the body the valid tremendous value of finding a way to
wake up into the body and maybe different ways than the karmic body that we often live in
but to know the other possibilities that maybe allow us to respect it in a deep way appreciate it
to consider the miracle of it and uh and now coming to this day
talking about the liberated body to this body that in a certain way
we can say has cared for us for our lifetime we can return the gift
and provide it with freedom the liberated body
and so
to free the body from our attachments to free our body from our
judgments to free your body from our desires
and to allow it to be
and to allow it to express itself to be itself from the
inside out in the sense that from what emerges from within the body
not what's projected on it from the mind and
wondrous so to assume a
posture of the for this body that
maybe expresses the dignity and value of the body
assume a posture that independent of how you feel perhaps
gives a chance for your body to feel present
respected
dignified and valued
here in this body with taking a posture for this body to
be rooted here in this place to inhabit
this time and place as if
not as if with the idea that it belongs here
no shame no diminishment no
self-effacing allowing this natural
animal body we have to have as much rights to be alert and
present in a nice way as a deer alert
to the great view across a grassy meadow
here and to gently close your eyes
and sometimes if it was comfortable for you to close your eyes closing the eyes as a way of
transitioning to being
connected to the body's experience of itself
here
so
and the body thrives on oxygen that breathes in
and carbon dioxide that it exhales and taking a few gentle
luxurious deeper breaths to bring in the oxygen
and exhaling along exhale
to release that carbon dioxide which is no longer
needed for this body
breathing in and breathing out
letting breathing return to normal
and taking a back seat relationship to your breathing
without being a backseat driver allow the breath now to breathe itself
and if that's not possible be okay with how it is
be relaxed about whatever way you're breathing
whether you are controlling your breathing or or
allowing the breath to breathe itself either way
the important work of the breathing of
the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide still happens
the purpose of breathing happens regardless of your role of
and then seeing if you can release
the tensions of your body the ways in which the mind
makes the work of the body a little bit more difficult entangled
mixed up with the body to release the tension of the shoulders
release the tensions of the belly
releasing any holding tightening in the thighs the legs
releasing any holding in the small of your back
softening relaxing the hands maybe adjusting a little bit how the
hands are so that the hands are more at ease
relaxing the muscles of the face
relaxing relaxing the mind
thinking mind in such a way
that the thinking mind is not interfering so much with the body
part of the gift of relaxing the thinking mind is the way in which that might free up
the body from the tensions and the pulls and
pushes activations that come with the activated mind
softening the grip on your thinking
relaxing the force that goes along with thinking
and then settling into your body
setting settling into your breathing
trusting the body to breathe itself
entrusting yourself to the care of the body
allowing your thinking mind
to soften
lighten up
release itself as you release yourself into
the continuity of one breath after another
breathing
so
and if it's possible see if you can free the body
from your thinking and judgments and attachments
ideas of what should be and marvel at
whatever way your body is
it's an amazing result of
an evolution of animal life on this planet
the amazing window we
have into the animal body
so much of it which we share with other mammals and animal animals
and this is the one that we have to experience from the inside
maybe gazing upon it like a naturalist gazing upon
the deer and the animals and wandering around in the woods
with an eye out for [Music] liberating the body
from your attachments
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to first say that liberation from suffering liberation from clinging
attachments is the liberation that buddhism most
emphasizes for each of us however it's helpful to consider
that it isn't so much that you will be liberated
when you're liberated you won't care so much about whether or not you're liberated
but what you will care about is that you're liberating everybody else
from you you're freeing everyone else from your
attachments your projections your bias
your judgments just as you're liberating your body
from all those so we can free others
allow everyone else the opportunity to live
independent of any influence from attachment and
clinging from us
may our liberation be a way of liberating others
from any clinging and holding in resentment and hate and envy and
jealousy desires that we're caught up in
may our practice lead us to giving freedom
to all beings may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
so
so then we come to the last talk in this five-part series on
the different ways to experience our body the kaya
and that the experience we have of our body is very much influenced
by our states of mind activities of mind our thoughts our judgments our attachments
and and as those shift and change then
the experience of the body changes as well and when we practice
when the different kinds of states and ways the mind works while we meditate
can give us a different experience of the body which experience is the true experience
of the body you know is is the one that you're most commonly
the most the most common way you feel your body you know your body is that the how you really are the true body
in fact um i think that uh there's no basis for
deciding that the karmic body is the accurate body uh or the you know the real body
it's accurate enough as a karmic body but it's that's what it is it's uh
experiencing the body through the lens or through the mind states that's caught in the world of carmine
as the mind becomes free of that world uh relaxes settles in
then sometimes we start feeling the the joy body
and wonderful feelings of suffusing joy or well-being
contentment and as practice deepens then the
tranquil body becomes more evident and the bodies is very peaceful equanimous
and as mindfulness develops we have the insight body
the body has experienced uh when through observation or perception
that's that's very present very attentive but freed of
the labels ideas concepts we overlay on top of experience
and part of the value of seeing free of the all the concepts and ideas
and seeing more of the stream and the flow of the body is to loosen up the
attachment to body attach into self from relationship to the body and all attachments
and as we release our attachments as clinging and grasping and
striving and resisting judging and bias and fear and hate
finally quiet down the experience of the body changes dramatically
and we can have uh the liberal experience of the liberated body
and and the liberated body is the body that's not entangled in the
mind the experience of liberating liberated body is a little bit a product of the
mind but it's the product of the mind free non-clinging at ease peaceful
and so the result is that the body feels much more at ease it feels lighter
it feels more refreshed it doesn't have to live with the weight and the stress
of the puppeteer the mind which is constantly maybe thinking and reacting and
being afraid being desirous being angry and all the ways that kind of
seeps into the body certainly in muscles being tense
tight but also in all kinds of chemicals that the body releases stress chemicals and things that
releases into the body from stressful activities of the mind things of the mind
and so as the body gets freed of all this it tends to have a feeling of of more
unity of flow of ease a certain kind of
delight joy lightness the weightlessness that way that kind of
grace goes with it it just feels like there's almost like grace to move an arm
or to walk or do anything
maybe partly because it's all just kind of a wonder a surprise a delight
it's uh and to be present for all that
the um the liberated body
is one where we don't impose on the body
all the then issues of identification me myself and mine this is who i am
we don't put on the body expectations that should be different or judgments ideas
that interfere with the natural functioning of the body a liberated body is a body that has
certain kind of harmony to it and a body that
all the parts of it as they are are just fine as they are
in and of themselves if a few days ago i injured my finger a
little bit and and
you know i kind of would like it to heal properly and it is it's not as a small little cut
but my finger doesn't mind my finger doesn't know
that it should be any different it's a just a natural way in which this world exists this moment that there's a
finger with a cut in it that uh from the point of view of our body and
itself whether we're bald i have long hair or thin hair or
curly hair or kinky hair or straight here
it's all just fine it's all just from the inside out it
just is what it is just like you would look at a at a tree and you wouldn't say well that
branch is all wrong that it's the angle in which it's coming off the trunk or it's twisted or bent in a
certain way it's just all the way that nature works and the way richer grows and
it can all kind of a marvel so to give that kind of freedom to the body and let the body be the body let it
be the natural event that it is that we don't identify this is my body
and we don't define ourselves by it and the same time we care for it
it is uh just as much worthy of our care our love as some other person or an animal
um some of you love your pet and
you know i don't know if your body should see as your pet exactly but it could be something that you care
for and love and treat well and with respect you don't it's not an afterthought
the body is not just a convenient vehicle for getting you from one place to the other
the body is you know a valued vital important part of this whole process
so i wanted to read a couple of quotes from the ancient buddhist texts one is from the
verses of the elder monks and i delighted this little poem
and i see it as kind of a poem in the liber about a liberated body
hey my body is light having been touched with vast joy and
happiness my body feels like it's floating
like cotton blowing in the wind
here's another quote actually from the buddha himself
i immerse the body in the mind and the mind and the body
and when i dwell having entered upon a blissful perception and a buoyant perception
in regard to the body on that occasion my body becomes more buoyant malleable
wieldy and luminous a luminous body
so these are all ways different ways of experiencing the body there is you know the karmic body is not
the only body to experience and we want to kind of free ourselves from the idea that this is the real body
of the singular real body it's real enough we have to respect the karmic
body and take care of it on its own terms but there are other ways of experiencing
the body and so free ourselves up from a kind of attachment or a fixidity on this is how
the body is and i have to constantly negotiate and struggle and work with this
as the mind meditates as the mind becomes freer more concentrated more insightful
the experience of the body changes as the experience of the body changes
uh it in turn it changes the mind there's kind of a reciprocal relationship
that goes on here and so as you begin feeling the lightness of
the body the freedom of the body the joy the tranquility of the body
that's a lesson for the mind that's a teaching to the mind what's possible
it's a reminder of the mind to yes here this is a good place to dwell
to be centered and relaxed here as opposed to being carried away
on the street on the kind of freight trains of thoughts that
carry us away so the liberated body
it's fascinating to me that how dynamic complex sophisticated this
human body is that's so many systems working so many
complicated chemical systems neurological systems mechanical systems are operating
that any one of us even with a phd in engineering and biochemistry simply could not track it
all and manage it all it's an amazing complicated thing that happens
mostly on its own and [Music] and in addition to that the mind itself
is a wondrous thing you know most of the mind happens uh off stage you know
that we don't really know that's all the complicated ways in which the mind works as well i don't think any of us is smart enough
in our conscious self the self that we consciously know to direct and manage and supervise
all the ways in which the brain works the mind works and all the ways in which the body works
the part that we can actually have some say and do the part that we get attached to and get cling to and get preoccupied
with is actually a very small sliver
of who we are we are in our totality and it's remarkable how much trouble we
can get into in this little slice of or that we're conscious of
where we take this is who i am and this is what i have to do and it's all up to me and
and i have to navigate and do all this this practice of ours can teach us
what it's like to put that little sliver that little subset of
of our whole our whole that subset which is the conscious part if we can let that rest
let that be at peace so that it can be informed
it can be guided by this huge
percentage of who we are that we're not so conscious about and that is where living a dharma life
living a life that's ethical that's peaceful that's not
caught up in greed hate and delusion that's where
we've come into this beautiful harmony of the dharmic body
the dharma dharmakaya the dhammakaya
the liberated body operating in the fullness
of all its systems integrated harmonious and free
so thank you for this week and for today and i hope this has given you an interesting
perspective for your body and if you
what i talked about today is of interest for you maybe through this weekend you can look you can spend some time
meditating and walking and doing simple things with your body and to see if you can kind of intuit or
feel into what a liberated body is like what is your body like
when the body has is not just peaceful or tranquil
but has a sense of being
operating free of attachments free of clinging thank you