good evening I wonder how the volume is it feels a little bit low is it okay for you guys
or is it okay let me just
so maybe I should say welcome to the end of daylight savings too right this shift
that we do every year is you would think we would get used to it year after year but right I don't know I
never get used to it so tonight I'd like to start by reading
a short poem by uh Maddie weingest and
Maddie read some of the poems that were written by in fact it's their earliest
human literature by women attributed by women and it's in the Buddhist tradition
in this tradition and he read some of those poems and was inspired by them and
kind of wrote some of his own poems based on some other earlier ones those
of you who are interested um the original poems are called the terrigata you can find in versions of it on the
website and Maddie weingus inspirational poems
from the book first free women so uh here's one of the poems that he
writes maybe I should say a little bit more about what these poems are about
they are Awakening poems so things that the women after like an Awakening
experience they would write a poem or you know say they probably at that time didn't write them but would say a poem
so it's a kind of an exclamation after Awakening some of it like how they got
there or what the experience was like or something like this
so and the poems are just named after the nun the woman who said them so this
one her name was Vijaya when everyone else was meditating
I'd be outside the whole wait I'm sorry when everyone else was meditating I'd be
outside circling the hole finally I went to confess
I'm hopeless I said the Elder nun smiled just keep going she
said nothing stays in orbit forever if this circling is all you have why not
make this circuline your home I did as she told me and went on
circling the hole if you find yourself partly in and
partly out if you find yourself drawn to this path and also drawing away
I can assure you you're in good company just keep going
sometimes the most direct path isn't a straight line
I love this poem it's very sweet right she's kind of like circling around the whole like okay I really should get in
there I really should settle down and meditate but I'll do it later okay but maybe I'll do this I'll distract myself
I'll take care of this I'll clean the refrigerator or all the you know all these types of things that we do right
when we think we should be meditating or whatever it is exercise
read more eat better you know all these things right we often are
doing something else but what I love about this poem a is
that kind of points to the humanity of this that we all have these ideas of what we
should be doing or want to be doing and then there's what we actually do
and then there's this nun the Elder nun who gives the instructions
that's what you're doing just keep doing it and this way that this uh
practice this Buddhist practice isn't asking us to be somebody that we're not
it's not asking us to completely change ourselves and pretend to be something or
somebody that we're not instead we start Where We Are
of course we do of course we start where we are and for many of us probably more
often than we like to admit right we're the ones that are kind of like circling the whole quote unquote instead of like
actually getting to the cushion or doing the things that we think that we should be doing want to be doing
so I know certainly for me there have been times when I was just like circling
the whole this expression that I just couldn't get myself to like meditate you
know even though I had lots of experience meditating and not you know lots of benefits from it and I just
couldn't do it I just could not find myself getting to the cushion
and it wasn't immediately apparent to me why that was until a little bit later I
realized that like I would sit down on the cushion and then you know 90 seconds
later oh no I need to take care of this I gotta do that or something like this I
didn't quite recognize that I was distracting myself because there was some uncomfortable emotions that would
arise when I finally would stop circling
and just settle down I don't appreciated the impact that
these difficult emotions were having on me they weren't I couldn't even tell you exactly what it was but whatever it was
I just felt like I did not want to experience it just this oh my gosh and
would distract myself or busy myself or something like this
so in this in the Buddhist teachings there
aren't a lot of distinct teachings about emotions specifically like had to be with difficult emotions or lovely
emotions or things like this and we might understand this in a few
ways one is that maybe in Ancient India that had a
different understanding about emotions I know we might think that well emotions or emotions what is there to understand
but I know that um researchers like when they
want to look into emotions they often will like have surveys you know the
questionnaires that they ask people to do to kind of learn about people's inner life or what's happening
and what they've discovered is that they cannot translate these questionnaires
from English into all other like many other languages because other languages
don't even understand emotions the same way for example like in a question like
well when is the intensity of that emotion the greatest some like some
cultures don't even have this idea what do you mean intensity of an emotion that just doesn't make sense we don't think
of emotion as having intensity or they would think about well it's I don't it's
only what's expressed it's not what's inside or I don't know exactly how it would be but this was like it turned out
to be a whole area of research on its own how different cultures have complete different understanding of what is an
emotion as well as the value of emotions so we
might understand that's why in Ancient India there just wasn't the understanding that we have these
thousands of years later after how many you know all this Psychotherapy and all these types of things now right we
shouldn't underestimate how much that's impacted our culture and in terms of how we understand what it means to be a
human and what it means to be a happy human
and I was thinking about this so uh well well how are our emotions
talked about and it occurred to me that I don't even I can't even think exactly
what the poly word would be for emotion probably where is the language the
pictures are written in for this tradition and I I can't even think of one but of course we know about
loving-kindness practices which are kind of like heart practices I mean kindness
and compassion [Music] we have things like generosity which we
might think is can be an action but also maybe it's just like an openness of the heart
so we have things like this but there isn't a emphasis on emotions and
how they might be a part of our path of practice
but what is clear I would say in like maybe contemporary times is maybe that's
not like the number one practice we talk about in terms of finding greater
Freedom finding Awakening finding peace but it might be I don't know if there's
been any research on this but it might be one of the biggest sticking points where
people might get stuck or tingled up or have a lot of difficulties is with their
emotions like just like for me like I just couldn't meditate because I was trying
to avoid my emotions but I didn't even know I was trying to avoid them it took me a while to kind of figure out and
discover what was happening so as sometimes as we start this
practice with the mindfulness practice we just start to become more and more aware of our inner life and or
we aren't distracting ourselves as much just paying attention more to
our life in all areas of our life and when we do that there might be some new emotions that arise
or there might be some recognition some uncomfortable realizations of psychological insights
Etc and so
even if we aren't aware of them I would say you know their influence you know show up in so many different ways
and the last time I gave a Derma talk not that last week but the week before
I talked also about emotions and introduced a practice that uh go for
install and Tonya Weiser have talked about which I find really helpful and I find myself offering it to a number of
people that's a way to support their practice and this is the r a f t
some of you have heard me say this recognize the emotion
allow it to be there it is there so you know just allow it to be there
feel it in the body and then tease apart are the emotion and
our reaction to that emotion r-a-f-t
so we happily give these instructions raft you can do this with the emotions
but I I want to unpack this just a little bit more because
this idea of to recognize this the first letter in raft
turns out to not be so simple
because also with some like this emotional research they've
when they ask people you know list uh your emotions Or List emotions
most people had a list of three sad happy and angry
okay but there's many more emotions but most people just in different cultures
and Western cultures non-western cultures had just these three but they didn't include things like
contentment or despair or embarrassment or hopeful or
overwhelm or ah you're like there's a really long list
but it turns out that people don't have this like vocabulary
for their emotional life but it's not that they don't feel these
things but they can't explain it or they can't share it or
don't really aren't really in touch with it or something like this and
in some ways this can be frustrating because
language if we have language if we're able to use word like ah or boredom or
contentment whatever it might be ashamed yes really long lists
if we don't have words then it's about this it's more difficult to not only
connect with ourselves with our experience but to connect with other people
kind of like share what's going on with ourselves to describe what's going
on or be able to relate to people because
a way that we connect with others and connection is important is through kind of this vulnerability and intimacy
through our emotional life but language also helps us to like see
connections between people Us and other people ourselves and others or connections
between oh this person had that expression on their face when they were talking about ah but when I experienced
oh it's different and you know maybe we just start to understand ourselves better and understand the emotions
better if we do have some of this language
so I've been saying just Do raft recognize
and not recognizing that actually this for myself to has been part of kind of
my path is to just kind of understand the whole range of emotions
as opposed to just happy sad and angry
and so one thing that might be helpful or supportive is to broaden our
emotional awareness or literacy and one way we can do that is just too frequently
throughout the day just check in how am I feeling
and it can be helpful to have these lists of these words and there's these lists are I've seen them all over the
place I've seen them in Derma books websites you know these just kind of
lists so this could be something to help us this recognize but then this idea of about allowing
allowing emotions that maybe it's helpful to
recognize maybe I could use that word that when or to keep in mind that
there is no emotion that is fundamentally wrong
there just isn't we have emotions that's not the same as
behaviors and acting out I'm talking about just the emotion Rage or
or lust or you know these types of things right they arise
and there isn't any of them that's fundamentally wrong it's just uh what we do with them
and how they how we get expressed because so we might say if an emotion is
felt or experienced it doesn't have to be different at that moment
we can just allow it to be there we might not know like why this emotion
has arisen how long it's going to be here we don't know if there's a lesson
connected to it something that it's needs to tell us or we might as I said
not even know precisely which emotion we're experiencing but what we do know that our emotional life
is legitimate it's valid it's a rich part of The Human Experience
and it has we might say it has a right to be a part of our experience
so what we do we don't know you know why
it's here or exactly or a lot of things that we don't know about emotions but what we do know that
it does have a right to be here and this knowing like it's okay it's what's
arising if we apply that like sincerely and
consistently to our life this leads to a certain kind of peace
it leads to a diminishment a softening of the struggling with our emotions
with our resistance to our emotions to our mistrust of our emotions
and this piece but I just recognize that okay this is pure and
let's I'm gonna allow it to be here it's legitimate because it actually is here
it's not like pretending that it's not there or trying to resist it is going to change the
the reality of it having a risen even though we might think that sometimes right we kind of might think
this but but as our resistance softens us our
allowing increases this peace increases in our life
Freedom increases in our life but why is it so hard to allow emotions
if they're just this natural thing that humans have however they understand emotions why is it so hard why do we
have to have a whole practice around it well I think for many of us we have a
mistrust of emotions and maybe a misunderstanding and in some ways this
kind of like seems so common
and I know I certainly have had a lot of mistrust of emotions
certainly in my younger life I just thought they were messy and
I don't know I just thought that they got in the way and life would be so much
better without them right teenage years young adulthood I couldn't find my way you know really
confused and just out of sorts
and so I felt like okay just things would be better if that entire emotions and I
don't know I can't imagine now I wasn't aware of it then but maybe that was part of why I became a research scientist
right because uh you know science is all neat and tidy and I love kind of
mathematics with the tidiness of that and so maybe that's partly what led me to in that field
and clearly I didn't stay there but uh so
but there was something that when I had kind of early in my Buddhist practice years I
was doing some training to be a chaplain in the hospitals
and Interfaith chaplain and as part of the training we read this
book called wounded healer by on Henry newin
I don't remember all the details of this book this was quite some time ago but just even this idea wounded healer and
renewance point is that all the difficulties that we have
helps us to connect with others helps us to understand others they are actually just it's okay it's a part of our life
and that book in particular was about how to like be a minister or a chaplain
to support people this idea that you know people are suffering and you can connect with them through your own
suffering and from what you've learned from it and that was a game changer for me to read this book like it never
occurred to me oh like all the difficulties I had when
I was younger actually could be helpful and I have certainly have found this to be true
and my role as a Dharma teacher and a retreat teacher you know sometimes in
Retreats you know are difficulties arise and people meet with me and I can hear
and feel and see their difficulties and I feel like oh you know I've been there
too and that's really different than just giving a clinical
explanation or something like this so this was a big surprise for me
that what I felt like needed to be avoided it
turned out to be a strength in some ways I don't want to say that I'm perfect with emotions or anything like this and
that I can perfectly match everybody that comes to talk to me and I don't want to give that impression
but just this idea that our emotional life even if it sometimes
is it difficult emotional life has a value
and might even really support us for ourselves or for other loved ones or
people in our lives and
recently I read this idea that with social media or we live in this world of
personas of people that are constantly trying to project the image
this I'm sure was happening before social media but now it's really uh
maybe he was exploded in some ways that we live in a
world of personas but we're trying to constantly give the image that we're
stable we have it together and we're unafraid and that everybody's walking
around trying to do this but not recognizing that actually all of
us have some of this suffering inside all of us
in fact we might say this is what the Buddha was pointing to with the first Noble Truth that there is suffering
is some of this difficulty that's humans experience and we're
trying to hide from this difficulty both from others give this impression that we
have it together and hide it from ourselves we don't want
to be with these things of course we don't want to it's uncomfortable
another reason why it's difficult maybe to just allow emotions
is that we have some beliefs about them
we have beliefs that well only certain genders Express certain emotions
and only at certain times or in certain settings or something like this or
just this general idea of I shouldn't feel this this shouldn't be happening
and so often we have beliefs you know that come from our culture from the
generation we grew up in you know our families of course of
course some people have this idea that you know every emotion must be shared with
everybody else and they're like talking all about it all their inner life and other people of the opposite trait that
they're not going to share anything but what are some of our beliefs that we
have about emotions like the role that they have in our lives or the value that
they have and we might explore this for ourselves just to ask
what are our beliefs about this emotion or what scares me
about this emotion or
what what if I could like fully feel this emotion what would happen
and the physiologists tell us that uh emotions last for about 90 seconds if we
don't get tangled up with them with stories or if we're not
fueling them with these kind of resistance okay this shouldn't be here
and oh this means I'm a bad person or something like this and I don't want to
be a bad person I shouldn't feel this and the last time I did this happened
and I can say in my experience this is true actually
I have had this experience on Retreat when the mind is a little bit more quiet and settled
of having this really intense like sadness I couldn't even tell you why
it's like oh my gosh it was so intense
and like the tears started and like wow like okay I'm I'm just gonna be with
this it was intense I'm about 90 seconds later it was gone
it's like wow that was amazing like I'd never experienced anything like that I'd heard
these ideas that okay emotions can be short-lived but we only prolong them
with our stories but it wasn't until they actually experienced that
and I had this idea like was that what I was afraid of
that wasn't so bad 90 seconds I can handle this so kind of gave me some confidence and
kind of also shifted my experience with emotions
so we might have some resistance we might have some of these
beliefs about them but this idea of
we our emotional life can just be folded into part of our practice
instead of something that gets in the way of our practice or this feeling of well I'll meditate when
um I'm feeling a little bit more stable or when I have this uh
emotional thing taken care of or whatever it might be
this idea of r-a-f-t recognize allow feel in the body
the feel in the body so we can get out of the thoughts and then to tease apart the reactions
most often our reaction is resistance so part of our practice is maybe just to
notice acknowledge and experience the emotion to the best
of our ability
and this we should not underestimate how powerful this is just how our life unfolds differently if
we don't have this feeling that we have to avoid certain emotions
if we don't have to avoid certain situations because they might create the conditions in which emotions might arise
so this idea of instead of like avoiding or distracting or circling around the
whole maybe there's a way in which there can be more like of a inter here
kind of way of enter here into the meditation Hall so to speak or enter
here as a way of our practice like our emotional life is a place in which we don't have to run
away from of course we have to use wisdom here too
it's not helpful to jump into emotion in a way that's going to cause overwhelm
so it could swim we're overwhelmed we are overwhelmed we don't have access to our wisdom and support and resources
so and we also need to take care of our trauma history sometimes that can really
tip us over and to overwhelm kind of rather easily
but our mindfulness practice our practice towards greater Awakening
needs to include our emotional life not because it's
once we have that all cleaned up we're going to be come awakened but because that most often is what is a can be a
roadblock to Greater Peace and Freedom and ease
so as a way to help work with some of the difficulties in our lives so our
mindfulness practice can of course include
our emotions recognize allow feel in the body tease
apart and as our practice uh
evolves our experienced with emotions evolve
let me beginning we often have like these interpretations or narratives
about emotions we have um stories about them and we talk about them and we might
feel like okay this is a an authentic way for me to be with our emotions but
there's a way also in which we do that which we're not actually experiencing or
feeling them we're just talking about them so it's different
maybe that is kind of like the recognizing part of this and then
further along with practice then we actually feel them we feel the heart break we feel the sadness the tears come
that we feel the anger the heat of the anger
and we also feel the resistance we feel that nerds and notice are the way we
want to distract ourselves from that and not be with us
and then with the further with practice then the resistance patterns start
dissolving we start to see how just in all areas of our life it doesn't serve us to
be disconnected from ourselves and to be trying to isolate ourselves from
everything that's uncomfortable we recognize it's not possible to do that and
it's not the end of the world if we're uncomfortable and then
we start to realize that the direct experience of emotion without any
resistance just the sheer emotion is perfectly fine
it arises we experience it and it passes away
it doesn't have to be more complicated than that but it's a journey to get to
like recognize that to actually feel to be okay to allow them and just to have
this be part of our experience and then maybe I'll end with this an
excerpt from a poem from Jeff Foster and this poem is called
how I became a warrior once I ran from Fear
so fear controlled me until I learned to hold fear like a
newborn listen to it but not give in
honor it but not worship it fear cannot stop me anymore
I walked with courage Into the Storm I still have fear but it does not have me
and then he continues with a bunch of other emotions I'm not going to read them all here
and then the ending of the poem goes once I ran from difficult feelings now
they are my advisors confidant's friends and they all have a home in me
and they all belong and have dignity I am sensitive soft fragile my arms
wrapped around all my inner children and in my sensitivity
power in my fragility an unshakable presence
in the depths of my wounds in what I had named Darkness
I found a blazing light that guides me now in battle
I became a Warrior when I turned towards myself
and started listening Jeff Foster how I became a warrior
this idea of our emotions are even though when the
kind of like the Buddhist scene we don't talk about them necessarily that much and they're not an integral part of the
Buddha's teachings but their integral part of our life
and we can welcome them into our lives and we can work with them and not avoid
them so I think with that I'll open it up if there are some questions
including if there's some questions on YouTube I don't know if anybody does or will but
hi thank you Diana again um well I with the raft
um practice I find that knowing that I have to recognize it
I don't want to allow it to be there and so I just feel unwilling because then I
know I'm like oh gosh here we go again but then I know it's stories that I tell myself and so rather
than what in your last poem what Foster put had put like there are all the EX my
previous experiences can help guide me I'm like I don't want to do that again because it
sucks and so when I'm in my when I'm trying to meditate
I I kind of just I have I put the timer on and I try to go with it and see what arises
but I'm just busy thinking and and I know that with this practice there is more
awareness but hard to deal with it because I don't sometimes I feel like because I don't
want to I just I don't blame you I think right right it's hard this is hard and I'm making it
sound like oh okay just do raft you'll be fine it's not like that right this life is
messy and complicated and all these types of things and there might be some real wisdom
to recognize say okay there's that sadness and you know what I'm gonna deal
with you later right now I'm meditating and maybe there can be just say you know
later or anger or something and just say it later so just recognize it and not just
like allow ourselves to just fall into it to say okay I see that it's here but
right now I'm not going to do this so there might be some wisdom into doing this and what happens is as we kind of
like gain some confidence or gain some um
yeah experiences where we're um are not being pushed around as much
then it becomes easier and I actually I recently I read this description thank
you for saying this I I wanted to bring this in the talk that um this idea that when we really don't
want something or let's say this there's this uh expression what we resist
persists you might have heard of this but I've heard of this other ways like so we have an emotion and I'll speak to
me and we have this maybe this reaction to the emotion and if we uh the reaction is what we really don't want it then
what happens is the emotion kind of like they lean end up leaning against each other and so they get stronger and
stronger but then if the resistance were to go away then the emotion just kind of Falls
away so the more we're resisting the stronger the emotions are but we can't
see that like we don't right now this is these are just words that I'm saying but as we start to have
more experience as we start to yeah I'll just say this have more
experience with our practice and the resistance just starts to soften a
little bit and then the intensity of the emotions softens as well
they go they go down together they're intuitly intricately related
so and you're doing the right thing I appreciate very much that you said oh no I don't want to feel this and then you
said and I know those are the stories perfect that's where we start like okay
I'm all tangled up here I have all these stories going with it and I don't want it perfect and then it's perfectly fine too
to say okay I'm all tangled up I'm gonna put this aside right now we don't have to jump right in I don't
know if this is helpful Andrews yes very much I and I thought that is what's been
happening I just resist and it persists on but and and that's because I allow it
to persist rather than just tease it apart or feel feel what it's like in the
body instead of identifying with it like oh so now this is what I'm and it
doesn't have to be like that so maybe being honest with myself too so thank you you're welcome
it turns out honesty is not a bad thing
is there one that so J can you hear me yeah so Jeremy has
a question um okay I need to scroll a little bit
I find that my mind tends to jump from recognize to feel
uh since I feel emotions mostly As tension
but then I have aversion to the tension what was that last word I have with a
version of attention do I need to slow down and go through accept first before feel
I often think about maybe I should talk here this way I uh often think about
feeling as a way to help us allow so accept is a little bit different than
allow and I would say like allow is like okay it is there can we not push it away
and to feel it in the body is one way that helps us to allow it because we are
um if we're in the body then we're less in our heads and the heads that is where we have the story about the shouldn't be
here I don't want to be here oh no here I go I'm always going to be like this or whatever we might have
so you don't necessarily have to slow down because raft doesn't have to be in that
order but um you might feel the tension I guess maybe you are
feeling the tension right if you're saying this so
the emotion might become the aversion might become the next
emotion so then you recognize that and feel the aversion and then there
might be a version to aversion and then to recognize that aversion and
then just to recognize oh okay there's some resistance here is there something that can soften and
it might be sometimes softening in the body can help too which can soften the
what's going on in the mind and the whole experience sometimes it's a deep exhale or something like this might help
so I hope I hope that was uh clear enough
okay so here we are at the top of the hour thank you for your attention
and I'm wishing you all a wonderful rest of the evening thank you