so those of you in the heat
these days rather than saying warm greetings
perhaps you could appreciate a offering of cool greetings
the that's been said that uh the english language you know because it was
evolved developed in england which can be cold and
rainy that the idea of warmth is very appealing and heart warming
whereas buddhism developed in india where it can be quite warm and there what is wonderful is coolness
to be cool and so the idea of coolness has very different connotations than it has in
english where you know being cool is is being you know pretty hip or
something but being cool is being refreshed and
being delighted and being all kinds of things and so the idea of nibbana
nirvana is very much associated with with the idea of becoming cool cooling down
the cooling of the flames and and maybe in this heat
you can appreciate why uh how that's really really really you know meaningful
metaphor that maybe sometimes english speaking people wouldn't quite be inspired by him
so um i'd like to say
some preparatory words for this meditation but no preparatory kind of guided
meditation i'll just want to say my words and and that'll serve as the
support for the meditation today so if you'd like to close your eyes as i say this kind of
hopefully you can just listen but kind of get yourself settled and on your own as you listen
so these qualities of the dharma for today it's the one that says come and look
come and come and see and
and so insight the name of our kind of meditation insight meditation
does involve seeing and it does involve seeing more clearly
what comes into view as we see so coming into seeing more clearly the
experience of breathing the body sounds the thoughts emotions
and that's part of the value of it but one of the profound things
you know to see if we're trying trying to see something if we're looking to find something and
like there's some insight that will be profound something to discover that's
kind of profound if you're seeking
then what you're looking for
can be found in the seeing
not in what you see what you seek is found in the seeking
not in what you're seeking for out there
the thing to be aware of is the awareness itself
to be aware of ourselves mindful aware attentive
where we're at our attention
includes what it's like to be attending
to what attention takes in and so this backward step this kind of
turning the awareness around almost to look at itself
there what do we find what do we see
and we might see layers of attitudes and reactions
opinions preferences
but if those are there then we haven't taken the backwards step
far enough back into that which is looking to the looking itself
to the awareness itself in its simplicity
and in that simplicity that is the place to rest
that's the place to then open up to be aware of this world
as we sit here meditating
so
and as we come to the end of this meditation
maybe again to bring your attention not to
something but to attention itself
the attending not the
looking not what you're looking at but at looking itself
and in doing so maybe becoming aware of the attitudes that come along with mindfulness
with attention the wanting and not wanting the aversion
the desires the fears and
that seem somehow entangled with our capacity to be aware
maybe the delusions the thoughts the interpretations concerns with past and future
and to think of these as visitors
to awareness visitors to our ability to see is very simply
the simplest acts of perceptions are free of all these complicated
attitudes
sometimes those attitudes crowd out awareness itself
are recognizing it are living in it in a conscious way
and as all our attitudes crowd out
even conscious awareness
so it also crowds out the deeper deeper capacity
for love all the flavors of love
kindness good will
care compassion
generosity and respect
to let go to settle in deep enough into awareness
itself gives room
for more and more inner beauty to come forth
and may it be that your inner beauty
manifests in greater goodwill
and natural goodwill welling up from within
simple goodwill for all the people in your life
known and unknown strangers
may it be that through your awareness
you can tap into greater happiness for yourself and for them
may it be that through a more settled mind and heart
you make a world that is safer for yourself and for others
may it be that as you
have fewer and fewer attitudes and reactivities to entangled with awareness
that awareness provides peace for yourself and for others
and may it be that as you are
aware without being caught in anything
you provide greater freedom for yourself and for others
may this meditation practice that we do benefit self and others
intentionally and unintentionally consciously and unconsciously may all
beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so find myself happy to be here with you this morning and
for this third talk on the qualities of the dharma
and today uh you know so i have the simplest way that kind of very kind of
simplistic maybe a way of understanding these five qualities is
that they are it's about here dharma is here the dharma is now
the dharma is looking
the dharma is flowing along and the dharma is to be experienced
so um today the topic you know in a simplistic way is the dharma is looking the the literal
pali word as i said last week is a very common
ordinary expression that suggests this kind of simplicity that
i'm talking about a simplistic way of saying it is because it literally means come
look come see some people say inviting inspection they
translated it some people say there's one wonderful chinese buddhist
saying that says awakening beckons us within everything
and awakening invites us within everything so everything that we
see and touch is inviting us come be awake wake up what a great idea that that's how it is
and it is that way in a certain way and maybe i'll try to explain that and um but come and look
and look and uh and what we find then in this five
characteristics of the dharma the first one is
san ditiko de diti it does mean to come to come see that
means visible so it's visible some people say visible
here some people say it's in this very life that we can see and live here
some people will translate it as to see here to visible here and now
but i think just say it's visible here the third one now is to come look so
here we both of them have you know seeing in in the meaning of it and then the fifth one on friday
is uh to to know to experience to know the
word it means both things to know so this way of seeing and knowing is really
steep in the dharma and you find the buddha throughout his teachings he keeps emphasizing seeing and knowing seeing
and knowing and and so
uh cultivating or developing our capacity to narrow to settle into here
and now to discover a way of being here and now that is not in conflict not fighting not
running away escaping not afraid of here now not um
putting layers of interpretation and and wishes expectations on here and now
uh coming into a simplicity of being with here and now it's a lot of what
we're discovering in this meditation practice here and now here and now and
and that gives us an opportunity then for the looking the seeing to be relatively simple to be
uncomplicated not a lot of baggage comes along with it and it's all
too easy to have baggage come along one of them is to look and be mindful
with kind of a self-consciousness performance anxiety or
measuring oneself how am i doing and you know i'm not doing well enough i should be further along or
uh you know it's too difficult for me all these kinds of kind of forms of self-consciousness
take us out of the simplicity of here and now and also out of the simplicity of this
seeing what's here just this looking just being mindful just aware here
and one of the challenges for some some people will be that this simplicity of
here and now and simplicity's mindfulness here is boring
that it's uh it has unpromising and it's not going to provide us with the rich
things the special things the wonderful things that and um
and uh but maybe that's the price of coming into a wonderful state of
being is a willingness to be very simple without expectation
without wanting anything so that we can put down
the activity of boredom put down the exp activity of
of selfing and wanting something and building itself up just very simple
so and then to be able to look from that point of view to see to be mindful to be aware
in a way is very respectful of whatever is happening in the present moment that each thing in the present
moment is allowed to be itself without our interference and our desires
the kind of pristine primordial
kind of appearance of whatever is happening in the moment okay this is allowed to be here
so all our emotions there's an art to allowing them all to be there here
without being entangled reactive and without being pushed around by them
without being influenced by them and so this simplicity of being might not seem so interesting
in the in some ways but it's a radical alternative to being
influenced by our inner life and some you know desires wishes and emotions and all that
something different can happen but as we begin to look more at some
point what becomes interesting and fascinating is not what we see and not that we can
see clearly but we can the it's the looking itself
we begin appreciating more and more that the mindfulness itself the way we are aware awareness in itself
the inner perception the perception we have itself that
maybe that's where the treasure is maybe there is where we find
a freedom awakening that this wonderful cup to turn around
and look awareness look at perception perceiving perception perceiving itself
looking the inner eye looking and seeing itself awareness aware of itself
in such a way that we begin shedding
all the extra baggage that comes along with it all the extra attachments clinging
stress levels that come along with being aware being mindful
and this is one of the kind of ways in which mindfulness really opens up to a
deep equanimity is as the mindfulness as the awareness begins shedding
the complexities that we add on top of it it just becomes simpler and simpler awareness simpler and simpler looking
the simplicity of it becomes the guide oh there's where non-clinging ears
there's there's a little bit of stress there and how i'm aware oh and as i become aware of that stress
something opens something relaxes as i become aware as i become aware of
the stress in mindfulness i notice there that that awareness has
no stress in it so we're stepping back we're going kind of these layers and layers
and to finding that place where awareness has no stress no tension associated with it
and then kind of staying close to that letting the how we're aware of the world
come from that place of no tension no stress no pushing
no straining no resisting no pulling away no leaning forward
so that's why sometimes it's powerful to to
realize that or to have this attitude or understanding that what we're looking for
is in the looking
that attention we can in being attentive
we're we're being attentive to how we're attending
attention and attending i could use together in in having attention
we're attending to the attending itself
in the mindfulness we're being mindful of the how we're being mindful
in looking we're mindful of how we're looking and attending to anything we're
paying attention to how we're attending and and that is where we begin can
understand something a lot about what's going on in our life it begins shedding
all the different activities within
associated with attention with a practice that involves stress strain
tension involves some kind of discomfort
until we find this equanimity of simplicity the simplicity of equanimity
so this idea of the buddha says come and look here and now in the here now
with the here now come and look come and look so today
as you go about your day uh you might um
take some time you know maybe set a timer be reminded periodically sit and
have tea whenever you have a chance but it's been making an assignment that today
i'll start becoming more aware of the characteristics the quality
of your awareness itself of your attention itself of your mindfulness turn around
and see how much extra that might be there along
and see how simple you can allow your your attention to be
and if there's a any kind of extended period of time this simplicity of awareness
i suspect that you'll discover that your breathing shifts and changes
it might become more useful so
i hope that it's a wonderful day of exploration and
i look forward to our time tomorrow thank you