there so so formally hello and welcome to happy hour uh all those who are
joining on zoom in this moment in time whatever the time zone those hello folks
from youtube uh as well as joining us later on audio dharma many folks joining
later on audio dharma so we have a larger sangha now and then i receive
notes emails from folks who join us asynchronously later in time
nevertheless their heart is with us we are with them so we all practice together one large
sangha one large happy arasaka so so for today's uh scene
i'd like to invite us to um explore simple meta practice for
ourselves just simple meta it's very simple kindness
loving kindness care warmth for this person who is me
ever so simply um in
in the teachings in the concentric circles of how meta loving kindness is developed
traditionally the first concentric circle is ourselves we start with ourselves
in the west sometimes because folks have trouble starting with themselves we
start with a dear being and then we turn to ourselves just to prime the pump of the heart
and and yet the teaching the buddha has taught that
has said that if you search the entire world you wouldn't find anyone worthier than your own
kindness your own metta your own love so we are as worthy
as worthy not more not less just as worthy as anyone else just as worthy as
anyone else for care and love and
kindness so so yeah i thought for tonight we would just go back to the basics basics are
delicious very very nourishing to just hold ourselves in care and kindness so
um yeah i think i don't want to say much more to frame it i'll just
guide us in a meditation uh as always we start by settling in the
body with the breath for a few minutes to get grounded to settle
and then i will make some invitations
for practices and feel free to
follow them or not adapt them as they work for you in this moment in time
giving yourself a lot of permission to care to care for yourself for this
being who is you this body this mind this heart this being with all the causes and
conditions of suffering and joy so
so with that let's practice together let's practice so i'd like to invite you to make
yourself comfortable you need to shift move if you need to lie down as long as
you're not going to fall asleep that's a perfectly fine posture too
or to stand up if you're super sleepy
i will give the instructions for sitting but see what your body needs in this moment
so arriving landing in this body in this moment
hello dear body greeting greeting this body
mindfulness of the body important
the basic foundation of our practice
always starting with the body feeling feeling our feet
on the earth
feeling our sit bones on the earth or the cushion or the chair in lieu of
the earth
feeling the source bones releasing under the earth
really connecting
the weight the weight of the upper body dropping into the chair
and turning our gaze inward the mind might still
have a lot of repeats from earlier today thoughts activities
it's okay nothing wrong with thinking per se
and in this moment we choose we intentionally bring our mind
invite our mind to give up to give away to relinquish
not because it's bad but because there's something better here stillness is so much better
stillness is so much more delicious internally
so we turn away from thoughts entanglements
come back thank you we'll come back but for now
we'll turn and we'll turn again we may need to turn a hundred times
turn away give up relinquish thoughts entanglements
and turn let let awareness turn internally
and let awareness connect with the breath in the abdomen
we give up go away give away the thoughts and entanglements
awareness needs something [Music] to connect to
to attend to let it be the breath as the anchor breath in the body
nourishing calming soothing
trusting that the simplicity of this moment is more delicious the stillness
more calming healing and figuring anything out in this moment
and the mind is still the heart is full things will be figured out on their own
with a different mind einstein says we can't solve our
problems with the same mind that created them so bow to that mind thank you
not now i'll let there be a turning towards a calm quiet still
mind here just this breath
just this breath here just to spread
how can this moment be nourishing for this body for this heart
as if you're talking to yourself as a beloved other beloved child
sweetheart how can i take care of you in this moment how can i be with you present with you
give you my full attention no words or thoughts needed just to be
so
okay
and now if you wish
i'd like to invite you to
imagine as if you were
the wise or the wise kind
parent of yourself
seeing a younger version of yourself perhaps or not younger maybe the same age
the same way parents mothers fathers they see
coaches they see a potential they see the goodness they see a bright light
often in younger people or in others that they don't see they don't appreciate in themselves
knowing trusting there is this bright light about you
and it's hard for you to see it in yourself maybe let yourself be seen
by a compassionate being in your mind's eye but they see your brightness they see
your potential they see your goodness
and when i say potential here in this case is the beauty of your intentions
your intentions for cultivation [Music] for kindness for wisdom
for not causing harm in the word world for ethical conduct
that you try you try
they see in you what's bigger than you what's not diminished or diminishable
not diminishable by your suffering by your challenges
whether times you feel small lost in pain none of that affects
affects it at all
they see you or if it works the wise part of you sees yourself
however this being seen works for you
there is so much potential for goodness
for good kind thoughts words actions
so much potential in each and every one of us so much potential the future is not
written yet so much potential for goodness for acts
of service love kindness
not self-centeredness
may this person knows me may i
my inner goodness i appreciate
my inner potential for beautiful acts thoughts
deeds of kindness love care generosity
may i say myself for who real i really am
and if words come oh no you're not deserving you're not worth it
you don't have to believe the thoughts the judgmental thoughts just say thank you very much for your
opinion please come back later you don't have to believe them they're just thoughts
just thoughts no need to
give power to them
not getting in your own way may i may this person who is me
may i be safe from inner and outer arm
the harm i caused myself the inner harm and the outer arm
which i may not be able to control so knowing this wish for safety is
a wish an expression of kindness from myself it's not
clinging to the outcome just expressing kindness
good will towards myself with this wish without attachment to outcome
may i be safe from inner and outer arms
lingering with this
a second bishop met her may i be happy may i be truly happy and joyful
i wish myself joy this being who is me i wish this being
joy again not clinging to the outcome
it's just an expression it's a gift we give to ourselves this wish
when you give a gift you don't expect something in return
in pure generosity this is pure generosity of the heart may i be well may i be happy
and i have joy giving this gift
at the third wish of mecca may i be healthy may i have health
and strength in my body
and if not fully healthy right now may i be as healthy as possible as available
it's the wish i have for this being who is me sense of good will care
and the last fourth wish of mitta may i have ease or may my life unfold with ease
or may i take my take care of myself happily
connecting with yourself with the phrases as they're useful [Music]
whatever version works for you just staying stay with this being who's you
let it be nourishing this meta for yourself or this person owns me
calming soothing loving at the end of a long week
may i be safe may i be happy
may i be healthy may i have ease
see your own goodness as we see someone's goodness it helps them
flourish it's true it's true for all beings can
you see your own goodness your own potential
help you flourish be nourished
can we just love ourselves
this being who's me may they be well
i know their story so many challenges may they be well
may i be well
may i be safe may i be happy
may i be healthy hmm
may my life unfold with ease
listen any visualization works for you holding yourself a younger version of yourself
wrapping yourself in the blanket of love of care
irradiating love meta through your body if there's pain
feel free to be creative
uh
and for the last minutes of this practice period whatever
rose or did not arise it's okay
let there be ease lack of judgment for yourself you showed up you tried so
all that matters we're planting seeds we don't know when they're going to
sprout non-attachment to outcome
may our practice be cause condition made support
awakening freedom of all beings everywhere including ourselves
may all beings be free may all beings be happy
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes any reflections any aha moments any questions
might have come up from this simple practice of mitta for
ourselves and the difference that at the beginning we started with seeing our own goodness
seeing our own potential and that's really important because we often see perhaps other people's
potential children's and then with adults or with ourselves we just see
faults we just see problems we just see what we do wrong
we have so much potential for goodness for kindness to see that it actually
brings it out when you clearly see and may want to reflect on the experience
you've had clearly seeing somebody else clearly seeing
their goodness their potential and that has that being seen has helped them
flourish just help them flourish maybe you've mentored a younger person at some point
in your life can you be that younger person you
a mentor so reflections questions complaints it's
all welcome private message lovely thanks you are welcome thank you for your practice
and you're welcome to raise your hand um especially if you haven't spoken for a
while or you can type in chat either privately or publicly
sarah please
you're still muted
hi there um thank you first of all
oh oh can you hear me yeah thank you and i actually wanted
i actually wanted to comment on um the practice from wednesday
because i was very very surprised at how often
in the past two days the question how can i give service has come up in daily
life i i during the meditation during the and
the the framing portion i was like oh gosh i'm never gonna remember this and like i'm gonna get
down on myself for never remembering to ask myself that and i was i was seriously surprised how many
times it just floated to the surface and it it was like
it was like it needed it like needed as a kneading dough like needed my heart
like softened it for the past couple of days and it's been really important for me in
the past couple of days so i just wanted to thank you and give a reflection on that practice
thank you so much sarah thank you so much for sharing that reflection on the
practice we did on wednesday for those who may not have been here you can go
back listen to it but really the question was how can i be of benefit how can i be of service to
myself and to others thank you so much sarah for for sharing this reflection
this is so beautiful that you know again the mind was like you know you're not going to remember this bubble and that's
like wow it just came up and kneaded your heart what beautiful metaphor needed your heart
and uh and was supportive and nourishing thank you it just ah makes it needs my heart
in gladness and happiness for you and your practice and being of service sarah thank you so
much so lovely beautiful yeah um nancy says mitta for self is keeping
the well full so you can continue service to others exactly beautiful
will this talk be available later tonight yes it will be soon after we're done
um
one of you says did you have ears in my small group wednesday i was saying i longed for a simple meta class maybe
once a week i felt content during the meditation and found a smile on my lips
and still have it and and have it still smiley sweet yes i have ears
just kidding [Laughter] and i'm i'm so glad that this uh
spoke to you and supported you and supportive for you and i hope for many others this
is lovely yeah simple meta is good charles lee i saw your hand appear and
disappear was that intentional you're welcome to unmute if you wish
anything oh no that was a mistake oh sorry it's all right it's always nice to hear your
voice anyway well thank you thank you i think that's all that i have
that's that's sweet thank you for being here and and practicing
it's a regular regular member of the sangha
any other reflections before we turn to to practicing together
in small breakout groups any other reflections questions
complaints anything is welcome for the benefit of everyone
okay space is quiet so i take that as a sign that maybe we're ready for turning into
small groups so so as i make small groups i'd like to remind us
uh the ways that we practice in the small group
is the purpose is to bring our practice into a sandbox not just from our eyes
being closed and we're on our own but actually interact in this same spirit
same space of loving kindness with others and not
get out of it like okay my meditation is ended now i can be mean to everyone okay
i'm joking but of course i made caricature out of it but can we relate to other human beings from that
space of kindness care can i be of service can i be kind can i see their light the theme tonight can i see their
light their goodness can can they see mine or inviting them inviting myself to
be seen not shying away i mean not boasting but just being as you are
so the invitation is you speak from your own experience alone um you don't
comment reflect pro ask probing questions manage the group
you just say simply from your own experience what this practice was like for you and if
you want to be quiet and hold space you can say pass and hold kind
generous space for others that's okay you have five nuggets some five things
just say one then the next person will say one and the next person will say one and they'll come to you and they'll just
go around it's just it's like a stone soup each each person contributes something
to this space of kindness relating to others and may be nourishing for you
and lastly let's uh do a person whoever's birthday is closest
to january first not the year but just date will start first speaking first and
then second and third and you get to interact a little bit in the space of meta that way just holding each other in
meta i think that's really where the rubber meets the road and you speak for your own benefit
really not to educate not to impress anyone so so the rooms are created i'm about to open
them take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
okay the rooms are closed everyone's back so we have
a few minutes any reflections questions comments
especially any reflections that might have come up any aha moments from
from being in the room uh interacting with others
what might be of benefit anything feel free to sheila there you are
hi everyone good evening nicki i just wanted to lift up one of our
um sangha members moose of the word faith as a reminder
it was a really sweet reminder faith in ourselves faith in our practice
so i just wanted to acknowledge that beautiful
thank you sheila yes beautiful yeah such a powerful
um word and a way to be a sense of faith and another word that we often use
in this tradition is trust faith in the same meaning of the sense of trust
that yes there is goodness here there is goodness there's sense of trust confidence confidence faith trust
confidence whatever version of that works for some people the word faith really lands we use that
please for some people trust works for some people confidence whatever works yes yes
and beautiful to be reminded of that by fellow travelers fellow sangha members yeah
beautiful sweet sweet so dear sangha my heart is buoyed
lifted and i have full trust and faith and confidence in every single
one of you every single one of you in your capacity in your goodness in
your cultivation so thank you all for your practice for showing up for
[Music] supporting each other supporting yourself and doing this work for all
beings everywhere may all beings be free may all beings be happy
including ourselves [Music]
thank you all