hello everyone and welcome happy to be here with you and
happy to read these chats those of you can read them there
lots of good mornings and lots of
warmth in those chat comments
and this is the theme of today is in fact to be happy or maybe to be
a little different word to be inspired inspired as a form of happiness
of delight of joy of gladness and it's inspiring to sit here with you
and to have the opportunity to appreciate
meditation the teachings community
that's so so widespread so thank you
and maybe to be a little provocative
for this meditation and I hope you allow yourself to be I don't know provoked is the right word
or evoked
and that is um to allow yourself to be inspired
and maybe the provocative question is why not be inspired
why hold back why
not recognize in spite of the challenges and by the
difficulties and the sufferings of yourself and your circumstance your world of our world
why not be inspired there is a tremendous amount of good in
this world there's a tremendous amount of people
in spite of also being the other who live lives of generosity
who support and help and do so much for others many of them are unrecognized and
unthanked even all the parents do so much for their children
to be inspired by the people who are ethical who are
honest who avoids sometimes at almost all costs too be
causing harm to others and to themselves to be inspired that
this is possible even if only a very few people in the world do it
wow it's possible the possibility is inspiring
but there's a lot of people who do it to be inspired by your ability
to be inspired by the almost divine
circumstance of being able to sit and meditate
regardless of how difficult again so much of your life is to have the circumstances sit quietly
to sit still in a place that has a modicum of safety
modicum of comfort and modicum of Demands perhaps on you
isn't there something about this that's Divine that's
the Heavenly just so different in ordinary life
and to be inspired to not be
chasing after desires of all kinds some people get up in the morning and
it just kind of going one way of analyzing a life is going after one
desire after another incessantly
so much of human Pursuit is the pursuit of comfort and pleasure
much more than people realize
so here to be inspired for these few minutes
here and inspired glad happy why not
why not be inspired in such a way
that you want to partake of this
potential this Heavenly capacity heaven like
to really appreciate it to really take it in to be nourished supported
in such a way that the heart can feel safe and contented and
happy your mind
the thinking mind is happy to be turned inward on this
experience here to become quiet and still
so that whatever the thinking mind is it can become quiet enough
that it really partakes of the goodness
that's here in you with you here
why not be inspired why not be glad
for what it for what is possible right now to be glad for to be happy for
to be happy with so to gently close the eyes
me and to feel here in your body
what is happening for you now after hearing these words
was anything touched was anything repelled
is there some is anything within that now you can take some time
to be glad about to be inspired
I like to think that the word inspired is related to the
Latin word for breathing
what is it that you can be
filled with gladness filled with the light happiness
in being filled with your breathing
and this idea of filling ourselves with every breath with presence with embodied awareness
and a gentle quieting inspiration to do so
where the path of practice is not linear
going down the path in a linear way to better and better
but the path is more like filling out filling ourselves more and more
with every breath
feeling out with awareness
embodied attention here now
with happiness riding along
inspiration riding along every breath
every movement of awareness of attention Here and Now
filled filling with peaceful inspiration
why not be happy inspired
why prioritize thoughts that are unhappy
that are nothing to do with Here and Now why prioritize feelings that might be
but other things why not
be happy with what is good right now
inspired by the Simplicity of being here breathing
and as we come to the end of the sitting why not be happy
even if the happiness is modest why not
be available to that modest inspiration or happiness
gladness Here and Now
and is there a kind of Happiness inspiration
that supports you in being more
receptive available now here
so you're not asserting yourself on the world or close down to the world
but in that happiness as modest as it is
more available to be present to be receptive
to discover how others are by stopping and being
available
maybe it embodied a pause to
receive register be available to others
where others the experience of others is received
in your happiness
and maybe from some even modest happiness Within
after having taken the time to know others to feel others experience others
to wish them well
May those who I'm aware of this day
may they be happy
May those who I take the time to know
may they be happy and safe
May those who I take time to have empathy
may they be peaceful
May those who take time to really register
make room for allow them to be here
in the fullness of my awareness
may they be free as they are free in my attention
without the hindrances without desires and resistance
they freely in my awareness may they be free too
may all beings be happy and may we contribute to the welfare
to the benefit and Welfare of the whole world
[Music]
thank you so hello everyone and
continuing on the theme and I was thinking we're just this
morning that this theme of I call it ready for change
is um seemed perfect for the end of the year or getting ready for the new year
to look forward a little bit to the new year that we are preparing ourselves so
that we can be changed in a good way beneficial way with what comes in this new time
so how do we prepare ourselves and so for the Buddha he prepared people
for his liberating insights he would give Dharma talks that created certain
mind States for people or kind of created is the right word but inspired it in people
and so those there were five things that he when he saw were present in people he
would give them their his deepest teachings and those five things that uh that he's
recognized in people's minds was there was a Readiness a receptivity
there was there is a malleability a workability of the Mind
the mind is soft enough to really you know take something in and be changed by it
they're free of the hindrances and the usual translation for the fourth
one is for today is elated to be I think inspired is a good way of
talking about it and then we'll talk about tomorrow is
um as the usual translation is confidence I like the word trust there
and we'll talk more about it tomorrow though where it also means kind of voluminously bright
so um but today is elated so there's a way of being inspired that certainly can
be so preoccupying so we can lose ourselves in it that we're not available to the world
and to experience the teachings to be changed by it but it's also possible to be inspired or
or gladdened or elated in such a way that the mind gets quieter still to
really now listen well to really take into really allow the experience of the
moment to really penetrate deeply and um and so that's the second type of
inspiration is uh what I think the Buddha was pointing towards
and so this word um to be inspired and
um and uh or to be elated or to be happy
in a way so the Buddha uh would Inspire that in
people uh the classic Tech say that by giving a talk giving Dharma talks that
covered a range of of themes that I think were inspiring were really got people's
attention really they got kind of absorbed in a sense concentrated
in in the talk and these five qualities are all the qualities of a kind of absorbed
concentrated mind like really present and so he'd give talks about generosity
and I don't know we don't know what he says no they don't specify the text so uh you know what
exactly he said but so what that means to me is that when it's unspecified then it's up to us
for ourselves to understand to figure out how do we get really inspired
how do we become a better person by reflecting on considering the topic of
generosity for me I lived for years in you know
secluded from the world you know living in deep mountainous monasteries
um in in here in this country and in Asia and it was lovely it was uh fantastic
for me and um no regrets having done that
and and it's quite wondrous to be in society here I am in Redwood City in a
in this middle of a city and to living the kind of the full life
of a householder here and uh and to see how much generosity
there is that I never knew when I was younger knew about and um and you know for example raising
children here and uh seeing all the adults so many who were putting on
sports events and coaches and um all kinds of things are volunteering
their time their generosity to make a rich life for the children growing up here and I think it's really something
to experience so much generosity for children there could have been more certainly but what I saw was you know
inspiring and then uh caring for my mother as she uh aged and and then you know went
through her dementia and and died again I saw so much generosity the particular
care place where she was she was in it was phenomenal to me the
generosity the care the kindness of love that she received and there were so there also there were so many volunteers
who came to offer extra things for the people there the care home and musicians
who came and played and artists and all kinds of things that came and did things with people there
and then I live here you know I came here to this place in Redwood City right uh IMC is I think of as kind of like mid
in the middle of the city and um and it's become a wonderful
collection here of so many generous people I mean the IMC is completely run
by volunteers and volunteers volunteer out of the generosity out of their care
or their love their happiness and um and to be kind of experiencing
the growth this phenomenal kind of outpouring of generosity that's allowed this community to grow
and develop and we do so much here and and our at our Retreat Center so
inspired this there's a lot of generosity that's inspiring it brings
out the best in people and does something to my heart that just makes it kind of open and soften and
and then there's ethics to be inspired by people's ethics there's plenty of if you read the news of course there's not
the opposite of being ethical uh virtue doesn't stand high in front page news
but uh for every horrible story and in the news there are lots and lots and
lots of unsung heroes of Ethics people who have committed to to being honest to
be to not steal not kill not lie and you know a lot of this what
they people don't do is never seen because there's nothing to
see and so it's not celebrated it's not appreciated but there's a phenomenal
amount of of ethical people in the world and I see lots of little examples as I
go through my day and there's plenty of examples of the opposite of course but where does our minds settle on what
does it focus on what is the world we want to live in do we want to live in the world of of
uh unethical world do we want to live in an ethical world if we want an ethical World be ethical
love ethics love virtue love this kind of and um and recognize it see it
appreciate how much it's here to be inspired by it and then the
absence of the hindrances is uh in the Buddhist teachings is a is
meant to be a source of gladness a source of contentment of Happiness wow finally uh I'm not uh in debt not in
prison not a slave to the hindrances something else I'm not now I'm here and
kind certain kind of way more in charge rather than hindrances and desires charge
and then the Buddha gave a part of this series of talks was he gave a talk on the first hindrance
an essential desire so as a hindrance it's clear it's a problem
and uh but I think he highlighted as being a particular characteristic of the human realm is
that people are very driven by sensual desire and sensual comfort and um and there's a way in which that
there's dangers in pursuing sensual desires lots of people make all kinds of
horrible mistakes and suffering in the world and harm others through the pursuit of sensual desires of different
types there's um uh he talked about the
dangers of it he talked about the vanity of sensual desires it's interesting to kind of think how
vanity or conceit is part of it especially when it hurts other people
and he talked about the the stain of sensual desire and in the modern
kind of English-speaking world but I don't think we like so much to think about that their stains but there's a
way in which we feel kind of you know if we really feel some of the ways that people act around sensual desire where
they objectify other people for example and it's all about their own pleasure and not about a human connection
um there's a stain there's a diminishment there's a contraction Within and to feel the benefit of the ethical
dimension of how to live with our sensuality ethically they can be inspiring
to feel this so to be inspired by this to feel goodness of it
to feel the the what's going right in our life so that we have the right balance of
input into our hearts so that our heart is not weighed down or struggling
and how do we get the right input how do we get inspired enough not the Inspire inspiration where we
lose ourselves but you know uh you know but rather the inspiration that allows
for a deep kind of availability full presence for this world and for
experience and for here so that we're ready to be changed
we're happy the unhappy is to not the opposite of
being ready for change is to be maybe caught and tight and limited and
deflated and but to be happy in a way yes
I have the courage I have the willingness I have the availability of
trying something new of trying a new way and being a new way of letting go of
some places where I'm stuck letting go of some things I'm holding on to yes I'm available
so um the
so these are all wholesome qualities and Buddha said
it's possible to cultivate the wholesome if it's not possible to cultivate the
wholesome I would not tell you to do so but it is possible to cultivate the
wholesome and so that's my instruction and so here these are some of the
wholesome qualities that the Buddha kind of held up as being valuable in
preparing to be changed to be open to really let the full impact of this Dharma practice work
and um so to be ready
to be malleable a malleable mind to be ever ready it's all about the mind it says Ready mind a malleable mind a mind
free of the hindrances an inspired mind and then tomorrow it's the trusting mind
luminous mind so um so
for today if you'd like for your homework your life work
is to um see if you can be
not exactly happier but see if you can tune in to the parts of what's Happening Here in
this life of yours that does make you happy glad inspired
don't give so much notice how much priority statistically you know in terms
of time uh how much priority you give to things which are the opposite of inspiring the
opposite of making you happy because whatever your mind is involved
in think about does have an impact on our mood our emotions our hearts
and is your mind spending a lot of time with things which are not inspiring and not
uh happy producing and if and can you switch the the
percentage to have more percentage of the time not all the time but just maybe just you
know ten percent more focused on what's inspiring what's happy and good I love the word
good these days and what is really good what's the goodness
of the moment here so thank you I hope that this homework
life work of inspiration is good for you and good for the people
around you today thank you