Okay so so for the practice today
um ah I'd like to invite us to um
to consider that the practice of meta this cultivation of
Goodwill good wishes for ourselves for others or the world is a happy making
experience hence called Pence happy hour hints hence um this
you know our our series our our program called happy hour The Pride dedicated to practice of meta and all the related
Brahma viharas they they make the heart Happy so so what I'd like to invite us to um
to practice to relate to is you know maybe you've had a long week it's either Friday evening or Saturday morning or
afternoon even given all the time zones we're in right now in this moment in time while I was joining in this Zoom
room from from Australia and Japan and east coast and Hawaii and all the time
zones of course not Mission California um the the creepy sense of okay heaviness
fatigue like okay I'm tired okay this body is tired this mind is tired it's the end of the week we're beginning a
weekend so so so an easy way it really easy if as the Dalai Lama says if if you
want to if uh if you want others to be happy to practice compassion if you want to be happy practice compassion and the
compassion then meta in some ways are in they're not exactly the same but as you know they're related practices so I want
to say you want others to be happy practice kindness if you want yourself to be happy practice kindness love and
kindness so so today's practice I want to invite us to tune into and there's so
many different things we can tune into you know we've been practicing together for a long time
and there's so many different aspects of these practices that we can choose to tune into it's not always the same thing
may I be happy maybe well maybe we'll be happy maybe it's never boring it's
always new and different and interesting because there's so much to learn keep learning keep cultivating keep uh
exploring so today would I like to invite us to explore as we are practicing as we will practice uh just
simple meta simple meta radiating simply radiating meta simply radiating Good
Will kindness just our goodness letting our light shine and then inviting you to tune into how
lighter even a tiny tiny bit happier lighter more more resourced our own
heart can feel through this practice to tune into that so that's the exploration
we're going to do in this happy hour so
so I think that's all the frame I want to set before we actually uh engage in
the practice together and explore together um our own mind heart
so so let's uh let's arrive let's arrive in
your sitting posture if you need to move
um to sit on a cushion or even lie down if you're not going to
fall asleep but your body needs that right now that's okay maybe standing if you're feeling sleepy and if you want to
do this practice standing that's fine so I'm into what this body needs right now
ah Landing arriving
in this body however it's showing up right now
connecting with the breath oh
I was taking a few minutes to settle foreign
to rest let go of all the busyness all the
thoughts that have come before
taking a moment of Refuge in the body with this breath
nowhere to do nothing to do now now [Music]
huh just this breath
send breath this out breath just to settle at the beginning of our
sit together
foreign
connecting with yourself in this moment
this dear being who is you foreign might be excited whatever is happening
connecting breathing being breezed is yourself
intimacy with yourself with this breath
foreign
be calming ah soothing
enacting you to the Earth to your old body
feeling the sensations if you're free to connect it to the
Earth sit bones connected to the chair to the cushion
hands on your lap
the intimacy of this lived experience
foreign
in with each breath
so if you're breathing in peace
breathing out peace and calm
with age in breath and out breath settling more
with each in breath body feels calmer the Mind feels calmer
on the beach out breath spreading your peace as much as available
foreign
breathing in calm
breathing out calm at peace and maybe trying out a smile maybe receiving the
in-breath with the smile the out breath with a smile sharing your
smile with the world
foreign as a gift not expecting anything back
it's a sign of your good will for yourself also
even if their challenge is present in the body if the tired is bodies tired aching the heart
is achy can there be a smile of benevolence the
half smile of the Buddha smile of benevolence foreign
a caring grandmother
for yourself and the world
realizing it doesn't take much it really doesn't
even if the thought goes the resistance goes I don't want to smile no try it on
anyway what do we have to lose
even if your heart is broken in this moment
can you receive the Brokenness with a smile
appreciation foreign
hello dear I I See You Smile of recognition
for yourself and spreading it with the world sharing it with the world
foreign let your body relax your mind soften
in breath the out breath calm foreign
peaceful smiling Smiler recognition
foreign s went to flow
bringing adding the phrases of loving kindness for yourself
may this being always me may I be happy
may I be healthy may I be saved may I have ease
or whatever phrases you have maybe it's a simplified version foreign
or maybe just spending time with one of the phrases if that speaks to you right
now may I feel safe
or may I be joyous
may I love and accept myself just as I am in this moment
may I be kind to myself
or you can say the four phrases may I be safe happy healthy have eats whatever
works let them flow with the breath
let them be blessings gifts to yourself not expectations but a gift
a gift that's given freely
no expectations no attachment
sharing your own kindness you're all good well with yourself gentle
kind
letting the repetition of the phrases or the words support the continuity connecting with
Goodwill
as of Each in-breaths Kindness Bellows your whole
body Bellows with kindness every cell through all your limbs your
heart your mind everywhere everywhere
spreading kindness internally softening all the cold
Frozen tight areas of the heart the Mind slowly slowly may I be well
foreign
interesting that you've done the best you can today this week
you're doing the best you can now
maybe this being who is me it was being be safe feel safe
feel happiness and joy
and healthy as much as possible
have ease my heart my life
and I have ease gladness goodness
and then your mind's eye
the home of your heart inviting a few people who are near and dear to
you maybe friends family pets opening the door of your heart and
inviting them to come sit sit with you take seats in this room
foreign quietly
and you breathe breathe together you breathe with them and with each breath wishing them well
radiating your good will your kindness
may they be well if they feel safe
happy healthy may they have ease
perhaps you can imagine it's raining out outside in this
imaginary space of your heart you invited them it's nice and warm cozy with your
kindness you've given each of them and blankets
of meta you're wrapping them in your meta they can just sit in the room
be warm feel cared for may you be safe happy healthy
have ease
feeling your good will your good wishes for them
wanting them to be well
feeling your kindness for them
your benevolence feel your benevolence
and now opening the door Curve Your Heart wider inviting whoever
wants to come in AKA and take a blanket you offer them a
blanket of metal they're plenty there's so many of them
so many blankets anyone can come in friends Neighbors
colleagues strangers into this room that's warmed
by your good will the fire of your Goodwill everyone can come take a blanket
of care and sit by the fire
and you just sit and just sit and breathe
fishing everyone well showing everyone goodness
feeling your good will it's an exhaustible really you don't have to try too hard
it's not like you have to push it out
they're inexhaustible sets of blankets
it's possible to be kind to everyone
in your interactions with them
you're a good will feeling the kindness of your heart this
light shining beaming radiating may all beings
be well near and far
if you want to bring the half smile of the Buddha back to your face
to accompany your a Good Will in your heart
acknowledging the good will
internally externally 360 Degrees no difference between internal and external
smiling may all beings including myself feel safe
be happy be healthy heavies
foreign
to myself and others may I feel and appreciate my own Good
Will and kindness
foreign
and as we bring this sitting period so close together
appreciating that we've done our best we showed up
accepting ourselves smiling to ourselves with kindness
thank you for showing up
letting go of any judgment or what happened or did not happen
so many causes and conditions they can give rise to agitation
sleepiness all we can do is our best
the results it's not for us to attach to
and if we can be kind to ourselves in just this moment
appreciating our own goodness this is one moment
of goodness it's infinitely better than none
and let us dedicate share the goodness of our practice I speak there is
goodness here there is goodness created co-created
with generosity with kindness we share it as if we're
beaming beaming our care love our generosity
it's the entire world seen and unseen
may all beings everywhere be safe happy healthy happy may all
beings everywhere including ourselves be free
[Music]
thanks everyone ah for your practice
so we have time for any Reflections questions you can raise your Zoom hand
if you like um the share Reflections aha moments
challenges you can also um type it in chat if you type it to me
privately I won't read your name it'll be a private reflection I will just read the reflection if you
type it to everyone I'll read your name also and you can just
yeah say what what you discovered What Might Have Been new or different or not
and also maybe one question I ask you do you feel is there more sense of calm or
gladness or happiness appreciating your own goodness
and before this practice that you notice a shift
a difference from when you started to sit I definitely do I feel calmer more
connected bill says definitely more calm I guess I agree with you Bill
I feel calmer and happier too I feel like I want to
smile more or something about the invitation to smile right which is not force that half smile of
the put and I see some of you nodding yes in agreement I love that I see some Smiles look at those Smiles on the
screen love it love it oh my God this is so great yeah do you find it you want to smile
more isn't that sweet Diana I see your hand please
I was reminded um quickly during the meditation of a
prayer when I was a little girl when I was going to bed my mother would have me
say and I don't know where it comes from but as I wrap myself in a blanket of
love and fall asleep filled with peace
and I grew up saying that even as an adult it comes back so so here we are
full circle with the blanket image I love it oh this is so sweet thank you Diana oh I
love it I love it I never heard that before I don't know where it comes from yeah I love it and maybe in some way I
have heard it I don't I'm just joking but it's it's just such a beautiful image thanks for invoking that that that
you uh yeah as a little girl um repeated them it still comes back I
love that and yes this is a invitations in the practice Yeah I love that thanks for highlighting that thanks thanks
Diana oh very sweet Andrew joining us for the first time
from Japan I just want to thank you for the um
the blanket metaphor or the visual was was a nice uh Riff on the kind of more
more common loving kindness uh friends I said thank you for that
thank you thank you so much yeah it's there's so many different ways to do
this this practice and we find our ways with different metaphors and just what works and to remember what works for you
and and uh and uh invited in it is this practice is
a skillful means this practices skillful means and there's so many skillful means
we all have individual ways so if that the blanket image worked yay
have endless supply of blankets at the door for yourself than others thanks
Andrew yeah another reflection happy hour has
been good medicine for me this week while I spend time with my new friend
covet oh thank you Nikki and Sonic oh so sorry
well since you're a reflection came to only me I won't say her name but hope
you feel better one of our Sango members has had covered this week and all hope you feel better oh oh dear
yeah happy hour can be good medicine yeah practicing while
sick with with care compassion for yourself or this body
[Music] I do appreciate the um earlier when I
asked you about the smiles so many of you lit up just so sweet to see all this miles
coming and lighting up very sweet so tell you what let's um
let's turn ever so gently as if we're wrapping ourselves in blankets of care
wrapping each other in blankets of care very calm gentle doesn't have to be
energetic but the question the query for tonight is can we engage with two other
human beings or practitioners without the usual ways that we show up like
wanting to do like pulling forward can we just kind of be wrapped in our care
and having them be wrapped in care when it's just gentle being together for
maybe five six minutes in the room and notice can you can you share your
kindness for yourself and for others can you can you do that and and be aware of
the way that your um you're you're relating the way that you're relating
um again with kindness for yourself kindness for others say a word and say you can share
something about your practice going alphabetically or you can say past just hold space next person can share
something and then the next person or say pass so
so um yeah I'm going to create the rooms
and invitation is see what it's like in this other way to to uh practice with
folks to stay very unique way of holding yourself with care others
with care okay I'm going to open the rooms be kind to yourself be kind to
others and it's okay to be silent it's okay to just smile and be silent in the room and see what that feels like it's
very sweet actually to be smiling at other people silently so there you go
and just opened the ropes okay welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed we're all back and I do see lots of smiles ah lots of smiles sweet and we
have a couple minutes does anybody want to share what came up Amy I see your
hand please hi so I
um had a test for attention challenges today it was like a four hour test so IQ
and I had previously had to do it as a kid and I did so poorly as a kid because of my internal self-talk was so negative
I was so distracted by my thoughts and why aren't you going faster and this and that and this time I just made his
curiosity and play and like every time my brain was challenged I would just
like kind of laugh at it and like take my time with it and just think of it in this totally metal way and and it made
me feel like I could do harder things and like my mind worked in ways I didn't expect and I pause and I closed my eyes
to listen like we do in Retreats and everything helped like I feel like so much of these practices has like Made Me
Stronger and more able to challenge myself and it's it's I'm geeking out on
it right now I'm geeking out on how much I think it helped yay oh thanks so much for sharing that
Amy oh that is so sweet it makes me happy to know it and I see the the
clapping and the hearts that the community is sharing for you and delighting and taking joy in in this
report in this practice report it's just it's beautiful it's so sweet wow the
power of these practices right the way you're describing so eloquently that it
challenges come up and instead of beating ourselves up in the moments like oh sweetie you know the metaway the
total metal way and the Curiosity and the interest gosh what a different way of being right
yay yay oh thanks so much for sharing that that is so precious beautiful
it's so sweet what a lovely note to end on tonight what a lovely note to end on
ah so thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for your cultivation
for your own sake for the sake of everyone else oh and one I'll also share
Linea shared in and chat on YouTube but um Linnaeus is my father my friend's
father-in-law just was brought home to hospice care the practices allow me to be with with
my deep love calm how precious these moments I hope that in the future if I
am in hospice my light can leave this life with such spacious peace beautiful wishes may it be so for all of
us maybe so for all of us so thank you all thank you for your practice may you be well may you be happy and free all
beings everywhere
[Music] thanks everyone take care be well bye