so so hello hello and welcome friends lovely to be with you in this moment in
time i've missed you earlier this week and i know you've been in good hands with
others so for today's practice um
what i'd like to invite us to explore um [Music]
is is one of finding our place
finding our place and what i mean by that finding our
place in some ways it seems like it's it's
personal yes it is personal finding our place finding our home
our home in our hearts and yet it's our place our place it's
the sense of not just in my own small world
me me me all about me because as we know we know that when we fall into
our own difficulties challenges maybe physical pain aging difficult
whatever it might be the world becomes kind of small becomes very small and the heart feels
tightened maybe a sense of pity even arises poor me poor me
and it's all a matter of perspective the same issues the same
matters um seen from a different perspective
as we see our place as they find our place in the midst of this amazing
life this amazing interconnected humanity open up to our condition and
everybody else's condition and holding it up with awe with
with amazement with lack of expectation there is so much that can shift in our
in our expectation maybe gratitude arises maybe joy arises um
it's a matter of finding our place with shifts of perspective where every shift
of perspective are are helpful are
supportive i'll give you one example so um so recently um
someone that i care about they've gone through an operation and
they've been in a knowledge of physical pain which is normal after the operation completely normal and another person who
cares about them they were so unhappy and they were so depressed and sad oh
this beloved person is in pain after the operation
and the refraining that that we that i offered this this dear person who was
really in grief thinking about pain was gosh if if this person if their
operation had been unsuccessful and say all the nerves were cut
and they had no sensations if they had become a paraplegic
wouldn't you give anything you had to transform this situation so that they
would feel pain right now so yay this this sign of pain in this
particular situation is actually a good sign so so what are
what are some reframes what are some ways that we can see
our situation as wow if it wasn't for this this this
what seems like a challenge right now it seems like a very difficult situation actually
it's it's a gift in disguise can it be a gift in disguise is it a matter of
shifting our perspective to see how things are gifts in disguise because the
opposite would be so much worse so um
so difficult so and i trust i trust there's so many examples
you have in your own life i'll share some more at the end
[Music] like for example if a pipe burst and you know say your home
um there was water leaking everywhere it would be very upset and then what if you
think all of a sudden wait this could be sewage i'm so glad it's not the sewage pipe that broke it's just fresh water
that broke yay totally fresh water that has broken the pipe right it's an
instantaneous shift in perspective and
it's still the same situation a pipe has broken and yet our perspective shifts
and these are all wise perspective in fact the number one
on the uh list of um
the eight-fold path the eightfold path number one is wise perspective there are
many many ways to consider what a wise perspective is
of course everything is impermanent to really appreciate that it's a wise perspective it's not personal it's not
about me to to open up from the prison of me me
me to a bigger perspective of care and love for ourselves and others
as well as [Music] unsatisfactoriness things will be satisfactory perhaps
wonderful for a period of time and then they will shift and change so what is a the wise perspective how can we shift
our perspectives um so i think i've said plenty there's a lot
more i can say but i'm going to pause now i think that's enough setting uh
enough framing just to get us out of perhaps our our
um yeah whatever perspective might have been challenging let's open it up let's open
it up anyway so let's practice together let's meditate together friends
so arriving arriving
ah arriving in your seat whether you're sitting
you're lying down whatever this body needs in this moment
to feel supported in this impermanent moment in life
precious moment of this life this heart this mind is body breathing
letting go letting go of all the words letting go of all the words thoughts
concerns letting yourself be simple in this moment
can this body release can the body relax
as the body releases and relaxes the mind
tends to release and relax so see if there's there's any tightness
any holding in your body gently gently kindly
offer it up
letting the breath breathe you
the body knows how to breathe how to be breathed
not to make breathing into a project
letting it happen in breath of breath
let it be enjoyable
those thoughts arise as they will inevitably do not a problem not a mistake
clearly seeing what thoughts have arisen
i'm then releasing this moment to release
any thoughts perspectives that are not helpful
for the benefit of this cultivation
feeling the connection [Music] the feet
on earth the sit bones contacting
cushion the seat your hands touching each other or your
lap the breath moving through the whole body
received in the lower abdomen
here here just this breath
just this breath the entirety of the breath
entirety of the opera
calming soothing nourishing just this is enough
letting go releasing releasing whatever is not helpful
is not supportive in this moment
and now i'd like to invite you
with care with kindness with metta
before this being who is you
this being who suffers this being who has high
intentions
for goodness for cultivation
values this being who is you who cares for
others sense of dedication
love kindling rekindling the sense of
kindness warmth
care for this being who is you
i'm as if you were your own wise friend
wise and loving friend as if you're stepping out of yourself
the sense of wisdom and compassion for yourself
or if it's easier you can imagine some other being whom you consider to be wise and
compassionate it could be the buddha kuan yin
another human being
holding you with care with love
with unconditional acceptance
letting yourself be held before we proceed
and now see yourself with this dear friend
it might be yourself or the buddha kuan yin the deer being
symbolizing compassion and wisdom
as you're held with kindness and care maybe you bring up something
that you are maybe upset about or
challenged by
let me share this with this being compassionate wise being
and
imagine them listening with care with compassion wisdom
really listening really holding space
as you describe they give you their complete
attention non-judgmental attention
and maybe what is needed is just for them to hold whatever you shared with them
with compassion with kindness letting yourself
and whatever you brought up to be held
yes it's not easy yes
and now if it feels appropriate it feels appropriate
not necessary but it feels appropriate
maybe you invite your wise compassionate being
to help open your eyes to a different perspective
regarding what is happening for you that is difficult
or challenging
maybe they have a wise and wide perspective
spacious perspective about what is happening
they allow you to see it they invite you to see it
what's happening from a different perspective
let yourself be surprised
and when perhaps this different surprising
perspective has been offered to you
notice what arises in you in your heart so surprise gladness appreciation
gratitude
equanimity and can you rest with that
can you rest with this breathing in and out
with the sense of goodness that might have opened up
trust trust your inner wisdom
symbolized by your wise compassionate being
maybe a gratitude arises for this moment
feeling okay enough in this moment
just this moment can it be enough as it is
in fact plenty a gift of grace as it is
here just here this moment
letting yourself be held in kindness
with care with meta
may i be safe from inner and outer harm
may i be happy and joyful
may i be healthy and strong
or may my life flow with ease
let yourself rest with kindness with mental or this wise perspective
that has been opened up to you opening up the sense of gratitude and
appreciation for what is even if it's challenging
what would you do what would you give
if things were different what is this challenge significa signifying that's actually a
blessing it's a pain in your body
that actually your nervous system is working
and you can feel pain that you're alive
and for the last moments of this practice period
letting whatever rose or did not arise be just as it is without judgment
needing it to be different offering kindness wisdom equanimity to
ourselves for this period of practice
and trusting that there is kindness goodness generated and offering it freely
generously to all beings everywhere including
ourselves may all beings everywhere
be safe happy healthy and happies may all beings everywhere
be free from suffering and causes and suffering especially those in more zones
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone
so we have a few minutes or any
reflections any aha moments any questions anything came up for you
that you'd like to share offer
sangha for your own benefit and benefit of others you can type in chad which type to me alone
i will uh not read your name if it's uh
offered to everyone chat to everyone i will also read your name so
so what's any reflections anything you notice especially
with the invitation for the wise being to show you a different way
to see what might be challenging it might be difficult
was it surprising did it surprise you finding your place
mary [Music]
hi thank you um
so it this is kind of a very uh simple maybe question which is
i think at one point i heard you say offer it up
and i was raised catholic and offer it up kind of
in in my culture said you should keep suffering
so i know you meant something different yeah
i did so so let me help me understand so in your culture offering it up means
accept suffering or like well you know
i'm sure it was twisted but it but it was sort of like
and especially for girls women you know that's your lot in life
accept it accept it this is what god's giving you oh offer it up oh yeah i see i hear it
different okay so yeah yeah that i see how the words can fit there okay so thanks for bringing that up mary so the
way that i actually offering it up i have this image this vision sort of offering
up like like okay i'll just talk about the way i see it is um
[Music] i have this image of our practice our being our existence
with so much beauty and sacredness and the world as a sacred
and there's this altar our our practice our what we do we're offering it up we're
putting it on an altar of humanity we're offering up even our suffering as a gift
it's just we're offering like this is this is my peace or our gifts are our
happiness we offer it it's just like everything we are our practice here is my practice my mind was distracted but
but i offer it dear humanity dear universe it's kind of offering it
in that way making an offering of ourselves whatever is going on i love that making an offering of ourselves
and and our efforts i guess that's what how i'm hearing it our efforts our commitment
our desire of everything of commitment efforts
of ourselves even i would even and this might be
this is this might be kind of surprising or not make sense so i'll leave this for
later reflection perhaps but even our joy we offer to the world right it's our
joy is an offering so is our suffering not in the way of oh i'm just gonna suffer so well i'm gonna carry but there
is some there's a nuance of of um of i mean not that we that's that we
want to hold on to our suffering that's not the idea but there can be a sense of
beauty there can be a sense of grace and yet this is what i'm going through right
now dear humanity this is what i'm going through right now it's just so it's it's subtle it's a
sense of sharing it's a sense of offering making an offering of all of ourselves
bright the light and the the shadow all the challenges
yeah thank you thank you mary thanks so much
any other reflections questions
okay since i don't see anything else any hands raised or any reflections in chat
maybe i'll give it another pause i'll talk about
um relating connecting in sangha together with other human beings this is
where our practice meets the road and um
of course a lot of times we consider practice to
be private internal but it isn't right it isn't it's it's in
it's relational our practice is so relational we cultivate all this not just to have internal peace in our minds
but to also as we're just talking with mary earlier offer ourselves offer the best of
ourselves offer ourselves to others to the world to be this vessel of
of stability equanimity love and care so can we do that in small groups
together groups of roughly size three and let everyone each person
is invited to speak just from your own experience
not commenting not reflecting not managing the group just speak from your own
experience few words perhaps about how this practice was for you what came up
there's no right or wrong it's challenging it was lovely it was terrible it's all it's okay you're just
sharing your humanity it's all right you just share for about just one minute and then
the next and then the next person will say one uh nugget and then the next person
one nugget short nugget they'll come back to you and you'll go round and round a few rounds and it comes to you and
there's nothing you want to say you can just hold space and say pass just hold wise compassionate space for
others so that's the invitation
and i will create the breakout rooms now
and you can go and say alphabetical order just so that it's
easy i'm creating the rooms
uh here we go okay i think i need to recreate the
rooms um there we go let's see i think
what's going on here oh i see what's happening the count just changed okay recreating the rooms all right
and i see one comment before i open them thank you for the refraining i was able
to refrain a seemingly heavy-handed remark from someone else now i know how
that feels grateful oh beautiful thank you for their reflection yay maybe there will be more insights coming
back after you you share in small groups so i'm opening all groups take care of yourselves take
care of each other okay
the rooms are closed everybody's back and we have a few minutes for
any reflections that might have come up um
i'd love to hear from you if you like to share you can type in chat or you can raise your hand i see more smiles than
when you went into the group it's always sweet to see
what did you notice with this practice any a-has you like to share
for the benefit of yourself and others was there a shift in perspective
for anyone yes debra
i think i think it really helped me to [Music] look at it as the reframe and to
just know that i'm where i am today i don't like it but i know that
i'll be somewhere else tomorrow and i'm just offering it up
and it's just kind of like a um a temperature take taking your
temperature and realizing that well i've come a ways with my practice because i realize
it's okay to be this way there's no right way i'm not going to just sit here joyful
all the time so yes exactly thank you debro what a
beautiful insight it's okay it's not it's it's the human condition we're not
always joyful all the time yeah we have a body i mean hello
but the realization's important because you know we don't want to think i'm i'm going to be here for the next 20 years
this would not be fun oh the truth i mean if of impermanence is
on your side that bruh if everything changes of course it changes it's never gonna stay the same
of course it's the truth of impermanence we just have to see it over and over and
over again as it becomes internalized as you're saying yeah i'm
just this is temporary i may not like it okay it's like that that's saying if you don't like the weather in london just
just wait five minutes you know it's like you don't like the internal weather just wait the conditions are going to
change it's all impermanent yeah beautiful thank you for that
thank you for that reflection so dear ones we have come to the end of another
happy hour practicing together bringing our hearts and minds together
may all of our practice be a cause and condition for
ease freedom freedom for all of us and all things everywhere may all
beings be free may all beings be happy
[Music]
thanks everyone