there so hello and welcome everyone hello and
welcome to this rendition of happy hour makes me happy to be with you to see you
to practice together so for today's practice um
i'd like to invite us to to engage in
in um simple meta
and uh there are few different themes i want to bring in tonight um
yeah how much do i want to say to frame it you know maybe i'll say more i'll reverse the order we'll do the
meditation together first and maybe afterwards i'll say a few things
um about it yeah let's let's shake things up why not just for the fun of it so
so let's let's land together let's arrive together in
our bodies ah
arriving
arriving wholeheartedly if you need to shift and move
to be comfortable is a good time to do that to be kind to your body
letting go letting go of
what has come before whatever thoughts engagements
occupations preoccupations also letting go of planning what's yet
to come afterwards carving this time out this moment in time in this moment just
to take refuge to be simple letting go
it's like moses parting the red sea thoughts of from the past thoughts of
the future hold on for a second
a path paving a path
of safety [Music] in this moment
to gently walk down ah
it's peaceful here it's peaceful
it's peaceful
letting your awareness turn to the body hello body how are you
with kindness turning to the body
dear body sweetheart are you tired
are you anxious are you relaxed are you hurting
however you are however you are you can be just as you
are welcome welcome to be you are welcome to
be just as you are dear body ah
i appreciate you i appreciate this amazing body just the same
this incredible work of nature
thank you body i let the breath
be breathed
let there be appreciation for this breath this good
and there may be comings and goings of thought of sounds sensations
it's okay it's all okay
connecting with the breath
the breath soothing calming
comforting like a lullaby
whatever is happening the body and the heart and the mind
let the breath the sensations the breath in the body
be harbingers of peace here here
here dear heart just here simply here
breathing
and if you like to add the phrases of meta for this body for yourself
sitting quietly may i be safe
from inner and outer home
may i be happy and joyful
may i be healthy and strong
and may my life unfold with ease
simply dropping these gifts these blessings these wishes
as a gift not attached to the outcome
who knows we can't always ensure
safety happiness health ease conditions are changeable and yet
we offer this to ourselves to cultivate our heart
and kindness towards ourselves with our good wishes
may i may i be safe ah let the goodness the kindness of this
wish land for you in your heart
may i be happy taste the deliciousness of this wish
sense of happiness even imagining yourself happy smiling may i be happy
may i be healthy
receiving the kindness the good will imagining yourself healthy strong
as much as possible
may my life unfold with ease may i have ease
feeling yourself with ease ah
ease of well-being how nice
oh [Music]
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease
safe happy
healthy ease
and now if you would
bringing to your heart to your mind someone
who has been kind to you
maybe they've supported you
they've been there for you
thoughtful caring someone for whom you feel a sense of
gratitude in this moment could be some someone recent or from
your past doesn't matter the first person who comes up
this feeling of appreciation just appreciating
this being
let your heart light up appreciating this being and their
goodness this aspect of goodness
that they've shared with you
this aspect of their generosity
that has impacted you
that your heart lied up feeling this goodness their goodness
their care
maybe the words thank you bubble up in your heart or smile shows up
or maybe you just feel happier lighter bringing them to your heart let yourself
rejoice really enjoy
this goodness this bright light
relish it relish them
as if you were basking in sunlight let yourself bask
i feel nourished by this kindness
this goodness soaking it in
and if just in case you get in your own way feeling undeserving or
a shameful word oh too much kindness
don't get in your own way who are you to get in the way of goodness this
person offering their kindness their light
shining brightly
give your heart to praise to praise their goodness
don't get in the way of goodness being appreciated
being recognized
celebrate it
from this place of joy celebration appreciation
letting there be the metaphrases for this being
may you be safe not attach to outcome just offering out
of generosity utter appreciation kindness your own metta
your gift of mitta may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease
appreciate how good it can feel for you for your heart
to be offering these wishes to someone else
to offer menta how happy making it is for you
uplifting uplifting to be kind to another
inner thoughts
if you find your mind wandering reconnect connect with this being
their kindness their goodness sharing meta
may you be safe happy healthy
and have ease dear one
and if you like to turn [Music] back to yourself meta for yourself
or mental for both of us may both of us be safe happy healthy and happies
you are welcome to do either
let it be nourishing this practice not a grim duty but nourishing
joyful
soothing uplifting
and as we bring this practice period to close
opening all the doors and windows of our heart and shining our mentha
our goodwill our good wishes offering it freely to everyone to all
beings
may all beings everywhere all beings
be safe happy healthy at ease
may all beings everywhere be well
no goodness know their own goodness and the goodness
of others may all beings everywhere
be free including ourselves
thank you all thanks for your practice
so we started five minutes earlier today since i didn't give a darn it slice
so i stopped five minutes early too 30 minutes sit together
went by quickly at least for me so
so the couple of themes that i brought in uh for our practice today we first
started with as always with grounding with the breath with the body settling and sense of
kindness towards this body acceptance of this amazing body then we turned
to meta for ourselves simply with the four phrases of meta or
whatever your phrases might be and then we turned to appreciate
goodness someone's kindness to us recently in the past
and we let our hearts we invited our hearts to rejoice celebrate really
um feel the beauty the goodness of the kind act as a
way of uplifting appreciating kindness goodness
and i do wonder whether you felt an up uplift in your heart
i know that i was smiling just feeling this kindness this goodness from this this person
a young person in fact just just relishing wow goodness in the world goodness
shining this person and then from there turning to to meta
sharing kindness meta good will for this being
as our gift of generosity um
and then at the end turning again to ourselves or to both of us and then opening to all beings
so all these turns um many times you know we might start practicing and
maybe practice feels heavy or like a thud and then we turn to say appreciating
this body and maybe something opens up or we turn to appreciating someone's goodness and wow the heart just lights
up there's a sense of brightness in the heart [Music] and that lights up the rest of our
practice for them for ourselves for others so there are lots of helpful skillful means
that that we can use in this practice to cultivate to cultivate kindness to
cultivate good will to turn to keep turning our heart to kindness towards others ourselves
so we have a few minutes um [Music]
for reflections questions comments what came up for you if you'd like to share
for the benefit of the sangha maybe your opening if there was an aha moment that helps others also
for their aha moments if there's something challenging you can bring it up how do i work with
this because if you have this question the chances are other people have the same question
and there's no wrong question here treat it all with kindness
you can type in chat if it's typed to me privately i won't read your name it's time to
everyone i'll read your name you can also raise your zoom hand
your physical hands i may not see so i'll take your pause
as i sip my tea
pat says on youtube thank you nikki very quiet tonight nice for the evening yes
until tomorrow morning yes i'll see you tomorrow morning very grateful for this work radiant thank you pat ah grateful
for your practice radiant catherine
um hi thank you all right for the practice
um i'm in a moment where i'm i can feel like i'm
triggered into old habits hold old patterns that are really
deep ones and i kind of called the situation in because i want to work with them and
heal them um but i'm seeing that like part of that
pattern or habit is to really feels like the door is really
shut on self meta um and
[Music] the way that that is shut is through like disconnection as opposed to like i think
it's easier for me when i'm feeling like a big like fear or anger or sadness to like turn
love towards that feeling but towards but this is kind of like a dissociation
that makes it very hard to even stay focused enough to remember to to come
to or even remember what it feels like what self kindness feels like
so i think personally i'm just naming that because that helps like bring it back
because i can feel emotion coming up now um but i just wanted to name that in case
other people have that experience too and how to work with that yeah yeah thank you
thank you katrin and don't meet yourself just yet um thank you for bringing that up and
and just to reflect back what i heard you say was
some challenge with another person and you intentionally brought that in and you call that in uh to to
work with it to to bring some method to it to yourself to them and and then it became perhaps a little
overwhelming in in a way and and the old pattern habit patterns of of your mind came in i
was like wow overwhelmed okay i've lost contact i've lost contact with myself
because i'm hurting right now and yet this is so hard i'm so angry and afraid
and all there are like wait how do i connect here and and you actually naming
that and sharing that oh it's brought some connection yes it's like this and it's okay it's not as
overwhelmed when you actually say it out loud it's not as overwhelming as it seemed silently in your mind a moment
ago isn't that amazing and yes yeah so that overwhelm oh yeah it
it uh it comes down uh it comes down a notch and like oh yeah i
can connect with myself i'm here yes and there's and appreciating them the sense of uprightness that has spoken up and
shared this said this out out loud and another thing
i would suggest as you may know is is bow to this uh
you know what you've brought in to work with when it becomes a little uns unstable and then disconnect and just
bow to it thank you i will come back to you i respect you and now let me
put you aside for a moment and and stabilize with my hand with my feet just
just loving the connection i mean it doesn't have to be any more than that just like i'm here i'm here and imagine
yourself you're the buddha you're the buddha sitting under the bodhi tree touching the earth but you just touched the earth
ah mister has been my witness i'm here yes i'm here i'm here and that sense of connection
can to the earth can bring that sense of connection to yourself and the way back
into meta how does that sound yeah it feels good and it's helping me
with the piece that i that i think was making it so hard which is um to
actually offer compassion and love to the part of me that shut down out of
such a like out of care right that the overwhelm into like dissociation and even like
self-criticism like i s i can see again how like oh sweetheart like you're really doing your
best you're doing your best to to protect this tender heart and this overwhelm
um and that feels like the the way back in beautiful beautiful beautiful he said
beautifully felt exactly oh sweetheart thank you thank you
thank you and sweetheart you can relax it's okay yeah that's beautiful thank
you catherine
so yeah the reflections from today i see there's a question
uh privately is coming by something i taught actually yesterday morning on uh
youtube when i talked about not breathing into the nostrils that
that if you're doing if you're noticing your breath here at the anapanas but the
mindfulness spot uh notice it outside not inside
your nose and
[Music] and asking for a little more explanation
about that so so the problem again if you just practice a little bit here and there you
wouldn't notice if you're doing deep sinus breathing but if you keep practicing more and more
and more there's a sense of constriction in the nose they will become so
prominent that inside the nose it will feel like bricks and you and one will not be able to
breathe actually just one will feel heartless hardness what's called the earth element sense of hardness in the
face in the back of the nose happens so that is the problem with deep sinus breathing as a practitioner bad habit
so so time has come let's turn to practicing in small groups together
and the invitation is to [Music]
share kindness share kindness with each other this is an opportunity the small group's an
opportunity i mean now if you've been sharing kindness in your mind to yourself to others
now you have the opportunity to be kind to show up with kindness
to turn your heart your mind towards kindness and the prompt i'd like to give you a
prompt the prompt is um as you are showing up with kindness this is the
how the what is um if you'd like to share something about an act of kindness that has been
shared with you recently maybe what came up for you in your meditation tonight or or
anything else or you can also share silence and space with others
let's go reverse alphabetical order based on your first name
one person will say maybe just one nugget not a long monologue maybe just a minute
the other person will say just one more minute and then the next person another minute they'll come back to you and
you'll go round and round until the time is up and just speak from your own experience
not managing or or um
you know trying to control other people's experience let them be as they are even if they are with you in silence
let it be just as it is so going to create the rooms here
and um yeah take care of yourselves
take care of each other be kind be kind be kind i cannot
emphasize being kind enough here we go opening the rooms
there okay that's probably better okay welcome back everyone hi so we've got about a couple of
minutes left um and would love to hear if there are any
reflections comments um something that maybe came up
in the groups any aha moments anything else
sharing kindness you can raise your hand or type in chat
uh seems like jennifer is waving so i don't see your physical hands so i have to
okay jennifer i see you i'm gonna ask it on me there okay mine is really fast i um
just had a really nice looking group tonight and it felt so good in my heart so i'm grateful for that
oh that is so sweet oh thank you thanks for bringing that in it it uplifts my
heart always to hear how lovely connecting and warm and supportive the groups
um can be is so lovely so thank you for bringing that into into the space
jennifer lovely so dear ones it is 7 p.m
the end of happy hour thank you for coming for practicing for cultivating your heart
for the benefit of yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be happy
may all things be free [Music]
thanks all take good care be well