so so hello and welcome welcome everyone to
happy hour what a delight to be practicing together
um from all over the world so many different time zones and northern
southern hemispheres love it love it so coming together and practicing so so for
today's happy hour I wanted to invite us to um gosh
um yeah this is what I've I've been sitting with so I want to share a little bit about my practice what's been coming
up for me is is the sense of um guys respect uh all I would say all
for for having the opportunity to be alive and love and how amazing it is it is to
be alive to be human in this form however this thing came about Evolution
or however like here we are these conscious beings and we have the ability
to be kind to love ourselves and others it just boggles my mind that's the
that's where I've been sitting today so I wanted to share that with you and invite you into that space with me and
I'll guide you little by little even if you're like what is she talking about don't worry I'll guide you with me to so
that we all really um we don't see this practice of
cultivating kindness as a chore or a duty and so it's hard to be
kind and I am going to do this again ah but as
as Grace as um a gift as a rare opportunity that here
we are what are the chances that the book of Our Lives
was to be written anyway this life with all these causes and conditions yes
plenty of challenges plenty of of difficulty plenty of beauty
plenty of of Grace
um but the fact that the book of Our Lives this book is written at all that
of all the cause and conditions we were the one to be born our parents meeting
the conditions all it is here we are through all the cause and conditions
this being and and here we we have an opportunity we
have this gift that's called life it's impermanence it's very very short and now it here we are in this happy
hour here we have come together in this way wow
what what an amazing gift what an amazing opportunity
um to be able to to consider to think to to Incline our
hearts our minds through thoughts to feelings of kindness
of Love wow as I say this actually I I want to drop down and kiss the ground to
be in the space with you what a what a Grace of an opportunity this co-creation
of all of us together to be able to do this wow this is amazing this is
incredible to know the Dharma The Good Fortune to know the Dharma to have access to the
Dharma to be able to to come together not even leaving your home
this good fortune that each and every single one of you has even if you are not well right now if you are sick as I
know some of you have been the past week this disgrace this this gift of being
able to spend your time the privilege really such a privilege
to know these teachings to be able to practice in community in this way
through this technology this amazing stuff this Zoom thing that didn't even
exist 20 30 years ago so all of this just relishing giving thanks giving
thanks gratitude for all of this being able to and giving our heart to it being
nourished by it and giving our heart to it this cultivation so that's what I'd like to invite us to
to swim in our minds to swim in tonight so I wanted to set the stage this way
and [Music] um and yeah as always we'll start by settling in the
body and with the breath just settling arriving arriving and then I'll have
some invitations for us to to um to explore to explore this the space
together so okay all right let's uh let's begin
let's begin so um so if you need to move and shift
to land in your body where you're sitting your shoulders your
back your neck or just physically getting up and moving to to a cushion or lying down see what your
body needs In This Moment
and then planting your feet if you're sitting on a chair planting the bottom of your feet
and the Earth this Earth
the floor and Lou of the Earth letting yourself sit upright
as if there is a little magnet ah gently pulls up when
you're the top of your head your torso and
lengthens
I'm not pushing it up it just gets in strengthened gets
lengthened on its own ah
sitting tall like a mountain and then the rest of your body can drop you can land
oh the mountain has a wide base feeling your sit bones
feeling your sit Bones on the cushion on the chair
I'm letting the mind rest
rest
thing to do right now if you're holding a little
little baby or a little young puppy your kitty
whatever speaks to you you can say rest sweetheart rest
press rest hold it
smooth the hair the fur whatever it might be in your
imagination rest sweetheart rest my heart rest my
mind okay rest yes
resting resting letting the breath move through the body
with each breath resting some more
and if the mind wanders not a problem not a problem at all
no need for judging or yanking
sweetheart it's okay rest rest come rest
come rest be soothed yes yes yes you've been thinking all day
dear mind you've been busy all day dear heart it's okay
it's hard to slow down it's all right
releasing the body lightening lightening your load
of preoccupations
you may need to let go many many times do it
lovingly lightly ah
every time you let go of thoughts for occupations fold yourself
in The Refuge of this moment
let yourself enjoy gift the grace of each breath each and
breath each out breath
on the surface it's just a breath
but pause really relish notice
complexity
the gift
the Nuance of each breath each one's different a little different
each breath is like a Sonata a piece of music
the symphony
if you listen to it from afar oh it's just noise
but as you get to really pay attention
you get to appreciate how much really it has taken
Revolution this body
make the Perfection of this breath
bringing oxygen to this body keeping it alive
the release the joy the Delight the pleasure of each Opera
expansion of each and breath so intimate
you don't have to think about it let yourself feel it is swayed by it back and forth
let yourself be rocked back and forth
by each breath
their great great great great great great great my grandmother was a fish with gills
here here is this being who's me
this body breathing in air breathing out air wow
so amazing
letting this body really feel the grace of the breath it's not to think about it
bringing these invitations drop in and appreciate the sensations
more not to ruminate Let It Go if you're thinking about it all Let It Go
rest rest to your heart rest of your mind
be rocked by the breath
the way a baby is rocked back and forth
in the crib
being able to breathe wow being alive
being able to think even if we call him distractions right now
how amazing these thoughts these bubbles
of creation foreign
how amazing to be able to
reflect to think to feel
behind thoughts we know how powerful
they are
our powerful thoughts are
inclining our actions our tendencies
or personalities our future who we become
who we are who we become these thoughts
the way we interact with others Who We Are in the world and the Legacy
we leave as we will leave all of us in this world
relaxing the body choosing to Incline our hearts
the kindness first for this being who is me this amazing miracle that breathing
and walks and heals and suffers and
is joyous and has hopes and dreams and all of that the full catastrophe
let's incline our hearts our minds our heart mind our chitta poly language of
the Buddha or heart mind
kindness
you like to experiment putting a hand
and your chest middle of your chest heart center proverbial Heart Center
connecting with your body it is being who is me
if you're holding yourself with care may this being comes me
may they be well maybe she he may I
whatever works for you in this moment try a few variations
may I be well
let's say it was just simple wish may this being who is me be well
yeah wow how amazing to be able to consider think a wish of kindness for yourself
wow this is pretty cool
not to be taken for granted can think
consider kind thoughts for myself
drop by drop wow
try it again may this being who is me
be well as if you're a friend to yourself
inclining this goodness this Goodwill for yourself
also if you are experimenting with putting a hand on your heart center this
sensation actually feel the sensations pretty amazing to feel yourself
both feeling and being felt is not to be taken for granted
you're just so used to it when we touch ourselves but hold yourself
your child chappy wow there's this warmth of a hand on my
chest a calming how soothing this is so sweet and let the hand feel the
the warmth of this chest this
alive being it's touching as if your beloved other
can feel so miraculous to touch ourselves being touched
and touching shift your perspective from your hand to your chest and drift your
chest to your hand feel the warmth feel the pressure
and maybe if you're have the sense the perspective of the chest it's as if a dear friend putting
their hand on your chest sweetheart may you be well
well switching your perspective to your hand oh dear heart Dear Heart dear being
dear beings was doing their best oh sweetheart
may you be well
well let your hand feel powerful of intention
full of grace
endowing endowing it's an important touch this act
of holding touching
sometimes when we don't have words actually just this gesture is enough
when you have empowered it when you have endowed with meaning it's all that's needed sometimes
in the middle of the day just holding
oh sweetheart just being held
how amazing how amazing we can hold ourselves with kindness
wow what an amazing amazing world
where each of us has the capacity ability to hold ourselves literally
physically your hearts and our minds with kindness and just for a moment with one thought
with one wish
such a world where beautiful music exists love exists
care exists wow we have the privilege to be living
in this world for this brief time
in a world where other people live too people we care about
invite invited being to your heart space someone you care
about present maybe pass as long as there's no too
much grief or sadness invite them for the world where this
person exists has lived with their nuances with their
particularities their joys the way they show up
who they are it's pretty amazing their history their likes their dislikes
their laughter the way they look
the way they look at you
what a world and what a world where you can love them
feel care for them wish them well I wish you well
or maybe thank them just another expression of mitta of love
sense of gratitude appreciation see what feels right
with someone from the present from the present has been called up showed up
submitta for them may you be well
or I care for you
or I love you
someone from the past
thank you opening your heart feeling the grace of
gratitude
live even if briefly in the world where you love or have loved you care
for another being
in a world where Beauty exists and nature and art and music whatever
uplifts your heart Beauty lives in the heart
beauty of Love of care
perhaps inviting both of you both this being that has come up
in yourself May both of us
have goodness be held in matter
safety happiness health and ease
or maybe simply thank you
I love you or thank you for caring for me as you have
gratitude to live who exist in this moment of time all of
us exist in this brief moment of time in a world where
we can feel appreciate be grateful
for love and love
Goodwill kindness readliness all its Shades forms however it shows up that
night in this moment for you Hallelujah
and as we bring this period of practice and to an end
together hmm appreciating appreciating coming
together in this moment in time to cultivate to
turn our minds or hearts to meta to love this brief moment in time this
cultivation God grace what a gift
be able to cultivate to love
have meta to have received meta and continue to receive good well and love
in this world
may all beings everywhere
no truly no
the grace the depth the expanse of
matter of Love in This World in this Universe of ours
internally externally never feel far from it may all beings everywhere
be free
thanks everyone thank you for being here for your practice
showing up hmm ah
so many gifts so so we have opportunity right now a few
minutes for Reflections for questions for for um
comments what you notice what came up for you in the
AHA moments you like to share um challenges anything and the invitation
is to share for the benefit of yourself and everyone when we share our
practice it opens more doors for others so what came up for you
always do different practices as happier or the same thing twice I don't think we
had ever done it this way as far as I remember the past two and a half years or the past actually more than two and a
half years I've been doing happier for what three four five years I don't know I'm losing track
Karina please
what was coming up for me was like um I I guess I was just like is it
really so amazing that I'm here and like we're having
like that we live in I don't know I think I like at times they feel really connected to that
um that feeling of like gratitude and at times like today I felt just like really
flat and like yeah my brain can recognize like that that's amazing and
but my heart was like not there today yeah yeah not a problem no worries
um thanks for sharing that and and it's all okay we are planting seeds right
we're planting seeds so in some practices you might actually feel that
that sense of awe and some other times as you said the heart is flat and
and the more you actually plant these seeds the more
your mind will find an inclination towards gratitude and connection so and that's how meta and all these
practices work um it um yeah this is how they work it's
expected it's not not every single time there's connection with them and and it's perfectly annoying but hang in
there keep without being frustrated I didn't hear frustration in your voice voice which I appreciate it was just
like yeah it wasn't there today fine no problem you showed up you planted seeds
and now notice how it might show up this is the other interesting thing how it might show up tonight tomorrow the next
day you just don't know the story of um and I've seen so many practitioners
actually that that practice and and sometimes they say like it feels dry nothing is happening and then later I'm
saying wow I'm a different person my life's changed I'm acting differently I feel different I'm like yeah yep yeah
great yes exactly that that so thanks for sharing that bit uh let's see
Stephanie please hi everyone I first want to say thank
you I'm new to this group and um I usually I usually do a Zen practice and this was really really different and in
a great way so I really appreciate it you know the gentleness of it as well as
when we're invited someone we loved in so thank you that was really helpful and
then I have a quick practical question how can I get this recording on YouTube because I want to I want to do what you
uh led us through again and again yeah yeah yeah so um all these uh so thank
you and welcome Stephanie yay welcome uh to happy hour and and um all the
recordings are available um on YouTube through the IMC inside Meditation Center Channel as well as
Audio Dharma okay audiodarma.org so if you easiest ways
actually go to Audio Dharma one word Audio Drama dot o r g and you'll see
their recordings and the videos it's all there search for happy hour and there thank you Neil just posted the link so
if you link clicked on that it'll take you there thank you you're so welcome
beautiful and we have a reflection from let's see
on on Youtube Learning so much also this makes makes me remember old insights how
beautiful love that connecting to Old insights that's lovely any other Reflections if you also want
to share in chat you can if you type it to me individually alone I will uh read
your reflection privately not read your name so it'll be uh private reflection
um and if you want to uh type it to everyone then I'll read it out loud I'll
take another moment any other Reflections any aha moments
anything that really perhaps connected for you or not
pay me please
I was I was hesitant to say anything because I wanted to leave error time for everyone else because I tend to speak
when I'm here but um well Nikki thank you so much that was wonderful
um so I'm in the ninth month of um the year-long program at Spirit Rock
um a year to live so I've been spending a lot of time you know thinking about death and dying
and this was a wonderful um counterweight to that
um to just you know be reminded of how um precious and fleeting our lives are it
was wonderful thank you thank you Jamie yeah thank you so much for for speaking and bringing that in
yeah it's uh it's such an important aspect of actually mindfulness of death but though I appreciate the the program
at Spirit Rock and and the way I teach it I want to prove I like to bring in as much emphasis to the preciousness of
life and preparing for death I think that's just as important so thank you for that yeah Claire will let this be
the last comment here thanks so much Nikki this this was a
beautiful evening uh it happens to be my birthday so it was a lovely gift happy birthday Claire thank you uh but and
what it brought up for me was really beautiful too I come from a musical family and for whatever the reason my
mind went deeply into some of my favorite music and I just sort of heard
it and I was practically singing through it because I wanted to come but
I was hearing in my head and I was really a wonderful experience for me so thank you oh so sweet thank you Claire
thanks for sharing that and happy birthday again I'm just loving your your practice share your practice report
makes my heart so happy that you're spending your your birthday Eve with with the Sangha very sweet you're my
people yay very sweet thank you let's see a couple of Reflections before we go
into groups one person privately uh I had been
challenged to Incline towards gratitude until recently when I took your retreat on death as a practice but that focus on
how we don't know when or where we may die has sharpened my focus on the
preciousness of every moment oh beautiful thank you so much for sharing that reflection oh that makes me so
happy yay beautiful beautiful and let's see
um Neil says quotes Richard Dawkins we are going to die and that makes us the
lucky ones most people are never going to die because they are never going to be born yes I love that the potential
people who could not have been here in my place but who will in fact never see the light of day outnumber the sand
grains in Arabia oh my God I love that perspective thanks for adding that that is so great oh that's sweet oh and we
have a friend joining from New Zealand who also sends great great to appreciate people close and far thanks Nikki from
New Zealand very sweet thanks for joining us John beautiful
yeah and somebody asked what other groups do you lead uh check my website multiple ones
um and here's another old uh OG boy saying sometimes I go about pitting
myself and all the while I am being carried across the sky by beautiful clouds yes oh my goodness you guys like
I'm loving the the wisdom that's coming from the community that's so sweet so
sweet so so so let's uh and that the question about
what else I lead check my website Nikki mergafori.com you can just search for
Nikki Dharma or Nikki meditation you'll find my website and you can see all the things I teach on my calendar
um okay dear ones let's um let's turn
to spend a few minutes with each other so it's one thing to practice with our
eyes closed uh go internal and now this is a practice to put this is an
opportunity to put our practice uh to to practice practice with others in small
groups so I'm going to create the small groups of size three and the invitation is
um you are welcome to share maybe a word or two about how the practice was for
you the sense of awe appreciation or you can just hold silence and say pass uh
just speak from your own experience and then the next person will say something from their experience and then the next
person or pass and you just go around and around a few times please be kind to yourself be kind to
everyone else don't direct or ask direct questions just share from yourself your
own insight and maybe you'll say this was hard this was really challenging it was flat and just perfectly fine
it's really a benefit to yourself to to relate to others and
with kindness so okay uh creating the breakout rooms and
here we go I cannot get home it's gonna take me another moment to make the
groups and uh [Music]
let's see it's okay all right uh I'm going to open
them I might have to do a little bit of okay I think it's good to know all right I'm gonna open the rooms here we go take
care be kind to yourself be kind to others here we go
okay everyone the rooms are closed welcome back and we are out of time
because we had so many wonderful Reflections at the beginning so what I'd like to do is to to honor the time and
and close uh and yet I'll uh what I'll do is that afterwards I'll stay on Zoom
for the next couple of minutes if they're in your Reflections or anything anybody would like to ask or share so so let's dedicate the Merit and end so
thank you all thank you for joining the practice for cultivating kindness for
yourself and and others may all beings be wealthy may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you