so welcome welcome everybody it's nice to see you all to be practicing together
so we'll start just with a silent sit and nancy will read the we'll ring the bell
for us at 8 15. you're welcome come on in no problem
and also a welcome to our friends from the other side of this camera
on youtube welcome
part of the beauty of this practice
is that we don't have to do anything special
we just show up the way that we are
and we notice
how are we
what's happening this moment
there's a trust
for this moment it's sufficient just to pay attention
we don't have to do anything different we don't have to breathe different
often we sit in this way just to support the posture but we don't have to sit in this way
we're just noticing
with and letting the body breathe itself
and letting the mind notice
so
we can be mindful of whatever is arising
might be sounds
might be experiences in the body
maybe there's some sensations
where we're sitting on the cushion
and we can notice our relationship to those experiences
is there ease is there aversion
no matter what you find
can you just hold it
without a sense that it has to be different
we're just noticing with mindfulness practice we're not breathing in any particular
way we're not doing any particular thing we're just noticing
it can be sounds sensations the breath
and when you find yourself lost in thought
it doesn't have to be a problem just
begin again
so [Music]
so
so maybe i'll let those of you that are leaving oh okay pick your exit if you'd like or
can stay
tonight i'd like to continue on my
just exploration or the discussion about these seven factors of awakening
they sound so lofty right these factors of awakening it sounds a little formulaic too as long
as i just get these factors right then i'll be awake and easy peasy
so tonight i'd like to talk about the fourth factor of awakening which is joy
i know i was surprised to learn that joy is part of this
awakening schema just quickly i'll say that first
starts with mindfulness and then investigation then energy
then joy then tranquility concentration and equanimity
seven factors of awakening and
in some ways we can think about you know this path towards awakening
is related to this uh the four noble truths it's kind
of the quintessential buddhist teachings
the truth of there is suffering the arising of suffering
there's the ending of suffering the cessation of suffering and there's a way
leading to this cessation of suffering and so
the seven factors maybe are we could consider as part of the way cultivating them
but this one joy in particular is with the third normal truth the
ending of suffering right when there's joy present there's not a lot of suffering
and i appreciate this very much because often it's easy to fall into this idea
that at the end there's going to be some whatever the end is right but there'll
be some shep zam kind of moment and there'll be no suffering but we have to
wait until completely the end but it's not like that right the
means and the end are related so there's all these little letting goes of suffering that's happening with our
practice there's all this joy some of it's joy not all of it some of
it is joy that's just part of the practice so i'm going to talk a little bit about that tonight
but before i do before i talk about a little bit about joy i want to talk
about how we don't talk about joy very often
there aren't that many dharma talks about this there aren't so many buddhist books on this i guess maybe there are
some but right when we think about buddhist practice we think about it's grim
suffering very often but i will say as a general in general
as a society we don't really appreciate joy
as much as we appreciate like productivity or efficiency or something
like this so this idea of cultivating joy
is maybe doesn't even enter our minds or it's really low priority
so it might even just be some a new idea
that we can cultivate it and that it's encouraged to cultivate it
because in some ways joy can be really restorative and that the same way
that a beautiful delicious meal can be it can kind of be some nourishment and maybe
provide some uplift or some energy or something like this in the same way
there's maybe like some inner hunger some spiritual hunger or
whatever words you might use that joy can help address or heal or alleviate or
diminish something like this
another reason why we might not like hold joy or cultivating joy into
such a high esteem is we might have this idea that joy and happiness these are
luxuries we might have this idea okay oh yeah okay they're very important but i'll get around to them after i solve this big
giant problem or after my life is
just and everything is in place and then i'll go you know look at some joy it's easy
to fall into those types of thinking but i'd like to encourage us that no
this is an integral part of our practice without feeling oppressed that we have
to feel happy and joyful all the time right that has its own tyranny or it can
another reason why some people might have this hesitation around joy is
maybe they want to just stay kind of like in the middle
of the emotional range not too many eyes not too many lows kind
of if they could have this really narrow range that their emotional life is in
then maybe they won't suffer some of the really lows that are possible as humans
if we kind of dampen any highs maybe we won't feel any lows there's a way in which we might have
this kind of like unspoken or maybe not even really we're so aware of but this
idea in the back of our mind somewhere like okay i'm just going to keep all my emotions in this narrow range enjoy
sounds like it's a little little too much
part of that also is that if we keep our emotions in this kind of
narrow range then maybe we also have this idea we are protecting ourselves from any sense of
disappointment like if i'm kind of always assuming the worst
then i won't feel so bad when the worst actually happens i can say oh yeah see i was right
but you know this comes at a cost that sometimes we don't even recognize
this not availing ourselves of the delights and the joys the happinesses
that are possible and i know that i found myself doing
this whenever like a project like oh yeah it'll take
three to four days i just naturally assumed okay it's gonna take five days we'll deliver that in four to six weeks
okay it'll take seven weeks you know i just kind of don't want to be disappointed so i i'm assuming the worst
and then just noticing i don't have to do that it can be three to four weeks and if it
turns out to be five weeks i can just deal with it then
without having to kind of like preemptively try to make sure that i never feel disappointed
or something like this
another reason why we might feel hesitant to cultivate joy oh i forgot to turn on the recorder
so i'm going to turn on the recording and i'm just gonna repeat like one minute just to introduce what i'm
talking about okay so for the purpose of the recording
i have been talking for a little bit but i'm just gonna say that i'm talking about joy
and i've listed a number of reasons why we might be hesitant to
cultivate joy and i'm just going to continue on this list
for the benefit of those of you who have been here the whole time
but one reason why we might feel hesitant or somehow maybe just doesn't feel right it
feels uncomfortable to cultivate joy it's because
there's so many sorrows in this world
there's suffering everywhere and somehow maybe we just don't feel right like well who am i
or i do is it okay or something like this
i appreciate very much jill shepherd a wonderful dharma teacher
she says it is precisely because there's so much suffering in the
world that i've needed to make the effort to turn toward
non-suffering towards gladness towards joy in order to restore myself
so that i can face life's challenges just this way of taking care of
ourselves and staying balanced in the midst so we're not trying to be pollyanna
we're not trying to like turn away from all the difficulties we're just kind of like opening it up
yes there is suffering and difficulties but that's not the only thing in the world there's all also beautiful things
happening babies are getting born it's so beautiful people are getting married
people are getting dream jobs they're getting good news from the doctor's
office these things are happening too
and this poem by rosemary traumer i appreciate very much how she's
pointing to how just a little bit of joy can kind of
restore us or support us in the midst of all the difficulties
so this poem by rosemary trauma is called strange balance
let's see here so make sure that i have this here we go
when the boy is sneering or the glass is breaking
or the woman is weeping or the streets are crowded with anger
and rage it is hard to believe a small joy has
any real value hard to believe a single red gerber
daisy or a cup of grapefruit scented tea might have
any relevance could bear any weight on the scale that
measures what it is to be alive but
last night while i was steeping in worry aching with injustice
my daughter created a stage between the threadbare couches
and hummed herself a soundtrack as she lapped and spun and shuffled and flapped
and oh how her her brief flair of joy
changed the flavor of the night an
improbable balance the way even the smallest
amount of sugar transforms the bitter sauce
the way just one note resolves a minor chord
the way the barest hint of rain makes the whole desert erupt into bloom
i'll read this last stanza an improbable balance
the way even the smallest amount of sugar transforms the bitter sauce
the way just one note resolves a minor chord
the way the the barest hint of rain makes the whole desert erupt into bloom
sometimes we forget this sometimes we forget that
it's we don't need like this same amount of
bitterness just a little bit of sugar can shift it
we don't have to change all the notes in the chord just one
so there it doesn't have to be this equal balance so sometimes it's easy to be dismissive of like joy or happiness
or well-being when it arises think it doesn't matter it's not going to make a difference
but it can and it does this is why it's in a factor of
awakening it does make a difference
and then maybe this last on this list of why we might have this hesitation
to cultivate joy or even to think about joy as part of our spiritual practice as
a support for awakening is we have this idea that we're not
supposed to cling to pleasure right sense pleasures
that's not the way to awakening if it were like all of us in the western world would be awakened by now right
kind of after how we're chasing after pleasant experience after pleasant experience
but we might have this idea okay so such pleasures that's not the way to weakening and to it's not a source of
lasting happiness but there might be a way which we're kind of conflating joy
and sense pleasure it makes sense there's they're kind of in the same
neighborhood but i'd like to unpack it a little bit and talk about how joy
is different but maybe i'll point to there's all
kinds of skillful beautiful
inner experiences that are wise to cultivate and
experience and really have as part of our lives
generosity gratitude contentment
equanimity happiness joy is in this list too
but different than sense pleasures but they really serve to help sustain us and nourish us
on this path in this life
so maybe i'll just add this that when you feel like you're stuck in your
practice or you've lost momentum and kind of wondering
what am i doing here you can ask yourself
well what is your way that you're relating to some of these pleasant experiences that are just
arising as part of meditation practice or part of your whatever your spiritual
practice might be and might there be like a secret aesthetic streak that like i can't have
anything that's enjoyable or pleasant no pain no gain if it doesn't hurt it's not
going anywhere you could just check to see if there's a maybe a quiet little
belief like that that's operating for you i'm not saying that meditation will be
fun and delightful all the time any of you who have meditated before know this is not true
but we can just check to see if you feel it feels dry and
there's no enjoyment nosing no happiness no i don't know juiciness to it just check
see if what your relationship is to your any pleasant experiences that are arising
maybe i'll just say even because you know the buddha got it wrong even this
before he was awakened we call him the bodhisattva before he was a buddha right
his life stories he had this life of incredible sensual pleasures
so that's not going to work that's not working went the other way to have like asceticism no essential pleasures at all
and it was until the story is that he had some meditative ease
while being calm this kind of inner joy
that he realized oh this is the way this is the way this beautiful in inner
joy this is the way and that's part of the teaching
so maybe i'll unpack a little bit what i'm talking about when i'm saying this word joy
there's a joy that can arise from engaging with the practice with
meditation practice as buddhist practice in a wholehearted way
without straining without a lot of ambition or a lot of i
gotta make this work kind of feeling not you know like uh clenching our teeth and holding on as
tight as we can but more of this uplifting feeling this kind of like
energetic feeling so i'm using the word joy to translate
the poly word pt and there's three words in poly that are related and
different translators translate them in different ways i'm going to talk about them in a little
bit here so i'm going to use three different words gladness joy and happiness
this is one way that i kind of like to describe them gladness pamoja
in poly gladness is like when you've been busy for hours during
whatever and you realize oh yeah i was supposed to stay hydrated and you
go and drink a glass of water and that just if it just feels good having this glass of water
it's not anything you're going to write home about but it just feels good you're doing something good for yourself you're like oh maybe i was a little bit thirsty
i didn't even recognize it i would say that's gladness this sense of oh that
was nice joy i'm saying it's more like champagne
wahoo this fantastic they're celebrating and there's a lot of energy and kind of like a lot of uplift so drinking
something that's carbonated and bubbly and joy has a little bit of that feeling right we have champagne at big
celebrations happiness i'm saying it's more like hot chocolate
it's more like this coziness maybe around a campfire with family members or
you know something like this with maybe marshmallows on top you know this kind of this
happiness this feeling love so that's how i'm kind of making it a
distinction between gladness joy and happiness and i'll become clear in a minute here
why i'm making this distinction
so joy i described it as kind of this energetic bubbly experience
but it's a wide spectrum it can be just maybe even a little
tingly like this inner tingly you know like when you just
when it's uh your birthday and and you somebody that you hadn't heard from in a long time
sends you a message oh happy birthday and it's just a little like oh that was so nice or something like this
and the spectrum goes all the way to like sticking your finger in an electric
socket you know real very powerful physical
um waves or a little bit overwhelming can be overwhelming
for some people it's really can be a lot so this really wide range maybe sometimes
it feels like um a little bit like hair standing up
or it feels like um
yeah they're just uplift i like this word kind of like a bubbly uplift
there's absolutely no requirement that it has to be anywhere on the spectrum everybody is different some people i
don't know why have you knock your socks off kind and some kind of have a more subtle quiet
they are not different in terms of what's gonna support your practice
they are not different in what means you're a better meditator or more spiritual or anything like that
there's no correlation whatsoever between the intensity and how it is
and your practice is unfolding
so there's a wide spectrum and i'll also say it can just be a brief moment
or it can last for a long time even when you get up maybe it arises
during meditation and when you get up and leave the meditation it still is with you in some kind of way
again it doesn't have to be any way it can be really short and really subtle
but one thing that's really powerful about i mean this joy
is that when that joy is there for the most part there's not ill will
there is not this of a little bit of hostility or aversion or something like that
and i talked about how the cessation of dukkha the third noble truth and joy is it related to
that well here's one way it's related the cessation of dukkha the cessation of
suffering difficulties is linked to the ending of greed hatred
and delusion and we can say that when joy is there this hatred is not there
and there's a softening of the greed and a softening of the delusion
this is one way in which it's just support for our practice
so i've mentioned that pt joy shows up in the seven factors of
awakening but i want to talk about how it shows up
in this teaching that we don't talk about as often one thing that we can name this is the
gladness pentad i just like that kind of it's not an alliteration there's a word for that
when the same sound in the middle of the word gladness pentad
it goes gladness joy tranquility happiness concentration
and it's this what makes this pentahod so special
is that if this is a like a cascade event it's like dominoes
it's like water rolling downhill gladness
creates the conditions for joy increase the condition
let's see yes for tranquility creates the conditions for happiness creates the conditions for concentration
so it's when these like these good or wholesome qualities just lead
one to the other and so
the buddha he talked about this and we might have okay diana maybe this
sounds interesting this gladness bent out but i don't feel glad at this moment
how do we if this is true these dominoes is naturally flowing
but how do we start with gladness how do we
allow this to unfold so here is a
an excerpt from asuta buddha says an ethical person
need not make a wish that may i have no regrets it's only natural
that an ethical person has no regrets you have no regrets you do not
need to make a wish may i feel gladness it's only natural
that gladness arises when you have no regrets when you feel gladness you need not make
a wish may i experience joy it's only natural
that joy arises when you feel gladness
when your mind is full of joy you need not make a wish may my body become tranquil
it's only natural that your body becomes tranquil when your mind is full of joy
when your body is tranquil you need not make a wish may i feel happiness
it's only natural to feel happiness when your body is tranquil
when your body when you feel happiness that you need not make a wish may my mind be immersed
in concentration it's only natural for the mind to become immersed in concentration when you feel
happiness kind of this rhythm just pointing to how this flows and this
list continues goes past concentration it goes to liberation
so it starts just with this idea of some not having regrets
not having remorse living our life in such a way
that we have the least amount of regrets remorse possible
and it doesn't mean that we never can ever do anything you know that isn't perfect again right
we don't have to wait for that we can reflect on and remember some of the good
things that we're doing have done we don't have to wait until we've done
absolutely everything perfect all the time
those times when we put the shopping cart back to the place where you put them in in the
parking lot instead of just leaving it next to your car
a time when you called your friend that you knew was having a tough time
when you told the teller at this store oh wait i think you gave me a 10 back but i only needed a 5.
these small things we can allow ourselves
we can recognize this in ourselves yes i i am doing some of these good things in the
world without waiting until we're absolutely perfect
and then allow ourselves to feel the gladness of that and feel
the appreciation for this
this recognition that our life is going in a direction
we're in a way that we would want it to go with i have to say this every time
without demanding we may not be there yet but we're going this direction
and so it turns out there's actually quite a few things that can start this gladness penthead it's not only the
absence of regret or remorse it's not only like ethical conduct
we might say that there's this movement of the heart that starts gladness
faith this confidence and this practice
sometimes we only have that after we've been practicing for a while and we have this confidence that okay yeah this
is tough but i know that with my mindfulness practice i can hold it
there's also a this expression kind of like unwavering confidence in the buddha
dharma and sangha there comes a time in practice when we feel like
this this this is for me i this
i'm gonna take refuge in that buddha dharma and sangha this i'm gonna make this the orientation of my life
it doesn't have to be for everybody i'm not here to convert anyone
but there when you have this clarity about where direction your life is going
there can be some gladness about that but it also
points to this gladness arises when there's this untroubled mind
i could point to this non-regret but also this idea of
let me talk about this is guarding the scent stores
not going down the cookie aisle when we're trying not to eat cookies
or lessen our cookie intake not
spending all the time on the internet just scrolling or doom-scrolling
if we feel like you know it's not good for our mental health we find ourselves in a bad mood and fearful and angry
to not not go outside wait to yet to not go
outside or move our bodies in some ways that's healthy and supportive
regarding the scent stores can be a way in which we are taking care of what we know to be
helpful and supportive and trying to we don't have to eliminate them we don't
have to have this move live in some pristine but just this recognition of what is
supportive and what isn't and can we put our energy and our
attention there
and lastly i'll say in this list the things that can allow the gladness to arise
is to work with or have some awareness of the five hindrances
so for those of you who are familiar with that i'll just list them
and i'll just say this i appreciate this very much that
thousands of years ago they were talking about this they were talking about
sometimes when you're meditating you just feel like you just want something sometimes you want to jump up and run
out right or sometimes you feel like no i don't want something and we just feel
unsettled because we want something we don't want something or we just feel like we have
too much energy and restless and fidgety and can't sit still or we feel like we're falling asleep you
know this kind of thing or maybe we can't decide what practice to
do we feel like i don't know there's this so i do mindfulness of breathing should
i do mindfulness of sounds try to do mindful body should i do loving kindness
whatever so this unhesitation and uncertainty
the five entrances so maybe i'll end there with this idea
of joy as an awakening factor it's an integral part of our practice
to not dismiss it we can't really notice it when it arises
and a support for joy is gladness
something that's a little bit more mundane maybe it's more just a general sense of well-being
and we can tune into this well-being and we can allow it to
maybe expand or grow
and then it can shift into joy but often joy arises in initially in a
meditative context when there's a certain amount of um
stability and not a lot going on so often it's you know we've been meditating for a little bit longer and
then once the mind and the body have a sense of like oh wow okay i didn't even know that kind of
joy was possible then the body and the mind had access to that outside of the meditative
experience so often it first arises in the meditative setting
but then it can arise in other settings so joy
it can be subtle it can be quiet it can be really powerful
but just an opportunity for us to think about the role it has in our practice
as well as the role our relationship to joy as in our practice
so with that i wish you all lots of gladness and joy in your life
while meditating while not meditating on the cushion off a cushion everywhere
thank you
and so if you'd like uh like to ask some questions we can maybe pass the mic
around if there are some questions
there might not be that's okay
hi good morning good morning good evening thank you um i have a question regarding
how to remind myself to not just to see
like about joy like if i'm feeling really overwhelmed with something and i know you had mentioned
uh just like a single dropper it doesn't have to be super big like i received
this morning a birthday card that my mentor sent to me and that was a moment
of joy that i had before i was brushing off to work but i
is it just being mindful and present is that one of the ways
yeah yeah that's one of the ways that we can be with joyright is just notice when
they naturally arise like you just described and maybe you've heard this rick hansen he says that um
how does he say this this i don't remember his exact words it's like the uncomfortable experiences are like
velcro really sticky and the pleasant experiences are like teflon they just uh slide right off
but we would need to spend a little bit of effort when they do arise to like wait wait wait wait
let's let's you know uh go back and if we can like wait how does this feel in the body
how does this feel in the in the moment so that's one to savor it when it does arise
but you started by asking when can i remember and you s and you said when something is
overwhelming this of course is a great question we want to be experiencing joy right rather
than any overwhelming experience i'll just say briefly there's a few things
one is is a way to put the brakes on the overwhelm
we might still have to be having some difficulties but to get so it's not overwhelming is the first
step i would say and there's a few ways we can do that one
that when we're like in overwhelm or when we're like right on the brink we don't have access to our wisdom we're
not gonna remember joy we're looking at this stuff right you might have this wish that we could but
here's something that's can be really helpful is just simply feel your feet on the ground
there's something it's very simple and it's kind of literally grounding and it
kind of like interrupts the what the mind is doing the mind is often kind of
like oh my gosh what am i going to do about this and this means that and i better get around to this and i can't believe this happened
we often the mind when we're in overwhelm is going fast or or it's going really slow and can't land on anything
so to feel the feet on the ground is one way to just stop the overwhelm
and then often there's a number of things and then i'll just say this one other thing
just i could give a whole talk on this right a whole another 45 minutes and i have and other people have to
one thing that can be helpful is to find anything neutral to look at and what i
mean by neutral i mean boring like just to look at the
corner of the door where the door meets the
let's i'll just say this corners where the door meets that corner there and then there's a corner here where two
walls here's a corner on this chair there's a corner on this step here
there's a corner on my little podium thing and about that fast and it's helpful to
actually move your head there's like a physiological reason for this
so just this looking at things that are boring neutral like corners where two things
are meeting will help us get out of overwhelm really just kind of like slows everything down
and kind of brings a little bit boring and then you might have access to
all your wisdom and memories of joy or something like that so
that was maybe more than you asked but uh no it's great thank you so much diane yeah yeah that's some kind of practical
things and what we can do when we are feeling overwhelmed
thank you um i i think i can relate especially in retreats right once you've
been practicing you know by the second or third day you
at least for me i i i'm allowed i allow myself these experiences that that
certainly go even i would say from joy to euphoria and
and i worry sometimes because the other side of that is you you can become
clingy to that you know and say oh boy i didn't that didn't happen again you know so
you know it's obviously wonderful when it happens but it also you know kind of the oscillation of the
emotions is itself kind of a part of the reason i meditate right because it helps me stay
you know the equanimity so equanimity and joy seem to almost be you know
kind of opposites in some sense you know but anyway i i i i'm curious because i feel like euphoria is outside you didn't
mention you for you're very sort of outside the spectrum of where you'd want to go so how do you sort of manage that
you know yeah yeah thank you that's a good question yeah so sometimes there is euphoria is a
good thing arises does this kind of arise like usually in a kind of a meditative context often on retreat when you've
been in there for a while and enjoy it
roll around in it drink it up you know just hang out in it and i don't know a single person that
cannot cling to that so and you'll cling to it this is what
will happen and you'll try to recreate it like wait i was wearing these socks and sitting in
this place and you know just exactly trying to get it again
everybody will do this this is just how it happens and then i don't know then it will rise again
when the conditions are right often when we're not grasping and then we'll hold we'll cling to it
again and then it's only after it starts to arise a little bit more regularly then
we can let go of the clinging so there's but what often sometimes we do is when there's um
we kind of beat ourselves up like oh i'm having i'm clinging for this nice experience and i shouldn't but give
yourself a break and also so many of us kind of are hungry for this good feeling
so why not allow it to support us nourish us it does support us and nourish us
so i just offer that
okay so here we are at the top of the hour so thank you thank you for your kind
attention
so
you