so hello everyone and welcome to our meditation
and um yesterday
meditation i recommended the word yes
as an expression of an affirmation and a confidence in the practice
today i'd like to offer the word no and uh
and the word no to say no to something not this can be done with love love for oneself
love for the situation not as a hostility towards anything
but a wise caring for the whole situation and in the context of meditation
some of you have meditated for a long time and you're probably very familiar
with movements of your mind thoughts and ideas and
maybe even certain attitudes that you have that are not really don't really serve you or
sir doesn't really serve the world that they're not healthy not helpful
in fact they are might be detrimental or a waste of time
and so to recognize that and you know and to say no that's not
what i'm going to do now no thank you or
not now or no you know again no thank you
it doesn't have to be harsh it doesn't have to be hostile
it doesn't have to be proof that you're doing something wrong or proof that you're somehow
you know a bad person because your mind has done what it does the mind does all kinds of
things that we don't have to identify with but we do have the choice to say i don't
have to be involved with that there's no need to be if we don't identify you don't live in
those thoughts those attitudes we can at least
and then step back and say no i don't have to pick that up i don't have to be involved in that
not now no thank you and uh and have clarity about this no
no and then come back and be with a practice be with a practice
and when the mind starts you see the mind going off to do these other things again
say no in a way where the attitude of the no the
word no is expressed in a way that feels
healthy that feels caring that feels friendly to the situation
and um so that when you finish saying no it isn't that you feel like you're harsh
or curt or something you feel oh yeah that was good to not choose to go in that
direction there's more valuable things to do
so to say no to
a slumping posture by taking an upright alert posture
or your equivalent depending on what posture you're in
a posture that evokes a certain kind of healthy
alertness in the body
not tense or stressed but alert
and to lower your gaze relax the focus of the eyes
and to gently close the eyes
and as a affirmation of being here and now at this time in this place
you might take a few long slow deep breaths
long slow deep breaths
exhaling as relaxing as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal and it can be an affirmation
of being present here and now to go through your body to relax it
relax the muscles of your face
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the chest softening in the heart area
and softening the belly
perhaps as you exhale relaxing the whole body
so the weight of gravity and the weight of your body the pull of
gravity and the weight of your body becomes a gentle affirmation
here now is a time and place to be
and also maybe relaxing any mental tension
pressure to think maybe now as a gentle no
not now this is not
healthy or useful to continue with the tension and the
pressure of the mind and to whatever degree it's possible
soften and relax the mind
and then to gently settle into
the body breathing settle into the moment here and now
and when you find yourself wandering off in thoughts or having attitudes which are not helpful
see if you can find a loving way to say no
not now not this
and no that protects you from pouring your life energy into
those thoughts those attitudes maybe even those feelings
and instead this valuable life energy that we have
to let it go into awareness attention here and now
breathing breathing in and breathing out
a gentle loving no to step away from
preoccupations fantasies
attitudes that are not helpful right now
to step away and then if affirmation a yes for here
and now in the practice
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider how our capacity to
say no or not this capacity to
turn away from unhealthy and unhelpful states of mind and activities
how it protects people others
from our words our actions
that are harmful
to ourselves and to others and how the ability to turn away from
harmful tendencies gives us the opportunity to turn towards
what is beneficial to recognize benefit
to recognize discover where we can meet the world with friendliness and kindness
care compassion
and so as we come to the end of this sitting to do so to turn our attention now
outwards to the people we know and don't know out in the world
people suffering from poverty and war and oppression
racism hate hate
and to all people to wish them well
to wish them to be free of their suffering
internal and external may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
and may the influence of our meditation are collectively and individually
spread out into the world today for the welfare and happiness of all
[Music]
so
so today i'm going to talk about the second of the five by bindings the ways
that we get bounded up caught tied up
and the second of the five untyings things that loosen us and free us
and um the um
and uh so the second of the findings
is hostility and the second of what unbinds us it's
related it's a compliment to that is uh to
restrain ourselves to avoid to turn away from
things that are harm producing so both of them can involve turning away
from something and so the word version
if often in english we think of aversion as being a kind of hostility but it comes from the
word avert which means it turned away from and
so there's two ways of averting there's a way to do the hostility and there's a way to do it with
wisdom and care and recognition of what really is beneficial here
and what is not and both movements are should be known
the hostile one we should really be able to be to recognize how it's harmful for us
when we have acts of aversion which are hostile or have ill will as part of it
it's considered to be a poison uh for ourselves or a way of to burn
ourselves like you touch uh put your hand in a fire you burn yourself put your hand in the fire of hostility
and you get burned and uh and sometimes hostility
is or ill-will can feel justified sometimes it can feel good there's like power there there's
energy there sometimes there's a very strong affirmation
of conceit of self concern of identity in creating a strong sense of separation
like that's wrong that's bad and extreme one form it takes is in
racism where uh there's hostility towards another race
and in do having that hostility it's an affirmation of my specialness that i'm special that
i'm something good and kind of creating an identity in
opposition to other people and so hostility as much as it burns
people there's a confusion about it where some people go towards hostility to ill will because
they feel it's justified they feel the certain kind of pleasure from it
at the same time as they're being hurt by it and hurting others by it and so the um
to begin to recognize the impact that ill will has on ourselves is one of the
great possibilities of meditation resentment is a kind of ill will towards others
that when you sit and meditate you feel how much it harms oneself
in fact in when you're sitting in meditation to be simmering in resentment um
as clearly you're not causing any harm to the person you're resenting
in some ways if you've been hurt by someone else you're enabling that
hurtful behavior to hurt you hurt you even more and more because you're kind of repeating and
reinforcing the the pain of resentment in a way that is um you know continuous
continues to hurt i don't want to diminish the importance of care and attention to
things like resentment i don't want to diminish the fact that people do do things that
are wrong that bring us cause us to have ill will or resentment or hostility towards
others what i like to say is does it doesn't justify the wrong
it just means that what i'm trying to say is there's a better way there's a better way of living a life
than being living a life that is motivated by hostility hatred and that can take care of ourselves and
take care of the world uh just fine and one of those ways
is to avert ourselves from doing harm avert ourselves from the
internal movements of mind that are self-inflicted hurt to ourselves
so for example the poison of the fire of hostility harms ourselves
sometimes hostility is directed towards ourselves and then we can people can be very
critical to themselves and and so this kind of behavior is
something to avert oneself from to say no i don't need to do this this is not useful helpful healthy to do
no thank you and and what some of the ways in which this a healthier verting is done in buddhist
practice that traditionally is a very strong emphasis on is the practice of restraint
that we hold our tongue we hold our physically our body in such a way that
we don't punch anyone out we don't do anything physically with our body that will harm anybody else
and and restraining this way requires
mindfulness and it strengthens the mindfulness muscle to uh
it can require a lot of commitment to really kind of track oneself and stay present and not speak not
blurt something out that's hostile no i'm not going to speak i'm not going to say that
and and so to a practice of restraint the practice of avoiding
abstaining so if we feel like we're going to break one of the precepts that we're going to kill or steal or
cause sexual or sexual activities and cause harm harm other people if we're going to lie
if we're going to intoxicate the mind that there's where averting and saying no
restraint avoidance abstaining averting no
i have better things to do this is not useful this is not going in a good way
and there's a lot of inner strength that can be built up in restraint in avoiding in
turning away you know it could be starting can be something as simple as
avoiding opening up the refrigerator to have a snack when you don't need a snack you've had plenty of snacks you know
it's not useful to have more and and develop that capacity to say no
to change directions to avoid getting involved in that direction in an unhealthy direction
this develops a lot of inner strength inner strength that is
not meant to be not not punitive it's not harsh it's not critical
it's actually a kind of done the right way it strengthens our love
our good will our care for ourselves and others
and um and so uh we have to be a little bit careful with the language of
um using the in in buddhist english using the word aversion because
sometimes people believe that any averting away any saying no not this
is somehow a negative form of aversion that should be avoided that somehow in buddhist practice we're
supposed to just practice accepting mindfulness of everything be present and accept things and hold things and and
somehow not ever say no to anything but just be with things
certainly there's time and place when practice mindfulness is strong when the mindfulness overrides the
tendency to get involved with unhealthy states of mind where it can be very
powerful and very significant to just hold it in accepting mindfulness
but we do it because we know that we're not going to act on these impulses
but there is a definitely a time to say no not this not now and
and in fact the practice of mindfulness increases our capacity to recognize what
is not useful and not pick it up not be involved in it not go down that road don't need to do
that so um two powerful movements
potentially very powerful movements of averting one towards hostility
and one is an expression of of kindness of goodwill towards oneself
and others and there can be power in hostility that's why some people love
it and there but there can also be power in this healthy averting
and some people are afraid of that power that strength but this is one of the things that we
can develop in this practice and it's easier to develop that power and strength
if if we know what kind of averting is healthy and helpful for oneself and for
others and then oh you know no i'm not doing that
and as we become stronger it becomes easier to
to not get involved not pick up things it's almost like as we become
stronger we're not so easily influenced
by the impulses that we have we still might have them but they don't land anywhere they don't get picked up
anywhere because of that strength because we have something else going strength of mindfulness strength of care
so the
so you might for this next day look upon
all the movements that you have that are averting movements where you're turning
away from one way and in order to do another way or just turning away from one way not to do it
and see if you can recognize the distinction between when it's done with hostility
frustration ill will irritation and
when it's done with care with maybe even love or wisdom
with a clear sense of doing what is helpful and beneficial and hopefully you'll see these
difference with these two forms of averting and you'll see that the healthier verting feels good
that it's beneficial in and of itself to do that movement to act on that kind of
so i hope you enjoy a day of
healthy averting and and the study of how this works
and for you thank you