okay okay
great yeah
I'm just going to take a breath for a second close my eyes and maybe invite you to do the same just
there's a lot of you know coming to a new place getting here get set up
so just let things settle for a minute
okay
I'll just say a few words says you just settle and
just want to welcome you here really welcome you here
you guys hear me okay yeah great
and I'm going to tell you just before I talk much about the class I'm going to tell you a little bit about IMC
about the place you're sitting in
this building and this um what can you call this I I don't know
what it's not uh IMC is a community more than anything else
um it is completely built on volunteers and donations this this building was
bought by Sangha members some years ago about 20 years ago maybe 15 something like that
because um the group that have been coming together they were renting a church room and over time they just there was enough
of them and they all donated to buy a space to make
make this place available for people
so welcome come on in if you don't mind
sitting over here and if you feel comfortable coming closer
you can um just makes it a little bit easier for passing the mic and that what what not
so everything here is offered freely so there's you don't you know you don't
have to sign up for things you don't have to pay for things um you're part of IMC if you want to be
a part of IMC there's no like membership you don't have to become a quote-unquote
Buddhist to practice here and mindfulness doesn't require uh
signing up for any particular beliefs actually it's a very uh
Buddhist thing to not have not want to adhere to beliefs or views and opinions
so any religious affiliation you have keep it if you wish
welcome bring it into your practice nothing needs to be left out
so just um the this class is in a three-week series
starting tonight it's an abbreviated version of the introduction to
mindfulness meditation course usually it's a five-week course I'll be doing the five-week course in
January and then through the first week of February so if you want to come back for
more please do absolutely do normally we had have week one would be
breath and just breath week two so it's sequentially taught right breath body
emotions thoughts and then open awareness in daily life
is week five so we will skip that last week we'll combine breath and body tonight
and that will be the focus of you know what I'll provide instructions on is how
to be mindful of breath and body and um
let's see so
it would be helpful for me if you would be willing to share kind of what your
what you're hoping for what you think you're what you're expecting you know why you're here a few words because then
I'll I'll try and tune into those things and and speak to them if possible during
the class so there's a microphone right there if you somebody would pick it up
and turn it on so we record the sessions
and so it's really helpful to speak into their microphone
we're also streaming on YouTube so pretty much all anybody can see right now is me just so you know you're not
you don't have to be have your image recorded although that can happen if you're you know okay with it
you don't need to say your names if you don't want to on the recording so
but would you be willing to tell me a few words about why you're here tonight
I'm just curious about the Buddhist practice meditation just learning
um that's I guess this is my second or third time so okay just stop enjoying it
and uh trying to do some of the meditation throughout the day so what was that last
time they're trying just to do some meditation throughout the day trying to do meditation throughout the day great
okay
hi my name's uh Michael I wanted to take on a new uh task or uh I don't want to
use our challenge but learn something new and then I hear a lot about the benefits of mindfulness practice so
something I want to try and learn and incorporate great and also the stress reduction aspect of it okay beautiful
thank you Michael oh yeah I'm just here to learn too great
that's it mostly I want to learn how to control my
thoughts control my thoughts Health focus better
hi I would like to learn how to be in the present moment instead of thinking
about the future all the time or worrying about the future great
I'm here uh in support of uh friends and also to reinvigorate my own practice too
I learned about meditation through a mindfulness stress reduction class and I
really enjoyed the formal practice and need to learn how to connect with my
body more I end up having um a lot of emotions and crying whenever
I do any type of body meditation and so I want to explore that more okay great
um I'm I'm here to um probably just like continue my practice
and like continue I like doing it in person with other people just like makes it um
easier to do and like better for me so yeah
um yeah that and just like yeah continue to develop like inner skills and knowledge in the pursuit of becoming a
better person beautiful on YouTube
when on YouTube just to check the stream as well so let me respond a little bit to what
you've shared um so let's see stress reduction
body emotions and you said something
that I want being in the present yes yes yes
big one great so
oh you know what the fan way out there is thank you it's
really loud sorry um
so the Mind mindfulness is about bringing and learning how to bring our attention to the present moment
um that is very much what it is about and
and part of the way the class is taught in these sequential ways is because if
you think about how a movie is made it's all these frames put together super fast
and it's got soundtrack and it's got the lighting and then whatever enhancements
right all these different things are melded together to create one image our
brains operate very similarly and so what we've got is all of these
facets of our experience and we'll just the name I'll just name the ones we teach right breath body emotions and
thoughts are all kind of merged together like a movie right normally we're not sort of
aware of all these things as distinct parts of our experience
but it is possible to tune in very intimately to these different strands of
experience to bring more awareness into each one not as this kind of um
movie-like experience part of what happens in the movie making in the mind is that the mind is drawing
on past experience and making assumptions and interpreting
our experience including you know memories or things we've read and so in
mindfulness we're trying to simplify and do less and less of that and get more close to sort of this very direct
experience in this moment
it's not um complicated but it's not easy to do right like it's it's it's pretty simple
what we're going to try and do but it's not very easy to do it does that make
sense did I say that right um because the mind wants to weave
it wants to weave all of this stuff together our beliefs with our experience our
reactions all of these things get piled together and can make us very reactive
in our lives instead of responsive in our lives
so the way it might help with stress reduction
there are there are types of meditation that are specifically for relaxation
mindfulness meditation can be relaxing but it isn't its goal
it's more like if you think about the Buddha's teachings the Buddha sort of wants us to pay attention to suffering
right and so this is vipassana based So teravada based mindfulness meditation
this is the origins from which John cabotzin created the mindfulness-based stress reproduction program so you don't
have to believe in the Buddha or the Buddhist teachings but what I teach will reflect what the Buddha taught right and
so the Buddha said to pay attention to suffering and the reason we want to is
because it's a clue it's a clue that says oh something's going on here that doesn't need to be
going on here that's causing more difficulty for us so when we meditate sometimes we notice
things that are distressing or the body carries memories and when we
tend to the body and we're aware of the body sometimes that means emotional men memories which surface
so it's not that I'm not going to teach you practices that are going to Bliss you out right but as we learn as we
practice we learn to be more simple with our experience and then we learn to have less reactivity and more choice and those
things all lead to more ease more relaxation
in terms of crying when you sit down I'll just tell you probably for the first year that I meditated I probably
spent five minutes meditating a day and I cried almost every time and I couldn't
do much more than five minutes it's just keep practicing keep
practicing and then there are different things that I can talk to you about if you continue to have issues things
different there's these other kinds of practices that might you might need to
do that are more of the soothing and calming things to help you
start to be able to sit and be able to stay with your experience so but you are
not alone You Are Not Alone okay
another thing to say is whatever comes up in your meditation we're not trying to get rid of anything that's kind of
one of the philosophies it's more about learning how to be with so you said you
want to control your thinking my experience is more that I have control because I now re know how to respond to
my thinking as opposed to being able to turn on and off what thoughts come or
how quickly or any of that it's more like oh I can start to see thinking as
thinking not who I am not my choice not you know something that I get to will
but rather oh unskillful thoughts okay watch that no I don't want to follow
that you know and that um to me that's where the freedom comes
right that I think you're wanting yeah
was there anything that I didn't address that you all shared or any areas you'd
like me to be more clear about please please your questions are so welcome so if there's anything at all
don't hesitate no I did perfectly okay
well I'm glad all right okay all right so
um a few just a little few things direct
experience we're going for Direct
experience how do we have direct experience in this live life what ways
do we have direct experience your senses right
we can directly contact the moment through Sensations in our body
right through seeing through hearing
this is how this is how we help ourselves be clear about what is direct
because the mind is making movies and it's real easy to fall into the
movies and not be with direct experience yeah
now this doesn't mean that um it doesn't mean that there's anything wrong with concentration practices that
you know maybe where we have these you know we Retreat to certain States in our
minds that are wonderful it's we're not I'm not there's I'm not being critical in any way about that it's wonderful
but the mindfulness based like meditation practice is very much about Here and Now Here and Now direct
experience and it's helpful to think about wanting to
learn this because it does help you have choice
it helps you have choice about where you direct your attention your attention is
your life force it's your everything what you pay attention to is the most precious you
know thing is what do we want to give our attention to or awareness to
shoot um
okay so let's do a little exercise together
let me just reconnect here my computer just shut down
I need to make sure I have my notes in front of me
okay it's coming up here so
first of all let's bring our awareness so where we direct our attention
into our feet so we're gonna just as bring as much of
our awareness into our experience of our feet as possible
so you might notice things like pressure
you might notice how different it feels where your foot is in contact with
something versus where it is not
you might be able to feel warmth or coolness
can you feel where your toes touch each other or between the toes can you feel
into those spaces
can you feel where your toenails are and if you can't sense this you can just
kind of hold your mind your awareness where that area would be
right it's just it's okay if you can't feel a lot this directing your awareness towards
your feet noticing any tingling pulsing
maybe you know spending 10 more seconds here
really feeling your feet just as simply as you can without a lot of narrative
we're not judging our feet we're just trying to sense into them the
direct experience of the feet here
all right and with the next exhale letting go of the feet and let's
move our awareness up our body and into
our head and maybe just start by feeling all of
the head as much as you can sort of like oh this whole round orb thing here
and then maybe shifting toward feeling like the back of the head
where the head and the spine connect
maybe feeling the ears
in the top of the head
and the temples forehead
and just notice there's usually some tension in this area and just seeing if you can feel
oh what happens can I soften my eyes
my forehead at all just feeling into that
and if not no problem maybe feeling
the cheeks eyes
the jaw lips
noticing how the tongue is even
noticing the tingling the air the feeling of hair
Can You Feel the air on the ears
and then with the next inhale and exhale Letting Go the
directed awareness to the Head
and then let's bring our hands together and then what's commonly called The
Prayer posture and feel you know where the hands meet
each other versus the backs of the hands where
they're not touching Can You Feel the difference there
pressure sensing pulsing
is it possible to feel the right hand being touched by the left
or the left hand touching the right or being touched by the right
can you shift your awareness from one hand to the other
and is it possible to be aware of the area between the palms of the hands
where there is a gap space is it possible to feel and be aware of
that
and taking one more breath being aware of the hands
and with the exhale allowing your hands to rest
and so what happened to your feet when you were
paying attention to your hands were you aware of your feet in the same
way no but your feet didn't go anywhere did
they right and what about you know were you even
aware of your hands when you were directing your attention to your head
not really right so they don't go away
but we're choosing where to direct our attention what to attend to and we're
choosing to bring more and more of that into focus and as that happens we're
less aware of other things this is a really powerful thing
to be able to choose where you give your attention because what you pay attention to
affects you deeply and how you pay attention affects you as
well it's a little bit more complicated but it is also true
so we're going to look more now we're going to move into being aware of breathing
kind of in the same way that we just did we're moving our awareness around but now we'll choose to focus on the breath
as this doesn't mean just like your feet didn't disappear
when you weren't attending to them and you weren't aware of them it doesn't mean that
these other aspects of our life don't still happen
like thinking like emotions like Body Sensations
we don't have to try and get rid of any of those things it's not necessary
we can just tune in more more finely more closely to particular parts of our experience
and the reason this is very very helpful is in that untangling
it's also helpful in getting to know really have this experience of getting more intimate with different aspects
of our direct experience
so before we I start full instructions on breath let's just do a three breath
Journey just we're gonna like okay we're gonna
be in a meditation posture or not and we're gonna see if we can follow
intimately three breaths in a row and you might even watch to see if you
can't once you finish an exhale can you feel even before you start to breathe in
that pull the pull in the body for the inhale
and stay with that whole range so you've got that pull and inhale
and then what happens at the top of the inhale and is there a pause or is the quickly
moving to the exhale and then we're back to the beginning again the end of the exhale
and then feeling that oh there's the catch the breath that comes in
just feeling the full range like riding a wave sort of like you're on a
surfboard but the you're just staying close and connected to that flow of the breath and
see if you can do three breaths in a row without losing contact if you can great
if you can't great it's all okay so whenever you're ready
just follow three breaths in a row
and whenever you're finished with your three breath turning just open your eyes so I know
where we're at
what did you notice anybody willing to share anything
we have the mic right there if you don't mind picking it up and just seeing if it's under your paper yeah
anybody willing to say anything that they noticed great
Michael right I I noticed certain like Body Sensations
like a tingling wanted to scratch my ear or or you know move my knee or something like that great and so um
that's you know great those are direct experiences that's in the body and were
you aware of the breath as those things were happening yes I almost took the sensations as like
kind of interference or sort of uh taking my attention elsewhere yeah and
so um one thing to think about because that's this is going to happen in your meditations
thoughts Sensations and it can feel like interference especially when we're being directed to pay attention to one
particular part of our experience so one way to play with that is
um one remember we don't have to get rid of the other experiences they can be included so that's really important
two is there's this idea of foreground and background so you can play with this idea of okay
that's the itching is there the itching is there maybe it's really strong but just can I still just stay with a breath
can I keep my connection with the breath as this is happening and then at some point the breath can
come back into the foreground again right and so just it's and another way
to put it is see if you can't preference the breathing like oh yeah these things are happening
and let me just invite the mind to put a preference on being connected to the
breath is that helpful great anybody else
have anything that they notice that they would be willing to share looks like you might
I noticed just the innateness of breath like it wasn't that I was telling myself
to breathe and um beautiful so breathing happens the body
knows how to breathe
we don't have to make it happen yeah and that's a really good thing to
recognize yeah that we can just trust the body to breathe and we we can just be aware of
however we're breathing because sometimes I'll find myself you know it's like
almost like I feel like there's hunger for the next inhale right there's
just this pulling and movement toward trying to get more air and sometimes there's these
long pauses between an inhale and an exhale and I don't have to control it I can just
know how the body is breathing in this moment and be as you know comfortable or as at
ease as I can with it so one other thing that can help before
we start is um we'll take a we'll try and take a formal
posture here now in this next part and part of that is let's lift up our
shoulders toward our ears really kind of squeeze it in tight and then roll the elbows
back toward each other behind your back or they're behind the chair and then push the arms the elbows down
oh and you might just have an instant deeper breath and then just allow your
arms to relax resting your hands Palm up or Palm down
or Palm on Palm finding what feels comfortable I need a pillow in my lap
for my arms not to feel like they're like pulling on my shoulders right so
finding that posture that works for you but like letting the arms rest in a comfortable position that isn't pulling
on your shoulders and then it is helpful to have the feet
flat on the floor if you're sitting
and feeling a sense of uplift in the spine
so letting the head reach up toward the ceiling right just letting the spine
lift up and letting the muscles hang from the bones
letting the belly poof out we don't need to hold our bellies in for meditation
and let's take three longer deeper breaths just conscious inviting some
deeper breaths to get started as we begin to focus inviting our mind
tune in to the experience of breathing
so we're being naturalists we're scientists here compassionate scientists
we're just going to be curious about this experience
it doesn't need to be a particular thing her way
rather just kind of developing that sense of awareness of observing
and we're inviting the mind to be with the breath sometimes I feel like I need to invite
my mind mind can you please attend to breathing right now
can you may the mind make breath the primary
object of awareness the focus of my awareness best I can
so we're not muscling our way here
we're inviting invoking and tending
I'm just noticing this breath this one right here
giving ourselves permission to Value being aware of breathing
that we don't have to be thinking and creating stories and planning for later
but what's it like to just give ourselves permission
to have our only job right now to be to just experience
receive the breath however the breath is showing up
we don't need to evaluate the breathing judge it
just tuning into the sensations
we might notice the nose
and how it's impacted by the breath like warmth or coolness
the feeling of the breath pulling in versus exhale
the feeling at the tip of the nose under the nose versus in the nostrils
and we can notice the throat the back of the sinuses
which flows into the chest
and there's the front of the chest and then there's the back and the sides
can you feel them as you breathe
in the stomach
Can You Feel The Belly Button expand with the inhale and then move toward the spine with the
exhale
and maybe really noticing the difference between how it feels
to breathe in in all of these areas versus breathing
out what can you notice about that
remembering the mind will wander thoughts will happen it just will happen
it's all okay it's all part of our normal experience
just seeing if you can't still stay in touch with
the experience of the breath nothing needs to be a problem
another way to attend to breathing is to notice the beginning there's sort of three
phrases the beginning the middle and the ending and just sort of seeing what happens if
you hold that framework in mind as you attend to breathing
Happening Here and Now in this body in this moment in this room with this people never
happened before will never happen again this breath
only happened one time this way
maybe considering this intimacy
this intimacy with the breathing and the body
and as you're attending notice where it's the easiest for you
to be with the breath part of your breath what part of your
body and just let yourself rest in that area
like right now you can hear the sound of the train
and stay Tethered to the breathing
feel a sensation or have a thought and just letting the breath move right through it
we have about one minute left
this minute just see what you can notice how can you witness about your breathing
in this minute something you can share with the group
and I'll ring the bell at the end of the sitting
foreign
so congratulations sitting still
doing your best to pay attention to breathing how was it for you what did you notice
what can you share with the group it's a really is a gift to each other to
share what you've recognized or what your struggles were so
do you mind
um I guess I can go I haven't really thought of anything to say yet actually if anyone else wants to go first okay
thank you
hi I well I was concentrate in the breathing I had a lot of physical
Sensations more than thoughts my right neck and shoulder hurt
um kind of like the mouse and and then I started noticing my heart and the heart
beating and I felt like I was rocking with the heart beating but I don't know if that's
a sensation or life was really doing it yeah yeah like it was more than sad he
was more like the body kind of yeah being aware of different areas yeah yeah
yeah thank you
you can just maybe hand the mic and see if anybody will speak into it
hmm uh yeah I think I pretty much noticed um that I was in uh that I'm carrying
like a lot of pain and tension and stuff so that was kind of distracting but yeah yeah so you noticed a lot of tension
yeah yeah and that was distracting so it was was it the tension maybe was
uncomfortable or is it painful or um yeah so the pain can really draw our
attention to it it's really can be strong right yeah yeah
did you try that kind of idea of breathing through it or letting it be in
the foreground background yeah um I I was just kind of with it yeah
okay anybody else have anything to share about your what you noticed I have more
like a question sure is the purpose of uh I guess just putting all air into my
lungs I mean like having a full Breeze or just a normal blinkers yep just
normal the more I was trying to kind of get the full breed just to no only we do
the I invite the full breath in the beginning just a few breaths just to help reset
um what tends to happen is that as we're driving we're phoning you know or
stressing our breath starts to get really short and small right
um and so it just can be helpful to open up the lungs and take some
deeper breaths to reset and just let the nervous system then take over and we
breathe the way we breathe it's all good yes thank you
anything else any other questions about this and experiences anyone would like to share
yeah great let's bring the mic back over here thank you thank you
um nothing big but I it was pretty antsy you were antsy and you were aware of it
great yeah I like opened my eyes a few times
um it was nice to be here with that though because usually if I
am trying and then I get antsy I'll just stop you know ah but being
here it's like oh man see but like I can't like stop really you know
so I kind of would just be antsy and then like
eventually I was a little more calm nice so you didn't have to get up and do
anything you could be with it and it still changed on its own yeah
that's a nice experience yeah thank you for sharing that and you
know there's no small thing to share or no big thing it's all great right it's
all beautiful to share your experience yeah all right so the tears did come
um it's not sadness it's more like what happens when I let my guard down yeah
yeah yeah yeah yes boy you know um I just love what you just said about
that feeling of letting your guard down it's a lot of work to keep our guard up right and so sometimes
letting our guard down we're gonna just have that kind of experience and if
you've had to keep your guard up a lot you know it means that you're letting
some of that you know stuff out and you'll cry for as long as you cry
you know until you're done you know and and I'll tell you another
story about crying I was on a I went on a residential Retreat right and um it
was a week-long retreat and you know when you go on these Retreats you get your seats and you kind of stay in those
seats so you're sitting next to your neighbors right and um so you're by this person these people
for the whole Retreat most of the time sometimes people move but and I happen to get uh you know you when
you're going Retreat you also meet with teachers and right now mostly you do group discussions sometimes you do
individual so I happen to get in a group with someone who was sitting near me
on this Retreat where I was crying almost every time I sat down to meditate
this woman was so annoyed that I said why can't you stop crying
you know she was really bugged by having to sit by me crying but you know what can I do right what can we do we cry
because we've got tears and a poor woman had to endure it I suppose she could
have moved maybe she did at the end I don't remember but you know then she got to practice with her irritation I had to practice in
my tears and she had to practice with her irritation so I know
friends great perspective yeah Richard you got a question from the YouTube yeah
I have one from great Kelsey um I find myself focusing on the breath
with a kind of rigorous intensity any tips for transitioning to an
approach of curiosity rather than intensity
the words so I would just invite you to trust what you know here which is
curiosity what does it feel like when we're curious you know what is it like I like that
word I said it earlier but the naturalist somebody who goes out into nature to observe the wildlife
to just sit there and take notes you know they're not supposed to interact with the little rabbits and the
butterflies but they're there to watch and be curious and and just see what
happens and um so number one just yeah feel into
what curiosity feels like and sometimes for me what do you think about who who
who do you think of when you think of curiosity
a kid right I'm I think kids are such great role models for curiosity
so um do you have any children in your life Kelsey you know and if not I bet you can
think of some or memories or being a child and that feeling of uh Wonder or interest or being
mesmerized right and and this is that word too I used intimacy or there's a
way that we can start to fall in love with just wow what's happening you know
that just being with it like is so sweet just letting it unfold in this way where
we're not trying to control things and make them happen and you know when we sit down we are putting
effort we have to decide to come to meditate we have to set ourselves up
with our equipment and our timers and you know and and helping our minds
Orient to what we're doing setting these intentions taking these deeper breaths and that
that does take effort and then a lot of the work is once we
get established is to start to relax
and to start to kind of sit back a little bit even so notice your posture
you know are you leaning forward right if you are try and sit up and even
sit back a little there's something also right there about
sitting back right it's more of that kind of relaxed
or receptiveness so look at your posture how can you help
yourself be maybe more comfortable but still upright Kelsey I'm still talking to you so feel
free to add more things in the chat if I'm not addressing you know something for you here
but um helping the body relax helping the Mind relax
giving yourself permission and even just the invitation well what
if I try 10 percent less hard right now what if I try a little try to try less
you know what's that like to give a little bit less effort because we we really can we need a lot of effort to
get going you know unless we've got some continuity and a regular practice
and then we might need to learn how to let go how to back off on that effort because
we do we get in our own way we get in our own way by trying too hard yeah
so anything in there from Kelsey at this point or
great okay all right
so um any other questions before we
thank you
enjoyment it helps a lot yes yes
yeah Perfection is not helpful no and trying
to have the perfect meditation that's a that's a recipe for disaster so that's
also like you know this idea that um I talked about is we don't have to get
rid of anything we don't need to have a particular kind of experience you know it doesn't have to be Blissful
if we can just be with our experience without running out of the room
you know that's a success that's that's being mindful
it's good practice all right so the another thing I just want to say is that um
the breath is typically used as an often word that we use is anchor for our
attention sort of it's um like if you think about a boat when you come in you know and
you're gonna be near the shore you need to drop an anchor so the boat won't drift out to sea or get pushed up onto
the shore we're kind of like that boat and the waves are a little bit like our
thoughts and emotions sometimes our pain it can really you know carry us out to
sea and we are lost and we don't even know where we are anymore so with meditation it's helpful to have
something that we're using as a thread an anchor a tether
something that helps us stay connected to here and now because as you notice
I'm sure your mind can really transport you to other places right other dimensions
so if the breath is something that can work for you to have be sort of like this
grounding connecting reminding bringing you back here here here it's it's really
helpful the nice thing about the breath in this way is it's always moving it's it's
changing it's much easier to stay connected to something that's changing than to something that's static and not
moving not changing so the breath is dynamic it's felt in so
many different ways and places you know that it is the preferred anchor but it sometimes
doesn't work for people and that's okay it's not a problem
you can alternately use something like the feeling of the feet
on the floor something that's very neutral for you so if there's a part of your body that isn't connected to a lot
of pain if you have chronic pain or trauma or whatever you just you choose
that as a nice anchor the other option is listening sound meditation receiving
sounds it's a very receptive thing but you know sounds sometimes is quiet and they come
and go but um sometimes I'll do a combination of breath and sound or breath and body
so you play with it but what you want is is to create a connection
you really do grow a relationship with your anchor
your tether your support line to being here in the moment
so for me over time that the feeling of breathing start to like just when I'm walking
places the breaths just starts to become really dominant in my experience feeling
in my chest it helps me stay in the present moment so
um the invitation unless it's really triggering for you or boring for you is to find the breath as
your anchor and if not choose one of the other things I offered and that's what you want to kind of this over this
three-week period right really see if you can't make friends
get close to be intimate with be curious about have this be like if you're a
naturalist and you're going out and you're studying particular butterfly well instead of the
butterfly it's the breath or it's the the sensation in your foot or it's the sounds right and just really start to
connect notice how it's there all the time available to you anywhere you are no matter what's going on
any questions about that the idea of an anchor or a tether
any questions about using alternative things to the breath okay
all right so now what we'll shift to is in normally so just to remind you normally all we would do tonight is the
breath that's all we would take our time with is just practicing again with breathing talking more about being aware
of breathing and then you'd spend a week so the invitation would be for you to go home
and spend a week practicing and so normally you'd have a week with just practicing breath but we're combining it
with body that actually works really well together it's not a problem so
um but I just want to kind of give you you know a contrast that we're going to be adding already
the body and you've already been doing that I invited you to and so we're just going to expand that a little bit more
and you know the body we need our body it's it's what is the body's always in
the present moment so you don't have to be Buddhist to be here but you do need a body
so and we need the body it's such a huge part of meditation I cannot even
emphasize it enough it is so much a part of mindfulness really you just you you really need your
body to be mindful it's the gateway to the present moment it is always in the present moment
Sensations happen right here and right now right here and right now
the Mind does not play by those rules but the body does
so it's your friend it's your friend if you want to be present and embodied in your life
um the other thing is the sensations by themselves you know they're just
experience the mind will comment on them but we don't need the commentary we
don't need the judgments they're not really relevant that's just the mind adding to experience
so we're always trying to just preference just the direct feeling of pulsing
itching pressure even pain if we can just try
and be with it as simply a sensation that's changing moving and don't forget
to notice that it ends it comes and goes so if we're having
pain recognize when it passes away this is very helpful for the Mind very
helpful when we start to label it and start to
um like oh my God what's wrong with me I'm gonna have to have surgery or you
know we're gonna really work ourselves up and it actually will amplify the pain it
will make the pain much bigger so trying to be with it direct with that
direct simple way of knowing like this this this real simplicity
and um you know the body isn't thinking or ruminating that's not what it does
so it's a relief to start to get into that just being with this natural like
way of just sensing life it's a very pure kind of sweet way of
being the body communicates it carries a lot of actually wisdom and it carries
history and emotions and and it communicates through Sensations
and the way that we listen to the body is to feel
to feel not interpret and judge but to
actually just receive the felt sense and then the body feels heard
right it's pretty remarkable so
yeah what else do I want to say
Body Sensations can be so you know it can be helpful to have a very simple
way of noting the kind of Sensations you're having um like Pleasant unpleasant and neutral
so then we don't get into a lot of like I don't know graphic words or just you
know analysis just oh this is unpleasant this is unpleasant just as simply as we
can oh this is Pleasant oh this is this is neutral you know just sort of having
this very simple way of tracking Sensations can be helpful it's a way to
hold it um
um so I've I've talked about commentary so now I'll share a story that Gil
franstall tells um and I won't even tell it the way he
does I'll just say have you ever like watched a TV show or a sports game
right with the sound off it's a whole different experience yeah
it's not nearly as exciting you know and it's also you know much
easier to tune out of and you know sort of lose track of what's going on the way
the commentators you know tell Sports it is to keep us engaged to focus excite
you know like but it it really adds a lot of tension and stress so if we were
just sitting back and watching the game without all of that it's like more of this movement this dance this
choreography right it's it's um it doesn't have to be so dramatic what
makes it dramatic is a lot of it is this narration
so our minds tend to narrate our experience in the same way internally
when we're practicing if the mind is left to its own devices it will become
the narrator and it can make your experience much more intense much more
difficult um or add all kinds of stuff that really isn't needed
so narrating if I'm crying might be you need to stop you what's wrong with you
you know um you're bugging that Neighbor Next to You who's now I'm not happy about her
Retreat because you can't stop crying I'm adding so much difficulty to my
experience when I start to talk to myself that way it's the invitation is just like
whatever let me just be simply with my experience the mind can offer these thoughts it's
okay I don't have to try and shut the Mind down I won't be able to anyway
but I can just be like turning the volume down
yeah all right so we're almost out of time so we'll just do a short practice and then I'll create a little bit of
time for any other questions before we end tonight okay so are you ready for another period of
meditation great however you want to set yourself up whatever posture you want to find
yourself in just taking a moment to recognize okay I'm sitting I'm gonna feel the Earth
right here it's also helpful Orient to your present moment look around
you know okay I'm here
taking a few intentional breaths just to start so don't keep making yourself
breathe deep just a few if it helps you kind of reset your nervous system you're
breathing ah
[Applause] and again you don't have to make other
things not happen and we'll just this invitation to start
to feel the breath in the body just connecting with that tether that
anchor that thread that can help us come back stay with this present moment
it's not a problem the thinking and emotions and pain all of these things
are going to come and go
just inviting yourself just to tune a little bit more fully into that breath
three breaths maybe let's do a ah three breath Journey not too many not
too few
and another way to be with the breath as we sort of take a few minutes to settle
at the start of our meditation is something called noting practice
so noting is a very simple word we might say like in when we're
breathing in and out when we're breathing out
this just sort of helps us stay connected to what's happening
and it can feel too busy for some Minds if it feels like too much don't worry about it
if it feels helpful practice for a minute here
you may scan the body and notice areas of tension and just without forcing anything
[Music] with an exhale just inviting a little letting go
a little sense of whatever like okay shoulders neck whatever tension isn't needed just
may may you let go
so while staying with the breathing we're starting to bring the body in
just a very gentle scanning through sensing into areas of tightness or
tension and maybe even lingering
in areas of neutral or Pleasant sensation
and if you like you might sort of Imagine [Music] that each inhale
sort of we bring awareness into the body and that awareness can expand and spread
sort of like a balloon blowing up with the breath and letting the awareness grow
just sort of naturally spread and be as large and fill up the inside of the body
eventually maybe it may just grow a little bit or it may actually
feel you may feel it moving to the edges filling up the whole
feeling the whole body breathing
and as this is going on you might be still staying in within and out with the
out hell exhale or you may just be you know connecting to the sensations
and whatever you're tuning into in the body
it's all great anything that's happening that's a sensation
is happening here in the present moment
now the goal is to be with it as simply as possible
and if it's a hard thing to be with just maybe thinking about
unpleasant just that simple label
maybe it's possible to sense how the body
feeling into the whole body and how it just receives the breath
now I just want to invite you to connect with a sense of kindness
what is it like to feel kindness
what is the sound of a Kind voice the feel of a Kind touch
that's a kind gaze feel like
can you bring that kind of kind energy to your own experience
of mindfulness of body and breath right now
whatever's happening right now there's nothing wrong you cannot do this wrong
bringing this kind regard respect
caring attention to however this is for you
giving yourself permission to be exactly who you are
and how you are whatever that is right now
in this body in this breath
[Music] good [Music]
thank you so just a few things and then if anybody
wants to share anything or ask another question anybody have a a comment or a question
before I actually say my summary things how was that for you to breathe with the
whole body be with the body was that okay
great anything else quiet people there's a mic right there
thank you Corey
I really enjoyed um experiencing
the whole body as one uh taking in the breath rather than just
picking you know one little area so that was that was nice and then um
I also like the uh kindness towards yourself and towards
the process of engaging in it because it's not always easy and
sometimes I know I have a perfectionist streak of a
self-critical streak so I think that's that's something I know I can work on thank you thank you
I like the simplification of pleasant unpleasant and neutral great because
this is what you said about the sport you know instead of overly to romantic
saying like oh it's painful is it like it's a pleasant is that's great thank you beautiful
beautiful
I found myself jumping from thing to thing like breath thing I kept doing it um at first it was kind of annoying so
like I'm jumping back and forth and as I was doing and I was like all I'm doing is just thinking about these things I'm
not thinking about work or nothing about anything else you're fine as I did that everything slowed down too okay
beautiful
anyone else okay so I'll just you know we got one minute left so I'm gonna talk fast
and I'll let you go um you're starting or you have started just continue keep practicing even if
it's for you know I'm going to encourage you to practice for 20 minutes a day
okay if you can do more great if you can't do that long do 15 if you can't do 15 do 10
if you can't do 10 do 5 if you can't do five do three just do it sit down
and set a timer and don't get up before the timer goes off right so don't also
push yourself for too long right but just try and that you know an amount
that you know you can do and practice not giving in to the impulse to get up
so you don't want you know maybe you you'll have some sessions where you know you're a little more fluid but have some
periods where you're like no and then once the Bell Rings just stay keep your eyes closed just stay don't move wait
just a minute because we start to develop this like habit of jumping out of our meditation but it's really
helpful to like linger there and notice what it's what's happening how does it
feel different instead of jumping out just give yourself a little bit of space to absorb the impact of the practice
okay um let's see
being attentive is enough being aware of what's going on is enough
you don't have to over control your experience right and and tuning in to the felt
sense is is really helpful because it helps you stay connected to the here and
now if you can feel your feet pressed on the floor you know at least part of your
awareness is in the present moment yeah yeah Richard do we have another question or comment no from the YouTube
okay all right so meditate daily
and maybe um there's you know in the handouts it has lots of other suggestions for
homework maybe just choose one or two other things that you want to do this week based on what feels easiest
to you start where it's easy don't start where it's hard okay
all right thank you so much for being here hope I see you next week Take Care thank you thank you so much