so good evening everyone is this volume okay for everyone
this is good so i didn't know i was supposed to be here today
somehow the scheduling happened such a way that i didn't know it so much and then i see
like somebody texted me 20 minutes ago and said that then i looked at the
schedule and sure enough there i am
so uh i'm happy to be here but um i think that uh
we're gonna have to do this together i don't have a talk to give
not anything that maybe you want to hear so um at the moment
so um there's a few things we could do one is you could just the classic thing is you
could ask questions i was home with my wife just now and i said oh there's no one
to be there and i'm scheduled to be there and what do i do and she said well you can just go do
questions and then i said okay i'll go
and uh so we could do that or i could ask you questions but that
might be scary and so what would you like to do
yeah or you have other options
but that's those are the two i can think of
sorry questions okay let's see if you have any questions
and i'll do my best to respond or ask a question in return
maybe we can maybe pass out the mic i'll be ready with that to put someone
test test
i always have lots of questions for me uh
i'm very new to all of this sorry i'm new to all of this but uh one question lately has been
what is the role of fun you know the role of fun
having fun just fun pleasure
how do how do we work that into improving uh-huh
yeah that's a good question the uh i think the fun
some people find this practice to be quite fun believe it or not i don't think i
associate it with fun but um the greatest happiness three greatest joy that i've
ever had in life in a long sustained way is through this practice
i've had uh i've been on retreat for months
and it'll be it was kind of like non-stop joy just kind of ecstasy
so it was that fun um you know i don't know if that's exactly
fun but uh it was kind of unsurpassable kind of joy that was wonderful so that that
can happen that way um to this morning i had a conversation
with someone about um grief in
this practice you know in buddhism is there a place for grief because it's in the ancient texts
it seems like there's no real place for grief grief is something to overcome and there's no mention of
fun there's a little bit of mention of play but there's not much in a fun either
and so does that mean that this is like a really flat uh tradition and you the only thing
you're allowed to do is sit and close your eyes and be quiet you know and just deal with it or is there fun is there grief is it
what are the range of things a human person can do and
so that now i'm speaking for myself rather than for buddhism is that
i'm not that interested i don't about looking to buddhism to tell me how i'm supposed to be
i'm looking at buddhism to inspire me to look deeply at what is happening to
me so if i have having fun i don't have any idea that i
buddhist should have fun or should not have fun i'm just having fun
and then the practice of mindfulness is for me to look at that as i'm doing it and there's a ways in which i'm attached
to some things a ways in which something unwholesome or unhealthy is coming out
in that fun and if it is then i'd like to stop that
but if it's not then i'd like to keep doing it i don't see any reason not to fun is fun
so the same thing with grief if if i feel grief
i don't i don't really care whether the ancient tradition has no room for grief it's just supposed to really matter just
overcome it and not have it and it's a complicated question what the ancient tradition really says and what
it means and and scholars are you know looking looking into this try to tease apart
because we're talking about a language that no one speaks anymore from 2500 years ago and to understand exactly where these kind
of crucial questions are played out is a big is a topic but um i'm not so
interested even with grief or anger or anything
to judge it automatically as as i should or shouldn't be that way
if i'm having it then it's real and if it's real i want to see it i want
to know it more deeply i want to see what's going on and i want to see if there's something unwholesome unhealthy in the way that
i'm engaged in it am i attached to my clinging to something and if i'm clinging to something
then for me it is
i'd rather not but if i'm not clinging whether it's fun or grief or whatever it
might be if i'm not causing any harm to myself or others then i'm fine with
it so that's not answering your question directly but it's offering you a
buddhist principle which is uh
be mindful when you're having fun and see what it's like see what's going
on so it is probably not a satisfying answer but if you have if you want to ask again
or maybe maybe you want to say why you're asking
i think at the center of it is that question of i should or shouldn't
and behavior based off of let me have this clear cut i should do this or i should do that
but i think your answer to me kind of says
that there isn't this or that that it's an investigation of each thing
and just again that mindfulness approach of
when i recognize what i'm calling fun what what's there
is there attachment
is this something is it behavior that is moving towards what i want to be
or is it behavior that's moving towards something else right yes so that's so i think you understood what i had to say
yeah so shows and shouldn'ts are not as interesting as looking deeply and if you look deeply
then you maybe have an answer to whether you should or shouldn't you know if you see that it's causing harm to you maybe then you shouldn't do
it or it's causing harm to others maybe you shouldn't do it but you don't start
with that premise you start with investigation
great thank you yes
uh hi um if you say say your name i'd love to know oh sure i'm theresa
teresa priva uh teresa like mother like mother teresa it's hard with the masks
it's not so good so we could turn it up a little bit because my hearing is is hard
um i also went swimming it's about evening and so i think there's a little bit
of water in there uh so um so i've been on a journey uh so
i have been meditating for maybe like uh three years now but still like i noticed there's been
like like phases in my psychology um and like uh kind of like
observing myself and seeing how i react to things that i anyway i'm still i'm still kind of going
through phases and i was kind of curious since you're taking questions
um in your journey in this practice of mindfulness
have you kind of been through a similar journey
of like the evolution of your psyche um like going from like like right now i'm
observing my tendencies and then now i'm like watching myself in action and trying to observe those actions
and then i noticed i've been um kind of just like shifting in my perception
and and then it influences my actions but anyway i'm still like kind of in the mix of it all wonderful
and i was actually really curious for somebody who's been practicing for longer and deeper and kind of
way more uh you know progressed i was curious if there was like a
like a progression or like some sort of like phases or like um trends of like
observation yeah and then like and then and then where did you end up i'm sure
that's still a journey but like like now when you practice do you
are you just kind of going back to center and like do you like do you feel like you're
going to different states of consciousness where i mean samadhi is like kind of like you know like a a huge
thing i'm just kind of curious like how that like how has evolved and gone towards them
wonderful yeah so the um i love i love the very much the
metaphor of the journeys of journeying the unfolding the evolution of practice and uh and i find that
the stories that people tell or the teachings that kind of lay out an arc of practice
inspiring to me and uh yes i've had all kinds of journeys arcs phases in my practice
i probably wouldn't have worded the way you were did yours but that's always going to be personal
so i was delighted delighted to hear the things that you were mentioning and that so what i can affirm for you is yes
there are phases and what you describe is are good faces to go through
and there's a lot more there's some more that are more classic for buddhism
and uh and some which are very personal and you know that aren't really part of
i wouldn't say they're not part of buddhism but they're not really classically discussed or something but one of the
that one of the interesting things to the shifts over time that makes an interesting study
is um how does your interests shift over time
how do your your perception shift over time how does what you tend to notice in yourself and environment shift over time
um what how does your motivation shift over time and these all will unfold and change
and uh sometimes uh intentionally so it's like this is what we want to see the change and we move
towards it sometimes you know it's a surprise how we change
but if you do this practice you will change so is that
you can you can welcome to ask more more specif specifically because
i'm not sure i touched exactly what you wanted to yeah i i guess i was curious if there were like
like what are the arcs and i guess we don't have to sit here listening to like the whole scripture but like um
was there like very uh striking like clear like i'm like where did it take you on
your journey um and how did that help you um
evolve the like you know i've been doing this for almost 50 years so there's been a lot i
could cover a lot over this time it's still unfolding the
the when i was a beginner
i started i was introduced to meditation at first and it was kind of nice for me and it
wasn't buddhist meditation but it was it was nice to do and then it wasn't college and then i
had summer vacation and then i stopped meditating and then later about nine
months later i was introduced to buddhist meditation through zen meditation and i wasn't just really caught by the
meditation but i was interested in the some of the teachings that i read about
and then it took a little i got serious about doing it but i felt like
so i was ready to really give myself over to zen practice but uh i i didn't feel like it was the
right phase in my life for it to to give myself over to it in a big way
and so i felt like i had to take care of loose ends in my life i was 21 20 or 21.
and um and so one of the loose ends was uh i'm from norway
and i had i didn't grow up a lot in norway but i had this uncertain relationship with
and so i thought before i you know i need to go back and resolve my relationship to the country what you
know where i should live and things like that so i went back to norway for a year and
and then eventually i came back to the united states to continue college and
and i was suffering and i had this idea that if i meditate it started zen meditation it would help
me deal with the suffering i had so i started meditating every day twice a day
and and something shifted for me after a few months of meditating and then as i
discovered i was meditating for no reason and i'm kind of a rational guy and so it
was kind of strange for me to not have a reason to do what i did but i was going to do it anyway there was no question about it that was you know there was
something in me that was motivated but i didn't know why why am i doing this you're doing it
and uh and so i thought about it for a while and i came up with the um
the two things i began to realize was happening to me one was that
that i wasn't doing meditation for a reason
any more than a musician plays music for a reason or a dancer
dances or an artist paints it's a kind of an expression in the moment
and not you know and that's not so much to get through the music as fast as you can it's to express something in the music
or the dance with something so i thought yeah i'm not doing it for a
reason but it's a form of it was the fullest kind of self-expression i discovered i knew and that was so
meaningful for me and as that became clear then i i felt what i was
experiencing was integrity and uh later i realized i don't think i
meant moral integrity ethical integrity i think what i meant back when i was 21 or something
a sense of wholeness i was developing that i hadn't had before and
and that sense of wholeness then changed my trajectory of my life
and so first i had it in meditation and that was really nice and then i discovered that then i had
this question what kill the line between meditation and daily life is an arbitrary line
why do you only be this way in meditation so i i said i wanted i want to be able to do
this whole this integrity thing in the rest of my life as well
and and so that's when that's the reason i moved to live at a buddhist center
and so i lived there i lived at the san francisco zen center for many number of years and
and in this quest to kind of be more integrated with this wholeness
be able to live it in my my everyday life paradoxically i kept going i went deeper and deeper into the monastic life
more and more meditation but it wasn't exactly i wanted to meditate more yet i just wanted to
somehow ex expanded my life and then
but in the process of all that there was all these phases right so in the process of that i
began seeing my psychology my neurosis
uh the the uh social games i played and uh it became more more obvious you
know this kind of this the oddities the foibles of my mind
and i really was motivated to then work with them and like in the monastery one of them
that i saw painfully was how much i wanted people to like me
and i was doing a social gymnastics to get everyone to like me and i was the manager of the kitchen
managing a kitchen crew and that's like the last place you want to be if you need to have people like you
and so it was really hard and it was exhausting and and after i you know and
one of the ways wisdom works is gift wise if you you do something long enough to
see the suffering of it so i saw the suffering of wanting people to like me and how it was just it was overrated
and so and then because i was meditating a lot it was a very interesting juxtaposition between seeing the
suffering of this psychological complex of wanting people to like me and feeling it was i was ready to let go
of it but i go and meditate and meditation not to have this feeling of wholeness and
goodness and deep some deep deep satisfying feeling of just being alive kind of
and so that going back and forth between that um between this radical alternative to
wanting people like me and this that was kind of like reconditioning me whatever conditioning
i had growing up that that was difficult that led me to want
everyone to like me in meditation that was being reconditioned by this that something was changing and
shifting for me and uh
anyway so i know that i mean i i could say i could go on all night for 50 years and
tell you but that that's what comes to mind the kind of beginning years of the things so is that uh relatable for you yes very
much thank you so much it's definitely a good journey it's definitely a wonderful thing to go
through their phases and and uh yeah
it's uh it's one of the greatest things in my life is to have done doing this practice and
you know where it's taken me and brought me and things i've discovered and got to see and
it's you know it's been the greatest thing thank you
so this is kind of actually a segue uh i think that will move on from teresa's
question i actually happened to be listening to a dharma talk
that norman fisher gave at green gulch today while i was walking my dog and he started talking about you
and he was saying that he was talking about how
you received dharma transmission in zen but now you're a vipassana teacher and as someone who kind of has like a
foot in both camps myself i'm kind of curious about what made you ultimately
kind of make this commitment to to be a vipassana teacher rather than a zen teacher oh because of all your students
clearly all the people who came to practice and were studied coming wanting to get to vipassana teachings for me and they were so such sincere
practitioners and it was so clear that how good it was to be that had a big a lot to do with it
um and my idea of right as you know i
i came to go to stanford in 1990 and i was also being trained to be vipassana teacher then
and i was still doing zen training and there was a small sitting group in palo
alto and i was asked to take it over and be kind of a teacher for it and that group grew and grew
and my plan was at some point it was growing and i said okay i think the plan is to i want to grow it
big enough so that i can invite another teacher and i can leave
i wanted to live in the country someplace and um but then uh you know i've been out here
32 years so i haven't left yet um and so it was um but at some point it
became clear for about seven years that i wasn't going anywhere because
i felt a commitment to the people who were here and practicing and and
so we had a meeting where i wanted i wanted them to know that i was making a commitment to be to
be a teacher for the group but i didn't have any expectations or you know requests i just wanted them to
know that's what i was making this big life change life decision so at that meeting i said that and then
somehow the meeting kind of quickly unfolded to it we should get a center
and so then we started this process to buy this place it took about five years
to do it so that's not your question uh the question is oh the zen be pasta thing
well norman fisher
he has a dual allegiance too you know did he confess in that talk oh he did
not oh i hope he's listening on youtube
he's deeply immersed in judaism and i don't know exactly what his
connection to judaism but i think he's very deeply connected in his heart and
his best friend for until he died was a rabbi and so
um so this idea of you know having it being in two traditions is there's lots of room for that
in buddhism
so to be more specific to your question i never made a
in the early years of doing this i didn't make a definitive decision to i loved zen i had no i really had no
trouble with it i'm actually i felt very at home in it i was ordained as a zen priest and uh
and uh it worked really well for me but then we had um
a back in the 1980s there was a whole slew
of buddhist teachers who had ethical challenges to say it politely
and and that was the abbott of san francisco zen center was one of those
and so when he uh kind of was that happened
that kind of freed me up from zen center to go and i went to japan to practice in japan
and uh but while i was in japan i oh and when i got my airplane ticket to go
to japan i knew i had to leave japan after some months to get a new visa
and i discovered that for 25 dollars more i can get it then it would cost a
round-trip ticket from san francisco to japan i could get a round-trip ticket to bangkok with free stopovers in japan
both ways and so i knew i had to leave japan to get the visa a new visa
i thought that's really cheap 25 to go get out come and so and so um i got a round trip ticket to
bangkok so after being in japan for about three months i'm you know working in monasteries
there and i flew to bangkok and and and i and i
knew that uh i was as a zen priest then and i was
beginning to have conversations with people who had meditation experiences i hadn't had
and they thought i didn't feel like i needed to have them but as people coming to talk to me i felt i needed to know the map of practice
and i knew that in thailand the map of my practice was in some ways much more
clearly laid out than they ever do in zen so i think i'll go to i'll just while
i'm waiting for my visa i'll go visit different the monasteries and talk to the teachers and find out that map
but then i decided when i got there no i'm just going to go to one monastery
and just say i'm here tell me what to do and so i had a little address for a dog
patch little meditation monastery in the edges of bangkok dog patch means kind of archaic
and pigs running around and all kinds of interesting things going on
and i showed up and the guy said teacher said okay here's a little hut for you to live in
and you all day long you just do sitting meditation and welcome meditation and come and talk to me in the morning
and it's okay so i was happy to do that and so i was waiting for the visa to
come and it took me 10 weeks to realize the visa is not coming
and then i realized i could i could go back to japan now and i'll get another six months under you know without a visa or
something so i can you know to finish my year there but those 10 weeks it was like 10 week
retreats and um i'd never sat in silence that long the most i'd sat in zen is seven
days so to do it for 10 weeks was a and i got more concentrated than i ever
been before and i touched something uh inside that
i'd never touched before and it became essential to touch that again and it was kind of when i left
there was kind of a dark night of the soul time i went back to united states but all i could think about was go back because i
didn't know anywhere else to touch that place again except through that practice
and so uh and so as quickly as i could i i worked
at a restaurant fast food restaurant for a while to earn the money and when i had the money i went back and this time i knew that the
meditation practice i had studied for in thailand came from burma so i decided to go up to the
headquarters this the source and um but you know i hadn't i wasn't leaving
then it was just like it was just accidentally discovered accidentally set
a 10-week retreat it made an impression on me that changed
me so i had i had no choice but to continue with it so i did and that was next retreat was
eight months long and that made a huge impact to me it was a life-changing event for me
and and then i came back to zen center and
actually i didn't come back what happened was in those eight months i hope i'm not boring you
it's okay stories like this so san francisco zen center is where i practiced but when i was on that eighth
month retreat i got really really quiet and deep and
still it was really you know and then i would still have these little thoughts
and i had thoughts about zen center and positions in zen center an advancement in zen center this teacher
at zen center and you know it was all these zen center intrigue kind of thoughts and i said gail what in the world how
did the world did zen center get into the depth of your psyche and i made a vow i'm not going to go
back to zen center until i i've zen center out of my mind so i went back came back to us from
burma and um i wasn't planning to be back at zen center but i had a girlfriend
and she really wanted to live she was she had psychological challenges
of and so she really wanted to live at zen center and so i went back to zen center to live
with her and then i stayed for another year year and a half and
and then i went and then i was ready to go back and continue with the vipassana practice
and so i went to the three-month retreat at the ims but by that time they wanted me to come
be a shouso the head monk at sahara it's kind of like a rite of passage for just in the cups cusp of being a zen
teacher and i said you know i didn't have anything going you know i wasn't like i was i had a career
it wasn't like i was had ambitions you know i just wanted to
practice and so i was delighted to go back and be the sad monk
and then it felt enough i'd done 10 years of intensive practice modest monastic practice
so then i thought i need to figure out i'm not it doesn't make sense to go back to zen center but it makes sense now to find but what
am i going to do i'm a zen priest i'm dedicated to the dharma that's what i want my life to be about
and how do i get make a living or what am i going to do and so i decided i would get a master's in religious
studies specializing in buddhism so that i could teach in a community college like an intro class to buddhism
so i went to get a masters and while i was there
uh jack cornfield called me up and i hardly knew him i met him once
talked to my phone on the phone once and uh he invited me into his teacher training
and then i had this very strange very can you can't hear this
they said that my life came together it's like wow so of course i said yes i mean who would
who wouldn't say yes to that to study with jack to be a teacher like that i wasn't really thinking so much that i
would be a teacher maybe i don't know what i was thinking but i just like just oh this is right
and then i came back to the bay area and was it living at zen center and studying with jack and
so it was like i was always in and out it wasn't like i chose one or the other and uh
and then i started studying to get dharma transmission from mel weitzman
there's antiqued my zen teacher and he knew i was being trained to be vipassana teacher
and then at some point i got this it's called dharma transmission
authorization to be a zen teacher but um usually the understanding is when you
get this dharma transmission in zen you're kind of responsible to pass the the lineage on to the next person like
pass it down but mel gave me a dharma transmission and he said to me because he
um i'm giving this to you with no expectation
you have this other path that i trust you i trust what you're doing and and you do what you see is fit
and and then so i wasn't living at zen center anymore and uh
and being outside of zen center they didn't really invite me back to teach much i had something to do with them but
but the vipassana world invited me to do a lot of teaching and so i entered into it
and i studied it a lot and studied the teachings the early teachings of the buddha and i felt a strong affinity to
it and and right now i feel a strong affinity to these early teachings more than i do
to the zen teachings and so what i say to what i said i said to myself or say to
people is that in a kind of way zen is my religion
and theravada or vipassana is my practice is that kind of different however i'm
not very interested in religion
i'm interested in the practice and this this is the my the practice tradition i'm really practicing it now but i love
zen i'm very grateful for it and i stay connected to san francisco and
my gratitude resent center is really great so i have this commitment if they ask me for something i say yes i try to say yes
so does that tell you kind of the convoluted story of my connection between the two yeah i've
been so curious so that was really interesting and super nosy this is very satisfying
thank you
someone else said something over here did you have a question
i kind of answered it okay
and then
um so you said you went swimming and you hold it up kind of yeah you said you went swimming earlier yeah what's
what's your relationship and connection to swimming and meditation what do you see in the overlaps of those
oh i know there's people who are swimmers who feel like that's what they have what
they do they meditate they get concentrated they get absorbed and just really right there with a swimming
i'm not a swimmer like that i just swim because i enjoy swimming and
i like the exercise and and i have a little year and a half ago i got a
cataract surgery and so now i can for the first time in
like 50 years or more i can see when i'm in the
water because they don't eat without glasses and it's so wonderful to um swim now in this lake up here that
is outdoors in the lake and i just like look around at the trees and they have green herons sometimes there
and they have ducks and i swim sometimes it depends how i swim if i'm crawling i look around it's so
nice and then i do the breath then i do know when i do breaststroke i look around my
crawl i don't look so i just [Music]
swim and with this mindfulness practice that i do it's kind of i've done it so long that
it's second nature for me so no matter what i'm doing i'm being attentive
to what i'm what's happening with me but i'm not using swimming as a means of concentration or getting quiet
the those are all great states but the primary thing i'm interested in these days in terms of phases
i've been i've had so many wonderful states of mind and concentration states and
all kinds of things and they're they're great but that's not the point the point is not to suffer
it's to be a and to be just to have some feeling of freedom to be able to kind of have that freedom
as a as a current is a threat that goes through everything we do and so i'm swimming and
and one of the primary practices i do whatever i'm doing including swimming is it could be summarized by a simple
question am i am i suffering
and if i am then i stop and take a good look at that and i practice with that
but if i'm not suffering if i'm having fun i'll just continue doing what i'm doing
and i think i think swimming is fun is that uh how's that answer for you
i mean every answer so far has been amazing so i can't complain
great maybe if we have one more time for one
more question if anyone would like to ask or comment or
you want to ask or you have a question from chat great do you want to can we
have the mic back so that maybe sveta can read it
so we have a question from robin [Music]
i have a question could you speak about setting intentions at the start of your meditation practice uh can i speak about
using intention at the start of setting intent heading intention and start a meditation practice
yeah it's some people i've done it and it's some people find it tremendously helpful
to be conscious about the intentions that you live by one of the questions one of the uh ways
i've understood i stood i learned one things i learned from zen practice is that
to to be investigating considering what is my deepest intentions
uh it was one year that uh yeah anyway uh what's the deepest intention you want to live your life by don't take your
life for granted kind of reflect and what's the deepest heart wish or the deepest thing that you want to do and
and so this deep intention and so to live with that intentionally maybe why not follow your deepest intention
are you scared are you do you have some kind of ambition or greed for something else or but what
about your deepest intention i think it's the one of the greatest resources we have and i trust it very much
if i keep asking questions what is in there what's is there something deeper than that something deeper than that
and i spent a whole year asking that question every day
and uh it was phenomenal useful to do that and were phases that i went through asking that question asking the question
every day and and so as we get in touch with some
intentions that are important for us then it's uh interesting at the beginning of meditation
to uh remind oneself of that intention and then make maybe make that the
context for why you're practicing so you know
or it could be the deepest intention is um the way to reach it is through
becoming more concentrated or becoming more mindful or more clear and so to set an intention at the
beginning of a meditation is um is a little bit like
setting a direction for yourself but there's many ways of doing it but the way that i found it most useful
is to set the intention at the beginning and then don't think about it again
and it works a little bit like um uh it sets the mood sets the kind of general container for what we're doing
and so it's kind of like rather than going along merrily and whatever motivations you're living your
day by and there's a real much bigger shift then to really be here intentionally to
be to practice but also uh it works a little bit like um
some people have the experience of going to sleep at night and saying to themselves i'm going to wake up at 5 00
a.m and without an alarm clock and boom at 5 am they wake up
and so there's something about setting an intention going to sleep the intention kind of can survive and live
and be expressed somehow in the subconscious you know that kind of offline and because we're sleeping
so sometimes setting an intention in meditation can be the same thing you said it
you set the direction the course you're going and then you don't think about it anymore
trusting that something has been set in place in the deep conscious parts of the mind
and then sometimes you'll be surprised about how it kind of is there to support you or guide you or open new things up
so i think it's it's a fun thing to do to practice with intention
but you don't want to get busy with it don't have too much high expectations of
what it can do for you but it's a wonderful thing to do so i hope that was okay
so it's uh just about nine o'clock so thank you
and uh thank you for accommodating me not coming with a talk maybe this is probably nicer
it was nice for me so thank you for coming and and um
and we're going to uh probably change the
for july change the protocol for coming into one for the the sittings here monday
so it'll be posted or you know i think you'll probably get an email you're probably all registered
right you get the email so it'll you'll be notified about the change it'll be easier to come
and now you probably will stop doing the sign up so um it'll change and it'll stay in
july when we get to july so thank you very much