there okay great so a warm warm welcome to you all to happy
hour lovely to be with you to feel your presence in cyberspace
in this moment in time and the theme for our practice today um
i'd like to invite us to to explore
the sense of interest investigation curiosity for resistance
so something very specific i'm pointing to let me let me unpack that so
so this practice i want to invite us to explore and
pay close attention it's not about thinking about the past
or the future or circumstances in life it's not a lot of thinking it's not a thinking practice
what it is it's about what is arising in this moment
right here right now in our bodies in our
hearts in the emotional space in the experiential space it's not so much
spinning out and thinking about things but what what is felt what is
what is known what is known and then
noticing if there isn't resistance if there is a pushing away of reality how
it presents itself right now and
there could be some say unpleasantness in the body unpleasantness in the emotional space and the mind
um in the thought space too but again present present moment let it be felt in
the body and then being curious being really gently lovingly curious
about that resistance about that pushing away
this curiosity is not about pushing away the pushing away it's not
about adding aversion to aversion which gives it more power
and it doesn't solve anything but it's about
releasing or one might say healing healing these
nooks and crannies and edges of our hearts and minds that often hide
often hide because we just push it away we resist it we don't want it to be this way and then we
fall into thinking habitual pattern problem solving okay how do i do this
how do i shift and change my life my relationships my this my that ah
it becomes you became to become tight but to actually feel into
what is what is the edge here what is the edge here and can we even if we don't
like it even we don't like how things are right now can we release into it
with curiosity with love with interest with care and care and
interest are synonymous to love and meta sense of being undefended the sense of being open to
what is arising in the experiential field
and letting letting it teach us letting it teach us
what needs to be what needs to be known in this moment and it take this practice
takes patience it's not okay i have an insight i just let go into it okay i
know exactly what to do but it it takes patience it actually trains
us in patience in non-reactivity
i'll say that again it trains us in the value of patience and kanti
and non-reactivity kante this beautiful board
patience in the ten perfections ten parameters in buddhism sense of patience
with an opening to an and um it's not resigning it's not giving in
it's not giving up but there's a sense of aliveness there's an aliveness of
curiosity aliveness of interest for right here
right now which is which becomes the leading edge of our growth the leading edge the
the inside producing edge of where we haven't been before in our
psyche in our minds in our hearts in our humanity just being patient
because if we get to difficulty and or and we go into habitual patterns of resistance we don't like you like how do
we fix we're doing the same thing over and over and over again like this karmic knot
that maybe we have and we keep just tightening it further and further
but having gentle loving curiosity
releasing into it and being patient lovingly for ourselves for what is arising
and this can be transformative can be transformative can be the way
the way into loving what is loving what is opening the door into further
being fully being perhaps becoming maybe i'll use that becoming yourselves more fully
so maybe what i'm teaching or what i've just taught seems conceptual seems
complicated uh i hope it isn't because i'm giving very specific and clear
instructions and i do see some of you taking notes which is great because this is a step-by-step
direction so [Music]
so if it seems so heady don't worry about it i'll lead us into a guided meditation for us to explore
but one thing to remember just to simplify one thing to remember
ah whatever arises in this moment not future not past not thinking if there's
a story let go of the story right away come back let go of the story come back to the
feeling in the heart in the mind and gently explore gently open to with
curiosity don't have to think about it's not thinking but just being with
what happens if you if you just sit with it sit with what is arising
let it teach you whatever it needs to teach you maybe the lesson takes
days or weeks but but is worth staying with all right
let's let's give it a try so so let's practice together
so i'd like to invite you to land in your
body in this moment
ah here here
letting go letting go of whatever has come before
letting go of even thinking about
what tonight's theme is about just let go arriving here
in this moment
the simplicity of this body breathing
just breathing in breathing out
let the breath be nourishing in the body connecting you to your feet
and the earth
the breath moving through [Music] the lower abdomen
letting go letting go if thoughts arise
thanking them for coming and saying not now gently ever so gently
ah landing landing in this body with this breath refuge
taking refuge
just this breath this body
let awareness connect with the in-breath with the entirety of the in-breath
the entirety of the out-breath
in your sit bones to ground you
now spending a few minutes feeling your sit bones your bottom on the cushion
being breathed to your hands your feet your whole body
in breath opera
let the breath be calming soothing
and can each breath in breath and out breath
be comforting
as if you were breathing in kindness
breathing out kindness
letting good will
feel your lungs fill your abdomen to your whole body
a sense of care for this body
calming soothing any anxiety
stress difficulty
letting go letting go
letting go of whatever is not helpful in this moment
letting the breath in breath bring in kindness good will
soothing into your heart
gentleness ease into the body
and let each out breath breathing out kindness
breathing out good well
around you all around you into the space around you
so that with each breath your body your mind your heart
is permeated with
goodwill and with each out breath breathe out all around you
and don't try too hard don't try to control just
let it let it be happening it's already happening each every single one of us
as goodness inside us trust it trust
this goodness that receives care from the universe and breathes about
and breath and out breath
that whatever difficulty is arising perhaps in the body or in the mind right now
let it be infused with the breath with kindness
relaxing releasing with each breath with each out breath
and now you can stay with the breath breathing in breathing out
meta into the body the heart the mind
maybe that's what is needed today
maybe that's all that is needed right now and if so trust it
continue to be nourished and healed in this way
to benefit yourself and all others
and if you like to take on the suggestions
you're welcome to and yet let them be from
your body following them with your heart not with your head
these invitations are not to think about but to explore in your lived experience
so feeling your breath in your body
your abdomen and your heart center and your feet
and your hands and your shoulders
feeling embodied
invite your heart to open up to relax into
whatever is arising right now in this moment in the body
there is an emotion a body sensation
a feeling if it's a story let it go
if it's the story let it go come back to the body
open up to the felt sense in the body
see if there can be some gentle kind curiosity
interest not resisting whatever is here even if it's challenging or difficult
at the sense of grandmotherly mind tell me everything child remember tell
me everything
your heart your mind opening
this challenge in the body the heart in the mind not the story not the story
but to be known as a felt sense
without resistance
just breathe and be patient
making more space in your heart
maybe it's a headache let it be just as it is not to fix it
push it away just breathe with it
gently opening up
it's a very subtle interest
interest synonymous with love
expansively hold whatever is happening give it space
fashioning a new pattern a new way of being
new way of being with what may be challenging
just breathe be breathed be with what is arising
without an agenda
this sense of open curiosity gentle
allowing being with the synonymous with meta
with care in the deepest sense
not pushing away fixing but really
deeply making space
with a huge breath for what is
and you don't have to get answers
simply with humility sit with interest
and care
and for the last minutes of this practice period
letting there be a radical acceptance of whatever rose or did not arise
in this practice period
opening the doors of your heart as if embracing a big hug
thank you for sitting thank you for showing up
for yourself hugging yourself with your own care with your own meta
regardless of what happened or did not happen you showed up you did your best
let this be a moment of radical acceptance and care
patience interest
love
and may or cultivation of care interest
care for ourselves and for others
the way we can sit for our own challenges we can offer to others not
trying to fix make it go away
because we are uncomfortable with our own suffering but to make space with care
curiosity and patience may our cultivation
be of service to all beings everywhere including ourselves
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so invitations to be
to let go of the story to open up with curiosity interest
patience and radical acceptance of what arises in the heart
and in the body to fashion a new way of being with what arises
so we have time and space for reflection or two you
can raise your zoom hand you can also type in chat if it's typed
to me privately i will only read your
reflection not your name it's typed to everyone i'll read your name also
any aha moments any questions about this practice maybe
something opened up for you that was unexpected
or maybe it was challenging or maybe you were not clear as to what to do
one reflection privately to me absolutely beautiful
i'm delighted to hear that and if you are moved to share what came up for you for the benefit of
the sangha i invite you but don't feel compelled you can type it
in chat privately if you like
maybe we're all very quiet right now so tell you what if there aren't any reflections right now jerry i'll make
space please jerry um
thanks i guess i was finding it
i was trying to understand what was different from what i would normally do
in terms of i did try to follow your directions so i was happy when you said oh well
let's go and try to do some meditation
and so i was just trying to understand what was to be different in this meditation
from others so perhaps i'm a bit simple here but i just didn't get what was the
difference ah well maybe this is what you usually do i
don't know what it is you usually do jerry so i can't answer that question i wish i could be in your mind and i could
read your mind would be fun if i were a mind reader but i don't know so it's for you to discover
my dear okay thanks how's that zen answer
you it's true thanks jerry
um a couple of reflections i'll read them and then we'll go into groups
let's see here uh one person says the best i was able to do is to bring my attention back to the
breath there was so much shatter in my mind no problem just bringing the
tension back to the breath is is beautiful practice especially
appropriate if there's a lot of chatter just called it no this is chattery buddha this is busy mind buddha
it's okay no no judgment uh another person says so awesome not to
be with inner critic meta and loving kindness to you ah to you as well
another reflection aligns closely with where i've been trying to go beautiful
another reflection i've enjoyed this practice tried standing
quietly which kept me alert and in my body great beautiful i'm glad that you tried to
stand up take care of your body your sleepiness very skillful to do
that keep yourself alert and in the body beautiful thank you for all those practice reports
so appreciate them one after another great so dear ones um
let's turn to uh practicing in community
and and the um reflection the invitation
as always is to first take care of yourselves take care
of each other with kindness um in the breakout groups
um maybe going in reverse alphabetical order and um
and the prompt tonight is um with this practice is there something
that you perhaps explore that seemed different for you opened up or maybe not
it was similar or maybe you don't know could just be the question of i don't know
and and what particularly about the steps that we went through if anything
was new to you or is this what you usually do aligns with what do you do what is what which of those steps is
really um lights you up is really how you've discovered is really uh
opening for you is it the letting go of the stories is it the putting with curiosity staying in your
body could be all of them but maybe being clear about one helps you be
witnessed by others each person can offer a nugget could be
i don't know it could be the silence i pass right now the next person will offer a nugget the next person offer a
nugget and we'll go round and round a few times make sure everybody has a chance to
share and and uh um yeah and be witnessed so please take care of
each other take care of yourselves and it's going to take me another minute to
to finish creating these rooms please be patient
with me and um
i'm taking a long breath here we go
okay i think i think i have them
okay here we go take care of each other take care of yourselves
okay oops
all right so the rooms are all closed everybody is back and we've got just about a couple of
minutes um for any reflections what might have come
up in the rooms any aha moments
questions
mary so
a question um i experienced a lot of physical agitation and mental agitation
and um you know emotions that just felt like they were overtaking me and my body it wasn't a
decision my body i'm in a swivel chair and my body just turned
and then i settled back down and it it was more doable and i guess my
question is is that skillful or unskillful and should i stay with
what feels like terror yeah yeah thank you for sharing that
mary and and listening to let me reflect back to you what i heard because i think the
answer is already there so so you said that when
just you're being assailed and it was with let's say mara with your assail with all these thoughts like the
trickster mara the in buddhism is the trickster with all these thoughts and and then your body so it wasn't so much
what i heard you say wasn't the decision like okay mary no it's turn it's like your body just like okay this is what
we're doing now mary i'm gonna take you for a ride like oh different perspective
right that's what i heard you say mary it was definitely the body there you go
so trust the wisdom of the body and there's a lot of wisdom in in in this shift it's it's like you know
when you're in a funk the best medicine is go for a walk like get out go for a walk
right you're let your body take you for a walk and you walk around like oh yeah different
perspective so the wisdom of bodies like all right darling turn around like okay different perspective so beautiful
thanks so much for sharing that thank you thank you that's great
yeah so it's time dear ones thank you so much for
your practice thank you for sharing yourselves with each other
all beings everywhere and may our practice together be a cause and condition
for waking up for ourselves for all beings
when all things be safe may all beings be happy