so this i'm using the opportunity these days to
emphasize the knowing quality of attention that our capacity for attention
awareness has many different faculties many different ways in which it operates they can all come together
and work in harmony and so there's the more cognitive knowing where we
recognize something for what it is there's also feeling it fully
and kind of being with it experientially in the body where the knowing might not be as
central but just the the embodied feeling is what central
and there's uh observing there is um
kind of a clarity of awareness where things just arise so a variety of
things and so we're emphasizing knowing because it's useful to get a sense of the richness and the possibilities
potential of this knowing faculty we have and for today i want to say that um
[Music] then it's possible to
know something with some intentionality with some uh
choice to really like let's know this let's be clear about it and to know it and as we know it
it might be in a word it might feel you know just the in-breath is in
and we know it as an in-breath but uh it might be a word in the mind it might be a little bit an
image or people think more in images perhaps a nice image to have is the image of itself the chest moving perhaps or the
belly moving and so what i want to emphasize today
because it's a little bit intentional no matter how else you might be feeling
engage in the knowing in a calm way calmly know
and uh even if you're agitated take a little time to calmly recognize
agitation is here
and sometimes what uh you know the mind maybe is is uh racing or is fast or is
is um energized or maybe it's really dull and
sinking all kinds of ways in which the mind can be and it's very common for us to
let the mind's mood or state influence than how we are how we use our
attention and this is an exercise to kind of take hold
of your knowing faculty and use it with a certain kind of
clarity intentionality consciously use it and as you use it do it calmly
so in a certain kind of little gentle lovingly determined knowing the in-breath
knowing the out-breath knowing a sound that's coming in
knowing a warm tingling in my belly knowing
an itch knowing the itch some more back to the in-breath
health breath so let the knowing become and so it's a little bit like um
um like the story i like to tell of my son in
preschool that um it's a wonderful teacher and and he would uh where the kids were
playing less preschool kids do in the playroom kind of noisily and happily and
running around and when it was time to do something different tell a story so they could
take their nap or something he would stand in the middle of the classroom
and start talking softly and as he talked softly and calmly
steps over a few minutes the kids would begin gathering around him and likes like the pied piper and kids
would all gather around him and sit down and look up with great delight and
expectation as he prepared to tell a story
so maybe that kind of a calm knowing
that is not trying to fix anything or do anything but it becomes a little bit of
a reference point for your psychophysical system to maybe finally relax as well or calm down
so beginning with a meditation posture
that for you represents or allows for a combination of
being alert and relaxed alert
alert and calm and then to
take a few long slow deep breaths beginning the movement of being calm by
how you calmly breathe maybe three quarters full breath
nothing that is a strain and a calm long exhale
as long as it doesn't strain you relaxing as you exhale
breathing in breathing out
and then to [Music] let your breathing return to normal
and perhaps there's a little margin of adjusting
that's natural enough easy enough to breathe a little bit calmer
maybe by relaxing the belly
maybe some there's a softening in the chest that's possible
maybe you're not breathing in deeply but there's this gentle intentionality
to breathing in that allows you to breathe in calmly
breathe out calmly
and as you exhale calmly without much ambition
soften in the
face as you exhale calmly soften the shoulders
as you exhale
softening the belly
and then settling yourself more fully on the body's experience of breathing
experiment with knowing
inhale calmly experiment with
a clear knowing when you're exhaling
you know you're exhaling
and whatever
grabs your attention gets your attention that's different than the breathing
explore the possibility of calmly knowing it a calm recognition
this is what's happening a sound an itch a thought
a feeling
in a sense things are always changing
so stay in the flow of change
with calm recognition when you're calm you're not going to
know it all recognize it all but just be content
with what you can calmly know moment by moment
and whatever seems appropriate center yourself in knowing the breathing
calmly knowing
the experience of breathing
right now what would you need to know
so that you're more in the present moment
what experience would you need to recognize
to arrive here with what is happening
calmly know it
so
knowing is an essential aspect of being a human
being
what is your knowing like can you appreciate
your capacity to recognize the simplicity of what's happening
and to know it recognize it calmly
as if to know it is precious
as if to know is a treasure
which it is our human lives our homo sapien lives
would not be possible
without our capacity to know
taking a few moments to continue
knowing calmly whatever is happening in the
present moment recognize it calmly
and recognize it in what's how it's obvious
without searching for the right word or
sometimes it's not clear what's happening it's enough to recognize it as
something
in the last minute or so here to see if you can get a
feeling for [Music] what it's like to calmly know
kind of like you're imprinting the memory of
what it's like to know calmly
and then
bring to mind people in your life
strangers you know [Music] neighbors colleagues friends
mail carriers store clerks
and what is it like to think of one of them
you know with this calm knowing just calmly know like imagining them in
front of you calmly recognize
and perhaps the calm recognition
can be the channel through which
your good will can travel
calmly having good will
well wishing kindness
and perhaps your good will can have some the same qualities of
calmness tranquil
well wishing
and when that well wishing spreads out widely in all directions
we might say to ourselves may all beings
be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and then i'll bow and that bow will be the end of the sitting
thank you
um
so i think often we take our knowing for granted
throughout the day we're constantly recognizing things but we're doing it at
a kind of subconscious level and that's kind of needs to be that way if we were
to take the time to recognize each thing that we come across
we would never get anywhere there's so much to recognize but our brain can process things subconsciously and and so that we
take in a lot and know how to find the way to the door and through the
door and without having to think about it or
but it's still kind of even though it's done so automatic pilot sometimes
so much of it it's still an essential quality of being a human being
and [Music] without it our human life would not be possible
and but because we're so interested in we have desires to do something and want
something to think something we seldom take the time
to recognize how special it is to recognize to know
for deep mindfulness practice the knowing faculty of the mind becomes increasingly important
and now it does so in a natural way so it's not like you have to work at knowing but
the deeper the practice goes the more acute the more clarity there is in the knowing in such a way the knowing
starts being more and more liberating it it's uh it's kind of like a way of
freeing ourselves to greater and greater freedom and
um so it's very basic and uh it's
when practice is strong when we're meditating is going well and concentrated and quite calm
then um what's interesting is to notice what it's like to come out of meditation
get up for your seat and start walking and if you're really calm and settled
there's probably very little tendency to want to rush into the next thing
and then as you walk from your meditation seat there might be a kind of very relaxed almost
almost automatic kind of just knowing that you're walking
you're so present and in the walking that you just know that you're walking
the um there's a famous zen story that's told sometimes of two zen students who
were teaching and talking and they were talking about their respective zen
masters and uh one of them said that um
my zen master is my teacher so great can
can enter into the deepest states of concentration can walk on water
fly through the air all kinds of miracles kind of things
and the second one says well mai's the teacher when she walks she just walks
when she eats she just eats when she talks he just talks
and the first one said oh bowed down deeply oh you your your teacher is really advanced
so the idea that the simplicity of just being in the experience that we're we have while we're doing it
is such a pleasure certain times and so when meditation is quite centered and
settled that's one of the times it's kind of really a pleasure that as you walk know you're
walking because you're inhabiting the walking when you're standing no you're standing
when you're sitting no you're sitting and when you're lying down no you're lying down
and so this second exercise of sati patana it can also be seen as a way of
continuing the meditation into our daily life and so the first exercise kind of gets
us settled and the second one is the encouragement to stay present
stay in the knowing and the calm knowing into our daily life so there's a continuity
and and [Music] what can easily happen is that our meditation ends maybe we're
somewhat calmer than we were before but we get up in order to do things take care of the next thing
make breakfast go to work you know whatever it might be
and what's interesting is to watch how quickly we
lose touch with the simplicity of when walking just know you're walking
and instead we're already ahead of ourselves into planning what's for breakfast and what we should put
together and and uh you know what kind of ingredients we're going to use and
and uh and then thinking about where's my newspaper or my my device my my pad that i'm going to
read from and read the news and i wonder if i should what podcast i should listen to while i'm
having breakfast and you know on and on it's we're already in the flow and of all the different things ahead of ourselves
thinking ahead and there's nothing inherently wrong with that however it does involve a loss
it can be a loss of some kind of deep inner connection to the present moment and to oneself
it certainly has a as can be a pleasure to do some of these other things and i hope you do some of them with joy and
delight but if we do if we keep losing ourselves to them throughout the day
we're lost many people lose are lost to themselves because of all the things
they're doing and all the things they're thinking about and concerned with
so this simple instructions to when standing know you're standing
walking know you're walking is a
especially coming out of meditation is a opportunity
to both continue with the calm state you're in and experiment with how it is
to live that way and uh and it's it's really cool
the way that if we can get calm and settled and quiet
that the knowing of what to do next the knowing of how to do things can happen kind of
organically automatically we don't have to be the agent we don't be the one figuring it out and always
and this have this kind of arising of a certain knowing and a rising of intention
um and then and uh from this place of calm uh tends to bring forth some of the best
qualities of who we are but also what happens is instructions
just to pay attention as you leave meditation is to notice how quickly you lose your calm
and this became a real important turning point for me in my meditation when i noticed that how quickly i gave
up my calm my subtleness my clarity when i got up from meditation because i was on to the next thing
and and so to then stop or slow down and notice what is that next thing
where are you rushing off to what are you getting caught in what are the feelings what are the beliefs
why why are you sacrificing your calm your clarity your centeredness
why are you why are you sacrificing it with other things is it is it a worthy sacrifice is the
cost-benefit analysis in your favor that you rush off to
look at the news while you're having breakfast
is that the best use of your human life what happens with this kind of
deep sense of connectedness that can happen and a life that arises and flows out of
that so to know
to know simple things
in the moment so simple as your posture and
enjoy that and also to do that in such a way that we start becoming more sensitive
to how we what we're doing with our minds and our feelings and our life
and so to seek more clearly how we rush off or get involved or get
preoccupied and then ask the question
is this worthwhile is this the best use of my time and if it is go ahead
then you do it consciously and if it's not maybe there are better things to do
and i would suggest that for most of us [Music]
being calm some modicum have come even when we're having fun
is being playful some some degree of calm or having calm
close by just enhances everything makes everything richer and fuller and more
embodied it's not a not the kind of calm that would limit
you but allows for a deeper wellspring of engagement with life
it's just a great thing and um
so when you walk no you're walking when
you're standing know you're standing when you're sitting no you're sitting
and when you're lying down no you're lying down so thank you
and i'm here at irc for a couple of more
days so that we'll be with you here again and thank you for um
for participating and i look forward to our time tomorrow