so welcome so what i want to do today is to read
and then discuss a famous verse passage from the dhammapada
that is sometimes called something like the universal
discipline the word patimoca is the word that's used for the discipline of the monastics they have
all these rules they have to follow somewhere between 227 and 311
and more some others they stop counting at some point but there's many many rules for
monastics as part of their discipline and this one sometimes is considered kind of like the universal
rules of discipline the not just applying for monastics but for everyone
it's a relatively easy to memorize so you might want to
memorize it so this is my translation the first line uh
is translated as most people do and then i in recent times i did this 20 years ago
this translation of the dhammapada but i think i'll offer you my
my more recent doing no evil
engaging in what's skillful and purifying one's mind
this is the teaching of the buddhas so it's very poignant and it is ending
with this this is the teachings of the buddha puts this up elevates this as being a
pretty important little passage and maybe it's the kind of underlying principle that all buddhist teachings
can be kind of be an extension of and arise from
and so uh the word evil i think is a little bit problematic to use it to translate this word
the the pali word is papa and whether it should be evil or not i
doubt it should be evil because in english the word evil has such a huge
western judeo-christian association that i don't know if it's appropriate for
indian religions and for buddhism and so i now would like to translate it as
doing nothing malevolent not doing nothing malevolent
and then engaging in what is skillful the word skillful is kusala
which can also be translated as wholesome and wholesome has more of a feeling or
something for me of something that's nourishing something that is healthy health producing
where as skillful has the connotations of uh that just you know you that is
has someone has is capable of doing something in a useful in a
beautiful way or skillful way and it's a very important word and the fact
that this word can mean both wholesome and skillful speaks to something very profound about
the training in buddhism how we're training ourselves to become skillful in what is wholesome
some translators will simply translate this line as let's say do no evil
do what's good just it's kind of very simple easy to remember then
but doing nothing malevolent engaging cultivating
intending you know working at doing what is nourishing or healthy or skillful or
wholesome and and then purifying one's mind
so when i was thinking about this today i was reminded of
medical ethics it's on my mind regularly enough because i'm on a ethics
committee at a local hospital so the the the
basic ethical principles are quite important for the ethics committee and for
hospital staff to consider and it's a little bit similar in that uh
it depending on what order different places have different orders of the basic principles
but is avoiding um
maleficent's i think i'm pronouncing it right maleficents so doing harm
doing ill and um doing what is
practicing beneficence so doing what's beneficial
and then in hospitals the other important one is respecting the autonomy
of the patient of the person under care that everyone has the ability to make their own choices if or if they do have
the ability sometimes people don't have the ability and that becomes a that's one of the reasons why an ethics
committee in hospital is engaged because if the person can't choose for themselves should it be the doctor
should be a wider committee what's the ethics of it and then it's
the respect for the patient respect for the the human rights respect for their
dignity kind of respect for patients and and sometimes what's added
in hospitals is solidarity that the medical staff should be in solidarity with the patient so i kind of
be their champion be their their companion be their you know in their camp kind of
so i kind of think that's pretty good for buddhism too
that um so this you know this first two are related for sure
and um and so it has this very strong statement the
beginning do no evil do nothing malevolent and that's like a line
how do you know what's malevolent how do you know what is you know some of it has to do with our intention
is there ill will is there hatred um is there hostility
and that's what's for me is behind malevolence making things worse you can make things
worse with good intentions so i also like the idea don't make it
worse because there's a little bit higher sensitivity than just simply it was my intention good
and that's sometimes not good enough and so um
but here's it's kind of very clear do know nothing malevolent
the second one it doesn't say do good like you know this is what you have to do
it says engage or cultivate develop your capacity to do what is skillful and what is
wholesome and those are the things by definition in buddhism
that come from non-greed non-hatred non-delusion
and then the positive terms of it would be comes from the things that are opposite to greed
opposite of hate and opposite of delusion and some people like to make it really
simple by saying do what is generous do what is kind or loving
and do what is
wise last night i'm still a little bit
what's the right word to say here sitting here i'm still under the influence of the movie that i
saw last night it was kind of a movie that would kind of
discombobulating in some ways and as it discombobulated you
intentionally more and more and more it comes to the final conclusion
which is be kind so is this movie
everything everywhere all at once so if you've seen it
if you want to be discombobulated
you can just take the message be kind then you don't have to see the movie
so uh the um
and then um in medical ethics one of the challenges
is sometimes there that you don't want to cause harm but you want to benefit and sometimes
those two principles are not positioned to each other and so then there's a whole discussion about how to work that
out and i suppose that's also true in our ordinary human life as well that it's not so often so
clear you know or so always just one way or the other it's like maybe a little bit of both we we do
make it worse i mean some of us uh so you know maybe the transportation
how we got here today you know it's probably made the world worse place
but if you if we avoid any kind of making the world worse
would we then not even make it much better and my hope is that
is that i mean i've dedicated my life to the idea that buddhist practice and
these buddhist values will make the world a better place make better people people who are interested in benefiting
the world changing the world for the better and so maybe we have to compromise a little bit you know we drive here and
the bigger picture maybe we find it inspires us moves us makes us more capable
of living a life that uh that's maybe with the challenges that come so we we become agents for
good in this world for benefit so you know we're balancing all these things
but here the buddhist principle is not make it worse
which has beneficial to see that but also has challenges to understand exactly what that is and how do you
balance stuff but here the principle is do nothing malevolent
and that's a kind of i think a wonderful line maybe hard to do
but that's the line we were trying to live on on this side of malevolence
we're not going to go into the into doing something intentionally with hostility and harm
and we still might make things worse but at least we know ourselves well enough
that we are not doing anything malevolent you know intentionally and
you know most people don't think of themselves this way and it might not be an inspiring
teaching you know do nothing malevolent but
i think this world needs a dedication to this and and for those of us who are
basically not malevolent i think it's possible to up the game be even more sensitive more attuned and
i think this is one of the things the benefit of buddhist practice is to become more and more attuned to
the subtlety in which this works in our minds and our conversations and our
our connection to other people and i mean it could be something i don't
know if it's subtle exactly but some of something so small is um
the way that you complain you know there might be complaints that are appropriate
you go to the complaints department because you know something didn't work
and complaints maybe you know they say something so by the way i want to let you know something didn't work and
you know and maybe you should know about this and they say oh thank you we're grateful to know that
versus coming say you know you guys messed up
and you know then you're kind of like sticking it at them you know and then there's there's malevolence there's some
hostility some you know or you know like if you're living with someone and
i can't believe you left the dirty dishes in the sink again
you know and you know it could you know just you know the tone of voice the way it's said
you're kind of you know you're kind of like angry and so i was a little bit hostile
and it's a complaint right but does a complaint have to be hostile
i have a notification to make about dishes in the sink
would you like to hear it it would be helpful for me if i could say something about the dishes in the
sink is this the right time and as opposed to growling or something so
so i'm just trying to maybe say something something very basic but even this you know as we as we develop in this
practice there might be enough we might not think of ourselves in terms of doing something malevolent or evil it's a big it's a big
bar right maybe i hope it is but to start becoming looking at it in
more subtlety and more subtlety and i think that's natural as people develop
in the mindfulness and the practice and the concentration and the stillness that there's a more and more sensitivity
to the impact our own states of mind have the impact of our
words the impact of our intentions that we have and one of the principles we'll discover
is that if you do something malevolent if you have it do anything with any hostility towards anybody else
you might be harming them but you will definitely be harming yourself
and you can't harm anybody else intentionally with malevolence
without harming yourself at the same time and i've known people who have only given up their malevolence
when they realized that ouch you know why i had no idea how much i was harming myself
i you know people who have harbored resentment
or anger for years and and resentment is a kind of i think it's
a kind of malevolence maybe other people use the word differently than i do but i think of it in that way
and um and then i've known people who only after years realizing oh
the person i'm resentful to probably doesn't even remember i exist
i'm not harming that person anyway i'm not getting back at that person anyway the only person who's hurting
by my continued resentment as myself and i know in some people that was that
was the key that oh okay they put it down so this increased sensitivity to this
mutuality of you know the harm goes both ways and then this wonderful word uh
skillful or wholesome kusala it also has the same direction that as
we've been as if we do something skillful do something good wholesome
for the world we're benefiting ourselves if we're cultivating what's good
wholesome ethical skillful in ourselves
inevitably it will be beneficial for the world the world needs more examples of people
who are living a skillful wholesome good life
now how do we do this and how do we do it so that it's not just um
you know living by principle like this is how i'm supposed to be doing and that's the third principle here
purifying one's mind and i don't know how it is for you to hear this term purifying one's mind as a
principle i know that for me when i was younger i was
repelled by this word purification purity it had connotations of maybe
of some kind of excessive puritanical notions some idea of dualistic ideas that you're either
completely pure or not and and um and it seemed like a standard that um
that lended itself to a lot of judgmentalism
of people that you know you know if you're not pure you're not good or something
sin and purity kind of idea but over the years
i've come to appreciate it more and more and and what i appreciate about it is that
i now associate this word purity with something that becomes clean
something that becomes clean for the mind to become clean
and uh and to view your own mind and see that it's clean
that it's kind of clear there's no there's no um
you know there's no i don't know you know you know any negative word we use
you know will arouse some resistance for some people
but there's no dirt in there there's nothing malevolent there's no hostility
there's no nothing greedy there's nothing that we would feel somehow
awkward about having in the mind
if um you know your mind got plugged into a monitor so that everyone can see what
goes on in there no look you look oh wow that's what that
person that's what he she they think or are doing
so if your mind was public to everyone it would be no problem because it's clean
and and you know i think that i came to
appreciate this through doing this buddhist practice where at some point
the most beautiful thing that i've ever seen in this world i've seen many beautiful places and
many beautiful things but i think that the most beautiful thing a person can encounter and see or
perceive is a clean mind and to have touched that which i feel
like i've touched in myself that it's just astounding to see that this is a possibility for us
so you know clean your mind we clean our teeth hopefully every day
we clean our bodies most days shower or whatever we do and we clean our dishes
why not our minds and you know if you brush your teeth
twice a day maybe you should clean your mind twice a day meditate twice a day why not
you know why isn't it why not why do it is that the mind is probably
one of the most influential
forces in this universe of ours one of the most influential at least in the human world
it's like really really influential and
the harm comes from it the desirable benefit comes from it love comes from it hate comes from it
and so to clean the mind and then or empty the mind another way of saying
it is to empty the mind of great hatred and delusion empty the mind of of attachment
and then the amazing thing happens is that uh it just feels natural then
to avoid malevolence it's not like a moral injunction you're just like of
course why would i why would i do something malevolent when
that's doesn't just make the mind dirty again it actually scars the mind
it's a powerful language isn't it it scars the mind that if the mind is overly scarred one
more scar you don't notice you don't even know you're doing it but when the mind becomes clean you see the effect it
has and then and then engage in what's skillful and
what's nourishing what's wholesome it's not an injunction it's like of course
that's what the clean mind wants to do that's what it is about is to do the things which are clean to
do the things which are healthy that's nourishing supportive
and and so the last one purifying the mind uh i was um
uh i had a little bit struggle with that for a while because i came my first uh buddhist practice was
in mahayana buddhism the buddhism of zen buddhism where they had
three kind of principles like this the first two are basically the same
avoid evil do everything that's good but the third one was
liberate all beings so there's an idea of compassion and i love that the idea that we'd live
for the liberation for the benefit of others and that that was a dedication to practice for that purpose
and then the criticism of mahayana of our tradition is that we're the selfish ones
we're the ones who are just involved in our you know our own practice for our own liberation so then the contrast of
this line purify your mind versus liberate all beings seems to accentuate
this divide and so i was a little bit troubled by this for a while but i came eventually
to realize that um that these two things are not so separate
that if we clean our mind purify our mind empty our mind it's uh then there's this greater
sensitivity to harm and to
other people and the state of other people empathy mirroring other people understanding other people
caring for other people that the natural outcome of a clean mind
is in some appropriate way for each person that we do care we do want to liberate we do want other people to
benefit and it's a little bit like you know on the airplane where you're supposed to take the
oxygen mask for yourself first before doing the children or someone who needs help
um it's a little bit like that that you know before you help someone else not be malevolent
maybe you should do it yourself first because how much how much good how well
can you help other people to be non-malevolent if you're still being malevolent
how how much can you help other people to do things which are skillful if you don't know what's skillful or what's what's
wholesome having to cultivate it for yourself and so these these all go together and i
don't think that the any of these are so separate self and other benefiting oneself
benefiting others they come to they can become more they come together more and more as we practice in buddhism
as as a singular whole and and with inseparable from each other and that just seems so beautiful to me
that that's the case so um these
um three principles that kind of
kind of simplify all the rest of buddhism and some of buddhism is philosophically
profound which can mean sometimes that it's
difficult to understand complicated but if you remember it all arises from
these simple principles everything is an expression of that or manifestation of that or a
commentary on that or or support for that
you know then maybe it's all kind of simple so i'll read it again with my current
um translation choice doing nothing malevolent
engaging in what is skillful wholesome and purifying one's mind this is the
teaching of the buddhas
so that's the talk we have a few more minutes left in the time that we for the scheduled
dharma talk time and then after this we'll have a picnic outside for those of you like to stay
but if you'd like to ask any questions or have any commentary about what i said
you're welcome too and um
uh thank you dr bronson i thought your uh commentary about
the the medical connection was pretty apt i believe that the foot that goeth alma was actually referred to as the
physician so i just found that connection nice
yeah yeah i'm inspired by the connection as well or the overlap and and inspired by the medical ethics and
just in general it's i wish it the rest of society would adopt it yeah
thank you
yeah you can pass that back but edna speak first
you very much for the talk girl um i have a question about uh you know purifying the mind and cleaning one's
mind what about when the emotions are really strong and kind of rule then
how i guess what would be the the method of cleaning ones cleaning
one's teeth cleaning one's mind with strong emotions yeah i think that uh
meditation practice is a optimal way of doing it for many people because we're cultivating the
mindfulness to recognize what's happening in the mind and the recognition is
is very very helpful especially if the recognition of what's in the mind goes together with
relaxing the mind settling the mind stabilizing the mind because then you're
beginning to let go of the agitation of the difficult aspects of mind the
unclean aspects of the mind and so to see it clearly and allow it to settle
and that more it settles the more you see kind of a calm mind a clear mind a clean mind
then the more you have a new perspective to catch the
the difficulties that arise when they do arise because we have this background now of like a clean cloth you
see a little you know spot of grease on it right away but a really a
cloth that's full of grease you don't see one more spot so we start seeing more and more so i
think meditation is a great way to do it thank you and everything else buddhism
teach us
um yeah there's i really appreciated the talk i think there's so much so simple
but so complicated as well in terms of how to apply but i just wanted to make a
comment the idea about resentment for um a good friend of mine had said resentment is like taking the pills and
expecting the other person to die
i've watched some videos on medical ethics in my teaching and i remember one of the
pillars the four pillars one of them is justice yeah and i was thinking about justice as
yeah that's sort of working things out in the bigger system in the whole
community maybe more of a sangha way of looking at things yeah yeah justice yeah and also sometimes that has to do with
equity and fairness and the fair fair big part of it is the fair
usage of limited medical resources who gets it and how do you decide who gets it when it's limited and how is it
how is it justice how is it fair and
there's one back there oh yeah go ahead
so grappled a little bit with the the speed
of response so the dirty dishes analogy for example the one you gave
the amount of time it took to settle yourself and ask the question you
know rather than the gruff like why are the dishes dirty again
you know the calm equipoise non malevolent way
feels like the environment is our dirty dishes and our response is not speedy enough
so how do we approach that with non-malevolence
if if you understand the question well maybe not but let me try anyway is that um
i think that as we develop mindfulness more ability to monitor ourselves as we do it we
might not have the capacity to notice the subtlety of the intentions what we're doing in the mind
but ideally we get enough ability to monitor what we say and what we do with our
hands and and so to really bring a lot of attention to
the our tongue and our and our body and
and then learn how to restrain and then
at least restrain any anytime you're going to say something that you have doubts whether this is really kind
and and and uh and so
and that restraint which is not very popular thing to do might be the protection you need so you
have the time then to go to go look deeper and that's why the principle of do know
don't make it worse so just learn to restrain learn to hold back
and um and so if your hand goes into a fist
you know restrained well and the follow-up there is the even
the restraint feels like a um an injury to self like as i contemplate
climate change and and what i should be doing yeah if i'm not doing then i'm
somehow harming myself and not really um all that
a beneficent actor yeah so so uh we do the best we can but i
don't make it worse so so if uh if you're
the best you can do is not make it worse in the environment but you're still you know harming yourself in some way
but you also want to kind of look more deeply at how you're harming yourself you know yes if you're driving a car
you are indirectly harming yourself coming back comes back to you a little bit
uh but if uh but but uh if then you're um uh
drowning in guilt grounding and self-hostility drowning in in self-criticalism
then then you've added maleficence towards yourself
then there's a malevolent feelings attitudes towards oneself and any malevolence is not needed
so so then the training the practice is to discover how not to view oneself or to add
malevolence hatred hostility towards oneself and and
and that's i think is brilliant how to live in this world without
malevolence towards oneself or others so we're not struggling with guilt and in buddhist in
the buddhist definition of guilt it isn't just simply that we did something that's wrong and know
it guilt is has a sense of self-hatred in it
and so the practice is to purify ourselves of that that's as important as not having malevolence out there harming out there
you know you don't want to pollute yourself this reminds me of that penultimate um
moment of the buddha's enlightenment where he turns to in inwards and notices the second arrow
yes and pulls that out and this is but i've been stuck with that second arrow recently
with some of these uh you know the the events of the
the globe yeah yeah it's challenging to be a human being especially in this modern world
and so part of part of part of the skill of practice is also to learn to somehow
be a little bit more relaxed or have the capacity of have the capacity
to feel the discomfort that we feel to feel the challenges of the mind and
and not not to add second third or fourth arrows but to kind of somehow build the ability
to open up kindly to how challenging this for us and what we're doing in our inside
so one last one behind you okay thank you very much um
i just wanted to sort of add one one slight thought on the
physician's oath which also begins with first do no harm yeah and it seems
really interesting that there's not only that parallel but the comment you made about the rules for
the monastics in some sense the physician has an extra
obligation as a decision maker or someone who's in charge of the the patient's life
and another way that they sometimes think about it is don't let the perfect be the enemy of
the good which goes back to your initial point of you know don't make it worse yeah so
that that's something that i've sort of ruminated on as as you're um a dharma talk sort of unfolded and it
thought great sure thank you yeah it's a wonderful principle don't
make it worse i think it's fantastic to carry that with you and like what
what thank you so much there's now we're going to take one question from the youtube audience that someone put in the
chat so so uh so evelyn asks um gail how do you
navigate the idea of putting one's mind on a screen where everyone can see how clean it is
with avoiding shame and embarrassment about all of the current blotches
he has a good question how to avoid shame and embarrassment um
well some degree of embarrassment seems healthy you know it's not
that does not necessarily uh self-harm or not necessarily self-hatred or something it's just like
oh you know this is unfortunate and um but shame maybe is much more painful
and difficult and and so what degree shame has some kind of self-harming aspect to it that's unnecessary
it's a profound thing there's a lot of people who feel shame and it's a difficult state and one that
sometimes learn from society learn from
other people and and we internalize it for ourselves
so it might be that before uh making your mind public to everyone
maybe resolving the issue of shame understanding a little bit the the
you know i don't want to make it harder for anybody this idea of of shame what i'm about to say
uh it's meant to be kind of freeing and compassionate but shame uh is uh
involves a degree of conceit and not the conceit of being arrogant the conceit of being a little bit
excessively preoccupied with ourselves with self-identity and how we're represented how we're seeing and how
we're understood and of course we are that way where our society trains us to be that way
but buddhism buddhist practice shows us how much we can let go of self-preoccupation self-definition
um kind of the attachment to self-ideas that we have self views about oneself
and then it's a lot easier to um to have our behavior transparent so
other people can see it because we don't um we don't feel um
it doesn't get stuck in our self-concept for ourselves we don't we don't linger in it we try to do
better but we don't define ourselves by it so to really study this idea of shame
and free ourselves from before we become more transparent i think it's really worthwhile
uh when i was i was ordained as a zen priest and monk 40 years ago
and and one of the remarkable things that happened with that
ordination that i wasn't thinking about or planning it just kind of happened and i saw in the weeks after the ordination
was that um now i was a public figure you know i had a shaved head i wore robes
and um and so much i called it my shortcomings were
much more obvious and i was much more conscious of them that i had before
and and at the same time
it was more okay to have them but it wasn't like i barreled ahead and
just did terrible things in the world because i had these shortcomings i i was going to practice with them and try to
work with them and i had anger so i had to kind of work with my anger and try to keep it in check so it didn't didn't
cause harm but i became much more sensitive to these shortcomings but it was more okay to have them
because in the language i had back then i was now a child of the buddha
i had been ordained and somehow being a child of the buddha was now in the fold of the buddha's lap
you know it's not being held by some this compassionate caring force in the universe somehow
and i was accepted for who i was as a practitioner with my shortcomings
so it was wonderful i thought it was really significant to both become more sensitive to my
shortcomings so i could practice with them and work with them and clean at the same time it was in certain kind
of way more okay to have them and and that made it a lot easier to work
with them if because i didn't have the conceit the concern i didn't feel the
shame for having them it's more like of course i have them now i get to practice with them
so evelyn i hope my answer is a very important question you asked and i hope that my
my answers gives you something to chew on that's useful