warm greetings and from a dark morning in Redwood City
California at the IMC Insight Meditation Center
and um from this kind of
seat in the middle of IMC Dharma seat
um seeing all your names and greetings and I kind of imagined that the IMC is
has stretched and stretched and stretched in circles of the community now extends around the globe and
it's a very nice feeling so
for the meditate oh no sound one person says they have no sound but
when it's only one person it probably has to do with them their their technology rather than here
so I'm going to continue and um
so one of the
I'd like to say something that maybe is a little bit um
hopefully in a good way kind of provocative and um
and maybe make an impression on you for this meditation maybe help you become
quieter think less and more be curious
what you're capable of discovering or being
when there is more silent awareness in the way that if you listen to a sound
you don't need to be thinking to hear the sound when you're tasting food you don't need to be thinking while you're
tasting it in fact if you think distracted thoughts you might miss the sound or miss the taste
so in the same way so we can put this the thinking mind is not needed for the
Deep awareness that's possible in uh
in just a deep kind of silent and wonderful awareness
and that this awareness that we're capable of um this kind of a natural functioning of
our minds our being and if we can leave it alone
but our if we're alert to it alert to awareness
foreign of awareness by itself just kind of attending to it and the Silence of it or
the Stillness of it or whatever there will be no complaining
no blame
and in that lack of complaining and lack of blaming
there is something in the family of love
exactly what that is it would might be vary from person to person maybe just a
simple tenderness or a sense of gentleness towards all things or warmth
maybe it's compassion kindness maybe doesn't need to have a name
in this wonderful vague English word love is all we need to know
so what is it when you sit and are alert to awareness
if mindfulness is very simple and open receptive to
what is how is it that there's no complaining
and no blaming in that
and instead there might be something in the family of love in that
could it be how is that and I'm hoping that this evocative
maybe if I could have introduction doesn't uh lead you to do a lot of
thinking about this complaining about what I said for example uh making exceptions install that that
can be for later is plenty of times to think it out and
but maybe there can be a curiosity
as you do your practice and show up for your experience with this
clear awareness in that awareness
is it characterized by an absence of complaining and blaming
might it be somehow maybe subtly
characterized by love
so to begin with a
yeah assuming a meditation posture
and maybe the somewhat silent sensing and feeling
of the body can be how you begin your meditation to
sense and feel your posture your body and your posture
making small adjustments to your posture in ways that
support the body to be more aligned more settled
more at ease
and gently
closing your eyes
and perhaps with a curious quietness of mind
or where the quietness of sensing and feeling the body
taking a few long slow deep breaths
stretching the Torso of the rib cage as you breathe in deeply
and let go relax
settle on the exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
and on the inhale emphasize the way the body
can feel and sense itself
not really needing the medium of thoughts ideas images
on the inhale feel where the body might be tense or holding you
tight and on the exhale
allow the body to soften around that area
and for the next two or three breaths
feel your whole body as you inhale in whatever way that is easy
and as you exhale see if you can quiet or let go of your
thinking
letting go into your breathing
letting go into your body I meant to say
letting go of your thinking and letting go into your body
and as we continue with whatever capacity you have to be
aware without needing to think about it
hearing sounds feeling sensations of the body
simple knowing simple registering of
emotions and thoughts
being alert to a silent awareness
thought free your thought reduced awareness
perhaps being aware out there and that awareness
there's no complaining complaining or blaming
even if some other place like in the place of thinking there might be
go to that place where there's no complaining no blaming
being aware in a quiet way
and in that quiet might you find something in the nature
of love within that awareness accompanying that
awareness supporting it
and as you continue this meditation stay close
to the awareness that doesn't complain the awareness that is
Associated comes with something in the family of love
thank you
where is that place in awareness
where there is no complaining no blaming
might there be some place of awareness
um which is in touch with qualities of kindness and good will
love
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
imagine that you're sitting on a park bench next to someone maybe a friend or
someone you know but the after some conversations and
talking and there's no need to talk anymore it feels very content to sit quietly
and imagine in this quiet Silent Way of sitting with a friend next to each other
that you are aware of them you even think of them without any complaints without any blame
but rather with good will not a good will that is a doing
something doing good will but rather from a place where awareness
has tenderness gentleness good will love care
something like that within it maybe your care Your Love can be private
do you have to you don't have to tell them you're sitting quietly
and maybe in this privacy of sitting quietly next to each other you can allow yourself to feel
fully the warmth the care of this other human being loved
that maybe now can extend outwards to the park the trees the children playing
the people strolling
and out into the world
there is a way in which a quiet mind
can give room for the heart's capacity to quietly love
generously love and
may it be that our capacity to do this practice to free ourselves from complaining and
blaming hostility of all kinds
may it be so that we can promote the welfare and happiness of everyone
may it be that we learn to live effortlessly
with the welfare and happiness of everyone may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so this will be the fourth talk on what happened called condition to
consciousness with this wonderful
phenomenon the fact that one way or the other in our waking hours maybe other times
that we're conscious we're aware we're conscious beings so we're beings
and um and maybe that's enough to know but that we also have some way of
constructing a sense an idea a Feeling
of what it is to be conscious as if there's something called Consciousness something that we can call awareness
and the danger of that kind of word is that we make it into a thing and so then
we try to discover what is that thing whereas maybe it's not a thing maybe
it's more like a hologram and that is kind of something a hologram but is it a thing
then we get caught up in issues of linguistics and definitions but
but um there's some uh this condition
conscience is conditioned sense of what this being conscious is a lot to do with states of mind we have
and attitudes we have and all kinds of things and um
and so today I want to talk about the difference in Consciousness and
awareness between blaming and loving complaining and
caring so when we spend time blaming
planing and cotton in in the grip of those States
it there's a they were caught in the grip there's a tightening there's a narrowing
and uh and often that tightening and narrowing of uh around those feelings
with ideas are closely connected to the sense of self and it becomes kind of a a
a a lumping up a coagulation a a condensing
of a lot of different things awareness Fielding Sensations in the body attitudes energies of the thinking where
everything kind of gets you can take a strong feeling of me yes Me Myself and
mine the self and and um and it's when the blaming is this is
this place of contractions oftentimes that's a source of uh or the the origin
of this a strong motivation to be blaming and complaining about things
and the Paradox is that this tight place of self that can be felt experientially
somehow um is a it's kind of like a um a solid
wall that experience of the World will hit it and uh and it's it hurts it or it
threatens it or you know it's this wall is fragile or
whereas when that self-coagulation this contraction of self is not there
then the events of the world can still be known very clearly but the known has
the knowing has no weight that has no substance it has no resistance and what
is no it just travels right through and we can still be responsible and take
care of things but it doesn't hit anything it doesn't reinforce that coagulated that's contracted
sense of self and so the blaming and complaining is kind of this world and universe of self
and other and conflict and tension and uh in which
um there's awareness gets contracted gets small and tight uh it gets filled with that
as the uh as we learn to sit quietly and
shed the contractions of the Mind the tightness of the Mind things we're holding on to and clinging to
then the preoccupation with complaining and blaming will quiet down
the motivation to be hostile this sense of hostility within which is part of the
same complex will settle and uh and then awareness has a chance
of not being so congested with a lot of concerns a lot of feelings
a lot of this a lot of the self that we can live under and this contracted self
this tight place of where we're caught up in ourselves and um
and so the sense of awareness then our capacity to sense or feel that being
aware becomes more and more empty of all this Gunk all this stuff
and this emptiness is a fantastic thing um because we then to be aware of
emptiness there's awareness of the emptiness and but emptiness can grow in a certain
way and have no boundaries can be as big as this room because the cathedral because the space over the ocean
and but the but that which knows it kind of begins to share some of the
qualities of that it's a kind of like part of the we construct this idea of uh
for of what Consciousness is from the way that uh we know the way that not
knowing sentencing feeling or wearing um a kind of kind of is and if it's more
and more empty it has different characteristics and part of that care part of that is
that the more empty it is it allows for something deeper to surface and be present
and and I say the call that's something the family of love
and I think we find many spiritual Traditions will say something like this in Buddhism sometimes especially
Mahayana Buddhism they equate the Deep experience of emptiness with compassion
somehow that emptiness and compassion are rise together or there's compassion in emptiness
and um and uh and this wonderful kind of uh phenomena of how
somewhere other is some sense of emptiness they talk about uh is uh
coterminous with Compassion or impregnated with Compassion or something really wonderful
and um and uh so to
we have this capacity to nurture others to parental nurturing of children
is a deep Instinct we have we have capacity to care for the welfare
others like a like a nurse who tends and cares maybe lovingly and
and warmly for whoever's been wounded or hurt or sick
and maybe even someone they don't even know but they there's a care there's a
kindness there's a warmth that comes and can come in that kind of caring
so so this uh kind of amazing capacity that as awareness feels more expensive
more peaceful that it's it's a more empty in a certain
kind of way there's a room for something to surface in it that doesn't
detract from that emptiness because there's no contraction there's no tightening up around it like there is
with blaming and complaining um but the the Mind stays open the heart
stays open and then um
and then kind of penetrating it all or oozing from it or
radiating can be Good Will kindness friendliness care
tenderness warmth compassion um
sympathy empathy and then maybe just plain old-fashioned
love and this is one of the great things of this kind of deepening of practice is to
have that kind of begin to surface and for some people certainly my case
that my own capacity for compassion kindness loving kindness meta
was not something that I cultivated or worked at developing
but it surfaced as I in my practice as I matured in this Buddhist practice there
was room for it and something began to emerge and to grow that
um uh you know changed my life around this family of Love kind of experience you
know we have and uh it felt kind of like this was what was in there waiting to come and in
the open space of awareness quiet settled
and uh so um um
so I would like to propose to you that complaining and and complaining like
blaming blaming and in a complaining way is really a waste of time for you
it's really a form of undermining yourself
in fact all hostility is an undermining of yourself
your hostility if you have it your hostility
keeps you hostage not hostility
frees you from captivity
hostility makes you a hostage your own hostility
makes you hostage non-hostility frees you from captivity it's that
dramatic and um and so
so check it out if you have a tendency of complaining
especially if you have a tendency but even if you have an occasion to complain and with that kind of complaining be
blaming someone else you are then um giving
someone else responsibility or for your happiness and
your peace don't be a hostage don't give away
your peace to someone else that way live in your own peace take
responsibility for it don't sacrifice it if you need to take care of something a
problem in the world it's chances are it's possible to do it to do it even better if you don't
complain and you don't blame maybe you can do it better
when you're kind support loving caring compassionate
so much better that sometimes it's better to wait to address a problem until you
have some modicum of Goodwill some decrease of the blaming blaming and
the hostility so thank you very much and um
may your conditioned consciousness nourish you with love