hi everyone and welcome
this evening i want to talk about
the topic of resolve and maybe resolve is a
burdensome concept like you have to work at something
the ancient word for it is aditana
one person translates it one book translated as the foundation
the the word can mean some literally can mean
something like closer to the english words to take a stand or to stand in something
or a special place to stand
so it's a place where we kind of come out of take our stand stand on or supported by
and um part of the value of this resolve
some people translated as a vow or aspiration
is that to the degree to which buddhist practice
encourages us to let go deeply or brings us to a place where the
ordinary idea of self is not operating so much
or where brings us to a place where we have
we no longer can live with some of the values we've been living with before some of the orientations or purposes of
our life that we had before it's easy to feel disoriented it's easy
to feel a certain kind of what's the purpose or
how do i orient myself now the buddha said once you know nothing
whatsoever is worth clinging to
well if nothing's worth clinging to and i've been clinging my whole life to something or
other to be motivated to know what to do then what do i do when i don't cling do
i just sit at home on the couch you know what what do i do
and so in this kind of context buddhism offers
resolves aspirations vows a certain kind of orientation way to live in the world
that can guide us can support us could be a place to stand a standing place
orientation a foundation for ourselves and um
and in our early buddhist tradition there are four resolves
that are taught and that is to stay close to these these
can guide us these can support us so when in doubt
live with these resolves and i think of them as being so important such a good foundation or
place to come from that if someone asks you
you know what do you do i think in modern english basically they're asking you what what's your work
i think that's what they mean it's almost almost anonymous
but i think sometimes in our modern society his career and work is kind of overrated
sometimes sometimes people's sense of worth comes from the worth comes from the work they
do or their status or their what you know their
their the appreciation that people think oh this person's special is because of the work they do
so so someone asks you what do you do
one answer is you can say oh i
do these four resolves i stand in these four resolves so they're they're that important that
if you know if that might for some people be actually be more important than a career or work
that they would this is this would be the guiding principles of a life
so the four there's four results the first is to be resolved on wisdom
the second is to be resolved on the truth
the third is to be resolved on letting go or giving up
relinquishing it's a wonderful word the pali word here
because the word can also mean giving or generosity and the fact that these two the word for
letting go or relinquishing also means to give or be generous it's kind of a fascinating
topic and the fourth resolve is to resolve on peace
so wisdom truth letting go and peace these are worthwhile places take a stand
or to be oriented you can ask yourself as i'm sit in any situation you're in
how do i relate to this wisely
what's true here what's really the truth here what's the the significant truth of the moment that
i'm overlooking and not noticing because i'm involved in my desires or my fears or my
planning for the future but what's the truth of this moment
what is it that is appropriate to relinquish here to not hold on to anymore to let go
and how is this letting go in the moment here a generous thing to do
not a diminishment of self not a diminishment of our life or not um impoverishing us and letting go
but something that is generous and generosity maybe that comes from a
feeling of inner wealth we have an abundance of
well and of course we happy to let go so other people make space we don't we're
not impoverished and then then uh where's the peace here
is there peace in this situation a peacefulness is there a place for that here
now this might seem kind of like a maybe artificial or strange orientation
to have as we go through the life but
when we think about what many people are actually resolved on
maybe sometimes unconsciously they don't even know they're resolved on things what people mostly do with their lives
and they make the center of orientation of their life these are pretty good resolves to live
live by some people are resolved on greed
some people are resolved on complaining and hostility and blame
some people are resolved on fear and anxiety
some people are resolved on hanging on to the past and memories and
ideas some people are resolved on fantasies of the future
or delusions of grandeur of some kind or other
or resolved on being safe
there's i like the little quote to the little cliche that says that
a boat is safe in a harbor but that's not what the boat was built
for you know if we spend a lot of time trying to keep ourselves safe we weren't
actually built to be safe you know to be always safe so that to be resolved on that maybe we
shortchanged ourselves some people are resolved on money and
wealth status power
all kinds of things some people are resolved on being loved
being respected and some of these of course are not
necessarily wrong to be oriented towards but if they're the center of the life
maybe that's not maybe we're missing out on something maybe we're diminished with those
results if that's really what we're all about these four resolves i propose it's
different that if we resolved on those they don't necessarily prevent us to do all other kinds of
things they don't replace the things that we might do in our life
but if we take our stand in these four resolves
that will radically change how we do all the things that we do
and maybe some of the ways in which we engage the world
are not so healthy for ourselves and for others and to engage in the world to do these
things that we do but to do it from a different orientation
can be powerful so these four resolves
so the first resolve is wisdom and
and this is to uh to be wise about how we
view our situation to be wise how we approach our situation
why is in what we do and how we understand what we're doing and um
and just to ask that question you know what's the what's the wise thing to do here
what's the wise approach to this what's the wise way of seeing the situation
and then it's you know almost i can repeat myself and some of the ways that we view
are not particularly wise if we look through the filter of our greed ambition
our hostility or blame or anxiety and
those aren't really wise ways doesn't help us see clearly it doesn't help us to see how to live
usefully in a good way so are there different ways of seeing
different ways of relating to the situation we're in oddly enough one of the wise ways that
buddhism emphasizes to what we look for what we study
is to study where the stress is to study where the
is to it's wise to notice where there's tension where there's suffering where
there's pain not so we can suffer more
but so that we can it's wise to understand that it's
happening that it's there so that we can be within a different way
part of wisdom is to be with what's challenging with the stress
situation uh in order to understand it better
to understand particularly our contributions to it what are we doing that contributes to
the way we feel uncomfortable or stressed or afraid or upset or whatever it might be
and to um it's wise to study this why is to look at this to understand it
and if there is ways that we contribute to our own stress
then maybe we can let go of it if we know what it is but if we ignore the suffering we have
the stress we have the tension we have and we ignore then
our contribution to it then there's no way of knowing what we can do personally to make the situation
better one of the ways that's not wise
is to spend a lot of time blaming others being resentful or complaining about
others i'm certainly i'm sure there are people who are definitely appropriate too
i don't know blame for things that happen in the world but if we're resolved always on blaming
other people and never look at ourselves we once again limit
their lives we narrow our lives and this movement of looking in
ourselves wisely and where our suffering is where our attention and grasping and clinging is
and letting go of it is actually a movement that opens us up
that does the opposite of limiting ourselves it creates more an unlimited way of being in the world
and so to be resolved on what wisdom and this is what i just described today was in the
core forms of buddhist wisdom be wise about our suffering or
truth to be wise about what's true to know the truth to ask what is true
here and of course there's many things you can say is true
you know so someone asked me you know what's true in the moment here i can say well there's a blue tape but
then the floor that's crooked and uh you know that's not gonna
that's not the kind of truth that will set you free unless you're a zen master they can say
things like that but um but the uh
you know but it's not going to go that far but you know if i'm sitting here what's true
might be that i appreciate sitting here with you i value that you came here today and
i take your interest in the dharma seriously and i feel like i would like to
to offer something to you that respects your interest in coming here that's true
if that that has a different feeling to recognize that than to recognize that
someone put the tape down crooked it's okay for me to say it because i was the one who did it
and they um
i suppose what's true as well is that uh i have a teeny bit of
apprehension nervousness maybe a little bit that here we are back in person again and teaching in person and
and uh my my offering something that's useful for you and helpful and
worthwhile your time to come here and so i don't know how useful that truth is
but i recognize it that that's also here and so rather than having that
concern be something that you know eats at me or bothers me or
inhibits me or you know i just recognize it's there it's true and knowing it's true then
it's like okay you know it's like a it can it's okay it can accompany me it's not going to interfere with what i
do here i'm not caught up in it and concerned so i don't know if those are good
examples but the idea is to to recognize that what's what's true what's really true here what's true that
has to do with our suffering what's true about our freedom what's true about our appreciation of
things the love of the moment what's the truth that that
brings this moment that we're here into a kind of a full fullness into a
life into a place where we can meet other people and be connected and
feel grounded and feel like feel like it's wonderful to be alive
is there a truth that would provide that for us what if there is
wasn't it kind of sad not to stop and notice it and recognize it
so to discover what is true and uh and part of what the buddhist
tradition emphasizes that's important is to recognize the truth
of where we're grasping where we're clinging what we're clinging to what we're resisting
to because that if we recognize the truth of that then there's hope to release it to look
through it to the other side but if we don't see the truth of that then we can't do that work
and or the or sometimes it's the opposite that we can see as a truth
we can see the truth of our freedom the truth of our vitality and connectedness
to ourselves to others to the world that comes when we're not caught in the grip of clinging or resistance or
preoccupation and to recognize that truth and to live it and connect to people and be present
and then this truth of relinquishment letting go
if if i use the word giving up
uh it might be kind of depressing there are all kinds of relationship
connotations but but it has the word giving in it and the word chaga the c-a-g-a the word
for relinquishment also means generosity giving
and you find that in buddhism the buddhist language is all these words
that have this double meaning generosity or giving and then letting go
and we find that in english the word um giving up apparently originally
um it was related to the word or the expression to offer something up on the altar
like some sacred thing and um i don't know if that's true but that's what i've read
and now to offer up uh we have the expression uh giving in
you give in to someone and it's you know it's a little bit depressing that you're giving in to someone but but then they have the word
giving in it so maybe there's a deeper wonderful way of giving in on the
freeway sometimes i like to uh i give way to people someone's coming you
know wants to merge into my lane and you know i probably have the right to be there
i probably you know you know it looks safe and you know and i have
the right and that took a long time to get into that lane and not someone once it gets in front of me they're coming off getting onto the freeway
you know i i could you know just kind of like
insist that i get my way and let them kind of deal with the shoulder of the road
but i like what i like to do is give way here you can have it please sort of give way give in
give up i don't know i don't know if there's other giving words give attention that's not giving up though
i like the expression giving attention but to let go
so what can we relinquish here where it's just where it's a a healthy
wonderful place to take a stand where do we relinquish
not so that we're diminished but so we're somehow we become bigger or more alive or more
present or life feels more worth living than being closed in and held down and
holding on to something what are we holding on to what are we holding on to what are we
clinging to when we feel socially awkward with other people
it's remarkable and sometimes offensive this buddhist idea that
i think it's buddhist other people can say it too that you know certainly
there's a lot of attachment when there's conceit of being special but these buddhists say that
there can be just as much conceit in being shy
that's what's kind that's kind of like what shy people aren't there that's because they're they don't have much self or
they're kind of like but there's still a concern with the self there
where is it appropriate to let go of self concern self-concern we have
is limiting us and certainly shyness can be limiting
but so can conceits of grandeur that i'm special even if they people agree with you and
so it feels pretty good it actually limits ourselves a lot it
actually becomes a scenario or a world to live in and to let go of conceit
wow what a great thing
and so what can we really what to take a stand on the relinquishment
and let it be a kind of generosity what would it look like if
there's a benefits a form of wealth or happiness that comes
from relinquishment to to relinquish out of a place of abundance
or to relinquish to tap into the sense of inner abundance that's not dependent on
material goods or status or all kinds of things
and that's one of the great possibilities of meditation practice is to discover in the simplicity of
meditation or to awaken a feeling of inner abundance
that comes with that freedom that comes from a fullness that comes from no longer limiting ourselves
with fear and all the different things we can limit ourselves with
and to both feel like we're the relinquishment is almost like an offering of that
abundance outwards it's not a giving something up it's a gain
i'm fond of the idea that um i think some people when they think of letting go
they think it means uh we're going to drop something and
and the teachings of the buddha as far as my reading has been um he i think it's rare if ever he talks
about letting go of anything uh he talks about um but he just talks
about letting go of the clinging and if you hold something and you let go
of the clinging to it you might still be holding it if you respect everything
you don't drop things you just you hold it and it was what this gesture now
this is a gesture of generosity like here or safety or something here
and then we can use our wisdom to know whether it should be given to someone or put down or do something
but to let go so with this movement with the palm of the hand
facing upwards is holding the whatever's there rather than dropping something
which maybe it's not so healthy but this then we can put things down if we need
to so to take a stand in that relinquishment
that's generous that releases gender a certain way to freeze a certain generosity they come
maybe both comes from abundance and provides a sense of abundance
and then the fourth resolve is the resolve of peace
and there is a really good time excellent time
to be resolved on peace really good there's a there's a particular circumstance where it's
really a good thing to do the best time to resolve result on peace
is when it's better than the alternative
and how often do you think that occurs that it's better than the alternative if
you have a better thing going on than peace by all means forget about the peace
but if the alternative isn't as good you might want to consider it
i like the word ease rather than peace somehow the word
peace is nice but ease has a for me a more embodied feeling it's also how how
i act how i live what kind of process they're going on inside there's an ease to what happens
whereas peace in my vocabulary feels a little static my ease is more dynamic
you might not have that associations but but to be be
take a stand on peace the alternative is to be take a stand on
war on conflict take a stand on
being in opposition with reality the reality is not cooperating
the weather is not good it's raining
it doesn't really understand that today was not the day to rain i had important things to do to be resolved on peace
one wouldn't then be angry at the clouds
well uh where is the peace in this circumstance where do i find my peace where i find
ease with whatever is going on
it's not an acceptance of the situation it's not condoning situations not becoming passive in the situation
but it is operating from a place of being peaceful
being at ease being calm perhaps tranquil certain tranquility
in engaging and doing the things maybe that we have to do
there are times in my life where i've when i was younger where i was quick to quick to be alarmed by
situations like ah we got to do something so like i call 9-1-1 i did a few times
like oh there's something terrible going on we have to call 9-1 and um
and then after a few minutes later uh i think was calmed down i looked at
the situation and said there's not a problem here so i hope that never happened to any of
you but uh but the ability to be peaceful or calm lets us see the situation clearly
i haven't had i haven't had this situation but i have a lot of friends who
had dangerous things happened to them and because they stayed calm
there was some creative thinking that arose for them in the moment to take care of the
dangerous situation at the time um
one person i know was being held up in san francisco by some teenagers or something
and um it looked like a dangerous situation and so the person suddenly found himself
saying uh you're no christian what would your
mother think and that kind of stress you know just stunned them a little bit and then he ran away
he had a little moment there that somehow got them off guard so i i don't recommend that strategy
particularly but but something in him knew as a strategy but something inside of him knew that
that was to to do that and so so you know this creativity or this
intuition or this kind of understanding situation well when we're peaceful
that we aren't if we're anxious so
someone might ask you
where do you come from and conventionally they might say where were you born or where did you grow up
or where you live last or where do you live now but if you want to say what's maybe
where you're most coming from if you're resolved on these you can say
oh i come from i resolved
under i come from the resolve on wisdom truth
relinquishment and peace
they might even ask you who are you
oh you might say truthfully the thing that seems more true than
anything else it's not what they're asking for but might be more true as an answer that you might say to them oh
i'm i'm the resolve on wisdom and truth and relinquishment
on peace so these things can be that central that you could answer that way
but chances are if you did you'd annoy some of the people you say so you probably shouldn't do it that easily
the um but there might be some people
it seems appropriate they might appreciate it they might be inspired because it's
unusual in this life to have people who live on really base route route their lives
on beautiful values beautiful inspiring values
and i think that's what buddhism is recommending and pointing to
it's not just a life of meditation a life of stress reduction a life of being calm
but it's a life that's really rooted or centered on some inspiring values and
possibilities and these four resolves can be seen as
part of that
and then when you have these experiences or where the self seems to dissolve or
where it seems like meaning it is not found anywhere
or disoriented from or kind of
having let go really deeply then these provide a foundation to hold
you these provide a place to stand and you know it's okay
it's okay because i'm committed to wisdom truth letting go
generosity peace
and what a great place to come from what a great place to be resolved what a great place to base one's life on them
especially if you can understand how these four resolves
how healthy they are how how they really bring forth a kind of
delightful spiritual health to ourselves and the world around us
so for results
if you have better results great and if they're
and if uh these four resolves are the better alternative for you you might want to consider them until
you get until you find something better they're pretty good you're not going to
go wrong with them so thank you
those are my thoughts we have a little bit of time if i just
if i take five minutes or so if any of you want to ask a question or comment or
just say something about any of this you're lovely lovely to hear your voice a
little bit now it's kind of i feel it's very special to be together
yes and maybe also say your name you start
hello uh ryan is my name um i
i i think what resonated for me most what you're talking about was about truth um and i thought it was an interesting
contrast that you said you know kind of the this objective truth like the the you
know that there's a blue piece of tape on the floor that wasn't as meaningful a truth as
this kind of subjective aspect of your experience like it was like the kind of feeling apprehensive
about what you're saying like that's not like a you know kind of an objective like objectively verifiable
truth but you know that it's it's all it's almost like an opinion yeah you know from like i think from maybe our more standard way of looking at things
those kinds of things you're talking about are like the less important you know facts um
and so just you know the fact that you're kind of calling attention to the fact that there's this like aspect of our inner experience um
that it's not even really a fact or you know it's it's a it's just a kind of an aspect of our
feeling tone or the way we're relating that's like the kind of the most fundamental truth like i thought that was really um
really interesting so thanks for saying that yeah yeah i think that um that's very important what you're saying and
the distinction you made between facts and truth is very important and i think uh i like to think of truths
as being aspects of the heart so so like like lying about something
is an aspect of the heart something there is it's kind of an illness of the heart and
you know some people lie a lot and we might you might say you might say that in a way that's factual
but you might also someone might recognize oh i really spent my life lying i lived
a lie boy i wish i knew that truth before and it's not just a fact then it
changes them in some deep way so they um
in you know in india the mahatma
and some people have translated as the power of truth some people it
it's uh like the adhering to the truth
so anyway that's beautiful he said thank you thank you
thank you anybody else
well thank you for being here and i hope to see you again sometime