so warm greetings and welcome to
this meditation session and as an introduction to the meditation
that the theme for this week is equanimity particularly particularly the
kind of love that has a quality of equanimity in it
in talking about Equanimity uh one of the things that we can lose
Equanimity around is if we're operating too much from
conceit too much from holding on to some fixed idea of who we are who we should be or
what who we shouldn't be there's something about that um
hardness or that grasping to that those conceit that makes us easily agitated
easily Restless easily reactive to what's going on and that one of the movements in
Buddhist Meditation is uh
so warm greetings and welcome to
so warm greetings and welcome to this meditation session
and as an introduction to the meditation mentioned that the theme for this week
is equanimity particularly particularly the kind of love
that has a quality of equanimity in it and in talking about Equanimity uh
one of the things that we can lose Equanimity around is if we're operating too much from
conceit too much from holding on to some fixed idea of who we are who we should be or
what who we shouldn't be there's something about that um hardness or that grasping to that
those conceit that makes us easily agitated easily Restless easily reactive
to what's going on and that one of the movements in Buddhist Meditation
is called lowering the flag of conceit
and this ancient metaphor of uh likening conceit with the flag that's
held up high I believe it's a little bit of a war metaphor
that maybe it's like Capture the Flag if one person is holding the flag
then the other team will be really trying to get that person or you know
get to that person but if they if they put the flag down then they
don't care so much about that person so if you're holding up the war Banner for your army then the other Army is
going to go after you perhaps it may be a less uh
war-like metaphor is that of an open window that if you throw the baseball through
a closed window the window will break but if the window's open the ball just goes right through
and um so to lower the flag to not have something
that can be attacked within to not have something that is struck by the words
and actions that people have towards us to have like an open window and things
just go right through they don't land anywhere or strike anything within and in particular what that is is the
the absence of conceit the absence of self-preoccupation and self-definition
and um there's a lot more Equanimity then and things will just go right by
kind of like yesterday's metaphor of um the boat and just um you know the
water just washes off the hull of the boat and it's kind of kind of left behind
so to sit and meditate without conceit to sit and meditate without
with the with the windows wide open where nothing has any nothing can land
anywhere nothing it doesn't strike anywhere with a thought a feeling all kinds of
things might arise but it just let it arise and go let it
wash right by imagine yourself just an open window
with vast fast space in front and vast space
behind and things just passed right through and
and then the mind the heart can be at ease can be equanimous by with what arises
and passes so to take a meditation posture
and a posture that hopefully will allow you to
feel recognize some part of you is alert some part of
you is has a certain energy of presence engagement
in some way it kind of means be careful you're not too comfortable
but also be careful you're not too uncomfortable
I think kind of an idea would be that a happy middle way where we're no longer concerned with any
discomfort and no longer involved with any comfort
we're just here unconcerned with Comfort or discomfort
but alert present
and to gently close your eyes
and taking a deep breath gently settling your heart
as you exhale settling the upward activated energy
that if you have that in your body in your heart
so that the your sense of energy in the body your sense of activation in your body
settles down and it allows you to kind of
your whole system to come to rest on the foundation of your lower torso
feeling the lower torso if you're sitting if you're sitting
if you're lying down feel your rib cage not your your back grip gauge and your spine if you're on
your back place that receives the weight of your
body
as you exhale let go into that
relax into that
taking a few long slow deep breaths
and then to soften the shoulders the belly
Release Yourself to the pull of gravity
while sitting upright
letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale continue the process of relaxing
both the surface of the muscle surface of your body
and also deep inside as deep as you can feel or
sense where there's holding or activation
and if you feel some tension activation that doesn't relax that's okay soften around it
soften the muscles of your face
and soften your eyes
maybe letting the eyes in a sense Look Backwards and down if
that is more restful no need to be looking
at anything
and notice any tension or activation pressure
in the area of your brain forehead temples
sides of your skull inside your skull
and for a few breaths breathe with that activation that tension
and then see if you can relax the brain
that whole area the thinking muscle
giving your brain your thinking at rest
from trying and doing making something happen
always thinking so much
and then and then really now becoming aware again
of the body breathing
in a sense having your awareness join the rhythm of breathing
breathing in and breathing out
imagine that as you breathe all the rest of you is like a big window
that opens as you breathe an open window
through which the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out flows
and with the help of your breathing
maybe as if breathing is the window with well lubricated hinges that just opens
easily stays open whatever arises
instead of it hitting anything or being a concern
or something to react to or be involved in
imagine that it just travels through the open window of your being
with vast space in front of you
fast space behind you fast space above you and Below you
and you an open window
things just pass through no need to be involved or react
judge compare no need to relate it to conceit or sell
for Me Myself and mine whatever occurs
does not need to be taken personally it's just something that passes through
the vast window open window of awareness
if you find yourself caught in some concern or preoccupation
see if you're going to open your window really wide
create a wide open vast space of awareness
it just allows whatever is happening I continue to just pass by Flow by
without touching anything without disturbing anything
without it hitting anything within you it's just phenomena that appears and
comes and goes it doesn't touch anything
that makes it personal no definition no involvement
and your your job is keep the window open fast open
awareness through which phenomena travel
thank you
and with a vast open awareness the open window
keeping the window keeping your awareness open is a vast space that things can just
travel through open that window widely wider
to include the people in your life
and see if you can just keep the window open
so there's love and care and friendliness but without
the stories the ideas the responsibilities of with those people
Landing anywhere just let it pass through the vast field
of awareness and love
and opening more widely to include the people of your communities
of your lands of your continent
and the world and what is the quality of your good
will love care compassion
if you settle back and allow the love the care
to be like a vast open window with no going forward no going back no
closing down just a field of care
nothing to do nothing to be
nothing in the field do you need to use to define yourself or
prove yourself defend yourself
just fast peaceful equanimous Goodwill
perhaps a way of being that you'd wish on others
May others also feel safe enough open enough
wise enough to rest in their capacity
for vast love Goodwill compassion and care
may they be happy enough and safe enough to rest in this vast field of love
without needing to prove themselves defend themselves
assert themselves May the people I know
experience this wonderful happy way of being
and wishing it for others remembering
to wish it for yourself give yourself the gift
a vast open window of care and love Goodwill
that doesn't automatically need to do anything or prove anything defend anything
be anything just an open window
it may it be that we learn how to abide this way
so we can share it with others
so we can meet each other together in this space
so that way when we wish people happiness and safety health and freedom
we kind of have a deep reference point for how full and complete that can be
from our open window of Good Will to whatever degree we have it
to express to evoke the wish
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe and healthy
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings live together
sharing this wonderful capacity we have
for open liberated love so open is the window
the frames of the window disappear
[Music]
so the topic on this fourth talk on Equanimity Brahma vihara
is that of the relationship between this Equanimity this kind of love or
care Goodwill that is non-reactive or non-contracted
non-agitated or in the classic language isn't automatically involved in pursuing
or can being attracted to things chasing things
or isn't automatically involved in
repulsion or pushing away or pulling away
but a mind that's able to be present and open to what's happening in the world and to
maintain its Good Will its friendliness its love its care
in spite of the dangers in the world and now we're coming into maybe uh where
the wisdom and practice really comes to a kind of maturity
it's easy enough to have some idea of in
that we're supposed to be loving and everything is wonderful and practices
accept things as they are and and um
and um and for that to be kind of a pastoral image of Life a kind of idea that
everything is wonderful and good and and sometimes when there's a lot of
teaching Buddhist teachings about just sitting in with awareness accepting
things as they are being open to how things are and non-reactive I do feel that sometimes it's the
teachings of people who are relatively privileged and well off and don't have a
lot of challenges in their life that um that many people in this world have
many people live in danger zones and of all kinds in their families and their
communities and their countries and um and there are dangers in this world
so how do we maintain a loving heart a Caring Heart
in the face of dangers so that's one of the important topics and perhaps it's a nice way of also
coming to the end of 2020. where a year ago many of us did not see
the dangers that were going to come for this year and a surprising amount of danger even
fear that now exists in our society that didn't exist a year ago and
or maybe caution at least I mean it's remarkable that walk down the street and people
will avoid each other and I'll step out into the street and let someone else
have the sidewalk someone else will step out in the street and let me have the sidewalk
um even though everyone's wearing masks and um who would have thought I mean it's kind of like living in a science
fiction movie or something too to uh you know it's such a radical
uh kind of change in our society and um so how how can we be wiser with
this how can we be equanimous with this in a wise way an appropriate way and how can we learn from 2020
so that we enter into 2021 with more wisdom with more
Street smarts with more Equanimity and more love and compassion
given what happened during course of this year how we learned how we've matured with all the challenges we've
we've had so I say all this because in the ancient texts the path of the book called The
Path of purification where they talk about the near enemy
of equanimity
they the uh
it's the near enemy what looks like it and it's not really Equanimity but it
looks like it is the Equanimity is it's called ignorant equanimity
and its Equanimity that's ignorant of the dangers in the world so it's easy to be equanimous if they do
you know don't if one that doesn't see the dangers doesn't understand uh what's going on in this life
and um the
so here it says the near enemy is the ignorant Equanimity that is not aware of
danger the far enemy is greed and repulsion
it is not possible to have either greed or repulsion and equanimity
but there's near enemy uh that doesn't really also doesn't really
allow true Equanimity to be there is not aware of danger and I don't think we hear very often in
Buddhist teachings like sit down and close your eyes be aware be in the present moment and now become
aware of danger that there are there is danger in this life
life is fragile life is short they say even with a hundred years life
it's a short life and life is it's easy to get sick
there are people who are not good people go in the wrong
places the wrong times and it is dangerous we live in a world of danger where our
lives can change Forever on a dime in a very quick and I've had I've known plenty of people
and myself and involved also where some accident happens and then we're never
quite the same again and we didn't anticipate the danger that would come
so this is not meant to be a depressing way to end 2020 but it is the classic
way of appreciating that true Equanimity also understands
that the world has dangers and learns to develop the strength the capacity or the openness
and the wisdom of how to be equanimous and loving in the face of danger with
Danger and without that message it's easy to kind of think that we're supposed to just live in a protective and
environment live in a monastery or someplace where you know we're completely safe so we can do this work
of just being completely non-attached to un you know
unfazed by what goes on in the world but I hope that that's not what we're doing I hope we're learning how to live
in the world as it is with its dangers and learning to be
loving in a way that doesn't succumb to repulsion and and pursuit or or
actively kind of you know going after things or actively pulling away automatically automatically going to
help when help is not really needed trying to fix automatically trying to push away or
deny what's there and in some ways this is the maybe one
it's it's said that Equanimity is one of the most mature and developed forms of Buddhist practice it comes after many
years of practice to really have this strong sense of equanimity so it's kind of like the North Star
but it definitely doesn't make us indifferent in fact I mean sometimes here in the west people often say that
the near enemy of equanimity is indifference and um and it's certainly not an indifference
it is it involves a deep caring a deep love and in having it to have an open window
to not have hold on to something that can be hit that can be hurt
and a different analogy for this is that if we hold our hands in a fist
then something can hit it and it can hurt because it's you know maybe it doesn't move very well with very well
but if we open our hands up wide and the fingers wide then things can hit but they kind of just kind of we kind of
like a bamboo flows With the Wind you know back and forth or or maybe it just goes right through the fingers open
fingers and doesn't really touch us and um and so there's a we we go in the
world very differently if we're fists it up and knotted up in something then if we go with an open hand an open heart
and so this ability to not have attachments not have clinging not have
self-definitions we hold on to for dear life but to just relax the heart Relax The
Mind open the clinging and in that be able to be present for danger because
then actually we're in less danger in our hearts we might be in physical danger but the
heart is never in danger if the heart doesn't cling
because there is one way that one kind of implication a Buddhist teacher teachings
is that the greatest danger that we live under live with is it is a danger we
provide ourselves the danger of clinging the danger of giving up our ethical life the danger of
giving up our ease our peace the danger of giving up our love and our freedom
which we do if we cling and get attached there is no intentional and ethical life
without clinging there is no intentional intentions maybe stronger word
the the deepest well-being of the heart doesn't is not lost because of what
people do and the world does around us it's lost because of how we react and respond to that
and so to realize that there's danger here too
and as we practice to learn how to really this idea of staying open an open
window is partly so we're protected from ourselves and then we we're much more protected in
the heart from the dangers of the world we might still things might still happen to us
but um you know they don't run into this you know tight Fist of the heart or in
the mind that things are hard and difficult so to cultivate to discover the form of
love called Equanimity the flavor of of loving equanimous love
that is able to be equanimous and loving in the face of danger
so this is a tall order it's not an easy thing to discover how to do
but uh today you might spend time reflecting on this
and maybe you wouldn't be served very well by arguing against what I'm saying
maybe there's arguments to make against it but maybe you're better served yourself
by exploring and experimenting with this idea is how can you stay loving caring
friendly in the face of what you might think is
dangerous and um don't put yourself in danger please
please take care of yourself but but maybe you can explore this and ride the
edges of it and and maybe there are dangers that you think that you're worried about that maybe
aren't as dangerous as you think as you open up and no longer have anything knotted up inside
maybe talk to friends about this and explore this topic of having equanimous
Goodwill in the face of danger and um
so seems like a wonderful way of learning from this last year
and reflecting on this last year and becoming better people because of this last year and not being the victim of
last year's but really building and preparing for how to go into the next year 2021 and wiser more caring more
loving more Mindful and more for the benefit of the world
so I look forward to seeing maybe as many of you tomorrow morning if you're up early enough
and uh we'll welcome in the new year with um the last Reflections on
equanimity thank you