hello everyone welcome to this beginning of the week
meditation and I want to begin with a little saying
cliche that I like to say but to say it for for the purpose of
this meditation and that is uh
Buddhist practice mindfulness practice does not work
if you don't do it and this simple idea that we have to do
it is actually at the heart of what's necessary to engage and to think about
to be involved in but what I'd like to propose today
is as you're meditating from time to time you'll notice you're not practicing
you're lost in thought or you've drifted away or something fallen asleep
and when that happens then um
you can um not just kind of then Gear Up and
tighten up and really do the practice but rather to appreciate that
recognizing that you weren't doing it recognizing you're not doing it that is mindfulness that's that you're
actually doing it when you're recognizing you're not doing it
and why that is why that's useful to see it this way is it that simple recognition hopefully
relaxed the first initial see oh I'm not doing it
that is kind of clear but relaxed
it's not forceful there's no strain there's no tension hopefully in that simple recognition
oh I'm not doing it and rather than then
buckling up gearing up to do the practice build on that continue in that kind of
ease that kind of simplicity to begin again with your breathing maybe inviting your breathe breath back in
and there's something about this relaxed but then diligent attention diligent doesn't mean
straining but it means that we keep doing it
so relaxed awareness of the present
where the effort is made to keep that relaxed awareness as continuous as possible
and we know it's not possible to really stay continuously continuous
so when you the continuity has been interrupted
you'll have an opportunity again to recognize oh I'm not doing the practice
and so it begins again so
establishing yourself in a meditation posture
that supports both alertness and relaxation
gently closing your eyes
into real relax your body take a few long slow deep breaths
feeling whatever tension there is in the body as you inhale
relaxing whatever can be relaxed in the body as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal and with a normal breath on the inhale
feel your thinking mind and on the exhale
see if you can calm the thinking mind
let it settle
and then settling into your breathing
noticing if there's any ways in which your breathing is tense or held
there's a resistance to either bringing breathing in or
breathing out
and if there is can you lighten up ease up
any tension associated with breathing
and then settling into mindfulness of breathing
as if you're going to do it for the Long Haul each breath
is a breath to be aware of in a relaxed
diligent way
and if your mind wanders off and you're not doing the practice
when you eventually realize that I appreciate the Simplicity of that
realization the earliest inklings of it
and if it's relaxed let that be the basis
for relaxed awareness that begins again with the breathing
how are you doing the practice
or might you be doing the practice half-heartedly with your attention divided between
kind of being present for the breathing but mostly involved in thinking
and if there's a kind of aware of breathing appreciate that
and then put more attention into that
focus on breathing
all right foreign
all right
if you can identify relaxed awareness of breathing
relax to mindfulness add to that the effort
for it to be continuous
where you don't lose the relaxed quality but there is a heightened attention
to hanging in there with it staying with it
being settled on it
and then gently to almost Savor the fullness of
breathing breathe in slowly
and deeply a long inhale to reconnect more fully
with your body a long exhale to settle your body in
preparation for ending the meditation
long deep inhale to feel
Your Heart Center to feel whatever capacity you have
for tenderness warmth kindness or love
for yourself for others for the world
letting your breathing return to normal
we're bringing it now to mind the world that you'll go back to
or enter into and you finish the meditation
and to wish that world well
appreciate how wonderful it would be wonderful it would be
if people were safe and happy
their lives could be peaceful safe free
unburdened with no oppression
and wishing that extending that
wishing that your life can contribute
to a better world may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
hello everyone and today we'll begin a new series five
part series and this week it'll be right effort
I gave the talk yesterday morning on this topic so some of this will be repeating it
and um but I've been appreciating lately quite a bit uh renewed
understanding of right effort that value greater appreciation for it
and uh the importance of it and uh there is a bit it's a right effort
the word effort for some of us at some point at least for me at one point was
probably something I didn't care for or worse because I interpreted effort as being uh somehow
a strain so you have to kind of apply more effort than it's needed if you're
making effort and um I'm a person who enjoys doing
kind of a lot of things I do physical work I enjoy doing and mental work I
enjoy doing and the doing of it I don't think of as effort the word or didn't used to the
word effort to me means you do it but then you do it with more more Force
and uh which causes a strain or being tired so I historically I didn't have a very
kind of much relationship to this um what's the sixth factor of the Eightfold Path
because of the word effort was being used um I value when one I heard a teacher
talk about right effort being right engagement then I had a better feeling
for it this is how you engage what you engage in and sometimes it's called a right
endeavor and that means uh that kind of interpret that to mean this is the right activity
so what's the right activity and it's my right effort has to do with mind what's
the right mental activity that we're involved in when we do meditation and these alternatives to effort uh
engagement endeavoring activity
they for me kind of protect me from straining or making forceful effort
but I'll use the word right effort and perhaps this series should go coming along with
a big you know warning that says warning these teachings
might cause over efforting so
um hopefully with that warning we you know we don't interpret it that way but there is something in this Buddha's
teachings on right effort that is uh
um you know very determined very clear like this is what we do
and that Clarity and that kind of uh emphatic nature of the teachings
um should be taken a little bit as we understand there's a intentionality a
resolve a even a commitment to staying present and I love the word commitment because
apparently it comes from the Latin root like the same as Mitten to hand or to
touch and so um to uh to touch something to stay in touch commitment is staying
in touch with your breathing to make that commitment to stay there with the experience
okay so uh in in the teachings of right effort there are four right efforts and
many years ago I heard that there was a meditation practitioner who heard these
teachings and came up with uh kind of an alternative or kind of came up with an example she said but you heard the
teaching oh um I kayak off in the in the open ocean in
Alaska and this is exactly how we had the effort we have to make when we're up there
and she then uh listed as you said when you're kayaking in the ocean and stay out of danger
if you're so that's the first effort so stay out of danger make the effort to stay out of danger
the second is if you're in danger get out of the danger
the second effort the third effort for a Kai actor and the kind of dangerous situations potentially
is learn good kayaking skills and the fourth effort is to maintain
them keep them going so in the Buddhist terminology
it's danger is unwholesome states of mind so unwholesome activities of the
mind that in and of themselves are afflictive and we don't always see it's
if they're afflictive because like for example resentment really hurts the
resenter probably more than the person were resentful towards but we don't see that because
we're so focused on the object of resentment in mindfulness practice we turn the
attention around 180 degrees and we start seeing feeling the cost oh this is
actually painful for me so the unwholesome is always hurting the person who has them but we all we don't
often know that and it's afflictive it's called so the
um so that's what the character called being in danger so avoid being in danger
avoid um unwholesome states of mind
the second is if unwholesome states of Mind arise
let go of them abandon their languages abandon them and I'll talk more about that tomorrow
and then the third uh the uh the skill part the
[Music] the learn skills evoke wholesome states of
mind and um and you know generosity and goodness and mindfulness and Equanimity
patience there's a whole slew of things that we can call upon and develop and strengthen the paramis the ten paramis
for example the the seven factors of Awakening and um and then so developed uh you know
bring them on evoke them learn those skills and then maintain them
but actually we'll see we talk about this fourth right effort it's more than
just maintain them it's to expand them grow them help them to
flourish within us and um so avoid
abandon evoke and and maintain
these are the four kind of Endeavors engagements activities we're doing with
the mind so it requires mindfulness it requires a mindfulness and and the
skill my mind mindfulness of really recognizing what's going on in the mind and the skill one of the wholesome
mental qualities the ability the wisdom to see the difference between mental
States activities thoughts that we have that are afflictive
to ourselves that are somehow undermine us or debilitate US and those which
benefit us and this includes being able to navigate
the strong lawyers in the mind or the strong uh
debate champions in the mine that have the ability to argue the case for why we
should be resentful the person deserves me to be resentful or to be angry or to be spiteful or to be greedy and to have
more of something that we can get kind of enamored in this
world of the unwholesome so we don't see and feel how detrimental it is to ourselves
and we might not know and people who don't know that there's a much better alternative in the wholesome side of it
all um including better ways to take care of ourselves and protect ourselves
will often feel like it's Justified or required to continue down the route of
the unwholesome and um but it's uh not required in fact
uh if we take so some people it takes a long time to appreciate how much they're
undermining themselves they're at a dead end that doesn't go anywhere um and um you know sometimes we have to
kind of redo the same unwholesome behavior many many times to finally
darling us this is not really working are not working well enough for not working in the way that's helpful
so uh the first one is to avoid
having unwholesome states of Mind arise and um and whether that you know so
agreed hate and delusion Envy conceit covetousness contempt cynicism
the you know they maybe insolence all kinds
of things that includes and um and to avoid so how do we avoid them
first uh as we become more mindful of ourselves what's happening really
staying in touch with ourselves then we start recognizing uh when we're in
unwholesome states of Mind are not present and so with this heightened sensitivity
to seeing when the stressful States arise so so then we you know then we can let
go of it which is a second but also we start recognizing
behavioral things that we do that might be the condition for these unwholesome
states to arise if someone's addicted to something on
the web certain kinds of you know drives
then maybe stay away from websites that support that addiction
otherwise you know it gets stronger and stronger get pulled into its vortex if if uh you know just something as
simple as if you walk down a street that has a lot of stores in it and then you start thinking about you know all the
things you want to buy and then you find yourself in a store or buying things and you tend to buy things too much then or
impulsively then maybe don't walk down that street if you know you have that tendency if they take the long way
around the block or something if there are certain people for whom you find yourself you know becoming
increased having increasingly unwholesome States arise when you're with that person then be very careful how you are with
that person maybe always show up well rested well fed well hydrated
um come show up in a good state of mind so you can kind of withstand the example or
the atmosphere of someone who is always angry and it gets you angry or something
and um or limit how much time you spend so you've noticed that if you spend half
an hour with the person an hour it's okay but more than that then you get grumpy and then once you're grumpy
things start going downhill so you know be careful monitor yourself at the input
what you do the behavior you have and make sure you get enough sleep be sure you get you know the basic
healthy things you do for yourself and exercise whatever it takes so that
you are protecting yourself from the arising of unwholesome states of mind
and uh might I say also one of those things is to meditate that meditation is a protective uh
means that meditating every day really can protect you from getting swept away
or cut up or even even um you know in unwholesome states of
mind so it takes it takes some this is so on
one hand there's mindfulness and then there's the right effort to avoid unwholesome States
to arise and that avoidance involves using your intelligence
it does involve thinking it out and planning and considering and reflecting how did how is it that these unwholesome
states arise in me and what behaviors what conditions what context does it does this happen and
what can I do to change my behavior to change how I live what I do to protect
it and um so a wise Dharma life is one that
actually reflects in a good healthy beneficial way the kind of behavior we're doing and
what behaviorally what can be changed if we're only relying on mindfulness without changing our Behavior we're
probably not giving ourselves the full opportunity of what this practice can do
so uh so you might over this next day
consider this first right effort the effort to avoid the
arising of unwholesome unskillful unbeneficial states of Mind activities
of mind and now see plan ahead now if you are
think about the rest of the day for a few minutes and what do you think would be a good way to go about your day
is to optimize that avoidance what are the contacts and conditions
that bring it about and what can you do what can you change behaviorally so for this day today there's less chance for
unwholesome States arise and it might be as simple as if you're going someplace
that you give yourself extra time to get there so there's a much less chance that you
feel hurried or angry at the traffic or whatever it
might be because the extra time built in that kind of ease and to the whole
Endeavor so giving yourself lots of time to do what you have to do
is one way to do this avoidance so thank you and uh
tomorrow we'll do the second factor of right effort thank you