there so so hello and welcome to this
edition of happy hour happy to be with you all and um
um i notice actually as i'm starting to to to speak and smile and try to smile and
speak it's a little hard to talk because i just had a feeling done earlier this
afternoon and part of my mouth is still numb so it um that's what's happening anyway
we'll see how much it impacts my my speech but um the vowels that the round vowels are
going to be hard anyway so um [Music]
so for today um [Music] i wanted to invite us
to this this new exploration i haven't quite taught it this way so i wanted to set the frame
so to set the frame i wanted to invite you to consider um you know there is this this game
uh that uh is played in um the context of maybe team building or
i've taught it in improv courses and i'm gonna describe it and then
i'm going to invite us to see well actually i'll just do it let me just
tell you what it is so so there is this game that's called a mirror where you get in front of another
human being physically and one person is a and the other person is person b
and for a while a leads with physical motions raising their arms maybe winking
and physical motions and b tries to follow b is the mirror tries to follow
really follow the lead of a okay got that can imagine yourself doing that
in the second part of the this game person b takes the lead
and moves their arms maybe their body their legs walks back and forth or whatever it
is movements and and person a is the mirror tries to follow all their try
to tries to mirror all their physical movements to follow them so now b is the lead and a is the
follower the mirror and then we often surprise people uh
with this third one which opens up your thinking open opens up this this
traditional way of thinking about being a leader or following in life
and the third part of this game is no one is a leader no one is a follower
and both are leaders both are followers so the idea is you learn you you get a
sense of how to become in sync no one really takes the lead otherwise
it really loses its edge but movements happen there's maybe little movement and the
other person continues it and the other person the person so so lead is kind of
handed back and forth and bad following is handed back and forth and so both
people are following and leading at the same time both entities okay
and if you've never done this game it can be mind-blowing how it works and how
it opens possibilities up actually and if you've done it now
hopefully you're you're remembering the joy the beauty of this of being in flow
with another human being and leading and following so
so with this i wanted to invite us
to consider the difficulties or the challenges in
our lives what if we were dancing we were dancing in the same way
with our challenges we weren't trying to to lead trying to
dominate trying to say okay challenge i'm going to put you in a box i'm gonna deal with you i'm gonna get rid of you
and we were not dominated we're not completely following the lead
of wherever difficulties and challenges took us but
what if we're actually in a dance we're gonna dance with life
we're when the dance with our challenges so the challenge leads a little bit
and then maybe we're following then we lead a little bit with oh this maybe this challenge actually is opening me up
to see in this way to move in this way and then maybe the challenge opens you up and moves you this way a little bit
and you move and then yeah you take the next league so it's a it's a dance it's a dance
and dance isn't a fist fight isn't an act of domination
but is what life is made of it's an infinite infinite game it's not a finite game
when there's a winner and there's a loser it's an infinite game of expression
so the title i want to give to this section to this practice that i'm offering is
dancing with grace and there are two meanings to this so what if
this dance you're doing this challenge isn't just that you're dancing with challenges
in your life what if challenges are actually expressions of grace
goodness in your life and through the stance you're being opened up to more grace to more goodness
to more wisdom to more compassion for yourself and for others
so dancing with grace so your partner is grace your partner is grace you're
dancing with grace you're dancing with grace
and the great and grace is also the challenges too it's both grace and challenge at the same time
and also dancing with grace another way that that in english that phrase
uh has a meaning is oh when you dance with grace there's a sense of um
move your movements your your actions there is a sense of
uprightness there's a sense of goodness that the whole dance the whole
being in the world so dancing with grace dancing with grace both of those
meanings so the invitation i'm going to make i'm making for our practice together in the
guided meditation as we're about to to do it together
uh of course after we settle in with our breath our bodies as always with our intention
is to see to see our challenges as grace as if
we're dancing with them is there a way that they're pointing and opening us to
goodness to to seeing things differently and maybe seeing this whole
dynamic as dancing with grace instead of oh poor me i have all these problems or
these challenges in my body and my mind and my life but seeing that you're dancing with grace dancing with grace
giving giving a much more dimensionality in this plane so
so enough of the framing let's practice together so
like to invite you to land in your meditation posture
you need to shift and move
arriving arriving in this body arriving this moment
connecting connecting with your feet on the earth
your sit bones on the cushion on the chair
hands on your lap the uprightness of your of your spine
[Music] sense of integrity of your posture
and then relaxing [Music] ah releasing
all the tension your forehead your back torso your chest
onto the earth each breath opening you up further
for possibility
openness to possibility in this moment
letting go releasing thoughts entanglements in this moment no need no
need if planned memories
stories arise
gently tell them thank you but not now please come back later
please come back later i'm giving my heart
all of myself to this practice in this moment
every breath in breath and out breath
just this breath in breath and out breath receiving receiving wholeheartedly
kindly letting each breath grace you
grace your whole body your abdomen
your lungs your whole being
the gift of goodness gift of life being received
this mystery of being human
being breathed in this form
letting your whole heart your body your mind
release let go with each out breathe
and you notice the beginning of the in-breath greet the beginning of the in-breath
the middle the end of the in-breath can you greet at all
middle of the in-breath mit the pause between the in-breath and the
upper beginning of the outbreath
the middle of the outbreak the end and the pause between the out breath and
the in-breath as if you're
dancing with the breath
this breath being a dance
you're not leaving
all the time you're not following all the time you're both leading and following
and the breath in the body this body knows how to breathe on its
own
it's also leading and following this body is its natural breath
breathing is a dance not too complicated
don't think about it you weren't thinking about this dance of
breathing until a moment ago let it be natural let it be joyous
as if it's where a partner dance
a delicate dance like the tango
with the breath
there be kindness the giving and the receiving
lightness
enjoying the movement the rhythm [Music]
delight of dancing with the breath
nothing more joyful than just dancing with the breath in this moment
all thoughts can wait they can wait not now
receiving giving
dancing with the breath with grace
as a practice for what comes next
maybe when challenges arise in the moment just remembering this
dance with the breath it's dancing [Music]
giving taking [Music] kindly
spaciously can help bring perspective
groundedness grace
grace to our dance with a challenge a difficulty perhaps
what if you imagine yourself
dancing with this partner
this challenge in your life dancing with grace
maybe a different attitude a shift in attitude is needed not to dislike your partner dance
partner not to try to dominate it not to be scared of it but to open your
arms hold their hand
as if in the partner dance
a sense of trust and let yourself be held
both leading and following
not so much thinking you don't have to think about solutions
but energetically shifting your relationship to this difficulty
an energetic shift you're dancing you're participating
you're leading in some moments and you're following in some moments
it's a dance
completely engaged in this dance
you're engaged wholeheartedly in this dance it challenges you it also nourishes you
there's some moves there's some areas in the dance floor you've never explored
ever and this partner leads you there
you don't have to know what they are [Music] but trust you follow
and oh [Music] you notice another corner and you lead
let's explore this do your challenge together
and the more you dance the more confident you feel
this is the worthy dance partner
challenges you helps you grow opens your heart
teaches you
but it's not always in the lead sometimes it follows
as you lead both leading and both following at the same time
passing the baton back and forth seamlessly
it's a graceful dance and again you don't have to put concepts
and words
it's just shifting a relationship
there's a sense of delight i get to dance i get to participate in
this dance maybe there's more zest
maybe as you're dancing in your mind your image
there's meta there is good will for yourself for the challenge for this
space between the two of you and this stands for
the space this dance floor of life
much wider than you thought it was much wider
much bigger more expensive keep dancing
keep dancing with grace
breathing in breathing out
and when your heart feels like this dance with
this partner feels complete in this moment maybe you bow to each other
or maybe another dance partner could be a challenge or could be gift
in your life a blessing
that leads you and you lead it you help it grow
it helps you grow the more you dance
the more full of vitality life grace kindness you become your heart
becomes
keep dancing with grace
in your mind's eye
whatever feels appropriate you can bow
to your dance partner maybe another dance partner or maybe you
simply sit and breathe
dance with the breath and feel into this shift in perspective
challenges with metta with kindness
spacious spaciously
you're still dancing maybe the dance floor keeps expanding
beyond your imagination wow so much potential possibility
gross
maybe the sand sludge has arisen or can derive is
through imagining this dance dancing with grace with challenges and difficulties
maybe there's a recognition of your own ability to dance
skills capacities goodnesses
that you're getting to recognize and have more confidence in
capacity to follow and lead lead and follow
into wisdom and love
unafraid fully present
who knew who knew i could dance so well
i can dance so well may all beings everywhere
discover their capacity to dance
more than they know with grace and may our dancing our practice
of cultivation serve all beings everywhere
goodness and awakening including ourselves
thank you all for your practice and for participating in this dance
exploring together
so we have a few minutes for any questions comments reflections
special reports from the field how was this for you
claire i do happen to see your hand i usually don't see people's hand there you go
you're still muted yeah i couldn't on unuse i was having some problems
anyhow um you may have noticed that i was smiling through the whole meditation
and this is because it's my favorite of anything you've ever done
my husband and i started dancing tango 12 years ago
and we dance every week and what you talked about speaks so much to
the practice of tango you know tango is sometimes referred to as dance as a meditation
um and it is very much tango people do not speak at all
the music directs what we do the man directs the woman through his
steps and when you finish you want to change partners you just say thank you
and that's the end of that partnership but it is such it's such a cool experience i really urge everybody here
to try it it's really wonderful it's the most beautiful dance you can ever do
and it does it does encourage meditation actually you don't talk at
all to each other you're just following the music so yeah you're so much in the space of
of leading and following yeah thank you claire thank you for bringing that in being a tango dancer yourself that is
sweet that's lovely yeah yeah appreciate that and uh and i do want to
point that that one difference between the dance of tango as you point as you uh mentioned and here in this meditation
it's obvious but i still want to note it is here we were imagining not
leading or following an entangle one person leads one person follows yes and here it is deleting and following
yeah exactly and here we're leading we're leading and following at the same time yeah thank you claire yeah
beautiful so lovely any other reflections that came up maybe
as you tried this on was there something about your perspective that maybe all of a sudden shifted with respect to
some challenge you're having in your life it was maybe not thinking so much but their
sense of wow yeah i can dance with this i can hold myself upright
madison uh can you hear me yeah
um i was at first confused by the idea of letting the
thing lead um i was working with like this character of my anxiety
that i have all the time with me and i was like this doesn't make sense i don't want to go down this trail that
they're trying to lead me but later in the meditation
when i imagined that like letting them lead it was like i'm not
afraid of you it's okay this is okay it just
i don't know it sort of helped me like not be afraid and and build trust
with it and like that created a lot of space so i just wanted to share that beautiful
thank you so much for sharing that medicine that's it exactly because in the dance right there's a sense of trust
right you know you're holding like okay i'm gonna hold your hand there's some and and there's a sense of trust and you
also have contro you know there's there's give and take so that's exactly it this shift in relationship exactly as
you said it beautiful thanks so much for sharing that that mates serve you mate support you
beautiful barbara
still muted my dear
ah still muted wait how can we help on mute you hold on
try again there we go there we go thank you i just want to thank you nikki this was
uh so different from other meditations other meta
practices and it was wonderful for me my mind went back over the over
40 years that i was married and times where my
husband was a lead and other times you know over all the years it just there was so much
things changed as you know causes and conditions and
health and you know different things that come up in life
and so just that's what came up for me was to run my
you know mind's eye through this sort of timeline of when i was leading and when
i was following and i think it was a valuable exercise thank you thanks for ever i appreciate
hearing the sense of or recognizing that actually you've been doing the dance of
both leading and following in your life in your relationship in your marriage
for 40 years did you say so leading and over 40 years leading and following well
yeah it's it's done now it passed away a few years ago
this was a a nice meditation to think back over
the thing that uh we did together and a sense of appreciation of of your and and
to bring it here in the present and here and now barbara's capacity to dance with
life lead and follow yeah yeah and that's a sense of confidence it
builds yeah wow look at that that's beautiful it's not always leading or always following
beautiful thanks for sharing the bourbon yeah beautiful [Music]
nice yeah any other reflections and you can also type them in chat if you type them
to me privately i won't read your name if you type them to everyone i'll read
your name and yeah anything else that might have come
up i'm saying oh this is interesting
and maybe what we'll do if i don't initially i think i see your hand there
um my challenge is very heavy but i noticed in the dance it got so
light nice and um
was could move around so i appreciate that thank you
thank you michelle that's fantastic yeah that's exactly that's the intention for this meditation it's to shift our
perspective from something that's heavy and unmovable it's like oh it's lighter
it moves and that that can create a
different perspective yeah different perspective of working with it beautiful thanks for sharing
them jerry says it seems that life is in fact a tense of change absolutely
absolutely so speaking of a dance of change we are
going to shift into small groups and practice together
this dance of life dancing together and um
i'll create the rooms and the invitation is each person will just share one nugget
one brief nugget maybe about this practice what came up for you or
maybe this this sense of dancing with life dancing challenges like really
speaking about that for your own sake really and be held witness so that this perspective this this sense can be
spoken for you and and really um and it can be about a challenge or it can be about something good or or again
by this meditation or in general and if it comes to you and you you want to say pass and just hold kind space for others
that's perfectly fine and so let's do alphabetical order
um first actually reverse alphabetical order just to shake it up a little bit
first name and one nugget next person one nugget next person one nugget again the first person one nugget
you go around around and remember you're just sharing from your own experience not asking questions directing leading
just offering yourself your kindness and it might be silence so
so ready opening the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other
figure that out next time anyway so any final reflections anything that came up
for you especially if you haven't spoken today or in a while
and i may not see your hand physical hand because there are only very few of you i see so
vicky oh you're still muted
yeah nikki i've been away um at different time than this time
but i just wanted to thank you for tonight because this is the first time i've ever really
been connected to what the breath is in meditation and it was just great
it was um a way to break down that breath to both leading
and following it was yay coming from a walk so i was
leading and following in the walk and it just matched exactly what i had been doing
yay that delights me to know and vicky that that lit up for you that really
the connection was really made oh yeah leading following yes
such a joy right such a joy and in the bread yeah
well meditating exactly such a joy with the breath like oh this is so good yay
it just it's an opening so thanks for sharing that that makes me happy to know and and clearly the sango members too my
sharing heart so it's great thanks so much for sharing that opening that you're
beautiful yay yeah so thank you all and thank you mary for
being part of the sangha thank you thanks to every single one of you for being part of the sangha whether live on
youtube listening to audiodharma later thank you for your practice and your cultivation may all beings be happy may
all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone be well