so good day everyone and
the topic these days this week is we could call it just pleasure
but it's pleasure and and this pleasure doesn't quite work as
the opposite the pleasure and pain play so we say pleasant and unpleasant
but for this meditation i'd like to focus a bit on pleasure
there is the wise use of pleasure in meditation and not just as there is the wise the
growth of wisdom in regard to both pleasure and pain the pleasant and the unpleasant
but for now let's do the wisdom of pleasure in meditation
that let's assume that you will not become attached to
pleasure assume that you're not won't be chasing after pleasure or holding on clinging to the pleasure that
might be there let's uh start with the idea that
with a very relaxed open-handed way open-minded way
we appreciate the pleasure that's here as part of meditation
and particularly those forms of meditative pleasure that
make it easier for the mind to be present i think the mind is happier being
present for things which are pleasant than unpleasant and so if we can find things that are
pleasant in the meditation that's part of the meditation
that support the mind enthusiasm for being present
then it'll show up more in this present moment so as we're meditating i'll guide your a
little bit to experience pleasure and and i know that
some of you will have already have physical discomfort you're dealing with physical pains
and i'm not trying to say that you won't have those or it's wrong to have those
but it might be that even with the presence of those you can loosen up a little bit the focus
on them or concern with them just a little just enough so that you could also take in
that which is pleasant so you could also take in
to
so taking a
alert meditation posture
and if there's already some pleasure just in the posture which can be the case for people who
have been meditating for long enough that there's a kind of a visceral memory of the
goodness of the posture allow yourself to feel
the pleasure of the posture
and then gently maybe very gently so it's kind of
enjoyable take some deeper breaths just deep enough that it remains
enjoyable
and is there a way that you can exhale that you enjoy as well maybe almost as if uh the enjoyment of
ah as you exhale
and the joy of an inhale which is like a fresh breath of air filling in
the lungs it's almost like you're smelling the freshness and taking a delightful inhale
and a relaxing exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and if you can now as you exhale
relax different parts of the body but if you can notice
any pleasantness or pleasure that comes with relaxation with a relief
maybe beginning with the muscles of the face
releasing around the eyes
releasing around the cheeks and the jaws
releasing the shoulders
softening the shoulders
softening and relaxing in the belly
and is there some way you can relax the whole body releasing any ways in which you're
bracing yourself against life
and appreciating the way that there is some pleasure
enjoyment in any degree of relaxation or calm there is in the body
and then letting the attention settle on the body breathing
familiarizing yourself with the experience of the body breathing
what moves in the body as you breathe what expands and contracts
what sensations are activated and appear and disappear
and then as you experience your breathing is there any pleasure
pleasantness in any of the sensations of breathing
maybe the pleasure is more on the inhale maybe it's more on the exhale
maybe it's the in the release of the chest as you exhale or the belly
maybe it's the speed and flow of the inhale
allow yourself to feel any pleasure
that's present in breathing even if some of the breathing is uncomfortable
is there any part of it that is pleasant
maybe the air going in down through the nostrils
maybe the subtle expansion and contraction of the back ribcage
if there's a gap between the exhale and inhale maybe the pleasure is in that pause
and if there are very simple ways you can adjust your breathing
adjusting it so it still feels like a natural breath
maybe adjusting by slowing the breathing down or a little bit faster
relaxing the belly and more breath belly breathing
maybe a momentary pause at the end of the exhale
where all things become still and peaceful
and if there's any pleasure in the breathing
be sure to feel that each time it appears stay close to the pleasure of breathing
let the thinking mind become quieter so that you can better register the
pleasantness the pleasure register it with your body
let the mind be pulled into the pleasure of breathing
pulled into whatever meditative pleasure that's occurring for you
gently allow yourself to be filled by it
awareness to be filled let it be a support
for present moment mindfulness
letting there be the kind of stillness that highlights the pleasure of
meditation
and let the pleasure of meditation
be a support for staying present
feeling whatever there is to enjoy about being physically present in your
meditation any pleasure pleasant sensations in your
body breathing
if you're more settled and calm in your body
maybe that is pleasant enjoyable
you breathe breathe with a pleasure breathe in and out with the enjoyment of
sitting here and see if there's something you can learn
about letting go by resting in the enjoyment of the
moment
and then it as we come to the end of the sitting
to whatever degree of enjoyment there is for you pleasure pleasantness
how might that
inspire you to wish pleasure enjoyment to others
that they can go through the world experiencing
well-being peace pleasure
delight happiness
maybe your own enjoyment can be something you wish others to
experience as well wouldn't it be great if everyone
could enjoy this life we would probably care for each other
more
may all beings be free of their afflictions and their
pains their sorrows may all beings
feel the pleasure and joy and happiness of life
may they be happy may all beings be safe
so they can enjoy this life
may all beings be peaceful
so the simple pleasures of a life are available
may all beings be free so they can live a life
that they enjoy and value and delight in
so we can live a life will we also delight and enjoy
caring for each other may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so
so there's this amazing quote from the
buddha after he spent his time doing ascetic practices
he went back to meditating in a way that he knew from earlier earlier in his life
where he experienced meditative joy and he said to himself that there's no
reason to be afraid of this kind of joy this kind of pleasure
and so the idea that there is joys and pleasures that we can experience that we
don't be afraid of or be hesitant to feel that actually our important part of
the practice the buddha went on to say that what he was discovering then in that pleasure and the joy
of meditation was he said this is the way to awakening this is the way to freedom
and so there is a path that opens up with
pleasure and delight joy in practice and how to find that and use that wisely
is one of the tasks that we're doing in meditation meditation is not supposed to be an
endless series of grim pains i've known people who have sat with a
lot of physical pain in meditation as i have and benefited a lot from doing so
i've known people who said with a lot of pain and discomfort meditation and have not
benefited from it or have benefited for a while but after a while it just it just
becomes grueling it goes on and on and some people will end up sitting with
unnecessary pain because they think they're supposed to sit in a cross-legged meditation posture
and they move to a chair and immediately they feel so much better and now they're able to kind of give
themselves over to the present moment rather than struggling with the pain of practice
but we don't want to only avoid pain and discomfort and we don't want to only pursue
pleasure and delight and the pleasant because the chances are
when we stay close to our attachments the idea is to become free
and the idea is to engage in the world of pleasure and pain in a way that is freeing for us and that
requires some wisdom like how do i find my freedom here one of my favorite quotes is the idea
that if you're only free when you when things are pleasant
you're not really free if you're only free when you're comfortable you're not really free
you need to become free in this practice when things are uncomfortable when there's also when there's pain
but uh but we don't want to it's not supposed to be stoic and we're not like just putting up with pain pain pain it's not
supposed to be all difficult there is a art to opening up to pleasure
and all that but part of that art is to really understand our relationship to pleasure
and pain i think that without putting in putting a spotlight
magnifying glass to really study what our reactivity is what our beliefs
are attitudes are towards pleasure and pain we probably won't find a wise way of
being with pleasure and pain rather we'll just kind of be driven by
maybe the lack of wisdom we have or the attachments we have or the unhealthy beliefs that are weighing
us down so to spend some time looking and seeing what do we believe
so some people believe that life is only successful if there's pleasure as soon as there's
pain or discomfort or emotional discomfort or mental discomfort it's a sign that somehow we
failed some we're not living up to that standard of a successful human being is
has um you know is wealthy and has is filled with the
joy and pleasure and and is able to navigate the life everything perfectly and fine and drifts
on a cloud and and if we can't do that then there must be something deeply wrong about who we are
but this uh this is just a delusion to believe something like that
every human life will have its share of pains and pleasure
both of them come with being human being and and so rather than having a belief that
has to be one way in the dharma we believe that we're practicing with whatever
comes our way and finding a wise way through it not trying to avoid it and not trying to
hold ourselves to some high standard of perfection and um
so um sometimes people who feel discomfort or pain
uh will be angry at it uh hostile even to their pain into themselves
some people get restless some people get bored very quickly some people
have a lot of ideas about who they are that they're trying to live up to or trying to avoid
and they get triggered sometimes by the by experiences of pleasure and pain um you know the ones that i'm the victim
it's happening to me and all this discomforts me me me so i'm the one who's so much of
it all about me and there's a way in which we all the discomfort discomfort of life gets drawn into our
identity or idea of who we are the idea of my history and my
and it's not necessarily wrong exactly that there's a lot of challenges in life
but that it's a magnet all the things that are difficult to the concept of me myself as the victim as the person who's
experiencing it the experiencer is
uh just makes things so much more difficult one of the exercises we do around pain
is um is to feel i mean you might try this right now if
you want just close your eyes and and see if you can look around in your body for some place where there's some
discomfort and um and probably the within reason the more
uncomfortable it is the more better for this exercise and then um
just in your mind and tell yourself that this is my pleasure my pain my pain is
this way um you know my pain is my knee my pain
is in my ankle my pain and just keep out of the word my
or i'm having pain i'm having pain and then take a deep breath and letting
go and then be aware of the pain or discomfort
and just call it pain or discomfort without the me or the eye
and perhaps there's a difference between these two ways
i don't know if in youtube like this we can i can convey this adequately but the um
but so it's not uncommon for people to start realizing after a while that if they let
this comfort just be discomfort without the pronouns or the i or me or
mine as part of it that uh probably some micro muscles around the pain don't contract
some of the micro emotions don't contract and get tight that the me myself and mine kind of
brings along a lot of extra baggage and to keep it so simple just pain just
pleasure and then when pain does arise also
then uh there's attitude towards them of being for against there's intentions there's agendas there's
strategies we have about how to and one of them is to get rid of it if there's pain
if there's pleasure some people don't feel safe with pleasure there's reasons why some people feel
distrustful of pleasure and it's going to go away or i've been burnt before
or i'll get attached if there's too much pleasure or something
and and so
what is the intention you have what's the attitude or the reaction to pleasure and
pain and one of the remarkable things that's possible to learn
is to have equanimity towards pleasure and pain to be able to turn towards it
with mindfulness and look upon it just as you would look upon
maybe if you saw a bird maybe you can't identify the bird even but it's high up
in the sky the blue sky just moving through the sky and has a certain grace to it perhaps or
whatever you look up and you see it and and that
that bird high in the sky you don't take it to be my bird uh don't take it to be
you know that bird is probably flying you know not not flapping its wings uh just quite right it should probably
be soaring a little bit differently and you know someone needs to give it to flying instructions
and or i'm gonna tell i'm gonna try to explain to it what it needs to do we don't get involved we're trying to fix it we don't
associate it with ourselves it's just a bird flying in the sky so there's a lot of equanimity just like letting it be
in the same way you'd watch a bird fly through the sky without appropriating it in any way or
needing to do something about it so it's possible to um
to have that kind of equanimity towards pleasure and pain
and um and that's one of the these are this is a very important part of the training in
vipassana is to learn that kind of equanimity but it's not a
training than to be stoic with all pain and to be uninterested in all pleasure
the we want to be there's there's a appropriate interest both in pleasure and pain some pains we learn from
um we learn how to take care of ourselves better by paying attention to the pain and adjusting things
but pleasure um uh the pleasures of relaxation the pleasures of that uh just being
the pleasures that arise from meditation itself are a um
it's like a someone who's saying hey come here come closer
this is the way follow me there's a way in which meditative joy and pleasure
is a support for the practice and it's support for opening up
letting go and relaxing more fully rather than holding on to the pleasure
it is to kind of open to it feel it more so that there's a settling and opening
into the present moment and a deepening connection so the mind gets quieter and stiller
so there are so becoming wise about pleasure and pain
helps us then become also wise about pleasure wisdom about both is really helpful but
for meditation both are helpful and sooner or later in meditation you'll sit with pain sooner or later you'll see
it with pleasure and and for most of us it's sooner rather than
later and so rather than so this is part of the field of the four foundations for
awareness is to use the pleasure and pain of our experience
as a support as a as a foundation for learning to be aware
so pleasure and pain is not to be turned away from or grabbed onto but we're developing a
heightened awareness with this pleasure and pain which is part of all
experiences and as we do that we'll
start making this remarkable transition
from uh we'll talk about this tomorrow from the worldly dimension of pleasure
and pain to the spiritual dimension of it and
and that distinction i'll talk about more in detail tomorrow what that means and how it works
this is part of the four foundations of mindfulness is to make this distinction and to be able to appreciate the
difference between these two forms of pleasure and pain the worldly pleasures and pain and the spiritual ones
so that's for tomorrow and so for today i hope that you will uh try to discover
some more equanimity and spaciousness with pleasure and pain
and you might try freeing yourselves from appropriating
pleasures and pains as part of me myself and mine just pleasure just pain
and you're allowed to experience both and be at ease with both
so thank you very much and it's a pleasure to be with you this way
thank you