here we go okay so hello and welcome everyone
to happy hour lovely to be with you
so so for today's practice i'd like to invite us
to hold both the sorrows and the joys of the world
it is said that the word there are ten thousand joys and ten thousand sorrows
and at times when [Music] it seems like the um
political landscape or the the world landscape and
the geopolitical landscape is so dire our minds turn to what is
painful what is difficult all the suffering in the world and the people
yes there is a lot of suffering in the world right now that we hold with care with compassion we turn towards we don't
turn away and in order to support being able to turn more towards
difficulty sadness with compassion it is
helpful to resource ourselves our hearts with gratitude for what is good
in the world in our in our lives for the people we care about and love
in order to resource ourselves so that challenges pain difficulty sorrow
grief it is not the measure
of all our waking hours it can be so difficult and draining and and
not helpful not helpful for anyone if we are not resourced to be able to hold and
hold witness and support and do what we can in the world so
if we are unsettled if we are
toppled over um it doesn't help anyone it doesn't help us it doesn't help our loved ones and
anyone in the world so it is helpful to have that sense of balance and this past week we've practiced with
equanimity we've practiced with equanimity and compassion we practice with stability and compassion just
different ways to bring stability to our practice of compassion and and tonight i'd like to extend that
and actually invite us to to dare to have the courage
to practice gratitude and joy in order to balance in order to support
the the compassion the pain the difficulty in the world it's not about turning away
it's not about la de da i'm just going to be happy and pollyanna that's not the idea
you know this i know you know this but i'll still like to say it that it's not about turning it
it's skillfully using skillful means
to be balanced to be resourced to be filled with stability gladness choice so that we can
contain so that we're available for more compassion in the world so that we don't
have what's called empathy fatigue or empathy distress and pathetic distress so
so that's the invitation to engage with gratitude with joy tonight
and not feel guilty or bad that um
[Music] there are people suffering in the world yes and there's also joy in the world and
it's okay it's okay to honor both it's okay in our humanity to embrace both to
honor both so
not turning away from either honoring both appreciating both
really shifting the perspective the perspective really an awakened perspective that
allows both joy and sorrows all of that to be just as it is
just as it is without toppling over so so in this practice tonight it's an
invitation to shift to shift our perspective to shift our perspective
um in that way so so
let's enter our meditation posture and practice together and whatever you need
i'll share with you in the guided meditation so if you need to sit
shift lie down even stand see what your body needs in
this moment and perhaps
if you feel comfortable closing your eyes in this moment turning your gaze inward
letting go releasing
releasing releasing [Music] what's not helpful in this moment
thoughts worries preoccupations
and giving our heart giving our heart our awareness
fully heartfully
to the inner world for a moment just settle just to settle and arrive
feeling our feet on the floor stable grounded
the bottom of our feet okay well rooted tree
releasing into our legs ah
the upper legs lower legs and feet let them be grounded
let them be heavy
enjoying the sensations of the legs of the feet
not a privilege to be taken for granted
hmm feeling the sensations of the sit bones
your bottom and the cushion or the chair contact points
releasing releasing the weight of your upper body
into your sit bones
if there's any tension the upper body neck shoulders
your forehead jaw
chest abdomen let them be released
smilingly released
allowing the breath to move freely through the body
this life-giving breath like a lullaby like a lullaby
calming soothing [Music] each and breath
every out breath
there there there there
and as thoughts arise as they will arise it's okay
simply noticing when a thought has arisen and smilingly thanking
thank you and not now please come back later right now i'm giving myself my heart
wholeheartedly to this practice taking refuge
in this moment
no need for criticism or judgment just releasing smilingly
ah and letting there be a sense of appreciation
for this breath this in-breath this
breath releasing relaxing the body
maybe there's an area of the body that feels good
content peaceful warm stable relaxed any of those qualities
let yourself enjoy
maybe there's an area that feels like a warm sunny day maybe your hands
maybe your cheeks your feet
or your breath in the abdomen
the simple blessing of the warm sunny day the sun
felt in your body
maybe in your heart heart center
let there be enjoyment let yourself relish
let your heart be full of this goodness open up to it
if any hesitation or fear i say thank you thank you dear protective qualities
emotions not needed right now this is safe
it's trustworthy in this moment
let your body be nourished in your heart
appreciate the goodness the simplicity of just sitting and being breathed
sensations of this body the stillness
the groundedness the spaciousness within
[Music] the heart center as if your breath is expanding inside
do not shy away from tasting how delicious it might be
to just sit and be breathed
if you've ever seen a butterfly in the sun
opening closing its wing rhythmically
warming itself the grace the beauty
the colorfulness of the wings of emotion
your breath too
this beautiful rhythmic warming
of your wings in the sun of your beautiful wings in the sun
wings of awareness
riding on the breath
let there be this inner nourishment with the breath
enjoying what's comfortable what's beautiful inside
maybe it's the joy of the mind being quiet and still deliciously for a few
breaths picking refuge
in silence and peace
simple gratitude for this breath
now for this breath and then again for this breath see what
happens if you keep being grateful for each breath
each new breath see what happens when it builds up
can there be gratitude appreciation
for knowing for awareness this amazing
indescribable ability to know
to be aware of sensations of thoughts of the breath
of sound this amazing miracle
miracle that we all have or privy to
have the privilege of which we can't turn off can turn on
it just is can there be sense of appreciation or
awe gratitude for the gift of knowing
describable in being human
feeling the gift of feeling sensing knowing
can there be a sense of appreciation for the sangha supporting you
practicing together with others
the goodness the goodness of this web invisible web of humanity
supporting us
the people we know people we don't
coming together
we wouldn't be here if it weren't for others support and participation
letting the goodness of that in
is there something that you're grateful for today maybe in this moment or today or this past week
let your heart open and appreciate daily relish
as if you're polishing a sacred stone stay with it stay with this appreciation
let it bring a smile to your face
and ease to your heart gladness joy to your heart
let your heart feel expansive in gratitude and joy
for this blessing
can you be glad for your own gladness for your own good fortune
can you be glad for your own gladness
can you be glad for this blessing in your life for yourself as if you're stepping out of yourself
feel afraid to bring [Music] to mind another blessing maybe someone in your life maybe a
friendship or family member or a gift of some kind
another one if you wish or you can stay with this one whatever
expands your heart enjoy and gladness
staying embodied feeling your body the breath the groundedness of the feet
the hands
while allowing your heart to feel expansive
and relishing goodness gratitude and blessings
for the last minutes of this practice period
letting our hearts be expansive
as we can contain more joy we have more space
to meet with compassion sorrow and grief in the world
so offering the gift of our joy to ourselves to the world as a blessing
as an empowerment to support us to serve others
deeply bowing in our hearts with gratitude for the blessings
for the joys and allowing there to be alignment
to serve the best way we can
serve others in their joy and their sorrows
may all beings everywhere be safe
happy healthy heaves
may all beings everywhere have joy
including ourselves may they be free
thank you for your practice everyone
[Music] i hope there are at least a few
mind moments of joy of gladness
of expansiveness of stability or maybe even a smile or two showed up
on your face i hope so i like to open the space for any
reflections you like to share as a gift to others
maybe an aha moment something that opened up for something that was challenging that's okay too of course
especially if you haven't spoken for a while or shared please feel free to raise your zoom hand
if it's your physical hand i won't see you you can raise your zoom hand you can
type in chat it's typed to everyone i can um
i will read your name if it's typed just to me privately it's only your
reflection charles the please oh thank you
hi everybody can you hear me yes yep okay great
great yeah just uh uh the the phrase being breathed really
uh really opened opened things up for me
i'm just really and i don't have words for it but uh
but just uh it just felt so caring and so like it was being
held i don't know held by the air
held by the atmosphere just really beautiful so thank you
thank you charlie i am so moved by your sharing by your report
um [Music] yeah the way you felt held and carried
is really permeating resonating through the peace
of your words of the space you're in and that carries me into it more deeply so thank you for
that beautiful thank you for your practice jersey yeah
beautiful ah fazel says thank you very much it was
perfect after a long stressful day a reset to a mindset of gratitude ah thank
you faso thank you for those words
and larry says you led me into my clenched heart and allowed me to play around in there oh
thank you larry for being led into your clenched heart and playing around there like a
butterfly spreading your wings thank you all for your practice so
beautiful and you're sharing too and the other reflections
questions comments complaints before we turn into uh
holding each other deborah says thank you for helping me notice all the many wonderful
people and moments in the day ah thank you deborah i am touched
with that reflection all the wonderful people and moments so many of them it's amazing being human
even if there are sufferings challenges pain difficulties still there's just this
blessing this blessing there's so much blessing even in the midst of
challenges so thank you for your practice everyone
so if there are no more reflections i'd like to invite us to share
in small groups and sharing our joy sharing our gratitude it's actually such a beautiful
practice so the invitation tonight is after about 15 seconds of silent meta
for ourselves for others is to um
around go around round and round and round so the first person shares
something they're grateful for something in their life maybe in the moment maybe it's just as simple as
ah i had a moment to sit and be breathed tonight and then the next person shares
a nugget something they're grateful for and then the next person shares a nugget so this way
it's we go around round round robin so the one person sharing a monologue it's more sharing in
nugget and this format is called the spiral because we keep going around and increasing joy and
it's so nourishing to hold each other people's joy just hearing what they're
grateful for it brings us joy notice that the medita the the vicarious joy
that can come up it's it's so nourishing can be so lovely
so so i'm creating the rooms
and um yeah take care of yourselves
take care of take care of each other and
yeah let's uh i'm going to open the room stay take care here we go
and the rooms are closed everybody is back welcome back everyone i see folks
smiling this is sweet so um we have a couple of minutes for
any reflection so what happened what did you notice especially those who are smiling we'd
love to hear from you
yes person who's on the phone please
michael is that michael oops
uh you're there now you're unmuted okay now i'm unmuted pardon me apologies
i am so grateful for the prompt and the teaching this evening i think this was really rich and i i'd love to be able to
do it like once a week the prom of going
uh and around robin for things that we're grateful for bring us joy
what was that like for you tonight in the round robin michael
uplifting yeah watered my happiness seeds oh
oh that's so sweet watered my happiness seeds i love that oh that's so sweet
thank you for that like i love it what did my happiness seem oh may your happiness seeds always be watered this
is so great i love that well maybe since you requested maybe i will bring in more joy maybe once a week maybe we will do
joy for a while it's kind of fun right you can't have enough joy and gratitude
thanks for that request michael fazel says we laughed a lot oh that's great that's very sweet that makes me
happy any other reflections if you want one other reflection anybody wants to share
catherine says the things other people shared prompted me to think of other things i am grateful for oh that is
great oh that isn't that awesome oh that's so fantastic
um peggy says grateful for my little group that so reminds me of the prevalence of
good kind people in the world oh that's sweet tess says my heart felt full
ah yeah that's great yeah
so oh yes and i see neil neil you get to have the last word my dear
i i just want to say i am just so grateful for you know for you nikki for diana these classes and the sangha
you know it is such a big part of my life and and yeah
oh thank you neil and and we feel grateful for you
all of you and and since you spoke i'll make you personal especially you because you offer so much support to the sangha as
as a regular member i see people are nodding appreciating you and and you help support the the mailing list not to
make you blush right now but if you're blushing it's okay please take in the appreciation and the goodness from
from me and diane from and the whole sangha and so thank you neil and also for that beautiful reflection yeah
yeah and thank you all katrin says echoing neil yeah and thank you neil
exactly thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for your beautiful practice for showing up for supporting
yourselves each other um us just it's such a mutual goodness
co-created in the world happy hour it makes me happy every time so thank you deep gratitude
uh to all all of you in all the causes conditions may we all be happy
joyous and free and all beings everywhere as well
[Music]
thank you all thank you