and good morning everyone and
i'm uh warmed by
your greetings on the chat thank you so
today this week we're doing the final of the
exercises
the discourse on establishing awareness ways of
establishing awareness and the last exercise is
one of the most famous of the teachings of the buddha
the noble truths the four noble truths four truths
so for the meditation today the entry point to the four noble truths the
really deep one of course is our suffering and i'll talk more about that later
but the way to experience suffering the way to experience life weight experience
is to be able to observe it
and observe its changing nature not to hold on to anything
not to get fixated in our mind with thoughts ideas judgments fears about how
things are but to be able to be quiet and still
observing the change changing nature of phenomenon
and for those of us who meditate
doing especially sitting meditation or any kind of meditation where we're stationary
it's possible to use the stillness that's here to highlight the change in fact that's
one of the values of sitting quietly
is that we establish some modicum of stillness and then we see
what is not still for someone maybe who has
led a busy life caught up in activities that
they they might be surprised to sit down and be still
to realize how much agitation there is in their mind and their hearts and their body how much of spinning and momentum
there is going on and on and on
and and then as we get quieter as things
settle down we're moving towards greater stillness not frozen
not holding ourselves still but the kind of delightful stillness of when the wind
quiets down or the waves on the ocean
or the lake become still and quiet you can see into the bottom of the lake
so this delightful stillness soft gentle malleable pliable
that highlights things it's kind of like the fog has cleared and now we can see
clearly and the more still our system becomes
the more we can observe that things are changing in more and more subtle ways
eventually we become aware of how thinking changes all the time
our preoccupation with our thoughts or ideas might mask that escalate thoughts come
and go there the dime a dozen maybe even cheaper
that uh you know and i'm a diamond million they're just they they come on and on
and on and but the moment each one might seem important but they're just another one in the endless cycle of thoughts
that come and they go and at some point we've we've gotten still enough and
observed thinking enough that we're no longer caught in its grip no longer
seduced by its authority like this thought so important
and there can be a disengagement maybe even a disenchantment with this endless cycles
of thinking and we're finally willing to step back settle back into that still place
where we just see the thoughts are changing all the time
and we find a refuge in that awareness which is not caught in
thought which is not not involved in discursive thinking
so to settle back be still to highlight what is changing
so begin by assuming a posture meditation
posture that allows you to keep your body
somewhat still
stiller quieter than how you usually usually are an activity of life
some of us our eyes are very active looking searching
and to let your eyes rest by lowering them 45 degrees to the floor
so the eyes begin to be quiet still
not looking at anything in particular loose open focus
and then to
gently close your eyes if that's comfortable
taking a few long slow deep breaths and exhale deeply
into the stillness of the body maybe a stillness that feels deep
within him
and then letting your breathing return to normal
with whatever degree of stillness of the body you have
a global awareness of your body notice if there's any tensions in your body
tightness contracted muscles
and if there is as you exhale
relax and let go
letting go into the stillness of the body
the stillness that maybe feels soft
and appreciating whatever degree of stillness there is in your body
remembering that
remembering that the stillness will highlight movement
not to worry about the movements of your body
but appreciate the way movement and stillness can
highlight each other
and one of those movements is the movement of breathing in the body
as you exhale gently quiet your mind
let your mind also move to a stillness
becoming stiller
if it's if it is comfortable to do so
see if you can breathe in a restful way
maybe you find that by
resting for an instant at the end of the exhale
and allowing a restful inhale to begin
some forms of stillness involved
involves holding on holding on tight clenching tightening
resisting
if there is such a stillness in you let that be massaged by
what is moving and changing maybe with the breathing
movements of the body as it breathes massages
clinging holding on tightness
as you move to a deeper soft
comfortable stillness
in meditation one of the things that begins to stand
out and highlight is where we're stuck
where awareness thinking is stuck on things where we're attached holding on
resisting and it's a kind of stillness
which is debilitating which is draining
to see that more clearly holding on
is part of the function of meditation it's not a mistake
but it allows us to then breathe with it to observe it
from a quiet place until we see
that even the ways we hold on and freeze
are part of the changing world
and we relax and just let everything change let everything flow by
flow through us
settling back in the knowing that all things change
sooner or later
observing watching being in the place that knows change
the stillness
and then we come to the end of the sitting
and we know that there are many kinds of love
some loves are agitated with desire and wanting
longing and some loves are
content settled at ease a gentle warmth that needs nothing
but cares for everything
a warmth a tenderness a gentleness
a kindness that maybe is associated that place
within which is delightfully still
quiet
the place that is free of wanting and aversion
that contented love or care kindness
it's very simple ideally we would realize it's ordinary
but more often the active love the wanting love the doing love
eclipses this quieter softer and sometimes powerful kind of love that
flows from stillness
and may it be that our ability to become quiet and still
calm and settled
our ability to see more clearly may all this support our ability to gaze
upon the world kindly
caringly
inspired that our practice
motivates us to live and act for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so for this week the topic is the buddha's noble truths the four
truths and these
are uh often seen as the
pinnacle of
the insights the core insight of the dharma
excuse me
and now the way they're worded is that one understands one knows
dukkha as it as it really is
one knows the arising of dukkha as it really is
one knows the cessation of dukkha as it really is and one knows
the practice leading to the cessation of ducam
and um these are uh the insight that these represent
are not one two three four insights that are separate like first you know one then the other than the other
the way the tradition offers them uh the ancient tradition is that these all happen together in an inst in an instant
they um they somehow uh uh there's a maybe you can see the singular
understanding singular insight that that then can be
kind of explained or
parsed out in these four different ways and sometimes it said that this occurs
like lightning just boom there wow now i understand something
some people find it very inspiring that this is one of the central
teachings of the buddha that the emphasis is on suffering some people find finally someone's talking
about suffering and stopping and taking good luck and willing to address it directly
rather than covering it over ignoring it or something
but it's not just a teaching it is an insight it's meant to be something to experience deeply for
oneself and and that might be not see seems so
interesting when you to experience duke god intimately and fully so that we could
know it's a rising is ceasing in the way to its ending
the and what we're seeing here is uh well
these four noble truths down through the centuries have been explained many ways it seems like
they're a wonderful template for all kinds of teachings and
and all kinds of ways of perceiving or understanding our our human life and that's part of the part of the
richness of them is their adaptability and uh and um and so we find if you you
probably just you find modern books in english on the four noble truths um people who talk about them and start
comparing how they say it with how they explain it and you see very quickly that
people have little different different nuances and different ways of teaching it thereby buddhists will teach it
differently than zen buddhists and buddhists differently tibetan buddhists more traditional
tarabad and buddhists from thailand might teach differently than than
teachers in the west and you see this there it's it's changeable malleable and i kind of trust
that everyone is speaking from some idea or some experience of what is most helpful for
them and then they present it that way the
the in this ancient buddhist tradition
or say this way there are two primary interpretations or understanding of the four noble truths that i think are the
most useful one is that it talks about the cause of suffering
their suffering the cause of suffering the cessation of suffering and the way
the other is that it's uh it's knowing there
has to do with the changing impermanent inconstant nature of dukkha suffering
and so we see it arise we see it cease and we see it cease in a definitive way
in such an important way that something shifts and change there's a deep kind of change in the psyche in
seeing the whole world of dukkha somehow crumble down somehow dissolve
drop away temporarily and then we know something that
is very powerful some people in the ancient world felt that the buddhist path only begins
when there's been this deep insight into deep enough insight into
the four noble truths then when now one really knows what the path is about
because one has the personal experience of where it's going albeit a temporary experience but no one
knows and so now now we can oh now i'm on the course now i know the practice leads someplace it leads to this
this cessation of of dukkha of suffering so both of these seeing the cause seeing
the inconstant nature of it are quite powerful for people and so i'll talk a little bit about both
of them this week and but today i want to say a little
more or say something about the first noble truth and the first one is
understanding as it really is and what is dukkha
it's often we say suffering in english some people find that troublesome because
they only use the word suffering for huge traumas huge
catastrophizing difficulties
in the buddhist term uh the the um the literal meaning of dukkha is pain
and and sometimes it's a lot easier to understand what buddhists are talking about it if we understand be pain or
painful so for example the classic description
of what dukkha is in the first noble truth is that
birth is painful it's an adjective the reducer so birth is painful
sickness is is painful aging is painful death is painful
um uh associating with what is uh
uh unloved unlovable uh associating with what is not liked
is painful associating with what we love uh not being able to social what we love
is painful not getting what we want is painful in short
clinging clinging to the aggregates that we've talked about some weeks ago is painful
so here's a statement about all these things are painful it's not saying that it's always painful
um but uh they're so so commonly painful that i think most people if you say birth is
painful um most mothers will say yeah it was painful but that's not all it was
some people die and it's not necessarily painful to die but
but to say it's painful seems like oh yeah that's often the case or there's something painful about it
aging doesn't have to be painful but i think most people who get started getting older will discover that there's
pain involved with getting older and this very human thing of being with
what is uh we don't like being with something that is unpleasant
is painful and being with what we love and what we are close to
not being able to be close to it not being with our loved ones can be painful
and and so it's just naming a series of things
that in this human condition i think what they're trying to do is to lay out the full range of where
people experience pain emotional pain oh there's one more i didn't list
anguish lamentation pain depression despair is painful
all these things are painful so if that's all we do is to name it
then it's depressing then we can have anguish lamentation pain depression and
distress despair but
this is an honest a look at an appreciation and recognition that
this is part of the human condition and it's there's something about this
that is not that is optional it's not necessary to be caught in this in some aspect of
this pain and there's some way of freedom stepping outside of the
outside of the game of what is pain and painful there is an alternative
and that alternative involves seeing the changing nature
the inconstancy of this pain and now in constancy that it means it comes
and goes maybe it is not good news it means it's going to come back but what it does it allows us to some
point for the mind to find a place of letting go someplace where it's not
part of the game not part of the cycles of pain and
that keeps appearing and appearing it finds a place of rest or freedom or
openness or expansiveness or some other game in town
that changes the whole perspective because what this four noble truth is leading to
is a life that is free of this kind of certain kind of pain certain kind of dukkha or
suffering that comes from how we relate to or live in
this world of suffering and in a certain kind of way we stop living in it
the mind the awareness has found a place of refuge a face of place of safety
that is not separate from it all but not identified with it
and and but rather if if identified with
anything it's identified with freedom it's identified with peace
with happiness and so we start by
a willingness to to look clearly
at dukkha and the text says one sees as it really is
and whenever the text says as it really is what it means is we're seeing the inconstancy the changing nature of it
that's the key thing that's what makes it a noble truth not that we see suffering and suffer
more but we see suffering and somehow we're able to
have the stillness the focus the clarity of mind to see it as part of the inconstant flow
of changing river of our experience so
if this makes sense to you you might try today as you go through your day
to um observe
the ways in which your dukkha comes and goes appears and disappears
that the rises and falls surges and recedes
that if chances are your dukkha is not constant if it is constant then chances are
you're holding on to something and what are you holding on to i'm not saying that dealing with
suffering is easy but uh can you begin looking at it
through a different lens a different perspective than your usual one
and can you step outside of the yourself almost to be able to look at
dukkha as something that's flowing changing and constant part of the stream of perceptions
that are constantly shifting and changing that sometimes comes back to dukkha
but then flits away and
to begin kind of breaking up the solidity of everything
and into the flow the stream of experience and
so um if that if looking at dukkha today is too much for you of course you can stop don't don't
do it too much but if to understand what we're going to do the
next for the rest of the week this very important topic you might see if you can
gaze upon your duke in a new way and see what happens
so thank you and very much and i look forward to meeting here again tomorrow