foreign foreign
you're muted Nikki that's what's going on that's why I didn't get any thumbs up you couldn't
hear me hi okay hello and welcome to happier can you hear me now
yes now I have the thumbs up I got confused somebody gave me a thumbs up anyway all right hello hello and welcome
so let's warm up the space by um saying hello unmuting ourselves if
you wish you can say hello I start by saying hi I'm Nikki in Mountain View
California on the UN seated or lonely land who's here who wants to help warm
up the space hey everyone Jesse San Rafael California hi Jesse
Neil in Drury New Hampshire it's very New Hampshire okay welcome
is it raining there what's happening yeah it's rainy like in the high 50s and
just I don't know I'm having tea
well well thanks for warming up the space by saying hello
anybody else wants to say hi hi from Toronto Jerry here hi Jerry
hello from Cherry San Diego hi you welcome
Catherine says hi from Minneapolis Dakota land welcome anybody else wants
to help warm up the space
why is Fred from Oakland hi Fred good to see you
hi Barbara hi Richie from Cleveland hi Richie
welcome great you're from New York City hi Claire good evening to you Mary from
Oakland hi Mary and fazel says hi from Chicagoland and came from Tofino British
Columbia we're International of course yay and of course Jerry already said
hello so we have more Canadians joining us so
hi Bill from Dallas so let's let's uh get started let's formally get started
thanks Neil for posting information about the happy hour group of groups if
you're new to happy hour we have a mailing list it's a low traffic mailing
list but um it's um it includes information quotes
references as well as interesting articles Etc that folks share so you're
welcome to join that mailing list and at this point I changed setting so
accidental muting won't be possible we keep the space quiet for the duration of
our guided meditation or that noises of course there's always noise coming here
and there which is which is okay but not accidental I'm muting I meant um
I change the settings so that all chats will only come to host but I ask you to
keep the chat uh silent quiet until the end when we
open it for Reflections and questions and comments but uh last but not least turning on
recording for the sake of Audio Dharma here we go
okay all right so welcome lovely to be with you all
for this rendition of happy hour
so so for today um I wanted to to invite us to
um reflect on so we'll we'll do some meta practice some simple meta practice but I
also what I wanted to bring in was an invitation to reflect on our own
goodness in this particular way so we all
have been reached out to we've all reached out to others through simple acts of
kindness and um these simple random acts of kindness
and sometimes they don't seem quite random we text a friend how are you doing or or
um we we are generous with our time with our care with our attention
and um we tend to underestimate the value
underestimate the power of these acts of kindness in fact
there was a research article that was published uh
about a month ago and Neil sent a wonderful paper from New York Times to
happier Google Groups and I became really interested in that article and then then I wrote and I read the uh the
original signs paper and then a few other science articles that all point to
how we underestimate the power of these random acts of
kindness and in fact if you happen to listen to yesterday's talk at IMC
Sunday's talk at IMC I talked about um to this theme this this underestimation
this delusion we have this confusion we have this cognitive bias we have about
our kindness about how impactful it really is we don't
realize how impactful it really is and how it both impacts the receiver and it also
impacts us so there is goodness all around in these acts of kindness
so by bringing our awareness to them to appreciate them
after the fact recognizing our own goodness recognizing our own
intentionality the Ripple effects which we may not even know what the Ripple
effects are but but to appreciate the goodness we can
make it more possible that we will do that we will strength the karmic
potentiality that we might actually pick up the phone and reach out to a friend or we might
say hello to a neighbor and smile not realizing that that might brighten their
day because they're having a tough time etc etc so bringing attention to to
appreciating the goodness Within can make these random acts of kindness
more likely for us to actually do them
it's a long-winded way of saying it but I hope it makes sense what I'm pointing to so
number one we tend to underestimate the impact of of random acts of kindness
on others number two we underestimate the impact the the
um the positive impact that they have on us on how happy they make us so number
three what we're going to do in the practice today besides practicing simple meta is to bring awareness it's like
we've planted seeds let's water them let's water them so more
more flowers will bloom more kind flowers in
daily life will will Bloom and what do you know will become a kind
person drop by drop by drop little by little by little through these small
little acts of kindness okay I think that's plenty of Framing
and if you want more framing you can go and listen to the Sunday's talk uh on Audio Dharma but without further Ado
let's practice together let's let's settle let's arrive
ah so
arriving Landing letting go of all the words
here
oh sweetheart here
referring to ourselves kindly gently lovingly
oh dear one
oh dear one I've brought you to sit to practice
I care for you this is how I share and I show my care
for myself softening relaxing the body
and just letting yourself be breathed
for a few minutes without an agenda
just taking Refuge
feeling our sit bones and the cushion and the chair
feeling supported connected to the Earth through our feet our legs
our bottom ah relaxing the body the upper body
offering the entire weight of the upper body to land
the way to offer it up to the Earth
my thoughts arise if you find that we're entangled in planning remembering it's
okay it's all right this is what Minds do we know this we
know this mines are like puppies
being kind to the puppy of our mind
releasing letting go
of the juicy bone that seems juicy but it's really Hollow
and say not now we'll come back later
I'll come back later and taking Refuge in our hearts in this moment
and what is the most nourishing
nourishing to our marrow to our bone marrow
resting resting
that our hearts rest and be breathed
and as each breath is welcomed each in breath each breath
with your body your heart be filled with kindness breathing in kindness
receiving kindness breathing out kindness
the world around you
and it's not so effortful it's not that you're doing it just
imagine it's happening there is goodness here there is goodness in your heart
your good intentions for cultivation otherwise you wouldn't be showing up right now
for this practice so trust
trust this desire this intention for goodness for cultivating kindness
as if you're bellowing you're blowing on an ember
your breath
it's blowing on this emperor of loving kindness
making this Holy Fire of loving kindness this warmth
this care for yourself and others a warm heart
with each breath in your heart center
as if with each in breath may I be well with each other breath May others be
well may I be saved May others be safe
may I be happy May others be happy in breath and not breath
can do the four phrases of mitta having to do with safety
health happiness and ease or just keep it simple
in breath may I be well out breath may all beings be well
Let It Be easeful effortless if it becomes too hard
let go of the phrase and just let yourself be
breathed that's kind enough
foreign
and if you like and stay with this here
or if you wish
you're staying embodied breathing in and out
you bring to mind
some kindness some random act of kindness that you received
in the recent times it was as simple as smile or
would be someone being very kind to you going out of their way
or whatever it might have been let yourself feel
the goodness of that gesture how it impacted you
how it still impacts you
let yourself relish be open
to relishing this goodness in the world is kindness
is quite possible that the person who shared this act of kindness didn't quite
appreciate or underestimated how it impacted you
maybe in your heart in your mind saying thank you
I appreciate them be grateful to them
nourishing this goodness goodness begets goodness
let yourself feel inspired
and now let yourself bring to Heart bring to mind
some kindness random act of kindness maybe it was a smile Maybe
was letting someone go ahead of you and align or maybe reached out to a friend
hey how are you I've been thinking of you are offered to help
or helped in some way
went out of your way to be kind
let yourself bring that to heart and relish relish the goodness
goodness begets goodness
and as we often underestimate the impact of our kindness let yourself really appreciate turn up the appreciation
of the ripple effect you may not even know
yourself feel inspired by this kindness as if
as if you are your own twin and it's your twin good at this kindness
you're inspired
by your twin wow that was nice ah
this is not a time to judge yourself like oh I could have done that I should have done that I was not good enough
this is not the time at all if that comes up say thank you very much
this is not the time to be judgmental I am relishing goodness and turn your mind to relish goodness
you have choice we all have choice exercise it
relishing goodness
and that's a point whenever feels like your heart is full with appreciating
goodness received and shared you can go back to Simply
breathing in kindness breathing out kindness may I be well May others be well
may I be well May others be well
age in breath may I be well each out breath spreading kindness
spreading loving kindness
May others be well
and as we bring this practice the area to close
spreading your kindness far and wide your good will your meta internally to
seep into every cell of your body and externally 360 Degrees
no preference of inside versus outside outside versus
inside may I be well it may others be well
all the same it's all the same no separation between me and others really
may all beings everywhere be well may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
thank you all for your practice foreign
before we transition into small groups
which will have an interesting prompt tonight but before we do that any Reflections you'd like to share
Fred please
hi hi thank you I had an experience today that was uh so much the mirror of what you had
prompted and of the article that Neil sent us thank you Neil uh so I was I was
standing in line at Kaiser to get my covid and my flu shot
to do that they would put different colored ribbons on your chest
and so I moved down the line and right at the threshold where we're about to enter there was a woman who had one
ribbon on and she and her partner came up and told her oh you could if you get the other ribbon you can get both shots
and there was a moment she was about to go in the door into the further chamber
of this routine and she froze and I could see that she was anxious and
wanted to go back there but it was afraid about losing her place in line so I just took mine off I said here
please take mine and she went in and I went back to get another uh ribbon for me and took me all of you know 30
seconds and then later we were in another chamber of this routine and she she was
somewhat ahead of me and she looked at me and said are you the person who gave me the ribbon because we were in masks
and we had just seen each other for a moment I said yeah I was and she said you made my day
and um you know that was much more than I thought I did but of course when she
said that that sort of made my day uh and I was then thinking
as we began here uh that I think I did that without
a hesitation and without embarrassment or fear
but also with a moment of scoping out the situation and looking in her face and seeing is this the right thing to do
and I might have made a mistake but in this case I didn't and I
I think it's from coming here for a year and a half that made that more possible
and it strikes me that oh well this is another case of the Ripple
from your being here Nikki and from Diana and from the other people and for
everybody else here in Sangha um in which these things move and there
this is one of those rare occasions when the the trajectory and the origins seem
apparent to me um mostly of course they're invisible so thank you
thank you thank you so much red so eloquently said spoken thanks for
sharing the beautiful story of of your random act of kindness how it made your
day and and uh how it made well how it made her day and how it made your day
and now you're making all of our days by by uh bringing bringing these this
ripple effect and thank you Fred yeah thank you so much
um yeah yeah oh yes thanks for posting the article
um yeah thanks Neil beautiful
any other Reflections before we head into groups
and and maybe I'll share the prompt of the groups tonight
which is um Reflections on on when you had you
didn't act a random act on kindness um just just as Fred shared and
um it made your day or or somebody was kind to you and it made your or you were kind
it made their day made your day yet they were kind to you it made your day
um so just sharing these random acts of kindness with each other so in small
groups we'll be roughly groups of three and let it be a chance for mudita from
meta for vicarious joy for Joy for this Ripple for for inspiring each other with
these acts of kindness sharing your Ribbon um I love that thank you again so I'm
going to create the breakout rooms so please take care of yourselves take
care of each other each person will say one nugget maybe one little story briefly and then make leave time for
some for the next person and the next person so so that everybody has the chance to share so I'm going to open
their rooms take care of each other uh take care of yourselves and let's go
alphabetically if we can according to the first name here we go
okay welcome back everyone all the rooms are closed
so we have a few minutes now for Reflections how was it the sharing
about random acts of kindness receiving giving what what did you notice both in
the process or speaking about it was it inspiring was it
seating or planting more seeds I saw it there you go
Neil I saw your hand please so it was a lovely meditation and a lovely breakout
um so I was I would have to say entertain during the meditation when I noticed
that I was like so thrilled at the random acts of kindness that happened to
me and so disparaging of the acts I gave to other people I kept switching looking
for one that actually made a difference and then I'm like that's the article you sent her it's what she just talked about
um you know yeah yeah yeah apparently I'm stuck with my human mind for now
oh thanks for sharing that Neil that is that is so human and and I love that you
got to see it so clearly and that you're sharing it out loud and laughing at it because that's exactly it you know in
Buddhism when we call talk about you know greed hatred and delusion that
confusion that one one um uh synonym I've just come up for uh
with is is um uh cognitive
um bias is cognitive bias is like radical cognitive bias and you just saw
your radical cognitive bias right and these cognitive biases are measured in Psychology expert we know we have them
it's just the Illusions like wait a minute I know this and yet I'm doing it wow isn't it interesting to be human so
this cognitive bias of oh yeah what other people's people do it it's impactful and what I do is just not good
enough like oh sweetheart that's such a cognitive bias so thanks for sharing
cognitive bias or clearly naming it yeah thanks to you
that's great that's great other Reflections what else came up
groups in in your practice also in breathing in kindness breathing
out kindness that was actually that was a new experiment uh I had never let it
in this particular way I have to say we've done many different ways but but
with the in-breath may I be well um and out breath May others be well to
pair that I wonder if notice the shift and and if you noticed the shift with that
um one person says so much to learn from my group and how to find the moments of
light in the dark in the day and ask for help beautiful thanks for sharing that
yeah beautiful [Music]
other Reflections I have a couple of minutes parents
Nikki I wanted to comment that uh within within my small group
the uh the consensus was that we get so much goodness from being in this group
that kind of tunes us into these little you know little moments in life where we
can make a difference and it helps a lot it really does be being in the group
over the year year and a half that we've been coming so thank you so much
thank you Terence and thanks to the Sangha really we co-create This Together
We co-create this together all of us yeah thank you turns and and well said
doing this practice um and and
um I I think no I think Diane and I have been doing this for two and a half years we pivoted the march of 2020 went online
from from being um from just doing it in person at IMC
and and what a gift what a gift we feel it's been for us and this community when
and we keep going we keep going we keep going strong yay what a one what a
wonderful practice to do on a daily on a weekly basis so thank you all and it's
seven o'clock and oh yes couple of last Reflections I read Marianne says that
in-breath and out breath change was more useful for me quite relaxing yay and
penis is the image of nurturing the Embers of kindness was so evocative I'll be returning to it beautiful thank you
for your Reflections thank you for your practice thanks for being part of this
Sangha and your random acts of kindness Not So Random uh your acts of kindness
thank you all may you all be well may you all be free and all beings
everywhere too oops [Music]
thanks everyone