so good morning good day
good week welcome and uh
happy to be here feels quiet here at imc and
in our town so um
the teachings this day this week will be about the body
something that i see is central to buddhist practice more gen
at least it is in many different schools of buddhism and if not explicit it's implicit
and certainly in the teachings of the buddha and um
one of the things that we'll talk about today is the karmic body
one of the things we become aware of when we first start meditation is
what can be called the karmic body the body of holding patterns intentions
that come from the activities of the mind impulses the desires the aversions and
the fears that we carry with us and how they're transferred into our body and
in gestures and muscles and all kinds of ways just and posture
and uh so when we first sit to meditate we become aware of this karmic body
and there are three sets of instructions the buddha gives
on mindfulness this year we did the discourse on the four foundations of mindfulness
last year we did the discourse on the mindfulness of breathing
and the third one is the mindfulness directed to the body each of them begin
with the same exercise that is to
become attuned to the breathing familiar with the experience of breathing in the body a little bit centered and connected to
the body through the breathing and then to become aware of the body more broadly
and then to relax the bodily formations the bodily constructions
the bodily reactivity that has built up that makes up this
karmic body sometimes it's the karma of the day
that can we can let go of and sometimes the karma of of a lifetime
the activities of a lifetime so we'll do this first exercise today many of you are familiar with it
and since it's one of the uh it's the common thread through all three of the buddha's
instructions on mindfulness it's a good place to begin
so i love the way these texts begin with
going to the foot of a tree to an empty open space outdoors
to an empty building
one sits down and sits upright
the kind of expression of deliberateness deliberately going to a place to sit
and then with deliberateness assuming with the body
a dignified a appropriate
posture that one way or the other
might express the dignity of being a human being not with tension
but kind of attitudinal attitudinal uprightness
lowering your gaze and letting your gaze be relaxed and not
looking at anything in particular
and if it's comfortable gently slowly let your eyelids close
and then to center ourselves in the body to take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full
comfortably deep breaths and on the exhale
to relax to soften the whole body
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and with a normal in-breath feel the different parts of the body
i'll direct your attention to and then on the exhale relax soften
inhale feeling the face and exhaling relax the face
relaxing the face almost as if the air around you receives your face and holds it for you
inhaling feeling the shoulders
exhalings softening the shoulders
releasing the shoulders
so
on the inhale inhale feeling the belly
on the exhaling exhale relaxing the belly softening
when they inhale having some kind of global awareness of your body
and on the exhale a global releasing of your body
and then on the inhale you might feel your mind your brain
for any tension there might be there
and the exhale gently relaxing the mind
and then to settle in now to
discover the body's experience of breathing
every day the experience of breathing shifts maybe slightly but it shifts changes
becoming familiar with inhale
exhales
so
um
um receiving the inhale as it
expands the body the lungs
relax and let go with the exhale
settling in to your body
so
as you exhale let go of your thoughts your thinking
so you can better feel sense take in
the body's experience of breathing
letting go of thinking is preparation
for a deeper connection to yourself
so
and then as you're breathing as we say similar to how we began on the
inhale feel
the whole body the global body
in whatever way is easy to the extent that's easy
as you exhale feel how that global experience of the
body changes with the exhale
with no hurry as if you have all the time in the world
feel your body as you inhale
and relax the tensions the holdings of the body
as you exhale
without expecting much or being ambitious as you exhale
soften the body release the body
letting the mind be still so you can feel your body better
so there's more room in awareness in which to
release the body
for these minutes we have left put aside giving any importance to your
thinking thinking is a source
one source for the karmic body the tensions we hold
put aside your thinking the best you can and prioritize breathing gently fully
into your body with your body relaxing the body
settling the body
appreciating the calm of the body
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to appreciate what you can appreciate about your body
to appreciate the experience of being embodied
even if there's pain and challenges
i appreciate the
all the nerve receptors in the body that allow you to take in the world
around you even with your eyes closed
that when we're not preoccupied in our thoughts the sensitivity of the body
can sense others our environment
in valuable ways and may it be that as we go about our
day today that we stay connected to the body's
sensitivity discovering what the body
recognizes feels understands
in our environment and our meetings with other people
appreciating the deeper empathy or understanding or
appreciation of others that's possible
when we take them in with all our faculties
and then to aspire to a day of good will
aspire to a day of kindness friendliness
aspiring to offer even in the smallest possible
unseen ways unrecognized ways by unrecognized by others
a day of being generous for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may we
contribute to this
[Music]
so on this monday
i begin the five part series on the body
mindfulness of the body is a core aspect of the buddha's teachings
he repeats it often and with great enthusiasm talking about how
all kinds of wonderful qualities tranquility concentration peace
whatever is wholesome skillful the different stages towards liberation
liberation itself is all founded or based on or experienced
with the body with through mindfulness be more more specific through mindfulness of the body
and in my years of buddhist practice
and practicing in this country and zan and japan and in
asia what struck me was how much the body was
used in the practice certainly the meditation is a physical
meant to be a physically embodied practice but also in the monasteries there's a
lot of physical work and activities and chanting and bowing and ritual
that involve using the body and
the what gets awakened in the body through the kind of practice activities we're involved in
was probably as important as meditation for me and that wasn't that was given i was not
given instructions or told that this attention to the body the engagement of
the body was important um but it kind of slowly kind of seeped into me
and changed me from the inside out to give one example
in the monastery we did a lot of bowing and most often kind of standing by like even
as simple as if we pass someone in the path as we were walking around the monastery we were supposed to stop for a moment
and bow to them as we pass them and and our people served us food we always
had to bow before and after being served uh if we came into the meditation hall we'd always bow coming into the
meditation hall and just you know over and over again you know lots and lots of bowing throughout the day
and do that for months and years something changes this gesture of putting the hands together in front of
the chest and bending forward a little bit is not just a physical gesture it evokes
certain kind of emotions certain attitudes within and for me it was attitude of
appreciation attitude of a certain kind of attitude of letting go of self-centeredness
a certain kind of feeling of reverence and respect and as i um kind of
you know it wasn't dramatic that i would feel that but it would be teeny feelings of that sometimes unrecognized even because i
was busy doing my life doing my things but slowly drip by drip drop by drop the
those little gestures kind of establish those feelings in me in a
deeper way and valuable way for my life and so there was a transformation in the
body of sentiment of attitude of feelings of sensations that i became familiar with
and then multiply that to all the different things we did in practice a whole bunch of things would come up i
would change in the body and meditation was especially so
and the way that i experienced my body surprisingly
changed dramatically in the course of the years of meditation practice that i had
sometimes they would change within a single meditation practice session sometimes certain ways it changed over
years and years of practice so much so that i came to appreciate
that we have different bodies um and what i mean by that not that you
know we we the way we experience our body the body that we experience
shifts and changes depending on the states of mind we have how the mind is used the attitudes the
thoughts the perceptions the intentions all kinds of things come together to shape how we experience our
body and it isn't that we have it you know the material body changes um in and of itself
um that you know doesn't change particularly except you know
in ordinary ways we all know exercise or lack of it aging
the but the way that that body is experienced is very much conditioned by
what is going on the mind and with the kind of the very
significant ways in which the mind begins to shift and change in meditation
thereby are the way we experience the body changes as well
and and so this week i'd like to talk about um five different bodies that we can
experience don't take this to be ontological like this is like a real
um you know like different bodies physically the material body doesn't
change but we're talking about is the experienced body how it's experienced
and so i want to talk about today a little bit about the karmic body
about tomorrow about the bliss body the peace body the insight body and the
liberation body so each of those are kind of represents different ways of the body can be
experienced and and the karmic body is
the body that we have shaped through the activities of
our lifetime and especially those which are volitional those that come from the
deliberateness of the mind as opposed to you know if you have a particular
profession that um you know that uh
you know uses your body over and over and over again in certain ways it shapes the body and maybe it's um
it's uh we can consider it karmic but it's uh it doesn't come from the
necessarily from the attitudes of the mind that exists there or people's faces are a little bit
different because of the language as they speak and depend different languages engage
over a lifetime different muscles on teeny micro muscles in the face and so there's a subtle differences in people's
faces depending on the languages they speak so those aren't necessarily karmic
they're just you know i don't know what to call that but the karmic has to do with our
attitudes it involves the tensions that we hold the holding patterns in our body
when there is uh when there is anxiety and fear we hold our body a certain way
and if that fear is chronic that tension gets built in and becomes almost like
almost hardwired into us if we spend a lot of time being angry and the anger is chronic that affects
them also the micro muscles of the face around the eyes and the shoulders and different places
if there is uh um if we're oriented more for desires
that i are searching and looking the eyes the face the movements of the body
are kind of a shift and change are expressive of that desire those
desires if it's more anger that we express the body kind of takes a different
stance different posture um the confidence
generosity love are all different things which shift and change all kinds of things in
our body not just the muscles but also the chemicals of our body and um
the how the neurons fire in our body and so when we sit down to meditate
uh i mean for many people what we're encountering is our karmic body and uh we
can experience it initially for a lot of the tensions we hold in our body
the shoulders the face the belly anywhere at all the hand
and i discovered when i was early years of meditation that i carried tension in my thighs
and that tension my thighs traveled up and affected my lower back and
and so the attention was a little bit bracing myself against something going to happen
i've known people who have a tremendous feeling wanting to bolt out of meditation and so the feeling of kind of
escaping running away that might be encased in some bodies it shapes the
experience we have of this body of ours and so sometimes some of the pain we
experience in meditation in the early stages of meditation practice
is karmic pain most very common places experience that in the shoulders
shoulders that are held high like mine were when i was younger
as they begin to release they begin hurting it could be that
there's a certain kind of despair or something that we're experiencing so we're collapsing and kind of giving up
and that certainly affects the musculature and the feelings in the chest but it also
made a big big impact on the upper back and as we sit in meditation we might
feel the legacy of you know long term time sitting a certain way and muscles or muscles are tired some
have contracted and then working with that is working with a karmic body
and so knowing that's what it is hopefully gives us a lot of patience a
lot of compassion and a lot of understanding that that's often what we're working with when we first start meditating the karmic body
the karmic breathing how breathing has been affected by our emotions our attitudes our experiences our traumas
our challenges we've had in our life and um
and so too and this is what we're slowly working with and relaxing and breathing with
some of the relaxation we can contribute to and some of it we don't want to make it
too big of a project to relax all the time but some of it it just comes with
sitting quietly and meditating and letting go of thoughts and being present in a in a sincere way here and now
it gives the body a chance to unwind it gives the things to to release to soften
and slowly it's wonderful to watch meditators over you know a few years and
to see the slow evolution into what sometimes called the yogic body
you know your body of a meditator you can see in their how they sit down and there's a comfort level there's an ease
there's a embodiment there that has evolved over time
and and as the karmic body begins to recede
at least temporarily sometimes as we get concentrated the karmic body recedes and other kind of experience of the body
enter into the foreground but then as the concentration leaves the karmic body returns
and we back in touch with his tensions and holding patterns we have and that massage is part of the process
of healing of opening up and coming to some resolution of the karmic body
and um so um
so as you go about your day today you might
see if you can notice what i'm calling the karmic body
notice the holding patterns you have that both you know in the in the muscles but
also in your posture how's your posture affected by your attitude
by your desires and your aversions by your confidence or lack of confidence
um and where are things tight where are things holding
and maybe even some of the physical pains you have that really come from physical
conditions sometimes a small percentage of them might be from
activities we've done the activities have expressed um
these are you know are as karmic are the activities we've done expl has expressed
anger impatience uh being in a hurry um desire greed
um resistance all kinds of things then then because we were that that way
maybe something got injured and now we have to live with the after effect of this car this part of this
karmic body we have to work with uh we're not stuck in the karmic body
this is what practice is about to some degree find freedom from that karma
and and that we'll talk about for the next few days so thank you