so one of the with the central
aspect of doing mindfulness practice practicing meditation
is attention and there's a wonderful verb activity
associated with attention that i just really love that we use in kind of common english
we say sometimes giving attention we give attention to something
and so i think that for much of my life i just took that word that expression
to mean you know the same as pay attention which seems like a strange word concept
to me but to give attention has the idea of giving of generosity
an offering that we make and what if your attention
was a worthy gift what if attention is a
is a an act of generosity that we do with attention to ourselves
that attention is so precious so so valuable that when we offer it to ourselves offer
it to the world it has some of the wonderful rebound effects of generosity
that when we're generous when you're a host for someone
that was part of the delight of it is
the kind of delightful giving away or giving putting aside some kind of
self-preoccupation self-concern if the
dalai lama came to your house for tea and you knew he was coming you would
probably try to be a good host and if you had a favorite chair that's your chair
you would probably let the dalai lama sit in that chair and if you had
just the last tea that your favorite tea
that you want to keep for a special occasion for yourself but dalai lama comes here i have my best tea
and there's certain kind of putting aside self-concern self-preoccupation
at the same time as asserting oneself in a certain wonderful way
in giving in an act of generosity when we bring attention
to ourselves or bring attention to anything so perhaps for today when we sit to
meditate you might want to consider a way of
engaging your attention that feels more like a gift
than a debt that you're paying for paying attention more like a gener act of generosity
that's freeing and the giving here have this and it just feels so good to
let go to open up just here have this here have this attention
and then see what happens then do it again and do it again
generous with your attention so sitting
in a alert posture
and perhaps with your eyes closed or not
you can allow for a gentling of your inner life
a calming of your body
a calming of your mind
and every moment that you are attentive
for anything you're doing while you're meditating the attention part of it
see if that can be a giving a generosity
so in attending to taking a few deep breaths at the
beginning an act of generosity to yourself
to feel be present for those deep breaths
if you relax on the exhale being present for the relaxation is the
gift
um
letting your breathing return to normal
and continuing to maybe relax on the exhale
where the attention given to relax and the attention given
to feel the relaxation are gifts you give yourself
and then to settle into your breathing
settle into the breathing body your body that's breathing
and in what way can you let it be a gift
an act of generosity to offer attention
to this body that's breathing the breathing body has
been serving you for years and years
keeping you alive and now you offer your attention back
a generosity that can't be a duty can't be a strain
can't be a forceful or aggressive
and attention that feels
generous open allowing respectful
giving attention offering attention moment by moment
just now to what's here
you
uh
so
alright
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to consider to imagine different ways to
offer your attention to others to give the gift of attention to other
people where your attention
is attentive not demanding or expecting
where your attention is available
not assertive where attention is
friendly not mistrustful
where we begin the default is with a generous attention
an offering to be present for people as they are
carrying with it a feeling of being generous trusting available
to discover what is here
and in doing so may we see people more fully
see them in ways that engender our good will
our care maybe even our love
and may it be that this practice of mindfulness that we do
supports us
and offering the gifts of goodwill safety
peace and freedom to others
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings
be free
so
so good morning everyone and i'm gonna ask first is it loud enough
here for you people in here and at imc and i wonder if it's loud enough for people
on the volumes high enough for people online and uh
for those of you who came in person thank you i'm hoping that this is a beginning of
uh now of a direction that we start feeling and we can be more open and come
together in community more often and it's a wonderful thing to practice together
so it looks like the sound is good loud enough online thank you
so today i'd like to talk about one of the core virtues or core
practices and attitudes and kind of realizations of buddhism
and that is generosity and in talking about generosity i would
like to talk about in three areas
that of giving that of gift and that of generosity
and if we begin by giving there's many ways of giving and we can give freely and we can give
expectingly or demandingly or obligatory there's a whole range of giving
but giving in and it's all its forms
is really integral to what human beings how they are and how we live
and our societies our communities our families often are
are held together in a network of giving that without people giving of themselves
giving supporting they're probably very little real community and connection
anywhere we go i was really struck as i was raising children here in redwood city
that my kids participated in all kinds of uh
sports soccer and baseball mostly basketball and uh there was a whole bunch of
parents who volunteered their times to be coaches to be managers to the teams and
to set things up and all kinds of things and i was struck that this was a really
important part and valuable part of my shield thrilled his upbringing my children's upbringing to be able to be
part of the community in this way both both be able to play and have fun and be with other kids
but also they felt connected to the redwood city community of parents and
you know wider community like they're a part of something bigger than just our family and it wouldn't have happened i
think it was if unless it was all these adults who volunteered their time they gave of themselves and they knitted
the community in certain ways together
sometimes occasionally it happens as it ha it did happen to me when i started being a new parent
i had the thought what my parents did this for me
my parents you know you know sacrificed this much or gave so
much of themselves you know it's for me that i had no idea that that cloud worked
i never thought about it i just kind of took my parents for granted and i don't have memories of when i was a baby so i
just you know i didn't think about it but i as a new parent
uh you know certainly it was a lot of work a lot of demands and you know up up
all night sometimes with the kids waking up in the night and feeding and this and that
and when they were could do when they were babies and could do almost nothing of themselves
it just felt for the most part just very natural to give time and effort and all this
and uh and i didn't think of myself as being generous but i did feel you know when i when i
wasn't too tired it just felt that the light and part of the delight was the way in
which uh uh i became in a certain i would say i hope
to hopefully healthy way my needs became unimportant
and so it didn't matter if uh you know i was sleepy or the next day or tired it didn't matter if i wasn't thinking about
you know that you know the fact that i hadn't showered in three days
that anybody would care the fact that uh
you know that i was still in my pajamas at 1 pm because there hadn't been any time to do anything else and
someone came to the door or something you know all these things that maybe ordinarily i would have been self-conscious about or had ideas about
or something they fell away and in the early period of
you know babyhood it felt really freeing to have this sense of self-concern drop
away so fully and completely and then as the children could do more for themselves then it felt natural
enough and to become more important again if my my situation became something to care for
and take care of and and that grew over and now they're not even home anymore so
you know just then it's you know a whole different story of how to be
and uh but without that to kind of someone giving themselves to babies
babies don't grow up very well but the feeling that there's people there caring attending to them is
formative even if they don't remember their babyhood there's all kinds of ways in which if it
goes well they feel safe in this world they feel belonging in this world that they're not going to feel if they
feel you know repeatedly abandoned and no one was there to care for them and so this healthy growth of people i
mean depends a lot on you know it's something you could almost not pay someone enough to do
because it's uh maybe because it's there has to be this more than just a job i think it has to be a love
a care that's infused in the giving
it's an epic so the society is kind of kind of to the greatest the extent
depend on it here in the united states there's a culture of non-profit giving
maybe it arises out of the church religious scene here in this country
that where there's a kind of a understood way that of
giving to nonprofits to churches to causes all kinds of things
that is kind of absent in europe and you people in europe are certainly generous but they don't have the same
relationship to organizations like this partly because maybe the government fills in and
there's the governments there take care of people in a much different way more extensive way than
here in this country so here's often we have to do it then because the government is not
filling in or not expected to do certain things
and uh so uh
so the society of giving many years ago i uh
in the early 70s i read a study at the biological study of
some people's community tribe or something in the philippines that lived somewhat
removed from modern society
and they were a dream culture apparently one of the central features of their community was
focusing on dreams and they would wake up in the morning and tell their family about their dreams they had
and uh so dreams were kind of central and but one of the customs they had was
that if someone had a bad had a dream about a bad dream or a dream that where
someone in the village in the town uh was somehow the relationship was
strained or difficult or there was some kind of challenge there
in the dream when they woke up in the morning they would go give that person in the village
a gift what a phenomenal thing to do you know to i don't know what the
unconscious is doing you know when it shows a difficult relationship in a dream
but uh but the fact that they would respond to that with a gift oh you know what does that do to this
community what does that do about the relationships and how people relate to each other
i recently talked to someone who had a very difficult landlord
seemed to the landlord was just kind of unreasonable and demands and expectations and all kinds of things
and so what should i do when i go back to you know i've been away for a while
and i didn't know what to say exactly except the one thing that is kind of a buddhist thing to say
i said when you go back bring a gift for your landlord and the person was kind of a little bit
shocked like what this person person's so difficult but yeah bring a gift and
maybe bake some cookies or buy something or do you know before you go and just bring it and say you know i was
thinking about you and my retreat and i just wanted to bring you a gift or something
and uh and i've known i've offered this advice to other people who had like difficult in-laws
and uh and it it turns out that it's a kind of a leavening a kind of a
tenderizing something changes when we bring gifts that sometimes can't happen if we don't it's people's go they lower
their guard somehow or they soften there's no guarantee of course
but the emphasis i want to make here is that giving is a huge part of our lives and
for me at least i think i under-appreciated growing up i didn't understand the extent of it
so then if giving is kind of in the network of our human connections
uh one of the features of that is the gift the gift that's given
and there's many gifts that can be given there's a giving of our time a giving of our
services giving of material goods giving of money there's all these things
that are given given of smiles just you know giving smiles is a wonderful thing to do
and that's a little hard with these masks on and uh
sometimes i want people to see me smile because i just want them to feel my appreciation delight and seeing them
being with them and and i realized you know what a wonderful thing it is to communicate the light and
appreciation that's harder with these masks on it and i don't think there too i thought
about it too much i just kind of was smiling and just because i was happy and and now i want to
be able to it's almost like a communication that's being gifted or something
what's interesting about uh the gift in buddhism in indian buddhism
is that it's one of the word for gift and ad forgiving
is donna uh d-a-n-a and uh
and some of the ways the buddha used the word donna were somewhat equivalent but different
from their early indian idea of sacrifice which is a different word it say
and but he kind of used it in similar ways and so i'll give you one example
one of the things that uh in in some of the religions of his time they would make
sacrifices to the gods that was a big part of the sacrifice was for the gods and so some of the gods was brahma one
of the great gods and uh and the buddha said
that your parents and your family especially your parents
are brahma so here he's redefining what you know what a god is from some invisible god up
in the heavens to people who are tangible in this world people you know your parents
they're your brahma they're your god and then he said give gifts to them
so rather than giving a gift the offering the sacrifice to brahma in heaven the buddha is redefining the notion of
giving to what's happening in our immediate experienced world our social world here
now we might not think that very much of this but i think in the ancient world
there was a big change from where the central focus of some people's religious
life was all these elaborate rituals of sacrifice for the gods
and the buddha was changing it where the religious giving was not the sacrifice to invisible gods
but a giving of generously to people who were known and here in their society
and so the word dhana has this religious quality in buddhism it's a gift which is somehow
carry spirituality in it and exactly how it carries spirituality each of us can find out for ourselves
but it's uh it has a heightened value the gift of dawn of the other words
forgiving and pali in the early in buddhist language then then donna but
often like like the sacrifice were religious in nature donna also has a religious nature to it
and we see that in some of the lists of things that you can give you can give uh ethics your virtue you
can like live living by the precepts is the gift of of ethics or virtue a gift of safety
you can give your kindness you can give material goods
possessions you can give the gift of fearlessness that the people
don't fear have any reason to fear you and uh so these different kind of things
that you can give are pointing back to some quality that we have inside
and so uh to give and then there's and then so there's uh
the giving and there's a gift and and then the the different gifts have different
values and this is where it gets a little bit complicated and often uh challenging for
people in the modern west to appreciate some of the logic that's used in buddhism for for valuing
having value on gifts and part of the idea of the value of
gift giving the gift where you give a gift what you give is because gifts have an impact on the
giver we like to think i think often we're kind of kind of be altruistic we just
give without any concern for ourselves to have any concern for ourselves that can we benefit from the giving may be a selfish
it can be selfish that we have to be on the guard for that i hope but self-regard and self-care doesn't
have to be selfish and so one of the things that buddha talked
about was give gifts that bring you joy bring gifts that are uplifting that
inspire you and uh because you benefited as well so the
gift just goes in both directions you're both gifting someone else but you're benefiting from your own gift
so it's kind of a gift to yourself as well so for one of the things he said it was
for example he encouraged people remember it's an ancient world 2 500 years in the bronx era age
he said give with your hands give directly
and uh you know we should stop you know please don't stop donating to organizations you know
online or whatever way you do for sure but uh but something different happens
when we give in person the i know someone who uh like to uh
they used i don't know if it's still the hair but there's this thing somebody called a free cycle and you would post your things you have
available someone come to your home and you would give it to them personally and the person said i could go and give
it to the good will but then it's impersonal and when i give it to someone directly
who can use it it just feels so much more inspiring and nicer and afterwards i feel and remember
this thing oh this is a good thing that's very different than just giving to the goodwill
if uh if you give for example ten dollars to someone who clearly seems destitute and
challenged in all kinds of ways and then you find out that the person
uses that to buy alcohol well maybe it was still useful because a person
felt someone cared for them and that's a little memory that someone cared it was attentive to them and they weren't
abandoned completely so maybe it had some benefit but but then you gave 10 to someone else
you know some teenager for example who's quite poor but with that ten dollars they could buy uh you know maybe they
were able to buy maybe this is the old world now but paper and pen
so they could write their college essay to get it applied for college
and with that essay they got into college and they came to you and said you know that later said you know by the
way you you gave me the ten dollars what i did was i bought this paper bought these pens i was able to go and
just kind of in my free time keep writing and writing that essay with that block of paper i didn't have any paper
at home this was phenomenal that and you helped me get into college without it i don't think i would have
gotten to college so there's different value in where we
give in in terms of our happiness and our inspiration our delight
i think some people really dislike this idea of putting value like that because then sometimes there's a feeling well
some poor people don't deserve our gifts and we should just give the places where it's really wonderful to give
and you see this in some buddhist cultures in asia i saw it maybe here too in this country
where some buddhist centers temples were clearly over the top wealthy
and people would come with gifts to the temple and on the street on the sidewalk
outside or just you know they've been living nearby are people who are really destitute really impoverished
and people would just walk right by them and uh and give to the temple
there is value in giving to people who are poor and have a great need
so how do we how do we see do we just how do we decide where to give how do we
decide what gifts to give is part of the i think part of a considered life
reflective life i don't think there's any clear and obvious answers to the
question but the buddha's idea that you give somewhat personally so it's
you're giving part of yourself from the process and also that you're giving it away that
inspires you that brings you delight and joy he also said the buddha said
don't give harming others or harming yourself
that's also a very interesting guideline for this don't give in a way that harms yourself
or sometimes you can harm other people through giving so this is not a call for you know some
kind of uh harmful self-sacrifice just give at all costs but to do it the way that you get it you
get the you benefit from it and if you give in a miserly way you
there's maybe not so much benefit but if you give it a generously way
then there's a lot of benefit and then there's uh for yourself and then if you then we go to the third
thing today generosity giving gift and generosity
that generosity you can give without it really being generous
but it's also possible to give with generosity and generosity is this beautiful quality
where things are given that are not obligated to give
you can give and it's when it's obligated to give and it's just an obligation but generosity can never be
obligatory it's always giving more than is expected and more than is
called for and uh and so it's a kind of opening up to something that's given from us freely
a kind of an inspiration a delight a opening up letting go
to give in a nice way from a good heart from a good mind a healthy mind a good mind i want to do this this is great
this doesn't harm me this maybe benefits the person or brings joy or delight
and it just feels so warm-hearted and delightful to do this thing oh yeah
give there was a time in when i was young where i was younger when i
started to do the practice of generosity and giving that i kind of would give not miserly exactly
but i would give but i was a little bit tight and closed because
i didn't feel like i should enjoy it i didn't feel like i should kind of
like like that i should be somehow if i if i felt kind of all good for doing it
that somehow that diminished the giving but i've learned since then that this is actually the opposite
that the the more delight i have in giving uh the more it seems like other people can
feel it's really given freely and generously and i've certainly felt it that way i've
i've i've uh received things from people where i felt that you know they were kind of
they wanted to do it but there also was a challenge for them and struggled for them and then it was a struggle for me
to really appreciate it but then i've had people just kind of wow just like wow that's so easy for
that person it's like so fully just clearly offered and then i have a whole different
feeling for it oh that's as good then i can enjoy it more and take it in
and so uh one of the features of this word dhana
in buddhism that in the buddhist sense of the word that's kind of a religious giving spiritual
giving as i said there's other words in pali for just other kinds of giving
but the tendency is for donna to have a spiritual or religious quality to it
and one of the qualities of it is that it's freely given and maybe that's what generosity means
but uh it's freely offered with kind of kind of with no expectations of an exchange
but perhaps with an expectation that this is healthy and good for
everyone involved including oneself that some we benefit from it ourselves
and uh that somehow it it feeds the good qualities it nurtures the best qualities
of our heart you know to to
be generous supports generosity in ourselves and if generosity feels like a
warm-hearted kind of offering and opening and letting go
then uh you know we benefit and we see this little bit with the the
pali word for generosity it's uh
paulie word is chaga c-a-g-a and uh
the uh first meaning in the dictionary is not generosity but it's uh letting go
or and then the second definition has to do with generosity
but it makes some sense when you give something you're also letting it go
and uh so rather than calling it letting go uh we could use the languages like giving
up giving over because then it has the word giving in it which since the chaga has both that
meaning remains to renounce something and jim being generous and how this becomes beautiful is that
uh is it when the letting go when the giving up is so freely and
and unrestrainedly given that it just feeds a lightness an
openness a a softness a warmth
to of to ourselves like our heart begins to sing because of in the letting go and
the freedom letting go is not supposed to diminish us but to enhance beautiful qualities
within it there's a story from the
two stories from the ancient indian tradition of uh uh you know there's a in buddhism
traditionally there's all these ideas that you make a lot of merit make good karma for yourself if you give
and there are these two people who uh were friends and they wanted to acquire lots of good merit for themselves build
up their store of merit so they decided why don't we just give back and forth
i'll give you something then you give it to me and i'll give it to you
and um and so when they died they got reborn as poisoned wells
they were kind of poisoning each other doing that rather than doing something really good it's
and then there's a story of a of a monk who had been given a golden
begging bowl and uh and he was going to go to sleep one time
in a grove of trees and he noticed a thief was lurking behind the trees seemingly to wait for
him to fall asleep so he could come and pick up the bowl and steal it so
the mug sat up and said hey come over here and he handed him the bowl here this is for you you can have it
and the guy was so happy he got the golden ball he ran off and you know didn't have to steal it he was
given and then he came back the next morning he came back into the monk and said
uh i've never known anyone to give so freely and not be attached to what they
have and you were so open-handed in how you gave it to me and without attachment to this wealth this thing
how did you manage to do that and then the thief became the hmong student
and then they ever lived they lived happily ever after i guess
and uh so these are fables but uh they point to something
and so this month being able to give so generously uh was inspiring for the thief
but the way that the buddhism understands the ecology of the heart of the mind
the book was also benefiting from that something was opening and freeing and being supported
in the person who'd benefit who was giving as well and one of the ways that this is
discussed in the ancient tradition or you know in buddhism is that
one of the purposes of giving when it's done well generously maybe in a certain kind of
selfless way uh is that it beautifies the mind
isn't it so giving that beautifies your mind so isn't that great if you're it's kind of
great if you're kind of selfish but you realize you can't be selfish so you give up your selfishness
so you can so that you can give freely so you can get this benefit of getting a
beautiful mind it's a strange logic right but sorry
but uh this idea that uh you know that's if you give cleanly and openly and
freely it does something for us and the reason to emphasize that
is that it's good to be available for the
nourishment the support the benefit that comes internally when we do good things
we count we're important as well and allowing ourselves to benefit to grow in
the dharma to grow in good qualities and skillful qualities grow in wholesomeness
is one of the great things to do human life it's how we can mature as a as an adult as a practitioner
and you mature more if you allow yourself to feel
to be present for the the benefits
present for how things shift internally in a good direction
so if your generosity is such that uh you
uh you know if you do it miserably then maybe
there's not that warmth that nourishment and wholesomeness inside but if you give freely and openly you
learn that way then something inside benefits
and that's kind so what makes it spiritual in buddhism i propose
is that its generosity is offered freely and openly
it's offered wisely with some some attention to the consequence of giving and who you're
giving to and why and where it's inspiring and it's giving that also supports the
growth of wholesome beneficial beautiful qualities of mind of heart
for yourself and for others and the protection that provides from
selfishness when you're concerned with beautifying your mind is that selfishness is
if i'm allowed to use this maybe you'll forgive me or you'll reword it uh
uglifies the mind you know it it sullies the mind to be
selfish and so as we kind of get a sense of this beautiful open clarity
luminosity of the heart the mind the warmth the glow you'll feel that the selfishness
contracts it clouds it over
and so there's this wonderful way that attending to the beauty of your own inner life
supports greater and greater freedom and so when you're going to sleep in a
grove of trees with your golden bull next to you
and someone clearly wants it maybe it's easy for you
to let them have it to give it to them and one of the gifts of that
is that they um the person doesn't get the bad karma of
stealing you save them from that karma by giving it first
so giving gift and generosity
the word for generosity also means to let go to renounce and it's a very special
meaning in buddhism very special kind of part of the let it deep letting go of of liberation
so finally i like to say that this
idea of giving is also a practice in buddhism
and what that means is that sometimes it's useful to give even when you don't feel like it
because it begins to be it can be a mirror to understand ourselves better
to understand where we're holding on where we're afraid where we're uh where we're calculating
in all kinds of ways about why we should give and how we should give and you know all this you know
and to give where it feels difficult to stretch in order to learn more about ourselves
and to learn what it's like to let go and to trust what we're what we're doing
so for example there's all kinds of ways we can practice jet practice generosity
you can practice generosity driving a car where you always give someone your practice is no matter what you
always give the other person the right of way it's kind of generosity you never force yourself
even if it seems like you know it's your right or something but you kind of practice it could be that
you uh you know you see that the
you're in the store and there's the question is in the supermarket which line checkout line do you stand in
and normally you might calculate you know where's the one that's going to go fastest the shortest for me
and you see one up ahead you see someone else is heading there too you're slightly ahead so you clearly you
can get there first and you get it what's that generous thing to do most people are eager to get through
those lines you have it you hold back and let the
person have it and find another one these are simple things to do maybe but you do it as a practice
means you do it so you can study yourself and learn what's going on and stretch something and
discover how you're challenged by it and and see is it really necessary what you're holding on to and you're holding
on to more than just you know who knows what you're holding on to discover
another nice practice is to take i don't know if it wasn't again these things don't work so well anymore our
society is changing so much maybe but uh worked better before when uh
to carry with you some significant amount of cash when people weren't so it was much more
of a cash economy i guess and uh and i don't know what's a lot money but
20 or 50 cash or something and then uh you have the practice of looking at
studying as you go through your days of uh of someone you can give it to
that you don't know something you can give it to that just seems like okay this person i think i'll
give it to and uh and then see what comes up and maybe you never give it but the lot
came up and you learned a lot about yourself in the process or maybe you do and
and then you learn some things and maybe you learn that well that was a mistake but uh it is a practice to do as well
and uh and it's a practice that supports the exploration
of the beautiful possibilities of giving of gift
of beautifying the mind and the most profound reason in buddhism to give
is to discover how to be free not to be clinging to anything
so giving gift and generosity
are three topics that are well worth reflecting on living with
focusing on as part of the wider world of practicing mindfulness
so thank you and uh
and then coincidentally uh
nancy came up to me before this talk and and was just mentioned there's an opportunity for some people to do
something generous here at imc and she was going to ask for some volunteers and do you want to ask
do you need to use the mic or maybe maybe let's get them let's get the mic and that way at least the people
online can also hear otherwise they're going to be curious
thank you thank you if i could get five or six people to help
i think the battery is low is the green light on
to help outside to pick up trash and sweep and do a little weeding
for like 15 minutes i think we could get a lot done so they can meet you just out in the
hallway there in that bigger hole actually if you can meet me out in the parking lot just out the back
door would be great when you get your shoes on i also have gloves for picking up trash
great so thank you all and uh
wish you all well and that the world where we giver and gift
and receiver maybe are all interpenetrating each other all mutual
and all kind of disappear in each other can we really can we really tell what is the gift what is the gift and
what is the receiver so thank you