so good morning good day hello and um
sometimes it's useful to see ourselves in a different way than
we habitually do so it occurred to me to say to greet you
calling you all earthlings so you know good day earthlings
and for me that calling ourselves earthlings
immediate identification with this earth that this is our place this is our home
and that uh there's kind of a mutual kind of identification with all living beings
that are here not just human beings that share this planet and so um to
you know to have this different name like different than homo sapiens or people or something
and so this idea this ability to you know to shift our orientation
simply with a word uh can make a huge difference in meditation practice and in mindfulness
and in liberation because we often are unconsciously many times
conditioned by concepts we've internalized that our society our family
experience somehow points us in that direction so that we think in that way all the time
and i know that sometimes with um
like with kovid my son got coveted and i had had contact with him about
almost two months ago now and uh and i had contact with him before he knew he was
he had it and so he called me up and explained the situation and
so that day i was oriented towards
all kinds of little changes in my body temperature and the raspiness of my throat and
was that is that a headache or not a headache i was having and i was just like enough that my orientation became focused on different
body parts that were associated with symptoms of copaid
other times uh you know i you know there have been times my life where i've see i used to
have very long blonde hair and i remember uh seeing other people with long blonde hair and
and now i was you know concerned with comparing myself to them and my my orientation who i was through
my hair so the ways in which we understand our body
can be biased the way we orient ourselves towards our body can be to a particular lens
and that lens can be wind drag that lens can be a little bit of a weight
maybe it's a little bit negative self-talk maybe it's we orient ourselves in a way that towards ourselves that we're not happy
with our body and just connecting to our body is a little bit discouraging and
because of the orientation we have so this 32 or 31 parts of the body
exercise one of its functions is to begin shifting the way that we
understand or oriented towards our body the concepts in which we hold it by
from one that often can produce a lot of suffering to one that doesn't the one that
actually helps us become concentrated and i think so
so that's all i'll say for now so um you know we're kind of taking a
a side tour a detour right now and the kind of the simplest way of continuing
with sati patana but this is the way the text goes and maybe for good reason it's uh now that
we've kind of done the foundation work now we're continuing to lay down a stronger foundation with this
32 parts of the of the body
i keep saying 32 the usual meditation practice is 32 parts but in this discourse we're doing
there's only listed 31 the brain is left out and
so for today what i'd like to do and for the beginning of this sitting is to
do a version of this practice of the parts of the body
often people when they learn it they learn it in groups of five so i'll teach you a group of five
i'll guide you with a few rounds around how doing this and then we'll be silent and you can either continue with the
rounds and just keep doing it and see if the focus on it both
develop some concentration and also and or also um
kind of begins orient yourself to your body in a different way that maybe brings more
stability more freedom more ease maybe so see what the difference is how
you do it so
so the the five parts of the body is the
progression from the external to the internal so the first is the skin
then the flesh then the tendons then the bones
and then the bone marrow so skin tendons
skins flesh tendon bones marrow and i'll post it here on the in the chat just
if you want to see it there skin flesh tendons
bone marrow and you might try repeating it with me a few times out
loud or silently so you get the hang of it skin
flesh tendons marrow
tendons bones marrow i need to get the hang of it skin
tendons there we go again skin flesh
tendons bone marrow skin flesh
tendon bones marrow so
taking a meditation posture and
kind of maybe shaking a little bit in your body and
swaying back and forth a little bit to help you settle in
and
gently closing the eyes and letting the eyes be relaxed
some people find it helpful to imagine or feel the eyes as cool cool eyes
and then a few long slow deep breaths settling into your body as you exhale
letting your breathing come to normal
and again with the ordinary breath continue this process of
relaxing into your body softening
and then bring your attention to one of your hands
and you feel the sensations of your hands of your hand
the warmth and coolness that's there
any tingling and pulsing that might be there
any contact of the hand against some other part of the body
pressure weight softness
and then for a few moments here now focus on the sensations on the skin
the warmth or coolness that might be there
if the skin is touching something feeling the content the contact of the skin
to be aware of the skin but see if you can feel
from the sensations of skin more than your thoughts and ideas and
memories of what your hands look like we see the hand from the outside
when we look at it but we can feel the hand from the inside
to what are the sensations of the skin surface of the hand
with your eyes closed maybe no need to have an image or memory
or ideas about your hand just to feel the skin
and then to spread your attention of skin throughout your body
letting the awareness float to wherever in the body the skin
has sensations
and be aware of skin
underneath the skin is flesh
the muscles that we have
maybe it includes the fat that's there and can you kind of feel your way or
imagine your way to someplace in your body where
you feel the sensations or you sense into it the flesh that's there
the sensations that are deeper than the skin
and feel those
independent of what you think about it the ideas you have
that this exercise is giving permission for the flesh to reveal itself
in its own terms the flesh has no ideas about
how it should and shouldn't be it just is
and allow the sensations just be
and then going deeper in there's a tendons ligaments
perhaps the tendons connecting the bow to the bones
maybe you feel i can imagine them stretched if your knees are bent
maybe there's no obvious sensations but vague sense of
location or place or  shape
of tendons
the achilles tendon
and if you don't feel it then the exercise is to imagine it
imagine maybe what it looks like
and then deeper is the bones
perhaps some version of white white bones
perhaps you've seen nowadays around here a lot of life-size halloween
skeletons skull and rib cage
hips
if your ability to visualize you can visualize your bones
where you can feel or sense the hardness the solidity
the structure of the bones that hold you upright maybe
and then deep in the bones especially some of the larger bones in the body
is marrow
where blood is made life-giving blood is made
a little bit more fibrous perhaps than the outer side of the bone
imagine visualizing the marrow feeling yourself settling into the
center of some of the bones
so for a few rounds i'll just recite this five areas of the body
and let yourself follow the path from this surface to inside
feeling imagining visualizing sensing
these important parts of your physical body
without which you wouldn't be able to manage in your
life
skin
flesh
tendons
bones
marrow
i'll do it one more time and then you're on your own you can do it slower or faster or not at
all skin
flesh
tendons
bones
marrow
you
and then as we come to the end of the setting
to consider other people and maybe for them also to
see them in a new way different than the usual one
but perhaps to see them as skin flesh
tendons bones and marrow
to imagine to visualize
to reflect that they too just like you have skin
flesh tendons bones and marrow
they too have the skin that holds everything together
flesh and muscles that store nutrients and
house the muscles to which we can be active
tendons that hold the bones together
the bones they too have bones
and marrow
all material that it's arisen out of this earth
all material which is recycled
our physical beings are made up of recycled materials
atoms that are in us now and
will be somewhere else when we die
we are made from this earth
earthlings all of us
and perhaps sensing the physicality and the earthiness of each being
perhaps seeing them differently in a way that
we share so much commonality we share
our earthling-ness we share
in this endless recycling of material
may we live together as a community of earthlings may we live
together with care for each other with respect for each
other with generosity to each other
may we live together with love for each other
and may we in small or large ways
find ways to live and express that love the care the respect
for other earthlings may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
[Music]
so we're exploring the fourth exercise
of the satipatanasuta and perhaps some of you who are settling
in to the sequence from before feel like we're taking a little detour
and now we're using parts of our mind that are usually not associated with mindfulness practice
imagination reflection consideration
of these body parts that we have and
i think it's worthwhile pointing out that this is a time-honored practice in the buddhist
tradition and monastics are so many novice or new monastics this is the
first practice they're given and it's meant to set the stage the
foundation for developing practice further it kind of changes the kind of the
mental ecology in a certain way that maybe makes it easier to settle when we get back into kind of really
focusing in the in the more you know classic idea of what
mindfulness practice is and for one thing what it does it's
meant to cultivate concentration and so uh some people will memorize the list of
31 or 32 if the brain is added to it and
and then once you've memorized it just keep reciting it and some people there's a practice of doing it forward and
backwards so memorizing it from from from the
starts with the head hair it ends with urine so you go in that direction and then you do it backwards from urine to
head here and it requires focus and attention to stay on it and
keep it at a regular pace that it's very hard to think about other things and wonder off
and to keep doing it over and over again kind of like a little bit like a mantra but do it over and over again it was something that requires uh alertness and
an eff certain kind of effort uh over time that that disgrace distracted mind might quiet down and
settle and we find there's a gathering together a focusing of the mind
that then we can stop using focusing on reciting the parts of the
body and just focus now on the practice itself because we're stable or steady so
it's a way of building concentration the other thing it does is that
it shifts the orientation towards our body from one maybe if if one has a kind of
unhelpful orientation to the body for example just body image some people are caught up in body image some people
spend a tremendous amount of time fixing their body image making it just right
and and then body image often involves a lot of comparative thinking
and um the um
and the painful comparative thing a lot of suffering when we make involved in the world of comparative thinking of how
i am compared to others and to shift out of that mode the concentration is one way to do that
but to do it also to begin developing a different way of understanding perceiving the body
and to see the body not as a unified whole which sometimes lends itself to a
kind of abstract concepts but to look at the parts of the body individually as if
each of them stands out by itself and there are two uh analogies given
um known as one here one analogy given here for this particular way of seeing the body in parts
and that is um a bag like a bag of skin but a bag
that contains a lot of
rice and beans so here's the description just as if a person with good eyesight
were to look into a sack with an opening at each end filled with various kinds of seeds such as fine rice
patty rice mung beans garbanzo beans sesame seeds and husk rice
one would recognize this is fine rice this is patty rice this is mung beans these are garbanzo beans these are
sesame seeds soda practitioner reviews visualize imagines
this very body uppered from the soles of the feet downward from the head of the hair
covered with skin and full of various kinds of unclean things in this body
there is head here body here nails teeth and skin
flesh tendons bones marrow kidneys
heart uh liver diaphragm spleen
lungs large intestines small intestines contents of the stomach
feces bio phlegm um
pus and blood sweat
fat tears oil um
fat tears oil and snot
saliva fluid of the joints and
urine so the
so when we've used oneself the same way and when i imagine this bag full of seeds
and beans and different colors and be able to see each one you know clearly for what is being different from
the others and be able to see the difference but don't all blend
the same they're all different and distinct and i've i imagine these seeds has been
quite beautiful now fresh dried new seeds are so beautiful to have to see
at least i admire them and and so there's a kind of uh positive
association then with how we review this body uh even though so
this it is a house and the idea of seeing it as being unclean or
impure or something and um but we're shifting our orientation
and in a new way to these parts of the body and feeling different ways so
so to go through and have memorized the 31 parts and then to use it as a body scan
and simply go through over and over again so it's not just like a chant that you do but it's uh now it's a guided meditation
you give yourself and you go steadily through the body to feel the different parts or imagine the different parts
and so it certainly breaks can break up the hegemony of the old body image and body
ideas and body challenges that we have on image and ideas of the body to a new way of
experiencing the body that can be much more compassionate than freeing
but it also begins awakening our capacity to feel the body to be in the
body and this is also one of the great functions of this exercise is to start feeling more connected to your body
so that it becomes easier and easier to practice breathing with the whole body
sensing the whole body and the more you can feel your whole body
then as the meditation practice continues to develop it the body then becomes a better
receptor or repository for some of the good feelings that
develop through meditation some of the relaxation some of the joy some of the
delight some of the pleasures that come as we settle into the practice
and the practice can build on that foundation of well-being that
can be spreading through the body it makes it easier to stay grounded and present
so uh these are some of the functions the last function is that is um
is for people who have a lot of sexual lust and sexual imagination of partners and all
kinds of creative things human bodies can do with each other that
sometimes this 32 parts of the body are given as a way to somehow
break out of the way of considering bodies if that were required for sexual lust to happen
and maybe you don't feel like that's very interesting to do or you know valuable
to do but for people who are trying to meditate especially like a lot of meditation
and find themselves repeatedly pulled into the world of sexual fantasy sexual desires
it's one of the antidotes and so it ends up being less frustrating than trying to continually working against
you know their sexual ideas their feelings desires one has
and um and remember that this practice is often given to the new
monks you know and young men who maybe have a
you know young women nuns and maybe you have a little bit more orientation around that than
older people sometimes do so
so this is a practice of concentration of developing contact to the body
awakening the body and finding more freedom through a new connection to the body
so we'll do this uh spend one more day on this tomorrow and then we'll move on
to the next exercise and um and i hope that uh
the little contact we do here gives you some appreciation for this practice and also some sense of how it
can be beneficial and be a resource a way of practicing it at a times when
it'd be useful so hair
head hair body hair nails teeth skin and flesh tendons
bones marrow kidneys heart
liver diaphragm spleen lungs large intestines small
intestines contents of the stomach feces bile
phlegm pus blood sweat
fat tears thoughts saliva joints
fluids of the joints and urine
may you enjoy your body today may you be connected to your body
and um and curious about your body and more familiar with your body
so thank you