okay so uh so welcome welcome to you all
that's very sweet to uh see the uh
youtube sangha in the chat um
okay you know how this goes um
please uh please settle in
so sometimes we practice just
stopping all at once
sometimes we ease our way in and sometimes we stop all at once we just
open to everything now
and of course there's this kind of gravitational pull to nursing this wound
or planning that pleasure
mapping out these contingencies
so there's a certain kind of courage maybe even faith just in
stopping
meditation requires that we tolerate all the loose ends
of the human condition
we don't need to tie them up we just
stop
and we we treat all phenomena like
a gust of wind blowing through awareness
we're neither braced against that gust
nor are we trying to bottle it up
and hold on to it
it's often skillful to have
a line of definition around what is in the focus space and what is out of it
so maybe we draw a line around the sensations of the breathing
the nostrils the belly
or maybe the line includes all of the soundscape
while excluding everything else
maybe the line includes all of the body sensations
and leaves the rest of the world behind
or maybe the anchor [Music] is everything
the five sense gates the mind
but just know what's inside the circle and what's outside it
rest with a kind of balanced energy
either bracing against nor holding onto the wind
when we relinquish the agenda to
direct our life
when we just sit here
all phenomena become a kind of gateway
to wisdom love
it is not the case that only the preferred gusts of wind
or the gateway
everything is a door
we just keep walking through
when we actually open to our life
in this way when we put down some of the impulse to engineer it
just open
a kind of love for ourselves becomes almost self-evident
this love is not based on
our characteristics the pros and cons of me
but is a an appreciation of the condition of being sentient
feeling pleasure and pain longing to be safe
longing for peace amidst the intensity of samsara
and that kind of love dawns on us
and it's a love that can't really be contested
by our self-harshness and judgment
we rest in that
this takes us more deeply into the present
so it's good to good to see with you
this is the essential avaricious nature of loss
it encompasses without distinction the trivial and the consequential the abstract and the concrete
the merely misplaced and the permanently gone we often ignore the tr its true scope if
we can but for a while after my father died i could not see stop seeing the
world as it really is marked everywhere by the evidence of past losses and the
imminence of future ones this was not because his death was a
tragedy my father died peacefully at 74 attended
throughout his final weeks by those he loved most it was because his death was not a
tragedy what shocked me was that something so sad could be the normal necessary way of
things in its aftermath each individual life seemed to contain too much heartbreak
for its fleeting duration history which i had always loved even in
its silences and mysteries suddenly seemed like little more than a record of loss
on an epic scale especially
especially where it could offer no record at all the world itself seemed ephemeral
glaciers and species and ecosystems vanishing the pace of change as swift as in a time
lapse as if those of us alive today had been permitted to see it from the
harrowing perspective of eternity everything felt fragile
everything felt vulnerable the idea of loss pressed in around me
like a hidden order to existence that emerged only in the presence of
grief
it's catherine schultz from lost and found
i wasn't planning to uh to talk about this but here it goes
so when we
love in a world that changes a world that
trembles in all directions grief becomes a part of life
and we have to love something it's it's just what what mammals do
and so grief is is woven into the fabric of our biology
and um really when we we care about other
beings when we care about sentience itself grief becomes a feature of life
and so monday was helplessness how helplessness can
illuminate our power yesterday renunciation freeing us up to
enjoy pleasure more fully less compulsively
and today uh grief grief freeing us up to love more deeply
now when i use the word grief i'm not just talking about the loss of someone it's broader than that and
i'm not talking about the species of grief that debilitates us
it freezes us although that's a part of life too
but the way that the dharma interacts with the grieving heart such
that we are changed by it positively changed by it
our love is deepened by it
and spiritual practice is it's a form of growing up in a way it's
a form of growing up and growing up entails growing pains
you know sometimes like kids will get um like these diffuse pains in their legs
or something like okay no problem growing pains
and they're growing pains of spiritual maturation too for each of us
they're growing pains of evolving our sila evolving our ethical commitments
yeah of of actually growing up ethically
maya angelou said um do the best you can until you know better than when you know
better do better
we have to be willing to know
when you know better do better we have to be willing to know we have to be willing to come into a
deeper alignment with our existing values to
actually trace out those values what they mean for ourselves
in the world to come into a kind of alignment with the depth of our own heart
we're willing to be stretched to widen the circle of moral concern
and the movement of the heart in that that can feel a little like grief yeah
that circle widening you know
more and more of the world feels like
a worthy moral concern
and there are growing pains in associated with deepening compassion
yeah like when when love meets suffering there are kind of
two byproducts yeah grief
and compassion love meeting suffering
grief and compassion and the movement the movement of the the
kind of uh the clenched fist of grasping that gil often
speaks of the movement of the clenched fist of grasping to the open hand of
letting go that feels like something that movement feels like something
and it often feels like grief
not so long ago in teaching um
i sort of had this this insight arose and it was kind of like wow how did i not put this together before but
much of the fruit of practice unfolds through a process of grieving it feels
like something is being lost
and for sure something gained
now we don't have to make this some enormous
project my grieving project we're just willing to feel
willing to feel and i hold um
grief in a kind of reverential way you know it does not belong in the family of afflictive
emotion in my mind and i i can imagine a
a life that is free of agitation and anger and anxiety i could i don't
live it but i could imagine it i can imagine it i cannot imagine a life free of grieving
i don't even know exactly what that would be but it feels like it would be an
abdication of our love and care in some way
people are they're often grateful when they're given permission to grieve
to to know that this is part of the path this is the part of the path
amidst loss this is part of just the growing pains of the the evolution of
our compassion of our love the expansion of the scope of our moral concern
that the movements of letting go entails some
sense of grieving
now the the traditional phrase about the fruit of this practice is
um beyond you know
beyond grief sorrow lamentation and despair yeah we get beyond griefs our
lamentation and despair but
i want my buddha to grieve
maybe not maybe that is controversial but um
just for me i want my buddha to grieve
grief is um it's redeemed by different things we're certainly redeemed by art
but um but also by growing our love yeah
and a love that is uninformed by
grief is a naive love what we
what we find in a in in uh
grief is that um the ego is just all out of moves
do you know that feeling those moments where it's just like the
ego is all out of moves there's no energy for it to move in this way
or that way and there's some beauty and opportunity
in that itself and so we do this work um
for ourselves it's important for ourselves it's important for our society because the failure
[Music] to grieve the failure to let go
that spills out it spills out and
it the failure to grieve can distort our love you know
our love becomes too reticent or too controlling
and so yeah the courage to love is the willingness to grieve
and when we're willing the love deepens less reticent
less controlling
sometimes our hearts fully enlightened beings are described as being consummate in shame
consummate and shame and what's being alluded to is hiri and otapa and the
shame around moral transgression around causing horror consummate in shame i'm
always struck by that translation
i wonder maybe it's possible
to be consummate in grief too
um it's possible i am pushing through solid rock
flint-like layers as the or lies alone
i am such a long way in i see no way through and no space
everything is close to my face and everything close to my face is stone
i don't have much knowledge yet in grief so this massive darkness makes me small
you be the master make yourself fierce break in
then your great transforming will happen to me and my great grief cry
will happen to you
for this for consideration it's good to
be able to talk about these things together
you