so good morning everyone and welcome to our meditation time together
and i'd like to offer you a little exercise today
and now it's not meant to have you be busy but actually help you maybe become quieter and attentive
tranquil and alert and
as you know a big part of mindfulness practice is
being mindful of the present moment and the question is
how long is the present moment and i'd like to propose that
independent of any logic that you might use or other things that
the present moment certainly can be seen as in an instant
it could also be seen as uh some little span of time
maybe a second there's a sense of as we are present
mindful of now of this moment there is a sense of some continuity of
the moment some fullness of the moment some uh span of the moment
and um it's not exact it's not in different contexts that span might be
different but it's partly this length the span of it is
related to the knowing that is aware that this is the present
moment that um
that uh you know it's kind of like the timeless moment that's there for a
little while as we're here as we're present but then mind wanders off or maybe it doesn't feel like a timeless
moment but it feels like um it's a a um as we say what's happening now
and there's a little kind of pause or little opening that little
amount of time to take in now and so the question is how long
is your present moment how long is the now for you
and it'll come and go it'll be there for a few as long as it is
and something will happen and and uh you know you
reset it you find it again and you find it again and there might be even a sense that you're in a river of time
and that you're kind of somehow maybe um kind of i don't know you're you're in
the current of it for a while and in an eddy or in a current of it for a while then
maybe you've you've gotten stuck on a branch sticking out from the shore of
the river or and then you're back in the current and but the current how long is that current
or the present moment for you and and if you if you're interested in this
exercise maybe um you can um try to do it in such a way
that the mind becomes quieter stiller tranquil and alert
maybe because the mind that's tranquil and alert that's not trying to think about this
is [Music]
the one that reveals the richest feeling the richest sense of this
moment now so to take a
alert posture
and gently close your eyes
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale maybe extending the exhale
a bit to allow for a deeper relaxation
and letting your breathing return to normal
and then see if for a few moments you can give yourself over
to relax further maybe each time you exhale
relaxing the muscles of the face those muscles can fall away from the
skull maybe
it's held in place by the skin
no work on your part to keep your face together
softening around the eyes
the forehead
relaxing the shoulders
maybe relaxing down the arm and into the hands allows the shoulders to relax further
softening in the belly
deep relaxation the belly the torso
to relax the body
is to begin to abide peacefully
here and now
breathing in and exhaling relaxing the thinking mind
letting the thinking mind become quieter
maybe thinking is slower
maybe thinking has pauses between the sentences or
images
okay
and then to center yourself from the body breathing
noticing where on your body is its easiest
to experience the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
or where in the body is it most pleasant
to feel the body's experience of breathing
and if you're aware of breathing in the present moment
how long is that present moment
how long are you in the knowing of the present
moment
is it brief touching in is it somehow extended
through time through a timeless time
and how long is the present moment if you're relaxed
at ease with it a leisurely present moment
being with your breathing
to be mindful aware
attune to this present moment
is an attunement to the present moment
that's independent of past and future
independent of time just now
paradoxically for the duration that your mind can rest
in this moment
hello
so
and within this present moment for however long it
extends for you personally there is change
the breathing the body experience of breathing changes
like a current in a river
always in the present
or like standing on a bridge over a river and looking down in the timeless present
the current keeps flowing
relaxing into the present moment is to relax into the
current of change
perhaps experience these most easy
in the changing sensations of breathing through the inhale and the exhale
relaxing and settling into this present moment
maybe near this after sitting for these minutes
maybe there's a better sense of an extended present moment
not something we search for but something with
which within something within which we rest
trust
the gentle current flow river
of the present moment
forever long it lasts and then again
and again
and as the sense of the present present time
becomes more extended and relaxed and open
we have the greater capacity to know
to sense to feel others
and our connection to others her response
and may our ability to be present for others be present for
ourselves in an open extended way no hurry
may it be a time for respect and care and
a deeper attentiveness
to the full humanity of all of us
and may this deeper connection be the wellspring of our care for the
world a care which is simultaneously a caring for what's best
in ourselves may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may our attention ability to pay attention
support us in making this a better world
[Music]
[Music] thank you
oh
this
so this week
i'm taking the time to talk about the five descriptions of the dharma in the famous expression
the dharma is well spoken by the buddha
it is visible here and now it is immediate
it invites us to see it is onward leading
and to be known by the wise
and so today this idea that it's immediate that pali word is akaliko
a k long a l i k o or a
and it's um the etymology of it is
not in time not of time and so
some people will translate it as timeless but that suggests something that
that's a wonderful experience if we leave it just as an experience experience of being in a
timeless moment but sometimes when the word timeless is used
it goes along with some idea that there's some there's a transcendent place that
very far removed from this world here kind of a transcendent consciousness or
something and at least that's how i hear some people talk about
it uh it um probably a little bit more literal
meaning is rather than timeless is not of time
in the sense of being immediate and and when the buddha doesn't when buddha
kind describes what he means by akaliko this knot of time
he refers to it as the ability to be with the present moment
as it's changing as it flows as it arises and passes
and this ability to really be in the present not in the static present but the
dynamic present that's how it's immediate
so that's how it's and out of time because the immediate flow
in the moment it takes it takes time takes a little more different more complicated
or active activity of the mind to have a sense of the past and the future and to bring it into the present
but the present by itself and um and so with it it's in the it's a
dhamma is a kaliko the dhamma is not of time because change the seeing of change is
immediate it's it's a part of the immediacy of attention here and now
and um and of course you can argue that well whenever there's change
there has to be some sense of time but
but if you say immediacy in the immediate present really there
then there is the sense of watching flowing with the changing nature of time
but what do i find even more interesting about this um you know
alcalico this immediacy the immediacy of now the present moment
is that the human sense of how long the present moment is
variable i would say that for myself if i'm playing ping pong
the present moment is quite short but if i'm
laying on the lawn in the park on a nice day looking up at the sky at the drifting of
the clouds going by the present moment kind of has a feeling of being more
extended more relaxed than uh the rapidity of the present
moment in ping-pong and um and so there's a
it's somewhat subjective this experience of what is the present moment how long is it
how long has it extended the
william james the american philosopher called the president referred to the saddleback of the
present moment you know rather than being like that it's last briefly for a kind of a
saddleback it and maybe i don't know it comes and then it goes
like the bottom of a wave maybe a trough and so um
and it does it extend up the sides of the trough of any period of time or is it just the
very bottom of the trough and i think his idea is it extends somewhere in some
indeterminate way up the edges of the saddle and
something like that so but again what i find most interesting is that
how we live our life it can be seen in relationship
to our sense of how long this present moment is that when there's greed
when there's fear anxiety panic when there is um uh hatred
these are emotions that want something to happen right now or fear afraid of something that's going
to happen now and so of sometimes there's a quickening of the mind a quick hitting sense of
time quickening reactivity and the faster the reactivity
it's kind of like ping-pong it's the faster the reactivity the impulsive activity
the um you know the the shorter the moment is
uh and when there's a very short moment with that very like rapidity of things
uh we might not even be aware of time or the timeless present we might not be
aware of the you know what's really going on more importantly though i think
is that as that sense of time becomes a little more extended and more leisurely there's more space for the moment to be
there and so the present moment you know the with the trough of the wave
becomes wider um then there is more opportunity
for some of the deeper reactivity responses emotions that we have
that are don't come from reactivity but come from some deeper wellspring
within to operate and i think so i in my sense vikkan is
not so not to make an absolute case for this but generally
things like greed and hatred
anxiety
i are kind of needed for human beings in order to be able to respond quickly
to threats to what's going on that have to be immediately taken care of and maybe that's one of the reasons why
these emotions began for human beings evolutionarily but when they're chronic in us and
always there it kind of leads to kind of stress and and kind of a rapidity and a fast mind
and a spinning mind and probably a kind of tendency to create a lot of cortisol maybe even
adrenaline stress in the body stress systems in the body stress hormones
and and those limit our capacity to feel
the emotions the attitudes that have more to do
with um being relaxed being at ease maybe maybe have more to do
with um oxytocin or serotonin or different kind of hormones and chemicals in us
that require maybe a different kind of relaxation and ease to come forth
and so qualities like generosity and love and kindness and friendliness
these these feelings belong to the world of extended
time where there isn't the rapidity and it's kind of like again if you're
you know really maybe caring for someone who maybe is
distressed or hurt or maybe someone a child is hurt that
maybe the child is not hurt that badly but is upset then the parent or the adult who's there
maybe the person who's there it's just there an extended way caring
giving lots of time and space not kind of like you know tapping the finger and saying you know get over it you know and
yes i care for you and stop it because we have important things to do it's like okay now we're here
someone who's dying and we're accompanying their death we're just there
and uh and hopefully peaceful at ease extended sense of time or when i've been with
people who are dying the present moment seemed very extended like timeless present everything had
stopped i'm just there and i'm tapping into something or what's
arising inside of me is very different than if i'm driving my car in a crowded freeway and
late for something and it's smoggy and trying to find my quickest way that i need to get to where i'm going
that that tends to elicit all kinds of other emotions feelings then care and love and
generosity so this idea of the akaliko the immediacy of now in this
practice the dhamma is immediate it's now but in this extended now
in this more available and present relaxed time
and i don't know if it's okay to say a leisurely present moment and not because we are kind of basking
in luxury with the leisurely present moment but rather the relaxed and open here and
now with this allows for some deeper wellsprings of our life
to appear that cannot appear if we're
in the rapidity of greed hate and delusion the wanting the monkey mind that's reaching for the
next branch before it has as soon as it grabs one branch it's
reaching for the next branch if our mind is that way always reaching going going going it doesn't give a lot of room
for some of the most valuable parts of who we are and um
the valuable parts that don't seem to have any obvious monetary value or obvious status value or obvious
obvious value and getting what we want maybe from life but this deeper place
that has lots of
time for time where we give we have a lot of time
for the immediacy of now for this moment and this moment just seems to be to extend
and maybe even extend and become longer and longer and
then how long can it last this timeless now for you
so the dhamma the dharma is immediate
it doesn't belong to time and how long can you rest in this timeless moment
and can you extend it and what are the benefits of that for you and so i would suggest that this would
be a great day for you to experiment with this um take take time
to do this take time maybe even put a timer on your on your if you have if you have a like clock you
can time maybe once an hour or randomly or something
through the day experiment with giving more time making room a
pause to see if you can and experience the extended present moment
you know if you're playing ping pong stop playing or the equivalent stop doing it and sit down and let there be an
extended pause maybe as you have a cup of tea or something and see what's available to you that's
different than in the rapidity of some of the things that we're doing what happens what shifts in you
what comes so the dhamma is akalikos
immediate is
now is not of time
so thank you and and
we'll continue this tomorrow
foreign