well it's uh it's quite wonderful to see all the
greetings i know the chat today and all the different ways it said in
different languages and even different ways of saying it in english
different areas so thank you it's so wonderful to feel the richness and
the variety and i think every every language every
ethnicity every person is a gift and it's nice to kind of feel
the giftness of it all in one place so um
i didn't see it in my native language which is norwegian so good morning
and other languages that i've spoken through my life so far is italian which is a
bona matina for good morning and and french
bon mater and japanese ohio gozaimasu and i don't speak
sign language but good morning in sign language as you say the the the gesture for the sign for good
like that and then the sign for um morning
so it's uh so
here we are
so um we continue here on this adventure on
with attention i think one the whole area of buddhist practice buddhist meditation
is i think of it as an adventure a wonderful journey to discover
ever ever discover keep discovering aspects of our ability to
be conscious ability to be attentive and it's such a rich multifaceted domain
and and it gets richer when we start appreciating
the potential for awareness for attention to bring us
freedom to bring us peace and how to
unhook attention from our reactivity unhook our awareness
from our judgments and our preferences and to free
mindfulness from a certain kind of self-referencing a certain kind of self-preoccupation
and so these are some of the things we're discovering in this process and um one of the ways that this text we're
looking at this talks about it is in the end is uh to um
to abide not clinging to anything but to abide consciously aware
so for now i'd like to emphasize that um that it's a discovery process to
discover how knowing the simple capacity to recognize something
can be done radically in a radically simple way and that's one of the
stepping stones for this satipatanas mindfulness path
is to begin discovering how knowing can become simpler and simpler
and uh just know without the baggage that comes along without the entanglement with being for
or against the experience so um
it can at first begin to feel kind of plain and boring and dull just to know something
but as that sense of knowing gets stronger and gets developed it begins filling out and becoming
broader or more expansive more freeing more peaceful
more happiness producing so um
to um so to begin with a little exercise
and that is to close your eyes and bring your attention to some part of
your body that feels neutral someplace in your body where you have sensations but the sensations are not
particularly pleasant or unpleasant comfortable or uncomfortable
if they're a little bit that's fine and it could be where your
something your hands are touching could be the contact of your lips against each other
it to just find a sensation in your body that's relatively neutral
and then in the simplest way be aware of it
if you're observing it imagine that you are looking at it from above from below from the sides
it's kind of scanning it to feel it more fully
and then have a few moments of recognition
maybe it's pressure maybe it's warmth coolness
tingling vibration whatever it might be and if you're not sure what it is just
maybe recognize it as sensation
and then continue with this little act of recognition of what it is
and see if you can experiment with having that recognition be very simple
almost as if it creates space around the experience
so you're recognizing whatever the sensation is in and of itself
in terms of itself without a past or a future
without meaning and purpose and to the sensation
maybe even without self-reference just a sensation
and then you can also continue to know it gently simply
and if you use a little kind of act moment of recognition for naming it for
what it is let that recognition be like dropping a pebble in
a still pond and then
be there to feel the ripples to feel more fully it's like you're opening a door
window recognize and then feel and experience
the sensation more fully
in a peaceful mind an open mind
open awareness to the sensation
and now with the same attention
have your awareness become aware of breathing
wherever in your body you usually experience your breathing
see if you can have the same simple awareness of the sensations of breathing
being aware of breathing on its own terms the sensations
as they are not taught not how you want them to be
not what you're trying to accomplish
as if the sensations of breathing have permission to be there just as they
are they can be themselves
and you know it know the sensations of breathing
knowing and inhale as an inhale
knowing the sensations of exhale as exhale
and then also becoming becoming aware of the quality or the characteristics of
the knowing in knowing your breathing
are you in a hurry is there strain
are you trying to make something happen
is there some concern that something special is supposed to happen
how simple can you let your knowing be of the knowing of breathing
and can you appreciate that knowing simple open
peaceful where there's a joining of knowing
and breathing one inhalation at a time
one exhalation at a time
instead of thinking about things know what's happening with your
breathing is your breathing
loose or tight
are they long or short
shallow or deep
without any judgment or need for it to be any way any particular way let your breathing be
itself and you simply know it
as if you're going along accompanying the breathing
listening deeply as you would with a friend who you're listening to
accompanying your breathing with your capacity to know it
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
considering how attention
is a gift that we can give to others
when we listen to them carefully it's a gift
when we see them clearly in the world where people often often
are not seen it's a gift
if we are present for others it's a gift in a world where people are
often not don't take the time to be present for each other
and may we at the end of this meditation
dedicate the cultivation of attention that we do here
to bringing a richer more valuable attention
to the world around us to the people in our lives
and with that attention may it promote the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
so probably this will be the last more introductory talk for the sati patana
suta the discourse on the four foundations for
awareness the foundations upon which we can grow a particular valuable particularly
valuable form of awareness awareness and
the text begins with this
confident statement that there is a direct path a direct way
a direct journey to um and the word the word is maybe more like
a going a direct going to um
to freedom through liberation and what is this direct way the text
asks and then it then the buddha then describes it and in shorthand
he first says [Music] to observe
the body in its own terms the body in terms of a body
to know feelings in terms of feelings to know
mental states in terms of mental states and to know mental processes in terms of
mental processes and this word in terms of uh in the literal
language it says it's if you really did a literal translation it would say the body in the body the feelings in the
feelings mind states in mind states and mental processes in mental processes
but this uh this word in or this the grammatical form that gives us in can
also mean in in terms of in regards to in respect to and the usual interpretation for this is
that the observation is meant to be very simple
and the word observe here such an important one our ability to kind of settle back in a
nice comfortable easy chair and just see what's happening without
judging it or fixing it or doing anything with it this kind of very
spacious and peaceful way of just to watch just to see and
and to do so the body in terms of the body meaning not in terms of our judgments in terms
of our memories in terms of the other mind states
in terms of mental processes just the same radical simplicity being with the body
so to observe it that's the way to do it but i use the example of sitting in an easy
arm chair and just kind of watching it as a kind of as a reference point for it
but the text actually says to do it ardently
and i love the word ardent to do it with certain kind of engagement like really there
and then and do it with awareness and do it with a clear
comprehension clear recognition of what's happening having
put aside covetousness covetousness and distress for the world
now suddenly it becomes kind of a tall order of this whole thing it's not easy to be able to observe
without judging to fearing thinking about things reacting
let alone being in the present moment it's not easy to apply a certain kind of
healthy peacemaking urgency and it's not not easy to maintain a
continuity of awareness a continuity of clear comprehension and it's not easy to put aside
the greeds we have the covetousness the wantings we have or the distress we have
and um but that's the uh so what this text is doing saying there is a path to freedom
away go this is the way to go to freedom but uh maybe recognizing it's not easy
to do that then the text goes on and offers 13 exercises
for how to get there and the first one is this
first tetrad of anapanasati is being attentive to breathing in a certain way which we'll go through over the next few
days and after that as as a person learns this exercise
then that exercise is onward leading things move and there's you're part of
this journey this ongoing this going this movement and the buddha's teachings is full of
movement and it's not about
only about going nowhere being no one doing nothing
which is a wonderful teaching in a limited way of understanding it but it's not the full teaching
the buddha's teachings are this kind of ongoing quality of it now if you uh
went to the playground and there's a child on a slide in the top of the slide and you
said to the child oh let me give you some profound spiritual teaching there's nowhere to go nothing to do and
no one to be just sit and just sit and do nothing um
the um the child would just be like perplexed or like a child might be a wiser that knows what
they're there if the child is there for the fun of the process of going down the slide
and um and they're up there to do that and there's a kind of a kind of it's as they're not greedy for it they're not
maybe or they're not it's not it's not like trying to prove themselves to anyone they're not trying to accomplish
any great thing like they'd be the best slide maker in the world they're just going to go down the slide for the fun of the slide
so i use that as a as a reference point for
there is a kind of leaning into or into the slide into this onto the slope
of mindfulness of this practice it's not only about staying exactly
where you are and nothing ever changes the language of change though that the
buddha uses that is bhavana which as i understand it means something
like to cultivate or to develop as you would a farmer would or gardener would cultivate a plant
or you a parent would help a child develop by feeding them and treating them well
so that in a healthy way they can physically and psychologically develop
that the parent is not stretching the child so they grow faster we're allowing a natural process to
unfold so the same way with this mindfulness practice there's a radical simplicity
being aware of the body in and of itself being being aware of breathing just a
simplicity of breathing knowing it and being allowing for the possibility that you're
on a slide or there's a growth or development that goes on here so the text begins
with a promise or you know kind of some people call it promise that there is a direct way to
freedom the way you do it is observing is this
very strong this kind of mature place of mindfulness to observe the body
in and of itself feelings mental states and mental
processes but the heart of the of the text is then the exercises that it gives and we'll go
through the 13 exercises after each exercise
there's a refrain it's usually called a refrain and that's the part that goes
gets repeated over and over again for those of you here monday when i read the
my synopsis of of this whole process the refrain was represented by
the expression observing change in the body abiding not clinging to anything in the
world and the refrain itself continues a journey it actually is a four part
journey a three or four part journey that is describing and unfolding that goes through
observing change in such a way that
the awareness gets more and more clarified purified simplified
until awareness becomes
kind of lucid and it's so lucid that then we then we
can relax into it then it's kind of like relaxing into a long wonderful comfortable slide down a
hill we then the process takes over and
the process of deepening meditation takes over that leads to non-clinging to freedom
and and so it's important not to be in a hurry to
go through all this it's important not to hopefully to get discouraged but actually i find it phenomenally
inspiring this idea that the buddha describes a process of growth the process process of
unfolding we're not expected to be free just quickly like okay like instant
enlightenment as some people would like to have it but rather there's something very mature
and maturing about settling down for the long term
and beginning to putting the steady pieces in place of
of developing cultivating growing awareness our ability to have
be more and more present in the present moment with awareness with attention
to learn the art of resting in there and opening to it so that it's peaceful so that it's inspiring so that it's
happiness producing so that it's it has there's a goodness to it that we open up to as we uh cultivate
and develop this simple capacity to be aware as we go through the text uh
different um faculties of attention
are called into play at different times and i think of attention is kind of like
the the swiss army knife of the mind it has all these different tools that can be used
and so at different times we learn these different tools and apply them each of them useful at
different times different circumstances to help us be present with our experience and not only be present but
to have the kind of awareness that is onward leading that has space in it
peacefulness in it that's not complicated by our expectations and our
pushing and our wanting uh it's just kind of like making space
for the organic cultivation organic development maturation
that leads to freedom and so
today the emphasis was discovering more and more about this
quality of knowing recognition and how knowing and wrecking recognizing
things has a power to it and a beauty to it and a and a kind of
a peacefulness to it um sometimes to name something
is a uh gives some kind of space in the heart the mind oh it's been named oh it's like that yes that's how it is
someone might say that you know there's a lot of tension here and um in the group and then oh you someone named it finally
oh yes that's what's happening and then everyone kind of relaxes a little bit
so so to do that with the breathing
to establish attention establish awareness with breathing and then to know the breathing
and as we know it to begin discovering some of the qualities of knowing or
discover how to know so that knowing is unburdened
with all the baggage we carry with us it's so simple and to feel the delight or the peace or
the freedom from the disentanglement from that
simple knowing at first it might seem like it's nothing it's like it's okay what's the big deal
but uh to um it's a big deal to develop this capacity
to know beautiful thing to do so um
thank you we're norwegian mangan tuck and
molto grazia so i look forward to our time tomorrow