so good morning I had to turn off the speakers at the
the speaker system had been left completely on so then I hear the booming speakers that
are above me in the wall and it's nicer just to be here with all of you
without that extra voice coming in so um
to begin
when we sit down to meditate we can ask ourselves
are we ready to be in the present moment
are we ready to be receptive and present and engaged nicely in the present moment
in a way it might be interesting or evocative to say that
the present moment is always ready for you are you ready for it
is the Mind ready and this mind that we have can be busy and
caught up in thoughts and ideas and feelings and agendas preferences many things
that might interfere with the capacity to be ready
to be available and ready available
for this moment to receive receptive
and sometimes it takes part of the meditation
a lot of the meditation period for the mind to finally be present enough where we can say it's available
to the present it's ready for the present it's ready to allow something to grow and develop
and one of those things is a greater Readiness a greater receptivity a
greater availability to really feel sense be here
in what can be called our experience
and that's a Choice expression because it means what we're experiencing not what we're
thinking so much what we're experiencing is always here in the present
we might have agendas about it and preferences but those interfere with our ability to
be ready available receptive here
so to begin this process of readying the mind
to assume a meditation posture
a posture itself that
if someone saw you could see that this posture is
available for the present is here attentive
is awake alert if you are sitting back a lot in a chair
take a few maybe just a two minutes or so to sit up and as straight as you would
if you suddenly heard a you know maybe a car come up to your
house that sounded like that car of an old very good friend like oh what's that I hear and you sit up to kind of like
pay attention what's this it's just maybe for a couple of minutes
to get a sense of in a certain kind of alertness
which is ready available for here
gently closing your eyes
being receptive to the experience of your body taking a few long slow deep
breaths
relaxing the body as you exhale long exhale
maybe slightly longer long enough to get your attention it's
time to breathe in
so the inhale is a little bit more conscious than automatic
letting your breathing return to normal
and what would it be like now sitting here quietly to establish a Readiness of Mind
Readiness of attention for whatever might happen during this
meditation that you're available
to be attentive kind of Readiness where nothing is a
surprise is just one more thing to with this too
is the experience of the moment
Readiness which is not assertive but rather receptive available
may be ready available even for what would be unexpected
relaxing the body
where the more relaxed you are
the more receptive ready available
and then settling into the experience of breathing settled and ready
as if each breath is a new event each breath as if it's Unique and almost
like the first breath ready for it
available as the breath is
if this time now was the beginning of the meditation
will your Readiness be different
your receptivity availability to the present moment
has it changed over these minutes
foreign
and as we come to the end of the sitting
is there something about how you are right now
that feels more ready available
in a relaxed way in a receptive way
maybe it's in your body
maybe it's in your mind or your heart
symptom part of you is more settled
at ease so that it's open and available
for whatever Here and Now
and then coming to the end of the sitting to invite into your
mind your attention your thoughts
other people who you might encounter today
people you know strangers on the street stores
people that you might somehow encounter on your screen and media
and is there a way of being ready receptive
to others that helps you tap into
appreciate appreciation of others Good Will of others
for others a generosity of spirit
of attention for others
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this beginning of the week is uh
weekdays week that is between these two holidays that we have
kind of a some ways a liminal or limbo or alternative kind of
week for many people and um
we have a new theme so last week the topic was the four
right efforts where the emphasis is to let go or
the unwholesome and develop the wholesome and today this for this week I wanted to
talk about five wholesome States that can be cultivated and developed
that are appreciate could be appreciated in our lives
and it's not the common wholesome states that this early Buddhist tradition is maybe most associated with
um often the Buddha would begin had Dharma talked to lay people especially
on topic of generosity and generosity is often a preeminent wholesome state in
our tradition he might also talk about uh states of
ethical integrity kind of a wholesome integrity
there might be meditative joy and happiness tranquility
the variety of things that are fairly well known in our tradition and but for this week I want to do
something which is not so emphasized or hardly at all that um the Buddha put a particular
emphasis on an importance of as Holston states to be developed or cultivated or
to be evoked in preparation for real insight to really be able to
see deeply into the nature of our hearts our minds Our Lives
and um and so uh these five wholesome States
are to be are a Readiness of mind
a malleability of Mind a mind free of hindrances
a a
think they uh a I forget the fourth moment the fifth
is a bright mind or a confident mind so ready receptive free of hindrances
right at the moment maybe some of you remember the fourth but we'll get to it it somehow it slipped my mind
and um so these are five states that the Buddha would evoke in people in
preparation for giving the deepest Dharma he has the deepest teachings he had
and so he would give a Dharma talk to to prepare people for deep teachings and
prepare and these are the five ways in which he prepared their minds so the first is the word is kala
k-a-l-l-a and it's um it's usually translated as a ready mind
a Readiness of mind it's a mind that's receptive that is available
that's prepared in order to receive something really significant to be
and um and so one of the functions of meditation is in fact to cultivate
this Readiness of mind the Zen masters of Suzuki roshi the
founder of San Francisco Zen Center and his books and my beginner's mind his definition of mindfulness
was is in fact Readiness of mind and to be ready and available to attend
to whatever might be coming up next the next thing that arrives in the present moment
if we're distracted if we're already retro respective thinking like thinking
back at what just happened then we're not there for the next moment the next moment
and um and this art of being able to let go of what just happened enough not to
think about it dwell in it to really be fresh and available ready for the next moment is a phenomenal gift when many
people feel like they're obligated to review and think about and criticize and
comment and be way down by what happened in the past even if it's just a few
moments before and this Readiness it's always available always open for the next thing the next
thing um is uh is um a mind which is prepared
a mind which is receptive is available to be changed
and this is one of the aspects of Readiness of mind is to be ready and
available to be changed there's some idea that a real dialogue with other
people if you have a conversation that it's a dialogue a dialogue is only possible if each person is willing to be
changed if we're stubborn or resistant and kind of in a dialogue or in you know
some kind of serious conversation with someone and we're not willing to change there's not possible possibility of
dialogue of dialogue in this kind of definition is one where maybe each
person is changed by the conversation they learn something new they see something new they understand something
in a new way or so the same thing with meditation
are you available to be changed and now I don't think that's such an
easy thing to be because of the intensity in which many of us will be
involved in our concerns our beliefs our attitudes that we have
and and so we're holding on to it or resisting something or we're we're hunkered down or tight or Frozen in time
even sometimes and so part of meditation practice and
in time of the Buddha part of a Dharma talk was to engage people in such a way
engage yourself in such a way that something softens and opens and relax
and you kind of finally arrive here turning point in meditation practice is
arrival when you really feel I'm here I've arrived I'm in the present moment
of course you are you always are but the mind the attention the thoughts are not
and so in a sense uh the life energy is going someplace else and when your
Consciousness conscious alive attention
settles here on this moment then we've arrived
and that's the beginning of being available of being ready
uh kind of receptivity and um
the so part of understanding this
is to understand that it's important it's valuable appreciate the role in place of this
kind of Readiness here and understanding what gets in the way
of it and so each of us probably has the top Tunes the top
um maybe three concerns ways of being in the mind that
prevent us from being ready it might be that we have chronic anxiety
about what's happening and needing to plan and so the planning is to get ready
but it's not being ready for whatever's here that kind of willingness to almost
not know not assert not to project onto life because we're anxious or we
want and other top one which might be
wanting pleasure wanting good things wanting to light and wanting
is not a bad thing in and of itself but it can uh if it's two Intense or two and caught
up in it then we're not available we're not present for what's actually here
the art of having desire is having Desire with such a light touch
that it doesn't blind us to hear and now
and then there's also the top kind of what interferes with maybe Readiness is
some preoccupation about the past emotional preoccupation maybe resentment
maybe Delight or some kind of
reviewing and some kind of trying to figure out or
um so in many ways so those are possibilities but what are the what are the top three ways in which your mind
operates that interferes with your mind being ready
your mind being uh present in a way that doesn't overlay your
preoccupations your projections your your knowing your belief that you know
what's happening your belief that in your opinions about what's happening her Readiness is a willingness to put
those opinions aside as if so we can see and hear and know in it as if everything
is new and in a certain way they are
and if we don't see in this way that everything is new then
there's a way in which we limit the possibilities for our own transformation
the our own way of being changed which is part of the purpose of
cultivating this Readiness of mind because the ultimate purpose the Buddha gave for this was to give deep teachings
in order to awaken people in order to what he called opening the Dharma eye
so um the
so a wholesome state to be cultivated We Begin by appreciating it the value of
it the value of having a readiness and
availability and then to evoke it or recognize it in ourselves
and let it expand Let It Grow let it push against the edges of what
gets in the way of that so you really see the what interferes with it
and um and then
experiment with what it's like to live in this world ready available receptive
with a kind of not knowing mind meaning that you know the mind doesn't assert or insist that it knows
everything it's available so uh this is a wonderful wholesome
state of mind that supports wholesome life supports a wise life
supports a compassionate life supports the ongoing
development of this practice that we do and and it's one of five states that the
Buddha emphasized and we'll go through the next four and maybe all in in
preparation for the coming year maybe we're getting ready
for uh for 2023.
so thank you very much and I appreciate this chance to be with you all