so a warm welcome everyone to happy hour
so for today's practice the theme
of the practices of the heart i wanted to invite us to
to explore this amazing beautiful
powerful empowering [Music] emotion
that is part of the hard qualities we usually don't talk about it so much
in happy hour i think i've talked about it before maybe a couple of times i think
but the topic is all all having a sense of awe
just can be so supportive for opening our hearts our minds to our
life to this precious human birth instead of yeah yeah yeah okay what do i have to do
or whatever just kind of we go through life often
um with our eyes closed sleep walking we sleep
walk through this this amazing this incredible
being alive being human we're so concerned
with activities with the objects of the mind
we're so concerned about the thoughts that arise about the suffering that arises about
the peace about what we want about the desires about the pushing away about wanting we're so
concerned with all of that that we become um
single visioned single visioned as if we have put blinders on
as if we are in a darkened room with a flashlight we're just focusing
the flashlight on what we want what we don't want what we
need to get done the distractions so with awe
we get to turn on the light of the whole room instead of just turning around with the
flashlight we turn on the light of the whole room and we look around
just it's amazing not just that the objects but the fact that
there is consciousness there is a mind there is presence this this being this
aliveness that we take for granted
i mean it's amazing that anything exists at all it's amazing that we exist at all it
it it's it's just america we do and we don't quite if we really really
sit to think about it we can't quite understand any of this being existing it's such a
miracle it's a quandary that anything exists at all that that we exist that we
can think and cognize and talk and it's just such a
sense of miracle even if we have a scientist materialistic perspective
which is great with that even with that it's this miracle of consciousness is just not
explained just cannot be this feeling of being in this body and
being alive is so amazing that if we really
take it in we would want to fall to our knees and kiss the ground
for just this amazing i mean if if we were say some other
animal and then for a little you know for a day we were told okay now you can be human
be human and like oh this is amazing this is incredible
whereas we just take it for granted wake up in the morning brush our teeth
whatever whatever anyway so oh and all can really support us
on the path to awakening on the path to to
liberation not suffering however way putting that works for you
because when we get too stuck in our ways um
[Music] we lose we lose track of the bigger picture it's as if we have this
tunnel vision as i said as if we're looking through a small hole and all allah allows us to to expand our
vision to expand our vision and um and be
more present for our life and we'll have a more expansive vision
not get stuck so much not get stuck in what
troubles us etc etc so you'll discover for
yourself i've said enough to to set the frame so
so let's explore for ourselves and see what happens and then one last thing i want to say is
is whatever arises or does not arise be kind to yourself
no need for self-judgment no need for self-judgment instead of okay now i want
all all needs to come up yeah maybe it doesn't come up right now maybe
you know it's like a shy kitty we we encourage it maybe
it'll come later tonight or tomorrow or sometime this week you're taking a walk in the middle of nature and all of a
sudden you're struck by awe so
let's let yourself swim in these teachings i mean all may not be on demand we're just planting seeds we're
just planting seeds okay so so with that
let's settle ah let's rest
let's arrive arrive each moment a new arrival
in this body even if there is unpleasantness
[Music] even if there is pain present
arriving arriving with open arms
as if we're embracing our minds and praise
whatever is
ah
with fresh eyes with beginner's eyes in this body as if
as if you were a martian just now you were allowed this privilege
of stepping into this human body to experience wow
what is it like to be in a human body
this martian [Music] has a sense of appreciation novelty of
for experiencing all the sensations of this body
that is yours hello oops
huh
i'm taking every surprise every surprise
with a sense of awe every surprise in the mind and the body
allowing the awareness to connect with the breath
and breath of breath
the miracle of this body knowing how to breathe
on its own
releasing releasing tightness tension holding thoughts
releasing
letting there be ease the belly
in the limbs and your feet your sit bones
shoulders
awareness connecting with the entirety of the breath
appreciation and awe as much as it's available not pushing
not demanding but tilling the soil
what if you were resting in awe not so active
but as if it were a warm pool of water
calming soothing inspiring
holding you your tired muscles body
working through you in whatever ways
in whatever ways
your heart needs to be touched
maybe maybe this swarm pool of water
imbued with awe
which you're resting relaxing into
which you're soaking in allows your awareness to be imbued with all
so that whatever comes in contact
whatever comes in contact
with awareness awareness holds whatever
thought whatever sensation
there is all quality of awe
very subtle but there
safe awarenesses receiving the breath
sensations of the breath
the quality of all
is there receiving
awareness imbued intertwined with awe
receiving the objects of the mind and the body
don't try too hard let it be relaxed at ease your practice
just sitting and being breathed
amazing the thoughts arise on their own
pretty amazing
that sensations are sensed on their own
notice no effort is needed
it's just happening on its own
rolling rolling on and on the field of experience
sensed and known
c
if you find mind is thinking no need for judgment be
in all the thoughts arise on their own seemingly with no
control they just arise pretty amazing
bring all not judgment
to your awareness
so
i'd like to suggest some invitations like to consider
this body of ours
is made of cells so many living cells
that communicate interact we're alive
our immune system and marvel of ingenuity
communicating repairing [Music] remembering
so many brilliant mechanisms
this body that we don't quite understand
both personally and the state of the art of science
our cut
filled with so many
other bacteria that are helpful
that we wouldn't be able to live or digest food
if it wasn't for this host of helpful healthy bacteria
that isn't us not us
different genome
pretty amazing this body would take
take it to be ours
is a miracle of nature our brain
all the synapses the connections the way it works the neurotransmitter is all
amazingly balanced
being able to remember see act
hear smell just
amazing right here
instead of focusing on something going wrong with the body why is it not
working why do i have pain
so amazingly incredible that it works as well as it does it has all these years
internally sense of awe externally sense of awe
magnificent interconnection between so many beings
our lives we live
because of work generosity kindness of so many beings
past and present their ingenuity
their service
and to expand even further
looking as if we were looking up into the night sky
we are on this planet called earth so many stars
so many galaxies
such an incredible privilege to be alive to be conscious
even for a brief moment in time
to have the opportunity to have agency to think to serve to love
to give how awesome is that
how awesome is that
resting in all opening our hearts to all
for this magnificent being who is us it was me
with intentions goodness kindness in ways we understand and we don't quite
understand
this amazing interconnected world
this
and for the last minutes of this practice period
feeling the body connecting with the breath
the body this amazing body knows what to do breathing
being alive
male beings everywhere including us
be in touch at least now and then [Music]
with the amazing nature of their minds and their bodies
to help open up the realization
to awakening may all beings everywhere be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so i have some time if there are any reflections
questions comments and again
as i said at the beginning this might be
planting seeds if so if i didn't arise it's okay you're planting seeds
one reflection your comment about walking through life with
our eyes closed reminded me of a saying from the
ojibwe sometimes i go about pitying myself and all the while i am being
carried across the sky by beautiful clouds oh that's beautiful thank you for
sharing that that is lovely i read the quote again from ojibwe
sometimes i go about pitying myself and all the while i'm being carried across the sky
by beautiful clouds yes great reminder
ah appreciation coming from youtube [Music] thank you you're welcome
any other reflections what might have come up for you in this
practice offering it for the benefit of others
if there were any aha moments jamie
uh just a a question nikki um awe seems to me in some way
related to gratitude but i'm not sure how can you can you comment on the relationship between them
yeah yeah um they're related but they're not the same
actually before you meet yourself let me ask you let me turn it back to you
what what comes up for you as you've explored this how is this question coming up let's let's explore it
together um i uh i think that i have a uh more
capacity to feel awe if if i'm in regular practice of
being in touch with gratitude okay okay and can you te so so if you're
more if you're more in touch with gratitude it allows you to have ah and and more uh ah and and how do they
qualitatively feel different for you if i ask you to and as much as it's available
um well i'll uh steal something from the writer annie lamotte
you know she her paradigm is christian but she said that there's there's basically three prayers
which are help thanks and wow so oz the third
yes yes yeah nice nice it's not helped it's not thanks
which is the second one gratitude and it's wow
yeah yeah um yeah yeah so
so gratitude and all so as as i feel into my own experience then to share the
gratitude feels like an appreciation opening of the heart a thanking a
a um there's a personal relationship with gratitude there's a personal
relationship that i am grateful for this i am thankful whereas ah
it takes us out of ourselves that's perhaps yeah this is how we compare the two
all it takes is out of ourselves it's just wow wow
wow not from me and mine but just wow this is amazing
whereas gratitude is more personal relationship with with gifts and goodness so that's something to to
explore uh perhaps yeah thank you
deborah says but there's also a way that after a while you often find thanks
oh yeah that's true too there you go that's yeah wow yeah could be
one more reflection here how does discernment work in this context
it seems like you are allowing everything yeah yeah yeah this is a very
good question um [Music] yeah
it's yes allowing everything which in many ways actually
is is the sense of you know when when um awareness when sati is open there's a
sense of opening open awareness opening open
don't don't put away nothing don't don't push away anything just open open to
everything so well aw allows us it tells the soil to uh for us to open to everything
uh claire says suggest reading a brief history of time yes that's a great book
yeah yeah yeah i see your hand is that your hand is
still up is that what you wanted to say claire is there anything else
you can either unmute or stay muted
okay i think you're not unmuting either you can't or you don't want to
hear your lips moving it's a gita says is it appropriate to say that ah is a sensation not dependent
on thinking yes it is appropriate to say that ah is a sensation
i mean reflection can bring up but it's not dependent on thinking we can just
sit with awe without thinking claire looks like you succeeded i finally got unlocked here i'm having
huge technology problems tonight but uh the reason i brought i thought of that book immediately when you started the
topic because um stephen hawking was in such awe of the
universe as a brilliant physicist but the other thing that was really awesome was that he had lou gehrig's disease and
he did all this while he was totally immobile i mean he could barely speak
uh and yet he produced one of the most brilliant books of all time and to me that's just an awesome there you go
there's all there yeah it's just and there's a movie of it if anybody's interested he did he also made it it's a
movie it's beautiful thank you claire yeah but it was just expressing his art
for what he had discovered his thanks claire yeah
so yes so speaking of all let's have all
that we have come together here on zoom and youtube and listening
on audiodharma leader here we are these amazing human beings just like us
want to practice want to wake up um aligning want to align
their um heart their actions
with their best intentions so as we move
to the next part of our time together in small groups what i would like to ask you
is to first of all speak from your own experience not
commenting not managing the group just from your own experience
just stay close to your own experience and
you are welcome to say share what came up for you or hold silence say pass
each person has the opportunity to share one nugget if you if 10 things came up for you just share one
and then pass it on to the next person we'll go reverse alphabetical order
and then the next person will say something or we'll say pass and then the next person and then it will go around
and round a few times and again just speak from your own experience not managing or
or facilitating just it's a way of sharing it's a way of sharing your own awesomeness even you
don't think there is much awesomeness you are awesome you're a human being this is pretty incredible and holding
other people's awesomeness so so [Music]
i'm going to create the rooms now and
here we go okay oh yes the einstein quote this is
uh actually i've had this as my signature for many many years you can live your life as if nothing is a
miracle or as if everything is a miracle exactly so
i'm suggesting you live your life as if everything is a miracle because everything is a miracle
so i will open the rooms now take care of yourselves take care of each other here
we go okay welcome back everyone welcome back the
rooms are closed and we have just about a couple of
minutes for any reflections that came up while you were in the room so i'd love
to hear from you what what came up
you can either type in chat if you like or raise your hand if you haven't spoken
what did you notice any insights you'd like to share
catherine says i notice that i'm always smiling when i come back from breakout groups how awesome yes how awesome is
that indeed catherine and so many people too yes i see thumbs up i see hearts
i see lots of smiles it's very sweet yeah it's so sweet so
heartwarming how awesome is that yes connecting with other beings
ah mary says grateful for small groups and nikki i'm so grateful
that you all all of you come together and support each other
co-creating this the sacred space for practice how awesome is that how awesome
is that yeah so on that note of awe for our
small sanghas of small breakout groups let's let's bring our practice to close
tonight thank you so much for practicing cultivating your heart
for your own sake for the sake of all beings may all beings be well may all
beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone