so to thinking about Earth care I love the
word care because it has so many connotations
you can one is to have care for something is to be concerned for its
well-being and it doesn't have to be limited to animate beings we care for objects we
care for you know all kinds of things that we care for that are inanimate that are
maybe important for us in various ways and to care for it is to be concerned for its well-being
to keep it in the way that it makes it sustainable and honored or respected a
lot that kept clean perhaps depending on what it is and uh kept keep something healthy or
functioning caring for your car just means making sure that it runs well enough I suppose that some people care
for their car and it means waxing it every Sunday you know there's all kinds of things that people do
but uh care also implies not only a concern but also actions like cleaning
the car or helping a neighbor caring for a neighbor
and um so but those actions in that care can be overlapped with the idea of compassion
and love and kindness we're to offer care is to offer some of
the most important ways that human beings um
you know care for each other connect to each other support each other they we have you know child care that
when my first son first went to preschool I was one of those parents who has little been tears about so
appreciative of the preschool teachers caring for my you know caring for my son and it was such a profound thing for me
to feel someone else's care and and um in some ways the same way I felt
somewhat similar well last week I suppose it was or two weeks ago where
um my mother died and I accompanied her with the mortician who
came to put her on the on the gurney and and wrap her up and accompany her out to the
van that we're going to take her away and and then thinking about where she was going the funeral home and for
cremation and I felt kind of tenderly moved I was entrusting them to
entrusting her to um to their care and it meant something for me that you
know that you know it meant like something profound for me that they were kind of caring for her in her last
times in this body kind of and so this idea of care is very touching and paternal care which it kind
of is a necessary for children to grow up well is to feel paternal care and
that children growing up who don't feel their care of their parents the
um you know they grow up Kind of Rescue something goes a little bit dysfunctional there
and I like the word care because more commonly we talk about parental love and but there are parents who love their
kids who don't care for them or the cares a little bit Askew and so you know just to limit it just to
love kind of maybe it's not the full equation to care and uh
and so Earth care what is all about all the things that implies and what is the Earth
um and what does what does it mean to care for it and one of the things that it means for me is this very profound
Buddhist principle uh for us to support what supports us
that whatever supports us is something for us to support in return and whether it's our community or people
around us or it's the the natural world it's the Earth itself
the whole earth with all its people somehow we have this very profound
connection that where does the where's the limit where's the where's the boundaries
of what supports us as individuals where's the boundaries for what supports us as a community
you notice it you know Redwood City has boundaries is that it
you know that's all that that's my community that supports me and I'm not going to care about anybody else
and obviously not right there's the support circles or support to extend outward and outward and outward and
these days it's pretty clear it extends to the whole world with that uh so much of what we consume
and and receive and are influenced by it comes
from come from anywhere in this planet so we're supported by this wide range
and so do we support it in return and this idea of mutual support what
does that look like and why would we do it why would we care about the Earth why
would we care about you know you know natural resources why we would
care what happens to the species in this planet whether they go extinct or not
and you can give an argument that you know it's very logical and they can lay out the data and you know and really lay
out why in a practical way but that's not the specialty of Buddhism
so when I was Anew to practice actually then it just occurred to me before I
started practicing when I went to college first months in college I had we had this communal
you know bathroom we shared in the dorm and um and I had a friend who would
brush her teeth next to mine sometimes and she did a really strange
thing she turned the faucet off when she wasn't using the water for
brushing her teeth you'd wear wet her toothbrush turn the water off to brush her teeth turn it on get it wet again
back and forth but she's always turning it off and I'm like what's that about why would someone turn off the water
that was mystifying to me and um and then at some point she said
you know I'm conserving water and now but why would someone do that
and then when I first got interested in Buddhism I went to a Zen Center in Los Angeles
and the way that they did the evening schedule you did a period of meditation
sitting meditation a short period of walking meditation and then another sitting meditation and then a Dharma
talk and the walking meditation was all done together in a kind of a circle and it's really
slow so you're walking behind someone you know being really attentive and present
and there was a someone in Black robes and robes maybe a priest or a monk or
something that was in front of me and we sit on these black like these
here with their Zen things that we have here it's black uh mats that I'm sitting on if there's a meditation mats so in
Zen they have they all have that black mats and they're lined up in the room and one of them as we were going around
was slightly askew and um so there's a priest or this
practitioner in front of me uh she kind of matter of factly bent down and straightened it out
and then again why did she do that why bother why would you straighten something out
it was I mystified by this strange Behavior so I'm I was I was strange
right so you have to appreciate that maybe uh foreign
who knows what influences Me growing up but anyway so so why did you do that
and then uh just a little while later there was a senior practitioner when I
was at the San Francisco Zen Center who was receiving a kind of an admin
role received a letter fundraising letter from a neighborhood non-profit that was doing work in the neighborhood
for some kind of good work I'm not sure what it was and he showed me the letter like I don't
know I don't know why she showed it to me oh yeah and then he asked me again like what do you think how much should I should I give
and I was kind of mystified to give why what's this about
and I didn't compute quite and so uh and they thought oh you know I'll send fifty
dollars he said and I said what why so you know
it feels very strange to even say this that'd be so so mystified by these strange simple things
and then uh I came to I was living at his and practicing at um during a
retreat that is then Retreat and I was having tea in a little bit formal way with the Japanese visiting Japanese monk
sitting next to me and it was time to the people came around and collected the teacups when
you finished having tea and before he was going to let the handists teacup back to the people who receive it taking
it he bowed to the teacup why would you bow to the teacup
that there's nothing that is a world why would you if a tea it's a teacup it's inanimate it's just a thing you
know why would you bow to a teacup so um so that's kind of you know how
clueless I was at some point in life and um and so uh but what Buddhism
reveals as you practice it um is How Deeply we're connected How
Deeply we're part of for an intimately related to teacups and water and
neighborhood community and and uh and even in some way we're actually related
we're almost like kin to the way the math is down there on the on the floor
and you know straightening it out does not straightening out the mat it's maybe straightening of oneself
you know what's going on there what is this connection we have so then you come to uh the kind of
Buddhist teaching and we have this very important word Dharma and uh it often represents the Buddha's
teaching the Dharma but Dharma is also the word in the
ancient language which is the best match for the English word nature
I don't know of any other word that it fits as well and it's used that way sometimes it goes in dictionary you see
that it's one of the definitions of it it has a lot of as other meanings as well but that's one of its important
meanings and um and if you make it instrument that the word Dharma into an abstract
noun then um translators will translate it as
a natural it's natural as part of the natural order of things it's a natural thing
so Dharma but what is Dharma besides it maybe being nature it's kind of abstract there's a very famous
um very famous little slogan from the early tradition that to see the Dharma
you see the Dharma in how things are interrelated
and when you see how things are interrelated you see the Dharma and the way this is discussed is in a
particular way the interrelatedness is on the way in which things are arise
occur exist depend on other things depending on the support of other things
they rest we rest on things and then when they get a little bit more sophisticated they recognize that some
things co-arize they arise together mutually supporting each other
and um and so if Dharma is nature where
is nature is nature found in the trees outside in the squirrels is it found in the weather
is it found in the whole shebang of this whole you know everything that's kind of
born from natural conditions what is nature and one baby maybe very profound way of
understanding it that kind of turns things around for us in a I think a profound way
is that nature is not found in a tree or the squirrel in things or in you even
exactly nature is found in the relationship between things the
relatedness how how things exist in kinship with
each other and that relationship is a little bit invisible
you know it's like you can't touch it you know you can't you know I can hit the Bell
um and uh but is the Bell nature is my fingernail hits the Bell nature
for people who like to focus on the world of things I'm here and things are
up there then it makes sense that out there is nature just beyond the edges of
the city is the natural world some people will say um and and I used to say that as well
and it was quite a surprise for me when I spent three years practicing in tosahara Zen Monastery which is in the
wilderness really in the wilderness in Los Padres National Wilderness at sir
and Inland from Santa Cruz uh Big Sur the
coast of Big Sur and um and after almost three years living
there I went back to live in San Francisco and one of the big surprises was after
that experience of deep monastic practice was I started seeing nature
everywhere I saw it on the in the asphalt in the city in the cars of San Francisco I saw
those that's too as part of nature but it was still a little bit outside of myself and what I didn't see then was
that the reason I could see it as nature had to do with the way that I was relating
to cars and everything had changed and uh rationally I explained it not
that way I explained it everything comes out of nature everything's coeg Rising together and we can't really point to
anything which is not nature it's kind of how I
explained it to myself but I think what was really happening is with the way in
which I was relating the relationship that I was forming or was being formed because a relationship is not something
that only comes from me it's mutual it happens together and uh and that relationship is where
maybe what nature is at least in this Buddhist idea where Dharma is called nature
and and so what if that relationship is kind of so important to pay attention to
what's the nature of that relationship and that's where Dharma Brethren and
Buddhism you come up with idea of karma karma is our contribution to that
relationship the actions the things we do things we say even the things we things we think
and believe has an influence on that relationship that we are in with everything with the
water that we get from our sink with um the local neighborhood with the
teacups whatever it might be that relationship is influenced we
contribute to the nature of that relationship and um and so in a simple way if we
contribute if we hate something or hate someone that relationship has qualities of that
hate in it I've known people who have a predisposition to being angry
and there I get angry at all kinds of things and they're upset with the world the world's not doing the right thing
and I could watch and see how the world responds to those people people don't like it
of course people don't like those people because they're coming at them you know expecting and mistrusting
them and suspicious already kind of like thinking that you're wrong and so then it's a self-fulfilling
prophecy and so that relationship gets formed in a certain way that's shared it doesn't have to be but
and I've watched and seen how people who are kind or supportive or friendly
disarm people who are angry or hostile uh sometimes you know you see that you
bring something to the relationship and it helps shape the relationship of course there's no guarantee just
because you're kind that it's going to change it but uh it can make a huge difference
um I I was once saved from a violent attacks I don't know how serious it would have been
by my friend who was so amazingly both kind friendly
and funny and that he disarmed the people who wanted to attack
and uh I didn't I don't I didn't have that ability but that was quite impressive to see
so what do we bring so karma has to do with our contribution to that relationship
and it gets even more interesting is the karma that we bring the attitudes
the approach we have to what we do what we contribute
is also the Dharma of ourselves meaning it's
also the relationship we have with ourselves you can't hate
without it affecting you you can't be kind without it affecting you
in Buddhism they have dramatic language for this that hate is a poison
guess who is poisoning it's poisoning you and it can poison the world but this is where it really has
the biggest poison craving and greed is considered a poison it's dramatic language maybe some of you
won't like it that this way but but the what it's pointing to is this way in
which the karma what we contribute to the relationship can actually has an
effect on us as well so if we live
with greed and craving then it comes back and bites us
it also creates a skewed relationship out in the world
but it's invisible right so who cares you know it's not obvious so you know
probably most people don't think that they're rampant consumerism consumerists
but we have a society as a whole that is and that does it to a lot of people all
over the world now don't do it without much thought there's a lot of conceit there's a lot
of idea me and I want my things for myself I do acquisitionness you know
acquisition null kind of quality of I want this and then went down to one don't want it
anymore then I throw it away and someone else is going to take care of it I mean I pay people I pay the trash
people to take it away so not my responsibility but and so and there's a kind of
ignorance there there's a kind of uh forfeiting of responsibility maybe it's okay in some kind of abstract
way I'll do it that way but it's a lost opportunity
the most precious thing we have the most valuable thing we have is the contribution we make
to how we relate to this earth to this world to others that's the real treasure
and you can feel it I hope if you meditate enough in meditation that's the
case I've been meditating now for about 50 years so you know I have a little bit of
experience around it but the main thing reason I say it is that I still to this day
um but literally this day when I meditated this morning is uh I'm going around the kitchen and
getting ready to meditate and doing stuff and that didn't get too much trouble just time I woke up and sat down
and um but if I sat down to meditate it was so good to sit down and I noticed
that my mind had already began spinning a little bit where there was a kind of compelling
feeling like it's all you know like I'm on the right track like this has to be done I should do this and and this is
important and um and it was a little bit kind of self-centered in my little universe
and then I sat down to meditate and that just kind of dissolved and what was left was so much better
this is real this felt like this is like I feel I felt free I felt warm I felt I
felt centered I felt at peace at ease in a way that I felt all I'm healthy everything was present
and in contrast to what I saw was I was deluded for those few minutes in the
kitchen in a certain kind of way ignorant I was being Swept Away by the
by the things I had to think about and do and all this kind of stuff and it was enough and I didn't see how I
was losing my ease losing being connected in some deep way it's that easy
and imagine if someone never has a way of disconnecting from that they believed
their minds they believed the momentum they believed the desires the wishes that conceits it's about me and what's
best to happen it's radical to shift that move out of
that and come into a place where we have a chance to relate
in from a place of Health from a place of being centered and easeful being at
peace and so when we talk about Earth care
it can come across as Duty as obligation we have a responsibility
to do something and let's go out there and fight the good cause and let's kind of shame everybody else into
doing it too something something like that can happen occasionally
um but I think from a Buddhist point of view My Hope Is that we were tiredly
tirelessly care for the world for the Earth entire sleep but not because it's an obligation
because it's the most natural thing to do in the kind of relationship
that is the healthiest most meaningful most inspiring way to live in this world
anything short of that probably doesn't come from this natural place
where we're creating a healthy relatedness
where we honor the relationship we we respect it we understand it
where we have this cup of tea and I don't think the cup may be itself
responds to the monk about to it but
what a radically different relationship that that monk has to the cup of tea
than someone who just tosses it in the trash can because they don't want to bother cleaning it no no there's so many
teacups of this at the Zen Center so you know I don't have time it's a very different relationship
I hear this beautiful story yesterday of a Native American a professor a professor a Lakota man
who's a professor I mean I think of Environmental Studies in somewhere and um so he told my friend the story of
of having an undergraduate class and maybe Environmental Studies
and the first day of class the students come and sit down and he stands in front of the class and he says
um I have an unusual request if you kind of please do it you know you know every
unusual request but if you would please look be any kind would you something can you I know you just sat down could
you get up and go outside and touch a tree and they people looked at each other and like
apparently they weren't so enthusiastic but what's this going on we came to learn or something but they went out and touched the tree
and then they came back sat down and he said well I know you touched the tree I know this is a really strange request
but I'm going to ask you to go do it again but however this time before you touch a
tree wait until the tree gives you permission to be touched
and so they went out and did it and when they came back into the class the students were in a whole different state
of mind they were kind of quiet reverential they were kind of ready to learn they were
they something had softened in them you know their relationship was to learn it was had shifted
from that simple exercise he had them enter into a relationship
with the trees and whether trees can really give us
permission is maybe less important
that something transpires in the relationship between the trees and you
that you feel that's there's a there's an imitation a permission a request
When I Was An undergraduate I took botany and
I was so amazed by the beautiful Circle uh circles written on the chalkboard of
the oxygen carbon dioxide kind of cycles that go on with the plants and you know they make the oxygen that we need and we
make the carbon dioxide that they need partly you know so this wonderful cycle and then I went out into this Courtyard
in Davis California where they have this Majestic old oak trees in the courtyard of the
Auditorium and I just was stood in the middle of the courtyard stunned
by the trees and wondering where do I end and where the trees begin where the
trees end and where do I begin I could give away one of my kidneys was my hand
all kinds of parts of my body I don't really have to have to live but I need those trees
to be alive where's the who where am I who am I what's going on here I stood there in
silence kind of just in awe of it all that was a very different way of
relating to the trees they know that that looks like firewood yeah and I think you know I need to be
warm so I'm going to take my ax and chop it down we are supported by what supports us
no I say what supports us is what we want to support if we don't support what
supports us we just destroy our support and that's what we're seeing we've seen
down through history now through the centuries we've seen this and I grew up
you know in places in the world there's been visiting and I lived right on the
um on the Adriatic Coast for a while and uh in a city in Italy called Trieste
right on the border with what was then Yugoslavia and we used to go down
the coast of uslovia beautiful islands Stark and Stony
they used to be covered with soil and trees and but they were denuded and all the
all the water rushed away because they they thought they harvested all the trees to build room
and things like that we've seen Down Through the Ages that people human beings have overextended
their agriculture their wood cutting their farming all kinds of things and destroyed the place of support
so it's not a new thing for us to be doing in our generation but there are places in the world where
that's happening and perhaps it's what's changed is the scale of it
and so we come back to Buddhism what we have to offer for this we have this beautiful principle
that we wanted we want to live in in attuned to our relationship our
relatedness our relationships because that's the heart of where nature is found
and we contribute to that to the degree to which we have agency
we're contributed to that relationship and we want to be careful that we
contribute something which is healthy something gets me that really is healthy
for us as individuals as a community and healthy for the world of itself for the
natural world itself that's represented by the slogan that
to support what supports us we support what supports us it would be the ideal
and so here we have this Earth care day which is celebrating this possibility
celebrating that the the Dual meaning of Earth care
could also mean that uh we're recognizing the Earth cares for us
that Earth care day is recognizing how we're cared for how we're supported
and it can mean the day the day that during the week the week that we
that consider and reflect on caring for the Earth
and so in saying all this to summarize now
at the heart of it this is Buddhist practice is caring
for the attitude the motivation the contribution that we offer to that
relationship and uh and if we care for that
then I think we'll find how to care for others for the world for people and
everything in a way that doesn't it doesn't drain us doesn't oppress us but
rather we'll learn how to do it in a way that uh feels natural it feels like this
is this is what we were built to do this is how humans were made to be this way
something that's very hard to appreciate unless you have some way of connecting
to the deeper sources within us than what the places of real real Health that
goes on inside or connecting to
the tree that we ask permission to touch
the strawberry plant we wait to pick the strawberry until it feels that we recognize that the plant
says it's okay now why would you do that maybe because there's a shift there's a
change there's a there's a receptivity there's an openness there's a caring
there's a attentiveness in that of course questions
that brings forth something deep within ourselves that we then contribute
to our kinship with all things
so um the Earth care week so in a few minutes we'll have this
chance to have tea and talk with each other and and meet with the Earth care committee but before we do we ended a
little early like to just start doing what we used to do before the pandemic
um is to uh for those of you who are comfortable with this simply turn to someone who's near you and say hello and
introduce yourself there's a lot of people here who've been here for the first time today maybe and um and also if you care for it you
might want to say oh Hillary wants to say something