so hello it's nice to see all of you coming on
joining from so many places in the world and we'll be continuing with this
theme of mindfulness as protection looking at different aspects of that
every day so why don't we go ahead and get right
into the meditation today so finding a
posture where you'll be able to sit for a little while
just tuning in to the sensations of the body sitting
you can close your eyes if that's comfortable for you
it's often helpful at the beginning of the sit to just check in with the posture
so you know feeling the the body is upright and balanced
where it's sitting [Music] or even if you're lying down there can
still be a sense of straightness in the spine
and often we can feel the energy associated with the
straightness or uprightness of the body and balance that against uh relaxation
so it's not a tense or bolt upright straightness but
a relaxed [Music] almost raising up of the body as if it were being pulled from above
and then we just settle in to that
we can take a longer deeper breath than usual
and on the out breath just soften around that
straight central part of the body so softening the face
the jaw the shoulders the arms
the
legs and then inside the body
softening the heart area
and the belly
and then tuning in to the sensations of the breathing
when the body is at least somewhat relaxed there can be a sense of the
breath washing through the tissues of the body
it's a bit of an imagination but we don't have to think of the breath as just being in the lungs
it can be helpful to feel it throughout the body
and just as we had a sense of alertness and also
ease or relaxation in the body in the mind we can also
sense the alertness but it's a relaxed alertness
perhaps fueled by a an interest in our experience
so often we don't take the time or sometimes even have the
time to tune in deeply to our experience
we're busy with something in the outer world and now is a chance to really listen
really tune in
so again we consider we can consider the sensations of the breath
to be like a home base to which the mind can
return or wake up to at any time
but the sensations of the breath are not the only thing happening of course there may be
other body sensations and there's sound
there may be a dominant emotion or mood
and there may be various thoughts so it's okay that these other things are
happening we could just think of them as being on
the back burner while the breath is more on the front burner
or that these other things happen and we breathe through them kind of
favoring the ex feeling of the breath but these other things are there
more softly
so this kind of meditation allows there to be multiple experiences
and it can be that the mind will switch the positions of the breath and
something else and go off into thinking or
listening and if that's the case when we notice
we can just bring the breath back into the foreground
and if you'd like for this meditation you could also just note
what it was that the mind was doing when it was caught up in something
like hearing or thinking
or a body sensation and we just note that
so that we know and then continue on in a simple way with the meditation it's kind of an easy
investigation
one of the most common things that the mind will get caught up in
is a thought trail very normal
because the mind thinks that's that's what it does so there's certainly nothing
to criticize in that but it can be interesting
if you'd like if this doesn't feel too busy
to make a little bit further investigation of thought in particular
when the mind is on a long thought trail it's called pancha
which means proliferation [Music] and the
the main three things going on during proliferation of thought
are either craving or conceit
or views so there's no judgment of these things
but it's it's often that we're wanting something or that would include not wanting
something or we're explaining something about
ourselves how we are how we compare to someone else
or we're stating our position on something
explaining it figuring it out
so craving concedes and views so we could on the
noting of the thought we could also if it's simple enough just
note which of these three seems prominent and if it's not obvious then then it's
just thinking it doesn't matter so much
sometimes it's interesting to know what we're trading our piece for
when we investigate in this way we may come to realize that there's a
certain grace to the return of mindfulness
since we weren't present we didn't do that
so it's something of a gift that mindfulness reappears
when the mind has been wandering we can be happy for that
although we didn't do it in that moment there is some momentum generated from
earlier practice so we can enjoy that
return of mindfulness that sense of brightness and presence returning
i appreciate the gift
so in the last few minutes of this sitting [Music]
we might bring to mind just how much of the suffering in the
world comes from
these three things craving conceits and views
first of all internally for the person who is
wrapped up in that because we can see that in ourselves
and then also actions that are taken
based on these things
it's just part of how it is to be human that we have these streams in our mind
and it's mindfulness that helps us see that and
be disentangled from it
so mindfulness is our natural protection from
into these streams or
domains of unwholesome tendencies in the mind
so for today we could be happy for the moments of
mindfulness the stretches of mindfulness during which we know we won't be
acting on these forces that aren't so helpful
and it may even be that our mindfulness or our presence could help someone else not to act
on such things we can't assume that or try to make it that way
but it may be that way
so this wonderful gift of presence that arrives on its own in a sense
it's a great protection for ourselves and others
[Music]
so we'll be continuing with this theme of mindfulness as a protection
and we'll be using various different images to build up maybe a bigger picture
of the multifaceted way that mindfulness operates
and a lot of that has to do with protection in various forms so we started out with the fundamental
idea that mindfulness is a good protection for us and then today
we're actually going to talk about the flip side of that which is the danger of not being mindful
and the buddha gave a number of images that are about this seems that he was quite willing to
approach from the side of of danger maybe for some minds that works well
and um and then we'll talk about ways to address that danger including something that the buddha himself did
in his practice so the reason that we would need
protection such as through mindfulness is because there is genuine danger in
our situation as humans i don't want to over dramatize that but
we can certainly see i think in our own mind that there are a lot of
long-standing habits not all of which are beneficial you know
you know we may not be acting on these various things going on in our mind but we can't deny that they're there when we
have mindfulness so again not to worry that's normal for humans everyone who's born as human
has various kinds of greed hatred and delusion that comes with the territory
they're actually not very personal even though they have their specific manifestations for us
so as i was reviewing various images about mindfulness i couldn't help
but notice that there really are quite a few that relate to the danger of non-mindfulness so i thought we'd look
at just a few of them today so one of them is about a a beauty queen
and i'm sorry for the gendered imagery in this suta you're you're very welcome to alter it in your mind
however it's appropriate so the buddha is telling the monks
a story about a beauty queen who is
walking through a city and singing and dancing as a large crowd of
people gathers around and so then he goes on to say
then a person would come along wishing to live not wishing to die
wishing for happiness averse to suffering and someone would say you must carry around this bowl of oil
filled to the brim between the crowd and the beauty queen and a man with a drawn sword will be
following right behind you and wherever you spill even a little bit of it
right there he will fell your head so what do you think would that person
stop attending to that bowl of oil and out of negligence turn their attention outwards and amongst say no
so the buddha goes on to say i have made up this simile in order to convey a
meaning and here is the meaning the bowl of oil filled to the brim is a
designation for mindfulness directed to the body so
there you have it the sense that we could walk
with a bowl of oil filled to the brim in the midst of a jostling excited crowd
and not spill any of it so it's pointing toward the importance of
precision i don't know that we need the anxiety that might go along with an image like
that but it does you know it does convey the importance i think the buddha was trying
to relate in that case then there are also two images given
that relate to an idea of a homeland or a domain where it is safe for us to dwell
and then outside of that it's dangerous so i'll just we'll take a look at those
there's another suta where the buddha is talking about places where hunters set up traps of
pitch in order to catch monkeys and so it says those monkeys who are not
foolish and frivolous when they see the pitch avoided from afar
but a monkey who is foolish approaches the pitch and seizes it with his hand and he gets caught
and then thinking i will free my hand he seizes it with the other hand and gets caught
and then thinking i will free both hands he seizes it with a foot and then the other foot
and then the muzzle and so he gets caught in five different places and so
the buddha goes on to say please do not stray outside your own
resort into the domain of others mara will gain access to those who stray
outside mara being the in this case the forces of distraction in the mind
and what is the resort you know what is the place where we should remain safe
it is the four establishments of mindfulness so
i i can relate to this monkey image and that there can be times where i know the mind is caught up and my my attempts to
free it i say oh i shouldn't think about that i'm going to try to think about something else then the mind is actually just
continuing to think in some way and so then there's this sort of ongoing
finally there's a realization oh i just need to i need to drop this effort it's not
going in the right direction oh and i said there were two of these
images about the homeland or the safety so the second one is about a quail that is
um living in a field and it's being attacked by a hawk when it uh leaves
leaves the field it's a similar kind of image as the monkey and in both of these sutas the the
dangerous place is specifically said to be the five chords of sensual pleasure
you know meaning eye ear tongue knows body so the usual ways where we would want to seek comfort or pleasure the
things that occupy the mind and then the safe place is the four establishments of mindfulness
so it's important to note that although the similes are about
physical places because that's easy to imagine what the buddha names as safety is not
actually a physical place but a stance of our mind so we're safe when the mind is mindful
so he's not saying that we need to be locked up in our house with the door bolted in order to be safe
he's saying instead that there's something to do with how our mind is
so we begin maybe with we begin with this practice of guarding the sense doors
that's what we talked about yesterday and usually when people start they find it
useful to actually avoid situations that are particularly triggering and that is totally fine when
we do actually have that choice it can be skillful to do that and for instance
people who are in recovery should definitely choose not to go to bars
or we may choose not to go to a big noisy party if we don't have to go or maybe we would
simply be more subtle and just choose to have fewer conversations with our neighbor whose political views are very
different from ours so that's fine to do
but in the end the buddha is pointing toward the real danger being from within it's our own
lack of mindfulness or our own lack of capacity with mindfulness
so like strengthening muscles we have to exercise mindfulness in order
to grow our capacity and you may have already seen in your practice that there once you started
cultivating mindfulness there came to be situations where in the past it would have been very difficult
to stay mindful or to be skillful and then one day
you're you're present for it and you realize oh i didn't i didn't automatically lash out when i i
think i would have a couple of months ago and so we realized oh my capacity has
grown a little bit and so it so this is nice to when we notice it
spontaneously but i want to talk a little bit about deliberately
cultivating our capacity so at some point just like we would have to increase the
weight stack at the gym we'll probably have to venture into more
challenging situations and try to remain mindful in them kind of
move into new domains expand the domain of safety for our mind
so we're not you know we're not seeking out difficulty willy-nilly but it is really a kind of a fun point
in practice when we start doing little experiments to see if we can be mindful in more challenging situations
so we're trying to stay in the safe domain of mindfulness but gradually develop what is needed so
that that domain gets larger and the buddha talks about doing this in
his own practice at one point this is before he was awakened so there is a
suta entitled fear and dread where the buddha deliberately went to
scary forests scary forest places to practice in order to remain mindful
during the experience of fear and dread so there's a lot in the suta and i'm
just singling out one point for today but one of the key points is that he
consciously considered ahead of time before he went into the situation he
consciously considered that he possesses certain good qualities
including mindfulness so he actively reminded himself before
going into the woods that he is ethical he's mindful he's
caring and even has some degree of wisdom and this sort of buoyed up his mind and
heart so that he could stay aware even during experiences that were bringing up fear
so we can do this also in our own lives there was a time when i
did a program in uh chaplaincy training and
when i this is a while ago and when i started the program i didn't really have i didn't have any experience with
going into hospitals and meeting people there and talking with them and part of the
training in this program is that we needed to do volunteer work and i i chose to go into a hospital
and i joined the spiritual care volunteer team and i would have to go into rooms with
very little information about you know i didn't know anything about what was wrong with the person or anything about
their background or very much at all i think you get their name and their religion listed on the sheet
and um i would go in and i would offer myself you know how can i be helpful
here would you like to talk and at the beginning i was i didn't know how to do that and i felt quite
uh nervous of course i had some you know i was going to the training program so i had some ideas of where to start but it
took the practice of doing it to be able to be present and mindful in situations
like that that were very unclear or uncertain and just lead from the heart and
see what i could do so that was very good training and it did expand the domain in which i was
more comfortable with being with with challenging situations
so you can try this as you approach a challenging situation is to bolster the confidence ahead of time by
bringing to mind some kind of inspiration from our practice we could
recollect our own good qualities as the buddha did and it's also recommended that we can
recollect the buddha the dharma the sangha you know other inspiring themes for us
and then and then you can let those go and just go into the situation intending to be mindful and see what comes up
so we're working with this idea of danger and protection
and with the protection of mindfulness more and more of the world looks safe to
us we're safe from things that are essentially alluring or things that
bring up aversion or cause agitation in some way
and when we have that through the establishments of mindfulness it's a kind of safety that we can carry around
with us so we become free in our own awareness no matter what the situation
of course it's it takes a while it's a long process to to expand that so i want
to respect that process very much but we can maybe be inspired that awakened people can go anywhere in peace
and safety everywhere safe for them so may your range of mindfulness and safety
keep expanding as you continue to practice you might consider
if there are conscious ways that you could do that so thank you we'll continue tomorrow