so hello everyone and welcome to the sunday morning talk
and uh i'd like to begin with a little
something autobiographical that when i was in my twenties i was
living at a zen monastery sahara monastery here in california
for about three years and i had recently graduated from college
and had been accepted to graduate school which i then deferred
and i was living at the monastery living a monastic life
and i spent a lot of time reflecting thinking about what was i going to do with my life
go to graduate school do something else what what should i do
and i was happily engaged in the monastic life and four days of the week they had had a
five day week cycle so i'm following the monastic routines for four
days and then the fifth day was kind of half day off or something and so i would go in
hiking in the mountains there and those days off were my the hardest days for me
because i was left with myself in a different way and i had to reflect on
my concern about what i was going to do with my life what had to make a decision
so i did a lot of reflecting on those walks and after about a year of these kinds of
walks and reflexings and reflections and thinking what to do and
but uh i think it was beginning to be kind of
maybe i'd done enough reflection thinking about it with no answers
and at some point i realized that i was operating in some general
generalizations in imaginations imagining a future imagining things that
were beyond the monastery about what i could do and should do and
possibilities and i became acutely aware how much i was in my world of my imagination
thinking about all this and and so i made a decision
it wasn't exactly a conscious decision but it was like i don't know exactly but it was a decisive
moment where i decided somehow i decided that
i had enough of all these reflections and thinking it hadn't hadn't helped me
i decided that i would start my life over
i'll just i'll just start all over again with the next step as i walked
and and you know looking back at it now 40 years i don't know if that was naive
sure but anyway i did it that's what i did that's what i
and i just happened to be living in a zen monastery that was a kind of a cool place to start
all over again because then the bell rang and i had to go meditate bell rang he got up and did
went to work or did things so it was a healthy whole very wholesome place to be
and i just then followed uh what opened up in front of me
and uh and at some degree that was the that that represents the rest of my life that somehow
that just taking the next step and then seeing what happens and then responding to that and taking you know things open
up and doing it eventually you know let me hear you know into what's happening in redwood city
now and rest on my life and i'm still doing that just kind of
and uh so that was nice for me and that was a nice decision to make
and uh it turns out that uh each of us
every day every moment comes to that juncture
without realizing it every day you kind of start over
every moment you kind of start over believe it or not you could start over
and the way you start over is that all the things that you did in the past are now in the past
things you did in the past contribute to this moment but whatever decisions you made in the
past have been made you don't have to make those again
we find ourselves here and now and now is when we can decide how to
step take the next step now is the time we decide given
all the conditions that are present here and now now we're making a choice
to do something and the choices you've made in the past
they are what they are the place that's really dynamic the
place that's really significant for us in our lives is a place where today
and this next step we take the choice we make today and the choice we make today of how we
walk how we talk what we say what we do is consequential
and sometimes we there are unconscious choices we're influenced by things around us
but the choices you make have consequences that shape your future
imagine that there are two identical twins who grew up together
and people couldn't tell them apart they looked the same they had the same mannerisms and way of speaking
the same personalities you know they were just all like so similar
but then they decided to go to different colleges when the time came to go to college
and each of them had a different roommate one of them had a roommate who had a
strong tendency to complain the other had a roommate had a strong
tendency to be grateful for everything and then
they didn't know that it was like well this is what each one of them thought oh this is just what roommates are they didn't have any reference point to
think anything different but you know okay i'm your college you get a roommate this is what roommates are like
and they didn't and so slowly they came under the little bit the influence of
the complaining one learned to complain and you you know you one learned to be
grateful it wasn't exactly a choice that's where you would it's like a conscious choice
but there was a choice there was a kind of subconscious choice like okay
under the influence of a roommate it became you know like you got reinforced if you go in the complainer if you
complained it was like you know you had camaraderie ship you could
but the one who was grateful you had the camaraderie ship by being grateful so slowly
you know and and the person who the twin didn't recognize what was happening
how they're being shaped by the situation and after a year you could tell the
difference between the two twins easily and their lives started to change
dramatically the one that
started to complain more and more people kind of held their distance from that person
people everyone who was grateful people like to be with them different opportunities opened up
the one who complained because things you know things are a little bit uncomfortable it's an uncomfortable mental state to
complain stressful mental state that reinforced
certain other uh inner reactivities
annoyance at the state of mind and certain self-criticalness and made it
easier not only to be complaining but to be angry at things the person who was grateful
supported other mental states more relaxed states more feeling more of a generosity and
that's what came out so they both came to the same moment
going to college where they in a certain way started their life over
and then things went a different different way for each of them
so today is a new day for you today is a new beginning every moment is a new beginning and you
come to a fork in the road and the question is which fork do you
take there's no one who's asking you or telling you i think really about what
fork you should take moment by moment but what if you really took it seriously
that you're starting your life over today fresh new
because in a way you are and the way that you are maybe i'm repeating myself is that
this is really the only place today and now
where you can make the choices engage in the activities
that are going to shape your future that's if you're going to be kind of the
one who shapes your future to whatever degree we can shape it it's only you that can do that
even if you get a roommate who complains how you respond to that roommate how you
take it in and receive it is really up to you even if it's subconscious
when we are mindful we put it it and have this kind of pause
and ability to stay present we have a much higher sensitivity to
notice the choices we make higher sensitivity
to be wise about which fork we take the one that's
healthy and the one or the one that's unhealthy the one that creates a better life it creates crazier
kind of worse life for ourselves and
and so when we have this mindfulness practice we can really appreciate we start over
in that sense in a certain kind of way it's very forgiving
yes you've been influenced by the mistakes you made in the past that's part of the conditions that brought you here
but we don't have to be weighed down by the past buddhism the buddhist approach is to
think enough about the past reflect on it learn from it just enough
so we can aim to do better in the future buddhism in a way is forward-looking
so you know some people think that buddhism is all about being in the present moment it's it's about being in the present
moment part of it the reason to be in the present moment is so we can in looking forward looking
we can make the choices today that make a difference for tomorrow
in a good way for ourselves and even something as simple as
complaining as innocent as it is maybe sometimes
is choosing a fork which maybe one little complaint is not going to have much impact but
once we start making complaints more and more it affects our mind states if it affects our habits it affects how
people treat us and relate to us and it begins creating a new world
so how careful do you want to be in the world that you create
for yourself how you create yourself there's an expression in english i don't
know if this expression you know it's a not a not a set phrase but um it goes something like uh like this
if you do x you you'll you own it you own it and so i don't i couldn't
think of a good example but like you know if you if you um
i don't know if you if you decide to
balance all the teacups in your house on top of each other
you know and you insist on doing it when someone says you know that's not safe it's gonna they're gonna fall they're so fragile they're gonna break
and so the person then said i'm going to do it it's safe and you say okay well the person walks away so okay well then
whatever happens you own it meaning i think it means that you're
responsible for it it's up to you to take care of it it's it's your your your karma some people would say
yeah you own it indirectly this is what or directly the
buddha said that too 2500 years ago he said you're
you are the owners of your actions
you are the owners of your actions and then he goes on to say something else he has a there's a wonderful almost
like a liturgy he's kind of a very famous thing among buddhists um
line about action anything encapsulated what i'm trying to say today
uh beings are owners of their action
he air he heirs to their action they inherit them
and they originate from their actions
they are bound to their actions and they have actions as their refuge
so we're owners of our actions that's kind of what i'm saying here once we do
something the consequences of that somehow
continues for us so to be careful with what we do so we you know the consequences the results
the momentum we set in place is one that we want to live with live by
uh we inherit our actions so the heirs of our actions
and um so some of the uh you know we receive again some kind of the same idea but
um they're passed down to us from date from one day to the next
through habits through conditioning through whatever way that these all these different ways that
infinite ways in which actions kind of carry with them consequences in the future
the idea in buddhism is that
there's no free lunch when you come to action or there's no
free you know free consequences all actions carry consequence
and so we inherit them we inherit the consequences
and then we originate that's the powerful one all beings originate from
their actions so if in this way i'm talking about it today that
who you are today is partly the consequence of all the actions you've done in this
lifetime before today and it's all these things are so subtle
and small and how they come into play and build up over time
i was i think i was told once that abraham lincoln said something like by the time a person is 40 they're
responsible for their face and i think what he meant was you know all the little gestures and all
the different ways expressions we have on the face you know build over time
a certain kind of face and uh and i've been impressed i've seen this
sometimes with i see people who grew up in different cultures different countries
and like someone who their parentage was from one country
but they grew up in a different country and you can see sometimes like the difference facial
features or muscles or expressions how they are in their face may be built up differently because of
um partly might just be different muscles are used for when we speak different languages
and as you do that over you know decades it affects the face but also expressions
and all this stuff so we originate from our actions i don't know if that was the best example but
from the buddhist point of view it's not about our face but it's about our hearts our minds
and so much was shaped by all the choices we make
and then we are bound to our actions you can't get away from your actions you can't get
away from the fact that actions are consequential even if you your action is to do no
action just be a couch potato do nothing that's an action too
so you know we're bound to actions we're human beings that's what we are we're
human and we say we're human beings i don't think there's very very little
time we spend just being you know sooner or later you have to pee
so we're more like human it was actors that
human activity ears constant activities that we're doing
so to embrace that to appreciate it to find a new way
to be an activity activity actor an activiator
i don't know trying to do something equivalent equivalent to being
and because we're bound to or we're bound to
action we can't get away from acting so let's look at action and activity in a serious way
and then we come to the last part beings have action as their refuge
the buddha said that you can make yourself a refuge so we're not we're trapped in
action we're not trapped in you know creating problems for ourselves by what we do and what we
say and how we act we can act in ways we can engage in the world and behave in ways
that uh we become our own refuge our own support and the refuge in buddhism is a very powerful word it's almost like that
one of the i don't know it's um it's kind of like a word like um
i don't know if i don't know if it carries the same it doesn't carry the same meanings but maybe the same um
associations or the same heart feeling or emotion as in other religions they might talk about having a conversion experience
or having a really deep i'm a devotee of some wonderful religion or something
it has this very deep religious sense that their refuge but rather than the refuge being outside
of oneself the refuge is not exactly in ourselves it's not like you find some essence
inside yourself oh i can you know now i've discovered my true self in there and for the teachings of the buddha the
refuges as our actions how we live what we do
and it makes a huge difference how we live and what we do and we can do the things that are
supportive and nourish us and benefit us
so it means simple it's not so simple maybe but simple to say
we can live by live ethically we can live by the precepts it makes a big difference believe it or
not whether you kill people or don't for your heart
it makes a big difference whether you steal or if you don't it makes a big difference if you engage
in sexual activity that harms others or you don't it makes a big difference
whether you lie or if you don't it makes a big difference if you engage
in intoxication or if you don't it makes a big difference whether you're
greedy or if you're not big difference if you have hatred or if you're not
it makes a big difference if you're generous or if you're not
it makes a big difference if you are grateful
or if you're complaining it makes a big difference whether you take the time to see people
with respect and even reference or maybe the opposite
and those are all these are all actions these are all behaviors and choosing the side of the equation
that is healthy we create our own refuge
we create a inner life that we're happy to be in that we're proud of that that brings us
a sense of joy and delight more importantly for meditators it brings us a possibility of relaxation of
ease we look within and we're not we don't find conflict we
don't find this is you know oh no my regrets of what i said or challenged by what i've done but we look
inside so oh it's good in there imagine oh
it's a nice to be in there who's your best friend
your own heart your what you find inside but to do to discover that to find that
it's through our actions that we do some people uh
feel like they have a lot of doubts and lack of confidence
how do you find confidence how do you find faith
some people think it's by reading a lot of books until they find the perfect teaching
sometimes just thinking they have to find some state of you know meditative state of mind that's going to come out
correct everything but the way to build confidence
is step by step in the actions you do
and it might be that uh it's just like you know after a while you've been practiced honestly
for you know in small little increments slowly getting more honest then after a while you you feel that oh
i think i have confidence i've learned the skill to communicate honestly in a way that's effective and helpful and
and safe i've but we learn and develop that
we learn to be generous maybe in small steps until we feel oh i know how to be
generous i know when to be generous and how to be generous and and you know i know about the world of
generosity a bit and so it's through actions
that we develop ourselves cultivate ourselves it's by actions that
we develop confidence and faith the faith and the dharma faith and buddha in buddhism is not like faith
in buddhism so much there might be some of that but you want to have enough faith in
buddhism that you begin acting in different ways behaving differently
and then the the refuge the faith becomes less and less about buddhism
and more about yourself knowing how to behave and act
beautifully and and so the word beauty
now when the buddha talked about action he talked about
the word here is karma he sometimes in english translations
you'll read his teachings they'll talk about good and bad karma
the word for good literally is in pali ancient language is
beautiful there's bad karma and then there's
beautiful karma what a difference there's bad behavior
and then there's beautiful behavior that creates a very different feeling it doesn't have the moralistic flavor
of good karma i think and so what are we creating here what are we
living our life as what if we say we're doing what's beautiful
living our beauty living beauty and that
is more an ethical life but it doesn't have the heaviness
of being of calling an ethical life it has some sense of maybe for me
some place of freedom and delight and joy that we're living at the joy we're
living the delight of what we want to what we do
and uh so to um
so the teaching about that's so that's so central to the buddhism that it has to
do with action how do we live our life behave in our life
is not always conveyed for people learning meditation
and it's uh there's a particular syndrome among a few individuals here in the modern west
of being uh uh
any any emphasis on doing and doing doing something ties them in
knots because they feel like they they're not they can't do it right they're wrong
they have to strain they have to push they have to try too hard and get tense like this is serious i have to prove
myself all these kind of ideas that weigh down
so much so that if you hear a talk about action you feel exhausted
just hearing about it oh no i have to do more i think i'm just you know i've been that's all i do is do i you know
you know i just need meditation as a break so yes meditation can be a break and to
get that break some people love meditation teachings and buddhist teachings that talk about not don't do just be
it can be very profound to hear the instruction just be and don't do
as an antidote to all the being and doing and proving that goes on in this culture
but as good as this that the teaching is it doesn't really represent the fullness
of what the buddha had to teach the buddha taught about action
and how to do it wisely and one of the ways to do it wisely when
we pay attention we start learning from the feedback loop
when and how our behavior adds stress and stress
how and when our behavior is refreshing and
brings ease we start recognizing the extra attitudes
and that we pile on top that make it kind of heavy and difficult
and we are learning other attitudes that our behavior acting in the world can be
light and easy and fresh and you know there's not we don't we don't care so
much at stake it's just oh i'll do this and i think this is one of the
important things to learn is that as we recognize that actions can
be our own refuge how do we act
so that it's not a burden how do we act how do we live and behave in the world
so that there's a fees and it's beautiful it's it's uh
enjoy it's not what you enjoy to do so by when we finish doing something
we're not exhausted by it but we feel revived by it
it's possible to do that much more than most people realize so that means again mindfulness to keep
the mindfulness turn on oneself and track carefully the extra attention the extra
stress the extra straining that goes into what we do
and to learn how to to act the solution is not to avoid
acting the solution is to act without all the extra stuff
when i was at that zen monastery they there was stories about the founder of it
a japanese monk named shinri suzuki he was pretty short i think maybe it was five foot tall or something
and uh he was in his late 60s and and uh
this young american strong tall he really he kind of loved having tall americans male students
and one of the things he liked about them was they would come to him and help him to help him with his rock garden and
they had these big they had his big boulders and um and uh the stories from those
people who worked with him in the garden was that when when suzuki russia was going to move a big boulder
um he seemed to have used no extra effort than more effort than it was needed
his body seemed to stay relaxed and he knew how to engage move the boulder without any extra strain
so i wasn't there so i don't know what they actually saw but but that principle stuck with me yes you can even move
boulders adding extra on top of it
so beings are owners of their actions
heirs of their actions bound to their actions
originate in their actions and have actions as their refuge
you have actions as your ref can be your refuge and it's your choice
which those two you whether you make it a refuge or make it something that keeps you
bound up and caught and in a certain kind of prison
so those are my thoughts this morning so um we have a few minutes if any of you want
to ask some questions or comments or testimonials about actions or
complaints
or anything else it seems to me very hopeful because i get a new chance all the time
yes it's hopeful you get a new chance all the time yes you do carry with you the effects of
the past but you always always can see okay now i get to start over
so you don't have to be weighed down by it yes
well i do try to do the best i can most all the time
but since i can't guarantee that i will not offend you because i don't i'm not there and you're
being i asked the people around me that if i offend them in any way please
tell me because then i can look at it maybe and correct my mistake but if i don't know
about it i can't so i think i think that's really wise
that's really wise yeah so we we have a lot of you know unconscious behavior and a lot of
foolish behavior and you know all kinds of things we do and so how do we take that into account
uh you don't want to be in a straitjacket and so that's what you just explained was is a really important way of
having a community to support us and finding our way and so to make a make agreements or
arrangements with people you know or to choose friends who can offer you feedback and places
where you're safe to make mistakes and be told about it and find your way forward
this is a really really useful yes
it's difficult for people because people don't want to offend you right yes
thank you thank you
if you would say your names it would be nicer so we can also my name's jeannie
and i'm suzanne i just had the thought that
what you were talking about living with a teenager you start anew every day
because now that i'm in there the the teenager's mood changes from day to
day sometimes moment to moment and you're seeing a new person each day or each moment
and having to learn to flex and change with that and
decide you're going to do things differently is probably very good buddhist practice fantastic because maybe you'll then
learn to do it for yourself because you probably changed more than you realized
great thank you
thank you gill for explaining actions as a refuge it was confusing to
me when i first saw that statement but now it's very clear that good actions can
become certainly a refuge for going forward great great
and beautiful actions too i'm inspired by this idea of called you know calling it beautiful actions
because rather than good actions and uh i don't quite know what to do with it
it's honest to be honest but uh it inspires me quite a bit
hi my name is abhishek and can you please explain what's the difference between a
dread action and a beautiful election that's uh can i distinguish between a good action and a beautiful action
um you know the word good probably both words need
need defining we use it so lightly word use the word good so easily as if everyone
understands what we mean but i think you can ask what do you mean by good
um i i i would like to use the word good that it means that it's useful and a bit
uh beneficial for some purpose uh rather than focusing on the morality of
it its good action is an ethical action which certainly is for some people
that it's useful it's healthy and beneficial for certain things and
whereas beautiful for me is that there is a
uh it's certainly pleasant it's uh it's almost like it like looking at art that just it's so nice to see
someone says something beautiful to another person it's not just useful but there's a kind
of a grace there's kind of a pleasure delight kind of inspiration
uh it's kind of that this you know wow that was well done that was a nice thing
um so you know if i i don't know if this i can i you'll you'll forgive me for being so
poor at examples but if i just said something like well you know
well thanks for that question that was great that was a good question thanks that's one thing right
but if i say wow that was a really great question that
was important you know it makes me reflect on it now and it kind of gives me something to think about even more
that difference and and i hope my answer was was good
but uh thank you so maybe the first was not so
beautiful maybe the second approach beauty is that how is that my getting am i in
the ballpark for you yes so it's what i get is like how we do things uh
relates more to beauty and what within what we do let's move on good oh
the beauty has to do with how yeah i like that very nice
[Music]
okay so i guess okay and uh
thank you all very much for coming and uh you know we used to when we met before
the pandemic we would often periodically ask people to turn next to each other and say hello and all that and i feel
you know a little hesitant to do it now with the pandemic and all that and how we are with masks and being closely
together but if you go outside in the gravel or under the tree or something and
and just maybe some of you would be like to say hello to each other and uh
maybe people you have never met before and if you're standing in the gravel or
you're available to say hello to and maybe chat a little bit yes uh and if anyone's new i'd be happy
to you know show you around or ah
right perfect and yeah jeannie used to do that before pandemic so yes so so she's offering
anybody who's new or relatively new and would like to just say hello to an old timer and hear a
little bit about what goes on here um yeah go see genie you'll be outside too
right great okay during the hall just outside yeah great
okay thank you all