so welcome hello and formerly welcome to happy hour dear sangha
lovely to see you whether this is your first time as for some of
you here yay welcome and if you're
a regular high pr participant yay welcome lovely to be with you and
and practice together in this moment in time so for our practice this
in this moment in time whatever time zone you're in i'd like to um
build on a practice we did on wednesday and if you think oh wait i wasn't here on
wednesday don't worry everything you need i'll share with you no problem
and also to say this practice we've done before in other ways i just want to
relate to it in a different way so let me set the context as i always do in a
few minutes and then start the guided meditation so
so the practice i'd like to invite us to ex to a and to explore
is a merging a combination of
compassion karuna the second brahmavihara the second
heavenly abode together with mindfulness of the breath
also known as anapanna sati if that term makes sense to you so
mindfulness of the breath and compassion combined
and the reason why i'm saying it's building up on what we did on wednesday because wednesday
for those of you who might remember we explored meta loving kindness
and the breath just the sense of the breath being very easeful the the mindfulness of the
breath the breath being infused with kindness with ease
as if you were petting a kitty and it would start
purring in the sense of calm and ease and many of you observed about that oh yeah
what a lovely combination of these two practices meta loving kindness in fact for ourselves for our
bodies that's what we did on wednesday together with the breath so
so related to that today we'll explore compassion practice compassion
when meta when kindness means suffering when
challenge when challenges are held by love kindness care
and combining that together with the breath right
so and today what we'll do is we'll we can start with ourselves and then we'll turn
it outwards we'll turn it outwards
to both have a sense of nourishment of compassion for this being who's ourselves
as well as turning it outwards compassion for the world as we breathe in and out especially because right now
there's a lot of turmoil in our world and there are many beings who are suffering right now and in a war
zone so not to turn ourselves away or gaze away but to sit with to make space
with compassion with care and stability stability not to fall into it not to
fall into grief and despair but to hold to witness hold presence
with compassion with love with care for what is happening in our world
okay the last word i'm going to say about framing the practice tonight is
compassion practice plus
mindfulness of the breath is also what we have explored before
in light of some of you might remember tonglen the practice of tonglen
and yes in the later schools of buddhism not so
much in theravada but in later schools especially in tibetan it's a primary
practice and and we've practiced that before compassion and the breath it's a
beautiful practice many of you have shared that it's been nourishing to you so this is another way to enter into the
same practice i didn't mention tonglen at the beginning i mentioned at the end so that you think
you're you realize oh there are other ways to get into this practice on a panasonic mindfulness of the breath
plus compassion all right enough theory let go of theory
okay i've set the frame we can let it all go ah
let go of the thinking mind so now i'd like to invite you to
sit enter enter the sacred space of practice
together letting go of thoughts letting go of words if you need to move and
shift so that you are comfortable
whether you're sitting in a chair on a cushion
whether you're lying in the bed it's all okay
and arriving first and foremost we always arrive in the body letting go of
thoughts of memories of plans
taking refuge i am here this moment of this precious life here now
right here right now in this body
releasing relaxing
letting the animal of your body to just be
to just breathe you don't have to be any particular way
you don't have to be impressive or great or grand or smart nothing just
ah let go let go release
release oh dear heart dear heart
release it's okay
your body your heart your mind can just be
can just be breathed
in breath and opera
your master breath enters your body
for the purpose of this practice can we imagine can we imagine that
it's entering [Music] being breathed in and breathed out from
the center of our chest the heart center proverbial heart center
and with each breath ah
more kindness is breathed into the body
with each out breath we let go
c
maybe with each in-breath we become more become aware of
the body if there are any challenges pain or tightness and with the out-breath
ah there is goodness ease love care breathed out
unto these challenges unto whatever is ailing us in this moment in our heart or
mind practicing
self-compassion with each breath
c
and this challenging thoughts are arising [Music] the in-breath noticing
with brightness oh this is challenging sweetheart this is heart
with the out breath flowing out of the heart center ah releasing releasing
and bringing breathing out goodness and ease
onto yourself onto the thoughts
with every out breath releasing of goodness care love
with each in-breath recognizing this moment
especially if they're challenges
the body mind and heart and in the out breath letting the love the care wash over the
difficulties hence it becomes a practice of compassion
challenge is met with care with love with warm-heartedness
it doesn't have to be any different in this moment you can meet
we can meet this moment with love with care
with ease for ourselves
c
remember if thoughts are arising it's okay you can release
we can release with kindness with care
without judgment
turning the gaze inward are there any areas of the body
that are achy or tired or tense
the neck shoulders the usual areas
the jaw the forehead
eyes maybe the lower back
as if you were breathing in breathing in the challenges
collecting the challenges the tightness the pain of the body
they're being collected they're being observed through your breath collect it
in your heart center where the breath is breathed in transformed
transformed into a healing light
and breathed out to the whole body
challenges difficulty breathed into the heart center harvard center
this amazing
space of transformation transfiguration
challenge is breathed in transformed
the holy fire and the bright light ah they become
they become goodness love healing energy and breathed out
breathed out through the heart center through the whole body wherever is aching
tired either
literally achy or figuratively aching
even if it's your heart that's aching right now breathing in
challenges breathed and underwater
thank goodness ah sucker
healing light breathed out ah covering the whole body
breathing in breathing out
leaning into their breathing out releasing
releasing ah the tail end of the breath
ah the tail end of the out breath release relax ease goodness
healing here
do
and this orb of light this holy fire in the heart center
transforming transformative
transforming challenges sorrow pain
into goodness into love the path through love
suffering as a path to love
this bright
bright healing light
the heart center is both yours and not yours
it transforms it heals
just holding witness with the breath don't let it become effortful
let ease be your guide
the
so
there have been any challenges today or right now arising
let them be breathed in
let them be breathed into the heart center transformed into healing light
and breathe out throughout the body
do
c
the out breath the out breath bringing healing love care
releasing releasing holding [Music]
as if wrapping this body in the blanket of meta love compassion with the out
breath
there there sweetheart
now i'd like to invite us
to expand our blanket
as ryokan says ryokan respected
zen monk oh if only my monk's robes were wide enough
to hold to protect to cover
all the suffering beings in this entire world
expanding our blanket
as we have stability and care for ourselves
may this being have ease this being who is me
may she he they me may i have ease
may all beings everywhere
have ease be free from their sorrow
and just as with the practice of our breath challenges were being breathed into the
heart center to this magnificent
beautiful bright holy fire transforming suffering
into bright light of love and healing and good will
so too challenges difficulty
pain can be breathed in it's not ours
this heart center is not ours it is ours and not ours it's bigger than
ours greater than who we imagine ourselves to be
greater humanity access
to this amazing possibility of universal compassion
this heart center of ours has to trust to trust just holding witness without tightening
our body or our mind ah challenges difficulty sorrows breathed
in and witnessing it be transformed wow
i didn't know my heart could do this wow
transformed internally into love good will [Music]
healing wishes for the entire world and breathed out
shared with the entire world
may all those beings who are living
without safety in war may they have ease
my breath with each breath i hold witness
and share my goodwill personal and universal goodness
for you dear sisters and brothers dear siblings
in common humanity
may you have ease may all of us have ease
breathing in breathing out
breathing out kindness to the entire world
do
my
so
and for the last moments of this practice period
letting letting your heart shine letting it shine
trusting in the goodness of our heart the good will for ourselves and others
don't get in the way let it shine it's empowering it's powerful
to just be humbled for a moment move aside let your ego move aside
and be humbled by the capacity to care
the capacity to love capacity of goodwill
beyond our imagination for ourselves all and all beings
everywhere may all beings
be free from sorrow and suffering may they be safe
may they have well-being may they be free
[Music]
thank you so much for your practice everyone
hmm
so so we have time for reflections
you can type them in chat if you wish if you type them privately to me i won't
read your name if you type them to everyone i will read your reflection and your name
and if you uh like to raise your zoom hand you're also
welcome to do so
bill says warm and comforting thank you nikki you are welcome bill
another reflections this one private nikki your voice after a long day so
soft so relaxing zzzzzzzzzzzzzz i'm putting you to sleep you are so
welcome if that is what is needed what is healing at this point yeah
yeah so any reflections about the practice
about what you observed what came up for you about this practice in particular
to support you to support others lisa
hi nikki hi um i was just feeling like i woke up
into the fact that it's friday night and
i'm here like practicing and tending to compassion
and it's just i'm just like ecstatic about this like i'm with everyone it's like oh
yeah like this is how i'm spending my time and i and i couldn't be happier about it
so it was like i felt like i just arrived in yeah i'm doing this like other people i
know tonight in particular are are doing other things and i was feeling
care for them and joy for them but like and i'm doing this
yay in in your word so thank you yay
yay thank you lisa thank you for that reflection i am so touched touched by that your realization
of landing i am here you know friday night quote unquote has
all these right associations right in the culture friday and here this is
what i'm doing and i see hearts going off here people are sharing are loving your reflection so beautiful
here i am actually gives me chills here we are here we are
turning our hearts to compassion for ourselves for the world how beautiful how profound
wow yay i'm doing this in my precious time in my
precious life yay wow thank you lisa thank you so much for
that reflection beautiful thank you
yay yay yeah another appreciation thank you this
was very calming [Music] yeah another one lovely inter-healing
meditation now i am better prepared to reach out and send healing energy to others oh
lovely oh that's beautiful that touches me yeah it's lovely
and charlie sends a heart on youtube thank you charles lee good to be with
you practicing ah
so dear ones how about we turn we turn now that
perhaps we've had a few moments to be with ourselves to open up and both
hold each other and hold ourselves in community the nourishing healing power of sangha
so healing yay here we are yay friday evening or friday morning
if you if you are in australia or other time zones uh yay uh us
dear practitioners so so with that i'm going to uh invite us
into small breakout groups for us to practice together and we'll
start with um 15 seconds of silent
meta for each other silent compassion for ourselves for each other and you're welcome to share as little or as much as
you like about your practice or just hold witness if you don't want to speak it's okay just compassionately hold witness
just your presence is enough your presence is enough no words needed
and stay to connect with each other so precious so i'm opening the rooms
here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other yes period of practice here we go
okay everyone welcome back the rooms are closed
and we have just a couple of minutes for any reflections that might have come up
as you engaged and held each other in community
after practice either about your practice in sangha with care and compassion or any reflections about the
meditation at the beginning you can either type them in chat or
raise your hand richard
can you hear me yes okay well i i found myself sort of breathing
in the pain of from my loves and passions from my youth you
know and sort of the unfit finished element of those experiences and
and what i found you know and i tried to just breathe out vanilla compassion but what i what
finally finally worked for me was you know bringing out the gratitude you know
grateful that i had these experiences and that um you know not everyone does and um
and they were very you know deep-ending and transformative at the time
beautiful beautiful thank you for for sharing that richard and there's so many different
flavors of the brahmavihara right the heavenly abode it doesn't always go
where we want it to kind of go it's like yeah meta shape shifts sometimes to compassion sometimes your gratitude
sometimes to equanimity sometimes to joy so what you're actually describing is it's shape-shifting
to um to joy to vicarious joy for yourselves
like wow i'm grateful i have joy that these things happened even if they were challenging which is surprising and
lovely yeah thank you richard well i'm a very lovely
person i know
yeah as as we're all yeah it's great
so so thank you thank you for your practice thank you so much for showing
up for practicing for being together supporting each other in community may
all beings everywhere including ourselves may we may all beings who are in
challenging circumstances right now in places of war may they have ease as much
as possible may they be safe may all beings be happy may all beings
be free
thank you all take good care