okay so formerly hello and welcome to happier
lovely to see you to be with you dear fellow practitioners
yeah so for the theme for today um
the theme is inspired by a conversation i had um
with a practitioner was talking about who was um or having a practice discussion and
about um how they wake up sometimes in the middle of the night
with and they have insomnia and pain and
and this is part of the human condition anyone anyone has ever any one of you who has
never i can't speak tonight the question i'm trying to get out is to
feel into your own experience and remember the times that you have woken
up in the middle of the night with insomnia um or with pain
um anyone not anyone who's not had that experience in
their lives yeah it's it's we all have that experience of waking up
with pain with insomnia or or if not in the middle of the night
um we have a body we have a human body all
of us experience pain at some point it's a part of being human
um it's it's a mark of existence having a body
that experience illness it experiences pain and experiences aging
um etc it's a mark of existence so
so knowing that these are parts of being human it's not a mistake
it's not that you have done something wrong and you're being punished or you're bad it's just part of life these
things happen insomnia happens illness happens because we are human
beings things arise causes and conditions so many of them out of our control some within our
control but so many of them out of our control so many of them out of control
out of our control so so how do we work how can we work
compassionately and with meta with these causes and conditions so
so keep this meditation this teaching your back
pocket the next time you wake up in the middle of the night perhaps with pain or
with uh with insomnia so
so the first invitation the first invitation
is how we approach the perspective we take
with what is arising do we um
self-flagellate do we apply what's called second arrows in the buddha's teachings the first
arrow is the pain the first arrow is the suffering this insomnia that has arisen
because of all the cause and conditions do we then take and and
hit ourselves and injure ourselves with second arrows
of oh why me why is this happening to me why
what's wrong with me like i it's my fault i'm terrible like me bad
bad bad ouch ouch you're already hurting and you know we often take daggers and
just like uh uh we start injuring ourselves even more or this is terrible this is awful make
it go away as if by the force of will we can make it go away
and guess what's especially sleeping in pain the more we tighten the more our
bodies and our minds tighten around it with aversion with wanting to push it
away guess what happens the opposite right they get worse they
get more wound up both with the pain and with being awake so
so the invitation is to recognize if there are second arrows
and if there are second arrows again don't don't take on third arrows like oh
i'm a terrible practitioner i i'm self-flagellating i i've been
meditating for a while and i still i'm hard on myself okay please don't take
third and fourth and fifth error just have some humor kindness it's okay
it's okay it's part of the human condition it's okay this happens
this happens and instead instead what if we turned it around what if we
turned it around let's say in the middle of the night when you're awake thinking
okay great here is an opportunity for practice i could be sleeping but no actually i can
practice in this moment i can practice i can
calm and settle my mind and heart and deepen because often pain often as
you well know already pain suffering sorrow are the doorways
to awakening they are not problems to get rid of
to push away so that now you can practice oh this pain is this physical
pain is bugging me if i could only be comfortable so that i could meditate
like that's such a funny perspective right the pain the suffering this insomnia is
the doorway is the invitation hello dear human being
who is suffering this is what suffering is like ah welcome to acknowledging to opening to
the human condition for yourself and all other beings you can be sure
there are other beings in that moment in time in the world who are also
either having insomnia or having pain thousands thousands of us given that we
have they're what seven or almost eight billion of us or something like that now i think the most recent
uh count i heard um there are there would be hundreds if not
thousands of human beings in that moment who are having the same condition as you
are having so i'll say more in the guided meditation but essentially
we want to open up to the pain to the suffering to the insomnia
ah hold it with with kindness hold it with kindness
hold it with kindness because sometimes we don't you don't
have a choice it's here it's here it's here
it's already here there's not much you can do about it so you can't push it away so by trying to push it away it
actually makes things worse so opening up opening up and you realize actually when
you stop resisting when you stop resisting that some things
let's go something releases something let's go
and so that's number one and number two is meta meta really a lot of meta
a lot of self-compassion because in fact working with challenges it's you know
meditation is not all about bliss and hanging out in blissful states but it turns out that actually working with
pain and sorrow and insomnia can lead to bliss states i mean it seems
counterintuitive how can holding being with challenge lead to
bliss lead to ease but that's exactly what happens which is
which can seem so counter-intuitive but that
i invite you to open up open up
the way that your mind habitually treats pain like okay make it go away
i don't like it terrible i just want pleasure i just want ease open up to the ways that you can grow in
your humanity the ways in which your humanity your wisdom your
compassion can open up can flourish for yourself
for and for others through this pathway
so there is so much to say so much opportunity in this and
i've already spoken plenty and i think i like to switch invite us to switch
to um practice and uh maybe what whatever you need to
no i'll share in the guided meditation i think that's enough we're adornment so
so i invite you to arrive [Music] in your seat
i invite you to arrive in your seat
in this moment arriving [Music]
blending
as always connecting connecting with the breath
arriving arriving in this moment
arriving in this moment
arriving with the breath
with the body whatever is arising in the body
letting go of thoughts of plans whatever has come before not needed
taking a moment of refuge
the breath connected connecting subtly
let it go let it go here
just connecting with the breath in the body
gently ever so gently
ever so gently making space
letting the breath be nourishing healing cleansing as it
moves through
each breath arriving more fully with each breath
imagining that in this moment you're woken up in the middle of the
night with insomnia and maybe some discomfort
it's not turning away pushing it away with aversion hating it
can you turn towards open your heart turn towards let your body relax
open up embrace
this moment of being awake being aware
feeling the body and being breathed fully embracing it fully embracing it
it is like this right now
can i open my heart as if i'm opening my arms wide wide
the way you would open your arms wide to embrace the sunset
very beautiful sky or the clouds or the ocean
this moment is like this
this moment of being alive being awake is like this
what gifts what wisdom what gifts of wisdom and
compassion does this moment have for me
shifting turning our attitude
to open up to this first and foremost
lending awareness running awareness ever so gently
be aware of the body breathing on the body
nooks and crannies maybe there's some discomfort
as if you're holding holy little child [Music]
a baby that was hurting her in your mind's eye holding all the parts
of the body that might not be comfortable
not pushing them away but letting awareness
hold them gently lovingly
can there be patience can there be gentleness
as the mind connects with the body
the discomfort in the body as if cooing is as soothing as a singing
a lullaby
to any part of the body that's not comfortable
that's in pain
gentle gentle gentle care
as if you're rocking this little baby that is your body
goodwill love care for this body
that is mine and also not mine completely
it's nature
this body doing the best it can
with all the causes and conditions of this life
thank you buddy i care for you i hold you with ease
with care tenderness
and now if you wish imagining inviting yourself
to consider that you are not alone
that you are not alone and whatever is arising
in this moment whether it's insomnia
or physical pain challenge
considering that there are so many human beings beings around the world
go have this condition right now or you can expand it they've had it
before or they will have it
and wishing well opening to meta to compassion [Music]
for yourself and all the beings
with this predicament may all of us all of us have ease in our bodies all of
us imagining
perhaps
a man here in the same country a woman in a different continent
an older being on an
island it's okay to use your imagination to get a sense of the common humanity
of this see if you can connect if you can
connect at least one or two a few other human
beings in your imagination
their challenge their difficulty not so different from yours
in order to open in order to help open up the heart the compassion may all of
us may all of us
have ease you can be supportive instead of just
thinking of myself to feel solidarity
so many humans all of us
holding our challenge our difficulty with grace
with dignity may all of us have ease
may all of us have goodness all you dear fellow human beings
just like me may all of us
be free be free from this challenge
may all of us have goodness in our lives
all of us held with universal compassion and love
by the buddha being of light or whatever compassionate
archetype works for you
or perhaps all of us holding each other with care solidarity and mutual
compassion see what works for you
maybe going back and forth to giving compassion may you
imagining a few individuals or one individual may you be free may you have
ease fellow human being dear friend
or may both of us have ease may all of us have ease
giving receiving sharing
opening your heart
teacher in compassion and wisdom
and deepening your humanity
noticing how your heart
can experience generosity generosity
pain not as a problem to hate
to be afraid of but as an opportunity to open the generosity of your heart for others
for yourself
the last few minutes letting your body be
held in the physical body be held in this expanse of
care generosity
wishing [Music] wishing sharing the generosity of your spirit
because of through this challenge all beings everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you everyone thank you for your practice
so so we have a few minutes if any
questions comments any insights reflections
that you like to share for the benefit really for the benefit of others
out of wisdom out of your care compassion
you're invited to share in chat
or raise your hand [Music] and if you share with me privately i
won't read your name if you share publicly i will read
your name and the reflection one private one that was lovely
thank you you are so welcome maybe of support to you now and anytime
in the middle of the night or anytime you have pain or insomnia
which i have had my fair share with my chronic illness it's
a great opportunity for practice it's a gift
a gift of darkness as mary oliver would put it in a poem she says
something i'm paraphrasing um a friend once gave me
a box of darkness as a gift or a friend once gave me a bar a
right a friend once gave me a box of darkness it took me a while to realize that too
was a gift so may we realize that the gifts of darkness boxes of darkness or
to our gifts dave i see your hand
another private message thank you so much for that you are welcome so dave please
yeah i really thank you for this so much this is uh
exactly what i've been needing so much lately uh some time ago
you said something i thought was just the most remarkable thing i've ever heard anyone say so brace yourself this
is going to be a little praise uh when you said i get to suffer
i get to suffer and you were sincerely pleased with that and what a
benefit and a gift that is to uh the practice and
i've been struggling with tinnitus and that helped immensely and the other day
i said to my acupuncturist that i'm going to try to treat it
in principle as the hiss of mindfulness it's not much of a bill
so and uh she liked that and i i'm been working on that and it has
helped a lot and i just want you to know that uh it's it's not as bad as it was it's not
as bad as it was it i every once in a while i get a pang of dread for what it might be in the future
but that you know the future is not here and the practice is really helping me out so
thank you very much nikki i am so attached deeply touched dave
as to how supportive the practice has been to you and the shifting of your
perspective i am so moved i am so moved by that knowing how challenging tinnitus can be
for so many yourself included and how you've shifted your
perspective to be oh a hiss of mindfulness and wow wow how that that shift in perspective
has has um attenuated made it softer easier has
brought freedom in the buddhist words really that what is that that's what freedom is
you know nibbana awakening and freedom seems like so holy but this is freedom
it's right here dave you're experiencing freedom with respect to your tinnitus
so thank you so much yeah beautiful
oh and thanks morrigan for finding the poem from mary oliver someone i loved once
gave me a box full of darkness it took me years to understand that this too was
a gift what a beautiful poem thank you to mary oliver
yeah and also i do want to thank the uh practitioner earlier in the practice
discussion who offered what they were working with so that
their practice can serve everyone and so i want to acknowledge them and
thank them also for their practice as they've offered it
to us as the inspiration for this for this evening so
so dear ones let's turn into practicing together
in small groups and if you can stay please do it's such a privilege to be
able to connect just for a few minutes six seven minutes with fellow practitioners and if you have to
go it's okay but don't go out of fear don't go out of out of wow other human beings they're
just they're really nice so so i'm going to create the breakout
rooms and um as always take care of yourselves
take care of each other don't forget meta compassion and the
these fellow human beings you meet in the small groups are just like you
they have experienced physical pain they have experienced insomnia
we all of us have all of us so opening the rooms take care of
yourselves take care of each other here you go so
welcome back everyone and we have a few minutes for
reflections comments um if any insights arose for you especially
jerry i see your hand shut up please okay
uh yes uh thanks nikki uh we were uh
uh talking in the in the group about the uh
the sangha as well as the small groups as i've mentioned before being the secret sauce of this
additional secret sauce of the sangha but that also um
not just the physical pain as was mentioned to diet about tinnitus but
also psychic pain and the overlap and that both of them
even if they're separate or reconnected they seem to be
it's not that they disappear perhaps but there's a the experience of
the warmth of the sangha and the small groups actually takes the edge off of
this and it's one person called it it's like an
adhesive you want to keep coming back for it and i would say well maybe addiction is too strong a word but i get
withdrawal when i don't get here it's it's the best it's the wholesome
addiction it's the whole some um yeah dharma desire yeah it's it's it's
wholesome it's beautiful it's something that's wholesome and it's wonderful and and thank you for sharing that jerry
that the power of sangha really the power of connection with
with understanding with fellow humans who are on this path is so powerful
so powerful um yeah and thank you for highlighting that
especially when we're going through physical emotional psychospiritual challenges just
we can't we can't do it alone it's hard so hard to do it alone
so yeah greg i see your hand this needs to be quick because it's our seven so go ahead
yeah um it's a mark of of the quality of the
people in this saying i've unfortunately lost two of my best friends in the past week
one of them yesterday and to have the confidence to share that with the two
people who were in my breakout and have them offer
a meta to me in a very meaningful and sort of beautiful way
said something about the group and about the sangha and um
it gives me hope for what is best about about humanity so thank you and and thank you
collectively for that thank you greg thank you so much for
for sharing the heartbreak it's it's oh holding you with tenderness and care
to two of your close friends this in one week is it's hard
thank you for feeling comfortable and safe enough to bring it to the group to go to the
small into the big group and being open to be held with mental and compassion
and thank you for what you said yeah thank you
yeah so yeah so i went to i've gone over time i
wanted to say that i'll see you on friday but on monday and next wednesday and for the
future for wednesdays there will be someone who will be substituting because as many of you know i'll be teaching a
course called befriending mortality which actually many of you i think have already signed up for so i'll see you in
that course and one last uh reflection
says in my group there was mention of the brahmavirus and i recall how they are also useful for meeting suffering
within ourselves and in others i'm also reminded of the talk i heard before about discerning between the parameters
and their near enemies oh yes there's so much there to to discuss as we have also
covered and happier at different times the other such a rich area so i mean thanks for bringing that in
so thank you all thank you for your practice for supporting each other
and yourselves on this on this path may all beings be well may all beings be
free including ourselves
thank you