so hello everyone and welcome and uh
so we're at a day for a natural turning of the planet
and it's kind of symbolic of it's being getting darker for many months now
days shorter and now with no responsibility in our part
nothing we've done the days will get longer you'll be more light
and it's a marvelous wonderful thing that that's the case at least here in the
northern hemisphere and it's different in the southern hemisphere
but they'll appreciate the same thing in six months that there'll be a turn
that towards light towards something it's uh and warmth
and so the same way with meditation um we don't
cause the light the warmth the goodness the
wholesomeness to arise but we enable it we allow it we
make room for it the host the unwholesome mental Tendencies thoughts actions
motivations belong to a part of the Mind that we do activate we do get involved
in it's because they're more the reactive part of the Mind and they hold some certainly we can do
it and activate it and and kind of Bring It about the wholesome
State sometimes but in meditation what we learn is that
um is that we are
that a lot of the wholesome that develops a lot of the goodness that comes in meditation doesn't come from us
making it so much doing it but more allowing it creating the conditions that allow that
not what's reactive to occur but to real allows something
which is a unfolding and emerging and allowing the emergence the wholesome emerges
the unwholesome reacts in a sense
so what I'd like to offer today is one of the conditions that can be phenomenally helpful
for the emergence of the wholesome further and that is
to really stay close to not knowing
stay close to recognizing what's happening so in that sense there's knowing being with mindful of breathing
the body the experience you're having but beyond recognizing it the Simplicity
of it don't know what it means don't know where it's going what's happening
just get out of the way so I don't know this is what's happening I don't know
not knowing so that we're not riding close with the
signing meaning identifying making it Me Myself and mine operating from what should happen or
what shouldn't happen expectations desires for what's supposed to happen desires for what's not
supposed to happen just know what's happening in the sense
of recognition recognition clear recognition
and just not know anything else they're kind of not knowing that makes
room that kind of empties a crowded mind
of all its thoughts and concerns and projections and then emptying of the mind of it's
all the crowded visitors makes room for something to emerge
then what emerges from your depths trust that
trust the Simplicity of not knowing while recognizing oh
and the recognition can be phenomenally simple if there's not obvious what something is
you can simply recognize it as something don't have to go digging or analyzing
something and then over time just just something
and I don't know and then see what emerges what becomes clear
so to assume a meditation posture
a posture of feeling Worthy
of something important feeling worthy as a human being a
posture that expresses this even if you don't feel that way
because that sense of worthiness or dignity nobility
is a condition that allows something from the depths to emerge that's different
if we take a posture that's the opposite of self-worth or dignity
gently close your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths and as you exhale
and let go of knowing let go of
meaning making thinking about the future a past
what should be what shouldn't be
let go and begin let the visitors let the crowd your
mind begin to leave float away
letting your breath return to normal
just sitting here quietly for a few moments finding your way into a
wholesome satisfying attitude of not needing to know so much
not needing to judge or assign meaning or
even a sign of future through what's happening just being present
making the room of not knowing
and maybe in the middle of this vast field of not knowing
your body is breathing the rhythm of breathing
a rhythm that moves through
a mind of not knowing a mind that's present
maybe they're not knowing is replaced by a
greater attentiveness
a peaceful alertness to what is
and if your mind starts thinking about something you might take a moment to see or feel
that the thinking is operating
on some kind of thing that doesn't you assume you know the Mind assumes it
knows
even if that simple as assuming it knows that it's supposed to know
supposed to figure something out let there be a not knowing
that not knowing the mixed room
to be with the depths of your being
when you're lost in thought and recognize it
say to yourself not knowing don't know
you don't really know
or you don't really need to know whatever you're thinking about that's
not right here and now in the simplicity
of being with what emerges in the body and in the heart
foreign
not knowing
creates different opportunities than knowing
if you go into the world knowing
I think it can be effective and have good results
but if you enter the world and not knowing
you expand the possibilities
if you meet a friend and don't be and begin by not knowing
you get to experience more of the fullness or the uniqueness of that moment of your
friend and you get to have more room for yourself
knowing Narrows possibilities often not knowing
taking a few moments not to know but to discover
allows us to open to something new
so at this end of this sitting as we do the dedication of Merit
what would it be like to care for the world
where there's care
but also room for discovery
where there's love but the space of not knowing what's
supposed to happen and what's going on
so I'll say the dedication but maybe let it open you to not knowing
than not knowing that can be there together with love
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
may all beings know the respect
of others being available to know who they are
without projections and judgments and even a past
let people as you go through the world
have the respect of the not knowing mind as you bring your presence and attention
to take in another person and may that bring peace
than love and happiness
[Music]
thank you
oh goodness hello everyone and
done their souls to stay
and the topic this week is Right effort and today we turn towards
the effort to
allow the wholesome to emerge so there's a classically in Buddhism
there's a dichotomy the division between those mental States motivations
thoughts activities just about anything that is afflictive
and that which is beneficial and uh in this dichotomy
what might be in the middle that's neither afflictive or beneficial is not really addressed not really
talked about not because there's maybe a radical Duality between these two but the
neutral is not spiritually so meaningful so important to focus on it's as a place it
is what it is but uh in terms of the training and the growth and development
that Buddhism is about it's not particularly relevant
it would be like something like um
I mean I don't know what an example would be but if someone is training
for a bicycle race
there are things that they do that could undermine their training and things that can
support it and then there's things that can happen that do neither that uh it's just simply something
that's happening and so for example if you I don't know
um maybe if the person just likes to read about
um the score and football football scores and standings
it might be a neutral might be pleasant to do might be nice if a person likes that but in terms of the training for
the bicycle race it's neither the here or they're there so the Buddhism has this dichotomy
between the wholesome and the unwholesome and the unwholesome is afflictive and the and the wholesome is
beneficial and what it implies is that or what it indicates is that there are uh
beneficial states of Mind movements of Mind heart that can live within us
that are beneficial that are good and useful and so we want to enable that or evoke
those or allow room for those and that these are important
and it Buddhism is not just about abandoning and letting go and
renouncing the abandoning of Buddhism they're
letting go is that when the Buddha talked about it
he's very seldom talks about letting go of things it's always an inner world if you're
letting go of clinging to things attachments craving the things that we're caught in
so we don't have to necessarily let go of things of the world wisdom might tell us to do that
compassion might tell us to do that but in terms of the Dharma they what we're letting go of is the
inner the clinging the attachments in the mind but that's not all we're supposed to do
sometimes people kind of pick up some simple idea of Buddhism and think oh this Buddhism is all about letting go
but in fact that's important that's part of the four right efforts but equally
important is the cultivation or the allowance the development of beneficial States
wholesome States skillful States and there's a lot of them the ones that
are closely associated with the mindfulness practice are the seven
factors of Awakening so things like well mindfulness and investigation
effort endeavoring again Joy Tranquility concentration equanimity
elsewhere happiness is important patience wisdom
states of mind that are expansive open peaceful boundless loving kindness
compassion sympathetic Joy there's a whole slew of them and there's so many that the mind
can go dizzy we're like wow I have to get busy here and do so much but it isn't so much that we have to do
them all and all at once there's another art here and it's not necessarily the art of
making and doing but the allowing and the um the language is uh uh usually
translated into English as the arising uh when when makes room for one makes
space for what it puts energy into the arising and of wholesome States
the language of rising I sometimes like to to rather than calling it rising to
call it emergence and why I like the emergence is that it
doesn't imply that we're the doer we're the maker of it but rather there's something within us that wants to be
born something that has the capacity of emerging coming out and our job is to
make space for that emergence to allow for that and the reason I trust this so much is
that the afflictive emotions and states of mind I associate more with the
surface reactivity it's it's the world of reactions to what's happening in the world and how it impacts Us and how it
impacts our attachments and our fears and as deep as that those can feel take
they are uh they still have to do with this interactive world it's more on the surface
the emergent world comes from some a different place within
and it's uh and it's something that can well up as opposed to react uh react to
and so we don't have to have anything in particular happening in the world that triggers us triggers The Beneficial it's
more like we get settled and make room for it and this is a remarkable thing to discover in meditation that the more
peaceful we become more quiet and calm we become the more we have this kind of
sense of not knowing just willing just to be here in our experience and make room for
then then the beneficial kind of begins to flow and come out it's not
intentional but it's more uh something that um uh
the intention is to make room for it to allow for it to be with it
and um so it can seem a little bit passive it can be kind of a little bit magical thinking to think of you sit
there and okay I'm just going to sit here and do nothing and something will emerge that's wonderful
um maybe that's little like um um you know just you know and a little you
know too passive the language of right effort is kind of dramatic
um and Powerful I would say so here's the the classic description of
the third right effort practitioners take up
and so this is my own translation so if you look it up somewhere else you'll find a little bit different they're
quite different practitioners take up and take hold of their minds
so that take up and take hold of their minds it doesn't mean you know grab on and it means that they enter into the
world of their minds they're they uh the thinking mind and the reactive mind
doesn't have us we are there for our mind there's kind of Freedom there
who's in control the mind or you and in a certain kind of way in this practice you are
um uh and the machinations of the mind uh don't have us don't grab us by the
nose and pull us around so another way of saying this is uh to
really be present in a full way take up and abide in the heart
think up and take hold of their minds and generate desire
and then Endeavor and initiate courageous effort for the arising of wholesome mental
States that have not yet arisen
so generate desire so have some desire for wholesome states that is a good
thing and initiate courageous effort Veria
not to make space for it but trust it's okay to have it there are times where having
this kind of open experience of presence and attentiveness and and awareness to
the world in an open way feels very vulnerable and very scary
uh to be able to feel the depth of what's going on for us we have to go through layers of things which are
difficult and so they keep opening and being okay this too this too I stay with
and this courageous effort to not believe the thoughts in the mind that you have to fix and do and react and
blame but this courageous effort to really be present
in a simple relaxed way here putting aside all the other things
to allow something to emerge and first my wife might have emerges grief and
sadness and anger that's been long unresolved but trusting just opening
opening and seeing what it wants to emerge and the courageous effort is to keep
getting out of the way for that and and this idea of not knowing can be
a way to get out of the way to allow something to begin to come and this not knowing and this emergence
seems to work best when we're most settled most calm most peaceful
it doesn't work so well if we're caught up in our reactive world that's kind of a self-perpetuating world of samsara
and um and so to drop down to quiet down
or to be pause long enough to have this not knowing this availability
for something here to emerge and when you make room when you take the
time to stop the running the running of the Mind the running of
the body running around doing things if you take the time
to pause the sacred pause to feel and be available what is here
what wants to emerge what wants to be born even in times of great crisis unless
there's a danger but great challenges become quiet enough to ask the question
what here wants to be born in the middle the center of it all what
wants to emerge and as things emerge that are wholesome
that are beneficial that are nourishing uh that are nutritious for the heart
allow for them let them come
so a lot of this third right effort is not making something happen
but rather availing ourselves of what's already here
I'd like to propose to you that you have more beneficial States going on all the time available to you
that if you pause or make room more quiet down just a moment you'll start
feeling that things are good there's reasons for Joy there's reasons for happiness there's reasons for
kindness for love there's reasons for um
curiosity and interest in a delightful nourishing way what's here as opposed to oh no this again
um Avail yourself so more the feet more rather than making yourself a certain
way that's wholesome see if you can kind of pause and make space and Avail yourself of the
wholesome that's already here and available no matter how small it is no matter that it's
um accompanied by unwholesomeness don't give the unwholesome a lot of
authority that it takes you and grabs you and pulls you around or you have to kind of
listen to it or obey it Avail yourself of the wholesome that's
here and if you don't have it for yourself then borrow it from others
if you can be with people or somehow have connection with someone or even if it's you know
on the web something you know put yourself in the presence of people
who you feel are emanating something wholesome
and then kind of borrow it from them so you can Avail yourself of it and begin
begin exploring the world of the emergence of the wholesome
so that would be the homework for it uh today is make yourself available for the
wholesome so it's not so much it's not making it but seeing making space for it it may be
available for it to be there and if you're only running around then there's no space
no possibility so thank you
and uh look forward to our time tomorrow