so hello everyone warm greetings from
here at Insight Meditation Center and uh
dark morning I think it's just a little teeny bit of hint of light in the sky
out the windows so
what I'd like to say today from preparation of this meditation
is that um one of the discoveries in doing
mindfulness meditation maybe a lot of meditation that goes kind of kind of deep concentrated enough
is how much our experience is mediated by Concepts
Concepts that run quite deep in the mind so we don't really realize that we're
living in Concepts and so to give a very simple idea that
I'm looking here now that um the camera for seeing you all on
YouTube is on top of a bookcase with uh four shelves
I see it as a bookcase if we go back in history Maybe
a few only a few tens of thousands of years and bring this bookcase to the people
who lived on the planet at that time I don't think they would have seen it as
a bookcase I don't know what they would have
thought about it and I wouldn't know how they would use it maybe they'd put it down
flat on the ground on its back and use it to store different things
to distinct or maybe the store kindling for wood
maybe it was a kindling holder I don't know but they wouldn't see it as a book case that I'm sure
and the idea of seeing a bookcase I can do
uh you know effortlessly it's like you know
you know I don't have to think about conceive or have a thought bookcase it just you know what else could it be
so but as we sit and meditate this uh this subtle conceptual mind
begins to quiet and quiet and not seeing it as a bookcase in the
deep meditation is not a big deal particularly or relevant but what happens in with the eyes closed
meditating is that the concepts we have of our body
begins to dissolve begins to stop operating
so I think for the uh I think a couple of days ago
I clipped my fingernails and in my meditations over since then
uh I have not thought once about my fingernails
but I could have I could have thought my fingernails now short maybe I didn't cut them quite
right maybe they should have been more curved or rounded or this way or that way
and I'm having fingernail thoughts but but luckily for me I was able to
meditate without thinking about my fingernails I could think about
um you know that uh meditation think about my hair
and I have thoughts about my hair and how long it is and should I get a haircut or this or that
but luckily I did not have to think about my hair during meditation and so my hair and my fingernails
receded from attention receded from awareness something I wasn't really it
wasn't not only it wasn't really in my experience it wasn't really something that I thought about or that I I
perceived partly to in meditation to perceive
fingernails and hair I kind of need to have some concept idea
that's operating but without them they recede they kind of disappear
and um so as we sit and meditate if we sit in
front of a mirror and look at our face we have all kinds of face thoughts
but when we're sitting closed with eyes closed there's no maybe very few thoughts about the face
and the face is not that can still be a concept when we think about but there's no Direct
seeing of the face because there's no mirror that the eyes are open and the
ideas of her face come from memory and ideas unless there are kind of itching or pressure or tinkling in the face
warmth in the face then we feel Sensations but those Sensations can occur without the clear
mental image or clear uh self-conscious thought about what our
face looks like so this is a way of trying to explain that as we meditate deeper and deeper
the definitions the ideas the concepts that we use for the body begin to quiet
down and we begin finding the body after a while has no boundaries it has no edges
it has the things that we of course we have these things in the body but the conceiving of it the perception of it
quiets down and is entering into a world where the
body is experienced it's not experienced as solid not experienced as bounded
not experienced as something conceived or remembered
and it's uh just all these different uh um Sensations
but the sensations can exist without connecting it to a concept of that place
the warmth I feel the moment in my hand I can say hand
but I can also just experience the warmth without any concept of hand it's kind of
like in and of itself the warmth that just kind of hovering in a certain kind of space
and exists quite happily independently of idea of hand
the edges of the hand disappear and they're just warmth and other
Sensations there so so this is a direction that meditation
goes as the mind gets quieter the conceiving mind that thinking mind defining mind gets quieter
that the body begins to get more diffuse lighter
wispier there's feels feeling that there's lots of space in the body
that the edges are porous or the edges are diffuse they just
disappear so taking a comfortable upright posture
begin with being very clear idea of having a body
and you assume a nice posture with this body of you
and within this body aware of eyes
enclosing the eyes within this body a clear concept of
breathing and where breathing occurs in the body
and feeling what changes in your body as you take some long slow deep breaths
relaxing the shoulders and the exhale
relaxing the belly
letting the breathing return to normal
on the exhale relaxing the face muscles
and on the exhale relaxing
calming your thinking the thinking mind
so in the beginning of meditation Concepts ideas of the body are useful
and then to begin settling into breathing
and many other concepts of body are no longer needed letting them go in favor of
being attuned to the sensations of breathing
the rhythm of breathing
and as you breathe
let the attention
receive take in sensations of the body breathing
where what part of the body do you feel those Sensations
you don't you don't have to think about you don't have to operate with an idea
concept image of chest to feel the movements there
belly to feel the movements there
just movements just pressure release of pressure
expansion contraction
with every exhale quieting the thinking mind
or with every exhale letting go of your thoughts
letting them Drift Away like clouds drifting into the sky
as you're meditating there might be parts of your body
for which you have no perceptions of unless
you think about it for example you might not be perceiving
that toenail of your middle toe on your left
foot
maybe during this meditation so far there's been no perception
of one of the knuckles on your hand
until you go looking for it
if there's no backrest you're leaning against
the perceptions of your back rip cage are probably much more subtle than the
front rib cage
maybe there's a feeling of space around the subtle sensations of the back ribs
edges are diffuse
attune yourself to how within the body
that there's plenty of locations where there's more sense of space than there
is clear Sensations
where they're not sharp boundaries
and becoming aware of the space between Sensations
of your body
and in that place of space diffusion
absence of Concepts might there be a feeling of peace
Stillness maybe even safety
if there is stay close to that
breathe with it content
to rest for a few minutes
in this spacious Ness of the body
thank you
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine or feel or sense that the body is porous
that it's mostly made up of space at least the body that we
directly perceive with the eyes closed
the body that is not as is that is not conceived
but rather perceived through the senses
that that perceived body is diffuse spacious open
and that the words people speak travels right through that space not
touching anything the things that we see in the world
in a way just kind of doesn't land in the space
the space is not troubled agitated by anything
and so the heart can be receptive and opened
without reacting Contracting asserting
in the spaciousness of the body the heart
can be kind you can move the world with
simple good will
looking upon all things kindly
looking upon all things with the generosity of care
with the spaciousness of the body
maybe may we care for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so we come to the fourth talk on the similes for meditation
and we're going through the similes that are used for
strong concentration practice for the genres for absorptions
and where they these similes are particularly uh apt particularly representative of some
of the deeper experiences in the the kind of phases through which
clearly clear kind of stages or phases that we go through as the mind gets really settled and focused quiet
and I I appreciate how much these uh descriptions who work for meditation well short of
deep absorption that meditation even uh even mildly
excited meditation goes through phases and the body the sense of the body
changes or their sense of self changes all kinds of things changes uh and as we settle even
modestly and some of what the the similes for deep concentration
represent or how they feel can be experienced sometimes in lighter meditation and to
recognize and feel like kind of supports the deepening support's sort of opening up to settling even more and more
and part of the advantage of being sensitive to some of these shifts and changes in in um in uh
in more ordinary deepening of meditation is that we're starting to get comfortable with it to recognize it so
when the meditation is really deep we're already somewhat familiar and we
recognize it and we don't get excited or sometimes people get afraid or or kind
of confused by it we're already familiar with kind of oh now I know this is just
a deepening of what I've already had and know about
so we come to the simile for the fourth genre
the fourth John is estate a very deep tranquility and equanimity
and um and in it the uh because fourth child of
the mind is so still and quiet that there's very little Concepts
conceiving making of Concepts in which through which we see ourselves and the
world around us and in fact there's no but the eyes closed there's no thoughts no conception
no perception of the world around us anymore because we're so subtle and
content and peaceful here that everything else recedes
and one of the things that recedes from awareness when we're quite settled and peaceful and the mind is calm is the
sharp definitions of the body the sharp the way we understand the body
and so much of uh experience of the body
is in fact mediated through Concepts being self-conscious about the body
often has to do with maybe comparisons one concept versus another
We compare our body with someone else's body type our body is to
thin or too large or too small or too something and uh and it's possible to
get really wrapped up in body Consciousness and these ideas and Concepts that have a lot to do with
comparative thinking impairing ourselves to an ideal to other people to how we
were when we were younger and this is all navigating in the world of Concepts and ideas which belongs to the world of
of uh thinking mind conceptual mind
um the body in and of itself in the terms of its perceptions of
itself where uh perceiving sensations of the body the
sensations of the body are free and independent of the concepts we have
and this where someone you know with regular Street Consciousness this might be inconceivable
that there are we can experience the body without any concepts especially if
if their concepts are so deeply ingrained in the mind we don't even know
that we're conceiving them and um
and so uh but there's there's kind of this very you know deep layers of the
Mind where conceptions operate even without words even without images it's
just kind of there and all that can get quieter and quieter and we can start perceiving the body
um uh without kind of really any without seeing it without any clear sense that
there is a body here so the simile that's for this is a
delightful simile of a person a little bit I embellish it but the
person you know they're two earlier ones have to do of the being a lake kind of being in a lake
and imagine that you've gone for a nice bath lay swim in a beautiful clear water
and you've come out of the lake and and maybe you've been grimy and dirty even backpacking or hiking or something and
you're been maybe days without a shower and finally you're able to go to this beautiful quiet Lake and clean yourself
really thoroughly and well and all the dirt and grime is off you and
and you come back on the shore and you're very contented
very happy there's nothing to do nothing to be you've arrived where you want to come be
and um and you someone gives you a um completely clean
um soft cotton blanket to wrap yourself around in him and uh
completely enveloped in this blanket so that no part of the body is not covered by this blanket this
and um and in a land where there's flies and insects flying around you're
protected from those in the blanket you're protected from the Sun and nothing comes in
um that way maybe you're protected from the wind it just feels so nice and safe and protected inside this blanket
and because you're inside completely enveloped in this blanket uh no one no
one you can't see the body the blanket kind of the soft kind of
Gauzy blanket um means the body is not seen
but inside that blanket the person you is completely feeling clean so Purity
there's a cleanliness there's a radiating feeling that can happen after you're really clean perhaps a shower or
a bath or something and very content and and kind of peaceful
feeling of everything is good and everything is right in the world
so that's a simile that this person enveloped in a clean cotton blanket
um and no part not covered and um and so in this deep meditation of
the blanket shows us that you can't see the body we don't perceive the body in ordinary ways the body gets diffuse gets
it kind of disappears there might be individual Sensations the here and there but they're very almost disappear
entirely remember the similarly before yesterday there's still things in the lake
the lake still has a certain kind of substantiality there's water in it
that and there's individual lotus flowers floating in the lake so there might still be Sensations in
the body they're just floating in the lake floating in this kind of spaciousness of the water
and this four assembly there's all you know really almost there
can be almost no Sensations at all of the body um there's uh that almost like the body
disappears except for this feeling of cleanliness
of refreshment that's come from the from the bath this feeling of being peaceful
being tranquil this feeling of being equanimous just everything's okay the work the of what
you had to do has been finished nothing needs to happen there's nothing the next contentment there's no
reactivity of the mind no being for or against anything just very
very content and deep there's no clear sense of rapture or pleasure or Joy or
Delight there's something that feels more satisfying which is a kind of this
kind of feeling of deep kind of cleanliness and Purity and peace that
seems to radiate kind of where the body used to be
and um and it's a lovely experience
I've known people and I've done this where the body seems to disappear in these states
and kind of beginning doubting do I really have a body anymore has my body really disappeared and then opening the
eyes to see looking into the body's still there it didn't go away
because the sense of the body disappearing is so strong that that you want to check and make
sure you're still there and um so uh
the so one of the important lessons in this
kind of through the simile and but also the kind of meditation that's can be a little bit like this
is that as meditation deepens where uh experiencing ourselves experience our
life free of many of the ordinary Concepts that we live with on automatic pilot
and some of these Concepts that we take for granted We Believe to find reality this is what's really happening
turns out to be provisional turns out to be just concepts conceivings of the Mind
and they're not inherent they're not exactly what they have they don't have to be there
and when a lot of these concepts of ourselves our body and what's going on
um bring us a really heavy a burden or bring a lot of suffering and distress
it's kind of surprising and radical to have all those Concepts disappear and
stop and feel this deep peace and contentment without anything in the world having
been fixed or anything you know challenges in our body that we have fixed because the body
just has somehow there's a different way of experiencing life or a different way of experiencing that is not mediated by the concepts
that we are usually navigating or struggling with and that puts a little question mark
after the concepts after the struggles we have is this really as real as I
thought it was is this really a substantial and necessary as I thought
it was there is another way here the Buddha when he was a in the suit
does and the discourses there's um talking him himself as an old man 80
year old man and back in Ancient India there were no pain medication there was no the kind of
medications that we have that can make aging so much more easier there's there
was no palliative care in hospitals to reduce the pain
and um and he wrote he told you he talked about how much his body hurt and
was creaky and um that he was bent over in his old age his back and and um and that the only
place that he got relief from all his pain was to go into this deep state of
meditation that the symboly is for and I imagine that's where he got refreshed and renewed so that he can
continue going on with his life with this creaky old painful body kind of
lifted it for a while and refreshed him and and um and um
so this kind of meditation is very useful for us and can help a lot
but the biggest help for people doing mindfulness meditation it can begin to
free us from The Authority the hegemony of Concepts and ideas
and we see them as provisional conditional contingent
um not always necessary to live by them and this is kind of a paradigm shift
that meditation can take us to and hopefully in doing so help us be
much wiser navigating in the world of Concepts
so um thank you and so we have one more simile
and that'll be tomorrow and I think sometimes people go away on Friday
and so we don't quite have as many people here so maybe I'll make an announcement today and tomorrow about
the next few weeks is that uh next week uh Cod o'connellan
will be leading the the 7 A.M while I'm on Retreat and the
following week um May Elliott will give the
the talks also went on one retreat and they're they're related to each other
they're married and they're both of them in the imc's teacher training program they're wonderfully promising young
teachers and they have a little similar background as myself in that they have
also been practicing with the San Francisco Zen Center have a Zen background and kodo is actually a priest
there and um like I was and but also very deeply personal practitioners and
now you know in our in our the personal insight to teacher training program they're a delight and I think you'll
enjoy them quite a bit and um and then the following two weeks after that I'm going away for Thanksgiving and
then I do another Retreat so I won't be here for four weeks and um
and uh the um um but you'll be taken care of somehow
and uh during this time and I think it's very supportive for all of you when you
show up for each other here so I hope that you you know you're you offer that
support and I'll I'll um be back in in the beginning of December but I'm here
tomorrow great thank you