so good morning everyone and i appreciate very much the
many greetings on the chat and
and for the familiar names that i see it's nice to feel like i'm come back after be gone for two weeks
and it is nice to be here
so for this uh guided meditation
i would like to evoke equality uh impulse or
that maybe isn't evoked that often in buddhist practice
and that is um a strong desire
for practice to do this practice often the reputation buddhism has
sometimes in as a caricature it's about not having desires that desires are bad
and we should have no desires we can let go of them
and that's not true there are particular kinds of desires to be let go of
and other kinds of desires to live by to engage in
and we undermine ourselves short short week
um limit ourselves by not appreciating healthy desires that
we have and the desire to become free of suffering the desire to
let go of the ways in which other desires limit us
and bring more suffering to us the desire to overcome those
doesn't have to be limiting doesn't have to be a source of suffering it's the movement out of suffering we
need to have it and to have a strong desire
and learning how to have strong desire that's not stressful that's easeful
that makes the heart sing and feels great and yes this is what i want to do
so so to assume a meditation posture
and
perhaps sitting up a little bit straighter than normal so that the chest is maybe
without being strained or puffed up the chest is a little more open
to the possibility of confidence
being confident
and then lowering your gaze to about you know
down towards the floor perhaps or in some way having your gaze if your
eyes are open be soft and relaxed
not looking at anything in particular maybe even the eyes are gently
moving about but not really looking at anything
and then if it's comfortable to gently close your eyes
and gently let your body relax
almost as if there's an invitation from your body
to release the holding that's throughout your body
maybe in the micro muscles
softening the shoulders
softening the belly
maybe relaxing the muscles of the face
around the eyes cheeks jaws
maybe the area around your lips and your mouth can be more relaxed if you let your lips
fall fall apart slightly
and if you want them touching gently float them together again
taking a few long slow deep breaths
and relaxing again throughout your body as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
in whatever way it's available to you nothing
dramatic to feel the stillness or the quiet within
and within and within that stillness and quiet
say the word yes y-e-s
and see what in that quiet
what gets evoked in a simple yes
and then say again yes to this meditation period
to the practice of meditation now
yes
it may be a yes again for being mindful being aware here and
now yes this is the practice
perhaps yes that doesn't disturb
whatever degree of calm or quiet there is inside
but it does gently animate it energize it
with a sense of purpose sense of
willing to engage to practice
and then if you're going to be with your breathing during the sitting
maybe your label your note for the exhale can be yes
or for the inhale gentle quiet quieting yes
that keeps you on track keeps you here
a certain heightened
attentiveness to just this moment of practice
here now yes this is the place to be to practice
in this body at this time
an affirmation that gives some
weight or intenseness
to being here and now with a quiet attentive mind
so
it is all too easy to say
maybe unconsciously yes to a distracted mind
instead say yes to being here and now in this practice
of mindfulness let that yes
that affirmation of the practice the desire to do it
emerge arise out of the depth of your being
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn the attention outward into the world the world that is filled with both
suffering and happiness
filled with potential for greater suffering and greater happiness
and the look upon that world with a yes
to meeting it caring for it valuing all the people and beings of
this world
and saying yes to whatever movement of heart you might have
that wishes for the happiness and welfare of others for everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and may the wholesome desire to
work for this possibility may it live in us
for our own welfare and happiness as well may we become freer
through the desire to bring freedom to others
[Music] so
[Music]
you
um
so hello everyone and greetings on this beginning of the week
and this week what i'd like to do
is to pair up for these five days
teachings about five things that tie us down five things which bind us
with five things that untie us which unbind us
and i think often um this tradition of ours
tends to have a lot of lists for things that are the attachments and
the defilements and what brings us suffering but to clearly uh link these to their
opposite that which moves in the other direction i think we'll clarify
some of what this buddhist practice is about so the first so these five will be um
raga dosa moha
the moment i can't remember the pali for the fourth
conceit and ditty views and
the um so these are sometimes translated into english the first one is greed but
there's another word that's a better fit for greed and the word raga
is often translated into english as lust or passion and then there's
aversion or hostility delusion and conceit
and speculative views being caught up in stories and opinions
and the opposite of those because a variety of things but ardency and determination
is a kind of desire healthy desire restraint and avoiding
is a healthy kind of aversion in a sense and a
and instead of delusion there is insight and understanding instead of conceit there is a powerful
form of confidence that we might almost say self-confidence
and then in instead of speculative use being caught up in
opinions and all that there is um a real understanding
um so um so the first one raga
pairing that up with ardency with determination perseverance engagement a
desire to practice and here we point out that
there's often assumption that buddhism is critical of desires that all desires
are somehow wrong and the problem of life is that we have desires and
the ending of desires is the whole point of all this
um what we're ending is unhealthy desires desires which keep us limited uh in
bondage caught up in themselves and uh and we're awakening within us within
us desires for freedom desires which are healthy and healing and beneficial
and that it not just simply awakening healthy desires but also
letting become strong uh you know a real sense of
ardency of ardor of dedication getting oriented and organized like this
is important and really doing it putting our some some of us put some
people life and our life energy behind this this is what we're doing no question about it
and um and this difference between desires that bind us and desires which untie us that
free us is such an important distinction and that plays itself out in all five of
these that we're going to talk about this week that it's a distinction we want to learn to
be wise about to recognize the distinction between um
that which brings strain brings stress brings despair brings contraction
brings feel kind of limited and narrow versus that which helps us to feel
expansive and open and happy and free and and uh
one uh then narrowing contracting does reinforce conceit that tightening up the
inward focus of suffering um that that suffering brings is is a
birth or a certain kind of very tight kind of self-preoccupation whereas the expansive movement of uh of
the path of the practice of possibility of freedom tends to free us from excessive
self-preoccupation from this tightening around self and with that it it gives room
for there to emerge all kinds of wonderful qualities of heart inner qualities of
love of compassion love of freedom love of truth that love of peace all kinds of things
that come that are freeing of self speaking of the self-preoccupation
so um on one hand for this for today we have a raga
and raga as i said is often translated as lust sometimes as
passion and there is a raga which is the lust or the passion
for the senses and there is the lust for
raga the lust or the passion for views and stories
what it is is a strong intense form of compulsive desire
it i think of it as a driveness that desires which has us by the nose
and we have almost no cho no choice but to follow follow it or be pushed around by
it or give into it it's a very very compelling
and uh so compulsive passion so sometimes in modern english the word
passion is a very positive quality and when it's used to translate text
buddhist texts it's it's really a strong very strong
compulsive um force where there's no freedom in it a comp
compulsivity that involves suffering which is the original i think latin
meaning for the word passion the passion of christ was a suffering of christ
and um and so and raga is one of the fundamental sources for
suffering for bondage it is one of the one of the ways that three poisons
are listed that they're raga is something which is poisonous
and um so you might protest a little bit that but you have to appreciate that the
definition of whatever raga is is that it's a poison
is it it's a it's a uh it's something which hurts something has
has barbs and thorns in it that are often not seen because the promise of compulsive
desires of different kinds the promise is a promise of pleasure that
comes along with imaginations of pleasure and how wonderful it will be and how much good it's going to do us
and so we're tricks sometimes about the imagination and
by the by the future what's possibilities are so that we're not really present for the
cost of these compulsive desires in the present moment
and and but it becomes clear and clear these kinds of this kind of study this
kind of exploration when we meditate to argue about
desires without meditating probably is not going to be very productive
but as we begin meditating and getting quieter and stiller more mindful then we start seeing
the cost of what happens in our minds and something that to seem defined in
daily life because we're not really that sensitive as we go about daily life
we see that meditation is actually quite limiting it's quite not only limiting but it's
quite undermining of ourselves or brings a kind of stress and tension
that is very different from a calm quiet meditation where the mind is open and
relaxed and present and so in meditation it's a wonderful laboratory to see
when that the shortcomings of um
of uh compulsion shortcomings of of passionate
cravings and clingings the passion for power the passion for money the passion for the lust for money
the lust for power exactly the english words we want to use
to translate raga is not so clear but the raga uh all
uh it is not something that goes away quickly it's also something which slowly over
time fades away and uh one of the meetings of raga is a die
and the movement of the practice is v raga which is a fading of the day
so fading of of lust of this drivenness and how does it fade away
well partly by the opposite there has to be a strong desire
and it's the desire for freedom can be as strong or stronger than any
compulsive desire we have provided that there is not compulsion in that
there's not tension or strain in that desire the buddha emphasized a lot of words
for having strong desire for practice ardency ardor
sometimes it's translating to english the word striving a word which really is resisted by western english dharma
teachers even myself i hesitate to use the word striving because english speakers will often feel
tense from that and like straining if they're striving it's kind of synonymous synonymous with strain
but the the determination
the perseverance a big yes that's why i like the word yes
because it has this uplifting and opening quality to practice with a yes
this is what i'm doing i'm practicing on the path of freedom practicing yes to be present here
and so i uh we are allowed in buddhist practice
to have a strong dedication strong devotion to
the path of freedom and which might mean that we give it a
big priority in our life we maybe clear the table clear our lives
a lot of things which distract distract from that some of them might be worthwhile in
their own right but we have you know really an important thing to do
uh this path of freedom and to feel that desire to feel that awaken and
and to heed it to listen to it yes this is what i'm going to do
and certainly that would be nice to make that yes as a counter
to the ways in which we desire limit us constrict us
undermine us drain us or bring us in immeasurable suffering of
all kinds to have another path and to feel
the possibility of saying yes to it in a strong determined way this we're allowed to do in buddhism
a message with some peop some people don't hear
they hear the opposite uh almost like you just accept and be present and
in some kind of gentle soft way but to um
and um don't try a lot but trying
with this healthy desire is one of the great pleasures of life so
the pleasure of practice with enthusiasm the kind of enthusiasm that helps the
mind quiet and become peaceful and as i said
the laboratory of meditation is one of the great places to discover how there can be strong healthy desire
in a way that helps bring greater peace greater calm greater settledness
calm peace and strong order can go hand in hand
and so thank you
for this and i hope this has given you something to consider and for you to spend some time the next
day to see if you can find out the physical emotional mental
distinction sensations experience the difference between
a compulsive desire and freeing desire and if you can see that difference
maybe you can set your freeing desire free to support you in your life
thank you