good morning good morning or maybe it's afternoon where you are or
even evening wherever you are sending a warm warm
welcome so
some of you may be wondering wait this isn't Gil yes so for those of you who don't know
me I'm Diana Clark I'm sitting in for a girl this morning
so I'm going to be continuing with uh the series on the Brahma vejaras
and specifically on compassion and today we're going to practice with
and talk a little bit about cultivating compassion
I'll say for me that this is one of the most I don't know it's a beautiful
aspect of Buddhist practice that sometimes doesn't get the
I don't know what the word is the respect the recognition that maybe it needs this whole idea
that we can cultivate heart qualities we don't have to leave
it up to chance or we don't have to leave it up to getting all the right uh
all the right conditions in place
but instead this is something that we can make it more likely
that we will respond to our life with some warm-heartedness and some warmth
and then of course our lives just unfold differently if we
show up with some warmth openness
so that's a little bit of the journey we'll take together today
so to begin this loving kindness I'm sorry
to begin practice this morning
well just Begin by establishing ourselves and settling into a meditation posture that
feels comfortable
so a posture that has some alertness and some uprightness
the brightness either literally or figuratively
maybe it's best for your body if you're not sitting upright
but maybe there's a way in which there could be a sense of uprightness or
energetic sense that's not rigid
but instead allowing a quality of relaxation or
softness into this into the posture
settling into the body
with a sense of balance
with with this kind of the dignity of the balance
with wakefulness and
softness relaxation
and a sense of openness or spaciousness
if that's possible available
and taking a moment to feel into a simple Sensations
maybe the back side connecting with the chair
or cushion
keeping it simple
what does it actually feel like right now
to be sitting here
maybe tuning into sensations of contact of the feet
and the legs touching the floor
the chair whatever it might be cushion mat
feeling grounded feeling connected
maybe bringing some attention to the hands how do they feel right now
tuning into those Sensations
might notice what the hands are touching it's soft or rough
and a really simple way
just noticing
and noticing the sensations maybe like inside the hands or the
sensations of having hands
maybe there's tingling maybe there's pressure
whatever it might be
tuning in the sensations in the hands in a really simple way
no need to strain or strive
it's keeping it easy relaxed
and then bringing that same quality of attention
to the sensations of breathing
feeling the movement in the chest or abdomen or maybe the
nose
feeling the Rhythm of breathing
it's natural that the mind will get lost in thought
we just very simply gently Begin Again
with the sensations of breathing
when we find ourselves lost in thought we don't have to make it a problem
let me just with some warmth gentleness
we we could use the language receive the
sensations of the breath just opening to that
feeling the expansion and contraction the stretching pulling
and then we can do some loving kindness now that
we have certain foundation with
connected to the body to the sensations of the body the present moment
with all these Brahma vihara practices start where it's easy
start where it's easy
so bring to mind a lovable being
someone for a home it's natural easy uncomplicated to feel
warmth care Goodwill towards this
being
some people use their imaginations for kittens puppies babies
I can't help but smile when I say these
or maybe there's someone in your life that
you just like the heart sings in some kind of way when you bring them to mind
or maybe it's not someone that you know so well but someone who is
a big impact on your life that you feel very appreciative coach a mentor a teacher a leader
friend
bringing the lovable being to mind and
connecting with your warmth your
care kindness meta love
for this person for this being
some people find it helpful to connect by connecting
with the image using the imagination the image of The Lovable being
some people find it helpful to
Place some attention in the heart area
allowing that to soften and open and
radiate
some people find it helpful to use phrases
to help connect with a sense of warmth and
care
you can use phrases like may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you live with ease
connecting with the lovable being with love
with Goodwill warmth benevolence
respect care
and then to do some compassion practice
can recognize that all beings have difficulties
whether it's disappointments
in their lives some physical pain discomfort
or loss
all kinds of laws
so we can imagine The Lovable being having some difficulties
maybe not the most tragic or difficult again we start where
it's easy
and to connect with the tenderness the care
like arises when we imagine consider remember
the difficulties The Lovable being is experiencing or has experienced
again there's no need to go to the most difficult the most troubling
and can we connect with that with both The Lovable being and with a
sense of they're having dukkha
stress comfort
and tuning into becoming sensitive to
the tenderness that arises
again some people find it helpful to connect with the image
using the mind's eye so to speak
and that helps create the conditions for the tenderness
in the heart that's already there to come forth
some people find it helpful to tune into the bodily experience of this
tenderness towards the lovable being who's having
difficulties the feeling in the Heart Center Maybe
and some people find it helpful to say phrases
to help them connect with this compassion
we might say something like
may you be free from suffering
may you know peace
we do compassion practice
it's a way to tenderize the heart in some kind of way
so that we can show up for ourselves and show up for others
with openness and warmth and care
which turns out to be transformative
both for ourselves and for others that we meet
so may our practicing compassion together this morning
today be for the benefit of all beings
everywhere
[Music]
so I wanted to talk a little bit about um cultivating compassion as I said at
the very beginning of the guided meditation for me from it feels like such a
remarkable thing that we don't have to
be satisfied with our factory setting so to speak with uh the way that we our
heart opens or has room for or meets difficulties but instead we can
cultivate we can practice we can develop compassion
it's a remarkable thing I think sometimes we underestimate the transformation that
is possible with some practice and certainly the Buddha recognized this
with mindfulness practice with all these practices right with concentration practices they fold path
and certainly with the Brahma vihara practices
they do make a difference and they can be transformational in the same way
that all other things that we learn can be can have an influence on us and that is
drop by drop into the water jug is drop
by drop into The Jug is how it's How the water drug is filled or something like
that so each moment in which we spend time
cultivating has an effect even though we might not see it
at that time and certainly during meditation just because we're creating the conditions
in which Compassion or indeed loving kindness any Brahma vahara
might arise doesn't mean that it is going to arise
we're just putting the conditions in place
it's often the impact or the effects
of uh Brahma vahara practice isn't felt or seen on the cushion like during the
meditation but it shows up in our daily life as a way that slowly our default
reaction the difficulties or different um
situations that we find ourselves in just starts to be one more and more of warmth and care
so I just want to offer this that even though in the meditation practice is
certainly contrived um but it's a purposeful way in which we
can develop loving kindness and compassion any of the Brahma vahuras
does and even though it might feel like well I don't nothing's really happening
during this meditation period don't think that this isn't having an
effect that it isn't you know creating the conditions for changes
certainly that's been the case for me I'll just share that uh since doing some
regular um Brahma vahara practice loving kindness and compassion
Equanimity and sympathetic Joy I've noticed that
I've I'm more often saying warm-hearted or funny things to
myself when I notice that I'm making mistakes or where I'm forget something or
whereas before there used to be like a tone of little bit of disappointment or even some meanness
now there's some tenderness in this little inner voice when it speaks to myself
oh Toyota it's okay it's quite something
so I'm Gail earlier this week talked about compassion he or yesterday specifically he spoke about it having
different elements it is a contact with suffering
caring about this suffering and being motivated to do something about the
suffering so these different elements all come
together and you know different strengths different you know of course at
different times there's different emphases but I appreciate something very much that uh
Jill Shepard a really great Dharma teacher has said that she said that meta
I'm sorry that uh compassion is the love child of meta and Duca that is
compassion is what arises what is born out of when this warm-heartedness meets
difficulty sort of someone else having difficulties or ourselves having difficulties so I like this idea of
karuna compassion being the love child of meta and dukha
so I wanted to read just a short little excerpt from the sutas that talks about
the expressing um compassion and and one way that the Buddha described it
showing up in the world and it's an excerpt and then Buddha says
there are some who have given up and then there's this long list of
Maybe things that aren't so helpful so this long list includes covetousness ill will
irritability hostility offensiveness contempt jealousy stinginess deviousness
deceit unhelpful desires and wrong view it's really long list
so there are some who have given these up and the Buddha continues and when they have given these up they are
practicing the way that is proper for someone who is a practitioner who's a
follower of his and then he goes on and he says And when
they see themselves cleansed or abandoned these uh these unskillful
qualities these unwholesome qualities gladness Springs up
there's a certain amount of gladness like oh I don't have all those qualities anymore and then when gladness arises then Joy
arises I know when Joy arises Tranquility arises
and then when Tranquility arises happiness arises and then when happiness arises
concentration arises and then with concentration then the
person goes can does loving kindness practice and they meditate spreading a Heart full
of love to One Direction and to the second and to the third and
to the fourth Direction we might say this to the east to the South to the west to the north
and in the same way above below across everywhere and all around
they spread a Heart full of love to the whole whole world abundant expansive Limitless free of
enmity and ill will I'll just say briefly some of you may
recognize that little sequence of getting rid of things that are
and wholesome are unhelpful and then it goes into gladness Joy Tranquility
happiness and concentration might recognize this as what um Gill was
calling Dharma samadhi or samadhi Dharma at Dharma Samara I think and he did a
number of 7 A.M talks on this so kind of like connecting that to this Brahma
vahara practice but then this teaching goes on from the
Buddha so after having some concentration and then spreading loving
kindness and then the teaching goes on to say and they meditate spreading a Heart full
of compassion in One Direction second Direction third
Direction the fourth Direction and in its exact same way that was it
said about loving kindness then it goes to compassion
so we can maybe like translate this kind of like operationalize it if you will
we can think about it as first to let go of what gets in the way
of as part of the way to cultivate is to as
best we can so some ways that things that might get
in the way of cultivating and practicing with compassion is having fear that we might be too overwhelmed when we
meet the suffering remember that loving the compassion is
when loving kindness this warmth meets difficulties
then there's the this compassion this tenderness that just naturally arises
but it's of course we might have some hesitation we might have some
reluctance initially to kind of like really meet the suffering after all we're hardwired to avoid it to
meet difficulties so it's natural and sometimes it's appropriate maybe it's not time for us to touch into
the suffering of a lovable being or of our own or maybe we're just don't quite have the steadiness to meet the
suffering of others so part of the way we can practice with
this is to cultivate some mindfulness and some clear seeing
so that we can first recognize whether our hesitation is just a knee-jerk reaction towards
fear and or to recognize it's just a natural
hesitation as well as some mindfulness some stability of mind and being present for
what's happening can help us to become familiar with our
own suffering because often what happens when we meet the suffering of others is the
unfinished business of our own hearts to use an expression that Jack kornfill
uses the indigenous business of our hearts gets activated when we meet the
suffering of others so maybe it's worthwhile to spend some
time working with our own suffering that to increase our capacity as well as to
gain some familiarity when is our little bit of hesitation of meeting the suffering
when is it just a natural reaction or when is it some real wisdom say now is
not the time so we can spend some time with um
mindfulness practice and maybe getting some stability of mind like we did in
the guided meditation and like in the suit uh if we use this word uh concentrations Mari can also be
translated as collectedness or some non-distraction or sense of wholeness or
integrity in some ways it might be like
putting in place a keel in the sailboat that is you know that big long piece
that's at the bottom of the sailboat that helps prevent it from getting tipped over when it hits maybe the winds
of some suffering this is one way to how we can begin our
practice and to work with some of the difficulties we might have and then we might like warm the heart
maybe we might imagine putting on having some kindling
um and lighting the kindling maybe even sometimes it's paper things
that can catch a flame quickly and easily so we do some loving kindness practice
again starting where it's easy and allowing the heart to feel warm
and maybe the the coziness of sitting in front of some crackling
flames in a nice way in a really nice way
and then we can imagine some difficulties but the lovable being is having
and then allowing that warmth that is already there to be transformed into some tenderness and some care
and some able to connect with the suffering to care about it and to have a
willingness to do something about the the suffering and recognizing that at the moment we're
sitting in meditation doesn't mean we're going to get up from our meditation and go fix things
to recognize that sincere wish for the suffering to end
and we can do this as I said in the guided meditation just using our imagination and tuning
into the connection that we are having with a lovable being and a lovable being
that's having difficulties and just radiate compassion
that's what's in the suit does and then a later adaptation is to
include the phrases which is very common today and I often
am using phrases sometimes I'm just doing radiating maybe it's a can play and experiment
with different ways and phrases that um
might be helpful to use is may you be free from suffering
may you know peace and you might have your own versions of
that so some way in which we can
practice compassion cultivate it develop it
by purposefully bringing it into our meditation practice which will help us meet it or bring
compassion when we meet difficulties in the world either in ourselves or others
so I'm wishing you
freedom from suffering freedom from difficulties
but if you find that they do arise may you have some
warmth and tenderness and care for yourself compassion for yourself
and may our Care Connection compassion for ourselves and for others
May that benefit all beings or beings everywhere
thank you