hello everyone welcome if you are just arriving
it's great to have you here again my name is May it's fine to stand and stretch for a
moment if you'd like um I'll be
sharing a little bit about the Dharma with you now
so go ahead and find a comfortable spot
all right welcome everyone again my name is May so great to have you here
um I used to spend a lot of time
backpacking and during these trips we'd go
for many weeks out into the wilderness and during this time a lot of energy was
put into navigation because of course no one wants to get lost in the woods
and I was thinking about this because I came across an article recently and this
article discussed the various human responses to getting lost in the
wilderness and there's a there's a study done in
Nova Scotia tracking 800 cases of people who got
seriously lost in the woods apparently Nova Scotia is like the place people go
and get lost so um uh so
what they noticed in this study is that everyone who gets seriously lost
shares one primary behavioral characteristic they all have an unbearable desire to
keep moving to try to find their way back they can't stop
of the 800 people 798.
kept moving that impulse was so strong
so the problem is it's a lot harder for search and rescue
parties to find someone if they're always on the move right so
here's what really stood out to me in almost all cases
the people who are found are the ones who sit still
and this is exactly why the practice of
meditation is so extraordinary
in the midst of our busy lives where we might feel quite lost
amongst suffering or confusion despair grief
Etc that there's this practice where we can sit down and be still
where we can be found and one of the incredible impacts of
meditation is that we can begin to get in touch with our own inner compass
and this Compass can help us find our way help our find Our Help us find our way from dukkha from suffering to
Freedom and the the inner compass that we attune
to is Our intention so we start to become mindful of our intentions
connecting with wholesome intentions so intentions that are generous or kind or
compassionate and these lead towards greater freedom
we start to notice unwholesome intentions intentions that are based in
greed or hatred or delusion confusion and we see the ways that these lead
towards past that are not so wholesome where we are less happy if we're acting
on those impulses and so when we act with wholesome
intentions it's as though we've found a working compass that can guide us to our
true home that can guide us to a a happy life
so tonight that's what I will be speaking about I will be speaking about intention and specifically I'll be
talking about intention from the Eightfold Eightfold Path right in tension or Sama sankapa and that focuses
on three things which I'll get into shortly but first just want to spend a little bit more
time kind of defining intention or identifying intention so you're really
clear about it in your own experience so put simply intentions are our
motivations our reason for doing something or saying something
we can think of them as the about two moment about to do something or we can
identify it in the urge or the impulse before we think say or act right so it's
that impulse to do the about to moment and we have motives we have intentions
behind every thought word and deed so they're always functioning all of this
is fueled by intention so if I speak from a place of kindness or generosity
this will create one habit pattern of mind if I speak from a place of craving
or aversion that will create another habit of mine so this is how intention
actually functions to bring forth happiness or despair right it creates
different patterns of mind so put another way we can think of our life as
a garden and our intentions are the seeds that we plant
so if we want to be happy we want to plant seeds of non-grasping of kindness
of non-harming and these will grow a beautiful garden and this will yield a mind that's much
more resilient and flexible and joyful if we're planting seeds of green hatred
and delusion that will grow a very different Garden so you can consider you know am I planting seeds of fear or
seeds of self-aggrandizement or of insecurity so
we can see what's happening because if you want to grow a mango tree you
can't plant poison ivy seeds right so if we're trying to be free
plant a mango seed if you want a mango tree plant a mango seed
and so what I'm what I'm describing to you is also known as karma now these are intentional actions so we hear about
Karma a lot in Western culture and most of what we hear is entirely confusing
but as it actually appears in Buddhism as it's related to this practice it
refers to intentional actions So Good Karma results in happiness
an action based on a wholesome motivation results and happiness very
simple so so this is why the Dalai Lama says my
sincere motivation is my protection
my sincere motivation is my protection
we can't control our circumstances but our wholesome intentions allow us
safe Passage through our life
so I have a medical device that occasionally beeps
and I can meet that with an intention of kindness right so
without interruption we can meet whatever is happening in our life with attentiveness
and in the same way that a mother takes care of her child can take care of our
bodies meeting that with friendliness um
non-aversion Etc so
my sincere motivation is my protection
so this might seem like a very odd question
but I'm going to ask it anyways does stabbing another person lead to
happiness or suffering well
it depends if the person with a knife is an assailant or a surgeon
right each might use a knife to cut someone but one has the intention to heal to
help and the other has the intention to harm the surgeon is going to have a very
different life than the violent Criminal
so I want to speak now a little bit more about Sama sankapa right in tension from the Eightfold Path
um so some of you might be familiar with the Eightfold Path this path to Freedom this path of freedom and right intention
is one of the past factors so there's these three facets
of right intention renunciation kindness
or non-ill will and compassion or non-harming so renunciation also
known as letting go kindness and compassion so I'm going to start with renunciation we'll kind of move through
these three parts of it so renunciation
we don't hear that word a lot and it doesn't sound very appealing does it
um but I've found that it's one of the most uh
powerful aspects of this practice so many of us are propelled in our lives
by trying to get more of what we want and avoiding what we don't want um but we of course cannot control our
external circumstances and even if we get what's Pleasant and agreeable of course it eventually passes
away because all is impermanent and of course we can't get rid of everything that's unpleasant because
there always seems to be another problem um so getting what we want and avoiding
what we don't want is not a very effective strategy
so instead we can think about the second Noble Truth that the source of suffering
is craving and instead of obsessing about our external circumstances we can
pivot turn the attention to look Inward and really address the craving at the source
to look at the craving and aversion operating behind the scenes
so if it's craving that's the problem that's what we should really get
interested in that's what we want to find an antidote an antidote to
and this is where renunciation comes in renunciation is like
Kryptonite for craving renunciation letting go undoes
the craving impulse so if we can learn to let go of our
craving rather than being propelled by it we have a lot more agency in our own
contentment there's a lot more freedom there and we can practice this in a lot of
ways we can practice this kind of letting go impulse in a lot of ways this can release we can do it with others you
know uh do I always need to get the last word do
I need to say the snarky thing do I need to make others how I want them to be
and can there be some release there can there be some renunciation or letting go
we can practice it with sense craving with entertainment
letting go of the compulsion to binge watch Netflix or to have the second
donut just releasing and as wisdom grows in
our our practice matures renunciation doesn't happen by
repression or Force um but like by by a true understanding
of the insatiability of craving by really getting
how much craving is a ruse we begin to to release the impulse
so if craving had a favorite line I'd probably say it's this moment is not
enough this moment isn't enough and there's nothing we can do to fix that
and when we really really get that desire can naturally fall away on its own
so bikubody says real renunciation is not a matter of
making ourselves give up give up things still inwardly cherished
but of changing our perspective on them so they no longer bind us
we understand the nature of Desire when we investigate it closely with Keen
attention desire Falls away by itself without needing for struggle
so that sounds nice and in the meantime when that's not
happening for us and there's still craving in the mind we just deliberately practice restraint
when we notice that our intentions are based in greed anger or delusion
just practice restraint okay so that's renunciation let's talk about
kindness non-ill will so loving kindness can manifest in all
sorts of ways it can be friendliness it can be full-blown love it can be just a little warmth of heart
there's so many ways that it can come forward and specifically meta loving kindness
um it's a kindness without any strings attached it's non-transactional it
doesn't require others to be how we want them to be um
yeah that's without attachment the way the sun shines equally on all beings
meta is non-preferential so
um yeah meta can involve small Acts you know something like taking care of the
Earth turning off the lights using less water or it can be great acts there can be
great acts of kindness um I was reading about one in the news that
really caught my eye and it was about this woman named April de Donna who's an
assistant store manager at a Wendy's in Washington and April was she was reflecting on how
how common it is common it is that people hate for no reason and so she was
like well if people hate for no reason why can't I love for no reason and so
she was thinking like why can't I just love my customers so so one day she decided to try
something a little risky after someone finished placing their
order rather than saying like thanks have a nice day she said thanks I love you
little dicey in a work environment it was surprising to drop the L word in
that setting um but she ended up getting a customer
feedback form from this person and it actually had a really beneficial impact so she thought okay well I'm going to
try it again the second time someone pulled up to the drive-through
meal board the order the order board place the order again April ended the
exchange I love you and when this person pulled up
to the drive-through window they were in tears and the the woman
she said that her her husband and her brother had just died
and that she didn't have anyone in her life to say I love you to her anymore
so April continued sharing her love with customers and when they say it back
she writes a tally mark on the wall and over the course of three months
April had 2 549 tallies on the wall
and apparently April says that a lot of people are now driving up to the window
and saying I love you before they even Place their order
so this is of course a very very overt act
of kindness but know that any action
any deed based in love generosity
warm-heartedness plants that that wholesome seed that wholesome intention
that starts to pattern the mind towards a happier life
so next we have compassion this third facet of samasan Kappa so this is so
compassion is when the heart of meta that heart of kindness meets suffering
compassion is the natural response so the Dalai Lama said
if you want others to be happy practice compassion
if you want to be happy practice compassion
one size fits all practice compassion so
I read another story recently this was about a little girl named Michaela
and she was kind of coming up on her 12th birthday and so her grandma took her out to a
special birthday tea I had a lovely time they had their tea and everything was going well until they got home at which
point her grandma really realized that she hadn't zipped her coat pocket closed
when she had put her wallet in it and the wallet had fallen out So for anybody who's ever lost a wallet you probably
know that it is a rather distressing experience and particularly if one has
any um kind of financial stresses it can be an extremely upsetting experience
so meanwhile a homeless man who had been homeless for five years was
rifling through the dumpster behind the tea shop and he found a wallet
and I imagine that homeless man could have really put that wallet to use
but I also Imagine in that moment he connected with
some ethical thread within him perhaps connecting with a compassionate
impulse and before he knew it he was calling Michaela's grandmother to tell her that
he found a wallet in the trash so here he returned the wallet now this
beautiful wholesome intention manifesting and what I love about
compassion and kindness is that it's it has a ripple effect
um like it moves through people so when little Michaela found out that
this happened uh and you know her birthday is coming up uh she asked people to not give her
gifts but instead to raise money for the man who returned the wallet
so this is this is how compassion can function in our lives like one small act
one small intention leading to one small act and it moves through us
foreign practice compassion for ourselves for
others and for the world if you want to be happy practice
compassion okay so that's a brief overview of sama
sankapa of right intention the three parts of it renunciation kindness and compassion
and now I'd like to um just offer you some ways of starting to practice with
intention to try to to help illuminate it in your daily life because it can be kind of hard to catch them it can be
kind of subtle before we know we're saying something or we're doing something and we're not even really sure how we got there or why we're doing it
so um the best way to start is just by paying
attention to the intentions that are already present
you know as I mentioned earlier there's a reason behind everything we do um
even the really small things there's these you know micro intentions called caitana
um uh that you know um uh they're activating
when one goes to scratch and itch you know there might be a sensation and then
it's unpleasant and there's a little aversion to the sensation so we go to scratch so there's a little
intention present there is an intention when we go
for a slice the extra slice of pie intentions behind the clothes we choose
and the time we go to bed and the job we
decided on and how we brush our teeth you know it's
they're happening all the time right um so the the practice here is just to pay
attention to why you're doing what you're doing you're doing
um and this can be really Illuminating so just some areas you might have Spotlight a bit some areas to look
at in your life um check it out with food practice you know
are you eating for entertainment or for nourishment um
try it with conversation or speech practice are you speaking to care for someone
else or maybe is there a little Barb in what you're saying some tiny intention
to make someone know that they're wrong or you know something like that
[Music] um you know it might come up like are you complimenting a supervisor because you
genuinely want to want her to know that you care about her and appreciate her or is it coming from a are you
complimenting her so you might get a raise now what's what's happening there
um are you apologizing sincerely to your partner because you genuinely want to
make amends or is it a sort of um
what I like to think of as the G's shut up already apology I'm sorry okay those are two very
different apologies um so just checking out what's happening
when I was in college I uh I made a lot of pottery
and I really enjoyed it and I remember at one point I had a Vaz
that I was rather fond of and I um I was wanting to gift it to a friend
so that face value is like oh you know wholesome action you know you're based on the intention of generosity giving it
to a friend but when I kind of paused and checked
out the intention I realized that while there was that wholesome intention there there was this
also this part of of the intention that was like well
I'm also giving this to her because I want her to know that I am a highly
creative and excellent artist you know I want to make sure that this
person knows that I'm good at this right so this practice is humbling
it is not fun to see some of these intentions that are present so then we
can bring kindness to ourselves when we see that there's
part of the intention that may not be quite as sweet right and so what I'd suggest is just
remembering that intentions are often mixed like there might be an intention that's like eighty percent I'm being
generous and uh 20 seeking approval how
I was in that situation and when that happens you know we um really focus on the good
and then we just notice the other part without judgment oh okay approval seeking
approval seekings like this that's okay
and what we often find with unwholesome intentions
is that they're not moralistically bad just that they're misguided
they're not trying to yeah there's some part of us that thinks
that's the way to happiness right but yeah they're just just misguided you
know just trying to avoid pain just trying to be comfortable just trying to boost the ego a bit
very well-meaning um but when we really start getting to know
our intentions better these kind of micro intentions chaitana
it allows us to set resolves aritana it allows us to
have larger movements in our life reorienting our life to what we care
about most so if you in feel inspired to start
noticing intention in your life one thing that's very supportive to this
is sitting meditation because of course this allows us to slow
down this the system see the thoughts that are occurring in the mind and start
to get to know the more subtle impulses that occur within us and because we're seated and we're committed to sitting
there for half an hour or however long we're there for we're actually not acting out the
all the impulses that come up the impulse to rearrange all the furniture is being seen but not acted on so that's
a really great way to get to know our intentions better
um and then the other thing that I think is really helpful is pausing before acting you know just stopping a moment
to listen do I really need to press send on this
email now do I really need another cup of coffee just checking it out and maybe
you do maybe you're like you know that would be like the most gentle thing for this body right now or like that's what
this system really could use um but yeah you don't always have to act
on the impulse as I'm sure you all know you've you've been in this situation before
and we can do this with really small things like sometimes I'll I'll take a bite of food and while
chewing it I'll realize that eating that thing wasn't really
aligned with my intention that like you know I might not feel so great if I have that one extra bite
and I'll just spit it out like I won't even swallow it
so it's never too late to change course you can always change course with your
intentions and lastly I want to say uh that while
intentions are clearly very important we also need to observe the impacts of
our actions you know we're not operating in a vacuum and
sometimes we do something that's very well intended that has a really unfortunate unintended result
and um Buddhism is not just about intention we're instructed to pay attention to our
actions before we do them when we do them and after we do them so if our
well-intended action has a negative repercussion repercussion we're still
responsible for that and and we are expected and instructed
to take responsibility for that and to shift our Behavior accordingly to allow that to inform our intentions in the
future such that we're not causing harm for ourselves or others
so if you have been feeling lost in some way in your
life and your practice I hope that you're able to notice that
which motivates you I hope that you're able to practice letting go practice
renunciation that you're able to act with kindness
and compassion so that you can get in touch with your
your inner compass and navigate to a truly happy life
thank you so much let's sit for a moment
[Music]
thank you so much how wonderful appreciate your attention
so we'll now have some time for questions or comments reflections
anything that may be arising for you
and if you'd say if you'd like to say your name you're welcome to
hi I'm John hi John um I have two questions maybe we can just
cover one um one is about renunciation I've found uh
an aspiration for renunciation which is sometimes fueled by sort of judgment or
criticism uh you know an acknowledgment of like a deep longing or a desire and
then this hope or this aspiration to like let that go thinking this is sort of a noble thing to be pursuing
but sometimes I lose I I don't I've I've in the past not had
clarity about the fact that the motive for this Letting Go was
actually this like resistance to the desire or the longing that was arising and so
so then I with that realization I thought okay I need to sort of like welcome the desire and like allow it to
be present but I also would like to sort of like let it go and let it dissolve but I
don't want to be like pushing it out like you said it's not something we can force away so I guess what I'm getting
at is how do we sort of balance this like desire or how do we balance
pursuing renunciation while also not resisting that which we're trying to
renunciate yeah great question and I'm I'm really appreciating how uh carefully you're
seeing your own experience like being able to identify uh a desire and then really seeing how
you're relating to it and seeing that you know the the wish for renunciation
and noticing how that can can some sometimes make us aversive to the desire
which then as you're you're recognizing then where we're operating under the same Force again we're just we're then
rejecting something so how can we keep ourselves from getting in a tug of war and I and I actually I heard part of
that in in your question an answer within your question which was uh being
with the desire you know to to fully
recognize it feel it in the body get to know it get to know the stories it tells
us with mindfulness notice the emotional valence
um and explore it from that that angle and as uh as we do that
there's something else happening that's still not acting on the desire right we
haven't um uh if we're like straining to let let it
go that's just aversion so if it doesn't let go from like a natural a natural
invitation um then we can just let it be and that's
that's renouncing renunciation right right sort of the back door to
renunciation yeah exactly so you can just just let it be and something else I
want to mention about this is um uh
earlier on in my practice I had like a lot of zeal for renunciation and I think
there were certain ways that I was uh uh trying to eliminate
um aspects of who I am you know like trying to like kind of crush out Hobbies
or Crush out things that brought joy in my life um and I think there's there's a balance of
um you know we're not um we're not trying to eliminate our personality we're still a unique being
in the world and there might be something in the world that makes your heart sing that is uh that allows you to
to be uh generous with yourself that isn't based in sense craving
rather something more more deeper and more nourishing so there can be room for
that in one's life to engage in certain worldly things that that feed us
makes sense thank you yeah sure
any other questions or comments
how about your second question I was gonna say if no one had a second question or a question my second
question uh I need to remember it is about
um intention and uh I guess so you described you described
the the pottery scenario of like making this making this
vase and wanting to give it to a friend and is perhaps mainly a general there was a
mainly a generous intention behind it but there was also this other intention about being identified as a creative
artist and that really resonates with me there's a specific act I do in my life
which broadly has this very positive intention of sort of bringing light or positivity to people but there's a
hundred percent this underlying intention to sort of like get the attention of a specific person or to
sort of like you know sort of egoic based it's it's sort of like getting myself identified
in this specific way um and I'm curious about I guess the karmic
implications of that or he what how to
how to think about that I'm very aware of the intention that and and it's it's this tricky place because it's not like
this act that I'm doing is is somehow like bringing harm to people it's it's a good thing you know like giving the the
vase away that's not a bad thing right so it's like if you gave out a thousand bases I don't think Karma would be like
no so yeah anyway yeah I'll be at the idea yeah
um quite naturally in many of the things that we do
regardless of how wholesome it is you know if it's like
feeding orphans or like saving kittens from trees or you know helping grandmas cross the street like our ego will try
to hijack it yeah it's just what the ego does and you know it's like she's really
just doing her best but she just is confused sometimes um and so uh
you asked about the karmic implications uh
the function like the way Karma functions like in terms of like being able to map cause and effect is
unknowable so it's not an A plus b equals c um so yeah I can't say exactly what the
karmic implications are but I think what might be useful is instead
um to notice that just be aware of it
be gentle with it and uh bring a little compassion
to the part of yourself if that's available to you just some gentleness to like the the being that wants to be seen
wants to be recognized and known because often that being has some sort of hunger
to to be known in the world for approval or or love yeah yeah it
makes sense there's a there's a part of me which says well but then what about
all the people who are supposed to receive vases like you know if I cut off my gift my giving of vases and I'm just
using your example um but I think
compassion towards the part of oneself that wants to be seen can sort of help feed that
and then that there should still be space for vase giving outside of that yes yes let me be clear
keep giving the vases yeah keep giving the vases and as you're doing that you
know if it's like 80 percent wanna do this great thing for people which it sounds like this activity for you
actually like it it has this really beautiful wholesome intention to it and then you just you know that other 20 or
10 or 50 or whatever it is yeah sometimes yeah right right yeah yeah
whatever so whatever that other part is um uh as you give
as you engage in the act when that impulse comes over when that that inner being calls out for attention you can
just meet it compassionately like oh yeah I see you there makes sense thank
you yeah great questions
so about a renunciation um recently I so I have three wonderful
adult children and um uh so two of them get to get along
and with a third one doesn't get along with with the other with one of the
others and so um recently they kind of some of them two two of them said okay
look can you can you get this all to work out you know and and that's very
seductive for to me it's like oh yeah I'd love to have the power to
have them all appreciate each other and get along and communicate but then I
realized I have to let that go because they're adults and they have their own life lives and it's not it's not for me
to do and so just for me to appreciate and love each one of them and realize
that many times people don't like their siblings then that's okay it's maybe not
what my preference would be but to let go oh that's well
that's such a great example of renunciation and the way that Letting Go
can function and like of course you want your kids to
get along like that would be you know because you probably see uh the exquisiteness of each of them and
you wish that they could see that in each other and it sounds like you saw within that
how if you really latched on you'd suffer over it
and to to be able to hold that really lightly with such a a wise Act of
Letting Go that's really beautiful thanks Martha
we have a couple minutes left if anybody has anything else
any other Reflections on the practice or questions
okay I think we're complete then well thank you everyone I so appreciate
you coming tonight giving this time for your practice
and I hope that the um yeah the benefits of your practice go on
to help you feel more free in your life and benefit those around you
thanks so much