so hello hello and welcome dear sangha lovely to
be with you in if not in space but in time if not in
time if you're listening to this later um lovely to practice together however
it may be so so for the theme for uh tonight's happy
hour um [Music] i'd like to invite us to explore a
particular perspective um a perception
the way we see ourselves the way we see others and
to shift it a little bit to shift it um and then that shift from this shift
which i will name in a moment setting it up from this shift
and perception per perspective then from that then a sense of
meta kindness can feel different or a sense of compassion can feel different
from this shifted perspective so the shifted perspective that i'd like
to invite us to explore and i will guide us in the guided meditation
is this as opposed to how we often perhaps see
ourselves or see others perhaps we see ourselves as
or we lean into the way our minds perhaps focus on the negative
and what's challenging on the stukka and the suffering
[Music] so we have this narrative we have this narrative which is perfectly fine you
were human beings this is how we evolutionary we've come to be we have this narrative self-narrative and we
often in our self-narrative we see
you know narrating what we want to do and oh maybe this thing didn't get done
or what we did we go over it over and over again and maybe things that didn't
go well go well so there's often stickiness with
what's unpleasant what has been difficult and satisfying
um or maybe what i would call
our brokenness like oh yes our brokenness we often lean into that again
evolutionary er evolutionarily those uh ancestors who um
uh leaned into the pleasant they didn't live long enough to pass on their genes
but the ones who actually were more afraid um those were who had those were
the ones who lived long enough to pass on their genes so again evolutionary it all makes sense and yet in terms of our
personal experience we tend to see ourselves as these human beings that
are fallible and not perfect and we're working towards
goodness and we often forget our beauty our goodness
now balancing that perspective would i like to invite us to lean into tonight
to feel into is to see
our magnificence the inner goodness the
the brilliance not intelligence or smarts but just this brightness this brightness as if
as if we were an angel as if we were an angel
you can use the word or the concept angel if you like that or you can use as if we
were a buddha within there's the buddha within us you can use that language i want to be flexible with the language
and see what works for you or maybe there's a kuan yin within see what works for you
but maybe for this i use the word angel because there's something bright about again not making
any assertions about nature of reality but but this angelic
qualities of the inner angelic qualities of of goodness of service of brightness
of an open loving heart what if we saw ourself as an angel as
this angel who means who means well means to serve to love to
protect to be kind to guide what if we leaned into that vision how
would we see ourselves how would we behave how would we hold
ourselves our intentions our mistakes our aspirations our work our daily life our
interactions with others when we wake up in the morning okay i'm doing angels jobs okay this is my
work today this is as an angel this is what i do and then how would we see others in the
world other angels that they're here to serve to be kind to
to love to protect how would our relationship shift to our
minds to our hearts how would we show up it might be a corrective
this might be needed be a sorely needed corrective
compared to how we often go about [Music]
our days and our perspective the way we perceive ourselves so [Laughter]
that's cute oh on youtube pat says an entry level angel maybe that's fine
entry level is fine just whatever works [Laughter]
so dear angels let's let's practice together and and take on
these different perspectives and see how they might shift and guide our practice
of of love and kindness compassion etc from this perspective
hey perspectives are a dime a dozen we can choose our perspectives right let's
try this on and see what might shift maybe some habitual patterns of
self-judgment maybe they get loosened a little bit maybe we give ourselves a break
maybe love maybe we love ourselves and others a little more easily let's let's
try this on for size so so i'd like to invite you to sit
comfortably whether sitting or lying down
in a position where you can be for the next 30 minutes
with ease
allowing allowing the back to have a sense of integrity
to be straight but not over efforting as if it's being
pulled up there is a magnet on top of your head pulling up
your back vertebrae by vertebrae ah neck shoulders
they can relax they can completely relax
letting your feet your sit bones
letting them be connected to the earth
releasing releasing
the weight your earthly weight
your angelic weight onto this earth
as always we start by just grounding in the body grounding
in the body
each and every breath breathing in or rather being breathed and
let it be natural let it be received
the in-breath receive the out-breath released
as thoughts arise not a problem they will arise
it's okay
for the sake of this training together
smilingly smilingly tell them thank you thank you and not now
please come back later no need for self-judgment
let there be kindness let there be ease in your body in your heart
with yourself with the thoughts that arise
they're not adversaries just untimely right now
it's okay later later thank you
letting the breath in the body and the abdomen
let it be center stage
and breath readily received in the abdomen
not in the control tower of the head as if the body is an organ of perception
received received soothing calming the out breath
released ah landing
here now
here now not now dear thoughts
just simply here
let it be enjoyed let it be delicious
this moment of just sitting being breathed
let it be nourishing to your heart
gladdening your heart mind
now i'd like to invite you while we stay embodied
feeling the body the breath the body relaxed
to bring to your heart maybe a kind act
you offer to someone
the way you helped them supported them maybe a phone call with a friend
a patient ear [Music]
a gift
a donation to a cause you care about some act of kindness generosity patience
bring it to your heart your heart mind
and let it gladden let yourself relish the goodness
how it perhaps affected the other being or beings
and how it brings gladness to your heart
this release this generosity is giving away
letting yourself relax into feeling
this goodness it is wholesome to relish goodness
it expands our heart and more goodness more kindness more generosity
and let yourself for this moment can later go back to the other perception or the usual
perceptions but in this moment let it expand seeing yourself as kind
as generous these qualities let them be felt in your
brightly a slice out of time
seeing yourself as an angel
generous kind patient
the angelic qualities of service and care
and if your thoughts get in the way oh no i'm selfish and
not so good nothing angelic about me wait wait wait a minute
don't believe don't believe those thoughts don't believe
the self-judging thoughts let them go they're just thoughts don't have to
believe them
don't get in your own way don't let these thoughts get in your own way experiment
an angel serving helping supporting
other angels but first leaning into your own
in angelic job duty
nature
and to know that your growth as an angel
your freedom is not independent
of others
it's bound with others so you're giving your generosities not
just to help them is to free your own heart
is to bring more wings to give your wings more lift
is to uplift you as much as it is to uplift others
let yourself see yourself as kind
as generous in acts of service
not self-centered let yourself see yourself in this way
again we can always go back to the other way later the end of the hour but right now
experiment see what might open up in your heart and your mind
maybe there can be more freedom not being attached to fixed views of
yourself and others
play around with this image
of yourself
and maybe your daily tasks your work your cleaning [Music]
your dishwashing whatever it is you do [Music] it becomes angel's
work angel's job
your work isn't just a profession or a way to earn a livelihood but a way to serve
to grow to earn your wings
gives it more meaning and dimensionality
this angel doing angels work
angels like humans are impermanent have limited time to love to serve to
give to do this
angel's work
in this realm [Music]
on this earth
and this earth which is sacred
the only planet we have
to live on to love to grow
on
and seeing others seeing others as angels
their goodness their beauty their kindness
their freedom is bound up with yours
their angel wings their angel rank is bound up with yours
letting yourself receive graciously so others other angels can give and be
kind
earn their wings just as you
seeing your own goodness
goodness that is more magnificent
brighter than you can ever imagine give yourself credit for it
let it be expressed
notice from this perspective as we play around with perceptions
it becomes easier or if it shifts
how accessible kindness meta warmth is
for yourself appreciating your own goodness
does compassion become more accessible for this being
who is me who's yourself the ways that
you suffer things that are hard for you this angel
that's who's trying their best
and things can be hard in this body and this mind sometimes it's okay
it's okay dear
does it shift of this perspective how does it shift how does it change
kindness meta for others
if you see them as angels
see their goodness
their acts of service their kindness
but you can stay with this perspective or perception or you can release
and see what is here how the residue might have
shifted some things open things up for you perhaps in unexpected ways
can you accept the grace that is to be human
the grace
of living
having joy sorrows
being kind serving helping
or acting in ways that are far from your angelic nature
and learning from them returning learning growing
it's enough to be human it's actually quite profound to be human
how awesome
how amazing
may our practice may the wholesomeness the goodness of
our practice or cultivation
serve this angel this human who is me who is us
as well as all other angels other humans
and freedom in waking up
may all beings be free
hello angels welcome back
so we have some time for reflections
christine says every time a bell rings an angel gets its wings
it's great i'm gonna ring the bell a lot then so uh claire i see your hand is raised
please mine's all so short but all your references to angels made me immediately
think i do practice christianity and there's a hymn i love music and there's a hymn that i've always adored the main
i'm not going to sing this you wouldn't want to hear it but um the main lyric is this little light of mine like i'm gonna
let it shine and it's so sweet and but very much in the spirit of what you're
talking about yeah yeah yeah lovely exactly thank you for that
claire and i brought that in actually sometimes in the past and similar practices yeah let your light shine
exactly this little light of mine or this big light of mine yeah thank you claire
bill says i found the angel idea hard to accept but then i thought assume
if richo if you have it or not after that it was easier beautiful assume a virtue
if you have it or not lovely that's lovely yeah beautiful
aaron says on youtube well as manifestations of the cosmos we
are sort of angels of love serve others yep
absolutely indeed indeed able to serve others in many ways exactly that's
absolutely right that's the spirit of of this practice and and the invitation
for us to see ourselves a little differently really see see ourselves in this
um service
oriented way yeah yeah oh cute
merry christine says oh um buddy's ears are my wings i love it i
love it wearing christine that is so cute i love that that's lovely
yeah any other reflections in the other something that might have
come up for you did this open up this different perspective seeing yourself as an angel and others
did it shift something are open in your work in your meta and
your compassion for yourself for others any any aha moments
or questions or complaints everything is welcome
claire i see your hand but you've already spoken so i'm going to let other people speak
catherine please um
yeah it's so interesting since i was not raised like believing in angels but um
there's something about an embodied
cosmic experience that is
just feels really good like to to feel myself as like my body made of light and then
wings which just when i imagine i feel that in my body i my
chest opens and i feel this like you know my neck and shoulders are often so tight and sort of just like it's just
a gift to imagine and and not imagine but in my body
um that blessing so thank you that's lovely thank you so much for that
exactly it's just again my my intention and hope just as you said wasn't to appeal to any
religious views but just this different you know as humans we have this idea of angels these angelic great beings right
kind kind so it's just this yeah this physicality that you
you expressed and experienced just a different way of oh just uplifted shifted like feeling different
how how does that shift yeah beautiful thanks so much for sharing that i love that lovely
dave says thank you for this practice it really spoke to me i was washing windows yesterday and
thinking that i want people to know that i love washing windows so that they might feel
that love as they look through them oh that's lovely that is so beautiful
that is so beautiful yeah the sense of practice the service the service aspect
yeah yeah
so
yeah oh i hope you feel better dave yeah so how about we turn into our practice
um in small groups with other angels tonight just uh
um [Music] the rubber
meeting the road and just can we show up is just for a moment again we can go back
to our humanness just a sense of this goodness this beauty this expansiveness
and beat others in this small group for just few minutes six seven minutes or so
um and actually i think it'll be i've said it for seven or eight um
and and also see the goodness in others see the goodness in others hold them see them as angels see
how that perception might actually make how we serve how we relate different
so groups will be a size of three roughly and the invitation is to
speak from your own experience and
just one nugget just a minute and then next person will say a nugget or anyone
can say pass you can just hold silent space if you wish for others for other
angels to see what it's like to to engage engage in the space
of kindness together in this way so
um i'm going to create the breakout rooms and
again only speaking from your own experience not managing not
commenting um just staying close staying close to your own
experience so i'm about to open the rooms and take
care of yourself take care of each other in the rooms here we go
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we have a few minutes left for
any reflections and a couple of other reflections i wanted to share actually while you raise your hand um lisa on
youtube shared that in thinking of others as angels it broke down some black and white thinking
like their angelic qualities may exist do exist alongside the not as angelic
quality simultaneously not just at different times yes that makes sense thank you lisa
that's beautiful i love that thinking of others is angelic it breaks down the black and white quality
and syria was talking about how her body felt stress and discomfort at some point and
the idea of being angels was appealing but discomfort got in the way it's okay discomfort doesn't have to get in the
way it could be an angel that's having body aches it's not a problem so
can can it be can it be included can it be included
any other reflections maybe something that came up in the group if you haven't spoken for a while
i'd love to hear from you you can also type in chat um neil [Music]
so first of all i thought this was a lovely meditation um
so one thing that came up for me was right i thought of someone who i'm
having difficulty with at work um and gee it like this like didn't work for that right and
i i mean that was not the point of this meditation so i dumped him and just moved on right it wasn't like he like
tainted the whole meditation but someone else in my group mentioned talking about a situation that you know that they had
found you know an interaction with people they had found difficult so
yeah so i guess you know what do you do when you run into those when you're doing a meditation like this and you run into those sticky situations
yeah yeah good question um so so
sticky situation i mean there's a reason why these sticky situations come up right the mind is still
around you know grappling with just finding a way to find peace with this sticky
situation so so the invitation for example tonight would be is it possible and and you said in the case that you
tried it was impossible to see them as angelic but maybe what i
would do is maybe i would persist and i would try to see something kind they have done
in the past or they're doing not this sticky situation that kind of has is upsetting right now but maybe they've
been kind in the past maybe at work maybe there's something you did i don't know they gave you a compliment just
something kind or maybe to others maybe they've they're maybe they're on time
maybe that's one of their gifts one of the ways they serve like find something kind something good goodness about them
or maybe like they have family they love their family oh can you see them as an
angel loving their child or loving their elderly parent or something loving their
pet like maybe find a way in
and if it still doesn't work it's okay then you just bow to it and then realize that maybe this is a very
complicated it needs more time needs more time so those are my invitations thank you
thank you thank you so much so dear angels we've come to the end of
happy hour spending this hour practicing together cultivating a
different way of seeing being with ourselves first and foremost and with others in
the world so may our practice support ourselves and all beings everywhere may
all beings be free and happy [Music]
thank you all thank you so much