okay here we go so hello hello and welcome to happy hour everyone glad
you're here glad we are practicing together at this time
coming together with our intentions with our goodness to cultivate and support
ourselves support each other so the theme for
this evening um is uh self-judgment
self-discernment and self-compassion [Music]
so so self-judgment you're probably
well we're all familiar with self-judgment oh darn it i didn't do this right oh i'm
no good i'm bad i'm terrible you know hurling various insights at ourselves when we make a
mistake or we don't perform or we forget something
or or we don't get something done you know hurling insults you're lazy
you're not good oh you know your flavor fill in your your own versions of
of self-judgment now self-discernment is different
self-discernment with self-compassion so
self-discernment is when there is self-compassion actually let me bring you self-compassion self-compassion
is the best antidote is the best way to meet self-judgment because
we often have this wrong perspective that if we
self-flagellate and if we abuse ourselves we're going to whip ourselves into shape and yes we're going to
actually perform better and do things and and it's not true and there's research
actually supporting that psychological research that um people who have who are more
self-compassionate in fact they take more responsibility
instead of blaming themselves or blaming others actually they take responsibility
and and um the the
um instead of having shame they have remorse so let me actually say a little bit about
that so shame is not helpful shame is when you feel ashamed
really small this feeling of a sense of feeling small and inadequate
it makes you even smaller and more inadequate for taking responsibility for
doing what's right if you're either for yourself or or for the benefit of others
however what is helpful is remorse remorse is skillful remorse is helpful
to reflect to have discernment about something that went wrong and to intend
to correct it for your own benefit for the benefit of others so there's a sense of
uprightness clarity and a sense of kindness towards yourself and others
that self-judgment doesn't have self-judgment is very painful just it's as if you're
taking a dagger and and hurting yourself throwing perfectly good moments after
the moments that are already gone whereas with
self-compassion um when there is a sense of self-compassion self-care self-kindness
one has and this is really important i want to make this very clear
when there is enough kindness for oneself in the psyche
one can take responsibility and say oh sweetheart yeah okay that was not good
okay all right you messed up and i still love you you're not bad we'll do better instead
of the comparison if there is no self compassion it's like oh you screwed up
you're terrible you're awful you're not worth living you're you're not worth it like ouch ouch ouch one gets smaller and
smaller and smaller again i'm exaggerating but sometimes the way we speak to ourselves is not that
different whereas again the scenario is self-compassion one has the capacity and this is what
research has been done about that folks were invited to remember some
indiscretion something that they regretted having done and then one group
was asked to have a reflection of self-kindness and
another group was um i forget what the control group was with but it was definitely not a
compassion or kindness and the group that actually was uh primed with kindness and
compassion they took more responsibility for the action
um without shame but actually responsibly like yes this was not an appropriate and
they they um instead of pointing the blame pointing the finger
at others which is the control group which was not the compassion group
they pointed the fingers at others oh it was their fault it was their fault i didn't you know it would i was okay whereas
when there's kindness you can actually take responsibility for what you've done wrong
because it doesn't hurt it's like okay it's all right it's okay i'm still okay i'm still the word worthy of love and
care and compassion separating
the self-worth from the behavior separating those two and that's where
the discernment comes in the self-discernment becomes available when we have
self-compassion so self-compassion makes self-discernment
with mistakes available to to do better
with remorse whereas self-judgment just brings out shame and it's just a spiral downhill
so i have said plenty
and what i'll invite you in a minute is
we'll just explore we'll just explore these um
self-judgment self-discernment self-compassion just how they feel in the body these are not ideas i mean well
there are concepts but really we need to feel them we need to feel them in the body
embodiment embodiment embodiment so when all else fails
embodiment so let's begin let's begin
so landing landing in our seats arriving
here in this moment
in this body releasing releasing
any tightness or tension in the body
releasing thoughts releasing preoccupations
taking refuge taking refuge here right now in this moment
refuge in the goodness of your heart
your good intentions your kindness
your aspiration for cultivating
peace and goodness that has brought you here
feeling the bottom of your feet
kissing the earth
earth on earth
your sit bones
contacting the cushion the chair in lieu of the earth
earth on earth embracing
ah releasing your weight releasing the weight of this body
onto the earth
allowing the breath sensations of the breath
felt sensed in the abdomen the lower part of the body
helping to settle the mind settle the heart
let awareness hold meet the entirety of the breath
the entirety of the in-breath entirety of the opera
only thoughts arise not a problem
smilingly smilingly release thank you thought please come back later
giving my heart to this practice right now
and let there be ease let there be a sense of connecting enjoying the breath as it
breathes you not making breathing into a project
let yourself be breathed
and every time you notice awareness is resting on a thought and
you're lost in thought it's okay
if there is self-judgement ah here you go again
let there be compassion this is what happens
to everyone it's okay
release release smilingly with an easy
light heart release holding yourself with kindness with the
breath
this is what minds do this thinking it's okay
it's a part of this practice release and reconnect release and
reconnect with the breath in the body enjoying taking
refuge for another few minutes of settling
feeling embodied feeling the breath sensing the breath
the entirety of the in-breath the out-breath with ease
calming soothing nourishing each breath
and now if you like i'd like to invite you
to bring to mind perhaps something today
or this week
that you perhaps had some self-judgment about
maybe not the most challenging or difficult event but something relatively
challenging not top one but maybe three or four down
the list bringing this
event to mind
and perhaps as i invite you to do this maybe some contraction arises in the body
the heart mind manifested showing up felt in the sensations of the
body
first getting a clear description of what it was say oh you wasted time today
you had so much to do and you wasted time or you did this and it was unkind
or whatever it might be
and now i'd like to invite you to put it down
release it for the purpose of this practice release let it go
we'll come back to it in a minute we just did this to get a sense of the
contraction and what it feels like in the heart and mind
and now let us feel held conjuring up
your compassionate being one who represents
the paragon of compassion kindness complete acceptance for you
could be someone in your life maybe a parent grandparent
or maybe it's the buddha
or kuan yin [Music] or any being that
resembles that signifies
compassion acceptance for you it might even be your pet
it just looks at you lovingly completely compassionately kindly
acceptance maybe you see them as the deity of
compassion whoever whatever
fulfills this role this compassionate being for you conjure them up
and let yourself be held
in their kindness and their compassion their acceptance they know you completely they know your
past your challenges your good intentions
your trials and tribulations your missteps and they love you all the
same there's nothing you have to do to earn or deserve
your acceptance just because you live you are
this suffering beautiful human being
you are held in love let yourself be held
in this gaze of kindness
completely held
let yourself soak it up don't get in your own way
just receive relax your body like rays of sunshine let it come
through being health and kindness
acceptance
just as you are
now as you soak in their kindness
maybe even physically let yourself be held
if it feels appropriate maybe you're sitting on the lap of the buddha
there there here it's okay it's okay
let your heart be open stay open to receiving
kindness soothing healing
acceptance
just as you are
and now bringing up this
misstep this challenge you had earlier today
this week what you were judging yourself or earlier
the space of compassion come bring it up bring it up
and share it put it on the lap of this compassionate being
in your mind's eye let them hold it with you
and from their compassionate perspective pay attention listen to what comes up
and helping you supporting you with it
maybe the compassionate being reminds you of some difficulty that you've had
which has led to this maybe they remind you that you are doing
your best if you could have done better in this circumstance you would have
to be kind and gentle with yourself
maybe through their love and care they support you to feel
not shame but remorse
we should have been different but it couldn't be how can it be different
in the future accepting loving
that it had to be the way it was or it would have been different
given all the causes and conditions it had to be exactly
as it was given what came before
let there be discernment awakened in this field of compassion
and care and acceptance
complete acceptance
sense of a brightness empowered compassion for yourself
feeling yourself held
the compassion acceptance love of the compassionate being
returning to that is their primary
object in the awareness
feeling health it's okay
it's okay you're doing your best
coming back to the body
feeling the breath in the abdomen being breathed
here here offering your heart offering your
goodness
to all beings everywhere including ourselves
may we offer may we offer our best as much
as possible as much as we can
to ourselves and all beings everywhere may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
so [Music] he
one one phrase that was coming to my mind is one by suzuki roshi
that says you are perfect as you are and you could use a little improvement
and just the wisdom of acceptance and and practice and and doing our best so
perfect as you are and you could use a little improvement
so so [Music] you're welcome to uh you're invited to
to share if you like what discoveries aha moments perhaps came up
for you in your practice [Music]
maybe challenges for the benefit of yourself and benefit of others to
share them practice report report from the field
it's always helpful for others and you can type them to me individually
privately in which case i'll read the reflection not your name and if it's typed to everyone i will read your name
also or you can raise your zoom head your physical hand i will likely not see
thank you for the beautiful sitting you are very welcome says one of you
any reflections you like to share what what was it like was it did it feel
different when you [Music] brought up this shortcoming
and alone the field of self-judgment and then later in the field of self-compassion is there
something that shifted were there awarenesses observations or
empowerments oh that came up linda please
um oh i'm nervous about doing this so i'll try and give myself self compassion
i had a really hard time imagining anybody who could
who could give me that who could wrap their arms around i mean you know and
i didn't ever get that as a kid but but so that's my causes and conditions
but i you know i could imagine my dogs looking at me with those loving eyes
and i also could imagine myself doing it but i just kept going back to
certain people that i thought should be doing that for me
and you know it it wasn't there i yeah so that that was my difficulty yeah yeah
thank you for sharing that linda and and um to appreciate you bringing it up and and what i'd say actually i don't hear
that as a difficulty let me tell you why the difficulty perhaps there was
difficulty in trying to get it from places that's like yeah i'm not quite yeah like you should be doing yeah so
that doesn't work and yet what i'm hearing in the beauty of what you shared is that yes
it was available to you there's from yourself good heavens that is
gorgeous because i usually actually bring in the compassionate being you know the buddha kuan yin or being of
light or because often folks have difficulty
giving it to themselves so hallelujah
yeah this is great and of course you had your your your dog supporting you there too the the the um the the the
compassionate beings that they are you know it's always fun to make them into a deity of compassion you know your dog
looking at you here like you know sitting across i don't know cross-legged so
so yay okay yeah thank you thank you thank you so
much for sharing that yeah thank you thank you reflections coming through chat
um yeah yes allowing helped out sure
uh wanted to show my source of compassion [Music] wanted to show my source of compassion
not sure what that means claire steve says combining self-compassion
with the practice of seeing sleepiness distraction or whatever it is as awesome
as in monday's discussion is very helpful great great thank you steve
wonderful yeah great
one more reflection privately it's pretty incredible how it actually feels in the
body the reactivity and pain of the experience and then the warmth and
comfort and okayness when compassion was present we don't always need the answers or for
the painful experiences to go away sometimes holding and accepting
and loving just as is is enough beautifully said beautifully said i
couldn't have said it better thank you exactly noticing the difference and doesn't have to go away compassion can
hold it all beautiful yeah great
so so i'd like to invite us
um at this point if you wish to
to turn into practicing with compassion
in small groups and
and the invitation in the small groups is to
only speak from your own experience and you can also be silent in the small
group you can when it your turn comes you can say pass you can hold
compassionate silence for others it's perfectly okay being fully present
it's a way that you're offering support to others and to yourself so speaking from your own experience
alone not managing not reflecting on other people's experience
and um you're welcome to share one nugget one
brief nugget then the next person will share a nugget perhaps or say pass
the third person will come back to you and then go round and round and please
this is a sacred space it's not just go talk amongst yourselves imagine that you are the compassionate
being for these other two human beings and they are the compassionate being for
you giving and receiving in not an overbearing way but maybe it's just
silent so so this is the invitation for this evening
um and i will create the rooms in the moment
and maybe let's see anything else i want to
add before we start the groups and maybe we'll go reverse alphabetical order
um or just for the fun of it
and yeah i think i think that's it and stay
embodied stay in your body stay in your bodies don't get heady i think it's important
not to get heady so stay embodied um stay
yeah stay embodied don't get heady so all right i'm going to open the rooms
and one more minute
okay here we go
okay welcome back everyone all the rooms are closed and we have just about a
couple of minutes if any insights reflections have come up that you like to share
for the benefit of yourself and others
again you're welcome to raise your zoom hand or you can type a chat
or maybe what came up any insights that came up from practice in small groups
quiet bunch tonight
which is perfectly fine dave
yeah nikki thinks that was a great practice um great class i think he structured it really well i could see
clearly that self judgment is what i do when i compare myself to others my my college
classmates and how you know how well they're doing and how poorly i'm doing and oh you know and i can also see how
uh beating myself up is a way of feeling good about you know i'm right about being wrong and i feel
that's a strange dynamic but i can tell self-discernment is when i see it with compassion i see because of the way
things happened in my past the causes and conditions yeah so that's that's of course the way it went that way
so that really worked well for me thank you very much beautiful thank you so much dave thank you for sharing that
beautiful great steve please
i just it was very nice to ended up in a group where the other two
people were not only knew each other but were related so that was seemed to me quite synchronistic and
amazing but they said it actually happened once before as well so that's pretty nice
nice nice the pleasure of being in groups and when people are
related unrelated we're all human beings we're all related and maybe actually closer relationships beautiful
the joy of sangha and vicky you get the last word and needs to be quick here we go
yes i just wanted to tell fred and steve thank you i hit the wrong button uh too
quick and i left in the middle and you both were really good partners there
sweet there's an appreciation for for one small group yay
thanks vicky that's sweet so with that i thank you all thank you
for your practice thank you for supporting each other yourselves all beings whom
you come in contact with through this practice may we all wake up may we all serve well
may all beings be awake
[Music] thanks all
be well