so good morning my friends
and uh things are a little bit different today than usual i'm not at imc i'm at our retreat center
in irc insight retreat center and also it is my
today is the 40th anniversary of when i was ordained as a zen priest
so i thought i would like to mark this day and um so
we'll do a meditation as usual and then instead of continuing with the satipatana series i
thought i'd pause with that and kind of mark this uh occasion that's it's
important for me um in uh been talking a little bit about that for me they or
my my dharma life so that's the kind of the difference for today
and so
one of the things that
one of the ways in which my zen training unfolded
was that at certain point the practice was one of learning how to participate in
life how to really put myself into my whatever i was doing and
in zen training a lot of it was um practice was also in work and activities
and so sweeping to really participate in the sweeping be really there for it
i i did my first uh three-month training period in zen sanding um
those platforms in which all the monks were meditating meditating on in so i
have kind of my initial training in zen and participating practicing with sanding
wholeheartedly standing so participating and then
um and then at some point it switched to rather than participation it became
a non-resistance just get out of the way um maybe some people would say to um
to open up but um maybe that's a little bit too
neutral the idea was uh it was still participating but now rather than me
applying myself engaging myself it was more like engaging was happening and the life was
happening and now it was getting out of the way uh having no resistance to it
and so this participating fully in life but just not resisting life
i trained to do in the monastery in outside of meditation and then in meditation
and so as we sit uh today in the sati patana series it's
experiencing the whole body and what a great thing to mark this
practice of participation and we participate with our whole body
when we participate fully in life what else what else that's the medium that's the
the the the matter with which we can
participate in life is with our whole body very different than with our whole mind only
and then participating and feeling and getting out of the way and allowing ourselves to experience life
all of life in the way that is three-dimensional multi-dimensional from
uh all the different senses all the different capacities for attention uh that we have
so to assume a posture
of participation with meditation
so if you're going to bring all of your body all of your posture
with you to participate in meditation
so it's not not no part of your body is passive
but is alert is present
like if some important person for you walked into the room and you would sit up straight and really be
present like now you're going to now you're going to be attentive
and then to lower your gaze maybe 45 degrees to the floor
letting your eyes rest the gaze of your eyes rest
not trying to look at anything in particular
and then to gently close your eyes
in the practice that we often do here of breathing in deeply isip is a practice of participation
to breathe in deeply into your body the whole torso expands stretches shoulders
lift as you did breathe in deeply
and then a certain kind of surrender into the body into life
through your body in the exhale
breathing in deeply connecting to this life
exhaling surrendering to this life
the lived life of the moment not the life that you can think about
anticipate remember
but the lived life
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and every sensation you have in your body
is there because you're alive when you're dead your body has no
sensations it's kind of like proof that you're alive that you have sensations
even if they're uncomfortable
as you breathe in feel the life of your belly
and as you exhale relax
surrender to the belly
on the inhale feel your chest your upper torso
and as you exhale relax your upper chest your torso
perhaps surrendering to the lift life
that expresses itself through your chest
on the inhale feeling your sensations of your face
generously openly allowingly feel your face
and as you exhale relax
surrender your face giving up your
public face how you feel like you need to
present yourself to the world let your face have a break
deep relaxation as you exhale
and then the same with the mind maybe in the area of your brain your
forehead anywhere you tend to feel the mind
feel it as you inhale
and as you exhale relax your mind soften
see if you can soften any ways in which you're driving your mind
pushing it along with your desires and wants and fears
surrender your fears your desires
so you can better participate
through your body in this moment-to-moment lived life
and then settling down into the body breathing
either participating in this experience or breathing
or surrendering to your breathing
the live life of the body breathing
one breath at a time
just the inhale when you're inhaling
just the exhale as you exhale
so then as we come to the end of this sitting
may the intention of this practice that we've done
may the dedication the effort
be for the welfare be dedicated to the welfare and happiness of
others may it be that we practice in such a way
that we help reduce suffering in this world for ourselves
for those that we know in the whole world we live in a world where there is
incalculable suffering and we live in a heart
that has an incalculable capacity to love for compassion
and may it be that our care compassion our love
grows through this practice day by day week by week year by year
may our compassion grow so that our care
our participation in life is for the welfare and happiness of all
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and may we live a life that contributes to that or at the very least
doesn't contribute to more suffering
so warm greetings to everyone and
today i'm going to mark the 40th anniversary of having having
been ordained as a zen priest so it's a little pause in our series on sati patana
and um and uh
it's a i feel very kind of fortunate to certainly to
reach this 40th anniversary and spent these 40 years in the dharma
practicing and teaching but also the fact that i'm here at insight
retreat center is also very special that this also is a
part of the wonderful dharma life that i've been able to
be graced by or blessed by that to have this wonderful retreat center that uh
to practice in and be on retreat in and to teach in
to to be able to open the doors of the center to so many people to come and practice
here and then coincidentally
this the reason i'm here is that we have a two-day retreat for
our teacher training imc started its very own teacher training back in april
and in the past people who got trained in our tradition kind of got trained
through spirit rock or inside meditation center and and so here they were started their own
training for 15 people and
and um and it's kind of special to kind of a culmination of 40 years of
dharma practice more than more than 40 years 45 years or more
that come to the wonderful circumstance of training others to be full teachers
and uh so all this comes together being at irc my anniversary of my order nation and
and teacher training that i feel so fortunate to be able to do so i wanted to market
so 40 years ago i was ordained with two other zen
students victoria austin and gary mcnabb and i felt very
fortunate to know them both and um both of them dedicated their life to
um the practice for them in their case zen practice and
and the life of a what became a priest and i say became because
uh at the san francisco zen center where it was ordained at uh at the time of my ordination it was
called the monk ordination and the word monk being used both for male and female
and um to a monastic ordination and that's what i uh
what was thought i was doing was ordaining as a monk and i knew that it was you know there
was a track to become a teacher someday but uh there were so many other
monks priests ordained people at zen center when i was there that i calculated that um
it'd be something like 25 years before my turn to move up into even just the very beginning uh teaching roles or to
be trained as a teacher but i wasn't i wasn't being ordained to be a teacher i was
ordained to be a monk and to my surprise a few months after i was ordained the abbott
decided that to stop calling the ordination a monk ordination monastic ordination but rather a priest
or the nation and maybe partly because in um
traditionally in buddhism monastics are celibate and in japanese soto zen there's no rule of celibacy so there can
be marriage and sexual relationships
and uh maybe that's one of the reasons but also um there's a way in which the zen priest
is a life it's a little bit of life that's in the world in all kinds of ways and uh
participating in uh all the different aspects of life and in a way that sometimes uh traditional because
monastics hold themselves a little bit apart from the world and um participating in like a small
example would be that monastics are not allowed to marry people and zen priests
are so just it kind of represents a little bit that's that distinction
and um but what it represents for me this uh ordination and is that um one of the things is that
every time that i uh in my life and my adult life where i
chose the dharma the chose the dharma practice over any other possibilities
that it always worked out fantastically wonderfully i could never have imagined how well it was going to work out
and and um there were even times where i had almost no money and living a poor life
and um as a practitioner and um where i thought the reasonable thing to do was to go find work
and uh and but i was saying no i you know i even had a job lined up
once and then i said nope that's not what i'm dedicated to my life is dedicated to the practice and
and come with me that's what i'm gonna do and
so and then periodically you know it just became clear that this dharma path was opening up in
front of me the decision to become a monastic to be ordained
wasn't exactly a conscious decision or reasoned decision
i was sitting at the monastery monastery looking at the creek that runs through it and
reflecting about my life and what i should do with it and what direction to go
and and there was like lightning went through my body and
suddenly i just knew that i was going to be ordained and generally i'm a person who does
things for reasons and uh kind of a rational person perhaps
tried to be or something and and so then um afterwards i thought of
reasons uh for that and the reasons were sincere but the the
the decision was not reasoned it was just a deep knowing like suddenly i just knew
that this is what i was doing and one of the reasons i i gave myself
was ahead was that i wanted to live a life that responded
responded to the suffering of the world at the deepest place of suffering
and the only thing that i knew in life up until that point that somehow was able to touch the deepest places of
suffering in myself and in other people was buddhist practice
i didn't necessarily think that that was the only way to do it but that's the only thing that i knew
and i wanted to dedicate my life to responding to suffering at its deepest
level i i was gonna i was going to go
back to go to graduate school to study soil conservation
and i wanted to go support and help the world by you know
doing erosion control different places in the world where there was a real serious problem
and but i felt that somehow there was something inside of me that as important
as that work would have been it wouldn't have reached into the depth
of the human heart where suffering really lies at the core and i didn't know if i'd be effective as
a someone who somehow touch that people or supported people to but i wanted to
be in an environment that that's what the environment is for and to support it and my image of my long-term image of
myself with uh as a zen priest was uh to have a little neighborhood
storefront meditation center uh just a little maybe a one room storefront kind of thing and my job was
to open at the key keep the place clean and open up and allow people come and meditate
and that was you know that was kind of well i wasn't much more
thoughtful about what i was going to do in the long term than doing that but then i had this wonderful life of um
things just kept unfolding after i was ordained and even things that were
tragic for many people somehow kept opening up to
you know going further and further in the practice and that's one of the tragic thing was that the abbott of the zen center
had an abbott's uh ethical scandal and he left and it was devastating to
many people but uh i was invited by someone to go to japan
and and um my father actually he was working in japan
he said when you want to come to japan and and just coincidental it was coincidental with this uh
dabbit leaving and i said oh sure i'd like to continue my zen training in
japan and and so then i went to japan for a while but in order to stay in japan i had to
go to thailand to get a new visa and in thailand i discovered this practice we do here vipassana practice
and that opened up wonderfully for me and that then it continued for a while this dual track of
both zen and vipassanan and that's still a dual track
and the zen is very important for me still it's a kind of orientation or provides
kind of a fundamental i don't know religious orientation for
myself and and it's an orientation of participation in the world
of being fully present in this world practicing in the world
and as a place to be free and then
the vipassana practice is equally deep and valuable for me and um
and that is a practice of
deconstructing the world in a very deep way to discover the deeper
[Music] potential capacities we have for freedom
and this wonderful synergy of these two of uh vipassana allowing for really a depth
of deconstruction of seeing through the the condition
the world the conditioned world that we live in and the constructed world and really open up to greater and greater
capacities for freedom and then and then learning participation learning to give yourself to the world
enter the world and and uh participate with that freedom
one of the teachings or ideas in zen that was very
um influential in me was the idea that
we express our practice that practice our understanding the depth of our practice within us how we
mature in the practice is something not just to kind of be in enlightened retirement but it's
something that is expressed or enacted or um in the uh there was this uh
person many years ago who heard all these buddhists kept talking about practice practice practice
practice what kind of practice do you do i'm going to retreat to practice i'm practicing the word practice is
used very very quickly and a lot in our scene and the person heard all this and he
said um you guys all all you ever talk about is practicing
when's the performance and um so is then the idea that it's
you're you're you live the life of the performance so it's how you enact how you express
your understanding that um is the fulfillment of it
and um and uh and for me the
to the combination that the vipassana teaching freedom and zen teaching
living that in our life that's a duel and that for me those are these dual tracks
that were so important and it's not inherent that one is just one way and one is the other way it's
just that's the way that these two lessons came through to me and i'm very grateful for it
and i feel so fortunate to be able to live this dharma life and
and find my practice in everything i do
and you know so i have this fortune of being able to teach like teach here to all of you on
youtube and which is a kind of little bit of a manifestation of my practice but it
comes around is that it's also the place that i want when i'm teaching it's also the place
where i practice it isn't that this is only an expression of whatever practice
i have but also i see it as this is the location
for practice when i'm teaching so i'm tracking myself and noticing what's happening inside of me
and my thoughts my feelings my body kind of being present for the whole show
so that um so that it is a practice them tracking myself and
mindful of what's happening so that um i keep discovering um more freedom or more
depth or more fullness more participation more getting out of the way of this
life so um and someone i saw in the chat earlier
asked me for my what my zen name is my ordination name it um
in japanese it's a you know japanese name ryuke kojon
spelled r y u g e and that's one word in the second word
is kojon k o j u n and the way that the
the abbatu gave me the name he
translated as a dragon tusk
sunlight revere and so one of those names is supposed to
represents how you are when you're ordained and the other is supposed to represent your potential what you can become
so i don't know which is which um but uh it's kind of a little bit of a
nice i hopefully nice uh pairing these two words ideas dragon tusk it sounds a little bit
ferocious and so maybe i'm a little bit dangerous and uh but then the sunlight revere
and so that was the name i was given and
my pali name i call i you know you get lots of names in buddhism sometimes
and my pali name for this in the theravan vipassana world where i teach is uh dhamma dasa
and that means a servant of the dharma so both the zen ordination being a zen
priest and being a vipassana teacher and practitioner i feel very much that i'm a servant for
the dharma and i love serving it and supporting it and
letting it grow in our hearts and and spreading across the lands so
thank you so then tomorrow i'll be back at imc and we'll continue with the sati patana