hello and warm greetings for our time together here with
the practice of mindfulness as the practice of satina the practice
of mindfulness deepens there becomes a shift
that arises because we develop a reference point
that tends to be very different from how life is usually lived
mine in daily life it's very easy for the mind to be
racing around in thoughts to be pushed around by our feelings
desires aversions to have mind thinking can have stress
connected to it it could have unethical thoughts inclinations
all kinds of things that can be that are not necessarily for our own well-being
and some way or other we learn through meditation not some way but as we deepen
in the practice a reference point of a mind that's possible to be peaceful
a mind that's possible to be spacious non-reactive
that feels harmonious that feels like a valuable place to come
home to to rest in to be with a mind that is not stressed
not pushed around by the emotions and desires and aversions we have but the mind that uh can
see it all recognize it uh in a way that's does not cause by any of it
a mind that doesn't cling to anything but sees everything
and now when we have that reference point when we see that difference then
we know something that's valuable we know what direction to go
we know where to arrest the minor what to prioritize in the mind
that to go back to picking up the resentments that we were simmering about
or the fantasies we were kind of lost in is a diminishment or as a not the best
place for ourselves to rest in we know something better it's not to be this necessarily
dismissive or or aversive towards um certain states of mind
but it's just we know something better if you're walking down the road on a
rainy day and there's a puddle of mud ahead with your
clean new shoes we know that it's probably a little bit nicer to keep the shoes clean and so we
walk around the puddle and don't get mud on it it's like that's simple
so as we sit today today we'll just sit now and i finished speaking in silence
but see if you can find either through a memory or through some hints or some clear connection
a reference point for a state of mind that
is beneficial is valuable to rest in a state of mind where
thinking does not become obsessive thinking becomes calm and quiet
maybe even thinking becomes unnecessary because there's a state of peacefulness
or ease or calm or openness clarity
non-reactivity um that uh
state of rest for the mind so whatever it might be for you some reference point
and keep that reference point close by kind of uh lean into that place support
that allow it to grow and as your breathing perhaps breathe with that reference point
and as you do so two things might happen
one is that you might that reference point that place that reference state of mind might grow and develop and help the
mind become more at home and settled and calm and the other thing that might happen
um is that um you can't do it but you begin to see clearly
what it is you're doing that uh maybe interferes with or
is uh uh you know uh uh the direction that's going that something is going a
different direction you learn about your tendencies of mind and habits of mind
and as you learn about yourself things that are taking you away from that reference point and no need to be upset
no need to be critical learn the art of seeing that clearly
peacefully so with that i propose that today we'll just sit
quietly with no preparation you've heard a lot of me for these months and will sit quietly
and then i'll ring the i'll say the final words of dedication at the end
so
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
if you look back at the last minutes of the sitting
what states of mind have been prioritized
by your mind or by yourself
has the mind been in charge and taking you down the highways and byways of
thoughts ideas reactions
or have you taken charge in remembering to relax into
a beneficial state staying in touch with staying in contact
with a place of peacefulness or calm or openness
a state of mind which is not centered on thoughts
but rather is open at ease
what's which has your mind prioritized
and might have been possible for you to have more prioritized
tuning in being attuned to the place where the mind is peaceful
and one of the advantages of doing this is that the peaceful mind
is the mind through which it's easier to have
non-reactive good will love
which is generous but not needy a compassion
which cares but is not troubled
so as we come to the end of the sitting
with whatever love you have that's generous
compassion you have that cares but it's not troubled whatever good will you have
that is easy and peaceful
to dedicate the benefits from this sitting the learnings from the sitting
the reference points that we've learned to dedicate it for the welfare and happiness of others
to wish and hope that whatever we gain is shared with others
shared with the whole world so it's not only us that benefits
but through us the world benefits
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we have a state of mind from which we can contribute to that as
a possibility
[Music]
thank you so yesterday we
had a shift in this teachings of sati patana
in the second half of the third foundation and it's a shift to
a state of mind that is an outcome of cultivating awareness
an outcome of no longer prioritizing states of greed hatred and delusion or
thoughts or attitudes of greed hatred and delusion and all its subsidiary kind
of common ways in which we get caught in thought
limited by our thoughts and thinking where we are excessively focused
on objects of awareness objects of attention
if um you know if if
i suddenly started thinking about how it'd be nice to replace a carpet at home
and uh then i'm very mindful of the carpet here at imc the i'm focusing on it and i'm so
studying it that i even lose touch with what i'm talking about to you
because that becomes the important thing is to you know the object of attention becomes
carpets and but in that focus on carpets i'm
certainly present and mindful for it but that's not really the the arising of of
awareness which is free awareness which is present for things but knows its presence not lost and
caught up in the activity so this uh mindfulness begins developing
uh strong and stronger there's uh the sense of awareness is
is not limited or bound by what the object of attention is
and as awareness keeps developing that sense of awareness not being bound or limited but being larger is partly
represented by a sense and under feeling a sense
knowing that we know we know we know we're aware
the awareness is not submerged in something the awareness is kind of like the lotus growing out of
the muddy water the lotus is not blossoming underwater in the mud it
comes out of the water to blossom so the mind the awareness blossoms
and becomes kind of spacious and the important point here
that i want to emphasize is the mind is no longer caught or preoccupied
with thoughts with feelings emotions with reactivity with the world
it now the mind becomes uh much more uh infused with this wider
kind of awareness this presence this attentiveness some people might call it a broad sense
of being conscious of experience where the sense of consciousness is kind of broad and
inclusive and so at some point the the um
the then the mind there's a shift in it of what gets prioritized
rather than prioritizing our preoccupations with what we want to get and what we're angry with or upset with
or afraid of we begin prioritizing a state of mind which is peaceful or
calm or useful and in that calmness and that peacefulness there isn't that kind of
narrow tight limited attention on some particular thing the awareness now be feels broader more
expanded and so this shift in the third foundation
begins when one knows an expanded mind as an expanded mind
and one knows a mind that's not expanded as a mind that's not expanded
so when we begin to sense that the the the size of the mind can be a large sense of mind or spacious or even
boundless sense of the mind or the mind is in fact limited and constricted and
preoccupied in something and so this idea if mind under stress is
limited and sometimes as the mind begins to open up um we can feel the places where the mind
or the body the brain is tense and you can feel how that creates a limit or a boundary
or a constriction for this open awareness this open presence and consciousness
so at some point there's a shift where we have this as a reference point
this possibility of a calm peaceful more expansive awareness
and and that's a nice reference point but even better is to begin prioritizing
it especially giving it at least slightly more priority than the mind's
inclination to prioritize the unhealthy states of mind that we go into
and might say that i don't prioritize but the mind will do it for you
and we get pulled into this world of preoccupations and concerns that can be quite stressful
uh what about prioritizing the peaceful mind the calm mind or the open mind
and um and uh not to hold on to it not to make it an object not to con constrict
yourself around it but rather to kind of rest in or open to or allow
it would be a little bit like someone wants to go swimming in a wonderful pool
of water but they're you know maybe they're on their cell phone talking some animated engaging or
upsetting conversation they're completely absorbed in the conversation and so they walk right into the water
into the and the water gets deeper and deeper and deeper and maybe suddenly so there's a ledge and that there's no more
ground in it but they're so concerned with the phone call they're not paying any attention to
floating and so they drown but um you know as we get a sense as we
go into the water of consciousness we have a sense that we can there's also floating they're swimming there
and so we prioritize floating enough just like that person on the phone should not have the phone in the
water probably but would at some point prioritize floating in the water if there's no
bottom and so we prioritize this kind of wider state this peaceful place
as we do so and it develops and gets stronger at some point there's a we can know a
mind which is unsurpassable and we can know a mind which can be surpassed
or a mind that's ultimate and a mind which is not
you know ultimate and what this refers to is the states of enlightenment states of realization
that this movement into this open awareness calm peaceful states
can grow and develop and at some point there's a
it feels like oh this is ultimate there's nothing better than there's something higher than this because
in this state there's zero suffering zero stress zero tension
um zero fear nothing that kind of limits it
and so there can't be anything more ultimate than this because um there's no abs it's so peaceful there's not nothing
that disturbs it no there's not even a self that we're preoccupied or caught up in or
or or contracted around there's not even any kind of
ripple of self-concern and so it feels it feels so ultimate and
now that this becomes another reference point not just a peaceful mind but now a mind
that is so free of suffering that this becomes a powerful reference
point where we know what's possible we know it's possible to live and have a mind
and live this way that's this kind of radical freedom and um and then
the next sector's one knows a a steadied mind as a studied mind when
knows an unsteadied mind as an unsteady mind this is knowing
that there is that mind that's peaceful has no ripples on it that's so peaceful and my nose when
there's ripples on it and uh so after some very deep kind of
realization experience practice still continues but now there's a reference point of what it's like to
have no ripples and so we're much more sensitive to the subtlest little ripples in the mind or the big ones
and how there's subtle prioritization of preoccupations concerns and where there's still a little bit of attachment
and then the last thing it says in this one knows a liberated mind as a
liberated mind and my understanding of this is that that this is a mind which is fully
liberated that somehow the uh all roots of attachment all that have
been pulled out there's no more attachments nothing no more tendency for the mind to cling
and um and that can be known uh
and so this is the ultimate the final goal of satyapathana is this kind of liberation
and so this third foundation does describe the whole path of practice in a certain way
and and and then we'll go on to the fourth foundation which
presents that path in a different perspective and the third foundation is from the perspective of
um the mind states that we have so um one of the things i'd like to
leave you with in this third foundation is this idea of two ideas that you have
reference points and the idea of prioritization what reference points do
you have for a state of mind that is valuable for you really precious
that's that is certainly maybe better than some of the alternative ways your mind
functions in in maybe some of your life maybe something you attain in meditation
or experience in meditation or some other times and how can you beneficially use that as
a reference point many ways and one way is to give a certain kind of
prioritization to that state of mind don't take it for granted don't think that it's only available in certain
verified states like meditation the more you experience it maybe there's
hints of it maybe there's the smell of it or small clues of it
maybe it's always present to some degree and and so maybe
you can prioritize it or or or let it inform you let it support you
in being free and relaxed and present more often than you do an interesting exercise is to go through
the day or the end of the day review the day like write the autobiography of the day
based on what the mind was prioritizing and see if
you know did you have to prioritize that was that really to your best interest
and could you have done different prioritization so that something else could have blossomed so your lotus can blossom out
of the muddy waters so thank you and
next week we'll start the fourth foundation and so if you didn't follow and well enough
this third foundation the fourth foundation as i said does a similar thing from a different angle
and through the angle of insight
and then um finally so we have for the next days until monday
imc is doing this fundraiser for the refugees from the war in ukraine
and um i think it's a quite a powerful thing when a group of people gather together
to support and raise funds to support people suffering in the world i believe it's beneficial for them but
it's also beneficial for others that see this being done to see that there are caring people who
are engaged and collectively to make a difference and now so if you're wondering where how
you could support the the
people of the ukraine when the tremendous suffering they're experiencing right now invite you to join its imc effort
and the way you learn about it where you can do that is to go on imc's website
on the home page there's a section called what's new and there in the what's new section there's
a um you know it says uh fundraising for the ukraine
for ukraine and you can click on that and that'll take you to a a button donate button
that is specifically for us to make a donations to save the
children a wonderful uh charity foundation that's supporting people in the ukraine
and the money will go we'll we'll we'll receive it we'll 100 of what we receive we'll give to save the children 100 of
what they'll use is to support their efforts in the ukraine
so um thank you very much and i look forward
to starting again on monday