so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy hour
happy to see you so so for tonight's guided meditation
um I'd like to invite us to explore the marriage of meta
or love with wisdom love plus wisdom
equals equanimity Equanimity is a practice where the
Brahma vihara is the cultivations of the heart kindness
um compassion joy for Joy of others uh meets wisdom in
fact all the Brahma viharas need the factor of wisdom to be balanced not to
Veer into the extremes for say compassion not to become
um just Agony and pain just feeling the pain of others without the sense of
balance um or say wisdom is needed so that meta
or love doesn't become attachment or grasping oh I'm going to wish you well so that you're going to really be well
okay are you well yet I've been wishing you well for five minutes or the attachment of I'm going to love you so
you love me so wisdom supports the the balance of all the
these practices of the heart and
really the fourth Brahma vihara so the the four Brahma viharas just as a review
the four of them as you know them already before practices of the heart the first one being meta loving kindness
second one being compassion karuna third one being vicarious joy happiness or
happiness of others the the fourth one being Equanimity
um really Equanimity is where um
wisdom this this sense of of um
clarity not veering into neither falling into
nor with with attachment nor pushing away with with aversion
um it's so equipoise Equanimity is where wisdom of being with things as they are
becomes to full fruition with care with meta with care because if Equanimity
didn't have care in it it would become aloofness it would become like oh yeah
things are as they are whatever I don't even care but that's not Equanimity that's aloofness and and sometimes we
can confuse many of us actually do confuse aloofness like oh yeah I'm just being quantums whatever which also can
be spiritual bypass watch out for that in your practice with true Equanimity which which holds
with mixed space for things as they are so
if there are questions that have come up it's okay please sit with the questions uh well as you all know we'll have time
for uh Reflections and questions later but I think that's enough for
setting the stage for what I want to say and um let's just practice together as I'll
have invitations for us to explore the space together so
so let us begin with this land
let us land in our bodies on if you need to move at this point
either move your body so that you find comfortable position
rolling your shoulders back or need to move from your chair to your cushion
really taking care of the body what does the body need right now to sit
to sit comfortably with a sense of brightness
or if you're lying down with a sense of integrity could be standing up too not a problem
see if that is what your body needs
ah and softening relaxing letting go
Let It Go I think of the shoulders
letting go of the
holding tightness in your back
tightness in your forehead in your jaw
tightness in your chest
kindness in your abdomen
any tension in the sit bones and the legs feeling grounded
connected to the Earth with your feet your sit bones
and releasing releasing thoughts all that has come before so much is
happened today already or might be happening later today
letting go of planning mind remembering mind
no problem [Music] they are helpful but not right now
not right now thank you not right now
not now not now
not now not now not now
and let the breath move through the body let attention let awareness connect with
the breath the entirety of the breath the entirety
of the in-breath and the out breath
Let each breath empty you
empty empty empty empty empty
not with force not fighting content but your devotion with your Devotion to
loving the breath just this breath loving it notice Devotion to this breath can empty
you without you trying to empty it just happens
through loving feeling devoted to this breath
this in breath this out breath
thank you
Letting Go letting go lovingly thank you not now
I'm giving my heart to this practice right now I'm giving my complete heart
my devotion just being present in this moment with
this breath
thank you
can you imagine that each breath was calming you
is this elixir that is calming and settling you
maybe with each breath there is more space in your heart
space in your body
as if your body were a fluffy cloud with each breath
feeling more space
space molecules [Music]
in your heart and your body and your mind and all of your body
upper body lower body too feeling lighter
more porous
breaths in breaths South breaths don't need to be effortful
let them happen on their own
then your thoughts arise let them be light like a helium balloon
can they float away right now
Without a Trace only lightness
space remaining
and maybe with this breath and with each breath
maybe there is a whisper it's okay it's okay
a sense of expansiveness of it's okay
whatever there is here or there isn't
it's okay the wisdom of it's okay
a perspective that's wise and wide as the whole Sky spacious
it can hold everything spaciously
the body the mind and the Heart
it's okay it doesn't push away
it doesn't turn away with aversion it's not scared
it's not intimidating but it's so spacious
yeah this too this too yes this too
it's okay it's okay
we're gonna thought to rise it's okay
let them be a light helium balloon floating in this vast sky
vast kind Sky of the heart of the Mind
Let There Be kindness
sense of presence with everything that arises and passes
wisdom of spaciousness a wise a wide perspective
grander grander than our usual limited vision
that can get fixated tight
unbalanced unmoored
there is so much more that our vision our perspective can hold
or the age breath it's okay it's okay
it's okay it's okay
and notice it's okay is kind it's not a Louvre it's kind
same way that maybe if a child is
upset the parent the caretaker has a wise and
wide perspective that this is not the end of the world
it's okay it's really okay and yet caring so caring
it's okay it's okay
wide and a warm
whatever is arising whether a thought
sadness and emotions something in the body
it's okay stay with it with kindness
the wise perspective
thank you
even if something comes up that you don't like
can you hold the not liking the aversion with equanimity
new version can be the child that is upset I don't want to
and you have equanimity
spaciousness with the aversion with the resistance
let it be held wisely widely with care
not believing it falling into it not resisting it
not adding more aversion to a version
it's okay
thank you
a simple Equanimity oh it's okay
foreign
thank you
whatever Rises can it be okay
and if it's boredom can you meet it in this white Sky of the heart of the Mind
it's okay to be bored it's all right it's okay
not to be bothered by it
simply aware simply knowing
with care it's okay it's all okay
foreign
and it's okay it's not applied okay Hammer to make something go away
it's okay to make it disappear no it's to make
more space with aqua Poise it can be just as it is
just as it is
by being making space to be with what
arises just as it is
we cultivate more strength in our heart more courage
more stability more care
not turning away distracting ourselves
as we bring this sitting to her clothes
to hold with Equanimity with spaciousness mind like the sky heart
like the sky expensive spacious
for whatever Rose or did not arise in this practice period
it's okay we've done our best we've showed up
trusting trusting that we're planting seeds of stability of care
with every moment of staying
and turning towards
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
have the wisdom spaciousness care of equanimity in their
lives to support them the jewel of equanimity
may all beings everywhere including ourselves be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
ah well I feel more equanimous I don't know about you I feel more calm and
peaceful and spacious so we have a few minutes
and uh I hope in chat you're welcome to raise your hand your Zoom hand because
if it's your physical hand I won't see you there are many of us um
you want to share a report of the field practice
of what's what arose for you um Michelle I think I actually you're
one of the only people I do see in the small strip and I do see your head so please
um yeah um I was feeling um a lot of fear about an issue in my
life and um so to hold that with care and compassion
um is just saying oh it's okay it's okay to feel this
I'm making space for this so I I'm my question is I'm not clear on
how to hold an intense emotion with care
yeah yeah that's a very good question
so I'm gonna borrow a page from Gail's Book
for a moment because what he likes to say and I love the saying the way he puts it he often says you know let your
fear feel safe let your fear feel safe so so the idea is similar here that that
you are you know when we have a strong emotion when you brought up fear so let's talk about fear there could be any
other emotion fear here um and when it arises there is a sense
of of feeling seized up seized up it's it's all there is it's the the entire
visual like like the vision you know the visual field if there was a visual fit the entire field of knowing it's like it
becomes contracted that's all there is it's not that the fear is so great it's
not that it's that the our space of knowing has contracted right so that's
all we get to know it's like oh my God this is so overwhelming what's gonna happen ah what am I gonna do when
they're gonna like Ah that's all we perceive right especially with fear and
with all their emotions so so um so instead with this practice what I was
pointing to is to first open up have a sense of spaciousness in the in the
field of knowing oh yeah the breath oh yeah first you stabilize yes you
stabilize you expand the field of knowing and then oh yes there is fear
the fear is coming up but fear is is in a way it's being cut to size it's not it
doesn't capture everything oh yeah in my life there's also Joy there's also care
there's also love there's also this there's also gratitude like there are all these things oh yeah and fear is
there too okay all right fear there's a lot of space to hold you and I'm not
going to push you away because it's okay you can be here yeah it's all right
gratitude can be here fear can be here too and that actually that sense of care
that sense of spaciousness and care it changes our relationship to fear fear
might still be there it may go away it may not but we're not doing this practice to make the fear go away that
is really important we're not doing this practice to make the fear or anything else go go away it's a shift in
perspective the other fear can still be there but it doesn't scare you anymore
becomes really interesting does that make sense let me show what
I'm talking about yes I see yeah you're welcome to unmute or not it's all
good thank you yes that was very uh clear and helpful thank you so much
you're so welcome thank you yeah
any other questions reflections of what came up for you
foreign Sarah
there hi hi everyone Hi Sangha
um so I've been dwelling on this question for a couple of days
and it's because I'm I'm a first year teacher this year within a middle school
and I have been noticing some very immense gaps from between who I think I
am with my loving kindness practice and out in the world and then in the classroom when I lose my patience and I
get upset and I do things what that I look back and I'm like how could I have done that that is that doesn't that's
not me at all and I'm like kind of struggling with this perceived gap of like my the heart
that I know that I have when I sit and when I'm you know
like not in stressful situations and then when I am and these uh these very
new situations so I was wondering if you could comment on that a little bit those
like gaps and being out in the world and this perceived self that that I have
yeah yeah yeah thank you Sarah thank you so much for that question and and the
the beauty and you know the vulnerability of that question because it's not just you this is this is The
Human Condition right this is this is us right we have this intention which is
beautiful I hear what you're Sharing kindness goodness and and when you're in
a very stressful situation and being a first-year teacher I can only imagine how difficult the situation
must be with with youngsters um so so various things various
um invitations here so so one is um
first to have instead of you didn't say this but just just to um say not to
self-flagellate when there's a sense of wow how could I do that oh my goodness I raised my voice and I lost like oh my
God that is not helpful it's so instead oh sweetheart you must have been really
stressed okay yeah this was hard this was really hard for you this was really
hard for you because that if you if you self-flagellate if you kick yourself it becomes harder it really that that Gap
acknowledging that Gap becomes harder and and also doing something to support
it becomes harder but self with self-compassion actually you take more responsibility just as you have because
there is a sense of uh care like oh yeah this is hard like that was a hard day my
goodness that was a hard day I was hungry my blood sugar was low and that kid was screaming and the other one's
sorry oh sweetheart that was really hard okay all right well it's good that you didn't scream twice you just screamed
once okay let's let's just say right so so starting there
and then and then um it might be after the fact when you
think about the day that after you hold yourself with a lot of kindness and
forgiveness okay sweetheart yeah I have this intention and yeah this is what happened it's okay it's all right I'm
doing my best if it could have been any different it would have been I'm learning okay settled that's number one
and it's huge it's really huge to have that container really set the container
of self-compassion first number one number two think okay what happened again with
self-compassion okay what happened all right the height of the intention oh wait I was I hungry was I stressed was
that just like what was going on like try to get a sense of oh these are the
situations that really press my buttons okay so what can I what can I do so so
that when the situation so then when it arises maybe you recognize it not after
you know first maybe you recognize it after two hours then you recognize it after one hour then you recognize it
after 30 minutes then five minutes then at some point you'll recognize it while
it's happening well here it is my buttons are being pushed and also with
mindfulness of the body that's another thing that you need to strengthen with your practice really be aware because so
that so that before you get to that boiling point there's a sense of okay I'm I'm going
over the edge okay I know what the signals are my heart starts you know my my heart starts to race and my Palms
start to start or whatever it is for you you get to know it before it happens like all right this is time to say time
out like okay put your heads on the on the snap time or whatever it is I I need
time up right so it can happen little by little but it'll take time and you're
not bad you're not wrong it's just a stressful situation you're learning and
you'll come through more compassionate and kinder um
through the other side and the other side Sarah thanks so much for the question yeah
so so the time has come for us to turn our attention to
um practicing together care with kindness with Equanimity in small groups
breakout groups of size roughly three and um the invitation is to
share maybe just one nugget about what what's the ports you to have Equanimity
what supports you and what actually challenges you to have Equanimity so
inspired by the question that Sarah brought in what supports you and what challenges you so maybe you go around
once maybe you talked about what challenges you let's talk about what challenges you first
um and then maybe go go around one more time and talk about what supports you
um so um and each person will just say one nugget and
you'll go around and round a few times hopefully so I am going to create the
rooms uh hold on one second having trouble
yeah Okay rooms are created okay so take care of each other take care of
yourselves and uh here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back we have uh well we don't really
have any time unless there is a burning um reflection or question just do squeeze
in very quickly at the end yeah and somebody typed me a question a typed a question uh Jerry I'll stay and
answer afterwards so let's uh let's close let's close thank you all for your
practice for showing up for cultivating kindness and and wisdom Equanimity for
all beings everywhere may all things be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves [Music] thanks everyone
take good care