here we go so so hello and welcome everyone to
happy hour to practicing together in this moment in time
so so happy hour why happy hour well
it's self-explanatory but it helps to consider why this hour is called happier
the practices of what's called the brahmaviharas the heavenly
abodes meta loving-kindness compassion practice
um vicarious joy which is happiness for happiness of others equanimity
gratitude forgiveness just these various beautiful practices of the heart
are happy making they make us happy um make us happy make other people happy
it's there are happy making as you might have experienced and and also happiness
may not be experienced as uh you know a big
smiley face on you know the the round big smiley face on the yellow face i mean it's like no it's a it's a
different it can be a different kind of happiness there's a sense of peace there's a sense of ease there's a sense
of well-being that can come with these practices of course there are
various research studies nowadays that suggest that especially practices of
gratitude and loving kindness and compassion are conducive to happiness they haven't
done so much research yet on vicarious joy it turns
out actually i haven't seen too much on that because it's such an interesting concept in the
west to feel happiness for the happiness of others i think what usually comes up for people is envy but actually the
that that practice happiness for the practice of the happiness of others vicarious joy is the most happy making
is the most happy making practice as is equanimity there's a sense of
equipoise and ease and beauty that can come the sense of it's a deep happiness it's
a deep deep-seated happiness and and of course compassion
um it's not a sad difficult painful
experience people often confuse empathic distress when they're feeling
the pain of others so much that there is no cushioning of care
of love so they think compassion is painful and sad and difficult like i just i don't
want to you know compassion fatigue which is actually empathy or empathetic distress fatigue
so i just wanted to to uh
give a nod to why we're called happier um given that so many evenings it's you
know we we practice compassion etc which again for the old-timers you know you
know uh the change and the shift that this makes in your own
experience in your own um the landscape of your own mind
so so with that as the as the frame um
for practicing today um tonight i wanted to invite us um
this week given that there's so many challenges in the world uh especially
in the war zones um so much pain and suffering
that we turn towards it with the practice of compassion and equanimity
both to hold to hold witness both for ourselves and for the world
with this sense of care love which is stable which is stable it
doesn't topple over into into empathic distress or
or agony or grief but feels care and love meets the suffering meets the suffering
the love meeting suffering but with the sense of balance and spaciousness
because as you well know doom scrolling and exposing ourselves way too much
to to news that is challenging is
does not help us does not help anyone else it's important to be informed it's important to be
um to be aware and to help in every possible
way we can but to to be addicted to to have this addictive quality to bad news
and and challenging um uh
news that can actually veer us off into empathic distress is not helpful for anyone
so in that way i like to dedicate tonight's practice and happy hour to
compassion and equanimity both meeting suffering with care and
equipoise for the sake of ourselves as well as the world
um maybe i'll say just one last thing is in order to frame and the frame
also is as take not han said often on refugee boats if everyone
panics the boat capsizes but if there's one person who's calm
one person who cares cares enough to be calm
the boat can't survive so can we be the one who cares with a sense of calm in
the boat of our friends relative relative loved ones
for what's happening in the world now so without further ado i'd like to
invite us to to enter our practice
our meditation posture whether you're sitting or lying down
whatever is appropriate for you respecting your body
so that you are comfortable
you can be sitting or lying down or even standing up
and arriving arriving in this moment releasing
releasing what's not helpful [Music] as we take refuge
in the heart space in the quiet of this moment in this cultivation practice
relaxing the body here
releasing thoughts past future
and even releasing clinging to the present too hard
and abiding abiding
spaciously in the sensations with the sensations of this body there is a body
there is a body there is breath allowing each breath to be soothing
calming nourishing
in this moment
the thoughts arise as they will arise can we release them smiling with
can we smilingly not judgmentally but smilingly release them
release return take refuge
ah here here
the
releasing releasing what is not helpful right now
returning to the breath to the body
the refuge in this heart space
releasing smilingly
there is a body there is breath
there's the goodness of my intention
to connect to connect
connecting connecting with the breath with the body each and every moment
as we settle we continue to arrive
letting the breath move through
[Music] the chest the trunk the abdomen the whole body
whether it's deep or shallow
and let there be a sense of expansiveness with the breath
as if the breath isn't just moving through the body but expands
and includes the whole body expands beyond the body
as if a sphere of breath this sense of spaciousness
that you're sitting in spaciousness held
in spaciousness connected to the breath let the bodies
be soft and relaxed sitting in held in spaciousness
not effortful you were just sitting [Music] being held
in spaciousness inside outside it's already here you don't have
to work so hard and it includes and contains everything
even if there is tightness entanglement
challenging physical sensations pain
challenging emotions that hold everything it holds everything
spaciousness inside and outside
can coexist and hold every difficulty
pushing it away
not antagonistically but patiently spaciously
soothingly caringly holding all internally and externally
the sense of equipoise spaciousness already here
simply becoming aware of it as if through your peripheral vision not directly staring at it
oh yeah there is peace already
and other things too but the peace is already here
on this sense of spaciousness equipoise peace
expansive spacious holds you and everything that might be challenging in
this part of your mind with care
just breathing sensing feeling health
letting the spaciousness
that is holding [Music] ah this being who's me
with care with stability
acknowledge that it's expansive above and beyond
my imagination your imagination
a peaceful knowing a peaceful
stable caring loving knowing
pervading pervading
from this heart from this heart mind
expansively holding this being who's me and beyond
all beings everywhere in all conditions
spacious peaceful
caring knowing permeating through the entire world
boundless
this care caring knowing loves cares compassionate
can know suffering and touch it with love touched with care
meaning suffering balanced with care good will
well-wishing
like a bright bright warm light
the care bringing goodness to yourself and to others anyone it touches
you are deserving of meta of compassion yourself
justice is everyone else
they all pings everywhere including myself have ease
peace me pain sorrow
challenges
be held with ease be met with ease with love with care
may all beings including myself have freedom
both in the midst of and from suffering
for simply i care i care
i care
let there be spaciousness continuously as your heart and mind collapse
into tightness remember the spaciousness the balance the equipoise
ah expand your perspective
if it collapses at any point
i care i care
and as we bring this practice period to a close this meditation period they're
closed
appreciating ourselves for having tried having sad letting go of any judgment
that might be arising in this moment oh you were distracted you were not good meditator let it go let it go release
not needed and instead appreciate the goodness
we've come together you've come it's a part of the sangha to practice
how beautiful is that how beautiful is that appreciating appreciating your own
goodness efforts cultivations even if there was a moment a millisecond
of care connection for your own
sorrow for those of others and dedicate together we dedicate the goodness
of our actions replaying through the word replay through the world for the
goodness for the benefit of all beings everywhere may all beings
be happy may all beings everywhere be free
thank you everyone thank you for your practice
so so what
we were engaging with tonight today is a combination is a way into compassion
through equanimity so that there is a sense of stability care spaciousness
and then there is care love permeating that then can hold suffering so starting
from equanimity into compassion into holding compassion sometimes this
practice can work the other way around people you can start with compassion and if it becomes too overwhelming you end
up in empathic distress then you can ah bring an equanimity but i like well
both are good all practices are great and this is a lovely way lovely way to bring in more
equipoise into your compassion practice so any reflections any observations that you
made [Music] any insights that came up you're welcome
to raise your hand if you haven't shared in the space for a while you can also type in chat if it's typed
just to me i won't read your name it will be private reflection that i will read out
type it to everyone then i'll read your name also attribution so
what did you notice what was this like for you
was it different was it interesting was it this is something that opened up or not
maybe it was challenging maybe there was nowhere to land anything
for your own benefit and those of others
one reflection i thought of myself as a tree rooted to
the ground and offering shelter to others oh this is such a beautiful image thank you so
much for sharing this oh this is so beautiful it warms my heart i thought of myself as a tree rooted to
the ground and offering shelter to others that is so beautiful ah i am so touched
and inspired thank you for that susan please
yeah thank you nikki that was so timely for i was just
talking with a friend today who was just so overwhelmed with sadness about the war situation and
it's just like you were talking to her i'll point her your way but um yeah but just thanks for that
distinction between the empathetic distress and the compassion which actually feels good
and i and i know that but it's so helpful to hear that articulated and i love the spaciousness of
just bringing that large warm presence to hold everything
yeah thank you thank you susan thank you so much for your reflection and highlighting how
timely this this offering has been for you and your friend and yeah please send her a pointer to this guided
meditation on audiodharma on youtube and also this metaphor i love the metaphor
that shared this tree rooted in the ground offering shelter how beautiful is that also
yeah and and however wait came up for you also i love the way you described it susan this sense of care is
permeating warmth touching everyone so thank you for that
yeah beautiful
in the other reflections before we turn
yeah another reflection simply letting go
yeah it's with the spaciousness with the spaciousness
of equanimity there is a letting go and here there is also a sense of care
there's a sense of care um that permeates together with the letting go
yeah um one more reflection i felt the caring in
my body yay oh that's beautiful yay that's great it's when it's a physical
sense it can be quite strong great i see sarah and hickam
i'm saying your name right sorry
ishaam hi but this is sarah speaking
[Music] losing every word you're saying sarah
uh oh i i see other people move yes i see i see other yes thank you i see other
people move but sarah you are frozen ah i think you dropped out completely
you're probably not hearing anything i'm saying okay
so i'll go through the reflection from
deborah in chat um the practice offered a bomb i had to
deal with a lost stolen phone today ouch kept remembering that in the grand
scheme of things this was truly only an inconvenience a big one nowadays yes of
course throughout the day meta abounded
my heart is warm noticing all of it oh that is so beautiful wow
i'm so touched with your with your shared debra that it is these days losing your phone
it is quite an inconvenience as our lives depend on it so much
and and reminding that it is an inconvenience a big one and throughout
the day meta embounding and noticing your heart is warm noticing all of it so
beautiful just beautiful yay oh i'm so inspired and touched
ah yeah and and [Music] what you shared actually um prompts me to say that often when
challenging things happen when challenging things or inconvenient or difficult things happen
they're an opportunity to to open us to push us to be more kind
and grateful and gentle to even open us more to meta and care and presence
otherwise sometimes we go through our day mechanically when everything is okay or
the same so beautiful how this was an opportunity i hope you made it into an opportunity
deborah to practice um [Music] throughout the day with meta abounding
so beautiful so beautiful dear santa so
let's turn to practice together in small groups in small
groups of roughly size of three and the invitation is to start with 15 seconds of silence
meta for ourselves for others so equanimity caring for yourself caring for others
and you can share as little or as much as you like about your practice
holding each other holding witness and care for each other confidentiality
is very important speak from your own experience please not from other people's experience not commenting on
each other but really respecting holding holding close caring what does it mean
verbally to care for each other so the rooms are created
and i'm opening them now take good care enjoy
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
and we actually it's actually seven o'clock i think we don't have any time
now for any reflections anymore but if there's something you want to quickly type in chat i'll read
them but otherwise let's bring this practice
session to a close with appreciation for each other for ourselves
for the whole sangha and extending care to ourselves to each other and to the
entire world may all beings be well may all beings especially in war zones
be safe and [Music]
free thank you everyone be well