so warm greetings
and the theme for this week is the sense
stores the sense direct immediate simple sense experience
yesterday i talked about seeing today a hearing
and and
if we use the word listen listening that tends to be more of an
active idea something we intentionally do hearing it doesn't have to be that way
just now i heard the train whistle but i wasn't listening for it i wasn't
thinking about it until it whistled and uh
so it's possible for um some people find it
very nice to do mindfulness of hearing because um he uh of a lot of this
not controlling not adjusting not fixing anything sometimes with a focus on the
breathing there can be a lot of ideas about i'm the agent i have to breathe just the right way and how am i supposed to
breathe and what am i supposed to pay attention to whereas when mindfulness is of less of
hearing then it's there's a kind of letting go of trying to
control it trying to fix the sounds trying to have the right sounds
there's a receptivity an idea just to receive the sounds
and and then some people learn a kind of a non-uh
manipulative non-entangled knowing non-entangled mindfulness
by learning to listen well to hear well not listen here
so i'll suggest today that we start with hearing meditation hearing mindfulness
becoming sensitive to that door and as we become more sensitive to it
it's possible to notice how we get entangled in it how we get reactive to it or
involved in it or we grab onto the branches of sound so
i don't know if you hear the who is whistle now but one way of getting involved would be
starting to not wander off in thought and thinking about but we should really move imc to a quieter place so that when
we broadcast in the morning it can be quiet or it could be i could think wow that's
fantastic here i was going to do hearing meditation and and we already have wonderful
train whistles going and let's move imc closer to the train station to drink
wrecks so that i'm entangled with it i'm caught in it
and just allow the sounds to come and go and come and go as they wish
so we'll do it for a little while and then we'll i'll direct the same kind of attention to breathing if you'd like or
you can continue with sounds if that's nice for you and um
so so
making yourself comfortable nice
easy posture so you don't have to put a lot of
attention into your posture maintaining it so this is a little different than how
we usually are doing this meditation maybe sit in the easy relaxed posture
and gently closing your eyes
it will do the usual kind of relaxing to begin in a way that will support hearing
so gently taking a few deeper breaths comfortably deeper
fuller breaths and then as you exhale a comfortable fuller exhale
and exhale that you begin to relax the whole body
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and on the inhale feel these different parts of the body that i'll direct you to
and then as you exhale relax that part of the body
so begin by relaxing the belly
feeling the belly and relaxing it
maybe as you relax the belly there's a settling of the weight of your lower torso
into your [Music] into what supports your body
chair cushion bed
and feel the chest exhaling relaxing the chest
and relaxing the shoulders softening in the shoulders
and feeling the muscles of your face and relaxing them as you exhale
softening around the eyes
and then relaxing the thinking muscle
the energy the tension might might be associated with thinking
let that soften and relax
if there is any sense of pressure contraction tightness associated with thinking
or associated with the brain area feel it
on the inhale and soften it on the exhale
and then open your awareness to sounds
sound of my voice
where you are is very silent maybe this the sound of silence
if there's a ringing in your ears just to relax and
on the exhale soften on the inhale
allow hearing open and spaciously
if you find yourself trying to listen
relax the trying
instead of trying allow your ears to hear and if nothing comes no worry
sooner or later there'll be a sound and some of the sounds will be unexpected
and when they're unexpected
they come without any effort on our part
in the way unexpected sounds appear effortlessly
so
maybe each time you exhale letting go of your thoughts
letting go of efforting to hear
allowing hearing
perhaps hearing can arise in that place in the mind
where there is some silence some stillness
and then either continuing with hearing
letting that be your anchor to the present moment
content that each sound you hear
is an experience here and now or if you prefer
gently allow the experience of breathing to come into awareness
much like hearing sounds feel
the body breathing maybe relaxing
trying to do so or the effort to do so in favor of allowing yourself to feel
the experience of breathing
relaxing whatever effort you're making to think
relaxing the thinking energy
relaxing the trying in favor of being open and
receptive allowing hearing allowing breathing
to appear in awareness
so
and as we come to the end of the sitting bring to mind or imagine intuit
what it's like to most fully hear
without entanglement here without reactivity
most fully just allows the sound to come and go to be present
forever along its presence and to go when it goes
what would it be like for the mind to be so spacious relaxed
there'd be no searching [Music]
no analyzing no reacting no fixing
the sound would allow to just be there
and perhaps when there's no entanglement with what we hear
it allowed to sign for it to be registered
deep within a place within where there is
greater understanding greater love or kindness
care a greater peace with how things
are peace that is more enduring than the vagaries and
changes of the world
there is a buddhist bodhisattva kind of a
sacred being called kuan yin kannon
and it said that the name can mean the one who
hears the sounds of the world and now look at
is the embodiment of compassion
hearing the suffering of the world
to learn to hear well
allows us to be custodians and caretakers of the
suffering of the world without being entangled
to be entangled is just to add to more suffering in the world
to be unentangled
places places us in a better position to alleviate suffering in this suffering
world
may this practice that we do
be for the welfare and happiness of this world
may we living in the way that we're meant to live live
in a way that supports the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
so the teachings of the discourse on the
establishing of awareness
is uh has come now to the exercise on mindfulness of the sense
senses and sense doors and sense experience
and in the explicit teachings that i've heard over the these years on this particular
satibatana discourse my sense is the particular exercise that
maybe the two exercises maybe that are least emphasized is the last one of the first of the mindfulness
of the body which is the corpse meditations and this one the six senses
and it's a little bit of a pity that it's not emphasized more because um the sense experience
being really grounded in our sense experience of hearing seeing
touching smelling tasting and the clear clear seeing or knowing of what
happens in the mind is um really at the heart of
classic bipasuna practice and we're learning to stay present
in the simplicity of our sense experience because that's always in the present moment
and as we do so as we come closer and closer to be able to do that it's a process
we do you know progressively um closer and closer to just the simplicity of sense experience
at the same time it is more and more letting go of our entanglement the way we're caught and reactive and spending
our time thinking there's less and less attachment as we're able to stay more and more just to
the with the ongoing flow of the current of um the river of sense experience as
it occurs and
the little teaching from the buddha that's repeated a lot in
in this insight world teachers is the instructions
in the scene just the scene see the scene what's seen
just a scene in the herd just a herd and they cognize just the cognized
in the sense in the sense experience just a sense experience this is just just the scene just to hear heard that
simplicity it can be quite liberating quite delightful to have put down our preoccupations and
reactivity so today the topic is um
hearing and uh this is a maybe because much of these teachings
were done were composed before the the written word became popular
the the name of direct disciples of the buddha
is sabaka and savaka can be translated as the ones who hear the ones who heard the
teachings of the buddha directly but i like to think it as a deeper meaning the ones who hear deeply that
are attentive as if they're hearing to everything
the the christian order of monks called the benedictines apparently
their kind of code of conduct their rule book discipline
begins with the word ascolta in latin meaning hear listen here
listen so to listen there's a lot to be learned from
listening and hearing hearing in particular if we can hear
receptively openly and i like this idea of the 360 degree
panorama of sounds and to settle back and and allow the sounds to appear from
whatever in that prem that big circle that they occur and sometimes i have the sense that my
awareness is sometimes as big and as expensive as
the distance this from where the sound originates and that's happens when my mind gets
very relaxed and open and there's very little sense of boundaries to the mind or
or location for things in the mind and so the sense of location
uh it's just since it tends to become expansive and open and and it's a delightful feeling to feel
the mind so receptive and relaxed and open that it just takes in sounds in a very
spacious way um
well short of that um as we become aware of hearing
we can become aware of how we get entangled in what we hear the knots that could be gets formed
there's a sound there's the ear that hears the eardrums maybe
and then there's the knot the in that the fetter that gets formed
between those two and this can happen when someone's speaking to us
someone's saying something and we stop listening because we're we grabbed onto a branch of what uh
you know what how we feel hurt or how we have some new fantasy a new idea and we
go off thinking about something that's triggered by them but we're no longer really listening
and so so we've formed a knot around our thoughts
or maybe we don't like what we hear and so there's uh tension somewhere in the body
maybe we we like what we hear and we want more of it and so there's a kind of starts plotting
planning how to get more and let it continue
there's um all kinds of judgments that can arise there's all kinds of preferences there
are bias there can be ideas of self
that this sounds is impinging on me i'm a victim of all these sounds
i'm the one who hears it there's an uh kind of a
analogy that's used that if you hold your hand flat
and um and then you something comes and strikes it then you know if it's no the stronger
the strike the more it's going to hurt your hand but if you keep your hand open and relaxed so that
things can just go right through then you're less likely to be hurt
just let it go through or even better is you lower the hand and then the
sounds just go right through and they don't touch they don't hit anything and the equivalent of the hand in the
mind is sometimes is a very strong sense of self strong sense of me my experience i'm the
victim of it it's happening to me why are they doing it to me and
and and to be able to lower that that concern that
tension that preoccupation of myself me myself and mine is one of the great fruits of this
mindfulness practice and then as this selfing self relaxes then the sounds go
right through or we start seeing where where the sound what the
sounds strike where the knot exists and we can it becomes a
a mindfulness spell for us to notice that not to notice our reactivity our
reaction our entanglement with it
so um if you hear anything your ears are hearing
you are in the present moment sounds are one of those phenomena
that only exists in the current the flow of the present moment
and and so to be aware of sounds and listening
and you know to be open to it and receive it is to stay present here and now
and it can be a way that we begin to recognize
the the forces of the mind that take us out of the present moment the branches we
hold on to and it's not so much that we have to then analyze what we're holding on to
as it is to let go to come back to this receptive awareness of listening
and to learn to do this around sounds some people find this is
the the laboratory in which it's easiest to learn relaxed receptive unentangled awareness
mindfulness and then learning it in hearing and then to apply it to um other things as well
so for this next 24 hours i'd encourage you to give a particular attention to
hearing and maybe find sometimes through the day that you can sit someplace in a park or
an open window or someplace um in a very just kind of
allow yourself to hear sounds um kind of like you may be laying your back on the grass and look at the clouds
you know float by above and it's very relaxed just way
so kind of settle back and just take some time just hear sounds
if you like listening to music you could try to choose some music that is uh pleasant relaxing to listen to that may
be just a delight to listen to if um
in this way maybe even just listening with your eyes closed sometimes with the eyes closed
there's less entanglement and more ability to just receive what's happening
and um and in the course of the day you might also practice
this listening someone speak how simple can you hear how how fully
can you be present in a hearing way so you can hear and listen to what they say
without the entanglement so that as you listen to them you hear something you hear from a
deeper place in your heart in your in your body and your mind that you hear the other person you allow
those words to come and because there's no entanglement it doesn't hit anything
on the way in maybe it can resonate some deeper connectivity some deeper place that
may be a place of love and compassion care
peace may hearing
be a doorway for freedom thank you