hello everyone and welcome
i'll begin with a little story having to do with our theme for the week
something appears to our senses
we might see an object i might see the bell that's here
so i see the object and i feel the pleasantness of it
i feel the smoothness of it and the temperature of it is nice
and then i recognize it as something or cognize it i
in this case i recognize it as a bell in other circumstance i might recognize it as something else
and then once i have that bell
idea then i can begin creating a story
and the story is that this bell will sit next to me here
during the meditation and at the end of the sitting i'll ring the bell to mark the
end and that could be as simple as the story goes
or the story can go yes i'll
ring it at the end of the sitting and there's a lot of people listening and so i better ring it well
loud enough but not too loud with the night residence and to the story might end there
the story might continue if i don't ring it well people will not like me
if i don't ring the bell well my reputation will be sullied and then tomorrow i'm coming i'll be
quite self-conscious and it'll be difficult and and maybe i wonder if maybe i shouldn't even ring the bell maybe i should just
kind of announce the sitting's over and so the story begins spinning and going
but it all began with a very simple something appeared to the census seeing
of the bell it was pleasant in and of itself there was a recognition
not necessarily what it is but the recognition of what it is for me
here now it's a bell and then there's beginning to be stories
part of what we're doing in meditation is to stay simple with our experience
with the immediacy of what's happening now what's appearing now knowing whether it's pleasant or
unpleasant allowing yourself to have the simple recognition of what it is for us now
a recognition which is maybe empty of ultimate truth about the object just
this is how it's being seen now recognize now and then it once the stories begin
we come back to the breathing we come back to the simplicity of this moment maybe by first recognizing that i'm
beginning to construct and make stories beginning to elaborate
on on the simplicity of it all many people live in the elaboration they
live in their stories that's where the center of gravity is in meditation the center of gravity is
in this earlier steps in the process the appearance the feeling tones the simple recognition
of the experience and and it means that this
we don't need to get involved in complicated stories that involve judging or commentary or
predictions memories uh the things the mind becomes
simpler and easier when it's in meditation when it starts going at earlier steps in that process
earlier and step from the process doesn't mean that it's i don't know more primitive or less
important it actually gives us a vantage point to understand how we're getting
caught and how to let go or how not to be caught and then not being caught can simply
becoming as simple as just coming back to the breathing or come back to the direct sensation of the moment
with no elaboration so
assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and as you are right now how does your physical experience appear
how does it occur how does it show up for you
in the simplest version of sensations of the body
and is it pleasant unpleasant or neither
do you have simple ideas recognitions concepts for what's happening in your
body
not so much big processes but simple ideas of what is appearing what
is the thing what is the experience in the simplicity of the moment
and do you have elaborations do you have stories interpretations concerns
sentences that you tell yourself about what's happening in your body
bigger perspectives the meaning of it
that it's good or bad or right or wrong or
it could be better or worse
and if you take those and begin to elaborate that elaboration is going to continue and spiral out to more and more
complicated stories and we can sometimes live in the constructed stories
and so settling into your breathing
as you inhale feeling your body directly and simply
as you exhale relax the body
as you exhale relax into the contact of your body bottom to the
chair your cushion your bed
the floor
relaxing the belly softening in the belly
yielding to the pull of gravity
in the belly
softening in the shoulders relaxing the shoulders
relaxing in the face
and then relaxing the thinking mind relaxing the pressure and tension
of the thinking that makes the elaborated stories that constructs ideas and
predicts futures or remembers the past or makes meaning out of things
relax the thinking mind
and then settle into the rhythm of breathing
the bodies experience of breathing and see if you can
gently maybe lovingly and kindly stay with your breathing
as if your awareness your attention
is going hand in hand with the body's experience of breathing
awareness accompanies breathing and breathing a company's awareness
and if you get pulled into the world of thoughts ideas elaborations
recognize it as constructions
constructing stories constructing meaning
constructions and then begin again with your breathing
are you more connected to your stories and constructions
or more connected to the direct experience of breathing
if you're involved in the world of stories and collaborations
memories and future imagine
that all that are like clouds
and that you allow yourself to drop through the clouds and land back on the ground
of the body breathing here is a place to be grounded
one of the pleasures of meditation is being
content to rest in the direct experience of the body breathing
we arrest in the direct experience of what arises in awareness
either case do not be pulled into the world of stories and constructions
even though some can be pleasant wonderful some can be difficult
something profound about connecting to this lived life of ours
without the stories and there's something profound
about the safety and the directness and the simplicity
that can then also occur in how we are present for other people
we're present not through the filter of the stories the meanings the history
the projected future we're able to put that aside
to be present for the directness of seeing another human being and
letting them feel the safety the contentment
the ease of just being present with each other in the simplicity of the moment
and may it be that what we learn about being content to be
in the present moment unburdened by our stories
may it be a vehicle for supporting the happiness and safety and
peace freedom of others as it is
supporting our own happiness
safety peace and freedom
may this practice that we do express itself in this world
bringing happiness to all beings
bringing safety to all beings
bringing peacefulness to all beings
bringing freedom to all beings may we do this practice
for the welfare and happiness of all beings everywhere yourself included
[Music]
thank you
so we're talking about this important
uh topic which appears importantly in the teachings of the buddha prepares all appears often
sometimes it is presented in ways that it's hard for modern people to identify with or
appreciate but i think that this teachings on the five aggregates
the five groupings or the five divisions of our human experience
it might be easier to appreciate through presenting them as a story
and which is a little bit paradoxical since part of the purpose of of this teaching is to help us
kind of come to the end of stories or appreciate it's a different way of being
and the
um so that it begins these five aggregates
five groupings with uh with uh the direct experiences of things there's a sensory experience
and the poly word can mean appearance appearances
but it's just like in english the word appearance means what comes into view
but it also can be extended to be any sensation that comes into
experience with anything anything we sense and so it's kind of the raw sense data
from which we build our world from their understanding of the world and um
and then when there's a in the buddhist psychology and then the understanding is once a sensation has come since data has
come the first uh detail of that that becomes then
apparent is the pleasant unpleasant or neither pleasant or unpleasant of it
there's some idea that this kind of amoeba-like being you know for against or pleasant unpleasant is very basic
and occurs almost immediately after just taking in a sensation
before we necessarily necessarily even recognize what it is
and then but so then and we often react to the pleasant unpleasant toy
it might be that the recognition knows this is terrible this is uncomfortable or this is wonderful and that's a simple
act of recognition the third step but it could be recognizing what the object is
you know like i was talking earlier about the meditation bell we have here so it i see it it's a pleasant sight
i and i recognize it as a bell but we have to really appreciate that the recognition
is not that uh doesn't live in the object
the recognition is a often a construct a very simple
application or projection onto the thing in this case by its function
it's operating as a bell so we call it a bell
the uh many years ago in san francisco i saw someone who was um
a homeless person who was kind of asking for money but he had a beautiful
japanese bell surprised how beautiful it was kind of like this one here that i have and he's
going around and asking for donations and i said oh it's now the bell is a begging ball
and um so um the um
so the recognition so those are the first three of the aggregates the appearance of sensations
experiencing it either pleasant unpleasant or not neutral and building on that
uh there's the wrecking a recognition and the recognition is usually just one word you know just a simple label idea
of what it is concept and then once we have a simple concept then
there's an elaboration that goes on and that elaboration can be a story or
some construct that's that's more than just the object itself that we're recognizing
and so i see the bell here and i recognize it as being imc's bell
and i remember the person who gave it to us many years ago and that where the person gave it to us
or what inspired the person to give to us remember the person's name and uh my appreciation for that person
and wondering what's happened to that person and and um feeling this warmth for this
person as i think this spell think about the spell and so there's all this construction
this elaboration this uh that it rises in the wake of having recognized this is a bell
and that's innocent enough it kind of adds to the richness of life to have stories and histories and things like
that but it also is a place where life can get unnecessarily complicated
and a lot of human suffering gets born in this elaborations that happen the
constructions that happen after um the uh the basic recognition
once there's all these things together there's the appearance the pleasant unpleasant the recognition and
the constructions of stories and ideas around it and then there is the
fifth aggregate which we'll talk about tomorrow which usually in english is called consciousness
and in the way the story i'm talking about consciousness is not
prior to all the rest of it it's actually arises in the wake of all
of this so we'll talk about that tomorrow but so for today
it's so the fourth aggregate the fourth grouping which is usually
translated into english as mental formations the holy word sankara s-a-n-k-a-r-a
the sun means like with and kara is like related to karma to make or to do
and so to form something so that's why people say formations i like the word constructions
it doesn't say mental in it but that's by implication it has to do with the mind the mental constructions the mental
elaborations that go on in the mind the stories and um and how we build
our or the world we kind of live in some of it's built collectively and some
of it is built by our own projections onto people and things and ideas
and this world of constructions has has some to do with our inclinations our
bias our our preferences our motivations our presence of purpose
our fears as it's a kind of it's a huge uh world
uh that um just that is this part of the mental landscape that we
live in often we don't recognize it as such and we not only do we think that the
recognition the object we recognize the third aggregate is really what that's what it is and
we're attached to the idea we have of it i can attach to this being a bell
here at imc if someone wanted to use it as a
trash can i'd feel a little bit like what i'm not so sure about that
i kind of like to keep it as a bell and keep it clean and things like that
um because that but uh and then there's stories around it
constructs around it you know imc bell keeping it clean what it means for a meditation center to have
a clean bell and and some of that's normal but some of it can be
that's the world not only of constructs but that's also the world of constructions
now of of of clinging
now what's fascinating around these teachings of the buddha
is that this constructing aspect of the mind is
what constructs the other groupings that the appearance of things
is partly born not innocently because something comes
partly because we have an apparatus that selects that out of the environment
uh of all the things we could pay attention to where there's a selective process that this is important
and we're selecting this or we're selecting the feelings
feeling tones we're selecting the ideas the recognition more often we're selecting the
constructions themselves but for the buddha each of the five aggregates
is a construct made by the constructing activity of the mind
and and so many times people in the west will said the teachers will say that the
buddha said there's no self what there is are these five aggregates these five heaps and the buddha didn't actually
didn't say that he actually saw the five heaps more as the problem
and there he called them actually all five of them a burden and how i understand that is that the
constructing activity of the mind selects out of the suchness of experience the simplicity of the
experience certain things to prioritize and uh
and it's kind of in some ways necessary to do it but there's a kind of extra
extraness in it that comes with it that creates a lot of clinging a lot of suffering a lot of
burden in this world that's very different if we rest in the suchness of things we
allow things to be as they are almost as if we don't need to get involved
in the appearance or the feelings or the ideas or the stories around it
we're just very we're there in a very very simple way so um
so these five there's a story then going you can say like i did appearance
feeling tones simple recognition elaboration and stories
what's interesting for mindfulness practitioners is it's possible to go backwards
to recognize that we're involved in storytelling and the elaborations of the mind
and then be curious with with can i just recognize that that's
happening in this simple possible recognition thinking story making
and then step back further uh is that pleasant or unpleasant to be thinking and
telling these stories and then we take one step back and what are the actual sensations that come
along with it maybe there's pressure a tightness maybe there's some kind of pleasantness and
warmth and thinking about it and what we're doing is we're going back to the what's primary or foundational to
get grounded there so it's taking a stand on the simplicity of the experience we're less likely to
be swept away in the in the um
you know in the currents of of these elaborate thinking so sometimes we can watch from
appearances as things get more complicated into stories and sometimes we can trace it backwards
into the basic simple sensations that are there and uh and that's fascinating to kind of
be able to go play the scales mindfulness scales back and forth up this and find in doing that
that you start appreciating that the each of these five these four so far are experiences that
have a genesis they arise they appear and they disappear they come and they go
they appear and they cease and and so it's possible to begin in
being in the flow the current of these things which is much closer to the suchness of
them than it is to select them out and hold on to anyone
out of the general flow of the river so i hope that made sense and
then tomorrow's topic the last aggregate um i think is
very interesting for many people um when we call it consciousness so we'll take a look at what this is for
the buddha so thank you and i look forward tomorrow