into the last week of uh the year
welcome and it's quite something to have gone through all the challenges of this year
since March and um perhaps we're wiser
perhaps we are more equanimous about things that a year ago we would not have been wise and not had some healthy
Equanimity about and so it happens to be that the last
topic of the year is equanimity and right up until the first day of 2021
for on Friday and uh
thinking about equanimity I think of it as maybe a mind at rest or
very similar to a mind at rest with the following analogy the Buddha gave
a cow herder in ancient India
when the growing season for the rice was happening it was very important for
the cowherder to stay close to the cows chewing them away from the rice paddies and directing him and where they had to
go and and had to be very attentive because there wasn't a lot of space maybe between the rice paddies to where
the cows could graze and so a lot of effort and a lot of attention
but once the rice had been harvested and and uh there was no longer any need to
uh shoe the cows around
and and rather the cow the cowherder now could lean against a tree in the shade
and just keep a equanimous broad gaze out across
the fields and just kind of generally track and be aware of where the cows are but no longer a need to before or
against them going in this direction or that direction and so a mind at rests the same way
that has done its work there's nothing that has to be done the mind is at ease
and there's no longer a need to kind of follow every little movement of the mind to move in this direction back to the
breath the hear avoid those kinds of fantasies which
maybe you've done 10 000 times but the mind can sit back and just not
before or against anything but watch it all in a spacious equanimous mind and
and this idea of not being for or against not needing to shoe things this way in that way from a mind that's
settled and economist non-reactive is one of the great gifts
of this Buddhist practice and we'll talk about more about that this week so for now to
take a meditation posture assume a meditation posture
and gently close your eyes
and without much more notice the quality of your mind
is your mind jumping around is it strongly concerned with certain thoughts
and ideas is it agitated energized
or is lethargic
is it hesitant and reluctant
notice how your mind is and see if you can notice it with
equanimity with not being for or against how the mind is
but just to notice this is how it is for you
and then noticing the knowing in and of itself in the Simplicity of
knowing something there are qualities of equanimity
qualities of not being for or against just to know
and so you might as you're sitting here now
bring that knowing to experiencing your body
how's your how's your body at this time
and for a few moments just know as if nothing needs to change you don't need to be for or against
because if you're for or against something harder to know it clearly
to really see what's happening
but if there's some ways in which you can adjust your posture so that you're a little bit more
comfortable at ease maybe relaxing parts of your body
there is a subtle way which in the movement of the Mind as it relaxes the body
there can be a feeling of equanimity the feeling of also letting go of
for or against needing to do anything even though you are relaxing
softening the shoulders
softening the belly
softening the arms the elbows
maybe you can soften the whole waist area around to the small of the back
Maybe by relaxing the tops of the thighs
and maybe relaxing the muscles of the face
and then if it's possible letting your mind be at rest
as if there's for this time there's no more work
there's no more anything to be afraid of or to prove
or to avoid
trusting that the mind is Broad enough wide enough
to hold all things to make space for all things that are
and because there's so much space in the mind and the Heart
it's it's possible also to be equanimous
to not be for or against
but to be at rest in the awareness of what's Happening
and then within your body as part of your bodily experience
allow there to be room in your mind and awareness
for breathing Let There Be room
for the bodies experience of breathing to occur within
the awareness
and to experiment a little bit with your mind your awareness
to see if you can find a way to really feel and sense the inhales and
exhales without it needing to be any different than the way it is
whether it's comfortable or uncomfortable to breathe
whether your attention on the breath is clear and continuous or not
whether you're controlling your breath or not whatever way it is
can you kind of experiment or
look for that way of being with the breathing
that is spacious and equanimous
balanced and even allowing it to be just the way it is
and the mind at ease with that
thank you
as you exhale relaxing the thinking mind
as you exhale quiet your thinking
as you exhale let go of your thinking
thinking is often part of an agitated mind
a mind that's for or against things as thinking becomes quieter
you might look for The increased equanimity
or the way in which the mind is more at rest at ease
and you might find or see ways in which the mind is not equanimous
and you step back with awareness and really notice how your mind is
you might find that it's very much involved in wanting or not
wanting being disturbed or being
depressed in some way
can you experiment with knowing that knowing how the mind is
so the knowing itself is relaxed at ease
The Knowing itself is equanimous
and with some modicum of equanimity
in recognizing how you are
open up again to your breathing letting breathing be at the center of it
all
ever so gently breathe a little bit deeper
exhaling a little bit more fully
gently enough so that the mind is restful as you do so
the mind is curious present
let go as you exhale let go of all things
while you let go into the breathing just breathing
taking a few moments now to notice whatever degree your mind is
equanimous or at rest
or at ease or perhaps your heart
at ease at rest equanimous with
here in the present moment with how things are
breathing in and out
and to whatever degree that the mind is not agitated the heart is at ease
can you now feel your good will or your love
your capacity for care and warmth kindness
to almost as if equanimity clears the ear air
clears the agitation that allows the capacity for love
for kindness and friendliness
to be more clear more available
and perhaps there's a way in which there can be love compassion good will
that is itself at rest or is that itself easy or
equanimous not really involved in for or against
anything just gazing upon all things kindly
and allowing whatever sense of kindness you have
to Now open up and take in the people in your life
the peoples in your neighborhood communities
as if you're opening the doors of your heart wide open to take in all beings everywhere
and with equanimity with non-agitation
sending your well-wishing out into the world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be free
and may you
bring in equanimous care and love in your communication with other people
today experiment
with a heart that's at ease and equanimous
as you express your generosity and care and kindness for the welfare and happiness of the
people around you may all beings
be happy
[Music]
so I want to welcome you to the land of equanimity
the time of equanimity that this is the topic for this week's
five talks and in particular it's the Equanimity Brahma vihara
it's a form of love which is characterized by upeka which is
the poly word for equanimity and um it is um
maybe a counter-intuitive for many people to think of love as being
synonymous or connected to equanimity
because love seems to be something that's more proactive engaged going
towards people doing something it's being expressed many things
but in fact I think it's not too difficult to analyze love
the way that that's often practiced and in the world around us
is that it's often mixed up with other attitudes and needs and desires
that sometimes love is mixed up with what we need if we need company we need
security we need sometimes people feel like they need admiration
uh sometimes love is mixed up with fear and
uh sometimes makes love is mixed up with lust sometimes it's mixed up with um Power
and sometimes it mixed up with status and all kinds of things that comes along
with love and sometimes it's very hard to see the difference between some of these other
elements that come along with love and love itself
I like to think of the practice of mindfulness as well as the practices of loving
kindness compassion sympathetic joy and equanimity as being practices that purify love
that uh simplify it like you would simplify gold down to its beautiful
Essence and take out the dross take out the impurities that are there
so that as we simplify our love or clarify the love so it's not mixed up
with these other needs and other things going on it becomes more and more a wonderful treasure
a wonderful Jewel inside of us that um a source of
nourishment support and um so to purify our love to clarify our
love and so for example that they for loving kindness
what gets what gets purified from is any
form of ill will and any form of love that has to do with
our self-centeredness self-preoccupation what's in it for me
as we practice or connect to compassion compassion is freed certainly from any
tendency for cruelty to harm people and it's also purified from any sense of
distress any sense of uh of dismay horror that might be there
that sometimes is confused with it appreciative Joy
gets purified of envy and jealousy sometimes that's a very strong motivator
for insisting on love or holding on to love or protecting our love with someone
else when there's jealousy and envy going on and also it's uh also purified from any
kind of self-centered focus on oneself around feeling
discontented feeling or feeling kind of feeling giddy or
feeling like you know that I'm the one who's now enjoying or delighting in the
light of someone else and so it's kind of a carious way of living where the focus is really on oneself rather than
just being open to the the joy of others
and so Equanimity also is a purification it's a purification from they say from
two things from repulsion and pursuing
sometimes it's translated as this word is attraction sometimes as greed but the word the poly
word has the connotation of pursuing following after something and so love that is neither pursuing nor
has any kind of repulsion towards anything as a result of of it or part of
it and so uh part of the one way to appreciate this quality of equanimity is
that is in fact not so much to try to understand it directly but to understand
its alternatives that the mind that doesn't have centered in this restful easeful place of
equanimity is a mind that is either for or against things in some kind of way
that has qualities of pursuing or or of repulsing or pushing away in a way
that's not so healthy that's not really a place of freedom
and so to begin Discerning and noticing the small ways or the big ways which
we're pursuing with love wanting and getting than some of us who may be in especially
when we were younger maybe teenagers the drive to pursue can be quite strong
the um and so to find a Equanimity to find a place where love is not pursuing
is not repulsing anything pushing anything away but is able to stay open
and clear and in that openness and Clarity the purity of equanimity that
the love can radiate and shine quite broadly so the purification of Love is the task
here and it's closely connected to Freedom that love these different forms of Love
Are freeing and freedom
is a means for loving it's a opening to loving and there's a wonderful
reciprocal mutuality between the greater and greater degrees of freedom that the
practice brings and our greater and love and the greater love we have supports
the freedom we have the the
Buddhist the terravan tradition provides an analogy for these four kinds of love
and it has to do with parenting a certain you know maybe excuse maybe
ideal parent situation is that um if maybe parents have four
children one who is recently born and everything's healthy with a kid and
there's a enthusiasm and happiness and kind of lots of loving kindness lots of well-wishing and good will for their
future and delight and and that's very simple and clear
and just that just just all around kind of uh lots of delightful uh Goodwill and
loving kindness and then there is uh compassion as that
child grows up or one of the children maybe um has a an illness and so the second
child has an illness and or has some disadvantage that the parents feel a lot
of care and compassion and support that child in a different kind of way than others because the sickness they have
and and so there's kind of compassion someone else is in the flesh of Youth
and life is just opening up for them brilliantly and wonderfully and and there's just a lot of joy and
appreciation that things are working out so well and that the world is opening up for them and the opportunities are there
and then the fourth one is um well established in their life there may
be in their 40s or something and well established in career and family or
activities whatever their life is going to be about it's well established and it's going along just fine and the
parents don't have to think about them so much not be concerned with their welfare and so there's a kind of equanimity towards those uh those
children that child so so this idea of whether this is kind of a good analogy or not is not exactly
the point here we have to kind of shape these analogies for ourselves
but the um the idea being that uh it's association with kind of Ideal parental
love and a parental love is uh generally not doesn't have the complexities that
romantic love have for example can have its own complexities but the
idea is maybe it's easier with parental love to maybe feel a kind of a Simplicity and Purity there and
sometimes parental love is not about the parent this is especially true when when
I think for many parents when the baby's just born that just so directed towards the baby
that there's sometimes a self-forgetting that goes on for the parents because it's just caring for the for the babies
everything we need so this um
ability to love without it being
self-preoccupied love without it being For Me Myself and mine what's in it for me and what I need and
what I have to get there's nothing wrong with having needs and inappropriate needs nothing wrong
with pursuing what we you need to be safe and happy and content
but it's useful to separate that from our capacity for love
so that our capacity of love can be Simple Pure just a wonderful opening and
clear clarity and one of the ways that uh I've
experienced this in my life that kind of the door to really appreciate this in a deep way was or is through meditation
that uh through my first years 10 years of meditation practice where I'd had a lot
of suffering and sat with a lot of suffering unexpectedly it opened to a lot of
compassion and I learned to appreciate this beautiful capacity for just
compassion without any need compassion without any being for or against even
though there's movement towards you know certainly a movement towards help and to do things but the movement towards
supporting others are helping or uh caring for others can be done without
this kind of self-centered being for or against anything
and then my next year is a practice especially when I when I practice vipassana I discovered this wonderful
capacity of good will and uh of uh friendliness of kindness
and also the Simplicity of it and the purity of it and without it needing to
receive anything in return and then sympathetic Joy a lot of that
I've really come to appreciate a lot in my time as a teacher just feeling so
much appreciation so much delight and other people and other practitioners and
and learning there also a way in which that coming out of meditation that delight and joy can be so simple and so
without any needs or needing to do anything really just a delight in joy
and then equanimity and the love of equanimity has a lot also to do with meditation and the way
in which I've discovered freedom and meditation freedom from attachments and clinging and just kind of feeling
sometimes this real tender warmth and care and kindness that extends to people
who I don't really like or have trouble with or disturb by what they do
and to have the this ability to have love and Equanimity to suffer so widely
my love and Equanimity to spread out in such a clean way is also one of the
great Treasures so um
so this topic for this week is equanimity and it's one of the great important topics it has a lot to do more
than the others maybe with wisdom and we'll see that the wisdom comes into
play and and how the practice really comes to play and to really cultivate and develop
this Equanimity Factor and how it is also leads to Freedom
so uh um that's the topic for the week and we'll end it uh on Friday with the new
year and um on the first and for those of you who are up and early enough when the first
will begin the year with um an evocation of this quality of equanimity
and who knows maybe it'll be a great resource for 2021
so thank you so much and um look forward to tomorrow