so good morning everyone and welcome but we'll have a
zoom meeting when we finished here at 7 45 for those of you would like to come i'll announce it again the
the link is at the very top of this chat and i'll probably post it again later and say more about it
so to begin this meditation it's a little bit uh auspicious
uh many ways and
here in this earth care day we um earth day we
come at the end of the inner development that happens
in practicing sati awareness the upper reaches of what
happens with awareness practice in that we come to equanimity
and one of the wonderful really wonderful qualities
imagine that
this modern technology that we have and virtual reality glasses
imagine they make glasses that are attuned to your mood and mental state
and what's happening inside of you and so the frame of the glasses and the
glasses themselves morph and change according to how you're feeling and what you're concerned with
and so sometimes those glasses the rims get really really wide
sometimes they get really narrow sometimes they almost like uh
move away from your face like going towards something that you're interested in
sometimes they recede backwards and press up against your face sometimes they raise
one one side of the frame one like an eyebrow rise it raises rises really high
sometimes they wink sometimes they have all kinds of looks that they do
and people would start feeling maybe kind of almost naked because the way they keep their face
sometimes is not quite representative of what is going on inside
but now as everything's uh everything is there so um of course so we don't have those
kinds of glasses yet rather the glasses that we have those of us who do have glasses
are not reacting to the world around us they don't pick up our emotions they don't
are not interacting with the world in emotional ways reactive ways they're just there
peacefully we can say we could say equanimously and isn't so much that i want to make
this as an analogy for equanimity is i want to say that
all our responses and reactions all the rich world that we have out there
continues even with the glasses that don't react
but we see through the glasses the medium for seeing for some of us and so the
glasses have a fantastic function kind of independent of how we're feeling
in our mood and what's going on around so in the same way as
awareness gets stronger and stronger more developed there comes a time
when awareness has a quality of non-reactivity non-engagement
it doesn't it's not riding and being pushed around by caught up in the inner moods reactions
that we have the thoughts that we have it's not exactly aloof
it's there everything it goes through it in a sense like everything goes through the glasses
it doesn't diminish our humanity it actually enhances it it's kind of
like we can see things more clearly however there is this place of
steadiness stillness non-reactivity that is able to do a fantastic work of
seeing but does not interact it does not get caught in
just like my glasses don't get caught in what's happening right now so i say that so that maybe there's a
little bit less hesitation to explore this topic of equanimity
a balanced state of mind where awareness is strong enough clear enough where the clarity is clear
enough that we clearly see we don't have to get
involved not only don't we see we don't have to but the very name of
the very quality uh the very state that we're in there's no inclination
for awareness to get swept away or caught up in
all the different movements of the mind and the world around us
so taking a
a meditative posture
taking a few moments to feel your body as it is
any tensions you might have agitation you might have any contentment you might have
in taking the posture
allow yourself for a few moments just to breathe with however it is in your body
letting the tensions be there the holdings be there agitation contentment
whatever it is
and as you do so do you have reactions in the mind
is awareness hijacked by preferences
likes and dislikes desires for it to be different
and what would it be like to sit here with your body with an awareness that is equanimous
about how it is right now
an awareness that allows things to be as they are
and so now taking a few long slow deep breaths
and on the exhale relaxing the body
softening the belly
on the exhale letting go into the support
your seat your chair has for the weight of your body
relaxing the shoulders
on the exhale softening the face
especially around our eyes
that we often do in fact express our feeling inside
nothing wrong with that but the eyes could use some rest
where they don't have to be looking searching expressing anything
and on the exhale softening relaxing any tension
that's easy to relax in the mind
and now like we did at the beginning how is your body
and now you're able to be with your body more a little bit more calmly
with less agitation maybe more settled
and if you are or if you're not
breathe gently through your body
and as you breathe through the body especially on the exhale
settle yourself into a kind of
quiet stillness
quiet tranquility
where you know what's happening but you're not
entangled with it just knowing
as you breathe especially on the exhale see if you can settle your mind
allowing the mind to become quiet and still
where the mind is more at rest than it is working
the meditation
and as you're aware does awareness itself
have some quality characteristics of equanimity non-reactivity
being balanced without being for against
only the awareness steady stable
there might be other feelings ideas tendencies in the mind
that involve preferences and wants and not wants
but awareness knows them equanimously
just knows them without being involved reactive or judgmental
awareness stays clear
unagitated
let go so that your awareness can be
non-reactive aware but not involved
a medium through which you know what's happening
like a glass window when the curtains are pulled
and the glass is clean we see through it
without the glass being reactive
we see through awareness
with awareness at ease
and in the classic instruction around equanimity
one knows equanimity is present
or if it's not present one knows it's not present
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
one valuable contribution that equanimity gives us
it allows for love to flow freely
without being hijacked by our desires our
attachments our aversions our preferences
a simple love or kindness
generosity of heart in which we can gaze upon others
in loving friendship
and with equanimity helping us to stay
close to this loving friendship friendly love
perhaps with whatever equanimity or stability of attention you have right
now in whatever way makes sense for you
gaze upon the world gaze upon the people of your life
with loving friendship friendliness
allowing the preferences and opinions
desires and aversions hurts and needs
recede to the background enough
that the loving kindness
can join with equanimity for an equanimous love
stable relaxed non-reactive
just kind just kind regard
and may it be that this practice we do allows us to see the world in loving
through loving eyes may we see the love the world
through our kindness and care
may we live for the welfare and happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings
be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and we come to the end of the
five part series on the seven factors of awakening the second to last exercise
in the discourse on the s for establishing awareness
and um and that these seven factors of
awakening are the foundation for
the last exercise which is to have the penetrating insight
to see in a liberating way and awaken in a way that awakens
so that's one of the reasons seven factors of awakening are called factors of awakening
is they set the stage for awakening for freedom
and they also are qualities of that awakening itself so it's a beautiful thing where they
they were growing we're growing in the qualities that will be mature with our awakening
so i
still want to say what i've been saying all week that these factors of awakening are not ordinary
mindfulness investigation effort joy tranquility
concentration equanimity whatever ordinary might mean they are really the product or the
result or the consequence of having really
settled in doing this practice of mindfulness of awareness
where the mindfulness uh has brought us to a place of stability of clear lots of clarity
and uh where in our whole being our body our mind have become somewhat unified and
collected for the purposes of meditating of being here
we're no longer thinking about events of the day yesterday or what's
going to happen we're not caught up in our fantasies or our resentments or
um this you know distracted thought
no it's not easy to come to this point but at some point we come to this point we really feel like oh there's a
vitality in awareness vitality and being present in
the full way and so then these states the same factors
awakening there's no instructions to cause them to arise to make them happen
but one recognizes when they are present and when recognizes when they're not
and and we also recognize when they arise they're appearing
and our role is to maintain them to let them keep develop
and a lot of that has to do at this stage of practice getting out of the way
the um if a ball is rolling down a hill if you stand and stop in front of it and
block it it won't roll but if you get out of the way it continues to roll down the hill
so these seven factors awakening will keep growing and moving if we have learned how to stay out of the way
and a lot of that has to do with not getting involved in thoughts not getting caught up in our thoughts distracted by thoughts
not getting involved in wanting and not wanting not tinkering with our experience making it more refined and
kind of working it but beginning to just let go of the doer let go of the
activity of being the meditator and just getting out of the way and allowing
something else to emerge to unfold these seven factors of awakening
and and for that there has to be some momentum in the practice also so this is why
really having done the practice for a while maybe a long time so that it becomes like second nature to
do it it's like there's a kind of momentum there's a the body knows the
body is connected to this practice sit down to meditate and the body gathers itself together because it it's familiar
with this it knows the it's familiar territory and it's like coming home
so as these develop and uh following somali concentration stability
real stability unified mind the tendency of the mind to get
fragmented again to get caught up in any kind of mental or interstate that's
arising or any external thing um is diminished because the sense of
awareness is feels so strong so precious so rich in that clarity of being
that um uh it's it's it seems like it's much better than any
alternative any alternative of being thoughts and distracted and caught up in things
and um and so we come back to it and stay there and in that mind
there's a wonderful precious sweetness or beauty or
wonderfulness to this clarity of mind which is non-reactive
this clarity of mind that's not working the practice anymore not reacting not
fixing or tinkering where there's no doer operating
where there's just a clarity of being aware so and
and that stability that equanimity is what allows for there to be
deep insight then our seeing we don't see through the filter our projections our agitation
all the concepts and ideas and commentary we have about things but we begin we start seeing or
perceiving feeling what's happening in a much more direct
way and in doing so we start having insights into what's happening
that is freeing and that's for next week
so this remarkable thing that these beautiful qualities of being uh are a byproduct of uh mindfulness
practices and so at some point we want to recognize that these are beginning even the hints
of these are beginning to arise because it's the recognition of their presence
that allows them one of the factors allows them to grow so to recognize it becomes more and more
clarity of awareness that is mindfulness recognizing in that clarity
there is a capacity to choose between what's healthy and not healthy skillful
and not skillful to know how to stay present in a mindful relaxed freeing way
then there's the enthusiasm the energy to do that which allows the practice to grow
and then there's the joy of doing it and then with that joy perhaps a
contentment of satisfaction it lets so many of our anxieties settle and quiet down
and then um and then we have um
concentration a unification of mind and we have equanimity
so the seven factors of awakening mindful of the present mindful of their absence
mindful of when they arise so that we can get out of the way and maintain them and let keep them going
these are the what happens at the mature some of the mature level stages
of mindfulness don't worry about being in these mature space stages
the only thing that's important a moment by moment is this moment
this moment of practice as if you're putting drops
into a bucket each drop is as valuable as any other drop
and so each drop is it's complete in itself and so each drop of mindfulness each
second each moment of mindfulness is complete in itself and don't be so
concerned or caught up with attainments or getting somewhere
but when the seven factors awakening start showing themselves
recognize they're there know their present and maybe even know as they're arising
and then learn the art of maintaining them getting out of their way and letting them grow
so thank you very much
so a few announcements so in a few minutes we'll start with a zoom meeting
for those of you would like and now the zoom link is in a few places it's at the very
top of the chat and it's also on the imc home homepage
website the website on the what's under what's new there's a notice about it also on the cal imc calendar there's
notice it for 8 45. and there's a password you need to use and
the password is the pali word the buddhist word for loving-kindness which is metta
m-e-t-t-a m-e-t-t-a
and um there's a prompt there that tell reminds you it says buddhist word for loving kindness but it's um starts with
m and and it's all lower case so another and a couple of other
announcements that it is earth care day and day of both distress and
celebration and and a few things are related to this at
imc imc is starting an earth care group that will meet monthly to discuss
earth care projects and activities and study and there's information about that under
what's new on the imc website and that first meeting is going to be
next saturday the 30th of april and and i also there's also a notice there
in the homepage under what's new that i teach a buddhist eco-chaplaincy training program
training people to um to be chaplains offer spiritual care and relationship to the environment the
natural world and you can there's a little bit information there and discussion how to get find out
more under what's new at the home page of imc website so seems nice to mention these things
here on earth care earth care day earth day