so um let's begin hi hi formerly hi welcome
hello hello everyone it's good to be with you in uh
[Music] if not space but at least time to see you to feel your presence
so for today's practice what i'd like to invite us to engage with today
is the practice of forgiveness practice of forgiveness i've mentioned
it before here we've practiced with it before but there's a particular type of
forgiveness i'd like to invite us to engage with today practice with
and and um often
the practice of forgiveness is um [Music] there are different aspects dimensions
to it one is forgiving ourselves
the other aspect the other dimension is forgiving others
the third is forget asking forgiveness from others
and the fourth one which is a very interesting and perhaps in a way
symbolic or or maybe i would say it's a wisdom practice it's a wisdom practice
is offering forgiveness to causes and conditions to
circumstances for the way they are for
our not being able to meet the suffering of the world forgiving the world for giving
just the sense of general forgiveness it's it's quite a deep and beautiful
beautiful practice let me um read the the phrase actually we're going
to focus on this one and this actually this way of putting it is due to larry yang to give him credit
so the phrase is in any way that i have been unable to be with
and respond skillfully to the pain and suffering of our world
my own pain and that of others may i come to accept suffering confusion
pain ignorance to be part of the journey my own journey and the journey of others
i offer forgiveness for the way that things are and have been
as much as possible in this moment it's quite
a radical way to do forgiveness practice it's not
it's you know it's beautiful of course to to ask for forgiveness say in any way
that i've harmed you knowingly unknowingly by thought actions words i
ask for your forgiveness this is a phrase when we ask for forgiveness or offering forgiveness to ourselves or
offering it to others but this fourth way which is such a
radical way of offering forgiveness to the causes and conditions
in the world that this is the way things are
giving rise to my pain my suffering and the pain and suffering and of others to
offer forgiveness acceptance release
judgment for the cause and conditions as they are
especially as these days there is
global turmoil and there is global pain so many of our
siblings in this world are living now in a war zone um of course
there are many wars at any time going on and people
living under oppression especially now especially now [Music]
in the world stage so can we can we bring can we relate
practice of compassion is one way to relate to what is happening and we've done that the past
few days past few times and happier and this
radical radical practice of forgiveness is another way it's radical forgiveness
might be completely new to you you might have practiced in this way all good
let's explore together let's see what arises again forgiving the cause and conditions
responsible that have come to co-create the conditions of the world
for our own suffering our inability to engage and other people's suffering so it's a
radical practice of of forgiveness
there is both the wisdom practice coming together with compassion practice
the marriage of both so so without further ado i'd like to
invite us to engage with this practice together as always we start
ah we start by landing by arriving
in our bodies this moment in time
to let go of the words and just to arrive
here here
connecting with the breath connecting with the body
releasing preoccupations entanglements
just taking refuge [Applause] with the breath
the body inviting the mind the heart to settle
do
letting go letting go of thoughts
of plans past future present
relaxing releasing into the body
arriving arriving more fully
releasing releasing
ah thoughts plans preoccupations
not with a push but offering up offering up relinquishing
relinquishing with heart with love with dedication
to this moment of cultivation
thank you dear thoughts i'll come back to you later please come visit another time
right now give you up for the benefit
of this cultivation
returning returning spaciously kindly relaxatively
to the breath the body
feeling feeling the heart center
connected connecting
this can this moment
of solitude of silence be nourishing [Music]
to this heart this mind this body
to resource oneself this being who is me
and as we rest as we rest with the breath
and the body opening up can we open up our hearts
sphere of awareness with kindness
as if aware with compassionate awareness
this wide wide field field of experience
awareness that can hold our own challenge our own
suffering and those of the world
not full on not directed but diffused just diffused
awareness diffused with kindness with compassion
as if our awareness is water
and there is a dropper dropper few drops of compassion diluted
in this awareness ah holding
everything molding everything
holding our bodies thoughts
internally externally whatever is arising
this
moistening moistening the heart moistening the heart with compassion
and now if you wish dropping in
not forcing but dropping in this
phrase of radical forgiveness
i'll read it and first let it wash over you
see what resonates in any way that i have been unable
to be with and to respond skillfully
to the pain and suffering of our world
my own pain and that of others
may i come to accept suffering confusion ignorance
to be part of the journey to be part of the journey
my own journey and the journey of others
i offer forgiveness for the way that things are
and have been as much as is possible in this moment
offering as much as is possible not forcing
me
in any way that i've been unable to be with and respond skillfully
to the pain and suffering of our world my own pain and that of others
may i come to accept it to be part of the journey my own
journey and the journey of others i offer forgiveness for the way that
things are and have been as much as is possible in this moment
offering forgiveness to the causes and conditions
for the way that things aren't have been
not within my control not me and mine
as much as i would like control
or have the illusion of it
sometimes offering forgiveness
everything that has led to this
as much as possible
and know that it takes courage and strength to forgive
it's not out of weakness that we forgive we engage with forgiveness
it's from a place of strength courage letting go
wisdom and compassion that we engage with forgiveness
and if there are challenging states in the mind right now
in the body pain boredom distraction can you offer
forgiveness to the causes and conditions for that
and if there are an army of self-judgment such men says self-judgmental thoughts
arising can you offer forgiveness to that
even though i may wish for things to be different this is how they are
right now i offer forgiveness
to how things are as much as possible in this moment
notice if there's a sense of release freedom letting go
not hanging on that feels lighter
more ease arises
this
do
as we bring this practice period
to a close notice notice if there has been any moment of
release of letting go of holding on resentment
or a sense of strength wisdom
feeling empowered ah
in letting go
and offering together we offer all these moments of release goodness
personal entrance and transcendent freedom
collectively for the benefit of all beings everywhere including ourselves
may all beings be free
may all beings including ourselves be free
thank you for your practice friends
so so much can come up in this practice it's a bit
of a perhaps complicated practice i see richard's hand shut up what's up
richard how you doing
um i don't see how you can blame nature and since you can't blame nature
i don't seems irrational to forgive nature
yeah yeah it's it's not so much
nature in this way it's yeah this feels like a paradoxical
practice in a way it's let me put it this way many times
when we are in a state of ignorance we're angry at the causes and conditions
in the world like we take them personally right we take causes and conditions
personally so it's not nature i would shift your that word with causes and
conditions we take it personally and we're angry
and this way of relating to this practice opens up the possibility of wisdom actually
seeing the codependent arising of the causes and conditions and not take it
personally it's really a way to enter into that practice through
the forgiveness practice there's so many ways to practice for to enter into this
wisdom of seeing causes and conditions as impersonal they just are
and this is one way it might work for you it may not work for you but it's a way to enter into this practice in this
way thanks richard
and let's see a request to paste larry's phrase in the chat
let's see sometimes chat has a limited size i'm gonna try that and if it
doesn't come through here we go let's try uh
i think it all came through look at that and then uh bill says i'm aware that
resentment is unhealthy but part of me still wants to cling to it to not
forgive it's difficult to let go yeah yes i so appreciate
bill you sharing that and the authenticity and vulnerability and
saying that because that is part of the process of letting go it's part of
the process of forgiveness it doesn't happen overnight often first we realize like okay i'm not
ready to let go i want to hang on to this even though i know it hurts me i don't i'm not quite
ready it's okay the fact that you're observing and realizing that
see it clearly have kindness towards yourself that part of you that is very
hurt or upset and can you have kind can you have
kindness can you have kindness towards that part that is health that is
hurting it's like you're um [Music] it's it's likened
um to um the story of in asia
in order to catch a monkey it is said that that a catcher's poachers take an empty
coconut they put a hole in it and they put something yummy inside
and as the the poor animal reaches inside and grabs something yummy
the fist you know can't set itself free anymore that's that's the trap
if if the animal lets go opens its hand then it can open the hand and be set
free but the fist the fist so get to see get to see that the fist is keeping you
trapped and just have kindness have kindness towards not being able to let go
slowly slowly slowly
let's see hilda says i noticed that when i focused on forgiving gratitude followed soon
after gratitude for the learning opportunity through difficulty oh beautiful thank
you for sharing that hilda so connected yeah these these practices so connected
uh private question [Music] thank you can you point to more
teachings about how not to take things personally oh
that is a bigger container that's basically pointing to the
teachings so many teachings but but that's really um
the teachings on impersonality or not self or anata it's
impersonal things are so impersonal and the way to see
impersonality there's so many different ways but one way as i was talking about it this morning
at 7 00 am subbing for gail this week is through the practice of seeing impermanence
through saying arising and passing away all things are impermanent internally
externally and that's one way through seeing uh impersonality and not taking things
personally and there are many many other teachings so that's what i point you to it's it's
uh it's a whole canon of teachings on that but that's a little pointer here
yeah and uh one more reflection i share before we turn
richard on youtube says thank you for sharing the light of this practice it was very
healing to me as i sat in the space and stillness at the end of the day i
found i had been avoiding pain both my own my own and
and of the world and yet in this forgiveness able to hold it hold in
kindness all of it the fullness of being beautiful thank you for that
reflection beautiful at the end of the day sitting in the stillness turning towards the pain and seeing that
it's possible to hold it in the fullness of being and kindness
beautiful so
so holding it all with kindness
holding our pain those of others and um
and before we turn to small groups uh kristin messaged me personally that
her grandma secret uh passed away last weekend so
so holding holding with meta and compassion all beings
ourselves and others are suffering they're suffering
people who are near dear to us people who we don't know in war zones and sending compassion and meta to all
beings and their suffering including
kristen her family and her grandma who's passed away so
so with that let us turn to each other to small
groups a small sangha to hold each other with with care with compassion
and i'd like to um invite us today to start with 15 seconds
of silent uh silent compassion for ourselves for each other
and then you can share as much as you wish as little as you wish maybe holding
witness is what's appropriate for you and please take care
of yourself take care of others in the small groups it's a very tender space
what is shared is always private is always confidential
it's actually double confidentiality not only do you not speak out or blurt out
what someone has shared even speaking back in the group saying oh you
said blah blah blah like no no no no just be with your own experience speak from your own experience please
not about other people's experience and if if you notice if there's any
feeling of lack of safety and that's happening please kindly remind each other that yeah just please stay with
let's let's stay with our own experience take care of yourself take care of each other stay with your
own experience confidentiality is important in fact double confidentiality
not only do not say it to even to them in the group but of course outside you
never speak share anything that you spoke with you know things that people spoke to you and you
don't even bring it out outside with them oh you said that thing that day no it's just speak from your own experience
i feel the need to remind all of our us of these ways of taking care of
ourselves each other as community agreements as we enter the tender space
of the small groups okay so please take care of yourselves
take care of each other and enjoy
okay everybody's back welcome back everyone and we have a couple minutes for any
reflections like to share what came up in the groups any insights that came up
um yeah you can raise your hand please and i would love to hear from you
especially if you haven't shared in a while would love to hear from you or if
you know you can also type in chat of course as always either privately or to everyone what came up what did you
notice for the benefit of yourself and others any insights ah moments
melissa [Music] hello thank you to the sangha and to you
nikki for tonight i just wanted to share that in my experience of
forgiving the causes and conditions i felt that perhaps i'm worthy of forgiveness too
and the sort of universal nature of that
forgiveness and compassion uh kind of let me in the gate
so thank you very much thank you so much for sharing your
beautiful insight melissa thank you so
happy and honored that this practice opened up something for you and that you also
offered your insight for the benefit of others oh may it be made support them thank you
it's so beautiful thank you melissa sheila please
good evening as i shared with um in my group i
took the eight precepts today as i usually do on the
new moon and [Music] i was wound up killing a gnat
and it really kind of bothered me and has bothered me all day long
and um i think
this particular meditation really help settle me down
about that experience um so thank you
thank you sheila i am so touched i am moved the just the tender the tender beauty
and sensitivity of your sila of your ethics of taking the eight precepts of vow today on the
new moon and just it's it's beautiful to be
to be bothered right there's a beauty to that and as as of course there is
there is the what's called hirian or tapa there's this beauty of oh gosh i don't want to harm i don't want to harm
and yet it can go too far to become self-harm and that's what i'm hearing you so i both honor the beauty of that
intention and i also see and appreciate you naming oh yeah well actually it was
a little self-painful and ah it's it's wonderful to afford forgiveness to myself too as well
as all beings and the cause and conditions to that led to this accidental
harm so thank you that was so beautiful thank you and last word we gave to catherine i
realized i actually don't fully know how forgiveness feels or function
functions in me so grateful to have that shown to me i feel there will be healing in that exploration oh that is beautiful
thank you catherine such a beautiful insight and and and
way forward onward leading all our practices as we support each other is
onward leading so thank you all thank you so much for your practice showing up
supporting yourself each other all beings may all beings be well may all
beings be free including ourselves
thank you