so welcome welcome all nice to uh
got the the chats streaming on the side nice to see your names welcome thanks
for the uh warm greetings to the substitute teacher
um yeah happy happy to be here this week and um look forward to
exploring together so um [Music]
yeah we'll have the same same format as gil usually uh practices and um
a kind of lightly guided sit for a half hour and then some some reflections until uh a quarter two
so um yeah
just uh settling into a posture
and sometimes when we're queued to begin paying attention
it's almost like we imagine the spotlight of attention being shown
from the direction of our own head from our eyes
the perspective of looking down into our body
but that's just another thought actually
so maybe we begin with the image
of your body pervaded
by awareness porous to awareness
sometimes it's supportive to feel our bodies the kind of earth
element of our body the groundedness the weightiness the force
of gravity the downward pull of the earth
sometimes it's supportive to know our body
as vibrating space
to be present is to be unintimidated
by the flow of pleasant and unpleasant
to relinquish our preoccupation with control
molding ourselves molding the moment
every phenomenon kind of invitation
more deeply into the present
whatever narratives accumulated about this sit
how it's going how you're doing
just put it down
make yourself radically available
to this moment
there's a palpable sense that moment by moment
life is softening rather than hardening our hearts
we actually leverage the imperfection of the moment
for our freedom
and so rather than trying to extract something from the
moment from our practice
we let ourselves be softened by it
letting go is not a job we reluctantly perform
but uh an utter delight
and joy
and so we develop a kind of confidence
of faith in letting go
and it doesn't solve the complexities of being human demands on any life
but it does resolve suffering of this moment
and that's something
do [Music]
so uh yeah
it's good too good to practice with you
so william james said nothing includes everything or dominates
over everything the word and
trails along after every sentence
the word and trails along after every sentence
sometimes when when gail and i have taught a a retreat
we've we've done the three characteristics
and they're supporting opposite or apparent opposite
so we open to suffering but that is paired
with a consolidation of well-being we open to a nietzsche to impermanence
uncertainty but that's paired with a teaching on stability
we open to the teachings on selflessness
and that's paired with self-confidence
and there's a certain kind of importance in impairing pairing teachings
and so this week likewise some pairs that seem important to me
that seem maybe in conflict uh
with each other but actually support each other
so today the pair helplessness
and power so helplessness is a kind of uh defining
characteristic of any animal's life and
among the most harrowing experiences a human can have
and sometimes i feel like maybe maybe duke suffering and helplessness
are synonyms
we are in the end small small creatures amidst unimaginably vast
forces and humans we need a very very specific
environment of temperature and pressure mixture of gases
and just a kind of staggering number of things need to go
right in our body just to be alive
and so just to have this breath is um
is donna yeah is um is a kind of generosity
and helplessness the experience a moment of helplessness is it's very
frightening it's the kind of most extreme form of vulnerability
and we scramble to exert our power to keep
control to exercise will
and helplessness will take almost anything
over a moment of helplessness
people cry you know for many reasons but one of the main
reasons i've learned that people cry is a sense of
helplessness
and perhaps our our tears are a kind of plea
i need you i need you
and the movements of our mind um are so much of our cognitive and emotional
life is really organized against helplessness
organized around the sense that we can always do something it feels like we can
always do something it feels like something might always be
fixed you know like that is the essence of samsara
this realm like like that something might be fixed something else might be
governed some facet of our experience of our life might be governed
and that sense of what could be what might have been what will be
all those possibilities uh
are so deeply compelling to us and so we can tinker tinker with the moment from
cradle to grave and sometimes
in order to soften the blow of a nietzsche of
uncertainty and reliability we blame ourselves
yeah because blaming ourselves creates the illusion of controllability
well if i just didn't mess up yeah and in fact i think a lot of
self-hatred is really our attempt to conceal the truth
of uncontrollability from ourselves
we're helpless in moments to silence our minds to
protect ourselves from pain
to back our ways out of some karmic corners
like we get backed into a kind of karmic corner and our bed is made we're gonna suffer
we're helpless or nearly helpless in the face of so much
greed hatred delusion that seems to animate the world
our species there's a measure of helplessness in this and so
it is actually strange alien to hear the dharma teacher
say surrender that this is a path of letting go
actually open to the moment we we can kind of feel like we're doing it but we're
subtly trying to master the human condition
to really open not to try to master the moment not to try to get the upper hand on
helplessness that is profound
so we open we open to helplessness we let it soften
our heart we let it teach us everything is teaching us
as is said and our life
our families our world all of that becomes so poignant in light of helplessness
and when change comes were a little bit less
startled when death comes we're a little bit less startled
before we've come to appreciate helplessness we kind of try
to exert our power over all things over ourselves over others
but as we open to helplessness we stop fighting the first noble truth
and then we pick our fights wisely
we pick our fights wisely there from this understanding
we find our power
studying helplessness illuminates our power
we're no longer trying to govern all of this realm
yeah studying helplessness illuminates our power we actually know
what we want what we actually want
we're not so lost in the kind of fever dream
of egoic clinging craving
we know what we want and we're empowered
we're empowered because through our encounter with the human
condition through our encounter with helplessness we actually understand more
deeply how things work and that allows us to
exert our force wisely efficiently
this is kitty sorrow as our practice of the path deepens we
will naturally grow in personal power
cultivating silas ahmadi panya plugging into the measureless merit
of the triple gem we potentize our actions for good or for ill
it's vital to be interested and sensitive to our impact on the world and those around us
being a teacher or a dedicated buddhist practitioner we are waving the banner of the awakened
one representing that extraordinary heritage
partaking of that trustworthy power and prestige
when one has power once wholesome actions are amplified but so are the unwholesome ones
everything we do has more impact
we open to helplessness we open yeah
be open to it and through this we find
the places where we can exert power
we come to understand the human condition more deeply we come to understand others more deeply we come to
understand what we want more deeply and this is empowering
this is empowering we exert our power
in awesome ways exercise influence in ways
that matter and it comes
out of this willingness to befriend this most
radical of experiences helplessness
so i offer this for your consideration and
as always please um please pick up what is useful and uh
leave behind everything else
so thank you for for being here uh i'm glad we
settled into this first day i'll check the chat over there and uh
we'll keep going uh tomorrow so i wish you uh wish you all a good day thank you
phil for being a djing in the background to be continued