okay hello and welcome everyone
lovely to see you see your faces on zoom feel your
presence on youtube wherever you're joining from the world
lovely to be with you so so for the practice for today um
ah so many beautiful practices to choose from and many of you um
know that diana and i were teaching a meta retreat last week online in fact
some of you were on the retreat oh my see you here hi
good to see you good to practice with you so so having sat really having been in a
[Music] container of meta for one week how nourishing it is and also meta can shape
shift into the other practices of of compassion into
a vicarious joy gratitude equanimity etc etc
and having led many different practices this past
week and and sat in them myself what feels really resonant is
the last practice that i invited folks to explore on the retreat which is
um radiating radiating meta over in the entire world can be such a
joyous practice they can be likened to us feeling like santa claus just giving
gifts of kindness gifts of kindness and if you think of if you remember a
time that you have given gifts just generously given gifts
of kindness how how uplifting how supportive for you that has felt
to be giving gifts to just share your generosity here here i am here is this
being who is me just sharing your generosity without any expectation for
for return for reciprocity just sharing sharing
your generosity your kindness your gifts can be very um
joyful just it can fill our hearts with gladness and happiness
and and to say sometimes
when people are do this practice of meta loving kindness for all beings
um [Music] actually let me just say one more word so so
as you might recall we practice the instructions um for meta loving kindness practice are
gradual it's a gradual cultivation the concentric circle starting from where
it's easy moving out moving out including more and more expanding more and more and more
and then the final category of all beings just includes everything and everyone
this idea of radiating radiating for everything everyone and everything and sometimes when people do
this practice they tune into and this can happen not
just with meta for all beings but even meta for say dear person or even for ourselves
when we're sharing loving kindness and then our mind tunes into challenges into
difficulty say if we're doing it for ourselves we get this sense of oh but i'm having such a hard time
oh and then the practice of metta becomes a practice of compassion because it's
meeting challenges similarly this practice if we do it for
someone who's near and dear to us a benefactor or dear friend when meta loving-kindness meets
challenge we feel oh they're going through a hard time first we're just practicing meta simply may you be safe
may you be happy no no may you be free from suffering oh when kindness meets
compassion when kindness meets suffering it becomes compassion similarly
some people sometimes tune into when they're trying to generate you know share their
goodness with all beings everywhere um
then suffering in the world comes up for them they tune into the suffering like
oh but so many people in the world are suffering so many animals oh
then at that point the practice becomes a practice of compassion it's not
pure meta anymore because metta is when we're wishing loving-kindness for
neutral beings so at that point mitta has shape-shifted to compassion not to
say it's a problem or it's wrong not a problem but just to recognize at that
point oh your mind is tuning into the suffering so the practice has become compassion
which is okay and if you want to keep the practice as a
meta practice for aldi just wishing well then tuning into just the gift the gift
of generosity of the meta and imagining beings who are new in a neutral
situation they're not suffering neither are they really happy or nor
unhappy so that's the trick here to keep this practice in the channel
of meta let's say advanced pointer just does that make
sense give me a nod or thumbs up you're with me yeah great
so without further ado let's practice let's let's give our hearts to this practice
so so [Music] arriving in our bodies always starting
with the body
starting ah landing in the body here
here
connecting with the breath connecting
this breathing
sitting body turning our gaze inward
the gift of this moment the gift of this breath
my thoughts arise not that there is anything wrong with thinking per se but
in this moment we turn our hearts
we turn our hearts turn our attention
away from thinking thank you not now please come back later thoughts
turning away letting go [Music] gently smiling me
ah and turning towards turning towards
this breath sensations of the body in this moment
soothing healing nurturing like a lullaby
in-breath out breath
can we be nourished
can we feel nourished
receiving the breath just the simplicity
of sitting and being breathed
just this breath just this moment
imagining as if the breath
is entering and exiting through the middle of your chest
through the proverbial heart center with each breath
sense of kindness
friendliness is awakened on its own
as if there's a fire a holy fire in the middle of your chest and the breath is bellowing
billowing on the embers ah
feeling the warmth
maybe the image of a golden light works better for you if
not fire it's okay whatever works
page breath this light this golden light golden orb
of goodwill becomes brighter and brighter shining [Music]
radiantly with warmth
with care just appreciate
appreciating your inner goodness trusting in your inner goodness
your power to care
to be friendly and kind
just witnessing with each breath
letting this light this warmth
this fire to be nourishing to you first heating you up radiating through your
body
and let yourself feel nourished relaxing resting
warmed warmed by this glow [Music]
which is both yours and not yours
you're acknowledging it as yours perhaps and yet
it is it is part of your buddha nature
this goodness this capacity is here
you're just acknowledging it helping it
glow more brightly
let this practice be easeful not effortful you're not pushing it out
just acknowledging observing
the glow the warmth the care that's shining out radiating up
and first it touches you
now letting it acknowledging it radiating radiating outward
your whole body radiant your whole body
as a vessel of kindness just because you exist in this world
just because you breathe kindness good will can radiate out
from your thoughts your words
your actions in the world just as you're sitting from your
thoughts of loving kindness from turning your mind your heart
towards kindness goodness can radiate out
in ways you can't imagine let it flow
radiating outward in all directions
the front radiating from your chest forward your
body forward wow amazing
you're right
all beings who come in contact with this radiating meta
feel gladness feel your good will feel your care
may you be well dear being
your human four-legged animal flying
beings swimming beings
slithering hopping all beings to my friend to my right side
may you be well
let it be easeful just resting in the sense of ease contentment
let it radiate out not pushing
it radiates on its own you just hold witness
extending all the beings behind you ah in that
direction ah radiating
being radiated kindness backwards
to your left draped in light
all around you shining out
kindness may you be well maybe simply using may you be well
what are the four phrases if you wish may you be safe
happy healthy heavies
and upwards upwards
all the beings above you
flying orbiting
and all the beings below you
insects beings on the other side of the earth
all around you
as if there are tiny santa clauses dispatched all around the globe
hello we're little tinker bells of light
blessing sharing your kindness all beings may you be well
may be well sharing gifts of kindness
if it helps it can bring some classes of beings to mind
without it becoming too busy maybe all babies
or human babies
all over the globe whatever color nationality race conditions there
may you be well may you
be happy all animal babies
all the kittens
all calves all baby birds
all young fish
all baby spiders you can have fun with this practice
cultivating cultivating
and this radiating of meta remember you are included
you are part of all beings and so [Music] are your dear beings your friends
your benefactors family people who are easy loved ones
all the people who are neutral in the world you don't know them
i also let the beings you have challenges with
to be included if it doesn't make the practice too challenging
all beings everywhere let it be joyous practice of generosity
with each breath may all beings be well
may all beings be happy
also if mind states difficult mind states arise boredom
irritability irritation let that be held with kindness
meeting all experience too with kindness
with a smile
expansiveness of the heart may all beings wait be well may all beings be happy
expansive unbounded exultant
expansive expansive
imagining perhaps all the beings around the world all the two-legged beings may all be
well all humans
on so many different continents
all the creatures of the sea
may you be well may all the creatures of disguise
all the animals of the land
whatever the size might
be short medium or tall
and now i've been checking in to see what it feels like to be
radiating wishing well for all beings
excluding none whether there is a sense of more ease contentment
just suddenly maybe
after the last moments of this practice period
acknowledging this radiance of meta
is our true nature we're not creating it
fabricating it's already here we just acknowledge
and by acknowledging we cultivate it to be more readily available
and letting letting this goodness nourish us
pause as if we're sitting in it
this light this warmth as if it's a big warm hug
may i be well may i be safe
happy healthy
may i have ease and may all of this goodness
flow through me flow
to others beyond me through this vessel that is me
may all beings be well may all things be happy
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone dear sangha
those on zoom those on youtube joining us
so this can be a joyful practice
just giving gifts letting it flow let it shine let it shine let your light
shine we have some time for any reflections
what you might have observed and for the benefit of others for the
benefit of sangha we we share our reflections we offer it may be of
support this is what i discovered this is what opened up for me or this is what i'm confused by this is what didn't work
both for your benefit and benefit of others and you're invited to raise your zoom hand
if you like to share you can also type in chat if typed to me
alone i won't read your name you'll be private reflection if
typed to everyone then it will be a public reflection and i will read your name so any
reflections what did you discover
okay this says big thanks on youtube you are welcome thank you for joining and
practicing please
hi i just wanna thank you for a lovely practice again
it was just lovely to see you today i've been missing you both like for about a
week i guess okay so i was so distracted
by someone is cleaning my place right now so go back and forth wearing the mask and back and forth
um i really try hard to be this present
but then i was not able to i have to confess that um
so at the same time and um i'm trying to just let go of controlling part again
like oh you know what did she clean this part did she did what i said
so i was just sitting here i'm like okay let it be for 30 minutes
and whatever it happens just let it unfold it let it just let go of
it but i'm actually inside of the room small little room
and i'm thinking you know what i'll just let go of it whatever
yeah great thanks for sharing that sujang it's it's
lovely to be back to see you and everyone the sangha i've missed you guys
as well and what you're talking about two reflections one is regarding this
letting go the letting go like letting go of control letting go is also related to meta
related to meta because when we let go of control there's a sense of offering
generosity offering gift girlfriend like it's okay we're offering this gift of
meta to ourselves when we're not like you know holding tight just letting go
letting go so that's one reflection that comes out which i appreciate you're playing with this letting go another one
is when when with this other person rather doing what
i asked them to do etcetera etcetera you can include them in the meta you can
include yourself in the meta in this practice right because it's all beings and the person who's cleaning who's
offering their service their time can be very well included in that may you be well may you be safe
my thoughts of control oh just offering yourself kindness so expanding really directing
this meta to whatever is arising in the space of awareness does that make
sense what i'm inviting you to play with yeah next time you can try try that
of course letting go is lovely and yeah it's beautiful okay so let her do whatever she has to
do i think that that's also like a practice right yeah because that's what you're essentially doing anyway you're not
getting up to go interrupt so you might as well offer her gift of meta in your heart
because you're actually doing it but there's kind of a her you know holding back a little bit
right holding back memento with doubt is she doing the right thing oh may she be while she's doing her best
because you're not getting up to go interrupt anyway might as well you're ah in this way you're offering your own
mind piece that's what i'm pointing out by giving her meta you're offering your own mind and heart peace that's what's
beautiful about this practice we think we're doing a favor to the other person because actually we're doing ourselves a favor that's what i'm pointing at
freeing your own heart up from like oh what's happening
that makes sense thank you thank you
yeah and some reflections here lovely meditation thanks you're welcome
i loved generating the feelings of radiating love first before starting the words ah lovely
yeah do you have any suggestions for if i find it really hard for me sometimes to
believe that i have put a nature in me like i feel like i've forgotten how to have a kind attitude
i know i have it other times but today it feels so distant yeah i appreciate
the question um it's i think the last part that you say
i know i have it other times that that is the the stepping stone but you know you have
it some other times today it feels distant so you trust that you have it you you land in that trust that it's
available other times and that's enough just sitting with that it will trust me if
just sitting with that yeah i trust that it's available to me other times and then maybe even bringing to mind memory
of times you have been kind say to a friend or a child like oh yeah
it's not so distant so bring the memory in and that that helps rekindle
yeah yeah and reflection from someone who is on the
retreat so glad for this beautiful continuity it's really helping with the challenges
of integration and missing being steeped in the three jewels ah that's very sweet
so so glad kathryn that you can join papiar on
youtube and support the continuity and you can next time you can join on
zoom because now we're going to be enjoying the third jewel of sangha by
speaking with each other in small communities and just spreading spreading each other's
kindness receiving kindness and spreading kindness which is very simple it's not
big it's just we all have it we're all these candles
or light orbs or shining bright suns you know whatever metaphor works for you
tonight so with that i would like to invite us
as we get into the breakout rooms to start with um
15 seconds of silent meta for each other just silently holding each other with
kindness and then um then
um you can share as much or as little as you like about your practice
few words or just holding witness
listening to each other so uh with that i am going to
open the rooms and here we go i know we can have a little longer maybe we'll
have like eight minutes seven minutes tonight here we go enjoy
okay the rooms are all closed welcome back everyone welcome back
we have a couple of minutes for any reflections what might have come up during the
either the practice silently or in the group so
if you haven't shared you're welcome to raise your hand or type in chat what's up what's up
for the benefit of all beings
i see a lot of smiles ariana please
well i'll just um at least one other person in the meeting we referred to that around the breakout
group referred to this time as our reward at the end of a difficult day so i wanted to thank you for that it was
it's always a reward thank you oh oh thank you so much for sharing that
that oh that is such a gift to hear ariana thank you thanks so much for sharing
that fred i see your hand it's got to be quick
sorry yeah i was realizing during the meditation that um
earlier today a friend had asked me to help him on a project which i which i
i'm skeptical that i can be very effective in healthy and but i i could feel
uh some of the the muscles develop from this regular
practice that allowed me to say uh yeah what the hell let's give it a try
um and uh and i i think that was i think that's the source so who knows it'll work out but
it's you know better to try them tonight oh that's sweet thanks for sharing that
fred it's the the um the workings of this practice how it manifests in the world right in the
way of yeah why not i'm gonna give i'm gonna try to help you may not work out but i'm gonna try to
help you how beautiful is that that muscle thanks so much for sharing that
and allowing us me to hold witness in this beauty of this
this yeah manifestation in the world the way it's showing up this practice your
practice yay we all celebrate together our practice and the seeds the seeds
that we plant and the way they they uh show up and delighted that this is a
reward because it's so sweet it's so sweet to come together and practice a a gift really a gift at the end of a
long perhaps hard day yeah so with all that thank you for your practice dear ones
may you be well may you be free may you be happy and all
beings everywhere [Music]
thank you