so i'm a little bit touched or to find a wonderful
resonance that last sunday i gave a talk about
martin luther king jr and this day i'll talk about
tiknot han and they knew each other and they influenced each other
martin luther king was influenced by tiknot han to be opposed to the vietnam war
a monumental change in the direction of his work that he did one that was controversial and
in retrospect was probably a wonderful and important change
and in return partly martin luther king but the whole
civil rights movement united states had a big impact on han and
he learned about it while he was staying here in this country in the early very early 1960s
and when he went back to vietnam it's inspired him to do those
the kind of service work and anti-war work and that
that he dedicated himself to until he
was exiled by the government so um
tikhnathan was a one of the great teachers of the 20th century
and had a huge influence on western buddhism as i said he was exiled i think around
1964 so from vietnam and then he settled in france
and and from there started slowly beginning to teach more and more
and i became aware of him in the early 1980s and he was
i was living at the san francisco zen center and um and he uh
he was contacted to support uh when the zen center went through tremendous turmoil around
the ethical challenges of its abbott at the time and he tried he was a consultant for
both the abbett and for the zen center as a whole and and then he came to zen center
and he had a big impact on the students at zen center and for a
variety of reasons one was that he included children
and he would give a dharma talk and he'd have the children come and sit up front and he would talk to them and then they
would leave and he'd give a talk for the adults and while this seems like a small thing
in the kind of a little bit more austere or strict model of japanese end that
samsung center inherited it that was not done that kind of
blending and so it kind of broke the mold and opened up to a whole different kind of
softness and and kindness he also gave a lot of emphasis on
lay practitioners and of course the samsung zen center had a lot of late practitioners but sikna
han kind of elevated the importance of lay practice and also elevated the importance of lay teachers
i don't think san francisco's end center had really any recognition of lay teachers at that time
and a number of the senior lay practitioners started uh spending time with technohan some going to france to
be with him and then became we're transmitted we're authorized to be
teachers in tiknon han's lineage and this idea that a lay person could be
become a buddhist teacher it was also kind of novel and kind of opened up the field
and appreciation for lay people in the in the scene
he also had a gentleness and a dedication to non-violence and kindness
and softness and to joy and happiness that also was
not quite the ethos of cybersex center he came and gave us meditation
instructions that included using phrases which was very different from the more silent just sitting practice that we did
and some of the phrases were things like breathing in i calm my body
breathing out i smile stepping i experience joy
stepping i feel home and so he had all these kind of phrases
that would incorporate into the meditation practice and i remember using them
back then and feeling all this joy and delight that that was and to feel that this was
permitted and part of the practice was somewhat novel in the mid-1980s for me and for some of the
other zen students at the time so he had a big influence on the local
buddhist communities that i was part of but he did that for much of the world and he traveled around the world and
taught all over and um the after meeting at iknothan at the san
francisco zen center the next time i met met him was
coincidentally i flew into i went back to norway to visit my relatives
and when i arrived at the airport there are all these people clearly buddhists waiting for something
special to happen and my relatives who were waiting for me were i was a zen priest by then was a
little bit what's going on here are they waiting for gil but when i came out of the into the arrival section i i had no importance
with people who are waiting uh tiknot han was flying flew in on the very next plane so they were there
waiting for him so knowing that tiknot han was going to be there i spent the weekend with him
in a in a school classroom where he was teaching a relatively small group of people and that was really special to
spend this time with him the um
han uh was a man of i think tremendous emotional depth emotional capacity
he suffered a lot and uh and he openly talked about it to
suffering and he wrote poems about it he was very creative he was a poet he was a storyteller
he was he had a rich imagination a rich use of language very evocative
he was innovative uh he was probably one of the more animated teachers especially monastic teachers of
the 20th century pushing the edge and changing things and doing innovative things with buddhism
itself it's a famous idea of him is that he was one of the first buddhist monks to ride
a bicycle and maybe it seems like a small thing but this was kind of really pushing the
boundaries into the modern world he started his own monastic order that
the order of inter-being in vietnam in the 1960s because he saw a need to kind of
emphasize a whole different ethos the old different approach to buddhism
he coined important terms he called the term engaged buddhism
which uh involved buddhism that was actively engaged in the social welfare of the world and
and uh which he was to the degree to to endanger to at the
risk of his own life in fact some of his of colleagues had worked with him
lost their lives during the vietnam war in their non-violent work and
that was misunderstood by both sides of the vietnam war because he wasn't supporting one side against the other he
was seen as belonging to the other and so both sides saw him that way so he was kind of in a risky middle
but he was dedicated to not having enemies to working for non-violence working for ending the war
they made him unpopular so eventually he became uh you know exiled
but uh you know this was part of parcel of his engaged buddhism this you act you work in the world
and maybe it's not a coincidence that is his name
tiknot han the tick part means that uh he's a
kind of means he's he's a child of the buddha he's in the clan of the buddha and the family in the buddha family
and many monks in thailand are called tik because of that once you ordain you join
your child of the buddha kind of
not means one and han means action so
he was a man of action to engage buddhism tremendous action and what the one refers to i don't know
it's a lot of symbolic value what one isn't but one thing it meant was that when i
knew him and i think other people the tremendous presence he had to just
do the thing he was doing whatever action he was doing that's what he did if he was drinking tea it was just
drinking tea if he was walking just walking and to be in his presence was to kind of
slow down and um and he kind of like brought you into the
present because he was so present and there was a kind of commanding his gentleness and his softness and his
slowness was kind of commanding to everyone slow down and
and and so you know it wasn't like fast action wasn't like he was in a hurry for
anything no hurry whatsoever one action you just do one thing at a
time but in that one thing at a time slowly calmly
he was able to do a phenomenal amount of things phenomenal teaching
action support innovation started monasteries or certainly he got
lots of help at some point but in the beginning you know him and his colleagues were able to really
foster a phenomenal movement of buddhist movement one of the great
movements of the modern world and
and he had a tremendous amount of wonderful teachings that he offered him we get a sense of his emotional depth
and the degree to which he suffered especially during the time of the vietnam war from some of the poetry he
wrote at that time and so i would like to read some of that
and this poem is titled for warmth
i hold my face in my two hands
no i am not crying i hold my face in my two hands
to keep the loneliness warm two hands protecting
two hands nourishing two hands preventing my soul
from leaving me in anger
and he talks about you know much of what he had to deal with and work with in during the vietnam war and
later the things that people did to each other left him angry
and [Music] but he he practiced with it and here's an example of how he practiced with it
and uh this idea of holding his face with his two hands the cupped hands over the face holding
his loneliness holding his anger i think it's a very tender and way of being mindful and present
um some of his uh uh fellow monks some of them some of
them he knew i don't know if he knew all of them but um
uh where the ones who uh uh uh burnt themselves in protest to the
war they sat in the streets and poured gasoline over themselves and there's photographs probably most of you have seen them of these monks sitting there
in meditation posture calmly sitting and meditating with the
engulfed in fire as they're burning until they died
and so here's one poem
the fire that burns in you burns my flesh
with such pain that all my tears are not enough to cool your sacred soul
deeply wounded i remain here keeping your hopes and promises for the
young i will not betray you are you
listening i remain here because your very heart
is now my heart so
he had these things pained him tremendously the loss the pain the suffering this is a
man who suffered a lot but he was not afraid to suffer
he was not crippled by a suffering he practiced with it he turned it around
he composted it he dedicated it to a different way of living
here's another poem
and this was printed in 1966 for the fellowship of reconciliation as a
christmas card life has left her footprints on my
forehead but i have become a child again this morning the smile seen through leaves and
flowers is back to smooth away the wrinkles as the rains wipe away footprints on the
beach again a cycle of birth and death begins
i walk on thorns but firmly as among flowers i keep my
head high rhymes bloom among the sounds of bombs and mortars
the tears i shed yesterday have become rain
i feel calm hearing its sound on the thatched roof childhood my birthland
is calling me and the rains melt my despair
i am still here alive able to smile quietly
o sweet fruit brought forth by the tree of suffering
carrying the dead body of my brother i go across the rice fields in the
darkness earth will keep you tight within her arms my dear
so that tomorrow you will be reborn as flowers
those flowers smiling quietly in the morning field this moment
you weep no more my dear we have gone through too deep a night
this morning i kneel down on the grass when i notice your presence
flowers that carry the marvelous smile of ineffability speak to me in silence
the message the message of love and understanding
has indeed come to us so telling is a powerful poem to
describe his own despair his own suffering and the depth of it and probably it's true that he carried
his dead colleague fellow monk to be buried in mortars and bombs that were blowing
up around him and he was yet he was on the you know he was there working at the
not exactly at the forefront of the war but right there what was happening around him
and then to end with a message of love uh what a powerful thing
to do and then he um you know and then he he offered would
come to come to us to here in the west and he would do walking meditation with us he would do
team meditation with us and this you know to walk with technolon you know
outdoors on the ground slowly mindfully was quite a powerful experience
here's a poem called walking meditation take my hand
we will walk we will only walk
we will enjoy our walk without thinking of arriving anywhere
walk peacefully walk happily our walk is a peace walk
our walk is a happiness walk then we learn
that there is no peace walk that peace is the walk
that there is no happiness walk that happiness is the walk
we walk for ourselves we walk for everyone always hand in hand
walk and touch peace every moment walk and touch happiness every moment
each step brings a fresh breeze each step makes a flower bloom under our
feet kiss the earth with your feet print on earth your love and happiness
earth will be safe when we feel in us enough safety
when we feel in us enough safety so to go from
the suffering of vietnam and the first poems and his dedication to be in the present moment and keep looking keeping present
and seeing what is here and to be fully with his suffering then fully with the flowers the next day
and to be fully with the suffering and ready to smile soon thereafter
to be fully present for this and and here we are walking
and the earth will be safe when we feel in us enough safety
what does it take to feel say have safety within us is that where safety is to be found
is the earth safe when we find in safety in us i think he would say yes to all those
questions that and so he dedicated himself to teaching
people the what he called the miracle of mindfulness to show up for this moment right here
but it wasn't just to show up for it he emphasized penetrating through to the depth of it
um seeing through to some kind of to the ultimate that was there
and um and so what i read the poem i read the gata i read
um beginning of the meditation i'll read it again the the chan zen tradition that he was
part of um classically they used a lot of gatas the four line verses
and when i was in japan we were given verses to recite when we washed our hands we
used the toilet and do all kinds of ordinary things so he had one here
i have arrived i and i am home so this again this emphasis of coming
home but here finding it in the present moment i have arrived i am home
in the here in the now i am solid i am free
in the ultimate i dwell
here's another poem with his anger angry in the ultimate dimension
i close my eyes and look deeply three hundred years from now
where will you be and where shall i be speaking to his anger anger
in 300 years from now where will you be and where shall i be
angry in the ultimate dimension then he wrote
when we are angry what do we usually do we shout scream and try to blame someone
else for our problems but looking at anger with the eyes of impermanence
we can stop and breathe angry at each other in the ultimate dimension
we close our eyes and look deeply we try to see 300 years into the future
what will you be like what will i be like where will you be
where will i be we need only to breathe in and out look at our future
and the other person's future we don't need to look as far as 300 years
it could be 50 or 60 years from now when we have both passed away
and so he kept emphasizing looking deeply
but for him looking deeply in with impermanence was also
kind of opened this rich multi-dimensional world that also used the imagination imagining
300 years in the future and he would look at the famous exercise
they gave was was to look at a piece of paper and basically imagine
that you see deeply with your mouth if you look see deeply with your imagination you see more than just the paper
you see the tree that grew that became the paper you see
the the rain that there there in the soil that nourished the tree to grow you saw the sun that's
shown its sunlight on it that allowed the tree to grow you see the person who cut the tree down the
the people who converted the paper the people who brought the paper to the store the storekeeper who sold it to you
and you see this rich world that included the ecology that we're in included the social world we live in and
to see all of it together in in some big way for him was part of uh waking up to this
world and it's partly maybe why he has such a strong social message
um that he saw us living in this what he called inter-being world an interdependent
world where we our our own being was no separate than the being of everyone else we enter our
is we enter our we we exist because someone else exists
um here he wrote to poem
the title interrelationship you are me
and i am you isn't it obvious that we enter are
you cultivate the flower in yourself so that i will be beautiful
i transform the garbage in myself so that you will not
suffer i support you you support me i am in this world to offer you peace
you are this you are in this world uh to being
to bring me joy
so enter our inter being and so he saw this at a social level at
an environmental level all kinds of levels so he kept emphasizing
uh you know this level in which we enter our and powerful teachings for him
the last week i read a passage by martin
luther king where he said that god is love so i don't know if uh
what degree that influenced dick not han but he had this wonderful uh
book i mean it's a more he's a anthology of different people writing it but this
but just a title it was inspiring for me and very meaningful when i first came out
the title is for a future to be possible commentaries on the five wonderful
precepts so the five precepts that we have he called wonderful precepts he always would put these adjectives in
front of things and you know that kind of superlatives but wonderful and wondrous
and things like that and so he's talking about the five ethical precepts
and but for a future to be possible and uh i think it's a powerful idea
isn't future going to come futures will always come but will we be there as a human race for the futures
what kind of future will we have and so and so ethics is part of that
and but he wrote
the five wonderful precepts are love itself
to love is to understand protect and bring well-being to the object of our
love the practice of the precepts accomplishes this we protect ourselves and we protect
others i am confident that our children and
their children will have an even better understanding of the five precepts and will obtain even deeper peace and
joy this hopeful message so he was looking into the future he was
looking into the past he was looking at this worldwide imagination creative imagination throughout the world
and he was saying just show up here when you walk just walk only walk
and um you know really drink your tea and just drink your tea so this guy he had this capacity he had to switch
orientations to understand and to grow and develop and open up and focus and be
here and work through his sorrow and his grief and find happiness and joy was phenomenal
the humanity of this man and to bring so much humanity into his buddhism his buddhist teachings
was kind of exceptional i think for any buddhist teacher and
so he died i think on thursday we say he died
and i suspect
if he said that for himself i died he would have followed it up by
there is no death and he talked about that sometimes there is
no death but this idea of no death no birth or no
death um that's to be it's not to be believed or understood logically
but it's to be discovered in really being present just here and now
free of our abstract ideas or proliferations free of our stories
free of our concepts and there's something about just being present
in the purity of simplicity of presence that shows a deathless realm shows that
birthless realm shows some aspect of attention of awareness that is free of concepts and ideas of
past and future free of anything but just here
and to and to find his freedom and peace and to
feel at home and to recognize this is the ultimate this is profound um this is a profanity which is always
here it's a dimension of that in a certain kind of way doesn't depend
on our concepts and ideas and our thoughts in a sense doesn't depend on our existence
and but it's the kind of a true home um and so in it there's no birth and death
there's just being present so to be fully present the moment of your death for that moment is to be in a
timeless deathless moment um and then afterwards well it continues
to be the same timeless moment and something there's freedom there that's the avenue for love for this richness
that he was so much about was inclusive of all this
so he has a kind of final
tribute to him and maybe in a way that he would appreciate and to quote him again
he was a teacher and he spent tremendous amount of time teaching
and the testimony of all his teaching is all the books that those produced something like
a hundred books in english
but he wrote or said teaching is not done by talking alone
it is done by how you live your life my life is my teaching
my life is my message
so my life is my message
and um that message continues
he's still alive and
his example lives in us in our memories and those of us he touched and those of
us who learn about him and uh and it's a teaching that points
back to ourselves and imagine how would you live
if your life was the message if your life was your teaching
and then maybe we would realize our true nature in the way that refers to such language he said
our true nature is the nature of no birth and no death
only when we touch our true nature can we transcend the fear of not existing the fear annihilation
so
i'm inspired by tiknot han i'm saddened by his passing i'm inspired by his
passing because his passing is just as much as message and
to not see his passing as part of his teachings part of his message is to miss his teachings miss hui what
he was about and so to hold both to hold this wide range of feelings we
have and not to get caught in the feelings and stuck in them but see them too as
part of this inter-being that is not ours alone
and that which by seeing and with the eyes of impermanence seeing with depth
we find our freedom and perhaps our smile in the midst of our sadness
may it be that thickness life
grows the smiles that can exist in this world the smiles of the children may the
children smile a lot and may we support that the smiles of our elders
may our lives be one that brings smiles to them so they experience smiles before they die
their smiles grow smiles for our neighbors smile for our colleagues smiles for our
family our friends maybe live a life that uh
spreads smiles throughout the world
smiles that can help us to hold kindly lovingly compassionately
the sorrows of this world as well may the memory of thicken heart
dick not han support us guide us inspire us
and continue to to benefit this world for a long time
thank you all