so warm hello for this monday morning
and i agree with both you all who are
attending here now on this live youtube broadcast
in our youtube in the middle of our youtube sangha community
and also welcome those who might be listening to this later and realize there are people who
for different reasons all kinds of reasons listen to this later and and you're just as much part of my
heartfelt sangha youtube song guys those of you who are alive
so um
so people who meditate sooner or later
will contend with the mind's tendency to think some people think more in words some
people think more images some people do a combination of both
and there's a lot of variation in the whole thinking process
for how people some people are very somatic in their thinking some people are more
mental in their thinking it's just a wide range
and thinking has a big impact on our lives it can direct our lives transform our
lives and it can challenge our lives in big ways so
coming to terms with thinking what i'd like to suggest for this
morning is that if and when
you notice that your mind is thinking a lot wandering off in thought rather than settling down to meditate with the
breathing that you don't simply let go of your thoughts and begin again with your
breathing but that you take a moment to just
recognize how strongly or how much you're thinking and kind of the
the attitude of the thinking just uh just briefly touch into it that
way and then rather than letting go of the thoughts
and coming back to your breathing um
uh bring think about something bring up have thoughts
that are kind of like the balancing thoughts for the thoughts you were having
balancing in their pace their speed balancing in their in their
emotional qualities maybe they're in a way that's beneficial for you
so if you're thinking a lot about
i don't know if you're thinking a lot about you know concerns about what's happening
the rest of the day have some when you recognize that's what's happening
take it for just a few sentences or so to quietly have thoughts
about uh how you might be content sitting here now here and now
content that i you know at this moment you don't have to do something or content now that
you're comfortable enough in your body or something just have little thoughts
it's a little bit of a counter thoughts antidote thoughts and
be very helpful of these thoughts we're really aimed at meditation
so oh it's hard to meditate with a busy mind but it's okay
i'll do my best or now i think is the time to bring my attention carefully to my
breathing and then you bring it to the breathing and
so take a few moments to consciously think something
in the wake of having found yourself thinking and maybe those thoughts you do
point you back to the meditation in a nice way maybe their thoughts that are kind for
yourself maybe there's even kind thoughts directed towards yourself so that's the instruction for today
and if you really don't like it you don't have to do it of course so
so assuming an upright posture
and gently closing the eyes
and as you breathe perhaps you can gentle your body the
gentling within or a softening
and then to
leisurely take a few long slow deep breaths three quarters full
and leisurely relax as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and then direct your attention to the area around your forehead your eyes
and as you exhale relax
maybe as you relax these parts of the body you can have a very light
thought well-wishing or goodwill or appreciation
for this part of your body relaxing around the eyes and the
forehead
maybe softening the jaws
exhaling and relaxing the shoulders
and the exhale softening the belly
on the exhale softening the whole body
whatever way you might be braced against life
let it soften
and then settling in with your breathing and as a kind of beginning of
meditation on breathing tell yourself some supportive thoughts
for what you're going to do now give yourself a little
a few thoughts that with that thoughts that carry a nice attitude and have nice words for
yourself of encouragement and appreciation
for this practice your practice of mindfulness
thoughts appreciating your practice of mindfulness of breathing
and then settling in to the body breathing settling into the body's experience of
breathing
and you're when you find yourself drifting off in thought
take a moment to recognize something about those that thinking
and replace it with thoughts that are supportive of
your meditation that are supportive of you
as a meditator
thoughts of encouragement
and then give yourself over to the meditation
if you find yourself thinking the counter thought might be as simple
as here with the breathing is the place to be
let me center myself on the breathing again
maybe even adding a very quiet but delightful yes
affirming that that's what you'll do
you
so
if you find yourself drifting off in thought
have quiet thoughts that return you
point you back to here and now
that somehow are an alternative to the momentum of the previous thoughts
uh
and as we come to the end of the sitting to say a few
generous thoughts of goodwill
and how you say it is as important as what you say
to offer good will
to the people that you'll encounter today or those that you'll run into in the
streets and the roads neighbors
people that you'll somehow encounter through email or messages or
through the news
in an important way we are connected to everyone
our lives are deeply interconnected in ways that we can't even see
and to the degree to which they are part of your life your part of their life
even if you don't know each other and to come out of meditation and
to wish well to this world and to have this well-wishing be the
bridge between a kind of inner meditation
in the world around you
may it be that this meditation supports each of us
to make this a happier world for everyone
may this practice of mindfulness support us
in making this a safer world for everyone
may it be that our practice
is expressed in making this world a more peaceful place for everyone
and may it be that this practice
allows us or shows us how to offer freedom to everyone
the freedom from our needs and attachments and clingings
freedom from our fears
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
[Music]
so good day everyone and being monday we begin a new uh theme for
the week and i'd like to somehow continue with the theme of in general theme of
emotions it's in the background or the backdrop for what this theme is
and uh so the theme is going to be uh thinking and emotions
the relationship between our emotional life and our thinking life thoughts and emotions go hand in hand
and sometimes i've noticed maybe in myself and in people i've talked to
a very strong division between emotions and thinking
sometimes preferring one over the other but the more that i've meditated the
more i don't i can't really separate them out completely from each other that they come together as a piece peace
sometimes one stands out more strongly than the other
and sometimes one seems to be the catalyst for the other
sometimes thoughts evoke emotions
sometimes emotions arise who knows why and in their wake there come certain
thoughts sometimes emotions that we have
are somehow fueling the thoughts we have are fueling the thoughts that we have
sometimes the emotions we have are giving energy to the thoughts that we have
so to really be able to kind of get a handle and learn how to be really mindful of
the whole process of thinking of emotions our emotional life it really
helps to take stock of this thinking world and start seeing the connection between the two
and and today i want to emphasize the idea that you would study this for yourself
that you would begin during this week to really take care to notice
uh as you're thinking what role what relationship what impact
does that thinking have on your emotional life
and what in return what impact or role does your emotions have on the thoughts that you have
and for today i want to talk about one particular kinds of thinking
that uh very important for some of us to be mindful of
and that is a rumination and i just love this word rumination
because of its bovine kind of reference that
cows you know they eat all this grass and they regurgitate the grass and then chew it
and so we take and regurgitate these stories ideas
fantasies all kinds of things and and then we chew on it and chew on it
and this rumination is kind of thoughts turning in on themselves
so that there's kind of a black hole or kind of trapped in them and it's often repair repetitive
repeating the same kinds of thoughts over and over again um and um not just kind of the ideal
daydreaming but rumination is really chewing on something it's really kind of working something or
driving something home usually that's not very healthy for us um that's how at least how i kind of
under you use the term maybe there's other perfectly legitimate ways of refer of using the word rumination
but the idea that uh we're spinning around we're caught up in certain thoughts
and this idea of being caught in thoughts and spinning over and over again is so powerful
that psychotherapists will point out that one of the leading correlates or maybe even
causes for depression or is
for many people not everyone is rumination so how that works is we're telling
ourselves a story about how terrible things are or how frightening and
and maybe telling ourselves how you know having self-pity thoughts or discouraging thoughts
depressing thoughts that things are too hard or terrible things are happening to me
and think terrible things do happen to people but there's ruminating about it over and
over again that's a very distinct way in which we become a victim
we become a victim of our own thinking their own loops were in and it might be
true for example it might be true that uh i am a
in um maybe there are certain ways in my life that i'm a careless person
and so it might be true and the other day i spilled some coffee on
the kitchen floor and didn't notice it my wife you know pointed it out and she cleaned it up so there's ways which i'm
a careless person and so i can notice that i can say yes
skilled you were careless today sometimes you're a careless person and that's it
or it's like gil you're a careless person
people are telling you that this is bad to be a careless person you're a mindfulness teacher so you
should really know how be careful and be attentive and not be careless and it's very important that now all these people
know that you're careless and now it's really bad that you know i'm such a bad person i'm a careless
person and it really speaks badly for 40 50 years of buddhist training and you
know i'm really you know this is really you know it really casts a very bad light on myself and who
i am and my practice and my dedication that i should be a careless person so i should stop now
i'm sure you're getting tired already and um but uh so the idea being that
that uh uh i'm kind of like digging myself a grave i'm kind of like each of those
littles like a nail in the coffin like oh i'm so terrible i'm so terrible and some terrible
and maybe it's like you know each one maybe doesn't have a big impact on me but the continuity of the repetition of
it just begins to wear me down and kind of drain me and take things out
so that's what i kind of what i'm referring to is rumination this kind of wearing down of the same message over
and over and over again it might not be so conscious that it's thinking because it might be more of an
almost like an attitude like an emotion but it is a belief it is an idea
that we have and we're kind of repeating it so often and the negative quality of it is draining us
so the emphasis i want to make that is in case there's some truth to this statement
say it once learn from it do a course correction the best you can
but there's no reason there's no requirement as human being to repeat the same thought about
yourself over and over and over again now it's very hard to stop doing that of course
but one of the ways to change the direction of all this is start being cognizant that this is
working recognize how repetitive your mind is recognize that you're kind of telling
yourself the same story the same message over and over again and notice the and notice the impact how
is this affecting your energy level your inspiration level how does it what emotions does it bring does it bring
fear and how does it affect your body
some people who are very very somatic based bodies life will can see that as they have certain
thoughts that uh their body begins to shift and change certain muscles tighten up and
you know energies in the body shift and change and so to have thoughts about some frightening thing happen fantasy of
frightening things happening and fear uh feelings in the body are triggered
have thoughts of desire and ruminate about desire and sexual fantasies and
other sensations in the body get aroused have fantasies and
repetition about all the wrongs that have been done and
starts feeling angry and maybe wrongs have been done but to tell your story over and over and over
again don't confuse the harm someone else has done
with the harm that you're doing to yourself because to say angry thoughts to
yourself over and over again or critical thoughts against yourself over and over again or depressing thoughts over and
over again it's harmful to oneself to do that and so
this is the second arrow that we had and so the first arrow is life
and that we can't necessarily control but we can have some control over the
second arrows so along this line it's very common for people to say
that the meditation teachers like me that maybe you can't control always control your thinking mind
like in terms of whether you think or don't think but what you can do just like you can't control maybe a big
wide river but you can be in the river and find the right place the right
current to be in the right place in the river and avoiding the rapids
so we can be in the world of thinking and make adjustments get into a different boat on the river
of thoughts go into a different current or an eddy um and where it's
safe or worse you know avoid the whirlpools or the holes that you know the rapids
and so to to notice that the rumination notice the repetitive thoughts that are
maybe sometimes debilitating and then to uh
just notice that notice how repeat rep repetitive they are you can count them it's fascinating start counting how many
times you have the same kind of thought it takes some of the some of the
charge or the authority out of them to count them by the time you get to 300 it's like
they don't have so much authority or you can
see the effect it has in your body on your emotions and
you could offer different thoughts you can consciously begin thinking about
something that's more positive not a fantasy in itself but something that's true that's it's that's kind
that's generous that's soft and one of the ways to even do it if you're by yourself maybe driving or
something rather than ruminating difficult thoughts is to start talking out loud to yourself
in a nice friendly voice thoughts that are supportive thoughts that are good thoughts about what's
coming and and um because sometimes the the voice
that thinks comes from a different place in our mind than the voice that speaks
and so you're tapping into a different side of yourself when you're speaking out loud and maybe there's more wisdom
maybe there's more kindness maybe the more there's more access to a choice
of how to be than if you just let your thinkings keep going and
but also start experimenting with shifting what you're thinking about it might sound artificial
it might sound a little bit forced and effortful however it's pro if it's better than the
alternative try doing it if the alternative you've done it long enough of ruminating and spinning and
the billet you know this kind of draining kinds of thoughts maybe you know those are the ones we
should be questioned that they're artificial those are the ones that we should question about you know how much energy we're going
into them so you might try to offer an alternative
consciously choose what you think and think good things this is not meant to be
polyanish it's not meant to be an antidotal thinking necessarily it's
not meant to be pretending or that everything is fine it could be very realistic thoughts
about what's happening that sees reality what's happening directly and right in the eye
but that meets it and thinks about it in wise ways and kind ways supportive ways
compassionate ways the ways that maybe you would imagine
so the buddha would speak or the way that some wonderful person that you know
wise kind person that you're inspired by how they might speak about the situation
so uh this is this is uh what i'm offering today requires some
mindfulness but it is a practice that's kind of different than mindfulness but i'm hoping that
this investigation and this kind of practice of thinking in new ways
will be a tremendous support for your ability to be mindfully present
and something can settle the rumination can settle and you can be inspired by a different way to go
forward so um uh i hope that you
find a way to enjoy this and and take up the challenge
if you're one of those people who might ruminate in ways that are not useful for you
and and if you're not one of those people then tomorrow we'll take it in the world
of thinking from a different angle thank you