so welcome to our first time back after our latest
pandemic pause and so those of you are here welcome it's very nice to be together and
it's actually i i think i under-appreciated how valuable it was to
be together as community i mean i always valued it so two years ago i would have of course
it's valuable but now i feel it's a whole different dimension of value and just
sharing and being together and there's something almost like uh
like if you're thirsty and you drink some refreshing waters ah that feels good there's a whole feeling of being a
community that i get now that something i didn't know needed to be satisfied or get satiated
or something so welcome back and for those of you online welcome back and
know that there's about 25 people here here at imc
and so i'll have both of people here in my mind and also all of
you online so for the meditation today i want to uh
offer a variation or a dimension of this mindfulness practice
it's a i think it's a relatively common human phenomenon
to get preoccupied with something and to be fixated on something be concerned with something
and they say that some of us have negative biases so sometimes we get focused on what's negative or difficult
or off or something and uh and sometimes when we hear the
meditation instruction like just focus on your breathing which we kind of some people translate
that to themselves oh this is another time i'm supposed to be fixated narrowly focused on something just be
with that and then there's this tension between you know being narrowly focused because it's effort to do that
and the mind wants to wander away or something so there's an art to not having the
meditative attention fixated to not translate one pointedness to
holding the attention tight on something like the breathing but rather to have the attention we have
a softness to it a floating quality to it that allows you to take in the wider
context of what's happening so it would be a little bit like
if you're walking in a park with a friend having a you know you're involved in the conversation and with a friend that's
the focus of attention you would say the center of gravity of attention but you're also taking in the park as
you walk because you have to make sure you don't you know step on a rock or in a branch
that's fallen or you know when you you don't even think about it but then you're synchronized so you come to a
curve in the path you both curve around together so you're taking in
the wider context maybe even the niceness of it the beautiful greenery the peacefulness of
it and it just feels good not you taking in that kind of being relaxed or something inspired by the park setting
as opposed to walking next to the freeway on the shoulder you know with your friend the cars rushing by it'd be very different
right so this ability to kind of take in the peripheral
context of the situation it can be very helpful for meditation
and it can uh so as you're focusing on the breathing it's not just important to stay with the
breath but in a relaxed way almost like you're opening attention up you're also taking in the wider context
of you sitting there and one of those contexts context
is that which is that which is going well that which feels pleasant
where there's some sense of ease and the chances are that somewhere in the field in your field of attention in
your body and your mind there's probably something that feels pleasant enjoyable about sitting quietly
here what might be loud is that something that's not enjoyable not pleasant
can you be can you be open enough in your attention not to deny
anything that's unpleasant anything is difficult but to be wide enough you can also include
what is pleasant what's an easeful what's enjoyable about it all so if you're focusing on the breathing
relaxed soft attention of the breathing kind of like you're resting on the breathing
but without working at it too much just kind of gently open and there's some kind of
embodied context for breathing that feels nice it feels good
it feels pleasant or useful or even if it might feel you feel lousy
today we're not denying you're lousy feeling lousy not you like it i'm denying you're lousy but that you
but but that you might feel lousy does it make some sense
those of you here are not in good so so let's try that a little bit so
assuming a meditation posture
and a way that feels nice for you can you adjust your posture
so that yours feels nice to be in your body some of you it might help to
relax something some of you it might mean sitting up
straighter sitting up in a way that feels more confident
and then as if you're going to enjoy yourself doing it slowly luxuriously
take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe exhaling in a way that feels enjoyable or pleasant
maybe part of the enjoyment is as you exhale to relax your body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and perhaps you can continue relaxing on the exhale but if you're able to soften or relax
some muscles take the time to feel the pleasure of
that the goodness of that
relaxing the muscles of your face
if you can soften your shoulders
does anything in that softening feel pleasant
on the exhale relaxing the belly
and perhaps on the exhale a global relaxation of your body
and then sitting here quietly notice if there's any
pleasure global pleasure or
pleasantness that resides in your body
even if parts of you feel uncomfortable
maybe there's a subtle global feeling of
aliveness awareness in the body
a tingling or vibration that has a kind of subtle pleasure to it
maybe it's a kind of global or maybe it's very specific
sometimes it can be just simple as
a feeling of pleasure with the lips touching it especially if you make a little half
smile
and for a few moments let your global awareness float around your body
touching into wherever in the body it feels comfortable or feels pleasure
pleasant or where there's a sense of ease
not so much looking for it but it's just allowing it to
your attention to float and settle float and touch in
randomly wherever it goes
and letting that be their peripheral attention
center the awareness of the sensations of the body breathing
almost as if the breathing body is a like a wave in the
vast ocean that goes up and down
but the wave is part of this larger ocean
so the breathing the sensations of breathing in and out
we're part of this wider global experience of the body
and is there some way that you can
help the attention be enjoyable a soft floating awareness
that floats along with the comings and goings of the breath
not fixating
an attention which is receptive
loose awareness
so that part of the peripheral awareness is a very simple
pleasure of being aware
and as you focus on your breathing
the central focus the center of focus is breathing
and all around it peripheral awareness
it su supports you with a feeling of pleasure
pleasantness
however subtle it might be
you
if you're wanting one drink often thought
if you quiet your thinking mind
can you feel better the pleasure of being present here
and have that pleasure support the attention resting on breathing
you
okay
uh
you
if something within you is a little bit calmer or settled
than when you started meditating
perhaps you can feel the pleasantness of that calm or subtleness
no matter how subtle it is and gently breathe with it
breathe through it
and then from with whatever is pleasant
enjoyable has a feeling of rightness within you
from that place turning your attention outwards
to those of you here to the people sitting in this room
to the people online to the others who are sitting online
meditating now
and see if there's a simple way to
consider the people around you in the context of your pleasant feeling
perhaps wishing for them some of the same pleasantness
calmness ease that you're experiencing now or that you
have experienced in the past
and to end this meditation
with the aspiration the wish
for the welfare of others may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
um
hmm
so hello everyone and welcome
and the topic for today is
dharmic pleasure the pleasure that comes from dharma
practice and one of the principles that
i'm going to offer is the principle that sometimes
what is unpleasant can be overcome by what is pleasant
sometimes pain can be overcome by pleasure
or dealt with through pleasure but not just any pleasantness or any
pleasure but what can be called dharmic pleasure
so what is that there's a story in the suttos teachings of the buddha
about uh it's possible it's the the buddha's cousin
who is a layperson who comes to the buddha and he says
uh i have this preoccupation
that is getting in my way and i can't really
make progress in the dharma or something because there's preoccupation
and uh and the preoccupation is overly attached
to sensual pleasure and so that's a sensual pleasure is an obstacle because
i'm constantly thinking about it or imagining it or wanting it or something concerned with it
and the buddha says that's the way it is that if you're uh if you're preoccupied
and caught up in sensual pleasure it's really hard to make progress on the dharma path
and back in ancient india and in buddhist time there was other religious traditions
that saw this as well that uh that sensual pleasures of all kinds were
an obstacle to some kind of spiritual progress
and they advocated asceticism sometimes a radical denial of all pleasure and all that sometimes actually
intentional taking on the pain there are some people who believe that you can only overcome pain with pain
so you know get into it and uh
and so he said yeah that's uh but so the buddha agreed with a man yeah there can be an obstacle
in preoccupation essential pleasure and then remarkably the buddha said that
before i was enlightened i also was preoccupied with sensual
pleasures in a way that interfered with my practice interfered with things
so he knew intimately for himself how this can work and then he says the only way
something like this the way to overcome this preoccupation concern
is through pleasure is through what i'm calling dharmic pleasure he doesn't use that term
epidharmic pleasure that there is a kind of pleasure you can
cultivate that
has an antidote to the preoccupation with sensual pleasure
and one way to see this is that there is another kind of pleasure a feeling of wellness of goodness of
of uh that is a reconditioning factor
and uh we're very dif very strongly influenced by the conditions in which we live in
and that we say we can be conditioned by them they're a lifelong kind of conditioning
so people who live with constant threat growing up can be conditioned to be afraid and
anxious and wherever they go they're kind of have their eyes open looking at how to be safe because they feel that's what they've learned taken in
there are people who have been horribly wounded scarred emotionally by what happens to
them and that and that creates a conditioning that creates a
kind of an influence that leads a lasting impression and a lasting perspective in which to look at the
world like the world is a dangerous place because people are threatening or something
and there's all these series of conditionings we have some people receive the conditioning
that you're successful if you have a lot of pleasure and so you should really and you get you
get rewarded for having sensual pleasure and so you want to have lots of pleasure because that's how you feel rewarded you
feel good and feel like everything's okay in the world and that's been the conditioning now over and over again that's been
reinforced in different kinds of ways and and these kinds of conditionings can
lead to an intensity around the pursuit of sensual pleasure of all kinds
it could certainly can be sexual it can be the pleasure of
alcohol and drugs it can be the pleasures of the intellect
pleasures of adventures pleasures of a daredevil who just you know engaged
and fully absorbed in some kind of thing that has their it brings their attention fully into the
present moment and clears out everything else it feels so alive and so connected some people fear
uh you know and doing things that are frightening brings a kind of aliveness they don't have any other time in their life and so that feels so good to have
that aliveness there was a
i remember many years i told this story a few times many years ago i saw a little documentary
about a man who had spent his early part of his adult life
spending a lot of time like on the weekends riding his motorcycle all over and that's how he cleared his mind and
got ready for work and enjoyed just driving his big motorcycle around him
but then uh he and his wife had a baby
and he couldn't spend the weekend away on his motorcycle so he had to find a quicker way to clear
his mind and be ready to start fresh and everything so he took up the the sport
of uh paragliding and it looked this typical kind of paraglider kind of apparently i don't
know if that's the right word but he could put it into a packet into a backpack and uh
and then early in the morning at dawn he would climb up in these skyscrapers that were being built in his city
so it was still kind of open and everything but he would sneak sneak into the into the building climb up to the top
and and then he would jump from the top into the street below where there's no
traffic yet just as dawn was happening and he had a friend with a car a getaway
car waiting down below to drive off drive to hikimov and that's how he cleared his mind
you know and that's how you know he something good happened and he felt alive and good and present
so there's all these ways in which we are pursuing some kind of feeling of
feelings alive and good and that sometimes involves pursuit of
pleasure or exp having getting experience in life good things
and uh and sometimes those kinds of pursuits
don't really fill us don't really meet some deeper need that we have
and in fact as we almost need to can repeat the same pleasure in order to be distracted from some deeper wound some
deeper loneliness some deeper angst some deeper
depression some deeper or something and and so people then repeat the same thing
rather you're yearning for more and more and more so the buddha said that
what's you know that they said yeah that way doesn't work
but in order to kind of not have this pursuit of central pleasure be an obstacle
you have to experience a non-sensual pleasure a pleasure that's not of the physical
senses and a pleasure which he used the word unwholesome when it's not unwholesome that
uh unless unskillful and so and then what he used as an
example for this was the certain kind of pleasure that comes from meditation practice
that a certain kind of joy and well-being and happiness that can well up from the inside
and this idea of welling up from the inside is a is a
very different source for a sense of well-being than the sense of
pleasure or even well-being that can come from getting stimulated by good experiences from the
outside in so it might feel really good to have a really good meal tasty meal your
favorite meal and there's nothing wrong with that but if you're simply taking in the
pleasure of it that's uh what you're being then it's only of the
senses if the person who made the meal for you
did it with a lot of love and it touched something inside of you like wow
this feels i can feel the generosity and the goodness of this person who's doing something
that could touch something that's not of the senses that might touch your heart in some way
and that has a very different impact on us than the conditioning that comes from just just the senses just the pleasure
of the food it's not the food that we're benefiting from the most it's rather the
goodness of it so a story i like to tell is my you know a lasting impression that still with me
it probably was a at the time i didn't know it was it conditioned me it had his lifelong influence on me
but was staying at my grandmother's house when i was like maybe somewhere between seven and ten
and waking up in the mornings beautiful light and staying in bed with this all wooden room is in norway
with a norwegian comforter and this bright norwegian light coming in through the window and just being all cozy
reading donald duck magazines in norwegian
and uh she would bring in a tray with toast butter and cheese on it
and uh and it was nice i would stay in bed eating the toast you know with the reading the donald duck magazines
but uh somehow not unbeknownst to me at that time
i was taking in the goodness the safety the warmth the love of that situation of my grandmother
and i still carry inmate with me that feeling that memory of that goodness so certainly the toast with cheese was
pleasant essentially but it was some deeper
feeling that well spring from inside something deeper was born or was awoken
or was allowed that did something special just a simple thing she did
and uh and so and so to awaken this wellspring
something that can goodness a pleasure that can arise from the inside out
and not continually looking for it in the world is the the path of the dharma
certainly it could have been my lifelong pursuit is to find someone who was just like my
grandmother and make sure i had got the right kind of comforter the right kind of wooden
bed and make sure that they brought the toast and butter in every morning at the right time of day
when the light was shining through getting just to get everything set up and have someone who's just just like my
grandmother and so that that somehow but that's just that i think in a strict
way that in buddhism is just trying to get the world of the senses just organized around you
to try to replicate something but what is it to
but in dharma practice what we're doing is we're not looking at external world for this
but we're looking to see how can we awaken something inside that becomes a reconditioning
that dissipates any kind of attachment to comfort sensual comfort physical comfort
any kind of attachment to sensual or physical pleasure any kind of attachments to
physical or sensual stimulation of any kind at all including intellectual stimulation
and the so the buddha said you can't really overcome this addiction or preoccupation with this kind of physical
pleasure sensual pleasure without this dharmic pleasure
and uh you know one of the ways he talked about this dharmic pleasure more his language
he called it a pleasure not of the flesh
so not of the flesh meaning nothing physical was being stimulated
and so have you had any experiences where there was enough sense of well-being of
safety of quiet of comfort or something setting and the environment
was just right that you felt something not so much nourished from the outside
but allowed something inside to settle to open to be at ease to feel safe
so that there was a wellspring within that began to flow and move through you
it requires being in a different way than most people are i think in their ordinary life
where maybe we're just keeping ourselves busy we have a to-do list we're doing this and that we're trying to maybe just
be busy or keep ourselves entertained like you know some people have
do what's called it's a term i only learned a few years ago binge
watching uh you know there's some kind of tv program that just like there's all these series you can watch like 10
series and in one day stay up all night
so that might be physically placed this buddha would call kind of a pleasure of the senses
but it doesn't create the environment the situation the context that awakens something from the inside
out probably not and so what uh
so meditation for the buddha was he presented that as the means
for this deeper healing pleasure that's possible to have
and uh you know he didn't have netflix he didn't have all the things we have in
the modern world that people use you know to try to assuage
how they're feeling uncomfortable and so the buddha said buddha did not
teach that you overcome pain with pain he taught you overcome
pleasure you overcome pain with pleasure
he did not say you overcome pleasure with pain he said you overcome pleasure with
pleasure and overcome here means overcoming our attachments or preoccupation or fixation
so whether things are the vexation has to do with things that are pleasant or the fixation has to do with things
that are unpleasant both are uh kind of healed
through feeling this dharmic well-being this dharmic pleasure and so the art of
of discovering a way of feeling a certain kind of inner pleasure or well-being
and letting that be the context in which you experience your life so i'll give you an example for me
it's not dramatic but maybe you can fill in a way that's meaningful for you
it was probably something like this happens to many of you like sometimes i sit down a bit had a busy day
doing a lot of things or something or a lot of feelings a lot of something going on and i sit down to meditate
and i discover that my breathing is not relaxed there's kind of i'm contracted in the
chest a little bit and if i sit and feel that it actually feels unpleasant
on the top of the inhale but what i do is i
relax a bit around it and i feel it's not doesn't have to be dramatic very subtle sense of well-being
or pleasure in the wider body the global body
part of it's a pleasure that comes from just the pleasure or the goodness
of being conscious of things just being aware of things
it feels good for me and then i'll as i stay focusing on my breathing
i just contentedly feel the discomfort of my breathing without making it a problem
and but i feel the discomfort in this wider field of pleasure of pleasantness of goodness
that's there so i can end up being feeling very content
feeling the discomfort because it's not the f it's not the whole picture
it's not ever not it's not not the i'm not fixated on it
early in my meditation practice many years ago i would have gotten so caught up and
preoccupied oh i shouldn't be breathing that way this is a problem i'm a bad meditator what do i have to do to stop having this
discomfort i'm not supposed to have it and i've got what i i tied myself in knots around these kinds of things
and because of this kind of negativity by us perhaps or this idea that supposed to you know deal with these problems i'm
supposed to be just everything's supposed to be different and now i just oh look at that
i guess the cause the conditions of the day my breathing is a little bit is uncomfortable
and it's okay and and i feel that discomfort in this wider feeling of
pleasure and that has healed my tendency to be preoccupied the
shoulds the judgments the idea that i'm wrong something relaxes that way
and so this idea of there's a dharmic pleasure
a pleasure not of the senses not of the flesh something that kind of is belongs more
to the wellspring that we allow for that we open up to
and then we allow ourselves to be conditioned by it there's an art allowing ourselves to be
influenced by that and perhaps in your daily life there are moments
situations where you feel something like this
but maybe you're not you don't linger long enough in it you just have to go you know
you know you have your to-do list okay let's go to the next thing you jump in your car and you're tense
driving but the fact that you just were in the park with a friend and and going for a nice walk and feeling
kind of peaceful that's besides the point once you get in your car to go to the next important
thing but what about lingering or staying with
these feelings some of these dharmic pleasures can
we benefit the most if we allow them to take them in we let them oh this is good
in spite of the fact that i feel unhappy right today there is also this goodness here
if we get preoccupied with our unhappiness we're going to be
probably more likely influenced by the unflapping happiness
in a negative way but if we allow ourselves to be unhappy but feel it in a wider field
of something that feels easeful or pleasant or open
then that can be an influence that heals some of unhappiness
so what are some of the things that we can feel some of it is a global awareness of the
body that's bigger than any particular place where we feel uncomfortable or feel pain
in the body it's not always available to us but there might be some feeling of
subtle vibration or subtle energy flow or subtle tingling
or subtle spaciousness one of the things that's happened to me over the years of practice
i have a lot of space in my body now at least that's what it feels like to me
it looks like a very spacious beautiful big place in there i closed my eyes and i was so surprised when i went to
some years ago i started going once a year to a in a community college nearby that has a
anatomy lab where they spend time with the cadaver it's all get cut open you can see the
inside and i was so surprised there's no space in there
it's just packed with organs and everything like wow they don't have any space but i have
lots of space this this space is not real space but it's the space that of
you know just somehow i experience i feel the space i feel
spacious very inside and around very spacious and that spaciousness feels nice
when i was younger i would have didn't think that space like that was something to focus on
now i feel that it's kind of like you go into a big big
sacred space and it's a space in the high ceilings then everything that somehow makes the place feel kind
of sacred or quiet or peaceful and so to feel the spaciousness within
for me as a positive conditioning force
sometimes it's uh it's uh some of the things that we do
that has a positive influence because of the goodness of doing it being generous
not giving but a giving which is generous
or giving that has a feeling of love with it or honesty
not the honesty that's a duty but the honesty that sets something free inside you're not hiding or contracted
it's making it decontracts us and to feel that feel the goodness of
honesty of truthfulness the
kindness compassion the kind of kindness and compassion
again there's not a should and not a duty not a like you know
i'm supposed to i'm you know i'm a good buddhist i'm supposed to be this way i'm going to kind of buckle down to be kind
but rather to discover how to open and allow for a softness a
tenderness where of course you want to be kind of course that's good
and all these things learning how to do these things in a way discovering your way
not someone else's way we're doing living going through life you do things you speak things you act
in ways that feels really good for you on the inside out
some people sometimes say in buddhism they talk about actions which are beautiful
but i think the beauty is not the external grace in which you do things but rather the feeling of beauty from
the inside out as you do it and what does it take to do things in a
beautiful way i don't think you can do them in a hurry
i think hurry interferes with any of this deeper
well-being that can recondition us and heal us and show us something different
so it requires something of us and one of the things it requires is non-hurry
to feel to be present one of the forms of primary forms of
dharmic pleasure that the buddha emphasized for this purpose this reconditioning purpose this
way of overcoming preoccupation with sensual pleasure
was the kind of well-being that arises when we get
our attention becomes unified organized in a unified way
to be fully engaged absorbed in one thing
i say that very carefully and all these all those words because i could have said when we just
get concentrated on one thing but to say concentrated some people then
get fixated this tight attention they bear down they narrow down to
really stay and be present and that is not the unified
composed attention with which we get organized
around being absorbed in one thing
and so some of some of you maybe have felt a wonderful feeling of maybe well-being
being absorbed and reading a good novel just it just feels so good just to be like you know if the world around you
falls away you get pulled into the novel some of you might have the craft you do
where you're you could say i'm absorbed absorbing the craft but you're not fixating on any one part of the craft
it's the whole phenomena that feels good and you make you might be idly thinking about things that
but your your mind hasn't stopped thinking but everything is organized around the craft or playing a musical
instrument or doing art or going for a walk sometimes in a natural setting
so in meditation that's the kind of absorption that is possible
that uh the buddha was emphasizing that gives birth to a deeper sense of
well-springing of well-being of joy of happiness of
delight and that we're allowed to feel pleasure
dharmic pleasure we're allowed to feel good in fact to to be fixated
on what's uncomfortable what's difficult emotionally physically
in the world the fixation is a bad influence on us
the fixation is stressful
we don't have to ignore the difficulties we have but we can hold them
in a different context than one that's told by the being fixated on it and so they to using meditation to begin
relaxing the fixations softening the way we get preoccupied by things
opening up the developing a soft receptive floating awareness
an awareness because it's not fixated can start becoming aware of the
peripheral context of this of our situation
and by the way peripheral context what i mean is
uh if we're involved with our breathing for example that's the primary center of our
attention meditating we're not only taking in the breathing
hanging on for dear life but we're also the peripheral attention takes in the goodness
the subtle very subtle perhaps pleasure well-being of the situation we're in maybe
physically to feel where where does feel good
and there's often more more goodness more pleasure than most people take advantage of
and here's a here's an example that i find kind of fascinating
if i feel tense in my body it feels uncomfortable
i can relax attention and then notice that i'm tensed somewhere else
and you try to deal with that or something else is a problem
but what happened was that in i ignored the fact that as i released the tension
there was a feeling of subtle pleasure relief in my shoulders as i relaxed
so what should i focus on the the tension the painful tension
that i'm glad went away or the pleasure that replaced it
the same relaxation happens but am i keep focusing on what's
negative or can i focus on the positive side of it
so there's many situations where i learned to relax for example
and feel the goodness of the relaxation that i wouldn't have done early in my
life because i'm because i'm just going barreling ahead with one preoccupation
concern after the other check that off relax the shoulders what's next to do
what's what's the next thing to worry about but again this idea of not hurrying and
taking the time and chances are there's more
non-sensual pleasure dharmic pleasure that's available in any given time than
you than you allow that you recognize i've sat at meetings and been impatient
and the impatient didn't go away but by somehow settling into my body i could feel there was wider in my body
there was in fact a sense of feeling a little bit alive nicely vital relaxing
that created a different context for feeling the impatience and uh earlier in my life i would have
just kind of been caught by the impatience now i know better
now i think oh i'm impatient what else is going on here and can i feel that larger context
of just the pleasure of just being alive right now and now
breathe with the impatience now i'll be with it so i'm not fixated on it it's being held
in a wider context so i call this the peripheral attention
and uh and to float the attention between the central focus and the peripheral
to be focus on the on the central focus of what needs to be needs attention but to
hold that with the peripheral attention of what feels good which feels pleasant that supports this ability to get
absorbed composed gathered around unified about something
and then lo and behold this uh this kind of staying very very
still and quiet and absorbed in something like the breathing or other things
i can start producing this deeper wellsprings and i keep using the word wellsprings because the buddha and talking about
this kind of absorption uses the metaphor analogy of an underground spring underwater
spring in a lake a wellspring of water that flows into the lake from below
and uh i think it uses that metaphor uh purposefully because that's how it can
feel inside of us that this wellspring with us flows from someplace within and flows outward and
through the body this vibration this energy this tingling this
warmth this glow whatever it might i don't know how the right term for you is
and so to allow ourselves give yourself time to feel make room for some other
way of feeling they take the time and room to feel dharmic pleasure
and in this way pleasure overcomes attachment to pleasure
isn't that convenient and the buddha was very specific about
in the context of ancient india that we don't use
pain to overcome pleasure we don't use pain to overcome pain
but for him you use we use pleasure to overcome the preoccupation both with
pain and pleasure and so
how might this work for you i suspect that
uh probably for many of you i probably didn't speak about this very well in a way that
was specific enough for you but i hope what it did was at least turn the mirror
back to yourself and to see you know what is there some way that you know
in your terms and your experience what i'm talking about i've been talking about something that would be useful for
you to take more time with and make room for and not be in a hurry for
and not be tricked by the mind's preoccupations and the
mind's to-do list and the mind's previous conditioning
that maybe gets you kind of constantly on the treadmill of doing things which are actually
continue being a poor influence on you but being able to shift in gears
to allow a healthy appropriate new influence new conditioning
that allows you then to take in and benefit
from the deeper and deeper way that mindfulness can make gather you together to be
really present for your experience so just there's more and more nurturing there's more and more healing there's
more and more goodness and pleasure
in the practice so uh
i hope this is uh something that you can identify in yourself and find useful and
thank you for being here today and we have a couple of minutes would anyone like to ask any questions about this or
clarifications or
or anything else
here behind you bill i'll try those of you online i'll try to look at the chat and see if you have a
question but this question may be somewhat unclear
even to myself what are the gray areas between dharmic pleasure and the sensual
pressure where you can't tell the difference which one are you now engaged in
yes aware that the gray area where we can't tell the difference between dharmic pleasure and
sensual pleasure sometimes they come together that's part of the reason why it's not so clear
and so it takes some time to be able to allow for both to be there not assume that it can be it should only be one or
the other there's nothing inherently wrong with sensual pleasure and so
so in buddhism we're not dismissing sensual pleasure off hand it's the attachment to it
but so and as we feel this uh so so dismissing it or feeling that sensual
pleasure is wrong doesn't allow us to see how they operate they can operate together they can both
be there thank you very much blessing
gil i remember a quote that i think is from the verses of the elder nuns i'm not sure
that part of your talk reminded me of i take delight and attention to all
suffering states i take delight and attention to all suffering states that's how i remember it well that's a great
one yeah that's a good fantastic so i think it's a it's a uh
i think it's a common assumption by people that if you're suffering
that's suffering by itself that's all that all that's going on because of this negativity bias because of the
preoccupation with it because the ways which are thinking get so pulled into
that world that we're just thinking about it all the time but to learn to not be caught in
thoughts to learn how to open up attention into a wider field
and just the idea of discovering the preciousness of being conscious of being mindful being aware
and how awareness of something can feel pleasant enjoyable or just a rightness
to it there's freedom in in the awareness of it so so it's possible to be aware
of suffering states and actually feel joy
like when i talked about feeling my discomfort with my breathing sometimes when i kind of turn towards it with the
spacious mind and body and feel it just my ability to do that i sometimes
get a little smile oh look at that it's so good to be mindful
and whereas in the past i wouldn't have noticed that so so that i suspected something like that
so as i say it again i take the light and attention toward
all suffering states yeah it's a lot better than alternative
anything else
or is everyone else here online are you speaking about leaning into the pain
leaning into the pain well you know that might be fun that might if with the right kind of
mindfulness and attention that could be fun
but not but so i wouldn't rule it out but i'm not really encouraging people to lean into the pain but if you have pain
to begin with you want to be wise about it and you want to have lots of options and be able
to find your way with it and uh and one of the ways to find your way with it is to hold the pain
uh in in a wider field of pleasure well-being or freedom of attention or something just hold it in awareness
without being caught by it and one of the things that does is it allows us to
see the pain more clearly so we can be wiser about what to do with
it and there's lots of options so it might be that we should take an aspirin
it might be that we should ignore it and it might be that we should
you know really bring careful attention to really feel it closely and intimately there's so
many choices you know but whatever but you first have to stop long enough
to check it out so anyway that's my response to that
question so okay
so maybe that's enough you know i kind of feel like
i just gave you a hot potato and now you have it to practice it
and hopefully you get dharmically warmed by it in a nice
way thank you very much