there okay so hello and welcome everyone hello and
welcome to this rendition of happy hour lovely to be with you
in this on zoomland youtubeland or if you're joining later and listening to
this we on audiodharma we appreciate you so
so for today's practice theme of metta
there's this little story that came up to my my mind and i wanted to share that
to set the stage um the story of
of um as i remember it um
someone walking on the beach and and uh picking up
starfish and throwing them back into the ocean so they would dry out and they would survive as as the
conditions were such that that was a possibility and maybe it was hot or whatever it was
and there were thousands of starfish on the beach and the friends seeing this
person picking them one by one and throwing them in the ocean says there are
thousands of starfish what are you doing this is madness you know but you're doing this doesn't make any difference
and the person who's doing this act of service says well it makes a difference to the starfish i'm throwing back
so i've loved that story i've loved that story because even if at times
it seems like oh how can our acts of kindness acts of service act so just
listening to one person giving or caring ear or not losing our temper just this
once just this this little tiny act of kindness like ah what difference does it
make just the world is so overwhelming by challenges but it makes a difference
of course it makes a difference it makes a difference to the starfish to that one starfish
it makes a difference to the that person we're not losing our temper with or being kind with or or patient with or
that person we're saying hello to um so many stories like this
um [Music] say you go for a walk and
you smile to someone who's looking down and looks stressed maybe it's a neighbor who's walking by you walking past you
you just smile at them maybe this is the gift the only human interaction they
have throughout the day it's another story i'm now remembering just echoes and vestiges of
it and just trying to find it but the story of of how simple human
kindness is of just a smile just a kind world have been instrumental and really have
kept other people going without the giver ever realizing that the simple act
of kindness the simple act of service that they were sharing was really so
profound really so um sustaining the other person's
connection to life connection to life so do not underestimate
the power of throwing one starfish back into the ocean one starfish
one starfish one starfish
so that's the theme for our our practice tonight and i'd like to guide us in may
in a meditation um meditation with that in mind and again if you're new to
this practice um there's nothing that you need to know what ahead of time whatever you need
will be shared with you and um yeah let's
let's start let's start practicing together so like to invite you to get into your
meditation posture whatever that might be for you
sitting lying down standing
all fine postures of meditation
and allowing yourself to arrive in this body
really arrive and if you need to move and shift locations just get a sense of oh i'm
here hello body hi coming into your center coming into
yourself your senses i invite you to do what is needed
for you to reconnect with your body in this moment
ah landing landing releasing
lacing
your heart first of all releasing your heart letting it feel safe
it's okay it's okay whatever is happening whatever has happened today it's okay
offering kindness safety support to yourself a safe space
releasing your hands the weight of them
noticing how alive the energy in the hands are
alive alert and yet relaxed ah
let them drop their weight drop the weight of your
wrists
elbows shoulders
releasing your forehead notice if your forehead is tense or
tight release
soften is there tension in your jaw
releasing [Music] the weight of your upper body make
shoulders drunk to your sit bones
releasing the weight of your legs onto the earth
let the breath move through your body
through the abdomen
this breath a gift it matters to you
to this body this oxygen this breath makes a difference
to this starfish that you are
ah so if you're starfish back in the ocean
lid here
starfish limbs relax soft be soft and receive
the breath as if it were the waves in the ocean
this wave
and this wave
this breath
now this breath
and if thoughts arise thoughts that take you into the past or future it's okay
as if you're calling back a beloved not with judgment
calling back your beloved puppy that is your mind come sweetheart rest
rest rest just this breath
place of refuge
and can we see this moment of sitting here caring for ourselves
by sitting breathing in meditation
as a moment of care it's an expression of care
it's an expression of love for ourselves
attending to our deepest
highest needs
reconnecting with the kindness at our core at our center
simply through sitting breathing caring
refuge finding making refuge
if you like to experiment putting a palm in your
heart center middle of your chest sort of connecting with yourself
this act of kindness here here dear here
right here it's okay right here not complicated
can be very simple
simply sitting and breathing
if you like to add the phrases of menta
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may my life flow with ease
all the support that makes a difference for this starfish
knowing that no matter how far and wide you look
all around the buddha has said you won't find
anyone it's more deserving of your own kindness
sharing goodwill
may this being who is me this starfish this being [Music]
it's a lie sentient being that is me
may they be safe from harm
just offering this wish not clinging to the outcome just offering this
sense of goodwill to yourself without clinging
fully knowing that world isn't safe in every way but you offer this wish as
the gesture of goodwill
may i may this being who's me be happy
may there be joy in my heart
may this being who is me this starfish
may they be healthy
and well as much as possible
may this being that is me the starfish
have ease
ease in their life is the conditions
fully knowing that life has challenges and yet offering this good will
generously
offering it freely letting it light in your heart these wishes they're not hammers
not pounding them ah
offering them lightheartedly
just as if you were throwing a starfish back into the ocean with a sense of good will with kindness
oh dear starfish may you be safe may you be happy
may you be well may there be easeful conditions for you there i'll throw you back into the ocean
with metta it's the same gesture of the heart
it's free it's easy it's light-hearted
imagine you are a starfish you're throwing yourself back into the ocean with kindness
with goodwill
now in your imagination you're picking up the starfish that is
you and throwing it into the ocean picking up other starfish
other starfish in some ways they are both you you could have been these starfish
also there are other other beings and wishing them well
they're beings in your life friends family
strangers
sharing your kindness your good will your service lightheartedly
without attachment to outcome doesn't have to be perfect or complete
just a little bit of kindness a little act of goodwill
maybe you can't maybe you consider the meta
wishes may you be well for starting with safe may you be safe
the people in your life or strangers may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have peace
and i'd like to invite you if you would
to consider one act of kindness that you received
recently today this past week this past month
something that was kind maybe a small gesture
the first thing that pops up in your mind is fine maybe it was last year or a decade ago it doesn't
matter let yourself feel the appreciation the
goodness this act of kindness has made to you
appreciating appreciating the kindness the goodwill the meta
letting yourself receive it from this being [Music]
whoever was kind to you
it is the act of matter act of goodwill maybe phone call maybe a helping hand
breathe it in
saver
appreciating the goodness the impact of this act of kindness
for you you the starfish one starfish
and bowing to that kindness act of kindness and its
impact its ramifications in your life
small or large and now i'd like to invite you
to consider an act of kindness meta
but you shared with someone else
maybe you were a helping hand you offered a helping hand or
patient ear whatever it might have been
now let yourself feel the nourishment of this kindness
this goodness let it glad in your heart
feeling the impact the appreciation of the other
first the starfish you threw this one starfish
you threw once into the ocean
breathing in breathing out
appreciating the interdependence in this kindness
letting your heart be buoyed uplifted
not a time to remember all the previous wrongdoings remember kindness
let your heart be glad maybe a smile shows up on your face welcome it
we are all starfish and we all have the capacity
to throw one starfish back into the ocean
so as we bring this practice period to close
offering offering the goodness
of our practice together
touching into kindness intentions of kindness recollecting kindness
turning our hearts our minds our mind stream towards kindness the
benefits the gifts appreciation of it this is time well spent
whatever you frequently ponder and reflect upon becomes the
inclination of your mind says the buddha
so we reflect together on kindness so that it becomes
the inclination of our hearts and minds
may all beings everywhere all starfish all starfish
hypothetical physical imaginal including ourselves the
starfish may all beings everywhere
be safe happy healthy of eats may they be free
[Music]
thank you all thank you thank you for your practice
so dear starfish and starfish throwers both
we have some time for reflections you're welcome to raise your zoom hand
you're also welcome to type them in chat if you type them to everyone i'll read
your name if you just type them to me they will be
private and if you raise your physical hand i will not see you because there are many of us here
and pat says on youtube the star thrower was written by lauren eisley in the unexpected universe and
extraordinary man thank you for that reference pat lovely great
appreciate giving credit where credit is due
ah jennifer says though that was so incredibly beautiful thank you
thank you jennifer you're welcome and thank you for your practice
ah i feel like a starfish it's kind of fun to feel like a starfish pointy right
being thrown throwing udders this was a fun practice
not just profound but also fun it's good when practice is both and of course
some things may not have worked for you um so which is perfectly fine so any
questions any reflections offered
are all welcome any complaints
so as i don't see any reflections now
popping up i will invite us if something wants to pop up it's okay
can still come um i invite us to consider
to enter little little oceans little tide pools
in small groups in small groups of three and consider the the uh
each other as starfish and offering kindness offering kindness
offering kindness to ourselves to each other and the question reflection is what was
this practice like for you what came up whatever you like to share from your
first person experience and um
[Music] not managing not questioning not
you know guiding the group but just really from your own experience whatever you like to share
sharing one thing and then the next person will share one thing or they'll share silence say i'll pass i'll hold
silence today perfectly fine no expectation all welcome the third person will say something and
they'll come back to you so you'll go around a few times
question is is it possible to listen to recording later it really touched my heart listening oh absolutely this
recording is going to be available on audiodharma.org
also it will be available on the imc youtube channel both of those and um if
you go to my website uh nikkimergaforie.com
under teachings under happier all these links
to both audiodharma as well as the youtube channel are there as well as
on imc website that's also there uh maybe a little more complicated to
maneuver anyway okay i'm going to create the breakout rooms
and take care of yourselves take care of each other um you're all starfish tender starfish
so let's let's be kind let's be kind oh
also neil says i'll also email the links for the recordings okay thank you neil
so if you join the google groups the links will be mailed to you all
right i'm going to open the groups here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back
welcome back everyone and we have a few minutes for uh
for any reflections that might have arisen from uh practicing
either with the guided meditation or with practicing a community
meditating community so
what what came up the spirit of sharing with others and
supporting um our reflections can support others reflections
diana is your hand there
this is my starfish painting i'm i do watercolor i'm a student this
bit of a glare i'm sorry uh he's sunning himself
and from a stock photo of tidal pools in northern california
and i entered it in the student show this just happened a couple of months ago so
here's the ego coming out but i just had to show it to you i love
are lighting up and thumbs up our lighting and people are loving your starfish painting diana thanks for
sharing that in our group in our group we talked a lot about
the things we remember just all the various kindnesses and our appreciation for the
the um for this theme today and we were just some of us were remembering
just all the various good things and kindnesses just daily
that's it beautiful thank you for sharing your starfish diana both metaphorical and and
literal painting of it thank you i couldn't believe it okay thank you sweet thank you
it's great and michelle says this is way out of context for the
larger group but a mantra i use when i feel a negative emotion arising is these
feelings are inside me and someone's actions triggered me uh actually triggered them i have the
power to ignite these feelings or not that is that's true yes it is out of context and you michel and yes i
appreciate the um yeah the the way that you're supporting yourself with uh with with this mantra
yeah yeah any other effect jerry
real quick uh i would say uh um i was in medical i i was in uh
beef college before i went off to uh professional school and i was working
for the police and the intelligence unions and another student was with me from high school and
uh found this suicide note that bliss had collected and in it i would never forgot these
words i felt intrusive upon he was intruded upon the suicide note but only to say that
he had been ridiculed in high school and my mother had asked me to reach out and protect them which i did and in the
suicide note he mentioned that i never forgot that
and he said that he even said maybe he did this because my mother was talking about this i did but it reminded me you
never know the effect of kindness oh
so this has been very helpful to remind me that i don't know the
effect on others but it can be quite hormones yeah
thank you jerry thank you for for sharing that that
moving reflection wow yeah
exactly you never know the impact of your your act of kindness
yeah thank you all that's a profound note
from a story and from real life experience or one of you to to
end on to really appreciate that and to continue to throw starfish into the ocean and also let
yourself be thrown let yourself be thrown appreciate the goodness of kindness that's offered
by others and keep keep throwing starfish so thank you all thank you dear starfish
and starfish throwers for your practice for being here and cultivating your heart
may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music] thanks everyone
be well