so hello everyone and welcome to our meditation session
and we are coming to the end of the week where we're focusing on
the teachings on the five groupings areas that we tend to cling to
some ideas some people say these are the five five ways of grouping the ways humans
cling what humans cling to and um
which is a fascinating idea and the last one is people cling to
consciousness at least that's the english way of translating vinyana
the pali word and for now i want to say two things about
it as we meditate one is the highlight the miracle
of being conscious miracle of being of knowing what's happening in the present
moment it's possible to know something that we
are remembering and we can be lost in the memory
but to really know oh this is memory to really know this is thinking
to really know this is a feeling this is a sensation this is a thought
to know it with some clarity it's a miracle
how did we you know evolution lead us to this kind of clear kind of capacity to know something
and in mindfulness practice what we know is what is obvious
to be searching and clinging searching and stretching and analyzing for what's
what's really happening is not the path of mindfulness the path of mindfulness is
to appreciate the simple capacity to know what's obvious
it's almost like the capacity to know that happens
independent of our volition
if we are relaxed at ease if we're stable and centered here and
now what a phenomenal thing to be conscious to be knowing what's
happening and to watch the arising of that knowing in the present moment
happen in a certain kind of way effortlessly
it's a wonderful thing and then for that knowing
to be wise to that knowing to see clearly what's there
and not be fooled by it into clinging to it holding on to it an ancient analogy is
someone has a counterfeit coin is made and someone has the and
so someone someone tries to give a counterfeit coin to pay for something and the merchant
sees it as you know recognizes that the coin really sees it as a coin but sees it as a counterfeit coin
this is not you know real this is not to be accepted and um
so it isn't that things are not real but but the the the clear cognizance
that oh this is not something to cling to
so it's a kind of higher order uh concept understanding recognition of
what's happening that involves some clarity
oh it's kind of like it's aware of itself it's knowing
that knows that it's knowing
and it's knowing that might that has enough wisdom in it
to either cling to what we're knowing not enough wisdom so it clings
or wisdom so it doesn't cling so how is it for you to
be knowing your experience can it be obvious the obvious can it be
simple relaxed and in the knowing can there be a sense of feeling
intuition that that in the present you're knowing this is knowing
whatever it is you know you you kind of know this is knowing like you're walking
and you know this i'm walking now
and then is there wisdom or lack of wisdom in that knowing the lack of wisdom is that which
when knowing is reactive with wisdom it's knowing which
doesn't react doesn't cling it doesn't resist just knows
knows better than to cling so
taking a long deep breath
and maybe in deep inhale and as you exhale maybe a audible ah
here you are
[Music]
gently close your eyes
and feel the sensations of your body
each sensation you experience is evidence of life
evidence of the animated force of life by vitality
and here you are maybe the whole field of the body
feeling it for a few moments the whole vitality as it appears a whole
shimmering vibrating pulsing body
knowing the animated quality of the body
as you exhale to relax the shoulders
soften into the torso
relaxing the hands and the arms the fingers
relaxing the belly settling in the whole lower torso
releasing
on the exhale softening in the face
the eyes cheeks the jaw
as if their muscles
can relax away from the skull and gently be held by this sack of skin
and relaxing the thinking mind maybe first by
thinking more slowly calmly
and maybe also by relaxing any tension pressure in the thinking mind
and then to
find something in your body that's relatively neutral to be aware of since
some sensation like breathing or anything else
and feel it know it in the obvious way
no need to analyze it or figure it out just the simplest knowing
of breathing of sensation
and maybe little maybe just lightly a marveling
at the capacity to know
and as you know the breathing really know it
can you also know
that it's not something to cling to to grasp at to be
reactive to it just can be known
where there's no effort to know it's that simple it's more like attention
opens a window in the mind in the direction of
breathing and the breathing
is evident
if your mind wanders off in thought when you first wonder off
when you first notice that you're wandered off
be content to know it obviously
this is thinking and marvel at the capacity to know
the marvel before reacting or clinging
judging just knowing
and then open the curtains in the mind
to allow yourself to experience breathing again
and what is the obvious experience of breathing which the mind knows
where the knowing is not effortful
but there's a marvel at the fact that there is knowing
the moments of knowing come and go
we know one thing and then we know it's next thing and then something else
we know one thing and then we find ourselves knowing it again a second time and a third time
a relaxed mind that's present knows
very simple maybe the simplest knowing possible
and we know that we know
the simple knowing of what's happening
can be kind of like beginning to slip as you walk across the floor
and then you catch yourself maybe a wet spot and you
not a dramatic slip but just enough you catch yourself so you find yourself slipping into thoughts
and reactions and the knowing is the catching oneself
oh this is what's happening
without then getting involved in knowing or adding to the knowing
just the simplest knowing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
how simple can you allow there to be a moment of
knowing if you don't need don't need to know
anything in particular what's happening what's the direct experience of the moment now what's
really present that you can know and very simply
not being for or against it
without needing to think about it
just know
and can that knowing that simplicity of knowing
be a medium for knowing another person
where another person is allowed to be who they are
our knowing does not interfere with them does not
see them through the filter of our history or memory or
ideas just the simplest knowing of a person
it can be a gift to know
without interfering with others without judging them or needing them to be
different without fearing them just knowing
the gift is the gift of allowing them to be who they are
it's a kind of a gift of freedom of peace
maybe people will not recognize the gift
but you will may it be that this practice we do
is a practice that allows us to give the gift of kindness
freedom peace safety to others
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
and may this practice of ours contribute to the welfare and happiness of others
[Music]
so hello and we come to the fifth and final talk on the five
groupings the five kandas aggregates
and um so this is the an exercise in the
discourse on the four foundations for awareness for cultivating a kind of lucid clear
present moment awareness and um
we come the last one is conscious is usually translated into english as consciousness
and uh it's very likely that that is not the best choice as an english translation
uh partly because i think very few people either know what consciousness is
or people who study consciousness can agree on i think there's so many different
opinions and ideas and efforts to try to pin down what consciousness is
interestingly enough it was not a task of people
it's only for the last probably for only the last 200 years or so
the way the modern usage of the word consciousness is relatively recent
and and so and then around that concept has
gathered these different ideas or associations the pali word is vinyana
and it's a word that existed in india before the buddha but it seems to have under have meant
things like these many translators of the ancient hindu upanishadic texts will translate as understanding
even sometimes as intellect the
buddha very rarely defines it and it's possible that the um
the the word vignana is used in different ways in different contexts which makes
it a little bit more difficult to pin it down to what it is
the um in the these five kandas five aggregates
it seems to be a um a um ability
to differentiate knowing that differentiates
so to know you know if you're looking down at a
bowl full of mixed beans red beans black beans white beans
pinto beans all kinds of things the ability to recognize
the distinct kinds of beans from each other to separate out rather than one big blur
of beans separate out this this this so the buddha was talked about being
able to differentiate between consciousness is what differentiates between salty and not salty
bitter and sweet this does not very satisfying for modern english audience that has a
little more grand idea of what consciousness is but it seems to be
a kind of heightened knowing clear knowing
of direct experience and now it's it's related to the third
grouping the sanya or recognition consent the concept we have it's related
to that but maybe it's either can be more primitive prior to the concepts we had on top of
things and um or and it kind of heightened clarity
uh where we know more more with with understanding what's happening
so the ancient analogy that um
someone might a child might be given a counterfeit coin and simply recognize it as a coin
not realize it's counterfeit a merchant who's expert on how people counterfeit coins will immediately
recognize that's a counterfeit coin and so the recognition that it's a coin is
there but it's a heightened with clarity of knowing to not this is not real or this is not what we do
so the buddha talked about there's these six kinds of consciousness
there is the consciousness which is the knowing uh that we happens when we see so so see knowing
through seeing knowing through ear hearing knowing through smelling tasting knowing through the tactile experience of the body
and knowing what's going in the mind and rather than calling them all-knowing
it's so it's a six distinct kind of knowing the six consciousness or six spinanas
and now this is in contrast to what some meditators some people
some even some spiritual traditions will emphasize what consciousness is as a kind of a
continuous unitary field of knowing
that they did we're always consciousness always there everything is coming and going everything impermanent but it's
all occurring on this kind of screen of um oh that's always there or like you know
the consciousness is like if it was like the ocean then everything else is just the
the rain falling on the ocean temporarily there it's um the waves coming and going on the
ocean but the ocean itself is always there and just under the surface is vast and still and quiet
um the um the buddha seems not to have
emphasized this kind of consciousness whatsoever and in fact the more i think the
the um i believe more the kind of buddhist kind of at least the theravadin buddhists their early buddhist
understanding of with this would be that um the mind there is a con the mind is a
constructing activity and whatever this consciousness is that is emphasized in the fifth
aggregate is part of this constructed activity it's not innate it's not inherent it's
not always there it doesn't go from one life to it to another it is something also that comes and goes
arises and passes and and in its arising it's partly a
construct of mental functioning it's a condition of mental functioning as
opposed to something which is independent of the vagaries and changing nature of the mind
itself and certainly in this fifth exercise of sati patana of of the aggregates
what the meditator is meant to see is that this consciousness or this kind of
knowing appears and disappears
appears and passes away and so what we're looking at it is something that's changeable and
impermanent and constant and so what kind of consciousness is that way
and what kind of knowing and how is that different from you know recognition
and uh so i've suggested in the meditation that it's a very simple
very very simple but very clear so that there's a knowing
it's what knows all the other aggregates it knows there's a sensation it knows
there's a feeling tone it knows that there's a recognition happening at this moment it
knows that there's mental constructs happening and it knows that it knows
and you can do kind of can get caught up in influen infinite regress of knowing
knowing that i know that i know but don't bother with that just kind of very simple relaxed
and then that kind of knowing a sound arises there's a knowing of a sound that arises with the sound
when the sound goes maybe the knowing goes or maybe if the knowing goes faster if we get distracted
by something else there's uh we see something we hear it
we taste something we touch something we think something we feel something and with each of that there's a knowing
that arises a simple knowing that's and and the important aspect is not exactly
what consciousness is what exactly all this is but rather
whatever way in which we know there's a recognition that it comes and
goes that it's not constant it's not permanent and as we start seeing it's
in constant nature then we will not cling to it that's the hope that's the direction we're going
and so consciousness also can be an object of clinging and sometimes people can
easily let go of all things except consciousness if they're strongly identified with consciousness as being their true self
as this is who i am and this is how i survive this is how i uh you know will always exist or
something and um and uh the deeper the pasta practice
goes the less we less we can recognize or find
this kind of continuous ever-present field of
consciousness because everything is seen is just in its in its momentary aspect coming and
going and um and um
and whether there is a consciousness which is persists and over time in a sense that's not so very
interesting for early buddhism to specify um whether it is or not what's important is
in our direct experience as we practice deeper and deeper we won't find it
that does not mean we have to decide there is none it just means we don't find it and the purpose for not finding
it is so that we will let go of clinging to it and we're trying to let go of all
clinging and so the functional aspect of this practice is all about the end of clinging not to
come to philosophical conclusion about what consciousness is or isn't
so so that just in terms of what consciousness is or isn't
what i'm talking about today just just barely scratches the surface of a fascinating concept but i hope that it
gives you just enough information ideas of practicing to
somehow begin appreciating um the miracle of knowing
in the simple ways knowing hearing seeing tasting touching
um smelling and then the mind knowing the mind knowing things and then seeing how when
objects or experiences arise in these six cent stores they come and they go and the knowing of
it comes and goes sometimes the knowing comes and goes faster than the object
and that knowing can be very relaxed easeful just being with what's obvious
and free of all the self-referencing where we get tripped up where we slip
where we get caught where we suffer
and uh we're pointing here to a simplicity of being with our all our senses all our
experience but very very simple and uh and free
so thank you and uh we'll continue we have three more
exercises to do before we finish this uh the four foundations of mindfulness
and um and uh so next week we'll do the
uh the six sense bases and the fetters the knots that get formed around them
so thank you