good morning funga good morning online Sangha
greetings from Rainey Redwood City
and I'm loving seeing the weather reports local rain snow
cloudy
please feel free to share your weather Wherever You Are we're celebrating rain in our very dry
Northern California I'm confident that's not everywhere
we've got Chile Seattle
it's a cloudy a few minutes ago
and cold in Stafford Virginia biting me cold in the Heartland I believe it's
chilly and damp lovely to see all the warm greetings in
the midst of the cold damp or wet
[Music] bright and crisp and Glenside
Pennsylvania
sunny and cold lake effect clear and cold
cool and clear
so very happy to be here with all of you this morning
I love the little greetings the anecdotes the warmth of this Sangha it's really something
so we are at the top of the hour and
just want to invite you when you're ready to um turn your
attention from the weather report rolling in from all over the place
to the internal weather the internal weather of your body heart
and mind so you can do that by settling back and closing your eyes maybe you aren't quite
done with the chat but you just want to tune in you can share it if you like
before you settle in
men settling into a posture that will
support you for the next half hour
opening your awareness to the quality of the larger atmospherics around you
whether it's rain or sun or wind or damp
I'm feeling yourself embodied embodied within that larger
system atmosphere
and feeling into the sensations of this body
this moment internally
the overall sense of warmth are cool
relaxation aliveness
maybe weights or lightness
breathing out any excess energy or attention
and paying special attention just for a moment to your head to your
face allowing the eyes to soften in their
sockets perhaps
to gently roll down and back just a little bit this invokes a global
relaxation response
and also allowing the tongue to relax that soften
vest in your mouth however works for you
for me and for many people it's helpful to have the tip of the tongue
gently resting on the front of the palate that area of the roof of the mouth right behind your top teeth
and that can allow the rest of the tongue just to relax
another signal to soften the overall system
[Music] feeling your feet your seat your body
rooted held
held by the gravity of the Earth supported by the Earth
checking in now with the overall atmospherics
of mood just in a general
broad brush overall way how's the heart how's the mind today
can be an act of love to check in with that
acknowledging whatever's there
and settling settling into really allowing awareness mindfulness to
be at the Forefront of attention
360 Degrees all around you within you
thank you
perhaps resting the attention Awareness on the breath
if there are sounds effect of external weather ambient sounds of any kind
allowing that to to be an anchor and attention
gentle movements of rain or shifting sound of wind
distant sounds from outside
spaciousness allowing
resting resting on the gentle waves of arising
and passing away of sensation of breathing
experience of sound or sensation
[Music]
allowing the attention the awareness to rest In This Moment
to find the attention called are you specific
stronger arising maybe a sound sensation
internal mental or emotional process
turning all of the attention to the fact of that arising
acknowledging it kindly
and with the acknowledgment either staying with it
as an event in this moment
or as it fades or the Mind loses interest
returning the attention to the global awareness overall awareness
perhaps including breathing overall sensation
sound
so compensation internal processes to come and go
no need to get involved no need to be for or against
no need for judgment just noticing
allowing
being with
[Music] any more instruments of this meditation
together tuning in
to any calm or spaciousness
any peace relaxation even just a tiny corner
tiny drop that may have appeared emerged in this meditation
and tuning into the good qualities cultivated in this practice
perhaps patience persistence engagement
Stillness or collectiveness compassion self-compassion
kindness whatever good qualities
have been cultivated or experienced
imagining others in your life near and far
with whom they might be shared just in a way of being or a simple
intention
sharing increases these good qualities for everyone
and it feels right allowing these beneficial good intentions to flow
outwards towards those your life touches
May the goodness cultivated in our practice together here
be shared with the others in our lives and by the
sharing continue to radiate outwards
and further outward still may all beings
be safe may all beings be happy
may all beings be healing
may they be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you for the dedication the sincerity of your practice
foreign
the topic for this morning is again one of five bases for
cultivating spiritual power and um
this species basis is um
combination of again engagement
or padahana wholehearted engagement and in this case chitta quality or
subjective experience of the mind and heart and
again those two help to form collectedness immersion
stability concentration samadhi all of those are kind of
um synonyms or different translations of the words
so I have three main points to cover this morning
in the first overarching point really if you take nothing else from these 15
minutes it's that the quality of our minds and hearts
though the quality of that and that thought that emerges from it can Define our practice and it can Define Our Lives
and this this is most easily seen in meditation practice from me and
sometimes you know moments that it will pop in in daily life too of course
so it's helpful to learn to notice that's point one point two
and three are sort of subsets it's ways of noticing and the first kind of thing
but some of us can tune into you might find that you tune into is the overall
state of the Mind in any given moment and this is kind of like the
atmospherics that overall ecology or soundscape happening in your system
the second way is to tune into the kind of thoughts that are emerging and I don't so much
mean the story of the thoughts though that can be very important but the underlying quality
so I'll talk about that more in a minute so first the quality of the mind and
heart quality of thoughts how we relate to experience
I'm going to ask you again to kind of feel into these as I talk about them
and I'll give you another word cloud for the poly this comes from
a number of different translators mind
mental processes mental development
heart or heart mind state of consciousness
you just feel into those so far any associations coming up
overall awareness
kind of like the overall atmospherics
and then my personal favorite comes from the um very prolific early translator
Caroline Augusta fully rise Davids she calls chitta the subjective
experience of mind
a subjective experience of mind so this overall subjective experience
it's as I mentioned kind of like the overall weather the overall front here
in the Bay area of rain and the kind of overall
atmospherics you might experience in a soundscape
another way I've thought of it in the past that's been helpful is if the mind is spinning up movies for
those of us that are visual what's the tint or the color theme in the movie
or what's the general mood of the soundtrack not the words not the dialogue
feel
so this is such a helpful sort of um part of experience to tune
into that it actually has its own foundation in the Buddha's famous teaching the four foundations of
mindfulness one of the Central teachings of this tradition of Buddhism and perhaps of most if not all
traditions and that third Foundation is an amusing Guild franstal's translation here of
this discourse observation of mind
and there are certain things that are helpful to notice you don't have to like dig around for them but just notice them
one is and I'm just going to read a few of the paraphrases of the phrases from
this section one knows a mind with craving as a mind
with craving and a mind without craving as a mind
without craving one knows a mind with ill will as a mind
with ill will in the mind without ill will as without
ill will one knows a mind with delusion has a
mind with delusion and a mind without delusion as a mind without delusion in
other words Clarity or wisdom and one knows a mind
that is collected as collected
and a mind that is scattered as scattered
so that could be distraction collected of course is that stability that Stillness
Focus samadhi one knows an expanded mind as an
expanding mind or spacious mind you could call it and a
not expanded mind as a not expected mine and it goes on from there
just to give you a flavor this is General and it doesn't have to be something you
even look for but every now and then if things are going really tough in a meditation
or if they're going really really well just to check in what's the quality of the mind and heart
right now the shortcut that um teacher I've
followed now for some years his teachings said is is there tension in the mind or
relaxation or for me it's often helpful on shortcut
is it helpful or not helpful
suggest these are possibilities you don't have to go looking for them digging for them
but allowing them to emerge to be seen
so an example here let's say you go to visit someone who's
having a really hard time to support them to be with them beautiful thing to do right
there's a big difference during and afterwards between tuning into the
compassion and the care in your own heart or maybe the appreciation for them
and versus criticizing or blaming yourself for any little misstep or imperfection
of how it went the same thing goes for showing up for
ourselves in meditation right acknowledging what's happening without
putting on extra layers that aren't so helpful
so in meditation it's helpful just to notice the shortcut for all of this is just notice the overall mood notice the
overall tone and that tone that mood can feel so
authoritative that it's really worth remembering that the chitta this subjective quality
of mind it can change faster than a finger snap
we've all experienced that some new event happens a new person a memory
a realization and our mood goes from one thing to completely other
just like faster than a finger snap
the last area I'll cover just briefly is to notice the different types of thought
arising and this can be the kind of attitudes of
thought that I talked about earlier in Bill's translation of the third Foundation but there can also be
qualities of the mental activity itself and there are two qualities of
particular that are helpful in cultivating the idipada the basics for
meditative success and spiritual power and that is
the quality of directed attention at whatever your central object of attention anchor
of attention for the meditation is so that's like
the striker hitting the gong of the Bell and the other quality is a sustaining
quality like the fade of the Bell I'll just do it now so if you just connect it'll be a clunk
like that if you connect and sustain it's like
this [Music]
foreign there's this capacity to be with be near
what is being attended to that continues
you can think of this in terms of yesterday's topic of effort too every now and then a little pulse of
connecting and then this long sustaining it's like pushing a child on a swing
you don't need to be pushing the whole time the swing swings
so this is very helpful quality of Mind
each of these are very helpful qualities of mind for deepening immersion stability in the
meditation and again nothing that needs to be made to happen or dug for
but just noticing encourage you to notice in your life when you connect when your attention
naturally connects with something and stays with it for a while
okay so to recap chitta your subjective experience of the heart
and mind is one of the really crucial helpful qualities to notice in
cultivating a deepening of meditation practice the overall attitude quality
atmospherics of heart and mind the overall
sense of weather atmosphere presence and absence of skillful and
unskillful healthy and unhealthy qualities and these kinds of thoughts or types of
mental activity so in the next 24 hours if it feels right
just notice these in your life or in your practice maybe talk about them with a friend
and I'll look forward to seeing you at least in the chat or in my mind's eye tomorrow in YouTube
thank you for your practice