so uh so welcome welcome all it's nice to see the the
names and of those uh streaming over there with the uh the comments
um yeah so let's um let's practice together
so taking some full deep breaths
there's almost like a sense of especially on the exhale
kind of wave ripple of relaxation
that smooths out the energy of the body
so this kind of breathing we're making sure that breath gets into our belly
letting her belly be soft
letting our face be soft
area around the eyes the jaw
shoulders hanging loosely
the hands untensed
suffering usually arises as a kind of increase
density somewhere in body mind
and so we breathe in such a way
that smoothes out
the energy of body mind
we're we're not asking our breath to resolve the complications of our life
predicament of any human life
we're just using the soothing ripple
of the exhalation so as to suffer a little less right now
to bring tranquility
and a brightness right now
it's okay to put down the rest of our lives
just for this time
affect kind of emotional circuits
in our body or the the engine of so much
thinking
the kind of pool of energy increased density
in our body and this seems to necessitate
thought
we need to it's like our mind needs to understand
this little whirlpool of density in our body and our feeling
life yeah and
and our practice often
is just to smooth out the energy of our body
to breathe into it patiently
to commit to being softened by intensity rather than hardened by it
as we meet our bodies its densities
with this awareness and care
the whole realm of thinking
feels less urgent
just lavishing a kind of love awareness on your body
using the breath if that's helpful
in unifying the field of the body smoothing out
the densities
[Music]
okay
so quote so far as we are mere bundles of habit
we are imitators and copiers of our past selves
it follows first of all that the teachers prime concern
should be to ingrain into the pupil that assortment of habits that shall be
most useful to them throughout life education is for behavior
and habits are the stuff of which behavior consists
the great thing in all education is to make our nervous system
our ally instead of our enemy
it's william james
so yesterday we
explored helplessness and power
opening opening the heart to helplessness illuminates our power
and today another pair renunciation
and passion so
the fantasy of something for nothing
runs deep in my mind you know
like sometimes i'll notice i'll just randomly look down at the sidewalk
to see if someone dropped money there you know like the thrill
of something for nothing runs deep
but mindfulness is not something for nothing
it is a path of relinquishment
and we don't exactly
get to have the dharma and have our life
we don't exactly get to have the dharma and our life but i want my life i want my dreams and
my stories and my pleasures and my routines my habits
and i want the dharma but um
i don't know i don't think we can have it all that might be
a kind of american fantasy of buddhism
on renunciation the fact that the buddha was a monk gets
lost of course people are free to practice as they want nonetheless many western
dharma centers seem to marginalize but to the rest of the buddhist world is central and historically vital to the
whole process of dharma practice and enlightenment it's like opening up the chest attaching
all the veins and arteries carefully removing the heart and maintaining the body on a life support system
one can't help wonder is this thing really alive is this going to carry on
obviously my perspective is slanted
a card carrying monk but in wedging dharma teachings into a
comfortable life one may be missing something that's crucial to the dharma
i would suggest that people look closely at that is the dharma something that i tack onto
my life or is it something that i offer myself up to
i've always loved that phrase um it's the dharma something we
tack on or offer ourselves up to
we fear impoverishment in letting go
but as we let go as we let go the
the whole in the center of our being gets smaller
yeah the hole in the center of our being gets smaller we need less to fill it up in other
words as we relinquish as we let go this actually frees us up
and we know that we can let go we know we can let go and so we're not afraid
or less afraid of not having what we like
i think we uh
practitioners um are perhaps a little too vigilant about
pleasure you know it's like um at the slightest sign of pleasure we say
to ourselves kind of like oh my goodness like don't get attached don't get attached yeah
and so there's a certain kind of almost defensiveness against pleasure
in our practice in our lives
as we train we know we can let go and we're less afraid
about holding on we know we can just let go
again an attachment in the end is not uh it's
not a sin it's just tuka yeah
i remember um a friend uh a kind of wild brilliant dharma friend
um emphasis on wild you know saying uh
that the meditative path is um parasympathetically biased
biased towards the the tranquilizing side
but this path is enlivens and brightens us
rather than flattens us
and all this letting go this renunciation
frees us up to enjoy pleasure and goodness more completely
it's um it frees us up to enjoy pleasure more completely
and so sometimes we we make the distinction between
um craving and desire tanha
chanda um and tanja that craving is that kind of
bottomless thirst the fever dream of longing that's never actually
satisfied yeah and so sometimes i
say like craving is our frenemy yeah as the kids say
craving is our frenemy but what distinguishes desire from
craving is that desire can actually be satisfied
in desire and longing we're actually not asking too much of pleasure
we're asking just right
now this path is a path of dismantling craving
but as we do that as we work to dismantle
tanha sometimes chanda gets squashed too
and as we uh as we let go some of the driveness the
desperation around pleasure is gone
and so we can actually enjoy we can actually enjoy
now i talk about um um
equanimity with unpleasantness a lot yeah it is a this is a path of
purification and it reveres the wholesome unpleasant
the wholesome unpleasant has a kind of reverential place on this path
but what does equanimity with pleasure look like
we're being asked to have equanimity with that too and i would say equanimity with pleasure
looks like a very uncomplicated intense
delight and satisfaction it looks like
enjoyment without compulsivity
and um do we still prefer pleasure over pain of
course but um our heart is more
flexible less dependent less reliant on budgeting
pleasure in the usual ways we do
and even even egoic pleasure yeah
uh we're not defended against that either we feel that that feels better than
insults yeah or yeah we we're not defended against it
nor are we entangled in it you know
a big part of dharma is um
about um d shaming suffering
pain we were so moralistic anytime we feel
feel pain or kind of run into the first noble truth we're moralistic about it we
make it mean something about our being and so a lot of dharma practice is about
d shaming pain but it's also about d shaming
pleasure
and it's a tender zone for exploration because we are
exposed in our desire we are exposed in our pleasure
in our dependence and our need and our longing we're less self-contained and
more there's a vulnerability in that too
if we're we're doing this consciously
and um we start to
to free ourselves up to loosen up we become alive in our pleasure we ask our
pleasure only to do what it can do and not more
and so this gesture of relinquishment of renunciation of simplicity
actually frees us up in some
deep ways to to enjoy to enjoy deeply
and when pleasure comes pleasure comes it is satiating
it supports us it provides a kind of um
yeah sort of resource from which we can draw when
our next task is to have equanimity with
the inevitable difficulties of a human life
so relinquishment frees us up to enjoy
offer this uh for your consideration and pick up what's useful leave the rest
behind i'm gonna go check over there
on the uh chat which i saw was active during
his comments see what's happening