so again welcome welcome everybody nice to see you all
the air conditioning just went on i'll just say that this room ends up having a little bit of micro climates
it comes out right there and so if if the air conditioning is bothersome
under there is a little bit warmer i'm just pointing this out usually it's fine for everybody but
hmm so today i'd like to continue on this series that
i've been doing on samadhi and i'll explain what that is
and then this little series i'm doing on this is within this bigger series on the
seven factors of awakening so things that promote greater freedom greater peace greater ease
and one of the factors is samadhi and i'm just spending a few weeks here kind of flushing that out and exploring it
and maybe saying a few things more about it
so what is samadhi and why am i using this polyword and not an english word
first i'll start with one way that we can understand samadhi is that it's this uh we might say it has
these three elements the sense of unification kind of like this collectedness
as opposed to being really scattered and distracted and you know agitated
so it has this quality of unification and steadiness so that it can uh the mind can land on
something and not immediately just be bouncing around but just this feeling like you know can have a certain amount
of steadiness and some well-being to definitely accompanied with a real
sense of ease and happiness and joy and gladness and i'll
talk about a little bit about that as i go so this idea of samadhi
is something that just naturally arises and there certainly are things that we can do to promote it and kind of like
support its arising but it also is something that just naturally arises when we're doing
mindfulness practice and we're doing it for maybe like a little bit longer
longer being either just a longer meditation period or maybe we do a sitting period
for however long that the body can be comfortable and then it may be stained with this mindfulness for some walking
and then maybe another sitting so as a way that we can maybe for a longer duration but without the body
complaining too loudly so
this one english word that is sometimes used for samadhi is concentration
but the reason why i don't like to use this word is because concentration really is pointing to
this uh we might have this idea as this microscopic uh focusing bearing down
onto one single point but that's not really what it is i used to think this
and wow i really did a lot of there's a lot of suffering around you know trying to
do this so i've been trying to kind of like unpack this and explore different ways
in which we can have this experience of samadhi and then something else i like to say
when i'm talking about this is that it's not like there's
for somebody we could say that there's a switch it's either on or off it's definitely a spectrum
and so we're just like moving one direction towards more collectiveness more sense of well-being
or we're moving the other was being a little more distracted and it's not that we can't be distracted
i'm just talking about samadhi here so i'm not talking about all of our meditation experiences and mindfulness i
don't want us to think that this is the only way but it's just the topic of what i'm exploring and talking about tonight
so just a little bit more this idea of unification
there's a polyword i'm not going to bother talking about it but it's you know kind of this idea gets brought up
there's a number of ways we can talk about or think about this in one is
that the body and the mind and somehow are a little bit more unified
of coming together two ways we can think about that is the body is here
of course it's here where else would it be it's here but sometimes the mind is over there
you know fantasizing about the future or recollecting the past or something like that the mind is anywhere except here
sometimes so that might be one way we could think about some unification
is the mind and the body being more in the together or in the same
vicinity i remember this uh
one time that i was meeting with a meditation teacher this was early in my practice
and um i was running a little bit late and i wanted to be on time i wanted to give a good impression you know i didn't
want to be late and a little bit agitated you know when i'm driving i'll be irritated with everybody
get out of my way you know this kind of a thing and
i finally get to this appointment i show up and i'm in the room with the
meditation teacher and i kind of like sit down and like okay you know i wanted to talk about my practice
and this meditation teacher said why don't you finish arriving
and that was just like such a nice way like okay to finish arriving i can do this to kind of like get myself
collected in some kind of way so that's one way we might think of
unification so samadhi is another way we might think
about it is kind of like a settling and i often find myself doing this with my hands i can't help it it's uh
i think andrea fella she has this assembly that's really helpful about those snow globes where we shake them up
and then we put them down and then the kind of the glitter settles it kind of it can feel like that
so part of this maybe both a little bit of unification and settling
and arriving all three of these is becoming embodied to just like a
feeling like we're connected to the body that's one way we might understand kind of like this
settling but it's not uncommon for people to have
this idea that it's all about how much i'm thinking and so they're evaluating like am i
thinking am i not thinking how much am i thinking is this a lot of thinking and so i seem to be thinking less than last time but what can i do to stop thinking
right and they're just doing all this thinking about thinking and so it's not it's not so much that we
have to stop all our thinking that can happen that usually happens
after a lot of meditation practice and that usually happens in a retreat setting hours weeks months and
meditation so it's not so much about
not thinking as what is our
relationship to our thinking because why we spend so much time thinking of course
we do this is what humans do when problems arise difficulty so rise we want to fix
them and we're so used to thinking as a way that we sit fix and solve problems
so it's about what is our relationship to our thinking and i'll talk about this
a little bit more and what is the content of what we're thinking
is there a way or maybe i should there can be the content but also what is the manner or
how we're doing it i'd like to unpack this a little bit
so we can this idea of what is our relationship to thinking
is maybe one way we can think about it is what happens when we sit down
or to meditate and we have this intention i'll use the
example to be with the breath this is what we often teach about it is to just you know be with the
sensations of breathing and then the mind starts well what am i
gonna have for dinner or when is that dang bell gonna ring you know whatever it is whatever it is
lost in this thought and then it's just it's a mystery really like all
of a sudden pink they were kind of like a waking up oh yeah i'm supposed to meditate be meditating
and then maybe we begin again with the objects that of our meditation the breath for example
so what happens when there's that little being oh right i'm meditating
this could be a great place to kind of like check in with what is our relationship to thinking
because what happens in the next moment in the next beat is there like i keep on going
sometimes it feels like that like a little light goes back on like oh yeah right i'm supposed to be meditating
is there a the next moment is there like dang it how long have i been
thinking oh gosh i'm always thinking
everybody else they're probably not thinking oh remember that time when i didn't have
as much thinking and it's not like that now right so there can be this dang it or this kind of it's too bad i
wish this weren't this way and with that there can be a lot of
storytelling like i'm never gonna get this everybody else can do this or
whatever it is we all have our favorite ways of kind of like what's happening the next moment
or maybe it could be like distinct oh
thinking and just feeling the ribs expand
with the in-breath and with the exhale a little bit the
stopping of the stretch so that's another way right just to
label it we could just say this word thinking
and just begin again with the sensations of breathing it doesn't have to be drama there
doesn't have to be an analysis there doesn't have to be any commentary whatsoever
and i'm saying this like making it so simple but this is definitely something
we have to learn we're so used to commenting and we
definitely have opinions and ideas and how things should be and should not be
but one is to just notice what is our relationship and if there's any harshness there
and it's amazing right how harsh we can be on ourselves is there a way that you can bring in a
little more gentleness instead of dang it or maybe it's like
dang it oh it's okay sweetie and then come back to the breath or
whatever your anchor is so the first beat might be this habitual one
or whatever our habit is but then is there a way that we can soften it
do not underestimate how powerful this can be it seems like a you know pretty
straightforward and it's not even about being mindful or something like this but this can make such a difference
to soften as best we can our relationship to the thinking when we
discover that we've been lost in thought for however long we've been lost in thought
and then maybe along with this is to recognize that there's actually three moments
happening there's the being lost in thought and when you're lost in thought
no problem you're just lost in thought right you're just planning or remembering something or rehearsing a
conversation or whatever it might be right there's nothing you're just lost in thought that's how it is
and then there's this waking up moment and then there's our reaction to that
moment and sometimes it's helpful or i would say maybe it's always helpful to just
notice there's these three different steps because sometimes they get all mushed
together and it's there's only really one step that
there's a place where we can do something and we're lost in thought we're lost in thought that's just the
way it is nothing we can do there nor can we like make ourselves wake up
from loss of thought if we could you would not be here at a meditation center you would just be home you know wake it
up from whatever you needed to but it's that our reaction to when we
kind of wake up to our thoughts the fact that we've been thinking that's where there's something we can do
and to soften bring in a little bit of uh in whatever way is helpful and
supportive for you i use this word oh it's okay or oh sweetheart or honey for some
people that's like no way that just feels too weird and for some other people it feels like a nice way
whatever feels helpful for you to soften any harshness
and then just begin again with the sensations of breathing or whatever your
object used to be then i'd like to point out that like not
all thoughts are the same of course not all content is the same
but one way we might think about it is sometimes our thinking is like we're
writing a novel it's a little bit of drama and there's a plot and there's lots of characters and you know just you
turn the page and it goes on and on and this is when we're lost in thought like a lot of words
this is what happens it's okay but sometimes we can just get it down to
a chapter kind of like you know this train of thinking it's just a chapter
not maybe not as many different scenes or not as much trauma maybe there's just
one drama one thing that has some emotional charge to it and after that
maybe there's some waking up then it can be paragraphs
and then it can be sentences and there can be words
and so with our this settling practice is this kind of process of going for
long novels or maybe it's a non-fiction just some big book okay you know so the
down to chapters paragraph sentences and then words just like maybe a single word
so this um way of evaluating whether we're thinking or not
that turns out not to be so helpful because there's so much kind of like judgment that gets associated with it
there's often when we're meditating we have this idea i shouldn't be thinking this is a really common
idea i hear teachers talk about this maybe not as much mindfulness teachers
but it's such a common thing for meditation you have this idea okay it's supposed to empty your mind
yeah we can't just sit down and empty our mind that doesn't happen
so that's just one way to think about this we're just moving to the thoughts are less
it's less of a thought train less complicated you know it's just
less of a story and more when i'm talking about it just comes down to a sentence or a word
usually when it's kind of quieted to that within their space in between the words and the sentences
then those sentences those words are often about
the meditation so in the little example i gave before i
kind of said a little note oh thinking so like just like maybe a label that
gets put onto an experience is a way to kind of like okay i see you
and then i'm just gonna come back to my object so to just do a simple note
one word can be really helpful don't worry if it's the right note
just do whatever comes up first sometimes it's helpful to maybe sometimes the note is like sadness or
anger or itching or pressure like we feel the pressure of
the chair or cushion against the body or something like this
but there's a way that sometimes it could also be like a sentence that's a
recognition like oh the breath is really
slower than i realized or you know it might be something like this
so it's not uh really different than the meditation but it's a way in which we're kind of
connecting with or recognizing what's happening
so i'll just introduce this idea to that we can use thinking to support our
practice that is we might if we find that you know
there's this like pressure to think or and of course we often have this
because there's so much behind thinking like it's how we spend our days mostly
but is there a way in which we can use the thinking to our advantage or as a support
in one way is there a way that you can give yourself some meditation
instructions like maybe there's a guided meditation that you've heard that you've kind of internalized you've heard it so
often or maybe you're there's a favorite teacher or an app or you know a dharma
talk or guide meditation whatever it might be to just bring that up
and just do a little bit of a guided meditation for yourself
for me because i've done a lot of guided meditations you know with a microphone too
i find myself doing this sometimes i'm like talking to myself kind of like giving myself guided meditations
so maybe it's an acquired taste and i just offer this as something that's supportive nothing that's you need to do
but something that you might try or to if you feel like it might be
helpful or supportive or there's something like maybe some
like dropping in some encouragement like if the if there's this feeling like
that bell is never going to ring sometimes it feels like that
you could just say well everything has a beginning a middle and an end
or nothing lasts forever or it's going to end it's okay
trying to make it ring doesn't make it ring right so there's a way that we could
just like give ourselves this little reassurance or encouragement or
something like this to a way that we could use the power of thinking
or we could also bring in some what we might say some borrowed wisdom
maybe we don't have access to that wisdom right then but you know we've heard this maybe
we've understood it in a certain way but this idea of well things change
so this with the bell or with whatever we're experiencing just this recognition
well this isn't going to last forever or if it is changing we can maybe notice
that or we also know right that there is difficulties there's dukkha there are
things that are uncomfortable sometimes it's just helpful to say well
yeah this is uncomfortable without having to make it be a you know
a huge problem that has to be fixed right then so that's a way which we can use
the thinking to help support the settling this
this movement from book chapters down to paragraphs and sentences and words
then i also want to talk a little bit about this well-being that's part of this settling process
it just naturally arises we don't have to
go and search for it or you know manufacture it or drum it up
there's something that's naturally arises when there's a settling
is accompanied with this with some gentleness or some openness or
some not with some grasping or clinging and this is why i've talked about how
our relationship to thinking if we can soften that make a little bit warmer as best we can
can be so helpful because if there is some warmth and some softness and just the way that we're practicing
that definitely creates the conditions for the well-being to just simply arise
and this well-being like in the buddhist teachings they talk about this a lot there's a lot
in there about this and part of it is this um the word we could translate as gladness
so this gladness just arises when
the hindrances have softened so the hindrances are things that hinder
not surprisingly and they get in the way of this settling process
i'm not going to go into all the gory detail about this there's a number of talks on it and
um tanya wiser and i will be teaching a class on them um in the spring or in the new year
and i'll just say that it's uh some of the hindrances are like when you feel like you have too much energy
you're restless or not enough energy you're falling asleep or maybe there's this fantasizing i just
gotta get this thing or aversion i gotta get away from this
thing or what we say doubt this i'm not quite sure what to do and it's this
vacillation or this hesitation there's a lot more we could say about
that but that's kind of these five hindrances but when they start to settle then there's this gladness that arises
and this gladness we might think of it it has this um
quality of like it's if you go this happened to me
not too long ago that uh went for a walk and i didn't bring a water bottle with me and
i was just feeling thirsty like i feel like i really need to have a drink
it wasn't like the end of the world and you know the walk was going to end like i knew it was going to right but i just
this feeling like i would really like a drink and um i had a water bottle on my back
at the end of the walk and then when i just got the water
and drank and drank a drink there was like ah that kind of a feeling
so this satisfaction or this kind of this sense of relief
it's also can be like have you been on talking with somebody and for whatever reason their cell phone
or their bluetooth device or whatever it is isn't working well
and that you can't quite hear and you're like or you hear all this background noise they don't realize they're putting
away the groceries while they're talking to you and this bang bang and the grocery bags and all this kind of stuff
but you really want to have this conversation and then when they stop doing that
oh how nice that feels so it's that gladness that kind of this
uplift and this nice feeling that happens
but then this gladness if there's if this is arising right in
our meditation practice and there's with this settling there's this other
way we would say joy that arises and the joy
feels a little bit different than the gladness it's not so much of a relief or it's not so much of a nice
feeling but joy has this really bubbly this really um exuberant exhilarating
euphoric rapture like people use these kinds of words to
describe these experiences it can be a knock your socks off finger
in the light socket kind of feeling or it could just be a nice feeling this kind of bubbly oh
wow feeling it makes no difference where you are on
that spectrum nobody knows why for some people it's you know a little bit too much too
intense and for other people it's just this really pleasant maybe bubbly
tingly really nice really nice feeling
and if this gladness was like this glass of water i would say that the joy is
more like champagne like champagne happens when you're celebrating you're happy happy birthday
happy anniversary congratulations you know it has that kind of like uplift feeling to it
so there's this joy that happens
as the mind and the body are getting more and more like connected and collected and settling
there's also this happiness that then happens so maybe the gladness has kind of
moved away and it's a little bit more joy and there can be this happiness
and that happiness uh if the joy is like champagne the happiness is more like
this hot chocolate like if from at the uh when it's a
little bit cold or something or hot chocolate and look just the way you like it just the
perfect temperature just you know with the right amount of sweetness and if you like marshmallows
there is marshmallows or whipping cream or whatever it might be so it's this
maybe this feeling of uh contentment or this feeling of um
it's uh i'm going like this with my hands because there's definitely this feeling of this of expensiveness
like this sense of yeah it's this it's okay sometimes there can be tears associated
with it because like wow i just didn't even know that humans could actually feel like this
and there's tears like just i don't they're not tears of sadness
it's like wow so this is what's can happen
the vast majority of time this happens in a retreat setting when because this settling and the
collectedness it takes some momentum we have to to build that because we have to interrupt
the momentum of being distracted and being busy and doing this and taking care of that and
solving this problem and thinking and talking right of course we're busy with that but in order to allow this settling
to happen often takes time for some people it takes they haven't
they will have to meditate for maybe years before they have this that certainly was
my experience but it's always like a movement that
direction it's like we might have a glimpse oh wow there was something there
and these kind of like glimpses are nourishing and they support us and recognize there is a different way to be
in the world there is a way in which there is some ease and some of this well-being
there may be something that i'll say about a little bit more about this well-being and why i took the time to
make this difference between gladness joy and happiness is that as this settling and this
quieting happens and i don't want to say that um
sometimes we have this idea that we have to get like more and more and more concentrated but
another way to think about it is we're just noticing more and more subtle
uh experiences this happens with mindfulness practice right and with samadhi we're just noticing things
a bit more subtle and i'll say that the happiness is more
subtle than the joy i talked about like joy kind of this bubbly and wahoo kind of a feeling
and like i said for everybody it's different for some people it's just this kind of maybe tingly really pleasant
but to support concentration to support this movement of more samadhi or settling
is an interesting thing happens so there's this joy and this happiness there may be happening at the same time
but the joy is like so loud that's pretty much all we notice but then it starts to like settle down
and we start to notice oh yeah there's this happiness here that's less bubbly that's
more warm and soft and cozy and then
it starts to go like this to the happiness starts to be more and more
and the as there's more in the joy is kind of like draining out
and there's just this happiness so there's this kind of this shift in the relationship between that joy and
happiness and knowing this is a way that we can help support the
mind this continuing settling so i keep on talking about you know okay
well maybe this happens this knock your socks off type of stuff happens after a lot of practice but
there is a way as i said like like this it's just a natural process
so there are times if we give ourselves over to the
practice to the meditation practice as best we can
and like i said there might be maybe it's just like a sit walk set
maybe it's a whole day what maybe it's a few days
or it's just every day every day for you know day after day after day there's a
way in which the mind and the body just get used to settling and you can just sit down and this settling just starts
to happen so i'll just say here at imc right we do
have half days and day longs and then we have we have retreats at our retreat center as a way
to kind of like support this practice happening and we have you know we sit here for 45
minutes on monday nights for some people that's a long time for most people
most everybody you know 45 minutes is a long time so and it is definitely
something to i don't know i'll just say for myself i
would never go if somebody had a 45 minute set no way i wouldn't go because i just felt like that's just not
possible but it just happened because i just started a meditation
practice and wasn't like i had to was striving for 45 minutes it just happened
so i just am offering this i don't i want to send two messages one
that this when the settling the samadhi can really go into some beautiful places
that they're not the they're not the purpose of practice but they just support our lives
this um the sense of well-being that can be so nourishing
especially if we have this habit of being harsh to ourselves to have these experiences kind of like
helps uh i don't know like maybe place a salve on
that or something like this maybe so i want to give that message and i also want to give the message that we
don't have to wait till we have these fantastic or experiences but just to notice
and allow support senses of well-being that arise
whenever they arise they are arising but often we're so
often more dismissive like oh yeah okay i have to solve this problem i have to
take care of this thing like there's something that's not quite right and we just have this habit of course we do
to take care of the problem to tune into what's not quite right so just an encouragement to notice
though any feeling of well-being openness warmth that shows up
and this will be a support for the mind to settle
just like settling brings up well-being well-being brings up settling they work
together so i want to live a time for some questions
so maybe i'll end there this idea of samadhi and
thinking and well-being we don't have to get rid of our thoughts
they just will maybe we could use them to as a support
and we can use well-being as a support so with that maybe we can open it up for
questions i'm sorry richard i didn't tell you before that i was going to do this but
i said anybody have some questions if we could use the microphone it would be great or i don't know sveta if there's any on
people on youtube if they have any questions no maybe we can
good evening diana thank you again um well during the sitting
i found myself trying not to be so harsh but then once the bell rang i was like oh gosh
i was supposed to be in the here and now and i you know i was just feeling worried and
just that feeling of well-being supporting it just
you know when things happen at work and you don't feel that sense of just being present
and then you're just thinking about how to solve something and then you're getting frustrated
i just i know that this practice has helped me not feel so agitated all the time but
i still get really upset when i'm feeling that way because i'm more aware of that but
i just i want to be okay with that but i don't want to keep striving
this is great thank you for saying this i i appreciate this very much a few things that you said is that um
first of all i'll just say that i'm talking about somebody here on some other times i will talk about
mindfulness which uh can be a real support for this so i don't want to say
that we have to be doing this you know somali practice or um
this is what happens when we first start noticing like oh my gosh my mind
it's crazy and i can't make it do what i want it to do and i definitely want to feel better this is exactly what happens
this is a an uncomfortable place where we are start to notice more and more
how we haven't been noticing and so this anytime we
can bring in remember to bring in some kindness
and usually what happens like will set the intention like okay i'm gonna when i notice i'm gonna try to be a little more
kind or warm towards myself instead of harshness when i notice the harshness and what usually will happen is you
won't remember the whole day you will not forget i mean you will not remember at all
and then maybe the next day you won't remember and then you may oh yeah i'm going to go to imc on monday night
oh right they've been talking about this uh uh not being harsh with oneself and then
maybe you'll remember once or twice during the day then maybe you'll come here you heal
some things and then the next day you'll hear it a few times and then you'll forget again and then so this is what
happens that it's okay it's okay we are rewiring ourselves right that we
have a lifetime of being harsh or
trying to solve everything with you know pouncing on thoughts or something like this this is a process that will takes
time but can we just be okay with of course we want to solve it
but there's a way in which we can be okay with our not being okay
so that's the place to practice and then i just wanted to normalize and uh support your the idea that of course
we have these intentions to be mindful and sometimes and not to have the harshness
but this is exactly how it works just one step at a time one step at a time
thank you
thank you um that today was uh pretty brutal um
i but i didn't notice something i noticed like i would be switching positions a lot and
finding a comfort in one position and i think oh i'm comfortable now
and then like 15 minutes later then like the discomfort comes and i didn't really move at all it's just so i
thought it was really interesting that like you know i think i feel my body craving the
comfort of a sitting and yet it's not satisfied with that position and it has
to change and i just thought that was interesting so not really a question i just uh yeah
interesting it's quite something and we'll notice like if you pay attention during the day how often we are shifting
our butcher posture in our chairs you know maybe every two minutes or something where there's a little arm
moves or removes something like this we're always shifting our postures so 15 minutes is pretty good actually
compared to what we're often doing but there's a way in shifting our posture doesn't have to be a problem
we can say oh my my knee is uncomfortable
let's see would it be better maybe i'll um i'm going to shift my posture now i'm gonna move my knee
and then we just move the knee moving the knee feels like this
so it's just incorporated into the practice okay so that's but i appreciate you saying this
nathan thank you
um i'll sometimes be sitting and uh
i noticed that kind of something all this happened today like especially when i'm sitting with other people and it
gets really still something will kind of fall away and i feel like i'm in this like really glowy
like kind of i can't describe it really uh and i'm
just like really in my body and in the moment it just feels like glowy but then like so quickly there's like this little
thought that's like is this samadhi am i doing it i have to keep doing it i shouldn't be thinking you know and then
it like so it's just it never can last because my mind is trying to like hold on to it what would
you advise doing in that moment when the thoughts start to like amp back up
about the the state i guess yeah yeah this is very common i'm not in my head
yeah right of course this is very common um a few things um
one maybe you could make a note like oh thinking or something like this
and there would be it could be a way that uh that can have like stop the agitation of the thinking or
something like this um and something else would be
um do you have a sense of like when you say something drops do you have a sense of like what supports that dropping
i think it's oh i don't i'm not sure how to answer that specific question but like what leads to it i think it's just
time and sit like sitting and and the thoughts start to quiet more and more and i can let them go and just like the
novel it turns into words and then there's and then it kind of sneaks up on me it happens all of a sudden
and then um so yeah so it's not i don't think i'm quite and sometimes like those thoughts
are just like a little like it can hold the thought and it's just a little wave that comes and then leaves but then like
i'm like oh i did such a good job letting go of that thought you know and then it the more it's just
you know they keep coming yeah yeah it doesn't have to be a problem this is something that
happens it's you have to experience that like maybe a hundred times a thousand times like oh
okay that's just that and it's not a it's not it once we gain familiarity
with it then the then the idea oh was that somebody or not you stop caring
whether it is or not it just feels like oh okay this feels like the right way to go so your it sounds like you're on the
right way right right go in the right direction just do that like a hundred times a thousand times
100 stop caring how many times and then you're there stop caring how many times that's it
exactly exactly
okay okay so we're at the top of the hour here so i want to thank you for your practice
and i'll stay here if some people have some questions afterwards but otherwise i wish you all
a wonderful evening and with uh filled with some well-being so thank you