hello friends hello good day good morning
happy to be with you i'm nikki murgafury and i'm happy to be um
joining you for this week and supporting both the sangha and also supporting gail
while he is uh this down
technical difficulty here there we go okay so um supporting gail while he's
hiking and taking a well-deserved vacation so
so [Music] um [Music] for this week
i would like to present uh some reflections and guided
meditations on the mind's body and the mind's body
and what i mean by that of course will become a lot more clear in the dharmats and the importance
of that and um without further ado
let's uh let's start practicing together let's start sitting together
so i'd like to invite you to get into your meditation posture
whatever is comfortable for you sitting [Music]
lying down or even standing whatever is needed in this moment to be
supportive
ah and arriving arriving in this moment
arriving in this long fathom body here
arriving here
turning turning the gaze
inward
towards the body the sensations here
can we invite ourselves to feel comfortable in this body
even if there are discomforts present
can we be comfortable
with the discomforts with whatever there is
can we welcome the breath can we welcome the sensations
can we welcome having a body can we appreciate having a body
softening relaxing
the feet
feeling the solidity of the feet on the earth
letting go releasing
the weight of the entire body
unto the feet the legs wherever your
body is contacting the earth
as if we were a buddha statue sitting
sitting tall with integrity
with uprightness in our heart in our attitude
and just as a buddha statue has a base a solid base
sitting on a solid base well rooted well connected
feeling sensing sensations of the feet the legs your sit bones
as your base let yourself feel your base connected to the earth well rooted
in many statues the buddha is touching the earth this earth be my witness
i belong here i'm here i have a body
on this earth ah
releasing releasing the thoughts
the headiness bringing the center of gravity down down down
feeling feet feed the legs sit bones
your base
as if it were bronze or or marble
or jade nice and heavy
not hollow but filled out can you feel your legs your sit bones
your feet filled out this body the lower part of the body first
spend some time
feeling filled out not just the outline
of the lower body but fill down bringing awareness
and now feeling the upper body too
the buddha statue within arms
the outline of the arms the arms filled out
hands
solidity of this body
sitting with uprightness
feeling sensing your trunk your abdomen
your back your chest
neck shoulders
the head face
entire upper body not just the outline
but as let your mind fill out
again this buddhist statue
made of your favorite precious stone that you are
or metal or with whatever works for you in this moment
feeling your body filled out the solidity
earth element solidity earth sitting on earth
and in your mind's eye now having an image
a felt sense of your entire body not just the outline but it's filled
but it being filled out sense of fullness
cohesiveness of this entire body sitting
let your mind trace the outline
your body your back your bottom your legs
the front the sides
and this feeling of cohesiveness of the body
one piece one piece
not distracted scattered everywhere known as body one piece
breathing air welcoming air
both porous air entering
moving through so much air so much space
and also sense of solidity wholeness
notice how your heart your mind might settle for the next minutes
being settled rooted
the sense of cohesiveness of the body this whole body
relaxed soft whole the entire body
this buddha statue your inner buddha sitting tall
feeling the entire body as you sit as you breathe
both sensing feeling the body and also having an internal image of it
keeping the entire body an image of it
sense of solidity in mind
relax soft hold
integrated
okay
as if your body were
a three-dimensional drawing in a coloring book and carefully with your mind
seeing holding
three-dimensional drawing and filling out
carefully with your mind as if you had coloring pencils
sensations tracing the sensations filling them in throughout the body
have fun with it
and as we bring this sitting to a close
take a moment to notice
if there's any more sense of cohesion coherence
integration [Music] in your body and mind maybe sense of calm stability
feeling more filled out embodied
in this precious body long fathom body
appreciating whatever seeds have been planted
for integration [Music] integrity
presence kindness service
through our coming together and practicing
and let us offer generously freely our goodness trusting
there is goodness here goodness co-created
offering it together all of us generously our goodness collectively to
all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere
feel whole
feel integrated feel happy
and be free including ourselves
hello hello good morning good afternoon good evening
good day whatever time zone you're in
so lovely to sit with you grounding to sit with you i hope
i hope you did um experience and
and uh well i'll say a little more about the guided meditation and and
the theme so so maybe what i'll say first about the
guided meditation the invitations what um
what i was inviting us to consider um is the sense of
wholeness of the body body as a whole this entirety of the body
and mostly i was bringing in the teachings of um
the four elements the element of earth as well as actually i was bringing
[Music] all the elements in here and there there's so many different ways
to practice the four elements but the sense of solidity the sense of
wholeness of this body as a statue as a buddhist statue also for us to feel the
uprightness the the sense of integrity um
in this body so the element of solidity hardness
feeling the body sitting like a statue and then also
feeling inviting the sense of the breath coming in and going in which is the air
element as well as the cohesion the sense of
cohesion and that's the water element feeling the cohesiveness cohesiveness of the body that's the
water element and [Music] there's the heat there's also the fire
element there's a sense of heat which i guess i didn't bring in much but a sense of warmth in the body sitting
and also the space element sometimes considered as the feeling the spaciousness of the breath
that's the way i was bringing it in but the idea here the idea and the guided
meditation is to ground the mind in the body in this
wholeness of the body and the solidity of the body in the fullness of the body
and the mind can really settle and i hope you experience that a little
bit there's a sense of settling cohesiveness there's a sense of being embodied
be getting in our body instead of living our our lives from a few feet away from
our head from our bodies and our heads always running ahead running running ahead or running behind in the
past but the idea is that we can become embodied through bringing the attention
bringing the awareness to the uh in different ways and there are
different ways by by bringing our awareness and our attention to the body in different ways
there are different results that can actually come up it's not the same old
same old okay and pay attention to your breath in your abdomen rise and fall but the different ways
that we pay attention to the body to the breath as i will discuss in the next few days
can have different effects for settling for awakening for working
with the five hindrances there there are many uh techniques or many
wise ways to relate to the body so um
a little bit about the the guided meditation the intention of it and the
sense of cohesiveness wholeness to release have an image of the body and also part
of this practice i'm pulling a lot of different practices together also part of these practices from the visual maga
from path of purification practice from abi dhamma higher teachings which i've also practiced so i'm adapting these
various practices um and sharing them with you
today and this week to to explore some other terrains so
so the idea of of again with this meditation today having it
if you want to again repeat that and continue this having a complete sense of
body the outline the wholeness of the body sitting moving so
there's a wholeness that brings a sense of integrity so now i want to step back and and
say a little more about the context of of this week um
so the buddha in gujarat nikaya
4 45 said the end of the world
can never be reached by walking however
without having reached the world's end there is no release from suffering
i declare that it is in this fathom-long body
with its perceptions and thoughts that there is the world
the origin of the world the cessation of the world
and the path leading to the cessation of the world
so quite quite an interesting teaching here um
and and profound and and
i'll read this line again i declare that it is in this fathom-long body
with its perceptions and thoughts that there is the world
in this body there is the world the origin of the world's cessation of
the world the path leading to the decision of the world so basically in this fathom
long body is with all the thoughts and perceptions this is where awakening
happens this is where suffering happens this is where awakening happens
so the importance of the body
and relating to the body and awareness of the body working with the
body and i also want to remind you all that in the four and the sati patana in
the satipatana sutta the first satipata the first
establishment of mindfulness is the body the body is so important it needs to be
established and we need to relate to it and this practice is not about mind over
matter i remember teaching mindfulness years and years ago in an
introductory class and i i vividly remember there was a student who insisted this meditation mind over
body so that i can just rule my body and not feel my pain and that's not the idea
here that's not the idea here the idea of meditation and what we're doing here is not mind over body but
it's it's mind with the body it's the
the um mind working with the body because the body as you know affects the
mind and the mind of course affects the body so the theme of this week now i'm
bringing this together introduced introducing the theme of this week as i mentioned at the beginning of the guided
meditation is the mind's body
the mind's body yes we have we feel like we have a body it feels
solid there's a shape to it it hurts we have our usual relationship to our bodies
but there's also the energetic body or the mind's body if i say at the end
energy body or energetic body sometimes people feel like wow that
sounds woo-boo but it's really the mind's body the way
we relate to interact with we see we the way we bring attention
to the body the way we think about the body the way we engage with our minds
with the body it both changes the perception of our body
both in the in the uh in our mind of both our perception and also the physicality of
the body also shifts and changes and there's this idea of the mind's body is not so separate or different
from the body itself from the physicality itself
so so for so again coming back to the guided meditation
that we did by bringing attention in a particular way by seeing the body as a whole keeping
our mind keeping our attention on the body as a whole keep filling out
keep filling out as a whole as a whole over time
not only does the mind settle really really get grounded with the
sense of the body but the perception of our minds our bodies shift
and the sense of embodiment really living in our body
feeling connected and the mind being really rooted and the sense of joyfulness arises for
having your body wow isn't it amazing to to have a body
and i say this uh chuckling perhaps because on the buddhist cosmology there
are these different levels of existence there are the pita realm peter realms where there's a lot
of suffering and and um beings are being tortured in their bodies and then
there's the animal realm and then there's the human realm and then there are the what's called the
devil realm so the uh celestial realms and in some of the celestial realms
the beings have no body so there is no body
just just mind and yet it is said that this realm of the human realm this middle realm this
is where we are there is enough um [Music] joy there's enough suffering there's
enough challenges and enough agency all of that in is the perfect place for becoming
awakened there's perfect place so we have a body we have a sense of agency
and how we relate how we bring our attention to our bodies do we hate it do
we be rated do we feel [Music]
betrayed so all of these the way that we relate to our bodies so
so the invitation i have as we will collect and as we work together for the
rest of this week with mind's body is if you would continue
feeling your whole body today filled out filled out as you go about your day
feel your body filled out the entirety of it not just your feet not just your
hands you know there are these teachings about washing the dishes feeling the sensations of the hand that's great
that's a different teacher but feel your entire body filled out not just the outline but filled out
today as you move about your world and see what shift in perspective perception
of your body the sensations the mind your mind's body how does it feel this
version of your mind's body so we're out of time
and i look forward to continuing to explore these fascinating teachings with you
tomorrow and take good care be well