so good day everyone nice to be here nice to be back at imc
it was nice to be at irc yesterday i hope you enjoyed it and um
and we're back at sati patana and this uh awareness practice of sati
patana foundations for awareness for mindfulness
begins with a foundation in your posture
and then it goes into breathing and
as we settle into the breathing the instructions are breathing in
experiencing the whole body breathing out experiencing the whole body
and and in doing so
and last time last friday i talked about doing it for the whole length of the inhale whole length of the out hail and
that's one one interpretation of this though whole bodies the whole body of the
in or through time of the experience of breathing so there's a real continuity through time
with just staying with the breath another interpretation is that it
actually involves experiencing the body as a whole and one way to do that
is to uh this little bit having uh using both
central vision and peripheral vision at the same time whereas the centers of the eye you can
have your central vision focused on something and have some sense of the what's around it through the peripheral
vision so the same thing with attention to the breathing there's a focus on the breathing
and that's a central focus and then the peripheral is just open and aware to the
rest of the body and that's a very interesting dynamic to have both kinds of attention operating
and it takes a little more engagement so that there's less space in the mind
to wander off in thought the variation that i like of that is that
especially works well i think if you feel your breathing in your body in your torso
is find the place in your torso where the first sensations of breathing arise
or maybe it's the place where you're centered most if you're aware mostly of the breathing in the belly it would be
there just there and then from that place
feel the expansion that happens the expansion of the torso the rib cage expands the belly expands perhaps
and the shoulders maybe lift slightly maybe the back ribcages also expand outwards
the space between the ribs opens up a little bit so this expansion but feel it almost
like a wave of expansion that goes out through the whole torso the whole body
that you easily experience and even you can imagine that it kind of spreads out beyond the body
and then and then in the exhale it all comes back
and there's this this rhythm of expanding and contracting with a breath where
somehow that feels like the breath kind of move all the places in the body that
the movement or breath touches you're kind of opening to all of it in the inhale
and then opening or kind of allowing yourself to ride the return
at the exhale and this kind of rhythm of going out and in
broadly through the whole body the whole body that you easily experience with each breath
and what's interesting to do it one very interesting things to happen can happen this way
one of them is if you're feeling some strong emotions or
moods like you feel anxiety or fear or sadness or happiness and
enthusiasm or something prioritize that rhythm of expansion and
contraction as if it goes through your mood your emotional state but
untroubled by it don't don't go don't get involved in your motion don't try to fix it or try to judge it
and just like matter of fact you're just kind of walking through the weather of the day and your weather's not bothering you and
you just keep walking you just kind of move through the sensations in your body
connected to how you're feeling the emotions and you just kind of massage it you work through it without any concern
about what it means or what you have to do or anything just kind of allowing it to be
there just moving that rhythm through it through it same thing with sometimes there's certain levels of discomfort and
pain same thing just kind of feel it as the expansion comes the whole
and then feel it as it you know as you go through it with the returning of the
exhale so breathing in expanding the tension to feel the whole
breath body the whole experience in the body and then
the breathing and then on the return i kind of follow that through the body as well so hopefully this is understandable
so uh taking a posture for
meditation and gently closing your eyes
and to begin the rhythm you could do it
intentionally and largely by taking some deep inhales
and conscious long exhales
and with bigger inhales maybe it's easier to feel all the places in the body
that move and expand as you breathe in
and you might even at the top of the inhale hold your breath for just a fraction of a moment
just long enough that you can feel
the pull the draw the desire to exhale
and then ride the exhale through your body feel the return the
contracting the pulling in all the way back to the place where
there's no more sensations of breathing out
breathing in deeply
exhaling fully
and then letting the breathing return to normal but continue with that rhythm
and now it's not as dramatic but it's still as you breathe in
feel it's almost like you're riding the expansion writing the movement of
filling throughout the torso
sometimes i think of it as that being a bird that's soaring and it catches the updraft
on the inhale
and then it glides through the air on the down back to the ground on the exhale
and since we're still beginning here on the exhale you might also for next
three or four exhales relax whatever is being held or tight in your
body whatever is easy to relax
and partly what you're experiencing is the impact the influence
that breathing has on the body
allow yourself to be influenced by the breath allow yourself to
expand as you breathe in
and to feel the sensations of your body
allow yourself to release
on the exhale
and feel all the sensations of your body that come into play as you exhale
where the focus is on that rhythm of movement through your body
let that be the center so that you're not centered in your thinking
reacting and preferences also you're not centered in your
emotions but you're not ignoring them either if there's a mood or emotion
feel it in your body and let that rhythm stay with a rhythm
where the rhythm moves through
the physical sensations of how you feel
[Music]
like the waves wash up on the sandy shore over and over again
without any concern with the sand or the
the weather or anything just keeps washing up and down
so see if you can ride the breathing
feeling your whole body as you breathe in whole body as you breathe out
in that rhythm of expansion and contraction
as if it's forever un untroubled
by anything that it moves through any way it feels
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
if you're feeling the inhales an expansion through the body
imagine that your care
continues as you expand out across the land
out across the world
as if your heart can be open and expansive and
touch all the places all the suffering in this world
and as you exhale you return deeply inside yourself
to touch the place where you care
where your compassion your love resides
your tenderness it's in that rhythm of breathing in and
breathing out expanding as you breathe in
expanding outwards to the whole world
as the inhale can coming back the sensations return
touching your place of care friendliness kindness
back and forth
and may this meditation we've done together serve for our ability
to care for this world to care for our friends our family our neighbors our
strangers to care for the whole world
so that maybe in some ways known and unknown intentional or unintentionally
we live for the welfare and happiness of all may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so good day and
so we continue to explore and i hope you explore
uh your capacity for awareness for attention
and how the attention to breathing can be supportive and helpful
and one of the ways it's helpful is that the more you can
be connected to your breathing following the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
the less mental energy attention is available
to feed thinking if all our attention energy mental
energy goes into thinking we reinforce it and if what we're thinking about is not helpful
it's maybe debilitating even that we're reinforcing that unhelpful kind of
trains of thoughts but if we pour our attention into the simplicity
of breathing then that is considered in buddhism to be very wholesome and helpful that leads to
all kinds of good states of mind some people might feel like their concerns what they have are so important
that they have to think them some people can't help because there's so much energy in thinking so that even if they
don't want to it's just like mind gets pulled into it so strongly but it helps maybe to consider that
that sometimes we have to retreat from certain challenges to get refreshed
to put ourselves in a good state of mind so that we can come back and address them better
that's one of the functions of meditation is not to withdraw from life and not be part of it but rather to
step away in a sense by closing your eyes and meditating not being involved in the usual thing
but more importantly to step away from the mind's preoccupation with things
long enough to get refreshed long enough then to return with a
better kind of inner eyesight better wisdom to how to address it
so the rhythm of breathing uh is a place so there's something about rhythms of things
that it's easier to kind of stay and follow like the rhythm of the waves
washing across the shore you some people just didn't watch it for a long time just watching it something
about it that you you wouldn't be if you're just a completely still lake and the water is not moving
it doesn't have the same kind of absorption in it as i do the movement
so like a flowing uh river for example it's possible to watch that for a long time or watching a fire in the fireplace
just watch all the patterns of moving and coming and going and appearing and disappearing
it's much more stressful if you just fixate your attention on a single point someplace
and then don't move it there's something about the eyes moving gently
and the mind moving gently kind of following something lightly without the word doing work and rather than
stress just kind of doesn't get very relaxed about it and so with the breathing the idea is to kind of find that place of
relaxed attention like you're watching the river flow by to watch the movements and the rhythm of
breathing in and breathing out and so if you're too focused on being concentrated
and bear down on it that's actually stressful but if
if you don't have enough attention on the breathing the mind will want to offer under often the thought
and the middle way between not having enough attention and having too much kind of tight attention
is a kind of alertness of the mind that's relaxed a kind of engagement with the breathing
that's more like a play or more like love
than it is like work and um so it does involve some kind of getting absorbed
getting involved in it settling in and that's one of the reasons why sometimes i give these images that go
along with it like today i get an image of um the bird soaring on the in-breath
and somehow the way you know the as a as the updraft of the inhale as the movements
of the body to go up um to expand occur if you imagine that
like your wings are catching that then maybe it's a little more compelling to kind of oh ride it
and then sliding down again with the exhale
that might give a kind of a sense of how to do this without a lot of work but stay really closely connected to it
um or the image i like a lot is that of also is that as i used also the waves washing up across the sandy
shore back and forth back and forth so i don't know if that works for all of
you but it's so something that works for me in terms of helping me kind
of find the right balance between not being tight or forceful in the attention
but also not to lax with it just right there and then
and it's it's with time it's self-reinforcing with time as more attention goes into
breathing and less into thinking it mind finds itself more and more easy to get absorbed to be present for it
now one of the things that can help also with the breathing is uh it is current instructions it's
not just the breathing but to ride the breath be with the breath and experience the whole body
we experience the whole breath body as the all the different ways in which the movement of breathing comes into play in
the body both both course the bigger ones like the movements of the chest perhaps or the diaphragm or the belly
but also more subtle like it could be the back rib cage if you're very sensitive you can feel
a little movements of the spine as you move maybe the upper spine can move and
you can sometimes i can feel it right down into my hip joint i can feel ever so slightly alternating sense of
pressure and release of pressure as i breathe in and breathing out the shoulders can move
so all these places in the body kind of and and so this expansion into that
breath body experience the sensations are breathing and as you beco as we're aware of all
that uh chances are sometimes that uh that's also a place where you
feel your emotions maybe you feel sadness in the area of the heart and so that's also that's in
the area of this expanding of the chest as you breathe and
and so include that as part of experiencing the whole body but explain included not as an emotion at this point
in the practice but as just more physical sensations it's almost like um
you know this is as the war as the waves wash across the sand maybe there's some
seaweed there that's on there and it washes around or a sand castle someone built and mostly washes around it and
it's kind of untroubled by it but just comes and goes and washes washes around it to the side of it and
slowly the sand castle dissolves so maybe some of the emotions difficult motions dissolve if we just kind of
let it rock let it move or that it will be washed over but the more important thing that it
dissolving is that to have the experience of feeling the this
physicality the sensations of emotions without being troubled by it without making a story about it
when we feel emotions as emotions many of us have ideas beliefs concerns identifications
with it that make it sometimes more complicated it needs to be and to just feel the emotions there's
the physicality of it in this rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
moving through you and just feeling back and forth back and forth
and no matter what happens not being concerned with what happens
with the emotions just be concerned about moving through it and back and
forth and and um you know maybe it's a little bit like um
um you know like i like the idea of you know petting a cat so that you're petty
you know whatever is going on the sensations the awareness moving through the body it's like just stroking the cat
stroking a cat and whether it's difficult or not and so what we're learning here is how
to be involved with breathing without getting pulled away into the world of the mind
and thoughts and ideas and concerns and as i've said i said before this is
not meant to be a denial or pushing away or dismissing of how we're feeling
but it is very respectful to feel the physicality of it without adding all the stuff on top of it
and also it's a way of becoming refreshed or create more clarity
so that we have a more useful way of being present for the challenges of our life
then sometimes the usual way we bring along so much baggage with us as we go along
so learning to breathe through experiences learning to breathe with experiences
is one of the great skills that can come from this practice and so whatever is happening breathe
with it breathe through it stay grounded in your breathing and learn how to breathe with it breathe through it and
you might find that you end up being more balanced that way
you might find that you become less reactive that way less tense that way
um just breathe with whatever's happening so um
so in this teachings of the buddha the buddha begins by emphasizing taking a
supportive meditation posture and establishing awareness with the
breathing so this is you know this this is where the the
the this is where we're anchored this is where we're going to be rooted for the meditation and the breathing of
course it's not easy to be rooted there but that's the understanding and then become aware of what breathing
feels like the sensations of breathing get more familiar with it and hang out with breathing and stay with it
and especially the rhythm of the breathing and then as you get settled into it
then as you breathe in feel the whole breath body feel the whole influence that has
the movements of breathing heaven the body and as you exhale feel the whole influence
and why i use the word influence is that um uh
is that to a is that we don't there's a lot of different ways in which breathing can affect us
uh not just it affects us the physical movements of the body but it can there's a kind of um
relaxation there's an opening there's softening there's there's all kinds of emotional also impacts that
good emotional impact that breathing can have and so just to have the sense of allowing yourself to be influenced by it
being open rather than being the one who's directing the show be the one who's receiving
the full experience of breathing in throughout the body the full experience of breathing out throughout the body
so i hope that this kind of encouragement around breathing and exploring it and
discovering it encourages you to take your time to become more familiar with your breathing
and and more familiar with the skill of breathing with things and what's happening breathing through and
breathing with the whole body staying connected there even sometimes when you're talking or engaged in work what
happens if you're breathing with that experience and even if you've meditated for a long
time i think there's always room to discover more and find greater value with breathing
so if this uh appeals to you you might spend the next 24 hours
more with this experience of breathing in experiencing the whole body
breathing out experience the body just really feeling that experience get familiar with it make it second nature
to be connected to it and discover all the things that open up
when uh you're with your body with your breathing that maybe it won't open up if
you just stay kind of locked into your mental concerns and thoughts
so thank you and i look forward to being here tomorrow
you