Okay so good day to all
let's go ahead and get started with our meditation together this morning
so settling in for a period of sitting
allowing your body to come into its usual meditation posture
however it's disposed this morning
and just sensing in to a spot where you're sitting your seat against the chair or
the cushion or perhaps you're lying down
and just feeling the support under your body
and allowing yourself to relax into that
perhaps allowing the body itself to find a place of balance
so just gently inviting how can the body shift slightly to
feel like there's almost no effort to be upright
and then softening the face the jaw
the throat down through the shoulders
softening the arms and the hands
down into the chest area
feeling how when the spine is straight and alert
the chest actually relaxes
down into the Valley area
releasing any tension in the low back trusting that the
spine bones themselves will hold us up without the muscles
sinking a little farther into the seat
and releasing any bracing in the legs all the way down to the feet
so we just invite ease through the body and it's okay if
the body isn't relaxed in certain places or
they aren't making contact very well with part of it that's all fine
let me just have sense also that the body is okay as it is today
and we can invite a sense of simplicity
in the body and in the mind
or sometimes the mind is complicated a lot of thoughts or emotions
but the awareness of that can be simple The Knowing of it can be very simple
connecting in with perhaps the sensations of breathing
in order to join the body and mind in a simple direct way
I would invite now tuning into sound as a meditation object
so there's the sound of my voice and there's likely also some kind of sounds
in your environment maybe other people
or cars outside or wind
behaving system
and just allowing the arrival of sounds at the ear
to be a way of connecting to the present moment
there can be a sense of ease from not knowing what is next but just
knowing that we'll meet it with our listening
just relaxing into the flow of the sounds
now we can shift slightly to
applying this faculty of listening to the body
there's a bodily sense faculty that kind
of runs throughout the body it's not just the touch sensors on the skin
we can tune into that the inner sense of the breath is part of it but there's a lot more also
so we can incline the Mind toward listening to this bodily scent store not
knowing what body Sensation will come next or how they'll shift
I'm just resting in listening to the body
foreign
to the mind
here we're using our awareness faculty in a very open way
is possible for example to hear thought
as if a speaker we're playing in the room
thoughts just inner sound
seeing if we can simply listen to the mind
finding that same sense of rest that we can find when listening to sound
externally
and we're not listening for anything or we're not listening because we need to do anything
we're listening because these parts of us want to be listened to
yeah yeah simple way very simple
and we'll just rest with that for a while
in the last few minutes of sitting and listening to experience in the body and
mind you might reflect did I learn anything
to the listening bring about
some learning and even if it doesn't feel explicit
this kind of practice is kind of like deep data Gathering
something was going in
and it's worth feeling happy about that
content with having rested in our experience
for some undivided time that we know will bring benefit in some
way
from this meditation we can also get the sense that
this practice of listening and learning is actually a heart practice
we can feel that it's not just coming from the mind but it's a full being full
body hard experience
and that it may relate to what the Buddha simply called the Dharma
how things are practicing in line with the Dharma being
connected with the Dharma all those phrases that we hear
have something to do with this experience we've had in meditation
today
this is it our experience is it
and so we can hope that as we go forward today
will be a bit more connected to all of what's going on
through our capacity to listen and to learn
that will help all the others around us not just us
sometimes in ways we can't even know right away
[Music]
foreign
so this week we are talking about five Dharma resources that help us to meet
experience well and when we have these five readily at hand and we're also mindful
then we will find that appropriate responses are much more likely to come
forth so we've talked already about confidence and virtue
and how these are not automatically Dharma resources but they become so when we take them into the heart and let them
be nourished their so the third item in the list
is called asuta in Pali it's not suta
with two T's like the discourses of the Buddha it's uh suta s-u-t-a
and this one is interesting because we really need to bear in mind the idea
that it becomes a resource when it's linked to the heart so suta is a past participle of the verb
sunity which means to hear so suto means heard you know something
that has been heard and in the Buddhist texts it's often translated as learning
so we can consider that in the Buddha's time the teachings had not yet been written down and most people were
illiterate anyway so the only way to learn spiritual teachings directly was
to listen in person to a teacher and be able to remember what was heard
so suta doesn't just mean literal hearing but some something more like learning what has been learned what has
been comprehended what has been taken in intentionally so how can we understand its presence in
a list that is connected to things like inner wealth fortitude aspiration and
modes of spiritual growth as I mentioned on Monday those are some of the ways that this list of five is
named in the sutas so how does learning help us to meet life well
so for this series this week I'm translating suta s-u-t-a as listening
and learning so that we get a richer picture of it so we could say that we will meet
situations while by really listening and also by drawing on our inner wealth of
knowing Dharma teachings and that's not mental it's not the learning that's just in our mind but
it's more the learning that's happened through listening to them with our heart
how can we listen in a dharmic way
one time in a class of about 45 people where I was a student we were asked how
many of you feel that you are really listened to every day
and maybe two people raised their hands and this is you know this is significant
and maybe also a little bit heartbreaking there's so much talking and so much hearing but so little real
listening and this is actually something that we learned to do for ourselves in
meditation so if you meditate every day you can experience the feeling that you
are deeply listened to every day in meditation listening is related to
this quality that we call investigation which is one of the factors of Awakening
so we don't mean literal listening to the words of our thoughts although that
can be part of it if we happen to have that going but it's kind of deeper listening to the
sensations and energetic flows of experience it helps to listen with the
whole body of course the attention and the interest are coming from the mind to the mind and
the body are not separate but there is a way to bring in the body
such that we're connecting more intuitively and we can even take in the Dharma in
this way I was living at the Insight Retreat Center IRC when we held the very first
retreat in Spanish there and I went to the morning instructions
and the Dharma talks even though my Spanish is rather minimal but it didn't matter I could feel the
good energy from the Dharma in going into my system through some other channel
you know my linguistic mind was not getting much satisfaction but my heart could still feel it
and that uh that prepared me well for attending a couple of retreats in Sri Lanka that were given in sinhala
as an aside some people say senegalese for that language but it's properly called sinhala I don't speak a word of
it but still there was this sense of receiving Dharma
actually sinhala is quite an ancient language and it's it's related to Paulie
and when the teacher would quote the Paulie Canon during these Dharma talks he would read the quotes in Paulie
because you know the Sri Lankan people didn't need a translation and interestingly I found that I could
halfways understand the poly quotes even though I couldn't understand the sinhala at all it was a great experience
so all of this is to say that that we can listen to the Dharma in a language
that we don't understand literally and that means that we can also listen
for the Dharma in everyday situations you know is there Dharma in a trip to
the grocery store or out hiking or picking up your children at preschool
I would say yes it's just a kind of a matter of tuning in
and you know sometimes people ask where is the Dharma in My Crazy Life or often
how can I take my practice out of the meditation Hall into the world
and one possibility is to listen for it there's so much Dharma happening all the time if we listen for it
so here's where we can shift to the this other aspect of the word suta which is
learning or what has been learned we're talking about listening and learning
together today and so if we're going to be able to detect the Dharma in everyday situations
it helps to have some integrated knowledge of what the Dharma teachings say
not all teachers focus on this but I do encourage people to study and learn
something of the language of the Buddhist teachings and I don't mean Paulie I don't mean the poly language
but rather the the terminology and also the major lists and how the path Works
to lead us from a place of suffering to less suffering or even no suffering
not because you need to get a good grade in a class or that you need to memorize things or think about them a lot
but more like because we're always operating from some model or view of the
world and ourself and our life we're not neutral entities in our interaction with
the world and so if we want to support the Dharma path unfolding it really helps to see
things in a way that aligns with the Dharma so for instance seeing our challenging mind States in
terms of the five hindrances or seeing a difficulty that we're in through the lens of the Four Noble
Truths oh this is suffering that's what's going on I wonder if there's some
craving or clinging going on here
so maybe an analogy is um imagine if you're studying to be a
chemist in a modern Western setting but you grew up with a model of the physical
world that was based on the four elements of earth water fire and Air
and suppose though that you then insist in your Chemistry classes that you have
to use that model and you refuse to learn the periodic table of the elements that is the current standard way to do
modern chemistry I suspect it will be very difficult for you but it would instantly be easier and
more effective to just think in terms of the of the periodic table
so I don't know if that's a perfect example but there is some similarity between that and the situation of
learning the Dharma teachings in order to be able to walk the April path if that's what you're doing in your
practice but probably it's even more important in the case of the Dharma because the Dharma is not just a cognitive model
like we have in chemistry it's a whole body issue a whole being issue
and I've seen this in my own practice I started studying the Buddhist texts
maybe one year into my practice and I've devoted quite a lot of energy to learning the teachings listening to
talks and trying to understand some of the more difficult ideas that the Buddha
taught and in in ways that I can't quite explain logically
phrases and ideas that are rooted in the teachings sometimes come forth spontaneously in
everyday life and also on cushioning I remember one time I was doing a search
on the internet about a specific some kind of a scientific explanation for something and I found all kinds of
fascinating articles and videos which got me kind of excited and joyful because it was something really cool and
my mind can do that kind of thing and for some reason my mind noticed that
my mind state was similar to the first half of the Awakening factors which are the energizing factors of Investigation
energy and joy and because there was mindfulness I felt
like I sort of felt my mind naturally step back and expand to take in the
bigger picture of what I was doing and as that happened there was this natural calming of the energy and a release from
being wrapped up in the energy and joy and excitement um but there was you know there was
still joy and interest there but I felt the balance coming in of including the more calming factors of tranquility and
composure and equanimity so these were kind of everyday versions
of the factors of Awakening but still I I marveled at how my mind drew on its
knowledge of the Awakening factors to recognize some of those factors in my present moment experience
and then it drew on its knowledge of how the Awakening factors operate in the mind to bring them into balance
they operate by having the energizing factors and the calming factors present at the same time and in balance
so you know that can happen just in our everyday life and it happens on the cushion too sometimes I get Snippets of
teachings coming into my mind key phrases or verses they come in kind of
like a Dharma coach during meditation sometimes and I would guess that you might have some examples like this from your life
and practice also in the foundational text on mindfulness
practice the fourth establishment of mindfulness
is about seeing in terms of the Dharma so this is recognized and it's a
fundamental practice the fourth Foundation is mindfulness in terms of
dalmas which are then expounded as being the five hindrances the five Aggregates
The Sixth Sense bases seven factors of Awakening and four noble truths but
those are just representative what we're what we're generally doing is learning to see in terms of the karma teachings
through this quality of listening and learning or suta we gradually cultivate
what I like to call the mind of Dharma where we could say the heart of Dharma and in terms of the Dharma resources for
this week we're training our heart to bring forth the qualities that are named in the teachings which include also
things like the Brahma viharas the heart qualities generosity patients as well as the various lists that I mentioned
so this this heart of Dharma is a heart that knows the teachings that can stay
mindful in a range of experiences and that responds in line with ethics and
heart qualities and sees in terms of wisdom you might notice how that brings in a
number of other qualities that are on this week's list like ethics and wisdom and generosity
so as we listen internally and externally learning to recognize the Dharma
qualities that are all around us we will more and more be able to respond in line
with the Dharma which will be in a non-harming and Wise Way
so I wish you very well with your connection to the to the Dharma today
thank you