so good morning everyone and those of you here welcome to imc and
for some of you it might be one of the largest gatherings you've even been to in the last two years
and if that if that's the case welcome and i appreciate maybe that it's a big deal for your heart to do this
and for those of you who are online welcome and uh appreciate that
we have a such a wide ranging community coming together to
meditate this this day
so i'll do this uh meditation what i offer in two parts but i'll say a few
words now and then i'll follow up with that with the dedication of merit
and to begin with i'd like to say that it's a little bit is that hard to hear
is a little bit soft should i increase the volume a little bit so let's see
so if i listen in silence to see if it got louder it doesn't work is that louder now
you could also use the hearing system devices they they they work still
so so i would like to say to start
is
one of the principles especially in meditation that may be easier to understand here
than anywhere else but it applies in many other places in our life
and that is that peace begins in our own hearts
that peace begins for each individual it starts here in ourselves rather than
looking for it in the world around us and uh
and uh and in meditation if you can't do
start with peace in your own heart then we have peace
in our speech at least out loud we're not speaking
if uh and ideally we have uh
peaceful speech in our own minds where how we talk about ourselves or
talk about what's going on we try to do it in a way that's coming from a place of peace
of compassion of care generosity
if we can't do that then in meditation we're doing it with our body
we're sitting in a peaceful posture a posture in which we're
you know we're not going to move particularly unless you have to
make yourself more comfortable so it's not a posture in which you're going to punch someone out
to this time this is a peaceful posture and to take refuge in the posture
take refuge and inspiration that for these minutes that this is a place of peace
this body take refuge in whatever way in which
your mind can speak peacefully take refuge in that
interest intention desire to do so
and it might be more important take refuge in the desire to do so than our ability to do so
it might be more inspiring and meaningful to be with people and be oneself who has this wish to work and go
in this direction and perhaps in your hearts
maybe take refuge in your heart's capacity to sit in such a way that
it's peaceful and peaceful means that
my understanding is that it's a heart that wishes to do no harm
it wants to avoid causing harm anywhere to self or others
and this is one of the great things to do in this world and that kind of peace begins with
ourselves so to assume this posture meditation a posture
that's meant to be a peaceful posture
and to gently close your eyes
and it's possible you don't feel particularly peaceful and that's okay
as you start meditation
the it's okay beginning of meditation
is the beginning of being at peace with what is so for agitated or
angry upset it's okay
because here we're gonna meet everything that is occurring
with an openness with a willingness to be present and see it
without condemning anything for these minutes just to be present for
how it goes in us
taking a few minutes to feel your body how's your body now
and then within this body is the breathing and from this place within where
breathing the in-breath begins take a long slow deep inhale
and as you exhale relax your body
relax into here now the present moment
and then letting your breathing return to normal
with a normal breathing for a few rounds of
exhales continue to relax your body
and relaxing is a movement towards peace
towards being peaceful calm
and then letting go of relaxing
the body instead for a few rounds of breathing
if it's possible relax your breathing
kind of a lightening up softening and breathing it
allowing the body to breathe itself
not trying to use your breathing or influence or to affect your breathing
you do the breathing but kind of getting out of the way of
breathing and accompany it with your
attention
maybe the idea of being side by side with your breathing
in whatever way that you can easily do so
accompany your breathing peacefully with a peaceful attention
as if peace is your offering
what you offer your breathing
so
okay
you
so
and then as we come to the end of the sinning
the dedication of merit of care for the world
is not an addendum to meditation
it's an expression a peaceful expression that arises
out of a peaceful heart it's not a duty
obligation but rather continuation
of the care that we offer to ourselves as we meditate
i care that then spreads outwards into the world
it's also a wise thing to do for oneself
if you want to be peaceful
offer peace to others
if you want safety be a safe person
for others if you want to see heal your sadness or
your anger be a healing presence
for the sadness and anger of others
if you want to be understood understand others take the time to know
them in their challenges
we could offer ourselves in our presence the way we are the way we attend and are aware of
others we can offer so much and may it be that as we end this
meditation
that we offer our concern and care and kind regard for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
may everyone has been affected by the
fighting and crisis of ukraine may they find a way
to peace into happiness into freedom
may all the forces of goodness in this world
come forth at this point to offer this goodness to the world
may we offer our goodness may it spread from us into the world
[Music]
[Music] so
okay
so good morning all of you are here thank you for being here
and
hello to everyone attending online happy to have you
so uh from time to time
all too often there are
current events which are so big that it feels that
to not address them as part of the dharma talk it shouldn't be done i can't ignore them
that this dharma practice that we do is a practice to be present for what's happening in the world to be witnesses
and to care and some things are so big that they should be named and
see where we go and so the
fighting in the ukraine i think of has affected me this way i i don't think
i could not talk about it in some way but what do we say what do we under how
we understand this you know there was a earthquake in haiti last summer
and that was such a clear event that
you know we through the youtube channel and that else here at imc we raised over thirty
thousand dollars to dedicate to a wonderful non-profit partners in health
and uh and that was seemed clear but with ukraine it
it's just there's so much not known yet that's so unknown how this is evolving
and what's going to be needed and what's happening so in terms of responding
to the what needed there from people like us that's obvious to me
but i think being caring and concerned for the people of ukraine and people of russia and a lot of the ordinary people
in russia are going to suffer and maybe much of the suffering the world's going to suffer we don't know how
this is going to expand and will it spill out beyond the borders of the ukraine
and uh so we're kind of just you know at least
watching now and seeing and hoping that the people who have some role
in addressing this are doing it wisely and carefully and
for the long term and it's hard it's hard to know that it's hard easy to second-guess it's easy to have opinions
but it's hard to really know what's going on and what what what is consequential
what's going to make a difference 911 happened and as a community we
actually had a special meeting i think on a tuesday evening or wednesday evening
so we could just meet and process it as a community and then uh the second invasion of iraq
and the invasion of afghanistan and and these kinds of things go on and on
uh you know they've gone down through history there's been war and people attacking each other and
and it seems like most times when it happens people say it's different this time
and this time ukraine is different because it's always different it's always the same
in some ways it's not news that these things happen it's olds
and uh in a bigger perspective this is what human life is about this is the time of
the buddha there was a war the buddha died
you know around him as he as he was getting old and close to his death he was cognizant of that
the countries of his area were getting ready to fight and go to war to each other for each other and he witnessed
fortifications being built and on his last travels before he died
so what is it like to be a one of the great champions of peace in a peaceful way and
ethical way of living a non-violent way of living and dedicated his life to that and then
to watch around amazing oh to watch that
violence or you know getting ready to start
so here we are with this and uh you know and i don't know what to say do
you don't know what to say if i could offer opinions but you're not here for my opinions
exactly so what did we say one of the things that uh i'd like to
say is that uh this is a time
as if there's ever not a time but this is a time to stay close to the dharma
and the word dharma includes much more than buddhism to call say to go close to buddhism i think
would be almost be a i don't know i was going to say an
insult to buddhism because that's buddhism is not about itself the buddhism the dharma is about
the the
discovery and expression
of a heart that has no conflict a heart which is at peace with itself
a heart which doesn't cause any self-harm then one of the ways that self-harm is
caused is by harming others
i can't get away from it
the one of the definitions for evil a word
which i seldom use but many buddhist texts in english
translations of the suttos use the word evil as if it's whether it is or not is a
scholarly question whether it's appropriate to translate that way but one of the definitions of evil
is evil is when the mind turns on itself
to harm others the mind turns on itself to harm others
and what this implies is certain actions of evil
harms the person who's evil certain expressions of hostility
harms the person who's hostile and
there's a jataka tale these old fables
buddhist fables that were composed at some point and
there was a donkey who is being led to slaughter
i guess for meat or something and uh when the donkey realizes
it's going to be slaughtered the donkey's first reaction is to laugh
but then after laughing for a while then it starts crying
and after it cries for a while the slaughterer says to the donkey what's going on with
you i'm about to kill you but first you laugh and then you cry explain yourself
and the donkey said well for 500 lifetimes
i was reborn as a donkey and this will be the last time
it's so great i'm so happy that i'm done with it like he exhausted his karma of
being reborn 500 times to the donkey so he's laughing apparently he's happy
and then but why were you crying well the reason i was reborn as a donkey for
500 times was i slaughtered a donkey
500 lifetimes ago and then and now you are going to
slaughter me and you will be reborn as a donkey for 500 lives
so so you know the car and the teachings of karma is
that what you do comes back to you in some form or other
and this self-harm is a deeply you know we harm others we harm
ourselves so who's harming each other right now
and what how are they harming themselves so looking at ukraine and russia i i
almost don't want to answer that question i have that principle in my mind and concern
but the place i want to apply it the most is to ourselves
how do we respond to all this
because unless we can do something directly and if we can please help
but unless you can do something directly perhaps peace begins with yourself
perhaps that's the person that you can have the most impact on and if you can't if you don't know how
to be peaceful is there any hope for the ukraine
if we don't know how to resolve our own inner conflict and challenges who can
we expecting other people to do it friends of mine just went to spirit rock
to participate in the month-long retreat there
and and one person was concerned that it was the wrong time to go because what's
happening in the world is an international stage is so big and such a big concern and this seemed to be
maybe a person didn't say this but be selfish to go off and do meditation like this you know
and i said it's the opposite unless you can you know do something for for the
world directly this is actually meditating is actually one of the greatest responses you can do
because this path of meditation that we're offering in buddhism is a path to get into the bottom of our
own peace
to discover our capacity for living in non-conflict in a wise and
generous and supportive way how not to hate how not to get angry how
not to be hostile how not to be greedy how not to have
lust for power and money in such a way they were harming
people around how not to live in delusion it's a powerful path that's of really
uprooting the attachments the clinging the grasping the fears
that are kind of like barbs in the heart or close down the heart or
constricted or you know limited it creates a kind of heart that
the heart or the good heart we have is lost
and when we're not connected deeply to ourselves then it's our surface
reactivity which gets the upper hand and surface reactivity
is usually not so wise reactivity that you know anger for example reacting angrily to the world
it is usually not that wise the consequences are not that good sometimes they are
they accomplish what we want in the short term but in the long term do they really help
us live in a better world or better situation and i've said this story before but i
say yo please allow me to say it again because such a powerful for me lesson
that you know i try to live wisely that parent wisely with my
sons when they were young and sometimes they were challenging for me
with my parenting skills and i felt like you know it was hopeless
unless i kind of used my strong voice so i never hit them or anything but i
never was in danger of it but uh sometimes i use a strong voice which was done consciously
carefully because i didn't know what else to do and like you have to stop what you're doing that you cannot do that anymore
and it was effective but then one day i heard my older son
use the same voice to his one and a half year old brother
and i said what have i done i accomplished what i wanted to do in stopping the behavior but what was the
influence what a what a horrible conditioning influence example
i gave to a small child that it's okay to do this so he could turn around and do it to his son his brother
what does his brother learn and then it goes on right from one
person to another one generation to the other and they learn somehow at their early age
this is okay but what are the consequences
what are the consequences of invading another country the consequences of certainly the people
who kill get killed and died when i when i think of war and people getting killed i not only think about
the people who get killed but their ripple of their family and their friends and their neighborhood and
it goes out and on and on and some of this suffering goes on for decades and decades
in my family that i've in i mean i grew up
very much uh under the influence i was born after world war ii
but i grew up with it as a very strong presence in my family life
my parents my grandparents my parents-in-law
and their parents all were kind of deeply affected by world war ii and the
violence so much so that uh it still affects me
to this day i mean uh the uh some of the some of the horrible things
that happen to some of them it touches me very very deeply
especially because i have two sons the older one who knows firsthand that firsthand knows
has first-hand conversations with his grandfather actually um when he was 14 he interviewed my
grandfather and did a little video of interviewing him about his my grandfa my father-in-law's
experiences in the concentration camps in germany where he was a prisoner
and you know it's 70 years ago now or so and uh
more and so it's still alive so these things go on and on
the uh things that happen in around world war ii still are alive and communities
things that happen in civil war still alive in this country and communities
so and i would argue that if i may that the violence of the american
revolutionary war is still rippling affecting this country
coursing through it in a way that we maybe we don't directly see but i think that the violence of that time
is still an effect here so it goes on and on these things
and uh and so i think about that ripple effect of violence and
and what causes does it do so in buddhism there is a very strong in
the teachings of the buddha a very strong repeated emphasis
on non-harming non-violence on not killing the first precept is not
to kill and you don't have to go very far in the
teachings of the buddha to find all kinds of direct teachings about the value of
radical non-harming radical non-violence even to the extent that
if someone's harming you he says do not give in to harm
he does say that you can you can strike back
if someone attacks you in order to escape so you don't just stand there and
passively be beat up but uh but there is this radical strong idea of
non-violence and so some people some uh kings in ancient india
interpreted this to that they were going to have their army stand down and not
by violence not to have capital punishment and all these kinds of things
and uh and i have i've had an adult life where
i've i felt ever since i was about probably 18 dedicated to
non-violence and it was irrelevant for me because when i was 18
i was of the age that could be drafted for the vietnam war so it was very alive that i would be
called up and had to go and fight the war across the pacific
and uh so i had to kind of contend with that you know so war was really a live and present and what do i do if i
get drafted and uh and so i was not going to fight
i knew that i would not go uh i'm from norway
and originally and i went back there a few times and
i wasn't drafted because my draft number was so low at that point so i never didn't have to
go but a few years later a couple of years later i went to live in norway go back for a year
and there i was uh uh surprised to discover that there was a movement
of that you could you could be a conscientious objector in norway's mandatory military service for men back
then but you could be a conscientious objector and if you were you you didn't have to do the one-year
military service that all males had to do but you had you had to do two years
of public service a friend of mine spent two years almost two years working in a hospital
in order to do the you know the equivalent to support the country i guess but some of the conscientious of
objectors in norway protested and they said that um they knew about
russia being right nearby and russia you know within that time was still kind of
pushing the edges of the border going to see you know testing things i guess and so people
were worried about russia and norway in the mid-1970s
and and so some of the conscious objectors who didn't want to become soldiers and fight
uh waters wanted to be able to defend the country if it was attacked
and they were asking for a training in civil disobedience
training and non-violent resistance uh and they were lobbying
trying to get that to happen i don't know if it ever happened in norway but it has happened now in sweden and
finland they have trainings now i don't know how extensive it is but they train some
people there in the techniques of non-violent civil disobedience and non-violent
resistance and the reason i can bring it up in the following up talking about how important
non-violence is in the teachings of the buddha non-harming that very too often and when people hear
that they say well that just means we have to passively allow people to attack us
and there no self-defense is allowed you're not supposed to allow to fight back and down through the centuries
buddhist kings and buddhist countries have justified standing armies and fighting defensively
because defending yourself is allowed in the dharma they say just not attacking people they're not
being the aggressor but how do you know who's the aggressor and
who's the defender i mean right now i think the president of russia putin
thinks of his himself as a defender that's at least that's what he says and he keeps referring to me being
defensive but you know for many of us it looks like he's the aggressor but so where do
you decide that so if the if the justification for war
is that it's the you know that that's the only way to defend yourself
then the buddhist principle of non-violence is is conditional it's situational
and then which situations do we live by it and which don't we live by it
when i was also around 19 or so i came under very much under the influence of a
particular scholar in the united states academic named jean sharp
and jean sharp wrote these wonderful he was a scholar of non-violent
civil disobedience efforts around the world the non-violent way and resistance by which
people resisted successfully
dictators and authoritarian regimes and things like that and he has a he had a he has a
three-volume book on non-violence that goes through it was kind of
eye-opening for me to see ecosmart chronicles and lists all the different techniques
sophisticated techniques that are used by people who engage in this kind of work
and and how so many times it's been successful and sometimes it hasn't
uh it was interesting he points out that you know mahatma gandhi is the great exemplar
of non-violence civil disobedience
uh he was inspired by civil disobedience in this in russia in
1905. nicholas ii was the tsar of russia at
that time there were massive public strikes and
demonstrations non-violent ones on the part of the demonstrators
that eventually forced caused the nick that mother
terzar to create the first uh parliament in russia the duma
and then he had to contend with the members of parliament they shared the power and you know they continue that
way but so mahatma gandhi saw that and he said wow that can be done
and that inspired him in his work so it's interesting that how important russia would have been in russia as an
example given what's happening now in the ukraine
there was the orange revolution and you know about that 2004
and that was a student-led movement of non-violence that uh brought down the
the uh the the russian supported president of ukraine
who it probably was uh rigged elections and a lot of corruption
but the those students in the orange revolution 2004
they were reading gene sharpe he hit because he he was one of the
people i know who spent a lot of time as an academic writing and describing
the techniques and the methods of non-violent civil disobedience
and he says people will die with non-violent civil disobedience
some people say well it doesn't work because if you put yourself on the front line you know they'll just kill you
they will maybe but if you put soldiers on the front
lines they'll die too
fewer people his argument fewer people die with civil disobedience than with armed armed armed struggle
so when i say all this that
in buddhism this central uh ethical tenet is non-violence
non-harming not killing it it's possible
that that strategy that way of living should not be done naively
that this is something we bring our wisdom to our intelligence to our reflections to
to really engage and think about how can do this what's the practical way what's the wise way what's the active way
to do this too many people want to defend
themselves and their first strategy is to get a gun in this country
are they really safer is that the the instinct is that's how you make yourself safe but is that a really safe way
what about doing the research the reflection they look at all the alternative ways to become safe
are there other ways to become safe than having a gun are there better ways of becoming safe than having a gun
however it takes research and intelligence and engagement in this process
and not many people want to do that there's some you know that we want to do
the instinctual so i can get on with our lives so here we are with
the ukraine and this major event in this world the world and there's so much stress these
days with the pandemic and all kinds of other things and politics it's almost like the more stress there
is the more stress it produces the more people feel the stress of it
all the worry of it all the fear of it all the more they take on stress and then
when we're stressed it's a recipe for more reactivity it's a recipe for anger and for fear and
for dysfunctional ways of responding
with too much stress if we don't not careful with our stress
we add to the stress in the world so this practice that we do
is a revolutionary thing it's a radical thing to do it's not it's finding a way
to not contribute to the stress of the societies of the
world it's a radical way of being someone who does the opposite
someone who's almost like a a healthy a sink
where the stresses of the world can come into us you know we experience it and know it in
a present for it and somehow we can process it and empty it and
de-stress ourselves from it we can go through the world
committed to not adding to this stress of the world
not committed not to add to the violence of the world to the anger of the world
to do our work is such an important thing what we're doing someone has to do it
some people have to show everyone else that it's possible to become free
of these instinctual forces that one way the other contribute to causing more
harm and more harm and responds to harm with more harm and passes it on from generation to
generation someone has to do this work
and there are people who are doing it all over the world we're not alone in doing it
but i think this is what this practice we're doing is about most importantly
and i would say that the reason i'm here today
and because i'm here you're here today
imc is here in edward city today wonderful one of the
causes for why this whole youtube thing is happening and we have video camera on it happening today
one of the conditions for all this is because
i believe i believed when i was quite young
that this work of finding peace in oneself
becoming free and oneself of clinging and reactivity
is a way of responding to war in this world
my whole first interest in buddhism was as a response to the vietnam war
my whole reason to become to dedicate my life to buddhism was because of witnessing
from a distance the violence of war in the early 80s and
being deeply impacted by it war has been part of my life and the you
know something i'm conscious of and aware of without ever i never had the misfortune of being in the presence of
it really hardly at all but it's been it's part of my my whole
life experience that it's influenced me and it's part of the reason why i'm dedicated to be a dharma teacher and to
do all this for me this is not only
stress reduction so we can go back to work and live stress for you at work
this is a revolutionary activity if we go to the depths of our heart and really
find a way to uproot the deepest attachments we have
and we become peacemakers for this world
and maybe just locally maybe it's just for our neighbors
but uh how does it ripple out from your neighbors
who do you know who you don't know who you touch and how this goes out and out and out into
the world peace begins with ourselves if you want a peaceful world
start with yourself find out how you can
be at peace find out how you can walk in peace
how you can speak in peaceful ways how you can relate to others in ways that they don't
feel that they feel safe and feel like there's another way
and learn how to be in conflict
wisely and this is you know we're not going to not be in conflict
with people i think that's that's not part of what life is about
but can we be in conflict peacefully with them can we be in conflict or in a sense
where the the motivation for how we are with the conflict
is cooperation not competition
not not to win and they lose
but can the motivation be how can we both win there will be conflict conflict doesn't
betray peace it does not mean the absence of conflict to have peace is the absence of harm
so that's what not knowing what to do for the ukraine at this juncture
i feel like we do the the other great thing
for the ukraine at least let's do our practice
stay close to the dharma stay close to the practice let what's happening in the world to be
an inspiration and to evoke a wonderful aspiration
that this practice is so important so valuable
you know it's it is a way of responding to the world to happily know you have
something precious in this practice maybe there's ways you can give
yourself to this practice a little bit more that will feel like a reason that you
know is a response to what's happening in the world you're not ignoring it
you're responding in this powerful way by becoming a person
who's a beacon for peace wouldn't that be great for all of us to deal with
so those are my thoughts today and uh wouldn't it be great if this is
the last time i give a talk and responding to war in this world
i have i have hope that that's the case though that's probably naive
and one of the reasons i have some hope is that as much as we're seeing fighting
going on in the ukraine we're seeing right currently at least the international community
responding nonviolently and economically
who knows maybe it'll teach us that war is old-fashioned
and war doesn't really work and we have to find other ways
to work through our conflicts than through war so hoping so i have high hopes for
the sanctions the economic debate that this will be seen as a non-violent
way of responding to aggression and will make a difference
so may we all find ways to be non-violent in our lives
and support that in the world around us and if you want to learn more i read some of the works of gene sharp
thank you so thank you