so again welcome welcome everybody it's nice to practice together
after especially some of us right practicing on our own for these years during the pandemic it's nice to come
together so thank you thank you as well as thank you to the people on the other side of that camera
or on youtube also quite something right that kind of imc has really grown
so tonight i'd like to talk a little bit more or continue on this series that i'm
doing about the seven factors of awakening you wouldn't be surprised if i said
there were seven factors and i'm going to talk about number six
so i've done the first five and so the seven factors awakening are
mindfulness investigation energy joy tranquility
tonight i'm going to talk about samadhi and the next one after this is equanimity
so i'm using this polyword samadhi i'll spend some time this evening
unpacking that and what does it mean and maybe why i'm not using the
an english word that's often used one one reason is i like the sound of
this word samadhi it kind of has that feeling somebody
it's kind of this soft spacious maybe expensive experience
so the seven factors of awakening they have these kind of energizing factors
and we have tranquilizing factors and then mindfulness which is in between
so samadhi is part of the tranquilizing it's the with tranquility samadhi and
equanimity with the investigation energy and joy
being a little bit more energetic so it gives a little clue
about what samadhi means for now i'm going to use this uh
definition it's uh when the mind and body feel unified
settled and steady and there's a sense of well-being
unified subtle steady with a sense of well-being
and the sense of well-being sometimes can be really powerful or it can be really subtle
and i'll talk about this a little bit but one thing before i talk about maybe a
little bit more of a description of how it is or how we might cultivate it
i'll talk a little bit about why should we bother why should we even
you know be concerned with think about practice with learn about whatever might be this
idea of samadhi and we might say that samadhi prepares
the mind it creates the conditions it helps prepares the mind for some letting go
and for some deep letting go and it also prepares a mind for some
deep understanding so about this understanding and the letting go they often go together
this practice this tradition really emphasizes it's with we have these greater understandings
that it just naturally happens that the clinging the craving starts to diminish
as we start to understand and see how clinging and craving
is a way that doesn't lead to greater happiness it's not a source of lasting happiness
and so samadhi is a way when there's some settledness and steadiness we can
see a little this little bit more clearly in exactly the same way
in which if there were a telescope and we wanted to see something that
maybe it's not so clear not so obvious up in the sky it's really helpful to stick this
telescope on a tripod so we might think of samadi as this type of tripod
that enables to see things that we wouldn't be able to see otherwise
and one of the first insights that we have with our mindfulness practice
is oh my gosh my mind is out of control i didn't realize how much my mind is
like scattered and distracted and does everything except what i want it to do
this is you know i think all of us have this experience when we start a meditation practice
specifically a mindfulness practice
and so as the mind starts to get more and more still as they're a little bit more samadhi
then we start to see that oh this what seemed like was this just this
out of control mind this experience that's filled with thoughts and plans
and ideas and fantasies all these types of things
as the mind starts to get more still we can penetrate through these
which seems like maybe a solid way in which the mind works
and we can see oh actually these things are arising and passing they come and they go
sometimes really quickly sometimes really in a longer duration sometimes they seem
like they're flickering sometimes they feel like they're just moving like sludge
but with this samadhi we start to see different characteristics of our experience beyond
uh seems like i'm never present and this seeing this this inconstancy
allows some of this letting go allows some of this
softening and lessening of any clinging that we might
be doing so this is the direction in which our
practice goes is with towards greater and greater stillness and peace and sense of well-being
and so we can use this as a guidepost too with our practice
as we explore different ways of practicing as we learn new things is there a way in which we can
use this experiences and ideas of steadiness and stability and well-being
as a way to kind of direct the direction we want to go with our practice how do we know with
what we're doing is working or not working or is worth persevering with or not just something
that headed towards samadhi
so somebody involves is this kind of feeling unified so it
involves the whole mind and the whole body in fact this distinction between body
and mind starts to blur and in some states even goes away
so it's this real sense of collectedness unification
also this non-distraction we might say where things just are
like settling down you know i've heard andrea fella maybe some of you have to use this uh simile
of a snow globe you shake it up right and all the glitter goes but then you just put it down and things just start
to settle in the same way when the samadhi is present it's small it's kind of like
this settling process and one way that's nice of thinking about it as maybe like
a as a snow globe is that instead of somebody being this on or off
switch this idea you either have it or you don't we can kind of think like well does it
feel like the shaking is happening or does it feel like this settling is happening
so it's more like this recognition that there's it's a spectrum
right so samadhi is going towards calming is going towards settling
it's not is it there yes or no it's just one end of the spectrum of
the amount of busyness and distraction we might have
so this so we might think of samadhi then as this sliding scale or a continuum of a
spectrum and we might with our practice gently encourage more of this sense of calmness
so when we sometimes hear this word sometimes it gets translated as this word concentration
but i know certainly for me for years at the first of my practice i thought concentration was this real straining
bearing down working really hard way to practice
and yeah the mind gets settled a little bit more but it's missing that well-being
quality when we do this and it's missing this quality of
ease it's missing a quality of uh maybe it's uh
rather than like stapling the mind onto the object it uh it has more of a sense of just
being unified or or i don't know it's a
samadhi is a nicer feeling than just bearing down and really trying to focus
so there's a few qualities that are within samadhi that i'd like to
highlight to talk about to help us remember that it's not just this bearing down forcing the mind to really
get concentrated so one thing i'll say is
that there's this um some of the qualities that we find within samadhi when we're like moving towards that end
of the spectrum of a little of more collectedness and unification and well-being
some of the qualities we'll find is this steadiness
as it starts to become a bit more steadiness supports investigation
so there's a little bit more investigation or maybe investigation is
not exactly the right word but just as i said with the
tripod with a telescope with the steadiness we can see things differently so in the
as we're moving towards more and more samadhi there's a uh seeing things a little bit
differently than we might do with our just our regular every day and
which we just go through our business so there's this capacity to maybe look at
what's happening see a little bit more deeply to learn from what's happening
in a way that's maybe in a relaxed easy way for it to penetrate into our
experience so that's one quality that's happens
when there's samadhi but also we can see that there's a certain refinement we might use this word refinement or
delicacy of the attention sometimes when we're doing mindfulness
and where it's like the object and the mind drifts away of course the mind drifts away this is what minds do right
and there might be of like dang it you know just right this way in which there's this uh
a little bit of i don't know forcefulness and trying to really stick back here
so when there's uh as the mind starts to come down there can be a little bit more like oh
and maybe just with the subject maybe just touching lightly instead of i use this word kind of like stapling on or
forcefully on there's this way in which it can be
a little yeah a little bit more gentle a little bit more delicate and this delicate gentle
awareness can see things that are more subtle
so i just talked about how investigation enables to see things that you couldn't normally see but
also we can see things more subtle and as the objects are becoming more subtle
the quality of the mindfulness or quality of the mind maybe i'll say it's also getting i'll use this word
delicate or maybe uh refined
or smooth or something like this and so this is a quality that's
happening too this softening or maybe a little bit more subtle or delicate so this is another
quality of samadhi but or maybe i should say before i move on
part of the really powerful parts of samadhi is that with this as the objects are becoming
more subtle and the awareness is becoming more delicate
and that might be the right word i'm not sure maybe uh you know i'm going this with my hands
like refined it's not quite as rough you know like how sometimes there's material that feels rough and there's material
that feels like silk or something like this but then we're able to see more and more
subtle ways in which we are clinging more and more subtle ways in which there
might be some aversion where we want things to be different that we just might be so accustomed to that we don't
notice and then when we start to see oh yeah here's a little bit of clinging here's a
little bit of tightening here i hadn't noticed then there could be some letting go
which also supports some deepening of the samadhi and more freedom
more ease so another quality that is present when
there's some samadhi is this idea of malleability or
flexibility or plasticity so the mind can
is a little bit more flexible it's especially when there's a sense of
well-being as there's often right the mind doesn't do what we want it to do
especially like in the mid in the earlier in our practice and if you've had a day in which there's been a lot of
agitation right when we sit to meditate we notice like oh my goodness my mind is all over the place
but as the as we start to settle then
with samadhi the mind becomes a little bit more malleable and agile and maybe able to approach things
a little bit differently there sometimes there can be a way and with our practice we have a sense like
okay nope this is what i do i'm with mindfulness of the breath and when the mind wanders i come back
when i count 1 through 10 and and this can be really great to have this as a practice but there can also be
a time in which maybe that's not the best practice at that moment
maybe it would be helpful to open up and do a little bit of loving kindness or some softness
if we're really agitated with something that's uh some ill will is really prevalent with
us or maybe we're being really hard on ourselves and we're kind of like beating
ourselves over the head with this kind of mindfulness so this malleability is to be able to
recognize what's needed here what's what's the best way forward i'm
going like this with my hands to kind of like in a soft gentle way not in the way that we have to find the
most pleasant experience and flip around but in a way this i have borne out of
care sensitivity to what's going to support some settling like
what would be helpful here should i stay with the breath
maybe maybe i'll just pay attention a little bit more to the exhale the exhale
can be a way in which we can like calm or as i said maybe um we could do some
loving-kindness third way maybe we could open up the awareness and have this
sense of being receptive so instead of bringing the awareness to an experience we more kind of like open
up and allow the experiences to arise these are like subtle differences but
when there's samadhi there can be this malleability and this agility to
recognize what's needed without bouncing around too much
trying to find just you know the perfect perfect uh experience
and so and that maybe i was in this uh a quote here from the suta that sue does this
this particular quote is all is all throughout the suit is in there a number of times
and i i myself feel kind of inspired by this so the buddha is describing his own
awakening experience and he described that right before it was
his awakening enlightenment he described his mind
and he said that his mind was concentrated using this word samadhi
concentrated purified cleansed unblemished
rid of defilement malleable wieldy
and steady and it turned atta attained to imperturb ability
so right this is this is why it's a factor of awakening right this is kind of helps creates the conditions in which
awakening can happen but i appreciate very much these words you know malleable
wieldy you know and steady doesn't mean you know um
you know holding on for dear life and i'm kind of saying emphasizing this
over and over again because i suffered a lot in my early retreat practice with i had
this idea that i just had to strive strive strive strain strain strain as much as i could and oh my gosh it was
miserable it was really miserable you know i'm being on long retreats and
feeling like oh no pain no gain i hadn't quite got the memo
that there was supposed to be some well-being associated with this
so of course that's another quality of samadhi is this sense of well-being
for me this is like the ah part of samadhi like there's a sense of ah
yeah okay yeah i'm here i'm right here
just collectedness a sense of okay i'm here
so this well-being that comes with somebody is really not only is it an integral part
of the practice and the experience but it's actually really important
it's important for a number of reasons one is the letting go all these subtle letting
goes i'll say in the plural that happens with the the more freedom we find the more
closer or in the direction of awakening is all about letting go it's not about
you know accumulating so it's not about accumulating meditative states it's only about letting go and this is definitely
how one gets into somebody too are you practice it but the well-being
supports of oh okay yeah i can let go of this right when we're in the middle of
emotional distress or we're in pain we are not in a place to let go of things
we can't let go of our habits we can't let go of the usual way our views of how things work our ideas about ourselves we
just can't so this well-being supports this letting go as well as the understanding
we see the understanding that things are changing they're flickering they're not what we
thought they were and that also supports the letting go but so does well-being
and i'm using this vague word well-being because it shows up in so many different flavors
and so many different ways with samadhi so i kind of like this generic word
well-being that i'll use for right now but it's not only
because it supports letting go that this well-being is really important
if we have some of this experience in our meditative
experiences and our meditation sessions of experiencing some sense of well-being
then this starts to we might say permeate our experience
that carries off of the cushion and into our daily life
what we start to experience sitting we start to know oh this is available
the mind knows how to do this the mind and body together know how to do this
and it starts to allow some of this well-being to show up off the cushion
and this maybe allows for some emotional stability
this emotional well-being allows us to have a little more stability in our emotional life which really allows our
daily life off the cushion to unfold in a different way
so so this is kind of like dipping into this sense of well-being this
also helps us to no longer be pursuing sensual pleasures i need one
more dopamine hit i just need that for me it's cookies
or maybe it's you know the internet or buying things or
gambling i don't know what you know all of us have things right if we start to have these experiences of
well-being then we start to realize oh yeah these dopamine hits they are
actually inferior they clearly are inferior
to these sense of well-being in these meditative states so these
knowing that something better is possible they start to lose their pull
they start to be less compelling when we're able to have some alternative experiences and i
would say it's often not until people have some meditative experiences of well-being
that their relationships to pursuing pleasure really starts to shift
right i mean human beings this is part of our biology is to pursue pleasure so it's not until you experience
deeper more satisfying more pervasive
well-being than our experiences to all of uh what happens in daily life can
shift so in some ways i i maybe i'll just
emphasize this one more time that that well-being is just as important as like the settling
so these two things are happening the settling steadiness and the well-being
the way that we cultivate samadhi is we're cultivating both of
these both the well-being and the settledness
so to cultivate somali it does take patience it does take consistent practice
it's not something that will happen right away for many people
some people do have a propensity for kind of like a settling
part of this can be is how we spend our daily lives that if you are a preschool teacher and
you're having to keep track of what all the kids are doing no no johnny don't do this you know susie don't do that then
you know you're always trying to keep track then this is how you spend your days then you're getting really good at taking
being aware of many things at once or if you're an office manager and or people
are calling all the time or customer service you know these types of things is different than if you have for
example um a profession that maybe is a scientist who is trying
to look through a microscope for you know you have to kind of really be focused and you don't have a lot of
other sensory input or mathematician or computer scientist or
some of these things right so how we spend our days does have an impact what our
professions or if you're uh yeah if you tend if what how
i'll just leave that i'll say that how you spend your days as well as it's some of it's a mystery i don't know
why people don't know why some individuals it's just a little bit easier than for other
individuals there's no telling why but
there's this way in which we can think about cultivating samadhi
as it's not all about bearing down it's focusing i think i've made this point in
so many different ways right but one way to think about when we're cultivating this is that 50 a good half
of the practice is about relaxing
and letting go and kind of like tuning into the ease
whatever ease is available even if that ease is not your dominant experience that might just be a little
corner of your experience but not being dismissive of that
quiet sense of contentment or a little bit of sense of like ah when
the mind starts to settle down at least 50 of the practice is
tuning into that seems like this should be straightforward but right human beings
we have this negativity bias we want to just tune into everything that's wrong so this turns out not to be necessarily
so easy to just stay with what feels comfortable
what feels okay what feels good what's pleasant or even what's neutral so 50
there another 25 maybe it's just this attitude
of receptivity i'm going like this with my hands it's kind of like an openness
this maybe has a quality of equanimity so rather than going and trying to fix
and make that be different and do this or something like this with our meditation 25 of his is kind of just an
openness this can um allow
like things to arise and pass away without our chasing them or trying to change them or some way
and then it's only 25 percent whereas this effort to kind of like stay
focused or stay present on our experience
and often when uh with concentration practice very common to stay focused on the
breath the sensations of breathing or the movement
of the abdomen or often the feeling right here above the upper lip
but also the there can be focus on loving kindness some of you know this lemon kindness
practice there's a way in which the repetition and that's kind of this warm-heartedness
really supports some samadhi as well as a third way there can be rather than a particular
object or a loving kindness a third way is maybe a little bit
more open but for an example something might be
just noticing the changing nature of whatever object is in our attention so
sound but really the noticing of the sound arising and passing away and
sensations in the body but really the noticing is on the
other the flickering a little bit they're not completely constant this third way is a little bit less common
but for some people works really well so these are the three different ways in
which we might use that 25 that's focusing
so one thing that i want to say is
really important maybe
i don't know if it's the most important it might be is when we talk about samadhi doing this
practice it's really important for us to pay attention to our relationship
to this practice because if somebody says the word concentration
then two things often happen and uh i've had this experience but it
wasn't in a rob berbeau he was a fantastic dormant teacher he talked about this and
he's the one who kind of put words to this this definitely is i think a lot of people's experience certainly was my
experience when we hear this word concentration there's a way in
this kind of our sense of practice kind of shrinks and it all becomes about measuring am i
focused am i not focused dang it that was a thought okay i'm not focused okay i'll stay here there's kind of this this
way in which they're like here's the grind to get to somebody so this idea of measuring
shows up so i would say use this word
samadhi with this emphasis on the ah samadhi
that's opening and we're just moving along the spectrum towards studying
calming and more well-being because as soon as this measuring mind
shows up then it's there's kind of a collapsing a strong sense of self i'm not as
concentrated as i used to be yesterday i'm not as concentrated as that person sitting in front of me or that person sitting over there or whomever right all
this all this chatter starts to come up and that's not the direction we're going
so not only that not only is there this measuring
but often if we have a sense of focus we have to focus then there's also this really subtle
sense maybe it's obvious sense of aversion that arises
dang it i'm trying to concentrate don't those neighbors know that their dog should be quiet and you know we have
this little irritation or why is this somebody i share the house with why are they just right now decided to talk
loudly on the phone or whatever there's this aversion that creeps in if we have the sense that we have to
focus and of course right aversion is not a sense of well-being it's not a sense of receptivity so
really pay attention to the relationship and is there a way in which we can
stretch our idea of what samadhi practice is
i talked about these three different elements of well-being
focus and being receptive but now i'd like to stretch it even more
and say no matter what is happening in your samadhi practice
there's a way in which we can we're practicing perseverance
this is enormously helpful in our life we're practicing patience this is enormously helpful in
our lives maybe if we're focusing on well-being then we're noticing that oh i'm the mind
i was on the object and now the mind has wandered is there a way that i can come back to
the object that's with a sense of warmth and gentleness and
it has a sense of well-being like oh okay i'm just gonna come back to the breath
that is also enormously beneficial or we might start to notice oh yeah
there's not a sense of well-being here because i'm beating myself up because i'm not getting concentrated
and we might start to notice oh yeah this is what it feels like to have a judging mind
ouch it doesn't feel good so even
if you sit down and you want to be concentrate cultivating a little bit of
samadhi and you feel like samadhi is nowhere nearby that's okay too
that's okay too because what we're cultivating will be such a support for
our practice and for our daily life and this practice gets cultivated in
just the same way in which we might um gain strength you know some physical
strength you know by doing bicep curls right we don't get strong just by doing
a few bicep curls and we don't even notice that oh bam oh okay now i'm stronger
right it's just kind of like the repetition of doing this over and over again and it often is this settling
happens imperceptibly and i know for me sometimes i haven't
even noticed so much that the mind has gotten settled until like the bell rang i'm like
oh yeah there's a bell and it just feels nice and it's uh
arises in the meditation experience and and there's a sense of
oh yeah this is pleasant maybe i'll get up maybe i won't maybe i'll stay
so there can just be this this is quiet settling that we don't notice until the end
okay so i think i'll maybe next week talk a little bit more about
somebody but i wanted to introduce this idea
as one of the factors of awakening and now i'd like to open it up to some
questions if you have some questions about samadhi cultivating it the experience of
it maybe can we use use a microphone if
somebody has a question if you don't that's okay too but if
there aren't any questions
good evening diana i think uh if that's not true we might have to turn up the volume here on the
mixer you can see which is the blue microphone so if you look at that
okay is that yep yes thank you um the practice today was very nice
although all the things you had mentioned with measuring and aversion
and just comparison were all over the place and so mari i
hope i'm saying that right was nowhere near when i had i was just striving towards
and i was just like like oh i'm waiting for the bell to ring and i'm
like oh no that's not what i want and so i just how how can i cultivate that loving
kindness i mean i'm not supposed to say anything am i or like
uh or i mean i know there's the whole may you be at peace safe and
etc um yeah yeah so um there's a way in which with
mindfulness practice we might have this idea of like okay we just have to be with whatever arises but if you want to
do a little bit of smiley there can't be a little bit more intentional movement and i would um
there's a few things one is i'll start with it's like maybe the posture it's it's really makes a difference it
turns out if the posture if the body has some alertness it kind of allows the
body to the mind to have some alertness as well so i'll just say that's one
thing the second thing is i think one thing that's really
impactful maybe two things one if you see if you had this thought oh i'm just waiting for
the bell that's not what i do one thing to try is to label oh that's a thought
it doesn't have to be a problem it's just a thought our minds think and then just come back to
the anchor often the breath is the anchor i don't know if it is for you but so just to label it thought
and come back and that kind of interrupts the momentum of the thinking thinking thinking like oh i've been
thinking i don't want to be thinking the last time i wasn't thinking as much and i hope i don't think later and the bell's going to ring when is she going to ring the bell what time is it it's
got to be this time right this is the mind right our minds do this so
so just this quiet note thought can maybe interrupt that momentum and
come back the second thing is and this is not always easy but it's
something to pay attention to is to notice the
manner in which the mind come comes back to the object
is it i use this expression is it like a dang it get back here you know
and if you feel that so what's what happens is we see this
a hundred times we see this a thousand times honestly we see it many times and
then we're like you know what i this just doesn't make sense anymore and it starts to just be a little bit
softer a little bit softer so if we start to see experience notice
the way in which we're on the object the mind drifts away
then there's a waking up and in that moment is there cursing or is it like oh okay
i'm i've wandered and then notice how the mind comes back
can there be a gentle warm-hearted way
and this is subtle it's very subtle and it's can be a really strong habit
very strong habit to want you know like i kind of was doing this right you know to just come back with this a little bit
of uh like jerking it back a little bit of aversion so don't beat yourself up if
after you've seen it ten times a hundred times ten hundred times a thousand
ten thousand times it's something that just starts to shift so this is where kind of the repetition
of continuity of practice really comes in was that helpful very much thank you
so much you're welcome you're welcome
thank you diana you're welcome um i attended earlier this year
retreat on the aggregates we did the aggregates and it seems to me
we've been meeting since that retreat to discuss the retreat because it just
seems so rich that there's a lot of space in
the study of the aggregates to try and
find different ways to samadhi or samadhi sort
of generically or more
i don't know it occurs more easily when you're studying the aggregates
i wondered if you had any thoughts about that
well maybe i'll say this that i won't the aggregates are different aspects of our experience
let's say that and they are a little bit more subtle
and so having to see subtle kind of like the mind has to settle in order to see subtle and it's that
tuning into the subtleness kind of creates the mind settling and i would say that's kind of what supports maybe
the samadhi and then i don't know maybe i'll start i'll stop there does that make sense that
yes thank you yeah yeah and often we can't see the aggregates unless there is some settling and the
more we're looking at him and kind of investigating playing around exploring them you know the quieter the mind has
to be well it occurred to me from that retreat and also
through this discussion of samadhi how much of this practice is really um
learning about how your mind works yes i mean it's almost like a scientific
study of the how the activity of the brain works
yes i would say that it's so much
about this is the expression is knowledge and vision so being able to understand things and see things yep
that you can't that you don't see right without this practice yeah yeah
okay okay so we're at the top of the hour here so
just uh warm wish for everybody having some well-being and some settledness and
steadiness in their lives and an appreciation for practicing together
and i'll stay up here if you other people have some other questions otherwise i wish you all a wonderful
rest of the evening thank you