so hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be together in this space and
to practice together in community so
so for today's practice um given what has been happening on the
international stage the past few weeks um
i have been dedicating the sessions of of happy art different practices to
support to support us in in this
new world that we find ourselves with with with the um
war zones um and and different practices
and for tonight i think the practice that i'd like to bring bring in and support us with is a practice of
equanimity equanimity as a support for compassion and equanimity again with a
sense of peace peace sense of um
abiding in equanimity arriving to it through calming of the body through the
calming of the body the energy body we've worked with in the past couple of times and in a way
continuing that i think maybe calming centering
arriving is really what um what can be really helpful and supported because on top of
that then the practice of compassion can can be more stable
instead of veering into empathetic distress and grief and overwhelm so we
really need a basis a basis of calm base of stability a basis of
groundedness especially when times get rough in the
world so that's what i would love to invite us to to practice together both
for our own sake whatever is happening in on in our own lives our
challenges our bodies or whatever is going on that doesn't stop it just when when
there's more suffering in the world maybe it even intensifies our own suffering our
own individual situations and for all of this we need the basis for happiness can
is peace the buddha said peace is the highest bliss
peace is the highest form of happiness and
when we first hear that maybe it's a little quizzical because peace perhaps seems so
settled you know there's not a lot of happiness or bliss to it seems kind of like peace we think of peace as oh just
peace or as happy is like whoa i want that i want to be happy i want to be yay that's
where the juice is um happiness is good it's great not uh
bliss is great and yet there is a deep deep
seated sated a deep sated joy
to peace that includes that subsumes
joy bliss is really the highest bliss and we can see that for ourselves
experientially if you if we think about it maybe we don't get it because these things are not
um instead of constantly might have a concept that actually does not really
correspond to the true exploration and and i'll share with you
that from myself having explored this path this meditative path for
for decades now um yes states of joy states of bliss
delicious yummy wonderful yay and this states of of peace deep d peace
ah the most blissful the happiest state of all so
so given that this is happy hour the states of peace
are the epitome i would i would claim of of happiness so
and of course they serve as the basis for
for equanimity for compassion practice for meta
for all the good beautiful gifts of the heart comes from peace of course they can lead
to peace also but come out of peace all of these practices are related they
connect to each other it's like a cloth you take a thread you pull it the whole
cloth is one thread even though she's like oh this is this part of the claw this this part but it's just one
thread so so with that let's practice together
let's practice being peace let's practice being peace together
so arriving arriving in your seat
whether you need to move a shift right now to be more comfortable this is the perfect time to do it
moving shifting
perhaps even lying down if that's what your body needs
and then arriving arriving in this body landing in this body
here here
can we invite this body this living breathing body
to soften
to let go of any tightness or holding
and also releasing releasing preoccupations and thoughts
worries entanglements
of course we all have lives full complex lives
and in this moment bowing to all the complexity
perhaps smiling at it all saying thank you i'm taking a moment of
refuge right now entering this temple of my heart
entering this temple entering a temple taking refuge
in peace for the sake of stability
for the sake of groundedness for the sake of myself and all beings whose lives
mind touches directly and indirectly
release release with each breath
release landing more deeply with each out breath especially
letting the breath relax
and massage an internal massage
any area of the body that is tight tense
this expert therapist this breath massaging the neck
and shoulders
this
moving to any other part of the body that is tense
the attention moving with the breath internally massaging
releasing
this
let the breath be nourishing calming soothing
to the body to the heart
allowing yourself to feel really feel
the entirety of the breath the beginning the middle the end of the
breath in the abdomen in the chest
wherever it's felt
as a soothing balm
calming abiding in peace
the breath peaceful
creating the space internally
that undulates angeles
as if waves
letting the body relax ah as if the body is held
in this peaceful loving space internally externally
nothing to do nowhere to go
but just to be breathed
undulating each breath
the
if thoughts arise discussions in the mind
let the peace hold them let the peace inside and outside hug
them they don't have to be pushed away or squashed
let them be held
this undulating ocean inside outside there's plenty of space
expansive there's plenty of space
no need to be perturbed
plenty of space
the breath healing soothing [Music]
through the heart center through the abdomen through the whole
body
at some point maybe the mind maybe awareness
meets more peace clicks with
yeah there is peace there is calm in the middle of the storm
it's here it's always been here
awareness clicks connects
and settles more deeply into the still point
however small it might be it's here it's always been here
and always will be
if at any point it feels lost it's okay trust it's it's here
trust it's here
let the body and mind relax the breath ah
be the guide a gentle loving
gentle loving guide the entirety of the breath
to reconnect
this
the still point inside outside expansive
still point so expensive space of peace
whether or not we're aware of it or connect to it in this moment
or as much as we're able to connect with it
womb the space of peace is a womb
of equipoise equanimity
the risings and passings the comings and goings
to ten thousand joys and ten thousand sorrows
being breathed being breathed being priest
realizing there is so much more you can contain
than you've realized being peace
the strength the power of peace
and as we bring this practice period to a close
knowing that our peace our peace
is the biggest gift to ourselves to those in our lives and all beings everywhere
offering peace peace
starting from within not hatred not ill will
but peace love
offering our peace this cultivation as our gift
to ourselves to others expansively
may all beings everywhere have peace
may they be free
thank you for your practice everyone
so i'd love to invite you if you would like to share some reflections
you can put them in chat if they're typed publicly i will read your name if
they're just typed in me i will only read your reflection
and you can also raise your hand your zoom hand
you like to share reflections and you also understand if you're rather quiet
tonight it's okay but uh what what a rose what did you discover
what worked what didn't again offering any insights
for the benefit of others or the benefit of others
could be questions aha moments
um one reflection here privately
the meditation this evening is supporting my focus on
anata impermanence
unsatisfactoriness and not self
the three marks of existence thank you for that reflection and yeah thank you for
saying that this is supporting that beautiful scott says very grateful for the space
another reflection peace means non-violence yes exactly
yeah larry asks wondering if peace and open awareness are the same no
they are not um [Music] this
practice i was leading you was not a practice of open awareness it was a practice of
actually bringing the breath into awareness as the energy body calming calming
and then um to actually bring peace into your
awareness so is it directed it was not open awareness because open awareness is
open spacious undirected whatever the wherever awareness goes it goes so these
two practices are different and their point
their uh point their their objective is different also
thank you for that question catherine says i was sitting in the
garden [Music] being with the sunset and when i was done i felt
like flowers i felt the flowers as my friends oh that's sweet i love that the flowers is
your friends the flowers is all of our friends thanks for bringing the flowers in catrin i feel them in the space yeah
sweet yeah another reflection privately relieving anguish
relieving anguish yeah may it be so languish doesn't serve
anyone in the world ourselves or anyone else for that matter
not in this state to be supportive so i'm glad it's being relieved through
this practice ah
so so we're feeling pretty quiet so [Music]
so before i set up the groups tonight i wanted to say a few words about engaging how to
engage in [Music] the the groups in the small groups
especially as there has been some requests to give more guidance more
instructions so please consider the breakout groups a
sacred space sacred space both for yourself and especially for
others is a way to really respect each person's experience
so please consider
first of all being embodied being embodied it's not a place to talk from
your head and just blah blah blah maybe you actually don't say anything and you just
hold witness kind compassionate witness for others that's perfectly okay
and if you choose to share as you choose to speak please speak from your own
experience i me my experience and it's a way of
again not trying to impress others not trying to educate others
you're just sharing what feels safe and comfortable for you in order for others to hold you witness
you're speaking for your own benefit i say it again you're speaking for your
own benefit not benefit of anyone else it's a very different way of relating
your speaking for your own benefit it's quite revolutionary you're speaking
for your own benefit i'm going to say in one more time you're speaking for your own benefit
and you only speak from your own experience not
asking questions of others probing others
commenting on their experience please don't you're not here to
facilitate in small groups or especially if you act in
as a therapist or other helping professions please leave
that outside leave their profession outside here you're only speaking from
your own experience if you wish maybe you're just being silent that's okay but do not reflect do not give
advice to one another be very careful in this sacred space
it's a very beautiful sacred space of of relating to one another we really learn
how we can be different with friends and family and others this is a precious
sandbox don't take it as oh yes small groups all right here we go chatting
please don't and in fact also be very aware of the time so the
format i'd like to suggest from now on is that you don't do a monologue for
like two three minutes and then pass on no each person just say one nugget just one nugget
and then the next person will say a nugget about their experience and then the next person says something
about their experience and then again the first person and then you go around it's a spiral format you go round and
round just sharing or and it comes to you you can say pass i'm holding witness tonight and just holding other that's
okay just relating in this way a very different way it's not just
go chat amongst yourselves so i really want to take time tonight um
again you're speaking for your own benefit please do not manage
or or facilitate just
his spiritual friends a space of spiritual friends and entering with respect entering this temple with two
other human beings whose come whose lives are as complex
and dear as yours are to you so
so having said all of that having said all of that i'm going to
create the groups and um
take a moment here to do a bit of rearranging
arranging okay i think i uh oh wait one more thing i have the groups
okay so all right all set i'm going to open
uh open the rooms oh no i need to recreate them hold on it's always this
always happens numbers change left so meditate with peace meditate with peace
as the counts keep changing okay
all right ah so so opening the rooms take care of
yourselves and each other here we go everybody's back
any reflections you like to share from from this breaking out groups and what
it was like especially today with extensive invitations as how to be in the group
was it different i wonder in terms of the reflections
you're welcome to raise your hand if you want or type in chat
raise your zoom hand because if it's your physical hand i may not see it
any reflections about the practice about what you discussed
short one 30 seconds ah nice nancy says we were all appreciating
the silence between sharing beautiful oh i'm so glad there was a lot of silence
nice esther please
hi um i appreciated the instructions
it helped me to relax actually it helped me to feel like
safer and i like i appreciated the framework
and i felt that i could open up within that framework
beautiful thank you thank you for that reflection appreciate it so feeling safer that can open up great
thank you barbara
i also appreciated the instruction i think my tendency would be to
ask a question and i refrained so there was much more
um quiet reflection so it had a different
feel to it so great great beautiful thank you for that
and meredith please
hi thank you yeah i also i'm an overtalker
and um i found the silence comforting
great i also found a tiny tad of dialogue with someone extremely helpful
nice great but and i appreciate that it seems like the dialogue came out of the silence which
is a different way right to have a dialogue yeah beautiful thank you for that
reflection yeah thank you all thanks to all of you for the reflections that you share this is very very helpful so i
think maybe moving forward always giving more instructions about going into the group
and well we're out of time now one last reflection catherine says love the flow
and connection created by sharing small june small jewels one by one beautiful
so thank you all thank you for your practice being peace for yourself
for each other for the whole world may all beings know true peace and be happy
may all beings including ourselves be free
[Music] thanks everyone be well thank you see you on friday
bye