and um welcome and i have this in my imagination
i have this uh kind of an image of all of us together sitting in one very big
circle and that we're all welcoming each other to this into this meditation time
thank you for being here one of the [Music]
inspiring maybe even guiding stories from the buddhist tradition for me
is the story of the buddha's death how he died
knowingly and conscious consciously he died
prepared to die he spent his last times last days
saying for a well he said it's been his last days carefully asking
his disciples if there was anything else they needed to learn anything if they had any questions anymore
and [Music] perhaps as a very fortunate thing for him they
did not so that as he was dying he could feel maybe complete with having passed on his
teachings to others and then he gave his very last teaching
very last words two sentences that everything
everything that arises everything that's conditioned has a nature to pass away
i think he was now just saying of course i'm going to die and
and then he said
keep practicing to become complete to
become accomplished with vigilance with diligence
keep practicing in other words and then he lay down or he was maybe
already laying down he was outdoors which i find inspiring
between two trees they say it's the indian saul tree and
and he laid down between them and laid on the side and
he entered into uh meditation he entered into deep
uh concentration deep absorption went through the jaundice and it's kind of like he took one last
tour or visit to these meditation states that he was familiar with maybe they were kind of a
home for him and he went through experiences of being very settled and
focused experience of tremendous joy maybe even kind of
rapture as the concentration deepened so deep and further experiences of sublime
pervasive sense of peaceful happiness happy contentment
went further and experienced deep levels of equanimity and peace
this is a man who knew he was dying he went further and
went into deep states of absorptions that were no longer hearing
seeing touching the world around him the mind became very very still until
finally there was just everything kind of faded away in his mind and there was just almost nothing almost no perception
feelings at all and maybe you would think that's a place he would die but he returned he came
back out of his deepest absorptions and went back to the beginning and then
started again and he came to the the middle state of a very deep equanimity and peace
and we don't know what happened exactly what he did at that point
but that's when he died and it passed away and um
and this is a wonderful story inspiring for me because death is one of the great uh
things that terrify people a lot of people are troubled by death and
and and here the buddhist tradition offers a story at the center of its
religion of the founder of the religion who had this tremendous peace and
equanimity and it's an old man he was 81 years old knew he was dying he was sick
and and and he just uh faced it with a lot of peace and
equanimity and kind of a matter of factness and so that story is a reframing story
it's a story with for some of us story for people that don't have an example
of embracing or facing stepping towards death in a sense
and having capacity to do so with tremendous equanimity and peace to do it in a way that is just very
rewarding very satisfying the level of peace and happiness
and that the process of letting go that death and that kind of circumstance is
becomes a welcome process and in this way we have it's a story
that the buddhists tell that creates a very different context
not one of fear or closing down or horror or
running away or trying to discover the elixir that'll live us let us live forever
but something something that faces the inevitability of an end
with with freedom with peace
and maybe there are many endings in our life many challenges in our life
that maybe uh the story points to that we can meet it with a level of peace and attention
uh we can practice in the middle of it so these stories of practice that this
is what's important the stories that lead us help lead us to
our freedom so here we are now to do our meditation practice
and there is a long history of
mindfulness meditation as being a preparation for dying it's many other things too preparation
for living but it's a very important work this work of
waking up to here developing capacity to be here developing the capacity to let go of the
distractions let go of what takes us away from here that that capacity to let go and come
back wait come let go and wake up to let that become strong and developed
and cherished and loved and and and kind of a home homecoming to be
awake here might not seem so special today
but there'll be a time maybe even not just when you're dying there are times when you'll be so grateful that you've
developed this ability it'll provide you with tremendous benefit
so now we practice so taking a meditation posture
and doing whatever you do to settle in
to be here
perhaps with an intimacy to your body
to your breathing and a relaxing letting go as you exhale
each exhale letting go of your thoughts
exhale letting go into your body
here
each breath each exhale
as if you are the buddha and it's your last breath
so
as you're sitting here if there are any challenges for you
maybe reframe the challenge either is one more thing to let go of
or one more thing to love
and then as we come to the end of the sitting you might consider
a new way of viewing your awareness your attention
some people have the idea i mean maybe not the idea but
maybe deeper than idea just maybe even unconscious
that awareness receives the world
maybe we're oppressed by the world by what comes to us difficulties and things
and to rather look at awareness as
something with which we touch the world and it's kind of with a midas touch
that we touch everything with awareness
with kindness with care if we're fortunate enough to see
our seeing sees everything with kindness if we're fortunate enough to hear
everything we hear is touched by kindness
smell taste touch even if we think about things
and i offer this knot as a thing you have to do
but rather as an alternative that might be better than what you're
currently doing and if it's a better alternative you might try it
so that when we come out of meditation that maybe just maybe you're more
inclined to see each and everything to hear every
each and every sound with some modicum of kindness of care
of love may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
um
so hello continuing with this theme of stories
that we live by today's focus is stories that open
so using the acronym for story we have the source story trapping stories
and then today's opening stories and um
i've seen over these years that i've been a buddhist practitioner here especially here in the west
all kinds of attitudes towards stories and thinking and words that are dismissive of them
that treat them as traps that treat them as problems that uh we mindfulness practice is about
uh breaking out of stories completely and all stories somehow are our
obscure reality or is not quite quite right and um
or even even having any words for things words are somehow a barrier towards
wordless kind direct non-dualistic contact with reality something like that
and certainly it's true that stories and words and all that can interfere with our life that's why the talk yesterday
about trapping stories there can be trapping words that keep us restricted narrow tight constricted
but there are also words and stories that are opening that open us new possibilities that
kind of free us from the traps of stories and for me uh kind of the enigmatic or
the kind of pandemic example of this that i love when i saw
it or first read it was in the autobiograph autobiography of helen keller
who was was blind couldn't hear couldn't speak
and she um
was raised without any words at all and kind of a wild animal almost apparently something like
that and some of you know the story better than i do but she had a teacher
who at some point put her hand underneath a faucet of water one hand and the other hand she
spelled with her the teacher spelled with the fingers to teach the teacher's fingers the letter um
the letters for water and helen in autobiography writes that
the light went on for her she the world opened up for her that now
she's understood there were words that referred to the objects in the world
and and now she could have she could communicate she could understand she could organize the world
that the whole world made sense starting to make sense so this idea that the words interfere
uh stories interfere it's not not always the case there are some stories which are opening
and they open us uh and they open us from the traps they're what the stories that free us
from the trap the traps of stories that we live in and um
so i'd like to uh tell you or maybe a little bit reid tell you a story from my
book a monastery within that in the monastery
after new monastics had been there for
close to a year they were starting to get restless and started to wonder why they were there
and uh had settled in enough to start seeing their monastery has problems even and then
a lot of the interpersonal issues and monasteries are often places people go who
have the greatest need of spiritual practice but because of that great need they often will have
you know challenges that have brought them there and they bring the challenges with them and and so monastic life can
be difficult with the all the challenging fellow monastics there there
so um so there was a custom for the abbess of the monastery
to take after about a year to take the new monastics on a pilgrimage to the holy sites of buddhism
and when they heard this the new monastics were quite excited they'd read about the holy sites in
india where the buddha was born the buddha first taught where the buddha was enlightened where the buddha died
and and they so they packed their bags and ready to go and went on a bus
and the first thing the abbott did was take them to a old age home
and and there they saw people who were quite old and amazingly old and frail and
wheelchairs and blind and toothless and um
some of them um you know were quite frail and they'd never seen such a collection
of older really older people and it was kind of a surprise to see it they
went back on the bus and the abbess took them to the local hospital where they saw people
at all kinds of stages of illness that you know dramatic illness and
alzheimer's and major injuries that people had and
living with there was going to live with them there's their life and and the monastics were kind of stunned
to see the collection of illness and injuries and physical challenges that
people can live under and then the abbess took them to
the to a mortuary
and uh to see in a hospice and seeing people who are dying last days of
their death seeing people who had died seeing people laid out on the mortuary slabs to be
prepared for whatever is next and they'd never seen such a all in one
place so much death and so much dying and it was a little bit stunning
then they went back to the monastery and they went to their infirmary in the monastery and there was an old old
monk a monk who was a maybe you know 99 years old and had a long
monastic life and and he was also dying
but they went to see him in his room and there was a piece in the room there was a serenity
and when they went to sit with him he didn't really talk but he was certainly very cognizant aware that they're there
and he had this delightful sparkle and warmth in which he received
the visiting new monks and they'd never seen someone in the brink of death who
had such warmth and peace and love then the abbess took them back
to the
meditation hall to give them some teaching and she said you have now seen
the holy sites of buddhism now it's for you to practice
and the holy sites were sick old age sickness death and then the monastic who
has discovered peace and and so this story is a story of
reframing of opening up now the monastics had a whole different attitude to their life
in the monastery that they didn't have before
maria renee rilke writes that
everything terrifying in its deepest being is something helpless
that wants our love so that's not a story but it's a reframing statement
that everything terrifying needs our love that's a terrifying idea because there
are frightening things and now we're supposed to love them but this idea that we reframe we have
stories that reframe and open up our world to and
people if you have enough of this you begin to appreciate that maybe the trapping stories
shouldn't have the last word maybe they're not absolute or you know ultimately true and
this is how it is maybe there's other perspectives to bring and good stories
bring that bring our opening or are
offering a new possibility a new perspective that's freeing rather
than uh limiting and um
so um i'd like to end with a a story which
i'm also fond of that i've told told many times many times i
tell it in children's programs and so i'm sure some of you have heard it many of you heard it but
maybe as you hear it you can not dismiss it because you've heard before but rather apply it
because you know it how's this relevant for you in your life how is this a story which is opening
it's a story from china of a very old
farmer who was getting old and weak and he had a young son who helped him on his
farm and um but they also had an old horse
they were plowing their fields and taking care of things and at some point uh the horse died
and um or ran ran off into the mountains or something
and the fellow villagers said oh disaster has struck poor you and this
how are you going to manage this terrible what's going to happen to you now without your
and um and so um
the old farmer says we shall see and so the
young sun goes up into the mountains to look for the i guess the horse that ran away the old horse or something
he comes back with a founding wild horse and brought it back and
knew a young horse and the villagers say oh now everything will be okay for you
and the farmer says we shall see and then as the sun was training the
horse he fell off the horse and broke his leg
and they said oh this is terrible for you your son does all the work can't work now and this is a disaster and
the farmer said oh we shall see then the king of the country decided to
go to war with a neighboring country so he recruited all the able-bodied young men
but of course the young man had broken his leg so he couldn't be re uh drafted
and so then the villagers came to the fed oh you're so lucky that your your son wasn't drafted he's here and
he'll he'll he'll heal well enough this is great and of course the farmer says we shall see
and and there's no end to the story some stories you know a good story is supposed to have an ending but this
story just goes on and on and on we shall see
maybe so maybe not we'll we'll see so this is a an opening story
what are your opening stories what are what ways can you reframe
the trapping stories that you live by what are the stories that you live by
that do not serve you and is there in fact a better story to tell
not to make something up but the trapping stories are already made up
they're just perspectives and stories that tell of possibilities stories that tell of love
to love everything to care for everything is
neither a true thing or a false things it's a possibility thing
and so the stories that let us live into the possibilities that are
inspiring meaningful and help this world stories that teach us to love everything
so thank you and
we'll continue tomorrow and with a little different twist on this
opening stories the stories that release us and maybe they release us from stories
so thank you