so again my really warm welcome even if the ac is on and it's kind of
chilly i have a warm welcome so
so tonight i thought i would talk a little bit about mindfulness
and recognizing that this is foundational and maybe even it seems kind of uh
i don't know like kindergarten teachings or something like this but
this is something i appreciate so much about the dharma and the teachings is
that we get to hear things again and again and then often we discover something new
and it's not like there are these secret teachings that are wildly
different you know as we progress on the path to be sure
there are things that start to unfold and become known as we continue on this path that
aren't obvious or available at the beginning but how we practice with them and be
with them this really builds on this foundation of mindfulness
which of course makes sense so much about what the practice is about
is being present for what's happening noticing what's happening
and in some fundamental way that's just what mindfulness is
so i'd like to talk about this a little bit also because
mindfulness is one of the seven factors of awakening
it's the first vector it's kind of like the foundation that supports all these other factors
and the buddha pointed to these factors as really being supportive
if not required in some in some form for awakening for enlightenment
so sometimes as i said we tend to think well you know maybe mindfulness you know that's just some
nice to have something to make our life better and to be sure it is that
but it's also pointed to you as an integral part of this path towards greater freedom
towards greater ease greater peace
i'll be talking a little bit more about the seven factors of awakening and some subsequent talks but right now i'm just
going to introduce the idea of it and just start with the first one the
foundation mindfulness
it really is quite something to think about you know like what is mindfulness and we
might say that it's a unique capacity of humans as far as i know
to you a unique capacity that humans have to direct our attention
intentionally of course other beings other creatures
you know have attention but uh as far as i know humans are the
ones that we can choose okay i'm gonna pay attention to this particular thing
and not pay attention to that particular thing
so this is something that we can really use to support our lives
to support the way we show up in the world the way we show up for ourselves
and so for me and in the context of this talk i will use kind of like the words
attention and mindfulness and awareness as synonyms
sometimes teachers tease them apart and have some
other ways they want to separate the different ways that the
mind is aware consciousness something like this
some teachers do some teachers don't i've given talks a little bit to where i tease them apart but for here i'm not
going to really tease them apart i'm going to say it's just like noticing
paying attention being aware of being conscious of being mindful
kind of put those all together and this idea of you know paying
attention to something and for anybody who has ever tried
mindfulness practice you know that one of the very first insights you have is like oh wow
i had no idea that my mind was going everywhere
except where i wanted it to go i had no idea that this actually was
going to be not be so easy even though it might seem simple straightforward to
place our attention on an anchor for example often we choose
the breath it can be the body sounds emotions
thoughts those are often the typical things that we place our attention on that we're
mindful of but we have this uh insight like oh
i had no idea my mind was like this until we started practice i think this is true for everybody
just the way that humans or certainly humans
in the modern west i don't know about other cultures other societies but right we
have a certain busyness or a certain
maybe i'll even use the word certain little bit of agitation keeps our minds busy
so with mindfulness we just bring our attention back to the anchor the breath for example
again and again and again
and it absolutely does not matter how many times you have to do that
hundred one thousand one hundred thousand times it's just this practice of bringing it
bringing attention back to the anchor again
and we do this in a way that's okay this is what practice is so as best we can we do it
without a judgment without this idea like i wish it were different dang it why am i doing that
i'm never gonna get it everybody else is so quiet and i'm not or you know these thoughts that sometimes can arise in our
minds that's extra it does can be a habit to do this too
for the inner critic to arise or to be comparing ourselves to others
that's just part of what it means to be human also and so as best we can
we just bring our attention back in a simple gentle way
letting the judgment the inner critic and all those things letting them just soften and go
to the side we don't have to get rid of them just let it be there on the side
so in this way mindfulness is really about being present for our life
i talked about the breath being the anchor but we can just in our daily life
have this intention of being present for what's actually happening
it might be that we have this insight early like wow i don't know i had no idea my mind was like this
and then we might also have an insight regarding our daily life this recognition
oh in some kind of way i was sleepwalking or
disconnected or not really engaged with my life
mindfulness the practice of mindfulness in our daily life and whatever it is that we're doing
provides the opportunity the encouragement the
the setting or the intention to actually be with
our life engaged with our life not so much that our ideas or our conceptions
or but the actual experience and bringing this sense of aliveness
to the moment whatever it is that's happening whether it's pleasant or unpleasant what we wanted what we didn't want
but just to have this aliveness like yes this is my life
this can be beautiful just the being present for what it is even if it is unpleasant
and not only so it might be beautiful it might not be beautiful to you
but one thing i want to highlight here is that i'm talking about bringing
attention to things that help to bring some aliveness notice how i'm not saying that
mindfulness is getting rid of thoughts it's easy to fall into this trap of
thinking like okay as long as there's thoughts i'm not meditating i'm not mindful and this whole meditation thing
doesn't work or i can't do it or whatever it might be
because we might have this idea like either conscious or unconscious and to be sure dharma teachers sometimes talk
about you know in between the thoughts or the space around the thoughts or i don't
know no thoughts sometimes they talk about this and that is available
but usually that's only on retreat for some time
this isn't like so accessible certainly if we just have a like a daily
meditation practice as opposed to being on retreats for a long long periods of time
instead mindfulness is just knowing what's happening in the mind
when we're lost in thought we are lost in thought okay
it's not a problem because we're lost in thought so there's no problem with whatever's happening
but then there's a waking up that happens like oh i was just lost in thought
at that moment you're mindful there's nothing else you could have done
while you were lost in thought but when that ends and you're mindful again you just know oh now i'm mindful
and i just wasn't a moment before
as an aside i'll say well what makes it more likely that these moments of waking
up so to speak happens while you're lost in thought is
a moment of mindfulness preceding it so it's just the more mindfulness we do
the easier it gets the shorter the duration we're lost in thought
probably all of us have this experience whether it's a daily practice or being
on retreat or day longs or something like this
maybe we'll say then that rather than this idea that we have to get rid of thoughts or something
like that it's just you might think about it as keeping something in mind
if we're on the cushion we're keeping our anchor the breath
the body whatever it might be in mind in daily life it's
just uh returning to whatever's compelling whatever is easy to be mindful of
whatever is drawing our attention we don't necessarily have to put it on anything specific
but why would we do this this is a legitimate question like well
okay sounds nice maybe but what are the advantages or the
benefits like why would we do this and maybe you'll recognize some of these
for in your own life i know for me this uh first one had a
big uh impact on me this that we can understand
things when we are aware of them
i mean it says seems so obvious to say but we start to understand ourselves we
start to understand our lives which isn't always
pleasant right we don't necessarily see only you know rainbows and hearts and that kind of stuff but
i remember at the beginning of my meditation practice this whole idea of like okay i guess i'll try this
mindfulness when i'm not formally meditating let's see
and of course you know i so rarely remember to be mindful when i wasn't uh
sitting on the cushion but i don't know why there's this some uh
reason why this one incident really stood out to me i was standing in line and now i don't
remember where it was if it was the grocery store or something like this
and i noticed oh look at that posture i'm standing i had my hip out had my hand on my hip you
know i was like like really uh impatient and i had this little bit
self-righteousness going on and but i didn't even notice it until i noticed my
posture the way i had my hand on my hip my hip jutted out like
you better get going or something like this and that was so astounding to me like if
i hadn't noticed what was happening in my body i wouldn't have really noticed that i had this attitude or this stance
this is happens so much right that our body can inform us and just being aware
of what's happening in our body can help us be aware of sometimes what's more subtle
for me something that still is happens today is that when i have a little bit of a feeling like oh i'm not sure and i
gotta do it i wring my hands is it's sometimes my ringing my hands
i'm like oh okay i guess i'm a little bit nervous i don't know what's the next thing to do
is here so these are just some broad examples
but i'm sure probably all of you have some examples as well
of how just bringing mindful of things of your posture for example helps you to
understand yourself better
emotions maybe feeling just generally out of sorts
if we have this idea of keeping it in mind like well okay i'm feeling out of sorts
and if we just stay with okay out of sorts we might notice that maybe there's
a heaviness sometimes like the shoulders are drooping or the posture whatever we're
doing but there isn't uh there isn't an alertness or uprightness and
okay bring with that we might notice that uh there's a little collapsing around the
chest or on the heart or something and then we might be like oh actually i'm a
little sad yeah there's these sad thoughts
i hadn't really noticed it before i am sad
so one of the reasons why we have this mindfulness or keeping things in mind is
just to help us learn about ourselves learn about what's happening
so we can just better understand not so that we can beat ourselves up not
so that we can insist that we be different just so that we can understand ourselves
also being present for our experiences actually grounding right to be kind of with the
simplicity of the experience the actuality the reality of what's
happening helps us to feel a bit more rooted and grounded a little bit less like being
pushed around and like we can't find our way or something like this but
instead to feel connected to feel connected to our bodies
connected to the experience maybe it helps us mindfulness helps us
with our social connections people that we love that we care about people that we work with
being present also helps us feel connected to our environment nature
so it helps us to feel grounded and this groundedness could help provide
some stability in our life which can be a tremendous support
so being mindful also related to grounding and keeping things
in mind is also calming we have all noticed this and this might
even be part of the reason why some people start a meditation practice is this recognition that it does have
this calming of the mind and the body often right when we're formally
meditating we're not moving around that much
but there's this way that we often don't even notice how
busy literally and figuratively like how entangled or caught up with or
thoughts or this never-ending to-do list or whatever it might be
you might just be caught up in it and feeling like there's a certain type of
this kind of feeling of a rat race or something but
if we can be mindful of that experience like and just again and again
maybe if we're feeling uh really agitated we can choose an anchor
the breath the body just again and again bringing the mind
there it just allows some of the busyness the agitation to soften
not because we're forcing it it just kind of runs out of steam
as we're again and again bringing the mind to the present moment
to whatever's happening
so this is one of the things that's worth developing in our life
it's something that can be developed and is worthwhile developing is
this capacity to just return again and again and again in a way that's calming
settling in a way that
helps us to disentangle from those things that maybe
aren't supporting us don't disentangle from those things that
maybe aren't in our best interest
another reason to practice mindfulness or something like this is
every time that we bring the attention back to whatever it is we're
paying attention to as best we can in a simple gentle way
we're not feeding that habit of just jumping on judgmentalism and running
with it i'm not going to say that the judgmentalism is going to just stop immediately
but if we're not feeding it then we start to see oh there's another
way to be with my experience to just
accept that this is what's the reality of the moment
i'm not saying that we have to accept everything and never do anything and be
completely passive i'm talking about there's stuff that we to kind of allow the reality of
the moment to show itself for us to align with that reality
so often we're kind of maybe it's a little bit like the sleepwalking kind of
not really connected to what's really happening
there's a way that we are but there's sometimes we're a little bit disconnected too
so this mindfulness with this non-judgmentalism
gets supported gets developed this idea of like oh okay this is what's happening
that's it we don't have to add extra busyness around it or something like
this so some of these things are just to help
us have an easier more fulfilling happier life
but of course you know mindfulness is part of the buddhist tradition too
and in this tradition the the most common way that the buddha
talked about mindfulness was in the context of the freedom from suffering
the context of wanting to find more ease more peace more well-being
this was in the context of the eightfold path or the satipatanasuta the four
foundations of mindfulness for those of you who are familiar with that
there's a relationship between them of course but mine maybe i'll just say this that the
eightfold path is really uh is a road map towards awakening
the four foundations of mindfulness are also a road road map to awakening
but to point out that mindfulness is just one part of this
of the buddhist practice has many different elements including all aspects of our lives
but mindfulness really supports all elements whatever it is
that we're doing so this
freedom from suffering is finding greater ease
but mindfulness also addresses this maybe this uh drive or this hunger for
truth and for understanding
that um we might have this real wish to know what's real
yeah for me i'll say that uh this kind of wanting to investigate or to understand
or to really like be with what's really happening it's been really important i didn't even
realize how important it was to me in my life in general i was just forever like pursuing knowledge or something like
this but i think it's more about just wanting to connect with
some some reality some truth as best as i could
i think this is uh not unique to me this is like all the philosophers talk about this you know
through the millennia this idea of truth and so we can talk about like personal
truths and i talked about kind of like understanding ourselves understanding our psychology understanding how
conditions in our lives get played out later in our life of course they do how
could they not but also about some of these universal
truths about how things are
they don't last forever things are in flux they're changing
they are impermanent
inconstant but there's nothing as a lasting source
of happiness we haven't found that yet doesn't exist something that's going to
make you happy once and for all forever and this recognition that there actually
isn't a separate enduring constant self that's at the center of the universe
often feels like that seems like that but when we go to look for it we can't
find it so mindfulness helps us with this
addressing maybe this uh this drive this hunger for the truths
about ourselves about our experiences about the world
and as we practice continue to practice and maybe this is true for some of you
maybe the motivations the benefits or the reasons why you practice you know
starts shifts the more we practice maybe in the beginning it was just to
alleviate some difficulties or find some ease or something like this
but as we start to practice more and more we discover that maybe it's not only freedom from
suffering just for ourselves but for others
for all beings this recognition that we don't want
anybody to suffer we want everybody to have some
well-being so maybe it starts with just trying to
solve one problem but then there's this uh this opening that happens is unfolding
this expansion of our care of our concern
and maybe there's also a recognition of some love that we feel
like we've glimpsed or that we've had a little like a taste of where there's this maybe a
recognition that our hearts are capable of this greater bigger
love i'll use this word love
maybe mindfulness is a support for that or maybe that's the motivation for
continuing practice continuing our mindfulness practice our meditation practice
and we could say that one of the actually signs of somebody who've had some deep
practice is kindness is care is love
sometimes we don't think about that when we think about mindfulness instead we might think about there needs to be some
precision about exactly what we're being mindful of and something like this but
there's also this tremendous softening and opening
i spoke earlier about how part of mindfulness is this allowing this acceptance this non-judgmentalism about
our our experience of course we do this often enough with
meditation practice the mind the heart just adopt this habit
of being non-judgmental of being with the present moment in a way that has this
openness to it and that openness is a type of warmth a
type of caring a type of open-heartedness
and so as we become less entangled there's a little more space
as we become less getting not all knotted up with whatever is happening
a little bit more space around or during our our experiences
and in that space is some well-being and some happiness
it's often what is found there and this well-being and happiness kind
of like nourishes and supports us so then we don't have to
defend ourselves or try to get more instead
there's this warm-heartedness this love that's there when we kind of they're putting down
this trying to get happy or trying to defend ourselves or trying to prove ourselves
or something like that we don't have to do that because now there's this happiness and we got this happiness because there's more space but
we got this more space because we were just being present for what was happening as best we could in a
non-judgmental simple way
so mindfulness also has this quality of warm-heartedness this
and as we practice it has this i'm using this word love
maybe that's not the word that resonates with everybody maybe there's some other word that feels more comfortable
but this openness this warmth
as well as this just general receptivity
to what's happening allowing ourselves to be touched by the beauty
sometimes the difficulties too but by the
aw and appreciation kind of like arise just noticing the simple things of our
lives and yes i'm not going to say it's all
pollyanna beautiful but there is a way in which we also have the
capacity to hold it hold the difficulty so they're still
painful maybe but the problem-ness kind of like drains out
of the pain it's not as much as something that has to be fixed right now and
with a sense of urgency and the world's going to end if this pain doesn't go away
i wish i could say would take away all the pain but it doesn't but it just allows us to be with it
in a way that's insisting that it be otherwise
so this movement of mindfulness practice
turning to some appreciation simplicity some warm-heartedness
some of these things that maybe weren't our initial intentions of why we started mindfulness practice
but just this natural unfolding of practice leads this direction and then these qualities themselves
support the lessening of suffering
that increase of freedom
so as we move towards this completely
non-violent way of being
start to see how so many things open up for us
i create the conditions for even more opening for more letting go
letting go and shedding everything that's extra and unnecessary and it's getting in our way so that
we can do the biggest letting go that leads to complete awakening
so mindfulness even though it's this we might think of it as this ordinary
simple foundational practice it really is so powerful amazingly powerful
so with that i'm wishing all of you the mindfulness that supports your path
towards greater and greater freedom and peace thank you
so i'll stay up here for questions if any of you like
otherwise we'll just end a little bit early tonight so thank you
you know what nancy that's a good question are we going to do it with the microphone or uh
we can if yeah if anybody has questions
and when we yes the bell they always let the first ring completely die out before
they did the second which completely they have before they did the third but here in all the groups they do them very
close together is that a difference in a tradition or is it just
[Laughter] yeah so for the purpose of uh uh
for everybody to say come here like you come from a place where they ring and then they let the first bell all the
way die out um whereas here we don't we just do one two
three um i've actually never heard that where one goes and then it always uh dies out
and then go to the second i'll just say that i've been in meditation centers where they do one at the beginning two at the
end three the beginning two at the end three so as far as i know there's no magical
reason why we do one or the other i know that often we do three for like buddha dharma
sangha or something like that but i don't know of any particular thing
about this but i can imagine that's helpful to do one and then allow it to die out so that your mindfulness
you can just it's another mindfulness object you can just be with that while it gets fainter and fainter yeah thank
you yes i found and nancy don't know if this is
guessing it's normal um then so your practice deepens
do you find that you actually feel more strongly
is it just a matter of paying closer attention or
is it it just feels stronger
yeah so the question was as our practice deepens is it that duke i feel stronger
is this is this and you were asking might be like is this normal or something like this
yes this absolutely like arises absolutely like sometimes this um
we just weren't aware so much of some of the difficulties and not only that
we also um don't maybe have as available to us the ways that we used to try to
soothe ourselves or numb ourselves or however way we would work with that
yeah so in the beginning there can be a certainly a lot of just noticing more
and more dukkha but hopefully also there's a little bit more confidence in
like okay i i can't be with this it's not fun i wish it weren't here but
i know that i've had some difficulties before that i've been able to do this and with this meeting difficulty after
difficulty then our confidence grows and our capacity grows and slowly there is a way
in which that um more like that our
way that are moving through the world starts to shift as we start to feel like oh i don't have to avoid everything that
might potentially be difficult so our lives start to have some more
ease in that way that we don't have to navigate and negotiate our lives and
that particular any you know to try to make sure that we avoid things just because we start to
have more confidence that we can handle them
what i will say is that um it doesn't mean that we don't get angry or we don't get sad or you know whatever
it might be but it's often and probably you might have noticed this too nancy it's not that the anger or the sadness has gone
away completely but maybe the duration is shorter or maybe the intensity is less
and this is exactly how it happens it's just the duration of the sadness works i'm just making this up you didn't say
it but the duration um just for still feel sad for events but
maybe it's you know less amount of time and then less amount of time and then it just happens and then we just
maybe this sadness arises and like oh yeah there's sadness yep okay
well this is familiar and then you just go do the next thing and maybe there's a little bit of
sadness there but you know that it's not going to be the end of the world whereas before it's like oh i can't believe i'm
sad and i don't want to be sad and i'm gonna be sad for the rest of my life or
whatever it might be i don't know so thank you nancy for saying that too because sometimes if i mean of course we
wish that like wow this mindfulness thing is so great and couldn't it be a little faster
under the impression that the goal was to
really remove the huge peaks and valleys that you go through and sort of
maintain a much more growing um
yeah so you were saying that's kind of the practice is to not have so much of the peaks and the valleys but to roll with
them um i like you what you're saying here it's the idea it's not that the waves don't come but we just learn to
surf better right so we're just like surfing on them and they're not thrashing us around is in the same way
we could call that equanimity and equanimity is uh one of the
really uh it's often it's out of equanimity where the deepest leading goes and the deepest
freedoms are found out of equanimity so yes
yes she was dying guess what she said pray for my
beautiful also i'll just say for those who didn't hear that um
you said that as your mother was dying she said pray that i have equanimity yeah
this capacity to hold it
okay okay thank you all wishing you all a good evening