so welcome how's this sound a little loud yeah
not not loud okay um welcome to uh to to each of you
so we'll we'll sit till the top of the hour i'll lightly guide guide us
then offer offer a talk
so
okay
so just as we begin using the ambient sound
people trickling in to bring you more deeply
into the moment
we treat all all phenomena as a gateway
affording ourselves the relief of not needing to sort out
the pleasant and the unpleasant
everything helping us arrive
so
and we breathe sensitive to the whole body
as if the whole body were breathing
so
come back
um
this realm samsara
is relentlessly presenting options
of what might be what should be
and so often we're seduced into
optimizing the moment
maybe it's safe enough
to let go
to not read the tea leaves of pleasure and pain
to be present is to be utterly undefended
against imperfection
uh
so
you
welcome everyone time to see are there any announcements
hi it's nancy again if i could get a couple of volunteers to help just take out
trash and recycling take about 15 minutes after the dharma talk
thank you anybody else thank you great
and i have an announcement or two um for any newcomers uh i like to mention
that we do have a donna box donation box uh on your left just as you walk inside uh
a blonde wooden box with uh slots for both the teacher donations to teacher and to
imc and we also have an electronic device that we call a kiosk
on the counter just to the right of the door in the uh
in the social hall it's easy to use um but if you need to learn how and want to i can
explain it um and would like to uh welcome our teacher
today matthew brent silver one of the imc's longtime
somewhat frequent guest teachers matthew
thank you thank you um
yeah welcome welcome to all welcome to the uh online crew i see you
um
so in january tiknot han died at the age of
95. which was i think about seven years after a major
stroke and
when i i heard i didn't find myself especially
emotional but then i
looked at some pictures of him you know
found myself crying just seeing seeing his face
and all that is conveyed by his face
and one of my my uh first uh deep encounters with dharma was
a a tiknothon young adult sangha in uh in los angeles and
i had kind of passing academic interest in
meditation but had never really encountered the dharma and
i had a couple apartment mates at the time who
two friends moved out two new people moved in and
they were both meditators long-term meditators and um they they told me that they were going
to have a housewarming party which was their way of not
freaking me out that it was going to be a gathering of the sangha yeah
and um and so i at the time was working in
residential treatment uh with adolescent boys really intense
work beautiful work and really intense and i had no idea about like
self-care or anything like that every day i just sort of left it all on the table you know and
would come home just like kind of wrecked you know and uh
heartful and wrecked and uh i remember
one of those nights i uh i kind of like barreled in the front door
after a long day and a group of people were sitting around
candlelight talking about love you know
and that made an impression you know
like okay this is
like a parallel universe kind of and uh i sat down i sat down
i hadn't i hadn't heard from the group in 20 years that kind of everyone went their
own ways hadn't heard literally 20 years and
and a week before uh tiknahan who people call him tai the week before he
died somebody started a thread out of nowhere no
so i i went through different relationships to his teaching
sort of uh feeling like uh that it times it reaching me at times
feeling [Applause] somehow kind of sentimental or something
or idealistic and i found that as my own
practice my own encounter with the dharma deepens what what a text what a person what a tradition does to one's
heart changes too and you really see how much you might have missed in
earlier encounters and with his teaching
for sure i see
yeah just tremendous depth and grace
and so i was not uh you know i did not have a lot of contact with him but did practice at
a deer park outside san diego and
peace walks in in los angeles and
taught with some later taught with some of his his monastics and
yeah he left a kind of mark and so what a pay tribute to that
who can you talk who can you really trust when they talk about love
like who has earned the moral credibility to actually
say love and it's trustworthy
one way of earning that moral credibility is to
encounter tremendous hardship and persist
in a sense of love devotion to love
and tai was on the front lines of war of religious persecution of exile for
almost 40 years and so when he says love i take that
seriously when he persists in that that
um our redemption is through love i take that seriously
this is uh him in in conversation with bill hoax is 2000.
martin luther king was among us as a brother as a friend as a leader he was able to
maintain that love when you touch him you touch a bodhisattva for his understanding and love
was enough to hold everything to him he tried to transmit his insight and his
love to the community but maybe we have not received it enough
he was trying to transmit the best things to us his goodness his love his non-duality
but because we had clung so much to him as a person we did not bring the essence of what he
was teaching into our community so now that he's no longer here we are
at a loss we have to be aware that the crucial
transmission he was making was not the transmission of power of authority of position
but the transmission of the dharma it means love
it can be can be hard to trace the influences of
one's teachers on one's own being
and myself now doing some teaching i
am cognizant that i'm sort of like plagiarizing all of my teachers all of
the time without being aware of it it feels like it's my original thought
but it's not and it's not because they become part of us you know
like when we encounter them a teacher open heartedly their goodness we sort of like distill
out the medicine that they have for our own heart and it becomes a part of us and it feels
native to our heart and so it's hard to tell what is them
and what is oneself
and ty's teachings have they've had a major impact on
the kind of certainly the buddhist practice in this country many countries
one of the things i remember most was his body the way he
he moved it was just
it just had a kind of moral force to it you know it was like it was the teaching
itself and i don't know i'm not
temperamentally a kind of patient person
but to see him take a step kind of like issue this commandment you
know to like get still
because all of my movement or impatience or the activities of my mind in those
moments they just they just had this kind of absurd sort of
look in the mirror of his presence and stillness
and i heard that after his stroke uh two monks would stand on each shoulder
and two monks with his legs and would support him in taking mindful steps
yeah even given the the compromised state of his body
so i'd watch him move uh to and from the deus around the
monastery through the streets of los angeles and i think about what he said
the kingdom of god is available to you in the here and now but the question is whether you are
available to the kingdom our practice is to make ourselves ready
for the kingdom so that it can manifest in the here and now you don't have to die in order to enter
the kingdom of heaven you have to be truly alive in order to
do so
so much kind of yeah wonder in that what what is the
kingdom of god i would hear that you know what
in his ecumenical style of kind of mixing language buddhist and
theistic language would enter the kingdom of god be available to the
kingdom of god and i had no idea what that meant
but the best instructions are the instructions that evoke
sincerity and curiosity and wonder
what is that how do i make my heart available to the
kingdom [Applause] he says no mud no lotus and
that is really a kind of poetic way of rendering the path of purification
no mud no lotus and
some of the metaphors around purification you know of uh kind of
military metaphors of like uh you know killing the kaleisas the
defilements the force of greed hatred delusion you know sometimes a really strong language
of uh um the force that we we
must use the energy and effort actually required to meet the depth of
the forces of suffering of mara but this is rendered much more gently no
mud no lotus and so of course there is mud there is
great suffering and that is the compost and the fertilizer
for our growing freedom and so in this way life
becomes or our teacher i said in the sit something like um
to be present is to be utterly undefended against imperfection
that is beckoning us into this path of purification
where anything everything is a kind of doorway
into a deeper presence
he emphasized the non-duality of wisdom and compassion often rendering that as
understanding and love and
sometimes it feels like we have wisdom over here and love over here and on the
wisdom side it's like every phenomena every arising is a
gateway to emptiness and
then on this side there's an image of like love
pervading all things you know boundless measureless
and we can be attracted to one side or the other but tiknahan
articulated the the non-duality of wisdom and love
and specifically he tied the notion of egoic identification
with deficits of love
the real power of the buddha he wrote was that he had so much love he saw
people trapped in their own notions of small separate self
feeling guilty or proud of that self and he offered revolutionary teachings that
resounded like a lion's roar helping people to wake up
to break free from the prison of ignorance
and indeed we do see that um
i think ego is a is a function of fear
and its hallmark is defensiveness
and its expression is clinging
and the more energy we actually divest from the egoic
not the more it flows into
wholesomeness into love
and so wisdom and love they're connected
this is again thai
if you pour a handful of salt into a cup of water the water becomes undrinkable
but if you pour the salt into a river people can continue to draw the water to cook wash and drink
the river is immense and it has the capacity to receive embrace and transform
when our hearts are small our understanding and compassion are limited and we suffer
we can't accept or tolerate others and their shortcomings and we demand that they change
but when our hearts expand these same things don't make us suffer anymore we have a lot of understanding and
compassion and can embrace others we accept others as they are
and then they have a chance to transform
understanding someone's suffering is the best gift you can give another
person understanding is love's other name
if you don't understand you can't love
understanding is love's other name that is very
beautiful
and it speaks to this this um understanding that we develop this
insight we develop over the dharma life
that the more
deeply we look into conditionality the more reason we will have to love
the less tenable hatred becomes
yeah that that that hatred is never the last word it may be a first word it may be an
important first word but it is never the last word
and so understanding understanding is love's other name
i've returned to his uh reflections on on anger often
and see it as a kind of yeah service that he he was
you know he was ordained quite young and was a you know monastic for his whole life
and yet he was doing what he could to try to speak to a lay life the life of
of of family and relationships and the the
the joys of that and the upper spiritual opportunity of that and the
tremendous suffering of it and so
um on anger on anger the book i
um so it comes up in my own own reflections and
talks often is his counsel was not to suppress anger
not to vent he called venting anger rehearsing it yeah
and not to pretend you're not angry but to uh basically care for it as a one cares
for a child and so uh says just like our organs our anger
is part of us when we're angry we have to go back to ourselves and take good care of our anger
we cannot say go away anger i don't want you when you have a stomach ache you
don't say i don't want your stomach no you take care of it in the same way we have to embrace and
take care good care of our
anger and so um he described this kind of approach to i
think what he called peace talks to actually expressing anger
neither neither suppressing it nor acting it out
and to talk about anger to confess one's anger without doing it in an aggressive
way is very vulnerable it's more vulnerable sometimes than to
say i am angry with you than to say i love you
and he articulated a yeah a kind of
just a few mantras gatas to like
to support the conversation that they work like
in this kind of like they're diametrically opposed to the the kind of core
energy of anger which is to declare our invulnerability
our independence to declare our certainty
to be an island but the very truth that we are angry is a testament that we
can be hurt that we have been hurt
and so he invites us into the kind of courage of
meeting meeting this interpersonally
and in the context of relationship he offers these these three
kind of statements and one doesn't even have to make these statements even just to
reflect on them is potent enough to do something to one's heart
and so i would go to the person you know i'm
angry with and um after having practiced and done my best
to you know to manage to take good care of the the child of anger you know
and um and then the the the the statements the confessions the pleas
are i am angry i suffer
i'm doing my best i need your help
yeah i'm angry i suffer i'm doing my best i need your help
and i think what i find so so touching about that like okay
it is exactly what anger wishes to conceal
namely our dependence
and here we just come right out with it i need your help
tai highlighted um nonduality in a particular way that all
things inter are the order of inter being was his uh
um committed practitioners the order of inter being all things inter are
and at first it sort of sounds like a kind of philosophical analysis of
interdependence that that um you know of dependent dependent
origination that this is because that is when this is not that is not
but it it feels like more than a philosophical reflection it is being
invited into an in insight into uh
emptiness if you're a poet you will see that
there's a cloud floating in this sheet of paper without a cloud
there's no rain without rain no trees without trees cannot make paper
so we can say that the cloud and the paper enter are
looking even more deeply we can see we are in it too it's not so difficult to see because
when we look at this sheet of paper sheet of paper is part of our perception
your mind is in here and mine is also
so we can say everything is in here with this sheet of paper you cannot point out
one thing that is not here time space the earth the rain the
minerals in the soil the sunshine the cloud the river and the heat
this sheet of paper is because everything else is
if that's a sheet of paper what are you
yeah that can stop us in our tracks
this understanding provides a basis for um
for non-division for compassion
and
and it points to
this suggestion no no birth no death
there's no coherent place to demarcate
a life a birth a death
we think of our body as ourself belonging to ourself but if you
look deeply you see the body as the body of your ancestors of your parents of your children
their children so it's not me it's a not mine
your body is full of everything else limitless non-body elements
to die in our notion of death means that from something you suddenly become nothing
from someone you become no one that is a horrible idea
that makes no sense if something has not been born will that
something have to die sometime
and this he said was the key to fearlessness fearlessness
it's often said ignorance is the kind of fundamental wellspring of suffering but
i often have the thought that it's
fear that that this is even more foundational
than ignorance
and so fearlessness he said is the ultimate joy
fearlessness is the ultimate joy
and this understanding reframes how we construe death and endings
and so tai did not talk about reincarnation as a kind of
um the seed consciousness you know
reanimating a new body or something like this no it's like the the
sum total of our you know the
lineage or our kind of lineage and the effects of our life on everything else
and so one last piece this begins
the talk begins with ty saying
she was 20 years old when i first met her
and it's kind of like record scratch kind of like wait
20 years old when i first met her
in indeed it is a love story and he describes being a um
a 24 year old monk celibate monk and falling in love with a nun
and said as a monk you're not supposed to fall in love but sometimes love is
stronger than your determination and so this is from a series of talks
given in 1992 he was 65 i believe
and called cultivating the mind of love
and um he's falling in love and she seems to
be falling in love too and uh he has a
sleepless night and tries to write
poetry but can't even get one sentence down you know he's trying
to redirect the intensity of this kind of falling you know
and and he's up late at night and
desperately wants to go to her room and indeed
she has a similar kind of longing
and he because of his vows his commitments and and the sense of like his vow to protect
her to protect her he does not go
and they decide together given their vows that they they must be away from
each other they have to be a part in different monasteries and so she's
about to move to somewhere else
he says i remember the moment we parted
we sat across from each other she too seemed overwhelmed by despair
she stood up came close to me took my head in her arms
and drew me close to her in a very natural way
i allowed myself to be embraced it was the first and last time we had
any physical contact then we bowed
and separated
so what to do with that despair with that poignancy with that
longing what to do with it
no mud no lotus and through a kind of alchemical process
that is transformed maybe we call it sublimation maybe we call it
purification but there's a way of actually
he's describing of redirecting his own narrow personal longing into
the channel of a greater love and pro-social
commitment and so he says over time my love for her
did not diminish but it was no longer confined to one
person i began to see her everywhere
so this is a sacrifice and a renunciation and
it's one that he made for her and for himself and for
us we are the inheritors of that gesture
we're the beneficiaries of that love
and so the question then is like what what will we do
with ty's love
let's just sit for a moment
so
so thank you thank you for your attention practice
and um yeah yeah to
youtube group thank you and um
yeah i wish you wish you all well offer this for for your consideration pick up what's useful and leave what's not
behind okay