so greetings far and wide early and late light and dark
taking 45 minutes together settle in with ourselves and
reconnect with Our intention for practice
reflecting on these precepts again and beginning as we do with mindfulness
I noticed in myself a sort of quality of
appreciation or something edging on reverence for
the practice and the
the ability we have to come together as Sangha
something to celebrate as we settle so let's take our seat
coming into that upright alert
and useful meditative posture
reclining if that's the need for your body or sitting upright
sensing into balance
maybe the shoulders are asking to roll back
maybe the breath is asking for just a little more depth
with listening to the body taking its cues to guide us into
alignment
as we settle if there's any obvious tension or
holding
just a little relaxation it's okay to let go
relaxing releasing settling
and attentive attentive breathing in
attentive breathing out
foreign
thank you
attentive with the breathing
if the attention happens to be vague or
dull
perhaps adding just one more level of precision
with the awareness a little bit closer with the breathing
how is that connection between attention and the breathing
[Music]
and if the attention feels tight or over energized
rather than putting
the attention forcing the attention on the breathing letting the breathing come to you
foreign
[Music]
attentive breathing in attentive breathing out
allowing each moment of experience to arise
register and release
no Trace
foreign
[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
attentive breathing in attentive breathing out
if you notice both activity
in the mind and Stillness
to let go into Stillness
foreign
thank you
[Music] foreign
foreign
and as the sitting comes to an end
the moment of appreciation
for these minutes of practice
for our renewal of the intention
to be mindful clearly aware
discerning
letting any goodness of the practice permeate the body
in small ways perhaps May everyone we encounter today
benefit even invisibly from our practice together
thank you
thank you all and hello again my name is kodo
some many of us have been having a discussion or reflection on the
five lay precepts this week it's our fourth day
and the plan will be to address in some way
the fourth lay precept which is for the sake of our training
together I undertake the precept to abstain from
false speech to abstain from false speech
it's difficult to overstate the importance of honesty and
truthfulness and the Buddhist teaching
um so much so that the Buddha called
uh false speech non-dharma not Dharma
not the truth not the Buddhist teaching and he called true speech Dharma
broadens the scope somewhat about what is Dharma and what's not Dharma perhaps
but I think emphasizes just how important truth honesty
were for the the path of practice that the Buddha taught yeah
specifically we've been talking a bit about the middle length of this course is 61.
the Buddha's advice to rahula and in this teaching when he's advising
his own son in the in the training of a monastic the Buddha says something to the effect
of um for anyone who is willing to tell a
deliberate lie anyone who is willing to tell a deliberate lie
in dramatic language the Buddha says there's no evil that they will not do
I want to have a little bit of caution here as I say this because it's easy then it's very very easy to then appoint
the fingers to the dishonesty around us when the invitation at least for this
reflection this morning is to look look at our own conduct begin there
let's be sensitive there become wise there and then allow that to
um support us to be wise socially yeah and interpersonally
no evil they would not do so I think something something maybe many
of us recognize is the is the power with which true speech
honest speech inspires faith some might even some might even observe
the way that when we speak truthfully when we speak honestly um it it supports and establishes the
kind of confidence in US I can rely on my own word
uh it's almost it almost um a support for the mind that's observable
these little kindnesses we do for the mind in our practice somehow true speech
brings in this sense of settling Foundation oh I have my I have my feet
on the ground so
again poetically the Buddha the Buddha uh discussing truth and not truth Dharma
not Dharma he also compared them in these dramatic images not truth false
speech he compared to dung in fact and true speech he compared to flowers
can really sense into the Buddha's value for truth I think there may be something here uh
uh in my in my own speculation about how the truth served the Buddhism path
in the story that we that we know very well perhaps um the Buddha is a young one
was very very protected he was maybe royalties semi-royalty grew
up in a trio of palaces that were just perfectly suited for each season
never exposed uh never exposed to old age illness and
death and when he finally encountered them the truth of those drove him
into a different life and then he became some he became
and taught and practiced something that I think is possible for us
and that is to be devotees of the truth
devotees of the truth
I've heard mindfulness practice described or I've heard honesty honest speech described as mindfulness out loud
mindfulness out loud I think we can see when we reflect on our mindfulness practice
the the honesty with which we observe our inner world
the activity of our inner world supports us to see clearly outside
foreign Marlene's brought up this great question in the chat I appreciate questions in
the meantime it makes this more of a conversation what if the truth is unclear
wow that's a profound question isn't it what if the truth is unclear
I think um My First Response might be
yes yes
because how often the truth is unclear this actually touches on something else I wanted to mention uh came up as a
question yesterday how do we recognize harm I think as I explain that it may touch
on this question of what what about when the truth is unclear so I'd like to open this up maybe with
an exercise so just for a minute let's bring ourselves back to the
meditative posture but this time I'd like you to lay your
hands open in front of you your eyes can be closed but your hands open on your lap
and then I'd like you to bring your attention to let's say your left hand
your left hand let's take a minute to feel and sense
into the left hand and then maybe any tensions or
holding or twisting in that left hand and see what you can relax
just right there and the muscles the tendons the fingertips
of the left hand
grieving the tension in and out relaxing
relaxing
it's just for a few breaths
now I'd like you to sense into your other hand without that relaxation
maybe you can see or feel or sense the difference between those two hands side
by side one with some residual holding clinging
tensions discomfort and one that's been cared for and
relaxed it's just a sense into that contrast
it's a simple exercise but one that I think starts to point us toward how to recognize harm and not harm
and this applies to what happens when we're confused what happens when the truth is unclear
and reflecting on harm and not harm what I wanted to share with you is
we can begin where it's simple where there are say clear admonitions
about what to refrain from we can begin practicing there
and then what's required of us is repeated reflection
over and over uh we grow more subtle in our sense of what's what's harmful and what's not
harmful the training in fact isn't to isn't to always walk around with a with a clear
sense of this this um this activity leads to harm this one doesn't
know I should take care without saying this now
but the the notion is is that we will continually deepen
the skill of recognizing harm it too is part of the practice it
develops over time through repeated reflection and through a process actually of trial and error
one of the ways this can happen to describe this sort of as a developmental model that I think applies to both harm
and Truth is the is this simple but clear
observation oh they're suffering here in my life they're suffering I noticed this
specific suffering not a suffering in the abstract so seeing oh they're suffering here and our
mindfulness recognizes that our mindfulness meets that and through that encounter
um oh you may have seen my hand do this this is a reminder to myself that the
suffering that we experience often is repetitive often a similar suffering repeats itself
for us we end up doing the same things
but that also gives us the possibility the opportunity to recognize
that every time this particular kind of suffering arises for us there are all these conditions that lead
up to it through all these contributions that come and make this bit of suffering
and then seeing that seeing the conditions underneath we have a chance to
possibly do something different so we learned to recognize harm
we learn the contributions that go into harm in just over and over practice it's a slow growth in wisdom
and the same is true for truths in the
in the early teachings the Buddha encouraged encouraged a
person to remember three locations one was where they were ordained he was
talking to monastics but we can maybe remember the place where we first encountered the Dharma teachings
the second is where they saw all four noble truths at the same time
where they had some penetrating insight and to oh this is the ennobling truth of
the Buddha these are the truths of the Buddha and what do those comprise something
about suffering and its ending so maybe this is a long way of saying
that our our un our understanding our familiarity and our recognition
of harm and Truth develops over time develops over time
um we act with the best possible intentions available to us
and then make an honest assessment about how that went in terms of
in terms of true speech and false speech um
the we can take a cue from the vinya the monastic rules about how one makes
amends to recognize something important one makes amends
one makes amends through recognizing that something has
gone wrong confessing and laying that open to a
good Dharma friend in their case monastics and then making a resolve to try to do
something different in the future recognizing laying it open and making a resolve
d so in this sense the Buddha is very clear actually that our mistakes there
must they may be our mistakes but it's um it's a it's a source of growth he
actually calls it growth in the Dharma when we do this we recognize our mistakes lay them open and then resolve
for something different in the future so hopefully that touched on touched on
a bit the fourth precept with the time we have um before we do a short precept
recitation I want to say a little bit the plan for tomorrow we will discuss reflect on the fifth
precept of abstaining from intoxicants that are cause for heedlessness I'll make I'll uh
make some concluding remarks about this week and then I would also like to make
room for more questions tomorrow um so you may consider what is
um what feels alive or evocative or unfinished from our conversation not to
say we'll finish everything uh tomorrow but um anything you'd like to bring up
we'll have some time for that and then I would I would like to do a little bit longer precept recitation
tomorrow uh perhaps in the ancient language of the Pali just so we can all
be exposed to that uh or hear it again so
let's close as we have been all week and then we can say for a while here we have the five precepts
for the sake of our training together I undertake the precept to abstain from
harming living beings for the sake of our training together I undertake the precept to abstain from
taking what is not given for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept to abstain from sexual misconduct for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from false speech
for the sake of our training together if I undertake the precept to abstain from intoxicants that are cause for
heedlessness may we all be well
and may our integrity and honesty support us in the practice today
and those we encounter may all beings know the benefits of Truth
take care until tomorrow