all right hello and welcome welcome to happy hour
this this rendition of it so
so what I want to um
invite us to turn our attention to uh for practice today is
um is the need for rest the need for rest
as as an expression of meta and yet I want to bring a Twist to this
rest it's not just sleeping or vegging out in front of Television to
rest which of course sleeping is very important please get a lot of sleep and sometimes
vegging is actually the appropriate things to do sometimes it is the appropriate thing to do not always but
sometimes it is the appropriate thing to do so you know I'll talk more about that later
but but the twist I want to bring in um
is um the way our minds our hearts can really
rest their sense of deep rest
often happens and can't happen in
in easeful nourishing meditation so not to approach meditation as this
thing I have to do and I have to accomplish and I have to be but actually
seeing the act of meditating as complete rest letting the mind come to rest
oh sweetheart dear mine you can rest you can let go you can let go
there are many different ways to see and
under many different practices with it also even the Buddhist Canon different
ways to practice meditation as as you all know by now there's
paying attention with mindfulness there is meta practice there's compassion
there's uh you know there are all the prama we have so there are different ways we can pay attention and this this
way of the the um inclining the mind to rest to rest
with with things as they are to let go that
just to rest just to rest can be seen
as another expression of meta and care
it's also a practice of of it's a Liberation practice the
liberative practice it's of Letting Go not clinging it's the opposite of clinging when we cling I want this I
want it to be a particular way I want these great states of mind I want this pain to go away I want this distraction
to go away I want I want I want I want I want or I don't want I don't want I don't know which is actually the same
thing is wanting the want to just the it's the pushing away versus the one that's still
the wanting still the the grasping whereas this this idea of rest
depressed um I really really want this pain to go
Eric actually what if I just rest with with it oh I really want to have pleasant
experiences what if I let go of this wanting and just rest with yeah it's a pretty ordinary experience right now
well actually it's pretty awesome this ordinary experience when you stop wanting something else you wake up to
how awesome amazing this ordinary experience is
and say with the distracted or sleepy mind
again instead of wanting to push away the distractions like oh
letting go this this sense of letting go okay I see you thoughts I see your
distractions I see you planning and wanting and it's like what if I just open my hand yeah I know you're gonna
come back but it's okay I'm gonna let go not not throw you away but invite my
heart to just rest rest it's a different way of engaging I
was talking about engagement on Monday engaging with meta engaging our minds so
this is engaging with rest which sounds a little counter-intuitive how do I engage with
rest but it teaches our heart it teaches our mind a different way of being this
engaging with letting go and engaging with a sense of rest so
might be a con for some of you right now like what does she mean well let's
discover let's explore it together and see what we find out see what we find
out so okay shall we shall we let's do it all right okay so
I invite you to get into your meditation posture
ah Landing in this body in this moment
and In This Moment what if we let go of all the Notions
of what we all have collectively about what doing meditation is what if you
just let go of it all and for a moment just sit not knowing what to quote
unquote what to do next like oh you know what I'm sitting
okay now what stay in that moment stay with that
now what now what do I do nothing stay with that
and if you find yourself doing let go again
and rest take a radical stance to the practice
and you can also notice the the way your mind gravitates
I noticed that my mind wants to rest with the breath because all of these years of training
ah I just wants to collect itself and just rest in the breath
ah it doesn't feel like doing it feels like resting okay I'm gonna let it
see if there's any movement in that way in your heart in your mind that feels
like resting not doing if something feels like doing then just let it go and come back to that space of
not knowing like okay now what nothing nothing but if it feels the mind is resting with
the breath or the body ah because it knows a place of safety
ease Refuge then it's okay let it
the kitty of the mind is collecting itself in the Sun
the body of the breath and resting napping it's okay not
literally napping but a sense of rest is of non-doing
engaging with letting go of wanting
this deep rest another door into the Temple of Metta
care for yourself
if you find the mind is wandering notice notice can you let go
invite the mind to rest the heart to rest sweetheart rest it's okay you don't have
to solve all the world's problems right now Refuge Refuge rest
you might have to let go remind your heart
to rest a hundred times it's okay do it gladly
during this period do it lovingly
hear heart rest
keep it simple very simple tonight
let go rest
let go rest and enjoy enjoy
the Simplicity of rest profound simplicity
rest let go let go and rest pick Refuge
let go let go of thoughts
tightness in the body
turning away towards the Simplicity of not wanting
anything in this moment just
relish rest for the heart
and the mind depressed
no need to think to solve problems right now
can you see the goodness and rest
the Mind resting
resting with the body with the breath
simple
are found
if you find yourself thinking planning really Grog get to know
what it's like not to rest for the mind to be busy feel the energy of it in the body
and then lovingly for the benefit of your heart let go let go
and turn to rest find your heart your mind to rest
and see how that feels learn discover how that feels
trusting that resting is more nourishing right now than thinking or planning or
figuring something out trust it see for yourself
training your mind to rest we train our minds all day to be busy
busy busy and of course when we stop they're busy we've been training them
all day Now train your heart your mind
to rest sweetheart rest it's okay it's okay
eat pressed
and profound training and letting go
rest there rest rest
engaging and non-doing non-thinking letting go
just being caressed rest
there will be a million thoughts coming it's okay be patient be loving with them
all with yourself [Music] the puppy is so used to running around
gently Pat it love it rest darling rest
let go of the bones let go
rest
they might seem to see the bones but they're Hollow it's all
Hollow rest
let go let go let go let go
let go and rest
let awareness rest just with the breath of the body
and um
foreign
um
resting resting letting go
and as we bring this period of sitting practiced her clothes
noticing that even if you thought or you felt you were
distracted and you didn't quote unquote rest that
much yet take stock notice
that your body your heart your mind ah
slightly more calm settled rested
when you started or nourished more cared for
learning reteaching ourselves our minds our hearts how to rest not forcing but
inviting may we know may we know rest to rest
may all beings everywhere
know the nourishment the goodness of rest may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
foreign
s to rest
as an expression of care as an expression of Mecca for ourselves
loving this heart loving this mind
so we have time for Reflections and I do acknowledge that
I'm pretty calm myself so might be
um actually maybe some of you want to say something and just ready to jump in
but uh I also feel the quiet and the Peace of Letting Go and the
and the rest in my heart and mind that feels quite nourishing so
so any questions any aha moments any challenges
anything you want to check in about an offer
with this practice of turning away
turning letting go of Engagement engaging with thoughts and
memories and doing Neil says super chill in chat yeah super
chill indeed [Laughter]
I love it super chill yeah those two words
it's good it's this is there's nourishment of rest
in non-doing in meditation as non-doing that that's so nourishing especially if
our minds our hearts are so used to doing and doing and doing and doing some
more it's like okay all right let's train ourselves in this way
let's see Bill says interesting how many of my thoughts could be classified as
either grasping or aversion watching those two arise again and again
great oh how wonderful to be able to see the classification this is great it's
it's um you know there is the falling into the thoughts falling into the grasping and
pushing away and yet when we've graduated to actually
um seeing the classification oh yeah that's an aversive thought okay I see oh that's
a graspy thought okay grasp one you know team one zero twos
though three okay about the same I'm just joking but but when we get to actually see the process instead of fall
into the content that is fantastic so it's not a problem that they arise of
course they arise thoughts are dime a dozen we don't have to believe them so so Bill I celebrate
um that you get to see them and classify them rather than falling into
yay thumbs up ah Gene says rest equals less stress yes
I appreciate that reflection from um
from gene on on YouTube yeah there is there is this freedom of this rest this
letting go but uh letting go is not engaging with
with friction also Jamie I see your hand please
yeah uh Nicki for for a little while it just got so quiet
that I wondered um what the difference between rest and
death is I'm just curious if you have anything to say about that
huh so so wait so let let me follow the thread you're presenting before jumping
to the question um so it got so quiet for you it sounds like in this meditation right yeah
so could you say just a little more about that because then the question is interesting but I want to see where the
link is between the the peacefulness of rest and where where your mind jumped to
the question so unpackage for me a bit Jamie with you
um no it's just this this
profound deep Stillness and
I I wondered [Music] um
oh is this what that would be like um
so so before I go there again I want to ask you the Deep profound Stillness how did
that feel how was the quality of that for you in this experience
it was um exceptional it was so um
it was beautiful yeah yeah beautiful
lovely thanks for unpacking that great so this exceptional beautiful quality of
of deep rest deep Stillness wow how awesome is this it's nourishing it's not
scary at all and so so I invite you to consider
that letting go because what what this um sense of ease and Stillness arising
from letting go right and letting go Letting Go resting resting Stillness
so death is a kind of well it is a letting go it's an ultimate letting go
it's letting go of the last breath it's letting go of life it's letting go it's a releasing it's a releasing
and and what you just spoke of can be the
quality of mind can be the quality of Mind accepting approaching being with death
now as to what death itself is like I don't know and nobody has really come
back to tell us so let's have a don't know mind about that and yet this Stillness could very well
be an experience right before the ultimate letting go maybe maybe
does that make sense what I'm trying to the needle I'm trying to thread absolutely absolutely thank you thank
you so much for sharing this beautiful uh lovely inspiring practice report yay
I'm very sick today and I just to have this profound experience in the middle
of it is just so such a gift thank you um hmm thank you oh deep bows thank you so much
uh for practicing uh while sick which is actually quite
it's I love practicing while sick it's uh you know things can quite yeah
beautiful ah thanks for sharing that with the Sangha Jamie great
so dear ones I'm going to I would like to invite us all to rest with each other in small groups
today you can and when the your turn comes you can just say pass and you can
just be silent with each other if you want to say something you can but
you're invited to just hold Silence with each other if you want it's quite a
habit to develop and see if you can keep in your eyes open while you stay silent
and again maybe after a minute or two or three of Silence maybe somebody gets moved feels moved to share something
about this rest being in the space of rest with the others not rushing to fill
the silence and feel that tendency maybe this discomfort
of wanting to rush to fill it and maybe at some point it feels
appropriate to say something or maybe not maybe you'll just spend a few minutes in silence and metal with each
other it's an experiment right so I might make it tonight a little shorter so you'll come you can come back and
actually tell me how it was so let's see I'm going to
create the rooms uh for this experiment in being
being with being with one another um
okay creating your rooms here take care of yourselves take care of each other
here you go okay the rooms are closed we are all
backed together so we have a better minute for any
Reflections it might have felt different well how was it to be together in this
super chilled way in the space anybody wants to say anything
awkward interesting I learned something new about myself
Aurora please I'll say something
um it gave me pause to land in my body
and it made me realize that sometimes when I talk like I follow the words out
and I'm not here that makes sense absolutely
I was like oh oh I'm still here
and and that was nice
so what a powerful realization thanks for sharing that or I love it I love it wow that's a great insight to come from
this different setting thanks thanks for that any any other realizations any quick ones from
this different setup
foreign
last minute ahas okay
okay so I we leave on that note of realizing acknowledging oh yeah Landing
in the body when we speak I think many of us if not all of us can can
appreciate that they're following the words out so so thank you all for
practicing together for bringing yourself showing up to cultivate for the sake of
yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be
free thanks everyone take care