so greetings from insight meditation center in redwood
city and uh i delight in seeing all the good mornings the greetings on the chat
and have today especially stands out all the locations the places that you're
greeting from so thank you for being here those of you who are
both present now it's youtube and those maybe who will listen later
so the craft
of meditation of mindfulness and it begins
this uh journey we're on with the mindfulness of breathing and um so i'm taking some time with it
because it lays the foundation for what follows and also because
this is the first time we'll go through the so-called refrain where it lists the insights that come with
well-developed practice and so i want to go through that a little bit slower than we will do later
but for now i want to um go back to this uh these steps to the
breathing a little bit of shorthand there is uh
the first is to know your breathing know that you are breathing but then also to know
the experience of breathing to recognize it to have a recognition of
the sensations the characteristics the qualities of the breath where you're breathing
what moves what the sensations are and this is not a
a probing but rather it's a it's a
very simple recognition of what is obvious and as we stay grounded and become more
centered on the breathing what becomes more obvious becomes more subtle and we can start seeing more detail to
what's going on and then the instructions are as we do this as we
center ourselves on the rhythm of breathing the sensations of breathing to um experience the whole body
and uh what i'd like to emphasize today about this whole body aspect
is that um our emotional life the and the life that
uh of thoughts and distractions all have an embodied quality or
a root or association and and this this is often thoughts and
emotions often can distract us from being with the breathing
but this instructions to breathe in and experience the whole body breathe out and experience the whole body
can be inclusive of the very things that make it difficult to be present the things that keep us distracted or caught
up and the way to do that is to recognize
what makes it difficult to be present the distracted mind or maybe strong emotions or maybe discomfort in the body
pain and then when we experience the whole body experience that as well
uh and it might you might just experience it experience it as something mental or something emotional
but you're experiencing with this rhythm of breathing in experiencing the whole
body breathing out experiencing the whole body and so the center of gravity
is breathing and experiencing the body the center of gravity is not the distracted thoughts
the concerns we have and it's not the emotions we have emotions are important but
for the purposes of meditation we don't have to make them the center they're included
in the experience of the whole body and it has this wonderful thing of being able to
move in and out move through
whatever is challenging for being present and including it as part of being present
rather than letting it be something keeps pulling us away we assimilate it we
coordinate ourselves with it we let it cooperate with the efforts to be here
so breathing in experiencing the whole body as we breathe in and including how the experience of
breathing might go through or accompany the
thing that makes it difficult and it's particularly useful if what makes it difficult to be present
has a physical association a physical manifestation
so if there's a lot of emotions that's chances are there's some place in the body where those motions are
centered or most expressed or if there's a lot of thinking there might be some kind of mental
some kind of tension somewhere in the body associated with all that thinking in the furrow and the uh the eyebrows or
behind the forehead or in the jaws or all kinds of places
and then at some point the last step of this beginning exercise
is to relax relax the bodily constructs
we do this all we take our time with each one there's no hurry through them but
one of the ways to to really get centered is to be inclusive of the very thing
that makes it difficult in this way that i'm talking about so
to begin to assume a posture
that gives you some sense of being inclusive
that includes all of who you are for some people that means to kind of
sit upright and alert a little bit maybe a little bit tall
little my chest open
and to lower your gaze
as you lower your gaze to turn your attention inward
to how your body feels now
and then if it's comfortable gently closing your eyes
and maybe that allows you to feel your body more fully
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths three quarters full perhaps
then as you breathe in deeply and exhale more fully
imagine that you're including everything
within the scope the range of that deep inhale
relaxing everything on the exhale
a little bit imagining that you are
that your attention can flow out to include everything as
you breathe in everything as you breathe out
and then letting your breathing return to normal
then whenever there is some tension or holding
wherever there is some compelling emotion
as you breathe in feel that place
as you exhale relax that place
perhaps each time you inhale aware of a different place in
your body
the exhale relaxing that place in a sense folding everything
into the breathing
and then centering yourself more on the breathing
and now getting to know your breathing better
curious about the sensations curious about how breathing occurs now
the sensations that come into play
the rhythm of it the nature of your breathing
long or short shallow or deep in the chest or in the belly
feeling where there might be holding in the breathing whatever is there
just know it simply without worry about
evaluating it just letting it be and know it as it is
breathing in experiencing the whole body
maybe as if awareness spreads through your body as you breathe in
breathing out experiencing the whole body
maybe as if the awareness moves back through the body
if anything it distracts you from breathing
as you breathe in and experience the whole body
experience the nature the quality the distraction itself
the movements of the mind the body the emotions
breathe in and let the awareness spread and touch the very
place where you're distracted
and then breathing in relaxing the bodily formations
breathing out relaxing
the holding and tension contractions of your body
by breathing in and experiencing the whole body
it lets you know feel
where it's possible to become quieter more tranquil
maybe spreading a tranquility of body through the body
relaxation and tranquility that touches everything
including what is difficult
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
letting your breathing breathing in
experiencing the whole world imagine that your awareness spreads from
the breathing as you breathe in out into the whole world
out beyond yourself beyond the place you're living
and then as you exhale that awareness returns here to you
and the scope of your care expands outward with that
expanding awareness circles of care out into the world
and then it returns to you on the exhale centering you
connecting you settling you here
with this rhythm of sending your care your love compassion
out into the world as you inhale
as your chest expands belly expands as your lungs feel
so your care expands outward
and as you exhale it all returns back here
centered here on you
may all beings be happy
may you be happy
may all beings be safe
may you be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may you be peaceful
may all beings be free
may you be free
breathing in and breathing out may we hold each other
in mutual kind regard
so today i'm going to continue talking about the so-called refrain
of the satipatana the place where the fruit of some of the fruit of
mindfulness practice uh occurs where we start having insight we start
seeing in a new way and uh it begins by with the line
what observes the body in terms of the body internally and what observes the body in terms of
the body externally and um and as i've emphasized the word
observe is actually uh the fruit of being able being gathered and settled and centered
here in the present moment and the the tendency to be distracted and wonder often thought is pretty
minimal and i think of it a little bit like a um
you know a large bowl and the any marble you drop in the bowl will
will you know roll back and forth around the bowl but eventually it will always come and
rest at the center and and so the same way that and
as we practice attention eventually comes in rests at the center
of which is the present moment the sides of this bold where we is not very stable
is the future and the past and if we end up on the sides inevitably if we relax
we'll come back and rest in the center it takes effort and energy in the mind to be
pushing the ball up the sides this way and that way and then if we do
the momentum of that ball i will uh the
energy of that ball to uh to roll down uh will will you know as it sometimes it
takes a little while for it to settle but then eventually it settles in the bottom of the bowl
so our attention it settles in the present moment and as it does so then at some point we
can simply observe and the knowing and the experiencing isn't as important anymore they still
occur and it's important they occur but we're settling back and more than
movement of awareness is out of observing just watching freely relaxedly
um un not entangled or enmeshed in what's happening just kind of seeing
it not being for or against anything just just perceiving it
with the mind's eye or the mind's ear if you prefer the the metaphor of hearing
or feeling sensing in the body also can be done this way it's uh it's inner way of perceiving
that's deeper than than the direct experience of the senses
so this experiencing internally and externally there's one way that i uh interpret this for myself that i'll
share with you and that is that um
the external way so-called external is uh to experiencing it uh cognitively
so the knowing that's the beginning of the breath meditation knowing the breath is a cognitive experience of recognition
so there's the knowing that it's a long breath knowing it's a short breath knowing it's a shallow breath a deep
breath knowing it's the breath is fast and slow knowing that there's expansion as we
breathe in and contraction as we breathe out knowing there's pressure and as we breathe in the release of that pressure
perhaps as we exhale and there's tightening and pulsing and vibration and
and all these things are known and that's a little bit of a mental cognitive act to know
um and the knowing you know that you know when you could describe it to someone
when you have the words to say oh that was expansion that was contraction
that was long that was short and to have those words requires it goes through the cognitive functioning of the
mind the recognition and i think of that as a little bit the external
kind of uh the internal is to sense and feel
the experience of something so for example if i um
take my fingers together and maybe press my two fingers my thumb and my first finger together
that and i look at it i can recognize that the fingers are
touching and and maybe i can recognize that i can see they're pushing against each other
and that's the recognition part but as i as i touched my fingers together i
feel the warmth i feel the pressure i feel the elasticity of the skin a little
bit i feel the hardness and pressure as i push hard
and i can recognize those cognitively but it also can feel those sensations
and the the feelings are happening within the fingers and that's inside so the experience of
the fingers touching can be known two different ways cognitively as a recognition as a
knowing that the fingers are touching and knowing that that's
pressure knowing that it's warmth that it's elasticity that i'm feeling and
and it could also be known uh be i can be aware of it from the inside i can be aware of it
in the location in the fingers where the touching is happening and i can just
feel the f from the point of view the finger is how it feels so we have these two ways of knowing
to recognize and to feel recognize and experience and the two are closely connected
they're mutually supportive they can occur together uh it's not like one or the other
and um and there's a kind of a natural kind of going back and forth in the mind
between experiencing and knowing knowing and experiencing that when the mind is settled and
relaxed is a little bit like the the example i like so much that uh
you know please be repair with me it's like watching the river flow by saying on the banks watching the rivers
little currents you see maybe little waves you see and
and the eyes don't fixate on any one thing because everything is moving
and the eyes are moving along with it it turns out that when the eyes are locked
there's usually tension in their psychophysical system when the eyes the natural relaxed state
eyes kind of flow and move and move around and and uh here and there just kind of they don't not held at a single
thing it's actually work to find a little point in front of you and hold your mind there your eyes there
fixedly without letting them go but to let the eyes just wander around a thing it doesn't have to be a big thing
it could just be a small thing it naturally kind of it moves and round and takes in
everything of the thing so um so same watching the river go by
that's one of the reasons why it can be relaxing to watch something like that because the eyes naturally will kind of
move with everything going therapists sometimes will encourage people when they're stressed
or afraid to especially if they're you know locked into it to look around a room and just kind of
look at the corners look at lines look when i'm sometimes on the computer a lot like on zoom a lot
um i'll start looking at the for a while i'll look at the edge of the monitor just trace the edge of the monitor
there's something about just tracing it to a relaxed way that feels relaxing and it kind of loosens up something
deeper inside and so the same thing with our our inner
awareness our mindfulness that if it's locked in that it's actually kind of tense
but a way to get settled and concentrated in a healthy way
gathered in and unified is uh there's this kind of very simple
it's not exactly willful or intentional but there's natural moving feeling and
knowing knowing and feeling and um and there's something about gently relaxedly
allowing each to be mutually supportive to know i'm breathing to feel the
breathing to know the in-breath to feel the in-breath to feel the in-breath to know
the sensation and it might seem like it's busy work like there's a lot going on but it's
actually recognizing it's probably happening all along you might prioritize one
it might be mostly knowing and originally in the beginning like the exercise is it might mostly be feeling sometimes
experiencing it but each one includes the other
and so observing the body internally
and observing the body externally is to recognize this simple relaxed
income in constant constantly changing and shifting modes of awareness
sometimes feelings sometimes knowing and that and it's more like recognizing that it's what the mind is doing that
our system is doing that then instructions to do because the instructions are just to
observe and so as we open up our perception to what's happening
we're also becoming aware not only of what is happening what the what the experience of the body
is but they can that it's being known in different modes it's being node no in the mode of
knowing recognition in the mode of feeling and if you and then you get to both the best
of both of those worlds both of those ways of being they both are profound and
meaningful and uh it's important not to prioritize one over the other as being the thing
like the way of doing mindfulness but one of them might be the way we get
centered and focused so if you learn yourself well enough to know that you get more so focused by the knowing
that faculty great go for it if you get more focused by the feeling faculty go
for it and if you get more focused by the relaxing quality of this
first exercise relaxing the bodily formations go with it but the movement
is to go to this come to this place where we can just observe and one of the ways that i found helpful
this to observe internally and externally the body
is uh to recognize the shifting natural relaxed shifting that goes on
um between knowing and experiencing and now it's kind of like sitting at
their at the riverbank watching a stream go by just oh look at that it's just
this is constantly shifting and moving and and in that way it can be relaxing too
because there's no fixation so i hope that made sense if it doesn't
make sense maybe it will one day and in the meantime don't worry about it
and this first exercise of meditating on the breath
is phenomenally um
useful it kind of you just keep doing it and it probably keeps opening up and opening up just the simplicity of doing
the breath meditation without trying too much the techniques and
drawing everything all at once so today is the
teaching then is the foundation for the teaching tomorrow and the next step
in the refrain and in the meantime maybe through the day you can
study a little bit the shifting nature of when you know something cognitively and when you know
something experientially and how closely connected they can be if you relax
so thank you very much