so good morning good day hello everyone we come to the end of
this series on the six qualities of the dharma
five qualities of the dharma and one of them is that it's
not doesn't belong to time there was a i mentioned yesterday as a
story of a celestial being that challenged a young monk and said you're young you should
enjoy sensual pleasures and
you're pursuing things that are taking time pursue something that's immediate
you know sensual desires and the monk says no it takes time to pursue sensual desires
i don't know about time i'm not living in time i'm just being here present
for what takes no time and so this idea that
that this dharma is something that's immediate that's
right here implies that it is here
in some way and i think it's probably fair to say that when we
were often too preoccupied with our concerns to see the dharma operating right here
and how do we see it one of the most common ways in which these ancient
teachings of the buddha emphasize is we see it
by first seeing that there is attachments greed
aversion delusion that there is conceit there's concern
with self self preoccupation often our preoccupations are centered
and the main character is me myself and i
and we see that clearly so there's an honesty and like this is what's happening i see what's happening
as opposed to being pushed around by it and being carried by it and
kind of involved participating in this stream of thoughts and preoccupations just really
see it all this is what's happening and at the same time is seeing what this is what's happening
seeing there's something about that's here now which is not caught in it
something which is not right now which is not involved in greed and hatred and
delusion and conceit right here there is when where there
doesn't our preoccupations are not the whole picture
there is available right here something which is not preoccupied
something that's not involved in conceit
and one of the clues one of the one of the aspects of this
is the simplicity of awareness itself the more simple we can be aware of
what's actually happening we sense that in in what's happening
in that awareness there's no preoccupation that's where the timeless
immediate dhamma is found in seeing that contrast oh yes
i am caught up and yes there's part of me that knows that that's not cut up
to see what is not caught up and sometimes our caught upness goes
away and we just see and clearly know that we're just not caught
and i like i liken it to if we're holding something in our hand
we might be so concerned with the object that we don't notice that we're grasping
it noticing we're grasping it we might notice i don't have to grasp it i can
hold it with an open hand in a relaxed way just hold it up the hand upright and hold it there
and then i'm so aware of the relaxed hand i'm holding it and there's a relaxed
hand at the same time so to see those two things we see it
and to experience this for ourselves to know this for ourselves the dhamma that's
immediate that's here to be known by the wise
so take heart in your meditation
that if you should get caught up in preoccupations those preoccupations are the stepping
stone to freedom by seeing clearly all i'm preoccupied
and then appreciating that oh maybe here
in addition to being preoccupied there is a place of not being
preoccupied in the knowing in the peace that's there
so i hope that makes sense and with that we'll begin
and again for this day i will just sit quietly and you're left
to yourself
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
we come to the beginning as we come to the end of the sitting
when there is no time for the dharma
because a dharma is always here always with us
always onward leading in that it shows us
where attention needs to be so that we can be free
if attention is caught and involved in our thoughts we're not free
if we're thinking but also know we're thinking
we can also know
the timeless freedom of now
and in a sense you need to give time
to experience the freedom of here and now
you have to give time to experience the timeless freedom of here
that means there has to be some stopping of the incessant
leaning forward preoccupation rumination
just enough so you can see clearly what's happening
and in that clearing see the way forward
to be free and may it be from what we're learning
through this practice that we create a clearing for others
that we create the time the presence the sacred pause
the sacred openness to the moment in which we can receive others know
others that they can have the experience of being known
in freedom maybe they won't recognize it
exactly what's happening but something in their hearts will know
that they're being received and known by a person
who has space openness awareness
of them without our neediness and greed and aversion and
judgments resentments without our
fantasies and imaginations and delusions
what a great gift to give others may it be that through this practice
we give people the gift of freedom and attention and respect
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
and may our practice contribute to that
so [Music]
thank you [Music]
the last of the characters of the dhamma is that it's to be personally known by
the wise or personally experienced by the wise depending how the word
is understood but
personally means directly immediately here
and i think it's very hopefully encouraging and inspiring
that this dharma that we're doing is is pointed to something very deeply
personal that the answer is found in us
the book to read is in our own hearts is here that the teachings that are to be really
followed are the ones that you find here personally not necessarily by someone like me
talking about it these uh these the five characteristics
of the dhamma that it that it's visible here it's now
it's uh inviting us to see it's onward leading and to be known by the wise this is uh
in the ancient text this is the the exclamation the inspired
utterance of people who have really tasted the full potential of the
practice for the first time or have really experienced the full potential really never tasted or
this sense of how mindfulness how awareness can lead to kind of freedom in the midst
of our life we can experience that personal freedom here and now
and and there's no more there's confidence there's no more doubt
that this is what it is so uh so this whole expression you know
the characteristics of the dhamma are are in fact something to be experienced by their wise to known by
oneself to to discover for oneself not to be taken as articles of faith or creed
but they're pointing to an experience something that's personal no and no known
but in order to do that we have to be available for this experience of the present
moment we have to be available to experience to know something personally
and this ability to be available to be receptive to be
open to to have the clarity for experiencing what's happening here now
is not easy to come by um it's something that uh
uh you know for whatever reason this minds of ours mind of ours
like so easily races ahead so easily uh is
caught in his cycles of rumination is somewhat leaning forward into the next moment into the next moment
as soon as one thing is finished we're already on to the next thing because of the momentum of that mind
and uh and so the idea is to stop and be present
many years ago i had this analogy for this or kind of for myself that when i was young
growing up in europe there was much more handshaking than there is now
i think but i remember that sometimes then when there was
someone like a politician or someone who was somehow an
important person and was going around and shaking everyone's hands
there were a few times i experienced someone who would as soon as their hand was in my hand to
be shook i already i felt the hand immediately went limp because you could see their
their body their face everything was already um
looking for the next person to shake hands with and it was very unsatisfying because
there wasn't this little bit of firmness a little bit like that here i am or connecting and present for you
and so the mind is like that sometimes that uh we're on ready for the next
thing ready for the next thing and the kind of way we both grasp at something tightly
and we don't grasp we're grasping but we don't really know
in the buddha's language in buddhist teachings what we grasp at is the concepts the ideas the fantasies
the dreams the delusions the imaginations of things we don't really grab anything in solid
and so the very grabbing of things as it is keeps us going
and we're not available not present not here for the experience
so to make oneself vessel for
experiencing something deeply personal to experience our life ourselves in some
deeper way that allows us to tap into
what is really present here visible here
that concepts ideas and stories are not exactly something worth seeing or not really
seeing reality really they obscure it but if you see
how we get caught in thoughts see how we get caught in attachments and clingings and aversions
that's the way we begin seeing the dharma oh look at that
then with that seeing it's possible to see and find the alternative
but if we're so involved in greed hate and delusion that we can't even see it then there's no way
but to stop and be available to even see that which is not flattering in ourselves oh look at that
and rather than being discouraged by what is not flattering about ourselves in our minds and our hearts and our
dispositions in the dharma that's a source of encouragement of inspiration
not being inspired by what's not flattering but be inspired oh now that i know it
this is a stepping stone to freedom i needed to know this of course i needed to know this and see
this now where's the freedom and part of the freedom is found
in that seeing that recognition as part of that freedom is found in not
succumbing or collapsing or being upset by what is not flattering the faults we
have or difficulties we have inside see it oh that's what it is
and then we start seeing getting a taste of the simultaneous freedom
the simultaneous way in which we're looking come and look come and see
the way that it's we see then a way forward we're guided into that clarity guided
into that more freedom that more letting go and then the more we experience that
non-clinging where we experience that attention that's free and
not clinging not grasping then the more we can just really be
present in a full way for experience we can have that handshake with reality we're really there with it
and the mind is not already going off to something else
and and so to
be available and then to find a comment about this uh for
the buddha when he was talking about this uh what it means this um visible it's
here it's come and look at it it's onward leading
and experienced by the wise uh he wants and wanted an explanation of
all that he just kind of little bit changes seemingly change the subject and he talks about
not being involved in the conceits of feeling that you're better than
others worse than others or equal to others we're not involved in the game and the
ranking and the status of self and so
this freedom from comparing ourselves to others
that's part of this freedom that he's talking about it's available here and now
and what a gift to give to others the gift of not comparing
not making ourselves worse or better than others or even the complications of making ourselves equal
we don't play that comparison game and that the gift to others is that they're allowed to be who they are
and we can be present for them in a full way we can shake their hands or the equivalent and really be there and
present and give them them some kind of gift of freedom
so um to be personally experienced by the wise
may that be may you be a wise person may you be available to experience this
life in a deep way and may that availability translate to a greater respect reverence care
love for others as well and uh if you would like to have homework for
these time that them away or at least for the weekend um
make yourself available for reality don't go ahead long into into it make
yourself available kind of to let it come to you let reality find you
rather than you rushing into it so thank you
very much and uh i look forward to being back and i guess i think it's probably the third
of october and um or so first monday in october and
i i hope you enjoy compassion loving kindness and matthew brent silver