so good morning good day
and um i would like to start with a story
there was a zen teacher who came from japan in the 1960s here in the san francisco bay area
and uh his name was copencino and
he was once he was also a apparently a master of
zen archery or the way of archery japanese archery and uh he was invited to eslan
eslan was a retreat center that is very famous kind of
for its uh incubating much of the human potential movement of the 1960s and so
forth and it exists it lives the estlan retreat centers right on the cliffs
in big sur south of here overlooking the um pacific ocean it's a magnificent place
uh the nice lawn front in the front kind of goes right up to the cliff and you see you know
vast pacific ocean in front of you so kobencino was invited there to do a
archery demonstration and many people came out in the lawn to watch him and he was all set up and
and he apparently he was wearing kind of this formal japanese archery
robe or clothes kind of very formal ritualistic looking clothes
and he came up and to where he was going to stand and um
and he took a long time to prepare himself and apparently people watching just mesmerized by his care his attention to
detail his his focus his um uh
and uh in how he prepared and how he got himself in position and it took a long time to take his position and
get himself centered and balanced with his his stance his legs just right and
and um and then picking up his bow and communing with a bow getting ready with the bow then pulling out an arrow
and uh placing the arrow just right and it was a long process of very much very
very concentrated and uh focused and apparently the way he did it uh people were kind of just
mesmerized kind of came along with him and it was so uh like teeth ceremony some
beautiful ritual and finally he was then spent a lot of
time getting himself just making the aim to really you know
and finally he he released the arrow
and the arrow flew straight right into the mark
and it landed smack in the middle of the pacific ocean that's where he had aimed it for
and so this wonderful story that it's not about what he was trying to hit it wasn't about trying to hit something exactly
it was uh all about his presence his attention to the present moment to his body to his details he was fully engaged
in this process and then when he was aiming i mean i mean it was hard to miss the pacific
ocean if you do you know standing on the cliff looking in the general direction but
um he took his task very seriously he was very focused the point was not to
shoot the arrow and to hit the target the point was to
um um
the point was to really be able to
see to get concentrated in the process the sense of purpose
engagement of what we're doing he's doing so this is what i'd like to suggest for today
is that it's the preparation and the sense of concentration purpose of what we're
doing that's important don't worry so much about the results of your practice but really
kind of center yourself here have a strong sense of purpose like here is where you're going to get
into the present moment prepare yourself for it to get everything lined up
kind of aim for the present moment and really be here
and maybe you'll never shoot the arrow that's not the point is
what you're what you're preparing yourself to do it's the way that it puts you into the
activity of being present so
um so
um so we take a comfortable upright meditation posture
and take time with your posture
it could be that you make some big uh swaying back and forth
it's possible that you just do very small little movements
and the point is not to find the right posture the point here is to really be present
in the finding it really feel and sense your body
and feel the the weight of your sitting bones if you're sitting and feel if your
the weight above your torso is balanced comes down balanced way on the sitting bones
not too much on one or the other not projected forward or backwards just
everything lined up
and then with the same kind of care that every little details
is precious is tender is done gently carefully
close your eyes and then
to prepare yourself take a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in deeply
and exhaling and grounding yourself here this place this the body
on your seat place where you're meditating
as if you're establishing a balance stability
in the place with the place you're sitting on
that which is holding you up
okay continuing with some somewhat deeper breaths
long exhale relaxing
now letting your breathing return to normal and still the preparation of
arriving here being ready as you exhale relax your body
relax the face around the eyes
relax the shoulders softening
but not so much to just be completely relaxed but softening relaxing
to really be here in an intentional way to
embodied way as if you're preparing your whole body
for a very important task
softening in the chest
relaxing in the belly
and for everything to work together in harmony it's best to
let go of any unnecessary tension it could be in the hands and the fingers
of the arms
in the thighs calves and the feet
and then without changing anything in your posture to embody your posture more fully
think more of the preparation for engaging in the purpose of
meditation that you invite your whole body along
to participate in this attention presence
the setting up of your attention
and then to
prepare to to make the aim like the archer who aimed made it took a
lot of time to prepare and aim and establish that the aim
where the arrow was going to go so set your aim and the body breathing
this is the purpose here to really
connect be present for
the inhale the exhale
in whatever place in the body where
is the right place for you to put your attention
regarding breathing
maybe where you most enjoy your breathing
maybe where it's clearest
and the point here is now it's not to be successful not to accomplish anything
but rather to setting yourself up with the aim
really aiming gently lovingly
the sensations of the body breathing
entering into the sense of purpose and dedication
to be with your breathing
entering into the practice of mindfulness of breathing
with a sense of purpose dedication
we're part of what you're doing when you're meditating
is embodying inhabiting evoking
a sense of purpose this is what you're doing now is just
with quietly breathing
with every exhale letting the thinking mind become quieter
so you can really hold the aim on the full extent of the in exhale
relaxing present with purpose
if you lose contact with your breathing
it's okay
bring yourself back into the dedication of finding the breath getting centered
on the breath aiming at the breath
it's not so important that you drift it off it's important that you come back and
start again always whenever you can having a purpose
a very valuable purpose of really honing in on breathing
quieting the thinking mind relaxing tension
all in the service
of a dedicated attention to breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting i invite you to experiment
with reorienting yourself with this to us to a sense of purpose
dedication [Music] engagement with the dedication of merit
with uh turning our practice around and
wishing well for this world of ours
and how would you embody this change of direction in the practice now and
give yourself over to a new purpose the purpose of
wishing for the welfare of others a kind supportive caring concern for the
welfare of the world
and with this new purpose to enter this purpose for these couple
of minutes may it be
that any known and unknown ways that we benefited from this practice
may we let those benefits spread from us into the world
so that the benefits of this meditation benefit
others as well may it be that our practices for the
welfare and happiness of everyone may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
and may this be a purpose i carry with me on this day
did i look for ways to contribute to the welfare and happiness of the world
so
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and
come to the third talk in this five part series i've called it
finding our way and finding our way with these different
um pairs of states that we can experience that
sometimes exist in relationship to each other and sometimes can exist independent of each other
sometimes can be a healthy and sometimes can be unhealthy
and today the pairing is that of joy and despair
and uh for me the when i think of this the joy that i've
kind of been awoken in me through this buddhist practice i think of it as a big yes
yes and um even not knowing what i'm saying yes too
i mean i'm not saying yes to anything it's just the idea of yes that something brightens inside of me opens and
delights me the joy and that uh in that regard then despair
is just no oh no kind of a
giving up a kind of a deflation a kind of drop in loss of energy
sinking um a feeling of maybe hopelessness or great disappointment or great sense of
of um fear of what might come and
and so this yes movement and this no movement um that can
exist together a little bit like yesterday the gladness and the sadness that joy can come from
hope and when hope is dashed it can bring a lot
of despair or there is no hope it can bring a lot of despair but
but one of the uh my strong association with these two has to do with purpose
that um when we have a clear sense of healthy purpose that there can be um a kind of a yes to
that the kind of our system our being it gets involved in doing it
and when there's no sense of purpose or the purpose seems hopeless or or is not working out or we can't engage
in it then there can be despair about not fulfilling this purpose that's
important for us and the question is what is it what is the purpose we have is it a valuable
healthy purpose there can be joy in the engagement and doing of things
which are unhealthy you know you can really fully be immersed
in eating only desserts for lunch and for dinner just completely
engaged and the concentration the absorption that
everything else in the world falls away because it's just dessert can be
joyful can be have a feeling of the engagement is so nice but it might not be healthy for you
on the um and there might be things that you know are healthy to do
but the way that we engage in it is not healthy we might do it with resentment with reluctance hesitation
and and there's uh and we don't really give ourselves over to doing it and so maybe we can't be successful and
they're doing something half-hearted but it's an important thing to do and so we feel despair of something
that's healthy that we do so the sense of purpose what do we have a purpose for what's the intention is a
very important part of human life and it's a valuable thing to do in a spiritual life is to spend time
reflecting on the purpose the intention the reasons the
the goals in which we have set ourselves up what we're doing
and um and this can set up then joy or despair even
wonderful lovely important valuable spiritual dedications or purposes meditation purposes
can bring a lot of despair if we are unsuccessful in doing it we don't reach what we're trying to do
what i'd like to propose is that it's important to spend time reflecting on what our purposes are
and whether it's the purpose is just to cook a meal or clean the dishes or the purpose is to
develop or mature spiritually in our buddhist practice
these men these motivations purposes are important to become clear about so then we can inhabit the purpose
we can really say yes to it and engage and hopefully it's a healthy purpose
and um and some and then have a sense of uh of uh
of um appropriateness of how we attain these uh purposes
i mean if you if you sit down to my purpose purposely get enlightened but first you don't even know how to do
breath meditation maybe first you need to learn the basics of breath meditation and learn about the
hindrances and so the purpose there's all these uh
earlier purposes we have to inhabit and follow through on before we can attain the full ones so
the sense of purpose i'm talking about here is not an abstract purpose which might be you know some distant one which
might be important for us but rather each step of what we do
how we engage in the moment in the direction of that purpose
so if the purpose is to be able to you know develop strong concentration
then engage fully for a while understanding your hindrances without really becoming wise about the
hindrances you probably won't get reliably healthfully um concentrated
and so engage in that process study the hindrances and that's the purpose that's what we engage ourselves in
so when we uh despair can come and we don't have a purpose we don't have an
engagement and so this idea of of of a joy
and uh and despair which are healthy are founded are based on
a healthy sense of purpose and then learning how to
inhabit that purpose in the moment doing in the moment what's appropriate
for that purpose um not sitting there kind of just daydreaming about a big purpose far in
the future but if this purpose is important enough what do i enter into and have it do now
and so for example if now this idea of concentration and well i need to learn about the
hindrances so maybe the next step is to read about them
and so then you would sit down in a way and really purposefully engage you wouldn't read the maybe a
book or an article about the hindrances like you would read a novel and just kind of as entertainment and just kind
of be carried along to relax you would do it purposefully engage in
it but not in a way that's stressful of course and this is where the art of all
this is but it's a way that brings you joy and there's a yes
there's the art of doing of engaging that brings joy
and not a lot of people have learned this they've learned it in certain areas certain things which are fun to do
they can really enjoy doing that but there is an art to learning how to
do anything that you need to do in a joyful way in a way that's a big yes you it's the in doing it it's so
much good if you have to clean the toilet today the more senior monks in the buddhist
monasteries uh in japan it's they're assigned to the task of toilet cleaning
and maybe because they have the spiritual maturity to really do it so you have to clean the toilet so maybe
you don't like it it's a little bit gross and so you do it like half-heartedly but to do it fully just really in if this is
what you're doing this your life energy for this moment just clean the toilet do it as if it's the everything it's the
whole just give yourself to yes to doing that what i'm
teaching here today is a lot of what i learned through zen training where if you sweep the courtyard you
really that's what you do you give yourself over to it toilets whatever you're doing you give
yourself to it and the surprise of it is that
it's possible to learn to really feel a sense of joy and delight
and and happiness and just giving ourselves over to it even if you're sick and don't have much
energy then you have to keep what is giving yourself over really do something with purpose what does it look like given the
conditions of your life if you're sick or in pain whatever the circumstances are the sense
of doing is in harmony with the circumstance with yourself and the world around you
but this is what you're doing you say yes to this
it can be overdone it can be done with stress so you're exhausted at the end
and they can we can learn the art of doing that there's it's we're fully there
but we're relaxed and doing so this art of appreciating the value of
what we're actually doing while we're doing it can be a source of tremendous joy
and that kind of joy can grow and part of the despair that people can experience is when they
have no sense of purpose when the purpose they had for their life kind of gets shattered
and the um or they're unsuccessful on their purpose
purpose is very important and so the relationship between purpose and fulfilling a purpose engaging in a
purpose and your joy and despair is something to reflect on and look at
and consider and certainly knowing you're doing something that's wonderfully and
meaningful for you and purposeful can be a source of joy but it's only abstract in the head the
evaluation of it oh i'm doing something wonderful then you're missing where the juice is
where the real heart is of this practice of mindfulness and the way it can really grow in us grow for our life
and that is the uh give yourself to
the purpose of the moment give yourself to the whatever
bigger purpose you have if you're pursuing it or engaged in it
in the what is the steps in the moment so it i mean just to be maybe make the
point in this silly little example say that the purpose is to
your big purpose to get developed concentration in meditation you've heard now that reading about the
hindrances and learning about them and understanding them well is a very important stepping stone for concentration
so now you but now you don't have a book on the entrances you don't have anything
so you go to the library to get one the the town library said hey heaven
and so now walking to walking to the library driving to the library biking to the
library that's the task of the moment you forget about going to the library
you can you you set the course to go there and now you give yourself over to the
going to the library when you get to the library and this is how it works in the monastery
when you open the library door you give yourself over to opening that door
you give yourself walking down the aisles finding the book and so it's the doing
where something really important comes up the purp doing things in a purposeful
way intentional way so that you find joy in it
i'm not suggesting this is easy but it's possible
to live a life of yes and if the purpose is valuable and you
find this kind of value and in inhabiting engaging in what you're doing
then it doesn't matter if you're successful so much you might fail at things but you're so
happy about the way you did it it was rewarding the way you did it was rewarding
and if you're successful or not successful your joy happiness and well-being is less dependent eventually
on the success or failure but in how you do it did it how you were
involved with what you did so um
so for today you know i may be giving you lots to think about and to engage in for the day
but to maybe make key points uh reflect on purpose
what role does purpose have in your life and have you dismissed the value of purpose can you find a sense of purpose
purpose doesn't have to be big purpose it could be the small purpose of the next five minutes the next hour what's
the purpose you have and then the yes of engaging in purpose
in the in the step-by-step ways the small steps it takes whatever
purpose it is not to be ahead of yourself from the activity of the moment the
individual steps to get there and to find how a yes an engagement in
the steps to whatever you're doing the purpose that that is purposeful as well
finding purpose in how you do things is
one of the great joys and secrets of a well-developed
and it'll support your practice your mindfulness practice is a way of of
of manifesting your mindfulness into our life
so i hope you enjoy it i hope you find a delightful day with yes to
whatever you're doing and and exploring your sense of purpose thank you