so for tonight's practice i thought we would
practice some simple simple meta for ourselves and for others just bare
bones simple lovely soothing calming
loving loving kindness kindness warmth
it's been a cool day chilly windy day here in california dry and some warmth
some warmth in our hearts wherever you are however the weather is
internally and out and outside externally can be helpful we can never have too
much meta kindness warmth for ourselves and care for others so
that's all i want to say really to frame it there's not much framing i think i want to do
but to just dedicate the time to practicing together so let's just meditate together dear sangha
so so getting into your meditation posture whatever is comfortable for you
to sit in or your stand the next half hour or so
ah and landing landing in this body landing in this
moment in time
here here
inviting inviting your muscles to relax to rest
as if they're falling falling
falling dropping [Music] nowhere to go nothing to do
they can relax your heart can relax in this moment
there have been thoughts entanglements worries it's okay
they can all be there
we'll return to them later but now taking refuge
taking refuge in this moment
taking refuge
if it's supportive for you maybe you have this feeling this image of
as if you were a baby you were pre-verbal you're a baby you're being
held in the caring arms
of a loving mother just being held feeling that you're held
feeling safe the cells of your body know what it's
like you don't have to think about it please don't think about it don't start
thinking about your childhood this and that no drop all that
trusting that your body knows
your body your heart knows what it's like to be held and feel safe
as if you're held like a baby feeling safe
it's a feeling that's available to you to conjure it up we can't conjure it up
of course of course you can
being held right now the air is holding you
your clothes are holding you embracing you here here there there
just be just be and breathe
or let yourself be breathed just let it unfold
no [Music] struggling no doing no trying
it can be easy ah
drop drop drop let go [Music] of trying too hard in this moment
let go
let your mind rest rest be at peace be at ease
resting with the breath the lullaby of the breath
the mind when it's happy it stays it doesn't run around let your mind feel
cocooned let your mind feel cocooned
resting with the breath
the sweet breath in breath and out breath
and if your mind wanders to thoughts entanglements it's
okay it's all right tell us it's okay sweetheart it's all
right darling
ever so gently inviting you to rest with your heart
with the breath to take refuge knowing that there is more sweetness
more rest more nourishment here
than any thought no matter how pleasant it might be it's still entanglement
trusting trusting it's more nourishment
there's more sweetness here inviting inviting awareness to rest
here darling here right here
maybe imagining that the breath is entering through the heart center
the center of your chest calming soothing
like a healing self for the body for the heart the mind of
each breath awareness intertwined
awareness cuddling in the heart center with the breath
with kindness with care for this entire
being that is you this whole body mind and heart
very simple relaxed
easy peaceful
my
see what is needed in this moment
if you've had a long day maybe a hard day
maybe [Music] the warm warm healing embrace of metta
in this quiet
if you're feeling weary maybe menta feels
like a strength
both soothing and giving you strength
confidence support see what is needed
in each breath imbued with care
or maybe simply quiet is needed for whatever needs to unfold to unfold
and again if you find thoughts arising it's okay
be gentle with yourself be gentle with your heart with your mind
and releasing letting go releasing the body releasing the thoughts
let there be resting sense of cocooning with the breath
with kindness
taking a break taking a rest
trusting that rest in care and love
and meta brings solace brings comfort and
strength
in ways that are needed not needing to solve a problem right now
trusting that a different kinder mind will arise
later and it's on just stay
stay here
the heart with the breath and the body
and now as if you would open [Music]
the door and just let maybe
one or two beings in or dear to you it could be a child could be a pet
could be a good friend a benefactor
in this easy place of rest as your cocooning
let them rest invite them to rest
in your mind's eye
as you hold yourself with ease with kindness
let them be included also may all of us have ease
may all of us have well-being ease ease fullness
and how our lives unfold happiness
goodness
let it be easeful it's not that you're pumping out goodwill or meta
it's the breath you take it's the air you breathe
the air that holds you
and others your minds are it's the cushion you rest
on and them too
sense of care just palpable ease
easy easy kindness
trusting that you're planting seeds of kindness
goodwill meant for yourself and others
it doesn't have to feel like hard work
can be gentle easy flowing
soothing
meta can glow [Music] can grow and glow
with contentment and peace contentment and peace
in the heart planting seeds one by one
and that's we bring this practice period to a close
let there be kindness ease for whatever rose or did not arise
if there was agitation sleepiness distraction it's okay
and if there was one moment of awareness and mental kindness
which could be this moment this kindness it's okay i showed up
i showed up i planted seeds that's enough
celebrate really relish celebrate that we've come together
you've showed up to practice cultivate your heart and mind
and this brief flash of a life what a beautiful way to spend
what a beautiful way to spend to intend to spend your time
and offering the goodness offering
trusting there is goodness and offering it generously
to all beings everywhere offering or practice my practice
our practice collectively as a gift
to all beings here
i offer my goodness to you dear world may all of us beings may we
be free may we be happy may we be
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have some time if any questions
reflections if something came up if you are moved to share i'd like to
invite you if you like to share the benefit of everyone
maybe an aha moment maybe something new showed up for you or maybe it was challenging it's all
okay it's all welcome any questions comments
in this way of meta for ourselves as a way of
cocooning feeling held in care and safety just easy with the
breath and then extending it to a couple of other beings
who are dear to us any observations oh let me change the
chat i haven't changed it yet you're welcome to send me
directly in which case it will be private or send it to everyone in which case i'll read your name
and [Music] and also you can raise your hand as always
i'll share with you as i'm waiting if there are any observations you want to share
i'll say that i found this evening's practice quite [Music]
quieting and a lot of samadhi a lot of stillness with the
sense of soothing i see meema's hand mima
hi nikki thank you hi um i was moved right away when you first
started um because um the when you said to
um nurture myself to hold myself to the air was holding me i was really moved by
that i think i really needed it it's been a really hard day and
i had never experienced that before it just felt really good to to
how did they say to do me you know instead of doing everyone else i i got to do me i had a headache all
day and it went away and so must have been tension and i it just it's gone so i'm really relaxed so
thank you yay you are so welcome even that makes me so
happy your headache is gone come to dr nikki anytime i'll prescribe meta
for yourself that's sweet that's very sweet thanks so much for sharing that oh
it makes my heart happy sweet
yeah kenneth says resting the mind on the breath worked well for me great lovely
beautiful any other reflections you like to share
aha moments challenges how good it felt to
hold yourself be held with mitai here this being who's me
so needed
and if you're quiet it's okay too this was kind of a quieting
meditation like i noticed so we can just be quiet together that's
okay too hold each other in kindness rather sweet
[Music] put each other on gallery view
dave says i feel like a sleepy kid being carried from car to house to bed oh
that's such a sweet image dave i love that a sleepy child being carried from car to
house to bed oh that's so sweet it's so sweet
love it love it that's lovely very sweet
yeah oh nice and i see someone giving a thumbs up i
wasn't sure if that was thumbs up or they're trying to raise your hand if you want to raise your hand use the
reaction it's actually the raise hand button just in case path on youtube says thank you for the
quiet simplicity especially at the end of the day ah
nice you're so welcome pepper says i came to the meditation
feeling so depleted and have felt that way all day
after kind of overdoing it over the weekend this was needed medicine thanks nikki ah
thank you debra and you're so welcome hmm medtis medicine medtis medicine isn't it
that is medicine this kindness soothing easing not pushing it out
don't even need phrases just being hell the phrases work for you great use them
bring them in and if not it's okay
one more reflection this is uh privately to me i connected the practice to moments in
my life that scare me and was able to feel how safety
in those situations can be possible i felt it in my body
perhaps this will be a new way to experience scary situations
with this connections wired oh wow lovely yay
yay my heart is filled with joy beautiful to make that connection
that is so profound that is so profound to feel to be able
to feel how safety in those scary situations can be possible this is so
profound thank you so much for sharing that insight so perfect
profound yeah and and it is possible even in especially in
scary moments because the buddha taught meta supposedly originally to monks because
they were scared they had fear so this is supposed to be medicine for
scary times fearful times so that we feel safe beautiful
marianne says i felt like i was very well and so it became a time to turn to
wishing love to all of you ah that's sweet thanks mariah it's so lovely i love that
insight also that you're sharing experientially that when you felt very well
it your your failure yes my cup is full yes i can now fill other people's cup i
can turn and wish them well so beautiful to experience that right
yeah beautiful so lovely megan says i love thinking about medtis
medicine yes megan absolutely especially you being a healer in the care um
in in in the healthcare prof in the health as a
healthcare professional indeed mentalis as medicine and mary says i really
appreciate it the reminder not to go to the story of my own childhood but stay here here
lovely all these beautiful insights you all this is so touching
my heart is full with your practice thank you for offering your practice
your goodness your beauty your insights
so offering our goodness our practice to each other
let us hold each other with the sense of ease calm safety for ourselves
for each other in small groups as i set them up
please take care of yourself and speak whatever you want to share and
nugget from your experience something from your own experience only
and then let another person second person share a nugget from their experience and then
the third person will share a nugget they'll come back to you and you'll go around and round a few times
and and be kind holding each other holding
yourselves so i see something came in from christine i'm going to set up the
breakout rooms while let's see here we go
yeah wow i love that christine says question posted to my local sangha yesterday that i've been pondering in my
heart what kind of love can i give myself today that would set me free
a little bit more i love that what a nice question let's let's take that question to our small practice rooms
yeah i love that you can either maybe answer that in this moment
or or sit together and and share anything you'd like to share from the practice that came up for
you or maybe just hold silence or you can say pass
if your turn comes and you want to be quiet that's perfectly fine
so i'm going to open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other and here we go
and their rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
and we had such lovely reflections at the beginning that there isn't much time for anything
uh more but if there's a quick thing you want to write and chat maybe a gift that came from the groups
you're welcome and i'll read it out loud i'll pause for a moment
after something very quick that came up in the group that just feels appropriate must be shared
taking one going once going twice
okay seems like it feels complete so so with that
thank you all for your practice for coming together supporting each other
supporting yourselves may we all be happy and free
may all beings everywhere be happy and free [Music]
thanks everyone thanks dear sangha be well