and so good morning um it's morning good morning to you all
sweet to see the names I know a lot of these names you all are um
YouTube chat famous at this point
um yeah very sweet
um okay Let's uh
do that whole meditation thing
so uh
just sense in what you think you're supposed to do when you start meditating
in many ways you force yourself into a kind of slot of
one kind or another
and let's just see how natural we can be
in these uh first couple minutes
foreign subtly
we can be trying to prove something
to ourselves
to the teacher to the Buddha to someone
but you don't have to prove anything
in your practice
and so we relax truly relax
and then if tension remains we let her remain
but we relax the the energy that turns
us into a project
the energy that turns us into the project manager
and we sit together
maybe it's skillful to
highlight some phenomena with the attentional
Spotlight breath body sound
Darkness behind your closed eyes
but we attend not in a kind of brittle way not attempting to prove anything to
ourselves we attend
knowing that the ingredients of waking up
are more present than we might imagine
um to try and prove something to ourselves to another
entails that we fixate ourself we
subtly Imaging sense of Who We Are
of a kind of trajectory of where it's all going
what will be when we get there or what we
will be if we don't
we kind of sandwich ourselves in time
the dizziness of time
but we don't have to prove anything
Stone seduced by The Mirage
of the future
true the future is coming but it never comes exactly in the form
we imagine we never arrive in that moment
when it does come we realized that uh
wanting is always different than getting
and so we say enough this is good enough safe enough
we surrender into the bottomlessness
of the present
phenomena many are egoically titillating
but we don't need to spin out into the outer
orbits of the egoic machinations [Music]
if we can just absorb the body blow a phenomena
just this Pleasant unpleasant
it can just stay
resting back and uh the openness of awareness
foreign
okay as um yeah it's good to see with you
I think I'm really accustomed to uh YouTube
situation here um
yeah so thanks for thanks for having me
so um yesterday um introduced this theme about uh
different Dharma pleasures and uh spoke specifically about um
the pleasure of having a path the pleasure of having a path
and today it's the pleasure of
of sourcing our motivation from Love
so when I was um it was just out of college and I worked
in this uh I was not qualified for this incidentally but um when they pay nine
dollars an hour you kind of you get me so I was working in a
residential treatment center um and for uh
severely you know severe psychiatric you
know adolescent boys with serious psychiatric stuff you know that was
acute enough that they couldn't be in um in homes and um and so is residential
treatment and it was six kids in the house and in a
um just an ordinary house in the middle of LA and um and it was um such intense and beautiful
work and um and as a counselor my job was to
uh yeah to run groups of one kind or another do fun things together play cook
for them take care of them and and Implement a behavioral
modification program yeah whereas like good point you know points points for good behavior and the
loss of privileges from bad behavior and
um and you could see how
um you could run the behavioral modification program on fear
or love and at least initially and I remember
you know working with a whole like cast of characters all of us you know
counselors uh um fear at least initially could be more
effective yeah um that uh it was easier to change the
behavior of the children if um there is some measure of fear of the
counselor but uh in the end yeah uh I think love
wins out if if our Behavior if their behavior
is going to change in a sustainable way
it's going to be a function of of love
conditioned by love shaped by love and um
my question for you is uh
what what kind of Behavioral modification program are you running on yourself
yeah kind of program are you running on yourself where where do you Source your
motivation from um we have to Source our motivation from
somewhere we want to change and grow
right that that line from uh Suzuki roshi you're perfect just as you are and
there's room for improvement right yeah we uh
there's much we want to do we want to
yeah to love more fully to be less neurotic to take good care of our body
to to minimize the harm we do to others
to ourselves we there's a lot yeah
and um how do we actually motivate ourselves to grow and evolve to make
progress and the Dharma pleasure yeah that I'm
speaking about is is coming to Source our motivation from love and care
rather than self harshness or fear
or the kind of egoic machinations of proving
self um self-hatred has maybe many functions
some of which are actually soothing um
but one of the functions is is is a kind of Behavioral modification program we
run on ourselves and it's all stick no carrot
and it's this kind of commitment to okay I'll punish myself to motivate myself to
achieve something that I think is Worthy and
in that framework we often get very preoccupied with the gold stars and with the kind of imagine how we'll feel when
we actually get the gold star but getting the gold star never feels
like wanting it and never ever really uh I don't know it's almost the sense of
like well I'll be a grown-up once I do that once I grow in this way but no one ever feels like a grown-up as
far as I can tell and um and we repeat the habits of
self-harsness in our practice um uh
we can be harsh or even even sometimes really kind of cruel as we come up against our
limitations yeah when we no we need to let go but we cannot
when we're trying to be tranquil but we're agitated yeah when we're
trying to be equanimous we're trying to be okay with something but we're really not
we come up against certain certain moments of limitation
and um and we
are trying to kind of shape ourselves through mechanisms of fear and harshness
and that system of motivation can fall away almost completely
um one one meditator could touch me she said um uh I realized my inner critic loves
me yeah they're just confused something like this yeah
um when when are limitations and our Neurosis are no longer a kind of
commentary on Who We Are when we're at least a little bit free of
the these egoic pressures of proving proving
oneself proving the object of self to someone even if that audience is just us
when that starts to Fall Away
our Neurosis becomes a source of curiosity and humor rather
than shame yeah yeah we know we still have to grow we
have habits that get us into trouble but our Neurosis becomes a source of
curiosity and humor rather than shame
I'm one of the I don't know features of practice one of the things I've noticed is like it really has become such a
delight to laugh at myself you know like to laugh deeply and to laugh deeply I'm
not talking about like that little habit that's like really kind of innocent and
no I'm talking about like laughing deeply in the face of a real problems real Neurosis yeah
and in that laughter that kind of laughter it's it's like I can almost
feel what might become self-judgment or some shame inflected
state or something just releases
yeah we do we do want to grow and mature but
the the uh the desperate urgency of ego is gone
yeah that is not where we're sourcing our motivation from
and um the the poignancy of our of our
condition you know of The Human Condition is so is is etched deeply into our being
and so that's there for us to and um and we begin to Source our
motivation from Love from tenderness and care and sympathy sympathy with
ourselves with the plight of suffering
and uh and there's this sense of like oh yeah
there's nothing there's nothing left to prove to
ourselves to others we're not we're not growing and changing
in order to prove something
yeah and then
all of our our projects you know are whatever that is our exercise schedule
or meditation commitment or you fill in the blank whatever
comes from care yeah comes from care and comes from this very uh
sober appreciation about the strains weaknesses yeah and um
just feels so much less entangled and uh
and when we feel less entangled when we feel like
um nothing we discover about who we are is
going to break our heart uh then there's just a lot of uh you know
of curiosity a kind of urgency of discovery
and lightness yeah so um
sourcing sourcing our
our motivation from uh from love rather than fear
this is a this is a Dharma pleasure for sure
so offer that for your consideration um
I mentioned uh that uh just a kind of an optional
uh
Zoom session this evening 7 P.M to 7 30 on uh
uh on Zoom so the link is is on that that website there so just you can just
go to matthewbrandsilver.org it's on the first page you'll see it and um
uh it'll be a kind of opportunity to uh
um just to uh to sit together for a few minutes and have some questions yeah
and um uh yeah so that's that's it uh in 20 no
no 12 11 hours or so um yeah so you're you're warmly invited and
um I will uh if I don't see you there uh I will see you
um see you tomorrow morning yeah
okay thanks uh thanks so much um look forward to uh to being together
more