so hello my friends and uh
it's good to be here and uh
you know one of the probably one of the primary foundations
of my life is the dharma and dharma practice and
it's certainly nice to be able to share it but it's also nice very nice for me
that i have this time to sit here in my meditation posture and to
kind of tap into the dharma express the dharma live the dharma in a way that
is meaningful and and connects me to what i for me is this
foundation and to be able to live close to this foundation
through one's day through one's years is one of the great
vehicles for a meaningful life a peaceful life a
a life that brings a lot of gladness a lot of happiness
so each of you who are here whether it's the first time or you've been here since
the beginning of the pandemic are also here to
in a sense tap into something within yourself that is valuable
something inside of yourself that can be a refuge or support a foundation
that maybe you have some sense that it can be bring you gladness happiness
sense of satisfaction and exactly what it is in relationship to
what we do here is probably a little bit individual for each of you
but especially for those of you been here for a while now i'm confident that you have something
that is valuable important that you tap into
and perhaps as we go through the today especially it's meditation that it is
not the words that come from me that are important but rather
what you recognize in yourself that's important so underneath your challenges underneath
your sadness underneath your maybe resentments and
hurts and pains and frustrations anxieties
there is a foundation that's deeper a foundation that is
enacted to be known that is not something we search for
but something that we live something that we enact that we practice we
engage in and for people who spend too much time looking
for a foundation looking for something valuable they miss the
the key thing that it's almost as if the answer is in the looking
if the looking if their mindfulness if the awareness is one of being available being open
and valuing this capacity we have to know and to enact the knowing
and act the the uh presence the attention the
the uh the hereness here
so maybe this here-ness of your own can be a foundation
so to have a meditation posture and one of the advantages of meditating
for ongoingly is that maybe the posture you
find starts becoming part of this enactment
of attention of awareness of presence
and so maybe giving some care to your at your posture so
it can be an enactment it can be part of this engagement
bringing forth your [Music]
your beings your bodies your heart's capacity for being present
and to lower your gaze and even if you have your eyes closed
already it might be possible to lower your gaze as if you lower your gaze a little bit
so the eyes can relax in their sockets
to recognize that the eyes do not have to work when we're meditating
and then gently closing the eyes
and then slowly and gently taking some fuller breath in breaths
maybe three quarters full in a slow gentle way
and then exhaling with a longer exhale than usual
when you come to the end of the exhale maybe there's a way of relaxing
that allows exhale to continue
and letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale scan through your body to see if there's places you can relax
the face the shoulders chest the belly maybe the hands and arms
but as you relax these parts of your body see if that in that relaxation in the
softening there might be a little bit more
sensation sensitivity awareness
aliveness in those parts of your body
and one analogy for meditation
is that the awareness that we enact the awareness that we abide in
is a bit like the ocean broad and
deep and all the emotions and feelings we
have are like the dance of the waves on top of the ocean
sadness and gladness happiness and unhappiness
fear or confidence
anger or love they all have their place dancing on top
of the surface but rest in the depth the fullness of
your ocean rest in the
depth in which things appear on the surface
allow them to be there dancing on the surface without identifying or reacting to them
or needing them to be different but don't
base yourself on the waves base yourself on the deeper embodied
sense of presence attention awareness mindfulness
fast like an ocean the ocean does not need to identify or
be concerned with the shape and the character of the
different waves on the surface they come and they go
if you're sitting here with some concerns especially concerns that have an
emotional aspect to them
for these minutes think of them as the waves on the top of the ocean
they're there because of the winds but that you are not the waves
hear the vast profound ocean
vast profound ocean of awareness of attention of presence
of embodiment aliveness
rest in that ocean and allow the waves to do what they do
without denying them and without
believing in them
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
in whatever way you're feeling whatever way your you are
maybe for these last couple of minutes you're allowed to be that way
but in that allowance in allowing and being available and
maybe at the same time as you allow yourself to be as you are
you can allow for a greater sensitivity greater
awareness of others the eyes closed they would just be
bringing them to mind but later today maybe it's meeting people in person or
and to feel or sense or know people
from the place of depths within place of where we enact
a sensitivity a attentiveness a receptivity
where we feel something different about others than our opinions and ideas and stories
the ability to be mindful of oneself
gives us also the ability to be mindful of others
with the humanity of others for the ways that others
suffer and are happy challenged and successful
may it be that our capacity to feel and know and enact
mindfulness allows us to have deeper richer
respect and care even reverence for others
may we live
offering our attentiveness our care
to others may the expression of this practice in
the world be wishing for the welfare and happiness
of others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may our life contribute to that possibility
[Music]
[Music] thank you
so good morning and continuing now with this week's series
theme of the appropriate and inappropriate different states
polarities that exist in often in relationship to each other the healthy expressions and unhealthy
expressions of these things and today the the topic is um
gladness and sadness and um
there's beautiful inspiring forms of gladness and there are gladness which are not so
beneficial for us to experience there are profoundly
human and maybe a very important experiences of sadness to experience
and there are unhealthy ways of being sad there's ways that are debilitating
and so to be able to kind of begin teasing apart and seeing that
these can take a different shape form often people often enough i believe
people when they feel sad well just because it's uncomfortable often that they'll just take it as a bad
thing a wrong thing shouldn't be there or when they're glad this is great you're on top of the world
and this is fantastic but in fact just because it's gladness or sadness
doesn't mean that it's just one is just good and one is just bad one is healthy and one is not healthy
they both have their healthy versions and both of them have their unwise version versions
and so to be able to uh see those is helpful and it the unwise ones
uh the ones that are not so healthy to have tend to kind of live together
and in a as a pendulum swings they tend to rebound and react to each
other and live in relationship to each other so for example a person might feel
there's a lot of hope and be really glad and be delighted and by the hope the possibility of something
and then the and then whatever they're hoping for doesn't work out and so the pendulum
swings and then they feel really sad and sorrow and grieving
and um and to say it that abstractly does maybe get it across but you know to say that um you know you
you uh really had a lot of hope in your the lottery numbers you chose
and so certainly this is the number that and you're so glad that you finally had a strong good feeling these are the
numbers that are gonna and then they're not the numbers that win the lottery in and so then you feel
really despairing even discouraging especially because you put a lot of money into into that
and so here these live in relationship to each other
it might be hope around another person hope in a relationship if if only that
can happen then you know and yes that's going to happen i hope for it and it looks like it's
going to happen with that person and then it doesn't and then we crash because we we're being
energized and pumped up in the energy of hope and and when it doesn't work out then we
crash so these kind of exist together some of these that exist together have a lot to do with self
self-identity issues definitions of ourselves or judgments
about ourselves and so if we get praised or we do something that we think others
will approve of then um or then perhaps we feel kind of glad and
happy and kind of energized but um it turns out that what we did
wasn't uh approved of appreciated by other people in fact they were discouraged or upset with us and then
we've crashed and there might be a natural kind of feeling of some gladness and sadness
that is not so tied to our ego but there might be a lot of it is tied to the ego and so the ego is a fragile
thing that can be involved in these swings back and forth and so to begin not just looking at the
particular forms of gladness and sadness that we might have but to see how these live in
relationship to each other and uh and maybe to begin a feeling deciding that you don't want to live
dependent on things that are that are fragile things that swing back and
forth from one end to the other you want to find another way of living and so there's gladness and sadness
that comes from another way of living we feel glad that we have stability
that we're not so pushed around by the opinions of others or
fear of rejection of others or that we we're kind of centered and stable here
content content just to be present and not needing a lot and that gladness
knowing that we're kind of free from a lot of the social drama and games that maybe we were caught up in earlier
it can feel like a gladness that doesn't it's not necessarily so much a part of a pendulum or polarity of two different
states it can just be cloud itself maybe it's a gladness that comes from relief that i used to be so attached to
things and wanting things and spinning out and now i'm not and this new state
is really good and there's a gladness to it or satisfaction in it
and then there can be a sadness that is just part of the deep part of human life
that is just there because there's been loss there because of change that is so you
know that touches us in some deep way there might be sadness that we disappointed ourselves sadness that
yes i was in touch with some deeper way of being and integrity and honesty and
inner uh goodness and
uh i got distracted or i got afraid and so then i did something
that i never would have imagined i ever would have done i heard a friend i lied i did something and
and uh and now we're sad and disappointed we hurt someone and that sadness um it's just there
because there's been pain pain maybe we cause pain and that's not necessarily a problem
in fact it might be a sign of our healthiness that we feel certain kinds of sadness
that a life without sadness maybe is not a life that there's a time and place to feel
sad i remember a story i read many years ago about someone who struggled with a lot
of sadness and the teacher told this person at some point
well be a sad buddha and after many times long period of time
trying to sort out and figure out and escape and fix this sadness this little teaching be a sad buddha allowed the
person just to relax and say okay this is also a buddhist can be sad so okay i
don't have to fight it or judge myself for it there's time and place for it
and uh so just because we're sad doesn't mean that something is wrong
it actually can mean that something is right sometimes sadness is a fallow time
that some something is being prepared inside of us for a new way of being for a new
direction that we're going to go so so a little bit
sadness and gladness belongs to the world of evaluation of
figuring out the value of something the importance of something so it is a kind of a higher intellectual
kind of states than some of the more deeper spiritual states
that we can experience but we have to be very careful what we're evaluating what we think is
important and and then a foundation
for healthy forms of foundation for all forms of sadness and gladness we might experience
for buddhists and is what can be called refuge
that we have a refuge we have an orientation we have a understanding we have a way of seeing we
have a practice that we trust we have a
a presence an attentiveness that we trust
that we that protects us that informs us that guides us
that points us away that shows us there's a way through everything no matter what is going on refuge means
there is a way you might not know what the way is but if you practice mindfulness practice
meditation just keep practicing living ethically uh the dharma
your heart will find a way and so this idea of refuge the ocean of refuge the ocean of stability that's
underneath the um the surface waves that come and go and
sometimes there's a high wave sometimes a low wave and these are all just a surface manifestation they're important parts of
the ocean and and some people will spend wonderful time and difficult times
playing and struggling with those waves but there is a deeper place of refuge
the foundation for it all and if you remember that you have a refuge if you remember you have
you could trust this your practice or trust yourself in a deep way that you don't have to know the way
to know that you'll find your way then you won't have to be so troubled by
the waves you can allow the waves to be there you can study them see them carefully
learn from them learn which ones are healthy and which are not which are dysfunctional and which are
functional um a really important human skill
and you can learn to ride the waves you can learn not to identify with the wave so much
and and learn to uh trust that there's something deeper here than the waves
there's the refuge and there's certain stability a certain
home a certain a companion that always follows you along that is there protect you support
you guide you even when you don't know what's supposed to happen you have a refuge
and and that refuge can give a lot more clarity
and ease around how we navigate and experience the comings and goings of things like
sadness and gladness so um
so you might want to look today as you go through your day
at the small and large versions of sadness and gladness that come up for you
um you know you might not use the word glad gladness very much certain kind of mild joy delight
a kind of pleasant aliveness and then sadness can be a whole range of
things from depression to still sorrow to sadness
so just kind of see how these work for you and can you and without judging yourself and making it worse without the
ego coming in and with the swings can you start see it you think that the
way that your men this sadness and gladness is this really healthy or does it have a
good foundation or is it a foundation kind of fragile and weak and maybe even a little bit
diluted like with a lottery ticket for example and spend some time looking that at this
but remembering that to do it from this foundation of trust where um
you appreciate it's valuable to learn your spot yourself and be happy that you're learning about
yourself trust this learning process more than the judgments oh i'm wrong i
shouldn't be this way if you see how you are then you're on the path
so study your sadness and gladness and see if they live in relationship to each other like a pendulum
or see if there's a kind of a deeper or healthier forms of sadness and gladness
which are not a problem or actually healthy to experience appropriate and
and are not triggering one the other but that it's part of the richness of life the
fullness of life and the depths of life
and then can you allow for that maybe that gladness that sadness needs
its time with you and you might appreciate very much that's the case can
be the case for gladness and the family of glad glad things but you might not appreciate that for
sadness there's a time for it go for a walk sit and have tea allow for it
and then underneath it all the refuge and if the word refuge doesn't
mean something for you maybe what is it that you trust what is a deeper trust
wellspring of wellsprings that you can trust that
allows you to not be so caught in the waves
so thank you and
we'll continue this tomorrow