so hello everyone the warm greetings from
inside meditation center and
for this morning meditation i'd like to offer you a small technique
that works particularly well in meditation and with wisdom
works very well in daily life as well and it's called the one breath reset
one breath reset and that is if you find yourself
involved in storytelling in your mind and storytelling means having a
conversation with someone imagining some scenario remembering some scenario in the past
planning some scenario in the future story can be
uh making a story about the meditation itself that uh
you know conclusion this is uh impossible or boy i'm uh only
two breaths away from full enlightenment or you know whatever it might be if you find yourself involved in a story while
you're meditating do the one breath reset
and that is on the inhale gently lovingly
you say the word no and then finish the sentence on the
exhale with the word story breathing in no
exhaling story no story
and the alternative to storytelling and the reason to use this reset one breath
reset is uh we're cultivating clarity in the present moment
clear awareness clear attention to the present moment
and for many of us the anchor the the
the center of that clarity is being cultivated with breathing
and the simplicity of breathing the tuning in becoming clearer and clearer
on the ex the body's experience of breathing and the one and then find yourself in
stories i'm like you know i'm i'm breathing the wrong way
that's if you're too involved in that kind of idea it's a story and and then no
story one breath reset if it helps you the inhale can be
a little bit bigger than usual and so this the exhale and the nose story has a
little bit more uh strength to it
but i wouldn't do it too strongly just uh just a little bit more emphasis to it and a little bit kind of like you more
wholeheartedly you're involved in the process of letting go of story as you exhale
so um so maybe you won't need it today but if
you do then it can be quite effective the one breath
reset so to
feel your posture that you're in now before doing any other changes
notice how you are in your body
feeling your body from the inside
and almost as if you're discovering what the body wishes
and adjust your posture a bit so your body feels more
comfortable more aligned but also more
supportive of becoming alert and clear here and now
gently closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in deeply and feeling your body
exhaling releasing relaxing your body
and if you're already involved in story you might do the one breath reset
a practice that sometimes needs to be done repeatedly
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and is it as if you can get kind of deep inside your body
from the inside out as you exhale relax the muscles of your
face
on the exhale softening the shoulders
releasing the shoulders to the pull of gravity
maybe there are small adjustments in where your hands are placed
that might loosen up your shoulders a bit more
and softening your belly releasing the stomach the belly
this so
and also as if you can feel deep inside your mind
see if you can relax your mind on the exhale softening
on the exhale as if the mind can become broad and quiet like the surface of a
quiet lake
and then settling awareness into the body's experience of breathing
as if maybe curtains are pulled from the window of the mind
of attention let the curtains be pulled so that you
can experience breathing more clearly
experience that know the body's experience of breathing
and then whenever it's useful
do the one breath reset with the no on the inhale
and story on the exhale
be sure to say the words in a relaxed way
gentle way
so that it supports the quieting of the mind
the stilling of the story making mind
here
so
the one breath reset
can give the mind and the heart a much needed vacation
from storytelling meaning making
predictions and planning letting it all go
reset back to clarity to this moment
so
when we can clear our minds enough of stories
stories of other people that we meet it doesn't negate the stories
maybe they're accurate but it gives us a chance to see people
freshly to see how they are now
without seeing them through the filter of how they were or what happened
and what's one of the gifts that's possible to come from meditation
or from mindfulness this ability to reset the mind enough
to see people clearly as they are now
and therefore be able to listen to them better take them in better more
and know them this can be for strangers and friends
and the chances are as we get to know people more clearly and freshly
it's easier to have good will easier to feel connected to their humanity and
and perhaps or something we learn through this meditation some way that we're changed
that we can bring with us to our social interactions
to our concerns and care for people we don't interact with
may we be predisposed to good will towards others
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
and may we support that possibility maybe in the way in which we
encounter others may all beings be happy
[Music]
so good morning and we come to the
last day this five part series on
aspects of our mind or mental activity that
can be both wholesome and unwholesome helpful and unhelpful
and because they look similar to each other it's possible to confuse them confused
be confused by what part is wholesome what is whole when it's wholesome and when it's not wholesome when it's
useful and not useful so um
today's topic is in palis the word ditty and
and is usually translated into english as views
and views stories opinions philosophies that we have
can be a source of binding of being bondage of being caught
but views can also be a source of freedom setting us free
of wisdom and guidance helpful guidance in our lives and so
in buddhist english there's a tendency of treating the english word views
to refer to unhelpful opinions stories philosophies
metaphysical ideas about what's happening here in this world of ours
and now because it is a strong tendency of kind of pointing out that views are unhealthy
that sometimes people have the idea they're not supposed to have any
understandings any stories any interpretations any
wisdom or understanding that guides them in their life that supports them and is appropriate to have
and so um so but there are these two different possibilities
and so the word diti in as it's used in nepali sutas
is overwhelmingly used to refer to something like speculative views
to fixed views and these two things speculative and fixed are significant
speculative means opinions and views about things that we can't know directly
so they're interpretations or stories or or
about something that um and then fixed views
is when we're caught in and attached to the view so being
opinionated about our view meaning this is you know holding on this is the truth this is how it is
and the fixed views can even be for views understandings
that that are healthy are appropriate in and of themselves but
the way that we hold them there's a there's suffering involved there's attachment there's clinging to the views
i'm right and everyone else is wrong and so this attachment to
to our philosophies our opinions can be
operating whether or not our opinions are accurate and this is an important thing to
consider for those of you who have accurate opinions accurate ideas of what's going on accurate stories and of
what happened is that the way you hold those can be a source
of suffering for yourself and to others when there's an insistence and a dogmatic attachment to it
so um so a lot of buddhist practice is about
overcoming the speculative views dogmatic views views that are speculating about the
nature of reality nature of human being nature of our life nature of liberation
and discovering how to have in the views the understandings that come
out of seeing something directly to having direct experience for oneself
uh when we first get introduced to buddhism maybe that [Music]
we take a little bit the teachings the ideas the maybe even the philosophies a little bit on faith
enough faith that we're willing to do the practice but it's provisional faith this provisional view and we understand this
is provisional it's uh i've reasoned it out it seems like this is the best pretty good
but let's now find out and the idea is that we're moving the direction of
insight where our understanding comes from direct experience for
ourselves and so the what we the what we don't know yet from personal
experience that is taken on provisionally as something that we can discover for
ourselves so you can use a little bit reflection to think about
philosophies views religious thought ideas
metaphysical ideas that might be attractive and seem right to you but you might realize i can never
prove it for myself and so this is maybe outside the reach of
of direct experience and direct sensory experience and so
so if you want to hold on to that then you know that you can't discover this for yourself whether it's true it
becomes a article of faith and in
what we're looking for in buddhism are those understandings those views that we believe can be verified for
ourselves we can discover for ourselves and so something simple as
the idea the story that if you cling you will suffer and if that clinging is
released the suffering is released as well that is something that belongs to the
area of of direct experience it might not be easy to experience but
it is something that with time we can start seeing how that works so yeah in fact i was clinging
and that then i suffered before i clung i was no suffering
um and so to be and to begin uh and so a big
thing that buddhism teaches is that all our experiences are inconstant
and this is a kind of a central tenant held up high as a very important but it's
meant to be an insight that we can verify for ourselves and so the view of life that we get
through practice is a view that's built on this deeper and deeper appreciation of how
things are changing all the time impermanent in constant
and with time we see how this insight has a liberating quality
how how freeing us up from the the idea of constancy or the idea of
permanence the idea of fixidity makes us much more
valuable and fluid and adaptable to all the changes that go on all the time in
life the um uh you know there's a there's a view in
buddhism that there is no self that there's that view that people sometimes
advocate it's not actually what the buddha taught and with some reflection maybe you can
appreciate that maybe you can't really discover that there is no self how would you know
that what the buddha focused on is what you can know for yourself
and what you can know is that particular things in your experience
are not don't qualify as a definition of who i am and uh this is myself
so um
and how you know to so the movement is to see what in our experience that i took as
myself that is not really how i fundamentally am that actually to hold on to that is a
kind of suffering it is kind of a wind drag that slows me down
and that not to identify with that is actually more freedom and more ease in my life
but it's always something particular and as practice gets deeper and deeper all the particulars in our life are seen
as not self but it's but it's not an idea that there is no self
but it's also not the idea that there is a self the philosophy idea of what is and is
not a self that's considered a speculative view that we don't get involved in
what we get involved in is what we can see directly and know for ourselves
so um so in the understandings the views the unders that come from insight
that come from direct experience those we rely on in practice they can give a
sense of purpose a direction to our lives they can guide our lives in a certain way
when we see clearly that there is a possibility to suffer less we see it's possible to let go of
clinging it's possible to see below the fixed views that we have the interpretations we have and see things
more directly for ourselves this can give be a powerful
inspiration and motivation to to continue on this path of freedom in
their direct experience and uh and not to get hung up in
speculative philosophies which maybe we can never ascertain for ourselves directly
and if there are philosophies that we can ascertain for ourselves directly some way then if we're motivated we can go and
practice to see how we can discover that for ourselves
the buddha said once that in describing his teaching he said i just point out the way
it's up to you to walk the path and so to this
appreciating what we can discover through a direct experience that shows us what that path is that we
walk so we can get
we can get wrapped up caught up in opinions and stories and views and
philosophies about how things are or we can
have kind of understandings philosophies steven stories
that point to freedom beyond stories that point us to how to be free here
in the direct experience opening up to what's really here in a deeper way
and then discovering the stories that are possible indirect experience in
really seeing clearly what's here and one of those stories is the stories of freedom
the stories of moving from suffering to the freedom from suffering
the story of happiness and and
living a clear life clarity and release
and that's a story that's worth living and maybe we can share that story with
each other stories of what we discover uh for in being free
so thank you and um and uh i hope you have a those of you in
the united states i hope you have a wonderful three-day weekend i'll be back
here monday as usual even though it's a holiday and uh some of you might be away
and so i wish you well and in the meantime
you might over this weekend look a little bit about the role that uh
views stories opinions have in for you personally and see if you can discern the
difference between the views stories interpretations that you're caught in
and those that you're not caught in those which are helpful
to see more deeply into our direct experience with ourselves and other people and those stories that obscure
a real insight into what's happening here and now so thank you