so hello welcome good morning uh to you
uh those in around this time zone um
it is uh i know from my nephews it's the first day of uh
of middle school in berkeley unified school district and you
have a substitute teacher today so um
i'm happy to be with you all right my name is matthew princilver
and um yeah i was um was i'm always happy to do
whatever gil asked me to do i feel
inspired by by his service
and very happy to to be with you and be practicing this week together
and we'll have have uh the usual usual
format and um i will guide us in in a meditation for a half
hour and then offer some reflections starting at half past
so um yeah let us uh let us sit together
so much of meditation practice is about relinquishing reference points
but it's very useful to
to have the reference point
of love
love not so much in the sense of some ebullient feeling
but love in the sense of of knowing
that all experience can soften our heart
that any experience any experience might hurt
but need not harm our heart
so we begin with this reference point
and progressively surrender so many of the others
and just taking some deeper breath spreading
your breath through your whole body
it's like we we pour the awareness into
the whole body
there's no rigidity but there's a gentle
discipline
there's no turning any experience into an enemy thinking or whatever
but we do know why we're doing what we're doing
beginning to gather up the fragments of our attention
bring them all right here to the body breathing
the urge to fix and secure our life
such natural urges
it's easy enough we just put this down
remember in our heart of hearts what practice is about
but uh sometimes the the energy of fixing
securing our life is so strong that it
itself needs the blessing of awareness love
and so we move the spotlight of attention
from our body breathing to the urgency of fixing as it manifests
in our emotional body
the circuits that light up with the worried thought
or the conclusion we've longed for
the engine of thinking
is affect and so we invade that
in awareness and patience
and then perhaps it feels appropriate to
return to the body breathing
the field of attention
more unified
in meditation we all experiment
practice becoming temporary monastics
a monastic in the sense of
privileging the life of awareness
over [Music] our life of projects
and so to be mindful
is actually quite a deep surrender
it's good too uh good to sit with you
so um yeah happy happy to be with you
um
so in in
clinical treatment research um
there are uh two really two often two key questions
does this treatment work and if it does how does it work
yeah so the questions around efficacy or effectiveness
doesn't work and then the mechanism of change how does it work
and the the buddha made
claims about efficacy this works this is not a shell game
yeah and that's part of why it's so helpful to
have new experiences on this path bliss or insight or love or something
but new experiences because it helps confirm the sense of
like that we're we're not being conned like there's something on offer here
and um and so we start to get some sense of how
yeah this can work right so the buddha made those claims
but mostly the the teachings really unpack a
vision of the ways that practice transforms
the mechanisms of change and that language you know is
is borrowed from from pharmacology where uh
question of how how a medicine works it well it stimulates this
receptor system or and down regulates another receptor
activity and
i use that language here because um
all dharma talks implicitly embrace some mechanism of action
yeah when we give a meditation instruction or a talk or
something we we have a mechanism of action in mind we have a
theory of change in mind this is how practice gets under our skin this is how
freedom from suffering unfolds
and we talk explicitly or implicitly usually implicitly about the mechanism of action
for at least a couple reasons first really to
encourage you to keep going we really do need a strong why why do we
do this and why should we ever be willing to experience suffering
consciously yeah we we need a strong answer to that
to keep going and much of what dharma teachers do
is more or less just to say don't give up
yeah this is how practice works this is its mechanism
it's supposed to feel like this even though a part of our mind
is utterly unconvinced we're ever supposed to feel
like this so
relka says uh no feeling is final just keep going
don't let yourself lose me nearby is the country they call life
you will know it by its seriousness give me
your hand
so we we talk about the mechanisms to encourage you to keep going
and also when we understand how practice works in a deeper way
we can reinforce the positive effects and minimize the side effects
we can really determine what's what's important on the path and emphasize it
yeah and so classically you might say that the mechanisms of change what points to
the mechanisms of change is sila
ethical training ethical conduct samadhi the training of the mind gathering of
attention and pania wisdom these are maybe we say the classical
mechanisms of change sila
purifying purifying our karma
you can't really expect to be happy if you're perpetually
harming yourself and others
and the the kind of hatred and paranoia or separateness
that's bred by harming is not actually compatible with deep
happiness and so we start to build the foundation
of our spiritual home uh you know on on
uh the ground of non-regret
yeah there's so much that our ethical
alignment does build on the foundation of non-regret
and and there's a kind of transparency in our life we can't be found out
when we're acting in alignment with our own deepest values we we can't be found
out so like twain says um um
something like when you tell the truth you don't have to remember anything right
our whole life becomes like that
non-defended we don't have to remember anything
and there's samadhi there's samadhi in the deep enjoyment of being secluded from
the bombardment of samsara yeah
this this realm this realm of existence
i thought of uh bob dylan yeah i was
burned out from exhaustion buried in the hail poisoned in the bushes and blown out on
the trail hunting like a crocodile ravage in the corn come in she said i'll give you
shelter from the storm
just being human is a little overwhelming moment to moment a little overwhelming
and so uh we have to take shelter one of the ways we take shelter
is to um to rest in attention
and to really open to the kind of intensity
of the human condition without the shelter of some samadhi
it's it's too much it's too much
and so we take our seat and
sometimes we usually usual way we understand samadhi is the kind of stillness of the discursive mind
and that's that's real but there's almost another sense of samadhi
of just um sense of our body all being in one place
and even even when the mind is very active there can be a sense of
something is gathering something is stilling
and so we we settle down
we take our protection and the kind of
spotlight of attention isn't shaking so sharply anymore and we start to
perceive the objects of attention more clearly this is said to lead to
wisdom clear seeing yeah understanding understanding what brings happiness what
brings suffering perceiving the kind of hallmarks of
experience the characteristics of experience
understanding beginning to understand the
cause and effect in a more nuanced rich way
our maps of happiness are impoverished when we begin practice
we start to fill them out
complicate them see them in more detail what is happiness
what is it really how does pleasure differ from satisfaction
what is conducive to heart at rest
so these are the kind of maybe we say the classical
mechanisms of change and
this week for whatever it's worth i'll um
offer a kind of alternative map of the the mechanisms of action
yeah just a different way of framing how practice functions for us how it
gets under our skin how it begins to transform our heart
and it emerges from yeah from my own practice and
also from my encounters with clinical clinical research psychotherapy
research and um and so over the next four days i'll
unpack four mechanisms through which practice may
transform and inform our heart and hopefully feel familiar and fresh at
the same time and hopefully will will
animate your practice so that you keep going so
you know what's useful so that you have a strong strong why why to stay why should i stay
so offer this for your sensation and um
yeah happy too uh happy to be with you and happy to see what unfolds uh this week
so um yeah i wish you a a good day or afternoon or evening
wherever you are and look forward to gathering back
in about 23 hours okay
you