good evening welcome welcome to see you all
this December Day evening
before I forget I want to make an announcement that uh that we won't have
a meeting next Monday it's pretty unusual for IMC to be closed but we will
be not open next Monday so it just adds up about
that it's on the calendar too but uh
we don't always look at the calendar right so that we won't have a meeting here next Monday
so I've been gone for a number of weeks and partly
I was the reason why I wasn't here is because I was at IMS in Massachusetts
the Insight Meditation Society it's part of the teaching team for the
last part of the three-month retreat three months
so the way it's set up is that you can do the first six weeks you can do the second six weeks or you can do 12 weeks
all of it and this year about more than half did uh more than three did all
three months and they didn't do the three-month Retreat last year I think or the year before so
so I've done a number of three-month Retreats and and now in my role there as a teacher
I recognized in some of the participants some of the yogis that we call them
something that tripped me up and I saw a lot of people getting tripped up about the same thing
I want to talk a little bit about this and that is
maybe maybe I'll start by saying It's Perfectly Natural that if a person is
going to go on a three-month Retreat right this is a big deal to rearrange your life to essentially
drop out of society for a number of months is not a small feat
it's not a trivial matter it's usually something that gets planned years in advance
so that you know all everything can be taken care of and something like this and the three-month
Retreat is always in the fall every year at IMs it has been for the last 45 years
so something that you you can plan years in advance but when a person goes
it's not uncommon to have this secret niggling little thoughts in the back of
their mind that maybe they're not aware of but this idea of well if anything's
gonna happen with my practice It's gotta be here
I gotta make it happen I don't know if I'll ever be able to do a three month Retreat again in my life
and I gotta make it happen whatever it is right and we have different ideas
about what that is so there's this way in which we show up with this determination this sense of
okay I'm gonna go For Broke not recognizing not knowing because we
don't talk about it so much but this subtle type of
I'm like grimacing when I'm thinking about this I'm making a fist clenching my teeth kind of thought
is exactly what makes what they want to happen not happen
whatever it is right we all have different ideas with the goal of practices but there's this way in which
there's this straining this bearing down this spreading your teeth
that turns out not really to be the way forward
for me I my first time I was in a three-month Retreat I had this crazy idea
that I should never go outside
I don't you know I just felt like that was like the thing to do and IMS has organized that you can do that that all
the because it's colds there right this is New England so it's cold there in the fall it starts in September and ends in
December and you know by the time it ends the Highs are only in the 20s or something
there but but so it's all the buildings are connected so you can go from the dorms
to the dining hall to the meditation Hall you know without ever going outside I got a little weird
just staying inside all that time you know this kind of
mindful walking and eating and sitting and there's something that just you know
my world just kind of got really small and I kind of got really tight and in my role as a teacher here at just
this past few weeks seen people doing the same thing
so for me it showed up this idea of like gotta make it happen showed up in this
kind of the things getting really small and tight and that's how you could see as an an
observer just watching what Diana was doing but in the mind
was this sense of get out of my way I gotta get get
concentrated or something like this so there was this quiet aversion to
everything kind of being pushed away there was this quiet uh
sense of whatever I'm doing it's not enough it's not good enough or something like this
I just got a little weird and the teachers were like Diana can you back off a little bit and I was like what do
those teachers know they already have something I don't know
what it is they have but I don't have it I have to work yeah come to find out this turns out not
to be so rare to have this idea so I just thought I would talk about this a little bit
this idea of how do we have this sustained practice
this energy of showing up again and again and again without tension
without tightness without a sense of bearing down and
gritting our teeth how do we do that
because to be sure this practice does require that we you know put forth energy that we put forth effort right we
can't just be passive if we are I mean there might be a way in
which there are some people who are thinking that okay as long as I
maybe to have some heartfelt rituals or
commitment or something like that then something will
shift but those usually aren't the people that come to IMC because we don't have very much rituals and those aren't
the type of people that go on long retreat practice so I'm kind of talking this talk is more
towards those people who are really pushing and we're in Silicon Valley
there's a lot of really smart accomplished people here so the type of
pushing or perseverance that helps in our professional life helps in our education
is not the same type of thing that's going to help in our meditation life and
that's really hard to understand like we have this one way of accomplishing
things becoming successful attaining achieving in so many different ways in our lives
and it turns out that that works until it doesn't
it works a little bit until only so far but if you really want this practice to
take you further that same thing that helped you in other areas of your life is not really going to help with
meditation so maybe I'll just say so that's like
one extreme really the grin and Barrett and I'm going to talk about that but there is also of course this other
extreme of you know just complete passivity and just reading some good Dharma books that make us feel good
listening to some Derma talks that make us feel good and then don't do anything until we read the
next book or listen to the next Dharma talk but there's this way that we have to do a
little bit of energy because if we don't
our life will unfold according to our habits our life will unfold according to our
neuroses our life will unfold according to kind
of like Evolution as programmed us to be pursuing pleasure
right getting genes into the next generation is about food and sex and pleasurable
things so you know Evolution was in about
helping us to feel happy or satisfied or Freedom or have a good life it was all about pleasure so
it takes effort it definitely takes effort if we want something a little bit different than that
chances are we've been pursuing all these pleasures and found it's
not as satisfying as we had hoped it would be
and maybe I'll say something else so we have our habits nurses Evolution but
also just our culture it's quite something right how our
culture really wants us to pay attention to screens as much as possible Right we've kind of created a culture that
thinks it's the absolute worst thing we could ever do is be bored and once instead we need to be
entertained or we need to be assumed or we need to be outraged or
something like that so this it does take effort to turn away
from all these pressures that we experience
so how can we how can we do this have some sustained effort in a way
that's without tension without tightness without
getting tipping over into something that's not so helpful
so one way is maybe I'll recognize that um this
word energy shows up in a lot of Buddhist lists energy or we can tie together um effort
so the poly words aren't exactly the same but they're pointing to the same thing
and I'll say that energy it's in the seven factors of Awakening it's the
third out of seven it's in the parmies the ten Perfections
it's the fifth of the tenth it's in the five faculties it's the
second out of the five it's in the Eightfold Path it's the
sixth out of the eighth so something that we notice if we look
at that not only is in a lot of lists and it's in more or less but the other list I'm just mentioning the most common
one the most well-known ones what we'll notice Energy's in the middle
of these lists and so one way that we might like it'll
really you know ten thousand foot V 30 000 foot view we might think of practices
having an orientation a direction we want to go
and then using energy is a way to help us
get to greater Freedom greater ease
and you know these lists end with things like concentration Equanimity or wisdom and they start with
things like faith view generosity kind of like this
movement of connecting with others and letting go so energy is integral to our practice
but it's not the case that just more energy is better
right it's not like the end of the practice and it's not the beginning so just this recognition that as human
beings we have limited energy right we're not machines
and so it's not a case of just more more and more the kind of like this doggedly
pursuing something with all the energy that we have
but instead it's to use energy like in a wise Direction
and in a balanced way and I could do a whole other Dharma talk
and just how to keep balance but what I want to focus on a little bit is how can maybe it is a
form of balance but in particular how can we have this steadfastness have
this perseverance without getting too tight so
part of it is this recognition that our energy levels change
they change in seasons of our life they change in times of our life they
change during the day so just to recognize that of course
energy levels that we all have is not always the same and maybe to work with that and to honor
that and to respect that as opposed to insisting that our energy
be different or thinking that this practice is asking us to have
tremendous amount of energy it's not it's a it's asking us to work with the
energy that we have it's asking us to be Who We Are
with the life that we have so
not only are there like seasons and times that our energy changes but we can
also notice how if we're not quite like a battery
either or a fuel tank or something like this right that there's just this steady
diminishing of energy as the day goes on or something like this
it seems like I know for me you know this idea of battery when I was a kid
right I didn't think about batteries too much but these days like oh does my laptop have enough power does my phone
have enough power right we seems like we're often kind of like tuned into this idea what's the percentage on the
battery and it's kind of natural to think like oh humans are like that too
but we're not for example
this happened to me some time ago I was going to a public space to hear a
talk a Dharma talk and this was a
I was visiting some friends and we went together to this place so it's not anywhere here in California but
um the teacher was I don't know what it was exactly but I
could not stay awake you know it was one of these things that I didn't want my to embarrass my friends
and like okay okay okay like okay I've got to pay attention to this and the
room was kind of hot you know there's lots of excuses I could get afraid but my energy was like oh my gosh when is
this going to end maybe you've had this experience
maybe with me right you know sometimes I have my my energy right when I'm talking
is not always uh always high maybe it's a little aside
here's like a True Confessions here I um I have been giving a Dharma talk
and I remember thinking to myself this is so boring
I'm bored these poor people they're bored like when is this gonna be over
what can I do you know so just this recognition right it'll have
it happens right right so here I am listening to start my target feeling like I really have no
energy trying to stay awake as it happens the Dharma talk did end
like oh okay where are we gonna go to dinner oh yeah well let's think about this if I also the energy comes up and
let's go here no I don't want to go there and what about this I've never tried this I've never been there and like the energy comes up right so it's
what often is happening in the mind that is affecting the energy level
is this something for us to just be aware of because often we might think I
don't have enough energy but there's a way in which maybe it's
true but maybe it's not true also and so for us to just be open to that
possibility so what are some ways that we can
practice with kind of sustaining our energy with a have some resolve some
determination some commitment some loyalty some devotion we might use this
kind of language to our practice one is
the practice needs to be meaningful for us
sometimes we can get into this habits I listen to Dharma talks on this day
that's because that's what I do but is there a way
that or I meditate at this time because that's what I do this is fantastic but is there a way
that we can also connect to a way in which it's meaningful for us
because without this meaningfulness it can start to feel like drudgery or
dryness or like okay here it is it's the morning I'm supposed to meditate and redo it but there isn't this juice to it
it becomes like a chore or something we're supposed to do so
is there a way that we can connect to what we love about the
practice what is something juicy about the
practice is there a way that something that we care about or something that's
important for us right this is this brings energy to our
lives you know things that are important to us meaningful for us so it's helpful to really think what is
Meaningful about this practice as opposed to this is what I'm supposed to do or I'm doing this in order that this
will happen can we connect to it in a way that feels
alive and for some people it is a little bit
of devotion or I know somebody I've mentioned this before who does meta
practice in the beginning of every sit just and they chant sometimes it's
silent sometimes it's in their head doing the meta
because it's uplifting but kind of like opens the heart in some kind of way
so maybe some chanting is Meaningful we don't do a lot of chanting probably here
at IMC we do I don't know maybe twice a year of each and it's not really something that we do
here but if this is something you're interested in the abayagiri website
and they have a chant book and recordings of the monastics doing some chanting including the meta chant which
is something that I myself have found really meaningful and I don't know I found like
hard opening I made a little recording on my on a CD
player I had to chat like over and over and over and over and over and over again and I just put that in my car and that's
how I memorized it just tearing it over and over again this may not speak to you
is there something about I don't know so it's like the Buddha and some sometime we had a parachara here
this idea of these people that found some freedom in their practice and they just
through pure generosity pure care for others shared it with others
and somehow I feel touched by that this feeling that there was the Buddha and
also parature a woman this recognized teacher that just shared it
so this is one way to connect to some meaningfulness but
also there's is there a way that there can be this heartfulness
for me also I'll say that I heard a a talk this was years ago actually at
one of these three month retreats where one of the teachers this is at the beginning of the three months said
what would it be like if you'd dedicate it or
maybe dedicate feels too strong of a word but opened up the idea that your
practice helps others and recognizing that on a retreat that
long just and it's hard right there are six days weeks maybe months Maybe
when it's hard to get to the cushion but this recognition Okay my sitting
here maybe helps the person next to me the person behind me just knowing that
somebody else is meditating is helpful so I just started to say at the
beginning of my sits may this it be for the benefit of all beings
and for me that was meaningful this may feel a little too Airy fairy
woo-woo for some people it may feel too like I don't know that just doesn't make any sense to me
you don't have to do it but here's just an invitation to touch into what is something that would support you and
make it meaningful and maybe with some heartfeltness
make it you know the way in which there can be some enthusiasm or some joyfulness to this as
opposed to some drudgery
so there's also a way that we might think about practice
as I know I've said this expression a number of times and I sincerely believe this
finding our way to have a sustained effort
without tension without tightness without drudgery without like this sense
of bearing down is an art I would say this is an art
and we only find it by getting out of balance sometimes
but and this is the art of practice really because sometimes it takes more or takes more energy and sometimes it
takes less energy but what if we were to consider this
practice as kind of like an art and what I mean by that is
sometimes I I don't like to talk about myself so
much but I'm giving just examples hopefully so that you all can find your own way
but here's another story of something that Diana does I like to play with paper it's kind of
like a craft and I like to make things with paper this is just something that I do on my own is something that's fun
it started something that my mom and I would do and you know so you know now I
do it I make cards for people or I make little things I just something that I do
but I love doing this and part of what I love about it is like I'll have these
pieces of paper that I'm kind of creating I'll like look at it and like um no that's not quite right that's a
little bit out of balance it needs to have something there and it's a little bit too heavy here and you know playing
putting things here and like oh now this looks good but now that doesn't so I'm
gonna put this in and you know the scrap that I threw away go back to the trash you know actually this might be just
what's needed and I put it here it's fun I just like to do that
what if practice were like that oh I'm just looking at this this feels a
little tight I'm gonna try to can there be a little bit of softening and
part of what is fun about this crafting that I do with paper is it
it's okay whatever it is I'm just giving myself over to it and there's a little
playfulness exploration without this idea that it has to be perfect or that
it has to be one particular way so what would it be like to consider our
practice like that like a sit as having some playfulness and this is
like an art we're creating something we're exploring
we're experimenting we're seeing what it is
this the downside of this is that we Tinker we do nothing but Tinker for our
entire practice and that's not helpful either but is there a way to think of it like
okay there's a the art of practice part of the art is some playfulness some
exploration some experimentation
something else that is helpful to have this
I mean this sustained practice without this tightness or tension
is to recognize or believe that are our actions have consequences
of course we believe that right I mean when I say that I will say well of course they do
but there's also a way in which we might think it doesn't really matter if I
use my meditation time all fantasizing the whole time which you know we want to
do of course we want to do or it doesn't matter if I'm rehearsing um that way that that person hurt my
feelings and now I'm going to get back to them and this there's a way in which we might
think that it doesn't matter what we're doing
but it does of course it does there are a way that we spend our energy
has an impact on us it affects our moods affects the energy
level in the body it affects our habits which impact Our
Lives so it makes
a difference how we act and how we think
and what a difference our life is if we're willing to put a little bit of effort
towards doing some skillfulness um recognizing that things that are
unskillful unhelpful unwholesome do have an impact but can we recognize
it without you know getting judgmental about ourselves but just recognizing
that it's important to act skillfully to think skillfully
as best we can as best we can there's a way in which we might think oh
it doesn't really matter it does matter these minor Small Things what's
happening in our head nobody else knows about we might think that they're not important but
it it can be can it can make a difference it does make a
difference and there's this way here's another Diana's story
that um there was a time when I was really into yoga
and I couldn't explain to you why I liked yoga I was I was a research
scientist at the time and I thought yoga was this weird thing somehow I felt better when I did it so I
kept on doing it and I had no aspiration it was kind of
like a secret thing I didn't want my other scientists friends that I was doing this weird thing
so I had no aspirations I was going to be a great yoga that I could do and he
poses better or anything like that I just noticed that I don't know I felt a little bit more connected to myself into
my life when I was doing this without meaning to with zero intention
I just got better at these yoga poses right because I was just doing them more
often I just started to notice like oh oh yeah I didn't used to be able to
balance that way but now I can so it's just this recognition that
we can things we can learn things even without
this tension of having wanting to and that we all of us have learned things in
the past of course right we've learned to tie our shoes we learned to cook we learned to knit we
learned to play tennis whatever but all those things we didn't we weren't able to do them at
the first time we had to just apply a little bit of persistent effort and we could do it
so maybe there's this um maybe there's a little bit more I could say here but
I think maybe I'll do a few more talks on this idea and I'm gonna I want to leave or end
today with um talking about squirrels and I've mentioned this on a talk before
maybe I'll just mention some of you might know that there's this um internet uh YouTuber person
named Mark Rober he's a scientists he's here in the
Silicon Valley he's a engineer I should say he's not as much a scientists as engineer he used to work at Nasa I used
to work at Apple I think he has the more YouTube views
than any other human and he teaches about engineering it's I just love this
kind of geeky stuff but he makes it a lot of fun as some of you might have seen this that
he um noticed that uh squirrels were stealing
the bird feed out of the bird feeder in his backyard so he thought well maybe I'm going to
make it a little bit I'm going to try to um engineer the bird feeder to make it so
that the squirrels wouldn't get it make it long story short he ends up creating the eight part ninja obstacle
course for squirrels and it's so cute and the squirrels figure out a way to do
it it's amazing how they jump over fly around you know all this kind of stuff to get to the bird feeder right so it's
I can recommend it recommend it see he's now gone to part three of the Ninja
obstacle courses so there's also this poem
the squirrel determination by Rosemary traumer this poem is called again again
and I want to think that Rosemary traumer has seen these uh YouTube videos
as she might have this was this poem was written at the end of 2020.
right still in the pandemic and the poem goes like this
on a day when the world asks too much of me and I don't know how to give it
I think of the squirrels at the feeder when I was a girl
dad hung the feeder on a squirrel proof wire
dad set the feeder on a squirrel proof Pole
squirrels found a way surely there's some squirrel in me
some chattering tenacity some bushy-tailed resolve I can't be courageous and brave then let
me at least be stubborn surely inside this aching heart is a
scamperer willing to try again to try again
to meet disappointment and failure and exhaustion and try again
again
squirrels found a way I'm not sure that I would use the word
stubborn but she's talking about kind of like this tenacity and you know determination
and I like this kind of way like squirrels right they they find a way so
maybe it's not straightforward or linear
but they just you know find a way
so maybe there's a way that we can find a way with our practice keep on coming back
in a playful way squirrels are a little bit playful or
with some heart feltness I don't know if squirrels have heartfeltness but can we
connect with this playfulness a sense of maybe it's a little bit of an art or some heartfulness or exploration or
experimentation or some attitudes like that to help support us on this journey
so I think with that I'll open it up to see if there are any questions or comments
about this idea of persistence or
sustained effort without tension or getting some tightness
so maybe Jim behind you
uh maybe in addition to finding that balance between
effort and relaxedness there's also the idea of just if you can which is hard
for me getting into a rhythm getting into a rhythm a rhythm of practice of daily practice yes a rhythm
can be really supportive but also there can be a way in which sometimes Rhythm gets a little bit dry too so the point
is like can we have some I like this word juiciness but I don't know if that's a good word or not
because there's a way in which people we can kind of get stuck we're just doing the same thing again and again
without yeah maybe stuck so a rhythm is
fantastic if it works and until it doesn't work does that make sense
oh yeah and um maybe what was the word you
um maybe an interestedness yes thank you like all this stuff going on in my mind
and body maybe it's not always good news but it's who I am and it means oh you
know evidence hey I'm alive it's it's interesting and in an edifying way yes absolutely an
investigation rate is one of the Awakening factors and it's one of the enlivening Awakening factors just as you
said yep yep some curiosity like wow what is this this is kind of a way that
we could be with them our experience yeah I need to remember all these points because I'm a hard case it's hard
for me to get into my daily practice Yeah right it's easy to kind of like fall into a pattern and maybe a is that
what you said that it's it's hard for um for me to get into a sustained daily practice so so I I'm
all these little tips I need to remember you're not the only one
right it's not natural I think for us to have a regular meditation practice it
definitely takes effort yeah thank you
um can you talk a little bit about on a three-month retreat
is the schedule Pace the same as
like a three-week retreat but just longer or essentially yeah the sits tend
to be a little bit uh longer if you the sits are longer there's more one hour
sits but that you can do a one hour set right after you've been sitting in a
while yeah so it's the same thing from same type of schedules it walks it walks
it walks it walks it walks it walk do any of you
but it's but you stay at the retreat center you don't leave the retreat
center come back like you don't you may not go outside but if some people go outside do they go
out side and go away and come back or no IMS is um in particular is located a
little bit in the middle of nowhere but it's also in the middle of woods and there's all kinds of hiking trails so
people would go outside and sometimes that's a recommendation to move the body get the blood pumping and go out and see
some beautiful things that can you know uplift the heart and mind so yeah most
people go outside is it anticipated that people go
to that to those longer Retreats with
um a stated purpose or no
I know sometimes that IRC that they ask what your goal is
yeah um the expectation is that you would be
practicing like how we practice here so vipassana and insight so there's less of
um you're you're having to have a specific goal IRC does this more to kind
of just give people the opportunity to reflect on what they're doing so that
they don't waste their time in some kind of way but a three-month Retreat is long enough is that you know there'll be time
whether you'll be feeling motivated and great and then you're like oh my gosh what am I doing here this is so long get
me out of here and then it comes back up and so there's these natural rhythms that happen so and I think what people
arrive maybe with one idea but you know while you're in week seven week eight
you know those ideas are you have different ideas then the first time you set that length of a
retreat did you have any apprehension about it
apprehension like how can I do this or yeah I just I'm afraid that I would go nuts
at some point yeah I went through
you know I can't remember this was now quite some time ago so I can't remember the for the first Retreat if I I'm sure
I did right it's not a normal thing to do right so of course I I must have been
and then after that once I realized what it's like but and to be sure that being on Retreat
for that long that duration the mind can touch places that you can't access on
shorter Retreats or in daily life so it definitely is uh
a different experience so the effort that you're making actually changes
day to day or week to week during the retreat right
um so one thing I'll say in a retreat container right that definitely supports right the bell rings so you go to the
hole [Music] um but the um
yeah right because it's like sometimes difficulties arise things that are hard like emotions are coming up or memories
are coming up they're difficult and it takes energy to like stay not you know get up and run out screaming kind of
thing I'm exaggerating but you know sometimes it feels like that like you know this is what happens on Long
Retreats of course stuff comes up of course so um and sometimes yeah it feels like
wow this is like I never want to leave you know and sometimes you're like get
me out of here what was I thinking so yeah I guess maybe the energy changes
as that kind of experience changes
you're welcome okay so here we are at the top of the
hour so thank you all for your kind attention
and we'll see you in the new year can you believe that it's going to be January
2nd I think it said Monday that will be here next so deep house deep house
thank you