so hello everyone and
i'm happy to be here and and to be heard
i think we have the sound equipment everything working again
so um it gives me the
luxury of repeating myself which i don't like to do so much but
i'll say what i said yesterday that you didn't hear
so imagine that you're going down a creek someplace in a canoe
and there's a wonderful gentle pleasant current which is just carrying you
to your destination where you're going
but it's a narrow creek and lots of trees uh on the bank and overhanging and
and as you go down it's easy to reach out and touch the branches and even hold on to
the branches above to the side and you have a passenger you have someone along with you on the trip
but this person every occasion reaches out to hold on to a branch
and holds it for a while until the canoe stops and then let's go and you go a little bit further and hold on
and you go and hold on and you go and and in this way it takes a really long time to get anywhere and
so um this is an analogy how we can be in our lives then for now we'll look at it in
terms of meditation that there's a current that we're in the current of the present moment
that's always occurring that in a sense the future
comes into the present and flows into the past and the present moment is where
we witness this constant change constant transformation
and this unfolding of time and
and we could stay there in that current and let it take us where it goes
or we could hold on to the branches and the branches are our thoughts our
ideas our feelings that we hold onto and end up having retrospective thinking
something happens and we start thinking about it and then that's holding on to the branch we've lost we're not in the
current anymore or we start thinking about something that is completely unrelated in the past
or in the future the past branches the future branches
or we start making uh commentaries and stories and judgments about what's in
the present and those are commentary branches and story branches judgment branches
and as soon as we hold on to them we're no longer flowing in the current
and in meditation we're teaching ourselves training cells to stay in the current
and not to hold on to anything that interrupts our ability to stay present for what's happening in the
present moment and one place to train ourselves in this is in
the breathing it could be with other things could be sounds all right but the breathing is a classic place to
train us and to consider that the that the constant flow of sensations
connected to breathing in the body that those are the the current of the
present moment as you experienced it physically and the idea is to be present to rest in
to float in those uh sensations as they flow through flow by
that's the place where we tap into the present moment and the constant change
and then notice when we get pulled away into thought we're holding on to a branch
and how there's a disconnect if we get lost too much in those thoughts
and the idea is to kind of stay feeling sensing resting um
knowing cognizant of the the current of breathing
the flow of sensations that come with the in-breath with the out breath wherever in the body
you feel the breathing it doesn't mean you have to stop thinking entirely
it means that the the the weight of attention
is on the breathing not holding on to the branch some of sometimes the breathing can just
be like a branch on the side of the creek that you see and it just goes by
maybe it brushes against even against your uh your shoulder as you go by if it's a narrow creek
but you don't stop for it you know it's there but you don't you're you're staying
and for a canoer it stays nose they're floating in the river just feels the
current stays in it and there's that's the center of gravity that's where the weight of attention is
so assuming a upright meditation posture
and gently lowering your gaze
to about 45 degrees to the floor
and letting your gaze be relaxed not focusing on anything in particular
and then gently closing your eyes
and gently establishing a connection
to the body breathing
feel the rhythm of the body breathing in and breathing out
breathing in and breathing out
in feeling knowing the beginning and the end of the inhale
aware of the beginning and end of the exhale
being aware of the current of sensations between the beginning and the end of the
inhale
knowing the current of sensations between the beginning and end of the
exhale
so
and feeling the changing sensations of breathing
take a little bigger breath than usual
and as you exhale settle into the body breathing
relax the body as if you're relaxing around the
experience of breathing
let anger breathing come to normal
and for this meditation trusting
attention to breathing trusting floating in the current
of breathing in and breathing out
noticing if you grab the branches of thoughts
and you're no longer floating no longer flowing along
with the whole experience of breathing in the whole experience of breathing out
staying there resting sensing knowing
the full experience in time of breathing as it's occurring
so
thinking has a flow and a movement from one thought to the other
see if you can switch your allegiance from the flow of thinking
to the flow of breathing letting thinking recede to the
background and let yourself be carried along
in the current of the present moment
that appears with every sensation of breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
and take a few moments to appreciate whatever degree of calm
peace you might feel and if there is no calm in peace
what what you might have understood about your mind's tendency to hold on to branches
and what you might learn from led to letting go of the branches even if it's momentary
being present the flow of the present moment
and letting that be a place upon which to gaze upon others kindly
to look upon the world with the calm peaceful eyes
not filtered by the attachments and fears we might have
to feel fortunate to have the ability to sit quietly and meditate
and think of this meditation as a foundation for going into the world
with care and love kindness
friendliness may this meditation practice we do
be a preparation for living a wise and caring life
may the peace of our meditation spread from us out into the world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
so today we come to the next exercise of the discourse on the
establishment of awareness for establishing awareness
and this is called sometimes it's called the six scent spheres
and um it refers to being mindful at each of the sense doors
so the sixth sense doors are eyes ears
nose tongue body and its tactile abilities to know to feel
and uh the mind door so it's as if we have an eye or
a organ of perception that recognizes what we're that we're thinking that we have emotions the
activities of the mind and um that organ of perception is considered
one of them one of the six senses
and um and so the text itself begins with a very
simple statement it builds on it it says that
one knows there are sight objects things that we can see
and we know that there's the eye and in this simple
statement is the beginning of mindfulness a kind of certain kind of emphasis of
mindfulness which is very much centered in the present moment in the
direct experience of the senses so not anticipating the future or
remembering the past but right here in the moment so that um
if they if you're hearing you might hear the spell
if you're seeing you're seeing what's in front of you in the moment that you're seeing
and and it begins with uh sight
many years ago when i was um heading to going to the monastery i went to the
monastery at the zen monastery at tassajara i was there for a little while
[Applause] and and i noticed something unusual about
seeing and that was that um
i could look at a tree and i saw the tree kind of
and i was aware of myself looking i was aware of the eyes kind of engaged
in the process of looking and and then i noticed that in between
maybe it's almost what it felt like in between was my ideas of the tree
it was almost as if i was painting the concept tree on top of the tree
the concept was accurate enough so ordinarily i would have not not have thought twice about
you know there was anything more than seeing that tree but i became acutely aware of how there
was an act of conception act of interpretation act of
projection onto the tree and
and so there was the see the object of seeing the eyes that see
and something in between and it could be the judgments it could
be our stories we have our ideas we have what's there it could be our bias that we project
onto something and uh and so we don't see things
directly as they are we often see them through the filter of something
so uh in mindfulness practice it's possible to become aware of this filter
this thing that's in between but it begins by learning to
appreciate as the simple moment of sense awareness
that and so one of the sense stores is seeing and it's a wonderful exercise a
wonderful capacity to learn how to look with quiet eyes
relaxed eyes and and to look without
the agenda without the wanting mind looking for something
or the scared mind looking for danger looking how to be safe
but to have a very cool calm quiet
eyes that gaze in a relaxed way and and uh
i believe in the ancient world in the ancient buddhist world they sometimes had the idea that the eyes
rather than light coming to into the eyes it's more like somehow the eyes go out
to touch the object out there to grab the object and certainly i felt sometimes with uh
if i'm really intense on wanting something or or afraid of something or curious about
something i can almost feel like you know my head goes forward the almost like my eyes open more
and and like my eyeballs are kind of like popping out a little bit to see what's that
and or i might be straining trying to really look at something carefully and and
minutely and try to make sense of it and and i could feel the strain in my eyes
one of the wonderful ways to practice mindfulness is to under have a reference point is to learn how to let awareness of
seeing be become be useful
and generally a relaxed easy eyesight
their eyes you know it doesn't have to be conscious even but their eyes are slightly moving
around their eyes are not held fixed fix
fixedly held eyes strain and get tired but relaxed eyes
our eyes are kind of it's kind of like they float in this in the eye socket and
they're kind of like looking a little bit here and there or looking at a particular object is kind
of maybe looking at the perimeter looking different pieces of it just kind of roamed eyes roam around
and to allow the eyes to roam gently can release a lot of stress
a lot of fixation in the mind because when the eyes roam
it's kind a little and kind of look at different things it's kind of more difficult for the mind to stay fixated
on his preoccupation and the more fixated we are in our inner
concerns our thoughts the more the eyes tend to be held tight or don't don't have this that
floating feeling and so one of the ways to do this in mindfulness of seeing
is to settle back and allow sights to come to you
don't go looking for anything and see but don't look
the difference being that looking is an active intentional act to look for
something someone might say look over there and then you look if people don't say see over there they might say what
do you see and and it's not necessarily a request to go
looking but just to if your eyes are in that direction what comes to your eyes what comes into
awareness so one of the ways to cultivate mindfulness and develop it is at each of
the six cent stores and begin to appreciate a relaxed quiet
way of receiving the sensations at the particular sense doors so today
through a seeing and uh and just that is a wonderful exercise
if you're have the fortune of maybe being a passenger in a car for me it's even better a bus or a train
and just let the eyes gaze out in the countryside as you could or the scenery around yours are driving and
let the eyes just kind of be float and look and relax and don't hold on to anything don't
just keep the eyes soft and it's uh when i was a teenager i used to get very calm
looking at trained windows and just looking at things going by
so um so that's very nice maybe and then the exercise
in this in this uh exercise on the six cent stores
is to know the object that we're seeing to know we're seeing something to know
the eyes and to do and be able to see in a relaxed way
but then to notice one of the things that's in between and the particular thing that this
exercise is about is to notice the not the k-n-o-t
it's sometimes translated into english as a fetter but i think the word in poly i think
it's better rendered as the word not um and federer kind of implies that
we're fettered we're hindered by something which is true and not means we're knotted up in it we're entangled with it and i myself
personally uh prefer the language of entanglement or being knotted up in something
and so if i you know have some
problem with my computer my eyesight is knotted up tangled in
trying to figure it out then what's going on here and looking and my eyes are not relaxed i'm not just get gazing
at the issue and letting the some kind of quiet the inner exploration try to figure it out i might
be entangled and caught in the issue that i have and now so it's possible to become aware
that there's the object we see there's the eyes that are seeing
and then there's kind of in between some of you might have more sense that it's in the mind behind the eyes or something
but in the tr um between the two there's the or in addition to the two
there's the way we're knotted up those things are
entangled with each other that our ways the way that we're looking is not
relaxed and easily useful but we're looking in a way that is caught or
preoccupied or concerned with what we're looking at and
and then and it becomes stressful in the eyes eyes become locked they get tight they'll get tired
they've lost this relaxed way of being so one of the reasons to cultivate
mindfulness of seeing is to learn develop capacity for this
relaxed gaze so that we become more sensitive
to the knots when they occur and and so
this is not like an incidental exercise that the buddha is giving but rather it's another perspective
from which we can become aware of all the ways we get attached
all every attachment is an attachment that at scent stores
at some particular scent store and as we become aware of each of the different scent stores it's a different kind of
angle to become aware of attachment itself so it's sometimes it's with what we see
sometimes with what we hear taste smell touch and then the mind door is a big one and
and so uh in this particular exercise satipattana it's going through very
carefully repeatedly each of the six of these scent stores
and talking about uh seeing the scent store seeing seeing the object
now for this first one side object knowing the eye that's seeing
knowing the not that that's between them and more than that in
in the in style of how this teaching goes it's also knowing the manner in which
that that um that of seeing it appear
and see and then letting go of it and the seeing
the appearance of a knot is uh when it first occurs is this amazing uh vantage point
where it's easier to let go so relax seeing
noticing how the eyes get locked in knotted up
but noticing just as it occurs and then letting it go so for today as you go about your day
next 24 hours you might give a special attention to seeing
and see what if you can learn greater ways of looking
in in a relaxed way calm looking relaxed looking
where the eyes can kind of look at things and study them even but do it in a very
relaxed receptive mode and that as you kind of get a hang of
that maybe then you can start noticing when the eyes are not that way when they're
locked in or straining or something and that is the knot
and maybe you can let go of it so
that's the introduction to this topic of this week the mindfulness at the six
cent stores so thank you