hello friends hello and welcome to
two wires being overlapped okay here hi good morning good afternoon good good
evening whatever time zone you're in lovely to be with you in this moment in time
um on this day and uh as we bring
this week of exploring karma together this important profound
teaching of karma not as something intellectual
as something to be afraid of something unknown magical weird strange
but something a teaching that can
empower us right here right now in our lives
the way we live the way we show up the way we serve
the way this being is in this world so as an empowerment karma is an empowerment so
so without further ado let's sit together and i have some reflections um prepared
of course for uh for later for the dharmet so i'd like to invite you to
to land to arrive in your posture
here here
this moment of intention
intending gently intending doesn't have to be
heavy as a hammer can be a gentle [Music]
turning towards peace towards awareness towards stillness
towards kindness
ah an action of the body
mind and heart to release to release and let go
to arrive here wakefully
and landing you're releasing
the holding in the mind releasing releasing
landing here and releasing any tension in the body
any wholeness in the body
inhabiting
this moment in time fully expansively
with an expansive heart
just here trusting trusting that
if we are intending
inclining our hearts our minds to awareness to kindness in this moment and
meeting whatever arises
with awareness kindness peace
acceptance
when the future moments whatever they hold future moments become present moment
trusting in this capacity to meet them too in the
same way building
sowing seeds of trust
through this moments of awareness
peace inclining to peace the body
releasing the mind the heart releasing letting go
inclining to peace here
and knowing peace
tasting even if for just one moment
letting go tasting peace
in this moment here
so it's seeds are replanting in this moment in this moment right here
wake up what are you planting right now
becoming aware choosing to plant wholesome seeds
it's that simple
if you find the mind lost in thoughts or engaged in
thoughts emotions contracted in ways that are not helpful
become aware become kindly aware not resistantly
not grudgingly
but kindly aware
release release what's not profitable in this life
for you for others in this moment
it was a thought of ill will perhaps judgment towards yourself towards others
maybe let there be a thought of kindness
planting a seed of kindness intentionally with intention
kindness forgiveness generosity for yourself or others
for the world releasing releasing
giving
planting wholesome karma both in the way you become aware
not with aversion but with kindness
in the action of the mind
that then follows into peace into good will
into awareness presence here here
begin again and again and again if needed it's okay
and as we bring this sit so close together
let there be a moment of appreciation planting the seed
of gratitude appreciation for yourself for the sangha for the opportunity
to come together and to practice whatever arose or did not arise
in these 30 minutes
you have showed up you've done your best
let there be kindness
appreciation for the goodness that has been created
has been co-created with generosity offering
sharing that merit that goodness with all beings everywhere
all that we do our life is not
for us to keep any goodness of it it's an act of service it's an act of
goodness to be shared
others so offering this practice to this act of
goodness may be a support for all beings everywhere
and cultivating goodness kindness freedom for myself and all beings everywhere
may all beings be free including myself
thank you for your practice hello and
welcome friends so
so this week we have been exploring the teachings of karma together
and i'd like to share just a few minutes of review of what we've covered this week
so that if you feel inspired if you've missed any of the talks or if you feel inspired to go back
you can and also i'll add a few more teachings
today so so
karma not as a teaching of this magical
something that has been passed down from some previous life and whether i'm doing
well or poorly or others oh it's the fault of what they did in the past life ouch ouch very painful way to
to um contract around that teaching but actually to see it
as an empowerment as an empowering teaching of how our intentions actions here and now
can form can shape who we are who we become how we serve in
the next moment and the next moment and the next moment which is actually quite
concordant with what neuroscience nowadays tells us about how plastic how plastic our
brain we are we're so plastic in our actions the way we behave and act it changes it
it shifts the river of our thoughts our actions
and the way we who we become in the world so we talked about the three aspects
of karma karma's action there's the leading edge which is the intention there is the
action itself is the doing it's the doing which is the doing of the mind
thoughts are considered actions of the mind there's the doing in the mind actions of speech actions of the body
and then there's the trailing edge of the action what is left what is made uh
what is left these ossified karmic relics that we create and we leave in
our bodies minds would become and the image of a potter that's intending to
create a shaping forming and then leaves it leaves the creation in the cul in the
kiln and becomes ossified so in that way we create all these momentums all these
relics so we then talked about the next day we
talked about how wakefulness how actually changing
our karma in every moment intending to wake up and make another
choice is possible through mindfulness when you are mindful
not just on the cushion but in daily life so then the practice of karma
awareness and shifting your karma doesn't isn't just limited to sitting
silently on the cushion but it becomes a daily life practice daily life practice of awareness awareness each moment what
am i thinking oh sweetheart do you really want to be thinking about that do you really want to beat that dead
horse that you've been beating for 10 years and it's not really helping you're helping you or helping anyone so moments
of awareness with kindness darling please please let's let's try something
differently may you be well may i be well planting seeds of kindness
and then we talked about it's not so much the what the object in
awareness that arises but how we relate to it it's the way that we engage
that really shapes and forms the karma it's it's our engagement it's the our reaction or reactivity or or or the way
we interact with some so it's our engagement that emotional quality of our engagement the actions of the mind and
heart how we intend and engage that really shape and form and again concordant with neuroscience
in the ways that emotion when there is an emotion regarding an event an object in in the sensory
space it it actually it fixes it more in place in terms of a pattern
yesterday we talked about rebirth
reconsidering rebirth re-imagining rebirth um if rebirth were true it
wouldn't be uh again this magical thing perhaps or or this thing that we are uh powerless
against but in the way of gratitude as if we have an ancestor
at the same way we have physical ancestors we have this perhaps ancestor that has
sent us um some that sent us goodness and sent us
into the future and how can we how can we what we have received how can we make the best of this
karmic potentiality how can we make it pretty uh with with beautiful thoughts
beautiful wholesome seeds and pass it down and and with the teachings of
the self being made of causes and conditions it's it's really um the idea of rebirth
really becomes an understanding of gratitude and understanding of
appreciation and understanding of generosity how can we pass and how can
we make this karma as beautiful as shining as possible and pass it down to
this other human being who's going to have a different nationality and perhaps gender identity and color and
circumstances and different sets of neuroses and ah we want to give pass on
the best to this to this child to this quote-unquote child of ours so different
different way to perhaps if you wish to relate to that and what i wanted to bring in today in
the time that's limited left after this brief uh summary is um
is that there is a lot more detail there's a lot more of course in the teachings of about the teachings of
karma and um and in fact i pulled out that this book
by my my teacher um the workings of karma by venerable pox ida so you could
go let's see how many pages is this 370 something uh 400 you can read 400 pages
on karma the workings of karma and yet what is really really important
is how this moments really this moment's action
is conditioning the next and the next and the next with awareness really
that's practically that's what we need to engage with in our lives
but just to bring a little more detail here um there are many different types of
classifications in the um
in the teaching especially in the abidama in visudi maga in the higher teachings
there are many different types of classifications of types of karma i'm going to share just
one type of classification which i think is actually helpful uh for us the way to
relate to it so the cl this classification is
according to priority of effect and there are four different types
so one is the the heaviest the highest priority level is called weighty karma
or garuka karma and weighty karma can either be actually
good karma good weighty karma karma that has heavy weight but it's good and it's
good or or unwholesome karma and
for um on wholesome in in the teachings the the
weighty unwholesome karma is considered um killing one's parents and
and um um murder of of a fully enlightened being for example and and also a permanent uh
actually um a creation of schism in the saga is also
considered weighty sangha now to think about this actually in in
neuroscience terms there are some actions that have are so heavy are so heavy not just for ourselves but for
everyone else they have consequences so if you create a schism for example in a
community oh that has repercussions for yourself and for everybody else so we can see why that's number one in terms
of weighty karma and in terms of a weighty
wholesome karma their moments of awakening of course is is a wholesome
way to karma moments of awakening freedom peace uh deep states of absorption etc
then number two is a proximate uh proximate karma
so proximate karma um the teachings actually teach talk about that in terms of the what do you remember the
immediately the moment before you die the proximate karma for the next rebirth but actually it's a lot more general so
proximate karma we can observe it and really see and in the neuroscience terms
if you've been uh say grumpy if you've been or you've been thinking let's say ill will thoughts
then there is proximate karma if the la if the previous moment you've been angry and upset the chances are that the next
moment you're going to be angry and upset right it's the proximate karma's the proximate moment the mind moment
mind moments the approximate karmics it's what really gives shapes to how you
show up how you act so interesting to observe these in your own actions
in your daily life the third one is habitual karma achina
karma the last one was asana karma so number three is habitual achina karma
um habitual karma again that makes sense too right what you do most habitually if
you say after you after you work maybe you just turn on the
television or watch netflix for hours and that's just habitually what you do well when you
finish working for example oh that's what habitually you have done you will do you will do
so habitual karma and then the last the last one is called reserve or cumulative karma and and this
kind of is kind of a catch-all uh category in in in this buddhist
categories um and it's basically because it literally means because done so all
the actions that were not included in the previous categories and these are so if if the weighty karma if the ones
that's really heavy and if the ones that's proximate and if the ones that's habitual if none of those actually form
or shape this moment's experience maybe something you've done in the past something that has been done
anyway but if none of these other ones have very strong impact then something
you have done in the past some tendency of the mind that is not immediate that is not necessarily habitual and it's not
heavy but but has been done in the past so it's something that you can think or something that you tend to do
that is what finds fruition so i i can i think of these uh
categorization as being helpful as to ways to study and really see our own
actions and how the way we think we act we intend in the world can shape the
next moment and all of these how they interact again there are many different
ways um classifications and just to say at the end that it is
said that at the night of his enlightenment the buddha um before he was
enlightened awakened his mind woke up and he saw the workings of karma the
both so and karma is deeply connected with dependent origination
with the laws of causality so these teachings are intertwined and he woke up
to seeing the workings of karma which are complicated and yet what all we need to know really
for us for our liberation for how we this being lives and
and serves and is happy or unhappy and causes happiness unhappiness
in the world for all beings present and future is
just awareness in this moment what are we doing what are we planting in this moment
so so thank you dear ones thank you for your presence
thank you for your practice thank you for your awareness your your attention this past week
um it's been an honor to share these teachings with you these beautiful
teachings and i wish you well i wish you wholesome
karma wholesome deeds happy happy actions
happy results for the sake of yourself for the sake of
um all beings everywhere and future selves past selves present selves all the
selves that we are in every moment so thank you all
thank you and let's dedicate the merit of a week of practice
may all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere including ourselves
may they wake up to their own goodness to the capacity to
the capacity to wake up and to be free and to be of service
may all beings be free
thanks everyone be well