so so hello hello friends hello it's good to sit with you it's good to
practice together in this moment in time however
however the day has been for you so far whether it's been a
day with ease whether it's been a challenging day
and um it's nice to come together it's nice to
come together and practice so so for the practice in this moment last
last time on friday it was long long ago
we explored the practice of compassion
combined with mindfulness of the breath anapanasati mindfulness of the breath
and um really figure figuring that combining those two
practices uh is a way to practice tongue glen which is this beautiful compassion
practice in um [Music] in the later schools of buddhism
so so for today um let us continue practicing prac the
engaging with the practices of compassion for ourselves for others um for
however we are doing in this moment or have been doing the challenges
and the goodnesses as well as for other beings it is said that
this famous quote be kind for
[Music] for everyone you meet is fighting a difficult battle
for everyone you meet is fighting a difficult battle
at times we might think oh everybody has it figured out they're just
as happy as a climb in this shell and they have no problems in their world in their life
and oh it's only me only me poor me oh but guess what
everybody everybody in this in this life in this
world is fighting a tough battle in different ways we may not know
what other people are dealing with we only know our
psyche we only know our bodies we only know our story
but but but so
so cultivating compassion cultivating kindness can we bring more kindness to ourselves
can we bring more kindness to others can we imbue every interaction with kindness with
compassion knowing that everyone is having a tough time
in some way i mean we all have a you know put on a facade of yeah
everything is going well and maybe things are going well not to say everything it's challenge everything is doom and groom i don't want to give that
impression at all there are many many joys there are ten thousand joys and ten
thousand sorrows so appreciating the joys in our lives
bowing the joys the goodness
and and also having tenderness instead of taking out
the whip and self-flagellating ah having tenderness
and maybe i'll i'll add one last thing before turning our practice towards compassion is that
um if you forget everything i say tonight
remember one thing whenever you're having
a difficult time whenever you're hurting whenever
it's it seems hard either your body seems hard life seems hard
something seems hard we often don't recognize that we often
not to say every time but we often don't recognize that we often think ah
this is terrible you know get it together come on get let's get going you're not you're not
working hard enough you're being sharp enough or you're doing so we actually respond to when we're having a tough
time with trying to push ourselves further and or or turning
towards what is is challenging either with harshness with it shouldn't be this way pushing it away either pushing
ourselves away you're bad or pushing the difficulty away
that ouch that we feel that ouch is a signal ouch i'm hurting
right now i'm hurting right now this is hard this is hard
this is the time to bring in compassion ouch i'm hurting right now
this is hard and when we learn that we can also be the same way with others
ouch they're hurting right now they're having a hard time they're not just being difficult they're
having a hard time this is the best they can do given the causes and conditions
that's all i want to say to frame so so with that
with that let's let's begin let's begin
let's land in our bodies
let's arrive in this moment
in this body letting go of the words
letting go
if your mind wants to think right now and figure it out or still is processing
what happened in the day or or plan what's happening later tonight
or tomorrow can you bow smilingly
at this overactive mind it's doing just what minds do
and say sweetheart sweetheart dear mind it's okay dear
ah you can let go it's all right you can let go right now
you can let go let's release
release the entanglements right now and just relax
take refuge all these beautiful r words release
relax take refuge
release
release the mind relax the body
take refuge in the heart i'll say it again
release the mind
relax the body
take refuge in the heart
let's do that a few minutes see which one is needed more releasing
relaxing or taking refuge
releasing thoughts
relaxing the body
taking refuge in the heart
spending a few more minutes tilling the soil
collecting collecting
with mindfulness in the body with heart
now i'd like to invite you if you would bring to mind something
from today it could be in this moment perhaps
something that was challenging for you in your body in your mind
the emotional space perhaps or physical space relational space
maybe it was an instance where you didn't quite recognize you were suffering
and instead you took out the proverbial stick and
started to beat yourself up for not being enough
no such an instance comes to mind it's okay maybe it's just something that was
challenging for you or is challenging physically maybe a pain ache emotionally
see if you can really recognize the ouch ouch sweetheart
this is hard anyone anyone [Music]
going through this would be having a hard time this is not easy
just like anyone else would be hurting would be
feeling challenged i too just like anyone else
feel challenged hurt tender
by this recognizing the ouch it's not your weakness you're not bad
so many causes and conditions have together have come together this is difficult
and is it possible to recognize this
recognize yourself and hold yourself with care
as if you're holding a younger version of yourself
just having a hard time and recognize them in this image
there's both the honoring of the strength
of the empowered you the older you the one who is a source of compassion as well as
honoring acknowledging the tenderness the hurt both of them together
not just the hurt not just the strength both together
and see if a loving
version of you can hold a younger perhaps
tender challenged version of you it's okay sweetheart it's okay this is
hard and it's okay it's all right
it's okay i'm here for you
i see you i love you
and i see that this is difficult and it's okay it's okay
it's okay
you're doing the best you can you're doing the best you can
under the circumstances
if you could have done any better if you could do any better
given all the causes and conditions
you would have
trust trust
holding nurturing [Music]
soothing supporting
healing with each breath
let the image imagery be as vivid as possible
without making it too much work
now bringing to mind one interaction you've had with someone
today it could be in person virtual a phone call read email
some interaction you've had with another human being
maybe it was challenging interaction and maybe an easy one
doesn't matter let's bring to mind that everyone you meet
is fighting a difficult battle just like me this person has challenges i may not
know what they are i may not know what they are but i can
be sure they have challenges in their life it's part of being human
their body maybe
in their emotional space relationships something else who knows
and there's always old age sickness and death the heavenly messengers
that visit visit us or our loved ones
can you hold this being this person you've had an interaction with today
especially if it were jack who was challenging with compassion with care oh you too
fellow human being whatever your challenges i wish you
leaves just as i wish ease
just as i recognize my own ouch without judgment without adding salt to
my wound i offer you kindness i offer you
recognition and compassion may you have ease may you be well
may you be free from whatever is challenging
are you carried with grace
may not be in my control my power to solve what's challenging for me and for you
but i can be kind i can offer kindness
compassion
it's easier than i think to offer to myself and to you
you have well-being may you have ease
i wish you peace well-being peace midst of whatever is challenging for you
notice how good it can feel for our own heart
our own body to extend care compassion [Music]
ease to others
expanding expanding our circle a warmth of care
of extending wishes for ease peace safety
to all beings everywhere all beings
having challenges in this life
especially those right now living
in war zones with lack of safety with uncertainty
oh dear fellow human beings
this must be so hard in ways
can't even fathom wish you ease
wish you safety may you be free
from this sorrow this pain this challenge
you have ease grace in the midst of
this difficulty holding witness with each breath
holding witness without toppling into sorrow and grief
holding witness with each breath
surya khan said oh if only my monks robes were wide enough
if only my robes were wide enough
to cover to protect all the suffering beings in this entire
world
holding witness with care with compassion with each breath
machine safety and ease
may all pinks everywhere all pigs in all conditions
including myself this being who's me
may all beings everywhere have ease and they have well-being may they be
safe may they have ease in the midst of from
difficulties may they be happy may they be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone
so today's practice we started as always
by landing by arriving and the offering tonight which you can
take if it was helpful for you was the three r's
releasing releasing thoughts releasing the mind
relaxing the body and taking refuge in the heart
then we turned our attention to something that was challenging for
ourselves to recognize the out and to hold that with care with compassion
not with judgment then we turned our attention our
awareness to someone we had an interaction with today to hold them with care and compassion
and then we extend it to all beings especially those who are
in living [Music] in war zones
in the war zone especially at this time of turmoil in our world
and and many invitations along the way and
i'd love to hear what worked what didn't and especially if you haven't shared if you haven't
spoken for a while if you have put your voice in the space i invite you
to pull back from raising your hand you're welcome to type in chat
and if you haven't spoken for a while i'd love to invite you to pull forward
what did you observe what happened for the benefit of yourself to be held witness
and for the benefit of others if there was a discovery an aha moment
or maybe that was something that was challenging
and if you type in chat if you type to me alone i won't read your name it'll be private
reflection if it's typed to everyone i'll read your name as it is public
and as i'm waiting if you wish to share for with others what's come up for you
um [Music] say that one thing i invited you to
notice was the sense of of nourishment the sense of feeling good
when we extend when behold with compassion what's arising for us
challenges and also what's arising for others difficulty of others it can be quite healing soothing
compassion feels good the practice of compassion it's not supposed to be sad
or difficult or painful that's empathetic distress that's when we fall
into sorrow without balancing it with kindness and good will
so did you notice did you notice this nourishment of ease of
sucker of soothing again if you haven't shared in a while
you're welcome to raise your hand
say if you haven't spoken last week and the chat is open too
bill says tried feeling compassion for someone i had a bad interaction with
felt guilty instead then went back to trying to feel compassion for myself
great great
yay bill that is very wise that is very wise because we don't always have
control over the emotions that come up you know you're trying to feel compassion and
then you feel guilty like you can't and brilliant that you then you turned to
yourself with compassion like oh dear feeling guilty ouch this is painful ouch this
instead of well i'm not supposed to feel guilty this is what's not supposed to come up so great beautiful
one more um reflection my fear and my nurturing both
come from my heart so i found myself holding my heart with my heart oh that's
lovely thank you for that reflection beautiful esther
oh hi hi um i attended a prayer session this morning
for ukraine and uh people were sending compassion
to all involved and uh i noticed i got
very angry when one person was offering
good wishes to putin
so much judgment came up so much anger
i i couldn't go there i mean i couldn't go to feeling compassion for prudence
but as i'm sitting here thinking about it i could feel compassion for the person who
was saying that uh
and of course for everyone who's suffering in that in that warsaw
yeah yeah yeah i appreciate you praying the dubas
there so so what i heard you say is that the prayer service you attended for ukraine and
someone was offering compassion for putin and that brought up anger for you
and and you know how could you have compassion for this person who's causing harm and
and yet there was compassion for the person who did that and for everyone who's impacted did i hear that correctly
ascension um it was actually i was
i'm not sure if i heard you correctly i wasn't i was feeling compassion for the person
who was offering compassion for approval here's
yeah yeah thanks for sharing that and it's important i'm glad you brought this up because what's what i'd like to share
is that um let's take a bigger perspective and you
may not be ready for it right now esther so don't push it and yet let me offer this as a perspective
that often we have this limited viewpoint and and yet with the bigger perspective
with a bigger perspective you know i hold putin with compassion
too like ouch ouch the ripples of his actions the karmic impact ouch of what
he's doing just it it i feel pained in a bigger level
in the bigger in the in in a more transcendent view of life and
death and humanity our actions the ripple of our actions through generations through lives this person
who's causing so harm so much harm to himself and to others karmically ouch
ouch so maybe i'll just leave leave it at that and i'm not trying to convince you of anything but just to plan to see for
when there might be ready to readiness for a different perspective to rise is that okay
yeah thanks yes that's okay yeah so um
[Music] we so i see other hands i see more reflections and just to say
need to leave enough time for our practice together so i'm going to
quickly go to the reflections and the written one actually tell you what
how it to do how to you know what maybe i think it's
time let's turn let's turn to small group practice because i want to make sure we have time
and that's important 650 that's the time we always turn to small group practice so let's turn to that and i'll come back
to the reflections that you've shared in in chat if there's time afterwards so
so i will create the the rooms and um let's hold ourselves let's hold
each other with compassion uh taking care of yourself taking care of each other
the small groups wear it deep deep practice happens so i've created the rooms take care of
yourselves take care of each other and opening them here we go
the rooms are now closed everybody's back we just have about a minute and i wanted
to just share a couple of reflections that uh you shared before i went into the rooms
pepper said upon reflection saw that there was a point in my day when i had to push through to finish a project by
deadline even though my body was really needing a break happy that i didn't whip myself to do it
but rather was aware of the discomfort while continuing to do what i had to do nice thanks for sharing that yay that's
a great practice report yay and ah
and shinny says shame that i gave someone else an ouch ah yeah and that's something when shame
comes up of course turning as bill was reporting turning the the compassion back to oneself to hold the
pain that's arising um one more reflection anonymously this one this meditation was deeply
connecting to both release and refuge and wonder how to stay with the sorrow
of the war that brings tears to my eyes but not toppling and the last last couple of reflections
um also deborah saying i've included putin in my meta list referring to the
conversation earlier if someone like him acts in the way he is acting he must be suffering must need
the same thing we all need that is true indeed it is said that hurt people hurt people
hurt people hurt people and it is so true it is so true if people were not hurt
they wouldn't hurt others uh lastly from sarah thank you for this
space of practice it was challenging but i think it was good so it's oh we're
out of time thank you all for engaging with the practice tonight
may may it have been nourishing healing
for you and may it support you and support others in the
way that we all show up in the world may all beings be well may all wings and beings including
ourselves be free
[Music] thanks everyone take good care
see you on wednesday