so tonight i want to talk about
dharma gladness dharma joy
and there's lots of different flavors or ways of experiencing dharma joy but
and we'll talk a little bit about that different kinds but in particular i want to talk about um
dukkha and faith and their relationship to dharma joy
and just to kind of give you a little bit of a description
and a simile of what um i'm feeling into through my practice
around this is kind of uh imagine that um
the dharma joy the dharma gladness that i'm talking about is um
it's just that little those little like many off often many smaller moments
of uh delight surprise connection
that feeling of being fully present right of like wow feeling the sun on the skin
something really simple or a bird right landing somewhere where you can see or
um just that somebody's eyes making connection with yours right just
it can be um it's it's a really a moment of meeting
meeting our experience in the moment and it comes with some degree of upswelling
and so i kind of have this image of
maybe a river or something um that's flowing right the present moment of
flowing this movement and then there's all these little
tributaries or kind of it's funny in my imagination um
the river is up higher than these other things this is just because of the feeling of it right
and sometimes we're more in the muck of
things we're more in the mind and worry and more in the dukkha of life
and it doesn't feel like we're gliding along in that sort of clean smooth
feeling joyous kind of presence
but there can be this kind of weak might be
kind of in the muck a bit and something can happen something can come along something can shift and we
can feel this upwelling this upwelling and this lift and then we get to be in that current of
the moment and so um
this is sort of like the simile is you know the slower
muckier places can be where we get stuck in things and we're having some degree of suffering or we're
clinging and we're just not really in the flow
and as we're going along if we remember if we notice what's happening if we have some clarity about what's going on
if we see we're suffering the first noble truth we might be able to recognize what we're
clinging to what we're holding on to and when we see
we're clinging when we see with wisdom that we're kind of stuck
if we have been practicing and we've watched this dynamic we know
we know that if we keep clinging it's only going to get worse
and so we let go and then that letting go is that
possible moment of upswelling the faith the belief that if i shift in how i'm relating to
my experience yeah i can move more freely
so this is the little simile that i'll kind
of come back to and i'm going to
move through these three things this the dukkha the faith and then the dharma joy
and i'm going to read you a little short quote about the joy and then i'm going to talk
about the suffering and then the faith and then back to the joy
so tar brock says that joy arises when we are open to both the
beauty and suffering inherent in living like a great sky that includes all
different types of weather joy is an expansive quality of presence
it says yes to life no matter what
so saying no to life might be the equivalent of suffering
right when we say no to what's happening
in the dhammapada there's a couple of verses that kind of talk about the mind and
happiness and they go like this the mind hard to control
flighty a lighting where it wishes one does well to tame
the disciplined mind brings happiness the disciplined mind brings happiness
here's another one the mind heart con to control flighting a lighting where it wishes
one does well to tame the watched mind brings happiness
when it comes to dukkha and kind of seeing where we are caught in life
sayadaw utinia says we need to learn our lesson there's no shortcut
we really have to find a way to relate to our suffering in a way that
you know helps us choose joy choose happiness instead
so watching the mind right learning to watch the mind and
sort of like watching your footsteps you know choosing where you're going to place your feet we can
be like that with our minds we can choose what what trains of thought we're going
to follow what rivers we're going to choose to ride
and as we watch the mind and see kind of get to know its contents its habits its patterns
that's it's like you know in that boat on the river we become more skilled
getting more and more clear oh if i go down this tributary it's going to be really sticky
and we should we can choose not to go that way
the buddha um talked about five spiritual powers or five spiritual
faculties and that these are said to be incredibly important for our practice to move
forward and they are faith energy mindfulness concentration and
wisdom and they're progressive um we start with
faith it's necessary for us to step into the practice
and it's like an on-ramp it's on the on-ramp to the flow
and um
so what happens when we get caught and are suffering you know why why don't we
just if we know the way out why don't we always just choose to
be happy or easy or whatever not so not so simple but
made me think about um like this idea can you think about a moment
a very mild stress suffering dukkha you might have experienced recently
and just notice whether you were aware of it
and then notice if there was any tendency to either kind of just resign
or resist either just say oh
well i'm gonna just do it wrong anyway so i might as well just go for it and be you know
suffer here or you know no i don't want it to happen
that way i don't want it to go this way i don't want to feel the way i'm feeling the resistance
very often when suffering happens we either give up resign or get
indifferent or we rebel or resist it's very often our response is
well mine is it yours you notice is that familiar
in your practice to that sense of resigning giving in or
giving up or resisting trying to fight reality
i saw one head nod yes does that mean i'm not not talking i want to make sure i'm talking to all of you
all of you i need to change what i'm saying if i'm not getting you right right so
okay so there's an alternative
relationship we can have which is this one that you know when
when we see suffering when we start to learn to see it as
um oh i'm holding on to something i'm struggling i'm hurting
it's like feedback it's that simple it can be seen so simply as just
stop wait look what's happening notice pay attention
wake up a simile for suffering that i really like is um
similar to the river thing but this is on the side of a freeway
highway usually you ever drive down the highway and you start to
veer off the road and you hit those rumble strips on the side that kind of like make your tires
vibrate and your car bounce really quickly i kind of think about suffering is like
rumble strips it's when we're veering off the course when we're moving you know moving off
the path it's like this natural feedback that we're
going the wrong way and we can [Music]
we can resist and just keep trying to you know
drive on the rumble strips because we think we should be able to drive over there you
know or we can give up and drive off the road right or we can go
oh this is really irritating but thank you for waking me up
thank you for like giving me feedback that i'm about to drive off the road here
doesn't mean we can think you know we have to feel like it's a pleasant experience or
but we can be grateful we can have faith that they're placed there for a reason that they're there to
help us stay on the road we have a choice
another way yeah i like to think about the this relationship with suffering is a very
from a very uh kind of a i guess a therapy-minded position which
is um when we are when we're hurt
when we're you know in a situation where we're being harmed
the fight-or-flight response comes up right which is typically
we either fight it right so we're resisting it same thing
or we're running away right those are the two main responses
to being attacked or harmed to fight or to run
and then the other response is to freeze right when we haven't been effectively
able to escape or fight back we tend to go into a neurological state
of freezing and to me this is kind of the same thing it's just that the
dukkha that we're experiencing in life or the stress is is not something you know
like being attacked but our nervous system responds similarly
so if we can start to see suffering in a
different way maybe a radically different way
we can see that it's like it could potentially be that on ramp
to joy it helps us
see we have a choice and if we know we don't have to suffer
if we know we get to choose it's really natural to feel a sense of
faith and hope right when we recognize i can do something
right here i can shift how i'm relating to what's happening
there's a wow like how amazing is that
and that can be like a that transition from the suffering with
the faith to that joy
so the faith is what grows in us as we start to see ourselves over and over again
um seeing how we make things life make life more difficult for ourselves or easier
for ourselves right when we engage with the practice and we're paying attention to our lives
we can notice what the practice does for us it we can notice that it helps us
be more present be more connected be less afraid
be less anxious be more open
some of the things that also can support our faith in the practice are reflections on the buddha the dharma and
the sangha right so the teacher who got free the dharma the teachings
and the sangha this is a sangha look at this the source of inspiration
aspiration support and can help us grow our faith
i think faith grows in when we we take in this kind of goodness
take in the goodness of the practice
and said that in the samyutta nikaya it is faith that is one's partner
and wisdom that instructs
and faith is one's greatest wealth
do you feel you have faith in the dharma the sangha or the buddha
do you feel you have faith in your practice and that it can help you or that you've seen
others does that support you yeah
it's a precious precious thing for us and um
yeah you know seeing even seeing somebody else in their goodness or seeing how they've changed through
their practice can grow our faith when we can't see it in ourselves
keep looking around
so this faith is the supporting condition for gladness for joy
it helps us stay on the path stay present and helps us keep choosing this radical
act of turning toward turning toward turning toward
and lamont she wrote she has a quote i'm going to read for you which
i love she says almost everyone is screwed up
broken clingy scared and yet designed for joy
not great i think that's just such the greatest quote just you know we've all got the
stuff going on and we're designed for joy it's right there it's right in us the capacity
to experience connect to feel and i don't just mean like you know you
don't have to be like fireworks going off just that that feeling of that flow that feeling
of presence that feeling of it can be like wonder right aw
appreciation joy is the heart celebration of life
and uh
anthony demello says that you know
so there's this idea that we've gotta say yes to the joys and the sorrows right to connect with life we don't get
to say no to the dukkha if we shut down to difficulty we shut ourselves down to joy
as well right we have to sort of learn how to be with it all
so anthony demelo says when there is absolute cooperation with the inevitable
this is when we're really in our practice absolute cooperation
with the inevitable this idea that where we're not trying to
resist that we're already depressed resist that we're already
anything we're here we're right here we're in our moment and when there's absolute
cooperation with okay here it is right this this that is kind of like
that on-ramp to the freeway to the joy
we we can't divide the present moment into good parts and bad parts
we disconnect one from one we disconnect from both no i don't mean
i don't mean we aren't discerning in our lives i don't mean i mean talking about meeting that the
moment this moment that's already arising i don't mean don't be discerning about
your plans or your jobs or who you do things with
discern discern discern choose wisely but you know once we're here
we're here this is it you know this is it
this is now this is what we've got so once we're right here
we don't get to press erase life is additive not subtractive
so joy is that openness that includes both the joys and sorrows aliveness and openness available to the whole play of
existence the thing to remember is um
you know joy and gladness don't come first right um fearlessness follows fear
practice follows forgetfulness seeing follows not seeing
peace follows truth you know it's like the gladness can follow the suffering
the faith and the suffering it doesn't have to come first right
faith is there to help us remember help us see there's another way
an alternate route a different way than habitually responding and reacting
there's a man named ross gay and he wrote a book called the book of delights and he
he decided to write this book and so he went about it like every day going into
life looking for little delights and of course it was a wonderful experience for him
because the more he looked the more he saw right and he's just like
tumbling into delight after delight but one of the amazing things that he
says that he puts together is that our suffering and our our joy
are not so separate and one of the things he says is what if we joined our sorrows
what if we joined our sorrows i'm saying i'm saying what if that is joy
when we really come to ourselves really come to this experience we join
it instead of resist it
what what kind of a mindset would write such a thing right
what has he experienced that he could say that
i wonder you know i i was thinking about this and
i thought about being with somebody who was dying actually
somebody who i love deeply and being with them
so present with them right so here you know this is a sorrow right this is
a loss and being with him and being in that
sorrow with him was a joy it was such a joy it was so alive
he was dying but what does that mean he was the most alive person i knew at the time
joko beck charlotte joko back she has some nice quotes on
joy and differentiating it from happiness and she says joy doesn't mean the same thing as
happiness happiness is the up up up
i like that up up up joy
is the peace and what is
the reality is that when we experience the moment fully for whatever it is joy
is revealed you want me to read that again yeah okay
joy doesn't mean the same thing as happiness happiness is the up up up
joy is the peace and what is the reality is that when we experience
the moment fully for whatever it is joy is revealed
yeah so like how do we have that mindset
right what do we need to do to support ourselves you know
i like the quote right from from was it tony morrison designed
designed for joy what if we believe we're designed for
joy that it's right there that it's right there that it's
accessible that it naturally arises
it's not something that we have to make happen
rather we have to be available for it willing
to let go into it to receive it
and there's something right there a friend was talking about
uh giving a talk on dharmajoy and how everybody was so resistant to feeling
joy for me that's that negative negativity
bias in our brain right there's this part of our brain that's always more biased toward the
threat what might be negative and it just wants to pay more attention
to that so this is where i think we have to make ourselves available we
have to recognize that deeply ingrained survival strategy
that's not doing us so good anymore and step back
and go okay yes yes to joy yes to gladness yes to receiving a teeny
tiny moment a sip instead of maybe 24 ounce or
super size me drink right it's it's it's a small bit maybe bit by bit but how do
we keep saying yes right
so i want to just invite you to take a moment close your eyes
and just just see if you can connect see if your mind can offer you
a memory or the imagination
of an experience of this kind of dharma joy that gladness or happiness
this aliveness maybe even might be a word that could be used
it often feels spontaneous
just sort of like a gift that pops up
just connecting with that whatever comes up and notice what does it feel like in
your body as you recall or imagine
what do you notice how willing are you to sip it
to breathe into it to let it soak in to come in deep
how quickly is the mind ready to dismiss it and rewrite it or move on
maybe also take a moment just thinking about the rest of your
evening tonight imagine what it would be like if you
really received
the teeny tiny little gifts of ease and well-being
just the softness of a pillow or a blanket
the flavor of your toothpaste or the clean
clean water that you drink clean water what a gift
what would it be like to really open to each of these little
sips tonight and lay down and put your head on your pillow and
just feel it flowing through you all these little gifts
may it be so for you may it be so
i wonder if any of you um would like to share anything
about a question or reflection at this point
we're winding up i have a few more quotes i can share but if there's anybody that feels
inspired to share anything right now i'd like to create space for that
jim has a microphone so if anybody wants it he will bring it to
you
okay here we go thank you
thank you tanya um i think you're right that
when i'm meditating and i feel
a moment of [Music] mindfulness or awareness
i think there is some joy there but i think that what happens is that i
i do tend to dismiss it and and to say um
oh well this is this is the the most that i can that i can feel and there's and there's
so much more that i'm not able to access
rather than just appreciating the joy that is there
thank you for sharing that it's like it's sort of again this image of this river and you
know you're we're skimming we get a little bump right and then it's like but i didn't get all the way over there you know but it's
that it's just like oh you feel the bump feel the little bump and just be like
sweet just oh thank you yes let me say yes to
you not no no no no then it goes like it goes like that no no no you know back
down in the muck and then it's back slow slow slow come back and then you got another little bump and you know it's
like this process right where we just not good enough should be better
[Music] yeah i just appreciate what you shared so much thank you
yeah yes saying yes yes to the gifts yes
little little ones are good anyone else feel
interested here we go thank you this is funny what came up uh when you
were speaking about joy was um i always park about the same place uh
when i go to my office it's about five minutes from my office and i walk on this nice uh residential street and
there's something about i think like getting out of my car in the business of
listening to whatever i'm listening to and just uh seeing the birds or seeing the sun often
and just having those five minutes
just brings me right there
yeah one of my most profound i shouldn't call it that but a very
memorable retreat experience was just walking meditation
right but then a little bird was in the bush and it popped out
and i just was had the gift of a flood of like delight
it was such a simple thing but you know here i maybe was just practicing with trying to
be present so i could receive the gift but it was really profound
really small little things very moving and helpful right starting your day that
way every day what a nice choice what a nice gift
anyone else feel inspired
thank you natalia thank you dear sangha um i really appreciate
you showing the difference between happiness and joy because i feel like happiness
is almost like a semi-permanent or permanent expected expected state of being that i've never been able to get
to but i do experience joy frequently throughout the day
it's really helpful to know the difference oh beautiful yeah charlotte jokobek has another
sentence in there about how you know in the west in america we're like so conditioned we have so much
you know we have so much material and access to all this stuff and we're just
kind of grown to have some sort of expectations that we should be happy and we should
just we should be happy because we have things it's just not that's not happening that's not joy
i'd much rather have joy much rather have joy so i'm really
really grateful you've shared that thank you thank you so much
any other comments questions reflections
no worries if not just creating enough space for you to decide if you want to go for that microphone
just receiving just the delight of this sharing the space together
let's see yeah maybe i'll just say um
to notice the flavors of of gladness
the shades of gladness the colors of gladness of joy there's
it's it's a huge range actually
and you know the mind because of its orientation toward the negative
it it can very easily skip over anything that is neutral to slightly positive
even even really like positive feedback or
nice things that can happen if we don't attend to them if we don't
meaning give our awareness to them our appreciation if we don't receive them
let them come in they slip through they're just gone they
don't get committed to memory they don't get that attention they just slide on but
one trip one awkward moment
gets a lot more attention a lot more of our awareness
we're much more inclined to tell somebody about something that was hard
even couldn't find parking i had to drive around the block for you know
six times and but then they got out and they got to walk for five minutes in this beautiful neighborhood
and they don't even mention that they just talk about how they had to drive for you know too long to find
parking it's just the way the mind tends to operate
it's how it's evolved and how it's been conditioned it's not bad
but we need to we need to watch the mind that's what brings us happiness we start to learn how the mind operates
and we then can start to learn how to relate to it in ways that
are on ramps to joy so
i feel like that's probably the last thing i should say may you all choose on-ramps to joy
thank you for your kind attention and participation
and uh for those youtube people out there jason graham jane thank you for
your little chats tonight and for joining us namaste good night everybody and may the benefit
of our practice be for the benefit of all beings may everybody
find little on ramps to joy
you