well good morning or good day and uh
i feel kind of cozy being here this morning kind of
i'm alone in this big room with there's a kind of a fog low clouds here
today california and bay area and starting to be a little dark in this
room in the mornings now in the coming fall so it's kind of cozy nice
thank you for being part of this
so in mindfulness practice
we are using are the medium for it is our capacity for perception
and the primary example of perception that's used repeatedly in in the buddha's teachings is seeing
and one of the advantages of using this as an example
it can be clear that when we see something maybe you know outside of ourselves
that it is outside of ourselves it's there and that the eyes that see the ability to see is
here with us and that between those two there is the act of
seeing and which is the coming together of the object and the ability to see
and and that excuse me
and and that that ability to see
uh that that coming together to have the seeing that's where the dynamic aspect
of mindfulness or the revelation of practice opens up
and sometimes we look ex too much at the object as if
only the object has the answer just really bear down on the object look at it see it deeply
there's a role to that but it can be it's only part of the picture
the other part is the ability to see and it has to be there
and then there's the coming together of those two and if we're too interested in the
object reacting to it or bearing down it in some way
investigating it deeply we might miss the other two parts
and the other two parts are also where we can discover where we're caught in something where we're
entangled or attached to something which is often felt as a freezing
of the seeing freezing of the act of perception and locking in or
locking out putting pulling back and the ability this the meeting of the
two stops being so smooth and fluid in the present moment as it unfolds
so the ability to see
is discovered in the seeing and that ability to see how we see the
what is where we is a beautiful thing that's what the buddha people calls it
uh the beautiful witnessing
how we see is the
is where we discover the unfolding of the dharma of the practice
we have to see we have to stay close to that meeting place of the scene and the scene
but how we see how we perceive how we know and so in this meditation
you might take an interest
in how you're seeing which always happens
here and now which is always
part of the immediacy of the present moment how you see
and can that way of seeing the way of knowing the way of perceiving
way of seeing with the inner eye kind of what's going on inside of you
can you give a lot of time to that the extended present
moment can you allow for it to be calm and expansive and
unhurried just here
to now
directly visible in a certain way is our seeing it's the seeing itself
so to assume a meditation posture
and lowering your gaze to begin the process of relaxing your
eyes
so you're not really looking at anything
the central vision of the eye is not really engaged with anything
and it's more the peripheral vision
which is open [Music]
gently closing your eyes and no need to physically engage your
eyes or in order to be aware and mindful
no need to engage physically the eyes at all
letting the eyes relax in their sockets
almost as if they can eyes can kind of rest backwards
downwards in the sockets
and then with the as if you have
infinite time taking some long slow deep breaths
and to relax as you exhale
to let the whole your whole psychophysical system
settle into some
modicum of calm as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale as you inhale
feel your hands and wrists and if there's any holding there on the
exhale adjust your hands or relax the holding
if there's any ways in which there's holding in your elbows
they're pulled in tight to your side of your body or
or they're pull too far forward
adjust your elbows let them relax
and then feel your shoulders
and then the exhale relax your shoulders
maybe the shoulders can relax a little bit more
if you gently pull back and lift up your head
and if you gently incrementally
sit up a little straighter with your upper spine
and on the exhale softening the belly
letting the belly hang forward and down
and as the belly relaxes letting the relaxation
spread around the waist to the sides
letting the relaxation spread down into your pelvis
hip joints groin area
and then on the exhale to soften relax
the thinking mind
relaxing any intensity or force
fixation connected to thinking
and then settling in to your body breathing
and here with your breathing
there's the experience there's breathing
the parts of your body that move as you breathe
here's your ability to feel or know yourself breathing
and the meeting of those two
where you know and experience breathing
and avoiding being excessively focused on
the physical aspect of breathing itself
see if you can appreciate more
the knowing or the sensing of breathing
our ability to sense is one thing
the sensations are other and then the meeting of those two is
our sensing of the body breathing
and perhaps you can
have some sense some intuitive sense of the knowing the sensing
has its own thing
and then that knowing or sensing a wearing of
breathing
to let that be
expansive in time
as if there's
an extended present moment
to feel what's happening as your body breathes to know it
to experience it in the knowing
in whatever way you're aware mindful
relax back into it to see if there's a place where you can
be aware peacefully
where there's kind of like the window is open and the wind gently blows in
continuously
that your perception is open available
and what you're aware of is known in that open peaceful space and
continuously
and as we come to the end of this sitting
there is that there is these three parts also to love there's the object of our love
our ability to love and the loving
it's possible to relax back closer to the ability to love the loving
that may be there without the object
there's what we care for our ability to care
and the object and the and the caring itself
can you take refuge in your ability to
care have compassion to love
without so much concern with the object
where that care love compassion
is peaceful and calm may be receptive
so that when you meet the world
that suffers or that you care for
you do so peacefully calmly
the kind of peace and calm which gives lots of time to time
lots of openness to the extended present moment
and perhaps this ability to care from this relaxed calm way
ability to love
can be touched can be
inspired or recognized as you hear these words
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may our care
touch the world
not with midas touch that turns it into gold but with a meta touch
that turns it all into our friends may we be friends with this world
[Music]
so
so this is the third talk on the five characteristics of the dharma
that's an expression or it kind of is meant to express the kind of confidence
that it's possible that would people some people have in the dharma
and so this this the saying goes
the dharma is well spoken by the buddha
it is visible here and now immediate
inviting us to see
onward leading and to be personally known
experienced by the wise so today the topic is
pasico which is what sometimes translated as inviting inspection
inviting us to come and see and uh it's a uh
the this the compound word or two words that he
is the the kind of the instruction come come here
and um and pasico has the word to see in it come and see
the and it's the same kind of root uh as bipassana which has pasana in it
is that to see as well and so come and see and the buddha when
early in his teaching career when someone wanted to become ordained as a monastic
he would say to them come come monastic and that just simply that come come here
come into this was uh that was the ordination ceremony nothing more nothing more fancy
and so i kind of like this because this idea of ehi come
and see has this kind of association in my mind to this movement
to really step into their spiritual life the dharmic life really fully
as this come into this
and um so the dharma beckons us to see
invites us to see says come look come look and
and it's not telling us come learn come read these books
come memorize these teachings come believe what i'm saying rather it's saying come and look come
and see and it's a beckoning us
and the question is what is doing the calling what's inviting us to come and
see and some people have suggested it's the world
that everything that's there there's a request that we connect with it that we know it they really are present for this
world because everything is important and i've known
some wonderful spiritual practitioners you get a sense when you're with them that everything is important every
little detail everything we do and the inspiring little event story that i
witnessed was in many many years ago in late 1970s
i was a witness to a unusual gathering maybe the first time
of about seven uh maybe the only seven full
send teachers in the united states and most of them were japanese who were moved to here to teach
zen and they had a meeting and after one evening of their kind of
gathering they had they had a panel for us zen students and um
and someone they were there sitting behind a table and answering questions and things
and and some zen student came along with glasses
of water for them and then soon just reached behind them and put it on the table for them kind of
kind of innocuously kind of but as he went down the table he came to the
last person and a teacher may zumi roshi
and and when he the student left the water for the
teacher the teacher turned around as if that person bring the water was the most
important person in that moment and bowed kind of in kind of an appreciation and thanks
and the fact that none of the other teachers had done that it really started wow this is important
for this teacher this is important as anything else and the other teachers seem to me they were so involved in the q a that they
you know they didn't notice maybe but they said everything's important later i was sitting in a retreat next to
it japanese and monken i saw him bow to his teacup
i know why would you bow to a teacup so everything is important and so you would
maybe some what's inviting us to see is the world be present for it everything everything is
important another way of understanding what we're being invited to see
is the seeing itself that that that's a seeing that's
important come and see come and be involved in the seeing
that the freedom is found in how we see how we're aware how we know
and as we start tuning in to how we see how we know
it's a fantastic thing begins to happen is we start seeing recognizing
how our awareness our seeing our knowing gets hijacked gets
caught in gets utilized by our attachments our greeds our agendas
our conceits because we feel it getting it gets tight it gets frozen it gets
pressure it gets assertive the knowing is not spacious relaxed open peaceful
and and so come and see is i think to be partly an invitation
was not so much what you look at or in addition to what you're looking at
it's the act of seeing come really see learn about your seeing learn about how
you're aware learn about the the richness and the value of this
present moment ability to be present and to see and so what's been calling us to see
is the seeing itself because the seeing itself
wants to be free wants to be open is available and i think you know the analogy i have
for this sometimes is um um
you know if you sit and meditate like in a nice way and come out of meditation very calm and
centered and very present then the seeing of the world around us
um just kind of happens naturally easily and things begin to sparkle and stand
out and highlight in a way they weren't when we're busy and stressed in everyday life maybe before meditation
i remember the first time i had this experience i kind of felt everything was sparkling
and i said wow had someone gone around and cleaned well i wasn't paying attention and
wow or sometimes taking a nap during the day and i've woken up in a place where
there's sunlight coming in through the window and i can see all the dust particles playing in the sunlight
and i'm just kind of that is that's completely interesting to
see uh not because the dust particles are so interesting perhaps but what's so
compelling is the very relaxed open way of seeing
that just seems to happen on its own a kind of way of seeing it's free of
attachments and genders and all this stuff so come and see the dharma is come and
see see each thing may be as important come and see
be in the seeing and the freedom that's there
and and see deeply and as we do that there's a lot to see
and and one of the things to see is this what we'll talk about tomorrow a
another amazing quality of the dharma is that it's onward leading
and what is that onward leading well well i'm getting ahead of myself now but so that's where tomorrow i'm kind of
excited um but for now it's um
our capacity to perceive our capacity to know um a capacity to seize
literally and representing all the all the acts of perception
there's something that is welcoming us inviting us to let that come to the
foreground and the yeah that there's some feeling of invitation some
calling to it come is uh
is part of the dharma that's within us this call to be present this call to
know to see is lives within us
that gets obscured gets covered over by preoccupation by strong desires
strong aversions being in a hurry
and but as we are no longer in a hurry we live in this extended present moment
with where time gets stretched out or is more open or seems timeless
i think maybe you'll feel the call to being aware
to being aware in a way where being aware has been set free
of our thoughts preoccupation stories
past future where just being alive is enough
so eh come and see
come look may this be the day where you explore this and consider this
it requires what i'm suggesting and giving yourself that kind of extended time of now
because if you're in a hurry you can't feel the call the request the invitation
but take from time from time to time through the day to give yourself this extended time
and see what you can discover
that might be similar to this call to attention
that is free peaceful so thank you
and i hope you enjoy your day and you're exploring of this wonderful
invitation to be present and maybe that
responding to that call can be
entering into a deeper life fuller life thank you