very warm welcome to everybody it's nice to see you all
nice to practice together
and tonight i wanted to talk a little bit about practice
and there's so many different ways we can consider it and so many different
elements that make up practice but one way that maybe i'll begin with is
practice is kind of like a journey in some ways it's not helpful to think
of it that way but sometimes it's helpful to feel like okay it's a transformative path
and to help introduce this idea i'd like to read a poem like to start with a poem
that outlines or highlights this path
this poem is from thousands of years ago but somehow it feels for me there's a
certain timelessness about it and we can imagine that
it's um a similar scenario playing out today
and the poem goes like this plowing fields with plows
sowing seeds in the ground caring for children and family
people gain wealth
why is it that i thorough and virtuous conduct
doing the buddha's instructions not lazy or proud
have not attained peace
i watched the water the foot washing water
as it flowed from high ground to low
with this the mind concentrated
like a thoroughbred horse taking an oil lamp i entered my head
looking over the bed i sat down on the bed
taking a needle i pulled out the wick
as the flame went out the mind was freed
this poem describes just some ordinary experiences
the beginning noticing that other people are getting the results that they want
they are plowing fields they are sowing seeds
taking care of their family and they're gaining their rewards from their efforts
something that's really tangible you know you plant a seed it grows some grain you can take care of your
family and bring some to market sell and have some prosperity
so the author of this poem say well everybody else is getting what they want
but why is it that i am not getting what i want
even though i'm practicing i'm doing what she she's doing what she believes she should
be doing that following the instructions that she was giving she's working diligently
and still she's not attaining what she had been hoped to attain
and perhaps she's feeling a little bit of frustration or confusion why is it
that i have not attained release
maybe there's a certain like striving or straining or something like this
and then when she goes to do the ordinary thing at the end of the day after being barefoot or walking in
sandals just to wash one's feet before going to bed so that the bed
stays clean just an ordinary humble thing
and watching how the water the foot washing water after in my mind after washing the feed just kind of dumping
out the bowl of water and washing how the water flows
in some ways just obeying the laws of gravity this reality
things always flow downhill they never flow uphill
just this way of kind of quieting the mind and having it to get
um we could use this like this idea of flowing downhill as being reality is
part of what the dharma is about to collect the truth of the way things are
is just the way it is so watching the water flow downhill
kind of getting settling just being aligned with okay it's just this
time to go to bed it goes to bed and
just turns off the light maybe in the same way that we use a light switch nowadays
and something about this shift from going from light to dark from being able to see
to not being able to see allows the mind to let go
maybe it was the mind was clinging or identified with or something
whatever it could see the visual field but when the visual field all of a
sudden went away then it was the last thing that the mind was holding on to and
the mind was freed
i recently taught a retreat and one of the co-teachers
he came up with this um he was talking giving a talk about you know the postures
and then the way that he described it he said well you know the buddha has taught
about these four postures they're perfectly valid all for them
sitting standing lying down walking
and we sometimes give instructions for all four we tend to focus on the sitting but
and then he slipped in this little comment he said but i think they forgot there's this
fifth posture it's called inbetweening
somehow you know when you're moving from one posture to the next
and so we might consider that in this poem [Music]
getting into bed leaning over to turn off the light and just this ordinary movement
but having this shift in the visual field just when something different happened
ananda buddha's attendant the same story happens with him it's kind of this
in-betweening after practicing all day
he lays down on the bed maybe there's just something about going
to bed it was like ah okay well i'm finished with today
with ananda before his head hit the pillow he had this awakening moment
so in betweening an opportunity to
not it's something it happens i myself have had this experience like been on retreat and a lot of
sitting meditation you know really some trying my best with some real diligence while sitting
but then having like well standing up to go do walking
having a kind of like a flash of some of an insight
so it's not so uncommon that like putting in some effort
and then when there's a little bit of a release when there's some moments of maybe some unguarded moment
but then something new can arise
so this poem some of you might have recognized it it's the poem of parachara
she sits on the altar some she has been here on this altar
it's the awakening poem attributed to her preeminent nun from the time of the
buddha and she was a teacher of others
a number of people who report how she helped them find her awakened their
awakening the one thing that's interesting about patachara's a bit of her the back story
is that she came to practice after experiencing tragedy after
heartbreaking tragedy her husband dies
first one child dies the second child dies
then her parents die oh my goodness right it's just hard to imagine
so she was kind of like crazed with grief
and she in this crazed state she meets the buddha who gave her some
teachings and she decided to practice
and we know from this poem that she practiced with the way that she was in the world
she talked about being virtuous taking care with others taking care of
herself some way that we could talk about virtuous ethics is about having care and respect for
others caring respect for herself as well as she talked about in this poem
not being lazy or proud so doing what needed to be done but
also not you know lauding it over others or maybe not doing more so that
she didn't stand out as being particularly special not you know striving to be the bestest
or mostest in some kind of way but instead applying the right amount of
effort and creating the conditions in which the mind could be settled
could be aligned with just the natural way things go water
flows downhill just kind of just tuning into the
reality and the simplicity very uncomplicated just watching water flow downhill
so patachora's poem as many of you know come from this collection called the
gata these poems of the nuns from the buddhist time
something that i appreciate very much about the buddhist literature the sutras the
scriptures is that we could make this broad generalization
a really gross generalization but maybe it's a little bit helpful sometimes to make these i like to do this i like to
kind of lump things together into some really broad categories for me it's helpful
and one category i'm sure all of you know is this right one two three four five
and maps four normal truth seven factors
awakening five hindrances three characteristics ten perimes all this
right and the buddha kind of saying there are two things what too there's this and that or
you know there's so much of this myself i'm fond of these lists i like
them it's i kind of like to have things to be ordered and
systematized and categorized and all these kinds of things
so we might say that that's one style of the buddha's teaching
important and valuable but there's also another style
that includes poems includes things that isn't so systematic
and categorized poems stories similes
that evoke something else that touch maybe a different part of us
maybe there's a way in which there's um
this touches to the richness of our hearts and minds or
that's maybe painted pictures that are more evocative
and and dare i say there might be a certain amount of beauty
to these stories or similes i know sometimes i've heard similes and i thought oh
that's fantastic it's so evocative
one one that comes to mind right now is about the hindrances
and this sometimes the hindrances in particular described like being
there's a number of different ones but sometimes like the water boiling and
there's ill-will and you can't see through the water when it's water is still it can be like a mirror
but when there's a lot of ill will it's boiling and you can't see and i thought oh that's so
apt so it's you know communicate something very clearly
so this there's this to be sure there's a beauty also with the structure and the maps and the
numbers and all those kinds of things there's a certain elegance
there but is there a way in which we can tune into what the buddha is pointing to
with some of the stories some of the poetry some of the similes
and i know gill likes to use this word beauty sometimes to translate this word kalyana
and which talks about the dharma is beautiful in the beginning
beautiful in the middle and beautiful in the end
so allowing ourselves when i think of beauty as something often kind of inspiring
sometimes going to art museums which is a different type of beauty that's the visual and maybe
aesthetics maybe not which is different than a spiritual beauty which is
this can be associated with goodness or clarity or some warmth inside of us
but in the same way that sometimes some aesthetic visual beauty and spiritual beauty
they can really support sense of inspiration
a way for us to feel like oh i this is a worthwhile to do recognizing
sometimes it's difficult just like in this poem with she paracharis tremendous suffering
before she came to practice and then even when she started practicing right she's noticing why is
everybody else getting what they want all the farmers i can see that
they're able to reap the rewards of their efforts and why can't i
these are the words of somebody who is still struggling having difficulties
so i would like to suggest in practice that we need both we need both kind of the structured and the guidelines and
maybe maps and lists and holding them lightly but letting
them be a support but we also need to be inspired and have
our hearts feel touched and maybe there's something inside of us that resonates with some of
the stories and poems and similes these things of beauty
so i'd like to offer another poem kind of like along those lines
and this uh poem is attributed to a nun who her name is
chitta which we often translate as heart or mind
and for me it's a little bit interesting that um poem is attributed to somebody about
this that has this name it's just two uh two stanzas
maybe i'll talk a little bit more about it um after i read the poem
jitter says though i'm skinny sick and
very feeble i climbed the mountain
leaning on a staff
having laid down my outer robe and overturned my bowl
propping myself against a rock i shattered the mass of darkness
so chitta she talks about her body even though her
mind is about i mean sorry her name refers to heart and mind and she talks about her
body being sick and this difficulty of walking up a
mountain but i appreciate very much that she's losing us a staff she has a cane
she has something to help her we all need help at different times
different seasons of our practice and it can take so many different forms but here's
you know just kind of something that's uh very obvious maybe to
that we can see outside is that she has this cane
she's climbing this mountain and in some ways we are all climbing
mountains too we all have difficulties things that
maybe aren't so easy aren't so straightforward
hopefully everything isn't a mountain in your life but we do have these
in my mind she's just taking one step after the other she's sick and feeble
she gets to the top or maybe she's not even at the top but she's resting
she puts down her robe and her bowl so she puts everything down
and then the mass of darkness is shattered the darkness of ignorance the darkness
i've not seen clearly again we have this kind of this shift in the visual field before patachara went
from light to dark and now we have maybe going from dark to light being able to see something she
hadn't seen before we might
ask ourselves what would it be like for us
to put things down just like chitta's putting the robe the ohms bowl maybe the cane everything
she's carrying she's resting she puts it down she lets go
and there's awakening
is there a way in which we can put things down or at least uh loosen the clinging so maybe we're instead of
holding on so tightly we hold or maybe support with open palms
that allows us maybe to see things more clearly experience things more clearly
and then maddie weingast another poet who is inspired by this poem
writes another poem based on this one
that poem goes like this
somehow i kept climbing though tired hungry
and weak old too
at the top of the mountain i spread my outer robe on a rock to dry
set down my staff and bowl took a deep breath and
looked around it was windy up there
as i was leaning back against a large gray rock
the darkness that i had carried up and down a million mountains
slipped off my shoulders and swept itself away on the wind
as i was leaning back against a large gray rock the darkness that i had carried up and
down a million mountains slipped off my shoulders
and swept itself away on the wind
something i appreciate about maddie winegas version
is this idea of these darknesses that we carry with us
sometimes and this idea that it slipped
and swept itself away maybe less of the practitioner here making it go away
just with the wind just with nature off it goes
so maybe having put down or let go or
no longer clinging just allowed things to go where nature takes them
without us having this feeling like we have to make them up work or make them
go away but again this kind of interesting thing
about this person is climbing the mountain she's putting effort in she's practicing
one foot after another and then it's with this in-betweening
this leaning back against a rock then something else can happen
so this recognition of there's these rhythms of practice times in which we're really
maybe the more effort more intentional
and then some ease but you can't take the ease if there hasn't
been a certain amount of effort a certain amount of intentionality
which doesn't mean right that we have to be huffing and puffing and straining up a mountain
this is just an analogy but there is a pointing to a certain
commitment a certain intention
to spend one's time one energy wins energy doing this work
i'd like to read another poem in this uh poem this nun talks about how
she um what the expression is went forth
to go forth is to ordain is to become a monastic
to dedicate one's life you know full time to
the monastic life which includes going for alms rounds and living in communities especially if
you're a nun the nuns have less time alone than the monks
for safety reasons and
this a real commitment to practice
and i i appreciate that sometimes we might have this idea of like okay well the monastics
you know they uh because they've dedicated their life to practice that it's maybe a little bit easier for
them or you know they don't have mortgages and kids and partners and the
news you know all these things that we have the traffic you know this kind of whatever it might be
so here's this poem by sama in the 25 years since i went forth
i don't know that i ever found serenity in my mind
i'd failed to find peace of heart or any control over my mind
when i remembered the victor's instructions i was struck with a sense of urgency
though subject to so many painful things i have
through my love of diligence reached the ending of craving
and fulfilled the buddha's instructions this is the seventh day since my craving
dried up 25 years she talks about right this is a
long time but something about she's right when i
remembered the victor's instructions when she remembered the buddha's instructions struck with a sense of urgency sometimes
we hear things over and over again but it's not until a certain
conditions are in place in which we feel like they resonate or maybe that we
understand them in a way that we hadn't understood them before
i know this has happened to me so many times we're rereading a suta i love to read
the suta so often i'm like rereading them and thinking that i know everything that's in there i'm like oh wait oh
oh now i understand what's here hearing a dharma talk
like sometimes one that it was recorded and haven't heard it the first time
took something away from it but then again later realizing something else was there maybe you all have this experience as well
so just one time in particular she these
bringing to mind the teachings they this idea this sense of urgency is this
sense of really wanting to practice that hollywood is some vega maybe some of you
have heard of this this this inspiration to practice but with a sense
of urgency a sense of commitment or a sense of i
really want to do this this is the this is the what i this is what's important for me in my life right
now
so also this this practitioner wasn't able to find ease in the beginning but she stuck with
it she didn't disrobe she practiced earnestly she had this
she wrote the poem says with my love of diligence so just coming back
coming back in whatever way made sense for her at that time
and she talks about excuse me
thank goodness for mute buttons
she talked about um reaching the ending of craving i'm sorry
so maybe there's
[Applause] i think i'm making a mess of this there we go i think maybe my mask was over my
microphone okay there we go
so for her that freedom was described or expressed or
as the ending of craving
shattering the mess of darkness or ending of craving there's so many different ways this can get expressed
it's maybe not exactly the same for everybody or maybe it is i don't know
but the way it gets expressed or the way it shows up or is different for different people
i'd like to share also another poem that maddie weingast wrote
based on the poem that i just read having heard that poem feeling inspired
wrote another poem and it goes like this
after 25 years on the path i'd experienced almost everything
except peace when i was young my mother told me that
i would find true happiness only in marriage
remembering her words all those years later something in me began to tremble
i gave myself to the trembling and it showed me all the pain this
little heart had ever known how countless lives of searching had
brought me at last to the present moment which i happily married
can you imagine we've been living together ever since without a single argument
for this idea of marrying the present moment you know this kind of like commitment to well i'm just going to be
here i appreciate this very much uh this person
she has this uh you know had this socialized a certain way these
expectations how she should live her life and kind of you know
twisted it a little bit modified a little bit and uh made it her own way
found her own way marrying the present moment
and that's where she found the happiness
so maybe all these 25 years when she hadn't found peace she was always thinking that the
next moment would bring the happiness you know something
that's over there or in another time or something like this
but instead kind of when finally finding this commitment to be here
i also appreciate in here is this these lines something in me began to tremble
i gave myself to the trembling so just allowing to be
what her experience was trembling is uncomfortable i'm imagining
but stayed with it and that maybe gave her the confidence to say oh oh yeah i can do this i can be
with the present moment even if it shows up in this way that's
with some trembling
so in these poems i've read there's a few themes one that one we might say is some
diligence and practice which doesn't have to mean straining or
doesn't have to mean over exertion it just means like this
sense of this is what i'm going to do now i'm going to practice now
and this is part of the art of practice is to know like how much effort
right this one person became awakened when she leans back against a rock
right so there's a certain amount of ease that's required but also she was climbing up a mountain
so a certain amount of one step after the other
there's also difficulties on the path some of us might have come to this
practice because we had difficulties in our life and we were like discovering that there was some ease or
some maybe some wisdom that we could relate to that was happening that we could
find in this path of practice
but it's not uncommon for i would say this practice but i would say any spiritual practice
there's going to be some difficulties right if we want to be transformation or some shifting in our
inner life it's going to be uncomfortable sometimes how could it not be uncomfortable
so just a recognition and that that maybe things don't happen on the timeline or the way that we expect or
hope or had thought it would be
also this another theme this idea that awakening is shows up in many different ways whether we're talking about
complete liberation or just some awakening some liberation from whatever
is binding us up at that time some of the more
mundane ways in which we find greater ease some greater peace shows up in all
kinds of different ways and so many different ways to express it
different people express it differently and maybe at different times they express it differently
but one thing also that these poems have that's maybe a
more of a mood or a tone
is there a sense of confidence
and maybe a sense of delight also we hear in this
but once they have found greater freedom then there's this sense of
i don't know i i get this sense of a certain uprightness and this is what happened you know like that they're just
sharing their story describing what happened without being shy
without bragging just a certain sense of confidence and
delight and clarity using language that makes sense to them
so i'd like to end with this one the last poem
that's written by maddie winegast but
no i i feel touched by there's something um for me it's very evocative it's
it uses a simile i might say that i don't know i feel touched by
we'll we'll see how uh how you relate to this but
while walking along the river after a long day meditating on vulture peak
i watched an elephant splashing its way out of the water and
up the bank hello my friend
a person waiting there said scratching the elephant behind its ear
did you have a good bath the elephant stretched out its leg
the person climbed up and the two rode off like that
together seeing what had once been so wild
now a friend and companion to this good person
i took a seat under the nearest tree and reached out a gentle hand
to my own mind truly
i thought this is why i came to the woods
seeing what had once been so wild now a friend and companion to this good
person i took a seat under the nearest tree and
reached out a gentle hand to my own mind
this idea of our practice sometimes our mind feels
like a wild [Laughter] wild creature and
elephants right can be very destructive and very powerful
but to befriend them instead of this idea that they have to be doing something different or they
should do that or shouldn't do that but just to befriend them
so may we all contribute our own poems
in whatever way that makes sense to us whether they're actually written poems
or maybe there's just the way that we live our life but may we all contribute our poems to
the human race and may this verse this poem
be for the benefit of all beings everywhere
thank you
and i'll stay up here for a few moments if anybody would like to ask a question or
come up and ask a question otherwise i wish you all a wonderful evening and thank you thank you for your
practice and for your attention