good morning oh yeah we finally i finally grasped all the technology this
morning welcome welcome welcome to this moment
those people are in the room those people who are not in this room but in
their own rooms i invite you to join us all
all of us in this moment
of just being here just breathing just to this
justice there's no time
there's no need to do anything take a deep breath
let it out and just breathe just breathe
let's just sit together my intention for this morning
is not to lead a long meditation but rather to invite you
to lead your own moment of just here so i won't be speaking much until later
just be here just breathe
wherever whatever is conducive to feeling in this moment
that is what you do for now for now this person
this person just be here just as you are
and just breathe
give yourself over to just sinking into this moment
as you sit here recall this is what it is to be this person
in this moment
this is this person sitting here
being here this person
this body
as you're sitting here bring together all the threads of your
experience into just breathing here
all the threads of your thoughts just here bring them into the center of
your body and feel this person this is what it's like to be this person
in this moment
nothing else
just breathe
after this time there may be some stillness in your body
twitches pains irritations but the not moving through space
stillness be aware of that stillness
the body is still
no stillness
[Music]
welcome welcome welcome welcome to now
welcome to here
what i want to talk about this morning is equanimity
and actually the original title of my talk was equanimity in times of uncertainty
and as i looked at that title this morning i realized that uncertainty was not in my thoughts
it really wasn't about uncertainty it was about what is equanimity
what is it what we mean when we say i would like to be equanimous
i would like to realize equanimity in my life
before i begin i want i want to give a thank you
to the people that i have met who participate in the
online dharma practice groups because their questions and their
comments and inviting me into their practice in their lives stimulates
thoughts reflections their words reverberate
in my mind and in my practice
and i've thought about that in terms of equanimity when i woke up this morning
i thought what is it that i really really want to say
you know i had a private a long prepared talk with all kinds of things in it but what i really want is for everyone to
understand what equanimity means
in life why why do we value it what is what's important about it
i'm going to give you a quote from gil it was um in an article he wrote about equanimity
equanimity one of the most sublime emotions of buddhist practice is the ground for wisdom and freedom
and the protector of compassion and love
one of the most sublime emotions of buddhist practice is the ground for wisdom and freedom
equanimity when seen this way it's it's less a state to be achieved
but a way of being with our experience it it it is
a way of being and not something that smooths over
how we are what our experiences are there's there's a supplement a
suppleness to equanimity equanimity is not rigid
it is not defined in terms of these are the characteristics where you know okay
you're there it really is a way
of just meeting experience and what is it that allows us to meet experience and not be
blown away by whatever that experience is
one of the things we think about equanimity is that it's most accessible on retreat right you're going to get
calm you settle into your meditation and everything is beginning to get rosy
or not or you're experiencing an aversion retreat or but the equanimity
is what arises and you say aha now that none of this is bothering me
i can be in this state of evenness
but you know equanimity shows up in all kinds of buddhist lists you know it it's in the the seven
factors of enlightenment and the four brahmaviharas and the ten perimes
and it's the fourth giant factor of concentration
and the thing about equanimity is it comes after mindfulness
comes after concentration it comes after joy after tranquility
comes after all of these things we practice toward and the qualities of equanimity have to
do with presence with the experience
presence clarity and ease a lack of struggle
so of course it makes no sense to struggle to become equanimist
but what does it mean this presence and clarity and ease what do i mean when
i say that what do i mean by presence what is presence
you know someone asked me who were the people who influenced me what teachers influenced me in my
practice this is really a marvelous question not only who were they but why was i
influenced by them what about them caused me
to be motivated in practice and presence was one of them but
surprisingly to me i hadn't thought of it quite that way one of the earliest experiences i had was going to a
bookstore and sylvia borstein was talking about her book that's funny you don't look
buddhist so that'll give you an idea it was 25 plus years ago and she uh what i
noticed about her she was talking about her book was that she had no wrinkles in her
forehead that she was totally at ease she did not seem to be concerned about
anything and i thought wow i want that i want that just
just here in the room another experience was going to see the
dalai lama he had there was a a large conference in san francisco over 2000 people
and it was on peace and the theme was for peace in the world you begin with
peace in your heart and then peace in the family and then peace in your community and then peace in the larger community and peace
in the world and that it all began with you and as i was listening to him over the course of
the week at how he exchanged views with people what became really clear to me was that
everyone in the room felt like he was looking directly at them
and seeing them his presence his being their nus was so strong
that you could feel it across a room with two thousand other people
and everyone thought that it wasn't a sort of projection of guru isn't on him
it was really feeling seen
feeling seen and and that presence when we experience presence
we are fully engaged in whatever the experience is that is happening here
we this person this person who's showing up with these conditions
in these conditions this conditioning this person however it is
is fully engaged in this moment this this one this person
you you are in this moment this is what it means
to be alive normally we you know we we get lost in our thoughts and the thoughts are off over here and you know
the body is here and sometimes we're slightly aware of the body and what are we aware of
what is it that i actually know about this moment the presence of total immersion in just
this
this however irritating or sweet or
whatever emotions come up in the midst of it whatever twitches whatever bodily
twitches this this is totally in this moment this is the
experience this body is having and in conversation
the other person is contributing to whatever the experience is
are you there for that or is the mind off wondering what you're going to say in response
presence the absoluteness of just being aware of this experience
this is presence to embody presence is to just be in it
the second item was clarity and i spend a great deal of my time
talking about seeing clearly and when i went through this talk that i
created and went down all the pieces of it i found seeing clearly i must have written
20 times and i thought okay so that means something to you
what does it mean to everyone else it reminds me of a zen teacher one time who he he always told this particular
story at least once a year i i sat with him for maybe 10 or 15 years and every year he told the story about the monk
that turned into a fox and i asked him one day
why this story was important to him and he looked really surprised and i said but you tell it all the time it has
real meaning for you and he told me what it was
but in the process of that i understood that the seeing clearly part
has to do with knowing the honesty of what's actually happening in this moment
you know we we think we know what's going on and we apply a name to it we note and we
say oh it's this and then we dismiss it but the seeing clearly has to do with
saying what else is true about that
so so this becomes very obvious when you're talking to somebody and you hear what they say and you say oh well and
you form an opinion about what they say and then you no longer hear what else
they're saying because because you know already
or do you so so i've also inspired by a book of poems
that a friend sent me this is by ada limon and the book is a
new book of poetry of hers called the hurting kind let me see if i can find this page
the piece is called calling things what they are
seems fitting right i passed the feeder and yell grackle
party and then an hour later i yell morning dove after party
i call the feeder the party and the seed on the ground the after party
i'm getting so good at watching that i've even dug out the binoculars an old poet gave me back when i was young and
heading to the cape with so much future ahead of me it was like my own ocean
tufted tit mouse i yelled and lucas laughs and says thought so but
he's humoring me he didn't think so at all my father does this same thing shouts out at the feeder announcing the
party attendees he throws a whole peanut or two to the steller's jay who visits on a low oak branch in the morning
to think there was a time i thought birds were kind of boring brown bird gray bird black bird blah
blah blah bird then i started to learn their names by the ocean and the person i was dating
said that's the problem with you limon you're all fauna no flora
and i began to learn the name of trees i like to call things as they are
before the only thing i was interested in was love how it grips you how it terrifies you
how it annihilates and resuscitates you i didn't know then that it wasn't even
love that i was interested in but my own suffering
i thought suffering kept things interesting how funny that i called it love
and the whole time it was pain how funny that i called it love and the
whole time it was pain this is what seeing clearly is
about we have these ways of thinking about what's happening in our experience
and we get kind of entrained with that way of thinking oh yeah
love is glorious it keeps everything exciting right well maybe it wasn't really love maybe
it was something else and becoming enamored of one's own pain is not uncommon
it's familiar oh i'm this
life is so difficult and pretty soon everything falls into that
quarter of life is so difficult you know in in the last week there's been uh
the last week or two there's been a lot of trauma in my immediately immediate family health related issues
for various people and and i myself was worried that i might have had covet and i was you know
waiting to i could take my pcr test there's all that unlimited
uh free thinking about oh my god everything's falling apart you have this feeling that everything's falling apart
but it isn't falling apart it's just happening rapid fire appears to be like this
it appears to be like this but how is it really also during the week it turned out my
grandson had coveted and so he couldn't finish the last week of school which was very upsetting for him he's nine
and i got to read to him every afternoon by zoom for two hours which is a long time to
read a kid's book and sound you know enthusiastic and bright and carry on the meaning and the in your
tone of voice and how delightful it was
now it isn't that i was finding delight in the midst of pain and agony and sorrow
but rather that both things were present and that if i focused on poor malcolm
i would not be able to focus on the delight of telling this mystery story about these little kids in this book i
couldn't have engaged in the moment because i would have been so worried about how is he feeling how is he taking
it in right which seems like a very compassionate act but is it
whereas the total engagement in just this proved to be just delightful for both of
us truly delightful he was very eagerly setting up the next
appointment well let's do it at two tomorrow no let's do it 2 30 because i have to finish my movie
just the the excitement of just this
and how exciting that is to be engaged in the moment
and not focused on oh what could be wrong or what might be wrong and needless to say my pcr was negative
or i wouldn't be here
the moments where we believe we know what's going on are the very moments to say really
what is it that's happening it is this seeing clearly into
what my first impressions are and what what does that mean to me now
it's realizing that experience does not have to be tied into meaning
it doesn't have to be tied into meaning the mind wants to make a story of our experience you know it's a continuing
story but this is the only thing that's happening right now my life in the past has not happened to
me right now you know this morning i'm i'm planning to go up to seattle to
to visit uh another very new ill grandson and um it's at the university of
washington and so i thought of a friend of mine who works there is somebody that i went to graduate school with he was a
postdoc i was in graduate school and i thought wouldn't it be delightful to see him and thoughts kept coming up
of from 40 years ago which is are not about now
and i watched the mind go back to those stories and i wonder what he's like now and i reflected that i am nothing like i
was then but this person is totally different
really different however other characteristics may be true
equanimity is an intersection
of suffering identity with self and
ease and to see how they impermanence impermanence the ease of impermanence
when you when you really engage in impermanence you stop building meaning around every
experience you have
it's just the experience it's just the experience
and finally the other thing had to do with struggle and ease
i was thinking about that this morning as i you know i was walking calmly through my house
reviewing in my mind what i was i had 10 minutes i was going along next thing i knew 15
minutes had passed and i thought ah i will arrive later than i attended to
arrive now there's a couple of ways of thinking about that one is i'm i'm going to be late and the other is i'm going to
arrive later than i intended and the difference between them is seeing this
is what's happening and saying i need to move with alacrity
versus i'm rushing rushing has that sense of urgency and i have to change what's true
i need to move with alacrity is ah time to move the difference between them has to do
with how much i am struggling with how things are
how things are what is the struggle with how things are it's not so so it's not
saying that being later than i intended is good it's just how it is it's neither good
nor bad i don't even have to say it's okay it just is
that's all that that is what it is not to struggle that it's just like this
uncertainty can be unpleasant oh dear i don't know what's going to
happen or it can be exciting oh what's going to come next it's still
uncertainty the attitude that we bring to it that we impose on the experience
changes how we see it and how the experience then is conditioned into the next moment
the difference between loneliness and solitude usually turns up to be whether it was
your idea or not
equanimity arises out of clear seeing
and the absence of taking it personally the absence of saying this is about the
story of my life it's useful when you think about equanimity to consider
when equanimity is not present when do i not feel the stability
the stability of being in this moment because that is a key factor
stability of mind
what's generally true is that we get pulled around in life through the eight worldly winds you know the praise and
blame pain and pleasure gain and loss fame and disrepute
so this morning as i was sitting here there's a a new thing that has occurred in the
last few months in my sitting practice which could be considered annoying and that is as i settle in my jaw starts
doing involuntary movement it just moves quivers moves back and
forth and the first time this habit happened i was just surprised and now i'm still
surprised i still go oh what is that and the mind wants to make meaning
around it it may be uh
i've been storing things in my jaw all my life the tension of life and it's slowly
working its way out it may be i don't know something medical it may be
who knows what's true is it's quivers and as i was sitting here i wondered the
thought of royals what does that look like in a mask does that move back and forth does that
is that strange and then i thought ah working working on
on a fame and disrepute i'm going to look like i don't know what i'm doing up here
i watched that like laugh that comment i laughed i said oh it's easy that comes up all
the time things like that come up
what's important is to be able to see when they come up that's the clear seeing part
oh i'm trying to establish blame for why this happened i'm going to blame att or
i'm going to blame you know pick somebody to blame
pick yourself to blame that's where self-criticism comes in it it's being blown to the side
what equanimity represents is the suppleness of mind the stability of mind
that takes it in and stays here
takes it in it doesn't have to run off and fix it or change it or be blown away by it but just hear
there are two words that the buddha used when he talked about equanimity one of them was upeka the other one i
have to look up here because it's really something i stumble over
another word so upeka has to do with
seeing over it has the components of the word or seeing over so in equanimity there is a
a broad view where you're not upset by the ups and downs you become very aware
of the coming and going of all things and that looking out over that
allows you to not be blown away by it i may not be able to find this word i apologize
but i am oh there it is it is tatra maja tata tata maja tata and
what it's a combination of words polly words and it means to stand in the middle of all this
to stand in the middle so the standing in the middle
is not a rigid standing but it is a saying in order to be
in equanimity everything must be included
it's not about being a better person so that you can be equanimous about having a better
practice so you could be equanimist it's about showing up with this person in
this moment and having the flexibility the stability of mind
to just say this is what's happening in this moment ah
and when you see clearly you can take the intentions that you have
you can recall your intention in life and take the next step
it is about choosing as opposed to reactivity so yes equanimity and meditation is
quite lovely equanimity when you're out in the world with everything happening around you
is also quite lovely it's a recalling to
okay it's like this it's like this and that recalling
allows us not to be blown away by the eight worldly winds it allows us to be
present for okay here's how it is now i am still here
the presence of i am still here and i can see this is what's happening
it involves integrity honesty brutal honesty it's seeing when you what you think is
love is really pain is just being really honest
i see things coming and going i understand that things arise and pass
away they don't have some specific meaning it is not about me
it's just what's happening here and i have the stability and presence of
mind to allow that to be true
it turns out you know i i there's there are all kinds of prescriptions for how one cultivates
equanimity but it seems to me equanimity is really
a quality of practice when that practice is incorporated into
the moment it arises by a fierce attention to presence and
seeing clearly and that ferocity has to come
with an open soft heart because otherwise
we are rigid and unfeeling and uns insensitive to what's happening
so the very things that hurt us that rub our raw spots
are the places that remind us how alive we are how in
the moment we are and needs to be included oh
this this is what's happening so there's a
uh there there's equinumerity of practice how many of you have heard of equanimity
practice it's similar to meta in which you repeat certain phrases
that are intended to bring your mind into the space where you can actually experience what it is you're talking
about so i'm just going to briefly
i do this practice routinely routinely i have for many years because it reminds me
calls to mind the importance of the clarity of seeing
that is so essential things as they are so i'm just going to go through my phrases
i am heir to my own karma my suffering
depends on my intentions and my actions not what
others wish despite what i may wish things are
as they are may i see things just as they are
may i meet the arising and passing away of all things
with equanimity and balance
i am heir to my own karma my suffering or lack of suffering
depends on my own intentions and actions not what others may think
despite what i may wish things are as they are may i see things just as they are
may i meet the arising and passing away of all things with equanimity and balance
now those are just my phrases i've said them over and over and over
for years i repeat them to myself when i'm doing walking meditation
to bring the mind in see clearly see clearly
and what's happened over the years as i repeat these phrases to myself is i come
to develop a kind of insight which is a deep understanding of what
those words actually mean it was that that caused me to wake up
this morning saying what is it about equanimity i really want to say what is
it you know i could go through all these lists do this do that cultivate it this way
but what's true is that we need to learn to experience
and recognize when we are solidly present
when we are seeing clearly and we when we are not struggling
so i started the story about the difference between rushing and not rushing the moving quickly and and
rushing and as i was driving along i thought this is really interesting i know the
difference between wishing i was further along and leaning over the steering wheel and
and i'm just driving i'm just going there and i watch the urgency come into my
mind and i let the urgency go and say this is not life or death
so i've become suspicious of urgency in my life when i feel like this has to happen now or that
really does this have to happen now
what is happening now that this often happens in conversations
with my husband i'll be we'll be talking about something and i'll get enthusiastic about something and he will
be his mind is on something else he's thinking about i'm thinking about our upcoming road trip he's thinking
about the paper he's writing on an ecological
subject to support somebody's case with i think this is the uh the water
sanitary district i don't know his mind is there my mind is here we're having a conversation he finally says
i really can't take in anymore and i can feel the urgency of just this
the end of the sentence i have to just say the end of the sentence and i just stop this is not urgent
it's just a sentence and to feel the ease arise in that
that is experiencing equanimity in the midst of triviality
is what's important about equanimity is that it is not inaccessible to you
is it's totally accessible what's required is presence
seeing clearly and not struggling
i'm not saying that nothing comes up in life that we don't struggle against happens
daily it's to recognize the struggle
and to say how does this fit with my intentions and what's my next step not
two minutes from now or next week what's my next step
i'm going to finish my coffee and then move there is a patience that gets built in
when you let go of urgency
just be here just be here
so i'm going to read you yet another poem to close this is called proof
everybody likes proof right a kestrel eyes us from a high thin
branch and my husband is surprised it can hold the hunter's weight he's small i say
my husband says he's large obviously depends on what you compare him to
a hawk a white crown sparrow a ghost an abstraction
he looms not large to me but significant a standout something cool about him that
says today is the day to test his medal in the mid-morning air flush with dead leaves and the
ongoingness of rusted mums a surge of relief comes like a check in the mail
look i've already witnessed something other than my slipping face in the fog mirror the dog sweet seriousness
seriousness that being worshipped from nose to paw i have proof
a nearly twig like branch can still hold a too heavy falcon
it's not much to go on i know
don't belittle any of your experiences
equanimity has built into it a piece of hope
it is the hope that comes from the ease
of just this the end of struggle
is to let go of struggle
it's not much to go on i know
but the result is living a full engaged life it is about being alive
and this moment is what we have to be alive in this one
i wish all of you the ease of a supple mind
a stable mind a mind that's able to come into the presence of now
so that you can know equanimity not as an idea or an abstraction
but as a way of being with things as they are thank you
thank you