so hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour lovely to be with you and to practice
together in this moment whatever time zone you're joining in
and whether you're new to a happy hour or you're an old timer so for today's practice
um i'd like to bring in a theme um
that is so many favorite themes i have but this one is it's um
it's a theme of service and how it relates to our attitude
in daily interactions with people so there are many many ways we can show up
many ways we can show up in the world and a lot of times [Music]
maybe we show up or we've noticed in the past we show up or we still show up or others show up or let's say human beings
show up with this perspective of what can you do for me what can i get from you like
every interaction how can you satisfy my needs how can you satisfy my needs to be
seen to be acknowledged to be recognized to be applauded to be approved
of to be um uh how can you satisfy my my financial
needs my sexual needs like how what can you give me just this extractive
approach that we might recognize that you know it might be on
scene sometimes might be subtle um what if what if and this was really
eye-opening to me years ago to to completely shift that and what if
in every interaction we have um there is a sense of
what can i give what can i give you what can i what can i support you with and it
might be the answer comes up might be kindness um maybe it's a smile maybe it's a gift
or maybe just the stance of generosity of heart but really the stance of
what can i give you what can i do for you how can i serve you how can i be of service
and somehow maybe the words to be of service they sound grandiose and they sound big but they need not be
can just be dropped in into the background of our minds and
there's so many beautiful outcomes to this shift and perspective because when
our interactions with others and with the world becomes a matter of generosity a matter
of giving a matter of service it's not so much about us but me me me me
and it can bring a lot of freedom and not to say of course there are needs that need
to be satisfied needs for shelter and food and taking care of oneself and also it doesn't mean that we invite people to
walk over us it doesn't mean any of that it doesn't mean any of that and of course
one of the beings that we serve if we're serving 360 degrees and carrying
360 degrees that includes ourselves
so how can i be of benefit how can i be of benefit in this interaction how can i
be of benefit to this other being i'm interacting with and also to myself not in an extractive way it's just an
attitude of not being extractive but one of generosity
[Music] that can can make a huge shift and
and having been on this path perhaps for some of you been practicing for a while
you've heard this this teaching on um not self or or
impersonality there's so many ways to have insight into that and to acknowledge that and to to to manifest
that and one way is it's not about me it's not about
you know me me me it's not about me it's it's a different interpretation there are many different ways but not to say
this is the only way or limit ourselves to this vision i'm not saying that at all
but if we approach if we approach others if we approach the way we show up in the
world as a way of our gift of generosity i just i'm living for a short time my
life is a brief flash flash of light
in the cosmic sense what kind of gifts do i have to give can think of it as a legacy if that
helps you what do i have to give to this person in this moment might be the last
moment i interact with them i might be hit by a truck get an aneurysm tomorrow
life is so uncertain what can i give what can i how can i
serve so having that attitude as a shift and maybe i'll invite you to try that of
course we'll explore that in this guided meditation but then as a [Music]
weekly practice as a daily life practice um to
to bring that into into your mind into your mind when you're interacting
with others with yourself it can really shift and can also lighten a lot
of freedom it can enlighten a lot of suffering into freedom because if we're caught in me me me what am i lacking
what do i need instead this practice brings up a sense of abundance gosh i have so much to give
actually what does this person need maybe they need a patient ear right now maybe they just
need me to be silent and not give advice and just listen maybe that's the best thing i can give
right now not be a know-it-all just offer them my presence but what can i
give because sometimes also giving advice could be so that we feel good we've done something you know right like
we feel smart but anyway there's so many ways that this attitude of service of giving can uh
and shift conserve so so i've said enough to set the frame and
um i'll start the guided meditation together will be about 30 minutes roughly
sit in a way that you can be comfortable your back straight ideally lying down is okay as long as you don't
fall asleep and as always we start by
blending connecting with the breath with the body spend about 10 minutes settling and then
i'll give some invitations to explore um yeah this this practice of this attitude
of service so here we go so
arriving arriving in the body arriving
here here
this moment
letting go releasing any tightness any holding
releasing releasing thoughts not that there's anything wrong with thinking but right now we release them
release thoughts for the benefit of ourselves to give our hearts to this
practice in this moment turning away turning turning away giving
up thoughts turning towards this delicious seclusion of the mind the
stillness it's so quiet and still in here we just keep stirring it up
turning our gaze inward
dropping dropping your weight into your sit bones
dropping dropping your weight into your feet into your legs
with the next out breath releasing releasing into this body
letting awareness connect with the breath
in breath out breath received received sense of receptivity
this body knows how to breathe
receiving the breath or let the breath be received
the entirety of the in-breath the entirety of the opera
in the abdomen in the lower abdomen entirely of the inbrea entirety of the
opera
your thoughts arise it's okay it's all right
let there be ease gentleness it's okay sweetheart telling yourself
and release them it's okay it's all right
letting the breath be received nourishing [Music]
emptying gently gently
like the waves of the ocean
so
and as the breath is being breathed being received
if you allow the breath to be breathed through the body throughout the body
sensed as if your entire body
is bellowing not effortfully but
energetically
the depth of the breath the length doesn't have to change at all
it will make it more forceful and it just be received naturally as it is
acknowledging that this breath is nourishing the whole body it's the whole body breathing
i notice sense of and life and aliveness
sense of aliveness that can bring feeling enlivened
and let this whole body breathing let it enliven
sense of aliveness aspiration
inspiration
and to awaken a sense of goodness
maybe maybe the area of the heart center
aspiration goodness here i am practicing
[Music] showing up as best as i can
feeling feelings goodness sense of goodness
generosity kindness
that's your birthright that's who you are internally
breathing with breathing with
trusting trusting in the goodness in your own goodness i need your goodness
and let's bring to mind someone who's dear to you you have an easy
relationship with could be a person a pet a child
see yourself in their presence
with the question in your heart the question how can i serve you
how can i how can i be of service more generally
and how can i be of service could be of service to them but also including the relationship how
can i be of service how can i be of benefit includes them the relationship
that includes you in this this being who is you
how can i be of benefit
how can i be of service just
in your mind's eye i see yourself being there may not be any doing needed
in the scenario just feeling to the space
and don't ask the question desperately either just drop it in [Music] as if you were taking
a drop of color with a dropper drop off your fair drop of your favorite
color and dropping it into your whole body this attitude
defuse but definitely here in your mind's eye in your heart space
how can i be of service what can i give here how can i be of benefit
not necessarily looking for answers but literally there are this letting
there be this attitude the spirit of asking the question
and notice how your mind how your heart feels with this attitude of being of benefit
is there more gladness more happiness
more warmth more care more trust
more stability strength
now letting letting that go maybe imagining yourself
in the presence of others maybe those you work with if you work or volunteer
or a group maybe family
group that includes a mix of perhaps
dear beings neutral beings maybe those perhaps were challenging too it's okay
just a group and imagine yourself you can also simplify this if it gets
too complicated but in the space in your heart's mind
so you're just sitting just taking a splice of time and silence you're frozen
taking the moment frozen in time the question how can i be of benefit
all around to everyone myself included
how can i be of service how can i be of benefit
and not thinking about it just breathing breathing with this aspiration through your heart center
how can i be of benefit my presence my gifts
maybe it's just a feeling of radiating kindness radiating good well
how can i be of benefit all around
how can i serve
and letting this go letting that go in your mind's eye
now if you like you don't have to but maybe there's one interaction that
didn't quite go well or maybe you felt like
you had an extractive attitude interacting with someone
in the recent past
if you like if you wish you can bring that up to to awareness
and if you don't find anything that's fine just stay with one of the previous scenarios
radiating kindness and service but if there is something that felt like
just yeah that attitude of mine wasn't very helpful for me
it caused suffering for me and others bring bring this scenario to mind
your mind's eye and imagine if in the midst of this exchange
interaction you had an attitude of wanting to be of benefit
realizing you are an impermanent being [Music]
every interaction is unique and it could be your last
if your attitude was one of service being of benefit
to yourself and others and the scenario
how would you how would you act how would you have acted perhaps
not thinking too much but just dropping this question in and see what arises maybe nothing arises it's fine
note the difference
i'm dropping this scenario also
let yourself let there be this question living this question how can i be of benefit
how can i serve
others the world this being who is me
how can i be of service this living this precious human birth of mine
all these gifts that i have all these opportunities yes i do have challenges of course
everyone does of course i do i have so many gifts
so much to give how can i be of benefit
in ways small or not so small
radiating radiating your goodness
letting your light shine
may all beings everywhere be safe
may all beings everywhere be happy
may all beings everywhere be healthy
may all beings everywhere are these
wishing all beings well everywhere may i serve well
as best as i'm able to may all beings everywhere
including myself be free
[Music]
thank you thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so [Music] how can i be of service how can i be of service
we have a few minutes for reflections that might have come up
from your practice questions comments anything is welcome and i'd like to
invite you if you haven't spoken recently in the group you can raise your hand your zoom
hand i won't see your physical hand um or you may also type in chat
um if it's to everyone then i'll read your name if it's just to me it'll be private
i'll just read your reflection is there anything that you noticed was there an aha moment for you perhaps
you'd like to share
i'm not sure how to articulate this but something about the difference between
giving to please others or fix things or
fulfill a need versus really being receptive
and responsive when you ask that question how can it be of service like that feels really
different yeah and i had an interaction today where you
know i was just revisiting it in my head and i was like wow if i had just paused
and sort of like let myself like sort of ask that question i feel like
i would have had a really different interaction yeah so it wasn't like a
as as much like a transactional like what can i get from you but more like
what can i give you to make you happy you know yeah
but that wasn't really what was needed maybe yeah you know
yeah beautiful thank you thank you for that i really appreciate you
bringing more depth and nuance to this question because it's not just extractive it's also sometimes where i
just want to give you what you want right now so that you don't bother me or i think like you know there's it's some
ways of giving which are not responsive just as you were saying that are reactive maybe reactive and not people
like you might ask somebody what can i give you like how can i be of service and they'd say oh i need this specific
thing but that might and you give that but that isn't actually what you have to offer or like right that doesn't feel
good for you to give right right exactly and it also may not
be a question that you know how can i be of benefit maybe that's a better question this one or
maybe how can i be of service not something that you necessarily ask them out loud but it's what you're thinking
yourself deeply and as a way of orienting you that's more important than yeah
that orientation inner orientation will determine the correct words to say outward
which might even be silence but yeah the internal orientation
yeah thank you thank you thanks for that extra nuance and depth there appreciate
it lovely um
bill says thank you nikki wonderful meditation you're welcome thank you for your practice bill and here is a um
private reflection this practice was beautiful and also challenged me for someone who struggles to identify and
honor my own limits it feels like a thin line between how can i be of service and
losing myself can you talk about wise discernment in this space yes absolutely
very important um and i was trying to bring that in uh also
but i would i'll speak to it more directly because it's very important
that you know how may i be of benefit how may i be of service it needs to
include you it needs to include yourself it needs to be 360 degrees it's just
like the practice of metta when we practice metta say we're radiating meta
when it's radiating out of our chest whom does it contact first well it contacts us first it brings
us the goodness first and then it's radiated out and and touches all other human beings
so so there is the sense of yes this question of how can i be of service how
can i be of benefit it includes you and in in buddhism there is the sense of you
are as important as other beings it's not a sense of sacrificing yourself or just
there's no difference you are as worthy as everybody else so um
the sense of caring for yourself sometimes actually you might be asking yourself the question how can i be of
benefit sweetheart how can i serve you how can i love you better and maybe if
there is challenges with limits and honoring identity
honoring your own limits it might be if you wanted to engage in
this practice to actually step out to step out of yourself for a moment and
imagine you're you know you and this other person say in an interaction say
how can i serve these two people one of them being yourself so that you are included in
that care and that love like oh yeah this is what serves both of them this is
equally as if you know they were twins how can i serve both of these not
because sometimes if we have the perspective of just our bodies out of these eyes and perspective can
shift but when we step out of ourselves and see the relationship or how can i be of benefit to this relationship that
could be one way to have to bring in wise discernment
and you can let me know in chat if that helps enough or if there's more needed there
okay you're welcome um great
cheer hi nikki hi thank you for the meditation that was
really useful and i was new here and i knew here so it's my first time here so thank you for getting welcome welcome
lovely um actually the previous question resonated with me a lot about like how can we be
and then you answer that question right that really helps me so when i was doing meditation um my two days basically stay was just
like super busy at work and then responding to a lot of requests and then
and then i just feel like i need to sit down that's why i joined this meditation and then when you
guided me saying like how can i be served as service i think about myself how can i get service for myself and
what can i do i think well like maybe what i did today was to make a decision
and be here instead of like spending this hour in front of my laptop
and doing work right so that's actually the concrete thing i did when i
uh when i follow you like how can i yes there is myself i want to make a decision every time i make a decision
and when i want to think that is it am i limited is he like hurting my limit or
like is he good for myself right so i'm just curious my question and then that has been really helpful i just want to
say that and then i feel better after doing this half an about meditation i feel less a lot like i feel more settled
downs so my question to you is that do you feel that's a good techniques like just
contemplate that or do you have more uh concrete uh guidance in terms of how to think
through like things when when when i feel like exactly right yeah yeah this is great i
so appreciate i mean what one thing that i heard you say is is um
you know i sort of appreciate your inner wisdom that your inner wisdom decided okay how can i be of service okay the best way i can be of service to everyone
right nice to take care of me this person who is me i'm really stressed out i've had a long hard day and the best
way is to take care of me and sit and meditate and be in sangha like and and
yes of course that's supportive and beautiful so so you've interpreted this
this practice perfectly well it includes you and how may i be of benefit how may
i be of service is towards yourself and in fact this at that that
you know when i was talking about being extractive sometimes we're extractive towards ourselves we're like work hard
harder right there's so so it's it's just being of benefit so beautiful well done so if
i did the right thing yeah yeah beautiful yeah thank you so much thank you lovely
lovely so so dear ones let's turn let's turn
our attention now to practice together in uh in small groups and let's take
this same attitude to small groups of roughly size three in
small sangha and how can i show up how can i be of benefit to myself to others and maybe
being of benefit is just holding space for others and listening with kindness with care maybe that's how we can be of
benefit um so so in small groups each person will
speak from their experience only and you can say past when it comes to you you want to be silent it's okay
only speak from your own experience not commenting reflecting not managing the
group or other people's experience asking probing questions it's just from your own personal experience
the next person will speak from their own personal experience and then the third person will come back to you again
so each person will say one nugget and we'll go around and round a few times
and um how can i be of benefit how can i how can i serve that's the question let
that be kind as if it's a mantra in the back of your head you're not saying it out loud but yeah how can i speak um not
educate it's not about educating or impressing anyone but how can i share from my experience just a few words if
you wish from how this practice was for you the insights that you came that came up for you that often
helps others they can have their ahas when they hear your aha or when they hear your
challenge oh yes yes common humanity so with that spirit of kindness
we enter the space take care of yourself take care of each other
and in terms of order you can go reverse alphabetical order and i'm opening the
rooms take good care here we go welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed and we have come to the end if there's any reflections which are very very quick
and you want to share you can type them in chat and i'll read them quickly um
but but otherwise yeah we spent some lovely time with questions and reflections
at the beginning so so maybe i'll formally close and at the end i can stay a couple minutes as we
say or goodbye so thank you all may we all be of benefit may we all
serve well in [Music] in all the ways and all the ways that
we're able to may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thank you all
take care