so good morning everyone good day
and uh a little introduction to
further introduction to this idea of contemplation of a corpse
so we know that one of the core practices of
theravada and buddhism of much of buddhism is the four foundations of mindfulness
and within that those teachings is this teaching on the
corpse contemplating of a corpse but it's i think of it as as a part of a triad
of meditations the one on the parts of the body the ones on the four elements
or properties and this now this one the corpse and they come together because they all
involve um using something like the imagination
and some kind of the words that word that's used especially the first two for the
verb the action is imagine or or visualize something
and here also it's not we're not going to see a corpse literally but as if we're seeing one so using the
imagination and some people would protest that mindfulness practice is not about using
the imagination it's the opposite it's about seeing directly what's here
and that's true but uh we live in imagination quite a bit
without realizing it sometimes we think that we're in touch with reality but it's really through the
filter of how we interpret how we imagine things to be how we construct things to be
and so here we're using imagination to overcome imagination using
imagination to somehow pop the bubble of the previous imaginations
so that we can do this deep work of seeing things as they are
and so in some sense this corpse meditation is kind of preliminary supposed to help us
be able to go into the next three foundations and really see much more deeply
and with the parts of the body and the four elements we're beginning to
take apart what we take as a whole and with a whole we tend to then
project on all these ideas of what the whole is and we're starting to see
the parts but you kind of drop the image of the whole the idea of the whole and see the
parts of who we are and this ability to look at the parts
then we use the course meditation the classic reason for doing it
is to overcome identification with this body
taking this body as this is who i am or this is mine in some way
and we know that people are very body conscious in the sense that they very much identify with their body and their
physical body and how it appears to other people this body we have is all made from
borrowed material in a sense it's given to us for the
duration of our life or not even that because there's so much recycling going on even while we're alive
but all the material parts of this body are here temporarily
and they're here they've been recycled many times before and after these these elements in our
body uh our body is finished with them they'll go into uh into other other
transformations or their bodies or their living beings other
i take other forms at some point i will start dying will
die and this body will be transformed if we do green burial and bury our body
in the ground um fungi and worms and bugs and different
things will gently devour this corpse starting from the outside perhaps
working its way in bacteria
and um if we get cremated the fire just begins on the outside with the skin and burning
or burning its way inward in the old days you leave the body and
out in the open and the birds would come and peck at it and worms would crawl into it
and and start from the outside and so the skin would go first dissolve
first the flesh would dissolve next the tendons next they're harder
eventually just the bones are left and then the bones are left and they begin to
bleach in the sun and begin to get more brittle and eventually they
dissolve into dust and so the meditation on the corpse
contemplation of corpse is to kind of follow this possibility for ourselves
this dissolution of the body as a way of disidentifying as me myself
that i'm my body and this is me in some way to soften those strong associations
but also to quiet the mind
because the mind that is thinking a lot is the mind is a thinking that constructs many of the ideas we have
about the body and as meditation goes deeper and deeper the same kind of
journey happens as a dissolution of the body after death the corpse
we first the boundaries of the body get soft and they have skin and the boundary to the outside world begins to dissolve
and it gets very very soft and open and then the
we go in closer and the muscles the experience of muscles the sense of being in a
muscle body flesh body begins to fade away from consciousness
and then you get deeper into the body even the sense of hardness might be the last thing hardness somewhere in the
body heaviness and eventually that dissolves as well and so in the meditative process also
involves a dissolution and so this the solution of the corpse meditation
is both a way of disidentifying and a way
to begin preparing yourself for this deep process of meditation that can happen
so we'll do some of this today so taking a meditation posture
and the care that you give to your posture the love and compassion you give to taking a nice posture
is maybe the context for doing this meditation
and maybe with the same care and compassion to gently take some deeper breaths
to connect to yourself more fully to connect yourself more kindly
relaxing as you exhale
some people when they die the first minutes after they die occasionally
there's a lot of letting go of muscular tension they've been holding for a lifetime
it's good not to wait to let go of the tension
letting your breath breathe itself ordinary breathing
relaxing letting go of the holding which will let
go as you die
letting go into your body
and then taking a few moments a few breaths to just settle into ordinary breathing
as you exhale as you inhale feel any tension in your
mind your thinking mind any pressure or agitation
and with love with care on the exhale
relax the thinking mind
soften
and then whatever way that it occurs to you
feel the edges of your body where the skin
it either touches the air or touches your clothes
as you exhale imagine that you're relaxing
that contact with the world around your skin
maybe feeling the spaciousness the space that's around all around you
and maybe you feel the porousness or the soft boundaries of
the edges of your body and what's beyond the edges of your body and what's inside
breathing with it soft boundary
breathing letting go of the skin being yours
that you're defined by your skin
like a corpse loses its skin
it gets eaten or dissolved or burned so
let go of your skin let go of that boundary place
and feel deeper into your body
maybe the warmth of your flesh
the substance of flesh through your body
maybe it's a warmth maybe a coolness tingling pulsing
if flesh which right now is still alive with the sensations
this too will begin to dissolve and break up
and decay and disappear when your body is a corpse
the flesh will go
relaxing this flesh relaxing a sense that it's yours
that you're defined by your flesh
imagine that you your corpse is dissolving and the flesh
is disappearing
and then more deeply
all your organs in your torso all dissolve all
are eaten they're burned up these two are not
our possession not what defines us
they all the elements they return to nature
imagining a large empty cavity
in your rib cage and your torso as all the organs
vanish decompose
and then imagine that all you are left is skeleton
hard bones
and this skeleton is not your possession it's also borrowed materials
it too will dissolve this too we have to let go of
and first the skeleton all the tendons decay decompose and then
bones fall apart from each other and lay in a heap
on the ground disconnected bones
there's no more shape of the body
body shape has disappeared a heap of bones
and over time the bones
break into pieces are brittle slowly slowly
they turn into dust
and as the bones turn into dust they blow away in the
to wind across the land
falling into the soil on which new life
grows
let go of bones this whole body dissolved is gone
the absence of body vast space
vast openness in all directions
whatever way that you might be more settled or calmer in your sitting now
maybe more peaceful cozy
let go let go of everything
but let go into that calm let go of your body
your skin your flesh let go of your bones
feel the way that letting go
is a better alternative to holding on and being tense
let go
and as we come to the end of the sitting imagine
encountering other people in situations where it's safe to do so
safe comfortable situations meeting other people
and letting go fully just letting go and being present
with your caring with your care your love your good will
your warmth your non-defensiveness
free of impatience or desires or wanting things different
just with people
offering something profound a presence of attention that wants
nothing needs nothing just there to be present
and perhaps to care to love
may our care spread out into the world may it be that this practice of letting
go deeply is a support for the welfare and happiness of ourselves
and the whole world may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
thank you so
contemplation of the corpse it is um
in terrible buddhism sometimes it's understood that one of the best practices
at the time of dying is the four foundations for awareness for attention
it's the one that most conducive towards liberation towards freedom
and that's one of the best times better late than never to become free
and so sometimes this this text that we're studying becomes read at people's bedside that
they're dying sometimes in pali they don't understand it but somehow it's
meant to be beneficial and sometimes it's red after people die
so this text this text has a connection to death and dying and here it's at the
center of it with this contemplation of a corpse
and so there was i offered a small guided meditation on with this kind of in the
as a reference point and and um i don't know if i set it up well enough
and short amount of time we had but i'd love to see some comments in the chat probably brief comments but
what it was like if you were able to follow along with the dissolution of the body kind of meditation
and i'd like to know what uh how this was received or what
what you learned from it or what what benefit came from it so um
take a couple of minutes here and i'll say a few words until they start appearing
the um i think here in the west many people will emphasize the importance of the
value of mindfulness of death and dying corpse because of how it makes us really
here we go daunting freeing got a sense of no self very powerful got
to the point to the big question who am i made me smile freeing
love preparing for my death freeing we are not the body
i found it profoundly freeing i now notice a dissolving of attachment
very beneficial but do it again very powerful tangible perspective
and they were going very fast now the process helped with reducing fear of death
calming i pictured myself decaying in a field of flowers
felt like a deep knowing of our mortality the rising of deep compassion
i thought i'd be afraid but it's going so fast ended up in a puddle
beautiful spacious onward leading first revisiting then very peaceful
freeing an insight into true reality very spacious hard to come back into my
thinking mind i felt like i was in outer space
reassuring connection to nature in the universe is powerful and comforting
body is not myself connected was very light non-attached free
powerful helpful new and different dissolving into space
was able to follow peaceful i want to go back and listen to the whole series thank you
we'll have green burial just following breath
pouring in teaching but i was not so ready to take it this too to my heart
i wasn't into it my body was blown into the wind identification with itself disappeared
spacious really good work the sense of increasing space awareness was quite profound
each layer became more and more spacious very calm body just a vessel the experience of
emptiness relieving great well thank you for those who wrote that and i know that this wasn't going
to work for everyone and for those of you who might have found it and not so
peaceful or nice hopefully you can just put aside this part of this
we're going to get to you know
we'll leave this behind in a way as we move to the next next second foundation next week
before i go on i just want to mention that um i will i won't be here monday so we
won't have the 7 a.m sitting this coming monday but we will start again on tuesday
and that's when we start with um the
feeling tones the second foundation for awareness for mindfulness and this is often considered
kind of the pivotal part of the satipatana and i'll talk a
little bit in how structurally and different ways it's pivotal to a huge transition that's going to happen in the
practice as we go from the body to the mind
so i was going to say that many western dharma teachers will talk about mindfulness of
of death as a way of really cherishing that we're alive and really then appreciating we're alive and enjoying it
and being with it more fully and that's a certainly a wonderful thing to do
i think the tradition tends to focus on it more in the way that it helps us let go of attachment attachment to self
attachment to the body and in particularly attachments to concepts and ideas
that and all these things all attachments will keep us from
really sinking in deeply into this satipatana into this awareness practice that word of cultivating and developing
some people though find that this satipattani's contemplation of the corpse is a very
engaging visualization practice and some people who visualize well
find that they get really concentrated by doing this and having a you know actually the contemplation is nine parts
and so having is not this structure of nine parts to solution going through it over and over again
some people get very concentrated and that's one of the things that supports this awareness practice is
concentration and and the idea is to get it concentrated enough so we can do the refrain
so that we can we don't have to worry about the mind wandering off anymore and we can just settle back and just observe
our experience in a deep way and and then we're
let go of the corpse meditation at that point but uh one of the things we set back in this deep concentrated state and
just observe is the arising and disappearing the rising and dissolving of sensations
experiences thoughts feelings and and this contemplation of the corpse
prepares the ground for that because sometimes it's disorienting for people to see everything dissolving
and then appearing and dissolving and disappearing that can happen when the mind is very very still and quiet and
not organized around ideas and concepts and attachments
and um so um um so this course meditation kind of
prepares the ground also for the deeper dimensions of the refrain
deeper dimensions of the practice as it opens up uh in case so to make it a little easier more comforting or more
easier to go through when everything just appears to be arising and passing and rising and
dissolving so
sati patana helps us to appreciate this life to live in the lived experience
the only place we can know we're alive is here and now and and the sensations of our body our
thoughts our feelings they're like the manifestation of life of being alive
and to really appreciate that so we show up for it and they're present for it don't miss it by
being in our thoughts and ideas and being too busy and then to begin
being present in such a way that we feel it more acutely we feel more
sensitively to the the arising and passing of things so we can let go of the attachments we
have and as we let go more and more attachments sati patana becomes better and better it becomes like richer and
richer and more more wonderful and
occasionally a little frightening but the corpse meditation prepares the ground that it's okay to let go it's safe to
let go we can let go of everything so um
thank you and thank you for the comments that you wrote i will um
i didn't was able to read all of them as we were just they came so fast as i was sitting here but
when we finished now i'll go and read them all and see what you said and
and then i look forward to being here on tuesday to um
to continue with satyapathanam and given that what we did today was a
kind of a contemplation of a corpse dying maybe you should be a little bit careful
with yourself for the next hour or two or for the day that this can be very tender and touching and sometimes
challenging and even disturbing and so care for yourself and
err on the side of maybe being slow and calm loving caring do some nice things for yourself
go walk around the block and get you know yourself a little bit more
grounded if you need to and and if it's you feel spacious and wonderful
stay close to it stay close to this spaciousness and peace
one of the great things to do when you're peaceful is to then practice live your life
at the speed of peace meaning go about at the speed of doing things
whatever you're doing so you don't dissipate the peace so you stay close to it
so thank you all