group friends to join us and and it should be happening now okay
great anybody else wants to say hello just unmute yourself if you haven't already joined in
to say hello happy birthday casey [Music]
thank you oh nice great so
so here we okay great so i've got that started now i can look at the chats here so look at all the action i've missed
i've missed a hello from lisa from uh from berkeley from mark
uh oh i love from the squirm contingent and the puppy that's sweet
dane also says hello from berkeley casey from cupertino oh yes who says it's her
birthday happy birthday casey this is what i missed happy birthday very sweet
aw thank you for spending your birthday with us so we'll give you some birthday meta some
birthday love so oh thanks nikki ah very sweet and let's see
um current says hello from mexico ah hello you're on there on vacation but
usually from los alamos great welcome and our who also says happy birthday to
casey sweet and hi dave and hi aura let's see gosh so so many
hellos and greetings and all the lots of meta to each other very
sweet that's very sweet so so with with that warm welcome to
ourselves and each other uh let's let's all mute ourselves let's
all mute ourselves and um let's uh let's formally get started
here so um so let's see another couple of
meetings let's see let me do some uh here we go and oh yes thank you neil for
posting information about google groups happy hour just in case
you are new and are not uh on that mailing list um
it's it's where information is shared with the sangha so it's a lovely place to
join and also rebecca says we missed you this week at ims oh yes yes so
last week i was supposed to be at ims in barrie massachusetts uh
part of the teaching team to help teach the new year's retreat and given
the omicron situation and traveling and my immune system being what it is anyway
so i respectfully bowed out and i hope it was a wonderful retreat rebecca so
so with all of that all of that let's formally get started
and i will turn on recording for the sake of audio dharma here we go
okay so so
so for the theme um for tonight which
is going to include our birth um
being inspired it being casey's birthday tonight
the theme that i like to invite us to to practice with to
work with is opening up our perspective opening up
our perspective as if you were sitting on the top of a proverbial
mountain and looking at the entire entire trajectory of your
life not just this moment yes we will be embodied
in this moment um but sometimes actually if we're too much
in this moment and if our vision is too narrow not in an embodied way but in a
heady way you're just thinking about all the problems and the issues and all what i'm going to do
about this and this is terrible this is never going to end this is awful but that that tightness of vision
which you might be familiar with that tightness of vision
can um create a sense of
contraction a sense of tightness contraction and even sometimes meta might be hard
to be accessible in in that state and i trust i'm sure you have
experienced what i'm talking about we've all experienced um i should ask anyone not ex have not
experienced this tightness where you just your vision is so
narrow nor so narrow really as if you're just swimming in
what the problem or or the the most recent
drama might be whereas the invitation tonight
ah even just talking about that that tight vision kind of
gets my heart clenched it feels so contractive so letting go of that
view and instead instead having a sense of a sense of
openness and openness of vision and openness of vision
that here is this being who is you living this life
this being has been born has come into this life this being someday
will leave this world of course of course and this whole ark this whole art so
many things that have happened so many beautiful surprising
amazing and so many challenging things that have happened that you've grown through and
this road will continue so this this expansiveness of vision
including both you and including other beings and this expansive vision
can be with with the right invocation can be a perspective of equanimity
equanimity that things come things go
ah it's okay it's okay this is an interesting
interesting mysterious journey being human it's such an amazing mysterious journey
to to have a body even even if this body at times
doesn't work so well or or
has or this mind that has its you know it's kind of particularities and quirks and you know
funny ways that it it acts and reacts in the world oh sweetheart oh sweetheart
this interesting body this interesting heart this interesting mind that happens
to be me wow how unique is this it's so unique it's different from any
other body any other mind anybody else in the world so this sense of
tenderness letting there be a sense of tenderness for this being who is you who has
this ark of life and it's doing their best
doing their best and opening up opening up to the mystery
opening up to this mystery that is our life it's i'm sure you have noticed by now it's
not all under our control not our not our bodies not our minds
um which doesn't free us from responsibility and and and
in wholesome intention and yet it's so much of this selfless being that
is ungovernable so much of this body this mind is heart so having from this perspective having tenderness having
love not self-flagellation like bad bad me do this why can't you do this
like oh sweetheart oh sweetheart oh sweetheart this is
just being human is ah just being human is so
it's so challenging enough is so [Music] so amazing enough both challenging
beautiful profound so this expansiveness of vision
expansiveness of vision is what i'm inviting us to practice with so
so that's enough of a setting for our guided meditation so let's
let's land let's arrive let's arrive in this body
ah let's arrive
letting go of all the words
letting go letting go of the words letting go of any thoughts
just arriving in the body and the
tender sensations of this body sitting
this amazing miracle of life pulsating
breathing blood flowing through the organs
glistening sensing just this amazing body
ah inhabiting it fully arriving in it fully
my body wow so incredible to have a body
wow so much works so well even if there
may be challenges in the body's home much of it works so amazingly
well
dropping in dropping in the weight internally to your belly
dropping it
letting letting the breath be breathed on its own
the lower abdomen and with each breath
landing landing more deeply arriving more fully
into the present moment
just taking a moment of refuge taking refuge
in the breath in the body [Music] and as much silence in their silence
as is available
and if thoughts arise it's okay they will they do not a problem
not a problem smiling at the thoughts
saying thank you thank you so much please come back later
not though come back later
letting the body the breath ah relaxing the body
ah be the center of your joyful attention
just being breathed just being breathed
breath in the abdomen calming soothing
this
just here now deliciously here
in the body embodied
being in the body can help expand our vision not being in our heads
so come come back to the body
spending another minute or two just arriving
with the breath with the body before we turn open our hearts to mental
this
and now i would like to invite us
as if we were watching a movie of our lives still staying in
body feeling the breath being the feet on the
floor her hands her bottom and the cushion
[Music]
not getting heady but staying embodied and yet in this movie theater
we see with our heart not with our head with our heart
with our bodies we perceive the arc of our lives
the ark
having been born
a sweet sweet newborn
finding themselves in the world
maybe all smiles feeling of tenderness arises [Music]
feeling of tenderness
this being this being who is me and yet not me
this precious child
as if he were a newborn not thinking so much about what happened
or was she either loved or
challenging challenges even through none of that if those come up please drop them
not the door we're entering tonight but as if you were that newborn
embodied wow in this amazing miraculous world mystery
wow incredible everything new everything fresh
the sun clouds
the green grass butterflies
water
now bowing to that little newborn
and now let's move forward in time and for the purpose of this practice
of course life is so uncertain and we don't know what is going to happen when
and how long our lives might be we could be ahead by a bus and die tomorrow
and yet for the purpose of this practice this
let's imagine ourselves perhaps years from now
so there's a sense of spaciousness perspective
looking looking at the world from the perspective of let's suppose a life well lived by that
whatever needs to happen needed to happen did happen
or not just at the state of peace and equanimity letting go
now looking at the clouds from that perspective
of the end of life again
not knowing what it will be like but just for the sake of this guided imagery for a moment
clouds sun maybe sunset
trees butterflies
whatever images of nature
soothe and calm you maybe it's the ocean
maybe gratitude arises thank you
wow this miracle that i was a part of
maybe even saying goodbye to the body this miracle that was my body
this body that is me and also not me
this being is so much more magnificent
with so many dimensions
maybe a sense of warmth tenderness arises for this being
who is you and not you parting partying
thank you goodbye world
now bowing bowing staying embodied feeling your body your heart
feed your hands your bottom on the cushion bowing to this image
now letting your vision be expansive
including all these versions of yourself
so many versions so many ups and downs
between the moment of birth moment of death and this moment here
so many moments of joy bliss
so many challenges so much growth it's just all
beautiful mysterious
unique
letting your heart inviting perhaps inviting gently
your heart to include all of these
beings all these slices of this being
through time
the old movies there would be reals all these different images these slices of life
don't have to think about them all just letting your heart open up
oh sweetheart this being this being who is me
loving unconditionally offering love good will
to all their beauty their divinity their buddha nature their foibles all
their mistakes all their pain their sorrows
unconditionally loving it all
not picking and choosing
thank you maybe appreciation gratitude arises for
this being who is you doing their best
be warmth good will love
as if you're expanding your arms stretching wide far and wide
loving this being
given what seems unlovable at times
loving that too loving that especially that
especially that because often what's what appears to us as unlovable really
is suffering really is dukkha especially loving that
and maybe one of the images of the reel comes up there a moment in time
maybe maybe not that attracts you attracts your heart specially
wanting calling to be loved to be held unconditionally in love
maybe it was a time when you went through [Music] challenging time
valiantly courageously
or anything at all
living there beyond conditional love and acceptance
do
and now bowing to that image coming back to this body
this moment in time that is also one tableau an image
out of this reel of this movie reel
of this life expansiveness of vision including
loving yourself unconditionally for whatever is arising
in this moment
this being who is you and also not you
an expression of beauty goodness
divine buddha nature whatever words we
like to give it
to love and to be loved
by so many dimensions of this here
this being
as if we're looking into a mirror mirror looking into a mirror passing back and
forth infinitude loving this being and being loved
stretching into infinity all these images in the present moment
so many dimensions our humanity and divinity loving and
being loved
and as we bring this sitting to a close
maybe in your mind's eye bowing to yourself your divinity bows to
you you do you bow to
your inner buddha who is borrowing to whom
thank you keep going keep loving
may all beings including ourselves open up
our hearts with full love unconditional love to ourselves
to our own inner goodness may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you everyone ah thank you
for your practice thank you for being part of the sangha
even if this is your first time you are a part of sangha now
so we have some time for reflections questions comments
and the invitation is always is what you share is for the benefit of
both yourself to be held witness and also for the benefit of others the
sangha it's a gift so
it's sharing in questions confusions
insights aha moments it's all the gift we offer each other
and if you um just send it to me in chat i will
not read your name if you send it to everyone then it's public i will read your name as
well as your reflection [Music]
one reflection thank you for the vitamin meta you offer us here that is so sweet thank
you for that reflection vitamin meta i like that vitamin m
yes we all need our daily vitamin m don't we it supports it supports our heart it
supports our minds our bodies and the way we show up in the world
so [Music] so especially if you are new haven't spoken for a while
you're so welcome to re and if you want to speak oh yes please raise your zoom hand
and you go to the reactions on the computer and you find it there it's ray's hand
otherwise i will not see you because i only see just a few of you because i've
privacy that since this is um on youtube since
i'm on spotlight i only see very few people not every every one of you so
nancy says yes nourishing to be in sangha and meditation yes i agree
nourishing for me too to be with you friends so questions comments reflections what
did you notice jane says no words for how beautiful
that was ah thank you jane [Music]
may be nourishing practice be nourishing
so i can say more but i'm going to pause and invite to see any new voices would like to be brought into
the space what did you notice what came up for you
what happened curran says i found it so interesting
and mysterious to reflect on how i am and also am not the same self at
different ages i could probably think about that for a long time yes
pretty mysterious and magical current yes it's yeah
so appreciate that that reflection has been ignited for you
so the invitation i have is actually um drop that in because it's already been
dropped in through this meditation so take it with you see
it don't don't so much think about it because many of these reflections don't lend themselves to thinking about
but as it's been dropped in carry it carry it with yourself when you
go to bed tonight just open to it not thinking about it but just kind of let yourself soak in it
tomorrow maybe when you go for a walk outside kind of take take it for a walk
with you and uh and see what might arise yeah and see
more more dimensions of this mystery might might open up for you this is lovely
thank you wayne i see your hand is raised please
um i i've been it was helpful for me to sit with my i was not looking at
anything but just to almost not quite completely close my eyelids
but just keep them slightly open but my eyes unfocused and it just helped me
stay a little alert enough sometimes for these 6 p.m sittings
my when i completely closed my eyes i wander off and and my mind often runs more when i'm
yeah yeah great i am so glad you've discovered that and and also sharing it
with others because that uh opening the eyes was just a slight slit to let light
in that's a fantastic tool to be used when the mind is foggy or sleepy very
gently just it raises the energy of the body beautiful i'm so delighted you've
discovered that lovely barbara please
still muted oh there um
thank you nikki i appreciated what you said about the arc
of your life and i thought of my life like a rainbow you know
beginning little and then getting older and now you know sort of
kind of getting towards the end and it i found my mind went to
visualizing myself as as a a young child
exploring uh the beach where i i grew up near the beach
and i don't know it was just a lovely a reflection on
sort of where my life is gone at different parts
and ending up here where we are um
i know just a reflection on the
totality of the life experience yeah and i want to thank you
because it was it was a good it's been a good life it's hard now
what i'm hearing there's a sense of gratitude that has arisen for you there's a sense of gratitude and i trust
there was meta also for this being who is you that's what i'm hearing yeah yeah yeah with gratitude and metta for this
ark of life lovely beautiful thank you barbara and abraham i see your hand
and after this we'll go so please unmute yes you're muted i i also really like
that looking at the arc of my life and um it's helpful to not get too caught up in
whatever is disturbing wrong that's happening right now
but also you've made mention of seeing ourselves when we were courageous
when we stood in the breach when we stood up for what was
true and and didn't desert ourselves and uh i
appreciated that thank you abraham thank you so much for
highlighting that yes i did drop that in and and how um
how for you that ignited something in your heart in in appreciation it's beautiful thank
you all so [Music] yeah thank you all so it's 6 50 is the
time one more reflection that's just come in um viewing the arc of my life was very
effective i spent decades in addictive patterns i've had a lot of regrets i'm
so sorry then me said yes i know now me answered it was such a relief
thank you wow thank you that is so beautiful to be in
that yes to ask for forgiveness and offer
understanding to ourselves thank you so beautiful so powerful
thank you for sharing that so dear ones
let's turn let's turn our attention to
um practicing in small groups with one another holding each other with meta
with appreciation and if you can stay please do if you have to leave no judgment
but small groups can be so sweet they can be so supportive
so i'm going to create the rooms now take care of yourselves take care of each other see what kind of wisdom
others there's so much wisdom in this sangha see hear
the wisdom that your friends here offer you so
the rooms are created opening them take care
okay the rooms are all closed everybody is back welcome back
and we have just about a minute if there are any reflections especially if you have not spoken
today um if you like to share something in chat um
or quickly raise your hand just bring us home you'll have 30 seconds
please anything that came up when you're in groups
okay we're going once going twice just one to appreciate
um [Music] when jerry says the small group helped help me like myself better than the past
oh that's sweet it's isn't it nice oh and nancy says we discussed the arc of
our lives very lovely oh that's very sweet very sweet so thank you all thank you for your
practice and yes happy birthday and casey sharing part of you the arc of your life
all of us sharing arcs of our lives in this moment together supporting each other
practicing um supporting ourselves and all beings everywhere thank you for being part of
the sangha may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you and now