so
hello everyone and
welcome to Friday morning here in California
and um we come to the end of these five part
series on the gladness pentad and if you take a moment to imagine
a circumstance maybe in a time when things are going well for you
a time when you have no real concerns and that you can settle into your
meditation first with gladness it's like just uh just glad delighted
appreciative of the chance to sit in a place where
your senses are open your body is present
we're just being alive is enough when being alive is to be
present in your senses with your eyes your ears your body
with the mind here now maybe not the highest quality
but it's just nice to be here content kind of glad
and then you remember that you're here to practice
being attentive practice gently lovingly quieting your mind
letting your mind quiet because you can reassure
you can reassure your mind that your thinking mind that
don't have to do all this thinking going to have to fix anything or solve anything and it's
okay just to quiet and let the mind attention
be available for the Simplicity of being alive now with the breathing
and there's a joy in the Simplicity of presence with the breathing
and even if the mind wanders off there's a joy and recognizing that and beginning again
with the breathing with the breathing being kind of the representative representation of
being centered not at home here in this life in this body
we're just being alive is enough just breathing is enough
were we being present for the breathing the joy of it is partly
riding on the breath like a bird soaring on the updraft
awareness rides up and down on the breathing and
the updrafts and the waves
and in this Joy of the practice of being present practice
of keep showing up here feeling sensing the body the breathing
it makes a room for tension in the body to relax
there's a softening relaxing in the body
tensions of the face soften
tensions of the butt belly
small adjustment in the positions of your hands and arms too release any
tension that's held there
maybe there's even a little tension in the thighs that can be released
and maybe there's some tension or pressure
in the thinking mind some agitation and just being aware of it is enough
the joy of having an awareness practice that knows and sees
without making anything a problem
and so the within the mind has a chance to relax
also
and just being alive is enough sitting here breathing and being aware
attending to breathing
another level of contentment or happiness
physical satisfaction Maybe
that comes from a place that's deeper than places where the body aches or hurts or
the heart aches hurts
the place inside that maybe feels peaceful and quiet
and there there's a kind of well-being
there the breathing
gently arises and passes comes and goes
wave after wave
as the companion of an inner feeling of well-being calm
tranquility
where there's an inner place of Stillness and calm
maybe in the breathing
that is a center of gravity for all things where the weight
from the body gathers around this place
the weight of awareness Settles
the weight of your emotions your moods the atmospheres of your mind
a gentle pull of that Center gathers everything together here now
in the sense that your whole being becomes centered on
breathing centered on the Stillness or the peace
which the breathing moves through arises out of
even your thinking the weight of thinking settles into the
center and the thinking quiets Settles
and perhaps a sense that samadhi
is an immersion in experience immersion into this practice
and immersion at all of you together centered centering
gathered here now breathing
surrendering to the pull of the gravity of the center of your being
surrendering everything to that Center so it all gathers together
it's all working together here and now
foreign
at the center of your being
there's a sign a loving sign that says welcome
maybe he says all of you is welcomed here
give yourself over to this welcome at the center of it all
breathing in and out through that center of gravity
for all things
foreign
foreign okay
however far your thoughts take you away from yourself away from your Center
when you notice it let it all return
back to that Center in a sense bring your thoughts with you
so that they can relax and compost
back at the center of all things
and then taking a
gentle breath deep into your being
maybe taking a long exhale and pausing at the end of the exhale
in preparation for ending the sitting
brief pause
relaxing into your heart
and letting there be a whatever kind of sense awareness gazing upon the world
around you remembering it imagining it
imagining that your good will your kindness
your heart's deepest welcoming of everyone
welcomes the world and you
look upon it kindly may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
May the deepest way that you welcome yourself
to yourself extend out to a welcome to all beings
welcome letting them come well into your good
good will
[Music]
so there was unplanned the way that unfolded in terms of the meditation and
I was just welcoming you all to the sitting and having some thoughts about how to begin and
I was going to be explaining it and then somehow it transitioned into being I guess a guided meditation so hopefully
some of you understood and weren't waiting the whole time
and uh I think it came a little bit from my own
being quiet and settled and sharing that from with you
so we come to the last of the
gladness pent heads and this is samadhi and samadhi is a
powerful word in India and to translate it somalia's concentration we lose some of the
richness and the breath and the of it sometimes I have this idea that in its
Indian context samadhi is uh is has many meanings sometimes it refers
to kind of some of the deepest realizations a person can have
and um but in terms of and so some people will
understand it to be a deep absorption Emer immersion in our experience in
ourselves in the meditation we immerse ourselves in it some but it the quality of that
immersion that absorption at all is kind of like entering into a sacred
Place say sacred grove a sacred spot in nature a sacred Temple
there's really a feeling about this is this is where you know
allow me to say this is where church is this is where and if for people that are theistic which I'm not particularly but
this is the presence of God here it's it's a it's a really quite something to be immersed in with all this goodness
that samadhi is to translate it as concentration many
people take it to be kind of a laser focused bearing down a straining to look and be
but it's more like there's a welcome at the center of your being a warm happy
a loving welcome and that you somehow your system your whole psychophysical being feels that
welcome and uh and then is happy to kind of settle there settle
around it kind of like settling around the Earth or you know or a group of people kind of
settling around a fire and being cozy and comfortable together your whole being and so the part of what
samadhi is is a gathering together of all our faculties the classic language
is that of unification that there's a unified field nothing is
scattered nothing is fragmented we're not spinning out there's not a centrifugal force outwards with the mind
if anything there's a settling inward or here and as that's settling uh happens more
and more it's there's levels of it and the experience of somebody shifts and changes
and sometimes a sense of boundaries and barriers fall away then even though I
talked about this settling into the center um the center the idea that there's a
edge to the to the space which are centered on Falls away and sometimes
somebody just feels like we're immersed in um kind of like in um if we swim
underwater in a beautiful clear lake or some place and underneath kind
of in the scuba space it feels peaceful and quiet and we might look up at the
surface a few feet above us and see that there's some agitation of the water up there
but uh here where we are we're kind of immersed in this kind of boundless kind
of Water World so um
so samadhi and uh and the sense that samadhi is not
something to strain for is part of the lesson of this gladness pentad
that uh the um that it's built on the previous form
and you see in the teachings of the Buddha over and over again different kind of ways samadhi follows the the five the four
before it follows gladness Joy Tranquility of the body
and um happiness and then samani and it follows almost as a natural uh phenomena
and uh what we're doing here is a very profound principle of the Buddhas and
that is that we're not causing meditation to happen we're not causing samadhi or concentration to happen but
rather we're setting up the conditions that allows it to happen and and the way that these uh gladness
pentat is talked about is not something we do but rather something we allow
something that naturally flows that there's a naturalness to when we have
this Dharma gladness that from there there arises a joy from there there
arises Tranquility from there there there happiness occurs and from there samadhi
concentration happens so so
as we give ourselves to the practice we have to kind of practice as I like to say sometimes the practice
doesn't work at all I can finally tell you that practice doesn't work definitively if you don't
do it there is a doing of it that has to happen but what that doing is is partly
showing up really showing up here so we can begin allowing here to unfold
and here unfolds without our reactivity here unfolds without our straining and
wanting without our mind being scattered and distracted and so when we start becoming
undistracted and here enough it doesn't have to be dramatic enough that that
there's a there begins to be an unfolding a deepening that is not
necessarily our doing but what we allow for so if we're always staying the agent the
one who does uh in practice we can only take the practice so far at some point
we have to start being the doer that does something shows up but at some point we also start allowing then more
and more there's more and more allowing of something to flow through us something to unfold within us
it's not so mystical it's a very you know practical or very you know simple
that comes when we allow ourselves to kind of just be present and relax and
um one of the remarkable things that's kind of a little bit um embarrassing maybe for some of us
is all our grand conclusions about the world about ourselves and how terrible
things are how terrible we are or the challenges we have or even how great things are
that happen from the thinking mind the conceiving mind that's kind of living in its thoughts reactions ideas of things
that when those ideas and thinking quiets down we start living a different
world and where the conclusions are very different so even like this idea this is boring
boredom is a certain activity of the Mind actions of the mind that the mind
is kind of constructing the evaluation things are boring but as the mind gets quieter this kind
of centrifugal force away from the center that boredom is that there's a the boredom vanishes
and you see but it's not boring here at all um unless we return into that evaluative
analytical kind of mind which is an activated mind and this quieting settling coming
together uh immersing ourselves in our experience here that kind of begins to slowly occur on
its own and sometimes uh you know if you have a daily sitting practice
this process might be so slow it's inconse in in and can't uh
see it day by day there's almost like a slow and steady movement that moves us
through this gladness pentad so much so we don't necessarily see it or recognize
the stages as so slow but then eventually allows us to kind of sit down
to meditate and it's more like here I am and there's a entering into it or
allowing into it that maybe is a samadhi or it can be that sometimes in one
meditation session you can almost feel the cascading movement like water down
down a hillside of going through these different steps
It's relatively easy for me to talk about it it's not so easy to
have this happen so it's very important not to be you know be a kid in the back seat that's
saying am I there yet am I there yet kind of wanting it and trying to make it happen
a hugely important part of this meditation practice is a certain kind of
contentment to be practicing with whatever the circumstances are that you're practicing
with there's a very profound principle that I like that the Dharma knows better than
you what you should be experiencing that there are no mistakes when you sit down to meditate whatever you're given
is what we learn to practice with without trying it to make it different but rather to wake up with it to be
present with it in a very wise way if anything what we can do is we can
learn to relax relax with it all relax with a difficulty relax around
what's difficult let the thinking mind relax this
relaxing this tranquilizing is when as we stay present as we stay attentive is
this is the really the ingredient for allowing the gladness pent had to move
through us on its own then as we do that
and we come to some modicum of being settled and present here
so that we're not being scattered or pulled into the world
of thinking and reactivity and we're able to see and be present then the repented
gladness pentat opens up to being able to see how things are
uh just to see deeply and um and what we see deeply one of
those things is the nature of suffering we might begin the practice because we
suffer and we want to find some relief some freedom from that suffering
but we're not really ready to address it deeply until we've prepared the ground for it until we've entered into the
temple in a respectful and kind and appropriate way
and enter into the temple of samadhi then we have new eyes with which to see
the suffering so yes we're here to
overcome suffering don't be so concerned with it at first Let It Be the motivating factor and part
of what why you feel the gladness knowing that you're on a path to end of
suffering but don't try to fix it and navigate it as you begin your practice just develop
the ability to be present and then when the time is right that
when the Dharma knows best for you you will address the suffering in a deep way
and seeing things as they are is the the nature of it and then I wasn't planning on this but
that says coincidentally the topic for tomorrow's day long is the four noble truths truth of suffering
so it is kind of a follow-up today I don't know if there's still space in the day long
but it's it's online it's uh you find
the registration and um in the Insight Retreat Center
website where it talks about um
day longs online day longs there's also a link to it in the IMC what's new
and if there is space and you can only come to part of the day that's fine it's best to come early I suppose though the
whole day is going to be a cover the four noble truths it's kind of a little
bit of a teaching day and practice day and meditation day so
so thank you very much for this and I appreciate having this chance to teach
and be with you and and share this with you and um
and I do to look forward also coming back in the beginning again on Monday thank you