good evening good evening everyone nice to see you all
so tonight I'd like to continue on this series I've been doing on the seven
factors of Awakening and I've been on the last factor of
Awakening Equanimity and so this is another talk on equanimity
kind of fleshing it out and emphasizing different aspects of it
so this word Equanimity what is equanimity and as I as I said before it certainly
was not in my vocabulary before I came to Buddhist practice
but this idea that it's a steadiness of mind and a heart
maybe in in the face of whatever conditions are arising whether it's some
inner turmoil or some outer turmoil have some steadiness not be completely
blown off guard or blown off course maybe I should say
Equanimity is also in the maybe another word we could use is balance
and sometimes tetramajatas this poly word that gets translated as Equanimity
and that means like standing in the middle which also could be thinking about
balance or also a way in which to see kind of like
both the ends of a spectrum or to be in the middle is to recognize that it is
the middle that there are other things around it and not be just completely
lost in whatever it is that we're lost in
and it also has this um upeka is a second poly word that
gets translated as equanimity and this word
is probably literally means something more like looking upon
and I like this um definition of equanimity because to make this
distinction that looking upon as opposed to looking away
sometimes when we think of equanimity we think of okay so if you're balanced or
unshakable or steady we just assume that's kind of that means
you're disconnected because it's often how we think about things that if you're either in the
thick of it or you're disconnected from it and so Equanimity is actually something
in the middle of those two it's that you're aware of what's Happening you're connected to
what's happening you are feeling what's happening but you're not overwhelmed by it
you're not I said blown off course yours still
remain balanced so maybe it goes without saying that one
of the functions of equanimity it just makes life easier if we're not caught up
in the latest drama and you know in drama in terms of
something that's wonderful or something that's terrible but it also helps create the conditions
in which there can be some deep letting go right if there's some steadiness then
it's easier to see oh I don't need to hold on to this
I don't need to shove this away I'm just feeling okay and upright right here
so Equanimity is also a practice or a support for letting go
and so this uh simile that I I'd like to offer is about how Equanimity is part of
practice it's part of the way that we find our ways to Awakening
hence it's one of the seven factors of Awakening but here's a simile that the Buddha
gives kind of talks about Equanimity in the context of
um purifying or shaping the mind and the Heart
so this is the simile of a Goldsmith somebody who is taking gold
and heating it up and then bending it to be particular shape so that it can be
some jewelry for example or maybe coins or something like this
so the semi goes like this suppose a Goldsmith would prepare a hot
furnace heat up a receptacle take some gold using tongs and put it into the
receptacle okay right this isn't anything that's uh unusual have a hot plates a place and
then put some gold in a crucible and put that in with the heat
and then the semi continues then from time to time the Goldsmith would blow on
the gold from time to time the Goldsmith would
sprinkle water on the gold and from time to time the Goldsmith
would just look on as the gold was Heating this makes sense right of course back
then they didn't have a little oven that they could dial the temperature you had to just look at it and say I think it
needs to be a little bit more warm and then blow on it to increase the heater add a little bit of water to cool it
down and sometimes it was just right and to look upon
and then the assembly continues if the Goldsmith were to only blow on it it's
possible that the gold would just burn up get too hot if the Goldsmith were to
only sprinkle water it's possible the gold would cool down and would get too hard and you couldn't do anything with
it and if the Goldsmith were to only look upon the gold would not reach the right
consistency it wouldn't get up to the right temperature that then it would be malleable and flexible
but if the Goldsmith went from time to time blew on it sprinkle water on it or just
look upon it then it could become the right consistency an encryption of the gold purified
bright and blemished rid of imperfection this long list
those exact same words or how the Buddha describes his own mind right before
Awakening having all these qualities these
characteristics so the Buddha is pointing to you with
this simile that there's different things that are needed to help get the Mind ready for awakening
get the Mind ready for some new insights or for some letting go
you know whether this is like the big Awakening or whether it's just getting the Mind ready for more freedom
whatever way that might whatever form that might take
so as you might imagine this blowing on the Goldsmith is a
stands for like adding some more energy A little bit more effort to our practice or whatever it is that we're doing
to sprinkle water on it is to kind of like allow the mind to get settled and
cooled down to be collected concentrated and Equanimity is to just look upon
so I appreciate very much that that um here the Buddha is putting Equanimity
in the context of what's best for a practice at that time
this recognition that sometimes energy needs to be put in there this energy can
take all kinds of different forms maybe it's a little bit more investigation or just literally kind of
bringing up the energy not so much that one is restless but just to maybe apply
a little bit more effort but sometimes what's needed is to calm down maybe there is too much
restlessness and to calm down sometimes it just to look upon
and of course mindfulness is the faculty that can help us determine what's needed
more energy more calm or just to look upon
and these four faculties mindfulness energy concentration and
Equanimity are four of the seven factors of Awakening
so just this way in which we can they can all work together to help the mind
become bright I love this and malleable
wieldy so we'll D in terms of it can be shaped in terms of a bracelet earrings
or necklace but also wheel D meaning can recognize oh maybe there's a different
practice that's needed right here maybe there's rather than my usual mindfulness of
breathing I'm noticing that I'm having a lot of ill will for example and maybe I can do some loving kindness practice to
soften the heart and mind away from some ill will
okay so we might say okay well this Equanimity thing sounds interesting but well how do we cultivate that
how do we cultivate this steadiness this balance the scene the big picture
so there's a maybe it doesn't sound like um I don't
know maybe it's not too interesting or doesn't seem like So
Glamorous maybe Equanimity but when we put it in the context of what
our minds are usually doing right they're always trying to go towards the
pleasant and the exciting or to get away from the pain and blame and loss and all
these uncomfortable things so it's not the usual way in which our
minds are to have this balanced and steady way
so what are some things that we might do to support some equanimity
last week I spoke about the importance of some culturing well-being and
warm-heartedness number of ways we can do that
maybe I'll just say some loving kindness practice is an obvious way for some well-being and warm-heartedness
and I like this modern day simile that Rob barbaya uses another Dharma teacher
uses to describe well-being as a support for Equanimity he says
imagine that you don't know how to swim and you end up you know falling
overboard and you're in the in some water and then maybe you are
um because you don't know how to swim you're like thrashing about you know
maybe expending energy in ways that aren't so helpful when you have this panicky feeling
but now imagine if you don't know how to swim but you have a life jacket on
and you get put in the water then you have this buoyancy and you have this feeling like okay I don't know how to
swim but I'm not gonna drown and maybe you could find a way to kick
or Swim a little bit to you know paddle to where you need to go so you don't have that panicky feeling
so we might imagine that the well-being or some warm-heartedness is a way that can
be like a life jacket that when we do find ourselves in a place that's uncomfortable not knowing
how to swim when you're in water but it gives us some buoyancy and some
steadiness so what are some other things
that might support Equanimity what are some practical things that we might do
so some of you know that Equanimity is one of the Brahma vaharas
which is a meditation practice I'm not going to talk about that right now as Equanimity is part of a Brahma
vahara but I would like to say something that we can do in meditation practice
and that is maybe just at the beginning of our mindfulness practice to spend I don't know five or ten
minutes just kind of this with a settling and sometimes it can be helpful
just drop in and maybe the same way that we do with Brahma vahara practice where
we kind of like Drop in an intention but for Equanimity practice to drop in
may I see the world with quiet eyes
so it's not a demand it's not a plea
it's just setting the intention this idea of quiet eyes is not a usual
language and maybe there's some wiggle room in there in which you can find what what resonates with you in this kind of
unusual expression so this might be something that if you
find yourself really restless maybe you could drop in or at the beginning of a practice when
you feel like you'd like to cultivate some Equanimity is may I see the world with quiet eyes
or maybe there's some practices in daily life that we might do to support Equanimity off the cushion
and this is something that's been really helpful for me that uh when I first tried this I felt
like oh okay Diana this is uh good that you're doing this practice
and this is to um to evenly apply attention
to all stages of a project the planning the doing and the cleaning
up is there a way in which we can just just evenly apply attention to all three of
those stages so when I heard about this I thought okay you know I'll do this for this next
meal that I'm gonna make okay planning I can pay attention to that
preparing I can pay attention to that I did not want to pay attention to
cleaning up there was something about like oh cleaning up okay that's just something I'm gonna do quickly and look
at the last thing I got to do to finish up I just really didn't notice how much I was like in a hurry I didn't want to
do it I felt like oh this is this the extra stuff but there's a way in which we can just
notice how much of our life is kind of like planning and preparing doing and
cleaning up and is there a way in which we might notice that we only pay
attention between one of those three stages and can we
notice for one if we are not paying attention just bring a little bit more attention to that
and then this of course it turns out I'll speak for myself it turned out to be much more delightful to be paying
attention after clean it up after a meal and I'm not going to say that I'm always doing this
sometimes I'm like with the dishes not my favorite thing to do but
this is one thing that we can do Equanimity off the cushion to support us just pay attention to
or equal amounts of attention to all the phases of a project
but what are some wisdom practices that we can do to support equanimity
of course Equanimity as I've been talking about is part of the path of practice
and it's a big support for awakening and of course wisdom is a part of that too
so what are some other practices that we might do either in daily life or in
meditation as a support and one is just like I was talking about paying
equal attention to all three stages of a project whatever that project might be
so like just noticing in particular something
in the same way we can notice the changing nature of
things really tune in to
the way things that arise and pass away tune in to the things aren't always
exactly the same so this is a little bit different than
straight up mindfulness more that we're kind of like highlighting a certain aspect of our experience it's really
within mindfulness we do notice things arise and pus away but is there a way in
which we can tune in to be sensitive to pay attention to
that particular quality of all of our experiences
they're Rising their passing they're starting they're ending
and they're changing they're like getting modified as time goes on
and this is a practice because like all of us know we all know things are
impermanent right intellectually we understand this this isn't news to anybody but is there
is there a product it can be a practice to just tune in to this particular
quality of all of our experiences
and there's a way in which transformation can happen in which when we tune into
certain things over and over and over again
and of course seeing this change or fluctuation
in all scales right really small scales really the immediate changes of things
or the big scale the changes of the Season or in the beginning of fall
and starting to see that it changes the way our relationship to what's happening
if we're noticing that everything's changing then it's not quite as attractive to want to really hold on to
it because it it just doesn't make sense to hold on
it doesn't make sense to try to grab something that's like slipping away
and so we might even notice in our daily life reflection
are our moods exactly the same from the moment we we wake up until we go to
sleep how many different moods did we have how many different thoughts did we have
how many different things did we eat so just focusing on that particular
aspect of our experience the mind and the Heart can start to let
go because they see that things are not worth clinging to
and with that letting go this not clinging is a way in which we can maintain some of our balance or
steadiness because we're not trying to like grab on to things that are slipping away or we're not
trying to push things away so strongly because we're not insisting that things be a particular way we're recognizing
that they arise and pass away
another practice that we can do whether it's um in practice or in daily life
is what would it be like to not immediately have an opinion
about everything this is good this is bad this is this is this is really good and
this is really bad or something like this I mean so often we have opinions
and of course we do right things are Pleasant or unpleasant or neither Pleasant nor unpleasant
but an opinion is more like when we've kind of wrapped up a sense of Who We Are
with our whether we like it or don't like it often opinions are a way in which we
kind of Define ourselves I'm the person that likes this we don't
say it that way in our minds but it's definitely part of the the way that we
identify or with or get identified or create a self is to cling on to a view
also to it's also part of the way in which we align ourselves with certain groups of
people and distinguish ourselves from other groups of people
so what would it be like to soften that and to not immediately say
have an opinion this is good or bad might say well right now it feels
unpleasant and just end it with that it feels unfortunate it feels this feels
this feels Pleasant connected with that maybe some of you know this uh Zen story
of this farmer who is uh farming and he has a horse and
he uses the horse for farming to help maybe drag the plow or maybe he
rides the horse to help bring the animals in from posture the livestock in or
all these types of things right can use a horse
and then one day the horse runs away and the farmer doesn't have a horse
anymore some difficulty for him and then some of the villagers come by
and say oh so sorry to hear that your horse ran away this is such bad luck
and he says bad luck good luck who knows
and the villagers think that's kind of an odd response but they just go on their way
and then sometime later when he's working now it's a lot of work right without a horse
and he said his horse is returning and it's brought with it other horses
some wild horses that it had befriended so these other horses arrive with its
original horse and they follow the original horse into the Corral and he closes the gate and they go now he has
more horses whether this is a fabulous thing so then the villagers stopped by and say
wow this is uh what good luck you have that your horse brought back these other
horses and he says good luck bad luck who knows
and they think okay this guy's really odd person but that's all right
so then his son is trying to work with these new wild horses
so that they can really work there on the farm and while the sun is working with them
he gets kicked by one of the horses and gets really injured injured badly
broken leg and maybe some broken ribs they're not sure
so the villagers hear about this and say oh this is terrible that your son has this broken leg and is really injured
this is really unfortunate it's really bad luck
and the farmer says bad luck good luck who's
to say who knows so now right here's uh more work for
this poor farmer he has more horses but his son isn't able to help his son is
can't walk really sick or injured
and then there is a the Army comes by and they're
going to conscript any abled body young men
here's the sun of course who has this broken leg and is really sick and
injured and so he doesn't get conscripted into the army and so the
the villagers say wow what good luck that your son didn't get taken to get
put in the army and you know what he's going to say right good luck bad luck ooze to say
so maybe we have our own versions of this our story of this
Maybe we add some heartbreak When We Were
Young and didn't end up with a person that we thought we wanted to but then later found
somebody that was a better fit for us or maybe the same way with a job maybe there was a job that we didn't get and
but then we were able to get another job or we all of us have some stories about
this I know that I have to like when I reflect back on my life some things that
at the time felt really or heartbreaking for me but now I see oh
yep I couldn't have had this life now if I that had happened and this life that I
have now is so much better so maybe that's true for you also
maybe there have been some things that at the time felt terrible but turned out
in a bigger picture to not be so bad or maybe even to be great
so Equanimity is part of this not whole not having this opinion and really holding on to it oh this is terrible
right maybe it's uncomfortable maybe it's not what you wished but it was just a
reminder that things might turn out to you know in the bigger picture differently
so another maybe um reflection
to help support equanimity is often when we talk about Equanimity we talk about the support of these eight
worldly wins these eight conditions that affect
everybody without exception absolutely everybody and a modern translation or
interpretation of them we could say is success and failure status and disgrace
approval and disapproval and ease and unease
I said undies like underwear I don't know but that's opposite of ease
but uh ease and unease
and so we can reflect about these we can use our wisdom
and just you know maybe I'll just choose one of them this one approval and disapproval
if we think about it that um this is about what other people
think approval and disapproval and can we really control what other people
think no we can't we know this right we all know this
so is there a way that can read control the thoughts of others how many
thoughts do people have maybe that's just one thought that they had that they weren't so approving of
something that we did and the news cycles and the big picture but even the news Cycles in our little lives
right so interesting it's going to be different very soon so it's not that at that time
necessarily that people are going to remember this approval or disapproval so maybe
just kind of some reflection on this recognizing that it's not
we can't control what other people say or think and it's going to change anyway
soon and then lastly I'll say that
maybe just this acknowledgment of things that are uncomfortable or difficult
again this is a reflection or an acknowledgment
it's one way is strengthen our capacities it's not what we want
but maybe it's how we learn some things that are difficult
we learn how to be courageous only when there's opportunities in which we've
there's fear maybe we
learn to be patient only when we're feeling
impatient so in the same way whatever it is the
difficulty that we are having to work with and that we are not feeling equanimity
maybe it can be helpful to kind of reflect on the bigger picture and recognize that okay I'm learning
something important here maybe it's not even clear what it is
but difficulties are a way in which we can stretch our
capacities and we all have this
I've heard of this expression I wouldn't have wished this on my enemy but I can
see how it was really helpful for me it doesn't make the difficulty different
it doesn't make it easier but that is one way in which we might can see the bigger picture and
might be able to not feel off balance
with some of the difficulties
and maybe I'll close with this one quote which is um
from the Tara got these these verses from
some monks they're kind of part of their Awakening verses
and this is the verse from subuti
and this is uh something that he describes after his Awakening
but I think as if beautifully describes equanimity my little Hut is roofed and pleasant
sheltered from the wind so rain sky as you please
my mind is Serene and freed I practice wholeheartedly
so rain sky as you please
so this idea of having a roofed and pleasant Hut like he feels he has this
steadiness and he's this practice wholeheartedly that he's like giving him himself to the
practice so it's okay if it's really hot in the Sun or it's okay if it's
really raining and cold he's okay he's okay
it's the one way to think about equanimity
so now I'd like to open it up to some questions or comments about uh
Equanimity or some things that I've said here does anybody have some questions or
comments including anybody that's uh online with us
Sage behind you Jim has a question
thank you so much the question I wanted to ask is um basically a comparison between the
idea of equanimity and the like doctrine of not self it seemed like it seems like these two are
like very closely connected because the departure from our expectations about I'm sorry the last part I didn't hear
sorry I'm Ebola uh the departure from like our expectations about the little
like self in our stories about ourselves like is where the like Angus comes in I guess and I was just
wondering are there like sort of practices that are Equanimity plus like not all for
good ways to put that into practice I guess for the both not self and equanimity
I would say Equanimity by definition as you've kind of pointed out helps soften
the sense of self because we could might even say that whenever we are really
holding on really tightly that's when there's this self is really there and there's like so many things right that
we can hold on to so I would say any practice that helps soften the clinging
or the the holding on will support Equanimity and some that lessening of a sense of self
does is that helpful most definitely thank you I wasn't thinking about that yeah and maybe I could say something
else that um I talked about earlier with Equanimity not on tonight's talk but one
thing is something else that's a support for Equanimity is to recognize oh things are arising because this condition is in
place and that condition is in place and that condition is in place so of course it's I'm it's a rising here so that same
thing seeing the conditionality of things also really supports not saying saying that oh there isn't a self here
there's just all these conditions so yeah great thank you
anybody else have a comment or question
okay okay very nice
so thank you thank you for your kind attention and may you feel some balance
and steadiness and ease and your practice sent in your life thank you very much