so hello and welcome to this meditation session and to the talk that will follow
and as an introduction the um I want to use an analogy
that if um
you learn to float in water or learn to swim in water and then can feel very
comfortable and confident in the water and so that you can flip over on your back
and float maybe you're even in a salted body of
water or Salt Lake salted Lake or something that you're with the salt
we're even much more buoyant and just the stretch back lay and Float On The Water
and there's a way in which then we are trusting the the buoyancy of the water
the the water we know how to rest in the water be in the water and there's a kind
of a trust to it people who swim are trusting that they'll float and but they don't even
think about the trust they're just so obvious it's like that you know it's uh you know it's just so taken for granted
almost a second nature but there is a trust
and same way when we do Dharma practice
we are trusting we're learning to trust something that holds us up the word
Dharma uh the etymology of it literally means that which supports something that holds up
and um and so the Dharma holds us up and uh to be a little bit more practical
about it it's the practice that holds us up we can we can trust the practice
and you know that's not always so obvious but over time people who
practice a lot learn more and more that if they practice if they stay in the practice
even if they don't see the benefits immediately they can trust the practice it's like saying you can trust honesty
you can trust being present you can trust being present and non-reactive
there's something that deep that arises that's available that comes with that
kind of practice and but more broadly people will trust
the Dharma sometimes and that means trusting some of the basic principles
trusting non-harming trusting being ethical
trusting kindness compassion and
and so to put the put the meditation practice
in the contest context of this kind of trust and if you're new to meditation the
trust obviously and appropriately won't be there but as we keep practicing the trust
infuses the the practice story is connected to the the practice that we
do and that trust uh we're trusting something the Dharma the practice
that is a um Association of meaning
we're assigning a certain kind of
characteristic to um to the meditation the characteristic
being that it's not just our own efforts there's something else very profound maybe even more important than what we
do that holds us up maybe it becomes the practice becomes
second nature to float in the practice in the Dharma
so with that as an introduction you can
maybe take a posture assume a posture where the posture
is a posture of trust
posture that you can somehow relax very deeply
knowing or as if you know
that you're going to be in a trustworthy safe supported
during the meditation how much is the meditation will support
you no matter what happens trust the meditation trust the mindfulness
trust the keep showing up and being present
don't trust the reactivity don't trust the judgments the bias the fears
but trust the oh with a clear
honest awareness that there are judgments and fears
reactivity trust the practice of attention
trust awareness
taking a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in deeply preparing yourself for going into the water or into
a delightful place where you can trust if water is not a good analogy Maybe
your mattress is trusting going to bed laying there
breathing in deeply and long and relaxing exhale softening your body
letting the breathing return to normal
maybe on the exhale relaxing into your body
maybe like you're lowering yourself into a pool of water
as you exhale lower yourself into your body
and in this body of yours is there some location in the body
that you associate with a kind of trust or confidence that I've been talking
about when you trust the deeply
where in your body does that seem to live
and so sitting here maybe breathing through this place
breathing from it breathing with the trust
that being aware being present
is trustworthy more than anything else for these minutes
and if you wonder away if you wander away from that place of trust
then remember when you remember remember that place come back to that trust
and let the trust be the source
or the support
for this awareness practice we do
being aware being attentive and mindfulness Here and
Now not contending with anything
opposing or favoring anything just aware
aware of the breathing
the body
and maybe in the middle of the awareness
can there be Trust
you trust the awareness floating in the awareness
not so much doing awareness
but resting in it allowing it floating
and then as we come to the end of sitting
a meditation where trust has been evoked
there are other things to trust when we trust other things than just awareness
that we trust when we're in the Dharma
who we can trust generosity
being generous trust kindness
friendliness
trust compassion and care
especially when the opposite of those are strong for us we have to be careful not to trust those
we have to learn to practice with them and be wise about it but the idea of entrusting ourselves to
them giving ourselves over to Being Greedy or miserly being unkind
mean angry hostile uncaring
in the Dharma this is what is dangerous
and where our safety is found is in the generosity and kindness and
care
and when we trust those it turns out that it's easier to trust
being aware it's also a more wonderful and wondrous
to be aware in the context
of wishing well to others Wishing Well to oneself
may it be that your Trust of the Dharma your trust of
mindfulness is strengthened
with your good will well wishing to others
may it be that
you wish well to those people in your life
those you encounter
May others be happy
May others be safe
May others be peaceful
May others be free
and may I may I trust enough May each of us trust enough
to float on those wishes to act on those wishes
may we benefit bring benefit and Welfare to others
[Music]
thank you so this is the last talk on the theme of
meaning in the connection to doing practice doing meditation practice
and the meaning is the assigning of value purpose
um interpretations to uh
our meditation practice to Buddhist practice and there's many different assigning of
purpose um value that we can give to it and I've
said this already but for example someone might go and we have some kind of illness and the doctor says you need
to find some way to have less stress in your life I think you should meditate
and so the assigned meaning and purpose of meditation is that it's for
distressing and the primary interpretation understanding of what meditation is is a form of de-stressing
someone else might find that they are struggling at work because they have to
give regularly Little Talks publicly to a large group
of people at work and they are petrified really afraid and they stumbling over the words it's very hard for them to do
it and they think I need to find some way to calm
down and to work with my fear and so someone suggests that they try mindfulness meditation
partly to calm down but partly to kind of get a handle on what's really going on there for them and and to kind of
work through the fear or learn to hold the fear in a different way and not be hooked into it
and so that becomes the assigned meaning purpose value of it is to help them work with their fear
someone else might feel that in some
clear way they have been suffering much of their life there's been a sense of heaviness
or despair or or strain that they kind of live with and
even when they go on vacation there's something not quite right there's a dissatisfaction
and then they hear maybe some Buddhist teaching in a classic little example for some people is they hear the teachings
of the four noble truths and they say wow no one's ever talked about so so putting
front and center that there's there is suffering in this world and everyone I've talked to before is trying
to get away from it or say it's not really there it's kind of trying to paint a nice picture of how wonderful
this world is and I just see suffering everywhere and hear these teachings say
yes there is suffering but they didn't stop there they said there was a cause and a possibility of
freedom from that suffering and they have a path they have a practice for doing that
and that just kind of um so now so that excited them that kind
of void them and uh and kind of did yes this is what I want to do and motivated
them so now the assigned meaning purpose value of meditation has to do with some
of the deeper existential issues of being a human being that that person has
some people do the practice of meditation do other things that somehow
open their mind dramatically release them from ordinary kind of states of
being in the world where it's so strong me versus you and so strong like we have
to kind of just kind of chase after our thoughts or whatever our thoughts chase after us or very strong sense of kind of
alienation from everything or for the world or all kinds of ways in which people live
and somehow something they do a time in nature
time with a lover taking a psychedelic or
meditating and in meditation deeper and deeper they might get released
from so much of the holding patterns and tightness and constrictions of their of
their mind their clinging their wanting their fear and they start having a taste a feeling
an experience of what it's like to not have any of those present to be able to
breathe easily to feel effects of freedom to feel a sense of intimacy with the world a very different relatedness
to the world around us and to other people that it feels so much more meaningful
than anything else meaningful perhaps because the alternative way of being hurts is challenging is stressful
and it feels really good it feels healthy it feels more natural
to not be caught up in the fears and their desires and their greeds and the conceits that we can have happen
and wow this is Health this is psychological spiritual health
this some people it's not just psychological It Feels So pervasive throughout their life pervasive
throughout their Consciousness and how they touch the world or see the world or perceive everything that to call it
psychological seems to limit it to something kind of bounded or small
that this is big this is everything and um and so now the assigned meaning
to the meditation is that it's a way of living from that place or being
connected to it or finding it or or practicing in a way that
um is kind of uh attuned to something that's more than
psychological well-being and health but some kind of spiritual kind of or broad
existential way of being and so there's all these different levels or layers or ways of assigning
meaning and purpose and value and and understanding of what meditation is
and uh none of them are wrong they're all kind of wonderful it's
important for each person to find where it is for them right now so they can do it do that way well and engage well with
that each of them have kind of little different ways of practicing different orientations different
focuses for what the mindfulness can be um but for the topic for today is the
way in which meditation the meaning of meditation the assigned
value of it or the dissociation we have with it um it can be with what we what some
people might call the sacred what is most sacred and that's of course a big word that
some Buddhists don't care for we don't hardly I don't think there's any obvious Buddhist word that you know Pali word
that can translate our sacred but except maybe if we want to use the word Dharma
and um or sometimes the word noble is kind of used that way sometimes
but I like the word sacred because it's not so clear what exactly it means but
it has to do with our ultimate value what we what we see and understand and and Orient ourselves to that uh that
touches all aspects of our life it's kind of the heart or the source or the
the context for how we want to live our life that kind of what what defines our
life or what's value what validates something or our whole life the whole
existence it um it is all inclusive and um and my kind of favorite
definition of what is sacred in our Buddhist practice is an awareness that leaves nothing out
as soon as there's a selection process that says no that I'm not going to be aware of that I'm going to exclude that
is not acceptable for me to bring attention to this open clear mindfulness
too then we've kind of shut off from We're shut off from the sacred and what is most sacred is when the
awareness is all encompassing nothing it doesn't mean we agree with everything or condone everything but the awareness can
hold it all and we trust that awareness and then within that wide universe of
awareness that we float in that we live in that we trust and then we find our way with wisdom
with whatever is going on and if we have to say no to something we say no but but
it all held so and but other people have other ideas
of what is sacred or sacred is not the right word is Ultimate the what it says
ultimate value for us or what we are committed to
um to put at the center of our life some people put family at the center and
with family maybe is a Love or the connection or the sense of responsibility or devotion or some
people put of course put work some people put being of service to others
than his ultimate some people it's a connection to God if you belong you have
a theistic orientation and um and um but in in the in Dharma practice
at some point what becomes can become Central for some people is the Dharma itself the practice itself
and so at that point it's so ultimate so like the center like what gives the most
meaning the most valuable most purpose um to our lives that that's where we
want to have our life come from and be supported by and you know everything has
to be connected to this Dharma then one of the reasons for that is we've learned that anything other than
that of what we understand to be the Dharma non-clinging anything other than
non-clinging that involves clinging is less healthy is less less satisfying less meaningful
less you know just it hurts so when so at some point to the
meditation then becomes not something that we have to do and add to our life it becomes our life
and there's a wonderful transition or switch that can happen where rather than asking the question
how can I bring my practice into my life meditation is great but I want to know how I'm going to retweet is great but
how do I bring this practice into my life and that's a beautiful question I love when people ask that question
but at some point the questions changes at some point the question beat the
equipment becomes um how would I bring my life into my practice
The Practice Center Stage the practice is the stage
and the question is you know how do I bring the audience how do I bring the visitors how to bring everything up on
the stage to be included there rather than you know our ordinary life is the stage
and the practice is one of the people in the audience that gets invited in to be part of part of the
play so um so to then to trust this to have
faith in it to have confidence in it is one of the possibilities
in this topic this theme of meaning where do that the meaning is that this
is what I trust this is what I have faith in this is what I have confidence in
this is where I have certainty that this is this is the right place for me to be
the center the focus the root of my life and some people at that point will feel
well you know wait a minute I'm being disloyal to my family for example or you know I
have to love them and to have something else be have more Central seems like a betrayal
and this is my proposal is that that doesn't have to be betrayal
the love you have for the World for family the
uh and other things that's important for you they can remain just as important to
always as they are now there's no diminishment of importance
but more important is the Dharma is the practice of
mindfulness the awareness practice this that's that's more Central
and and rather than diminishing the love and the care the responsibility
the devotion towards the things that are important you were we float in the Dharma it holds
us up so we can do those things are worthwhile we can do them better
it doesn't diminish their importance it just makes them richer and more valuable and we we come to it as a better person
so it is safe to put the Dharma at the center of your life more important than anything else
because it's the water that we float in and how wonderful to float in that water
then you can be a lifeguard if need be but if you haven't learned to float
you're not going to save a lot of people