so uh so welcome welcome folks
um yeah nice to be with you see the names over
there um let's uh let's meditate
and just immediately when you hear that Q let's
meditate just notice what you
do to move from the mode of chatting with friends
to beginning formal
practice and maybe you do need to do do some of the things you
do but maybe not others
and so we begin by uh just being very
natural at this moment
not forcing us into some
slot that we think is meditation is very
natural certain kind of trust that the ingredients or wisdom
love are already here
e
e e
relax whatever can be relaxed let go
whatever can be let
go are clinging necessitates a lot of uh agitation in our attention
as we begin to uh make peace with the
imperfection of the moment
to uh to not
be constantly seduced by the the thought
that something could get
better so we make this kind of Peace the attention system Settles
the spotlight of attention that illuminates
phenomena the breath the body sound
whatever starts to Glide more
smoothly
e
e e
and sometimes
we relinquish uh control even further not
even trying to direct the spotlight of attention anywhere
come to rest
back in
awareness and so if I told you to stop
being aware you couldn't do
it and whatever you cannot
stop rest
there
e
e e
the attentional spotlight can be used
for developing some Stillness
focusing the attention or the attentional spotlight
uh also necessary for
clinging the awareness pointing to
only ever let's
go
e
e e
we're awake and knowing is
happening the field of knowing is
unpartitioned but the knowing doesn't feel like it depends on me
the awareness no longer
tastes like
me
e e
[Music]
okay so um a Dharma Dharma
Pleasures um we could have chose from many many
but um began with the pleasure of having a p PA the pleasure of sourcing motivation
from love purification the pleasure of
purification the pleasure of Tranquility of turning the dial
down and um today the uh the
pleasure of uh friendship
a colleague colleague of mine jezelle Jones um who's
uh couples who does a lot of couples
therapy it's a clinical social worker um she defines
intimacy and that she comes as a a guest speaker in this UCLA undergraduate class
for for uh mindfulness practi I of Science of mindfulness and um comes in each each
quarter um and to to give a lecture to the undergrads and um and defines
Intimacy in that context as the willingness and the ability to see and
be seen the willingness and the ability to see and be
seen and um I I believe that
we we need to be seen at our best and our
worst we need to be seen at our best and our worst if um we're only known in our
strength we might become arrogant or
defensive and if we're only known in our our
pain uh we might become
deflated and so it it feels important to be seen
clearly lovingly in both our strength and um and our desperation
um there are uh there are primary relationships mostly
family kind of relationships where where my defilements are known with such
Exquisite detail you know you know those relationships yeah
so there are there are several people in my life who could give a
topographically precise map of my
imperfection very precise you
know and it actually feels great to be known in that way yeah like if you
aren't it feels like you're hiding that hurts and so to be known in
one's imperfection feels vital but we also need to be known in
our [Music] Beauty and sometimes loved ones do this
of course but sometimes they're too close to see or sometimes they may not
know exactly what to look for and so we
have kalana the spiritual
friends and spiritual friends have have many roles in our life but
um uh one of them one of them is to see
the most beautiful Parts in US yeah that's part of the role of s yeah
we say s this community of spiritual friends
now that does not mean that a spiritual friend is ignorant about our Neurosis
but their attention their attention is directed to
goodness their attentions directed to goodness and there's there's much pleasure in abiding with others in
goodness uh the the the poet
uh canel said um sometimes it's it's necessary to reteach a thing it's
loveliness yeah and um that's part of the function of
spiritual friends yeah to illuminate goodness we become sensitized to
goodness we start to see it everywhere yeah and uh
and our our goodness is recognized the intimacy of of the
ability willingness to see and be
seen we um we need good friends because
um we're so we're so porous you know and
we're we're way more suggestible than we think we have this sense of like H I'm kind of an island
and or something like that even if we think of ourselves as very relational you know we think these are
my views I I my I'm Matthew Eric Bren silver and this is what I believe you
know this is why I believe that and it's like
please who knows who knows where our ideas come from all the places that
shape The View shape the nature of the fabrication shape the way the
confabulation of our
life we we just take on the tone of what's around us yeah and so I walk into
a fancy store and I start believing in wealth I walk into a party with fancy
people and I start believing in power and we need places
where uh we believe in wisdom and
love we um in other words must be continually
reminded of our goodness
and this all this Dharma stuff sometimes seems so self
evident to us in a moment of peace or Clarity so
self-evident but it's very inside baseball yeah it's very peculiar and
idiosyncratic and against the stream and
Fringe I I was driving through California from the Bay Area down down
through Southern California through Bakersfield and into uh to a retreat at um at Big Bear in the
mountains and um so many cities and towns and Landscape so
particular and I it was intense you know I I felt
like um just in seeing seeing it felt like I could kind of
infer something about the Mind States based on the geography
and the buildings and everything and um I I did not see the
Dharma many places it looked like it would be very hard to sustain Dharma
attention and um that's not that person's that place's
fault but it's intense yeah
and so maybe we have conditions that remind us of Dharma that reconnect us to
the necessity of wisdom of love and we need our friends to keep
reminding us of the urgency of that
project our our practice is you know Dharma practice sometimes
I talk about it as like okay it's making our heart into something like
art and um you know I don't know much about art an art
connoisseur like um seees something sees a painting say and they know so much
about it they see they literally see more than I
do um but we're connoisseurs of goodness yeah
that's what we're training in and um
start to see a lot of Beauty in others yeah and they see Beauty in
us and it's um it's a delight to Reve the
same things something in the heart is uh quenched
as uh we come to rever the same
things and teaching teaching this week teaching anytime
teaching is um is entirely about uh your goodness
resonating with mine a sense of um of mutual
[Music] recognition and
um sense of of a kind of um abiding
Abiding and um I I don't want to you
know the practice of teaching I don't don't don't care about being loved but I
do care about uh being seen
yeah and um to the extent that we we we
see and are seen together that is a beautiful thing and
um come to abide in the the kind of the goodness of Our intention here to
practice and and um that's uh that's very nourishing yeah
that's good Dharma pleasure it's all wholesome
pleasure and we're doing it right
now so um yeah thank you thank you thank you
all uh appreciate uh appreciate your your uh
wholehearted participation this week thank you for
being uh yeah being patient uh with me
and um yeah it's been been lovely to uh to
be with you so I um I wish um I wish you
all all well your your path and um the the YouTube SAA continues I'm
almost certain Gil will be back uh pretty sure that's the schedule he's
finishing a three-week retreat which uh it's a beautiful thing
too so um okay we will uh we'll we'll we'll pause
here and uh thank you all thank you Kevin who editing talks getting them posted to
Dharma seed and um yeah other IMC volunteers all volunteer you know very
appreciative of the work that uh happens So yeah thank you uh thank you all and
sweet to see these chats and um may we be well