so a warm hello from Redwood City
and the topic this week for meditation and for that little talks is equanimity
and one of the very important aspects of equanimity
to cultivate or to think
develop Equanimity is um to realize something very profound and very wise about the nature of choice
that people have choices that they the choices that they make
and this is true in meditation as well and we I don't think we have much talk
about choice in the context of meditation maybe because it brings up
too much the thinking and reflection and perhaps
too much self-consciousness where we're really trying to let go of self-consciousness and really settle
down and not think so much about what's happening but really get focused
and clear and recognize what is happening so the however choice is operating all
the time for us and one of the opportunities in meditation is to as the mind gets
quieter and still learn more focused is to see how much choice we have
and then to carefully lovingly
peacefully make choices and it can be as simple as a choice to
it's you're better off spending time with your breathing and getting focused then thinking about
um you know what websites might be interesting to visit today
and um and so you know you the thinking about websites can wait
there's a better choice to stay here with the breathing it might be a choice about how we return
to the breathing if we don't see we have a choice some of us might jerk the Mind back we might be
angry for being distracted and thought but if we see the moment of choice we see we have a choice about how we relate
to the mind being distracted How We Begin Again with the breathing and we
have a choice to perhaps relate to the thinking mind as a friend in a friendly
way or as a as a wayward friend who said friend you know that's not the direction
to go and come back here come with me um keep me company here so I can return to
the breathing something that's Kinder and softer and gentler than the harshness of maybe jerking back
or being upset with oneself and then coming back to the breath in a way that's peaceful
not in a hurry not aggressively not with high expectation but a simple matter of
fact peaceful way but also committed way to be back with the breathing
we have a choice when we're focusing on the breathing whether to do with laxidasically to do it without to kind
of complacently without much effort kind of wishful thinking oh I hope something helps me to stay on the breathing
or we have a choice we can make the choice to come back so okay I'm here I'm going to plant myself here
I'm going to organize my very being okay I'm going to be here and the best I can
lovingly peacefully I'm going to really try to stay connected to this as if uh maybe I'm carrying
caring for a young newborn baby and in
my arms and I just want to make sure I don't drop the baby I want to make sure the baby feels safe and held and cared
for and and I just really stay and be present and feel it
so a choice and the choices you make are consequential in meditation
so how can you use your capacity for choice for recognizing Choice as you
meditate so that it helps you get more peaceful and settled how can you make choices in meditation
to support you to be present at ease calm peaceful and really kind of
engaged in a peaceful and relaxed way but in a in a
dedicated way just this this is the most important time to make a choice
that this place where you're sitting now this is the most important place this is
the most important time this is where your life at your
attention your life force is most valued most beneficial
and to make a choice to really stay here with us
and if you don't want to make that choice if you have other things you would rather choose to do I think about
what websites to go on or plan the day and things like that and it's really clear then you maybe
know oh this I have a different preference I have a different purpose
and to be clear about that maybe changes your relationship to meditation or maybe
supports you so to take a meditation posture and
assume a meditation posture and to
choose a posture that is the best of your ability will support you
during this meditation time
and if it's comfortable for you you can close your eyes
and to have the choice the decision to
cultivate an ability to be present in this body at this time
and express that choice in taking a few gentle long deep breaths
and perhaps as you exhale maybe exhaling with a either vocally or
silently with a kind of ah
ah where that ah is it real
support for really being here and feeling here
if you do that loud uh uh maybe the way that the sound vibrates
from your vocal box and down into your bodies
carries you into your body
As You Are to relax the shoulders and the body here
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and to become attuned
to your exhales
a little bit more refined attention to the body
exhaling
perhaps ever so slightly letting yourself exhale a little longer
than usual not so much that it's a strain but just maybe for a moment more than
you would otherwise choosing to let the exhale be more
complete
and then as you do so to also relax places in your body that
can be softened and released
the muscles of the face
the muscles of the shoulders
maybe softening the belly
and if possible if there's a softening the hands and the arms
and then for the next few breaths being attuned to the inhale
really feel what it's like to inhale from the very beginning
to the end
and you have some choice about how you experience the inhale
maybe choose to the attitude to have towards it
to be one that's allowing non-judgmental
maybe just simply curious or
generous allowing it to be just the way it is and you choosing
to receive it or to know it
just as it is
sometimes I've imagined the inhale is like
riding as some kind of
some kind of vehicle that takes me up to the top of a hill
and then the exhale is uh sliding down
when it's time to Exhale choose to be there
for the full slide The Full Experience
be there peacefully allowingly allow this
way of this part of breathing to unfold on its own
and then as we continue sitting the mind wanders off or something new
happens notice at what point you have some choice about how to
respond or to that and as soon as you notice you have some
choice choose the peaceful choice
choose the ease will ease easeful way
of engaging your attention yeah it choose the peaceful way
of being mindful
when and as you get quieter and Stiller appreciate there's more choices to have
for being attentive peacefully
to concentrate easily
and you have a choice about how often you choose
be relaxed and at ease no hurry
but don't linger and use your ability for choice
to choose the peaceful mindfulness the easeful concentration
as we sit now in silence
your freedom is found in the choices you make
and if you don't make choices consciously your mind will choose for you
in a way that you're not really free
to find the peaceful place where wise choices can may be made
for using your attention
to choose to be in the present moment peacefully consciously
mindfully is the path to Freedom
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to appreciate that to love is a choice
to be compassionate is a choice
to be kind and have good will as a choice
it's a choice by where for how we where we put our attention
what we choose to notice in other people and
what we choose to notice in ourselves
and if kindness and good will love and compassion
is valued then a peaceful Choice can be
to look upon the world to look upon others with
kindness with good will
not waiting until we just happen to have good will or it's an accident that we have it
and it's an action to have good will and compassion
you don't have to feel it necessarily it's a choice of how we look
how we are present for our experience
and so as we come to the end of this sitting I'd recommend that to the best of your
ability you choose to look out across the world to the
people you know and others with kind eyes
with an attitude of Good Will and generosity
and to value our connection
our interconnectioned with others the mutualities of Our Lives
and then to have the desire to share
whatever benefits you have from meditation today whether those benefits are known or
unknown choose to share it with others
in the way that we do with the dedication of Merit May whatever benefit and Merit that has
come from this meditation today may I look for opportunities
small and big to share it with other people
if I'm calm may I bring some supportive calm to others if I'm Wiser
may I bring wisdom if I'm more able to choose to be
friendly and kind of generous let me do so in the
in the ways in which I communicate with people today
May It Be that the way I choose to live my life
is one way or the other knowing or unknowingly for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be healthy
may all beings everywhere be free
foreign [Music]
[Music]
so good day and
I suddenly find myself feeling I think quite happy to sit here
I think because of the topic of equanimity Equanimity Brahma viharas
that I'll be speaking about so this is the second talk in this series on equanimity
and um the um
so that as a form of care for others an attitude of caregiving and attitude of
kindness Goodwill for others uh Equanimity is when that Goodwill
is equanimous or not reactive or not um
agitated when at Goodwill is not influenced by any kind of pursuit of Desire of wanting
something and uh and not caught up in repulsion or pushing away or not wanting something
and so and this comes into play particularly
importantly when it's hard to have good will for people it's hard to have pure
love or kindness for people because of the circumstances they're in
and um and so one of them is that uh when people make choices
for themselves that are not for their own benefit and the um and to have Equanimity for
people who make choices that uh or for their even they're they're harming themselves with a choice
that's their choice and that's their agency that's their choice to make a
choice in a sense even if it's unconscious the choices they're making and but the choices of Their Own
and so how how our Goodwill comes into play when people are making choices of
poor choices is part of the part of the domain of the of this uh Brahma Brahma
vihara of equanimity so it doesn't make you know so certainly we can feel compassion for people
but the idea that you know to try to help them and want to help them and when
they're making the choices that are going in the opposite direction it's kind of exhausting for the person who's
compassionate and maybe maybe pointless uh to have appreciative joy for their
Joy when we know they're making bad choices we know that suffering is coming is also challenging for the person who's
wise and sees what's going on but to be able to see this person is
making choices there are unfortunate choices they're going in a poor Direction
I still keep my heart open to them I still have this Good Will and care about them but it doesn't and I harm myself if
I get all agitated by it if I get contracted around it or if I keep pushing to be compassionate and try
everything I can to help the person or if I go along and celebrate with them when what they're doing is actually kind
of quite harmful even though they have a kind of a joy um and uh so how now to harm ourselves
uh with our Good Will is a little bit the domain of equanimity
so the word Equanimity in Pali is upeka and it has that it comes from the root
verb to see to view to up to observe
and it kind of uh the etymology of the word kind of means to have an overview of the situation and I think of it as a
bird's eye view and so to not be lost in the in the details of everything but kind of have
the overview of everything so we see it see it we can see it with wisdom and see kind of the bigger picture of it so
we're not caught in the details so uh there are times when people for example uh will do you a favor and they
you come to work or someplace and a colleague says you know I had a really difficult night last night or that's
very hard you know I have a family who has covid people are dying or you know
or that my child was up all night and throwing up and having fever and
and uh and they come to work and they say they say you know it's had a hard time and I'm really irritable
and uh and you say oh thank you for telling me and then if you find that there expressed some irritable kind of
tendency uh that um you're much more forgiving of them you say oh you know
they've had a hard time you have the overview of why they are the way they are and so you they're more you're more
have more space for them to be that way they've warned you they've been kind enough to warn you and let you know and so you kind of get out of the way okay
that's just that's that's today they're that way and you feel for them you have compassion for them
a little bit so you you kind of equanimous about how they maybe say a mean thing or they cut you off going to
the bathroom because or something um whatever it might be
and so in that sense there's an overview of this equation a bigger picture of it and so we're more equanimous and we're
at ease with how what to do so upeka is a wisdom Factor where our
understanding of the situation is really useful for having that granimity to
Simply hold ourselves in an equanimous way is probably not so helpful if
because holding and assuming something which is not really true for ourselves can also be exhausting and be harming
for ourselves so to under to begin kind of finding how do you have that bigger picture how do
you have the view the understanding of circumstances and of other people so that when we have good will for them
when it's appropriate we have Equanimity meaning we don't get agitated we don't
get Restless or upset or contracted and and so one of the one of the classic
teachings in Buddhism is that everyone is has their actions as their
own and um uh the uh everyone people their
actions no one else makes like for your your actions are your own actions that
no matter your circumstances where you found yourself in life there's a lot of unfortunate things that happen to people
we get sick and in all kinds of ways or we end up living in a war zone or some
ACT some a car drives into us we're doing nothing wrong but someone else maybe is not paying attention they run
into us and we're injured and so those are not our choices to have these things happen
but uh but when we choose to we have a lot of choices and how we choose to
respond to any of that how we choose to live our lives we're always at a moment of choice
and when we are practicing mindfulness we start seeing more and more the places
of choice more and more we we notice that there's actually a lot of choices Moment by
moment if we're not mindful we're just on automatic pilot we don't see that we
have choices about how we stand and how we look at people and when we speak and
when we don't speak and how much food we eat or don't eat it just we're automatic
pilot a habit comes into play or craving comes into play or aversion comes into play
and it's a it's driving the the boat we are not in charge
but when we see the place of choice because it's just clear in the quiet
open mindful mind then when we exercise that choice
we it's up to us the consequences of that choice
so if I uh see a a you know a
a thorn sticking up out of the ground and I see it I know it's there and I choose to step on it and if I cut my
foot in his blood that was my choice to do that because I
I chose to step on it that's a kind of dramatic example but if
you see you have a choice about what you're going to say and you feel angry and you're going to use a swear word
with someone but you see you clearly have a choice if you say the swear word and the person
gets angry back that's partly a consequence of your choice that that happened or that person walks away and
doesn't want to talk to you that was partly a consequence of your choice but if you see that choice then
and then you can say well wait a minute I have a choice here what choice do I want to live by what is my deepest
Choice what's the deepest value as I want to live by here what's most important for me a pause and look and
choose what that is and uh and so
um when we want to have we see that other people have Choice as well
and we can't be in charge of the choices other people make and we might support them we might help
them advise them all kinds of things we might do but ultimately people make their own choices
and when they make choices which are not wise for them they are they they it's
it's their consequences they're going to have to live with and if those consequences are unfortunate it's
heartbreaking sometimes but to not get our our good will our love for them
tied up and dependent on the choices they make
so that we don't exhaust ourselves with our compassion we don't kind of regret the ways in which we
celebrated with them or um you know and so to have good will
with this overview of looking at people or make these people that I love that I
care for they're making choices and those choices are not wise
and so I have to allow them I have to be generous enough certain generosity to
give people the autonomy the Dignity of making choices of Their Own
and then they have to live with the consequences I will offer what support I can I'll try
to be supportive but I'm not going to be responsible for the all the consequences of their
poor choice they're going to have to live that out themselves to some degree exactly what degree how much we're
involved and don't involved has a lot to do again with uh the consequences we
think will come about by offering our support for someone if we think we can
actually turn the boat turn them in a new direction or help support them to
come to a new way of living maybe it's really great to offer a lot to them but there's you know but not to but be very
careful we don't harm ourselves in that process and this is why mindfulness is so
important to really track ourselves and see what's going on inside of ourselves and we have choice we make choices as
well and can we choose the peaceful choices it doesn't mean the passive choices it
doesn't mean that uninvolved choices it means whatever choice we make can we do
so without the the negative alternatives
to equanimity can we do it without a
Pursuit without chasing something wanting something
getting something and kind of getting caught up in that need for something to happen
and can we do it without a repulsion or contraction or reversion
or pushing away or closing down or pulling away in horror or something
can we do it without being restless and without being agitated can we do it with the mind at ease
and if we mind is at ease then the Good Will as as Equanimity and it becomes the
Equanimity Brahma vihara so um
beings are so I'll read you the very famous
almost it's used liturgically in Buddha about Buddhism about this that I see it as an understanding appreciating
people's place of choice um oh maybe I don't uh
maybe I lost it here um
beings are beings have beings have actions
I take as being choices as their own they have actions as their Refuge they
have actions as their Heritage and they have actions as their
as their closest relative as their what they're connected to
so actions and choice are closely related here and so be careful with the choices you
make and not to be hamstrung not to be inhibited not to be
um passive in some kind of negative way use your choices so whatever you do in
the world you do without hurting yourself so you say at ease
stay peaceful stay equanimous in a way that allows the
best qualities of who you are to be shared with the world too
thank you very much