good evening welcome welcome
you know there's not so many of us in this room maybe it would be nice just to say your name and where you're from you
don't have to but it might be nice maybe we can i don't know if we need the microphone
sir and we can start with you oh maybe we do need the microphones
having the masks on that people don't hi everybody
can you hear me i think so i think we can hear my name is sveta
my name is sally from menlo park
kath kathy from redwood city
ombuds for milpitas
hi edwina from san bruno
hi everyone anne rose from redwood city but sam bruno this that's my sister oh
nice
nathan robert's shorts hi everyone
hi everyone i'm kevin from san carlos
phil from redwood city great great thank you thank you for that it's kind of it's nice to
know the names and i'll try to remember but chances are not high
a test after yeah i think oh you're kevin right yeah
okay i got that one phil kevin uh nathan kathy
i don't remember your name oddfish ambush ambush
and what was your name edwina
anne rose edwina and rose sally and sveta and i'm diana
i remember that that's a good sign right
okay so welcome welcome everybody so tonight i'm going to continue on i'm
doing the series on the seven factors of awakening and last week i talked about samadhi and
i'm going to stay on samadhi again i'm going to kind of flesh it out and talk about it a little bit more today
samadhi i'm using the pali word not the english word because i think the english word has a lot of
associations that might not be so helpful or yeah has some baggage along with it so
let's give the definition that i would like to give and there's a number of dharma teachers that
use this definition so it's not 100 percent of diana ism but
it's a way that i think it's a little bit fuller and helps us appreciate it and that samadhi is
the mind and body feeling unified settled and steady
in a state of well-being three different elements there mind and
body and i'll talk about that in a little bit here the body's definitely involved
settled steady and unified so not distracted or
not uh split with our attention going anywhere and everywhere and then with a state of well-being a
state of like some niceness we might say and um
i'm using kind of these vague words niceness and well-being so that we don't have to get so caught up on exactly what
it is and uh maybe maybe not today but uh
maybe next week i'll unpack that a little bit more but for now we'll just use this kind of well-being
samadhi so i will say that um often the english
translation that's used is concentration but right when we hear this word
concentration we kind of think like of this narrowing and this burrowing down and straining and huffing
and puffing and you know trying to really stay on the object we don't think about well-being we don't
think about the body and it's often it can we have these ways of how we think about
samadhi so i'll be using this word samadhi
and i said this last week but um i just want to emphasize it again that it's not one
thing i mean i described it as a state but it's not like in or out
you have it or you don't you know it's not like that it's a spectrum and so we could say here's this more
unified collected and here's completely distracted and in terror and disembodied
right at one end and then the practice is just to move in the direction towards
more collectedness more settledness more well-being and in a way that includes both the mind
and the body is kind of a way of being unified
so one thing that as i said i'm talking about samadhi in
terms of it being an awakening factor so it's the sixth of seven awakening
factors i'll just list the other ones here i'm not going to talk about them but mindfulness
investigation energy joy tranquility samadhi and then the next one will be
equanimity so these are nice thicks right these kind of energy joy tranquility
so it's this all these um supports for awakening when i'm using
the word awakening here i'm pointing to this really greater freedom
that's available this freedom from whatever it is you feel like you need freedom from
anything and everything literally everything so it can also this we might even think
about it as a spectrum um i remember i heard to gil gosh this was
quite some time ago give this little analogy about freedom which has stuck with me all these years
maybe it was because uh he said it right at the end of a retreat and write it you know our minds are a little bit more
settled in the retreat and things come in and stick but he gave this little story
of he was kind of describing freedom and he said that in his household it was
the tradition that on sundays they would have waffles and that he would make the waffles so
every sunday you know make these little waffles and one of his sons uh liked to have
syrup with this waffle that's perfectly reasonable but they wanted syrup in every single
little one of those little squares and not any on the plate
so this kind of particular way that the syrup has to be right
in order for the waffle to be acceptable to be eaten and then so there's a certain amount of
suffering between the sun and the father who's uh trying to make these waffles and make them just
right for this one but then he said you know as his son grew up he just kind of outgrew it just
didn't make so much sense anymore and you stopped caring so much about this syrup having to be in exactly every
waffle and so gail was pointing to outcome sometimes freedom is like that you just
kind of like outgrow or you just naturally let go or it's not such a big part of your life
anymore some of these things that used to be a source of suffering i'm using suffering right in this really broad way
difficulty uncomfortableness but also what's interesting about this
story so this sun kind of grew up and
had this shift in his idea of how his food had to be so he certainly had more ease
but his father also had ease right didn't have to make the breakfast
being perfect so when we find more freedom it affects those people around us and this is part
of why we practice not just so that we feel better but just to make the world a better place
the world ends up becoming a better place whether we wanted to or not by the more freedom that we have
so how does this samadhi tie in with this freedom
this greater freedom so maybe this is uh
one thing that i can say that and i pointed to this also last week that as the mind and the body start to
settle less distractedness less
restlessness less agitation but still with some real brightness and clarity so
it's not a dullness it's not like we've kind of fallen into a stupor
or some cotton ball where we don't feel anything now the samadhi has a real quality of
yeah i use this word brightness so there's that there's a real clear scene
so as the mind settles as the body settles there's this increased clear seeing
and we there's a number of we can see a number of things quite a few things
that just like that story i told with a girl and his son
kind of like shifts our relationship like once we see that
then we're just like oh i i just i don't just our relationship to it changes so
we don't we aren't holding on to it in the same way it just feels natural just to stop just
let go so this letting go happens and turns out
letting go leads to more freedom absolutely every time
but right we have to know like there's the letting go has to
come from a place well maybe i should say i think there's old letting well maybe i can't make
blanket statements like this because of course right an exception showed up in my mind but
for the most part the direction to go is towards letting go
because we know that clinging brings suffering grabbing on
gra snatching this kind of like you know holding on really quick quickly that
does not bring more ease okay so what are some of these things that we
see that allows us the letting go to happen which allows the freedom to go happen
so i mentioned this a little bit last week and i'll just say this briefly again but
we as we this is as the settling starts to happen we start to see through or
maybe notice how oh yeah our experiences are not always the same
we might have this feeling i'm a happy person and we might not be noticing the times when we're not happy or i'm a sad
person and not just really noticing the times when actually it's we feel perfectly fine
when we're in the shower cooking breakfast or taking the dog for a walk you know there's our moments during the day when
that are maybe neutral we don't feel sad but as the mind and the body start to
settle we start to see not only in our daily life but really deeply in meditation practice
how things are changing ideas we had about ourselves
are not so solid and things aren't uh so
constant and stable and like square black boxes like okay this is
good and this is bad or i'm this way i'm not that way we start to see like oh wait some of these things
they actually aren't as solid and stable and many of them are flickering
with some you know really fast or maybe it's slow
and so this this ideas of solidity and continuity that we have about so many
things in some ways about everything we realize oh
they're not solid they're not continuous in the way that we thought
and when there's this deep scene we realize oh it just doesn't make sense to
be really grasping on to something that's really changing and isn't uh solid like we thought it was
it turns out that when we're really grasping we're actually grasping to a concept
those are the only things that are really solid concepts but you know other
things turn out not to be as solid as we think but i'm not going to get into all the physics and the metaphysics maybe about
that but just this recognition that things
don't they're not the way that we imagine that they are or that we're experiencing them
as our relationship shifts then the clinging shifts we don't have to stop the clinging it
just naturally happens that way and so one way maybe a little bit more
specific if we're doing meditation practice
and as the mind starts to quiet down often this doesn't happen until somebody's on
retreat and they have these maybe extended times of meditation
maybe a few days maybe it's different for different people
maybe it's not on first retreat but as the and maybe for some people it is
some people it isn't we're so different but the whole
experience of having a body starts to shift too
this perception of the body changes
the edges don't seem quite so definite doesn't quite feel as heavy or
in fact maybe there's times when we don't even feel like there's a body at all
or maybe it's just filled with this lightness or um lightness in terms of lack of
heaviness but also lightness in terms of lack of darkness so these two different ways
but then we might say like whoa what's happening with the body and then we might just uh check like we could open
our eyes or even check like oh yeah okay it's actually here the same way but it
feels different and we just might feel into that
and then we could just ask well it definitely feels different
and but i know i don't always feel this way and we can look and say but my body is
still here and it feels different so which is the real body
like which is the real way it is
and then well it feels real when i'm meditating it feels certain that real feels a certain way when i'm not
meditating when i'm not don't have some samadhi it feels another way
and so this is also one of the things that we see with samadhi is
our perceptions can change something that seems one way
can seem another way in another setting and we just start to see this in more
and more things and what i'm saying is not anything new everybody knows this
in some kind of way but maybe we haven't really thought about it we know that when we wake up on the
wrong side of the bed so to speak we're just grumpy then everything that day just feels irritating and bothersome
and we aren't our best selves and impatient with people or whatever it might be
just because we're grumpy and then maybe you get an email and makes you
mad but if you woke up that morning feeling refreshed
you had your waffles exactly like you liked them right and the day was then you know that
same emails okay yeah maybe that other person was in a bad mood no problem i'll
just respond to this right we don't have the same reaction so which is real
is it the way that it's perceived when you're grumpy or is it the way that it's perceived
when you're in a good mood so samadhi starts to help us see oh
maybe there isn't one way maybe perception changes
depending on how the mind is and we know this but when the mindset we
start to see this more and more clearly and then also there's some letting go like okay
i'll just use this grumpy example okay this email arrives and you feel grumpy but you might also recognize i'm just in
a bad mood today it i'll feel different like we have this expression oh just sleep on it things
will feel better in the morning right there's this recognition that it's not always just one way
but this we start to see this in more and more things and a little and more thorough and pervasive way
and this supports some let's i don't have to hold on to it because i know that it's can be seen another way
so there's some letting go and without letting go there's some more freedom
but maybe i'll say just um a little aside about this idea of the as the body
so it turns out that the body is really important in samadhi practice
and certainly kind of like the first stages of samadhi and we we might think like oh it's just
the mind and you just have to focus the mind but it turns out that actually it's
integral to have the body to have this sense of the body and
right now i can point to a few reasons why that is but one is
somali doesn't arise if we are like over efforting
i gotta get it dang it i'm supposed to get settled and why is my mind so distracted and you know this kind of
this uh restless or this i don't know what the word is but this irritation or
frustration with ourselves and trying to will power and trying to you know make
that mind stick but sometimes we don't even notice that we're doing this because it's a habit
it's how we show up in the world in so many different ways and of course we do right because
sometimes it's helpful to do that in our daily life but we try to take what works in daily
life and apply it to meditation some things work and some things don't and this is one of those things that
doesn't but we might not notice that we're doing this
until we pay attention to the body and we notice that maybe the shoulders are up and we have our hands for me i
notice i get tension in my hands and i'm like making a little bit of a fist or something or or maybe there's this way
in which we're really leaning forward or the way the chin is really up as we're striving trying to make something happen
so sometimes it's not until we're really aware of what's going on in the body that we know some of the subtle
stuff that's happening in the mind and as long as these things are
happening the mind that somebody won't arise this mighty arises with it's a letting
go it's a softening it's you there can be a certain amount of
focus but that you can force yourself to do but it's not really sustainable and that's
not the same as samadhi so maybe that's one reason why the body is helpful
but the second is i keep on talking about this sensitive to or having a well-being
and often this sense of well-being also shows up in the body
i'll talk a little bit more about this next week i think but i'll just say there's often maybe like a
literally a little energetic uh
effervescent glee maybe i'll use that word
um that just kind of shows up in the body like oh yeah this feels good
that's kind of a feeling so i just want to kind of throw that in
there how the body is part of samadhi practice and how part of it helps us supports us with uh
samadhi but another reason how samadhi helps us with
more freedom is when there's the mind is settled it's
more malleable it's not so brittle
and what i mean by that is you there might be this recognition of
okay when i meditate i do this for example
i have i have the breath as the anchor and when the mind wanders i come back to
the breath and then when the mind wanders i come back to the breath when the mind wanders i come back to the breath perfectly fine to do this practice and
it makes absolutely no difference how many times you have to come back to the breath honestly
but there might be we might not notice how the way that we're coming back has a little bit of
irritation with ourselves disappointment in ourselves frustration and that's a little bit of
it might be really slight but this little bit of ill will or a
little bit of like i said earlier dang it why is my mind not doing this
and so what might be helpful is to open up to
some warm-heartedness maybe do a little bit of loving-kindness practice one way to open up you can also open up
by doing mindfulness as sounds so somali helps the mind to be malleable
in terms of it can be open to different ways of practicing to be sensitive to
what's helpful here what's helpful to support this sense of unification this sense of settledness
the sense of well-being the sense of being connected or embodied so it's not like stuck in one groove
that can only go in this one gear or can only go this one way but morris can be
flexible and try new things and this malleability also goes with
this shift of perspective or shift of perception i was talking about earlier
oh we might see things differently and if the mind is malleable we can play
with that a little bit oh i noticed that i'm a little bit angry
about that thing that that person said earlier today
then we might have this well can i soften around that and there might
be this sense of malleability that oh yeah i can't shift my ideas about that
and that brings more freedom so that's another way that samadhi
helps us with some more freedom but also as the mind starts to settle
there sometimes we as we kind of like open to
little that more settled level and then we we remember
what was less settled we realized oh yeah there is there is a
little subtle dukkha in the less settled state
there was a little bit of agitation a little bit of suffering that this
level this definitely has less duca but i didn't feel like i had any duca before
but now that i'm a little bit more quiet i can see the subtle duke of this
subtle unsettledness dissatisfaction a little bit of tightness wishing things
were different or something like this so the mind settles it helps us to see more
and more subtle levels of dukkha and where there's dukkha there's
clinging we can almost say they're synonyms and so
when we start to see that then we might have a little bit of curiosity what is
that took about and maybe we can shift our relationship to a
little bit or let go soften whatever it is that's uh
supporting that dukkha
here's one other thing that we can see with samadhi with somali practice and as
we gain samadhi is it starts to become abundantly clear
how little we get to control what the mind is doing
right we all would prefer to have this collected state of well-being like why
not but we can't make it happen we can't just say okay mind do this
it doesn't work and we will try [Laughter] we will try and try and try of course we
will of course we will but what we start to see is that actually we don't control
what we think we can control instead
we can help create the conditions in which it is more likely that it will
happen we don't get to make things happen
and then once we see this very clearly with samadhi you start to see this very clearly
often if not every time in the beginning when somebody arises for people
it's a surprise because if you're really gunning trying
to make it happen it won't happen so usually when it arises it's a
surprise because you weren't looking for it and yet here it is it arose
as more as you start to see oh so many of these things arise when i'm not
trying to make them arise but i'm settling i'm kind of relaxing opening
softening being with what is in this gentle way with a real with a commitment to
practice with a loyalty to the object
but with also softness and openness then we start to see that things can
arise and we also see that things end
we don't get to control when they end even if they do arise so this recognition that things
are not controllable we start to see how many things in our
lives are not controllable a part of us knows this but we start to
see it in a deeper way and it becomes glaringly obvious right if we're trying to
quiet the mind so these are some of the things there's
a few more things but um maybe i'll save those for another time but way
in which this kind of like samadhi is can be a support for greater freedom but
it's perfectly natural that like oh okay diana if i've convinced you or anything it's
like okay it sounds like a good idea but and i'd like to try it but how do i do it how do i make this happen
and i as i said it's um it's about a com having
a steadiness to practice that has an orientation to well-being
which isn't the same thing as pleasure they're definitely related but isn't exactly the same
thing but with some softness and openness and this takes some practice to
how can we be sincere and persevere and consistent
and have ease how can we not like pounce on something and think like okay i'm gonna hold on
i'm gonna be with this but how instead can we just with some ease just come back and come back
to the object maybe i'll end with this poem that points to this
this poem is by maddie weingast who's a poet who was inspired by
some of the poems that were written by women thousands of years ago
it's quite something buddhist women thousands of years ago this is the oldest literature
by women that has survives to the modern time
and uh so maddie weingast he's inspired by these women so this isn't exactly what
the women said i looked at the paulie what what he's referring to it's not exactly the same but if the
mood is the same okay so here's this poem
this is a nun speaking when everyone else was meditating
i'd be outside circling the hole
finally i went to confess i'm hopeless i said
the elder nun smiled keep going she said
nothing stays in orbit forever if this circling is all you have
why not make this circling your home
i did as she told me and went on circling the hall
if you find yourself partly in and partly out if you find yourself drawn to this
path and also drawing away i can assure you
you're in good company just keep going
sometimes the most direct path isn't a straight line
i appreciate this so much like like okay if you're restless and just all you're doing is circling the
hall walking walking walking or whatever whatever it is okay that's what it is
this practice isn't asking us to be somebody we're not it's not asking us to be completely
different we start where we are we work with what we have and we don't
have to be different we just work with
what's available of course we do like how could it be otherwise so
i know i just i love this poem i think it's a an encouragement that even if you just
find yourself circling just keep going and this the elder nun who is uh
patachara we sometimes put a we have a statue of potato sometimes that sits here
so she was patatara was just encouraging okay just make it your home
so samadhi it's a number of different ways it's a support for our practice and the support towards
greater freedom it's part of the way in which it's one of these factors of awakening
so if you'd like we can take some questions now
and if there aren't any questions that's okay too but
and sveta i don't know if you can see if there are questions on youtube
and if there are then um maybe you can say there's a there's actually one question okay
um jesse is asking how is samadhi related to the four janus
yeah so samadhi uh i'd say the four genres is a subset of
samadhi um and i'll talk a little bit about that i think uh next week and for those
people who don't know jana's is a an absorptive state it's a particular
meditative experience or state and so smarty is broader has a broader
definition but jhanas are definitely are as part of a samadhi so
anybody else have a question
yeah maybe we'll use the microphone
so i heard an earlier talk that um you can think of buddhism of having two
wings cultivation and letting go and sometimes i notice when playing with
letting go and just um you know letting things arise as it is um there's this uh space and just you
know things are are how they are and like oh you know you can add in things
like um equanimity or whatever and i'm just curious
uh as you're adding things in uh these qualities then it's not um it's
harder to let go it's hard to do both at the same time and i'm curious um
your thoughts on like the balance between that and um yeah
so the balance between cultivation and letting go yeah
i would say that we are cultivating qualities to support letting go
and i would say that letting go is part of the way that we cultivate qualities
so the way that you you heard it is there kind of these two uh i don't know two movements of the mind
maybe cultivation and letting go um they definitely go together and in some ways they're the
two sides of the same coin but let's see
i'll definitely would say that this practice sometimes the way that we teach it um
it can feel like okay i have to acquire attain something samadhi i have to get this and
this tranquility thing or this mindfulness thing so we sometimes feel like we have to
acquire but this practice is really about letting go kind of shedding
but in order to really allow some of the deeper letting go
it's helpful if we have some other qualities if we have some
steadiness if we have some well-being if we have some understanding of what is underlying the difficulties in
our lives if we have some understanding of what are the things that we can let go if we have some understanding of what
is letting go and stuff like that so is that helpful yes very thank you
[Applause]
i have a question um so i know that tranquility i heard many
times tranquility is supported by tranquility right tranquility is supported by
tranquility so if there's tranquility there can be more yeah what do you think about samadhi so
so do somebody experiences they do they kind of train our mind to
maybe experience you know absolutely yeah yeah they really do if you have a if you
spend a lot of time in samadhi some of the deeper stages it really
becomes um some of these stages that are really pleasurable and just really
satisfying in a way that our regular uh thinking or something like this it it
gets so that like you can just remember them and you're having that experience just
because you're brought it to mind again so it's definitely but it's not until you have those
experiences of course right until you can remember them right so yeah it definitely does kind of
this might be going back to the first question about the jonas but is there a relationship between
samadhi and stream entry like when you enter that phase of awakening
i'm because i i've heard of stream entry being a part of awakening as well and there's samadhi too so i get a little
confused by the the terminology sometimes yeah yeah um so stream entry is the first level of
awakening and it's kind of like you enter the stream of the dorm it's it's kind of a clunky nomenclature
and so a question often arises do you have to have jhanas in order to get stream entry this is a common question
and i would say you have to have samadhi for stream entry you have it maybe
maybe not all the way full into adriana but you have to have cl you have to have a samadhi definitely
some settledness stream entry is just the first stage of awakening
if you want to go to later stages i would say probably some jhana is required for that is that helpful is
that kind of answering your question
hi dana i'll be quick i just wanted to say thank you last week i was a bit upset about my
meditation practice and you had brought up the measuring thing and that that's what i was doing
and for this sitting i was just kind of letting things be as they are and i
wasn't waiting for the bell and i was like and when it came i'm like oh
there it is and just that less of the resisting you know and just kind of letting it be
not that i experienced a state of samadhi but i kind of understood like okay if i'm
gonna circle or i'm gonna do it and i'm just gonna let
it be as it is and see where see where it takes me and fantastic
thank you yeah yeah i'm happy to hear this thank you thank you maybe one more or one last
question did you eat nope nope okay
okay okay so thank you all thank you all for your questions and
your attention it's a delight to practice together i really appreciate it
and may you have some sense of well-being some sense of a collectedness and maybe some embodiment
to you in your days and your meditation thank you
and if you'd like to come up here and talk to me you're welcome to do that too thanks