I'm David Cohen yeah and uh
what I'm assuming about all of you which is is that uh
we're all here you're all here for in your own unique way
you're here to uh be Freer from suffering than you are now
a little more liberated than you are right now
which is compassion
so we all share this this is It's So human
we all share this human quality of compassion
isn't that nice it's like a field a field of compassion
not just among each other but
you know with your family and your friends and
everybody in Redwood City everybody
all beings everywhere
poor people in war-torn countries poor people who are
you know afflicted by climate
floods and Heat and but just on a
every day is uh you all know it Duca do you know
what Tuka means duka yeah ducas Buddha said duka is a quality of
inherent dissatisfaction that human beings have
so all beings have duka all beings want to be free from dukkha I
want to be free from suffering all beings
have this we share this compassion for ourselves
for each other not just human beings all beings insects
Scurry away when they feel your
approach
and we also share a desire kind of the two sides of one coin
the desire to be happy we want to be happy
we want to be at ease and peaceful
have some sense of well-being which is like
a quality of love we have some
some intrinsic love
that wants to be happy once our loved ones to be happy
once our loved ones to be peaceful and at ease does that make sense
yeah we share this love isn't that wonderful we share love
a field of love in here we all have this it's all you know in your own way you're
all meditating tonight and
motivated and so you came here tonight motivated in some way by these his qualities in you
he's tender hard qualities
so I was reflecting as we were meditating
um who
who are well I'll say me who am I who are we who am I
who am I what am I you know how did this happen how did
this all this come about this
what am I
there's a a saying by Miller repatis is a saint
a national treasure in Tibet said something like
strong and healthy we don't think of sickness
until sickness strikes like lightning
caught up in the world we don't consider death until death strikes like
thunder
thank you so those are other things that we share
very soon older than most of you here but very soon all of you you know it's
like sick
won't be able to sit here and meditate
so um that's saying
that observation was meant to like well let's not waste time
here let's do what let's let's uh we don't have much time here
what do you want to do with this time do you want to get distracted until you get sick
do you wanna go
none of us want to get involved with the five poisons that you know greed and
hatred and jealousy and pride and all these things that hurt we don't want to
do that but sometimes we just
we want to you know spend this time maybe maybe
well something think about what
what really matters to you what do you want from this time honestly
truthfully which meaningful to you
the Buddha was amazing he
he had what many people would consider
um the perfect life
he had what many consider he had everything people some people would say you know according to the human value
system the worldly value system [Applause] he had wealth
sensual Pleasures his father um an oracle had told his father that
you're going to have a son who is going to take two two paths one of two paths One path
is going to be he will be like you our great king
with power over many kingdoms revered respected feared by
many people and or he'll become a renunciate he'll
become a sage a spiritual a monk a spiritual Seeker
and his father didn't want that
so he created this you know
Haven of Earthly Delights he was not exposed to any suffering whatsoever even
a nice sense pervaded the castle and music and art and
loving family and and he was the best at Athletics he was he was so smart and loved by his parents
and haddock wonder he had a family he had a loving wife and
one son rahula and uh
but then he went into the town unbeknownst by his
father I forget how old he was maybe 30 I don't know and it's late 20s
and he saw sickness he saw somebody who was
um foreign
I forget what the sickness was I forget how that was but it was clearly he said what someone was apparently very
apparently ill and asked his chariots here what's going on
there I've never seen that before and he said well that man's really sick
and then he saw an old man and what's going on there I've never seen that before well
human beings get old then he saw a corpse being carried
through the village what's going on there what's that all
about well human beings die
and then he he saw a man in with a shaved head and robes and
walking peacefully through the village who what's that who's that and he said well that's a spiritual Seeker that's a sage
he
so this this hit him
this struck struck him deeply that
that human beings get old and they get sick and they die
and he wanted to he was became obsessed with what is going on here
and and whatever he was was happening with him before these Earthly Pleasures these Earthly Delights
and and you know reputation and so forth
they paled in comparison to this this question of
who am I what am I what's meaningful
foreign and um
so he left the castle left his family behind
and uh wore robes and uh
he pursued yogic practices the most strenuous yogic practices that
were going on in India the greatest teachers and he surpassed all of his teachers
and they shall get practices and so he had no answer to these questions it didn't it didn't really
resolve anything and then he
did concentration practices John is
and he surpassed all of his Masters in these concentration practices and he went you know into deep levels of
space and peace and nothingness
and he would always come out of those so what nothing's happened
here nothing's happened to me I I don't I'm no further along in understanding
what's going on here this mystery
of finding meaning of finding who I am of what's
truly important
and then he he was
had five friends who were ascetics and they were practicing extreme
asceticism they didn't really even want to eat they barely ate
and that didn't all these practices all these Pursuits
didn't bring him any peace didn't bring bring him any resolution
and he was so thin it was like a skeleton it was said that there are there was a mustard seed could
separate his spine from his belly and he almost passed out by the side of
a river I hope this is okay I'm telling you this long story
it uh it'll come to a punch line pretty soon
[Applause] um so this shepherdist was watching him from
across the river and she understood what a great Sage he must be you know
and she saw him almost die almost collapsed by the river skeleton and so she she crossed her her
name was sujata she crossed the river and brought him a bowl of rice milk
and she said venerable sir would you accept my offering
of some rice milk and the Aesthetics were around him and they
were just appalled they would not be drinking this bowl of rice milk but he did he said
okay I will he and he he drank it and he revived
a little bit and then he went over and they left
disgusted and they and he went over and sat by a tree
and he gave up he had just given up on all this driving
all the wanting to become all the wanting to get rid of
get rid of negative states of Mind get rid of
thoughts get rid of
distractions get rid of
maybe everything emotions
he gave it up and he just sat by that tree and a memory came to him when he was
seven years old just an innocent sitting by a tree watching his father do
plowing exercises out in the fields
so this is what I'm getting to he just gave up
he just sat there and he gave up gave up striving
and he just became himself
gave out trying to become somebody else
trying to become some goal some some something other
something other than just this
and he became enlightened something wonderful
dawned on him and he had a lot of he had a lot of very positive Karma that
had been built up that allowed him to have this fantastic experience but it
just it just came over him just this enlightenment
just by being himself
and he he said this is peaceful
this is he described who he was like this you know what he'd been looking for all these all this time
this is peaceful
not even me just this this is profound this is natural he said
this is beyond Concepts
so this is Luminous words like that you know who knows
exactly what he said but these are some words that have been passed down
and um he sat with that he sat at ease with that
there's a story about a rabbi his name was zuzia
and he was a great Rabbi he had so many you know congregants that adored him and
he he would people would give him gifts and money he'd give everything he'd always
give everything away and he's his family it was penniless lived in utter poverty
and whatever and then he came as well he was yeah
just a totally kind man totally good man
and when he was dying
his congregates were all gathered around him as he was dying
and he was crying and he's his congregants would say Susie
why are you crying he said I'm afraid to go to heaven they
said why are you afraid to go to heaven you'll present yourself to God you've been
you've been as kind as Abraham you've been as wise and just as Moses you've
been a Supreme Being
he said I'm not afraid that God will ask me zuzia why weren't you more
like Abraham why weren't you more like Moses he'll ask
why weren't you more like azusia
this um craving that we have
to uh
create some kind of superior self or uh
get rid of inferior selves
or to Adorn this self with praise from others with reputation with achievements
hoping for all these adornments of self
I think it's safe to say these are common to all of us we want to be praised we want to be
liked we want to have a good reputation we want to achieve we want nice things we want pleasures
for this self
all about the self we don't want to be criticized we hate to be criticized
we hate to be judged we judge ourselves
we hate to fail all these worldly
Endeavors that have to that that are
have to do with a dualistic
perspective that there's this me
and other and I want this me to be
um acquires be seen and so forth
foreign
s of the self the
the pain and the suffering around
the self is something that's addressed by
all Buddha Dharma it's the problem the self is the problem
and when zuzia wanted to be himself
and when the Buddha let go of all striving
to become and seriously
all is striving to be like Abraham to be like Moses to be like the other
Patriarchs just to be himself is like a no self
it's like giving up
and just relaxing into whatever this is
in the avadan tradition it's called no self
and the Zen tradition or the Mahayana tradition it's called emptiness
in the vajrayana tradition it's called
the dharmacaya understanding
that we aren't a self
and the more we understand that and the more we let go
of our grasping to self
and our aversions to what's not validating the self that
we want to be validated the more we let go of this this kind of
dualistic perspective and come back to
what is really no self at all
it's like the degree we can do that is the degree that we are relieved of
suffering is the degree that we are happy there's a
a correlation the less we think about concerned about strive about
ourselves the more at ease we are doesn't that make sense
so it's like we don't have to do anything at all
foreign just to be
is enough
just to be foreign
there's this great master and he was
speaking to a large congregation he was on a platform Podium or whatever
and giving a speech and giving a talk to his followers and
over to his side was the president of the congregation and he said my dear
my dear follow the followers my my dear Congress
I've come here today to tell you something very important very profound
and then he started to cry tears came into his eyes he says
I have finally discovered that I am nothing
and then he started to cry and there was silence in the auditorium people were in rap just looking what's
going on here and um
then the president walks over to him and and he addresses the congregants and he said
you know I've been president you're president for for so many years and I followed the Great Master and
and he said and I too I I've I've finally plumbed The Depths and I realized that I am nothing
and he's crying too and people just don't just don't know
what to think they're struck and then from the back of the of the
hallway and the rear of this old small man who'd been the janitor
cleaning up there or taking care of the building for 30 years 40 years a long time
he was so moved and he he fell to his knees from the back of the hall and he he yelled out I am nothing I am nothing
I know that I'm nothing and he was crying
and the uh president goes up to the Great Master and he says so look who thinks he's
nothing
yeah so there can be spiritual materialism as well as worldly materialism
but to examine this this idea
and I'm not sure how helpful this is to you but um
this idea of no self this idea of emptiness
but it's like a bit of a scientific proof we're clearly not our bodies
I'm holding out of my hands if you feel your fingers you feel the the pulsations in your
fingers the uh the body's changing
on a micro level it's just pulsing pulsing the whole body is
in constant change from microsecond to microsecond
the blood going through the system the digestion of food
on a macro a little bit more of a macro level the the breath is
constantly changing
we're always changing our form is always despised so we are not this body
I was a little boy not too long ago look what look what I am now an older man
so you're not your body you're not your mind your thoughts are
like butterflies flickering and flickering and flickering changing every what were you thinking
30 seconds ago just
thoughts thoughts thoughts we often think we're I'm this thought
I'm that thought I'm just this happened to me and you know
but it changes very very quickly even the most stuck thoughts give way very
relatively quickly and the thoughts are tea bags for our feelings
so they change a little more slowly but what were you feeling a half hour ago
what are you feeling now
and if you listen what are you hearing
and you can sense the changing you can't grasp
and you know seeing we think we're seeing something but really I'm seeing Pieces Just My my
focus is always changing we're in a state of just
complete change all the time
so we're not our sense perceptions we're not our thoughts our mental formations
we're not our body
what are we what are you this is the question that was driving the Buddha
from a scientific perspective quantum physics tells us that we are
particles that the particles that make up this this
are the same particles that are everywhere they've looked at under a
whatever a microscope super magnifying glass
it's all the same and what's more the particles are
made up of subatomic the atoms are made up of subatomic particles that are made up of some and it goes on at infant
items so that you so that actually you cannot see you cannot see a particle
and they're moving at thousands hundreds of thousands time of times the speed of light
and to add insult to injury there 99.999 space
these particles that we are
so in a way we're like uh that great Master we are nothing
we are nobody and we have nothing because it's all just all yeah changing
so that's a very cognitive you know that's a thought but but
it's it's true you know you when we think about this
it's we can we can contemplation is is a
very healthy part of our spiritual practice inquiry
to get down to it what really is here who am I
what's worthwhile why am I practicing what do I want
it's important
for Buddha conclude just
to be
just to relax to let go
to not try to become some
illusion that we're pursuing
and just be like space open
empty
but we are not nothing
yeah we can see and hear and
more vividly vividly
alive present
wonderful it's wonderful what we are
we're conscious as we were meditating just now I was
reflecting on
the Buddha described we well we have this awareness we have this
you know we're conscious and I was I was looking to think all of you are conscious
you know we're conscious of hearing conscious of sight
conscious of thinking conscious of feeling
conscious of our the Buddha named eight consciousnesses
and besides the five sense doors there was just thinking
and then he had a whole separate category for self
self me me me thoughts and feelings and impulses the
meaning the meaning the selfing consciousness wonderful I have this self in
consciousness and then the afflictions the habitual
afflictions
so this is another just just looking whatever you know when today just looking around what what
Consciousness were you involved with at the time were you involved with consciousness of
an Affliction like low self-esteem
or were you conscious of the breath sensory perception
or hearing
so we can
when we relax and be
we are also not just empty not just nothing
but we are vividly luminous
so anybody you have any questions or
foreign comments any thoughts have been
raised in you
just hold it up like thank you David for the discussion uh oh
sorry okay um um I really like the part where you
mentioned uh what was like our level of or at least my level of Consciousness as I was
sitting and meditating uh and it just allowed me to think about
when I am attempting to sit in my striving for something or am I conscious
of the breath or whatever it is that I'm trying to or not focus on so thank you
for helping me be aware of that so you know it's good to have the the
breath as a support
but not as a goal this is the support to be conscious to be aware
a supportive Consciousness a supportive being here just being
simply not to be the best best breath meditator in the world
just the support to be simple humble
thank you