so hello everyone and welcome
and here the our youtube meditation begins
in the language of buddhism it arises it appears
and it'll be here for a period of time and then it will disappear it will
cease it'll come to an end it'll only to begin again probably tomorrow
and already this week the 7 am has appeared
and disappeared and appeared and disappeared and here appearing again
and when we hold our the hand of our mind open the mind open
then we can the idea is to just let the comings and goings
come and go to not prioritize one over the other
but prioritize the lack of clinging to any of it
the lack of getting caught up in any of it and so
the capacity to let go becomes the capacity to let be
when we don't stay involved and stay stuck we just let everything be and
and everything comes and goes in some way so
when we sit in meditation i often teach that using the breathing
as a default as the guide to support and they keep coming back to the
breathing the breathing itself is a uh
repeats itself the in-breath and the out breath the coming and going of inhale and exhale
each inhale begins it persists for a while and then it
disappears it's replaced by the exhale which begins
disappears and passes away and
so so one of the things we're learning and doing with breathing
is beginning starting to become attuned to the mind's ability to
receive and allow and to the comings and goings of something here
the breathing and at some point it isn't the mindfulness of breathing that's so
important the breathing itself though that's part of it it's uh it's the mind's ability
to just stay open and and receive the waves coming and going the arising and passing
of the breathings and of course what a rise in passing passes
are particular sensations so that how the body experiences the breathing
but at some point we start appreciating the inconstancy the con the constant and
constancy constant change of the breathing and it's getting centered on the
breathing then at some point we become more more sensitive to how
uh all experiences all things that we perceive all perceptions
are of the same nature they arise and they pass they come and they go they appear and they disappear
and and it isn't it isn't so much that it isn't that particular objects that we're looking at
for example we see the horizon pass but the perception of it
comes and goes i perceive something for a moment and then my mind goes into my thoughts thinking about it
i perceive something for a little while and then i'm aware of the sound outside and so we'll see this a constant moving
of perception in the mind that perception of things of everything has this nature
of coming and going coming and going and just as we get attuned to the coming and
goings or breathing in and breathing out as practice deepens we become attuned
to how perceptions of anything everything is also arising and passing sometimes
because the object arises in passing the sound comes and goes some thought comes and goes and
sometimes because our perception of it our focus on it arises and passes
the exception is when we get attached to something especially a thought or a feeling we get stuck on something
and we're holding on to it then that holding on obscures the nature of
anita impermanence nature of inconstancy and so if we take mindfulness and look
carefully at the holding the way we're stuck where we'll start seeing
that that too has a nature of inconstancy the perception of that and then it begins to loosen up the grip
of attachments begin loosening up and more and more as the grip of attachment loosens loosens up the more and more
the perception is open to the flow the river of change the flow
of things coming and going and this is the the deeper art
of sati patana so taking a assuming a
comfortable upright posture
and gently closing your eyes
and as you're sitting here now as your with your eyes closed
what you notice comes and goes what experiences
arises and passes changes
there might be things that stay for now and don't seem to change but what is changing
in your experience the coming and going of my voice
maybe there are sounds ambient sounds for you
maybe as you settle into your body
you're you perceive you're aware of different parts of your body and your perception your awareness moves around
through individual moments of knowing this and that perception in the buddhist language
is unique for everything that is perceived and so individual acts of perceptions
come and go depending on what we're focusing on
and settling into this more deeply taking a few long slow deep breaths
and relaxing on the exhale
softening the belly
letting your breathing return to normal and if there are there are other simple
ways that you can relax your body maybe as you exhale
and then settling into breathing
perhaps being aware of how the body experiences breathing
or knowing with very simple thoughts
the coming and going of breathing in the body coming and going of inhale
of exhale
maybe where the appearing and disappearing of the inhale the appearing and disappearing the exhale
massages the mind's tendency to hold on or be to
be attached to anything allowing the mind to relax and loosen up
in that rhythm of being aware of inhale and exhale
imagine you're sitting on a boulder
it's sticking up out of a river and the water is flowing by
and you sit there and let everything flow by
everything comes and goes appears and disappears everything is floating down this
large majestic river you safe on your boulder sitting
allowing things to flow by everything flows
so
if you look thoughts look at thoughts directly you'll see they're made up of comings
and goings get out of the way for the comings and
goings without being involved in thought
if you're not aware of things coming and going
maybe you can be aware of the way the mind is stuck on something
the way the mind is preoccupied or
holding itself at a distance from experience direct experience
and breathe with that feel that sense it sense the way that sense what gets in
the way of seeing change
maybe it's a belief
in the river of change changing experiences perceptions
let's go into it let yourself
become the change everything is changing everything
appears and disappears flows on and on
even anything that you can identify as yourself
it appears and disappears in perception
let go let go into the river of change
then as we come to the end of the sitting
might there be something within something tender
that is touched by the changing nature of reality
maybe it's some
apprehension maybe it's some joy
maybe it's some kinship feeling of this is
deeply connected to what's most
at home here in this world this is true
the changing nature [Music] of everything comes and goes
we share this with others some change is painful some is joyful
some involve sadness some involves joy
some involve relief some come with new stresses
we all share living in this world of change
and may we gaze upon the world kindly
in a friendly way offering our support our companionship
for others as they go on their journey through this difficult world
life of change may we
tap into good will wishing people well
may everyone be happy
may everyone be safe
may everyone be peaceful
may everyone be free
and may whatever we learn about freedom
help us to better support the welfare and happiness
of others may all beings be happy
[Music]
uh
so today i want to offer an alternative
interpretation of the second noble truth the one that
is how this truth is taught in the ancient teachings of the buddha
the more modern one is that craving is the cause of suffering
that's the second noble truth the more common one in the ancient texts
is that
that the second noble truth involves seeing
the arising of suffering seeing the appearance of it
without any explanation for why it's there
the search for reasons for causes is little bit challenging at times and
sometimes we'll leave it lead us astray and it takes us away from the simplicity
of our experience in the moment there's certainly a time and place to look for causes
for why things happen it's a wise life that understands conditionality and causes
but it's also one that lends itself to thinking a lot and reflecting and analyzing
the satipatana practice moves us towards more and more really abiding and direct experience
and in direct experience the idea of cause becomes less important you can still see it sometimes in the
moment see oh there i was grasping at something in the moment and i saw they were suffering in
that grasping so you can see there the causality but there's another way of seeing
and that is simply to see that suffering arises and that suffering ceases it appears and
disappears and um and and the suit does emphasize this and
this insight into a rising and passing of many many things and not just suffering suffering's like the umbrella
term perhaps for all the things we become aware of we see the arising and passing of the aggregates
rising and passing of the faculties rising a passing of perceptions um
rising a passing of thoughts and um feelings
so it emphasizes arising the rising and passing of things rising and ceasing of it
and the simplicity of that experience is particularly valuable
in deep concentrated practice of sati patana in ordinary states of consciousness the
world of cause cause and effect thinking about things is an all very common phenomenon as the mind gets quieter and
quieter and quieter more more focused clearer and clearer it's not inclined to look at experience
through the lens of analyzing it and reasons and cause and
why and what's going to happen but become just a simple simple
experience of the moment of the river of change flowing by
so i want to say again what i've said before that coming at the as the last exercise of
the satyapatana sutta i think we can assume that this
exercise on the four noble truths is represents a deep level of practice
a mature level of practice it's not easy to come into this as a beginner this level of seeing this kind
of insight and we get a sense of that from the refrain that we've looked at the refrain for each exercise
talks about this very thing seeing each of the things we're looking at the phenomena of the body phenomena
feelings phenomena associated with the mind and see it arise and pass
and um and the the aggregates the the
the hindrances the fetters the seven factors of awakening all those at some point what we're
seeing is they're rising and passing that's what's emphasized in the refrain
and um and sometimes you start seeing it so quickly that the text talks about first it says
seeing arising seeing ceasing and then it talks about seeing arising and ceasing all the where
rising and ceasing happens very fast in deep subtle practice the moment-to-moment experience of
direct experience comes and goes and so when we when suffering arises in
that kind of context it's not overwhelming it's not so difficult because
um it doesn't persist it comes and it goes it might we appear
quickly there might be disorientation that happens when we live in a world where every we expect things to be constant we
want to hold on to certain things for it be oriented and know ourselves and know the world around us know we're safe by
knowing like certain ideas are settled and so there might be a period of
disorientation that some people feel as the mind gets quieter and quieter in
meditation and the usual ideas usual ideas of self the things we're holding
on to depending on are no longer available because they had to be constant
some level of constancy in order to hold on to them but when things come and go there's a
whole different way that we're asked to relate to it so to see the arising of suffering
is to see its contingent nature see it's not permanent it's not solid
we can see that it arose from a time and place situation where it wasn't didn't
exist before it arose and if you see it cease
we know that it comes a time where it's no longer to be there and that begins to loosen up the grip of
the mind or the resistance of the mind the fear of the mind that we have about we just start appreciating that
there's the emptiness of it all the freedom of it all the the lack of um that this is not something to be
worried about or or upset about or cling to and this deeper deeper seeing of things
arise and ceasing the inc constant and constancy
begins to loosen up the grip of our attachments some of the deepest
attachments we have we had to let go of a lot of attachments to get to this level of meditation
a lot of preoccupations are fall away as we're getting concentrated and settled
and what's left is some of the deepest attachments attachment to self
even attachment to life itself and um those are all ways of interfering
with the flow of change it's becoming the flow of change and so as things begin to loosen up
massaged relaxed let go of then um then there is more then
then at some point there can be a more something in the mind gives away
it's uh maybe a little bit like say you're standing in the river at a
real river and the river is just flowing and you're walking deeper and deeper in the river and you can it's not dangerous
this the current you know how to swim and and you can just feel more and more the
river flowing against your body as you go d walk out into the river deeper and deeper and deeper
and then um and uh and just feel like more like you're very light you're floating it
feels very comfortable but it gets deeper and deeper until you get to a place where it's deep enough
that you're not touching the bottom and suddenly the current the gentle current picks you up and starts carrying
you down the river as we let go into more and more the flow of
change there comes a time where the bottom's not there
and we can start becoming carried in the current carried in the stream and that's
the meaning of the the the the buddhist idea of of stream entry
the word for stream sota means current it's entering the current
and it can be seen the current of change that's always here i'd like to
think of it the current of non-clinging non-grasping not holding on to anything
but then beginning to flow in a dharma current the dharma flow
that starts flowing through us because it's the f it's the dharma current that we're in
is the current of non-clinging non-grasping and this begins to carry us in on a
dharmic path to dharmic life and so uh this uh the third noble truth
is a truth of this ceasing of suffering and it means both the the seeing
together the arising and ceasing the inconstant change and coming and going but it also represents at some point
uh when the when the bottom of the river is out of reach falls away
it there's a more dramatic ceasing that goes on and um and now it's a ceasing that changes
things so for example in the analogy of going in the river when you're no longer
touching the bottom and no longer keeps you kind of stationary then the current has a chance
to carry you and so it marks a very important change
in going across the river and so going into the river and so the third noble truth involves
not just seeing the arising of ceasing of things the constant coming and going but it's when we really become the
coming and going relax into it that um there's a a more
complete ceasing that is more than just the particulars of the moment but a seizing that feels
just much more holistic more inclusive and
and this you know is uh is uh changes
kind of the whole flow the whole current the whole understanding of what satti-patana practice is
and i'll talk more about that tomorrow so
so the second noble truth has two meanings and both of them are good
they're in they have their value in different contexts
often much more ordinary states of mind seeing cause for suffering is very helpful
in deep meditative states of mind looking for a cause it just keeps the mind busy
and there we want to deep meditative we want to just kind of rest in the current the rising and fasting of direct
experience that's only possible if we have some level of stability and concentration
that we can we can we're not distracted we don't wander off in thought we're really here
and then we see the we're living in a rising and ceasing
and now the second noble truth is the rising seeing they're rising and the third noble truth is really
appreciating the ceasing the passing first initially kind of just as it comes
and goes the ceasing comes and goes until finally the seizing becomes much more comprehensive
and then that opens the door understanding for the fourth noble truth
the eightfold path and that will be the topic for tomorrow
so thank you very much