so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
um or the theme for for this evening's practice I wanted to
um actually do a revisit of what we did on Wednesday
on Wednesday I introduced taking refuge in silence
as as an act of care as an act of self-care and love
and many of you uh reported that that was really calming and soothing that
exploration of of a mostly silent said
as an expression of Love meta self-care so um it was so yummy and delicious that I
thought let's do it again especially during the um the uh holidays such a busy time that it
can be for for many so especially nourishing to take
refuge in silence in peace so
that's all I want to say to frame it and then the rest of it I'll just lead in
the guided meditation so so make yourself comfortable in your
seat Landing arriving in this body
In This Moment In Time
ah releasing releasing the body releasing
any tightness in the neck shoulders
forehead jaw letting your eyes rest
letting your heart rest
feeling your seat on this earth when your feet
and this Earth were rooted make the breath find you
let the breath find you when you find the breath
as if the breath is playing the music of life
and this body and this heart playing the scales most beautiful music
the music of Silence
putting down whatever is not necessary it's this thought necessary right now no
gently putting a gun taking refuge and
breath in the silence and the Peace of release
release release
taking refuge in silence
loving the silence loving oneself
this is an act of self-care self-love self-meter
nothing more rejuvenating more delicious than
and this the silence and if thoughts arise gently
releasing them not now thank you I'm engaging in self-care
just this breath in this body
right now
foreign
relaxing and receiving the breath it's an act of self-love self-care
and if the Mind needs more support
it's okay to offer the phrases of meta to yourself as an anchor
may I be safe may I be happy
may I be healthy and I have ease
but let the words be light so light as if it is a whisper of Silence
stay with the feeling
or maybe just the words with your breath say
breathing in happy healthy
breathing in ease
and if there are a lot of thoughts it's okay don't be disheartened it's the nature of mind to think to like
to think
release let go smilingly
hold the breath the silence dear
falling in love with the silence if you're falling in love with yourself
not now not now your thoughts are right still I'm not now
foreign
thank you
turning your gaze inward into the body Sensations
to support stability and silence Within
foreign
relishing silence embracing non-doing as an act of
self-care and meta in this moment right here in this body
inviting the attention to be right here with the breath right now
as we turn the end of our sitting
practice together
appreciating yourself or having shown up as best as you're able to
letting go of the outcome
planted seeds embraced silence
inner and outer as much as was available [Music]
that's it your work is done the mind was wandering or planning
remembering emotions are rising Etc it's okay
it's all right forgive yourself I appreciate the goodness of
coming together and practicing and offer that
goodness as a gift both to yourself
and to all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere
be free in all beings everywhere
be awake including myself
thanks everyone
so tonight I was embracing the silences an act of
self-care every visit revisiting
[Music] the theme from two nights ago and yet I intentionally provided even
less scaffolding tonight less than
I think it was less or at least that was the intention
um I'm wondering what what you discovered what a rose for you
you can type your Reflections in chat if you want to everyone if it's to everyone
I'll read your name if it's to me privately I will only read the reflection not your name
you can also raise your Zoom hand if you haven't spoken recently
uh you're invited if you have spoken recently I invite you to pull back and allow other people to pull forward
foreign
as a way to support yourself and others one of you says thank you that was
wonderful you are so welcome
it's quite sweet to sit together in silence as a self-care
Stephanie says it was both calming and chaotic yes both both and both and
appreciate you holding both yeah and usually the calming
nature of the set can support the chaos Within
the chaos that's happening
one of you asks how to relate this practice to Christmas well
foreign Christmas can be a very very busy time
and sometimes self-care goes out the window because we're running around
like headless chickens so taking Refuge
um in silence just sitting doing nothing for a moment just being with the breath with their
body as an act of self-care as a as a true Act of caring for ourselves
is how it relates to Christmas it's an act of care and another way it relates
is um by caring for ourselves in this way we can become calmer have a longer fuse not
they should refuse to actually be loving to others to be loving to others and that's the
spirit of Christmas kindness generosity Spirit of generosity
one person shares it usually is calming to have silence but tonight I didn't use
the opportunity wisely no problem forgive yourself
move on it's all right and just the fact that you showed up and
sat in silence as much as possible yay yay to that don't underestimate the
impact of sitting in in sanghae even though there was a lot going on internally
Charles Lee shares was able to turn towards an old Dark Knight of the Soul memory with self-compassion ah oh sweet
thanks for sharing that especially turning towards it with self-compassion yeah
beautiful we have space for one
more Reflections if anyone wants to share
another person shared privately appreciate your reminders that it is okay that thoughts are coming up
to be kind to ourselves thank you for your kindness thank you for yours
Suzanne oops
I'm trying to keep the ones that are sent to me uh private but sometimes I
slipped so just finish this when the person says just finish the solstice Retreat oh yes
no worries that was okay thanks thanks Susan one person just finished the
solstice Retreat so this meditation was synergistic on the retreat when I felt confused or
uncertain I heard your voice saying you know how to do this a simple meta it was supportive thank
you you are so so welcome and happy early Nikki Miss thank you it's
Christmas is my birthday so so I often celebrate I often well I always
celebrate Nikki mess with with my family as well as Christmas
um another person shares remembering some traumatic events but silence was
calming and I wasn't as activated as I might be experiencing self-compassion
beautiful such beautiful Reflections tonight thank you all ah lovely
oh more and more is coming uh yeah the idea of being in love with
myself is is wow powerful another person says when I focus on my
breath I start controlling my breath how do I stop this and just observe the breath
as it is the what can be supportive is to
consider um the two words actually three words relax and
receive relax and receive so keep relaxing keep relaxing
keep relaxing and keep receiving so that there's not this sense of focusing on
the breath going out and capturing the breath but just receiving the breath become becoming receptacle to receive
the breath become receptacle
another reflection at the end of The Meditation I told myself when you plan for the future I understand that you are
trying to help I understand that you value preparedness and you wish to help me meet the challenges that the future
will bring thank you mind when you remind me of past missteps I understand that you're trying to help I understand
that you wish to help me avoid repeating those mistakes thank you Mike oh beautiful that is such a lovely
beautiful comeback passionate perspective to take to to a Wandering mind to offer it appreciation and Grace
and and and ah and release beautiful
it's such beautiful Reflections tonight coming out of the silence
one more person I was trying to let go of a relationship hurting me so much but
gracefully I was so sad but now felt so peaceful yeah
great that all can be both sadness Grace
and beheld the peacefulness of silence and all so powerful your reflections
ah it's also I realize it feels more peaceful when the reflections are typed
in chat and I read them out loud um it's
I feel like there is a calmness in the space that remains not that I I don't
like you raising your hand and saying them in your own voice but just observing uh given that the theme was
peace and quiet
yeah they'll go back to the person who asked about trying to focus
who focuses on the breath and starts to control the breath yeah really have the
sense of you're sitting in this this embodiment you're sitting in a
receptacle of ease and receiving the breath however it shows up just relax
and receive relax and receive so can be quite powerful and they might
seem like simple instructions but they can really transform the way we relate to
the breath as if we're going out and trying to grab it so dear ones Let's uh let's turn
let's turn our um attention to practicing together in
small groups and again maybe we just sit together in
silence tonight can be so powerful so powerful in small groups
just sit together in silence and maybe maybe a ward wants to come up be a word
or a phrase or a share comes up maybe not maybe you'll say something maybe another
person says something um I'd let sitting in Silence with others be
predominant and it might feel awkward it might feel uncomfortable do not rush to feel the
silence do not rush to feel the silence because we often do that with friends and family
instead of just holding space these folks you're sitting with they
know how to hold silence they're good at it they love it as much as you do so so
just hold silence together maybe for a few minutes and then if
words arise and keep your eyes open actually in the group keep your eyes
open and hold silence maybe you're doing silent meta for one another maybe you're
doing silent meta for one another no questions just if share comes up you
can share something and if not just hold silent presence
with one another how powerful how radical yeah the breakout group or groups are primarily silent tonight
enjoy take care of each other take care of yourselves okay here we go
and if anyone is willing to and oh it's seven o'clock but if anyone is willing
to quickly very quickly share uh what it was like to hold Silence with one another
um can also type it in chat what
what did that feel like
holding patient Silence with one another so they're rushing in to fill the space
any insights
Stephanie says very powerful with very
Jonathan says very nice and peaceful great great
wonderful okay I hmm thank you someone says you're welcome Curry beautiful all
right so maybe I'll just leave it at that and yeah
most welcome all right we'll just leave it at that so thank you all thank you
for your practice thank you for coming together to cultivate your heart for both your
own sake and the sake of all beings whose lives yours touches may all beings
be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you all take care happy holidays Merry Christmas if you celebrated happy
Hanukkah take care gonna stop the recording