hello everyone and welcome to
beginning of our week week of meditation
discussion of the buddha's teachings on the
four foundations for mindfulness for awareness
and i want to begin with a little story
there was a once a novice who
entered the monastery and was being introduced to the teachings of mindfulness sati patana
and asked the question of the abbess
when should we be mindful
maybe the novice hadn't really heard about mindfulness before and seems like a reasonable reasonable
question when should one be mindful and the abbess replied
when it is better than the alternative
when it is better than the alternative and i think that uh certainly in my
experience as i've followed this path of mindfulness for now several decades
that it becomes clearer and clearer that
mindfulness somehow is the best alternative is the best option
and so rather than mindfulness being
rather than struggling wondering where i should be and what seems important
to have to have mindfulness in the middle of
our experience whatever we're doing is really
a delight it's really a wonderful thing
because it's a mindfulness when it becomes comes to its simplest
potential simplest form
it's also its most profound form it's a
clarity and a freedom of awareness that in and of itself
is not diminished not being hurt not being undermined or deflated
that's not being eclipsed that's not being
coming under the influence of some of the
challenging states of mind that we might have
and all too easily when mindfulness is not present when this kind of clear awareness is not present
the mind come gets can easily get under the influence of stress
of tension of one form of another
so what is it about awareness being aware the practice of awareness practice of mindfulness
that makes it one of the best alternatives for what to do at any given moment
and now here we are to meditate to practice mindfulness
so gently closing your eyes
and and perhaps
without trying to meditate see if you can have a very simple
awareness of your body
maybe exploring your body re-familiarizing yourself with your body
as if the two of you haven't connected for a while
and without the idea of meditating on the breathing familiarize yourself with your breathing
familiarize yourself with the body's experience of breathing
the sensations in your body that come into play as you breathe
and when there is awareness especially awareness that
almost arises together or out of
the body
the breathing can feel like the experience the sensations of breathing can feel almost as if they
are infused with awareness itself
at the minimum the awareness that has to be present to feel
sensations
and perhaps as if you're filling your breathing your body with awareness
gently take some deeper breaths and longer exhales
gently relax your body as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal continue a few more rounds of breathing
to relax on the exhale as you relax
some of the muscles of your body perhaps it's a relaxation into more
awareness in that part of your body
and then letting go of relaxation
in favor of a simple awareness of breathing in and breathing
out the simpler that awareness is
the more profound it is
letting awareness grow in the breathing with the breathing
and if you wander off away into the mind thoughts
consider whether mindfulness coming back to mindfulness
might be the better alternative than what you're doing
as we come to the end of this sitting
let there be an awakening of awareness throughout
your body
becoming more sensitive to your embodied existence
and it's with your body that you'll move and
walk and stand or
move your arms to eat whatever
movements you make with your body
imagine that you'll do that with an embodied awareness
so you're living in your body aware through your body
of the activities of your day
and that those activities
might also be the means for conveying
care and kindness for yourself
and for others if you're alone
your actions of your body can be done attentive to how they care for yourself
when with others you can be attentive
to how in some way or other
they convey your care and kindness for others
on this day may we explore how our activities what we actually do
in our actions might be
done with a greater dedication to kindness
good will love
appreciation
of self of others and this whole world that we make direct
contact with with our bodies on this day may we have midas as touch
that everything we touch we touch with kindness
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be healthy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free [Music]
[Music]
so hello everyone and we're continuing now with um
going through the discourse on the four foundations for mindfulness for awareness
and uh it's the ways of developing a heightened sense of attention
attentiveness awareness and it's in these four different domains four different areas of our life
that we bring attention to sort of different kinds of attention so that our capacity to be awake and
aware becomes stronger and stronger clearer and clearer simpler and simpler this all at the same
time and we're doing the third exercise in the 13 exercises
and it goes like this a practitioner is one who acts in full
awareness when going forward and returning who acts in full awareness when looking
ahead and looking away who acts in full awareness when flexing
and extending the limbs who acts in full awareness when
wearing one's robes or carrying one's outer robe and bowl for monastics maybe
for lay people a full awareness and wearing our clothes
and carrying our plates and silverware and
when we're eating who acts in full awareness when eating drinking consuming food and tasting
who acts in full awareness when defecating and urinating who acts in full awareness when walking
standing sitting falling asleep waking up talking
and keeping silent so this is mindfulness in activities
when i was first studying this uh i was probably under with this
coming with a strong influence in the zen training i'd done and i
read the text selectively and i read it selectively for the
passages that emphasized not doing anything but rather
more than just being aware that just being aware was enough just be present for what is without any attempt
to change it or do anything with it or judge it just to be aware and so is a kind of receptive or
somewhat passive awareness in a sense
but as i study this text more and more and as i studied the teachings of the
buddha more and more i see that the buddha's teachings are very centrally
rooted or grounded in action in act in
action of body speech and mind and that without understanding the role
in place for action in this practice we might not really find our way to
freedom find the full potential of this and
and so it turns out that this first three exercises of the text
has a lot of action as part of it it begins
with um breathing it says breathing in i know i am breathing in
it's not saying i know breathing is happening kind of a passive
kind of breathing just a passive thing that's uh going on
it's um it says uh i know i am breathing
and then it says
experiencing one's whole body and that's a kind of little bit receptive and open but it is a choice an
activity in the mind to receive and experience the body to really feel the full body
and then it says to relax the body that clearly is an activity the second exercise
begins with focusing on walking knowing you're walking when you're walking standing when you're standing sitting
when sitting and lying down laying down they're called postures but they're also these are all
certain kinds of activity we put ourselves in these postures
in the third foundation it's all about activities it's all about what we're doing
and one of the reasons i like to think that it begins with this way is that we're starting to get a hang of
how to pay attention to the way that we are we act the actions we do
and so it's not just mindfulness sitting quietly in meditation with the eyes closed
and then later we learn how to practice in daily life this is it begins right there with
activities and with our daily life all the things we do in our daily life
and infusing it with mindfulness infusing it with attention
and and it's not that is now it's certainly a distraction to do
this it distracts us from our distractions if you prefer to be distracted
then don't practice mindfulness but in a kind of
funny way to practice mindfulness is to do something different than being distracted
and it and so to be present for the activities we do when we're doing them
and to be present from the kind of the inside out so there's not just simply a knowing
we're doing them knowing that i'm reaching for something but there's also
um we're infusing like if i reach for if i reach for something like i'm going to grab the
bell that's here next to me if i reach for it i can do it
mindlessly i could do it while i'm talking and not really pay attention to what i'm doing
or i can really slow down and really put my attention in my arm
feel stretching out feel the weight of the bell feel my hand gripping it and then feeling what it's like to lift
it up and just infuse with sensations
this kind of attention if you do it initially it might seem like a distraction from living your life
but over time it we can live our life but we're infused with this kind of attention we're
infusing ourselves with an embodied awareness which gives us access
to a much wider range of who we are wider range of intelligence a receptive
perception of sensitivity of wisdom then if we're only in our heads thinking
and planning ahead and reacting to things with our reviewing things in the mind
when we start dropping down and having the body be the foundation from which we engage
it becomes more holistic our whole being with all the different capacities and
functions we have can start to be marshalled together for this purpose of being present and for being wise
so um the text talks about being of practicing full awareness and i like this
expression quite a bit but uh i think the pali word itself samphajana
means more something like with a clear recognition
to really recognize what we're doing when we're doing it but what do we recognize
certainly the activity in and of itself but the full recognition includes our intentions and purpose in
which we're doing something the context which we're in and so this wider intelligence this
wider sensitivity that can arise from the body because we're really present for our experience
as we do it not at the exclusion of everything else but because we're more here and we're
more attentive and sensitive to what goes on around us and so we also pay attention
in this full awareness full clear recognition the
effect the influence our actions have on us so if i grab my bell
out of out of greed and just kind of quickly grab it and hold it in tight this is mine
this kind of tension and tightness of holding it and grabbing it if i pay attention to how the influence
it has on me it's not very good it's kind of off it brings more tension
and but if i reach to grab the bell in a relaxed way
respecting the bell feeling the bell when i first touched it not grabbing it right away
and then holding it with just enough tight grip that just enough to hold it
lifted without gripping it just holding it and lifting it up and feeling it i feel the coolness
of the metal against my hand and it feels kind of nice to do that action
there's a simple pleasure in reaching for it and having it
and this is a hugely important part of this mindfulness practice is we can become mindful of the of
influence the effect our actions have on ourselves and the world but in ourselves
and is what i'm doing nourishing me is it benefiting me is it is it pleasant is it enjoyable
and the word that the concept that's most important is it wholesome is it
helpful for us part of the buddha's teachings on action
is encouraging us to do things actions which are beautiful
and so this idea of infusing attention into all our activities
can also go along with doing the activities in a way that is beautiful
and what the beauty is for any any individual is very individualistic but what is a what would you do how
would you reach for something if there you would do the reaching in a beautiful way
if you eat and chew and taste both in a beautiful way in order to
experience as beauty or as kind of a wholesome pleasure
a kind of beauty which is i love the word beauty because it's different than pleasure which many people will associate with
physical pleasure that just kind of you know skin deep because you know it tastes good or feels good physically
but beauty is a pleasure which is a deeper it's kind of like a dharmic pleasure
that's a deep feeling of residence with what feels right and good and wonderful
clean and ethical within ourselves the word for beauty here is kaliana
which uh some of you will know is kalyan amita is often translated as good spiritual friend
but kaliana that's first definition is beautiful so
literally kalyanamita literally is beautiful friend and so
to have actions one does to infuse it with awareness with
attention but there's even a more wonderful potential
possibility not only being present for our experience so we're really present knowing it
but do it in a way be sensitive to the influence it has on us be sensitive to the quality that comes
with doing the activity and it's possible to do things beautifully
so
one acts in full awareness when going forward beautifully
when returning beautifully looking ahead beautifully
looking away beautifully flexing and extending one's limbs
beautifully wearing one's clothes beautifully
eating drinking consuming food and tasting beautifully defecating and urinating beautifully
walking standing sitting falling asleep waking up talking and keeping silent beautifully
exactly what beauty is is personal but something which has a feeling of
goodness or pleasure deep deep pleasure dharmic pleasure something that
feels like this is worthwhile to do with my being this is a healthy thing to do
it requires being attention to the present moment and
the kind of attention i hope that you'll see your life begins flower around flower flower around blossom
around it doesn't take you away from your life but it infuses it with a great sense of
purpose and value and it lays the foundation for living a full life in the world
in a way that is beautiful in a way that is peaceful and moves us towards awakening and appreciation
beauty as a foundation for the path to awakening the buddhist teachings on action
has an emphasis on beauty on beauty and kalyana
so may you explore your activities you engage in your everyday things
may you take a heightened interest in them today and see what you can learn about
a heightened awareness in activities but more so is it possible to do them in a way that
has a positive influence on you that the very doing them is done in a way that feels good maybe is beautiful
so thank you very much