okay so welcome uh welcome folks um
yeah that's uh that's it
just landing in your posture
and supported by all the practice you've done
but not using all the practice you've done to predict exactly
what happens today
so if you're feeling a certain kind of pressure to think particular thoughts just think i'm think i'm hard
for this first minute
and then recognize
that thought offers no refuge
so directing directing the spotlight of attention
to some anchor
some object that [Music]
acts as a kind of feedback loop reminding you to stay
here
maybe the breath maybe something else
and the spotlight operator can be relaxed their arms
on that spotlight relaxed
we're not trying to make anything else disappear the rest of the stage
cast the characters but we're just spotlighting
the effortful quality of
the tension
attention training
supports the seemingly effortless quality
of awareness
i told you to stop being aware you couldn't do it
whatever can't be stopped is it possible
to rest there
there is space for all experiences to arise
but who can say where our life is
keep relaxing back
no effortful attempt to control the spotlight of
attention
as we become less mesmerized the attention becomes less glued
to discursive thinking auditory thinking
the awareness tastes less and less
like me
as the teacher pandan says let your face fall off
element of relaxation of course
the non-identification you are not your face
just another part of your body
like a foot or a knee
taking its place in the openness of awareness
so
[Music]
so uh
yeah welcome good to uh good to sit with you
is uh bertrand russell
all the laborers of the ages all the devotions all the inspiration
all the noonday brightness of human genius are destined to extinction in the vast
death of the solar system and the whole temple of humanity's achievement
must inevitably be buried beneath the debris of the universe
of ruins or from
the um the zen tradition may
i respectfully remind you great is the matter of life and death
life slips quickly by
time waits for no one wake up wake up
don't waste a moment
maybe maybe it's just our grandiosity
that makes life seem like it's no big deal you know
like it's not the freakiest of freak accidents
that were even alive
so this week i've been been making the case that there are there are many mechanisms
of action in the dharma many ways we're
healed and nudged towards awakening and started with attention training and
then said the dharm is also a cognitive therapy and exposure therapy yesterday
and today dharma as existential therapy
so how how can we how can we be
adults about our our existential situation
yeah great is this matter of life and death
now existential psychotherapy uh suggests that the failure to deal
with four core existential challenges is linked to
a lack of fulfillment or psychological symptoms
is for challenges of death and meaning and freedom not in the buddhist sense but
freedom to make of our life something and
lastly isolation and um
these are themes for all of us in one way or another and maybe sometimes
turning away from them or even something like denial can be adaptive for for
a time but in the end uh the chickens come home
to roost yeah and um
we want to prepare our heart before it's too late
dharma is not i feel not necessarily a perfect cure for all
of them but at the least it's a very deep
consolation [Music] it really does
help our heart acclimatize to a nietzsche
impermanence to groundlessness to the radical openness of all things
our heart needs a lot of time to acclimatize to that
and some of what we're doing as we practice is
giving our heart bearable doses of
groundlessness
so death death that all that is precious and dear to me is of the nature to change
um i i think i
some subconscious level got into dharma practice because some part of me knew
that i was utterly unprepared for the task for that task
yeah and
there are you know there are only those of us who have grieved and those who
who will grieve and um
and so in our practice we practice being softened rather than hardened by
anisha and
in some ways every moment of purification the heart is actually adapting in its
own way to loss
the antidote to a bad death is living a valued life
and that's part of what the dharma a dharma life feels like to me is like
valued i value it
uh yelum kind of linked to existential
psychotherapy says an existential position holds that the world is contingent that is
everything that is could as well have been otherwise that human beings constitute themselves
their world and their situation within that world that there exists no meaning no grand
design in the universe no guidelines for living
other than those the the person creates
whatever meaning we make we're going to have to make it
the the buddha said that the world trembles in all directions and that's
that skills translation trembles in all directions
groundless no ultimate foundation
for anything we build yeah
anything we build a life a democracy a species
even a civilization nothing nothing is guaranteed an existence
nothing exists on its own everything owes its
existence many other things but we must
build we must still build and build well
poet philip applemen um face to face with death we realize the
meaning of life is inside our lives not outside them
we cannot impose on our experience meaningfulness that we have not ourselves built into it
our true philosophy of life is whatever we choose to do from moment to moment the sum total of
our actions at a given time constitutes our philosophy of life
we're gonna have to spend our freedom spend our life what
will we make of our lives
i saw this documentary about uh leonard leonard cohen so organized
around this song hallelujah and and he spent some years in
zen rinzai monastery and um
and uh just one line caught me said something like um sitting in a meditation hall for
four or five hours a day you kind of get straight with yourself
we get straight with ourselves and um
cut through the pettiness and the idealism and the
naive fantasies what will constitute our philosophy of
life and we come to appreciate our aloneness
yeah no matter how deeply we sense interconnection or
abide in non-duality we are in an important sense alone
but how lonely does it feel to be alone
and the dharma trains us to get very
comfortable being alone
and being alone reminds us of everything else
so in all these tasks the dharma is uh is relevant and um
might add you know one more existential issue to death and meaning and
freedom and isolation
that would be what what do we owe others
what do we owe others what do we owe each other
what do the divisions across space and time mean
someone on the other side of the globe someone
yet to be born what do we owe to them
a lot we
learn that too
do the best you can until you know better than
when you know better do better
it's my uh right angelo
so i will um pause there
and um yeah thank you uh thank you for for
having me and uh um conscious my uh kind of style just to
throw a lot of stuff your way and so you sift through
the the value and the
rubbish yeah and um hope that something's useful
um i appreciate appreciate the opportunity to
be together and yeah thanks for for having me and uh
welcoming your substitute teacher uh i'll be back um
sometime in september i think maybe late september and um
yeah i wish you all a good uh
day and a week and all the rest yeah
okay thank you you uh you be well
you