testing testing it how's the volume is it a little soft a little low seems soft right
is that better
okay yeah we're gonna uh we were gonna
decided to start um with a guided meditation since people kind of trickle in and instead of
waiting or starting the intro we just thought we'd start with a meditation does that sound good to you guys
okay
all right okay great
yeah so welcome
just sort of welcoming yourself into the moment
getting settled
and maybe even you know orienting to your space Wherever You Are
looking around
this is sort of helping your your mind and body acknowledge being here in this
moment in this place letting the eyes see
letting the body feel
just here right here
in the sounds
I find that when I'm starting to get that alignment between the body and the
mind and oriented to hear it's almost like there's more
substance or gravity more weight to my body
I'm just noticing if there's a shift that starts to happen for you and how
that is for you
the settling Landing arriving
and as you do arrive
noticing what you find in the body here
what are you aware of
can you feel where your hands are touching each other
maybe noticing your shut neck and shoulders
seeing if the body would benefit from lifting the shoulders up or
pulling the back stretching open the chest
taking a few deeper breaths
and during your meditation tonight just paying particular
kind of a gently curious attention to areas
where there's some ease or letting go
I'm just noticing it may be fleeting
maybe it's a little shy so when you turn your attention toward
it it dissipates
maybe it warms up when you attend
broadens expands
you can tune into the breath and notice
just the change even there of ease and release and the whole process of
breathing in
and then the transition to breathing out
it might be certain parts of the breath that feel like a letting go or
easing up that happens
and just sort of gently inviting the mind to rest
those little moments or pockets of ease when they're there
for however long they're there
you may be aware of a constant sort of tensing and relaxing
kind of a like a tide moving in and out
or you might also be aware of a broader sense
of ease it's allowing the breath to just sort of flow in and out
and every this once in a while just sort of dropping in the question
where is their ease or is there a sense of letting go
resting could be in the toe
and the ease may come and go or maybe there's just a lot of tension
stress or tightness and that's that can be seen and held
an awareness you don't need to try and change
anything see if you can just notice
whatever is there with the ease or the tension
being open to it all as best you can
you might also be curious about um whether there's ease in the body in the
mind or both
I was taking the last few minutes of the meditation to
tune in to the relationship between ease and being
aware of it is it like a cat that wants to be pet
and it kind of comes closer purrs or like a shy animal that
when it's seen sort of hides
how does the ease respond to being seen
how does the Mind respond to ease
[Music]
so before Kim introduces herself and gets us started just to take a moment to
see if there's anything you want to share about what you noticed in your meditation
about you know how were you able to notice ease where what happened when you
noticed you both have microphones so ideal
um I feel like for me being at ease is very unnatural and my
like Baseline state is usually like anxious [Music] um
but I feel like it was helpful like I feel like you kind of added in like little reminders along the way and it
did help me like just try to like ease my body at first and
let that take me to a place where I'm like not super stressed out and
I tried to think of like situations in the past or moments where I did feel fully at ease like
sitting at a bonfire or like watching a movie things like that that
kind of helped me like remember what it feels like to be
in that state so and did you happen to notice any moments
here in the moment that you felt these where you were aware of actually
experiencing it now
I don't know if yeah sometimes like just remembering can help change what we're
feeling or maybe you were more aware of what was happening in your mind than in your body do you have any
I was trying to be like it's a China like the body scan kind of
um that kind of helps me like feel more present I guess but
I don't know if I don't know if I know what it feels like to be fully at ease I don't know if I
yeah it is it's on I don't know if I if I was yeah
no you don't need to be fully at ease there can be little pockets of ease but that's great thank you for sharing
how are you Michael um I think for myself I've become more accustomed to getting into the routine
of meditation when I first started I felt like I was harder on myself if I would think of something a bird or a
ball or something come into my mind I would kind of um reprimand myself like
oh we're supposed to be just focusing on the breath and so now things will still come into my mind but I'm not as hard on
myself so now a question is it working am I am I um am I letting down my guard
or whatnot because I notice like you know sometimes I'll catch myself being a little bit more Mindful and I think oh
it is working but I'm still cautiously optimistic
thank you Michael you want to respond Kim or just to shift whatever you want
to do
if I take this off
guys I think I'll just say that um for many people ease is an acquired
taste and it is common to feel like in fact this
is going to be kind of a theme running through I think what both Tanya and I are going to say is that we're not so
accustomed to noticing these because we're always much more tuned to noticing
what's wrong or the tensions or the problems or the possible threats and all
the things that come into the mind and it can be something of a surprise that on this path
um noticing ease and attuning to it and even appreciating it
is actually a big part of it and so that's what we're exploring this
evening actually is this um next of the Four Noble Truths shall we just get into that okay I know that
neither of you know me so I'll say that I'm a teacher here at IMC also and I was
very delighted to be invited by Tanya to be here for part of this series this is a wonderful series that's being
offered with Tanya each week and Sandra and then I just get to slip in for the best night
about freedom I feel so honored to be here tonight so
um so this Four Noble Truths that we're talking about this month
sometimes the four noble truths are called the teaching special to the Buddhas
it's like yeah you know a lot of people teach meditation or they teach relaxation or they teach self-awareness
and all these different terms but these four noble truths are said to be kind of the essence of what what is offered in
this particular set of teachings and I like them very much because they
can be comprehended pretty well at a top level there's nothing esoteric about any
of these truths and we'll talk more about this word truth but also each one of them goes very deep
and you could be unfolded over a whole lifetime to understand any one of them even though
we can also get it at a top level so each of the four has a task that's
associated with it so we've talked about the first Noble Truth a couple weeks ago the truth of dukkha and the task for
that one is that it's to be understood you know we're to comprehend what it is that this is of course we think at a top
level yeah I get it and we do you know we know about stress we know about struggle we
know about pain grief anxiety all the things that cause us
difficulty in our life and those are part of dukkha um but do we know it thoroughly
so the task of this truth to you know to comprehend or to understand dukkha
um we need to really investigate carefully you know where is that coming from what are all the different forms of
Duca are there things that I think are totally acceptable and normal in my life that are actually stress and Duca
and the short answer is yes so we're asked to look again to look again at
what we're calling suffering and seeing more carefully what it is and if we do
that we might begin to see more than just our initial impression so we might
sort of broaden our perspective to see what is also present when there's dukkha
that's the one of the questions that the Buddha asked you know what is here alongside duka every time I feel
stressed or I'm struggling in some way what else is here usually we're so
focused in on the difficulty and what I'm going to do about it and how horrible it is that we don't broaden the
perspective to see that every time there's dukkha there's also craving
we're clinging that's what was talked about last week that's what um so the Buddha named craving or tanha
as something that is present along with duka so it's this is the truth of the
arising of duka when duka arises there's one of these also there you don't have
to believe me you can just check for yourself in experience and so um the task
for this second Noble Truth is to abandon it Sandra talked last week very
nicely about the three kinds of craving craving for sensuality craving for
becoming and craving for non-becoming and those sound a little bit technical but again we can understand from our own
life we can feel when we're grasping after things or getting caught up in things or getting obsessed by things or
really wanting something there's a sort of an a grasp a grip associated with
that and that's the craving and so the the task of abandoning that or ending it in some way is not so
simple but that's um that's the AIM
so when we learn something about abandoning these three kinds of craving
even temporarily then we can experience the ending or the cessation of Duca of craving so that is
the third Noble Truth so the third Noble Truth states that the end of dukkha the
cessation of this suffering is the same actually as letting go of the craving we're going to release the cause or the
cofactor and that is what's going to help us get through to the end of suffering
so this is the task is to realize to realize the cessation and we'll talk
more about this in a moment that will kind of unfold that over today what does it mean to realize the end of suffering
so then the fourth Noble Truth which will come up next week but I just want to give a brief overview along this line
of the tasks is to is the Eightfold Path it's that there is a a path that leads
to the cessation of suffering there's a way to get from here to there and that task is to cultivate this path so again
it's something that we can start on right away but can also take a whole lifetime to do the Eightfold Path I don't know are you
done with the April path yet no no me neither so it's a it's a long one
so I found this lovely quote from ajan tsuchito about practice of the Four Noble Truths
the practice of the Four Noble Truths does not suggest a process of someone becoming enlightened
it's more that a particular Viewpoint is sustained and understanding arises
through it the Viewpoint is a focus upon dukkha in an objective dispassionate way
so when the intention is to penetrate the experience of Duca we could also say understand dukkha
attention gathers onto that feeling and investigates it this leads to a powerful
Insight because it reveals that Duca is structured created and not absolute and
therefore possible to be dismantled or not created so that's what we're talking about here
today we're going to look at this third Noble Truth the ending of dukkha
but I just want to pause for a moment to acknowledge we've made it to the good news we had duka we had craving you know
all these things that are kind of like uh but now we've gotten to the part oh it can end there can be an end to this
it's not all about suffering there's Freedom there's peace so we're going to talk a little bit more
about that and all start us off and then Tanya's going to have a few things to say also
about this third Noble Truth so when you hear this phrase the end of
dukkha you might think immediately that you know what that means so surely surely
the end of Duca would mean my body stops hurting and is functioning correctly
all the people in my life who do things that I don't want them to do will start
doing all the things that I want them to do my work will be non-stressful and
they'll start doing things the way I think that we ought to do them uh and the world will stop being so
insane and cruel and Society will start heading in the direction that's beneficial for all that would be the end
of suffering right so do you see a theme Here is it our
idea of the end of Duca is mostly about things going as we want them to that
would be our idea at some level we really believe this because that's that
we really believe maybe that that's even what's required for us to be happy we certainly put enough energy into getting
all those things to be true that's why we continually work toward them and it's not a bad wish the wish for health the
wish for good relationships for ease for World Peace those are all good things to
want um but if we consider that there are
maybe eight billion versions of these things like how the world should be how
things should be I don't know is it reasonable that that's going to come about
actually really so
the Buddha did take our wish seriously for happiness and a good life he he
wanted us to have that but he essentially took that wish that he knows is in everybody's heart
and he realigned it with something might that might actually be achievable that's
the brilliance so by noticing that suffering always comes along with
grasping for example he suggested that we let go of the grasping
it's brilliant right if we let go of the grasping then we wouldn't have to Duke
up so this um you know this is much more in the realm of what we can influence we
don't have exact control but we can at least influence this I'm pretty confident that there's no way to fix all
the other people and conditions in the world those things are really not in my personal control
now just to head off one possible objection that comes up at this point
and you'll talk about this more through the rest of the series that doesn't mean that we just blandly blindly accept
everything as it is that wouldn't be happiness either it's more subtle than that
so that's what we're starting to explore today so we can try to release in our heart this
immediate condition for dukkha this grasping that we have this desperate wanting that we struggle with
so we have this task that we're supposed to realize something about the end of suffering
so I've noticed that the word realize has two different meanings one is to
to recognize to come to understand something like I just realized that the
ceiling in this room is over 20 feet tall you know that would be a reasonable statement I didn't just realize it but
one could and then realize can also mean to make
real to manifest to actualize to make it real
and I would suggest that both of them are meant in this case of freedom from
dukkha the end of suffering so we'll start with the first one you
know this this interesting that that if we're supposed to realize the cessation of dukkha there's something there that
we're supposed to see something that we're supposed to recognize do we actually recognize the end of
dukkha that's actually a really interesting question it's quite easy to see the dukkha at least some of it
people are very happy to talk about their suffering and it's very rare that somebody can't say something about
what's challenging for them but when some instance of suffering ends
even a small one we often don't really take that in completely
so for example like when a noise is going on and then it ends like a sound
that's irritating to us and then it ends we might have a moment where we say finally something like that but then we
rush on to the next thing you know we won't we don't really take in the feeling of
ease from increased silence and when we're you know when we're
frustrated or rushed the shduka in that but when that resolves we tend to just move on to the next thing we don't
really take that in so Tanya's going to talk more about this I won't say more about that she's going to talk more
about our tendency not to notice what is useful and to not to really take that in
so there are also I mean I talked about some mentions some everyday instances of
something challenging ending there are also ways in which we have really deep releases along the Dharma path and these
are easier to notice you know when the mind or the heart really lets go of something but getting to the point where we would
have one of those releases take some practice it takes cultivating mindfulness learning about our own body
mind system such that we can move toward letting go at some point we'll understand what this
Dharma release means it's kind of a non-volitional opening up or a letting go of something that was
being grasped we can feel it can really feel the craving and the clinging coming coming to an end so there's something to
see there is something to realize in the end of in this third Noble Truth the end
of suffering so I tried to think about an example of how how Insight Works in this practice
you know how how is it that we're going to experience this
end of suffering or end of something and I came up with an example that I don't know if it's going to work or not
but check it out um so you guys are so young do you remember these um those old monitors
that were called cathode ray tubes CRTs they're like
they're like old style televisions they're like boxes so instead of being flat like Tanya's it would be like a
whole it would have like some depth to it so anyway all the screens used to be like that and the lot they worked by
having electrons firing at a phosphor screen on the front and it made it made the image you don't have to worry about that but the big ones had three
different sections to them essentially but you wouldn't know that if you just looked at the screen it looked fine they
I mean the technology was great the image looked perfect but if you knew
that there were that there were three different sections to the screen if you looked very carefully one third of the
way down and two-thirds of the way down you could see a tiny little black line
just tiny I mean you have to know that it was there in order to see it but once
you checked out on a screen you really looked and you found those two black lines you couldn't unsee them you know
you'd seen them you can't unsee them so you could go back you could relax your eye you could you could enjoy the full
image again but anytime you wanted you could find those two little lines on these old style screens
so my my theory is that cessation is like this so you have to know what to look
for and then you have to really look Dharma practice does take considerable
sustained effort as you're already finding from practicing meditation but if you keep looking there will come a
moment where you can see a gap you can see a little Gap in experience
and once you've seen something like that you can't unsee it so there's a way in which if this Gap
that you see which I'm calling cessation if it's deep enough and complete enough it will bring
genuine relief from suffering every time you look at the image you you have a sense of that underlying piece that
could be there that's kind of how Insight works so you'll something that you'll know for
yourself so you look and look and finally you see it and when you see something that you know you won't be able to unsee that is
a Dharma insight Richard's laughing because he remembers CRTs
so anyway so um then we get on to the second definition of realize right to make real make it real yeah make it
happen manifest it in some way so Awakening is not just some kind of big
bang experience that instantly changes everything well it could be but it's very rare
instead more likely we have to work at it kind of gradually setting up the
conditions for the mind and the heart to let go um and there are many descriptions of
how this process goes you know some from the sutas some the the original teachings of the Buddha some from more
modern teachers you'll hear next week about the Eightfold Path which is the main method that the Buddha taught the
main path that he taught but I want to name very briefly a description that I heard from a modern
teacher named Martine Bachelor and I'm I'm sort of going to paraphrase and
summarize it a bit but she talks about how we tend to let go of Habitual mental
patterns of dukkha that's the phrase I'm using habitual mental patterns of Duca
and so these are things that you would know examples are things like maybe we have a habit of interrupting
people and we frequently you know we frequently do that or we have a habit of social fear we we get anxious when we're
in big groups or we have a habit of getting angry easily and snapping at at
people when we tend to fly off the rails pretty quickly so there are four stages of how we might
let go of these patterns which brings suffering those are Duco patterns these are unpleasant patterns
so the first stage which we can be in effortlessly is that we blindly do the
pattern we have no clue that it's happening we're completely ignorant that we are constantly interrupting people
for example ignorance is not Bliss in this practice ignorance is not Bliss
so we do what we're doing our mindfulness practice we do meditation and suddenly we realize oh we see that
we have a certain pattern yay this is better than not seeing but we tend to
see it at first we tend to see it afterward you know like we realize oh my gosh I
I interrupted my friend 14 times in that conversation that we just had coffee you're driving home while you're
realizing this and so you know you didn't notice it in the moment um but uh so that's the second step but
then the third is that you catch it in the middle you know you realize that you're about to interrupt but you're
you're not fast enough to catch it and you do and so it's like look so you
watch yourself playing out this pattern or and this is a very painful stage and
you start thinking why did I start mindfulness practice I didn't want to know all this about how my mind works
but you're actually getting closer and closer to the moment right you're noticing it sooner and sooner and then
there's This Magic Moment where you feel yourself of wanting to interrupt and you don't
you choose some other path I'm just using the example of interrupting but you know substitute
your mental pattern and you might get caught again the next time you might forget but once you've cut through that
first time you were strong enough that first time that pattern is on the way out it might take another 10 000 times
of seeing it but nonetheless in a sense you were free in that moment
the pattern didn't overwhelm your mind so these are the stages that we go through it's sort of a small
everyday version of how the cessation of Duco works we very gradually
find that we can let go of a pattern it doesn't hold us anymore and we realize
you know the craving that went with I got to get my word in right now
that's gone and so the Duco of that pattern is gone also and these little everyday versions set us up to
understand the bigger releases that the Buddha was pointing to in his Dharma teachings about how we can free the
heart from really really deep attachments that we have so keep at it keep looking for the gaps
and little little releases looking for the patterns and just keep aiming to manifest
behavior that is somehow free of craving and clinging and that is the path toward
more and more freedom and I would love to pass it on to you
maybe before before I say anything I just want to give you guys a chance to if you have a question for Kim anything
that you would like her to clarify or restate
you don't have to of course just an opportunity
great
uh yeah sure I could ask something um so the the clean I think you had mentioned
uh the oh is it craving I think that's the word that's coming to my mind so what
manifests to go backwards what manifests the craving or where do these come from it almost seems like they
might be sort of ingrained or reinforced or oh great question yeah so you're very
in degrees and that's such a wonderful question I want to just acknowledge that this is
actually how the Buddha investigated also he kept looking back you know he's like okay they're suffering why is there
suffering and eventually figured out oh it's because of craving or clinging and he did keep asking that question so
um in the kind of classical teachings the Buddha would Point toward reactivity
to things that are coming into our sense doors so we see things and react to them
we hear things and react to them we're mostly reacting to kind of the impact
that they make on us and these this is very habitual stuff that we've conditioned and built up over our life
is that certain sight sound smells tastes touches and thoughts irritate us
or excite us or scare us and that reaction is where the craving comes from
because then we say I got to get more of that because I like it or this is irritating or painful to me I've
got to push it away and that's the seed for or grasping pushing away clinging wanting
reacting Etc and if you trace that back farther how did that happen well has to do with
even deeper tendencies in the mind to how our basically how our nervous system was conditioned
Tanya may want to add to that not right now but that was great yeah
yeah okay you wanted to
yeah I am sorry yeah I
feel like I'm having a hard time um understanding like
because you were talking about how like ignorance is is not Bliss and being
aware of like patterns and just yeah you know things that are
socially conditioned and all this stuff is is it's a good thing which
I know it is but then sometimes it's hard to
especially when it's something that is out of your control like other people's
um beliefs or values or just I'm you know anything that's out of your own control
then there's this feeling of like well now I know that this exists and it's
hurting me in some way but then it's also out of my control
and maybe I was better off just not knowing it existed
um I don't know if I'm freezing this well but I guess it's
hard for me to understand like how
to um let go of or like not do anything about
something that is now like in your awareness and you can't
it's out of your control yeah you want me you want to do that I want
me to I'll offer something and I have the feeling you might too um
I guess I would say that there isn't ever really anything that's completely
um like the ignorance part if you just didn't know about it doesn't mean it's not influencing your life and
your behavior it's actually subterranean so it's still if you have some pattern
that you don't know about it is driving your behavior and it is leading to Duca
and the only way to end it is to know it and then release it according to these
teachings so there isn't really um there isn't really you know out of the picture
kinds of things like that go ahead
so I'm gonna see if I address what I think something I think
of when you share so let's let me think you know it could be sexism
um so I become aware that I'm around a
bunch of people and they have um really fixed ideas about what women
are and aren't capable of what they are and aren't for where
they're good where they're not and it doesn't fit with my own experience of myself or how I want to be
seen so when I become aware of that
um it there's a whole phase of it being extremely painful I might be angry
hurt I have to go through a whole process right of starting to see it
recognizing it and I think that this practice one of
the things that it can teach us is that over time we actually can be in the presence of sexism
and get free of our own habits of internalizing the sexism
of reinforcing or automatically reacting to the sexism
that we can focus on recognizing the pattern and our
pattern of reacting to it and and that um as we get better at not reacting we
actually are probably going to get better at dismantling reconstructing our relationships or
creating other spaces and things like that but there's there's two parts there's the pattern of sexism and then
there's the pattern of our internal response to the sexism and both need to be addressed but we
often are more effective at addressing the outer pattern after we've worked on our our own
relationship to it and sometimes we stop going to a place because there's too
much sexism and we can't exist in it without wilting
or enraging right um so to me there's two two parts to look
at here and in the practice and for me this looking
at my own response to the source of my suffering is incredibly incred like
there's so much Freedom that can be found when I shift my relationship and see the
sexism as for what it is
I'll stop there it looks like you had a question or wanted to say something yeah this might be kind of basic question but
it's good around reactivity in general yeah and
um I am I I definitely am very reactive in
situations like that um foreign and I guess does being non-reactive mean
kind of having an attitude of like Live and Let Live Like or is it like in the
moment you're not reactive and then you kind of like take time to figure out how to react the right way yeah so
um for me if I stay with this example it would be the reactivity I'm going to
talk about for myself my internal would be that I don't feel shame anymore that that's my own internal I cling to
the idea of sexism I get caught up in the idea that I'm less than
I believe it on some level and then I feel like I'm less than I feel shame
that's my own duka pattern and I'm relating to the becoming or not wanting
to become of this image right and
when I'm free from my own response to that external idea
I don't get I don't feel shame anymore I actually feel completely fine
I see that somebody is seeing me with delusion
and so I feel like I don't have to I get to choose what I want to do I get to
choose like freely how I want to respond if I want to
respond I get to like I I have the capacity
in my reactivity and my shame I don't have the same capacity I'm struggling
internally with my own oppression internalized oppression
which causes you know it creates it activates the threat system it's hard to
think hard to speak hard to stand upright hard to look at somebody in the eye all of these things are happening
when I have internal reactivity when I see through that
there's no internal reactivity it's if there's a solidity of you know a clear
Clarity a freedom I don't I am not determined who I am
what I am isn't affected internally by how they see me they may still see me
the way they have it yeah that's super helpful thank you yeah
and I think um so one of my things that I think is
really helpful too to help us see this a lot that when I'm working
with people on areas where they're feeling duka a lot of times
we stay looking at what we don't want or what we want
so there's the sexism and then there's our response to the
sexism and the response is duka we'll call it duka right if we're having
reactivity and one of the ways that I help myself
get disenchanted with my reactivity actually is to understand
and be able to move my awareness between this is sexism
and this is the cluster of all the things it means and then this is what it
feels like in me when I'm reacting to the existence of suffering and taking it
personally does that make sense and that's the feeling that's the dukkha that's the
like the stress the pain so one of the things that really helps
me kind of disentangle all of this is to separate out
what the object is from what the experience of Duke is
because if I keep looking over here the Mind keeps getting caught up in all the stories about how this should not be
happening how wrong it is how oppressive it is and so it's hard to stay and let the
dukkah teach me like we learn that it hurts if we push
too hard on our pen or touch a hot stove we learn right well we we're gonna learn
from what we're clinging our clinging by noticing the dukkha is that making am I
clear am I staying like very clear okay so that's one thing that can be helpful
so for you like when you're if you if you imagine if you're struggling with sexism how do you shift your awareness
from external to internal the manifestation of sexism and then
your response reactivity to the sexism and then the reactivity you have to be
careful with when you pay attention to it because it can be like well that's wrong well yes it is wrong and then
there's this engagement with the thoughts around the sexism but don't miss that there's a feeling
right the dukkah in there when we're reacting instead of clearly just seeing
um and not getting caught up in identification yeah you guys following me oh yeah I
follow okay I was wondering if I could chime in a little bit on my own experience sometimes with reactivity I
found that I've um when I do respond I put my foot on my mouth and I've learned that it's a skill to respond
appropriately or accordingly um my own experience yeah
okay feeling good right there right okay
so let's see where are my for time uh
okay thanks Kim um
so so I wanted to name that anyway about kind of it one some of the things that
can kind of get in the way of our noticing the ending of suffering is because we we're we're still clinging
and we're not we're looking we're not looking at the right things or we're kind of still in reactivity so
in the first class I talked about Duca as like the experience can be thought of
like as a compass like noticing and tuning into the existence or absence of
dukha is is like referencing a compass when there is dukkha you can sort of
imagine the needle is pointing toward more suffering if we keep going this way
and when there's an absence of dukkha it's like okay oh you know I'm going
it's okay like I'm I'm moving in the right direction I'm Letting Go I'm
stepping in the present moment in a way that is present but when we're going through our life we
have to remember to check the compass just like if we're going on a trip we have to keep paying attention to the
street signs or if we're hiking we need to keep noticing what direction we're going in and it's very easy to forget to
check and get caught up in driving like missing your exit on a freeway
so one of the things that's really helpful is to keep checking in noticing how am I feeling now
what am I aware of now and when you notice that there's ease and well-being
oh pause like take it in because the mind has this Kim was
referencing this earlier this negativity bias the mind is you know programmed to pay
attention to potential threats now that's how we survived so species it
was really important not so important now in the same ways
it's connected to a literal life and death survival system and now it's much
more about all kinds of ridiculous little silly things
so in order to balance our attention so
that we're tuning into the ends of suffering or to the moments of well-being we need to be noticing
checking in and then you'll notice that your mind
gets bored really quickly it's like it it is really just like oh
yeah okay next and you sometimes you'll be talking to somebody and you'll see them do that
you'll go oh look you're doing better you know that's good that that part got better and then you'll they'll come back
with you to you immediately yeah but this and this and that might happen you'll see it around you all the time
you know things are going well in your your art project or in your work or in
your writing and then if you stop and you reflect on it or something the mind's going to be so quick to start to
predict something negative right a criticism or it could be better or I
should do more so
like those moments of Letting Go those moments of oh it's okay
it's like ah Breathe Right There like can you expand into it open into it
breathe into it like the idea of savoring
and this is in Neuroscience this is exactly what they tell you to do that
shows your brain changing is this idea of savoring
so just like you might Savor a nice piece of chocolate or some other
wonderful thing a sip of water whatever just that feeling of letting it it's
like letting the whole body take it in and it requires really a pausing a
staying with and then noticing the impact so not just
staying but then tuning in like feeling letting your body sort of
ride the feeling the impact because when we do stop and notice a moment of ease
there can be a quieting a resting that starts to happen
and we want to rush to fill the space
and this is about you know this third Noble Truth is about receiving the space
it's like a gift receiving the gift being willing to receive
some of us aren't so comfortable receiving gifts right so we have to practice that too
another thing that can be helpful for us is to start just tracking endings
little endings of things just start to help the Mind tune in because it's that
leaping forward thing it's always kind of anticipating so you can start to reorient the Mind
toward the ending of things and feel into the ending of things and that sets
the mind up also to be more open to and interested and curious about even
sort of those moments of ease or things ending and settling
in my work with people in addiction they'll talk about having cravings and
they can talk about having the feeling that it's like they think they're having a craving all day long every day that's
how it sort of ends up for them so I asked them to time their cravings
to literally pay attention to when they end and write it down
and and they start to go oh there actually are many moments I'm not having these cravings
but they all they could focus on was the moments they did have them
so we start to retrain our mind to be more oriented and interested
and this these little moments pockets of letting go
of not being caught up and wanting or not wanting
something
so that feels like a pause I'll just you know let's see if there's other thoughts Kim if you
want to add anything you guys have any questions
no it's so clear foreign
what is it I guess I'll just ask this question what does it feel like when you have a moment of letting go
do you know what it feels like
um I guess for me to repeat a phrase I'm cautiously optimistic um I I'll notice that I'd let it go and
then either emotionally or just sort of logically like well something will come up you know either the next man or next
day but it is nice to have that sort of um that a breath of fresh air and just
uh enjoy it for the moment yeah but what I'm hearing is
is knowing it's going to pass makes it almost something we want to dismiss there can be a habit of that or I can't
trust it so we start to protect ourselves from it a little bit and so it can be useful to lean into the
those moments a little well I don't know what's it like okay let me hang out with this though right now
but it really does take some it's like um leaning into
we really kind of do have to lean into it yes okay breathe and hold our our eyes
are gonna Dart away crazy the mind the eyes the body will start to
impulsively move on so it's it's a it's a conscious thing to
sort of help us learn how help the nervous system really learn how to just okay well what does it
feel like then if I just enjoy this for the moment I know yeah it's gonna pass
and how nourishing is it when you take it in
you want to say anything um I was gonna say um I definitely
understood and related to what you're talking about about like when one thing passes you immediately go like oh well I
have like 30 other things to worry about so it doesn't matter
um so I'm definitely going to try to lean into those moments where it's like oh I'm not worrying about this as much
and something I do um that was recommended to me is like if
I'm having like a very anxious thought or something I'm stressed out about I like type it out on my notes up
and then maybe I'll look at it like a week later and be like uh I don't really
care about this anymore and I'll like delete it um but I don't think I'm like fully
appreciating deleting that text and being like
yeah I have gotten past this and maybe this was some like future scenario I was stressing out about but now I feel like
it's not that important and it's not gonna have the biggest impact and so I can let
it go um I think that's huge to stop with that
moment and I just take reflect back on how different the Mind feels
with that thought now how it changed it's like oh my God I was gripped
and now I don't even it's like meaningless to me like there's such a profound shift and to let yourself
really get disenchanted really feel the ex impact of disenchantment with that
thought a lack of clinging around it is huge huge
this is such a great this is such a great place on the path really such a great practice to start to
be like as interested in the moments of Freedom as we are in
you know the Duke of which we it's really really helpful companion actually
but the ease don't miss it it's like so precious
I am I'm remembering it just came this anecdote came to mind just while we were
talking about how hard it is sometimes to trust or even recognize ease or in
Tranquility or calmness or freedom
just maybe as a comparison so that you'll realize that this mindfulness practice really gives us a gift of being
able to be with it this is a long time ago maybe over 15 years ago I was
teaching a Qigong class and I had a number of people it was a beginner class
and we did a certain we did some standing
meditation and some simple moves and you know Qigong is very much about balancing
and calming the energies of the body and by the end of the class like most people were feeling like you know really stable
and amazed that their bodies had these alive sort of alive but calm feeling
except for this one woman who was got really agitated and she came up to me at
the end of class and said do you teach this class at a different time ever and I said well I no not
really but you know it's like I didn't know what she was asking and it took me a while of like asking her is that she
had felt calm she had actually gotten calm like everybody else and had freaked out because of it she had never felt
Tranquility she had never felt calm and it was like she thought she was falling asleep she thought she was fainting she
thought it was because it was dinner time and she hadn't had enough food you know it's like she could she could land
she could not land on this experience of actually of having just calmed down
because of this practice she didn't have mindfulness you know she didn't know that and so I think you know
I was quite naive at that time and I I didn't quite realize that some people
really have a difficult time touching this that really woke me up to how hard it can be to have this experience so
I feel like both of you are already there really in terms of being able to
see this and just yeah just encouragement to continue with the
um the sense of presence of calm of openness for exactly the reasons that
Tanya said is that those that gives us the freedom of choice about what we want to do it doesn't mean that we're just
going to become passive or not care or just say whatever however the world is
is fine maybe it isn't but we can we'll be able to act much more freely much
more effectively and compassionately from a place of freedom in our own heart
another um practice place can be actually when
you're meditating and you you know there's something called Bell mind right where you can
start to get very fixated and when the bell's gonna bring and which is a form of clinging right
you're like grasping on to the end of the the bell and
you'll go people will go through a phase often where as soon as the bell rings they're like oh you know they're just
they're done they're like gone already and so it can be really powerful to
start to say okay I know there's I'm anticipating I'm anxious but I'm not going to break my posture right away
I'm gonna stay for a moment with being with this meditation beyond the
bell and just like notice just notice what that feels like
and the pressure you can start to re see how the pressure that builds up will
just start to dissipate because we've been practicing clinging to getting to the end and then we start
to practice not clinging and it changes and there starts to be greater capacity
to just to rest to be with and to be more at ease during the whole meditation
eventually you know or on and off yeah
so so this is actually something you can practice you can choose places and time like um
I've done it when I'm driving when I stop signs like there's the Habit to to
want to hurry and to practice pausing
right and then oh you can feel the absence right there right there's just
like oh it's kind of nice not to just be driven by the clinging that this
grasping this energy of chasing
so small little ways can help you start to tune into it
so the Buddha's claim was that you can reach the end of all dukkha
and experience life with no stickiness no clinging no craving
he called this nibana which literally means going out you know like a flame
all the flame of our craving and grasping if you imagine that as a fire
it's like just go out what do you think what do you think of that does it sound
possible does it sound inspiring impossible never thought about it before it's a
pretty like um if I can use I don't know if this word's allowed anymore it's like a pretty ballsy claim don't you think
what do you think of this
I don't know when I when you said that I was like that seems possible for like
people who are like deep into this kind of practice and maybe even like
have let go of all um
you know like material I don't know I don't know it's just yeah it sounds like just
Way Beyond what I could imagine happening for me
I think in theory it makes sense um it takes me back to like some of my philosophy classes that I had to take
and whatnot but um I don't think I'm anywhere near that uh capability
um yeah that's interesting I just wanted to ask
because sometimes we don't really come up against we don't really think about what the Buddha was really saying and
actually I noticed that both of you said it seems possible actually you might be interested to know that there are
um groups or uh sometimes Buddhist groups or strands of Buddhism get into
the idea that it's been too long since the historical Buddha and Awakening is no longer possible
so I see you don't you're not affected by that that's nice it doesn't mean we can we we should think oh tomorrow is
probably going to happen for me you know sure it's a big process but I love that
you both thought it was you know potential that's actually really big
do you feel I'm curious um do you have a better sense of what it might be like to be without craving that
it doesn't mean that you don't care it doesn't mean you give in to everything it doesn't mean that you don't do
anything but can you feel more into the sense of Freedom that might be there
I think I have a sense a new sense that um it will be okay
um whatever happens you know small problem big problem or a big win small
win tomorrow will be another day and another workable another page and it'll
be okay um then to to what degree or what skill level you're able to uh to roll with the
punches or to have a positive outlook um I think probably that's where I'm at
right now is uh it'll be okay
um I feel like to be honest I haven't given a lot of
thought to like my daily actions and like how much it relates to clinging
which is probably something I'll do now but um like even just sitting here I'm
thinking about like all the stuff I constantly tell myself or that's told to
me like for example like a few years ago like I don't know I was like oh but this
I know a lot of people do this but they're like oh by this age I'm gonna achieve these things and then when I hit this age I'm gonna get married when I
hit this patient and it's like I mean I'm obviously not on track for
any of that stuff that I decided for myself when I was like 18 or something but
um it now makes me think like oh I was kind of clinging to this idea of like
things having to happen at a certain time and stuff like that and I just feel like there's probably so
many areas in my life that I am doing that and
probably needs more thought and recognition
well take one of those examples that you clearly have kind of done some
work around letting go and how did it feel to not be so caught
up in that idea was was it was there anything good about going ah I don't actually have to do
that um I don't know if I fully gotten past it I think I still have moments of like
when I see other people doing certain things or achieving certain things in certain timelines I'm like maybe I'm
behind and maybe I'm failing at life and you know
um but sometimes I do have moments of being like uh who cares like if it
happens for me now or in 10 years I don't know if it's gonna make that big of a difference and
it definitely helps with the stress and anxiety and just
um being okay with that stuff yeah
well I'm thinking about how um when you each said yeah that seems
possible but I don't know about for me that's such a perfect setup for next week when because the the fourth Noble
Truth is there's a path and essentially says there's a path from here to there
and because our first thought when we hear that their Noble Truth can be yeah
right maybe for some people or maybe theoretically philosophically but
you know the Buddha was also clear that you know there is yeah there's a way
there is a way to get from here to there it's not just an ideal so that's I find the fourth truth
actually one of the most inspiring the third is good it's quite good but
the fourth makes it real in a sense it's like how you actually do make it real
it does involve change of life some way certainly a change of what we're how
we're seeing things but yeah
final questions before we do dedication of Merit or comments reflections
thank you
I think recently with the the pandemic and seeing the fragility of life it's probably given me a new perspective on
what's important and what's you know not important um I I kind of wrestle with them letting
go of the clinging because I think well some of these intricacies make me who I am and and um it kind of um what
evolution do I want to sort of fine tune and and you know what things
do I want to sort of keep of myself um but it is a it is kind of a an
interesting topic to sort of see how environment and time around me has made
me have a new perspective on things
what you started out saying with the pandemic has highlighted for you what's
important it's it's said that there are these Heavenly messengers of um it's kind of a
funny word but of Aging illness and death and at some point I mean these are
things that are real for humans and at some point we wake up to them because they come to us but if we're more wise
we can even see them in others or see them outside in society and be inspired
by them it's like yeah these things are real and and therefore what is important
to me how do I want to live how do I want to manifest and then the other questions of
is this working for me is this aligned with how I see my own spirituality and that's
something that we discern as we actually engage with the practices I wouldn't worry too much about whether
certain aspects of yourself are going to change or stay the same the Dharma
the Dharma takes all the best stuff that's useful and just enhances it to
help eliminate the parts of you that are clinging it'll work
I was just gonna say that I feel like this session was kind of timely for me and
this idea of like or I guess I've just been like reflecting a lot on
my reaction to things and like why I react that way and
it's kind of like coming full circle with like maybe I'm clinging to something and
um I can also see how that reaction affects
um how I relate to others and um
yeah it's just something that I I think is it this is helpful to
um explore that more it's great well it's been it's so nice
to have you both here it's just so wonderful to have you both so engaged it's
wonderful so I'm glad you're feeling it's good timing yeah
so the let's do our dedication of Merit and um you know the idea is to share the
benefit of our practice and with the theme of this third Noble Truth the end
of suffering are there any beings that you would like
to think of to bring to mind that we would like to wish
have the experience of suffering ending anyone you want to name
eternally absolutely no pressure just give him space so may all beings
everywhere without exception experience the end of suffering
[Music]
thank you