okay then I think we'll go ahead and get started
so it's nice to be with all of you again as you can see um Gil will again be away
this week so we'll have five days together and this week uh the theme is going to
be desire and letting go and you know we know that desire is a
big part of human life and once one begins mindfulness practice we see in
fact how frequently the mind is trying to get something or hold on to something
that it likes or finds Pleasant or useful even which incense just kind of wanting
wanting all the time and why is that
um mostly it's because we think that it will bring happiness and you know getting what we want is is
good getting things that are Pleasant or beautiful but mindfulness also shows us that this
isn't entirely true our quest to find happiness only by fulfilling desires
gets more and more suspect doesn't it on the path and it's tiring and it's not entirely in our control
um of course on the other hand it's also obvious that not all desires are harmful
for us and some of the happiness that desirable experiences bring is is hardly
a terrible thing so we're going to have to look more carefully at desires
and then maybe on the flip side we know that the Buddhist teachings are frequently
about letting go and how does that relate to desire so we're going to talk about some of
that during this week I think it should be an interesting Adventure
but first let's go ahead and get started meditating
so please settle in and find a
posture for meditation where you can be upright and also relaxed or if you're
lying down that's fine too but somewhere where you can be in a a straight posture
foreign
just allow yourself to feel where you're sitting
maybe your seat against the cushion or the chair
your legs or feet against the floor
and just allow yourself to be supported by what you're sitting on
thank you and we'll deliberately invite some ease
in the body so softening the muscles of the face
particularly around the eyes and even the eyes and the eye sockets
they tend to get a little tight when we're looking at the screen
releasing the jaw down through the neck
and letting the shoulders settle maybe letting the shoulder blades slide
down the back
softening the arms and the hands
and down into the chest area around the heart
rib cage
just sensing into that maybe letting it expand
use the three dimensions
softening down through the belly
in the hip joints and again feeling into where you're
sitting maybe releasing a bit more
and then letting go of any bracing in the legs
foreign [Music] for ease in the body it might be that
there's still places of tension or pain or places where we couldn't feel it very
well and that's fine the body is fine right now
so we also invite some ease in the mind
with how things are
we may gently turn attention to the breath
just the sensations of breathing in breathing out as a simple
present moment object
and just touching into the state of the Mind
as we continue to breathe
just noticing if there's any mood present
or generally the energy level is the mind a little bit tired right now or is
it a little bit agitated
just so that we have a sense of how things are
and I'd like to invite just a brief recollection
so I'd like to invite recalling a a past experience of
craving or grasping that was strong for you
and and clearly unbeneficial in some way it doesn't have to be the heaviest one
but you know the time when you wanted the coffee so bad that when the person
at the counter said they didn't have that kind you felt angry something like that an instance of
grasping that was where the mind was clearly
in a contracted state not a long story about it but instead
recollect what it felt like to have that craving or clinging
and once you have a sense of how that felt
then you can turn your attention back to
the meditation on the breath and inviting ease through the body
you can feel the contrast between those
and kind of let that recollection settle out as you breathe in and out
maybe even the grasping affected the way you were breathing you can just let it naturally
said aloud into how it is now
okay if it helps you can take a fuller deeper breath and on the out breath
encourage relaxation throughout the body just to help reset
and then continue on with simple mindfulness meditation of
noticing what's happening as it happens and in particular if the mind is
inclining toward wanting or not wanting noticing that
but mostly just saying with the simple object of the breath or the body
in mindfulness meditation
foreign
and as you're watching the mind and resting with the breath or the body
you might notice that various present moment
wanting or desire that comes in
has some similarity to that grasping that was recalled
maybe there's a sense of Leaning or contraction even if it's just a slight
one like I want a little more peace in this sitting or
I want that twinge in my back
to settle out it's maybe milder but it's of the same
family is that craving or clinging
and we just notice that this is just one of the movements of the
Mind the movement of wanting or or desire
foreign
as we continue to sit we may notice
some things that are kind of Desire that has to do with the body just the needs
of the body like maybe you're getting thirsty after
having sat here for a while or maybe there's some discomfort related to
being in the same position maybe you need to go to the bathroom
these are also basic kinds of desires and how are they similar
to these other desires that we've looked at
as we continue to sit with breath and body
mindfulness
and now I'd like to invite another
reflection or thought
so now please bring to mind an aspiration that you have for your
life or for your practice something that is clearly wholesome
maybe you're working on a degree or a certification
so that you can work in a way that serves other people
or perhaps you are aspiring to go on a
three-month retreat at some point or maybe you wish for awakening for
freedom bring that into the mind and then feel
how that is in the body
breathing with it
this is also a kind of Desire how is it similar to the other kinds of
Desire that we explored in this meditation and how is it different
without thinking about that just just rest with it
so what we see as we begin to explore
this very natural very normal quality called desire
is that it has a wide range
has a wide range it can be a wide range of how wholesome or unwholesome it can
be and how strong it can be
and how we relate to it let me relate to different Desires in different ways
so it's a big part of the mind of life
and it's a big part of what drives the world to be doing all that it's doing
and so it's very important to start looking at it
we can maybe see in our own life the drivenness that comes from some of our desires or or has come in
the past and this connects us to all people
because all people have this and we can also feel
compassion for how it is to be driven if we're not
seeing not seeing that so we can feel the wisdom even just of
these few minutes of looking at this quality of mind this Factor
of the mind and heart
and we can wish that our particular desires can be pointed
toward helping those around us and even if they're not doing that
directly simply knowing about our desires and being able to see them
that's going to give us some choice about how we interact with others how we
make choices in our life so we can
wish that those will be of benefit you'll be glad that we have the
awareness in order to make some of those choices instead of only being driven
foreign
[Music]
okay so we are talking about desire
and letting go this week and as I mentioned before the Sid
mindfulness practice reveals to us that are quest for happiness that's based in
fulfilling desires may not be fully effective
um because we start to feel the the disadvantages of how tiring it is to
always be chasing desires and also that we're not totally in control of what it is that we want to get
but on the other hand some desires are certainly useful in life and on the
spiritual path so we'll start to look at that and the
the topic for today is the diversity of Desire
so I think it's important maybe to say right up front
is all desire bad no no so we'll just say that clearly at the
beginning the Buddha was a lot more nuanced in his teachings on desire which is a very
fundamental movement of the human mind maybe we could call it something like we
could say there's a movement toward in the mind yeah we can feel that there's a movement toward and there's also a
movement away which is related but we're focusing now on this movement toward as
event very general aspect of the Mind and as we'll see as we go along this
week the Buddha actually used our tendency to move toward things as part
of the path to Freedom that he described and laid out for us
but often we know that moving toward is not not about freedom
you know we we know from the second Noble Truth the craving or clinging is
closely related to suffering so we're going to have to look at this desire this movement toward sooner or
later you know it's an important part of the practice to look at that
it's important territory let's say so we can see that there's a range of
Desire or a diversity of Desire I don't think it's quite a linear
Spectrum it's more like a space a space
or even a mandala of different kinds of Desire and the way I want to talk about it
today is to say that there are five different aspects of Desire that we
could maybe identify and so as we touch into each of these five different aspects of Desire or facets of Desire
see how each one resonates for you notice notice if and how it may be present in
your mind stream or even in your body or how it's been playing out in your life
so clearly in the unwholesome realm of
the space we find what is called a tanha in the Buddhist teachings and that's a
word that literally means thirst but it's usually translated as craving
and this is that grasping kind of Desire or clinging that is obviously painful
and harmful and it relates to things like lust or greed or strong wanting
and when this craving is about the world of the senses like something some
taste or sound or touch that we desire we call it comma
which means basically sense desire or sense pleasure like the Kama Sutra it's
the same the same word so comma tanha is strong grasping of sensual objects
um but it's not really about the object of course that the grasping is occurring in the mind
or we might habitually grasp but comfort food or or sex or sexual fantasies even
so you know we also see things like addiction to drugs and alcohol and then also tanha can relate to things
that aren't sensual like craving for power or for certain identities
and these kinds of desires I think I can just State clearly these do not support
our path to Liberation there it's clear enough because they are themselves they're binding the mind up we can feel
that when we are under their sway so that's one kind
and then you know to kind of fill out more of the space another kind is that we have some basic desires that are
related to bodily needs the desire to eat the desire to drink or to use the
bathroom um and sex as a basic desire in some
stages of human life so these desires are not usually seen as
inherently harmful but they are somewhat stressful aren't they take some effort
to do all these things um and I would say that how we relate to
the desires of the body influences how happy or unhappy we are
even awakened people have the desire to pee and they still feel physical hunger
um there's one suit that says that even arahants fully awakened beings
feel Sensations that are dependent on the body and conditioned by life
which I think means these basic bodily feelings so there is some distinction between
beings as to whether or not these very fundamental desires bring any Duco
so we'll talk a little bit more about that at some point but that is a kind of Desire
and then the Third Kind of Desire is that there are there are desires that
accompany trying to live a typical human life among other humans so we have the
wish to find livelihood we may have the wish to find a partner to be part of a
community to secure a place to live and to have enough food that's nutritious
and so forth and these desires I think we can say take a lot of energy and a lot of
attention and they're Myriad I don't think I can even name all of them
relationships family life all these worldly desires all of our political
interests and so forth Gill has said that we should be called a human desirlings rather than human
beings because there's so much Desiring and doing involved in all of these
and these are often the desires that we will defend as being very necessary and
very normal and in some ways yes um of course of course we have to do
these things but this is a big realm for Dharma practice
because many of these are actually mild forms of what I called comma before the
world of sense desire and sense pleasure we don't have to have deep pathological
grasping in order to be somewhat enslaved to our sense desires
isn't that true so the Buddha aimed a notable amount of
his teaching about desire into this space and we'll talk about it more as
the week goes on you know the desires that go with being human
so then as we continue with this space or mandala of desires
the fourth one out of five uh we could call the more elevated human
wishes if we could if we can use that word so these are things like desire for
the well-being of others aspiring to be a better person wanting to learn to
meditate or to study spiritual teachings wanting a peaceful and happy life where
we care more about how we're living than about money or status
these are generally very good desires there can still be some delusion there
could be a cell for an ego behind them but some of these wishes can actually
serve our Spiritual Development and our ethical development and our development
of compassion so the the Buddha used are elevated desires as part of the path he
encouraged these kinds of skillful wishes in order to draw us along the
path so it's good to pay attention when we have these kinds of desires and don't
don't worry about them don't worry oh I'm not supposed to want anything if I'm
on the spiritual path some of these good desires are very helpful and they will
they will lead us along the path and then the the last kind of Desire
that I would it's kind of part of the fourth but I want to separate it out it's the most powerful expression of
spiritual desire which is the desire to awaken the desire to be free to be liberated
and this even within this one there are several different facets of it one word
for it is somewega often translated as spiritual urgency and there can be times
where that's an accurate term it can really feel urgent that we need to we need to wake up or we need to do
something to move toward Liberation it can have almost a grip to it except you
know but not not like the group of tanha but we could also so sometimes it doesn't quite have that urgency and the
wish to Awakening to awaken is captured more by a word like calling you know a
calling to practice or a deep sense in the heart of wanting to be free knowing
that there's something more than what we're seeing conventionally
something that we tap into that's deep in our heart so we have this range we have
on the one end one hand tanha grasping clinging and then you know the animal
desires of the body the wishes of a human life the elevated wishes toward ethics and
compassion and then this wish to Awakening and so although they aren't quite on the
linear Spectrum there is clearly a division of wholesome and unwholesome skillful and unskillful
that's definitely relevant as we look at these different kind of desires some are
blatantly painful we might still be succumbing to them you know but it's clear enough that they're
painful right um for others of these desires we're making choices you know we decide to put
up with the stress or struggle of them because we decide that the result is worth it
um there's a kind of a cost benefit analysis going on in our mind to maybe subconsciously
and the Buddha asks us to look very carefully in that realm we'll talk a little bit more about that
and then some of the desires are clearly helpful like Compassion or ethics but on
the other hand even though we know they're clearly helpful that doesn't mean we always do them does it
so there's a lot of potential here for training um it's a lot to learn about our mind
and our heart and a lot of good effort we can put in to releasing the ones that
are really binding us and doing more of the ones that are helpful and that are elevating us
but to do that effectively we're going to need some wisdom some clarity about
what is actually onward leading on the path and what is actually binding our heart up we're not always clear on that
as humans in this realm of Desire and then to complicate things a little
bit more it changes along the path so something may not really feel like a
burden or a hindrance to us at the beginning of the path some kind of Desire that we have doesn't feel uh so
so stressful because there are other more pressing issues that we're working on but then later we might start to feel
the contraction or the limitation of certain kinds of Desire that we didn't feel before we start to realize oh this
is more like attachment the cost-benefit analysis doesn't work for this one anymore and so we have to change as it
goes along so this is the space that we're in this week this space of desire and letting go
and tomorrow we're going to have a look at this kind of Desire that I call comma
sensual attraction or sensual desire and also the movement of mind that helps us
to restrain it or shape it in various ways
so I hope you'll want to continue Along on this adventure and
um thank you I will see you tomorrow be well