so good morning to all of you here at imc and
warm greetings to those of you who are participating online youtube
it's nice that uh
nice that the people online are part of this community and that kind of the sense of who we are practicing together
meditating inclusive of such a bigger circle of people than it used to be when we just it was just the
people here so thank you
so um
one of the very interesting and important topics for people who do this practice
is to consider what the source is within you for what animates you
or to say it maybe in simpler terms where's the where what are the motivations what is
the sensibilities from which you act in the world you live your life
sometimes i like the idea of where do you take up residence
where do you where do you live what's the reference point
for your values for how you speak for how you live your life
and in buddhism one of the powerful words we have is dharma
and one of the reasons one of the nice things about the word dharma is that it's a word which is not limited to
buddhism oh kind of all the indians as far as i know almost all indian religions
and the indian culture has this very strong reference to this term dharma which
is not it's not limited to just the buddhist dharma so it's a and i think in india
i wouldn't be surprised if the word dharma encompasses the kind of some of the
overlaps or some of the span of what the english word spiritual might be where spiritual isn't limited to just
buddhism or christianity or something but spiritual has some is something that people in different
religions all can kind of kind of find some commonality or some residency
and um so to take up residence in the dharma or
have the dharma be the source of what animates us or this reference point for how we live our
lives uh is uh it involves a paradigm shift a very
radical reorientation of our life from where we usually live
and where do we usually live and i don't want to speak for any of you per se
but uh but some of the common places people live is some people live in their
fear their anxiety and fear is kind of the place where they have kind of taken up
residency though they never assume that they've chosen that residency but
in fact the so so much of who they are that it animates them it directs their thinking their speech how
they behave in the world for some people it's their desires
and their desires what they want is so important it's kind of like that's where they that's the reference
point the orientation for everything is their desires other people their reference point their
residency is uh their aversion
what they don't want other people it's their confusion
their uncertainty they're kind of grasping trying to figure out what's what in the world is going on here in this world and
what am i supposed to do and somehow that that's the center of gravity
for some people it's uh conceit some strong sense of
this is who i am some role quality a characteristic
something and the part of the difficulty with conceit is that it's often
animated by some of these other qualities fear desire aversion and confusion
and that's what makes conceits sometimes problematic when these others come in and make it much more complicated than
it needs to be and all these ways of being taking up residence
are limited residences they involve a kind of
but everyone's going to have a different way of feeling the difficulty of them or the shortcomings
of them i like very much the language of constriction they're all constricting
they limit how much we you know we're constricted by it or limited by it
and one way where they're constricted and limited is that it constricts the the range the span
of what we take in what we include as part of our lived experience
if it's fear that is the residence we're oriented some people then around more
than anything else maybe things that are threatening or potentially threatening
if it's desire it's the things that we want and we're kind of searching and looking for you know what we want and
we come to imc and for a sunday morning talk and like where's the best seat i
want to sit in the nice seat that's the seat where i set before you know that's what i want someone else comes is like i i don't
want to you know let me sit in the right place i don't want that place i don't want that place and by default i'm only
left with this one and and so we don't we don't see the
situation and abroad filled with potential filled with all
kinds of other range of orientations to understand it the perspective has gotten narrow
and in that narrowness and that constriction sometimes
how we respond to the world around us uh is uh
we call in english we talk about being reactive so something it strikes us
deep enough or impacts us or makes an impression deeply on us and it and it strikes these one these
residencies that i'm talking about those residencies will be become reactive or become upset or activated in
some strong way sometimes so that we act impulsively so
you know fear desire aversion confusion can lead to all kinds of behavior
people who are afraid can act very very impulsively
sometimes and some people who are take up residency in how they're hurt
how they've been treated poorly or badly and that's what they're or they're oriented around
if somebody comes from the outside and touches that limited residence of limited point of view in
which we operate for it's very easy we want to protect ourselves or we want to assert ourselves
or we want to you know we we want to have blame or we want to fix
or something and of course those some of that
can be healthy and appropriate but if that's their orientation
their reactivity in that kind of way it continues to restrict or constrict
the the range of how we see what we take in from the environment and also constricts and
limits the range of how we experience ourselves the more reactive we are the more less
we're in touch with the range of our humanity the range of who we are and how we feel
if we living with anger or resentment all the time then it's possible that there's no room
for a capacity for goodwill or love or friendliness
if we're living with desire as the primary orientation and then react to being frustrated desire
maybe there's very little room for feeling of having generosity or tuning into people
so we feel like we want to be generous to them because the orientation is the way we take up residency is in this
desire and the reactivity of it and sometimes the reactive mode we've
reacted to is taking it becomes comes so strong
that it's the reactivity that somehow has been set in motion
that becomes the place of residence where we take up where we live from
and what i'd like to propose is that that living out of reactivity living out of
these residencies of anxiety and desire and aversion and confusion
are places of uh heightened uh
mental activity there are places of of alertness or alarm
that i associate with kind of living a life that's more on the surface
and so it doesn't allow us to kind of drop below that surface
to experience something that's deeper within us which i associate with the dharma
if we're going to take up residency in the dharma some of you might not care for the metaphor of going deep
another way of another metaphor is is that an unrestricted unconstricted way of being
that the dharma is the way is how to of all kind of a wide open
heart a wide open sensibility that is not limited
in these ways but there's a kind of unlimited quality to attention to awareness and how we are
and and so and out of that dharma the life is not a reactive life
we could say it becomes a responsive life that those distinctions are
often used and they're nice but the language i like
to bring introduced today is there's the reactive way of living
and then there's the emergent way because the dharma is something that
emerges within us rather than something that gets
triggered by events of the life of the world around us all kinds of things can happen to us
but when we live a dharma life we take a presidency in the dharma in a sense residency in the heart presents
something deeper where there is a
a an arising of a response
an emerging of a response that has a very satisfying feeling that
it doesn't feel it necessarily has to do with conceit or me it's a different residency
taking everything to live in that place to live in that place of the dharma is to be available to something that is
much broader wider deeper fuller
than any of the constricted residencies that people commonly live by
so the uh the metaphor one of the metaphors that i
like to borrow from the buddha for this idea of the emergence is
that of a lake this has that's not being disturbed by
rain coming in not being disturbed by streams of rivers flowing into the lake
so there's no wind ruffling it but there is an underwater spring
in the middle of the lake that's bringing fresh water into the lake and the fresh refreshing water kind of
spreads out like a fountain and spreads out throughout the whole lake continually being renewed from the
depths of the lake and so this is a metaphor is used for
the buddha for what can happen in in when we're really absorbed in meditation
enough in this practice of meditation that the other residencies are not we're not living there we're not living
in the places where the rain falls where and that agitates where the water is
agitated or we don't have all these streams coming in that that somehow are
muddying the water so we're not operating from our reactivity
but we're allowing something deep inside the bubble up just and appear
the uh the other metaphor that's also one of water that i like very much the
naturalness of all this is uh the uh when rain does fall on the side
of the mountain and there's enough rain and the raindrops join together and create little trickles of stream of you
know water going down the side of the hill and the trickles be joined together and become teeny little streams and streams
become creeks and brooks and kind of then rivers and eventually you have something large
that's coming and just keeps flowing down the naturalness is it it keeps flowing down
it is flowing and sometimes if it reads if it comes to a lake and the lake is not full
it takes time to fill the lake but once the lake is full it spills over
the edge of the lake and down down the mountain some more if there's a big boulder
water will find a way around the boulder sooner or later even if it has to fill up above it or something go for the top
and but the naturalness that the the water just keeps flowing and joining and getting bigger and bigger until it comes
down from the mountains onto the plains and and then india for the buddha they get the ganges planes and maybe joins the
ganges and joy and then goes out into the ocean and uh the buddha uses this analogy to
say that as as we take up residency in the practice in the dharma
there is a natural unfolding and deepening or filling or expanding
flowing of our inner life that has a naturalness to it that's a
distinct from what we're trying any attempt we have to to construct to make to want to do
uh these dharma state dharmic states that can arise
things like certain even like mindfulness and
joy and tranquility happiness equanimity it's all kinds of wonderful things that
can kind of arise and flow i associated with
metta and karuna mudita and upeka is good will and
compassion and sympathetic joy and equanimity that uh
these also can arise from the bottom of the lake and surface and flow through us
and in fact so the the so these are the metaphors that buddha
uses for this kind of emergence and i think there's no appalling word i
think that obviously is usually translated as emergence but there's a lot of words that buddha used for the
arising the appearing of these things as opposed to the making
of them the naturalness in which these things arise
so one of the very interesting distinctions that the buddha makes that points to this little bit to this
distinction i'm making here between the reactive and the immersion emergent
is some people i call the distinction one between spiritual and non-spiritual or
spiritual and worldly some people translated it as these terms these two terms as
carnal and non-carnal which probably has very strong associations with certain western ideas
that maybe we don't want to borrow be too too associated with but
the literal uh meaning in the pal leave is that the the
first one sa amisa carnal or non-spiritual uh is um
or worldly is uh it literally means of the flesh so that's why carnal can kind
of work and and the other is which is uh
literally means not of the flesh so non-carnal and how i understand it is the first the
the non-spiritually carnal the worldly whatever way we want to translate not
of the flesh of the flesh is um it has to do with when experiences of
the world touch us
and it's that place where we're triggered so uh you know particularly if the six you
know this the five senses of eyes ears nose tongue and touch
that if somebody comes along and we get a nice massage and we feel the pleasure of it that pleasure would be considered
of the flesh kind of a worldly pleasure or a non-spiritual pleasure
nothing wrong with that pleasure buddhism doesn't negate the value of it but it's not it's it's coming from the
outside and stimulating our nerves kind of literally of the surface
the the the knot of the flesh this uh spiritual is part of this what
it can emerge from deeper within and this flowing of this of the of the spring
that can come and uh and the one of the primary associations that
this this knot of the flesh this dharmic flow
is joy and happiness but there's other qualities as well
confidence peacefulness brightness
sense of purity all kinds of things we can feel from this place exactly how we should feel it and be
with it it depends on individuals and circumstances and time but but
what i associated with is being available
to the world being available to ourselves a kind of a capacity for attentiveness for attention
that's not restricted not being defined by the different residencies we take up
that are not that limit us and constrict us we have a preoccupation we have a
perspective that we always bring but rather the attention the attentiveness is more
open available without an agenda
without a lot of hopefully presuppositions
preconceived ideas biased but it's developing this capacity to be
centered and present so that we're not leaning ahead of
ourselves into the future into things not pulling back not closing down but we're kind of opening up relaxing
into settling into taking up residency
in a place that is kind of unlimited that represents
something deep that where there's space for something to feel this life of ours in a deeper way
a place where there's space to allow some deeper motivation to animate our life
to guide our life feel our life
and this is you know i associate this with the dharma to take a presidency in the dharma
and then to trust it
rather than trusting or having faith in the reactive places we can take up
residency the reactive places where you know desire exists or frustration exist
uh aversion exists not all forms of a desire are
problematic it's a taking up residency with it not all forms of aversions are problematic
it's taking up residency so that it limits the scope of our
attentiveness our availability for this world for being here
well the buddha associates it with things like joy and happiness these beautiful qualities
i think it's by what's words really gets tested and where i find it most powerful
is when we're on when i'm uncomfortable when things are challenging and difficult
to then be available to sit in this place where the emergence happens where things can
bubble up and appear it's in a context that doesn't feel comfortable
and how to trust this place when we're uncomfortable as opposed to when we're uncomfortable
it's very easy for the reactive to fix it the blame that like something
is wrong here the judgments the stories the ideas the impatience to be there
and and then it can't be right you know this this is supposed to be the dharma world that i'm in i'm supposed to be
it's supposed to be you know riding on the clouds and being good and feeling right and everything is fine
occasionally that might happen occasionally but it's plenty of our life that is
uncomfortable the world we live in that's where the trusting
this place this deeper place the dharmic place is really significant really helpful
to take a rep residence for there trust that
more than the reactivity uh is uh
an area of tremendous growth tremendous challenge because you'll come you'll probably find in yourself
strong arguments this can't be right i can't i can't just be here and be
available for this i have to you know
be angry i'm supposed to be get something i wanted that to have to have something else to happen and
there's strong strong pull into this
what i call the reactive world or the this back up into this place where things are more superficial or the
activated mind the activated mind that is
easily activated reactivated reactivated over and over again
and the art of it the practice of it is to have discovered the dharmic dimension
the non-reacted place within where the wellsprings the naturalness of stuff
can exist even when we're uncomfortable to stay in that and breathe with it
to take our time with it to be available i'm uncomfortable but i i can be on i
can be available for now for this let's see what happens if i'm available as opposed to
rushing in with the reactivity with it's you know right now it needs to be
different this emerges place where things emerge
doesn't mean that we're just sitting patient sometimes with patients and just waiting for something to happen and
you know five minutes later you know the the rice is burning on the stove because
we there's something there's something wrong here and i'm just going to be available and
see what emerges the the
urge inside of us can act quickly sometimes they can act forcefully sometimes
but it's a very different place to live then
you know this dharmic this reactive place so where do you take a presidency
and i'm using this language residency today as an alternative to another way i could
have talked about it which maybe is more confusing or more problematic
sometimes and that is where do you create an identity what do you identify with this is who i am
and uh so rather than talking about that and then you question well i'm supposed to be somebody ain't i you know how can
i not be anything but where do you take up residency where do you live
and i like it because it also involves even though might be unconscious some kind of choice
that we've we've made that maybe we can make a different choice
and being able to make a different choice becomes possible
at some point i hope as we practice more and more as we meditate or
show up for our life with mindfulness and care and compassion that we begin to um
get a stronger feeling there isn't knowing we are stronger knowing
that there is an alternative way of living there is an alternative way
of showing up for the world that's not centered on conceit
we haven't taken up residency and this is who i am and that everything has to kind of fit into my desires or i have to
fit into everything the world wants and but it's taking up this place that
is uh is not you
but is found within you i love this kind of language
that so it's not something apart from you but it's not you but it's within you it's something so it's not the place we
don't take a presidency in an identity we don't take residency in claiming this
is you know claiming something as mine and that's one of the reasons i i find
it valuable to associate with the dharma it's the dharma the dharma knows the dharma is
responding the dharma i can trust take refuge in this dharma
so that we don't i don't you know appropriate it for me myself and mine
but to be available to be available
in an unlimited way and open to possibilities not constricted
not coagulated not
restricted but a place where attentiveness
care love
awareness kind of flows or is open or available like a
spring in a lake that might flow other there's fresh water might flow up into
all the places where we're uncomfortable all the places that are challenging they actually can flow into the place where
we are restricted where we are identified and caught
and but it's a you know wonder wonderful
an important part of dharma practice is to discover this other residency
not in opposition or as a complete substitute for the old residencies
but as a perspective with which now to begin investigating and seeing
the reactivities we have the places where we kind of keep kind of
taking up residency or acting from that are not healthy and for anybody and everyone
so there's the reactive side of us and there's the emergent
side of us and as we do this practice we begin to
discover an alternative to the reactive mode of being
to discovering the emergent mode what emerges from the dharma what emergence emerges from the spiritual
from the from the from that which is not of the flesh in a
sense that which is deeper within us that it flows like a
spring in a mountain lake so i hope this gives you something to think about i hope you practice with
something to investigate and look and see if there's these if you can if where
where in your life what i've talked about today uh you can identify or see and discover
and then maybe some point over the next week you might have the occasion to be
reactive to something maybe
and uh and then maybe right you know rather than brushing it off um
you know it's good to be respect respect our reactivity
but maybe you can try to meet it in a different way the the emerging side the available side
the place where there's a kind of open just being sensitive to what is this can open and meet the places of
reactivity in a new way what's that like for you what happens then
so thank you and
we have we have a little bit of time if some of you would like to ask a question
or comment about this a testimonial or
a reservation about it all anything else
i really enjoyed your talk this is wonderful points to live by i just wanted to mention that uh when
you are in a grip of fear uh you know which is seems at the time to be profound
and engulfing so forth and you um you want to work your way out of that
you know in that particular respect um i found
i had this problem last year over a period and that the
the consequences were pretty serious over over that period and i
i find myself when i just instead of being in a group of fear
i laid out a plan for myself and that plan really helped me
to get out of the fear and be more in more
uh how shall i say more at peace with the issue and how to
approach it and an end point potentially for the for the issue that was at hand
and i found that to be useful just at the very minimum just come up with a
plan be proactive about how do i deal with this great i love it i know what i
hear from that is that it's possible to step out far enough from fear and off the
grip of fear and operate from a different place and one of the different places is to sit down with a piece of
paper and pen maybe and uh and make a plan and consider what are their alternatives what are the ways
i you know you can't make a plan in the middle of the crisis but maybe ahead of time you could think about some options
and then to live with that plan it sounds like a wonderfully wise way thank you
sometimes in my life when uh uh
i've had some kind of personal challenge that really troubled me the uh
you know how to step out of the reactive mind how to not to have the usual way of thinking
always be the way that we live in the world is especially if the usual way of
thinking is just like second nature it's like you know it's like the like the fish doesn't see the water
supposedly that they swim in we don't necessarily see the thinking that we live in and don't really see what goes
on so when i've been troubled by some things occasionally what i've done is gone someplace where i was alone like
driving a car and spoken out loud and because i find that when i
speak out loud it's actually speaking from a different place within me
than where i think from and so there's access to different wisdom different understanding different
perspectives different attitudes different care it's it's different enough
but if i'm only thinking about things all the time i mean my thoughts i'm actually limiting myself the scope and
the range of how i can consider something and so you might some of you if you ever
find yourself troubled and want a new perspective you might try find a place where you're alone
or at least have you know earbuds that people think you're on the phone
and so so this is kind of building what you said this ability to sit back and plan
is also maybe calling on a different part of the brain the mind and just the usual just letting things go thinking go
along
great talk thank you so much and never um
heard exactly those two words coupled uh emergence and reactive a little bit
closer oh is that better yeah okay thank you so much was such a
beautiful talk and i have never heard those two words coupled uh
emergent and reactive so um and one thing i was
thinking about just now about where a person takes up residence
is um i follow on youtube and so your talks last
week about the different bodies and i just wondered if it would be possible
for you to speak about that a little bit again particularly the karmic body
and then um the like the intersection between um
emergence so the you that's not your identified you but or
identified self and your residency because i'm seeing that there's
great like that's so real right so something i think yeah so the uh i very much
associated the karmic body or karmic activity as being the reactive
and uh the word karma means activity action or activity
and so it kind of works you know reactivity you know reaction
so it's the it's the actions which uh reverberate or repeat themselves or
uh come from some place that is uh that
karma is activity which our activity our actions that we do or i like activities sometimes because not
always so conscious there are ones that leave a trace the ones that uh uh
trigger more things to occur and on and on the emergent doesn't automatically
require or trigger ongoing activity to be there it can kind
of exist without leaving a trace and so last week when i talked about the
four or five kinds of body the last four were the emergent qualities of the body
and and so yeah so the second half of your question about more identity what was that
um yeah in in a way you almost just
answered it but yeah just like the intersection of you you said to try to um
be with it you know when you're uncomfortable um to not uh
shut down or you know whatever that wasn't your word that's mine but um
and how to sort of uh maybe note or in so much as
it's even possible to know your own residency and how that is kind of maybe did i
understand you to say that your residency can is like thwarting
your emergence yeah so i'm not sure it's a great
question i'm not sure i have them good answer for you
that the deserves but the one that i prefer is that all this becomes known as you keep
practicing mindfulness just keep practicing mindfulness let your mindfulness become stronger and
developed and to develop a skill or capacity to be uncomfortable
to be to be comfortable some people have trouble feeling joy whatever it might be
but be able to become familiar with yourself more and more so you start seeing the places
where the maybe the inflection points between what brings stress and what brings the
opposite of stress and the more you do that the more you'll start getting the you'll start reading
the book in your body of what's pointing towards the emergent and what points to the reactive
but it becomes you know the real place is just keep studying yourself being present and seeing and learning
to now because because i talked about the emergent quality and maybe in a nice way so okay now that's what i'm gonna do
you know okay i'm gonna you know you know probably that's it's so too easy for that to come from a reactive place
or to take up residency doing that i'm gonna be the one who's gonna be the emergent one you know and just like that's not it
either but this is something that begins to arise to surface and become clear and
something we trust and something we rest in as we know ourselves better and better and as we know the difference between
these different modes and so i'm using the modes of reactive
and emergent today some people another mode that's related is skillful and unskillful wholesome and unwholesome
so there's there's all these different things but the the recipe is to understand yourself better
is that okay great okay well thank you
so uh last few weeks i've been here we've had a meeting out in the parking lot for those people who want to stay
it's been really lovely and taking off the masks and just sitting in a circle and talking unfortunately i can't stay today because
i'm going to the retreat center to be there early today to help set up for the retreat that starts today
however um it occurred well you're welcome i encourage those of you who want to do it today hillary will be
there and hillary will facilitate some discussion and and just sharing amongst yourselves nice
to hang out a little bit with each other so if you want to bring up a folding chair and bring it out to the parking lot
that would be quite nice and uh because i'm doing this retreat i won't be here next week
next week a long time imc practitioner and person who does a lot
of teaching here for us is maria stratman will come and give a talk and people love her talks when she comes
here so i think you're in good hands and um
so thank you very much and