hello everyone welcome and um
so
you know uh offering a welcome is uh kind of sharing my joy and
happiness with being here with all of you and i think a welcome carries the most
value if it's offered quite personally um
if it was every other word came out of my mouth was welcome to everybody and
everyone it might feel kind of an automatic pilot and not mean much but there's a person
if it feels personal actually a person personally feels the welcome or some
some the fullness of the person is welcoming you into into their space
it can feel kind of richer or fuller or something and and perhaps sometimes when uh you
come to some place where you really do feel welcomed it feels like all of you is welcome like
it's very it's a like you it's you feel it personally this like you're maybe in
your bones and your muscles and your heart just feels like it's a full uh experience of oneself that's being
welcomed so i i would like to do something that'll offer a little unusual for
a buddhist meditation and that is to really take it personally
uh welcome yourself fully allow yourself be welcomed fully
um but take you really let this meditation be very personal
uh sometimes uh the wisdom teachings in our tradition uh people say don't take it personally
whatever happens and um and it's very freeing to not take something personally and we have a
thought maybe it's a horrendous thought and don't take it personally
meaning don't define yourself by it don't let it be the whole being of who you are
just let it be something like the weather that you know it's kind of wanders through
and and um you know that it's uh impacts us but it's not us
so don't take it personally but today i'd like to suggest it to really take things personally well don't take it
that we're taking is a evocative word that maybe is part of the problem of it all
but let it all be personal but personal in a particular way
not personal in terms of letting yourself be defined by it where your ideas and memories and
ideas of the future your stories of self come into play but rather the kind of cozy
personal that you may be if you were engrossed in a very good book and really
kind of comfortable on the couch reading and just it's you wouldn't call it personal but
something very subtle and full and whole is there just being
in the pleasure of the reading that
maybe after a full week of activity and you go for a walk in a park and
everything falls away your concerns and your problems and issues and
and it's just so nice and full you feel kind of fullness and happiness just being alive and walking in the park
it's very personal the sense of aliveness may be a spring and you feel
like spring inside so not taking it personally not making it
personal but experiencing it personally
with all of who you are so as we sit today maybe
there's a place that has depth in you or or breath in you or fullness in you of
what is personal that's not your identity not what you think about yourself
but something how you feel or be or and it's so
personal and as meditation goes deeper and deeper in a way it's very personal
it's no it's not someone else's experience it's this experience of this body this
person here so um [Music]
maybe by going personal today and going all the way personal
something drops away some self-concern self-preoccupations and
self some ego drops away because there's no room for ego
in the depth and fullness of what's most personal
so assuming a meditation posture which is also very personal each person
finds their own posture and comfort
and gently closing the eyes
and with the eyes closing we sometimes you feel we're coming into a personal world
here maybe a little bit in internal
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths
and on the exhale letting go of your thoughts your concerns
your ideas reactions to what i've said
maybe an exhale letting go of a certain kind of self-preoccupation
that travels in the highways and byways of your thinking
and as you let go of
relax your body
letting your breathing return to normal and gently on the exhales
relax
there's a settling in as the body relaxes
the shoulders
the belly
maybe the thighs can soften
the arms and the hands
and there can be a settling in coming home to
as the body begins to soften
breathing in and breathing out
this relaxing deeply in the core of your being relaxing
settling into what is more personal
than personal that which is more personal than how you
usually define yourself think of yourself
in the depths of your being let this meditation be personal
maybe the breathing
your breathing can be
a gentle invitation
to come deep within
for all of you is welcomed
and as all of you is welcomed
there's a letting go of what is superficial
there's a relaxing into the depths of our being
breathing through the depths breathing with the depths of our
fullness our beingness
and whatever happens during this meditation it's all okay
but assume that it's uh means
of relaxing into something deeper more personal
not the what's on the surface of your thoughts and feelings and ideas
but almost from like the place where they are from where they arise
the depths of who you are breathe there
trust the depths that's within you
all too often thinking takes us away from the depths and
fullness of what is most personal here with us
more personal than our history and our plans
here deep within this body and heart
may be a quiet place a warm place
where we can sit with what is most personal here and now
so
how quiet can you let your thinking mind be
the kind of quiet that allows you to feel or listen
to the fullness or the depth of your what's most personal here as you
sit quietly and breathe
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to reflect for a moment how
when you are most comfortable with yourself at peace with yourself
at home with yourself uh when then that's when this might
happen that you become a message the medium is
the message you become a walking message that it's
possible to be at peace possibly at home and comfortable with oneself
and this is a gift for the world where so many people don't have that experience
and perhaps with whatever degree way that you are now that
maybe you're more settled or maybe more willing to
find a way to be it at home in yourself in this deep personal way
may this serve to bring greater well-being and peace to this
world whether it's directly or intentionally or
indirectly unintentionally may the benefits of this meditation
we've done today with all the many of us
doing this together across the globe
may it spread from us in benefit for everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we each find ways to contribute to this possibility
[Music]
thank you
so finding our way in this challenging world
finding our way with the personal challenges we have and with our minds and all that
and one of the things we're navigating and working against working with is the
the uh navigating the terrain of happiness and suffering
and in buddhists talk a lot about suffering
it's a big word for some people sometimes some people who come new to buddhism are a little disturbed by often
we talk about suffering because suffering just seems like such a you know monumental
thing but we use the term in a wide way
and but one of the ways i like to use it today
happiness and suffering is
is something that's deeper than contentment deeper than gladness deeper
than joy that but uh that happiness
is something that's deeply personal and that um
the opposite of that suffering is also something deeply personal
that some of the greatest suffering that people experience is when they've been a real a personal
violation whether it's a physical violation against your body
or whether it's been in a violation against some deep sense of trust or deep violation about who you are as a person
or in a relationship to others and um the um
i remember many years ago that a friend of mine had her car broken into
and she felt it was such a deep violation somehow that car
represented so much more than just a car and
so our sense of safety and place in this world our sense of belonging
and it is a very personal issue and to have the sense of belonging absence of
connection to the world or our sense of meaning uh personal meaning and purpose have
sense of um or even our sense of worth our personal
value somehow dismissed or destroyed or or threatened
can cause a lot of suffering it isn't just a simple suffering that i have a flat tire and i came late to an
important meeting that something is deeply personal and and with that it's you know can k we can
stay it can have deep conditioning factors within us on the corollary there's a same for
happiness it's not this happiness that oh now i fixed the car the tire and that's great
i'm not stuck here anymore and i think i'll get to the meeting on time that's nice and certainly can be happy
around that but by the time you get to the meeting you've forgotten about the tire and what
happened there but that the happiness that real sukkah and pali word the real happiness
of the dharma is something very personal that touches something very deep within
us of fullness and and and is overlaps with deep feeling of sense of belonging or meaning or purpose
overlaps with a sense of worth and value that is full a sense of personal
confidence and so there's a fullness there's a depth to it
some people might take exceptions to my use my my repeated use of the word personal today
i do a little bit to be to because it's something a buddhist don't tend to use to really kind of
challenge you to look deep or into yourself into a fullness
um and of course there's a little common
teaching in buddhism not to take things personally and i understand this to mean it's the
taking it's the uh appropriation of things and saying this is who i am
the act of defining ourselves by something the act of um
of uh proving ourselves or building up a self building up this edifice of ego that we have
which keeps us in some way superficial the happiness of
of of sukkah this happiness of the dharma is something that's full or deeper than
anything that you could take personally or assume to be or define yourself by
it's not about definitions it's more like being so comfortable with yourselves
that you will you don't need to be defined by anything you don't need to prove yourself towards
anyone you have nothing to fear because it's so deep the personal is so
deep it's kind of like we tap into that some depth inside of peace of well-being of
personal personal personalness that
can't be touched can't be hurt no matter what other people do to us maybe this is a place that
is a reservoir of well-being so it's very personal
now in terms of so part of the theme of today this week is
the pendulum that there is a kind of happiness and suffering
that live in relationship to each to each other and uh you set up one
and it almost it's almost like a preparing the ground for the other to come back and forth
and that's when we take things personally in a superficial way
we take things personally by some
appropriated identity or definition that is not really who we are
so for example if um if um
i define myself by being a youtube
producer producing shows for youtube or whatever and then the technology works well for a
few months like it has lately i could feel really happy about myself but when when somehow i forget to push
the right buttons then then the happiness that comes from the
praise i get from others and the delight others have with my great capacity on youtube
plummets and then i feel miserable because i forgot some push the right buttons
and um and so then i feel unhappy and i suffer and
and um and so that pendulum that happiness and suffering is dependent on these kind of
superficial things and fragile things is really it's because reality is always
changing it sets up for crashing and building yourself up again
so finding our way with this superficial will keep us superficial
the dharma practice is to connect something deep something that's not
defined by these superficial things or it's not influenced or affected by what happens
it's not affected by what other people think about us believe it or not not affected by whether we're successful
or a failure in the things that we do we do things sincerely and honestly
and some succeed and some fail and but the depth of our being
where we really reside and live inside where we're comfortable with ourselves
that is not um that is not you know touch that's
that stays intact and so um so to
not know the depth of and be comfortable and resolved and healed in the depth of us
can leave that depth in a place that there's a lot of suffering but if we heal it and work with it and
relax and open and deeply in it and this deep personal place where we can find
peace and home and trust and refuge it's not exactly a pendulum anymore it's
it abides by itself and and if it falls away it doesn't
necessarily go into despair or steep suffering
but deep suffering is there if we take things personally deep suffering is not there
if we are personal if we abide and rest in that which is
deep and full and complete inside of ourselves and
and so in buddhism we're quite fond of talking about not self
and one way to bring these two things together i'm talking about today and not self
is that when we are so personal so at home so resting what's most personal most
intimate most full that flows from within in us
it's so full it's so complete it's so that there's no tendency or desire
to define a self out of it to find a self in it to want to self in it to hold on to a self
there the any kind of the kind of idea of me myself and mine those kinds of concerns
just fall away just as maybe someone who's involved in
wonderful play or wonderful sport or wonderful playing of music
there's they can get lost and lost in the in the what they're doing
we say lost completely absorbed in what they're doing and it just feels so complete and good
to be there and there isn't occurred to them while they're doing the activity
the usual thoughts about myself and me myself and mine so the same way we meditate or in the
dharma this deep personal place where we can find comfort comfort
belonging healing happiness well-being
if we really can learn to be there and trust it and allow ourselves to get quiet enough to
really be absorbed in it there's no
movement in the mind no tendency of the mind for me myself and mine
from the point of view of the surface where we think a lot about me myself and mine and we live in that world of me
myself and mine um they might when i say these things might immediately come but i am me and
there are things that are mine so from the logic of that more superficial world
yes and maybe what i'm saying doesn't make sense but um but that superficial world that's
the world where the pendulum of suffering and um and happiness uh live in
relationship to each other and and uh we kind of get trapped in the pendulum we can swing back and forth
maybe and and uh and then it never ends but this the depth of who we are
the depth of well-being the peace of the dharma that's within us the dharma
and so when you become yourself fully in this personal way
then it said then the dharma becomes the self when you are yourself
the dharma is the dharma you are the dharma then
so um thank you and look forward to coming back tomorrow and
and then having our meeting at the in 24 hours
so thank you