warm greetings and a warm welcome to
inside meditation center that you get
so for the meditation today i would like to evoke the quality of
trust and that
sometimes in buddhism we talk about trusting the dharma
going for refuge to the dharma but i think that
when things come down to really practicing the dharma what we
learn is that we're trusting our hearts in some ways the dharma and the
and our hearts are the same and our hearts um
understand much more than our minds do or much more than we do
and to trust something that is wiser or deeper
is more able to protect us and care for us and guide us and sometimes our conscious mind can do
and that is not a maybe easy thing to find or come to
but when we sit and do this practice when we do a practice
of the heart the practice that connects us deeply to that which is
within us it's more than conscious then we discover that there's a place of
trust something we can trust the dharma in us the heart in us
so to sit with trust so
to begin with a posture
that you can trust maybe not maybe there's no perfect
posture i think there is no perfect posture for any of us
but maybe there's a posture that can you can trust enough for these minutes of
meditation a posture that allows you to
relax and to let go
and to gently close your eyes
and to feel this body
in a sense we learn to trust the body too
no that's not the body that decays or becomes sick exactly but something
something deeper about here in this lived body
is a place that we relax
and relaxing the body into the
pull of gravity wherever you're sitting or touching
whatever surface is holding up your weight
your weight being the
the interface direction of your body and gravity
and to let yourself trust the support your body is given
by the surface that hold your body up
taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing trusting on the exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and to progressively relax your body maybe think of it as a progressive
trusting each movement of relaxation means to trust enough to do so
on the exhale relaxing the belly
trusting enough to let the belly relax soften
on the exhale relaxing the chest and the heart
trusting enough to relax in the chest
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the shoulders softening the shoulders there's a release of
some fear or mistrust and a movement towards trusting enough
to relax
enter relax the face
the face is more engaged in our lived life than most people realize
and to let there be trust in the face so the eyes can relax
cheeks and jaws
the forehead
and then relax relaxing the thinking mind
maybe softening a mistrust or fear that's in the mind
for these minutes trusting there's nothing you have to
fix or save or protect
these minutes now you're safe and
protected and so you can relax the mind
from its concerns trust
a trusting
and then becoming attuned to your body breathing
noticing that if in the breathing there is any anxiety or fear
it's okay if there is
let the rhythm of breathing massage whatever
fear anxiety there might be
noticing if the fear changes
throughout the cycle of breathing in and breathing out
becoming aware of that rhythm of change
letting the breathing relax
soften
softening relaxing as you exhale
and allowing as you inhale
and here now in this lived experience of breathing
being in a body for these minutes that you're here
trusting being alive trusting breathing
being mindful being present
for these minutes perhaps that trust can be
entrusting just being here present breathing
is enough
so as we come to the end of the sitting
as we become come to greater freedom in this practice
one way of expressing that freedom is that just to be alive is enough
sitting here meditating breathing being mindful
that there's nothing to attain nothing to be or nothing to prove ourselves
just being here breathing being alive
is enough or is glorious
to trust that this is enough for these few minutes
and if you appreciate
the well-being that comes with just being here breathing with trusting
this moment this experience
if you appreciate the well-being the ease the freedom the absence of stress that it produces
imagine what it'd be like for others to have the same
to others to have be free of the stress of needing to attain and to prove themselves
the stress of being afraid and anxious needing to protect themselves
how wonderful would be if others could have this sense of ease
well-being have the ability to trust just being alive is enough
may it be that as we do this practice and we taste the benefits of it
that we share those benefits with the world around us
may we dedicate the benefits of this practice for the welfare and happiness
of everyone wishing
happiness on others wishing safety
for others wishing peace and freedom for others
and wishing that we find we notice
the small things big things we can do today to contribute to that possibility
to the welfare and happiness of others
[Music]
thank you
um
so here we have the beginning of our third talk
on fear and
yesterday i talked about holding the fear carefully
so that the fear feels safe another way of maybe talking about that
is to have the ability to be present for fear and offer attention to fear
without reacting to it without being for it or against it without being
impacted and influenced by it acting being pushed around by the fear
to just learn to learn the ability to be present the capacity to be present
and be in a certain way comfortable certain way at peace
with being afraid and these two who you know come being comfortable or being at peace with fear is possible
and what that does it begins to change our relationships to fear
and gives us a chance to look at it more deeply
it also allows the chance for the fear to do its own process
the dharma in us the heart in us has has a way of healing has a way of
moving towards health if we can get out of the way enough while at the same time
being attentive being present and that's the wonderful ingredient of
this practice is to have the capacity to be present to be attentive to something
without interfering with it without fixing it changing it judging it
but making almost like the attention gives room for something to unfold to unwind to
evolve the way it needs to evolve so some of that happens with fear
but fear also is a great subject for study to look at in respect
it's helpful to think of fear as a message and the question is what is it a message
of and to ask that question what is this message
what is this fear trying to tell me what's it about is a very profound question that
that is supported by this capacity to be present because if we don't know how to be present kind of in a relaxed open kind
of accepting way then the chances are that when we're attending to fear we're bringing with us
our fear of fear our aversion of fear our stories about fear and rather than just seeing it in a very
much simpler more direct way and so um
what is the message of fear now sometimes fear is a very good message that something is
dangerous and when the fear has to do with something in the moment like we have a
really clear sense right now there's something not right here something is off
that maybe should really get us to stop and pause and take look at the situation
you know our minds our hearts know more than what we consciously know
our mental processing is quite complex involved
involves much more than what we see on the surface of the mind you know the conscious mind
and so we're taking in a lot of information from the environment that we don't really
conscious processly consciously and so if there is a fear about something is
off it might be something to pay attention to i've done that in situations in cities
in san francisco and um there was a clear you know suddenly this is this this situation is not safe
this person who is following me is not safe and i would then
change what i was doing i remember once i uh that this is not good
and um and i didn't know what it was but something about that told me this is not safe
and so i walked into a grocery store and uh
and and i think it was a really wise choice
so there's all kinds of things that come up and so this idea that sometimes fear is a good message that there's danger
sometimes fear has no immediate danger sometimes we call them fear that kind of fear anxiety
but there's fear about something that we're imagining it might be coming in the future
and there might be there also there might be some deep understanding that maybe there really is
something to be afraid of and where we're going what we're doing and um
and so to stop and feel the fear take it as a message and try to study it what's what's this about
can you in fact understand more about it if there's an opportunity to reflect on and think about it
and there's two very i think useful directions for
investigation around fear one is what are we threatened by
and then more profoundly maybe something that really meditators could ask in a deep way
what is threatened in this with this fear what inside of me what
what about me what what what what is being threatened by the danger so what is being uh what is the threat
um is what's really the thing that seems dangerous here
and is it in fact a mountain lion about to pounce or is it fear
that of rejection that if i go into that social situation
certainly i'll be rejected and that those people are not going to like
me for whatever reason and and that might be i mean it happens
sometimes but if we every social situation go in there's a fear of rejection
and um and that's that's the threat is that people will reject me and it's always
that's a concern then maybe what's interesting is to look at what is being threatened here
what is it that keeps what's the common denominator that i bring with me to all these different social situations
what is it that uh is in danger in me and um
and sometimes we can find very interesting things there the um
uh you know i i had a fear of rejection when i was young
and as i looked at it more and more deeply it what is being threatened here
uh i saw because i because i started being a meditator it wasn't so much that i saw what was
being threatened though i saw it to be a lot of my ideas my imaginations of what would happen and
what the consequences of that if i was rejected then something else would happen it'd be
cascade domino affected in my imagination of things but when i looked what is being what is
really being threatened here inside of me and in this present moment
and i found that there was nothing that there was nothing that uh there was
a place inside of of of well-being
that was untouchable by whether or not people rejected me or not and that made a huge difference it
started to shift something in me about this fear that i had i it no longer carried much
force on me or i didn't invest a lot of importance in it and it was still there but it was like i could just shrug it
somebody just shrug it off okay there it is again my old friend and um because i knew a kind of
confidence and a sense of well-being that i could protect or i could stay close to
and i knew that that doesn't have to be threatened by what other people do
in fact i learned that the real threat and this is the question this first
question what is what is where is the threat where is the danger is that one in some many situations the
real danger is not what happens in the world but my own mind and what i do about it
and this fear of rejection i could see that the real danger was uh
the fear itself the real danger was the contraction i had the resistance i had
the the that free sometimes freezing sometimes the
collapse that i had in myself the attachment that i had around something
and um and that was the real danger to come to that place to see that the
real danger was in my own mind not out there around the sphere of rejection that was powerful for me
and because then i could practice with myself i wouldn't have to try to find
everyone get everyone to like me or stop rejecting me i could practice with my own mind
and it came to a point well if they reject me it was okay if they don't reject me that's okay because i work
through my own reactivity around this whole issue and have found this place
inside of peace of well-being that
i didn't want to sully i didn't want to i felt that this is important to protect from myself
and so the whole buddhist practice that was then learning how to work with this mind and mind
letting go of the attachments letting go of what what i was holding on to there in my mind
letting go of the reactivity the that i had there so to ask the question what is being
what is the threat what is a threat really to understand that and there's many many
answers to that but to ask that question but don't don't settle for the first answer
um you can ask keep well yes yes i'm threatened by that people reject me but
what's really the threat what's the really the danger if they do that what is really the danger what's the
danger here what am i afraid of and maybe there's layers of answers to that
question um and sometimes you do i'll go through the layers and you'll find that the real
threat is in your own mind surprisingly sometimes you'll see the real threat is
out in the world and because you really got to see it well and understood it that that's where the danger is
maybe you're in better position to address that danger out there
but they keep asking also the question what is being threatened that's a profound question
and sometimes even when there's real threats out there in the world that need to be addressed and taken care of or be
protected from at the same time
there might be aspects of what's being threatened inside that is the domain of practice that might show you something
very profound about what you're doing extra what is not needed
in the heart or in the mind the very thing that we're holding on to our attachments
what we are trying to protect or how we're trying to prove ourselves or
how we're trying to get other people to see us or how we're trying to kind of protect our a certain kind of inner
story about ourselves that we have and we start seeing what that's being
threatened my desire for security my desire to be seen as a particular way
my desire to um to uh
you know all kinds of things so the um what is being threatened so
what is what is really the threat and spend time and what is being threatened
and to repeat what i said at the beginning that investigation is a lot easier
when we've learned how to hold the fear
carefully and mindfully helping the fear feel safe then we're in a better position to ask
these questions in a good way so um
you might try that today the next 24 hours is look at things that you're anxious
about look at things that you're afraid of and and take some quality time reflecting on
what is really the threat to it and maybe it should be plural what are the threats what is be what is the threats
where's the threats coming from uh what is really the what's really the danger for you
in this thing and then what is being threatened in you what what what is what is the
uh yeah what is being threatened what is the thing that you feel is afraid will happen to you
or to your life what is that become clear about that and maybe there too there's layers of understanding what is
being threatened and i'm confident that whatever you discover
in that that it will bring you greater wisdom to understand how to navigate
your fear and live with your fear so um
i hope you have just the right fear today just enough to be able to do this exploration
and then we'll continue tomorrow thank you