okay so formally hello and welcome to happy hour
lovely to be with you lovely to practice together it just warms my heart every time
um even if right before it it's been a really busy day and fall and
here i arrive and ah just my heart already is warmed up sitting together
and i invite you to perhaps put yeah um those who are on zoom
uh if you want to put each other on on gallery view so that you can see each other for a moment if you want it just a
sense of oh here's a community of like-minded people coming to
cultivate cultivate their hearts um i'm not alone in this fellow human
beings just like me hopes and dreams just like me challenges just like me
just like me and in fact the theme of just like me is
going to be our theme for tonight just like me just like me and that just like me
teaching can be a powerful teaching both ways can
be a powerful tool or support support for
meta for compassion uh both ways so the way you can support
us for and what i mean by both ways is the following so one way is
um for us to take it easy on ourselves like oh yeah
i'm like anyone else i'm just like anyone else anybody else who would be in this kind of situation
in this physical situation with this illness or with this emotional challenge
they would be having a hard time right now they would be having a hard time so i'm not separate i'm not different from
anybody else just like others i'm just like others just like me
or just like them and the same way so you get the one way right so you're not separate because
we're usually so hard on ourselves like get it together come on get it together like you should be able to do this like
oh sweetheart anybody else would be having a hard time i'm just like others just like others a
human being not superhuman i have my foibles my challenges just
like anyone else that's one way this just like me can be
supportive the other direction where it can be
supportive is when we see others when we see others
um maybe other suffering and we feel with them we feel for them
that oh just like me this is a human being just like me they're just like me
they have hopes dreams challenges they have a body that aches i know what that's like well they get sad they get
lonely they get angry they get distracted oh you're just like me
oh just like me may you be well may you be free from all these just like me and
that can extend expand our heart to have kindness
towards others all beings expanding through um
concentric circles so those two different ways that this beautiful empowering phrase
just like me just like me or just like others just like them
can be super power can be really supportive in our practice so
so what i'll do tonight in guiding us in practice together
is um as always we'll start with
settling settling into our bodies with our breath we usually take roughly about
10 minutes just to settle it's so important to settle in the body and the breath before
starting meta we always do that always do that very important
and then we open up and what i like to do is to actually start with um
well i'll keep it a surprise you see you'll go explore and as always i like
to say especially if you're new to this practice or even if you've done it a
million times whatever arises whatever arises
even if or especially if it's not what you expect as long as you're kind towards it as
long as you're kind towards yourself you are doing this practice right
so if there's a little voice that comes oh you're distracted you're sleepy you're not doing this right you're
terrible if you're kind towards it oh sweetheart you're having a hard time it's okay
it's okay dear it's okay you are doing this practice right
as long as you have kindness towards whatever arises that's what we're cultivating here okay
so be kind be kind to whatever rises so
so with that i'd like to invite you to settle if you need to move to your
cushion or to a chair or maybe even lie down if that's what your body needs right now
take care of this body my body wants to shift a little bit before settling in my chair
sitting such that you can be comfortable for the next 30 minutes
sitting lying down standing it's all okay all postures
of meditation and arriving arriving in this body
letting go [Music] in this moment from how busy the day might have been
or full or sad or up or down you're here
you're here i'm here ah
touching the earth touching the earth this precious
precious earth with your precious body
this human body mine however it is
however it is in this moment treasured
unique and permanent only mine
for a short time [Music]
relaxing inviting this body to release
release release release any tightness holding weight
into the chair cushion
letting go releasing thoughts in this moment preoccupations
of course there are many and it's okay trust that they're important enough they
will come back at the end or late right now
[Music] give your heart to this practice give your heart to this practice
and the seclusion and the delicious seclusion of the mind
letting all the busyness be outside be away dancing on its own
you can rest rest in your heart
take rest dear heart
turning your attention inward
and letting the breath be received
each breath let it be received in your abdomen
not from the control tower no but as if the body is an organ of perception
receiving each breath the entirety of the in-breath the
entirety of the breath like a lullaby
soothing breath calming calming
as if you're a baby being rocked
with the breath
caring caring for yourself receiving the breath
with gentleness with kindness to yourself
and if thoughts arise it's not a problem not a problem at all
see if they can be received smilingly
and then gently gently released released from your heart your chest
your shoulders becoming lighter ah
thank you thought please come back later
and being with the lullaby of the breath
to settle be soothed
it's so sweet right here we don't have to get
entangled in the busyness of thoughts it can be so calm and sweet
enjoying enjoying the breath being received
it's not assured there must the grim duty
let it be enjoyable you're treat for the day for yourself
this moment of peace
and i would like to invite you if you would bring someone to mind who's
easy for you to have warmth care kindness towards
could be a pet a child a friend
someone who has been kind to you in the past benefactor so with with whom you have an
uncomplicated relationship ideally a little bit of complication is okay but
not too complicated so when when you think of just a smile maybe shows up a sense of
safety just a natural care
or this being for this person or being
breather image their sense to your mind's eye
feeling the sense of connection in your heart
with them and let there be a sense of kindness the phrases flowing out of
the sense of connection you have the four traditional phrases
you might have your own simply
may you have ease may you
let's no actually i usually say that at the end may you have safety
let's start with that the basis for all the other ways that we feel
happy and well may you be safe dear one may you be safe
from inner and outer harm may you be safe
may you be happy and joyful dear one
connecting with their image their felt sense
may you be healthy and strong dear one
and may your life flow with ease dear one
may you be safe
may you be happy may you be healthy
may you have ease
and realizing that this dear being of yours you're not so different from them
you're not that different at all they have a body you have a body
they have been sick have had pain
the same for you it's not unique they've had sadness sorrow loss
as you have there are people they care about
they love as do you
they have hopes and dreams aspirations
just as i do just as you do
they want to be happy this being wants to be happy there's not one to
suffer wants to be free from suffering
instead of ease just like me just like me
i am not different i'm not separate i'm not different
than this dear being of mine
just like them just like them i want to be happy
and just as i wish them to be safe i wish myself safety
may i made this being who is me be safe just as i wish happiness for them may i
be happy
may i be healthy may i have ease
just as i wish it for them may i have well-being
if you like you can wish both of you well maybe we both
have safety happiness health and ease
continuing with the phrases and wishes of menta for both of us
safe happy healthy
ease
i am not different than they than anybody else in the world in
wanting to be safe happy healthy and happy
to be free from suffering
there's a challenge right now you're having in your life physical emotional
situation in a relationship consider that anybody else the same
causes and conditions same background would be suffering in the same way
be feeling challenged it's not unique to you you're not a bad
meditator bad person human being
just like others i suffer in these ways may i be free
from this challenge may i have ease i am no different
i am no different from anyone else in this way
it's common humanity appreciating my own common humanity
that this is hard it would be hard for anyone
may i have ease in the midst of it
and i'd like to invite you to choose someone who is neutral for you a person
maybe you know them a little bit or maybe someone you have just a slight
bit of irritation with a tiny bit not the number one person on your list
and realize that this person the stand-in for all of humanity this other
being this human being or maybe just choosing a random person
you don't know here on zoom practicing together in sangha
just like me they're human being they suffer they have hopes and dreams
just like me they want to be happy they want to do their best in this world
in this life they're an object of affection of someone
and they care for others we have a tender heart for others
just as i wish to be happy and healthy and have ease i wish you the same
you are just like me in our common humanity the way that
we're human of course our life circumstances are different
maybe our gender identity or size or age
background but the basic basic humanity
you're just like me i'm just like you two human beings
on this earth without a manual
just as i wish to be happy i wish happiness for you i wish you well
just as i'm finding my way may you find your way
to ease and freedom
do
i wish you well familiar familiar stranger i wish you well
okay
you feel like you can open the circle wider
to all bigs all beings just like me
seeing your common humanity
or your common beingness
we're all stardust
alive doing our best
all beings everywhere i share my good will freely
generously openly i wish you all well
just as i wish to be safe i wish you all safety knowing that full
safety is not possible in the world but i offer it as a wish
as a gift of well-being
of kindness of goodwill from my heart may you be
safe without attachment to outcome
i offer it may you be happy all beings
may you be safe may you be healthy and may you have ease
generosity generosity and your good will in our goodwill
just like me you're no different
and just like you i'm a human being who lives and dies and
suffers not so different
including yourself may all of us all of us beings
may we all be well at ease
be free
and for the last moment of this practice period
releasing letting go of any judgment for anything that
arose or did not arise you showed up you did your best
just like anybody else with this background
the causes and conditions of your life maybe
everybody else would have been distracted or sleepy or whatever arose it's okay
just like me just like them
give yourself a break and be kind to yourself
appreciate yourself you showed up you showed up and you're still here till the end
yay you showed up and you did your best
let go of the rest and with generosity to ourselves
with generosity to all beings and sharing dedicating the goodness of
our practice trusting there is goodness generated trusting
there is goodness of course there is i dedicate i share the goodness of my
practice with all beings everywhere just like me
may all beings be happy may all beings
be free
[Music]
thank you all for your practice just like me
just like them powerful phrases powerful phrases
so we have some time if you like to to offer
any reflections any insights any aha moments any challenges questions
for the benefit of others and yourself too not a way to be impressed but just as a
way oh this is what came up for me be of support to me and others so you
can type in chat if you like your reflections if they're typed to me
alone i will uh not read your name if they're typed to
everyone i consider them public i will read your name and you can also raise your zoom hand if
you haven't shared in the community in a while um
if you have pull back let others pull forward [Music]
i would love to hear from you so please what did you discover
anything that was powerful or challenging
one private note i find it difficult to accept calming huh
yeah one way to work with that is to relax your body don't try to accept it in your
mind except calming uh just relax the animal of your body let
your body accept it kim i see your hand please
hi um i
if it's okay i want to share a birthday card that my granddaughter sent
to me and she was the person i chose i'll show it to you in order too
oh i see pink hearts lots of hearts and flowers sweet
he's six years old he wrote to grandma i love you more
than anything or anyone on this planet i love you so
much that whenever i see you my heart bursts for joy
and love for you from el
oh it's it's almost too much to take in i don't
feel worthy oh take it in take it in thank you oh it's so
beautiful that this child is beautiful child is clearly she's feeling so loved
so seen by you that whenever she sees you her
heart bursts with joy oh my it just makes my heart burst with joy that
there's a child in this world that just seeing this favorite person she's like
oh my god grandma i love you that is so sweet she spells burst b-e-r-s-t-e-s
oh my gosh that is so precious thanks for sharing that q oh my god
thanks for giving me the opportunity oh it's just yeah thank you it's
it it brought me so much joy feeling her joy and your joy and please
take it all in let yourself take it all in hey it's soothing it's healing
to be seen in this way by by children thank you kim that just brought me
someone with deeper so much joy for you and your granddaughter thank you it's so sweet
yeah so let's see um serena says i was able to see putin as a human being who
also suffers and cares about his family this is a big step for me i have been hating him thank
you syrian yeah that is powerful thank you for bringing that in to um separate
the actions which are not condonable and from the human humanity of the human
being there is so much delusion so much confusion so much hurt that
turning around and hurting others so thanks for bringing that in serena and yay what an opening for you mudita for
kim says peggy beautiful yes same here lovely mark says the five remembrances tell us
that it is inevitable that we will all get old sick die and lose all we love
how does it fit that we wish everyone health and happiness knowing they and we will get sick and lose all
we love oh yeah of course yeah yeah mark of course yeah it's not a problem um
it's that of course we know that that's what happens and yet we wish it it's without attachment to
outcome that is what's important because if you're attached to outcome if you want it to happen
then of course like it's not going to happen so why am i wishing it but you offer it as a generosity as a gift to
train your own heart and generosity it's a training for your own heart it's not
an outcome in in the world that you're attached to so that is the way and these two practices
actually are perfectly compatible with one another so i
invite you mark to sit with that um with sick sit with with that you
you're cultivating like knowing that there is no safety i wish you safety may you be safe as as a wish from my heart
so anyway i've said enough i'll let you sit with this there is a lot more here but i trust you will sit with us and you
will find your way um i've seen peggy's hand and then
vicky's peggy hugh and then i'll read vicki and they will be going into
small groups this time is short please peggy i've been having difficulty with the
woman who um just annoying the academy but um this this helped me see we both
probably have just the same wants and needs and we're just two different type
personalities on opposite ends of the extreme so it just helped me see her as more human and a little more like me so
it was helpful thanks how beautiful thank you peggy yeah i love hearing that
yeah thank you is this especially important for when we're working with people we have challenges with lovely
yeah and um vicky says i have difficulty thinking
people with less security as undocumented immigrants and unhoused people are just like me
how do we think our privilege is just like others yeah so so the idea of this practice here and
the just like me is not that everyone in every way is just like me i mean that's taking it too far
definitely taking it too far and that's not the suggestion at all the suggestion is that you see
their needs everybody else's needs for for safety for their wish to be happy to
be free from suffering as just like to see people's humanity not their background not there as i was saying so
any practice we can just take it too far and make it ridiculous so
just like me does not mean that we're that in those ways or just like me so
there's a way that we can get stuck or get ourselves stuck with every practice so i invite you not to do that pull back
um and stay with the humanity maybe this is
the way in for you vicky think that if you were born that you could have been just as well born
as they are it's so random they could have been born as you are it's so random
we have no control over it and that's another way to enter into just like me morgan i see
your note but it's coming i'll read this after we come out because
i want to make sure we have time for the small groups so so let's go into
small groups breakout rooms and here's the opportunity to practice
with other beings with other human beings who are just like me
in the way of they too suffer they too want to be free from suffering
they too have hopes and dreams not that we all have the same background and experience but
in the in the basic ways of experience so inviting us to practice together in
small groups and [Music] just a reminder speak from your own
experience please not handling or or working you know not
managing other people's experience and please share one nugget about what this
practice was like for you you can also say pass but please always have
kindness with each other with yourself and with each other so each person will say one nugget you say one nugget the
other person says a nugget the other person says a nugget and you go round and round
so that everyone has time to speak again be kind take care of each
other i'm going to create the rooms and um [Music]
yeah be kind to each other be kind to each other so here we go opening the rooms
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
so ah we are out of time but i will open the chat if you wanted to share anything
actually one thing that kathy shared i'll just read it out loud as an ending
comment here i have worked with many different people over the years in various contexts i've learned that
people are more similar than they are different it's amazing to think about the similar
questions conversations worries that i've heard from people thank you for that yeah
i hope your practice tonight was fruitful um thank you for joining
cultivating your heart for your own sake in the sake of all other beings just
like me just like others we all suffer
are born and die may we all have ease
may all beings be free
[Music] thank you all
so