um so last week I had a co-teacher with me on the monitor Kirsten she'll be back
next week and I think we'll redo the she'll stay for the first half and then
when we do breakout groups and stuff she'll sign off because she couldn't hear but um
last week we talked about wise understanding and wise intention
and how those two things those two factors help us with our practice so
just just to give you a little heads up about what the com you know topic was and in the handouts it has it kind of
says more than even I talked about so for those of you who weren't here
this is week two and so tonight the topics are concentration mindfulness
and the five hindrances so this is a lot and I will not be
talking in detail about these things I'm sort of going to try and just introduce these Concepts to you
I'll be doing more classes throughout the year and we'll go into more depth
like to many of the things that I'm introducing you to in this series
this series is sort of this jam-packed Jubilee of all the most important
components of a practice in my view so it's a nice kind of introduction but
don't feel like you're learning everything or that you need to learn everything right
um next week we'll be talking about actions that support joy in our practice and the
week after is about sustaining practice with wise effort so that's just the map
of what we'll cover um and
before we'll do it just a short sit just literally a very short little settling sit but before we do that I would like
to respond to you all and your your interests so it would be helpful for me
to know you know of these three topics for tonight mindfulness on and off the
cushion concentration and the five hindrances
I'd love to know if you could choose you know your your top two
um maybe that would be or you know I'd like to know your rank order preference in detail but of course
I can't get that so um who here is like most interested in
mindfulness on and off the cushion okay who who here is most interested in
concentration okay and who here is most interested in
the five hindrances okay well we'll just have to do a tour of all of them and
just know that we're we'll touch lightly on them and and then another question for our all of
you is I'm what's more important to you
a small group discussion where you get to talk to your fellow Sangha members
the question tonight will be about these three things and where you would like to
focus what you might like to try based on what you would you'd heard and the chance to hear other people so that
would be the small group Breakout and the guided meditation would be a
practice that's designed specifically for working with hindrances so
um who is more interested in the breakout group time who's more interested in the guided
meditation okay
got breakout group yeah breakout group more interested great
okay guided meditation on hindrances a little bit more okay so I'll try and
I'll just we'll still do breakout groups I'll just try and um maybe make them a little bit shorter
so we have a little bit more time with a guided meditation great okay let's settle let's find our bodies
we're just like a three minute little practice here
just finding some deeper breaths maybe helping the Mind Orient to
being in the body in this present moment
in this room with these people
you know right here work is done hopefully at least it is
now just helping yourself take that in
that you you chose to be here and you get to just be here
with your whole body so with that in mind
breathing a few deeper breaths inviting yourself
to give yourself permission to just be for two more minutes just to
be here until everything's subtle and catch up and kind of be in the same
place the same time
foreign
[Music]
and just take a moment to notice what changed what's different from just that
three minutes of sitting just to acknowledge for yourself if anything's settled maybe something
became more pronounced just acknowledging
the impact of the practice for yourself
okay so
and somebody willing to be a microphone delivery person me too great
so you go ahead and get that microphone if you don't mind and I want to start
um actually by talking about the five hindrances and
um the first the way I want to cultivate see how much you guys are aware of these
things already is what what happens that gets in the way of your practice what do
you notice that impacts your ability to practice mindfulness and to sit on a cushion
you know you might think about that because there's all of life but if we're
maybe start by thinking about when I sit try and sit down and meditate
what happens that makes it hard all right anybody have an answer
meats are great agitation agitation can you describe that at all
a lot of spinning a lot of spinning in the mind okay anybody else anything besides
agitation great Caroline
to say it's simple like emotions kind of agitation but not just just a
strong emotions okay great what else
great Ben what's next you start thinking what's
next you start planning kind of yeah okay great
what else makes it hard to sit down and meditate so we've heard agitation in the
minds we've heard strong emotions we've heard a mind that's thinking what next
what do I need to do next great
um I think distraction boredom boredom okay boredom and like seeking
distraction that happens okay and like bodily discomfort great
you wanna
there's so much to do so that I can be enough
okay so much to do so you is it like your mind gets involved in planning or
thinking um yeah there's this constant sense that um I need to be doing all these things
okay okay great anybody else anything else yes back here
um I feel like there's a bit of resistance resistance yeah okay great Tracy anything for you that you notice
so I start noticing tightnesses in my neck and my shoulders
and my body starts talking to me when I choose to listen
um anybody fall asleep get sleepy oh yeah
yeah okay all right so I'll list I'll name the five hindrances for you and you listen
for you know try and pick one of them or two of them that feel like they fit with
what you described okay and we'll see if it works but so they're typically listed as
desire like wanting right um
lust you know the whole the whole stream of wanting
um craving kind of thing aversion not liking not wanting
I don't like this get this away from me make this stop
um restlessness and worry so um that's there's two components left
bodily agitation can't settle and the mental right and um
sloth and torpor which is in the body tiredness you know
can't stay awake can't stay attentive in the mind drifty hazy
sleepy and the fifth is doubt
am I doing it right should I do this is should I do a different practice should I be doing it like this should I be
doing it like that or or why am I even doing this what's the
point kind of you know it could be a big doubt about the practice could be a doubt about my capacity
I'm I can't do this my mind won't let me do this I have ADHD there's no way I can do this you know like or you know I'm
just a no good whatever so but all of those are connected that I just to doubt
so do you the things that come up for you fit within those categories
yeah the mind that gets busy planning Ben is probably a Restless mind right
and maybe there's two things the desire the greed the wanting right that also
can fuel I need to do this I need to do that right
um so it can be that you have more than one hindrance happening at one time
so you're all normal you have normal Minds normal problems
you the same problems have been experienced by meditators since the Buddha taught and probably long before
so these are energies that happen in the
mind and they are really helpful things to learn how to work with and to recognize
right to start to say okay oh this is the hindrance of restlessness and worry
oh you know sort of like you you know if you're doing cognitive behavioral therapy this is my cognitive distortion
of the day right um it's also helpful because if we know we
have tendencies we can try and do things to balance for
example if we know we tend to be restless and worried and and unable to
sit we might think about walking or doing yoga before we meditate
we might think about a transition between being busy busy busy and when I
when we sit we might also think about the time of day we're sitting so some people it's
much easier to sit in the morning before they've fully launched in their day
so it's good to start to know a little bit about when the what hindrances show
up for you more than others and just to start recognizing them and as I mentioned I'll do a guided meditation
later but um it's nice to just sort of start
letting these things kind of um you know be curious about them and how
they they show up for you so greed desire lust aversion hatred not liking those
are two different ones right Polar Opposites one thing to look at in your body is if
there's leaning forward or leaning back it's a very visceral thing that starts
to happen with aversion and desire so for example
I'll just na I'll just say a few words just just close your eyes and tune in
and notice your body ice cream
dogs
driving fast
going to a party with lots and lots of people
being alone
milk water
The Color Purple
the color orange
a rainy day
a warm sunny day
a really hot day
okay what did you notice in your body
could you feel a sense of shifting when you heard something you
like how did you feel that in your bodies what did you notice where's the mic again
anybody willing to say a word or two great
well when you said ice cream I was I immediately leaned into it but then you
said so I there were a couple of like an extremely hot day like the heat wave from last week and I was just like oh no
so yeah definitely it's just instant so yeah it's like just your body knows
right your body knows so we can also recognize if we're liking or not liking
by tuning into our body sometimes our body can tell us before we can know mentally
thank you anybody you want to say anything different they notice it in a different
way it can manifest differently I can sense a hot day or a big party my body tenses
up tenses up and the rain and being by myself I felt like relaxes so great in
my body I felt it's great Corey
uh I felt changes in temperature like slight warmth or slight cold which was
interesting that's great great because yes right you we all know right we can
get hot or how you know when we think about certain things this is great anything else anyone wants to share
Ben actually I felt all of them were nice ah
you liked it all I liked it all I mean in this right context okay that's great
who else liked them all anybody else no
well Ben you're a Liker that's nice yeah
all right so maybe turn the mic off for a second thank you Mitra so much for your help
um okay so that's like our brief tour of the five entrances right and um like I
said we'll come back to that um later when we do the guided meditation
um so now let's let's talk about um let's talk about mindfulness
um I think I'll just start by uh sharing a
couple of quotes So first of all there really isn't anything you can do and there isn't anywhere you
can go that mindfulness won't support you it's it's it's applicable everywhere
and when the Buddha teaches mindfulness he talks about being mindful walking forward walking backwards you know
standing up sitting down laying down every posture you can imagine eating
going to the bathroom mindfulness everywhere all the time
so it's something that we can practice all the time
here's a quote by Anne Cushman if I view everyday chores as tasks to
rush through on the way to something more important they become a crushing waste of time
so I'll reread that again if I view everyday chores as tasks to rush through
on the way to something more important they become a crushing waste of time
but from the perspective of Buddhist teaching each of these activities is a
golden moment an opportunity for full Awakening there are Awakening poems of monks and
nuns who woke up doing one patachara was pouring water
it was just something like that somebody else that was turning a light on and off
so Awakening doesn't have to happen you know with your eyes closed sitting still
it can happen in the midst of your everything
another um quote I'll share is by Sayo dawu chataka
when the mind is not mindful it feels like a homeless person very insecure very unhappy
when you are mindful you feel really at home so mindfulness is my home
when you are mindful you are at home when you are not mindful you are on the road to nowhere
get in touch with the spiritual Part of Yourself the beautiful part of yourself be mindful he says
so when the mind is not mindful it feels like a homeless person very insecure
very unhappy when you're mindful you feel really at home so mindfulness is my home
I like that this one got a chuckle too when you're not mindful you're on the road to going nowhere right
so there's that automatic pilot that happens in our brains when we aren't mindful where we just start to eat and
do go we're driving we're not really paying attention we're putting things down we're forgetting them we're leaving
our keys our credit cards were you know yeah doing things that we're not
mindful of right we just sort of get busy doing consuming often too
clicking and the internet getting lost in that so
so mindfulness is uh it's actually kind of a I like one of the ways Gil talks about it is a
collection it's like a number of different qualities that we're cultivating
and and it's like together when they're all mutually working they provide you
know um what I like to think of as the raft the raft that helps us stay afloat and
not lost right so uh one of the classic definitions is mindfulness is paying
attention on purpose
in the present moment so we can't be mindful in the past or in
the future we can only be pres mindful Here and Now
and it's um we can be mindful that we're thinking but it's pretty hard to stay
mindful of thinking without getting lost in thought but it is possible
to be aware that we're thinking as we're thinking so that's the thing as we're
doing it mindful of breathing as we're breathing aware on purpose intentionally that okay
I'm breathing in and I know I'm breathing out and I'm feeling it
it's a it's a an experience it's not conceptual
so mindfulness is this awareness and connection to what's happening in the present moment
the other part of it is with you know um our attitude matters
so we want to cultivate a an attitude that is
often the word is kind that can be also allowing or open
so if we're doing this pay attention pay attention
pay attention is that kindness is that you know is
that has its that would be a hindrance that we're adding to the mindfulness
right an aversion you know critic critical mind
so that that is another piece that we need to start to learn to tune into is okay I know I'm aware but how am I being
aware what's my relationship to what's going on
you we're good okay so
practicing mindfulness helps us grow wisdom
we actually get grow the kind of wisdom the Buddha talks about it's a wisdom of
learning to discern and see what's happening with clarity
so it's not a a book wisdom it's an applied wisdom
it's the wisdom that starts to learn we learn and it grows inside of us and it's
there to help us and it's akin to the wisdom in our body
that knows a hot stove is hot take my hand away
it's that kind of wisdom that helps guide us through life
um it helps us meet our experiences without reactivity
we can choose to respond versus react so it helps us kind of slow things down
take pauses gives a little bit of space between ourselves and what's coming up and what
we're meeting and this ability to meet our experience
without being reactive to it actually allows mindfulness to go deeper
and deeper deeper and deeper into seeing more and more deeply the true nature of what's
Happening
this is where I think I'll just sort of bridge and then we can Circle back to concentration
so cult building our mindfulness moment to moment mindfulness will help us with
concentration practice it will help us
develop a mind that is more calm more centered more intimate with our experience
concentration that word I think is a difficult word
for many of us because when you think about concentrating I have to concentrate
there's a contraction that we often think about like I have to I have to work really hard yeah
but if we engage with mindfulness or meditation in that kind of way what
happens anybody have an experience
if you try really hard Ben oh
that's describing concentration I'll ask you to say it again for the the yeah I mean once uh up here up here sorry once
you're present yeah and you calm
and you see something in its totality it's just like just like breathing is a
flow yeah so as we establish mindfulness
right then the concentration begins to come and that is I I how one of the ways
I like to describe concentration is relaxed it is connected it is with
this feeling of flow and um there's different kinds of concentration
there's concentration that is a moment by moment kind of practice
and then there's a concentration that has to do with what they often will say is absorption
absorption like um
everything with concentration there's a quality of wholeness so we're not trying
to get rid of anything it's like instead it's like say we're we're focused on the breath
it's it's more like oh the breath just gets closer and closer it just like and
it gets it's almost like in the mind it it it starts to fill up the mind because
the the mind is so interested in the breath that it's like you know what we pay
attention to gets bigger right does that make sense we we pay attention to it's like a magnifying
glass for our experience but with this it's very relaxed way of
concentration that it's just this natural way that the
mind just becomes deeply intimate and connected with the experience of breathing for example
so you might your mind just gets maybe filled with the experience of breathing and as you're feeling it in your body
so there's not a lot of excessive thinking and other things going on in this kind of
in this kind of concentration practice yeah Mitra go ahead just use the mic
please so are we mostly talking about concentration on the cushion not I mean
our mindfulness on the question yeah that would be what this last part would be more on the
cushion yes it can happen you can have momentary concentration
like that sometimes when you're on a retreat and it can happen when you're
out doing things but it's it's uh you're going to have really been slowed down already
but you can also have another kind of like of just a very Crystal Clear Connection awareness with the
concentration that's like tracking very carefully you can see things as they're
coming up they can see what the activity in the mind you know you can see the impulse to do something before you do it
you know it's like you can kind of see things that you normally wouldn't be noticing
and that would be more like you could do that in the garden you could watch that
you know in their kitchen doing the dishes you could see that
any other questions about
concentration or mindfulness
can you speak into the microphone because there's people that can't can't hear you
I think if you try to force yourself to concentrate then it becomes more tiring yes
and you get tired faster absolutely so for if we put too much effort that was
sort of where I was asking a long time ago what happens if you try too hard like the the
concentration that we think of when we're trying if we bring that into meditation we do we get exhausted in the
way that I think about it is I get kind of brittle you know I just it's like
it's just too rigid it's too tense and um
you know the body gets uncomfortable and the mind starts to fall apart
yeah go ahead I guess on the topic of being tired of
being wary I feel like I've noticed that as I'm more mindful it actually tires me
out not because I'm trying but it feels like seeing the patterns of repetition can
kind of wear me out yeah so that can be the you know but the thing to notice is it is being aware of
it what makes you tired or is it your reaction to what you're seeing that makes you tired
does that make sense so if I have a version to what I'm noticing
it makes it more exhausting to notice if I am judging myself because I think I
shouldn't be doing what I'm doing it's going to make it harder
so part of it is to be curious um and notice how am I feeling about what
I'm observing and see if there's any hindrance in there
and then if it's if there's no hindrances you just feel like your mind's getting tired maybe you could
just sometimes once we start to establish mindfulness and we've got a good flow we actually don't have to work
as even as hard as we were we might need to just sort of okay what
if I try 10 less 20 percent less sometimes we need to do 20 more 30
percent more right but adjusting the effort that we're applying might be
indicated is that anything else about what you said I feel like maybe an addition part
of it is as you kind of are mindful of emotions and it kind of open up to it more
maybe there's also like a bit of fatigue from kind of just letting it flow more
yeah absolutely yeah absolutely yeah great point
um so maybe I'll shift to just talking about a few things that are kind of helpful for growing mindfulness because
mindfulness will support you know the concentration too right so one is being mindful of our body
our bodies right are always everything we experience
through the body is something that's happening right here so using our senses and staying
connected to what's happening in our body is a great Gateway back to the present moment and and so
building our awareness of our body as we move around having a practice of every time you get
up and walk somewhere to noticing your feet or maybe your chest
and your breathing and you start to build a pattern of standing a walking of sitting with
mindfulness it that that helps you it helps you it
just helps you stay with the more continuity of the mindfulness
and um if you ever are struggling to try and get
out of a lot of heavy thinking it is you know look through use your senses
site sound touch smell taste
these are like great doorways into the present moment and so orienting toward
touching what it feels like coolness you know warmth
um you know if you're doing the dishes starting to notice the smell of the dish
soap you know the fill of the warm water helping yourself come more fully into the present moment through the senses
so another thing is to start to notice Choice by being mindful you start to
grow your capacity to make choices so it can be kind of fun to start to
sort of say okay if I'm mindful here what might my choices be
just kind of drop in the question if I could choose this fine but if I was
wasn't going to choose this what would I choose what else could I choose
putting my right shoe and first or my left shoe on first you know just simple
things or standing up sitting down going for a walk not going for a walk just just opening the mind up a little bit
and and emphasizing how mindfulness support choice
um another helpful way to start to build this non-reactivity is to look for our
opportunities in your life where you have some mild discomfort
any kind but mild so it could be that you know just
sitting in your postures right now you know if you start to feel a little bit
uncomfortable just hang out with it just just a moment longer than you normally
would before you move or you know do something
just just practice lingering a little longer with discomfort an itch
you know adjusting
and notice what happens if you can bring like that mindful attitude of allowing
or accepting instead of the aversion of not liking not wanting
right just being a little bit curious now I'm not asking you to hurt yourselves okay at all
this is just like playing with your edges growing your edges being with
something that's a little bit unpleasant a little bit longer and learning about
about that for yourself we grow a very quick habitual response
to unpleasant experiences just and you know we've just through our
lives we just have grown to like do things to make ourselves feel better
all the time but some of it is unneeded unnecessary and it's fueling a
kind of a habitual pattern of just moving away right
another way to grow mindfulness in your daily life is to choose an activity that you do every day
like I'm brushing your teeth making your bed making your coffee and make it a habit to do that activity
very mindfully really going you know taking it in with all of your senses
and and then you can grow your your habits you know you start with one work
on it for a while when you feel like it's pretty natural then maybe you look for a second one that you add
and you just kind of keep growing and building it's also nice to practice mindfulness
in nature you know the sounds outside can be very
helpful for staying present and it can be interesting to um Kirsten
was here she would talk about this because she's a big nature person and one of the things she said is she
really likes to notice her impact on in nature itself too so how are the
squirrels responding to your presence what are the ants doing in response to
you like really kind of tuning in to how you're coming into an environment and
impacting the creatures and the life and that environment so that's another way to tune in to the
present moment um another thing that can be fun to
support kind of building our practice is having a meditation buddy
and it might just be that you have somebody who you text and you say hey I'm sitting now want to join me
or maybe you just say sitting now and they just know or maybe you have somebody who likes to sit with you
so there's just a whole variety of ways to to share and support each other's practice
yeah okay so let's
um let's let's have a little small Breakout
discussion maybe um you know three or four people together so you can just kind of cluster
yourselves and um I just want you to talk about
um well why don't you go ahead and move first and I'll give you your instructions
do you want to join a group Sage okay great
so yeah maybe just say your names um
see okay
and then the the thing to talk about is you know we just covered a lot of
grounds concentration practice mindfulness growing mindfulness and daily life and
the five hindrances so just take a minute to check in and and just say the question for you right
now just to notice for yourself is what which one of these what did I hear that I feel like I
really would like to work on I'd like to take a suggestion or I'd like to learn more about this
um where do you feel and some inspiration some energy
and you know what are you most inspired to do
and then with that what would be the easiest thing to do
to support you in that direction so if you could just um
take like one or two minutes each I'll probably give you about five minutes
so it's maybe keeping it about one minute one and a half minutes to share what your answer is and Rose
yes sure desire
aversion restlessness and worry sloth and torpor so those are two
couples right and doubt yeah and I'll happy to say it again yeah
all right so go ahead and um maybe the person with the shortest hair could start and then you can just go clockwise
from there
blurry area
something that was appealing to me was the idea
basically like physical activities [Music]
foreign so it's been about a minute so a little
over a minute
building images
[Music]
is
right now
just a minute timer just yeah you can go over not just giving you a little bit of
a um
foreign
hmm
[Music]
you can keep talking among yourself you know
you know
but they feel like really
so just taking your time to finish up your sentences go ahead
it's like
maybe think thank your buddies
all right thank you guys it's fun to watch you I
can't really hear you but it's fun to watch you so um
I think what we'll do is go right into the guided meditation and then we'll have a chance to debrief both the group
and the um the guided meditation before we end
okay so I'm going to share a practice
it's an acronym like usual we have acronyms for things to help us remember this acronym is Bella
as in beautiful
so the first thing that we want to do is
in your meditation just in your practice right now being mindful eyes open or
closed whatever works
we'll practice with a hindrance so just noticing if there's a hindrance
present already it's a greed or desire
aversion hatred restlessness in the body worry and the
mind sloth I think it's sloth like in a sloth
Sloth animal very body slothful and torpor and the mind is just
no energy doubt
so just being with and if it's not present now maybe thinking about one
that comes up for you that's not going to overwhelm you to pay attention to
so when a hindrance comes up the most useful thing we can do first is to let
it be to learn open up around it and notice how it manifests
doesn't mean giving in to it
doesn't mean letting it dictate what you do but it means not acting or reacting to
it there's training and being present for
this experience without being in conflict with it giving the hindrance some room some
space
the E and Bella is examine
so Freedom requires us to have wisdom
being able to work with the hindrance requires us to understand the hindrance
so getting to know it examining it to understand it
to recognize the way it manifests its components
the physical component of the hindrance how it feels in the body
the energetic component
the emotional
and the cognitive the way it affects how we perceive how we think what we
think
it also has a motivational aspects to it motivating us to do something
getting to know physically
energetically emotionally
cognitively motivational
when you're ready when you feel like you've gotten to know it as much as you can in the moment
the next part of Bella is the L to lessen
to lessen the impact of the hindrance and really that is happens by relaxing
relaxing the mind and the body sort of starts to soften the intensity
of it
maybe directing your awareness toward the breathing if that is a soothing relaxing
experience for you
if not that is there some part of your body that feels really neutral
and can you just pay careful attention to that neutral part of your body
[Applause]
the second L is still let go
you know when when it's not serving us when we can't really benefit from being with it anymore
it can be time to say okay enough for now
and how do we let go maybe we need to recognize that there is
a belief that's unhelpful that's fueling it so can we shift our belief our view
maybe we have a strong sense of I am this
and maybe we need to practice with non-identification it's just a feeling
it's just a thought it's not who I am
maybe it's already softened so much with the relaxing that
that's all we need to do it's already letting go it's happening
maybe we recognize that there's a habit we have in our daily life that fuels
this hindrance way that we're unconscious and doing
something over and over again that fuels this Con this this hindrance and we
see that so we feel you know maybe I can try to do this instead of that
and if it's really strong you might need to get up and go for walking meditation
or do loving kindness
the A and Bella the last part of the practice
is appreciate so just in the course of this short practice
was there wisdom that grew in sight that came a lessening a change in your
relationship with the hindrance was there anything in here that you can appreciate small
is fine
appreciating whatever is skillful and supportive
is very helpful might even just be I really appreciate
that I'm trying really appreciate that I sat here with
this as best I could and that is enough to appreciate
I'm gonna allow five minutes of silence for practice in whatever way feels supportive to you
you can continue with the Bella practice or you might choose an anchor
for your awareness like breathing or sound sensation
and just see if you can rest a little bit with being
not having to do
being with
I'll offer one other thing which is if you are finding it difficult to settle
the mind because we've just been looking at a hindrance a concentration practice
could be to count your breaths
so as you breathe in knowing you're breathing in you one
and then you exhale breathing into
and exhale up to up to 10. and then at ten you let go and you start
at one again and if you get lost just start at one again
very easy no problem so that's a concentration practice a
practice that can help settle the mind if you want to use that now please feel
free
foreign
and again just checking in noticing the Mind noticing the body
just noticing if there's any desire
any aversion
any sloth or torp her any restlessness or worry
or any doubt
and maybe just bow to yourself for seeing
seeing into your experience in this way
foreign [Music]
make sure you're ready for the microphone Duty and um Sage I don't know
if you can see I don't know you know if there's any YouTube questions or chat questions so okay
okay great all right so
what was that like for you that guided practice Corey right behind you Mitra
right right turn turn there you go
um well I noticed that during the examination portion
[Music] um I I was working with uh restlessness
and I noticed uh uh you know faster heartbeat or some
tension things in my mind were um you know I was I was thinking
bouncing around and during that examination I uh noticed
also something else there that there was energy there was playfulness there was nice excitement and
um so I took that as sort of like
it put a different perspective on on it that not to be pushing it away or one it was more like
being with it and then that allowed it to kind of dissolve a little bit beautiful beautiful Corey
thank you
I too I too was um during the examination portion I realized the thing
that I usually struggle with is restlessness and then I get and I'm very fussy and then I realized oh I think
it's because I'm very anxious like always anxious like as a person that's
who I am and I'm like Oh my uh all the questions like am I doing this right is this okay wait now I know I'm thinking
and so and then all those things started popping in but then I'm like but I'm like okay
um this is I tried to follow the Bella acronym but that last part
the a appreciation I'm like well I appreciate the fact that I'm Restless because it brought me to meditate
because I want nice so though it's like came full circle so yes
thank you
oh all um oh good Tracy go ahead yeah please
I could not stop thinking about a recipe that I read earlier
I think I must be very hungry um I just kept seeing it in my head over
and over again and so I said okay there you are
let's bake this recipe so I imagined myself actually making its
turkey sweet potato chili it sounds wonderful but I you know I I couldn't
make it behave itself this uh-huh recipe that
kept wanting to play in my head so I said okay well let's just make this recipe and I you know watched myself
making it and that's almost a meditation in itself is
you know preparing the food I could almost smell it cooking
I so rather than trying to push it away I
I decided just to go with it and uh worked out pretty well for me I think
but now I want to go home and make the chili for sure
yeah so there's something um really important about one thing you
described as it sounds like there was a lot of like trying to make it go away in the beginning that created a lot of
tension and more stress yeah and so this kind of giving in to it
or giving it some space now a very delicate thing to do right because
we need to stay mindful of of thinking is happening and be aware that we're imagining and
all of that but it sounds like it was helpful for the tension to recede but
also the desire is growing so just noticing that too right so that there's
there's in a way maybe it helped not grow aversion but maybe it also did
spark a little more desire yeah does that feel right okay great
anybody else have any Reflections or observations to share this is so
wonderful to hear from you all
does the Bella practice Phil it sounds like you you know found it useful it's actually not in your handout so
um do you want me to send it to you in writing the Bella practice yeah
I can do that okay
yeah usually mostly I just teach it when I'm teaching the five hindrances
yeah yes be Let It Be oh yeah
b-e-l-l-a so B examine
lesson let go and appreciate
yes Mitra um I was pretty calm and I was able to
follow that better for something imaginary yep but and then when you did
the concentration the counting the breath I started doing that and all of a sudden
something happens in my brain that it just starts a thought and it I can't stop it so I
get to that point and I completely um disabled I I don't know what to do
and I think I almost always get there that's called anxiety I don't know what
that's called okay and I just don't know I mean there's nothing that I can do to
did you that would be a great time to kind of um we'll see if Bella works so
you kind of just stop and be with what's happening so you know you're trying to count and
you're counting and then all of a sudden your mind starts thinking right and it's
you can't let go of the thought right so
um it sounds like you're not sure you know maybe just paying attention to your
body if you think about the thinking and how it felt was your body leaning forward leaning
back you know so I just get very frustrated and very
um aggressive towards the thinking so that's a version a version aversive
towards the thinking itself that's right so then you would practice with noticing
the aversion so instead of thanks staying focused on the thinking you go oh look at the
aversion oh there's not liking the thinking there's a lot of anger frustration about
and so what does that feel like so then you so you be with that aversion
first so feeling that just oh this is a version it feels pretty awful I don't
know how long can I stay with that yeah so you be with it as long as it feels right examine it just sort of so again
you're like noticing this is aversion not not getting caught and being mad at your
thoughts for thinking but paying attention to that energetic
quality of the the hindrance so you know
you it went in with a version and some other feelings it's hard to stay with them very long right so one thing is
our awareness can get kind of tight and it can be helpful to kind of invite it
to open up a little bit how um literally
you might take your hands and if this is your head thinking right now just go
ahead and feel the exaggeration of it let your hands hold here yeah and then
literally imagine sitting back relaxing and opening up just right and you feel
it if I see it in you right there nice so literally just helping yourself physically in this way what we do with
our body our mind can follow sometimes
um so then the um letting go you know like the lessening
and you've already lessened when you've done this so I just oh look it's listening okay and the letting go is
like okay well maybe I need to let go of wanting to count or wanting my mind not
to think you know that's feeding the aversion so let me let go of that practice let me
let go of trying to make myself stop thinking and
um thank you and then we even if you know everything
isn't the way we want it to be can we appreciate can we appreciate oh it shifted a bit oh
I got to see I got to see the hindrance and I got to practice with it in a
little different way and can I appreciate that does that make sense
okay
I'll read you a little quote and then we'll see if there's any more Reflections to share
um what we're doing here tonight is growing
our wisdom yeah you feel a little wiser yeah
and so we when we grow that wisdom and we practice and we really turn toward our
experience in this way we grow our faith
we're told the teaching we practice with the teaching we see how it works we need
to notice our own process so we can trust the teaching we have a
little more faith in the teaching because oh yeah I see this right
we might grow faith in the teaching the Dharma the Buddha the teacher or the
Sangha like what we're doing with each other here is supporting each other right doing this by yourself at home not
so easy but hearing other people share is hugely
supportive so these are the the gems that the Buddha really emphasized this Dharma the
teacher and the Sangha the Buddha the Dharma the Sangha and so we can grow our faith so noticing
I have a little more confidence I have a little more faith this might really help
there's something here this is a precious thing to take care of
it helps us when we have doubt or the other hindrances come up having a moment like you described Corey
you and Rose you know Mitra even just in that moment
you know Tracy all of you everybody who shared you have this moment you can be like okay
oh yeah things can shift I know how to shift oh they did it I can probably do it the
Buddha did it okay right this is very important
in part a very important treasure for us to grow in ourselves
it will support us in our efforts to keep sitting back down on the cushion
keep coming back to the Sangha to keep listening to the Dharma
so I want I want to invite you to notice and and share if you're willing to share
a moment where you felt like you gained some Faith or confidence tonight
if you're willing to share as part of honoring that and and sharing it with others that would be really beautiful so
is anybody willing to talk and about that name something
um so my aversion was desired
and um
examining that I tried to imagine
what what would it be like if I have these things this thing that I think I
want and realizing that if I had that thing I
would still be sitting right here and meditating and so
it really didn't matter if I have or have not
um so um it sounds like that that was a pretty significant reflection yeah yeah
it's very very helpful wow that's great that's great so something
to remember right beautiful thank you Caroline anybody else grow a little bit of Faith
or confidence tonight that you're willing to share
so I was actually I had a new resistance today which I normally don't have which
is aversion which because I uh when we started the whole Bella practice what I
kind of found myself thinking about some just like some uncomfortable experiences
and what I wanted was not to think about it but as I explored more of it like actually I
realized more truths about you know what that experience is and also kind of
I don't know if this will last or not but this I had like a new uh almost like
uh shift in my mind because I realized that the discomfort that comes from feeling a
sense of loss is I mean it's um the the shift essentially for me at
least in the end which was with the appreciate was that uh oh okay I actually found myself
appreciating the fact that I even had an experience that is worth losing like
even that is a grateful um I mean even that's something to be grateful for so I think I don't know if
I'll like be able to keep that maybe that's something that you know is worth practicing as well but that's not how I
think on a daily basis like normally I'm just like obsessed with my loss rather
than um and with the the appreciating you had the experience
yeah beautiful beautiful thank you wow
oh Sangha yay Sangha
I appreciate your wisdom and sharing your beautiful hearts
is there anyone else that wants to share before we we have one more one more or
we can just do a closing meditation
good meter can come sit down relax thank you Mitra
so just noticing how you're feeling now
a sense of appreciation or warmth connection
for showing up for others who did and were willing to share
it's a gift thank you
may this practice be of benefit for you
may you notice the benefit and appreciate the benefit
may you share that benefit directly and indirectly with others
May the benefit of our practice together benefit all beings
everywhere
[Music]
thank you
it's a wrap