hey it's nice to see everyone coming on
I appreciate the way you often write hello and where you're from
kind of give that feeling of us all being together and I'm always delighted with how
widespread this Sangha is so thank you for that
let's settle in for our meditation together
finding a posture where you can be upright and also relaxed
and allowing yourself to settle in feeling the
seat where you're sitting or whatever you're lying on
really feeling that contact and connection so that you can let go
and allow it to Simply support you closing the eyes if that's comfortable
for you bringing the attention inward
sensing the body in the posture that it's in kind of an overall way to help
Orient the mind
and so we could say give your attention to the posture
and notice how it is that you're giving that attention
when you turn to the posture at the beginning of the sit are you controlling
it from the top down making it relax and align in certain
ways or are you not quite giving your full attention because you're just coming
into the usual habitual posture that you always do
so I'm just drawing attention to this word give your attention to the posture
and wondering how how would it be if the attention is really a gift
that we're giving
so maybe offer your attention to the posture of this body
and does that change how the relationship feels
maybe in light of it being a gift the body feels empowered to orient
itself to straighten up appropriately to relax
into a form that feels supportive for meditation
it's nice to receive a gift so letting the body receive the gift of
your attention
and broadening broadening that attention [Music] giving or offering attention to the all
of the bodily Sensations as they are right now just letting them be as they are
and letting them be known as they are
now broadening the awareness to include the emotions
that are present
any thoughts that are in the mind
maybe various intentions or aspirations
just holding all of experience in a spacious awareness
that we are giving as a gift to our experience
and as we practice with this giving attention as a gift
we may notice how giving attention relates to letting go
we can't fully offer our awareness unless we let each thing be as it is
be known as it is and have its life of arising and persisting
and passing away
to be fully aware we have to let things be
let them go
so we're just letting experience flow and we'll sit in silence for a while
foreign
with great generosity letting go of our stories
letting go of our ideas
our complaints our judgments are wantings
just letting go of entanglement with all of those things that
grab at our attention
letting them calm be as they are and go without hooking on to them
and discovering how that generous way of being
actually settles the mind slowly brings the heart into alignment
foreign
practicing this way we may get a glimpse or a hint
of how we might be that way with others also
with the right balance and under the right conditions it can sometimes be the
best just to open
let there be other viewpoints let there be
other ways of being without leaping in and entangling
ourselves
and somehow that attitude can sometimes allow things to settle
in our relationships with others
that spaciousness
to us with the gift of our full unentangle attention
things can shift
letting go is a contribution to peace
foreign
[Music]
on with this list that pertains to meeting life well it's
a list of five items from the poly Canon that are described as inner wealth
fortitude inspiring things to reflect upon and signs of spiritual growth
and today we're on the fourth one the poly word is chaga that's spelled c
long a g a chaga and it has two
important and related dimensions so chaga is sometimes translated as
generosity and that's the first dimension it's the mental attitude or movement
behind the act of Donna giving we often hear Donna translated as generosity but
it more literally means the act of giving or the gift itself chaga is this wholesome motivation
behind giving so it's about wanting to share being happy about offering
I'll read the standard language that's used in the sutus
here a noble disciple dwells at home with a heart devoid of the stain of
miserliness freely generous open-handed delighting in relinquishment devoted to
charity delighting and giving and sharing so you can hear the description is
actually about the state of the person's heart um freely generous delighting and giving
devoted to charity these are heart words so we can ask well how is an attitude of
literal giving helpful as a Dharma resource I think if we can be willing to be
generous when under stress that is an amazing spiritual quality
usually in challenging situations the heart closes and easily succumbs to
feelings of holding on wanting to protect wanting to push away but if we've cultivated generosity
deeply enough we will be more attracted to the good feeling of giving than to
those reactive emotions that might come in the moment the Buddha encouraged us to investigate
the act of giving by noticing what is going on in our mind why we're giving how we're giving
and when we talked about virtue a couple of days ago I suggested simply watching
how we act and speak with mindfulness such that we can notice when we're
acting for one wholesome motivations rather than doing some kind of a top-down control of our Behavior to try
to be ethical so we can do the same thing with giving just watch how you give and notice what
motivations what emotions what mannerisms are present
and when we do that it will gradually purify our giving to come more often
from the wholesome side so just to offer some specifics that we
might notice sometimes we can actually give a gift out of fear you know perhaps we're
afraid of displeasing someone in power if we don't give we can also give out of Desire hatred
delusion even as an insult um we can also give of course due to more
complex relational and social reasons maybe we're giving to
um even the score with somebody who was given to us or were attempting to put
another person in Social debt to us or we may simply be following in the
tradition of our family or we might feel obligated to give because we have more
than someone else we might give in order to look good we can also give because it makes the
Mind tranquil and happy where we can give out of compassion or love these are very wholesome motivations
so actually everything I read There is are all mentioned in the Buddhist teachings they're all from the sutas so
people have been giving for these reasons for at least 2500 years and
they're they're not given I think to judge various motivations but rather to
suggest that it's good to know why we're giving the mind has many intentions as
we know and as we observe will naturally move toward the more wholesome ones which is what Roots this quality of
chaga deeply into the heart and helps make it into a Dharma resource
there's also a choice about when to give and it can be good to give immediately
when we feel the urge to do so especially if it would help to
counteract some negative mind state that we have remembering that one time I was talking
with a friend and I mentioned that I was intending to give some fruit to a
neighbor a neighbor with whom I had disagreed and this was a Dharma friend and she sat up straight and said would
you like to go do that right now and I was a little bit surprised but I agreed
and in a short time we had done it and I felt lighter you know there was a
letting go it was nice that I was intending that but you know why not actually just go do it right
and so then that leads to the the second dimension of chaga which is Letting Go
it's the the letting go that we do along the path distinct but related to the
actual act of giving a gift it's more subtle maybe this letting go that we do as part of our practice
so the Buddhist path is about letting go more and more deeply
there is cultivation there is cultivation on the path but even if we're actively cultivating a certain
quality we're generally going to have to release or dissolve the obstacles to
doing that so the idea eventually is to let go of the craving and clinging that
are at the heart of Duca so chaga is used in a powerful verse
from the dhamapata it goes like this if by giving up a lesser happiness one
could experience greater happiness a wise person would renounce the Lesser to
behold the greater seems it makes sense in the abstract we'll talk about it in a moment but
chaga in this verse is the word that's translated as both giving up and
renounce so if by giving up a lesser happiness one could experience greater
happiness a wise person would renounce the Lesser to behold the greater both of
those are the word chaga so we see that letting go is related to
happiness and particularly to finding a pathway toward greater forms of
happiness and sometimes this is relatively clear which is the greater happiness getting
some kind of enjoyable food or creating a harmonious relationship with your partner
some kind of material gain or being honest being truthful
so we can see that ethics and kindness and compassion are ordinary and quite
accessible examples of these greater forms of Happiness we don't need to be
thinking you know way high up but another you know another greater
happiness is the kind that comes from meditation so we gather the mind in meditation by
letting go of the five hindrances and other reactive line States and thoughts
that prevent us from settling down we give up the Lesser happiness of being
involved in our thoughts and emotions for the greater happiness of of meditative calm when when the conditions
allow us to do that um there's a quote from the sutus
and it says this is the Buddha talking should anyone say the five chords of
sensual pleasure are the utmost pleasure and joy that human beings experience I
would not concede that to them why is that because there is another kind of
pleasure loftier and more Sublime than that pleasure and what is that
and then I'm summarizing to say that it's the pleasure of meditative composure
so the Buddha was clear about that and then there are also various meditative
insights that emerge along the path and these are also typically realized when
the Mind releases its grip and is suddenly able to see differently in some way that can't easily be unseen you know
that's the one of the qualities of insight so as we as we practice with both literal
generosity and this act of letting go we can condition our heart to realize
that in many cases relinquishment is better than acquisition
right in general relinquishment is better than acquisition that's actually kind of a deep spiritual thing to start
realizing and then we still have to discover in each situation what it is
that we need to let go of there is some discernment about that it is possible to let go unwisely which
we wouldn't want to do but it's also very wise sometimes to let go
so we can meet life with this attitude of letting go maybe when we're
struggling or we could have the internal question what would I have to let go of to make
this easier and sometimes we're literally we need to literally give something like offering a
gift to someone that we find difficult or sometimes we need to release
Something That We're gripping internally like an emotion for example or some
Viewpoint or opinion foreign
Thanksgiving Day in the United States and in the mythology that surrounds it
it's a celebration of a good harvest that would be sufficient to carry the
early settlers in New England through the winter and apparently there was some
cooperation with the local Native Americans so there's this image of kind of a shared Feast together which is
about generosity and gratitude much of what we're talking about today and this
is the story that many people in the United States grew up with and so it's a holiday that centers around family and
food but for Native Americans of course there isn't such a Rosy view of the
interaction with colonists that came from Europe that didn't play out very well and it continues to be very painful
and some Native Americans even call today a day of War of mourning okay of
mourning but I've also heard that some Native Americans are now reclaiming
Thanksgiving day as an expression of values that are deeply inherent in
Native culture you know gratitude and giving are prominent in Native American history and why let white people co-opt
that so there's an example of flexibility in
order to find a way through differing views this is something that comes out of our
ability to let go and be generous is to understand that there are different ways
to perceive any given situation and it's helpful to find a way that
isn't so much involved with duka to find some view or perspective that is not
related to suffering so regarding this day maybe in a more
you know down to earth practical sense you might find that there are some conversations at the family dining table
with relatives who hold differing views and I would like to recommend
experimenting with the idea of releasing adherence to your own views in favor of
being together peacefully so it's a lesser happiness to win an argument or make a pointed statement
than the greater happiness of appreciating a chance to have a meal together and spend some time together
so you'll you'll navigate it in your own way I don't want to give specifics but at least consider this idea about the
Lesser and greater happiness and maybe try to look for what you could let go of in order to Behold a greater happiness
so we can be so generous with our mind and heart and so flexible and doing that actually
makes us resilient in the world and it's a wonderful resource for meeting life
well so I wish you a beautiful day of if it's
if you're in the United States a day of Celebration if you're farther out a day of
peace and letting go and generosity so chaga this resource of giving and
letting go thank you