so hello my friends and welcome i've posted near the top of the
chat the zoom link for today at 7 45 when we end and i'll post it again at the end
and it's i'll talk more about it at the end as well
so imagine that
you're going for a walk in the woods on a road that you've never been on
maybe a place you've never been and [Music]
someone gives you instructions of how to walk through this woods the instructions are
in this large wilderness area there is only one six foot dirt
path for you to walk on however there are lots of small little
paths that leave this large six foot wide path
stay on the wide path don't go off only walk on the white path
as you walk on this white path there might be all kinds of signs saying go this way
or that way pointing down some of the small side shoots side paths some of them will
say things like
easy way or you're going the wrong way go this way
or some signs will say you're not able to walk this path go
this way instead or some will say why don't you stop here
and debate what you're doing take this path to debate what you're doing
take this path to have doubt about what's in the world you're doing in the
forest take this path for questioning the authority
of anybody who knows what path you should be on and there's all these signposts that are
pointing you off and mostly these side paths take you to little spirals where you kind of go
right around and around in circles and and you're lucky if you manage to get out on the main road again
but the main road the six foot wide path just goes straight and as long as you
stay on that you're fine so the same thing happens in meditation
there is a wide road to walk and then there's all these other ideas and thoughts that
are pointing us in different directions take us a different direction and the instructions and mindfulness
practices stay on the main road don't get off and what is the main road
the main road is not uh erode literally
but the the way that we walk in mindfulness is we
acknowledge the primary thing we do is we
recognize the obvious thing that's happening in the moment
without believing it without pushing it away without being for it
without being against it just recognize there's a loud sound
just recognize the sound instead of well that's an interesting scratching on the wall maybe i should go
investigate that neighbor is having nice music i'll go over there and
listen with him it's just scratching sound music that's what's happening now
breathing that's what's happening now don't take the path that says maybe
there's a better way of breathing i'm a maybe my breathing is not the right kind of breathing and maybe i should
hyperventilate then i'll get concentrated these are all side tracks
off the main road which is simply to recognize i'm breathing my breathing is this way
there'll be thoughts that arise about am i doing the right thing if you take those road then you're off
the main track if you simply recognize
what's happening now is i'm questioning whether i'm doing the right thing then you're on the main road don't get
involved in those thoughts just recognize them so just recognize what's happening
that's the that's the main road stay on the main road one of the side roads is thinking about
what just happened a few seconds before that's a side
road thinking about what's going to happen oh if i just do this meditation practice
for another few minutes i'll get concentrated that's a side road just be present if you're not
concentrated then oh this is not being concentrated this is beginning to get some signs of
being settled no need to go down the road that says i wonder how long it will take until i get
concentrated so um thank you debbie stay on the main path
so that's the plan so if you could somehow uh
track for yourself the seven the you know then 20 minutes will stop um in case it goes on and off again
and then we will uh i'll try to fix it in between
okay thank you let's just sit quietly now
on the main road
so then as we come to the end of the sitting
the things that we learn what we learn from staying on the main road
is how to just stay present for what's in front of us what's here
and now and obvious
and sometimes there are other people who are standing in front of us we're with
and the ability to have them be the road or meeting them being present for them
where we take them in we see them clearly in their humanity
see them clearly in their capacities for suffering and for happiness
we see them with our hearts
and the main road is just to see and allow that to gently affect us
independent of the side roads of i need to take care of them i need to
get away this is too much
what can i get from this person will the person accept me or reject me
to be able to be present on the main road with others is one of the great gifts we give them and give the world
and give ourselves to be present
to see what's here in front of us clearly is there a
stirring of care of love of kindness
may all beings be happy
may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music] so
[Music] the last of these
hindrances is usually called doubt but it involves a world of uh
uncertainty uh indus indecisiveness um
and confusion about things and uh
and the opposite of this kind of doubt confusion and certainty is i think of it as trust
and for practice of meditation um it's trusting the main road
that uh the main road is this wide road that if you stay on
the wide road you're on the track but when you take a lot of those short little side paths that go off the little
thin narrow side paths that go off from the big wide road then you go off into the thickets of the
jungles the woods and the wilderness where you may not come back so quickly or
takes you back you know just just put you in circles or
as you're wandering around for a long time before you can come back to the main road
but trusting the main road of practice that uh just show up just be present for
this be present for this be present for this and um and uh when
the mind starts going down the side path uh remembering oh that's a side path just to hear and one of the side paths
is um doubt confusion it's wondering what to do and what am i
supposed to put where am i going and am i able to do this is the right teaching what about this teaching of
of not-self and it doesn't make any sense the buddhists teach it and what do they mean by it and i have doubts about
it and so all these are kind of side paths the path to trust
is the path of just being present for this as as
it's kind of like the path arises as we step on it and so if we are looking beyond our next
step for the path then it's easy to get into a world of confusion and doubt
but if we trust that next step then the path arises the path appears
in the step with the step so and the steps are in mindfulness
practice is the simple being present for the obvious experience of the moment
the the recognition of it and so if there's a
anything that happens that okay this is happening this is happening this is
happening um and that uh and one of the forms of doubt and one of the side paths people
might take is well how then will i take care of myself how will i take care of the world if i'm just
so simplistically taking this moment this moment two answers to this
one is that the primary reference point where we're talking about right now is meditation
and how we are in meditation might be different how we are in daily life we're mindful in both
but in meditation that's where we can have this radical simplicity of just being with the obvious being
present for this this we don't have to solve the world's problems while we're in meditation we
want to solve our problems what we're doing in meditation how we're present for our experience
doesn't have to be directly connected to solving all the problems around us
but being present in meditation prepares us to be able to be wise
and considerate and kind in how we respond to things outside of
meditation so this ability to just keep it simple it also teaches us how much we
complicate things unnecessarily because the radical simplicity of meditation
it kind of highlights the complications highlights how we bear away
and so uh in when we go back into our daily life we're wiser about that we'll
notice the kinds of getting preoccupied in thoughts which are not useful and be
able to recognize the way to be in thought in a way to be that is useful and how we can engage in problem solving
if we need to and so um to have this deep trust just
be present just be present and certainly doubts uncertainties
hesitations confusions will arise and the path of mindfulness is in the
sati patana is simply to know oh this is confusion this is doubt this is uncertainty this
is vacillation this is a lack of commitment but this is
what it looks like this is what it is to see it arise to see it be present see it's absent
to see it as a hindrance or to um in meditation
it's a hindrance for continuing to walk on that main road um there could be
there could be all kinds of healthy doubts that we have in our life
discovery and there's doubts in daily life
there's the blinking and and there's doubts in daily life
now we have we have one uh this happens
quickly quickly then we'll switch over to zoom
so i'm back so i'll try to finish quickly and uh now and uh it's just um
um you know i just this is what's happening this is what we're present for and in a sense we're kind of in this
dharma mode here i am talking and meditating after the meditation but this is a time
to not make anything a problem and um we can have problems later we have to
address and certainly this will be an issue we'll look at and and um
and all that so um um there's uh
there's all kinds of um healthy doubts that we can have and healthy doubts are ones that uh
encourage us to look more deeply consider more deeply a question in an appropriate way
unhealthy doubts are the ones that keep us indecisive or confused or or
hesitant in a way that without the kind of forward leaning or forward going questioning and wondering
uh what's going on and is
so to be able to distinguish healthy and unhealthy but in in but in this kind of meditative way of
satipatana is gives us an opportunity to see
the arising of it uh we can see it when it's not there we
get it what it feel for the sense of trust and clarity when we're just staying on the on the main road
and also we can see um um uh how we can let go of it when it
comes because we don't have to debate it or justify it when we're meditating
uh we can trust the main path just be present just be
present just be present and uh and then we uh things like doubt
arise and pass and they're not our business they're just kind of we pause for them briefly maybe like with like
with the blinking of the video we have today and and then we continue on the path
so um thank you for this and uh thank you for hanging in
there with us and i think it's you know kind of wonderful that we have an issue like this that is
kind of doesn't we don't lose the connection more than a few moments and then we can just practice
the main path with it and continue