so good morning everyone and welcome to uh
zero two zero zero two two two two zero two two
that's truly a tuesday and happy to be back here and i had a
nice visit with my father so um
to jump in we're beginning with the topic of feelings feeling tones
and the to be very simple about it the
idea the theory in buddhism is that all experiences have three tonalities three feeling
tones they are either they are pleasant or they're unpleasant or they're neither
pleasant or unpleasant and one of the reasons this is significant
is that one of the primary ways in which the mind gets activated to be for and against things to move
towards things and move away from things is whether they're pleasant or unpleasant
and exactly our relationship to what is neither pleasant or unpleasant is variable
and and so if we uh bring attention to the pleasant unpleasant neither
unpleasant or unpleasant it gives us a um and if everything has this quality everything has
characterized in some way by this tonality that we can
if we notice that we notice we have a big handle big perspective and noticing
on how we react so in this meditation as we're sitting here
and if you would um
maybe notice as you're exposed you do your regular meditation practice mindfulness practice
whether the experience is pleasant or unpleasant or neither those two
but more importantly notice if there's even the slightest little movement for or against or moving
towards or moving away from just that very simple
what is the response in our system our somatic our psychological psychic
psychological system and can you notice this ever so slight or very great
movement away from or towards away from the unpleasant towards the pleasant
or being in favor for the pleasant oh yes that's good and being i have an unfavorable reaction
to the unpleasant oh no not that again or something and as i said it can be very subtle it
can be just a slight shift in the you know texture or the
or the size or the strength of the awareness and it could could it could shut down in
one side and kind of open up in the other or it could be quite strong the whole body can move or the mind can get spin
out into kind of kinds of thoughts and reaction one way or the other so let's begin with that and
then i'll talk more about it so taking a comfortable
alert posture and gently closing the eyes
and then scan through your body to see
there are probably pleasant and unpleasant sensations in your body as you sit here
and scan through your body and just calmly recognize the pleasants and the
unpleasant ones and as you do do you notice any
simple movement for for and against
wanting and not wanting moving towards moving away
what is the response to being aware of pleasant and unpleasant
scanning around your body for the pleasant unpleasant and just not lingering any one place for long just
like an inventory
and then bringing your attention to your breathing
taking some long slow breaths and if possible breathe in a pleasant
way so long slow gentle deep breath in
and a long exhale where you relax and let go
and letting your breathing return to normal and continue to and exhale
maybe breathing it breathing in normally but ever so slightly exhaling longer
than normal and in the exhale letting go relaxing the face the shoulders the belly
anywhere in the body
and then letting your breathing return to normal completely and tuning in now to the simple experience
of breathing and noticing are there parts of the
breathing that are more pleasant maybe some that are unpleasant
and are you kind of equanimous either way or is there in fact some very simple
being for or against wanting or not wanting
moving towards or moving away with what is pleasant and unpleasant and
in the experience of breathing
and if other things in your experience come into awareness
besides the breathing be mindful of whether it's a pleasant or
an unpleasant or neither pleasant or unpleasant experience
and also see if you can notice any if there are any ways in which you are
responding reacting to the pleasant or unpleasantness of it
rather than somehow subtly getting involved in the preferences and wanting
and not wanting of pleasant and unpleasant
see if you can abide live in the knowing that this is happening just
to see and recognize it's like this
there is pleasant and there's wanting there's unpleasant and there is not
wanting
being aware of your reactions to pleasant and unpleasant
and if you're aware of them clearly enough
you'll see that you are not your reactions they're simply reactions responses
desires and aversions being for against
but not you when you rest in awareness of it all
just knowing as if awareness is larger
more peaceful than any reaction you have
and then in the last minutes before the ending whatever seems pleasant
comfortable in your meditation if there is such a thing
breathe with that and let the mind settle into that
supported by what is comfortable or pleasant in settling further into the present
moment thinking quieting down
and then as we come to the end of the sitting considering that
our lives will always contain degrees of pleasant and degrees of
unpleasantness comfort and discomfort ease and unease
it's part and parcel of the human life
and it's possible to be free it's possible to be peaceful
it's possible to in knowing
pleasant and unpleasant knowing our reactions
it's possible to feel peaceful safe happy
our happiness does not need to depend on things being pleasant or unpleasant
happiness belongs to something deeper in us
something that's related to our capacity for simple awareness
being present here in a full full way
and so as we come to the end of the sitting maybe we wish that people
find their way with the pleasant and unpleasant challenges of this life
and find a freedom and a happiness and a peacefulness
that's not so dependent on whether there's pleasant or unpleasantness
may we dwell with awareness that's independent not dependent
unpleasant and unpleasant and wish that for others so that all
beings may find a sustainable happiness
a sustainable safety peace and freedom
may all beings be happy and may our
careful attention to this aspect of the mindfulness
pleasant and unpleasant be in the service the welfare and happiness of all beings
including ourselves
[Music]
so good morning everyone and i appreciated uh comments about
paul farmer and his unfortunate passing and
i was i'm very thinking about him today and yesterday i was thinking i'm happy that we
as a community raised that over 30 thousand dollars last summer
for his organization to end their work in in haiti
and uh glad we could do it and he was still alive and
so um may his work continue and may our work caring for others continue as well
inspired by him so the
topic now for the second foundation of mindfulness is a quite a profound topic
and the simple explanation of what it is um does it kind of doesn't uh
clearly indicate how profound it is but there's a way there's a building on
or continuing a kind of theme that you find in the teachings of the buddha
around the idea of omniscience there were people who wanted spiritual leaders to be
omniscient back in the time of the buddha and there were apparently some spiritual teachers who claimed to
certain kind of omniscience and the buddha was one who didn't so much
push things away or deny things he would accept them and then redefine them in his own terms
so he he didn't say it exactly the way i'm saying it but i'm bill building on how he says that um
that he is omniscient and all of us can be omniscient in a
particular way we can know something about everything
and that's something is we can know the feeling tone of every experience we have
and it no matter what the experience is it's um it's either pleasant
or or unpleasant or neither pleasant or unpleasant
so there's no you know in terms of the hedonic tone those are the three options
there might be many other features of our experience besides the hedonic tone
but that tonality has those three characteristics and
and so you know something but everything if you know its tone its feeling tone
and to get a handle and to recognize feeling tone as it arises in all kinds it can be situation can be
very complicated and and then you realize oh this is a very
unpleasant situation it's just unpleasant and that recognizing the unpleasantness
of it gives mindfulness a place to land or to settle or to open so that the mind is not jumping around
or confused or chasing after trying to understand it or analyze it or you know just track what's going on
and allow something to settle uh same thing with something that's pleasant oh this is really pleasant
and and i no wonder that i'm leaning forward so much
and so uh to be able to um and then to be able to recognize
the reactions we have with pleasant and unpleasant is tremendously useful
it turns out the very high percentage of human reactivity of wanting and not wanting
is not based on the sophisticated analysis of the situation but rather and the very simple almost amoeba-like
idea of going towards what's pleasant and away from what's unpleasant
and if we could watch that movement for and against and see it clearly before we live in it
or pushed around by it um there's a lot of freedom that can be found and more than freedom there can be a lot
of deep understanding about ourselves like opens a window a door to a deeper deeper
understanding of ourselves and this is what this second foundation is about this my in my understanding my
interpretation is that um there's a transition here in the second
foundation from attention to the body
to the attention to the mind and the mind being something the cheetah being something deep inside
there's a movement to what's a little bit more peripheral to what's deeper inside in the first
foundation where the breathing the postures the activities of which the body does
and then there's this use of the imagination or use of reflection to
consider the parts of the body and to consider the elements of the body and consider what it's like for the body
to be there without any sensations at all and then um and now
we come we're kind of a rebirth in the second foundation where
following the corpse meditation that we did last week i think there can be a heightened
sensitivity heightened interest now in the sensations that are evidence that we're alive
and so there's a heightened kind of this is some this is you know you know this is some something to appreciate and
value and and as we go into the
the feeling tones we're actually beginning to get into the deeper functioning of
the mind deeper qualities of the mind and uh we'll see in a day or two that
this very tren this very um foundation of feeling tone
makes a distinction between that which is of the flesh that which is
kind of surface and that which is uh dharmic that the dharmic feelings the
deeper deeper mind what's going on in a deeper way and this transition from what's more
surface sensual feelings to what's more non-sensual or
deeper in the mind deeper in our kind of inner life is a phenomenal transition that happens
in this second foundation but at first we want to just understand
a little bit the these uh these three tones pleasant unpleasant
and neutral the word for pla for pleasant is sukkah
s s-u-k-h-a and um and unpleasant is dukkha
often we translate that as suffering and d-u-k-k-h-a
the most literal meaning of dukkha is pain and sukkah is happiness
and and then by by application it becomes because it is a such a broad range of feeling tones
rather than making it pain and happiness or pain and pleasure it's pleasant and
unpleasant to capture the subtlety but you have to remember it also applies to the most intense versions of
those and at first the the focus is much more on
sensual pleasant and unpleasantness that's why sensuality uh you i guess you can have pleasure
um but where the difference is between pleasant and pleasure probably has a lot to do
with how much we lean into it how much we get caught in it and involved in it
and there's less involvement with the pleasant and unpleasant but pleasant and unpleasant is
is understood in buddhism to be a quality of the mind and
it's not just purely physical and this was a confusion i had in my early years of studying buddhism i thought pleasant
unpleasant was purely a physical reaction to things that had nothing to do with
um my evaluation of it but if i like read deeper in the suttas
it's actually a little more complicated and it's not just we're not innocent bystanders of pleasant and unpleasant
there can be a subtle leaning into it or formation or prioritization of it or
preference going on in the very idea of pleasant and unpleasant
and um that is not completely only a physical phenomena
the mind participates in the formation of pleasant and unpleasant and so this points to how we're now
beginning to dip our toe into the deeper well of our inner life or our life that that the feeling tone
is not just physical and mechanical it involves uh a a
mutuality a reaction a resp a mental process as well as well are
touched as we feel pleasant and unpleasant we don't have to understand all how this
works but but we want to be able to start appreciating that pleasant unpleasant
comes off the tongue quite easily as is something that seems hedonistic or seems
distant from the full sophisticated life we live or the full
range of happiness and unhappiness that we might experience but to begin
keeping it that simple and beginning to recognize how often and how much we're
reacting to pleasant and unpleasant sometimes react reacting to what is neither pleasant or unpleasant
we begin finding we have more choice to not react
or or to step back in a broader awareness where the
awareness is not the reaction the awareness just knows the reaction and this
develops and strengthens mindfulness a lot and this is kind of the direction we're going to in sati patana we're going to
cultiva we're moving the direction of cultivating an awareness that can observe
the experience or can be wide enough to hold the experience and so pleasant unpleasant liking and
not liking wanting and not wanting can all be just seen
through awareness through mindfulness unknown no and and it makes a world of difference to
see it and to know it so um the um
and finally i'll say that uh and i suspect that the way i'm teaching it today maybe you don't get a sense of
um its full value for the buddha there were
this vedana with a holly word for feeling tone um
v-e-d-a-n-a is um one of the
uh he points to this as being one of the most important pivot points for our experience
it's kind of like there's a funnel uh an hourglass and and the neck
is where the feeling tones are everything goes through that neck and um there's all these different
things that go through but everything has to go through the neck of feeling tones before it uh
it fans out again in the hourglass and um so he buddha pointed to feeling
tone to having this central foundational role for mindfulness practice for getting a
handle or experience and becoming free and he pointed to it
he pointed to this as an alter alternative to getting wrapped up in philosophical enterprises
of his times philosophies interpretation speculation about metaphysics and spirituality he
was pointing to direct experience and in particular he pointed to this feeling tone as being so important to
help us become free to understand what's going on in a deeper way
and and then finally the the structure of the sativitana suta
is feeling tone is the uh is the seventh exercise
so there's a six before and six afterwards and so feeling tones right in the middle is to pivot and
we'll see as next few days this pivot that goes on as we get deeper into the feeling tone
of our experience so um
so here we go second foundation of mindfulness and and i hope that
you'll appreciate how wonderfully significant it is to bring mindfulness to this part of our life
thank you