so good morning hello everyone and Welcome to our
Friday meditation and teaching
the Thursday today's Thursday tomorrow so I'm already thinking ahead a little bit
so um the theme for this week has been the
Buddhist teachings on a right effort and there's four of them and today's the topic is
cultivating maintaining growing wholesome States
I'll talk more about that than during the talk but for this meditation I want
to point to a very important wholesome
State a Wholesome Way of being that maybe is the foundation for the
growth the development the allowance of other wholesome States
and that is being unwavering
an unwavering way of being in this world in meditation
so to be unwavering and are
application of ourselves are doing unwavering in our thoughts on wavering
in our mind and heart so in the body maybe that's experienced
as a kind of stability to feel stable here
to in the mind maybe it's steadiness to hold the course to be hold the Mind
steady on something and um and the
and maybe in the heart I don't know what uh is that what the
quality of unwaveringnesses of the hearts maybe it's uh kind of a devotion
or maybe it's a kind of a feeling an attitude of yes
to being present to being here regardless
and this uh idea of of being unwavering as being an important mental quality
the foundation kind of gives gives us a sense that it's cultivating wholesome qualities of
mind it doesn't have to be like all these wonderful things like love or
Good Will compassion uh which are maybe kind of very important
but uh maybe sometimes even a little bit forced or maybe not so accessible
but if we can cultivate stability steadiness unwaveringness
um then that is the ground from which the wholesome other wholesomes can grow
to be wavering to be unsteady unstable that's the ground from which the
unwholesome the unhelpful states of Mind grow
so for this meditation we can focus on being unwavering being steady and stable
and when the mind your mind wanders off in thought don't you come back to your breathing
come back or re-establish a stability of the body
a steadiness of the Mind and kind of a settled subtleness of the
heart settledness in the heart that is yes to being present
stable steady settled unwavering
so assuming a posture for meditation that
allows you to feel stable in your body
it might be a posture that's a little bit more intentional
a little bit more engaged and active than a posture that you have
prioritizing being comfortable
it's important to be comfortable up to a point but it can be overdone
with the loss of kind of bringing the body into an alert
stability
that supports a kind of
the kind of energy that of being present
gently closing your eyes and breathing deeply
relaxing the body as you exhale with the idea that the exhale
is moving to a stability of the body
where the weight of your body settles into the seats or the
place where your weight is supported by the chair or the bed or wherever you are
the floor
letting breathing return to normal
and then if as you breathe a normal breath is there some way that you can steady
your mind
kind of like you would if you were going to do a very precise Movement Like
threading a needle
steady the mind letting go of thoughts relaxing the
tension of the Mind settling whatever way the mind
is agitated in favor of the where the mind
is steady stable
and then as you breathe maybe on the exhale
just settle your heart
almost like your heart happily responds to the pool of gravity
to relax and settle on
quieting the agitation of heart
and if you find yourself wandering off in thought or very much caught up in thought
you might go through these three steps on your way back to breathing
find some stability in the body
some steadiness in the mind and some subtleness in the heart
and with that Begin Again with your breathing
with an unwavering attention to the next in-breath
to the next exhale
one breath at a time
chances are if you're wondering a lot in your thinking
the mind has some agitation in it it's wavering and unsteady
relax deeply as a way of steadying the Mind
stabilize yourself here in the present moment with your body
foreign
in the next couple of minutes before the closing
gently with a gentle way
can you be a bit more stable settled in your body
so the body is more present more
aware of its embodied nature
and gently steadying the mind the attention
may be on itself
underneath your concerns and preoccupations agitations
settling into a deeper layer in the mind where it's stable quiet
settled appreciating just being aware being
conscious
and settling the heart as if
you feel reassured
safe as if for this next few moments everything is good
all is good the heart can rest
for a few minutes be content
and from this unwavering stance of stability steadiness
subtleness from a deep within you
what a wholesome quality seems to want to emerge
what goodness what sweetness
what is it that wants to appear and Flow
that's something that's enjoyable or appreciatable
to be stable steady settled
makes it possible to be more sensitive aware of the world around us
to be with others and let their being registered for us
feel the connection that doesn't require words
in the presence of people that we care for when we're settled they might want to
love might want to emerge kindness good will
Delight
settling back
and then ending this meditation with extending our Good Will out into the
world may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
male beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may it be that inner stability subtleness steadiness
unwavering ability to be present
that we contribute to the welfare and happiness of everyone
thank you [Music]
so hello everyone welcome to this fourth talk on the four right efforts
and today's emphasis is on the fourth being the
a focus on wholesome states of mind or skillful helpful States or qualities
and um and the um
this is actually a very important part of the teachers of the teachers of the Buddhas
teaching that at least in my for me was not really appreciated very much in a
few Decades of being a Buddhist and practicing I think perhaps like I think maybe a
good number of people I had somehow become tuned into prioritizing
the teachings On Letting Go and uh and sometimes it was
indiscriminate letting go it was just that means it's very powerful sometimes especially in meditation to let go of
everything even the wholesome because sooner or later everything needs to be let go of no holding even to the
wholesome but it's possible to overdo it and not then support the growth the
cultivation even the presence of beneficial states of Mind beneficial
states of heart and that as we allow them to be there
and they're just let go of them or ignore them that we can actually promote or make it
possible for him to grow and it's possible to become filled with well-being filled with really good
qualities I was kind of really amazed and stunned when I started doing the long meditation
lots of meditation to discover how thoroughly saturated our the whole body
and being can be in particular wholesome states of being
uh joy and happiness tranquility um now the one that surprised me I think
the most was equanimity uh just the the Equanimity was such a
clear full embodied kind of way it wasn't just some like little policy in
the mind to be equanimous it was a way of being and um
so this idea that the wholesome is supposed to be proof so in this four right efforts
the first right effort is to prevent the arising of unarrisen
unwholesome States so states that haven't not really healthy for you to
have thoughts feelings attitudes motivations
if they're not there and they're not operating you know they're a common part of your life then
within reason maybe make the behavioral changes and other changes that would
kind of um prevent them from arising these unhealthy ways of being
the second right effort is if the unwholesome states of Mind have come up
abandon them so this is the Letting Go part and how to abandon them healthfully and
is is important but these four right efforts you were always using them as a kind of a perspective an analysis
of what we're actually doing so if we're letting go is the Letting Go
itself done in a Wholesome Way or is it unwholesome if letting go is being done with a
version with conceit with Greed for something better
if it's then it's not so wholesome and it kind of will backfire in some way
but if we're looking for how to do this in a Wholesome Way uh it's a it's a whole the whole it's a
game changer it's a very different way of being with it and then there's not so much self-involved or conceit or greed
that kind of comes in slowly we begin to learn how there's a whole other source
Within that is the source of how to do things in wholesome ways including this letting
go one of the things to discover is that letting go is one of the things that our
heart wants to do if all the conditions are right it's not like we have to let
go but we have to enable the letting go that that's already there that wants to
happen so kind of a very the third right effort is to evoke to
bring about to recognize wholesome states that haven't Arisen yet to bring them about
and that also might involve behavioral changes to stay close to things that inspire you
bring your gladness and happiness and steadiness and you know do the things
that help you be more settled in your life or stable in your life and uh rushing around is not helpful
doing things in a steady stable manner is much more helpful
and then the fourth is the this is a dramatic so it kind of goes comparable to the second right effort to abandon
uh the unwholesome states that have risen now it's to maintain the wholesome
states that have arisen so things that are good going on maintain them and
again this can be done with behavioral ways if you feel really happy and good and just feel like this is unusually
settled and peaceful maybe it's not the time to get lost on the web or in the news or
or you know start doing something that you know is going to just get you really
angry um you know just kind of maybe there's a way of maintaining it keeping it going
being careful not to lose it easily to sacrifice it for um you know some petty irritation that
you want to complain about and so um
however what I want to emphasize today is that this cultivating and maintaining
um the wholesome it gets actually much more emphasized by the Buddha because rather than simply
one word of what we do prevent
abandon evoke for the forthright effort there's a whole series of words so you
get a sense of kind of the emphasis the importance like like maybe we're supposed to spend uh you know more time
on the wholesome so this is a how it goes
practitioners take up and take hold of their minds take hold of themselves
and generate desire endeavor and initiate courageous effort
here we go for the maintenance the non-forgetting
the frequent cultivation the abundance the development and the Fulfillment of
wholesome mental qualities States characteristics that have Arisen wow I mean that's quite
a mouthful once something good has arisen in you be careful
don't lose it easily because you get caught up in your desires and your conceits and your you know
agendas and your fears and your you know rushing around and doing a lot
take time for that and and then are there ways
to maintain it keep it going not with again it has to be done in a
Wholesome Way not with expectation not with demand not with measuring your
success and failure your self-worth by their presence not by in a way that you
would be just you know distraught if it's not there and feel like somehow you're a bad person
there's a Wholesome Way a freeway a generous way a relaxed way to be with
all these things that you know is is kind of sense of freedom in it itself
and with that to maintain it to be conscious and aware and choiceful about
what we do so that affects our state of mind
for the non-forgetting I love this one don't forget it don't overlook it don't
lose touch with it it's so easy to lose touch and forget the the healthy way of
being in the world being attentive being here in a full way
the frequent cultivation abundance development and fulfillment
so the city of abundance abundance of good qualities the Fulfillment of them
so can't get any better I mean this is dramatic language I think to me it's inspiring language it
could seem exhausting like there's a lot to do but it's not meant to be the kind of doing that is exhausting it's a kind of
a doing which is fun which is nice which is relaxing which the doing itself feels good
and that's the art of this whole meditation and mindfulness how do we do anything
in a wholesome healthy beneficial way and that's the art that we want to
discover and find that's the key to a Buddhist practice Buddhist practice involves practice but how do we do the
practice in this Wholesome Way nourishing way inspiring way we're
inspired by it feels good we like we like doing it it's not automatic we discover how to do
it but that's what we're working towards and then and then uh overcoming the
strong urges in the mind uh from fear from desires from Duty
obligation to override the healthy way of doing things to do things in ways
which are not wholesome that are rushed that lead to maybe something as simple as becoming unstable and unsteady and
tight and focused losing touch forgetting about this Wholesome Way of being
because this idea of wholesomeness wholesome states of being that we maintain can can lift the bar kind of
high if we rush to the idea that has to be love and peace and these were dramatic kind of
spiritual feelings um the foundational one that I think
that we want to remember to always come back to and start with is the wholesome sense of being stable
here in the in the moment a physical embodied stability when we're un when unwholesomeness takes
over it shifts and changes the physical body and how we live in the world and I
mean how we're how we are not so settled but when we're wholesome there's the
wholesomes arises out of the settled body stable a settled mind
a steady mind and a subtle heart so if that's the first
step in evoking the wholesome and maintaining the wholesome maybe that's not so bad
maybe that isn't so far Out Of Reach maybe it's only you know ten percent
more stable ten percent more steady but that but without ten percent maybe
we don't make as many mistakes we don't live as stressfully as we do other times and that steadiness and stability the
sense of being living a life which is unwavering
is the soil in which the wholesome has a chance to emerge
and probably the more stable and steady and subtle we are the more the wholesomeness the
appearance the arising of it does it by itself we don't have to do it we just
have to recognize it allow it not forget it
support it to grow not be embarrassed or ashamed or
kind of afraid of it don't be afraid of the goodness that's in you
Let It Grow and let it become abundant so the wholesome maintaining growing
developing the wholesome within us so for this day's homework
I wanted you through the day whenever you can remember maybe set a timer at least do it once an
hour or something see if you can emphasize a little bit more coming into a place of stability
steadiness subtleness some places we feel kind of
feel this and then when you do something to do it kind of in an unwavering way from this place
and see if other wholesome qualities have a chance to follow and awake it's
almost like that stability opens the door and that Open Door what wholesome things
wants to come from you and uh and maybe make a catalog of what
wants to come it's uh you might be surprised what's in there that wants to come out
so thank you very much and uh
for tomorrow they'll be kind of a concluding talk on these four right efforts