so hello everyone and welcome to this period of meditation
and one of the ways that meditation can
unfold develop over time is through appreciating
some of the beneficial States beneficial ways of being that come with meditation
and sometimes in doing this appreciation
it's uh maybe keep the bar low
keep it um uh maybe in micro moments
of beneficial States because as we appreciate these
beneficial States that validates them it makes room for them it
supports them to grow more and they can last more than just a micro moment maybe
they last three or four or even who knows maybe even a second or two
so um the idea of appreciating something
and one of the things to appreciate is the moments the mind is not
preoccupied and I think meditators sooner or later
will begin being sensitive aware of how much thinking goes on in the mind
and how much uh our attention is pulled into that world sometimes people are Swept Away in their
thoughts and um and or they have something they're really churning on or ruminating
about and uh you know it just seems like the most natural thing in the world to be
thinking about it even uh in for about the present moment there's a continual commentary about it
it just seems like the most natural thing but it's a kind of preoccupation of the Mind the mind is occupied
with thoughts and some people because they identify
with their thinking uh well I have this idea there's nothing wrong with the thinking this is who I am and I should
be free to think whatever I want to think it's important and certainly those are you know it's a
fine attitude to have in and of itself but it doesn't really support the
deepening of meditation the deeper beneficial ways that meditation can
improve our lives benefit us free us and um and uh it seems so it's important
to begin being sensitive to the difference between being preoccupied
and the mind being I don't know if unoccupied is the right word but the mind being ready
receptive that it's getting to be malleable and
soft that it's here and this transition in a period of meditation from being preoccupied to
being here now I'm present and kind of being present that doesn't
require thoughts to tell us that there's a knowing I'm here
that's there before we have a thought oh I'm here
and so to appreciate having arrived
appreciate an awareness that's here for a micro moment
without being preoccupied available
to be aware available to sense to feel to be present for
what is actually here
now in this moment sometimes this is called arriving
we finally arrive in the present moment
with our attention
rather than attention being swept up in or directed to or he
utilized by all kinds of concerns preoccupations
in on an unoccupied mind
isn't it's not a blank mind or a lazy mind it's like a glass
a window which has finally been cleaned
and now we can see
in the preoccupations interfere with that seeing
so assuming a meditation posture
and if your eyes are still open maybe lowering your gaze
and then gently closing your eyes
and gently paying careful attention to the body and
what's happening in your body take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe the Deep inhale is kind of like saying hello body
connecting being present
and then letting the breathing return to normal and continue for a few more while
you breathe in and breathing out feel your whole body
the whole breath body
relaxing as you exhale
noticing
that while you're being present for the body breathing
is it also a pull into the world of thoughts ideas preoccupations
and what's it like to have both
an intention to be with your body breathing
and a mind wants to be with concerns
underneath the mind's concerns preoccupations
is there mental tension pressure to think
and if there is as you exhale
relaxing the mind
letting the Mind spread out wide
and still
taking a few moments to acknowledge any thoughts and concerns you have
and by acknowledging them maybe they can be put aside for now
so you can settle more into your meditation
more into him and embodied connection
to the present moment
and even face the smallest degree of being present for Here and Now
see if you can appreciate the attention you have
appreciate the micro moments of unpreoccupied attention
to being here and you're breathing your body in your experience
if you give your awareness intention attention over to breathing your body
it's almost like giving it life animating it
instead of animating energizing the thinking the
preoccupation
to be unpreoccupied is a matter of degrees it's not all or
nothing appreciate the degree to which your mind
is less preoccupied more here
in your experience
as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn our attention now out to the world
there's a difference between being available for others
with our Attention our hearts our care to be available
versus advancing on people
asserting ourselves being available rather than asserting
being available is to be unpreoccupied
to be unbiased
not to meet with judgments and preconceived ideas
and what we learn in meditation about being unpreoccupied
but available receptive
is invaluable for how to be with others
to be available not in some passive withdrawn way
but available to respond kindly generously
lovingly delightfully
respectfully to be available
to wish people well rather than caught up in our reactions
we are coming from our good will
on this day May the people that I encounter
or know about may they be well may they be happy
on this day the people who I will be encountering or
knowing about may they be safe
on this day the people that I'll have contact with
or know about may they be peaceful
on this day May the people who
I think about or meet may they be free
and on this day
may I be available to have this good will
wishing for the people that I become aware of
May everyone we have encountered or think about or learn about today may
they be well
[Music]
thank you
so
continuing with the theme of this week which is
to be ready for change to be able to have been willing to change in a good
way by the life that we live and
to the Dharma practice is walking on the path of being changed
to being changed for the better being changed out of the ways that we
live that are harmful for ourselves and harmful for others into a way of living that is beneficial
for ourselves and beneficial for others and so to prepare or to help the mind or
the heart or Who We Are be available for change to for beneficial growth
there are these five different areas one is
um it did already this Readiness to be ready for something new ready and
available to be receptive the second is we talked about yesterday
is to have a mind that's malleable uh the mind which is a workable that
um you're you're not not holding on to uh ideas opinions identities in such a
way that things are stuck or hard holding a stance we're stubborn we're
resisting we're asserting but but instead where there's a softness there's
a malleability there's a workability where where a work of art that we can
work on ourselves and today the topic of these five is
um um being free of hindrances and the hindrances are major
preoccupations that we have that we get caught in they're kind of like um
you know like vacuum cleaners so that get close to it and we get sucked into this vacuum cleaner and we swirl around
inside if this until somehow we find our way out
that these are very powerful forces that keep us preoccupied churning ruminating
caught up wanting not wanting um clamped down shut down Frozen
agitated spinning all kinds of things and there are five of them but the
shorthand is that there are preoccupations of the Mind and they're also they're poly word
nivarata translated as hindrances also means coverings and sometimes I think of them as there's
this wonderful Greenhouse that maybe because of it was going to be
a freezing night it was covered with big blankets big blanket
but then the farmers forgot to take the blanket off and it stays that way for months
and the plants inside can't grow and the warmth of the sun can't get in there
really and things shrivel and dry and and um get really thin and it's related
until you know they all fall over the plants so this idea that we have these
coverings that cover something precious that we don't see when we're preoccupied
and to let go of these preoccupations the image of just like pulling the the
blanket off so that something gets deeper within the seeds that the seed beds and seeds can
begin growing uh something beautiful can begin to happen we do have beauty within us beautiful
capacities beautiful potential beautiful attitudes motivations thoughts feelings
and to be available is to uh to be unpreoccupied and available so allow
something deeper to happen that can't happen when we're preoccupied
so one of the uh really important
features of doing vipassana practice inside meditation practice mindfulness practice
is to really become an expert on the hindrances on Central desire avariciousness wanting
greed uh ill will hostility
resentment and then uh kind of uh I call it
resistance and frozenness stiffness it's usually called sloth and
torpor but these are more strategies of not being present that shut us down
and then agitation and resentments regrets
and then um doubt so there are these five and there's
Dharma talks about them there are essays on them I have a little book about the hindrance is called it's
called unhindered that it's important for people who do this practice here to not be discouraged
turn away from these when they occur for occur to us but rather really take them
on as a worthy area to study to understand how this works
to until we really begin to see and how the magic is done that we no longer
tricked by the magic into thinking that something is real there and we start seeing you know how the the
the sleight of hand of the hindrances of why we get caught in it and why we think
they're so important and so valuable and they're just a trick of the mind to get us preoccupied and caught
and um and to find ourselves without the hindrances
is one of the great Delights so to begin having an unpreoccupied mind
is a pleasure so one of the ways to be prepared to
change and to grow is to begin appreciating valuing enjoying
being inspired by the degree to which we are unpreoccupied
and that's a hard thing to do because of the preoccupation seems so important
being un preoccupied can seem like nothing and you know I mean that's not any good what's good is doing things and
thinking about things and and um but this unpreoccupied mind that's available that's present for the
fullness of this life the fullness of our hearts and our minds just here
and present unpreoccupied and to appreciate take the time to
appreciate it take the time to Value it when it's there
and um and rather than having it all or nothing it's either preoccupied or unpreoccupied
um it's a matter of degree and hopefully we're tipping the the balance towards
more being unpreoccupied than preoccupied but begin appreciating the degree to
which you're unpreoccupied the degree to which you're available and present then um and that also then allows you to
have the same kind of attitude of availability receptivity of of kind of a
softness around the ways which we are preoccupied
it's not like setting up a battle between them the more we have this
availability of attention we can hold all the ways that we are caught and
attached and involved hold it generally generously
hold it non-assertively non I don't Advance upon it to blow it
away or fix it be available to know it fully in meditation maybe everything difficult
within us is something that um is a door
to a deeper understanding of of life and of ourselves
so this um so that if you if you really want to be to change in a beneficial way
begin appreciating at the unpreoccupied mind
and make time for it begin to learn to recognize when you're
preoccupied when you're spinning out when you're kind of you know being Carried Away by the
trains of thought and and really kind of oh that there it is there it is again and then step off
the train take off the blanket let the thought bubbles kind of Drift Away
let the tension and the pressure the need to solve and fix and judge and and
remember and plan settle for a while so you can be here in a deeper and
Fuller way so as the mind so that you're available
you're receptive you are maybe starting to becoming softer
in a place where creativity can occur in a place where deeper wisdom and deeper
understanding can arise it isn't like you lose your ability to take care of your life
if you're no longer preoccupied with your concerns you gain a new vantage point in which to
take care of your life when you're not preoccupied and it's possible to have the important
issues of your life come into your mind to be thought about it being a preoccupation
it's just something to think about in a light way an open way and a peaceful way and
have tea with your thoughts and think what needs to be thought about
so for today the
the topic now is to appreciate non-preoccupation
appreciate when you're not caught up in your thoughts and appreciate the alternative
appreciate what that's like to not be preoccupied caught I appreciate the the openness
the subtleness the availability the receptivity
appreciate maybe even the delight and the joy
of not having lost yourself to your thoughts
there is a way in which we lose ourselves when we get too preoccupied
and then we gain ourselves when the preoccupations the clouds part the preoccupations part
and we're ah we're here we're back here I am
and for the Buddha the absence of hindrances the absence of preoccupation
is a source for gladness for Delight for kind of happiness
so what today I'd like to suggest to you is you notice the times that you're not preoccupied
where you're available rather than asserting yourself
see if you can taste or find the hints maybe or the small ways big ways in
which there is something some gladness some happiness in this ability to be here
in an available way and think of it as micro moments
sometimes think of it as a degrees but see if you can find that the
well-being and the Delight the gladness the
appreciation for not being caught up wow I'm not caught up I'm just here
for this second and may you have a lots of wow today may
you have lots of appreciation and joy oh here it is here it is I'm back I'm back
we're back life is back so um
thank you very much and um
may this be day that sprinkled with joy thank you