well tonight we have a surprised guest speaker I was surprised when I got a call at 5
30 that our regular guest speaker wasn't able to be here tonight so
Hillary asked me if I would fill in
so I started putting a few thoughts together about what to talk about tonight
um and not only what I want to talk about tonight but I'd like I'm hoping that
I'll be able to hear from at least some of you tonight as well
as you know in a couple of days it'll be Thanksgiving it's a national holiday
we're obviously not the only nation that engages in Thanksgiving
um and
I've thought about Thanksgiving a lot in my life
um I think I I was I started out thinking
that Thanksgiving was giving thanks to other people was sort of a social nicety like you know kind of
an obligation that I'd have when I would get clothes for Christmas instead of toys
or uh or tools both both of which I really liked
um so there was I started out with a certain sense of Thanksgiving as being a little bit
artificial you know and something that you had to kind of
social ritual or something but I think particularly when I when I
came to the Dharma I started to recognize the
the ways in which I'm supported by so many people
um living and and no longer living and that
Thanksgiving in a way is a a recognition of that connection
with all of the people primarily people that support me in my
life so if I go sort of quasiqua
chronologically um
I give thanks for my parents they both
took care of me in many ways that I didn't really appreciate or feel grateful for at the time
necessarily but um they kept me fed they kept me
house that kept me clothed and they kept me educated I I was in
school from the age of three I was in preschool all the way through graduate school and
when I was 29 so I got a lot of years of education and through that all my parents
supported me um some financially some
um I think mostly just by encouraging me they they knew that this was something
worth pursuing even though as a chemistry graduate student I'm sure they
didn't understand what it was that I was learning but they they knew that it was something valuable
so they encouraged me that way
um
and then and then as I said they they made sure that I was stayed healthy and fed and
um and also looked out for my spiritual
well-being not just my physical and intellectual well-being but they took me to church
which as a young child I didn't feel particularly thankful for uh
I could think of a lot funner things to do on a Sunday morning than you know put on a sports coat and
get all dressed up with a tie and these uncomfortable clothes and have to
sit still for an hour but you know but they did
um instill in me a lot of qualities of heart and mind of ethics
of um
you know if I go through what the Buddha considered were the foundations for practice you know even
before you start meditating uh things like generosity
my parents were very generous
um virtuous you know that sense of ethics
of treating other people uh fairly and
kindly uh Simplicity renunciation
um we didn't have a
lavishly appointed house it was fairly simple but um
but it was supportive and enjoyable um
the need for paying attention the need for
exerting energy you know getting
um uh strongly encouraged to get out of bed
in the morning and face the the what the day had to offer
patience truthfulness honesty
determination Goodwill towards others
and Equanimity so those are the the 10 paramies that the Buddha
um says the Earth encourage people to
develop before they even started to meditate
I realized that as I looked at that list those were all qualities that my parents
encouraged in me and also modeled for me so I feel I feel real thankful I I
didn't know that they were preparing me to be a Buddhist um not that those qualities are by any
means uh strictly owned by the Buddhists I think their qualities that are
probably valued in in many if if not all traditions
and I'm thankful for the larger family that I had my grandparents
um you know we'd spend every Sunday night with them
um gave us many um books and experiences
my brother and sisters my aunt
I I realized that I I really had a
I'd say a I don't know exactly how to say
a non-dysfunctional family uh
they're quite functional
uh the friends that I had you know I've had a whole series of friends starting from you know before I
started school from kindergarten through grade school and
high school College brought me a whole another set of friends graduate school brought
another set getting married brought me another set
getting divorced brought me another set going to work
and then coming here coming to IMC is has brought me in contact with a whole
nother set of friends and people who
um have supported me have given me a sense of
being appreciated heard
um and many friends have come and gone and
I've seen changes in the to a certain extent in the people that
are around me but I still have a friend from kindergarten that I I've
remained friends with for I don't know 65 years now
uh I'm thankful for my health I've been fairly health healthful healthy
uh and what haven't been I've I've had the resources to get the the needed
procedures and surgeries for uh detached retina and
stents in my heart things like that
ah
so those are some of you know some of the I'll say almost ordinary things of life
that I feel thankful for that I think everyone has had some experience with
uh but the and in addition to all of those
things I feel real grateful for this practice
is this uh practice that the Buddha
uncovered or realized and passed down
for approximately a hundred Generations I went through a
What's called the um The Refuge class that's offered here
every couple of years and at the end of it there's a ceremony where Gill would hand each one of us a
little parchment that had a list of I don't know if it was an entire list
of every single teacher but kind of represented all of the teachers
going back up approximately 100 generations to the
Buddha and
so I can say that I'm thankful that first of all that the Buddha decided after
he saw what was possible what was possible for a human being
to realize and what level of Freedom could be experienced
he had to make a choice whether he was I think at first he didn't even believe
that anybody could learn this he figured you know this is this isn't even
teachable but he did The Story Goes have a discussion with a
enlightened being I think a God or a Deva that he should teach
and because of that you know he taught you know his his students and that got passed down
and passed down and passed down and ended up with people like Gill and
Andrea Joseph Goldstein
Jack cornfield uh and many other teachers
and uh about well I guess it was almost 25
years ago that I came to IMC I was 45 at the time
and even though I had quite a good life I mean I as all of the things that I had
described I had been well supported I had been well educated
I was in good health I had a good job with NASA
and yet I recognized there was just some uh
some lingering dissatisfaction you know something that I couldn't quite
put my finger on it I couldn't quite tell you why I was dissatisfied
uh you know all of the all the indicators were that
you know you've got it together
um but I knew that I knew that there was something off there just was this was
you know this wasn't
there was some restlessness some lack of peace or uh contentment
and so when I walked into I am the IMC meetings which at the time were in Palo Alto
um the first talk I heard was Gil talking about the four normal truths and talking
about the truth of suffering and it was that night that I recognized I've
come to the right place this is the place to be this guy is talking about exactly what I'm experiencing this
suffering and not only that it's worth paying attention to
but that there's a cause for it there's the possibility of the ending of
it and that there's this Eightfold Path there's this there are things to be done
to be cultivated to be um pursued in some ways
um to bring an end to this suffering and
I don't I can't tell you exactly how I I came to IMC almost
on a whim you know it's just I somebody had told me about Spirit Rock and from
looking at their website I found a link to IMC IMC happen to be 10 minutes from my
house and so I came and I sat and I listened
to Gil and I reckon you know and I saw oh this this is this is the practice is this is
what I'm looking for this is the kind of practice the
um potentiality that I wanna I wanna spend
my the rest of my life pursuing
so I so I it's hard for me to just Express
how much gratitude I have that that not only for Gill who's a
wonderful teacher and has really helped me a long ways but then all the
other teachers that he exposed me to I'd say maybe 50 percent of the about
half the time he would give a talk on a Monday night and about half the time it would be somebody from Zen Center somebody from
uh Spirit Rock um lay people monastics
people from a wide range of backgrounds and experiences
that um presented the dharm in ways that seemed very different and sometimes almost at
odds with what I had heard the week before but yet
uh gave me a sense of just what
the breadth of what practice can encompass
so in some ways coming to IMC 25 years ago um
brought an awareness to me of the first Refuge the Buddha
not that I had the same had developed anywhere near the the level that the
Buddha had to be as free as he was able to become but that that was a
potentiality um
the years and years of talks like this the Monday night talks
um that I've been attending well really for almost 25 years
except when I'm out of town uh
books um
you know suit to studies residential Retreats there's just so
many ways in which the the practices of
that the Buddha taught have been presented to me and I've been
mentored in I'm grateful for all of those teachers
and mentors the the third Refuge is the Sangha
and really at first I didn't really recognize what
I thought the the real important thing was the teacher having a good teacher
and I think after about the first six months that I was at IMC I came up to Gill and
I said you know I really want to you know get ahead in this practice I
I want to meet with you at least you know like once a week or once every two weeks and he didn't he didn't laugh
like you all are um I think he took me seriously
but he but also it was clear that he has so much that he does that that wasn't
really a possibility but what he told me was that one of his teachers
at Zen Center had told him many years ago when he I think sort of said the
same thing to his teacher uh it might have been Mel Weitzman
um that some large fraction of what you're going to learn
you're going to learn from your peers you're going to learn from
sitting with other people Like We Are Tonight
um and talking about practice what you know what are you seeing you know what
insights are you having what struggles are you having um
it was one of the things that was said to me over and over early in my practice when
I was doing a lot of Retreats was that we don't do this practice for
ourselves alone so there's some way in which
hello nobody but us can
sit and close our eyes and pay attention I mean there are things that we have to do only we can do
that the benefit of it and the result of it isn't limited to
this being I call me that there's very much a interaction
between me and the other people that um are part of my Sangha
so at this point in time there's three groups that I'm part of there's one that
meets once a month one that meets every two weeks and one that meets every week
and in both the talking and the listening in
those uh kalyanamita groups is where a
lot of the insight and the strengthening of qualities can occur and
a lot of the encouragement a lot of the inspiration
yeah so that's so that's Sangha so I'm
you know on this Thanksgiving week
uh I don't
I don't know whether it's karma or dumb luck that I was able to come across IMC
when I did right right when I uh was looking for
what it had to offer but I'm really thankful for
um the teachers the Sangha and the
hand the the teachers going all the way back to the Buddha
the other thought that came to me this evening around Thanksgiving and
around um recognizing and expressing gratitude is
that it isn't that that it's
a little bit like a form of mindfulness it's it's remembering
those things that happened that support us
you know that have supported us maybe today or yesterday or earlier this week
or this month this year this lifetime
it's not necessarily a Feeling
or just a feeling but gratitude I think is also an ability and ability to
to wreck to remember and recognize those things that support us
and connect us with other people
one of the practices that I've heard about in regards to gratitude is
some people will keep a gratitude Journal so they'll have a journal
oftentimes next to their bed and either just before they go to bed at night or maybe when they wake up in the morning
is writing down things that you remembered
that that you're grateful for that supported you you know it could be something like
just the way somebody smiled at you today you know some or you know some small
um gesture of Goodwill or um
you know whatever it is that that's one particular way that that that this
quality this strength of this muscle of gratitude can be um
developed I think it's also helpful
to not just recognize it internally but also
to express it verbally I mean maybe not all the time but I've had this practice for about the
last 15 years of um
when I when I get food or get drinks from Starbucks or something like that
I always like to thank the person that's made the made whatever it was for me you know
and also give them some tip but um I'm often surprised at how
surprised some people are when you just you just thank them for making you hot
chocolate um you know just that recognition that
um that there's that there's some connection there
so uh that's as much as I've prepared for
tonight but I would like to offer each one of you the opportunity
to express what you might be grateful for
so this isn't a you're not obligated to say anything but um this is your opportunity to uh
you know just Express you know share with us
some thing or some things that
um you can remember from today or
you know the last couple of days or whatever length of time it is
um that you've been uh
gifted so I don't know it's about that if you
couldn't if you feel moved raise your hand and sveta will bring the microphone
foreign
thank you Jim first of all I am
thankful for your practice and for being uh
um it's a pleasure to be in the same song go with you and to practice with you
and I think you're a great model for Equanimity and thank you for filling in
for tonight I did also want to say um
that I am grateful for my relationship with uh indigenous people who
this particular um holiday is problematic for
and I extend my love and respect to them and for the conflict it presents for
them uh and I just want to recognize that on their behalf
thank you Nancy
yes well thank you also for the the surprise to talk um
but yeah so I'm just this is the fourth time I've been here to IMC on a on a Monday evening and I'm happy I I found
it I used to sit a long time ago at cannondough for a few years but then I
was looking for a place I could get to that was on the Caltrain this was a that this was perfect so I'm really
enjoying it so far thank you
I'm grateful to be
to hear your talk and recognize the Heritage that we've inherited
why the lineage and the relationships that that you've built
and that are available um as I look at
um wanting to feel connected with friends and see the ones that are there for me
because there's been a death in the family and I really do have that need for people
reaching out and those relationships and I I know in this community that's the
priority you know is relationships and um growing together so to me that's
that's heartening that it's a priority
thank you for your share um I have come on and off to IMC and uh I
happen to come Sunday and both your share and that one were very uh connecting for me
um particularly the concept of change came up and I think
The Fall season is really one where we really see visually change
and I I got a lot out of the realization that
that's one thing that will always be happening and
gave me the insight to realize that there's a little struggle for me a lot
of the time about change and that if I can remain compassionate with my resistance but then be aware of
it that I can let it be exactly what it is
and so uh thank you again very very nice of you
thank you thank you
thank you for uh a great session and also sharing your experiences
I'm very grateful to be here to be part of this group
um in particular um
when I see you you remind me of
Gregory Peck of Indian theaters
um wearing a red top and you know the black trousers
um and uh Johnny Johnny Mirana
guide guide is one movie with a Polish
novel based on polish no guide from 1966.
um and I grew up in a rather modest setting
where access to TV or entertainment was limited
but today I am grateful that just with the click of a button on the internet any child
throughout the world through the invention of internet and
cell phone Technologies they can see watch movies and musicals and songs
featuring individuals like you and whatnot and
and you know in one that is another movie where he goes on
to talk about you know Buddha's preaching ahinsa parama Dharma
um and there also he is wearing this red top so what I am grateful for is
for all the people around the world all the children
that they have access to Internet and access to
you know the entertainment or music or movies or theater whatever or news or
Whatever by the invention of Internet and also keeping the cost down so it's it's
affordable for most people but if it is
even more affordable and accessible I will be even more grateful and being able to share that
with other people so that Joy thank you yeah thank you
by the way Gregory Peck is my favorite actor so that was quite a compliment for
me
Jamie thank you
um yeah and the meditation before this I
was sitting here and um
I I have a lot of difficulty keeping on the object of meditation my mind is
often going off somewhere and I guess lately I've
um become a little bit more equanimous about that and uh so I just sort of um
when it when awareness comes back I I just note what's going on and uh in
the meditation before this when I when awareness came back I was often thinking
about how warm and cozy I felt not just
because I'm bundled up and wearing gloves but also just feeling very secure in this
place and um with these people around me
um uh so I'm very grateful for
this place of all the volunteers that that help maintain it and uh
everybody that comes here to practice and uh
sort of makes us a warm and cozy Place spiritually as well
thank you thank you
thank you I I like what you said and I want to ask
you that uh Echo that the warm fuzzy feelings here
um Jim I'm so impressed you got a phone call at 5 30. no it's 7
30 you have to give a Dharma talk that's a wonderful Delma talk thank you
um I appreciate how somebody said earlier
all this service people and always see Nancy right sitting in front and walking
in just so happy to see you Nancy
this better is over there helping us to do the recording
and um I cannot see more say more about
Buddha's teaching because each one of you shared
it's really touching and we each of us
take what we can nourish us
and help us to go
to move forward in our life and to me seems like
takes layers I have to get on a certain level to see
there's additional teaching that I can comprehend
and um and this environment this IMC is so
precious is
there's no pressure it's very relaxed it's whatever
that we can be nourished and learned
and I just so appreciate it
and thank you Jim for giving us this opportunity to reflect
you know what what is Sangha offer to each of us
and everybody's different and that's what great about Buddha
you know we learn we practice and
um learn based on our own experiences
not uh it's a inside out it's not an outside in
practice thank you
thank you Lydia
we have a couple more minutes is there anyone else that would just like to
say anything
um at the risk of being a little bit of a buzz kale I wanted to say that I'm grateful for the folks here and out on
YouTube um you find it very difficult to go through the holidays like both
Thanksgiving and for the rest of the season um
those who find it uh difficult to remember when the last time
they had something to be grateful about was I just wanted to say that I'm grateful for you
and in the rinse I Zen tradition there's a practice of
looking at cohens which are like sort of inscrutable puzzle questions
um and for a lot of us these times kind of present themselves
as a co-op to work through um
yeah and I hope you keep pushing to figure out what the
answer is
Thank You Sage there's something that uh there's a
Tibetan teacher that I listen to every other Sunday unumtube chin and the last
talk from about two weeks ago was about
um welcoming what challenges us so there's always the possibility of
being thankful for the challenges I think they're
we don't always welcome them but uh
they hold potential
okay well thank you all I've really enjoyed hearing uh what you had to say and um
and yeah have a
have a good week