hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if you can hear my
audio okay give me thumbs up fantastic so yay great
sweet so hello welcome everyone and
um like to invite us to warm up the space is
something that we do as a part of our uh warm-up warming up the space with mitta
by saying hello by welcoming ourselves and each other and i start by
saying i'm nikki in mountain view california unseated olonyland welcome to have pr
and who wants to help warm up the space take it away
hi johnny in san francisco from ramayana to olonyland yes thank you
and hi bill from dallas who else wants to say how you can unmute yourself neil in new hampshire hi nia
this is don in decision hi don hi fred in oakland
hi fred marilyn from fairfield hi marilyn
manson nancy hi nancy
hey it's not from bali hey not from bali good morning afternoon what time is it
there it's morning good morning everyone good morning
anybody else wants to help warm up the space with their hello their greetings
from mark and terence and squint hi mark and terence and hi peggy
from you southern utah great nice
so i feel the space has been warmed up sufficiently and
friends are joining us also on youtube hello to you so let's formally get started
and the formal starting part of it is now posting information about happy hour
google groups in charge if you're new to happier you're warmly
welcomed to add yourself to the uh mailing list it's a low-key
uh low-traffic mailing list but it has a lot of heart
a light on volume heavy on heart and at this time i change
the settings on muting oneself won't be possible and last but not least i
uh turn on recording for audiodharma
here we go great so so hello and welcome to happy hour everyone
wherever you are of whatever time zone you're in and for today's happy hour
i uh wanted to um give the guided meditation
inspired from a few quotes on happiness i wanted to share a few quotes on
happiness i thought that would be fun to do that tonight um given that this is happy hour so let's
let's talk about happiness so here are a few quotes that i want to share with you
um [Music] first one is from mother teresa and she says
there is no key to happiness the door is always open
i love this one there is no key to happiness you know how people say the key to happiness is blah blah blah blah
blah there is no key to happiness the door is always open i love that i love
that which is kind of synonymous with what something that we've worked with and
i've shared before the title of this book happiness is a choice you make it's just a matter of choice it's always
available it's always here [Music]
and so that's one quote let's keep that one in mind i love that one oh here's
another one um here's this one is from the dalai lama
happiness is not something ready made it comes from your own
actions i like that too it's not something that is made but it
just comes from your actions and i think with to that i also add because in buddhism actions are not just physical
actions but actions of speech and mind and decisions are actions of the mind so
these two quotes are are related um
uh and this one is from marcus aurelius a stoic philosopher and there's a lot of
similarity by the way between stoicism and [Music]
buddhism and this is a great one actually
very little is needed to make a happy life it is all within yourself
in your way of thinking i'll read it one more time very little is needed to make a happy
life it is all within yourself in your way of thinking
and we've we've seen echoes of that in the other quotes and also in what we've practiced
oh this one i like to this is a good one um this one is from
um chinma yananda saraswati
and they say don't put the key to your happiness in someone else's pocket
this is a good one don't put the key to your happiness in someone else's
pocket such okay i'll give you maybe i'll share
one more these are so good i was having so much fun i couldn't choose which one to just choose one so i
figured i'll just you know as my little intro i'll share these different ones and and let you um
maybe for yourself see which one you relate to the most um
this one is from milton erickson and they say life will bring you pain
all by itself your responsibility is to create joy
life will bring you pain all by itself your responsibility is to create joy
okay one last one all right here's the last one okay really really last one
this is from friedrich koenig
and the quote is we tend to forget that happiness doesn't come as a result of
getting something we don't have but rather of recognizing and
appreciating what we do have one more time we tend to forget that
happiness doesn't come as a result of getting something we don't have
but rather of recognizing and appreciating what we do have
okay so i could continue but i think that's that's enough to set the stage for
for tonight's practice together um guided meditation i'll bring some of
these themes in and um yeah
let's begin together let's begin so i like to invite you all
to get into your meditation posture whether it's lying down
it's sitting whatever it might be
inviting yourself to land to land in your body
greeting creating this body this moment
whatever is present
if heartache is present welcoming that
embracing that sadness if
challenges in the body pain it's all okay we don't have to push anything away for
happiness to be here
it can contain everything so embracing embracing whatever is here
and releasing releasing the body
releasing the body the tightness the holding the tension [Music]
the forehead starting with the forehead
softening softening [Music]
this part of the body the forehead
usually signaling how much tension tightness there is in the rest of the body
softening the jaw
inviting your teeth to relax this is almost like you call on
say what how do i make that happen it's an invitation to make your face
relaxed
inviting your ears to relax
the muscles behind your face
no need to hold up any mask
as if you're attending a loving-kindness spa
and your face is getting an internal massage
lovingly relax to your muscles relax it's okay
every breath massaging the muscles of the face
hanging out here for a moment
no rush not rushing anywhere
inviting the breath to massage your neck and shoulders
inviting the breath to give a mental massage to your heart your heart center
holding making space for whatever is present
especially if there's tenderness you've had a challenging day
or days
fighting the abdomen the back to release
feel calmed cooled
or warmed whatever the need is by the breath
comforted comforted
sit bones landing on the seat released
releasing the tension your upper legs your knees your lower lips and feet
letting the breath move throughout the whole body calming soothing
like a lullaby
if there is pain in your heart
are any challenges in the body and the mind
let them be held kindly
as if there is this loving presence loving embrace holding you
holding whatever's challenging
with care with worms you don't have to be any other way any different than you than how you're
showing up right now
knowing that trusting that
for every being there are ten thousand sorrows
this being human is tough and
there are ten thousand joys
letting the challenges the sorrow
be held with kindness with compassion
and knowing that the capacity of our heart is expansive it can hold joy
our good fortune can turn to it
at any moment
not putting the key to our happiness in someone else's pocket
or even in our own pocket it's all no key needed
no key needed mother teresa said there is no key to
happiness the door is always open
not in getting what we want which is endless the list of what we want is
endless the mind will always come up something else to want
of course it does it's the nature of samsara wanting this
wanting that not a sin to want not a problem just
it's not doesn't bring happiness but to appreciate
appreciate
what there is already this amazing
life being alive
having agency being able to think being able to touch other people's lives
so many gifts
to be alive to have this precious human life
i'll read another quote from the dalai lama let it
drop into your body into your heart
see what might bubble up
every day think as you wake up
today i am fortunate to be alive
i have a precious human life
i am not going to waste it
i am going to use all my energies to develop myself
to expand my heart out to others
to achieve enlightenment for the benefit of all beings
i'll read the quote one more time
not to think about it let it shower your heart
feeling the energy of this quote in your heart and your body
maybe something [Music] rings true for you
comes alive here we go
every day think as you wake up
today i am fortunate to be alive
i have a precious human life
i am not going to waste it
i am going to use all my energies to develop myself
to expand my heart out to others
to achieve enlightenment for the benefit of all beings
let us sit with the reverberation of these words in
our bodies in our heart not thinking just breathing
or being breathed see what else might bubble up
profound time for reflection in silence externally and maybe even
internally
and whatever arises whatever percolates can we have
kindness acceptance towards whatever arises
even if it's a crowd of sorrows can we be kind to whatever arises
mated with a smile
a generous smile
the security blanket safety blanket
and also knowing that every moment we can turn we can
know that our heart is so expensive you can contain challenges can contain
joy aspiration to contain happiness
knowing the blessings of our precious human birth
and all the opportunities we have been given
all the gifts we have
every day think as you wake up
today i'm fortunate to be alive
i have a precious human life
i am not going to waste it
i'm going to use all my energies
to develop myself
to expand my heart to others
to achieve enlightenment
for the benefit of all beings
as we approach the end of this practice period
knowing in your heart that you are cultivating yourself
you're using your energies to extend your heart
to others to yourself to others through mental
that you are walking this path towards awakening
and knowing this not evaluating your progress every moment every five
minutes but knowing that you are practicing
this in and of itself is a cause for happiness
[Music] knowing this
brings up happiness in the heart
and let us together gift with generosity another act of cultivation
generously give generously offer our goodness
our actions of mind speech and intention [Music]
decision to create joy happiness to extend our heart
offer this goodness to all beings everywhere may all beings be happy
may all things be free including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have some time for any reflections you like to share
anything that came up any questions any complaints everything is welcome
as we've weaved through few themes through quotes unhappiness and
joy that it's about turning our minds to it
and also the inspiring invitation
from the dalai lama any reflections that came up for you anything that
shifted or moved and [Music]
or anything that didn't work it's all okay
sharing your reflections for the benefit of others fred i see your hand or
trying to raise your hand i say it's a clap but i think you're trying to raise your hand i was touring thank you sure
um so i i i just like to say what i experienced and see
see what you say um so i was feeling
a little agitation um you know some sorrow
and i was trying to then [Music]
open my heart simultaneously so that all these things would exist
together um not like a mental process
where you can't really think of three disparate things
simultaneously it seems that emotionally or psychologically you can
i think and um i wasn't trying to have a battle royale
between them but just um let them
coexist because they were going to anyway though though maybe maybe the sadness
and agitation would would be there without my bidding and i needed to
um to open up to the heart being
more more welcoming and and and more loving um
so that's my experience and um [Music]
what do you think love it love it fred i i love how you're talking
about these um disparate perhaps or different
um emotion states coexisting their sense of um
sadness agitation and then opening your heart opening your heart letting them
coexist in their way like it's it's that's what i'm hearing there's this coexistence of
and and i think that's what i was actually inviting you to do tonight which is invite allow
the the heartache or challenge to be there and for it
for there to be also be a soothing for it to be a soothing comforting and welcoming of it and to know that maybe
there could be a little bit of joy happiness acknowledging that oh yeah there are gifts here as well as
aspiration so it's like a big soup it's it's like that's our human condition
right all of these things present at the same time um so that was that was the crux of my
invitation and what i'm hearing is that actually yeah you were working with that like yeah it's not like i'm pitting them against
it's not like the comforting supposed to make them go away it's like yeah it's all present that's what i'm hearing was
what's happening for you and that's lovely i don't have a sense of it being
a success you know it's just all things are present yeah and i
i've been thinking um off and on sometimes during happy hour of the ending of a novel that i'm
embarrassed to say i can't remember but it was written by anthony mara
and it involves um really terrible things that happened in the
chechen war and at the very end there are a couple of survivors who are
maintaining a hospital in the midst of immense suffering and they do this with a kind of
they do it with duty and determination and occasionally joy
against all odds of things turning out well but but a young girl escapes and they
know that she's alive and that she will go on to do good things in the world she's like
their she's their heart who is their who is their missionary out in the world
it's um it's almost worth the pain of reading this book to reach the the last pages of
it um so anyway thank you um thank you fred
thanks for sharing that and and also what you're sharing about the the book
there's a sense of yes even in the midst of so much challenges
there was sense of joy that you were talking about this book and and also referring back and connecting that to
what you were saying it doesn't feel like a sense of success or like oh yeah i've managed and yet that is what the
quote-unquote success here is is it's allowing all of this to be it's is the
is the recognition that's it it's the recognition that all of this can be
that the sadness the challenge can be there with the comforting the soothing
the meta and with the aspiration and with the joy that all of these can be present together it doesn't have to be
one or the other and actually that is amazing you you may see you know i i
wonder if you you feel like there is is there more to this well maybe there is more to it maybe there isn't maybe
this this is it maybe this is exactly it i don't know if there's more you want to comment or if
it feels complete for you but yeah this is this is it this is exactly it
it's it's the full catastrophe of being human and can we embrace the beauty of
the full catastrophe as you beautifully just talked about
thank you thank you fred thank you yeah
sophie and one reflection
um one reflection coming privately and
uh it is i have been feeling jealous and being left out for the past week i tried
to be mindful of it but it feels a bit overwhelming i was wondering if you have
any suggestions on how to be with it yeah yeah um
yeah um
i think being mindful of it um it's the person
who wrote the reflection you know when when jealousy or envy arises
feeling left out i think um what can be
even more helpful than than just being mindful of it mindful of it is like okay
i know you're there i know you're there but i would actually recommend being with it
with compassion really holding it with compassion because there's a lot of pain
when one is feeling left out one's feeling envious just there's so much
pain so holding that pain with a lot of compassion instead of blaming oneself like oh you shouldn't be jealous you
should be you should rise and rise above as well in this moment sweetheart it's okay it's just it's hurting for whatever
cause and conditions in the past childhood this that the world zeitgeist
yeah this is this is what's here right now so that's that's what i would invite
the person who wrote that and others who might be going through this to to
really turn towards it with compassion just give it a lot of space hold it with compassion
and see what it might what's underneath it what's underneath the feeling jealous
feeling left out what is and is and as you hold it with compassion and care
maybe there is a sense of generosity that arises from that generosity towards
yourself generosity towards others when it is cared for when it is really held
completely i hope that makes sense if you give the the
hurt attention and really hold it with compassion and some generosity from the
hurt can arise you're welcome
when reflection on youtube touch the nerve the guided meditation i think they're referring to
so many tears and so much love and comfort thank you ah thank you for sharing that
lovely so dear friends let's turn as the dalai lama talks about
to expand my heart to others let's expand our heart to others
in small groups so i'll create the breakout rooms and see if you can extend your heart to others
in any way that that is accessible extend your heart to yourself
um not pushing not trying too hard but just extending your heart
what what is it like to to show up with an extended heart that holds
suffering and joy and aspiration and and
jealousy and all just it just holds holds the full catastrophe of being human for yourself and for others
and again speaking just from your own experience not managing others or or
managing the group just offering what you like also you can just offer your silence
when your turn comes a pass for one sentence or you're one one
nugget of one of thought the next person the next person they'll come back to you so
you'll go through it a few times so the rooms are created
and um actually hold on let me
there we go the rooms are created take care of yourselves take care of each
other here we go
okay the rooms are closed we're all back and we are at time so
i'm thinking we let's respect the the time i will stay a
couple of minutes extra on zoom if there are new reflections questions you like to share but let's bring this session to a close
i hope you had a a nice time connecting with each other thank you all for showing up for
practicing for cultivating your heart extending your heart to others may all beings be well may all beings be
free including ourselves
thanks everyone