so welcome welcome nice to see you all
hmm that was a very nice fit for me i i kind of
got settled in and felt kind of cozy [Laughter]
so today i'd like to continue on this series of teachings that i'm doing on
the seven factors of awakening
i like this idea that there's these certain factors that support awakening
like there's and then i'm going to talk a little bit about how we can cultivate them
sometimes we might have this feeling and i know i certainly did for quite a long time like
i don't know finding more freedom just seemed like it might be some random thing that happens or
if the conditions were just right you know or something like that
but there's some factors of awakening 0.2 that we can cultivate we can work with these things we can
help create the conditions in which there's more freedom in our lives
i'll talk a little bit more about that but today is the fifth factor which is tranquility
pasetti in pali probably we all know this idea what
tranquility is it's peaceful or calm
serenity contentment but maybe it's worthwhile spending a
little but a little bit talking about what it's not because sometimes we might have this
idea that um tranquility is just about
being quiet and there is a way in which it certainly is about being quiet
but we might think that it's just the absence of moving or the absence of making noises or something like this
or maybe something that it's more closely related to sometimes we might
use this expression near enemy something that looks like that but isn't
it's like this sleepiness right when you kind of have this certain amount of relaxation before you drift
off to sleep that's not quite the same thing as tranquility even though
there is certainly some tranquility there but the tranquility that's the factor of
awakening has a certain alertness to it even though
there's not activity it doesn't mean that the mind is kind of like checked out and there's some dullness or
some i don't know just not really being present
so it's not also it's not a complacency where or a lack of energy
where we might just be kind of a dolly sitting there right this is kind of it's not really tranquility
tranquility still has this uprightness but it has maybe we might say
just the right amount of energy not too much and not too little
right and this is something we always practice with is you know what is the right amount of energy what's the right amount of effort
and i'd like to say this is part of the art of practice it's not like we dial it in once and we have it and we never have to
work with it again maybe i'll say something else about tranquility it's not like this bored
indifferent disengaged like yes okay i'll sit here upright if
you're meditating and but we're off you know in some fantasy
or about what we're going to do as soon as the the dang bell rings or something like this
so tranquility it does it has a certain amount of alertness but and the mind is
certainly present and the body has some ease to it
it's other type of you know relaxation and it's similar to what we might say equanimity
but equanimity is pointing more towards like a view that we have and i'll talk more about equanimity it's
also a factor of awakening it's the seventh one whereas tranquility is more kind of a
feeling in the body this non-agitation kind of a
contentment so
maybe i'll just say i mentioned that tranquility is the fifth effect of awakening equanimity is the
seventh i'll just read the list here i'll say the list mindfulness investigation
energy joy tranquility concentration
equanimity and there is a way in which we could make a story about how one leads to the
each of the others we could start with mindfulness mindfulness can be a support all the way through or there's a way in
which we can just practice and cultivate each one individually it's a little bit of both
happening at the same time but i think it's noteworthy that in this list that
tranquility follows joy because when there's a certain amount of
joy and we feel that and we're like saturated with it
then there's can be a sense of no more looking for something else
no more thinking like gosh i wish things were different this is terrible
right when there's a certain amount of joy there can be a settling of that it can be so subtle and sometimes really
obvious a settling of that leaning forward looking for something else the next thing
looking for something better or something that has is more satisfying
so i think it's noteworthy that tranquility follows joy but it's not the only way to get to
tranquility we don't have to fill ourselves up purposely trying to get as happy as we can
so that we can have some tranquility
but instead i'll talk a little bit about um so what is part of the role of tranquility in
our practice and then i'll talk a little bit about how we can cultivate it
so part of the role is there's a way in which when there's some quieting down
then there's this softening of this persistent
feeling that something has to happen this persistent feeling of wanting to be entertained or
persistent feeling of wanting to feel like we're in control or that we're alive or something like this
when that has quieted down there's a lot of healing
that can happen and i'll just use this generic word
healing there's it's all the different things it can be
physical healing i'm not here to say that it's a miracle tranquility and mindfulness is
i know it can have a lot of shifts in people's life that can be really support for something different to show up but
there's a way in which just being quiet can be a tremendous support
for whatever's happening in our lives and sometimes this being quiet means that the inner critic
has settled down this kind of way in which we often beat ourselves up or
thinking like you should do this or you shouldn't have done that or you know this kind of also this persistent inner
voice we might have sometimes so when there's some tranquility that
inner critic has softened when that inner critic has softened then there can be this
opening and relaxation and we're maybe a little bit more available to
examine what's really happening or what's what is the wise thing to do or maybe
try something different or make room for some new ideas or some new thoughts to
arise so this tranquility can serve as a tremendous resource
in our lives and to be able to have know that it's
even possible and to have to cultivate it and develop it can be a real support
so one way that it can be a support i talked about how can allow healing and maybe a little bit of
space for something new to arise but some of this what's new to arise
might be wisdom i think we all know that when we're
agitated we don't have access to our best wisdom we don't have access to the best
versions of ourselves so gil franstal says
if you need wisdom try tranquility first
tranquility helps create the conditions for some wisdom to arise often we can't just you know conjure up wisdom
so tranquility is a way which can really be a support for as i said like the best versions of
ourselves and in this tradition of meditation and this
tradition of buddhism we focus on the development of insight
this scene deeply into our experiences deeply
into our lives so that we can see them differently and we can understand them differently
and with that understanding there's can bring a certain sense of freedom there can be
a realization like oh i don't need these things that i'm
really holding on to i don't need to prove that i'm right all the time
i don't need to bolster up this sense of self and make sure everybody
knows how wonderful i am or how they don't know how i think i'm not wonderful this
way in which we try to hide from other people and put up these
walls so these insights
often can arise when we have some of this tranquility and it serves like we might say it's like the best possible
soil for wisdom to grow and insights to grow
so in this way tranquility does support awakening it's an awakening factor supports liberation
because it helps creates the conditions in which not only can there be some wisdom that
arises some insights that arise but i think all of us know without my
having to say this that tranquility arises when there is
not a lot of holding on for dear life right there's a certain amount of
letting go there's a certain amount of ease that has to arise when there's some
tranquility and the same movement these exact same movement of letting go
the letting go that supports tranquility is the same letting go that supports awakening
awakening is a really deep letting go and so when the mind starts to quiet and
i'll talk a little bit more about this when i talk about the next awakening factor concentration
but when the mind and the body start to settle it starts to become more clear the way
in which we're clenching the ways in which we're holding the places that aren't tranquil just really become more
evident and so maybe there's a way in which in
that presence of some tranquility there can be a little bit more softening and letting go and that movement is the
exact same movement for awakening and whether it's a big shazam awakening
or just a little bit more freedom in our lives all of them have the same quality
of abandoning giving up relinquishing letting go
so maybe you'll have this idea like okay it sounds like a
reasonable thing this tranquility but how do we cultivate it
maybe the obvious one is meditation practice
i think probably all forms of meditation whatever form you do like buddhist or
not you know just really supports tranquility
and we might there's this way then
we might think that well i just can do insight or i can do concentration
or i can do living kindness those are kind of the three primary meditations that we do in this tradition
maybe i'll say that for the most part when we do
meditation on the breath which is often i think often when we teach introduction to meditation when we
teach mindfulness we often have this starting with the breath
something that can be a support to support tranquility
is two things one for the most part not to control the breath
as best you can i certainly went through this phase where i was like controlling the breath
that was like the only way i knew how to be aware of it was to somehow be manipulating it and
engineering and something at the same time i was paying attention like somehow i knew i was paying attention
because i was changing it
and i kind of struggled for a long time like i don't know how to pay attention without changing it
i'll just say that this is something that just kind of went away over time and so this might be a season of
practice in which you feel like oh i'm changing i don't want to change it
but maybe you can just soften about wanting to not change it if you notice
that you're settling subtly manipulating the breath
just notice we don't have to add additional problems on top of it just notice like
oh yeah okay here's a little bit of changing the breath
because there's a way in which we might be trying to control so many things in our lives
and why not right we want to control things we want to feel like we're in control the truth is we're not as nearly
as much as we think we are right but we want to feel like we are and so
it just kind of comes over into our meditation practice with controlling the
breath so now having said that
now i'm going to say to support if you're feeling really agitated and you're doing some meditation to support some ease
is to maybe pay a little bit of extra attention if this makes any sense
to the exhale a little bit more emphasis to the exhale
just maybe like to all the way to the end of the exhale notice in the beginning of
the inhale and there might be a way that can be like mindfulness all to the exhale for me i kind of has this feeling
it's going down and then there might be a way in which the mind darts away
okay here's another exhale but just noticing there's a way in which the
exhale really supports some ease
but one thing that we notice that when we're trying to meditate any kind of meditation and when
we're trying to cultivate tranquility tranquility will arise anytime we meditate
but if we have this idea we want to cultivate tranquility what we might be noticing is the
non-tranquility that's present
and we can work with that restlessness
worry anxiety these types of things
and very often we come to meditation as a way to work with these things
so one thing i'll say is like to understand restlessness agitation anxiety
probably the most helpful thing that we can do is to understand it
to get familiar with it this agitation which is exactly what we don't want to
do we want to make it go away but there's a way in which if we
understand it understand the conditions in which it really arises or what it feels like it
certainly takes a little bit of time we have to hang out with the restlessness we have to hang out with the anxiety
but this can serve us so much in our lives it can really make a big difference so
the first thing i'll say kind of like to work with the restlessness the non-tranquility is to hang out with it
how does it feel in the body how does it feel in the mind
there might be a way in which it feels like okay in the mind it just feels like i've heard the girl say this and i
really liked it like ping-pong balls bouncing around inside so is there a way that we can
just feel like we're bigger so maybe our awareness is bigger or just
like feel the maybe there's even feel like a bubble around us or something so that there's a
little bit more room for the ping-pong balls to bounce around
we're not insisting that they go away we're just making space for them
so this is something that we can do just maybe with the idea i'm doing this with my arms because i feel like this often
when i'm meditating that i'm creating if i feel like i need space i feel like i'm kind of creating a bubble in front of me
a bubble with my awareness also again i'll credit gil for this
something that um i appreciate is like this imagination that um you're
in an elevator and this really did happen to me i'm not a very tall person and i was in
the elevator and then this whole basketball team got in the elevator with
me and we were all crammed in there right and everybody's so much taller than me
and there's this feeling like i had this little like get me out of here it just wasn't a good feeling
so this feeling of maybe like being crammed in and then you're with the people and
you're in the way that gail explained it and this was not the case for me but like what if they're really smelly
and their clothes have all these stains on them or something like this really tall and big you know
that you're feeling um i don't know claustrophobic and then what if the elevator opens the
elevator door opens and you're in a beautiful cathedral
then you just take one or two three steps
and everybody they're all still there but they all just kind of move out into this cathedral
is there a way that you know without making this a big complicated
um thing that we're doing like just bring to mind if you've been in a place with
high ceilings or that big windows that you felt like wow
i had those feelings like going through some of these cathedrals in europe like wow
like this amazing feeling so there's a way we can incline the mind that way
and recognizing that there might still be some agitation but it just stops becoming so much of a problem
and then in the agitation that things can calm down
so in the mind agitation restlessness anxiety these things they might show up
in so many different ways maybe where the scattered thinking we can't quite land or focus on anything or
we feel like it's distracted by everything we have this in our daily lives we walk into a room wait
why am i here you know it's driving past our exits
these types of things but this restlessness this
non-tranquility it might be less noticeable if it's our constant companion
it's not uncommon these days for us to just be agitated
if you read the news a lot if you're on social media a lot if you have a job in
which it makes you feel frazzled or you have an environment which makes you feel frazzled
there's a way in which you can just feel like well this is what it means to be alive
is to have this certain amount of buzziness that's not tranquil
and i'd like to say that there can't be really be some ease that is available to us as humans
is possible but i also want to point to
maybe if it's our constant companion it's difficult to recognize but i also want to point to sometimes
we have this mixed relationship with this idea of relaxation or tranquility
we might feel like yeah i need to relax i need to be tranquil
and yet we're hesitant to get settled we're
reluctant to let go of whatever it is that's fueling the
buzziness we might not want to let go of these
anxious thoughts instead we might try to just distract ourselves from them by being busy or
doing something that increases or just sustains the
restlessness but there might also be this way in
which we want to shield ourselves we think that we're protecting ourselves
from avoiding any big emotional swings or something we don't want to get quiet
because we know we're just going to be anxious or restless later so we might as well just be restless all the time
because there's something about getting quiet and still
and then when that ends there's a disappointment or
something that just feels worse than just regular restlessness
but i'd like to encourage us to find a way in which we can get settled
because as i said earlier it's from those more settled places where the greater wisdom and the best versions of
ourselves can show up in which there can be some letting go
and i'll talk a little bit about that in a moment here but i also want to say that
there's also another reason why we are hesitant reluctant to let go of some
restlessness or it's because there's a way in which our
mind is thinking that it's solving a problem by just ruminating over something over
and over and over and over again i had this happen earlier this week i
was going to do something i'd never done before and there's a lot of things like i'm not
sure i know how to do this and i don't know i was just nervous about it
and i found myself like playing it over in my mind again and again like this actually is not useful
i'm either going to do it or i'm not going to do it and it was one of those things like if i didn't know how to do it well it would have been fine right to
know tragedy so this is just that mind you know our
wanting to feel like we're in control we want to feel like we're solving problems and instead we end up just
becoming restless and agitated but i want to say there's a good reason like we don't have to beat ourselves up
that we're this way our environments certainly support right
we have these huge industries that their sole purpose is to get us
agitated and distracted right all these apps on our phones and social media make us feel like we need to do
something else or advertising make us feel like we need something else right so i think we
can allow ourselves like oh okay this is what it is of course this is what it is
so practicing with restlessness recognizing how it feels in the body recognizing
giving ourselves a break that we might be reluctant to do this
but is there a way in which we can
let go of the beliefs that support this idea of restlessness
this movement oh yeah that's just a thought
it's just a belief i have this idea that if i think about this again and again
it's going to somehow be helpful or if i maintain this distracted
buzziness that is going to be helpful
but there's other types of beliefs that really support this having really strong opinions
that's a way of which holding on and i'm not saying that we don't have to
have any opinions and i'm not saying that we have to tolerate everything but there's a way if we have this really
strong opinion then it sets up like no all those people are wrong and i'm right
and we have to somehow make sure that we've rehearsed all the
reasons why they're wrong and we're right and this holding on just the holding on itself is agitating
and along those lines is can we soften some of these judgments judgments about
ourselves judgments about others things should be this way things that should not be that way
can we just let those go or soften them as best we can
so here's this uh the buddha talks about this uh a little bit and one of these suit does
and here he's talking about can we let go of some of these beliefs can we let go of some of these attachments
these attachments like i'm the one that knows i'm the one that has it right
those people are bad and i'm good or something like this which sounds
ridiculous when i'm saying this but there's might be subtle ways in which this is showing up
and can we just say yeah okay this is the belief i have right now
doesn't mean it's true it's just a belief i have right now so the buddha he's in this quote he's
pointing to can we let go of whatever it is that's binding us
whether it's a belief or an attachment and he starts by giving a simile
suppose there were a bull elephant with tusks like chariot poles able to draw a
heavy load and battle hardened we don't have elephants so much here in
redwood city but you know elephants are giant and have tusks like chariot poles are
really long and battle hard end right it knows how to go in it's tough right this
big giant big tough thing and suppose this elephant were bound
with a strong harness but just by twisting its body a little it
would snap apart its bonds and go wherever it wants we can imagine this
elephants are giant creatures would it be right to say that for that
elephant that strong harness is a strong firm stout
bond no for that elephant that harness is weak
feeble rotten and insubstantial
and then the buddha says in the same way when some people are told by me to
abandon this beliefs attachments whatever it is we find
ourselves really holding on to and it's amazing all the things that we can hold on to
when some people are told by me to abandon things they say what
i just have to abandon this trivial insignificant thing as this a belief might think like it's insignificant
and when the blessed one tells them to abandon it they abandon it and they don't nurse bitterness towards
me towards the buddha and when the practitioners who wish to
train have abandoned that they live relaxed
unruffled their hearts free as wild dear
so these attachments we might have he's saying that there's a way in which we can abandon or we can break these
these bonds we can by letting go
and then of course there's the opposite so the opposite of the elephant in
the suit is a quail i don't know if california quails are the same as what they have in india but
california they're so cute right these little creatures they run along and they have these
little things on their head they're like so adorable but they ran like really fast all over it
suppose a quail was tied with a vine and was waiting there to be injured caged or
killed you know just being stuck and this might even happen i don't know
quail might get tangled up with a vine would it be right to say that for that
quail that vine is weak feeble rotten and insubstantial
no for that quail that vine is a strong firm
stout bond a tie that is not rotted and is a heavy yoke
in the same way when people are told by me to give something up
to abandon to let go they say what such a trivial and significant thing is this
this teacher is too strict and they don't give it up
and they nurse bitterness towards the teacher like i can't believe they're asking me
to let go or soften or loosen this thing
and for those practitioners that trivial insignificant thing actually becomes a strong firm stout
bond a tie that is not rotted a heavy yoke
so something for us to think about what is it that we're holding on what are these
bonds is there some softening some letting go that we can do
so that we can live relaxed unruffled with hearts free as wild deer
as in this simile maybe i'll say a few more things here
about how we might do that some of them are obvious
relaxing the body we do some of that in a meditation practice sometimes if i'm doing a guided
meditation i will start with relaxing the body i'll lead us and relaxing the body
one is to just continue sitting often tranquility finds us right if we're sitting long enough
one is is there a way to cultivate contentment and gratitude in one's life
like this is enough gratitude practice can be so supportive
and this sense of like i i don't need more i don't have to
succumb to this fear of missing out or instead have like maybe the joy of missing out or something like this
and then of course tranquility is a support for tranquility
so the ways if we notice that the restlessness
as has quieted or maybe there isn't a lot of restlessness to just notice that
calmness it might be subtle but just noticing that calmness helps support more
calmness help support more tranquilly appreciating when it's there and noticing it
and then of course spending time alone spending time off of screens
spending time in nature i think i think everybody knows this right sometimes it's helpful to be reminded like oh yeah
it's good to spend time outside if we can't in nature
so tranquility is this factor of awakening so
great support for our lives and for our practice moving towards
greater and greater freedom so may you find some tranquility in your
life and may be a support for you thank you
so now i'd like to open it up if there are any questions somebody wants to say something
hi diana good evening i have so just to clarify from the text that you read or
the buddha's teachings on the elephant and the quail
it's not good to be tethered by the poles or the vine
to be tethered by the like you know how the quail was tethered by the vine yeah and and the the elephant was tethered by
the the those those poles or something it was tethered by a harness a harness harness sorry so you neither are good
yeah okay and this even this idea that like a harness we might think that oh
that's very uh it's significant but a big bowl could uh
be break does it won't be um [Music] tethered i guess by the harness
so but and sometimes we're quails sometimes we were held by things that are uh
maybe they don't seem like big things but they're they're
binding us and sometimes we're elephants but is there a way that we can be an
elephant with a little vine wait i said do i have that right
whatever it is i'm sorry like my mind just totally kind of left me so
if you can figure this out elephants quails vines and harnesses
thank you for this idea of letting go not being bound up yeah
anybody else have a comment
um thank you so much so as we were talking about um giving up agitation in certain parts of
our life i was thinking about a problem my own practice that comes up with like thoughts and
trying to like go back to the breath and things like that and i'm worried about it kind of can you
bring the microphone just a little bit closer i'm worried about a sort of like
recursion problem where you're like okay i'm going to create spaciousness in my mind like here's my bullet point list on
how i'm going to do that and like exert control over like spaciousness and then like
does that make sense you just kind of right so that you think that you're going to create spaciousness but the activity of creating spaciousness is
causing agitation yeah or it becomes like another thing to control yeah
yeah yeah this is something that is just going to happen that we're going to try to control things right this is what human
beings do but i think that as we i'll say one thing as meditation
sessions each individual session lasts longer then there's tends to be a little bit more uh tranquility that arises just
you know 45 minutes versus 30 minutes versus 15 minutes or something like that
and also i think that there's something about repetition that the mind and the body they just
recognize that oh yeah this is possible uh this little bit of ease and it just becomes easier and easier to access it
but in the beginning there is some more intentional and control that we're doing intentionally to get it there is did i
address your question yes thank you so much yeah yeah i mean of course right humans we we want
to do this we want to fix things we want to be comfortable
hi diana thank you um
i think that a lot of time in edge if i'm agitated or
upset about something that the walking meditation or some physical
activity some repetitive physical activity is often freeing just because it
somehow releases some sort of energy um
but is that the purpose of walking meditation is that why walking meditation became a
thing uh first of all i'll say thank you for
saying that nancy that's an excellent idea right we can like go walk in outside support tranquility or sometimes
like doing the dishes or some crafts thing that we love to do or something like that
so i think walking meditation became a thing because bodies cannot sit
for so many hours right we're just not built to do that unless you're in some really really deep
states then you can sit for longer so it's a way walking meditation is a way to um not ruffle the mind and yet
move the body and i'll say something else it's also walk-in meditation it's a great way to
kind of like um support our energy sometimes it brings our energy up if we're kind of
like you know really dull or in our sitting or it dissipates energy if we're
feeling restlessness so maybe that's
okay okay so thank you all for your kind attention
and i'll stay up here if anybody wants to come up and talk or have a question they'd like to
ask without a microphone so thank you