so good morning and good day as we continue with the mindfulness of
the body exercises and um
the exercise we're doing now is usually called the four elements
and i prefer the four properties but what's nice about calling it the
elements is the way that it connects us to
the natural world and so the elements or properties associated with
the earth with water with fire and with air
and um and uh these are all properties that are
essential for life and we take them in and and
they animate us we animate them and the uh but by one of the nice things
about seeing it this connection with the earth with the natural world around us
is for some people it begins to be an antidote to excessive self-preoccupation
excessive living in our head with ideas of me myself and mine
antidote to conceit and antidote to kind of the constructive aspect of the mind that constructs
somewhat an edifice or um
palaces of ideas and concepts and selves and histories and all these things that are
second nature for many people and there's certainly a place for that in life an important part of life
to see the whole but here in order to free ourselves from some of the deleterious effects of this
constructive activity of the mind we begin to deconstruct it
and deconstruct the concepts and take us back to the elemental level
to the building blocks of our experience to the core
sensations core sense data that we take in through our body with which we construct
much of the world that we live in and so uh learning to
tune in and get concentrated on the these properties these sensations in the body
can do a phenomenal job in teaching us how not to get caught in the constructs
and the ideas it's a way of freeing ourselves from them temporarily to have a radically different experience
of ourselves that gives a different reference point for living a free life
so these are sensations that we have the elements these
properties are known experienced through feeling the different sensations in our body
and and and to experience it just as sensations
independent on the ideas that are then built on those sensations
so we'll start with a simple exercise that i i kind of like to do i hope that you're
content to do it with me again and we'll build on that
so just gently closing your eyes
and maybe a few moments of settling in whatever way you
have
maybe a few moments of breathing deeply and
relaxing
and when you settle in and relax into your body you're relaxing into something which is
quite natural part of the natural world
as natural and perhaps as wondrous as a tree
as a bird flying through the sky
there's a gopher in the ground or squirrel scampering up a tree
a butterfly flying in the air a hummingbird
a river an ocean
all the wondrous parts of nature we're equally part of it is all those
things our body is
so then to begin now with sitting quietly
and begin sensing and feeling
the sensations of one of your hands
and perhaps you can feel pulsing and tingling
maybe something that feels comparable to the flow of blood through your fingers
feeling the contact of the hand against some surface
your legs the other hand
perhaps there's sensations of some weight heaviness or lightness
warmth coolness maybe both on different sides of the
hand
certain sensations in the palm of the hand
sensations on the back of the hand
sensations of the fingers
and if you become attuned to the sensations themselves
as natural phenomena you might even be able to feel them the
sensations of them independent of any idea of and
the way the sensations feel themselves
sensing whatever is sensitive enough to sense sensations
are not really two separate things sensing and sensation occur together
and we're in the location where sensing and sensations occur together
they occur before the mind has ideas
before the mind identifies it certainly with something as complicated
as hand or my hand
or judgments this is a good hand or a bad hand or anything
the sensations and sensing occur together
almost as if for themselves there is no hand there's just themselves the sensing
the sensations come and go
arise and pass
the energetics of them
originally derived from the energy of the sun
the solidity weight hardness softness
are considered properties of the earth
warmth and coolness are properties of fire
seeing if you can notice how different it is to experience sensations of your hand
without ideas of me myself and mine
how if you go into my hand or it should be this way or something it pulls you away
into the control tower but if you
relax into the hand into the sensations and let them just be
there by themselves
and now turning your attention to the area in your body
where you normally experience your breathing
and not so much specifically focusing on the ex experience of breathing
but in that area of your body
have the same sensitivity to sensations as you had in the hand
if there's movement that's associated with the air element
the wind element
if there's temperature it's associated with
the fire element fire property
if as your chest or belly expand if you feel that the expansion
the pressure the contraction
is considered part of the water element
a water holds things together
creates pressure
sensations of hardness and softness
weight are the earth element the earth property
and the exercise is one of becoming
attuned to the fundamental
sensation level of experience which is the building block more
complicated worlds we live in but it begins with sensations
the sensing and the sensations occur together
and in the location where they occur
in and of itself those sensations have no concepts no ideas
no preferences
let go of ideas and thoughts and preferences
so you can rest awareness in the sensations themselves in that
area of the body content to be with a dancing
flow of sensations coming and going
getting closer to them the closer we get the more they become a
dance of sensations
all in the area of your body where you're breathing
[Music]
notice the way thinking pulls you out and away from
this natural phenomena of the body the processes of sensations coming and
going perhaps you can dip back in like dipping
into a pool of water settle back in
to these properties and elements of sensations
for a few minutes willingly surrendering
to just sensations of breathing in the body
gently noticing
the different sensations that come and go
choosing to stay with the sensations not the thinking
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to appreciate how much of our
body is part of the natural world
majority of our body is water
essential for our body is the air that we breathe in
and out
we are in a sense continuing the energies of the sun and
our digestion and our temperatures of our body and
and we have within us atoms and molecules
that have circulated around the world in many ways some of them have
been in other forms of life before you some of them come out of the ground
absorbed by plants that we eat
just about every part of our physical body
is a continuation of the earth and the natural life of the earth
our body and all its elements belong
as part of this earth you belong
here on this planet in this world
and to believe you don't is to have lost touch with this
elemental level of our life and its connection to the planet
and as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps you can appreciate that others belong here too
they also are the fruit of the earth
of this universe and to offer them
the right to be here to offer them to see them through the eyes
appreciates them too as an important part of this natural world
to support others to feel like they belong on this planet
maybe get gaze upon others with respect and care and love
maybe even irreverence that's freed from our self-centered
self-preoccupied ideas
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so hello everyone and i want to say that yesterday we had uh
some kind of technology
breakdown here and we don't know what it is yet but uh we have
hopefully bypassed the area of the problem as we try to figure out what happened
and so um
so maybe that today can function then also as a another introduction to this topic of
the what's classically called the four elements the four datu's in poly
d-a-d-h-a-t-u and um
it's uh the way that we can or the aspects of our felt experience
the way we experience things that can be seen as to be associated with uh elements
of the physical world that's around us and that of course i think it can have
very profound meanings associations and that sense of connection to that
the i prefer to translate this word dotu as properties
because elements implies to me like some kind of molecule some kind of
something you know very essential elemental whereas it doesn't have to mean that in
english of course the word element but so i kind of prefer property and because
property points to a property of something
so now this is the property of our body of our sensations that we're experiencing
and so there are four
and they're kind of they're always listed in particular order
earth water fire and air and the reason for that order is that um
there's a way in which the ancient indian cosmology or geography
believed that the earth um uh
is um you know that's the bottom and then there's the water floating on the earth and then uh above that there's the heat
and the and uh the fires that grow up come up into the air and then there's the air so
it's kind of like a progression and um
the um and to do this meditation on the four elements of four properties
is to take a very different lens a different perspective for a direct experience than
what many of us will normally live in which we live in ideas and concepts and ideas of things
so for example i have this big bell here and um and i could just kind of be
thinking about it as a bell and this is what a great bell remember who gave it to us it was a gift
and how wonderful that was to receive this gift and how we've used it for so many years and and different places we've used it and
ways we've used it and and i can be kind of in that world in the mind of memory thoughts ideas bell
and or i could change the lens of my experience
to not be in the ideas the history the memory and and what this proves about imc that it's
a really worthy meditation center because that is a good bell i can just kind of feel the weight of it
i can feel the smoothness of it the temperature of it feels cool to touch right now with my warm hands
i can feel some smoothness in it and also there's little indentations on the sides that i can feel it's kind of fun
to have my hands kind of rub across indentations and they come and go and
and and so i can get into the sensations
independent of it being a bowl a bell
and um and the bellness of it doesn't need to be relevant i can close my eyes and just
be with the sensations and it doesn't have to be a bell it could be something very different
so the you know so different lenses different perspective so we can have
and uh think of it maybe as a different magnifications that we do
and a particular um idea that uh exercise i like is that of
what has to do with i remember my sons had had a little kids book that a couple of
them i think that had involved you turn the pages and it's a kind of
picture of the same location kind of but at different
magnitudes of uh of focus i think they they went by magnitude of 10 i think and sometimes
you started the universe and went closer and closer in and in and you saw the earth and then a little town and then
the lawn and then the grass and then the cells and then you saw the
the atoms and and you kind of just depending on what magnification you use
you see different things and you can imagine for example for you if uh
if there was a satellite video that you would watch and it zoomed in on the neighborhood you
grew up in and that would be kind of fascinating to see oh they've changed that the house is no longer there they've redone it there
or that house hasn't changed at all there's a tree i used to climb in there's the house of my neighbor who was
so unjust because i know i broke his window and my threw my baseball through it but
he never returned it and and you know how could my favorite baseball and
and then though there's a neighbor that used to give us cookies and we always felt so safe playing in the tree in
front of that person's yard and i've come so far in my life since then or i haven't come anywhere in my
life since then all my problems derived from that time and so all this ideas come into play so
for the certain magnification but if we kind of drop in into just a tree we used to play in
and the whole different set of thoughts come up but then if we go closer into just a leaf
and beyond the leaf to the cells and beyond the cells to the atoms beyond the atoms into the subatomic particles
and suddenly there's all this space and vastness between all the particles and it's like amazing it's kind of like
looking into the great night sky and the amazing size of the universe
depending on the magnification we have a different relationship than what's going on
if we're always at that at the magnification level where it's all about me myself and mine
and my ideas my history what's done to me what wasn't done to me what i should do
it can be tiring exhausting it tends to be the place where there's a lot of attachment a lot of stress
and it can be a labyrinth and it could also be a buddhist terms a cycle of stress where
the very attempts to resolve it and get out of it those that level of practice
the level of life magnification just kind of spins the wheel more and more and we just kind of do more and more
it's like rearranging the deck tears in the titanic it's just like you know
we're always trying to make things better and to solve things but as long as it's based on
ideas of me myself and mine there probably is no real solution to a
final happiness but one way to find that the real change
is to change the magnification level to change the lens in which we see our experience
and that's not an easy thing to do because the attachments keep us in that
certain magnification level the level of these thoughts and histories and ideas
and so we're training ourselves to begin letting go of that place not to dismiss it or abandon it
so that we're not so attached to it and so we can see it in a fresh way we can learn to be free
and also to connect to ourselves at a different magnification level that reveals a different level of
experience different kind of processes that if we connect to them
are much more freeing much more liberating much more helpful for
experiencing something vast and free and liberating like really getting down into
the particle level of the atoms and and just wow this is all amazing
and so these this four element meditation is this shift of magnification the shift of uh to a
different lens of experience and it's very important to understand it's not a dismissal of other
magnification levels but for many of us it's an expansion of the lenses we can
use so we're not always in one lens one magnification level but where we can
have the ability to go between different ones and when it's helpful to go into this
element level there's a lot of wisdom to be discovered here and also a fair amount of healing
because some of the stresses that we apply to our system limit the healing qualities of the body
and mind but once we drop into this elemental level of these properties that of the
sensations there's a freeing of this stress and this this whole physical and also
mental system can operate much more harmoniously and it's remarkable what can start happening then
so to shift our attention um to um
to the the sensation level it's really a sensation meditation
um sensory awareness that we do and the pasta practices has thought uh was
taught to many of us the kind of mahasi practice from this teacher mahasi sayado
the instructions were to experience the movements of the belly as we were breathing
and and so it kind of people thought it was a breath folk breath meditation but in fact the emphasis was not on the
breathing the emphasis was on the sensations that came into play as the body breathed
and and to feel the you know all these sensations that come
into play and get closer and closer more intimate like really get into the magnification that just
we we are just there with the sensations and we're not there with the ideas and
concepts and stories around them and it can be quite relaxing and easeful to
drop all the stories and just be with the sensations as they come and go and that is kind of the core
uh really core aspect of the pasta practice so this four elements meditation
is really indire is really central to this tradition
even though we don't know not always so explicit about it
so that's what we'll do for a few days explore these four elements and these sensations and how to work with them
and um and hopefully you can appreciate this uh this particular lens or magnification
level of our experience and we'll find some fascination delight and maybe even some
freedom in in it so thank you very much and um
so i'll see you monday
i'll be here monday and i won't see you but i'll be with you and
a reminder that tomorrow morning imc and zoom
is hosting a mindfulness circle for black identified practitioners so if you're black and
and or know someone who's a black practitioner who would like to meet with other black practitioners
it's a wonderful the third time we're doing it and it's a wonderful gathering of practitioners so if it's relevant for
you and you're very welcome to attend and the information is on the what's new on imc's website so thank you