so hello everyone and welcome
and one of the
great possibilities of doing mindfulness meditation
is do let everything become calm and quiet in the mind
as much as possible so almost it's an undoing
and there's a many uh processes in the mind which are operating all the time in
our needed for our daily life and maybe the operation of it is not something we
consciously think about but uh when we sit and meditate and start
undoing non-doing in some deep way that's even some of these deeper
structures or processes of the mind can go for it to rest for a while take a
vacation much needed and um and to give you an example of
some of the deeper things is where where there's a very strong kind
of processes operating all the time seemingly effortlessly
um for our spatial awareness our location and space
and um and have a sense of where we are in spaces and objects around us and the
distances and all kinds of things goes on which is a healthy and important part of
human life but it is a process that the Mind does it's a
engagement and and it's possible for that to be quiet
take a break have a rest anyone do that then
there's no engagement in location and creating you know getting a sense of the
space and the distance and the location of things and things still have location but it's
just the mind is not operating in that way there's deep instincts around self mind
Lady of mine is a I think it's uh almost built into the hardware of our mind in
some deep way and this idea of my hand and apparently there are people who have
brain damage who don't have look at their hand and don't see it as their hand and it causes some problems for
them and at the same time as important is that sensibility is
it's possible to put that to rest and to sit here without any orientation
any thought any idea any intuition even that this is mine This Is Me
so this this leads to
uh freeing up awareness attention or attentional
capacities to be aware and attentive
without focusing on the usual objects usual concerns usual ways in which
Things Are it's opportunity for attention and awareness to to become clearer
without complications Simplicity of attention
Simplicity of awareness where in a sense there's no inside and
outside there's no should and shouldn't
there is no right and wrong
everything is allowed to be in some very thorough going
almost unconditional way for a few minutes as the mind gets quieter and calmer
and at some point in different people to different points there can be a feeling of or or a sense
say perception a knowing of awareness
that can feel very clear that feels
like it stands out by itself as if it's
has its own kind of presence
whereas usually we're concerned about what we're aware of now we've become more and more sensitive
to awareness itself how it feels to be aware
and because there's no location it might feel like awareness has no boundaries spacious very open wide
because we're not constructing orienting around self there can be a delightful
feeling that just being aware without any concern for Me Myself and mind and
all that that brings so this is not necessarily an easy thing
to experience but it does come as the mind gets very very quiet and still so I'll do this guided meditation
and maybe even even if your mind doesn't get still maybe if you kind of follow along enough
even with your imagination you get some feel or some sense some intuition of of
what the clear awareness might be like the seleucid awareness
so assuming um
they've got a meditation posture and to
appreciate that sitting here we are
relaxing and calming deeply
letting go of the concerns of the daily life
just letting go of all concerns taking a deep inhale
and on the exhale a ritual of
putting aside for now all your worldly concerns
they can be put up on the Shelf to be picked up later
relaxing and letting go
maybe closing the eyes and on the exhale relaxing the body
softening in the body
and letting the breathing return to normal
and is as if breathing attention together
is a reassuring friend let your attention move around your body
to find where your tense where you're holding and on the exhale relax that part
relax into the reassurance that awareness and breathing maybe
provides
and with this reassurance of breathing and awareness
touch the places in the mine where your tense
and tight and concerned about things touch it with a breath touch it with
awareness to reassure it
it's okay for now it's okay to relax and put these things aside
and relax in in any tension or strain connected to
doing the meditation
with a reassuring Touch of awareness
your strain and tension dissolve and settle
it's enough just to be aware
and imagine that you're standing on a large
wide field maybe of beautiful
grass grassland grass gently
waving in the wind and the breeze clear skies maybe some clouds and birds
maybe it's so big this field it goes out through the Horizon you don't see the edge
but it's easy to see everything
settling back maybe sitting under an oak tree in the
shade
and just allow whatever comes to awareness
to be there in the clarity of attention of knowing
nothing is right nothing is wrong just something to know
to be aware of in this vast field
no inside and no outside
just phenomenon that exists arises persists and passes
away
with their Assurance of attention of awareness
it may be breathing in the middle of it all
let that reassuring awareness be Broad and wide
360 degree awareness inside and outside
allowing experiences Sensations
to appear on their own nothing you have to do or reach for
look at carefully just know
what appears to awareness in whatever way that is
when the ears are open to sounds
There's No Boundaries and limits that the ears put on how far away the
sounds might be
when we see the eyes don't put a limit
just open to what comes without a boundary hard and fast
so with awareness awareness can have no boundaries
even no Center
such an awareness attention can feel clear
opened spacious
let everything rest abide in the spaciousness of the Mind
to here without doing anything with the hearing what's heard
to see without doing anything with what's seen
to sense without doing anything with
the sensations to think thoughts
without doing anything further with our thoughts
leaving everything alone to be itself
without getting involved or being for or against
resting in the reassurance of
being aware
instead of doing and reacting
maybe you can Intuit or sense the possibility of clarity
clear knowing clear seeing
clear hearing sensing
a Clarity of awareness
and if there is such Clarity or intimations of it
as if it's waiting for you let go into the clarity
and then staying quiet and calm whatever Way You Are
listen to this dedication of Merit without participating
without doing it yourself but as if it is a
medicine for this boundless world
for yourself and for others like a fresh Breeze
moving through May whatever benefit
that has come from this meditation practice today
serve as a foundation for bringing goodness and kindness and
care into this world
so that their spreads throughout the land
an influence of kindness and care goodness
that spreads from person to person being to being
so that we live together on this planet caring for each other
promoting each other's happiness and safety
Peace and Freedom
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you so we come to the last talk on this five
part series on consciousness and I've emphasized that I don't really
know what Consciousness is but I have a premise an assumption
that it's not a thing it's not an entity it's not its own Standalone thing that
can exist independent of anything else but it's a little bit more the like a
um like a hologram Maybe a hologram can seem very real or very
fascinating and and it can be a hologram of a real object but the Hologram
um image doesn't exist except as a hologram and so Consciousness is a little bit
like a hologram it's it's kind of the combination of all the all the different
forms of faculties of attention we have combining and working together
or being gathered together by the mind's capacity to construct to the mind's
capacity to have an image or a sense or an idea of the whole
and and this is part of what the Mind does it's a constructing
um apparatus it's reconstructing constructing our ideas of the world
ourselves all kinds of things the necessary part of being in this complicated world that
humans live in and we sometimes will reconstruct things
inaccurately we can see something then first glance we think it's a snake and
next glance we look at it and it's actually a stick on the ground and um so we the mind is reconstructing
things and so it's kind of like the Hologram that's all these pieces
but it's a beautiful thing Consciousness and it's very valuable it's wonderful to abide in it and have
the clarity because when awareness or Consciousness feels very clear and
relaxed and not entangled and caught up with all the concerns that we have and
the objects of attention then the Consciousness can feel have a
sense of clarity of openness spaciousness peacefulness qualities of
freedom qualities of happiness
it can be a kind of a rich world that seems to be in and of itself uh
independent of what is known and when the mind gets very calm and
quiet in meditation where we're not engaged with our thoughts engaged with
things of the world sometimes it becomes very clear that or a very clear sense that we're
aware there's awareness but no object of awareness it's almost as if awareness stands out
by itself Consciousness conscious but not conscious of anything in particular that hologram can be that clear and
pristine and um in my meditation practice on
Retreats when it came to such a such Clarity and pristineness of um I went to my teacher and said I don't
know if I could I'm supposed to be a Buddhist because Buddhism teaches that everything is in constant and changing
and impermanent and I see that for everything except for this thing
Consciousness that seems to be Everlasting and permanent and rather than debating with me or
explaining it was different my teacher just said keep practicing keep looking
look and so I kept practicing and with a lot of confidence and faith in this
practice until the point came that I saw that Consciousness also isn't constant
can disappear can vanish and then it's Vanishing didn't mean that
I died and uh but rather there was a marvelous
uh unprecedented kind of experience of freedom and it can seem very frightening and
unusual to have this kind of Consciousness disappear and to experience that freedom from that
but I think it's one of the reasons why in Buddhism we don't um
reify Consciousness as a thing at least in the early Buddhism School the kind of the basis where I'm teaching from
where Consciousness is not seen as a thing or reified or permanent or
Transcendent or so something that lasts after we die
the um it's It Whatever Consciousness is it
itself is part of the inconstant changing nature of this world we live in and the freedom we're looking for is not
the freedom for an experience of anything including consciousness but something which is almost a
non-experience which is in between all experiences which is freedom the absence of clinging
and that is the most marvelous thing there is um and from Indies for me more marvelous
than this radical purity of awareness and consciousness
so as the Buddha teaches mindfulness practice he's teaching all these
different forms of attention that we can do he teaches um recognition the clear knowing clear
recognition of what's happening so important not to be overlooked not to be bypassed
he teaches sensing the kind of embodied feeling of experience
sensing of experience he teaches us sensitivity to the
pleasant and unpleasantness of experience he teaches observation as watching
seeing abiding resting in a seeing of things
and and when these all these become stronger and stronger more developed more highlighted less agitated less
preoccupied with our concerns then at some point awareness begins
standing out in highlight so much so that we know that we're aware
you know if I'm driving in the freeway and things are difficult and I'm late and I'm trying to deal with traffic and
trying to get ahead of all the other people because I'm late I'm not really aware that I'm aware I'm aware of the
cars around me and in that sense my awareness is impoverished
but to be aware of awareness that is a wealth that is fantastic
so finally when I get off the freeway and I decide I'm going to kind of meditate for 10 minutes before I
go to my meeting because I'm all frazzled then maybe everything quiets down enough at some point I know that I
know I know I'm present I know that I'm feeling I know that I'm seeing and and
so there's a kind of a higher order understanding knowledge perception
that we perceive that we're perceiving we know that we're perceiving and at some point the sense of awareness
a simple spacious kind of sense of What receives
every all perceptions all phenomena what kind of the medium through which it goes
and has no resistance to anything like the Hologram doesn't resist anything everything comes through that door of
the Hologram maybe to us and that sense of awareness
can be come strong so strong that it becomes more interesting or more the
kind of the focus of attention it itself is a focus of attention instead of
the other things in the world and it's kind of a paradigm shift for some people because some people's mind
their whole life has been about concerned about things objects of attention and objects of thought and and
just always kind of navigating the world of objects and things and aboutness what
we're thinking about but the paradigm shift is what is to
take a break a vacation for the Mind from focusing always focusing on something
to resting in itself awareness resting and awareness awareness knowing awareness
and in early Buddhism we're not reifying celebrating this as being the ultimate
in the final answer to everything but rather it's a there's so much
letting go so much ease so much trust in that place that sometimes will find that
that it's massaging or it's working even unconsciously it's massaging the places
of clinging and holding deep in our our psychology in our mind
and providing kind of the trust to prepare us for the time when the mind is ready the
heart is ready to let go of the deepest attachments the deepest clinging that we
live by and um and so this experience of awareness of clear awareness
that the Buddha focused on is there as a as a platform to help the Steep letting
go and um and the word the Buddha used for
this clear awareness I like to translate it as a lucid awareness is
p-a-t-e-s-s-a-t-i and patissati is uh this uh
awareness that's so clear and and present that we know that we're aware there's a
Clarity around it that you know that we as we sense
so the Buddha taught many forms of attention and that are leading to a
deeper and deeper concentration and simplicity of Mind Simplicity of attention
and it's a beautiful process to do this and there are other factors that come to
bear that are that influence this experience of simpler and simpler awareness or Consciousness are there
other faculties of the mind that affect the faculties of attention and we can maybe call those attitudes
the attitudes through which or by which we're aware and so I thought that maybe we can
continue this um the kind of series and maybe next week
and look at attitudes with a look at how attitudes might play a role in how we
um how we know the world how we know ourselves so
so thank you very much and um
and I hope that you have a nice weekend and maybe this weekend can be a time
when you a gift time to be curious about the nature of
awareness itself the nature of consciousness not to think figure out what it is
but to see what is it about the awareness what is it about consciousness that that's it is possible to rest in to
abide in and maybe you can find sit in a park or someplace looking at the sky or the
clouds or something someplace safe and reassuring assured and and kind of
explore what is this what would it be like to rest in awareness
thank you all