so good morning everyone and for those of you who were not here
yesterday i'm at spirit rock in marin county california
about an hour and a half north of imc
i'm teaching a retreat here um and uh through uh tomorrow so i'll be
doing the 7 a.m from here tomorrow morning as well and we have these wonderful um
rolling hills of the coast lots of oaks
if we're there might be uh lots of turkeys here and it's possible
that at some point we'll see the turkeys wandering around the background or the deer or something
so um and it's really nice for me to be
uh doing this outdoors um
and also these uh ren headland these these hills here
um my early buddhist practice was done at the green gulch zen center which is
on the coast in these hills here and uh when i lived there i did a lot i spent a
lot of time my days off hiking in these hills and mountains and and
the combination of the practice at the zen center and the walking in the mountains was the hills
was um an important formative time for me my meditation practice
so here we are so as an introduction to this meditation
um one of the premises that i'm offering you for what sati is
generally called mindfulness but which i like to call awareness is um
that it is a it is a natural form of awareness that's always here
but we're seldom established in it or seldom at rest in it or abiding in it
because the mind is busy in thoughts and desires and
trying to think of concerns about the future in the past and doing a lot of things
and so our activity our focus of attention is not on
this awareness itself and that the whole momentum movement of
doing mindfulness practices is to do those kinds of attentional practices
that helps us recognize and then strengthen and abide in rest in
this what can we call a natural awareness this awareness that's uh always here
but seldom um allowed to really show show us its full
potential one of the things that when people are doing mindfulness practice
one of the things that might interfere with the naturalness of resting in this awareness
and the simpler knowing which is um doesn't require much effort
is that we're making effort in the practice we're trying hard and we're leaning maybe a little bit
into the future like what trying to make something happen get something get concentrated or leaning into the future
to see can i really see here what's going on another approach is um to to
notice that we're aware and then uh
in a kind of way uh just uh wait in the awareness and not wait for
something to happen so much and just give time for things to be seen more
clearly um not rush off to the next thing but to recognize what's here
recognize that we're aware of what's here and then take a little bit of time to let what's here register more foot more
fully it's kind of like so it stands out more in relief
and so like here i'm sitting in the fog in these rolling hillsides
and you see a little bit of the hills behind me but when the fog is clear then you can see
the higher mountains there and there's more trees and you can see things with greater clarity
the things stand out in relief and then it's possible to take in more and more
perceive more of what's going on but not so much from trying too hard not trying at all
but rather lingering and allowing each thing to reveal itself
more fully because we're there for it and it might not be long it's uh we could do
this with the breathing where we're not ahead of ourselves trying to get accomplished something but
more we're being with the breathing so the breathing the different qualities
characteristics of breathing the movement the pressure the release of pressure um
is um stands out in highlight in relief
so maybe we can try this today and so to assume
a appropriate meditation posture for
yourself
and to gently close your eyes
and just not trying to do anything more
but to be to notice what stands out in relief for you
as you sit quietly with your eyes closed
not thinking about something and realizing you you know forgot to turn off the lights
in the living room or something but what's what's here
in your body at this time in your senses if you stay here to relax into
here stands out in highlight
to open this awareness to your body
what is revealed what's what stands out in relief
in the range of things you can experience in your body
so then in a moment to take a few long slow deep breaths
and not searching for anything not probing or analyzing
as you take some deep breaths what aspect of deep breathing
is revealed is received in highlight
and perhaps the contrast of taking some deep breaths to now
going back to breathing in easy way natural way
what stands out in contrast or what is highlighted now
not because you're looking for the contrast but it's just how
something else then something else stands out clearly
and then often i suggest that you relax at the beginning relax your body
for this exercise become aware of any holding or tension
there is in the body don't relax it just know it
allow it to stand out in relief allow it to like you're
making time and space to let it
speak to you to let it show itself to you
maybe in the face or the shoulders the chest the belly
the hands the arms
as if tension is the language of the body
the body is speaking to you and you listen
without relaxing or letting go of it just listen just receive it
let it stand out in relief
and gently can you be aware no notice
a little bit what it's like to have an awareness
that is more receptive than active
more allowing things to be seen and known recognized
been searching for something
[Music]
and then settling into your body breathing
with awareness being more in a receptive mode than a searching mode or a trying mode
we receive almost as if you linger with each thing
to let it speak to you let it reveal itself to you
only because you're available
you're not rushing you allow each thing that arises and
occurs
it's it's due it's it's time
so things become known more clearly
including the qualities of a mind that's abiding resting in awareness
resting in receptive awareness
as if every breath and all the sensations
is the language of the body that's speaking to you
and all you do is listen
all you do is receive sensations
so
when you are not receptive and open in awareness
chances are your mind has been activated in thoughts
concerns relax the activation
relax the effort of thinking
and relax back into a receptive mode of awareness
trusting the mind's ability
to listen to see to feel
experience as it comes and goes in the present
so
do
whatever yeah
so
oh
they're loud
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
what stands out for you is as beneficial from having sat
these minutes here meditated are you a little bit more settled or
calm more peaceful are you more self-aware of
aspects of yourself
maybe aspects that are difficult or aspects that are helpful
are you a little bit more connected to your heart we're inclined to be
kind compassionate friendly
and if there is any ways that you have benefited from this meditation
or if you haven't perhaps you can dedicate
any benefits known or unknown from having meditated
to the welfare and happiness of others
rather than keeping this for yourself it's like you're opening up your mind
your hearts your hands
in the wonderful way that says here delightful way just here
you can have it please
and it's such a pleasure to release and open up and just
give it all away may it be that the benefits from this
practice today
may it be for the welfare and happiness of others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and again i don't have a bell with me here so i'll bow to you all and that bow can
be the time that we end the meditation
thank you
[Music] um
so good morning everyone and
so this week uh the topic is the seven factors of awakening
and um the mindfulness investigation energy
joy tranquility concentration and equanimity
so these seven are uh qualities of our inner life
of the mind perhaps that grow and develop
as we do mindfulness practice as we do the practices that are the different sick you know exercises
that are taught in this text that we've been doing these last weeks and
the um and to something to agree these uh uh
get awoken seven factors of awakening i think of them as as we become more
awake more present these begin uh to become strong
and their ordinary faculties their ordinary states of being
that i like to i like to use the analogy of waking up from a very nice afternoon
nap where maybe there's uh the sunlight is streaming into the room
and um and it's and waking up content happy relaxed and
the mind is kind of clear and we might lay still in our back and the eyes open
and nothing needs to be done nothing we have to figure out or do and
just continually just laying there maybe looking at the ceiling or looking at the light is streaming
through the windows and there's dust particles in the air just kind of watching the dust particles or looking
at the texture of the ceiling or something and uh things are seen clearly
not because we're looking intently intensively but because we're not
preoccupied by other things and we're just there in a simple way ordinary way and
and uh awareness is present and uh just as present it's aware we're
not it isn't like we're trying to be aware we're just that in the wakefulness after
a nap we're just aware and there's a clarity to the awareness where we can see and look at
the details in the room the details of the particular texture of the ceiling or the dust in
the air or something and uh there's a kind of uh delightful energy uh that's not driving energy not
trying but it's we're certainly not um um about to fall back to sleep or
uh it's just kind of there's a a clarity in the energy that's just there
to do this wonderful gazing around the room in this after nap revelry
and it might feel kind of joyful to do it maybe joy is too strong
a post-snap experience but maybe it's a
sense of well-being and just being there and content and cozy and
there's a level of tranquility work there's a calmness there's a kind of feel tranquil and
feel almost like the body feels like it doesn't have to do anything it's just there and and um and maybe there's even some
degree of concentration present we're studying the dancing dust in the sunlight
and uh we're just kind of absorbed in that and that absorbed in in the dust and the dance is the concentration
and then there's equanimity like right now um all kinds of things can happen that
normally we would be concerned with but we don't care it's just like the mind doesn't knows it but it's not so concerned about it
and um maybe the there's some messiness in the room and
just be messiness is not something to be concerned about just more something to marvel at just seeing and
being with it so
if the seven factors awakening as as we settle into this practice
uh they become stronger and stronger and uh the second one is called usually
in english is called investigation the pali term the ancient buddhist term
that's translated as investigation is a differentiation
of dharmas so it involves a differentiation of things a distinguishing of things and
and i think of it as it as how we begin to distinguish things as there becomes more and more clarity
so those of you who are here from the beginning today you see that the fog is beginning to
clear the sun is coming out and now there's more details to be seen
in the hillside behind me and uh you see even see the faint outline of the higher mountain behind
the first hill and and so
as there's more as the fog clears and the light appears the eyes without studying and working
too much at it just notices more details and can distinguish right now i can
distinguish um there's a row of trees uh behind me
and i can start distinguishing uh different trees from each other and it just kind of i don't have to work at it
it's just obvious they're different colors and shapes a little bit and um
but before when it was so foggy it just i had a sense there was trees there but it was just a
row that i couldn't distinguish anything between the trees
so it might not seem like an important thing to be able to distinguish things from each other
but this is what comes with greater and greater clarity and and this word dharma
that we're distinguishing can mean different things um and i'll say what that is in a moment
but i just want to emphasize that it's this capacity to distinguish things to see things in their clarity
in and of themselves distinct from other things that begins to uh free the mind
uh from the fog of attachment the the mist of clinging and wanting and
aversion and preoccupations we have and um you know how many times have you or have
i met someone i've known from before and i carried with me
the ideas of who they were the past experience of them
and and in fact they had changed they were different today and it took a while to realize that
because i was living in the fog of my memory of them that i was little bit living projecting on them or seeing them
seeing seeing them and to not have bring with me the past
and be able to see something clearly for itself in the present a person a friend
then we have a chance to distinguish what's unique and what's really happening in this moment with them as
opposed to uh you know missing it because we're still living a little bit in the past information
so uh part of the distinguishing is to distinguish um
what we perceive uh one perception from another if you if you you're if you have a dim
morning light without the light on in the room you can't distinguish very much you kind of know maybe you see rough objects but
you don't see the details of the objects turn on the light and then without any
work on the part of the mind you see all these details um you know i if i take off my glasses
and look in certain distances it's all blurry but if i put on my glasses it's all
clear without having to work and now it's seeing the details so the same way as mindfulness gets
clearer and clearer more subtle to present moment awareness the details stand out
and as the details become clearer and clearer one of the one of the what we distinguish
is the difference between our ideas of an object of the effect of what we're
perceiving and how the the process of the perception the ways in which things are actually
impermanent arising and passing and constant and
and so the river of perceptions that flow through us in this relaxed open receptive mind
breaks up the solidity that is always going to be there with clinging we hold on to things or want
things to be a certain way or push them away because they are a certain way we don't like
and so beginning to distinguish the uh differentiate the process of change
that's constantly going on from the ideations of of constancy or
fixity or ideas we overlay on top of things the other part of this differentiation
of dharmas is dharma can also mean action activities and so we start seeing
that how we practice influences the practice itself so if
we're striving and pushing that we feel the tension of that the more clear we become the more
receptive we are in the present moment we become clear that
striving pushing actually hinders the clarity gets in the
way of the practice and we see that there's a better consequence if we don't strive if we
relax and open up if we spend a lot of time analyzing or judging after a while it becomes we
differentiate we see clearly oh when i'm when i'm mindful i've confused
thinking with mindfulness and i thought that if i spent a lot of time thinking judging my experience that
i was present for it but there's an in fact there's another way of being present without the
judgments without the thinking about things so much in elaborate ways
and so we're distinguishing how we're practicing and this starting to discover ways that
are more conducive for uh for peace for letting for relaxation
for calm for openness for clarity
in that dharma also means action we also begin more and more aware of the consequences of our actions in our daily
life and sometimes we start seeing that if i live
with dishonesty with not not breaking the precepts that that has a very deleterious effect
on me if i um and that consequence is not good i feel
the after effect of it and seeing the after effect the consequences that are not so
desirable helps us to uh clean up our life and live a better way
not so much because it's a moral thing to do not but rather because we see
clearly it's beneficial and we distinguish better and better of what is
beneficial and what is not and as the dharma practice deepens and unfolds with people get more and more
refined or more and more subtle or
clear about what is beneficial and what is not it's not a judgment it's not a moral
thing it's not like a statement about our our personal worth it just means as
a matter of fact you take your your hand off the hot stove uh you
don't begin uh gossiping about someone because it just feels like you take your
hand off the hot stove that doesn't feel good to gossip or demean someone or something
so this differentiation of dharmas so the word in when we translate it as
an investigation some people think they have to probe and peer deeply and kind of
analyze or figure out what's going on it's not that way it's more like we say
the question what is this and then we allow it to to reveal itself
to us there's almost like a little thing lingering an awareness that gives a
little time for every experience to show itself a little bit better to us oh that's how it is
so the perceptions can be clear perceptions can take in more fully what's happening
and so investigation is that that receptivity of the mind that takes in
everything with greater clarity so and in the clarity things become
distinguished become differentiated and then we're on the path to wisdom
when we start seeing with greater and greater clarity so you might as you go about your day
today experiment with this and that is i find times during the day
where you're not rushing on to the next thing the next thought but rather take some time when
to just stay there stay and just kind of take in the experience of the moment
and as if you're going to discover something new so even something you do every day
maybe take some time to just stand there or sit there with it and say just look around and relax like see what can you
see that's new is there anything new here that you never noticed before
stand in your kitchen and just look around the kitchen and let it reveal itself to you and see
if you can find something new that ability to see something new
in a relaxed way utilizes this differentiation of the dharmas the second factor of awakening
and as you do that that investigation that differentiation
see if you can notice how your mind is
and see if you can have a beneficial mind state as you receptively feel and look
and perceive around you to discover some what's something new that you've never noticed
so thank you and [Music] and as i'm talking i see that it's
getting a little more and more clear behind me and
it's a wonderful fresh air and the birds and the different the workers came i don't
know if you could hear them to begin their morning work then some kind of a
construction project that's going on so uh thank you all very very much and
i'll be here one more day tomorrow and then i'll be back in imc
thank you