greetings friends greetings from wherever in the world you're joining
so today we come to the fifth and final day of our exploration of the sati
patana suttas refrain together and
the refrain the part that we have come to today is
really the last part the last sentence the last couple of sentences
and um i'll i'll review the entire uh
refrain at the end uh in the darmet but maybe what i will read is just the refrain uh the last
part we're exploring today which is
one um one abides independent not clinging to anything in the world
that is how in regard to the body one contemplates the body but really the sentence here
[Music] is one abides independent not clinging
to anything in the world two aspects here abiding independently
and not clinging to anything in the world so the different aspects that we have
practiced uh and mentioned culminate to this
internal external contemplating the body internally
externally both internally and externally as well as
contemplating the nature of arising and passing away
knowing that there is a body this this lexical
use the skillful use of lexical noting there is a body there is a body
all culminating to [Music] abiding independently independently
not clinging to anything in the world
so so without further ado let's practice
in meditation together because life can be practiced or a practice can be practicing right now
listening and sitting with kindness and awareness so not to make
practice only limited to closing our eyes and meditating but let's meditate together let's meditate
together so ah
arriving arriving in our seat
arriving here
letting go letting go [Music] not clinging to anything in the world
letting go in this moment in time
not clinging not clinging to thoughts
not clinging to memories of the past
our preoccupations with the future
not even clinging to the present
as the sutta says not clinging to anything in the world
not clinging as thoughts arise
as entanglements perhaps arise not clinging releasing
abiding abiding independently abiding
can there be a moment of spaciousness
not needing not needing anything not lusting after this or that or
wanting any particular experience
abiding abiding independently
not clinging to anything in the entire world
see if this sentence this phrase
from the refrain of the sati patana
as you drop it into your body not thinking about it don't try to analyze
but drop it in
let it resonate let it open up
let it enter your heart i for one
have fallen in love with this sentence with this phrase as as an instruction
abiding independently not clinging to anything in the world
one abides independent not clinging to anything in the world
so much ease so much freedom
is possible
one abides independent not clinging to anything in the world
drop it into your heart let it resonate
find its way through you
when abide is independent not clinging to anything in the world
abiding independently
not clinging not clinging to greed once
ruminations
in the mind
not clinging
independent of grudges
independent of greed hatred
abiding independently
of the usual habit patterns of the mind and heart can we abide independently
independent of of those
and as we bring this practice period together giving thanks giving thanks for
this opportunity this privilege to come together
if not in space but in time to cultivate to cultivate our hearts our
minds in kindness in good will
in wisdom in non-reactivity and letting go in non-clinging
to greed and hatred to give thanks for this opportunity that
we have come together even if for a moment there was a sense of independence from the typical patterns
there was a moment of freedom a moment of letting go peace ease
celebrating that moment and even if it wasn't that moment whether there was a lot of
delusion confusion
trusting we have planted seeds that were flower in the future
if we align our intention with goodness and offering this
this collective cultivation no matter how shoddy we
deem it to be offering the goodness of ourselves
together with the community offering it to the world to others as a gift
here i've done my best
if i could have done any better or differently i would have it's the best offering i have in this
limited time on earth my best offering
and sharing sharing giving generously
this gift for the benefit of all beings everywhere especially those
in war zones
holding witness wishing safety and ease
for all beings everywhere may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so [Music] hello hello greetings welcome dear friends
wherever in the world you are wonderful to be with you in this moment in time
whatever the weather inside or outside
so today day five
of exploring the refrain of the sati patana sutta
sati patana sutta itself the four foundations of mindfulness of awareness
how [Music] how beautiful the teachings are how
beautiful the teachings are in the satipatana sutta and especially the refrain the refrain itself is so
significant and we've been building up we've been building up this entire week with the
different parts of the refrain building up one by one by
one and this last sentence really is an accumulation of the practices of the
previous days that really colton cultivates to this and i'd like to
put it all together and um and
this statement actually this last sentence that i was offering just to drop it in not try to think about it not
try to analyze it but as a cohen to sit with it and let it flower
it's it's as relica says to live the questions themselves to live the
questions not trying so hard to to answer or open locked rooms that
sometimes answers are not available to you yet
so instead of leading into frustration of oh just doesn't make sense but just drop it
dropping the question in living the question with patience trusting that the practice builds up and
it it will make sense so in the way of review
in the way of the way of review of where we are um i'd like to
uh let's see let me first put up the sati patana sutta um
see if i have that here there we go the structure of the satipatana sutta
especially if you have been just joined today and you're not quite sure where we are so
so the sati patana sutta sections the four sections on body
feelings mind and damage and after every teaching the refrain shows up the
refrain is so important that it repeats 13 times in the sadi
patana sutta so
so the refrain the refrain um
and maybe what i'll also do i'll re i'll share the entire refrain let's see if uh
it will allow me to share the entire text
here in chat oh it's too long oh
gosh okay so not possible to share it in chat oh well the limitations of
of uh of youtube only 200 characters this is
almost 700 characters the refrain oh well maybe what i'll do is i will um i
will read the entire refrain and um and and really really try to relate
what this teaching this part try to decode it for you a little bit which i
have to say i have fallen in love with the entire refrain
um and years ago when i was sitting a retreat actually on the sati patana sutta
with bhikkhu anago who was the author of the book i've been mentioning he did his
dissertation phd dissertation on the sati patana
[Music] i fell in love with this instruction
with this one sentence it was so opening it was so freeing
um this abiding independent not clinging into
the world and anything in the world there's sense of freedom and ease that can be created in the heart and
mind so there is peace and ease to actually engage in the world to engage
and be of service this sentence this this phrase doesn't mean that you're
aloof and you just go sit in the cave and you don't it doesn't say
um not engage but the world says not clinging there's not a sense of clinging
um and wanting so i'm actually doing this a little losing a little bit uh as uh
speaking a little out of order let me read the entire [Music]
phrase the entire refrain so in this way in regard to the body
one abides contemplating the body internally or one abides contemplating the body
externally or one divides contemplating the body internally and externally so so what we
did here in this t in this teaching and what we explored
is expanding the dimensions not just being internal not just concerned with
this self internal it's all internal but also
doing the contemplations externally for other beings so already this refrain is
building up the internal external if you just landed in the refrain with the last sentence
maybe you're confused like what does that mean but be patient be patient
so already the refrain is setting the frame of internal and external
and internal and external self and others and the world this contemplation is already actually
in the first sentence of it is opening us up opening us up so much to internal
external the second sentence and also to mention what it
also what it helped us bring bring up uh to to really get a sense of
objectivity because we are so stuck in our narrative we are often so stuck in
the way we see the world me me me my my mind the way i see is right this is good
this is bad so being stuck uh in turn with the internal this is
already opening us up to internal external and also that shift in the frame shift in the
perspective of both internal and external allows an objectivity of impersonality
to pop up it's it's suffering it's challenge it's beauty it's goodness it's not me there's
it's it's the sense of openness of heart and perspective that already comes from
this first sentence of the the refrain now the second sentence
you see how these build up together build up the second that we worked with a couple
days ago with contemplating the nature of arising
and passing away so with arising and passing away
impermanence really getting an understanding a deep understanding of
all things all things whether or not we want them to be or not arise and pass
away are impermanent and there's a sense of the heart doesn't cling doesn't let go
it does let go it doesn't cling already that observation that practice is
opening us up for this statement here that we've been sitting with today seeing the arising and
passing away of all things the heart the mind doesn't cling there's
a sense of freedom that arises that one can actually engage or be in the world
in a different way in a different way it frees up both insights into emptiness into
wisdom of openness and wisdom of compassion so as talked about a couple days ago
insight into impermanence uh really leads the way opens up one for
awakening it's required it's required for awakening one cannot
um access or or or uh enter the stream the first stage of
awakening without a thorough and pure insight into everything arising and passing away not
just one thing not just one moment not just one inside but the thorough thorough insight into impermanence
so that second line of the refrain is already opening up to a sense of ah
it's it's our it's all passing it's a passing show this life this body everything is a
passing show and brings up a sense of okay how to engage and the answer that
comes up is with wisdom and compassion already it's not it doesn't make sense to cling it
doesn't make sense to to be hateful it just doesn't make sense after
you've had these insights it just does not make sense anymore
the next phrase we worked with uh mindfulness that there is a body is
uh or let me read it mindfulness that there is a body is established in one to the
extent necessary for bear knowledge and continuous mindfulness we did this yesterday
and um the the the idea that the support the
support of bringing in a lexical note there is a body there is a body can be
so helpful to to support this this bare knowledge but but
just enough just enough to have this reminder lexical reminder
uh lexical note so that there's continuous mindfulness continuous mindfulness so all of these
practices together and now we have continuous mindfulness leading to this last sentence here one
abides independent there's a sense of independence from
uh all the things that we hang on to all the things that we are preoccupied not
in a helpful way and not to cling to anything and again
it's not for the entity it's not that you don't cling anything after you know
of course you can have your breakfast and lunch and and but there's a sense of clinging it doesn't again
listen carefully read carefully it's doesn't mean not engaging it it says not
clinging there is a different it's clinging there's a different energy of clinging to the things in the world
there's a sense of um clinging that word um
is is you know you can actually feel it in your body when you're clinging to something there is just this tightness
or greed hatred and delusion really shorthand for that it's
not regarding engagement so just a couple more things to say and
then to wrap up um it is said that the um
abiding independently according to the suttas and and bukunalia's analysis
that this abiding independently is really the absence of dependency through
craving as i've mentioned and speculative views and the not clinging to anything in the
world is not identifying not identifying to
um and not identifying with the five aggregates of existence and the five aggregates
will come up in a few weeks you study them with um with gil this in this
morning is coming up as part of the fourth satipattana so i'll just leave that as a way for you for your in
interest to be peaked uh like a preview of what is coming up
so all of these practices lead especially the refrain
lead to a sense of um equipoise equanimity and freedom not eye making
and my making where freedom can arise from fixed views
and it deep deeps wisdom and compassion to engage with the world to engage with
the world from true true compassion and love not from hatred not
from self views not from um [Music]
the ways that are actually create a war and create discontent
so these are really really deep teachings and beautiful teachings
so i i only hope it is my hope that this five days that we spent together
exploring the uh the beauty really the beauty of the
refrain it's it's hard to say you know every part of the surtozairi become my
favorite but the refrain i am i'm in love with the refrain is so
beautiful and so sublime and i hope that i've managed to share a little bit of of
the significance of the refrain and how this practice practices can be
awakening and bringing freedom for you in your life so
that you can serve and relate and be engaged in the world but not clinging not clinging
um so anyway it's been a delight to to serve
you and to practice with you this week thank you for your wholeheartedness
thank you for your kindness in listening and practicing together and
may you be well maybe all all us being all us beings everywhere
may we be safe may we be happy may we be healthy
and may we all have ease and freedom
thank you so much for your kind attention i wish every single one of you of us
well and goodness take good care