so hello and welcome to our last
meditation on the send spheres
and um and this is it
the word dharma is sometimes equated with the english
word nature to see the dharma as a sea nature to see
what's kind of what's natural in this world of ours
and meditation makes us a little bit a naturalist where we are
looking and understanding what the nature of this life is like especially the nature of ourselves and our mind
and the naturalist has the ability to see what's happening without disturbing
what's happening without interfering with it and um
and without holding on to the branches of the stream as we go down the canoe
we can just flow along with the natural flow so one of the most natural things for
human beings is to have thoughts and it's possible to just know that
there's a thought that appears and there's a kind of a marvel with the
arising of an individual thought sometimes because it just seems to appear out of nowhere
i just sit quietly and a new thought arises
and so in this exercise on the senses six senses
there is thoughts and then there's the reception of that thought in the mind there's the mind
knows it that there's a thought and then there's
the fetter the entanglement the knot there's a way we get involved in that
thought and the way that and one of the ways we see that
is when a thought becomes thinking a thought is a relatively brief phrase
or sentence or image that we have and then we get involved in it we pick
it up we respond to it we add to it we [Music]
and then pretty soon we're kind of lost in a whole train of thoughts and might take a long time before we come out of
it and know that we're even present and so it's possible just to sit quietly
and be aware of the thought when it arises and then distinct from that
know how we get involved in it no the pull into it the reaction to it
the horror to it the judgments of it all the secondary things that go on
that involves some kind of being caught in it but if we are able to be a naturalist of
thoughts thoughting it's a really it can be very relaxing
if we don't take assign meaning to a thought or
value to a thought or we don't define ourselves by the thought you know i'm having this kind of thought therefore
i'm a wonderful person i'm having this kind of thought and i'm a terrible person
it's just a thought this idea of just a thought just thinking
and this is one of the places where i think it's valuable to add the word just
uh in the label in the recognition of thinking just a thought it's just thinking
and just like a map is not
the location that the map represents so a thought it doesn't is not the thing that it
usually represents it's just a thought and to settle back and be able to just
see the arising of thoughts and then see if we lean into them or pull away from
them or get caught in them and that's seeing the not the entanglement
so assuming a dignified meditation posture
and part of the value of being careful with your posture is that the more you can be embodied in
your posture the less energy there is to pour into thinking
the more you can really be careful and embodied in your posture the more that's a grounding
here in the present moment it's like an anchor
that keeps you from drifting off
and then lower your gaze about 45 degrees
relax the focus of your eyes so you're not looking at anything in particular
and then gently close your eyes
and settle in relax with your body
gently calmly take some deeper breaths fuller breaths
and as you exhale relax
settle in
and letting your breathing return to normal
and it's really invaluable
to relax when you meditate to have an upright posture or a clear
posture intentional posture
and then to relax within that posture
so you might relax the muscles of your face as you exhale
and as you get more and more familiar with your face this way you might become more and more aware of
the subtle emotions the subtle muscles that can be relaxed soften
released
over time there's more and more awareness of muscles maybe you never even knew you
had
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
and going to the belly on the exhale softening the belly
in the exhale release your body weight of your body into whatever supporting it
cushion the chair
and then some global way of relaxing the whole body
if you're bracing yourself against life soften as you exhale
and then relaxing the thinking mind on the exhale softening
tension or pressure contraction associated with thinking
calming any agitation associated with thinking
and then take a few moments here to be aware of thoughts arising
turn your attention allow yourself to think and know the thoughts that arise
you don't necessarily have to know the content of the thoughts but just the event of thinking
and as you do so are you involved in your thinking
or can you just observe them from a distance
observing them as natural phenomena
no need to judge or define you define yourself by your
thoughts the thoughts just arise appear
sooner or later they disappear
are you involved in your thinking what does that involvement feel like
like a glue like a strong gravitational pull
strong interest
worrying about something
and then settling in with your breathing
but attentive to the rising of thoughts in any entanglement
with thinking and the alternative to entanglement is
to simply observe it as a naturalist it's nature
for the mind to produce thoughts
there's no need for you to get involved in your thoughts
come back to your breathing breathe with it all
it can be a relief to leave thinking alone leave thoughts that come and they
go leave them alone
not bothered by them not favoring them not concerned
they're just thoughts
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
one of the powers that come with observing thoughts
is to know which to put down let go and which to get involved in
and as we begin to come out of meditation the thoughts that are nice to have and
to participate with little bit are thoughts of good will
kindness friendliness and perhaps there's people in your lives
or people you know that you could
have a few moments here of thinking caring or generous thoughts
about them
with a light feeling not a duty or heavy just lightly
positive good feelings and thoughts about them
and this is uh not just letting your think stream of thinking be random and
without any agency on your part from time to time it's nice to
choose what you think about and think about goodwill and friendliness to yourself to
others
and in this way may we click keep close by as we go
through the day the friendliness the good will the care
that comes from the wish the wishes may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
okay so
this weekend we're talking about the buddha's instructions for how to practice with the sense doors
and it's to be aware of each door the object that that of
that that sense door takes in so for eyes it's site objects where
hearing its sounds for for the tongue its taste for the nose it
smells for the body its tactile experiences and for
the mind its thinking the word for
mind here is mano m-a-n-o which uh maybe
is closely associated with the thinking part of the mind and so
uh and so if if it kind of goes along with the other senses
the mind produces thoughts and that is somehow registered or known
by the mono by this part of the mind that recognizes there's thinking [Applause]
and and then on top of that in addition to that there's a kind of mindful knowing
so it's not just kind of vaguely or somewhat aware that there's thoughts going on
but this knowing of mindfulness is a clear kind of definitive like oh
this is thinking this is just thinking you don't necessarily just say those
words to yourself but there's a way in which we step back
or turn around and look thinking directly in the eye and say i see you thinking this is thinking
and and observe it and and i think this idea of being a
naturalist of thinking uh conveys the idea of uh
of that the thinking is natural natural phenomena and we are observing it
but not necessarily defining ourselves or identifying ourselves with the thoughts
and and this is a fascinating and wonderful thing to allow a thought to arise
but to not place ourselves in the thought some people
live in their thoughts their whole identity or their kind of feeling or sense of eminence i am i exist
is somehow taken up residency in the middle of thinking and so it's inconceivable
to think about not thinking because that's
who would i be if i wasn't thinking it's also um
some people feel lost if they're not kind of living in their thoughts and um
but we don't have to live in our thoughts we don't have to take residency in our thoughts we can have thought just be a phenomena
that arises that's no different than going outside for a walk and
and the leaf blows off a tree and blows down next to you and and
that you don't take the tree as you you don't define the the leaf as you you don't define you don't
define yourself by the leaf you don't maybe necessarily get involved with
wanting to take the leaf home home and deciding that you're a great leaf selector and you need to let everyone
know what a great capacity you have selecting leaves from the sidewalk
you don't get involved just the leaf just falls and it's just you know it's maybe a nice part of the
just just false so the same way the thinking thoughts can just be the same
relationship to them where we take up residency not in the thinking the thoughts but in
the awareness of them the knowing of them now it's a little bit tricky because
knowing of them could be seen as a thought itself but
this is a we're talking about maybe different levels of thinking different kinds of thinking and
the the this very simple thought that knows oh that's thinking that's just a thought
that's also a natural phenomena but that's a natural phenomena that supports this freedom supports this
disentanglement as we begin to um
so so this whole thing about the sense doors is quite fascinating because
the more and more we are able to kind of be present at the point of sense contact
and recognize the not the entanglement the bias the leaning into or pulling
back we start seeing our bias our our
our prejudices our desires our the influences we bring
on to on top of it and we said we are seldom innocent observers
we often have preferences wanting and not wanting and and and it can be very very subtle
uh i told this story before but when i was a teenager i i went to morocco
and and i don't know how it is now but when i was there the men
were yalabas these gowns there was striped gowns
vertically stripes and um and as i was walking around after some
while being in morocco i had this funny feeling that my mind was lighter
clear so there's a little different feeling in my mind and as i kind of tried to understand
what was going on i came to the conclusion that in the united states
i pegged people i didn't just see people i had a judgment about people
because i recognized something about them that was a a jock that was a
some kind of businessman or that was this or that and i had little judgments about them
and uh maybe there wasn't maybe one of the judgments judgments were not exactly
conscious but they were there and morocco where all these men were wearing yalabas
i had no context to understand anything about them about their professions what they did their politics all kinds of
things and so i um the
and so my mind was light lighter from not making any extra judgments
so to not live in ordinary thinking but to live an awareness
the awareness in which this arises and then be able to see the
entanglement and not and and it's a big part of the the knots the
entanglements we have is in fact to thinking because if i see something i don't
necessarily automatically get entangled to that i do have a thought about it
and it's a thought that i get caught in that's the somehow the the knot around the thing i'm seeing
and so to be able to settle back and observe thinking to be aware of thinking to be
quiet enough still enough open enough present enough to see the birth of a thought
to see a thought appear there it is
and it's just a thought and then it are you entangled with it
you chase it do you then have a follow-up thought and a follow-up thought
or do you just allow the thought to just be there like a leaf the same single leaf that's falling from the sky
just a thought and then
that kind of freedom that that gives of you know seeing and not being involved in thoughts
gives us a freedom to then choose what we think and there are things to think about
and one of the things to think about is good will is kindness is friendliness support to
others is to to appreciate people
that i think that this uh it's all too easy for people to have a negativity bias
and uh for all kinds of reasons and be predisposed to seeing what's wrong and
and what's not right and but if we can choose what we're thinking
about maybe we can choose appropriately appropriate ways
to really appreciate people and see their beauty and their wonderfulness and choose to think about how to support
people and be friendly to people
if in maybe that seems like a lot of work and extra to do a little artificial to do
that but it might be better than the alternative
if you're watching your mind carefully choose the best alternative for the mind
and don't choose the alternative the option that is for your detriment thinking
critical thoughts judgmental thoughts harsh thoughts
unkind thoughts it's not really healthy
so thinking thoughts mono so this level of practice of this but
talking about this week we are tuning into the knots we can begin also start seeing
the conditions how we get knotted the desires that arise the aversions
that are there the the frustrations the stresses we're living under the stress we have that
they're kind of the conditions for us to more likely get knotted up and
knowing those conditions then we can uh we can kind of maybe adjust those
conditions so it's easier to know how to let go of the knots we don't necessarily have to let go of
the thought but we let go of being involved in it and caught in it
and and this is a wonderful thing to let go of knots to to dissolve the
knots to untie the knots and the mind and one of the reasons that's wonderful
is that knots take up a lot of space in the mind a lot of energy a lot of bandwidth
and when that bandwidth is not preoccupied with the knots
there's then much more room open space on the
for the factors of awakening for some really also natural phenomena
but natural phenomena that's really kind of some of the great
treasures that are within us and those are the seven factors of
awakening and uh that's the next exercise for the sati britannia text
it goes from um the six sense bases to the seven factors of awakening
and then we make a transition now uh to looking at what leads to
liberation to freedom once we get a hang of the
aspects that keeps us from being free the hindrances
the aggregates that we talked about last week and now that fetters the knots that
we can we know what those are well those are the things that keep us from being free
and as we release them and free ourselves from them
then um this new energy this new possibility states can come ones that are onward leading towards
freedom and this is one of the great um i'm kind of rewards for doing
mindfulness practice when we get to the play the point in practice where we start uh flowing in these beautiful
seven factors of awakening of mindfulness investigation energy
joy tranquility concentration and equanimity so that'll be the topic for two weeks
next week matthew will be here and matthew brent silver and i'm doing
the 7am teachings while i'm away and then the following week i'll be back
i won't be here at imc but i'll be i'll be back on the on the youtube and
we'll do the seven factors of awakening thank you