hello everyone welcome
it feels uh particularly hello everyone oh
it feels particularly
kind of um peaceful to be here
this morning uh biking down here in the dark and somehow with her
pre-dawn quiet
it kind of adds to a sense of being peaceful and settled
and that is the part of the theme for today is to become aware of the contrast
between tension and peace and tension is I think of as a variety
of things but tension is something which tightens up Things become tight the muscles tighten
up and things are sometimes pulled in in a tight way and peace I think I think of as the
opposite of that over releasing allowing things to spread out to
be to open up peace is different than calm and at
least for me every everyone will have their own reference points to these words and some people won't see a difference between the two
but I think of calm as a I strongly associated with a settling
settling down a um and uh it's almost as if calm has a
little bit of weight that is kind of a settling like the the
mud in the pond settles full of gravity whereas peace is the broad widespread
of the Clear Water once the mud has settled and um
so the sense of openness wide wide so I think becoming wide becoming extend extended
in some way so we'll sit here with this contrast if
it's available to you and to respect them both
to not be at war with attention but rather to uh
hold it in awareness to hold it in attention
not intention I kind of delight in the word play of
the pronunciations of attention and attention and we practice our attention not like a
drill sergeant calling soldiers to tense up and be straight
but we call it attention to relieve the tension
to let it settle release the tension so that we can now become aware of
something which is peaceful and Broad open a peace that can hold the tension
and this is where the art of practice really gets interesting where we don't get rid of anything but
we know it in a context of peace
so to begin with taking an alert
not not a tense posture but a posture that has a certain kind of
healthy appropriate hotness in it there is some
energy that goes into the posture to hold ourselves in a way that the
there's an alertness even if you're laying in in bed and rather than sitting
upright um there's a way of laying in bed so that we're not just maximizing
comfort but we're laying there in a way that's supportive
for awareness maybe there's a kind of turning the shoulders
end it a little bit so that their shoulder blades can pull down the back a little bit
the lifting of the chest maybe a lifting of the knees so that
there's some effort there to hold the knees upright
in any case to take the posture and to lower your gaze
perhaps to let your gaze be calm and cool coolness
and gently close the eyes
and become aware of any tension that's in your body
and rather than trying to relax it which we often do at the beginning of a
sitting hold it in whatever degree of peaceful awareness
that you can know it without conflict without
agitation without trying to do something to with
it allow it to be there in a peaceful
attention
and as you do that maybe the
sensations of breathing can find you
so you're not only aware of the tension but you're also aware of the rhythmic
sensations of the body breathing
and maybe just maybe the breathing offers an invitation to the tensioner
to relax almost as if we feel the tension
we can feel it's the tension itself wishes to relax
so then settling into the body breathing
and if there's any tension associated with breathing
let that be Let It Be
as part of what you know peacefully
if there are tensions in your body sometimes those tensions have a way of
calling attention to themselves
if that's the case Let There Be awareness of the tension
but from a place of being peaceful
form of peaceful attention that is more like clear water than muddy
water
whatever you're thinking whatever you're feeling whatever is happening for you
let it be happening in a peaceful awareness
awareness that's like clear water not muddy water
even if there's mud in the water know it
with whatever Clarity is present
to help be peaceful with the presence of tension
you might breathe through the tension
breathe with it and maybe the breathing
can support releasing
the attitudes and desires we have in real to the tension
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to call on whatever sense you have of peaceful presence
peaceful awareness peaceful dwelling in your body
attention awareness Consciousness that's more like clear
water then muddy water or
agitated water
awareness is like clear water
in which the people that we know and see and
think of are also held or felt to be inside or
within that peaceful attention
within the peace the clarity that might spread beyond our
body out into the room the lands the world
and with a peaceful heart
to appreciate other people
to place value and importance on every living being
and to gaze upon living beings kindly lovingly
so the peace that we feel the clear water in which we live
is a medium for our good will
May our good will spread through our peace to touch and benefit all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
foreign
so the shape form sense image
feeling we have for what Consciousness might be what the of the combined
aggregate totality of awareness might be for us
is related to different attitudes states of Mind activities that we have
and two which have a big impact on on it is tension on one hand and peace
peacefulness in the other these also exist on a spectrum and a range
where it doesn't have to be all one or all another but uh oftentimes
one is present with the other and the advantage of that of seeing that
discovering that is that we could tap into the peace the peacefulness
in order to be present for the tension and so if the tension predominates
we can break out of the enchantment the Allure the strong maybe attachment to
uh do tension by by remembering there's also peace
here and knowing it peacefully a little bit sets us free from it
if there is a lot of peace then uh and it's easy to kind of not
notice any tension it's actually helpful to then from that peaceful place to
see if you can find where the attention Still Remains because if they're subtle maybe a very
slight tension that's still it remains if that's held also under this peaceful
gaze of attention then that also has a chance to dissolve
and be released and so that that peace can grow more and more at some point
with the greater the peace that we have rather than focusing on the peace sometimes it's helpful to notice in the
cracks of it all or in the somewhere in the subtle places there's still tension
and kind of began kind of working those edges and so the piece can kind of spread and grow more and more
then um so um enough intention is uh
part and parcel of life it comes and goes if it comes and goes it's fine but
the issue is when we hold on to the tension it's not just simply we're
driving and someone suddenly appears into our Lane in front of us and we
tense up in order to quickly kind of break the car or back up or do something to be safe
that kind of tension is a completely biologically important and but
when the when we're is driving is safe again to be able to let it all go
um it's when we don't let go we hold on to it that um that becomes a problem
and there's many kind of uh causes for being tense
um you know we can we can but to hold on to the tension for the tensions become chronic and tight
there's a fewer reasons there has a lot to do with what goes on in our minds that there can be strong desire for
something strong aversion to something and what I'd like to emphasize today there can be fear
and and fear is uh one of the one one very powerful condition for becoming
tense and some people have chronic tension that goes on for a lifetime because of uh some some fear that was
kind of inflicted upon them that the experience that they remained afraid in
some part of their psyche and that tension always is there bracing ourselves against life or something
and when there is uh tension especially attention of fear
if if we have a sense of being conscious or Consciousness itself that it tends to be shriveled and to be
contracted attention pulls in and so it makes something comes tight
yesterday's discussion about agitation tends to fragment the Consciousness make
it all kind of rough and jagged but the attention tends to shrink it and
sometimes the world shrinks to a very particular concern that we have maybe the particular thing we're afraid of or
upset with or that we want and and that shrinking of our attention to that one
concern um if you kind of open up and look at that
sense of the mind that's aware that way it just feels like it's tight and narrow
when the mind is not preoccupied or caught they're holding on to anything that's when awareness can become Broad
and spaces become peaceful and a peaceful awareness is one that has
been released and because attention that localizes it in one place has been
released it can feel as if awareness or Consciousness now begins to spread out
it gets released and opened up whereas calm and the difference between
peace and calm at least for me and for everyone's going to be different I think some people the two are synonyms
but calm for me is a settling things relax and settle it's almost like uh the weight of calm
helps you to settle into the pull of gravity whereas peace comes from release
and so and it becomes things things open up and become wide and spread
or to use a slightly different idea that um com is a settling of the mud in
water and the and peace is the clarity
that's left in that water and uh to be you know swimming underwater and have Clarity and just
kind of sense so that you can see so far it's quite lovely and that's what I've
swum in water which was you couldn't see for more than a foot in front of you and it's a whole different feeling very
different feeling when I was a kid I just like to go in places where there were waves
and the water was relatively clear and and very clear but it was waves coming into the rocky Shore and I'd love
to go dive underwater maybe about five or six feet and hold my breath turn
turn around on my back and look up at the waves and the turmoil above and I
felt so peaceful then below because everything was so quiet down there and peaceful and the contrast was so
wonderful so fear um if
the what's fascinating about fear and humbling and upsetting and irritating
and but also maybe hopefully um beneficial
is that um fear is its own Danger
if fear is fear of danger fear itself is a danger
when it's chronic when it tells it which conditions us to see the world the way
it's not to see danger at every corner and every location to always be looking
out for what's the the problems are and the danger is where that becomes a fixation of a fixated view
and we live only from that danger everything becomes something that's that's dangerous and in the way it does
because the fear is its own Danger and uh and so
it's kind of self-fulfilling if it's chronic that yes we're in trouble
because of the tension the contraction the the the lens that we see through
with the lens of fear and um
uh so to be so then if fear is related to tension
fearlessness is related to peace and so peace is not just some kind of
bland state but it's a powerful wonderful place through which we can be
Fearless and um and we have nothing to fear and of course you know if the car pulls
in front of us in the freeway having some fear is appropriate and it makes helps us become safe so it isn't like we
want to get rid of all fear but there's this way in which discover the value of peacefulness and
fearlessness that it does protect us because now we
become safe from ourselves so fear is a danger to ourselves
and fearlessness is how we become safe from ourselves where we're not going to
cause harm to ourselves we're not going to contract and hold attention and which can cause you know all kinds
of chronic physical and mental and emotional problems for people to be chronically
tense and held and so having something like meditation
made even something like exercise and other things that we do that allow us to relax deeply
to calm deeply to start experiencing kind of states of Peace where tensions
begin to dissolve where we're not living in tension and we have an experience
of being safe for ourselves and the Heart of fearlessness is to have
that kind of safety you become safe for yourself
and that sense of and then absence of fear
changes the nature of consciousness of how we feel we're aware it's so easy to be aware with such a
strong filter of fear and tension that that just seems like that's the nature
of certainly of Consciousness it's the truth but more powerfully is that
consciousness of awareness attention that is colored by fear
then sees fear in the world and we don't become necessarily
objective clear Seer of what's actually out there because in a sense everything becomes dangerous because everything is
then now seen through that framework of fear
if everything is seen through the framework of fearlessness then a fearlessness where we're not
we're safe for ourselves then we're in a much better place to
track the inner wisdom the inner Clarity the perceptions the hunches the
the reactions we have that we need to be in touch with in order to be wise about
what's out there of course there's dangers out there some are more subtle than others but there's
probably less danger out in the world than you can ever imagine
and so if you you know have the wisdom Fearless wisdom
wisdom to ascertain really know and connect deep inside of yourself with all
the different sources of intelligence that operate then you can probably tune into the
difference between what is really a danger and what is projected danger not
really there they kind of projected danger that often if self often enough is self-fulfilling
it sometimes creates the very problem that we're trying to avoid
so so for the next 24 hours if you like
um you might say study how it is for you the range from tension to peace
and when you when you're tense where's the peace when you're peaceful where's the tension
and may that kind of clarity in the in the in the range of who you are and how
you are May that clarity help you to uh be less caught stuck in
the tension but more fluid and more more in touch with the peace
that's in our hearts so thank you