so hello hello everyone from everywhere and
now here we come at the end of the week
and i believe that these days that i've been sitting down here i've been feeling fairly
you know empty in a nice very nice way i hope that
it comes across okay in in this youtube world
the um so
what if we study our thinking and
one of the ways to understand is we usually thoughts are usually about something
so about the meal i'm going to have with about the meal that i just had that wasn't just
quite right or the work or a conversation or an event that happened
or about some self-concern or about plans we're making
or about a fantasy we have we think about things
and the world of aboutness is at least one step removed
from the world of aliveness and in some ways the world of aboutness
is maybe a one-dimensional two-dimensional world it's a kind of a virtual reality world that
world of thoughts i love my thoughts mostly
i mean at least i have a very positive relationship to them and um so i don't i don't feel like i
need to be critical of them but i am aware that they are
about something and if i spend too much time in that world of aboutness
then i become separated from the world of aliveness
and one way of understanding this [Music] meditation is it's a switch
from aboutness to aliveness that we're
not so focused on the world as of aboutness but we're focused on the world the
living world that we can experience and feel and see and touch and know directly
here and now and so this distinction between think thoughts being
the world of aboutness maybe helps you to break the enchantment with them
or break the allure or the strong pull into the world of thoughts
and this idea that the alternative in meditation is the world of aliveness
maybe that is a welcoming idea to show up here for
your lived experience of the moment
so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
into gently slowly as if you're like you're entering into a
beautiful place a forest or a sacred grove or
gently slowly take some deeper breaths
just deep enough that it remains comfortable for you
and maybe in a way that's comfortable taking these deep breaths and then slow
long exhale maybe exhaling more than usual
and as you exhale let the shoulders relax the belly relax
let your body settle here
letting your breathing return to normal to begin meditation with relaxing
is also a way of settling into the lived body
the experience of aliveness in the body
so as you exhale you might relax the muscles of your face
and maybe the character of aliveness in the face changes as the face relaxes
on the exhale softening the shoulders
and as you do so perhaps the shoulders
expand in their aliveness
the range of feelings
softening the belly settling in
letting your belly hang forward and down maybe
the belly relaxes the center of gravity settles in the body
and then to have a global awareness of the body
meaning a wide broad experience of the body as
is available for you
and on the exhale i'm just softening the whole body
and softening into the sense of aliveness in the body
and then relaxing into the body breathing in
many ways breathing is an animating force for our lived life
and feeling though how the body experiences breathing
settling in
and if your mind goes into the world of thoughts maybe think of it as
the world of aboutness maybe even noticing that you're thinking
about something of course
but that's a bit removed from the world of aliveness
here here and now in the body
for these minutes choose aliveness
instead of aboutness
it makes a difference if we live in the world of aboutness
or the world of aliveness it makes a difference for the emotions
that can be present for us
some emotions are born from aboutness the thoughts the stories
and some emotions arise out of the aliveness
aliveness which has a quality of freedom in it openness
allowing
notice the earpoint what arises from your aliveness
not your aboutness
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to see if you can touch into
a place of tender love or good will kindness
that doesn't arise out of aboutness that you're thinking yourself into it
but maybe someplace deeper in embodied in your
heart an aliveness
that comes from being relaxed and open and available for this world
and imagine going into the world now
this way
maybe imagine going into the world with the equivalent of midas is touch
that whatever you touch you meet you touch it with good will
with kindness with care
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
uh so good morning good day
here we are at the in the last talk about anger
and anger might arise out of a particular incident
in the moment and even if it does if it lasts
it has moved from the world of immediacy and aliveness
into the world of our memory and thoughts ideas story making in the mind
and it turns out that a lot of anger anything that's chronic resentment and
irritation has a lot to do with the world of aboutness the world of thinking about
things the storymaking that we do and the more intense and involved we are
with anger the more there's a
diminishment or a loss that we experience there is a kind of suffering that kind
of pain and stress that comes with being angry and there's also the more stronger it is
the more there's a preoccupation with some something about something
and um and that preoccupation means that we're not available for a wider range of our
emotional uh spiritual inner life that um and in our life
that um that uh to not be caught up in anything we're we're
available for a range of responses a range of empathy a range of uh perception of what's happening
and that gets diminished the more we get preoccupied and the one of the
one way to get preoccupied is around anger and at times it gets quite intense
and it really diminishes our capacity to feel to sense to experience to perceive
the world in ourselves as the world of anger tends to get reduced more and more
and it gets reduced off into a world of aboutness even if there's a mood
that's kind of you know angry irritated hostile mood
it's probably being fueled by some background story belief idea that's
going on and to have the courage to drop the beliefs the courage to
drop the preoccupations the stories in order to be present more fully
for the aliveness of our of our life so in this week one of the things i hope
that i've conveyed is that anger is a worthwhile
subject for attention for mindfulness and for study
that rather than having some blanket policy that anger is bad and we shouldn't be angry
we don't need to have that policy because we have a mindfulness practice
that can help us find a way through the anger and we can understand what is
dysfunctional about anger what is causing our stress for ourselves with anger what is
unnecessary what is what diminishes us we can kind of
use it as an object of mindfulness to reclaim our freedom our independence our
ability not to be caught by it and uh in the process of that we learn a lot
and uh so using anger as a as a means a medium
for learning about the grievance we have about the about the difficulty that's happening
about the the challenge that's somehow rather
represented by the anger and by studying it we get to distinguish
between um where the where the essence of the the essential part of study is
sometimes we have to study what's happening externally and understand the situation better
and sometimes we have to understand ourselves better because that's really the genesis or the
the active kind of um center of the anger and that's where
it's productive to bring our attention to so as we as i bring this to a conclusion
this that topic of anger i would like to offer you an acronym
a bit long maybe and uh and the accurate acronym is mad
less to be without mad without anger be coming to madlessness madness
and if you're looking at this at the youtube now in the underneath the photograph where it says a few
information about imc and the information square i have written out the the um the
acronym so the m is motivation
the a is attention d is to diffuse
l is to learn e is empathy
and s is to have story substitution
change the story and then the second s is to speak
we don't want to be mindful and resolve our anger and then become silent when the world needs
us to speak the situation needs us to speak about what's going on we sometimes diffuse anger
so that we can address a real world need so motivation
anger itself think of it as a motivational feeling what does it want what is it trying to
do what's what's really happening there and we're trying to get rid of something
we're trying to change something are we trying to get away from something are we trying to attack someone is there
hostility which is kind of a motivation are we trying to
harm someone hurt someone with our words maybe get back at them
and or are we trying to change a situation that needs to be changed
is it uh or what change are we trying to evoke with anger
trying to make happen so to study what is anger about what's its purpose uh what's it and is it really the
purpose we we stand behind do we have another motivation that's more valuable for us more important that
comes to the surface if we spend time looking at the purpose the motivation of the anger
attention is to really bring a lot of attention to this experience of anger
one of the fundamental aspects of mindfulness meditation
is mindfulness of the body so bringing attention to the body if we really feel our body when we're
angry it tends to dissipate it tends to create some space for it it also it
teaches us a lot about how we're involved with the anger that we're contracted and tight and then
leaning forward or pulling back whatever we're doing
maybe we notice our fist is clenched so to keep coming back to the body i've
been angry in the past where i didn't know what was going on with my body many years ago i was really angry with
someone i didn't know it and there was a pause the person had to go away to do something
and so then i noticed my body and i noticed that i was leaning forward
and tight and so then i came back into myself and it made a huge difference
and so we use attention to notice what's happening here for us and all these different uh practices of
madness all require some use of attention
and then to diffuse it to diffuse means to use these terms in terms of not so
much to take the fuse away but is to dissipate or to reduce the tension
that's there and the less tension there is in anger
the wiser will become the less we're under the influence of the anger
so to develop and learn skills of diffusion of relaxation of calming
breathing deeply relaxing the body taking a posture that's stable and strong that allows
kind of you know a different kind of attention where
we're more present in a in a um
in in a in a way that we are in charge we were
more capable of making wise choices
um and then to learn i think this is one of the great uh
principles around anger always when we're angry there's something to learn
and take the time to learn it what's the lesson that's here
and now for many of us i think there's a huge lesson to be learned
within ourselves what is the attachment that triggered the anger what's the place inside the
belief the sense of self what's the history we have what's the
wound we have that's been now touched by the incident around us
the unattended unresolved wounds we carry with us and so to learn what's going on sometimes we
will learn outside and one of the things to learn outside is to learn
what's going on with the other people what's really happening there many years ago i read about it
that the new york in new york the bus system they
gave as kind of a training for bus drivers they showed them a video of
of people who get on the bus who are very annoying to
bus drivers that they just have behavior which is kind of troublesome difficult
and and they interviewed or described or talked to these people
and found out that they had all kinds of personal circumstances very difficult
learning disabilities maybe
all kinds of personal challenges that were not obvious on the surface and as soon as the bus drivers began looking
at these personal challenges these people had their anger and annoyance to people who
were difficult on the bus decreased dramatically that if we take time to learn about who
people are maybe there's much less reason to be angry
though there might be reasons for compassion and care and having a strong conversation
and then to have empathy to care about others to have love to
have um kindness to um trying to kind of
following up what i just said about learn really get to know people and and
understand more deeply what's going on with them when they behave even people pay very difficult
difficulty and but not so much because they deserve it
but because it's actually better medicine for each of us for ourselves
to have degrees of compassion love kindness then empathy than it is to do the
opposite and to be closed and
not
many of available anger has to do with some story we're telling ourselves and i've had anger with people and i had the
wrong story i had made up a story in which was an interpretation that wasn't really what happened
and and so be very careful the stories you tell yourself the fish gets bigger the more they tell
the story they say uh what stories are you telling and are are they really accurate
check out the story find out say this is what i understand happen and maybe it didn't happen that way
and or maybe there's more to it than meets the eye
and then speak we talked about this yesterday and as i said earlier
mindfulness meditation this buddhist approach to anger is not to make us
passive mute silent uninterested and uninvolved with the world and other people most
anger is social most anger has to do with people around us especially if it's really
really intense and simmers and lasts the anger we have for technology or the
weather or something doesn't have the same power as the anger we have with people in
social circumstances and and
so it implies that sometimes it's very important in the social world to speak and what do we speak how do we speak
how do we speak with kindness and clarity and purpose for bringing the welfare of everyone
involved and so that i think is one of the principles i'd like to end this
discussion on anger the principle that we live a life that
looks for what's best for everyone involved in a situation
we don't look at just what's best for ourselves we look at what's best for everyone
surprisingly even for the people who've harmed us that uh what's best for them
because what's best for ourselves and best for others fits into what's best overall
as we create a better society i'd like to end with a a quote from
mahakusananda he was kind of like the um mahatma gandhi of
of cambodia or i mean it was a after the khmer rouge
the genocide there he was the the buddhist leader of cambodia buddhist monk i met him lovely man very peaceful
very loving full of smiles and he wrote
here i do not question that loving ones of oppressors
cambodians loving the khmer rouge may be the most difficult attitude to achieve
but it is a law of the universe that retaliation hatred and revenge only
continue the cycle and never stop it reconciliation does not mean that we
surrender rights and conditions but rather we use love in all our
negotiations it means that we see ourselves in the opponent
for what is the opponent but being but a being in ignorance
and we ourselves are also ignorant of many things therefore only loving kindness and right
mindfulness can free us
so to practice bring anger bring anger under their purview of our
practice our mindfulness and maybe we can
negotiate with our enemies with love
so speak so thank you and i have a few announcements
uh one is that uh i'll be away on vacation next week and so my friend and wonderful zen teacher
paul haller will come and teach this 7 a.m this this sitting starting monday
and some of you remember paul he came and did a week back last april and april
may when i did the zen vipassana kind of retreat and
so i'm very happy he's coming and the um
tomorrow imc's earth care group has a wonderful teacher named nissera coming to give a dharma talk you
have to go into imc's website i think it's listed under what's new and finally
i mentioned a couple weeks ago i think that i'm doing a day-long retreat on
online on july 9th
and i think it was not so easy to find where to register or the information about it
it should be easier now because now it's in on in the what's new section of imc's website much more clearly
and eventually it'll be clearly i think on the calendar as well and um but for now it's uh you know in
the what's new in the home page so um thank you and i look forward to
coming back in a couple of weeks and i'll be here on the 4th of july thank
you