okay so hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be with you
the gift giving each other the gift of our presence the gift of our
um time our presence supporting each other
in this practice so i thank you all of you for showing up
uh whether it's in real time or whether later you're listening to this on audio
dharma so so for today's practice i wanted to
to bring our attention um to to practice that sometimes we um engage
with here and and happier and i i think they did last a week and
and someone um uh said that oh if we did
appreciation turning our mind turning our awareness to
to what's good what we often don't take uh in fully in
what is good i could do that forever so i thought okay maybe for a while i'll do that once a week at least
as i teach happy hour three times a week maybe once a week we'll engage with the
um heart lifting practice of of joy of joy joy and
which can show up in different ways gratitude can lead to joy vicarious joy happiness for happiness of others
can lead to joy appreciation for what's good about ourselves about others about
um cause and conditions about the world so there's so many ways
to to turn our hearts and minds towards what's good towards what's joyous and as
i said before again it's not in a way to to just be pollyanna's la de da yeah i'm
just going to be you know turn a blind eye to what's challenging the world quite the opposite actually
if we have a reservoir of joy of gladness
it serves us it helps us to face and be with what's difficult
more easily for ourselves and for the world so
it's it's not an avoidance it's actually a way of balancing it's a
way of balancing the 10 000 sorrows of the world with the 10 000 joys because they're it's all
present it's all here but we often because of our evolutionary
um conditioning uh we often turn to what's challenging
what's difficult what's not going right and we ignore
we just don't see as if we have blinders on
we get accustomed too easily to what's actually really really wonderful
really amazing [Music]
my paraphrase sam harris he has a quote about
you know when something really really catastro catastrophic happens in our
lives we and and any of us in some ways we're
just a phone call away perhaps from you know bad news from a doctor or difficult um diagnosis
you know we never know what's going to happen in the future but at those times we turn back we turn back and think oh
when time when life was normal when life was normal or normal enough
normal enough and consider this is when life is normal or normal
enough of course you might be dealing with challenges but of course what i'm saying i'm offering it in general ways
when life is normal enough and instead our minds when life is
normal enough it it turns to finding fault with what seems boring gosh it's
boring nothing is happening in my life or everything that we want everything that
we lack that oh if i had that i would be happier or i would be happy if
so and so and x y and z were in place instead of turning our minds not to say
we give up our aspirations of course keep your aspirations aspirations for
continuing to develop continuing to serve in the best way you can is being who is
you and all beings everywhere continue to aspire for the best
being you can be and let go of the the
the clinging
if i only had that if i only there's a very different feeling between
clinging which has an ouch to it which is kind of painful
versus aspiration that that lifts the heart that inspires that motivates
so i've said plenty and more will come more will come of
course with the guided meditation and whether you're new to this practice whether you're new to
happy hour whatever you need to know will be shared with you so [Music]
relax enjoy the ride so at this time having set the frame
for our practice a bit tonight i'd like to
invite us to land and to arrive ah in our bodies
embodiment embodiment embodiment as we start our guided meditation
[Music] our meditation practice together i invite you to close your eyes that's
comfortable for you [Music] settle land in your seat
arriving taking stock of this being here this moment of
aliveness here here
as always we start with just
sitting being breathed
sitting and being breathed
with each breath softening
releasing releasing the body
releasing thoughts releasing into what is here right now
however it is not wanting it to be otherwise
even if there is unpleasantness in the body or mind pleasant
can we release into it release into
the totality the spaciousness
greater larger more spacious
all encompassing
letting awareness connect with the breath the entirety of the breath
sweet comforting breath however it shows up however it's
breathed in the body
if there are a lot of thoughts
distractions might be helpful to attend to become aware of the breath
in the lower abdomen that can help settle ground
us
as if deep in our belly in our lower abdomen
deep resonances of the breath calming soothing
settling
when your thoughts are arising it's okay
smilingly smilingly
without any judgment release let go
as if blowing on flower petals
gently gently come back later
giving my heart to this practice right now and letting the sensations of the body
and the breath be center stage
calming soothing
you
the buddha says whatever free will you frequently think
and ponder upon that becomes the inclination of your
mind so instead of
pondering pondering upon what is lacking what is
missing what we want want want endless desires
with clinging and grasping let us turn and ponder upon
the goodness the goodness in our lives
the sources of goodness and let us first turn
to the goodness within our intentions our aspirations
for loving caring being kind
being generous being of service
being truthful not causing harm
whatever your values might be
taking a moment to perhaps touch into the top three
if there are more rising it's okay feel feel the goodness
the wholesomeness of these intentions in your heart
this is not a time for judgment and thinking of all the ways you lack
but to bring attention awareness to connect
with your goodness
the wholesomeness the more we connect with the wholesomeness the more it will increase
becomes the inclination of our minds
what inspires you what inspires you
now i would like to invite you
to imagine [Music] an earlier version of yourself
in some ways this earlier version maybe a few years ago or decade ago
this earlier version of you
in some ways we could consider
a better earlier our younger self
has sent us into the future in some ways we are
the progeny the the child
of this younger version of ourselves we are living the hopes and dreams the
aspirations the goodnesses
of a younger version of ourselves
our younger version might have had challenges gifts
can we have a sense of gratitude as if we were turning turning around in time
i'm thanking an earlier version of ourselves
a younger version of ourselves
for their dedication for their perseverance
for hanging in there for their cultivation
maybe for their hard work
maybe for setting the direction so that we are right now
practicing the dharma there was something about this younger
version of ourselves some aspiration for goodness
maybe it was their suffering maybe it was their sorrow their
challenge that drove them [Music]
that inspired them to seek to seek practice to seek
meditation to see community
can we turn around and with an open heart appreciate and think
our younger selves again this is not a time for
self-judgment but intend to turn your mind your heart
to goodness you can choose appreciation goodness
you have choice
perhaps the words arise thank you thank you my dear thank you sweetheart
thank you
thank you for sending me into the future with gifts
with your hopes and aspirations
i see i know there are times that we're hard for you you are suffering
you're in pain thank you for hanging in there for me for everyone
and the gifts the gifts of goodness of your character
stay with appreciating the good not a time to find fault
thank you thank you younger version of me
can also thank your younger self for their wholesome actions
awesome thoughts wholesome actions
awesome words
instead of regretting or shaming our younger selves let's really take this time to appreciate
their goodness their wholesome actions deeds
as if you were seeing a beloved other as if it's not really you
it's another being entirely see them with kind eyes
as if they are your ancestors you're seeing your ancestor
the heart of appreciation bowing to this ancestor
that is you ah
turning to this moment in time in your perception feeling embodied
feeling your body being breathed
the goodness the goodness of wholesome actions thoughts deeds
aspirations living through you
running through you take a moment pause to appreciate it
before we continue
now i'd like to invite you to imagine
the future version of yourself
again life is uncertain we don't know what's going to happen next ever
but for the purpose of this exercise this practice
imagine yourself some time into the future
and this future being future cell
as if they are your child you are sending them off into the future
future you will not see but they will see they look at you
they deserve your best
they are deserve they deserve they want
they ask the best of you
your wholesomeness your wholeheartedness
in service and kindness and love and truthfulness
they demand your best
in the loving in the most loving way
can we have a sense of love care for this progeny
for this version of ourselves sent into the future
to send as much goodness as gift
as gifts to equipment to equip them
to nurture them nourish them
the sense of wholesome beauty
loving duty loving duty as an offering to our future
self
if the word duty doesn't work for you try on loving gift
loving bestowal or anything else
just as they thank you for your effort for your aspirations
inspired wholesome actions and cultivation you love them you want them
to shine to serve
to be the best version of you they can possibly be
offering them your gifts out of love your actions your hard work
your dedication
both to them and to serve all beings
seeing yourself in this line now
your past self your ancestor and now bringing in other ancestors
if you wish to send you into the future
they could not reach
and you appreciating their gifts bowing to their gifts
and sending your gifts your actions your wholesomeness
it's an offering for the future
your future self and all beings who are impacted
by your goodness
looking at you with loving eyes carrying eyes for our sake
for our sake do what needs to be done cultivate what needs to be cultivated
for all of our sakes they tell you
and not to feel it as a burden but it's a sense of aspiration
opportunity agency receiving gifts
giving gifts present future
all around 360 degrees yourself and all beings
may we appreciate all the gifts we have received from our past selves from our ancestors
and appreciate the goodness the capacity to give
cultivate gifts to the future and to all beings everywhere
may all beings know
their deep goodness
may all beings including ourselves be free
[Music]
thank you thank you for your practice
appreciating goodness internally in this moment
all the gifts of the present moment gifts sent
to us from the past gifts into the future
so we have some time for reflections for any aha moments that
might have come up from your own benefit the benefit of
others offering them as gifts you can type them in chat
if only type to me privately i won't read your name just your reflection
and if it's typed to everyone i'll read your name you can also raise your hand
fazel am i saying your name right um it's it's fuzzling
um yeah so i've made a lot of mistakes in the past and i've
actually i've been doing the five contemplations every day
and it's kind of like thinking about how those affect my current situation so this is like a
nice balance that was very nice thank you hmm thanks to the contemplation on the
uh you know karma from past actions yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah thank you for that i
appreciate you bringing that in because with the five contemplations and just to catch
people up the fifth one for anyone who's not familiar with is um
acknowledging that i am the owner of my actions
i'm the owner of my actions my actions are
my arbitrator and protection and we often as you said we focus on the
negative reverberations of our actions and it's just as important to focus on
the positive to balance it with the positive and not just in the past but in the present that yes i'm the owner of my
actions and i have to say that with the five contemplations the fifth one is for me for different people different ones
are really alive and for me all of them but especially the fifth one wow i'm the owner
of my actions whatever do whatever i do for good or
for evil i am the owner i am born of my actions
i'm heir to my actions it's such a rich contemplation so so i appreciate you
yeah realizing oh yes bringing the goodness like yes if i do goodness in the world that's going to percolate
um and also appreciating the goodness in the past yeah beautiful thank you for
that thanks for bringing that in
[Music]
any other reflections or aha moments please raise your zoom hand because of
your physical hand i may not see or you can also type in
chat are any reflections
private appreciation for the goodness you are welcome thank you for your practice
and wonderful to see all the folks on youtube joining us from brazil and uk
and mexico so since no reflections are arising right
now i will say okay one more catherine
um i just had a really sweet experience of
seeing myself through my younger self's eyes and being like
i would be so proud of myself it brought tears of joy to just be like
oh my younger self would be really into who i am now
sweet sweet thanks so much for sharing that yeah that is very very yeah beautiful
yeah to connect yeah thanks for sharing that katrin yeah
yeah um [Music] so a couple of questions are coming so i'll
answer the questions that and then i'd like to go into the um
practice into the groups and reserve time at the end so one question that's coming up is how
to fit with contemplation of death yeah both and
both and as i said when i let this contemplation
future is uncertain we don't know what's going to happen tomorrow we don't know what's going to happen the next moment
absolutely and yet there is there is both and we don't just give
away and stop doing cultivation because we might we'll die we
live fully we live completely giving our gifts into the future knowing
that life can end at any moment so we have to be able to hold really complexity both this moment could be my
last breath and oh yeah i might live another decade and how what do i want to send into the future
another reflection on youtube that i really struggled with this meditation
anger seems to arise on me so how can i appreciate my goodness yeah
in this case might be need the need for forgiveness practice
forgiveness practice for forgiving self in the past for
forgiving letting go letting go and maybe even turning to
the self that is struggling right now with compassion with compassion
to the self that's really angry right now to hold this present self with compassion and
make some room make some room with kindness with kindness
so i do see your hand clear but i would like to turn right now to the to small groups so that we don't
run out of time so with small groups um i like to spend a little bit of time
setting them up and asking you first of all the reason where
we go we practice in small groups is to bring our practice from the cushion from
our eyes closed meet others meet the world in the space
of practice in the space of kindness the space of tenderness it's not about
impressing them it's not about educating them it's not about
managing other people's experience or facilitating the group please only
speak from your own authentic experience not commenting not probing
um others and holding silent
space for yourself and for others when your turn comes you can say pass or you
can share a nugget and please share one nugget we're gonna do the
format that's called the spiral so instead of a long monologue you share if you have five nuggets you only share one
one nugget one thing that came up for you then you pass it on to the next person
they might say past they might share one nugget one thought then the third person and then it comes back to you and then
you go around around a few times sharing from your own experience and sharing
holding space with kindness
for each other it's not just go and talk amongst yourself it's a very sacred space it's a
very it's a ritualistic way of participating this way
so with that i'm going to create the rooms and invite you to uh
be kind to yourself take care of yourself take care of others
let there be a lot of um yeah care let there be a lot of care
so so i'm going to open the room take care be kind
here we go welcome back everyone we have just about
a minute or two for any reflections that might have come up
during your practice in sangha you're welcome to ru to um
[Music] raise your hand or type in chat
bill hey uh i wanted to ask a question
and maybe the answer would be too long to fit in at the hour but i'm gonna ask it anyway we we talked
about you know aspiration at what point does aspiration become striving
because there seems like there's a gray area there where i aspire for things but i really want these things you know i
mean in terms of development yeah i don't know
yeah you know that's that's a very good question um that's and also i really appreciate how
there is sensitivity that you have bill that you know that yeah there can be a gray area and how to tell the difference
so i turn it back to you and turn it back to embodiment
feel in your body what it feels like there is a different feeling between
aspiration inspiration and striving it's just you can feel it
and and if you will know and if you don't know just
continue to sit with it you will know bill all right thank you thank you for that question lovely
um quick couple of reflections before we close uh sarah says i like thinking about my
younger self going for her aspirations and dreams which produce results that i feel grateful for today beautiful thanks
for sharing that mary says appreciation for sangha for the witness received ah beautiful
and dhanu says thank you niki for offering this so consistently during this whole pandemic time
it has enriched my life so much and attending in person today such a joy to be with your sweet loving self oh that's
so sweet thank you so much for being here and showing up and and yeah your
presence your practice and for you and all of you all of you thank you your
presence is a gift to me we give each other's gifts your practice is a gift to
me we gift each other give each other gifts so so with that
um one last thing sheila i hadn't previously considered the goodness of an
earlier form of myself who acted courageously in the face of adversity at one time in my life yes
yes may we consider the courageousness oh that touches me so much may we
appreciate so thank you dear ones thank you for your practice thank you for the courage of
your earlier selves that have sent you into the future and here you are practicing the dharma how beautiful may
all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you all be well