welcome welcome again it's nice to see you all here
so tonight i'd like to start with a little story so just a brief little story that's in the vasudi manga
this is the a little bit later than the polycanon
and i'm embellishing this story so this isn't it uh verbatim
but it goes like this so imagine that you're in the desert and you don't
have any water and you have some distance to travel and it's pretty precarious
and then as you're traveling you come over a little rise into the distance you see like oh that looks like that might
be palm trees but you're not sure it might be a mirage
so you head that direction and you notice yeah okay it seems pretty
steady those palm trees are still there as you start walking you start
encountering people and they have wet hair and they're carrying bundles of wet
clothes so this gives you some encouragement like okay this is an oasis
that's just right over there and you get really excited having been in the desert and then
saying okay here's an oasis so you keep on walking you arrive
and it's beautiful there's this big
lake of this cool water
you feel so happy like oh it's here
plenty of water nice and cool here there's shade under the trees
then you drink the water you jump in the lake you get cleaned up
you get refreshed you get out
feeling really contented happy
and then you lie down in the shade of a tree and have a rest if you're not asleep
maybe you're just resting against the tree maybe you're not lying down but a certain amount of contentment that
arises this certain feeling of okay
not a lot of troubles but just happy to be there
so this desert crossing the desert without
water might sometimes feel like our practice our life
that there's this uh burdensome and difficult and not feeling nourished not feeling
like we have enough in this sense that we have to go
somewhere we have to go across this uh sandy
desert that's not so easy to walk on sand sometimes
there's this relentless heat and maybe you're even feeling a little bit lost not sure where you're going
and then this idea of glimpsing an oasis glimpsing oh there might be something
here that can be a support
that can be something that's nourishing and find some respite from the heat and from
this thirst maybe in our practice maybe this was
early in our practice recognizing that maybe mindfulness is a place that can
provide some benefit or provide some
nourishment in some kind of way but in the beginning we often just have this
glimpse of it and we don't necessarily trust it
but we have a glimpse enough that we're willing to keep on going
and then when we have seen others who are coming with the wet hair or with
bundles of wet clothes or something that's kind of like being inspired by maybe coming to a meditation center
maybe meditating with others and seeing oh there's others who
practice this way they seem happy you're relaxed or however or satisfied or
they have wet hair and at that moment that's what you're looking for is wet hair
when you're in the desert hot feeling like you're thirsty
so we see clues that aren't just that are just a bit more than these little glimpses that we might have with
mindfulness and there's a certain delight there's can be a certain uprising of
maybe this is for me too
and then when we arrive at the oasis i realize there's plenty of water plenty
of water there's this feeling of happiness like okay
okay here's i can stay here for a while and drink some of this water and feel
like i like supported and nourished by it
and then we also dive in the water we feel refreshed and there's something inside of us that starts to settle like oh okay
there's something here that's can be helpful for me
then we have this certain amount of contentment
often we think about this contentment arises because we got what we wanted we
wanted some water but i'd like to encourage us to think about
another way to interpret this is the contentment arises is because we are no
longer have this strong desire for water it's the ending
of the desire that wish for something different than what we're having
that allows us some contentment rather than just getting what we want
so often in our lives we do actually get what we want but have you noticed how it doesn't
really the satisfaction for that doesn't last very long we do get to sleep in sometimes we do
have good meals sometimes the weather is beautiful sometimes right we we do get these things that we want
but it never seems quite enough so the contentment is
not just because we got what we want but because there's the desire has been
abated the desire has been rested and there's more than one way
to let the desire quiet to let it soften
i'm going to talk a little bit more about this but still i want to kind of say something about this uh this story
after drinking the water diving in the water then this idea of like maybe leaning against one of these palm trees
and taking a rest maybe we're not sleeping but now just viewing and seeing what
else is happening at this oasis this recognition that nothing else needs
to be done right now we got here we have some water
presumably there's some food too or maybe we already had food with us and so there's no sense of urgency if
things have to be different no pushing or pulling kind of you know like pushing trying to
shove our experiences away or pulling trying to keep our experiences with us but just relaxed under the tree
and so from this place of relaxing underneath the tree we can see things differently
than if when we were feeling lost uh in the desert so literally we see things differently we
in the case of the story we see the water we see the palm trees
but we all have this experience too that when we're hungry and tired or
didn't sleep well or got bad news or whatever it might be then we see things a particular way
compared to when we feel content relaxed happy we see things a different
way in the case when we're a little bit grumpy
and because we haven't eaten or retired or whatever it might be
then maybe we tend to kind of like look at the negative side or have a little bit more contracted view
but when we're relaxed and feel content a certain amount of contentment
then this can be a little bit more open our view what we see
but we're noticing and not only that there can be a little bit more steadiness
this feeling like things are okay yeah okay the kids are really loud when
they're playing in the water over there but it's okay whereas you know if we were
in a little bit of a bad mood we might get really irritated about the kids playing in the water for example
so we could say that buddhist practice is about just this being able to see
things differently to create the conditions in which there can be this being able to see the bigger
picture and to have a certain amount of steadiness
to not feel like we're being buffeted or pushed around by our experiences but to
have a little bit more relaxed and open perspective and to see
what's arising and what's really happening as opposed to just being caught and consumed with the
difficulties and to no longer be have this enchantment of
or lost in stories about how things are or how we wish they
were but to actually see how they are
so in this story there's a certain amount of joy and happiness
that supports theorizing of this contentment that supports the arising of being able
to see clearly so joy and happiness are an integral part of practice but
they're not the point of practice we need them we need them for our life
but they're also a support for practice partly because they help create the
conditions in which there can be a certain amount of relaxation a certain amount of openness
so that we can see a little bit bigger so our spiritual path isn't only about
having great experiences our meditation practice isn't only about having [Applause]
wonderful meditative experiences we all know that these experiences
cannot be sources of lasting happiness they can bring pleasure and there can be
happiness but they're not sources of lasting happiness
in contrast being able to see things clearly can be a source of lasting happiness
when we start to see how things really are and to put down the
stories we have or the busyness in the mind that we have that
prevents us from seeing
so this seeing the bigger picture with a certain amount of steadiness
we could call this equanimity and the poly word is upeka
and etymologically we could say that upeka means to
be look upon and one way uh one reason why i kind of
like this way of understanding is look upon is to highlight that it's
different than look away it's look upon
because sometimes equanimity people think like well it's a certain amount of indifference or detachment or
coolness or indifference or something like that and
i would say no that's more about looking away but equanimity
is born out of this joy and happiness and contentment is not the only way to
get to equanimity it's one way and it's about to look upon
to seeing the big picture not just our uh what we're concerned with at that
moment but to be able to see what other people are doing what's
happening with them to see that not only is maybe the children are
really loud that are plain but also it's comfortable underneath this tree
and maybe i feel a little bit hot but i'm not thirsty
so we don't get stuck on the things that are unpleasant or stuck on the things that are pleasant
but be able to see the whole range there's perfectly neutral things happening unpleasant things happening and pleasant
things happening so in some ways
we might imagine i talked about it uh this contentment is kind of like leaning against the tree but
maybe it's more about being at the top of a hill and then you can see you know further you can see a little bit wider
maybe that's a better way to imagine kind of this idea of lupaka
and so upeka has this awareness of whatever is happening it's connected to what's happening
seeing what's happening but it also has this inner balance
this steadiness this um
being connected to the foundation in some ways we can think of it like how uh
sailboats have achieved i'm not a sailor i know that uh
jim is a sailor here but a keel my understanding is this you know this blade i'll call it a
blade that's underneath the boat that helps it to not tip over when the winds are pushing on it
so equanimity in some ways is like having this keel that allows us to experience the winds
the winds are still there but we're not going to tip over with them helps keep the
boat upright so it's this steadiness of mind and
steadiness of heart in the face of still being connected
with whatever's happening all of our inner and our
outer experiences so not only what we see
out there is the way i was describing it but also what we see in here
our experiences maybe
we notice that uh some impatience with equine you're like okay it's just
impatience we don't have to add a story on i'm a bad person i've been practicing all these years i
shouldn't be impatient or something like that
and so with equanimity it makes our lives easier of course it does
not being pushed around so much by our experiences
whether our experiences include the news cycle or difficulties with finances or
partners or or our inner life feelings of
confusion or despair or racing thoughts troubling thoughts
whatever it might be but equanimity allows us to
not stumble around or be pushed around by these
recently i had to take some medication that um for a little while that i knew
was going to make me feel a little bit off i'll just use this vague word off
because that's what it felt like and and somehow just like having this
knowledge like okay i don't feel so great but it's just because i'm taking this
medication just that kind of a knowledge allowed me to like okay that's just how
it is right now so sometimes just being able to see the
bigger picture seeing that oh things there's conditions for what's arising
there are reasons for what's arising and sometimes having that
can help us to have this steadiness of equanimity so in this ways equanimity helps us to
see bigger but seeing bigger also helps us to understand the conditionality
maybe right no guarantees but we can see like oh okay
of course i feel this way i didn't sleep well last night i'm taking this medication whatever it might
be so equanimity also helps us to see more
deeply into our experience with this steadiness
of heart the steadiness of mind in some way can
equanimity can be like a tripod that allows a telescope or
it could be like a microscope that allows us to see more deeply something that we wouldn't be able to see just
with our regular busyness or regular
ways of interacting with our environment
and so what do we see when we see things more deeply
we see that they're changing there's so many different ways we can talk about changing there's can be the
all these different time scales right things that have the nature to arise have the nature to pass away
things that have the nature to be born have the nature to die
but also there can be when the mind is really quiet and really settled we can start to
see that there's a little bit even a flickering of our experiences
the things aren't as steady and solid as we
might imagine them to be so economically helps us to see this
quality of our experiences
unlike this sense of like something being stuck and
impenetrable or um unable to really
have a way in which there's any flexibility
instead of that we can see oh yeah okay this isn't as
as i thought it was this uncomfortable experience in my knee
when i'm sitting maybe that's not just this pain but with equinemen we
can see we have the patience we have the capacity to just be with the experience
a little bit longer and to see the flickering quality of it
we also can see that our experiences are not inherently satisfying
to be sure there are pleasant experiences and there are unpleasant experiences but
we still haven't quite found you know that experience that's going to be a source of lasting happiness
and with seeing more deeply we start to see even those things that we were pretty sure were going to make
our life better make things happy or satisfying in some way
we start to see oh yeah even those aren't as satisfying
and we find that even though we might be chasing after things thinking that this this is going
to be the thing that's going to make me happy
with some steadiness we can see oh yeah actually it doesn't make sense to
hold on to this thing this that promise of this
experience promise of this object
because it's not as steady as i thought it was
then naturally our relationship to those objects or those experiences shift it's just
natural we don't have to make it happen and we just are not holding on so tightly
and then when we're not holding on so tightly there can be more ease
more freedom more spaciousness
and as we do this and as we kind of explore our experiences with a mind and a heart that has some equanimity we
start to understand our experiences more fully and we start to see that
every time there's a liking of something that means there's a disliking of
something else it's just impossible to not have one without the other
and so we start to see like oh yeah chasing after our preferences
just really highlights everything that isn't our preference instead of just having a little bit more
open and relaxed view about things and not having to be so
much spending our energy and our time trying to just surround ourselves exclusively
with our preferences
so this not chasing after our preferences seeing
things aren't quite as satisfying seeing that there are changes as i said creates this
um conditions in which there can't be just letting go this kind of little bit more spaciousness
that that alone allows the mind to be even more unagitated
and liberation freedom is an unagitated state
so in this way spending some time with equanimity cultivating equanimity
recognizing equanimity is a way in which we are
kind of like the goals and the means get uh similar
if freedom is unagitated an equanimity isn't type of unagitation
we can see where equanimity is uh helps support the type of letting go
that supports liberation as well as itself being an experience
that's similar to a liberation in the same family
so sometimes we might think as a concept equanimity just might seem unappealing
some people say that they don't really want equanimity it sounds boring
it sounds flat instead they might want this juiciness this gusto this of the joy and we want
the excitement of experience or we might this passionate involvement with life
and it might sound like sometimes when we hear this word equanimity it might feel
like there's a sort of disconnection or not caring
and to be sure indifference sometimes masquerades
as equanimity and there will be times in our practice
when we slide into indifference when we kind of disconnect from our
experience and we're feeling a little bit shut down and maybe we're feeling a little bit
cold and removed that's natural this happens but that's
not equanimity that's more indifference and in some ways i might
say that it's important for us to have that experience to have this indifference arise
to recognize oh this is what it feels like to be disconnected
this is what it feels like when there's might be
some less agitation but there's also a sense of
disconnection or not caring or
um this is arises when there's a little bit of aversion has arisen
so sometimes we might even call this a version but it can feel we might have this idea that that's what equanimity is
but instead equanimity has this sense of aliveness the sense of vitality
the sense of connection that's with some openness and spaciousness and warmth
but another reason why equanimity might not sound like it's something
we're so interested in is because we might come to believe that
this there might be this uh underlying belief that
we're not so sure why would our life be like if we didn't have lots of drama
in some way or other the drama of getting rid of some
difficulty or the drama of defending the one sense of
self or the drama of bolstering one sense of self make sure we look good to everybody
i'm using this word drama sometimes it is dramatic sometimes it's really subtle also
these types of things but maybe we're a little bit unsure what would be there
if we didn't have this maybe i could use the word busyness this
busyness of trying to get rid of the difficulty solve some problem
trying to bolster this self make make ourselves look good
so that might be another reason why there might be some hesitation or
maybe this idea that i don't know equanimity just doesn't sound so interesting
but i would like to say that what we all really want
is some stable sense of well-being
that can't be shaken by circumstances
and this arises when we have some equanimity
in some ways like the mind with equanimity is like a mountain that it's remains there even when there's
tornadoes or hurricanes or these types of things
we we might have this idea we want to be happy and certainly we do
but what were um
there's this way in which always like searching for happiness because things that we think are going to be happy turn
out make us happy turn out not to make us happy so then there's this relentless search
which might be subtle but can you imagine what it might be
like to have like this really radical contentment
it's okay everything's okay i don't have to go
fix that it's not perfect i don't have to fix it i don't have to hold on to this it's enjoyable but i'll be okay if
it goes i think this is so much what human beings are really looking for maybe a
place to rest a place to feel safe
and a place that in order to have that it can't be susceptible to whatever is happening in
our the world or whatever is happening in our inner life
and i like this uh this there's these few lines from
um the awakening poem from cebutti tsubuti was a monk at the time of the
buddha and it was the tradition sometimes to
capture these uh poems about when people had awakening experiences
and the way that he describes this reminds me of this idea of equanimity
so that's part of his awakening versus go like it goes like this
my little hut is roofed and pleasant
sheltered from the wind so rain sky
as you please i don't know i there's something very
sweet about this i kind of like this that he's roofed that he has his refuge he
has this shelter and sheltered from the wind
i think many of us have heard about these eight worldly winds these things that push us around
praise and blame fame and disrepute gain in laws
and pleasure and pain and of course we only want one half of all of those
dyads but every life gets both
both halves of those we get all eight there's nobody that's immune to this
but sabuti talks about in his hat that's roofed and pleasant sheltered from the wind
so rain sky or sky rain as you please so he's not trying to
make things be a particular way he's maybe it'll be sunny maybe it'll be
rainy it's okay but having the confidence that we can meet whatever might arise
so equanimity i talked about the way that in this little story that i started with
is you know feeling like you're in the desert and then having the happiness and or the joy of seeing the oasis the
happiness of having actually drunk from the the oasis so that's one way
in which we can have some equanimity is to keep practicing
when we encounter joy and happiness there are moments that may not be large
giant moments but there are some moments of joy and happiness that do arise in
our life yay the the weather's going to be great
yay the newspaper arrived on time in the morning so if you
for those of us who still read newspapers i have them delivered
i was just visiting my mom recently and she does i have to say i just love this to go out
in the morning and get the paper i myself don't but i just love this at my mom's house
so to keep practicing when we encounter joy and happiness often we kind of like stop practicing
there's a way we might like stop being mindful or we might i feel like we don't need to practice
anymore because maybe in some ways we feel like oh we arrived we got what we wanted we have this joy we have this
happiness and that's the purpose of practice so i'm gonna stop
but there's an encouragement can we stay mindful can we still be with the
experience not abandon ourselves with it experience it fully
but not forget practice in a relaxed easy gentle way
and this is a natural progression to go from joy which tends to have a little more energetic feeling
happiness which has a little more subtle contented feeling and then to equanimity
doesn't always happen but that's one way in so just an encouragement to continue
practicing when you are experiencing joy and happiness
another way is to actually really cultivate this i might
say this inner reservoir of well-being this well this reservoir that can be a
resource no matter what the circumstances are
so to spend time really noticing when there is any sense of well-being
that feeling that we get when we are generous to others that feeling when we are
letting those people close to us know how much we care about them
when we're doing loving-kindness practice maybe there's a way in which the heart opens
so really tuning into these experiences
when they do arise maybe they're not that often maybe they're very often whatever it is for
you tuning in it's just so that the
heart and the mind remember that there is this capacity for this
feeling of well-being and so there's less fear about loss for
example if there's a part of us that understands where deep happiness arises
deep happiness arises from this letting go from this opening from this
relaxing sometimes it arises from
an external experience that brings pleasure but pleasure is not the same as happiness
and it's really would behoove us to kind of like explore that how are they related but distinct
not all happiness comes out of pleasure but the more we are able to dip into
this sense of well-being the less likely we are to be thrown off by balance thrown off balance by
these eight worldly winds play praise and blame
gain and loss pleasure and pain fame and disrepute
and so one more way that there's a number of ways we can work with equanimity
another way is to just practice with some of the wisdom
practices and to remind ourselves
yeah things do change
the nature of things to not be inherently satisfying
partly because they change and so to borrow some of this wisdom
that we know from other experiences that allows us to maybe relax and soften
a little bit and to open so that then we can sit on the hill
and to see a little bit bigger have a bigger vista bigger view
maybe you can imagine that you don't know how to swim
and you fall in the water and
and then you thrash around right if you don't know how to swim of course you do you feel like okay i gotta get out to
you but if you have a life jacket on
then you can paddle around and find your way you don't have this fear of you know drowning
so cultivating well-being or borrowing some wisdom
can be a way which can be some life jackets that can help us to have some equanimity
and no matter whether the water is cold or hot or or just right
so joy happiness well-being help create the conditions for equanimity to arise
equanimity is sometimes said to be a higher happiness
because it allows for this steadiness and the face of whatever is happening
and then equanimity creates the conditions for letting go which is said to be the highest
happiness
so without this idea that this oppressive idea that we have to be happy all the time and
that we have to have joy in all these things just in this talk i wanted to connect
this idea of happiness and equanimity
and then equanimity to liberation so this idea that happiness is an
integral part of our path we can cultivate we can
roll around in it there's no reason not to allow ourselves to be nourished by it
and then stick with it with the practice and allow it to turn into a certain contentment which
can be a support for equanimity that equanimity can be a support for letting go
which is support for greater and greater freedom which of course is happiness
so here we go kind of like this circle so
with that i'd like to wish you all a wonderful memorial day
i didn't connect this necessarily to memorial day but it occurred to me that oh today is
memorial day so wishing you all a wonderful evening
thank you