good morning or good day everyone and welcome
an English word that I'm fond of is the word aspiration
to Aspire and I think part of the reason I like it is that um
it uh from the Latin roots French Roots it means to breathe
Aspire is uh like respiration um and just like inspiration as well
they all come from this root word uh for breathing and uh pointing to the profundity of
breathing how it's deeply connected to so many things and to connect our aspiration our
desires to something that's so deep and integral and deeply connected to
ourselves as the breathing contributes to this idea for me that
aspiration is a positive word for desire it's a kind of Desire that is not
um uh
treated as somehow wrong in Buddhism there's a kind of simplistic
understanding the Buddhism that all desires are somehow wrong or should be transcended in some way
but there's a very important place for a healthy skillful desires and aspiration
to have the wish the
to direct oneself towards a particular purpose and goal that comes out of the
heart the heart's wish the heart's aspiration the hearts
calling may be your stirring that it wants something it like
it wants something but it's a wanting it's a desire that because it comes from breathing
comes from a place of feeling full it comes from a place of being content
and settled it doesn't come from a sense of lack that I don't have enough I need more it
rather comes from if anything from a sense of contentment fullness like I
have enough and what seems to emerge in this very settled Place peaceful place is an
aspiration and there are many that can be together or in the same
person certainly the aspiration to um
to somehow do good in the world it's a beautiful thing
the aspiration to become free ourselves to become free of our
the ways in which we're limited the heart is Shackled or contained
to become free from our attachments or preoccupations and
Neurosis Around Me Myself and mine this is a phenomenally beautiful thing
and so sitting in meditation can be motivated by this aspiration if
we get settled enough quiet enough maybe to feel and sense
that maybe at the root of where breathing begins that there there seems
to be almost like a natural desire or wish or or inclination towards something
profound so to uh
if you like this kind of language if you don't you can ignore it hear what I'm about to say
to take uh as you take your meditation posture make your body your temple
make your body The Meditation Center
let your body become the sacred grove in which you go to meditate
let this body be appreciated
is what as the field as a territory is the
the location
for a deep connection to life to oneself
to the depths of our stirring depth of our aspiration about how to live this life
and too gently close your eyes
and gently on the exhales relax your body
might start to the top your head and your face
relaxing softening
sometimes the face face of muscle muscles can hold a lot of discontent
wanting things to be different
than to relax those muscles of discontent
muscles of anxiety
and letting the relaxation send into your shoulders
softening gentling the shoulders
into then moving down to the chest
heart and the solar plexor plexal area relax soften
sensing deep inside the Torso
to what can be relaxed and softened there
and moving the relaxation down into the belly
softening in the belly
down into the hips and the legs softening
and perhaps a final relaxation is global throughout the body
releasing any holding in your body
and then feeling your way into your body deep inside to maybe where
breathing begins or where
aspiration arises from the depth of fear
letting there be an aspiration connecting to whatever your aspiration is here and now
about how to be present
aspiration of what to actualize in terms of
being present directly
being free of attachments fear
the aspiration to let the hearts be free the mind at peace Here and Now
and with the word aspiration meaning and
etymologically to breathe perhaps you can allow
a gentle aspiration to be present
to be free to let go
to be there with every breath breathing in and breathing out
as you're here in the present moment the best you can
being mindful being present for what is your breathing in and breathing out
let there be an aspiration
to be present connect to find and aspiration
that supports you in wanting to be present here and now
perhaps who you can be connected to something that takes you to the depths of your
life
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine that as you exhale
your exhale the exhaling breath carries with it
whatever wishes you have for the world
and if those wishes or wishes of ill will
you'll spread seeds of ill will that will Sprout all over
but if you breathe out good will
those will be the seeds that you'll spread across this world
perhaps in some deep place inside below all the layers of challenging
feelings and experiences you've had
maybe there's a place that you have good will for this world
will you aspire to spread Good Will around everywhere
perhaps as seeds so as you exhale
May these words that I speak
as I speak these words may your Exile exhale
carry your good will your aspiration for goodness in this world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
may all beings be free
and and may everything your breath touch touches
may it receive your well-wishing
[Music]
thank you
thank you foreign
come to the fourth third talk that's the series called conditioned
consciousness and the idea that our the way that we
perceive or experience or construct the sense of consciousness
is something that is conditioned it's uh constructed or or influenced by all
kinds of other factors and and uh in our minds and our hearts and
in our life and that um as we start understanding some of these
conditions some of these influences for our how we put together the idea of
consciousness that we can appreciate how much uh
some some conditions created Consciousness which doesn't feel so good
and others help produce one that feels wonderful
and then so today I want to talk about the range or the distinction between
craving and aspiring craving is considered to be a form of
suffering in Buddhism it's a craving it has a compulsion to it the kind of kind
of if it's strong has Us by the throat to by the nose pulling us around and
we're not very free the only Freedom we can find with intense compulsion there's
two kinds of freedoms you can find but with the with the craving itself there can be a sense of of Freedom when we
give into it but uh it's kind of just going going along giving in to attachments so it has
free reign it's not a real freedom the second kind of Freedom we can discover
is uh we can have craving but we don't succumb to it don't give in to it we
have the ability to see that we're craving and not pick it up not get involved
enough so that we have a broader sense of awareness of presence of attention to
it and part of the effect of craving it tends to like other tensions it tends to
narrow the range of of consciousness attention tends to be focused now on the
object of the craving and so it could be a laser focus it could be a narrowing of
the field that can be things get smaller and tight and kind of
both tense both and agitated sometimes
hot sometimes there's a feeling of pressure that comes with craving
kind of like it's uh saying it has to be now and um
and uh but craving it's a real relatively shallow as powerful as it can
be is a kind of a shallow uh segment or level layer of the Mind
that keeps us somehow alienated from ourselves disconnected partly because
we're constantly looking outside for the object of craving and and so we can't
settle back into ourselves as we settle back and relax and really
find a place to rest inside where we're free of craving free of that
compulsion and agitation contraction with time we can then start discovering
that there are well Springs of Desire of wishes of aspiration that arise from end
that it can occur without any compulsion and that those because a kind of a
Wellspring that Wells up the influence they have on our sense of awareness is to support it just to boy
it it's almost like it can uh if you're a practitioner knows something about
being present and mindful the underlying welling up of this aspiration to be free to be
compassionate to be you know whatever it is that comes from the depth of Who We
Are that it's almost like it spreads and expands the sense of Consciousness the
sense of awareness rather than contracts it and narrows it where this aspiration has to be
expectation free it has to be um
free of a certain kind of conceit all of which kind of tighten up again and
narrow the scope and aspiration that a wish that is not
compulsive doesn't need to be fulfilled even it's just like this is what the
heart's wish is and if it's possible great if not it Just arises and like the
exhale it just kind of can just flow out and you don't necessarily lose
aspirations like that if they don't get fulfilled or don't get acted on any more
that you lose your exhales just because you exhaled once another exhale will
come another the aspiration if it's a sincere deep aspiration it'll be there and come
as well and um and so part of the advantage of sitting
in meditation being Mindful and really kind of learning to settle below the layers of agitation layers of tension
layers of craving is to come to a place where we are have these deeper
Wellsprings of compulsive free desires
expectation free with expert expectation doesn't have to
come with sense of need this needs to happen and so this idea of
noticing that the difference between craving and aspiration is a very
significant exercise I think some people don't have much sense of what an aspiration is and the
way I'm talking about maybe they've never kind of been pointed to it and for me I was never I grew up without
ever having any sense of what that might be but it was through doing this Buddhist
practice that I I came to appreciate that there's this kind of I called it
sometimes biological a biological Drive sometimes a
biological and kind of desire
because it didn't seem to be connected to the ordinary cognitions of the Mind the ordinary kind of surface thinking
and concerns or the surface emotions they seem to be kind of more built into
kind of the depth of the whole operating system here and so biological if I use that word in
a sense that it um it uh
um you know it's deeper than than cognition and thinking and those things
this kind of aspiration can feed into our cognitions our desires our dreams
our imaginations are all kinds of things
and um and uh they can really enrich a person's life
phenomenally to come from this place so to begin noticing a difference
between craving and aspiration and noticing that the different way in which
it affects you physically emotionally and conscious wise how does it switch
and change the sense of being aware depending which one you're operating from
one of the things that I believe is often the case is that with craving there's often a feeling of discontent
that craving can often come from a sense of lack and so that sense of lack we're trying to Crave to fill it return to
assuage it we're trying to soothe ourselves or distract ourselves
or entertain ourselves so we don't have to feel the pain of Defense sense of lacked emptiness that we might have
in with aspiration there's a there's a contentment
there's a sense of No Lack a sense of fullness because we've learned to take whatever
lack discontent there might be and bring our attention right into it and kind of
massage it from the inside out turn it inside out and fill it with something
that's profound fill it with ourselves fill it with awareness
fill it so that the tension of lack the tension inherent in in this kind of
feeling of vacuity or pain or loneliness
begins to relax and soften and begins to settle
and um so I associate craving with discontent
and aspiration with contentment and the
and the funny thing about uh discontent is that um
the when we're discontented we're kind of
the mind is kind of content full discontent churns up thoughts and ideas
and desires and aversions and projections and
fantasies and all kinds of things so discontent actually it was kind of busy
agitated mind so it's content discontent is a mind that's contentful
contentment on the other hand allows for settling and quieting of the mind and
the heart and in a certain kind of way contentment is content free
there's space and room for inputs for things to arise and be
there and feel deeper more deeply what's going on in this world craving tends to create very little room
because it's so content full of all kinds of churning stuff
contentment tends to be content free in that there's a room for us to feel not
only the world be aware of the world in a significant way but also to be aware of ourselves
and be aware really what's going on to be able to be be sensitive enough to start living from
and feeling something that's more the depth of who we are the fullness of Who We Are
rather than than uh this funny thing of lack which tends to
be yes there's sense of lack that feels empty but then becomes kind of contentful or something
so I hope that this word play Within you know lack and fullness and
contentful and content free is points you to something that's possible that
allows you to begin seeing more clearly the difference between a world live from
craving and a world live from the from aspiration
and so may aspiration be your your Guiding Light
that supports you in living with desires in a way that's phenomenally free
compulsive free so thank you very much and
I look forward to being here again with you tomorrow