so welcome everyone here in person and
online i appreciate so much the chance to come
together for this purpose that we have and to share the dharma now
and uh with this pandemic we've had it's been two years since i've taught my the
unusual intro to meditation class i would sometimes teach it two or three
times a year and maybe since it's been so long i'd like to do a
demonstration that i often do at the end of the intro class some of you have seen it
but i think it'll be done a little bit differently than usual and
it has to do with holding up a flower
and and there is a
kind of an important zen story that the zen tradition began
when the buddha held up a flower and a particular monk mahakashapa smiled
and the buddha saw the smile and then recognized him as
a kind of a successor a teacher and he then passed the lineage on down through the centuries
until it came to the modern world and it's this little story is a little
bit of a co-on you know some some kind of
you know contemplative question for everyone like why what was it that both why did the buddha just
hold up a flower and why did the monk smile and why was
he smiling so significant is it volume okay is it going in and out
or is it good okay and uh so i can't exactly answer that or
maybe the talk is an answer to it but i just appreciate so much that uh
when we see this flower maybe we see the suchness of the flower
the flower is being held up by itself and so it's it's alone it's just the flower it's a nasturtium and some of you
might know and it has a particular color and
kind of number of petals and it just kind of allowed to be itself in
the moment and uh so one way of talking about that
is to call it the suchness of the flower it just is itself
but i could um i can do something interesting with it
and that is i could hold up another flower
if you can see it there's a maybe it's so small maybe you can't see it so well but there's a little yellow flower next
to the nasturtium and now we can say something we couldn't
say before we can say that nasturtium is the big flower
and this little composite is the small flower
and uh and now it's not just the suchness of the flower by itself the suchness now exists in our minds
in relationship to the other flower
i can i'm pretty confident that these flowers if they looked at each other
are not looking at each other and not thinking about each other and are not comparing each other and doesn't occur
to one that i'm the big one and oh no i'm the small one or something
it just the suchness of the flower so but then we could do something very an
interesting thing again is i could put down the small flower
and i can pick up this flower
a rose and now we can now something very interesting has happened
the small flower the big what was big flower before has now become the small flower
you bring up a big rose next to the nasturtium and the starshim is a smaller flower
and that contrast that comparison of the two of these
flowers does not exist in the flower itself
it's a provisional let's say interpretation it's a it's a it's a
provisional label that comes out of the comparative mind that sees one as being different than
the other so this what was big now has become small
so the uh
so a tremendous amount of human suffering comes from comparisons
comparing ourselves to ideals we don't live up to ideals
we do live up to them and now everyone else should should other people are not living up to them
compare comparing ourselves to people compare themselves to each other
sometimes the comparison is that i'm not
as much x as someone else someone else says that you know that uh
you're i'm more you than you like the letter u
uh and uh the uh
and then people you know tremendous amount of suffering when those has projected other people that people are somehow wrong and bad because of
something about them because they're old and people use ageism and people who are older will
often comment on how they're now ignored or not treated well or sometimes they're treated
you know ways that they wish they weren't because they're seen in some kind of category of being old and
incapable and people are treating them a certain way
people because of their size their compare this comparison people like their hair
color here the length of here kind of here skin color
uh ethnicity all kinds of things that people do to compare each other
that and make judgments about the value of one over another
we compare ourselves to who we were before before i was young and now i'm not and i
wish i had been young or still young or now i'm not as not as much
as my as as a z as i was before whatever z stands for
i'm not as you know now i'm wrinkled
and rather than and think well in our you know beautiful people don't
have any wrinkles whatsoever i grew up with a person a friend of my
parents the woman apparently never smiled
because she was attempting not to get any wrinkles
and so but what about the suchness of the human
being what about your suchness is there such a thing where you can be held up like a flower
and you're allowed just to be as you are in the
perfection of suchness in the simplicity of suchness without any comparisons at all
what's the beauty of each of us of each of you
in what way are you a flower in what way are you
perfect wonderful as you are and is that is that valuable
is that somehow sentimental or pollyannish or
not really realistic because we should be comparing ourselves or
those comparisons are real or they're not real but they're imposed on me the world around me is constantly
making comparisons and i'm having i don't feel i'm not i'm not safe in the world because
of what people are doing and their comparisons to against me and so to emphasize the suchness of us of us
maybe that just allows the status quo to be there the status quo is is harmful
is that the case or is there some way valuable way
where we can appreciate our own suchness can we gaze upon ourselves in such a way
that the gaze does not have any comparative thinking
we're not compared to before to after
to even ideals even wonderful ideals where we're not compared to
other people it's just the simplicity of who we are
in a way that maybe we allow the flower to be itself
now it's possible in the course of
flowers being flowers and maybe beginning to kind of
gather its forces together to focus on making seeds
that a wind comes along and it blows off the petal
now we have something new in this world that kind of maybe wasn't as clear as
before now we have the suchness of the petal
and the petal is just allowed to be itself and it's got a beautiful petal just
itself another option
is to look at the flower that's still here and believe
that the essence of a flower that we have to maintain at all costs
are the petals all the petals and if a flower loses a petal it's no
longer perfect it's no longer right but is that the case
the natural course of things that the petals fall off a seed is made
why do we carry with us the idea of the perfectly full
and blossom flower with all its petals is the only suchness of the flower
can't it be that as it as it begins to lose its its petals that
it's just as much as suchness as when it was before this rose that
came from the here at the grounds of imc
is already weathering up i can't maybe see it here but some of the pedals are kind of beginning
to curl up and turn brown and probably going to fall off soon and
it's possible to see it as being starting to become ugly it's possible
but is there a way of seeing this that is seeing it neither as ugly
or as beautiful just a suchness of it or is it possible to see beauty
in its decay after all it's just the natural process in which it takes
the suchness of it everything maybe it's beautiful maybe everything is beautiful
in its suchness maybe wrinkles are beautiful i've seen
people with exquisite face full of cobweb wrinkles and it literally i
thought wow that is beautiful there's something special about it
and i've seen people with just a little bit of wrinkles wow that's beautiful
and i've seen faces with no wrinkles wow that's beautiful
why not see it all as beautiful why do we have these judgments these comparisons
these ideas if we
take a flower let's take another one
let's take this one
and we single one part of the flower out as being the most important part of the
flower as being a thing that really counts and we're going to protect that at all
cost we're going to be upset if it's not there anymore maybe for this flower what's most
important is that it has supported by these beautiful green leaves
but then someone comes comes along and takes it or it falls off but but but but
that's what made the flower a flower or maybe it's a long stem maybe the length of the stem the more
longer it is what makes a flower a successful flower but then somehow or other the flower is
made smaller oh no shorter oh no
i was so attached to it being long that's what really made it a flower
and then the petals start falling off the people who thought that petals were the essence the most important part of
the flower and let's glue it back on
you know they have they sell petals at the the local craft store and you know it's important to make the
flower perfect so let's go buy some other bipedals and glue them on when they're falling off
these are all kind of silly examples but don't we do this to ourselves
aren't we judging ourselves and selecting parts of ourselves out as being what's important and what needs to
be held up and made to be the way it is
but aren't we innocent in doing this comparisons or in the sense or maybe isn't it
inevitable we do this when the world around us is doing it the social world the people the
advertisements the they're all doing it and they're all holding up a certain way that's supposed
to be the ideal in the right way and then people behave that way
and people do judge each other and if they're judging each other they
might judge me and if they're judging on me and then i don't feel safe and so i better figure
out the right length of here that an acceptable person
is supposed to have i better figure out the right something and this and that
and people do make adjustments to themselves and you know people i know people like
myself have moved between cultures and then there were different standards
and then you kind of figure out like how do i fit in here and what is expected and what clothes and what
ways of speaking and what ways of being and all kinds of things
and so you know this once we get into all this complicated social world it's sometimes difficult not to be
pulled into this world of selecting parts out of the whole
and maybe it's reason to protest maybe it's reason to stand up and point these kinds of terrible things out
that goes on but what about the suchness
is that going to be eclipsed is that does that never have a place
is there a time and place where we can appreciate the suchness of ourselves of the flower or the
situation the suchness of a moment in time
or do we are we always on the treadmill that keeps going on and on
of the mind involved in the activity of comparative thinking
the mind involved in not seeing the simplicity of the moment
seeing how much suchness is here in some wonderful way
the treadmill is that kind of going and going and going churning away thinking wondering
and i think sometimes meditators especially when they begin or maybe when
they i don't know can happen anytime
it's possible to be in awe at the treadmill in which the mind is just
thinking and comparison stories and ideas and concerns and just like the thoughts just keep going and going
but it's not not necessary to live that way all the time
just like it's important to eat meals or to eat
it's usually not a good idea to eat non-stop
but the mind somehow can go non-stop just churning away churning away
and even if some of that churning and thinking and reflection is important
it doesn't need to be all continuous and so we come to meditation
i think not just to calm ourselves down but it's possible to come to meditation
to come to gaze upon the suchness of ourselves
which i'd like to propose is beautiful
to be able to gaze upon the beauty of who we are
which is which is you know that which is most natural about being a human being
what is that this this rose which is decaying turning
brown is in the suchness of it all i would say i can i look upon it with a certain
reverence and beauty as it ages and gets brown
of course it will why why does it beauty only reside in
the full kind of peak vitality of the of the rose
and one of the one but one of the fascinating and important ways in which suchness can be seen
is with a mind that is not caught up in unskillful states of mind
a mind that's not caught up in these comparisons that are driven by
fear ill will greed vanity conceit
jealousy uh that a whole spectrum of kind of ways in
which we get caught in the mind that's tense and contracted and
attached to something that's selecting something out of the whole as being what's important
and some idea that it has to be a particular way
the mind that can see suchness is the mind that
is not caught in all these mental states of attachment
and that is a beautiful mind that's that's a mind that's as beautiful
as looking out across the here in california from the beach the the ocean view and looking out across the ocean
and seeing the beauty of the ocean looking at
half dome in yosemite looking down into the grand canyon looking up into the night sky and seeing
the constellations and stars there are times we look at the natural
world and we're in awe and it's beautiful
but to look into our own mind to look into our own being
and be as marvel with that as much as we would at the world at the universe the world
outside to be able to see our mind as being
they should probably make it a nation protected national monument
or maybe each of us that we know that
maybe you know if maybe that's where the next time the park service kind of makes a national park
it should be the suchness of everyone's minds the mind that does not caught up in
these concepts and comparative thinking it's a phenomenally beautiful thing this
mind this heart and to see the world
with that beautiful mind that beautiful heart allows us then to see the suchness
of people suchness of other people their beauty as they are we look at the
rose that's decaying and it's a beautiful rose maybe we want to bow down to the rose
it's so beautiful we have a reverence and care
the ability to see the beauty see the suchness of things
i've been to the bedside of someone who had died and it was profoundly beautiful in the
suchness of it is it okay to say that
probably i'd be careful to say that if the relatives are all quite upset and grieving and or whatever
i might not say it then but is there something about
seeing everything in this life except
those things that are driven by hatred driven by greed
driven by delusion or attachment do they belong to the world of suchness
in some ways they do
but they are born from an inability to appreciate the
suchness of life they they are born from a mind that doesn't see the beauty of its of
itself they're born from hearts that are withered and contracted and
in pain and so they don't have the ability to
touch into or be resting in or be grounded in this beautiful quality of our life
everything is beautiful when they are free
of great hatred and delusion
but it's a lot of it depends on the how your mind is the ability to see it
so if we're looking out and expecting to see
the beauty and suchness and appreciate that in the world without somehow
finding it in ourselves it's probably not so stable or so
accurate or something so some meditation
buddhist meditation as a way of coming into ourselves
to be set ourselves free of our attachments are clinging
not so that we just are i don't know detached
but so that we can appreciate and see the beautiful suchness
of this world where there's no clinging no grasping no hatred
and then we can be and then we can start kind of being the
suchness there is a acting living in the world
from the suchness with the suchness what's that like
it's a life which is free free of attachment
so for me this uh whole movement of mindfulness and meditation is such a phenomenally wonderful thing
we're doing something i almost have you know kind of a deep reverence for
like i do for the night sky looking into the amazement of it or
beautiful scenery in the night in the natural world or taking the time to walk in the garden
and see the flowers appreciate each flower for itself or
take a time to see a hummingbird and the incandescent color and the flittering around it's so beautiful
it takes time to stop and appreciate
the suchness of our mind the suchness of the world
and then we're available to live a wiser life
because of what what a wonderful thing to live a life that comes out of that
recognition of suchness recognition of beauty
that is so easily overlooked in ourselves and others in this world
and it's overlooked when we our attention becomes excessively selective
it's only about how long the stem is it's only about the kind of the full complement of
petals are there it's only about some aspect of it that we hold on to
this is what it's about this is who i have to be this is what i'm about
there is a few mentions in the ancient teachings of the buddha of
people who are just such
the suchness of themselves one of them which maybe is a little bit interpretive but there's a
the buddha most frequently refers to himself as not as the buddha not as this given
name gautama but he refers to himself as the tattagata
and it's a ancient title that probably preceded the buddha no one quite knows what it means
but it's a compound of two words but they don't quite know which two
words because of how the compound words can letters kind of merge
but my favorite interpretation of it is that
it means the one who is thus
the buddha is the one who is thus the one who is such like such
so imagine that you know you go up to the buddha and you're like he seems like an unusual guy
so you ask him you know who are you what are you what are you about
and you have your notebook out you're going to write down notes because after all you don't get talked to buddha that often
and he says uh i am thus i am such
i'm this is the i'm the suchness of this
would you be irritated or would you now appreciate wow
rather than picking and choosing the parts and defining who he is in some particular way
that the uh he just is not defining himself he's
just there and you can and what is apparent what is there he's not going to define it any
more than the suchness of it
here's a few quotes versus
so if you if you uh see the selective process that doesn't see the suchness as one that has a
opinion about things a story about things a view of how things are
then maybe you'll appreciate this poem one who is attached argues over
doctrines how and with what does one argue with someone unattached
embracing nothing rejecting nothing right here
a person has shaken off all abuse so there's a time sitting in meditation
where it makes a lot of sense to embrace nothing and reject nothing
if what we want to do is to see the fullness the wholeness of the suchness of this moment
here's another verse they aren't enemies to anything
seen heard or thought out how in this world could one have
assumptions about those who see in this way whose conduct is open
so people who are not opposed to anything that they see or hear or anything that's thought out any opinions
if they don't have that how could you make assumptions about them how can you define them
and they reverse them these are people whose conduct is open i guess you get what you see you see
with how they conduct themselves how they are in their suchness and one more this is
the one that one does not construct
prefer or take up any doctrine
a sage is not led by precepts or religious practices
is someone who has gone beyond who does not depend on beliefs
it is someone who is thus
someone who is thus so
so why did the buddha hold up a flower
and why did the monk smile
can you hold yourself up in such a way
that you smile
in your thusness your suchness i certainly hope
that you can gaze upon yourself in such a way be present for you in such a way with a mind that's quiet enough from its
attachments its fears its desires its
so that you can gaze upon this beautiful being that you are
in its suchness and then to look upon others
every other person with their reverence and care and respect
they can come to see the suchness of them as they are
and what a great world it would be if we loved and respected people just as they
are in a world where we don't see
the through the filter of great hatred and delusion
so thank you very much my friends my friends and flowers
we've been a bouquet here today and the individual flowers are just as
wonderful in the bouquet as they are apart may you take your wonderfulness with you
through the day thank you you