Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour high and if
you can hear me okay if the audio is alright give me a thumbs up you can hear me well fantastic
so welcome welcome so as always let's start by uh
um saying hello warming up the space with meta and I start by saying hi I'm
Nikki in Mountain View California who is here and who wants to help warm up the space you can just unmute
yourself hi Dan from New York City hi Dan good
evening foreign
hi Sarah hi basil from Chicago land hi faza
welcome Steve from Houston is here hi Steve did
I also hear Marilyn I think I heard Marilyn yes hi Marilyn welcome
Neely New Hampshire hi Neil
we're in New York hi Claire good evening all East Coasters Mary Oakland hi Mary
Californians Pacific timers Wayne in Richmond hi Wayne and Linnea
says hi sending lots of love from Spokane Washington on YouTube Jonathan
is also joining from Calgary our Canadian contingent
anybody else oh yes Aloha says Amy from Oahu yes we've got the uh the uh um that
time zone the Hawaiian time's uncovered too anybody else wants to say hi warm up the space with greetings
I think I heard Dwayne hi Wayne
hi Nikki Vicky from Oakland hi hi Mickey welcome great beautiful okay well let's
get started let's get started so thank you Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google groups in
chat if you're new to happy hour we have a uh uh low traffic mailing list where
quotes resources information is shared
um and at this time I change the setting so accidental unmuting won't be possible
and the chat will just come to me host only but still let's keep it quiet uh
the the that channel quiet unless um something uh drastic happens like my
voice sound drops out and you need to let me know otherwise let's keep all the questions until the end it can be quite
distracting and I turn on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
here we go okay all right hi hi and welcome to this
edition of uh happy hour so so for today's practice I wanted to to
um uh bring in uh a couple of different themes but but I
think the lead the way I would lead into it or the title I would give to this uh
practice session is um choosing the high road choosing the high
road choosing the road of kindness and compassion choosing the high road
we live in a world we live in a world where we interact with people
it's it's part of Being Human It's a Wonderful part of Being Human all these
interactions and of course some interactions sometimes can be challenging interactions or difficult
interactions or surprising interactions and we always have a choice we always
have a choice with every interaction whether it's challenging whether it's actually easeful whether it's loving
whether it's it's neutral all the interactions we have we have the choice
we have a choice of uh in for the sake of this this pra today's practice the
high road or not the high road the low road and the high road here is is uh the road
of compassion the road of care the road of Good Will the road of wisdom also I
want definitely want to bring that in because um compassion and and kindness without
wisdom can become idiot compassion as as especially I love this term from
from the Tibetan tradition uh it can it can be cuddling too much if we're
coddling um but the high road is one of wisdom compassion and sense of Integrity really
a sense of Integrity in our actions so that when we look back at our lives at
the very end um we have a sense that we cried with every interaction as best as we were
able to yeah maybe not every interaction it went flowingly well but but at least
we tried as best as we were able to to take the high road
to take the high road the road a wisdom Compassion Care
even if even if it went terribly bad terribly terribly wrong at the end but
at least we tried at least we had the intentions so when I bring another aspect in here
and that is with respect to the difficult and challenging interactions that can arise because
sometimes it's um no it's easy to respond from a place of
reactivity it's so easy to respond from a place of reactivity
and and to to take our time to sit to
really literally sit or or do what is needed to take the time to um to respond
with compassion with wisdom and and not just responding but also
responding to to what comes even if it's challenging um uh
in interaction but um but also another thing I want to add
is sometimes um I think or or actually all the time it's
important that we don't just kind of stuff stuff our our pain down like oh
yeah I'm gonna take the high road and I'm just going to be wise and compassionate and then continue to Stew
continue to Stew and maybe it'll show up in other ways so that's not exactly the
high road but um for the sake of our own heart we also if
there is a pain that is left over or hurt we need to to
um honor that work with that acknowledge that or sometimes maybe the right response is to bless it the right
response is to bless it so what the heck do I mean by that so I
want to give you an example um often when we give uh Dharma toxin
dharmids we use ourselves as an example so I'll give a story so
[Music] um I received a a text that was very
surprising to me from someone um and
what it it was surprised it was surprising and also hurtful and and the
way I interpreted it actually was that this person was in so much pain in so
much suffering that um they were igno they were saying that and
yet they were pointing fingers because there was so much pain so the the when I
received uh this text in the morning there was a sense of oh I need to write this is what's going you know this is
wasn't the intention this is what's going on and I thought wait wait no no you need to sit with this don't don't
respond right away I actually did a little bit of yoga I sat and and later I
thought no this is not the kind of the place this person clearly is right
now is that they're hurting so much things are so hard that that reason this
case of reason and explanation is not exactly what's needed just to send Goodwill just to send Goodwill I wish
you well may you be well may this may you be well it's just and what I had decided was that no
explanation is needed because explanation is like all right it gets to more explanation that's like around but
they're in a place that they're really really hurting really really hurting so
so after a couple of hours they decided okay just just send Goodwill and there was still real people reacted but just
let let you know sending good will taking the high road of wisdom compassion and then I realized oh there
was still this hurt for me like okay I something was called out that just didn't feel Justified didn't feel right
didn't feel appropriate and right now doesn't feel like the right time to
point this out to this person so so sitting with this hurt and I didn't want to stuff it and and act out of it later
and this this idea of blessing this hurt oh yeah it's it's
um there is care there is care for this person there is care there in this
relationship to see to see the goodness to see the and the perhaps the Divinity
in this in this hurt even that has come from a sense of care so blessing yes
seeing the goodness um maybe I can unpack that little little
more in the guided meditation but uh that's what I mean that's the intention
for this meditation today and this this dharmint song so I'm going to to
pause with the dharmet because I think I've said plenty to set the stage so
let's just practice together let's practice together so so I invite you to let go of all the
thoughts and Reflections and thinking and history and cases where you took the
high road or the low road or let go this is now the time to enter your meditation
posture let's practice together ah
arrive arrive in your seat arrive in your seat
here arrive here
this moment is an opportunity to ground yourself
when your body and your heart
and to sit
you open up let go of thinking
let go of analyzing let go of the past stories where you're the protagonist
you're the protagonist in This Book of Life the main character of your own story let
go let go let's go
let's go
connecting with the breath each breath in the body
breathing in being breathed in being breathed out
Letting Go letting go pension in the body tension in the mind
let go of stories just this breath
this breath emptying cleansing calming soothing
inviting with each breath in breath inviting your own goodness
to rest in your heart to rest
in your goodness your intentions for kindness
Good Will wisdom
just this breath in this body grounded stable
with each breath opening to more goodness
needs space each breath opens more space in your heart
to rest to rest
can be so nourishing just to sit be breathed and if thoughts arise say
not now thank you giving my heart to this practice right
now can be so nourishing just to be here resting in your heart
for a few minutes no agenda no past no present
no future even letting go of the present
not holding on too tightly to this moment
ah maybe more space opens up when I say that
a spaciousness of infinity
when even the present is not climbed too
just this in-breath in the abdomen just this out breath
foreign
just this breath
the continuity of being breathed in breathed out
with care
each breath calming soothing grounding
and I'd like to invite you if you would you can stay here
if this is what's needed today feeling grieved calming soothing with each
breath and if you like you can
proceed to experiment with the invitations
feeling grounded in your body and your breath not in your head
but breathe in your body and your heart
stable
spacious you can invite if you like
some recent interaction that wasn't too challenging please don't go for the most challenging interaction
please don't maybe even a neutral interaction
with someone or maybe it's still in progress It's in
process
and feel into what in the what the high road
they responds and action
a reaction of Integrity kindness wisdom
Goodwill what does it feel like in your body
not to think about what to do don't think about that
feel into
the relational field or this this being could be a neutral interaction or
written or even a kind one a positive one
in your body what does the response of Goodwill
kindness generosity feeling their Humanity
for a moment the common Humanity what they're going through right now if you
could put yourself in their issues
there are circumstances
for a moment see the world through their eyes
foreign to be them right now
every human has their challenges
if you were in their shoes how would you want how would you hope people would
treat you kindness compassion
generosity understanding
coming back to your own perspective
can you just feel into not into actions or what to say or what to do
but into your own goodness into your own kindness generosity
wisdom just breathing breathing into it not
thinking but just breathing trusting it's there
and offering in your heart's mind
just as if a dear friend or someone you care about was going on a long trip and
you wanted to give them a gift
a small gift token to take with them
as protection thought carrying your thoughts good well and
say you would hold that gift in your hands and in your heart your mind you would bless it with all
your good intentions for this person all you care All Your Love
is object
being blessed are your good intentions
before it's given to your friend going on the long journey
in the same way this interaction that we've been sitting
with consider a gift
of kindness not a physical gift but in your heart
a good well something
an empty infinite box of Goodwill
that you offer that's blessed with your kindness blessed with your goodness with your
good intentions
of course this imaginary box is empty there's a sense of Goodwill kindness
and you realize in the process of giving this gift blessing and giving this gift
do you feel blessed too recognizing your own goodness
your own capacity to be expansive
your best self
and just in case there's still any hurt or difficult feelings left from
this interaction this too can be blessed
held with care with good will
and offered offered up
offered up and the altar of your Humanity
we don't have to carry all the hurts
like rocks and Bricks
in our sack making us heavier and heavier
when feeling ready each Rock
be blessed
touched with intentionality heart Goodwill goodness
let go of offered up placed on the altar of
Humanity so many hurts
part of our Human Condition
to both benefit each other hurt each other
not unique so maybe this rock too could be blessed
and left offered up
if the time is ready
and as we bring the sitting to a close
when we are ready may all the rocks
be released may all beings everywhere
be free including ourselves
foreign [Music]
thanks for your practice
so we have a few minutes for Reflections questions comments complaints it's all
welcome if you like to especially if you haven't spoken in a while like to welcome you to
uh share your experience your maybe an aha moment Eric please
thanks Nikki squanda offer up a joke I made yesterday about the
effort of taking the high road and my wife to mentioned a person
without knowing she said don't you find them so annoying and I said
I'm trying to dislike people less but they make it so hard
[Music] it's you know it's so interesting um
one thing that comes up for me in situations like that is I I
have this usual reflection this reflection that gosh I I get to interact
with this person I don't know one once in a blue moon or
one hour a week or whatever it is or or five hours a week or whatever it is right I get to interact with them this
limited amount of time whereas this person gets to be in that mind and that
heart get they get to be them 24 hours a day ah I could have been born as them I
could have been born as them It's So Random right our causes and conditions of who we end up being
um so I offer that reflection this is what I tried to bring in like oh my
goodness this must be so hard it must be so hard for them so and it's not pity
and it's not pitting them it's it's really like I'm I'm I could be them I am
them in some ways so I offer that thanks for their reflection
if there's anything you'd like to add you're welcome to very good okay
yeah any other reflections Claire
thank you Nikki I just want to say that it's very very a very funny coincidence
brought this up tonight because I do volunteer work yesterday I found out
that some people were added to a team without my knowing it but I didn't
really want to have happen and my go-to place was how dare they and my little
ego went way up how dare they and what am I going to and how am I going to get them off or whatever and then I paused
and I thought you know it's not going to go anywhere and it's just gonna make a lot of people unhappy and so you
know the nice the great the the right thing to do would be to send them a note and tell them how happy I am with their
work they're working with us and how you know how pleased I am to have them and
that's why I just wrote it like before I came here um because that's I know that I'll feel
you know however they feel I'll feel better okay sorry thanks Claire thanks for the
report from the field that you just went through this this contemplation though okay this is okay this is what I could
do or this is what I could do okay let me reflect what do I really want to do
who do I really want to be in this world yeah beautiful thank you Claire thanks for that example sharing that that's
lovely yeah yeah the reflections
and also type them in chat if you like they could be privately to me in which case I won't read your name
Neil so you were kind of talking about like
feeling hurt or offended what happens if you feel anger how does what's the
connection because right the example I picked there's a lot of like anger
right and it didn't quite feel the same as matching what things you were saying
yeah yeah yeah yeah so so what if there's anger um so so I'll share with you that yeah I
feel angry too for me there was anger too when I felt like yeah this this feeling no the feeling of anger can can
have many reasons but in this case I don't know if it's the same for you but it was feeling
um uh you know um unfairly this is you know something that
feels unfair like that's not it like uh it doesn't fear right uh and so for me
where um where I've been sitting with that and I'll offer this
maybe relevant or supported supportive for the situation you're working with is
um I think it became more released more more easy to work with when I really put
myself in their shoes like what they are saying how they're seeing the world right now what's happening to them
they're in such a difficult circumstance that when I put myself in that situation something happened to the anger like I
could start to see like wow that's so painful where they how what they're
going through how they're seeing in the world is just oh and that's something it's something happened to the anger it
softened it and then also it felt like um holding the anger as a blessing as as
a to as as I was saying again I tried to unpack it during the guided meditation it's hard to say but but blessing it as
yeah I see you I see there's there's there's a goodness there's a there's a
beauty in here and that also released it uh in in a way and and putting it on the
altar so I'm offering these um some of the ways that I've been working with with it in in this and and
it's not one size fits all of course but um what um
yeah I am I don't know if any of this this this you've tried this kneel or it
hits home or not yeah
I I some of it hits right it it feels difficult
right it's it's comfortable to be angry with this person it's comfortable it's comfortable to be
angry yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah right right you know I've worked with them for a
couple of years and they're like the most disgusting human being that I've ever met in my life
um you know you know I don't mean like you know they don't watch right I mean they just do
horrible things yeah so but but it's you know it costs me to be angry too yeah
exactly but that's the other thing yeah yeah
yeah thank you yeah there's there was more there and yeah thank you Neil
um there's one quick uh let's see um Rada I see your hand but I um let's
come there's very little time I see we need to go to the practice meetings and there was one question that's been posted in the chat very quickly I want
to address which is in your view where is the line between blessing hurts and conflicts and toxic positivity very good
point there is there is a difference and that's where the wisdom comes in uh that's where the wisdom comes in to know
what is appropriate what's the appropriate response and sometimes it's not appropriate you know what the
appropriate response is to say no this is not appropriate you can do this
um and and sometimes it's it's appropriate not to pick a fight with someone who's already so hurting that
that they're just hurting um so that's where the wisdom comes in
but so I think that's where I would say that wisdom can tell you where the differences between toxic positive
positivity which not helpful and um
and uh and and and and and appropriate compassion Jerry says this practice
gives me hope that we may develop a different way personally and more widely of working through difficult situations
that this would May survive and thrive hopefully may it be so may it be so yeah
so uh we usually turn to practice to small groups a minute or two earlier but
here we go I'm going to make out the breakout rooms and the invitation for
tonight's practice is um if you like sharing
um something about this practice or about um how it was or maybe a case where the
you're you're feeling into what's the high road what's the lower you know what's the road of wisdom and compassion
without falling into toxic positivity all of that is exploring you can you
know having a minute to offer something and let's do alphabetical order first
person and the next person offers a nugget and then the next person will then come back to you so you go round and round in the round robin way sort of
a long monologue make sure everybody has time to speak okay all right so I'm
going to create the rooms and open them up take care of yourselves take care of each other please be kind mind
and the rooms are open here we go
okay the rooms jealous closed everybody's back okay
and the time is seven o'clock so um tell you what I'm going to
um stay a minute extra if there's any Reflections or questions otherwise let's
let's close dedicate the Merit thank you all for your practice for cultivating
kindness goodness wisdom for the sake of all beings everywhere including
ourselves [Music] okay take good care everyone be well