warm greetings to everyone who is
here today for us to spend our time together meditating and hearing the teachings exploring the teachings and
also those of you i want to agree to will be listening to this later and
i also want to welcome you to this time and
i think we're all together whether it's in so many different places but also in
so many different times the amazing way in which
we can share this practice
in this electronic age
one of the
very significant very effective ways of engaging in mindfulness practice
whether it's on the cushion or in daily life is to develop the
orientation the dedication the love
for doing one thing at a time and then when you're doing something
to within reason unless something you know the something dramatic happens the
building starts burning or something and you know uh within reason uh stay with it and see it through to
the end to do one thing at a time and see it through to the end
so in meditation that can be as simple as
being present fully for the in-breath and seeing it through to the end staying
there really having a sense a kind of an attitude a
orientation a dedication a valuing
a um savoring a
love of just seeing it through to the end that in-breath
and then when the out-breath comes just that seeing that through the end
one thing at a time and sometimes we we do it kind of
renew it every in-breath and every out breath and a different way of continuity
develops and the continuity of okay now i'm going to just stay with the in-breath and out-breath without leaving at all
that kind that may be too big of a goal but the goal of just seeing this one thing through to the end
this one through through to the end and
and if that's the primary activity here then that's a wonderful place to be the
place where you do one thing at a time if you're doing the
first tetrad of being with a breath knowing it
and then experiencing the whole body and then relaxing the body
each of those steps that's what we dedicate ourselves to and perhaps it's a
it's uh again it's kind of like the in breath and out breath it's kind of temporary
we're just there for this relaxation this moment of experiencing the full body
and then renewing it this gentle renewing loving renewing
we're renewing and starting with the next moment the next activity next you know thing that we're going to
moment we're going to see it to the end even if it's just one even the same thing over and over again
can be a very effective way of building and developing settling in to this mindfulness
so to
begin with doing one thing at a time just give yourself over to your posture
to establishing a meditation posture
with the details of posture kind of
cared for tended to
feeling how the weight of the torso is centered on the
sitting bones is are you leaning forward with
leaning backward or do you have a sense that the your weight is
balanced on a kind of vertical center of gravity
maybe sitting up a little bit straighter
breathing in breathing out adjusting where the hands are and the arms the elbows
noticing if the elbows are a little bit locked in or tense there's a way of just kind of flapping
your elbow slightly like your chicken or something just to kind of make sure it's loose in
the arms
you can kind of also just kind of
shake your ever so slightly shake your hands to see if they're loose
making some care for how your head is on your that the
that somehow the meeting of the back of your neck and your skull
doesn't feel scrunched like you're lifting up
like you're lifting up your chin and kind of opening the space there and the last vertebrae in the skull
being careful that the chin is not pulled down or your head is not tipped down too much
so there's a kind of a pressure in the front of the neck underneath the
jaw from being crunched a little bit
and if you haven't don't have your eyes closed to gently close them if that's comfortable
and then to do one thing at a time
take a one deeper in breath as if that's the only thing that's important
and then one full exhale just doing that to all the way to the end
breathing in breathing out
on the exhale relaxing the body
and letting the breathing return to normal and again on the exhale
take a few breaths to relax the body the whole body parts of the body
but to do the relaxation on the exhale as if it's the only thing happening
giving yourself over to this one thing breathing on the exhale relaxing on the
exhale
and then settling into breathing
and seeing if there's some way attitude of attention
that maybe makes attention to the breathing enjoyable
maybe a friendliness a love
maybe a peacefulness or a tranquility
whatever way that maybe it's enjoyable to really take in
the breathing on the in-breath
just the in-breath that one thing all the way to the end
on the exhale the one thing that you give yourself to
gently
receptively all the way to the end
and then start over
and if something takes you away from your breathing
let the knowing of that thing be the one thing that you do
just knowing thinking just knowing feeling
patiently openly and then begin again with the breathing
um
to help you do one thing at a time
while you're breathing just the inhale just the exhale
you can gently say the word one count up to one
on the inhale then start over again counting up to one
on the exhale just long gentle one
to really be there for this one thing
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to shift the focus of attention
to the dedication of our efforts
to benefit others through this practice we benefit
ourselves and the more we benefit ourselves the more we have
to offer others may we benefit ourselves so we can
better benefit others may we benefit others so we can benefit
ourselves may this wonderful
circle cycle wheel of mutual care
keep rolling in our world
and so as we come to the end
evoking the wish the desire the good will
that wishes everyone well
which is the best for everyone may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
and in so doing may all beings be free of their suffering their
oppression their poverty their illness
may all beings have the opportunity to breathe easily
and have their heart be at ease
[Music]
you
so we're still staying with this third exercise the
at the buddha taught in the discourse on the four foundations for awareness
and it is um
and um it's easy to overlook overlook this exercise because
uh the four foundations for awareness are often taught as meditation practices
and so people will kind of focus on the parts that have more directly to do with
meditation and here it's not meditation that's being focused
on but rather activity and so it's mindfulness in daily life mindfulness
and activities we do and it's it's worthwhile take some time with
this and to really begin to appreciate how this can be done in practice in our lives
because there's a mutual relationship between how we develop our attention in meditation
and how we develop it in daily life and they support each other and they certainly support each other in
that both places are places where it's getting stronger and expanding our capacity to be present
but it's also uh important because the two areas kind of highlight different
aspects of life at different aspects of ourselves if all we ever did was meditate we go to
monastery and just meditate all the time it might be wonderful but it would just
be a very partial experience of who we are not a few people have gone off on retreats and been able to meditate all
day and hello wow this is great and i'm so wonderful and i'll never be challenged again because
i'm so balanced and clear and peaceful and then within a day of leaving they're
angry and upset and yelling at other drivers or
you know or they find themselves completely consumed with desires and
and um and so they've certainly learned to settle themselves on retreat but they
haven't learned how to bring attention to what happens in daily life and how to
be in a daily life so that uh mindfulness carries the day not our
reactivity and so to uh so in one in meditation we
get to look at part of who we are in daily life we get to look at other parts of who we are and find a way to live
wisely in both ways in both both both situations so in terms of
[Music] mindfulness in daily life in activity one of the great ex
approaches is to do just one thing at a time whatever you're doing just do that
and um uh and part of the advantage of kind of going on retreat or going and living in
a buddhist monastery is that uh the situation there is tends to be set up the ambiance the
the atmosphere the dedication the what's happening around you it supports uh more often than in daily
life just doing one thing at a time and when i was in the monastery there
was kind of understood if you're sweeping the monastery grounds just sweep if you're [Music]
washing dishes just do the dishes and it's represented by the story in japan when i was in the monastery there
where i went into the kitchen in the evening for something maybe a little snack or
something and um and there was a one of the other monks
was preparing the vegetables for the next day's meal and he was chopping them away
and i stood opposite the table where he was chopping and faced him and asked him some question i
have no no memory of what i asked him and and what i remember was that he put down
his knife that he was chopping with and he stood up straight and looked at
me and answered me in a very matter-of-fact nice way and then he picked up his knife and started chopping again
and that's why i asked the second question he put down the knife stood up straight faced me and answered
the question and i sway so not really understanding what was going
on i asked him a third question and so he put down his knife again
and faced me and he said gilson he said gil the
you know i'm here in the kitchen to just you know to chop the vegetables this evening and
and if you're going to talk to me then i can't really do my work focus on it
and so then i so then i bowed and apologized and and left he was just doing one thing at a time
when he was chopping he was just chopping when he was talking to me he was just talking to me and he was
dedicated to that so this was not really the ordinary time to have a conversation so it was reasonable that he wanted to
dedicate himself to his work and it was the evening he probably wanted to get ready to go to bed
and um so um
so that story kind of represents this kind of dedication to just doing one thing at a time
and of course um it can be overdone and there are times of course when the
one thing we do is a number of things and but then just do that i think i
think i told a story yesterday being a fast order cook and i just did one thing not one thing just one
job and i was absorbed and just doing the job just surrendering to everything that was needed i was tracking multiple
things but i was just cooking and
so exactly what one thing means various context or context but the principle of just when you're
doing something just do that and don't be involved in things which are extraneous to it
this one thing this one practice um can enhance the experience of daily
life so that it it begins to approach the kind of wholeheartedness
that uh monastic life has not that it's monastic life it's just kind of getting some of the benefits
because a big part of monastic life is this ability to just really do one thing at a time
and then one of the ways of really uh getting into this is i add to it the idea of see seeing
that one thing through to the end so like if you're walking in your house
from i don't know the living room to where the laundry is to move the laundry from the washer to the dryer
and you're walking that's the task just do that and if you see that something needs to
be cleaned up along the way or something grabs your interest along the way you see that there's a
something male has arrived and you want to check the mail the
uh if you're doing this one practice at a time seeing it through to the end practice since you set yourself on the course to
go to the laundry room and cha move the laundry just do that
and it might be a little bit less efficient than doing something along the way but it's more efficient in terms of
cultivating mindfulness just do that and if it's important to do something else along the way then of course then
switch and do that but just kind of practice more and more just seeing one thing one thing through to the end
and then when you're finished then go look at the mail and do that that one thing
and at first it might seem a little artificial but as you get into it you will find that
that there's kind of enhancement of awareness of presence it helps kind of
uh evoke the various capacities we have when we're fully present for something just
being there it can be very relaxing uh it can be very uh freeing of the
preoccupations and the stresses of the day because a lot of the stresses of the day don't have so much to do with what often
i don't have to do with what's happening in the moment but have to do with our imagination our projection into the
future or fantasy or anxieties that are uh you know more have to do with a
thought world then they have to do with what's happening right here and now
so to be able to just kind of just see this thing through to the end and develop that capacity can be very
freeing in terms of what builds up stress in our minds and then to learn to enjoy doing that
to learn how doing just one activity how embody in that embodying that with awareness
so it's not a duty it's not like a mental thing like okay now i should you know just be here it's a embodied
all-body thing just the body is there for itself and this also represents in the moment for
me the experience i had in the japanese monastery where
sometimes it was my job to bring the food from the kitchen to the dining room and tape where we would eat
on the table bring food to them and um sometimes i was given the rice to carry in the big pot of rice
and it was you know kind of big but it was i could carry it with one hand and so i would carry it with one hand
and it seemed like a fine thing to do and it was doing the job and and um and whenever i did that some
other monk would come along and say gilsan when you carry the pot carry it with both hands
just really be there and um so in in zen also if you're drinking tea
you wouldn't just drink it with one hand you would actually be there fully to drink the tea just the tea seeing that
tea just all the way with both hands something about using both hands which uh contributes to this embodiment
this like let's just let's hear be here for this this thing and um
and then also with our posture that uh there's a posture that
maybe is relaxed enough but the posture is not participating in what we're doing
so it's not just a matter of doing one thing with attention but also how much of our whole being can we
gently lovingly bring along to do something so that there's a begins to be a feeling
a sense of being absorbed in one something and the more we of ourselves we bring to
the activity actually the more pleasurable it tends to become the more it tends to enhance
our capacity for presence and so certainly i can
you know sometimes it's nice to be the one thing we do is to relax the end of the day and then sitting in a nice easy
chair and maybe just reading something or having tea and just reading and having tea and drinking kind
of mindlessly the tea because you know you're doing that one relaxing thing that's completely fine because you know
this is what i'm doing but there's qualitatively a very different thing if
you say okay i'm really going to just now i'm going to really the one thing i'm going to do is drink tea
and you sit up a little bit straighter so your kind of spine is involved too
and then you pick up the the cup with two hands and you really kind of
meet it and really go this is what you're going to do with two hands with your whole body
and there are times when that begins awakening a very different kind of
mindful presence awareness embodied awareness then the idea of that mindfulness is a mental activity of just
knowing you know knowing i'm lifting knowing knowing the cup knowing a feeling
and that's sometimes part of what mindfulness is but it's and then it's kind of a partial awareness it's a using
just one faculty but to bring our posture our body into what we're doing and feeling it and
sensing it is um is how a sense of absorption or pleasure
in the activity can grow and then in doing so
can over time you find that actually the result of doing it
is that you have more clarity more wisdom more understanding more
ability to tune in to your environment and be in harmony with it or be wise with what you do
doing enjoying one thing at a time is not hedonistic
it's um it's uh it sets up the conditions
for wisdom and for freedom and for clarity so doing one thing at a time one
activity at a time and and then kind of seeing it through to
the end so within reason of course
so thank you very much and uh and we'll continue a little bit more on
this topic of mindfulness activities because we'll see that at the some of the lessons we learn here
uh are then uh relate to what we learn in meditation practice and and uh we learn to apply
that there as well and um and it supports the meditation so
thank you very much