so good morning Welcome to our meditation
and one of the areas we're navigating we meditate
is our interests both intentional interests but also
unintentional and I think a big part of
the terrain of mindfulness meditation is navigating the mind's interests when
they're different than our own so if you're distracted
about something that happened long ago your mind is interested in long ago if
it's planning the future your mind is interested in playing the future
and if it's in the present maybe if something troubles you
and so the mind is even if you want to excuse me for a moment
even if you want to uh
be interested in your breathing or in the meditation your mind keeps going into your troubles
and part of meditation is to start becoming disinterested in some things
and to Value the process of this interesting this interestation becoming
disinterested and um I do appreciate this is part of it's
almost like a natural process so for example as we get more centered
focused comfortable delighted with being meditating
then um then naturally the interest will go towards is good the goodness of
meditation and will become less interested in other things
if the meditation is difficult then it's a little bit more difficult to become disinterested for things have more
interest for meditation as we become wiser in meditation wiser
in practice the wisdom guides are interest and the wisdom has some sense of the
significant the value of becoming a disinterested in some things
and so this natural process of becoming more and more disinterested in things which don't serve us don't help us
become stronger and we become more the wisdom teaches us oh even though
it's difficult meditation even though there's challenges it's really Wise It's really good to be
interested to be present but these experiences so this whole idea of it's a one way of
understanding all this is navigating interest so for this meditation I'd like to
suggest that another distinction
we can have troubles in our lives or troubles with ourselves within ourselves
and then we can be troubled by it so I can be troubled
by a car one of my troubles might be a I have a car for example that it's not the
case but a car that needs to be repaired and that's just a trouble that the issue
a topic that has to be addressed I can be troubled by it I can feel
stressed by it I can feel afraid I can feel preoccupied I could feel angry all
kinds of ways in which I I feel troubled by it
one of the things to become disinterested in is how we feel troubled
we might be troubled by what goes on inside of ourselves our thoughts our feelings our emotions our judgments
about ourselves but the thoughts are one thing
being troubled by it is something else and to sit and meditate and lose
interest in how we feel troubled we still can be aware of it mindful of
it but don't not to invest energy belief
Authority um importance in this feeling of feeling troubled
because if we invest in it it gets stronger it persists
and learning to become less and less interested in the
feeling of being troubled and more interested in our experience as
it is in the Simplicity of what it is is one of the ways in which this
meditation can deepen so
assuming a meditation posture
and gently close your eyes and maybe you're troubled by what I said
so there's a lot of thoughts and feelings reactions so you're welcome to those
I certainly don't want to take those away from you you know
without you choosing to do so for yourself
but if you recognize that whatever troubles you at this moment
the subjective experience of feeling troubled
maybe you can switch your interests with your orientation
so that feeling doesn't influence how you bring attention now
to your body breathing
so your interest now goes into
how your body is experiencing breathing at this moment
every day we breathe slightly differently
relaxing being interested in how you can relax
your body your mind
softening
letting go of any thinking that takes you away from the present
moment takes you away from mindfully mindfully breathing
and if there's any gentle quiet thinking
that guides you to staying with your breathing staying in the present
let those thoughts encourage a greater quieting settling
you don't have to let go of those thoughts
foreign
might it be all right to lose interest
in your distracting thoughts
thank you
what is your mind interested in
what desires might be behind those interests
is there a way of letting go of interest in your desires
so you're more fully present here
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn your interest outwards to the world around you
to the people who are nearest to you and wherever you're
meditating maybe someone else meditating with you or someone else in the house or
neighbor
an outward Beyond to the cave the county The Province and
which you're in colleagues
co-workers out across the lens
to be interested but in a particular way to be interested in their welfare and
their well-being to be interested in with kindness
and respect
and is there something about having meditated for half an hour
being maybe a little more calm or settled that allows you your respect for others
your kindness to others be more embodied
emotionally Fuller
not a casual impulse of the moment but something that's maybe
embodied Within
and this interest in kindness and care and Welfare
perhaps in your own mind silently you can repeat these words as a way of
giving voice to what's Within
giving voice so it spreads out across the lands
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may my care and kindness for others
stay with me as I go through the day
[Music]
so here we are the second day of this
series on the insight pentad
and um these pentads of yesterday last week and
this week the gladness pentaton the insight pentaton are descriptions of a natural unfolding
in Buddhist practice and meditation practice so first there's the idea that we don't
have to be the and always in the driver's seat of our meditation always controlling it making it happen
measuring it doing it to kind of you know writing writing close and tight
and there's a time and place where we want to kind of allow a natural process to
unfold that unfolds better if we start giving up control
and allow something to happen but that giving up control and allowing happens what best happens when there's
already some centeredness in the present moment so momentum of being focused here
at present that them that there's very little tendency to get distracted
and a lot of tendency a lot of interest in being really connected to our
experience connected to the breathing and um so uh because if this if there's a kind
of a um if this momentum exists within us of
being present then letting go and giving up control we're letting go into that momentum and
something can begin happening but without some opening and allowing something to happen there's no room for
it to happen sometimes if we're you know trying to trying to always trying to operate from our control and desires and
all that so uh with time
as we said settle in there's Insight we see something really
clearly and exactly what we see varies from person to person and classically one of
the key things to see is how changing our experiences Moment by moment
and we can't hold on to it we just kind of allow allow for the changing nature of it
uh some people don't understand why this is so significant and some people have other insights so
their understandings that are key as we kind of kind of keep unfolding so what's interesting to see
is uh what these insights lead to if we would the kind of insights we're looking
for lead us in a certain direction and open to something
and if we understand what they're opening to then we can look back and see personal understanding of all the
different things that might support all the kind of insights that might support that opening
and um and what it opens to in the is
English is usually translated as disenchantment and um it's a kind of uh uh strong
disinterest in continuing with some of the business as usual some of the usual things that
are mind heart does and um so a disenchantment a disinterest
a kind of a healthy uh you know enough already and I've done this and this and
I've done this enough kind of a certain healthy kind of wariness or tiredness or
uh yeah God this is you know enough already uh and it can happen for example if in
meditation say for you meditate every every morning for half an hour and after
252 days you realize that every morning um you are obsessing about lottery
numbers and that's all you think about so you get to the 253 days and you
realize wait a minute a good part of this last year I've been thinking about lottery numbers
to no avail it doesn't help me win any lottery I haven't been had a single accurate number in any Lottery anywhere
in the planet and I'm spending an inordinate amount of my time in meditation thinking about lotteries let
alone outside of it you know maybe uh it's enough already I
feel tired from all this thinking and figuring and calculating I do with meditation and I'm you know I'm really
getting tired of this now and so there's a disenchantment a disinterest maybe a person hasn't won any lotteries and so
there's a real there was they were so enchanted and so entranced for the possibility that of what would happen if
they won the lottery and so after after 253 days of this that finally the person
starts becoming disinterested disenchanted with um maybe they start
falling out of the trance of instant wealth that maybe the lottery provides
so um so and we call it disenchantment I like the word disenchantment because uh
it implies that you've been Enchanted you're under the spell of something and we can be under the spell of our
desires under the spell of our fantasies under the spell of certain beliefs that if
only my partner behaves better then I'll be but then I'll have a good life if
only the if only spell there's the spell of conceit and this is
all kinds of ways in which we are overly interested or caught in ideas about how
terrible I am how wonderful I am how mediocre I am all these ways of being
entranced with that and um and so as we sit and meditate
sometimes the repetition of the same kind of thoughts and behaviors and interests we start seeing it more and
more and more clearly and we start seeing this as a high cost you know I've been resentful for 252
days you know maybe I didn't realize I was doing it every day
now that I meditate I see it and only because of their of the familiarity and seeing the regularity do
we understand the cost of daily resentment resentment meditation
and so then there starts to be a disenchantment starts to be a disinterest and um and so
the our attention or Life Energy doesn't go into those thoughts around that thing
and um and rather now it's more available for this momentum that we're talking
about in practice this momentum kind of making it getting out of the way even more for the momentum of concentration
the momentum of mindfulness attention the momentum of being more settled has a
chance to kind of operate because we're not activating ourselves with it all
so to become disenchanted with craving disincented with ill will
disenchanted with a all kinds of fantasies we have disenchanted with conceits
self-preoccupation boy I'm always self-preoccupied some of that might be okay it's not
necessarily wrong but to see the regularity and how little it does for us how it not only doesn't benefit us it
actually sometimes deleterious for us to have this and the opportunity of meditation to sit
there quietly dignified uh valued respecting ourselves and
seeing in this kind of embodied respect and presence wow
there's a lot of nonsense in that mind I had no idea and we start maybe becoming
disenchanted disinterested and so this movement towards disinterest
and some of that comes from starting to see more clearly
the difference between events in the world and our relationship to them so as I
said earlier in the meditation we might have troubles in the world you know the car has a flat
tire that's troubling maybe or it might be a much bigger one's troubles we have maybe we have family members who are ill
and we have to care for them and it's troubling it's a trouble you know it's a trouble it's a trouble it's
a challenge it's a problem to figure out how to do it well and um so there's a the troubles and
then there's being troubled by it and just that distinction separating those twos two out
then we can start seeing the the feeling of being troubled as being Something That We're contributing to it something
that was as subjective and arising from within us and we might not feel like we have much
choice or ability to do anything about it but when we sit and meditate regularly
I know really bring a lot of mindfulness to our experience and see how often we're troubled and
start kind of stealing getting some handle on it seeing it clearly and being able to kind of observe it not being in
it not being absorbed in it the relationship to feeling troubled
might change and we might become disinterested disenchanted with the value of feeling
troubled and some of the energy that goes into it the tension that we hold around it
begins to soften and relax and then we might discover we can take
care of the issues we have to take care of much better if we don't feel attention or the burden the weight that
comes with feeling troubled so there's all himself kind of becoming
disenchanted with some of the reactivity and responses within us to events in the
world disenchanted with the second arrows we we shoot that ourselves
so um um so
the idea of becoming disenchanted it's considered to be a form of wisdom
that will support the momentum and the
deepening of freedom in our lives so it has a tremendous value
and it arises out of insight into seeing something clearly and so whatever you see clearly enough
that allows for this deeper movement of disenchantment maybe that's insight for
you so the question the homework for today would be what wisdom what understanding
what Insight do you have about what's happening for you and how you react how you respond how you think how you feel
how you desire um that uh might
awaken or support a healthy disinterest disenchantment
with some of your desires some of the things you've been caught up in
give yourself some time today maybe having tea going for a walk and considering this topic of disenchantment
healthy disinterest and where how might that kind of be
evoked more more strongly so that it supports you in your life
so thank you very much and so we'll take this another step tomorrow
and to see where as this disinterest because healthy disinterest
disenchantment begins to take hold what that allows for or what we can
allow to happen next on this journey to Freedom thank you very much