so good morning everyone and welcome to imc and
in person and online just to say if you do some brief words
about the meditation practice one of the
wondrous miraculous aspects of being a human being
is having an equal ability to perceive what's happening
externally to ourselves as it is to uh perceive what's internal
to ourselves and i like to think of mindfulness sometimes
as sitting at the interface between the outer world and the inner world
and either one of those or both of them can be agitated can be challenging
but the meeting place the bridge the interface between
the inner and the outer the mindfulness that's a place where perhaps we can sit
calmly we can sit peacefully
in our capacity to be mindful
that to explore what it means to be mindful what it means to be aware
peacefully even if what we're aware of is not
peaceful and we have this ability because
mindfulness sits not in the world and not in
the outer world not in the inner world but this magic place
between the two and with that kind of image and idea
maybe you can experiment today and sit here for the next half an hour
with seeing what it's like to be aware of whatever is happening internally and externally
for the awareness the perception of it the mindfulness of it
is peaceful even if the rest of you does not feel peaceful
so assuming a upright posture
into some simple way that's easy maybe setting your body at ease
taking a few long slow deep breaths and relaxing
setting your body at ease
perhaps relaxing the face
the shoulders
the belly
maybe there's something about your mind you can set at
ease relaxing the pressure to think
and setting your heart at some peace moving towards ease
no matter what challenges you have
and when we get preoccupied with the inner world preoccupied with the outer world
there's a way in which awareness attention becomes narrow
when we were when they were sitting in that interface the meeting place of inner and
outer world and we're mindful they from there
sometimes the mind can become broad wide
aware of all things
but with awareness not troubled by any of it
you might be troubled but mindfulness does not have to be
just aware what is that place
of peaceful
awareness of what is
so
foreign
[Music] so
uh
so
mindfulness can be aware of the outer world
it can be aware of the inner world
in a sense mindfulness sits at the middle
in that middle place
mindfulness is also connected to our actions
what we do in response to our inner world what we do in response to our outer
world
and if awareness is agitated
so will our actions if our awareness is peaceful
our actions will come out of that peace carry with it qualities of the peace
may it be that whatever peace
that we have from this practice that it inspires us to act in the world
with kindness
with wisdom with compassion and care
may whatever peacefulness that we encounter
support us contributing to a better world for everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music] so
[Music]
so i spent the last two weeks teaching a retreat at our retreat center
and it was a peaceful life
it was nice to be there and i was very aware that
there was lots of absence of peace the opposite of peace in many places
around this country and around the world
and that one of the concerns that exists especially in this country
but all over is the presence of hate
and so some people are now preoccupied with the amount of hate that exists
some people are preoccupied with hating
so i thought i would talk a little bit about buddha's teachings about hate
and maybe it's a bit of a
reflection that supports us as we consider our relationship with
the hate and the violence that exists in our country and elsewhere
and it's not a incidental topic
for buddhists or for the teachings of the buddha the buddha placed
the understanding hate and overcoming hate
the destruction of hate at the center of his message of his teachings
and it goes together with two other afflictive mental states mental states
that harms the person who has them and uh greed
and confusion delusion
so great hatred and delusion it's often those three come off the tongue of
buddhist dharma teachers very easily and
the buddha said that someone was asked how do you uh know the dharma how does one know the
dharma for oneself and if dharma means the teachings of the buddha the great wonderful philosophies
of buddhism and great books are written that you could study what the dharma is
but how would one know this know the dharma surprisingly he defined it
as understanding great hatred and delusion and
the ending of it he talks of one of the
great little phrases describing the dharma is that it's directly visible here and now
and how is it directly visible here and now in seeing the ending of greed hate and
delusion so you know we have all these you can read
philosophies of buddhism and all the stuff and you know great philosophies of
emptiness and consciousness or all kinds of explorations
but the heart of it is this you know is this ending of great hatred
and delusion what is the goal of the buddha's teaching the buddha said
the goal is the ending of great hate and delusion so
when i first encountered this frequency in which this is being taught my mind started to glaze over it
and and it kind of was a little dismissive of it that this part of the
teaching uh it also seems so reductionistic it's like where's the great spirituality
where is great spiritual states and spiritual kind of realities and whatever you know like there must be you know
that that can't be it but apparently it is
it might be disappointing for you to hear
but uh the um but as long as there is
hate in the world i think it's pretty wonderful to have a
religion that's based on coming to the end of hate front and center
other religions have other things front and center center and then the virtues and how you live maybe is a
little bit on the edges of it of that center but
for the buddha front and center was the end of greed hatred and delusion
and uh and so the dharma practice becomes understanding how hatred works
lessening our hatred not acting on hatred enough so that we can find our way find
a path that takes us to a time where it comes to an end for us
and but that and that that includes not just hatred it's a big word and some people maybe feel i don't have
hatred i'm just irritated with my neighbor or there's bitterness
there is resentment all those are considered to be forms of
hatred there's also hostility and the hostility and hatred and the
buddhist teachings are closely connected like almost synonymous to
whatever hatred is it always involves some degree of hostility as part of it
and does irritation always have some quality hostility in it
does frustration have some degree of hostility in it
i don't know maybe maybe you know it depends how we define these words but if you're frustrated with your computer
and you throw it across this room then there's hostility
in it right so for the buddha even the mildest
irritation and frustration is a seed bed for hatred
so as we begin looking at this you know the ecology of hatred
the frustration irritation all these things are part of it and part and parcel of it
there's a uh uh i like to think that uh
the buddhist scriptures don't have like a formal beginning like the bible has the book of genesis and it's kind of
like you know it has a clear beginning but i'd like to think of the big the
dhammapada this is a collection of verses it's such a popular text one of the most
most read scriptural texts from the time of the buddha that
kind of at the beginning of that i think of this little bit like you know the beginning
and what's interesting about it is that uh you know the bible begins with
reference to god like god created everything in contrast to that if i'm allowed to
contrast it which maybe i'm not but it may be just you know
provisionally that uh that
the buddhist beginning dhammapada at least is not nothing to do with god or
anything outside of the individual it's more like it all begins in our mind
it says all experience is born of the mind made of the mind
creative the mind the mind leads the lung
so it's quite it's quite a contrast between pointing towards god or pointing towards one's own mind
and after saying that the text then goes has it in two verses and then it goes on to the next one
and it says
he attacked they attacked they attacked me
the emphasis is important they attacked me they abused me
they defeated me
harboring hostility like this hatred does not end
they attacked me they abused me they defeated me
not harboring ill will hostility like this
hatred comes to an end hatred does not end
through hatred hatred ends by non-hatred
this is the ancient truth and some translations like to translate
non-hatred as love which makes it a little more inspiring for some people
hatred does not end by hatred hatred ends by love
but i like i like to translate it as non-hatred which is a literal translation because there's more than just love that
can end hatred generosity care uh
friendliness there's all these kind of range of things that oh they're they are the alternative to
hatred and so here we have this text you know that here again we find this emphasis on
hatred front and center emphasizing the importance of the mind
and then being careful with your mind because what you do with the mind has consequences
and uh those beginning verses go like this something like this all experiences
born of the mind rooted in the mind created by the mind
speak or act with a corrupted mind
and suffering follows like the cart a heavy cart
follows the oxen that's pulling it along so this burden you carry along
and then it repeats at the beginning again it says all experience is born of mind
made by mind as mined as a forerunner
speak and act with a pure mind and happiness follows
like the shadow behind you more or less i'm paraphrasing the verses
a shadow has no weight let me try weighing your shadow
and uh and so the difference between a burden this weight that you carry with you
versus there's something that has no weight that comes along everywhere you go happiness follows like a shadow
and that's this you know wonderful descriptive descriptive difference between suffering and happiness
and uh and so what we do we say and what we do are consequential
for our happiness for our suffering for the burdens we carry
and for the happiness that we that float along that easy for us to have
and then that goes on talks about hatred
hatred is considered to be a fire it burns us
it's sometimes referred to as uh it's kind of like a
if you hold a liquid poison in your hand but you have a wound in your hand a cut
then the poison can go in and they can you can get poisoned so so having hatred is like having
poison in a injured wounded hand open an open wound in that
hatred is considered a kind of bondage people who are caught in hatred are
caught in bondage so it's clearly the tradition buddha understands that hatred harms the person
who hates but to tell that to someone who hates
or someone tells you when you're full of hate following doesn't help
it's you know so but to understand hatred one of the things to understand i think
is very important is that hatred creates a strong sense of
separation between oneself and others
hatred narrows the broadness and the openness of the mind
and it creates creates definitions creates very strong definitions or
boundaries are between who i am and who someone else is
and whereas the absence of hatred loosens and dissolves some of these
strong definitions strong boundaries strong ideas of me my people
you those people or something but is is that reasonable to point out
to someone probably not i was struck by how much the news
they read the popular news concerns things that relate to great
hatred and delusion violence lots of it
and it was not violence you know that from people with hatred i mean i don't think the hurricanes and tornadoes
hate us but uh they impact us with a lot of you know very
challenging and so it's very evocative people read about the challenges
how often do you have headline news that uh you know
someone loved someone else someone cared about someone else
you know or you know i wonder i i haven't read any news about how many people have been mobilized
to help the ukrainian refugees i heard a friend of mine recently the
other day told me that she has a friend who um
bought an airplane ticket for eastern europe and told friends and told whoever may
had a gofund fund me page that i'm going there to help the refugees and if you want to give me money you can
i paid my own ticket my own way there and so he went there and just on his own
initiative and he spent three weeks driving people from the ukrainian border to wherever they had to go refugees
that's what he did and so that didn't make headline news
maybe it doesn't deserve that but the question is why do we why does the news focus on problems always and
expressions of violence and hatred and i think that one of the i suspect
that one of the reasons is that human beings have a strong survival instinct
very strong sense of wanting to survive wanting to exist as an individual as a person
and so things that threaten our survival get our attention
and and as we get as we read about things and learn about things or have
experiences that threaten seem to threaten our survival in some way
directly or indirectly it strengthens the sense of self
it strengthens me who has to respond do something protect myself and all that
and the focus becomes increasingly on me and my people
in order to be safe or get our way or be able to have our
be fulfilled in some way and that's what and so when we read
about these things these things are born from self-concern
conceits selfishness sometimes we read about it and get horrified or be
upset or get angry it points the attention back for many
people back to themselves now i feel terrible now i'm worried about climate change and what's going to impact me and
now you know all these terrible things happening you know something has to happen and you know and
so this self gets involved in a way and one of the ways that gets involved
is um now apparently in here in this country
is astounding amount of conspiracy theories astounding amount of speculation about
all this and i read recently that um some idea that that whole movement
towards conspiracy theories had its birth with the the aftermath of the assassination of
john f kennedy i remember when i was i was i was a kid then
i remember my parents and their friends would read all the books that got published right after the assassination
about all their theories about what really happened there and i remember my listening to my
parents friends and having these conversations about what could have happened
and of course people want to understand what's happening it's how we protect ourselves or how we find our way but
also understanding ourselves and standing the situation often reinforces again the conceit
i'm right i figured it out now i know i need to know
and there's those who don't know and those are no and in a confusing world where it's hard to know
it can be the confusion is frightening is you know how do we survive how do we manage ourselves this way
and so the whole spectrum you know of political spectrum are full
of filled with conspiracy theories ideas theories coming up with ideas and and uh
you know i was it's quite something even you know to have these conversations with good friends and
feel going down a rabbit hole you know with people presenting with great certainty this is how it is you know or
and you know in some ways sometimes it is how it is in some ways but what's the context for what they're saying what is
the wider view and what's useful and how do we find our way with all this
so buddhism doesn't have a final answer to this
i don't think buddhism ever expected the buddha never seemed to have offered
a recipe to solve human problems the world
is that maybe that's disappointing what he offered
was how to solve us as individuals
so that we could be forces of good in the world
we can change rather than looking for god as the creation of the world
we look at ourselves being the creators of the world the world that comes from out of us the
world that will grow from how we live this life and one of the core principles
of this is don't succumb to hate
don't live with hate work to end hate
in yourself and promote the ending of hate in the world
speak up when there's violence
make a refuge for people who are suffering the violence of the world
be a refuge for the people who are struggling and afraid
move in the direction of love of care and compassion
not not in the direction of excessive self-concern and self-preoccupation that narrows the
scope of our attention and how do we do that when so much
reinforcement is to get narrow again back to oneself my concerns my needs and everything are
my opinions and i am in these conversations with people
sometimes we're talking about what's happening in the world and they get people get opinionated
and as they get opinionated i get this feeling like i'm supposed to have an opinion
i'm either supposed to agree with them or if i disagree like like then i have to assert myself and
and then i'm kind of like now i'm caught up in this whole thing you know who's right who's wrong my
opinions correcting people them wanting to correct me or tell me
this is how it is and and you know the focus is on me you know it's it's not a comfortable world to be
in i don't think it leads to that to be in conversations but that's the
kind of the consequence of the conversations doesn't lead to peace
so what leads to peace if we ask the question what leads to
world peace we might be missing the point we might
be missing where we can make the most change which is in ourselves
can we not narrow our scope narrow our attention narrow focus can we not be caught
in self-preservation self-protection in a way
that creates a strong separation of self and others creates the other and defines ourselves
in relation to others and the people who are a threat and people who are not
in one passage in the teachings of the buddha it said that the buddha brought
an end to greed hatred and delusion and then lived
with courage bravery and taking a stand
kind of powerful language to live with courage bravery and taking a stand so this is not
you know being peaceful for oneself and ending hatred and therefore just kind of being
passively and disappearing into some nice meditative meditation state
to then what does it mean to live with courage and bravery out of non-hate
non-hate does not mean we become passive but what is a state of friendliness of
love of care of goodwill that we're capable of capable of
which those are all states where the the focus is not on
excessively predominantly on oneself one's own survival
the doors of attention are open and the attention is concerned with others
and this ability to open up the doors of concern out into the world
um can be frightening because aren't we
supposed to take care of ourselves how are we gonna manage then
and that doesn't and that that movement doesn't get a lot of uh press in the paper as i said the news
because it probably doesn't people don't click to read a lot about love
because it doesn't trigger their self-preservation concerns
or artilation concerns i mean how many times do we read because
we're kind of titillated by it all maybe i think uh there's a there's this uh it
may i don't know i i don't i just read headlines and some people talk to me about it this amazing um
libel trial that's going on and on and on between these two actors
i mean i'm just blown away at that public resources courts and judges are
being used for such an amazing amount of time
for this crazy libel thing and uh
and then you know is this and why are people so interested why is
it in the news every day why isn't such a big deal so i haven't read the articles i don't
know maybe it's really central to the progress of humankind
and i'm missing something here that uh
um but what about the you know the news
about love with the news about care and support and what's the news that inspires that in us
where's the news there's news about the art the size of armies and how many soldiers are killed
what about the news of all the many people who are helping you
and all the lives they're saving him
so this movement towards opening up to ourselves
to the wider world and in buddhism it's not about only
focusing externally we have this amazing ability to be aware
at the meeting place of others and ourselves the outer world and the inner world
and buddhist practice is to have that awareness open and broad
to be encompassing both so we can be careful with what's going
on inside come to a resolution around our own hostilities and resentments and
bitterness as we have to bring those to an end
while also being open to the wider world so the non-hatred that we
grow in then can meet the world with all these wholesome and positive
ways with goodwill
and so
so now we have in this country you know that it's horrific with the violence that's happened just these last months
and that number it seems like phenomenal number of mass shootings going on like a record
number in terms of frequency in a short period of time
and uh if you read a little bit the statistics of hate crimes in the united states
the numerically the greatest number of hate
crimes are directed towards blacks
and then the second greatest is people who are lgbtq
queer people people who have you know other gender orientations or sexual orientations
it doesn't get the same level of um press the violence against
lgbtq as other violences except maybe the shooting in orlando some years ago
and and then it's hispanics
in terms of frequency in terms of um per capita for the different population
size of these different groups of people the greatest amount of hate crimes
per capita of is uh in this country is against jews
there's about five six million jews in this country but the disproportionate amount of violence
or hate is directed towards jews given their population size
and then blacks and then lgbtq and hispanics
and now we have this growing amount of hate for against asians
it seems to just be increasing seems like the whole pandemic and how the pandemic was
how certain people blamed chinese for the pandemic
was kind of the catalyst for a whole new level of violence against asians
so so i think we have to i think you'll
have to be very careful not to have that kind of reaction to all
this that were horrified maybe
but to continue the movement of different groups in this country
seeing each other as being separate and distinct the care that goes into
recognizing the individual horrific horror
problems and being careful not to not to exact
exaggerate or extenuate the separations of people and the
hostility between people and is that possible is it reasonable to do
that so not to have to include but rather keep opening up
and imagine that if each of us could be a refuge for anybody who comes into our
view could we be a friendly
presence with goodwill for anybody who comes into our purview
what would it take is that reasonable is it
and how do we do that how do we keep how do we make room in people for our hearts even when people
do violent things even when we have to oppose the violence and say no and try to stop it
but but you know there's this that you know never succumb to hatred
is the message of the buddha work for the end of hatred
in your in yourself promote the end of hatred in the world
and perhaps with an open heart live with bravery with courage
and the teaching was that the buddha took a stand and what do you take a stand in
one of the things to take a stand in that the buddha talks about is taking a stand in peace
taking a stand in non-hatred
and then living in the world
living with love and good will and kindness
supporting our hearts peace supporting a possibility for other people to have their heart at peace
what does it take so we might not have the solution for
what our society needs
but in my mind
if we can be friendly to people
who knows what that impact of that friendliness has on someone we meet
one of the sources one of the one of the prime conditions for a certain degree of violence in our society and hatred
is people who are bullied people who feel marginalized people who
feel that the door has been closed to them
who knows if you're friendly to the little kid down the street
you might never know how how significant that was because that act of friendliness
might have prevented someone growing up to have all kinds of
horrific violent tendencies
what if someone had
been friendly to someone like hitler when he was a kid could that have changed history
i don't know is it naive to say so we'll never know how many
hitlers have not become hitler's because they had
a loving grandmother or a neighbor who believed in them and supported them and
gave them kindness and support we might not have the solutions to the
world of today
but it's possible that each of you has a solution
for the world what it's going to be like in 50 years
you'll never know it but maybe you are kind
to a small child or to grow an
older child or a teenager or an adult
maybe you showed them that they were lovable or
you showed them that they were worthy you showed them a different way
that people don't see too many people don't see in our society too many people are ignored and
forgotten and marginalized
it's possible that each of you one of you not each of you maybe i met all of you
but maybe even if it's just one of you and we don't know which one it's going
to be yet one of you and you will never know actually
but turns out that one of you here today is going to be responsible for the
fact that in 50 years
someone did not become hitler but became
the force of goodness and support
we don't the cause and conditions of how things evolve where do they
begin like to propose they always begin here with us with our actions just like the
beginning of dhammapada it begins with our actions what we do
that's the beginning for the future
i trust it i trust that we can live
in wholesome supportive ways with love and care and compassion
i trust it and i don't need to know
what the consequences are in 50 years for doing so because i believe in it now
so may you each be a force of good in this world
so in 50 years it's a better world so thank you
and [Music] if some of you are interested in uh joining me with some chairs out in the
parking lot we can have a little discussion if you want now we're in for a little informal time
i can maybe say 15-20 minutes and i'll bring a chair out and be out
there if for some of you want to join me and we can have a discussion that'll be great
otherwise i look forward to our next chance to be together thank you