welcome to our meditation together
and as an introduction to
mindfulness meditation and buddhist practice
perhaps everything that you meet everything that
you encounter everything that you hold everything that you see
everything that you hear is very important
when i was in college i took a history class and near the end of the term
preparing for the final or something i asked the professor i said to the
professor so this little detail in history this isn't really so important so we
don't have to remember it and he looked at me very kindly and he said look at me you know like he looked
into my soul kind of and said to me everything is important
that really stuck with me everything is important
some people say there's no sound and
is that right let's see let's wait and see if there is uh other people say sounds good here okay
so i'll continue
so so this idea that everything is
important everything is of value and what it would be like to live if
that was the case everything is of value everything is
important that you don't want to miss anything and the idea is maybe everything that
you in the moment you want to really be there for it it's one of the things i learned from
zen training was this very idea to meet each thing every moment
as the important thing as the value thing
and in order to do this the key
is to be able to bring our attention to what's going on to bring our attention to each thing as
if it's the most important thing and mindfulness practice can be seen as
a training to develop such a capacity of attention
and to do that it actually helps if we appreciate
that what's happening to us here and now is valuable is important
whatever it might be that each breath is appropriate to meet and fully receive
and be present for as the most important thing is a very important thing valuable thing
that every feeling emotion that comes along is important
every sensation every thought and
activity of the mind but as soon as we cling to it as soon as
we pick it up and get involved in it resist it ignore it
deny it we diminish its importance and we diminish ourselves in the process
we diminish our capacity to really offer full attention to this thing
so of course we can't do this for everything happening in the present moment
so we take our time settle in and we do it for what's
most prominent we do it for what's maybe most simple to train ourselves
to bring in attention bring attention which is not scattered
not distracted not swept up in thought or swept up in
reactions boredom the grass is greener somewhere else
there's more important things to do just here with this
everything is important you are important
and you are so important and valuable precious
that you it's important not to diminish oneself by being lost in thought
closing down with reactivity and clinging and resistance
so important to stay fully open here
and that's why we allow us train ourselves in the training that everything we bring
our attention to is important maybe the most important
thing of the moment so to
take a meditation posture
part of the art of meditation posture is to take a posture which is
solid diff like you're definitively
assuming a posture of attention in whatever way that's
works best for your body
and gently close your eyes
and the thing that's most close in most intimate here and now
in our direct experience is our body
valuable important in its own right and to begin the process of
meeting our body is the most important thing of the moment
you might take a few long slow deep breaths
as you breathe in deeply to feel your body as widely and broadly
as possible especially in the torso
and as you exhale
to release and settle into your body
exhale and come home to this body relaxing the tensions that
are kind of pulling away from the center
as you exhale settling maybe the weight of your body
all the way down into the bottom of your belly
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale relax further
relaxing some of the tensions of the body is a way for the body to become whole
the body all works together so no part of our body is closing down
or pulling away or tightening in on itself
as you exhale relaxing the face
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the belly
relaxing and settling the belly down to the very bottom
core of it all
and then this giving your attention over to your breathing
as if breathing is the most important thing
as if it's the fir your very first breath the inhale is the first inhale
maybe as if your exhale is the last exhale
something so important
and what's it like to give attention over to the breathing
relaxed open maybe even loving attention
as if breathing is the most important thing
and if anything becomes compelling
a moment to recognize it appreciate it
as if it's the most important thing of the moment it's so important
you don't want to interfere with it or latch onto it or pick it up
get involved so important you just want to let it be itself
recognizing it as it is with care and attention
and then begin again with your breathing
whatever arises don't dismiss anything belittle anything
if it takes you away from your breathing
be content to be mindful of it for a few moments
and then begin again with your breathing
because each thing in itself is important you don't have to be trying to get
something or get anywhere in a sense you already arrived
where you need to be here
offering your loving attention your caring attention
to each thing and it's the nature quality of your
attention relaxed open clear
present that's the real
way in which we discover each thing is important
as you're aware of your breathing as you become aware of anything
relax your awareness too your awareness is
also the most important thing
and don't compromise your awareness by straining or pushing
or doubting relax and allow the awareness
to do its thing simply openly in whatever way awareness
is aware that's enough
awareness aware of breathing
whatever is important
calls on us to care for it
to have a sense of care both caring for it's it's getting a sense of its
value we care for it but also to offer our aid our support
our good will
for it
they're all things
even if we throw some we put something in the trash
if it's important that also we don't toss it away
no need to use words like tossing or discarding but rather we place it
in the trash not as an afterthought or an aside
but as if placing something in the
carefully and well and so it can go on to its next stage of existence
to recycling or the dumb forever with our care and our
intentionality
and for all people all the living beings of this world
to take the time to let them be the most important thing of the
moment we can care for others as well
we can care for their welfare and wish for their happiness and well-being
maybe there's something some way in which seeing each person is valuable important
where it becomes almost second nature for some part inside of us
to care about them to value and appreciate
so that there's good will well wishing
and if that well-wishing is a light bulb
turning on the light bulb of meta of kindness
so that it radiates and shines out from us almost as a light
as a glow as a care a warmth
and as we come to the end of this meditation
to send out with our light with our care and
goodwill with our attention our well wishing
that all may all the people that we know in our lives
may may they be well
may they be happy and safe and healthy
may they be at ease in their life
and may those people that i encounter today in person or in communication or
learning about them in some way through the news or some way
they're also they are also important each living being has importance
and perhaps some some aspect of goodwill can travel from you to them
some kind gaze may all of you
be happy may all of you be healthy and safe
may all of you be at ease
in your life
and then to turn that kindness and goodwill to yourself
that you yourself are also important
at times you're the most important person for you yourself
you're the one that you're most intimate with the one you know the best
and to wish yourself well to aspire
to wish and work for your own happiness
you might say to yourself may i be happy
may i be healthy and safe
may i be at ease
may i be free
and may it be that on this day that you experiment
living a life as if each thing is important each thing
is something you can care for and every person
is someone who you can offer your good will
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe and may all beings be free
[Music]
and then to continue their talks on loving kindness on metta
good will i just i delight
in just saying those words i think there's such wonderful qualities
and touches something precious and valuable inside to just evoke the qualities of
meta kindness friendliness good will
and that wasn't always the case for me
when i was first introduced to uh the teachings of meta loving-kindness
i had a background where the way i rece understood them
is that they were artificial they were kind of uh dr uh
creating artificially feelings of goodwill or kindness that were kind of
sticky or excessively sweet or something and maybe sentimental and
and i was much more practical and pragmatic just i just wanted to have a spirituality that was just about
um waking up just about being present in a direct
unmediated way and this loving-kindness thing was just kind of getting in the way
and uh so when the teachers my early theravadin teachers would do guided
loving kindness meditation i just tuned them out and just continue doing my basic mindfulness practice
until such a time that uh through the mindfulness itself it was kind of like mindfulness is a
tenderizing force something settled relaxed something way i was holding myself closed began to
open and at some point i started having this very nice feeling inside
that was kind of new to me and
and uh it had a very very pleasant very peaceful warm nice feeling very
different than compassion which i had already tapped into through practice but
this other thing and then at some point i thought maybe this is what these teachers are
talking about yes it is this is what they mean by this good will and this method
and so rather than being something i had to construct or make happen it was welding up inside
and then recognizing it then the whole thing about practicing meta loving kindness
became quite valuable for me and a very valuable part of my life and
a life and so when i say these words the beginning of meta goodwill kindness
just saying the words kind of touches something in my heart that kind of
kind of has a feeling of kind of a little bit singing my heart sings a little bit to those concepts and ideas
and so anyway so this is a topic for this week
and and one of the things i want to say is that
in emphasizing good will and loving kindness and this tradition terrapin tradition also does it for oneself
also meditation practice is closing your eyes and kind of focusing inwardly to your own inner experience
it's easy to criticize it as being self-centered in fact i when i
back in the early years in which i was meditating i haven't heard this for many years now
but people would complain that met people doing 40 minutes of meditation each day
were spending their their time being selfish and you know someone who's religious should
really be out there doing things to the world sacrificing themselves
and um and the people who complained about the selfish meditators meditating for 45 minutes or 40 minutes or however long it
was we're probably spending two or three hours a day watching television but that belonged to a television
watching belonged to a different domain of life than the religious life and the religious life should really be
about being altruistic and that doing religious life there was you know inwardly inward what they saw
as being selfish i don't think it's that way at all and certainly wasn't for the buddha
it's not a self-centered path because self-centeredness being kind of preoccupied with oneself is a way of
actually harming oneself and if you really care about yourself and see yourself as important you wouldn't be
selfish because of this harm it does for oneself also the idea is that
there's a mutuality in in this world of ours that the more we care for ourselves and
love ourselves and free ourselves
the more that we benefit others and the more if we benefit others
without harming ourselves that we're also benefiting ourselves
and so this practice of loving kindness you can see this in it that as we offer
our care to others this meta care this way of this kindness and this friendliness
um we benefit also because these fee if if they're really genuine
not artificial not forced not obligated but arising from this kind of wonderful
place inside that that as we express it as we live it uh
this vibrates this flows this opens up there's a warmth happens here
it's nourishing for the person who has the kindness compassion also is meant to nourish the
one who's compassionate and if we're not somehow nourished or there's not some satisfying feeling
and having loving kindness it probably isn't quite loving kindness or it's loving kindness that's mixed up with
other things and
so in loving others the loving person benefits and in the teachings of buddhism you the
loving person is allowed to benefit from the love it's not selfish
it's just a byproduct it's not selfish because developing oneself and growing oneself is a way to become a person
who's more beneficial to others more able to meet others and
and really see other people and offer a presence as if that person is important maybe the most important
person at the moment of the time and if we diminish ourselves and feel somehow that we're less and not
important or we demean ourselves or critical of ourselves or
don't have you know this care and valuing of ourselves
then actually we have less to offer others than when we meet someone else we're not really meeting them
fully they don't feel the full goodness of who we are they feel a kind of goodness if we're
trying to be nice but it's not really full and it might be a little bit
trying too hard sometimes but to relax deeply and be at ease and
be at home in oneself and to feel uh that you know regardless of one's
foibles regardless of our shortcomings that we are completely deserved and
appropriate for us to love and care for this being that being here for ourselves
it isn't like everyone in the world deserves love and care except there's one exception one person
who it just doesn't make it the cut and that's oneself it doesn't work that way
everyone is so this practice of mindfulness is practice living kindness is a practice of
including caring for oneself and mindfulness is a self-care process
so the idea is um to um to care for ourselves and love for
ourselves see ourselves as important and really learn how to
soften and relax the ways in which we suffer the ways which we
close down and diminish ourselves so we have more to give others
you can't teach a foreign language unless you learn the language first yourself
you can't um there's many situations where you you can't learn
a teacher a path of freedom unless you've been on that path for yourself
and and you can't know love you can't offer love unless you really know it here for
yourself and so to really it's okay to benefit
from the practice of love of kindness and all that
um now it's not selfish this focus here
and this love for ourselves because um it's possible
um one of the great delights of i think a spiritual life and i've heard other
people in other religions say this outside of buddhism that
it's possible to have lots of love for others warmth kindness friendship
good will whatever those words work for you and not need
to have it come back so not be that our well-being doesn't
have to be dependent on being loved by others we have a bigger need to love as adults
we have a bigger need to love than we do to be loved
and and if we have a strong need to be loved chances are that that need i want to
respect the need for sure that that need is most uh
benefit most benefits or is more profound or resolved if we're the one who love ourselves if
we can learn to offer care and kindness and goodwill to this person here
and if we do this if we practice the practice of loving kindness or just practice more good will in our life and
learn to explore it and feel it and appreciate it when it's there and
expand it to enhance it whenever we can the
the buddhist tradition lists seven eleven benefits that come from doing loving kindness
and the ancient description of this
specifies it's really developing this to a high degree but i think we get some of these benefits even if we just start doing it
in small ways so it's kind of a delightful list and i wanted to read the list of 11 benefits
of loving kindness one sleeps happily
one wakes happily one has no bad dreams
one is loved by others so one doesn't need to be loved by others
but one is loved by others so that's kind of a nice balance
and one is loved by non-humans so maybe that means animals
or maybe it means the devas buddhism believes in all these kind of
kind of devas that are floating around and because the next one is one is
guarded by the devas and i think that when one practices uh kindness and friendliness and goodwill
that there are seen unseen ways in which the situation the people around us then
treat us differently and there is a kind of protection that comes with it
a fire poison or sword won't touch one so i don't know about that but uh it's
quite a wonderful benefit if it's true that you're protected from fire and poison and weapons
uh the next one is good for meditators one's mind becomes
concentrated quickly someone's mind becomes concentrated
quickly because you have less to be agitated for or less to be upset about if
if there's more love and and so it's easier to kind of get settled
and then uh it says here number nine is once complexion becomes clear
so that's nice it's a lot cheaper than other ways of getting a clear complexion
one dies with the mind free from confusion now this is a real benefit i
think how we die is i just see it as such a to die well to die
at ease at peace to die with kind of an open heart
without confusion is one of the great potentials or possibilities
and mindfulness is said to support that but so does this good will this method
and then the eleventh one if there's no higher attainment is reached one is reborn in the brahma realms
and so some of these benefits speak to some of us us moderns and some of us don't but i
just delight in this grand list of wonderful benefits of it all
i'll read you one more that it says that
a wonderful quote that um
where is it maybe i don't have it here um yes
the buddha wants to ask the group of three monks are you living together on friendly and harmonious terms
as milk and water mixed together do you regard each other with affection
and the monk said they were and the and the buddha said well how do
you do this and they answered since it has occurred to me one of them
answered since it occurred to me that i am fortunate to be living with others
in the holy life that practice life i have loving kindness towards them
in speech i conduct speech conduct and thought i openly and privately extend my
loving kindness so um to live together like milk and water
harmoniously mixing together with others is one of the benefits of loving kindness
so thank you and look forward to being here tomorrow and
sorry i went over it hasn't usually happened this way and
but you know the topic is love so thank you
you