so hello and welcome everyone [Music] happy to be with you lovely to be with
you so for today's practice i'd like to invite us to
practice um [Music] both equanimity resilience just quiet
stillness for the benefit of compassion with what is going on in the world
it's time it's we need more we need more stability we need more resilience we
need more peace and calm so that we can be available we can be available both
internally for ourselves not to be completely toppled over into sorrow and grief
but also available for others how can we help how can we support how can we serve
and maybe one way we can service through our availability of space of kindness space
of of stability and i also like to bring in some
practice of with meta and compassion for all who are suffering in the world which
in some ways includes all of us all of us human beings and especially for those who are
especially suffering in really really difficult situations right now
um in ukraine and in russia people who didn't choose the political situation but they're
being severely impacted and hurt by it in so many ways
so so maybe there's not much more i want to say but but to say that
yeah we'll start with a lot of silence tonight and just settling with the breath with the body
and then um in in order to build stability in all
order to build spaciousness and then i'll have invitations for us to
both include ourselves in our mette and our compassion because even when difficult challenges are
happening in the world and in war zones our own personal suffering and dukkha
does not end does not cease so to bring our own
[Music] dear selves to mind to heart to care for this being who's me and also sharing our
our care our good will for other beings in the world who are
suffering so that's the framing
so without further ado let's practice together let's arrive
fine our meditation posture
sitting lying down whatever is nourishing or supportive in this moment
oh dear heart dear
taking refuge in the heart space
with each breath settling more
to the body
to the lower abdomen
feet releasing letting go of any tension
being embodied with the breath
the entirety of the in-breath breathing in
the counts counting slowly up to four
then pausing for a moment holding the break breath briefly and then
exhaling for a paw for a count of five
do it together first a couple times and then you can do it in your own time just to help settle and arrive
breathing in one two
three four pausing the breath
exhaling one two three
four four briefly pausing
and again inhaling four
exhaling count of five pause
letting the exhale be longer than the inhale can help settle
the body the mind we'll do that just a little bit before we let the breath be natural
if the mind is particularly unsettled tonight you can continue
this counting with the breath longer to help support arrive
and land
this
if you are still using the counting device with the breath
let it be gentle and again
breathing at the count of four pause breathing out gently
releasing the count of five
you can change the count and make your breath longer both the in-breath and the
out-breath that might happen naturally as you settle in and arrive more
deeply
and imagine the breath
gentle the body relaxed as much as possible
that the breath age in breath out breath
is like fluffing a feather bed
fluffing making it soft ready your body as if your body is a feather
bed and i'm fluffing it gentleness kindness your body is the
soft gentle welcoming
nourishing home
that's holding your tired heart and mind
with each breath gently being fluffed
let the breath fluffing
be nourishing fluffing the energetic body
or the energy body let it be nourishing healing
soft supple [Music] kind
maybe the image that works better for some is
a mane of a horse soft being mentally combed
same idea the breath doing that with the body energetically
is there any proverbial death
dirt oh it's gently fluffed
calmed out the body kindness
gentleness holding this tired heart and mind
resting resting
each breath combing fluffing the energy body
the heart can rest and the kindness of the space
relax feel safe
with each breath
so
creating a safe comfortable kind loving space for ourselves
it's an expression of meta of care
let the breath be breathed
and the inner g-body fluffed
just as if the mane of a horse soft gently brushed
where a feather bed is fluffed
let it be nourishing healing for you
if you've had called specially challenging day or time in your body
your heart and mind you can stay with yourself if you like
otherwise if there is space capacity to open up further
here are the invitations
continuing the same metaphor of fluffing
comfortable feather beds
or brushing the hair the maid
of a horse gently
as tightnesses maybe pieces of dirt
are released to smooth it out and there's just a harmonious
flowing
main afterwards as if symbolically as if you had a big
brush
combing all beings
just gently fluffing [Music] as if all the ills all the sorrow
all the challenges brushing them through
bringing healing sucker comfort because you care
sharing your care
whereas if you are fluffing pillows feather bed
for beings around the world many beings many humans
especially those in challenging situations they're there
offering your care if you're laying a comfortable bed for them
covering them with your love with your care in a blanket of meta
may you be free may you be free from sorrow from suffering
may you have these
may there be as much ease and comfort and well-being
for you in this difficult time
those in places of war famine
the orphans of the world
as the ryokan said oh if only my monk's robes are white enough
to protect all the suffering beings
in this entire world the same spirit of generosity and care
it's an aspiration aspirationally of course
our robes can never avoid them but we offer we offer our kindness
our goodness our compassion as a training as service
imagining that your care brings comfort
and if you fall into distress and grief come back to yourself
come back to yourself
holding yourself with care
and compassion
remember if you fall into empathic distress come back to yourself
with compassion and care
and for the last few minutes returning back to yourself
with each breath letting the energy body be fluffed
naturally place of comfort ease sucker
may all beings everywhere especially those
in the war zones
maybe free from suffering sorrow pain
distress may they have a
peace of being [Music] as possible
in the midst of the challenge
may all beings everywhere including ourselves be safe
healthy and have ease
may all beings be free
thank you for your practice everyone
so [Music] you are invited if there are any reflections
questions and both for the benefit of the sangha to
share your aha moment or challenge also for you to be a health witness
especially if you haven't spoken in a while you can also type your
reflections in chat if they are typed to everyone i'll read your name
and if they're privately sent to me i won't read your name
frazzle says [Music]
and also knowing that the practice tonight was
very calm very uh there's a lot of emphasis on calming and soothing and the
energy body there can be
that's completely understandable if that's happening for you
megan says i love all things fluffy so that was absolutely delightful it's
great i could see this meditation being very useful when encountering difficulty at
work yay delighted to hear
that hey the work that you do and the way that
you serve others may be of support to you this fluffy practice fluffing the
energy body basically yeah one reflection on youtube and in and
emotional practice thank you you are welcome yeah
nicholas [Music]
oops there can you unmute yeah there you go
can you hear me okay yeah wonderful um try to not make this too upsetting i uh
i read an article um that was about
a unit of snipers in the ukraine and it was really on my heart just because the article kind of really
portrayed them in balance as people who kind of celebrated their craft which is killing people
and also people who are very brave and very much defending their homeland and somehow the this this very calm
space that we kind of held today was i think a very supportive space for just kind of sitting in that realm of
like you know i don't really know i don't really know the full picture here you know on both sides of people who are
killed and being killed and you know i mean there's just there's so much and yeah somehow it was it was a very
healthy space of just kind of holding that that not knowing and
kind of just holding the bigness of what's happening so thank you
thank you nicholas thank you so much for bringing that in that bigness that you mentioned and and how this
holding the space of spaciousness for all the suffering so
much suffering all around us just the the killer and the killed it's just so
the snipers and the it's just it's beyond imagination all the suffering of
everyone involved and everyone watching holding witness it's just
and also to know that humanity has gone through cycles of this right humanity
i think we're hopefully better a little bit but but but still it just keeps
happening so just holding spaciousness oh dear dear humanity which i'm a part
of oh holding all of us with compassion yeah thank you nicholas
mima i see your hand please um i appreciated this because it feels
so overwhelming sometimes um the um
the amount of suffering that we hear about and not feeling like there's nothing i can do about it
and knowing that being here with the sangha and meditating and contributing in that way
um to me is very significant it gives me peace
yeah yeah thank you mima it's it's important because
it can be overwhelming and then if it's when it's overwhelming we want to just
turn away and completely tune out um and that's not helpful either right
so so having the space to actually
hold witness and and offer care which which it is you know as the
buddha says whatever you frequently think and reflect upon that becomes the inclination of your
mind so the more we upon kindness care compassion
for others that becomes the inclination of our mind and our actions too so it's
not just in the mind space it's not just in the the holding space space which is
important too for our own equanimity stability and those of others but it's also it leads to action
wholesome action in any way we can in our community
he says thank you for the breathing reminder to arrive tonight if anyone awakens in the night wide-eyed
thinking about the world your recording of
uh it went oh re-recording of overwhelm was just the ticket to settle back down with
more equanimity and compassion thank you nikki i had a better day because of your guidance oh thank you
vicky so appreciate it to hear that it was supportive for you especially in the
middle of the night that i think we did i did maybe it was monday or la i think it was last week
it was about uh practicing with equanimity when suffering of the world is overwhelming so i think that's the
one you're referring to vicky i'm glad it was supportive for you in the middle of the night may be
supportive to others
yeah yeah and dipper is bringing up the complexity of the
the pain of of both the killer and the kill and i think i'd rather not get entangled than that it's a bigger topic
it's more than i want to spend time and talk about right now but yeah
but it but everyone suffers really everyone suffers in that entanglement
so i'd like to to invite us now to hold the space this
fluffy energy body fluffed space as if we're fluffing um
comfortable blankets and and uh pillows for one
another as we enter into the small sangha with another couple of
practitioners can there be sense of holding space and there may there may not be a lot of
words said tonight and that is okay but can we hold space for each other
and also ourselves with equanimity with care
in this space so let's start with maybe 10 seconds of of
silent meta and then
silent meta and then you can share as much as you want or
or just hold witness that's okay too so i've created the rooms
and i'm going to open them so take care of yourselves actually i'm going to recreate the rooms
um hold take care of yourselves take care of each other um
yeah take care of yourselves take care of each other welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed and we have just about a minute if there are any reflections you like to
share
to be quick okay
i don't see any hands or anything typed in chat so maybe we'll
we'll um close so um i actually one announcement i wanted
to make is that um on saturday i'm teaching
a half a day i'll put information in the chat if anyone is
on through the new york inside meditation for anyone especially who missed
the befriending mortality course this is a half day it's a it's a crash course
so um we'd love to see you if you like
this with that if you need a a uh if you need a way to to
bring fire into your practice catherine says those metaphors are
fluffing and horses were delicious oh that's so sweet thanks catherine that's a great note to
end on so thank you all thank you so much for your practice for your dedication
may you be well safe happy may all beings everywhere be safe
[Music] thank you