so hello and before we start i just saw my screen turn black
and and then i think twice i think did anyone else have still having problems with the image
transmission black for a moment this happened last night as well
i don't know what it is but i'm going to last night it happened and and it um
we kept the transmission going but uh there was a
strange things with uh um
with the image it was a kind of uh stretched out like a like a amusement parks me uh kind of
mirror that you stand in front of so um
so we'll see if a couple of things might happen one is that i might it happens again
i'm going to switch the the screen is frozen
yes also saw that yesterday during the eee day long well the day long had nothing to do with um
well that then i think might be a internet service provider problem
um and it's uh supposed to student's image goes black and fourth for you it's
it's intermittent it seems to be i'm going to uh switch our uh
service provider we have two of them here and i'll be right back in a moment
yeah so some people are having this issue and we're having it here as well some people are not having the issue
of the screen going black and i made one change now and now so we'll
see if that makes a difference and if it doesn't then
i have one more change i can make if we lose the youtube connection
you might have to log on again
so we'll see so
in some ways having things not go
right is not wrong in for the purpose of dharma
practice it's just something else to fold into our practice and to be mindful of and
and be careful that we don't succumb to some kind of um
you know for the the topic for this week to succumb to the hindrances
so in terms of the hindrances today's topic
is aversion or ill will and
uh this is very uh closely connected to its positive
uh companion it can look like it sometimes
and um and there is a way of uh saying no to things
that does not have to involve aversion and so for this purposes of the meditation
there is say no thank you or i'm not going to follow that train of thought i'm not
going to pick up that kind of situation or i'm not going to
be aversive no thank you to aversion i'm not going to be swept up into the
desires and and
so rather than only kind of being mindful of what's happening there is an appropriate way of saying no
and it's not so much a no of pushing something away but it's a no of choosing not to be
involved in it not to pick it up not to get entangled in it
and this makes a lot of sense the more we have a have some feeling or experience
of peace or well-being and meditation
so that we can
feel there's a loss there's a we could diminish a little bit
as we get involved in certain things so in particular
in particular we could have um a healthy no
to the mind's movement of aversion of of the minds
contracting around it wanting something to go away so here it went away
so it happened again this blacking out it seems to be happening intermittently
so i see some people are reporting it when it hasn't happened here
and some of them and maybe it's happening here um
i wonder if it uh i read they're supposed to be solar flares today
and i wonder if there's something large like that but i'm going to make one more change
and see if that makes a difference and if it doesn't then and and it's possible
we'll lose the connection and i'll log back on again and then we'll sit in
in silence and meditate with maybe with a healthy no towards aversion so hang on for a moment
so let's meditate quietly for the next 20 minutes
and that way there might be all kinds of
blacking out blanking out that goes on and if it happens on the screen
we probably won't notice and if it happens in our minds may it teach you something about letting
go deeply
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
sometimes the opposite of ill will
is love and all the variations of love
good will compassion kindness
appreciative joy appreciation delight in other people
warm-heartedness we have this rich capacity
for love in many many flavors
to learn not to be caught up in ill will releases our capacity freeze our
capacity for love
it's one of the most significant and healing aspects of our personal and social life
so may it be that whatever we learn these days about
the hindrances and today about ill will may it be a support for going into the
world with at least a teeny bit more orientation
to love kindness benevolence good will
appreciating and respecting every person that we meet
may this practice that we do today be for the welfare and happiness
of all beings everywhere
may our respect for each person that we meet
be a medium for bringing well-being and peace into
this world may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
well if it blacked out again the last 20 minutes i wasn't watching the screen so i don't know
hopefully it's stable again and we can continue with the talk
so today's topic is ill will as a hindrance
and the opposite of ill will is love of all the different kinds
uh the closely related because it looks a
little bit like ill will is our healthy capacity to say no
to uh to avert ourselves from activities which are harm
producing or unhealthy for us and and so
whereas love and ill will can be seen as quite distinct
this healthy averting can be confused with the aversion that
comes with ill will and and so we have to be very careful here
and so it can be part of our strength our capacity to say no thank you to things
so mostly here in meditation we're talking about internal things so certain trains of thought arise and
we've been down those that been on those trains a lot we see that they usually end up in in train
crashes and so we say no thank you and now we say no where we we turn ourselves away
from the involvement with those it's not being aversive or ill will towards them but just knowing that this
is not a good place to go and
so we have to kind of it helps to see those two as distinct because in relationship to ill will
there's a healthy way of saying no to it we're not supposed to only accept it and hold it in awareness
we're also there's times when we say no thank you enough not this we let go
and so the hindrances uh are fascinating
they are one of the primary areas of study investigation for people
who do inside meditation there's um it's because these are the primary
forces that are said to interfere with insight into fear with concentration interfere with our ability to really
have clear attention to the moment and the way to
one of the healthy ways of working with hindrances they don't predominate is to understand them well
and so rather than being upset if one of the hindrances arises for you
take it as an opportunity to understand it more deeply and this is where turning around and looking at it
deeply is part of the what we learn and what we do and some of the things we
learned can learn for some of us is that sometimes the hindrances are strategies
for us to avoid things that uh aren't comfortable for us things that are painful difficult
and uh and some people run off to desire to food and
pleasures and things that could take them away some people get involved with aversion
anger and blame and that's how they kind of are not really stopping to really be with the
discomfort they're pushing it away or directing you know the attention outward
towards the object of ill will and so forth for the other hindrances
there can be ways in which the mind is trying to avoid stopping and really looking carefully
what's happening here really learning the skill of being present for what's uncomfortable rather than
reacting to it and um so in ordinary mindfulness everyday
mindfulness when the mind is not settled and concentrated um there's some wonderful ways of
practicing mindfulness with the hindrances one is to appreciate that often
they are they have an object or kind of an object some concern that we have
space especially true for desire and ill will and and when we caught and desire new will
we're often uh preoccupied with the object of the desire the object of the ill will
and so it's kind of like the attention is directed
it's a objectifying or objective attention and
and so what we try to do then is to turn our attention around 380 degrees
to feel what it's like to have desire what it's like to have ill will
we let go of our concern with the object the best we can to to really be present for the
experience of desire the experience of ill will and that's what we're trying to discover or investigate to understand
deeply and that begins to break the trance the allure
of desire and ill will when we're no longer committed to the object
but rather we're committed to our own well-being and then we start feeling that um
that this ill will the desire is a kind of alienation it's a way of being not connected to ourselves
because we're so involved in the object and even if the object inside of us
um if there's a narrowing in the alienating kind of way in which you're only present for us ourselves partially
and so this turning the tension around 180 degrees away from the object to what the experience like how it feels within
us is a effective way of working with the hindrances
as we do this then also you want to start feeling what are the different emotions that
come into play so with ill will
for sometimes anger or ill will hostility is people's people recoiling from their
own sadness underneath ill will there could be sadness sometimes sometimes there's hurt
sometimes there's a loneliness sometimes there's some kind of inner pain that's the kind of the catalyst for this
objectifying kind of ill will and hostility so as we turn the attention around
we can kind of see the underlying emotion that's might be the fuel for it and chances are that's what needs our
love that's what needs a caring careful attention more so than the than
the hindrance itself um sometimes in daily life what we can
learn to do with the hindrances is not maybe it's hard to kind of pay attention to it carefully and turn
around and look at it deeply it's it's so strong and life is so busy and we know we have a hindrance but we're kind
of in the midst of all the activities of life and it's difficult to stop and sometimes the
significant thing to do is uh is um uh restraint
radical restraint just no i'm not going to do this i'm not going along with this i'm not going to speak from my ill will
i'm not going to act on my ill will you know just just simply no it's not pretty it's not
deep and insightful but sometimes that's better than than the alternative when we give into it
and there's a kind of wonderful muscle that gets developed the muscle of restraint that will serve a meditator tremendously
through a you know a lifetime of meditation when meditation is deep
deeper clearer and this is the i think the premise for the fourth foundation of mindfulness
is that a person has kind of followed the journey of practice
and they've gotten quieter stiller more present then we have the opportunity to
see the hindrance in a new way and that is to see it as a inconstant experience
to see that it comes and it goes to feel what it's like when it's not there get to know it when it's not there
uh and the in meditation sometimes the the quality of the absence of desire or
aversion can be quite high there's a real sense of peace perhaps
or some something that feels really nice that's really finally we're free of these hindrances that maybe is part and parcel of our
ordinary life and so to take time to now feel that
turn around and really feel the well-being the peace the quiet the stillness that might be there
let it register deeply the registering it sometimes allows it to grow and become fuller
but also to see the unconstancy of it and and this is where the
insight meditation and the satipattana really comes to
its maturity is when we start seeing things arising and passing
and in terms of the hindrances um it's a little bit different because there this text seems to imply that we should
use our agency to let go of it so if we can be really present
to see it be a ill will or virgin hostility
arise and we're right there to see it come into being
this is a opportune time a a unparalleled time perhaps
to um let go say it's almost like the body and mind has almost a memory of what it was like
just before when it wasn't there and it's seen as a provisional state
seen as not having the absoluteness of really strong fiery anger or hostility it's just a
something that's appearing the buddha called it a visitor
visitors that cover over or hide the luminosity of the mind
and so and so be quiet enough and it's kind of a delightful even
amusing thing to be quiet and still enough and watch a movement towards ill will arise
and then say no let go like and not going there and sometimes
just letting go is just more like letting be because we're not we're not picking it
up we're just letting it be letting it go by and and this is one of the deeper ways of
practicing with the hindrances and the reason it's deeper is that it's it's now beginning to align
the practice with the emphasis in the refrain of the satipatthana sutra to see the arising
and passing of phenomena and to really be there for at the place where we can see how inconstant how
changeable our experiences our perceptions are or and um and this is where um
and so this clarity we're trying to develop by not having the hindrances obscure
the mind becomes this clarity of sitting quietly
in the changing flow of experience in the present moment the inconstant arising of passing coming and
going appearing and disappearing the flow of change that is the present
moment if we're in the present moment things are always changing
and uh and that's a deep liberating place to sit and be
the entrances are not liberating but we're moving we're developing attention to the
hindrances so that that attention can become liberating for
us and the hindrances are just as good as object as almost anything else
so so see today if
you have ill will anger hostility aversion
that feels painful to have and stop and stop for it stop a lot really
take your time with it do that the the the practice of turning attention 180 degrees around to really
feel it get to know it and and if you have it then when it's no
longer there feel what that absence like and if you are tracking this through the
day perhaps you'll catch and see the arising of ill will maybe it's
driving your car and someone cuts you off and you see it arise right there and um and what what what opportunity
what's how's that different to have ill will you see it arise
than it is already in place so i hope you can this way
maybe not enjoy your hindrances and enjoy ill will but maybe
enjoy and maybe even be amused in being mindful of it
seeing it clearly for what it is and uh and find a very different relationship to ill will than many
people have when they um are pushed around by it
thank you and i appreciate our time together and
we'll continue with these hindrances tomorrow
you