so good morning everyone and here we are in the last day of
discussing the four noble truths and in terms of uh
how it relates to meditation it's it's central to the whole process
in buddhism but what i'd like to emphasize for this meditation
is that an um word in the
wording a description of the four noble truths that's often overlooked
and that is the word understanding
to understand the noble truth of suffering to understand
the noble truth of the arising of suffering to understand the noble truth of the
cessation of suffering and to understand the noble truth
of the practice leading to the cessation of suffering
and so you see the word understanding keeps getting repeated and
it's it's uh we tend to kind of look at the rest of the sentences to understand
we means we have to understand something we have to understand what it's the meaning of the statements are
but half of what we're doing also is beginning to appreciate more and more
value recognize um the understanding
the awareness the the knowing
that goes on and it's kind of a little bit maybe the secret that rather than
solving the four noble truths and seeing them understanding them a big part of what we're doing is
heightening the our recognition our appreciation of
the mind's ability to be attentive and that takes many forms one of them is
to understand to know to be conscious of
and as this sense of has a sense of
attentiveness awareness knowing clear comprehension
mindfulness becomes stronger it becomes a refuge
it becomes a place to abide in and it becomes a place where we feel
safe present as we're able to look out into the world or look into our own suffering
in an effective way it is we're not blinded by
or absorbed or about what suffering is but we appreciate the ability to step
back and just hold it in awareness so for this meditation
maybe there's some way that you can switch
the paradigm of how minds often operate where they're concerned about something
and when if we do mindfulness we're trying to be mindful of something and that's all fine
but there's a whole other half of what's happening and that is the awareness itself the
knowing the attentiveness the clear comprehension i
use a lot of words because different people resonate with different words or their minds work differently
and so their attentiveness is different using different capacities
so
i see some felt sense a felt sense to feel what's going on is
also another way if if we don't get caught up in how we feel
but are able to rest and be receptive in that feeling sense that we have
so let's see how that goes today so beginning the meditation
lowering your gaze if their eyes are open and looking down
and not looking at anything in particular
but the eyes see there is seeing
that seeing which make has no effort to see
maybe things are not in focus but still the eyes are taking in
light and
receptive receptivity of the eyes
and then gently closing your eyes
and there's the receptivity of hearing where it maybe it doesn't matter so much
what you hear but if you can hear something
i appreciate the hearing
the hearing-ness of hearing
the receptivity of the ears
and then there's the sensations of your body
sensing the body
but not searching for sensations but the way the body is receptive to
sensations and sensations appear
are present and being appreciating the receptivity
of our sensing the body
if you feel any holding or tension in the body
maybe on the exhale relax the holding soften
and letting yourself just take a few moments to breathe consciously
to breathe attentively
where the attentiveness to breathing
is appreciated as something important
just attentiveness itself
the fact that we're conscious
is kind of a miracle
and to be conscious is always something that happens in the present moment
to appreciate being conscious is to appreciate the present
a consciousness which is not searching or trying to do something
that is more receptive
as you exhale perhaps you can relax any tension or pressure around or within
your field of attentiveness around consciousness being conscious
perhaps allowing the sensations or the experience of
breathing to be like a gentle wind
flowing across the field of consciousness
gentle waves washing up across the beach
coming and going on the beach the beach being consciousness
being conscious
when a new sensation arises a sound
feeling in your body a thought a feeling
the beginning of a new in-breath or beginning of a new out breath
when things arise
in awareness i appreciate how that arising
can remind you of being of being aware itself
of knowing itself things are known
sensed felt experienced
the arising of something new is an occasion to appreciate
that we're conscious
perhaps you can notice
being conscious being aware
that you can notice now what arises effortlessly in awareness
maybe it's something unexpected what arises effortlessly and is known
effortlessly it can be anything at all
a new sound a new sensation a repeated sound repeated sensation
whatever it is maybe initially before we get involved
in it there's a effortless knowing
recognition
and appreciate that part of the mind
that is attentive effortlessly
the part of the mind is not choosing what to attend to
not directing the mind part of the mind that just is
and experiences arise are known
sensed felt
and now with this kind of
knowing kind of
attentiveness that has this effortless quality receptive open
become aware of something that's uncomfortable here and now
your body some emotions some feeling some thoughts you're having
anything that's uncomfortable or stressful or
and see if you can know it that kind of awareness
the receptive open effortless awareness
where discomfort is just known but it's not a problem for this
effortless mind effortless consciousness
the mind being conscious of it is more appreciated
more valued than the discomfort
and then bring to mind some suffering you have in your life
maybe remember it think about it but rather than prioritizing
the thinking about it prioritize
the awareness that knows it quietly peacefully
prioritize the capacity to be conscious as you
are reminded of your suffering
and now gently softly
take a few long slow deep breaths comfortably longer
and relax let go as you exhale
settle deeply more deeply into this body relax
settle in
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
maybe relaxing into a simple
capacity for being aware or conscious the place where things are just known
receptively or effortlessly
and from this place of receptivity maybe clarity
maybe a kind of stillness gaze upon the world
kindly gaze upon yourself
kindly
with compassion for the suffering of the world with compassion for your own suffering
and perhaps from some place deep within some place that feels
maybe a place of home or a place of integrity
it can express the kindness the compassion
with the aspiration the generosity
of wishing yourself well
wishing yourself happiness
safety
peace and freedom
and then gazing out across the world a world where there's
abundance of suffering
and not getting caught in that suffering appreciating being conscious of it
and the kind of place of conscious stillness or openness
that's a powerful channel
for your compassion for the world
where your aspiration your generosity for the world
might be taken in the with the words given with the words
may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
[Music]
i wanted to read a wonderful passage from the teachings of the buddha
that
uh the buddha talks about he says it is enough
it's it's enough to do this this is a a good enough wonderful life
this is enough just if you just do this with your life somehow something like that
so rather than thinking this is like a high standard something but maybe it is but this is enough this is
uh this is a wonderful way this would be enough if you just did this it would be enough
um
um practicing for your own for your own welfare
is enough practicing for the welfare of others
is enough practicing for the welfare of both the
self and others is enough
there's a little bit more it's a little bit more than that it was a little bit of a paraphrase of the text
but um here we are uh practicing hopefully for the our
welfare and the welfare of others and we're this week we looked at the
four noble truths and the wording of the four noble truths is
uh to me is very simple the wording itself but very
evocative so one way it's evocative is that there are no pronouns in it
it says uh one understands the noble truth of suffering
one understands the noble truth of the arising of suffering one understands the noble truth of the cessation of
suffering and one understands the the noble truth of the practice leading
to the cessation of suffering and
there's no pronouns there it's not it's not emphasizing one's own suffering
or the suffering of others and i like to uh interpret this to mean that uh when we
practice we are available we to be to recognize suffering wherever it is
in ourselves in the world around us and and that we can it can be equally our
care to care for the suffering of others that is care for ourselves each of them is enough this little text
suta says and um in someone else in uh it's in the samyutta
book 12 22. and
it's um uh so each each of the each is enough but
whenever we're at paying attention to the suffering of others if that's what's salient that's
what's prominent that's enough that's good paying attention to our own suffering
that's good as well doing both here it says is enough but i think that doing both is really
the best because if we only pay attention to the suffering of others
but not our own we can easily say and act in ways that cause more harm
for ourselves and for others if we only pay attention to our own suffering
then it's too easy for that to be to reinforce self-involvement
self-preoccupation uh selfishness of a certain kind and it's too easy to um then to not pay
enough attention to the suffering of others to similarly cause harm because we don't understand people we don't know the
impact we're having or what is supportive for people but to be able to do both is a
phenomenal thing and one of the phenomenal aspects of the keeping the four noble truths at the
center of buddhist practice it's a form of self-protection
and a protection for others because the ways because we notice
when we start becoming uncomfortable tense stressed
de-stressed we stop and pay attention to that this is worth
understanding this is worth looking at and that's a very different approach
than just barreling ahead with the suffering kind of being preoccupied with in a way that
reinforces it but with this special awareness we're developing and mind mindfulness the ability to kind of in a
in a metaphorical way step back and know it be conscious of it
where being no knowing and conscious of it is in some ways more important than the
content in what's happening where the knowing of it is where some freedom is found
and where the knowing of it gives us information about how maybe to correct your course
correction how do you know if you notice the shoulders are tense maybe we could that's maybe simple to relax the
shoulders if we notice we're attached to some outcome maybe that's not so easy to let
go of that or we're holding on to some pain and being attached to suffering that's not
so easy to let go of but slowly we begin to learn that to have this different relationship to
suffering where it um where it doesn't uh
it's not driving the show it's not uh confusing us or
or preoccupying us in some deep way we're learning this ability to step back
and be conscious so that in that consciousness there's
some ease some freedom and there's the information we need to maybe
do course corrections so that's how it's protective so that works for example in in meditation
practice at some point we become aware that we're straining
maybe we're trying too hard or or we have an expectation that should be different
we have this idea that i'm not doing it well those kinds of thoughts
uh and those kind of that kind of strain probably you can feel
some discomfort around having them some dukkha some strain or stress
and if you notice it then you're you're on the road to becoming free of
it especially if you've developed this capacity to be consciously aware
in this very clear way that we're talking about today and um
so this is a this and then and then we can make a course correction we can maybe change
what we're doing as well so we're not so much focused on the content of what we know
and we're not necessarily focused on the process of what's happening but we're
prioritizing being conscious of it some people might feel um that that's
not enough that's not you know that's dangerous or we're not going to take care of ourselves properly
but the uh what happens is as we can be relaxed and open and conscious in this
kind of effortless way that then we have access to deeper places of wisdom within
deeper knowing deeper we have time for some deeper process to unfold and
um and uh and uh enter reference how we what we say and what we do
we can reference it with uh against or with this freedom or this spaciousness or
this ease of this kind of knowing so
so to be [Music] so the four noble truths
and instead of trying to understand what they mean
which is appropriate i hope you under you know understood more this week what it mean
but to also remember how important the word to understand to know
to know each one and the knowing grows the capacity to know present
moment awareness present moment conscious awareness can grow so it becomes a place of abiding of
resting a place of freedom where we discover
that um in a deep way what we're looking for in
practice in a deep way the freedom the peace the deep what we're looking for
maybe is not found in what we're trying to understand
but it's found in our capacity to understand
it's not found in what we're trying to know but it's found in the knowing itself
and that's a paradigm shift may you appreciate your knowing
your con your ability to be conscious to be attentive to be aware
may you over this weekend uh try to go through the day
periodically tapping into or exploring what i talked about today about this
value of understanding knowing in this being conscious in this kind of effortless way we're used to receive
and see what you'll learn see but you learn how difficult it is when it's easy what benefits come from it
even if you just have a little hints of it from here and there and then monday we'll start the last week on
these on the four foundations of mindfulness now that we've gone through all the exercises there's a foundation for
um for bringing it to a close
so thank you very much and
look forward to monday