so now I think you can hear me um
so welcome I find it very
um I don't know delightful and and uh
kind of homey to be sitting here Monday morning to be able to speak to you all about the
Dharma and and for me to I speak to him speaking to myself as well
um this is as much as Dharma exploration for me is it is offering you things to
explore so um in this Dharma practice that we do
there's a wonderful way in which contrasts support us to
find our way to deepen the practice to help us use this practice to become more
free and uh and to be able to be aware of
two contrasting States kind of at the same time or have
them in mind at the same time or evoke our connection to it or
intuition of them at the same time can be very significant way
of the heart the mind kind of finding the beacon finding the
the the path forward so uh one example of this is the
contrast between agitation and calm
agitation and calm there's always I'd like to propose
there's always going to be some degree of both
present for us short of Awakening sort of enlightenment
and when all agitation disappears but otherwise there's going to be a
little bit of both sometimes we're more on the agitation side sometimes we're less sometimes we're
more on the calm side and sometimes or less but the two are there and the
degree to which you recognize sitting down this morning you're maybe a little bit agitated
or already a little bit calm you've already beginning to find yourself on
that spectrum between the two and uh
and it's not really so necessary to have the idea that you should be
anywhere else in the Spectrum if you find yourself much more on the agitation side of the spectrum
for the purpose of this meditation that's fine that's the door that's the
where we practice uh mindfulness and the mindfulness can developed wonderfully
with agitation I've had wonderful meditations with
restlessness we just felt like this energy of like ping pong ball energy bouncing around
inside and at some point it became even entertaining to feel all the energy in
the body just that bouncing inside
and um and so but if you can kind of be aware of both at the same time
the chances are that your heart
will or your agitation will be reassured by
the calm somehow the calm will more and more
be a companion to the agitation so the agitation can quiet can settle
and that's one of the ways to use this this uh the wisdom of contrasts
to help us along this way so to take assume that meditation
posture and
lower your gaze down towards the floor
without closing your eyes and soften that gaze
so you're not really focused on anything in particular but a broad Focus as if
looking at a mountain far in the distance soft relaxed
and now gently close your eyes
and feel in this body of yours and the posture
where there is agitation and where
there might be some modicum of calm
now as I sit here I do feel a little bit of agitation in the area of my front of my chest
but in the back of my chest it's calm
I feel some energy maybe agitation a little bit in my hands and fingers
but they rest on my knees and thighs which are
feel calm and settled
I feel a teeny bit of tightening and
restlessness in my eyes tension
but behind them in the back of my head
it feels peaceful and quiet
so where is this contrast found for you
feeling your whole body
and recognizing the degree to which it might be calm or agitated
on the spectrum between the two
and then gently calmly take some deeper breaths
even in the breathing there might be ways in which there's agitation and come
and see if you could know agitation and calm calmly peacefully
noticing which parts of breathing feels more on the calm side what part of
the cycle feels more in the agitated side
at least relative to itself
letting the breathing breathe naturally continue to feel
the contrasts and breathing maybe it's
more agitated to less agitated and more calm and less calm
or the two sides calm and agitation
and if while being with your breathing you feel agitation or tension in your
body maybe on the exhale
bring a wave of calmness to hold to touch
the places of the agitation
and you're thinking behind is it more agitated or more calm
if it's agitated it might be you know pushing itself out of the body
or upward or just spinning unconnected to the body
maybe you can allow the thinking mind to settle back and rest
in the body
perhaps you can think calmly
about how to bring attention to the agitation
attuning yourself to The rhythms her breathing
maybe as if the breathing is like the tide moving up on
the beach and back coming and going
as if the breathing comes and goes across the calm and agitation that's in
you gently
agitation and calm it touched
by your breathing
foreign
after these minutes of meditating is the balance of agitation
and calm shifted for you either direction is fine
not being troubled by anything
even agitation is a support for calm
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to gaze upon your experience calmly
to have a kind calm awareness
whatever you're thinking about whatever you're aware of Here and Now
and then to let that calm attention
calm thinking be directed towards
the people you might encounter in next 24 hours
whether foreign people you know or people you don't know
strangers on the street neighbors colleagues
people you'll read about in the news or see
on the news anywhere
and imagine gazing upon them being present for them
calmly
free of agitation
so that you can take them in be aware of them
from your heart
and we from that heartfelt place within
wish them well
may all the people that I have some awareness of today
may they be happy May the people that will have contact
with may they be safe
May the people that I'll know about may they be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may my ability to stay connected to calm
while I'm also on the Spectrum from agitation to calm
May that come support the welfare and happiness of all
[Music]
all right
so this will be the first talk in a series Following last week's on consciousness
where I'll attempt to talk about how different factors of the Mind mind
activities can affect the quality or the
characteristics of Consciousness how we are aware of being conscious
and if
overall if that purpose of these talks don't quite work for you
don't worry too much about it I think what I'll be teaching about will have other value in addition
so what I'd like to do is to set up the idea of contrasts that different contrasts of different
mind States will have different effects on how we feel aware how we have a sense
of what being conscious is and to the degree to which we have a
sense of being of consciousness that that sense of Consciousness can be affected by these different contrasting
mind States and so for today that talk is about agitation
and calm agitation is uh
it can be coarse and many people associate meditation with becoming calm
and uh but one of the not known recognized is that as we become calmer in meditation
we start uncovering deeper and deeper layers of agitation
maybe quieter more subtle layers of it that are invisible to us in the ordinary
states of mind that as we go and in fact some of the
places that we feel is recognize the deeper very subtle agitation
is in contrast to ordinary states of mind when we're agitated it might seem like a calm state
but when we're deeply calm we still see there's a little bit of agitation that
tension pressure so learning to recognize the contrast between common agitation learning to be
accepting of agitation so that we can be aware of it carefully and fully is important part of this path to
Freedom and to emphasize this part of the classic teachings of Buddhism is that
agitation sometimes is explicitly that word sometimes restlessness it's that
word that's used are the last attachment the last hindrance last
piece of of Duke ouch suffering that remains before a
person becomes fully liberated in fact you have to be fully liberated to let go of of the last vestiges of
restlessness and agitation and um so if you have some agitation in
your meditation um then it certainly means you're not fully awakened but it also means that
you're human and this is part of parcel of Being Human that we're working with and becoming wise about how to be with
agitation um the
so um and com can set it in all kinds of
different stages of meditation or all kinds of kind of qualities of it there
can be a the first really palpable and impactful experience of calm that I
experienced uh it needs to kind of been my spiritual life especially before I kind
of was interested in spirituality was when I was 18 and I went into a little
chapel for a Catholic Chapel in France and and this immediately this calm
descended and the cool kind of Ancient Ancient Chapel the stone walls and there was something about the cool
clear crisp air the history of the chapel maybe in
the atmosphere there or the associations I had with it who knows but I felt this calm settle into my body that uh was was
uh I just found so stunning and I kind of stayed lingering with it for a long
time and then I found myself being agitated in rush hour traffic here in the Bay
Area freeways and then decided Well I'm here for a while and I have better things to do than be
agitated and then finding some simple modicum of calm to settle into and to
settle in the chair in the seat in the car and and be still and look around the
other drivers wish them well and nothing that too dramatic nothing
that I would want to linger in or or feel that was you know something
spiritual but um it was what was available and content with that
part of the advantage of com in the path of Liberation is that as we become
calmer we're able to see more clearly as we become calmer we have access to
more wisdom and and skillfulness and understanding of where
to go from here including how to not feed the agitation how not to get
agitated because we're agitated um but rather to support to nourish the
calm to feed the calm is the language of the Buddha the nourishment and he says the nourishment for calm is calm
so um if you don't have any comment can't nourish yourself with it but if if you
recognize some degree of calm within even a small degree then that calm
can as the food for becoming more calm in the same way agitation is the food
for more agitation so to be able to see the contrast between calm and agitation
it gives us the wisdom to know which one to attend to the most not to ignore the
agitation but to learn to tend to the calm enough that we can be calmly aware of the
agitation and that way we're not feeding the agitation and each of these common agitation has a
different effect on how we experience Consciousness how we experience being aware
that agitation can make the awareness agitated
it can agitation is a kind of a movement that feels uncomfortable and so it's
localized you can feel it's a certain place and it tends to ground or settle
or or gather or kind of tie Consciousness to a bounded smaller
tighter place within and uh sometimes it's so agitated it's
really hard to even know we're aware or to be you know to tune into what Consciousness is like when we're
agitated it's impossible it's almost like it's absent um but as we become calm calm I can have
a location in the body but it tends to have soft boundaries it tends to be not moving and jumping around so much and it
tends to kind of uh have a smooth or relaxed or porous
boundaries it spreads out through the body um and sometimes the calm especially
mentalcomm can feel the same way that it just uh has no boundaries
so much so that the calm can feel like it's in the room even though the room conventionally is agitated
um because our calm is so strong it kind of spills over into our sense or feeling of the room at least at least how we're
aware of the room the awareness that is there and um and so
one of the most precious resources we have is our capacity for attention for
awareness of being conscious and this amazingly precious resource
amazingly precious kind of treasure that we have its characteristics and its availability
and its um it's a way in which it supports us
can vary a lot depending on how agitated we are or how calm we are
and one of the things that you might consider doing today in the next 24 hours is there are two things one is just
become attuned to the presence of agitation and calm
and just that Attunement that a recognition of them it might be enough you don't have to fix
anything but just what happens when you see it clearly you might find yourself shifting even
unintentionally in a positive direction by that clear awareness of it
and then if you can be calmly aware of your agitation what happens then
what shifts then and I'm not going to suggest that you become aware of the calm in an agitated
way but that if you did that that would have a different kind of effect
but then also a second thing to do is to be aware of what kind of see if you can
notice what is your sense of being conscious like
being aware like at the times you're more agitated and at times that you're more calm does your
sense of what awareness is or its location or its qualities or its characteristics shift and change
depending on the uh you know where you are on the agitation
com Spectrum and um
so um finally I'll say that uh
the the the deeper we go in this exploration of calm
uh and agitation one of the things we can discover is a lot of the
agitation that we can experience is connected to our idea of self
our idea of Me Myself and mine and um and that's one of the ways to get
a handle on or to put a big question mark next to our agitation not to make it as such a rarefied thing but to
realize that what's agitated is our sense idea of self
and that as we get calmer our idea of self shifts and changes as well
and the relationship between Consciousness and self is um one of these fascinating kind of um
things to discover and so
um one saying we could say to assert the self
is to be agitated to forget the self
is to be calm and wise to assert the self is to be agitated and
foolish to forget the self
is to be calm and wise so thank you very much and um
I hope your exploration of calm and agitation makes you wiser