foreign
and can you hear me okay wonderful and uh
I guess a little bit to our social distancing but I like the number we have here it's kind
of cozy today I wish we were all kind of sitting closer together and
don't I guess we don't have to move I'm just I'm sharing it not as an idea that to sit closer together but rather
to express my kind of my warmth or my coziness that we're here together this
way and so thank you for being here but maybe in
order to feel a little bit of that maybe we can go around the room and you can say your names if you're willing with
the mic so I can hear it
I'm Sage yeah my name is Jim
my name my name is sveta I'm Nancy
Sally hi my name is Abhishek
hi I'm Jeff
I'm Andre hi I'm Catherine
I am Janus hi I'm April
hi I'm Kathy I'm malvika
and keep the mic there you turn maybe turn off Alpha thank you all very much this uh
just kind of I would remember the name so well but it was um
just as a way of kind of coming together and our voices a little bit
in down through the centuries and religious circles people would chant together or
sing together and sharing of voices and breathing breathing and sound and
everything kind of begins to meld and something think deeper melts deep inside
and I think the same thing happens when people meditate together maybe it's not so quick or so obvious
but it's remarkable to um the kind of inner sensibility or
their ins in the inner kind of sharing of a certain kind of
purpose a certain kind of sense set of values a certain set of
of uh awareness that kind of is born in meditation and then to do that together
in other with other people nearby um I think for every each person that
the whole experience is different but it's also something we share something that happens in community
and it's very valuable part of all this and um and maybe that could be a good
introduction to the theme of what I want to talk about today and that is
some some words about the ethics in Buddhism and particularly the five
precepts and um I think it's kind of natural it feels
much more natural to living in Epic living an ethical way where you live careful about the impact we have in
others so we don't hurt them when we're in community when we have a shared life together and and so if you
sit and meditate people or share some kind of something that's kind of intimate and close where maybe you're
touched Yourself by the opening the relaxation the the inner kind of sense
of connection just so maybe a little more calm or Freedom or something that you have and to share that with others you know
is a remarkable thing and probably you don't want to kind of just walk up
to someone here and just kind of you know swear angrily at them they just
it would feel kind of a little bit like feel kind of off I think
or try to kill them or steal from them and they might have better shoes than you
and uh you know so you need to go home with them instead um
many years ago when we were in Palo Alto a lot of people used to have Birkenstocks then much more than now and
so I had them and one evening there was somehow three different pairs that ended
up on three different people's feet and I ended up with better Birkenstocks
I tried to find the owner but that never happened but anyway so you know we tend to kind
of have a different feeling and relationship with each other like this and then imagine that this sensibility
of how we are maybe sometimes not saying we have it here today completely the way
I'm saying it but you know some sensibility of kind of sense of connectivity and sensitivity and
appreciation and with meditation sometimes we kind of tend to see people as beautiful
that's kind of wonderful and um so we begin discovering it in
kind of in this kind of environment and imagine if we start seeing everyone in the world that way
you kind of walk you you you kind of that becomes more your default for how to see people and be
with people rather than default being fear thinking about people or or hostility
and because blaming you know people are somehow um you know at fault
they're not behaving properly and all kinds of things anyway so this idea that ethics would
come from some uh wouldn't come from a rule like you should do a certain way
and let me tell you all the good reasons why you should be ethical but rather it's our comings because
we're we're somehow we're changing inside there's an interchange of perception
change of disposition a change of sensitivity change of values and so that becomes
something that we want to protect or something when we live by or Care by or something
and so the precepts then don't become rules to live by
the Epic can be seen as protections to
um that keep us in that state there they are ways of living that
um protect us from falling back into the
opposite way where we might have hostility where we might have anxiety and close up where we
might have greed predominator desire is predominant that we were not so attuned
to others and not attuned to ourselves and so um but if it's Attunement
then you know you there's something here that's valuable to protect
there's something here that is precious and valuable
so um you know if you I don't know if you have this I've had this at home
a drawer full of electronic wires and I don't know you know how they end
up in this way but they're like this big knot the mess of wires
and it takes a while to sort them out and put them out and change you know get them all kind of free from each other so
they can use them easily later on and that usually I think people don't say well I did the work that's great now
they're easy to use and then you just bump them throw them back in the drawer I mean it's kind of silly right there's
a kind of instant you don't so we do all this work to untangle all the wires in our hearts and our minds
our complicated entanglements with people and ourselves and our history and our memories and our hurts and our
vengeances and our our hopes and aspirations I mean it's like that drawer in there is like
pretty and then we sit and meditate then we undo all those Tangles it's worthwhile
not losing and not putting it all back in the drawer and getting it all and not only putting back a door we put it in
the washing machine laughs you know it's a worthwhile kind of
protecting it a little better so in this practice after a while we have a clear sense
a kind of matter-of-fact sense a practical sense there's something really
great going on here and this wonderful thing we're tapping into this is worth protecting this is
It's Worth kind of keeping it this way so from that point of view
these five precepts that we have the ethical precepts are ways of
protecting ourselves from losing something important
and their way of protecting our community from losing something important the
Community Connection the respect for each other they care for each other some deeper more attuned way of living with
each other and um so the five precepts that
um you know I probably most of you live with most of them but the world doesn't
all you have to do is read the news news and you know the world doesn't live this way
but there's um so not killing and so this is a this is like the number
one Cardinal the precept in Buddhism and that doesn't just mean don't kill other
human beings but live a non-harming life be careful ideally you wouldn't kill any
animals any pests any insects you would be really careful with that
and you know where the line is between what you feel like you have to do to protect yourself
you know I mean some of us will take antibiotics so that's kind of you know
can we kill those poor bacteria before they kill us but uh you know where does that line go
where we feel like that's I can't allow that to live because that crosses the line for me that is too
difficult but what I've seen in meditation circles is that as people meditate the line gets
or the line around what's is okay to kill it gets smaller and smaller smaller smaller thing
and so much other people will not only not kill insects or little animals
they'll go out of their way to protect them I've known people who like
when there's a lot of people a place where there's like cars or bicycles something going after a fog and there's
all these slugs on the sidewalk and the people who go and kind of help the Slugs out of the sidewalk or
out of the road because they know otherwise they get squashed so you know is that silly to do that
it's not silly for the people the person who's doing it they're feeling attuned and some something very important and
it's not silly for the slug who's going to survive so this idea of not killing
not as a punitive rule not as a moralistic
commandment but rather a rising out of a desire to stay true to something that's
being born something that's been awake awoken something we've tapped into of course I don't want to harm someone
if you find that you want to hurt someone and punch them out something
the recommendation is you stop and take a good look at what's going on
if you take enough time to pause and check yourself out you probably find
You've Lost That Attunement You've Lost That connection to something that's very
valuable and important that way of being a value a disposition
all kinds of things that is some of the most beautiful ways a human being can live
in Buddhism we can't we use that when we use the word wealth we're not referring
to a wealthy person as someone who has a lot of money from the Buddhist point of view of what some wealthy people are
really poor because they don't have that Attunement they don't have that disposition they don't have that access to something that
that is um you know quite beautiful they're living with anxiety
Sophie if you want to punch someone out or you want to kill them they pest because we think it's bothering us
to stop and take a good look and see are you still attuned are you still coming from the place that you want to live
from because you know this that's where it really is good way of living
to get lost in stress is to get lost in entanglement while the
wire is all messed up again and sometimes it can take a while to do the untangling
the second precept is that's all the other precepts are kind of extensions of the first not harming
the second precept is not to take what is not given and you probably know this that the
reason it's worded this way rather than don't steal is that it's a two reasons
it's a it's a higher bar you have to be real it isn't that simply
you take something you have to wait until it's given before you use it even
so that there's real care about possession we'll care about generosity we don't care about understanding and uh
and exchange and friendship and you know the communication between people
and so you wouldn't take anything unless it's clearly been offered even if
uh sometimes if even if I think it's being offered but then you kind of wait and see you
know is it really being offered um food you know that someone has then
there's often a common thing for Buddhists to do is is if you go to someone's house on the coffee table
there's some kind of snack kind of the Assumption is that that's already being offered because that's
otherwise why would they have it there but some practitioners would simply not touch it when you know
until there's a clear oh please have some is that silly
have that kind of care what it does is it it conveys that you're a trustable person
you can trust me you can trust me with your things there was a at our Retreat Center some
years ago five six years ago someone
um dropped their wallet in the community hall floor and they so they they just put it next
to the Buddha at the altar there and uh because no one you know no one opened it no one I think it was they
felt it was a safe place no one's going to take it there so they just left it there and some few days later the person
who lost the wallet realized it and were looking for it and there it was they hadn't moved 40 people living
together in a wallet you know it's right in the center of the building everyone to see and I think everyone kind of appreciated
this was a safe place this was a community people you can trust they're not going to take what is not given it's
like okay it's okay to leave it there I mean that's kind of remarkable in our society where do you find 40 people
where you have that level of trust especially if you've been strangers you know didn't know each other before
so they said you know cultivating trust and you know trust trusting between
people and helping everyone feel safe and then there's uh not harming others
with sexuality so not engaging in sexual misconduct
this is so much suffering in this world around sexuality I mean some of the
suffering you know one event the suffering can last over the rest of a
lifetime and it isn't just sex that that's so painful sometimes and what goes on but
sex that conveys power and aggression and and forcefulness and and violence
and and objectification and self-gratification conceit there's so
many things that can happen that make it askew sexuality sometimes can be phenomenally
selfish without really being attuned to someone else and it can be phenomenally selfless it
can be for beautiful expression of care for someone else so this is so and we don't even know
I've had to counsel people who were involved in
causing harm with their sexuality and um and they've insisted it was consensual
but what it what they didn't know on the surface it was but what they didn't know was their partner
had had a very abusive history and so it couldn't say no
and and then the impact of sexuality
touched these deep places of wounding and Earth and fear that was not there on the surface and so
so how do you stay attuned to not cause harm with sex with our sexual Energies even sometimes uh
I've known I've known people who feel felt somehow violated just by how people looked at them because of the sexual
energy that goes on which makes Society the world uncomfortable
I was kind of a little bit horrified when I was 18.
and kind of what it meant to be a woman in some societies because I had long blonde hair that went
down halfway down my my torso and I was
so at some point I was I've been in a cross-country trip and um
it wasn't the United States another country and um and I was driving along on the
freeway every car that passed me that had demanded it turned to look at me
because in that country back then long blonde hair was very unusual to have for
men and um this was like 19
70 I think and um and so um
72 so so um but I was like wow is this what women
happens to women every person looks at them every man is is that kind of challenging
and um so is this doesn't this fit a little bit into that third precept of
of uh you know not abusing sexuality isn't that going to be some way that's
going to cause some people to live in fear or distress or to shut down or hide
away or do something so it's such a sensitive thing so to be
careful with this is such an important part of protecting something that's so valuable
not and at some point also with practice as we practice more deeply we feel how fragile or how vulnerable
this kind of inner disposition of openness and care and sensitivity and freedom can be
that we want to protect other people for having that as well we don't want other people to have their hearts closed
I had my heart closed when I was 15 and or a teenager a number of times where I
just felt like a door just you know closed because of what happened to me
and it took sometimes years took this practice sometimes too that I did to
have that finally have the trust to be open that up again
so the same thing can be true with a fourth precept not to lie
to lie is ruins Trust causes people to feel afraid if it's the
Betrayed some people again will close up and say well if I'm betrayed in that
kind of lie I don't know who to trust so I'll just keep to myself and not open up
it can cause a lot of harm to people to go around lying
and it it undermines the level of trust that we can have in society and with
each other and so to have a high
sensitivity in high care for being truthful
and and to be truthful in caring ways
there are people who use truth as a weapon that that doesn't feel good
people use truth carelessly and say things what's true so it's okay to say it
and that's why the first pre-step is so important you want to you know if you speak you want to speak in ways that
doesn't cause harm and the strict meeting of the first precept not to kill
can be used metaphorically that a line can can something can die in other
people if they uh if they receive they hear you know live a lie or notice some
someone lied in some powerful way on them and they feel betrayed
but more importantly for people who do mindfulness meditation mindfulness meditation is a practice of
truth-telling to oneself I like to think of that mindfulness out loud is being
honest and saying you know honestly what's happening so if you're not if you lie you're doing
the very opposite of what we're trying to do in this practice even if you know your line you're
mindfully lying you're still a part of you is going against the grain of mindfulness and the kind of clarity of
practice so if you're serious about this practice why would you lie it's the very thing
you're trying not to do you're trying to actually you know you know live a truthful life even if it's only to yourself
and then the fifth one is is to avoid intoxication
and this one's a little bit more it's a little bit ambiguous because
um and in the Buddhist tradition kind of recognizes it kind of stands out as an
anomaly compared to the other four so it doesn't quite fit in the same category
and and so for example I don't remember exactly the ancient language but it's
kind of like they say the first four are referred to as being a kind of
corruption or impurity but they never say that about the fifth one not drinking not getting intoxicated
and I think the reason for that is best there's no explanation for why this is the case but one of the best reasons for
that is that it's possible to intoxicate oneself
um uh alone without it having to have an impact on
anyone else there's no harm being caught being wished on someone else there's no harm
being wished on oneself there's no um there's no
um sometimes actually it's the opposite there's something inside of us that's trying to protect ourselves or or
protect ourselves from Despair and anger and pain and and try to you know escape
the difficulties in life it is a kind of caretaking sometimes that people are doing
and um and also because uh there's uh
there's you know taking small dosages that some people are used medicinally or
something it doesn't really cause people to get intoxicated so are we really supposed to avoid all all intoxicating
drinks for example and for Buddhist monastics they're actually allowed to have alcohol
in food provided that they can't taste it
and and only if someone offers that the food to them they can't go make their own food and
put in and um so uh you know the the
you know it's you know it's only in very rare circumstance but that can happen
so um um
but the uh again there's so much amazing
astounding amount of suffering that happens in our societies because of
intoxication people die I mean every day there's probably I
don't know lots and lots of people are dying from overdosing drugs somehow from alcoholism
it's phenomenal the destroyed families the children I I
hear all these stories of people growing up with alcoholic parents who are raging
parents when they're drunk and the impact that has in the children is is dramatic and that also can last for a
lifetime if they don't find some way to heal from it so to um
uh if we live this kind of meditative life
and that's the emphasis here for today's talk then I think we would feel or sense or
be concerned with the impact our life has on the world and the impact Our
Lives has on ourselves and the deleterious impact of
breaking the five precepts both for others and for for us doing
them is such that we're destroying the very kind of inner life that we're
cultivating and Awakening through this practice so what we're cultivating here The
Awakening here is in fact worth protecting
is in fact something is worth kind of safeguarding
and a powerful way of safeguarding it is to live by these five precepts to have a
very high commitment to them and so be very careful
and what you'll find if you do this is that there's a kind of
you know you know I think most of you I'm probably all of you in most ways are
probably very ethical then what happens we get more and more sensitive to nuances just that we never
thought about before so for example exaggeration is that a kind of lie
and then if you look why am I exaggerating because that's what we do we always ask why why why why am I exaggerating
and sometimes it's not very something to be proud of why we exaggerate
we're trying to build ourselves up and say no I went to the best restaurant in town why did we why do we want to tell
people that because we wanted we made a good choice We want to see that show people we've
you know but a good wonderful person we are because we had the best or something
or some people exaggerate because say what because they
I don't know if you all kinds of reasons that are not necessarily so healthy
so it isn't that we accept you know there's a requirement to stop at
um exaggerating it just says you know what is what's their request what's the inspiration
that comes out of this inner life that gets born from
meditation if we ask our hearts after meditation what's your what's your request part
how should I live I doubt the heart's going to say about the kill
or break the precepts it's the opposite the hearts the hearts request is to live
a good life is to live a life that lets that heart sing and be happy and
safe and contented and so in this practice
there comes at various times in the practice where we discover something has been born something has been awakened in
US that becomes a treasure and that treasure is something we want
to care for we don't want to cling to it
certainly though there's a lot worse things to do to cling to honesty
so don't worry about it if that's what you're clinging to um the
but uh you don't want to cling to it or you don't want to uh use the precepts as
a way of being angry with ourselves disappointing or feeling bad about ourselves there's
an art to using this precepts not as a way to measure ourselves and that we
didn't live up to our standards but rather to always live with the idea I'm going to try to do better
I didn't do as well as I maybe hoped I could feel the impact on me and I'm
going to so I hope I'm committed I'm aspire to let's do better here let's now
start over again find a new way today wake up tomorrow morning and I'll see what I can do to do
better rather than wake up the next morning and kind of be ground down by the self-criticism that can happen
because that's kind of coming out of this beautiful place that we have inside
and the more this beautiful awakened feelings and sensibilities Attunement occurs Within
the more treasure we have the more reference point we have that then guides us for how we want to live our life
and so it's not just a way a way to feel through meditation it's a way to live as
well and finally this kind of a commitment to
practicing with the ethical precepts is a significant way
of helping the mindfulness practice touch all kinds of difficult places in
our lives and our hearts and our minds to to help reveal where mindfulness
should go so we can understand ourselves better and work through things it's a fantastic thing
so um to have something to we have something to safeguard
so what do you think of this this that's kind of the main point I wanted to make today
we have something to safeguard when we do this practice and I was wondering if some of you would
maybe be willing to say some words if you have discovered something that was worth safeguarding that's coming from
this practice and uh and so then share some of your ideas on this
topic anybody
sometimes it's dangerous not to speak because
I could call on you but I think actually oh you want to say
something sure great
um so I I can't imagine not safeguarding all of them in some way
or another but I will say it's complicated
it can be just so complicated
but is there some reference point inside you oh I feel like I I have a barometer
in my body I feel like I have a barometer because there's a level of
sandwich and how does that uh barometer show itself is it doing you know my my
shoulders rise my flywheel goes faster and it's like my body
speaks to me when I'm what would you call it crossing a line
Maybe Crossing online great great thank you that was nice to hear
yeah um I know for me before I started this practice
um yeah I just think back and it's it's quite a transformation of
just uh five six years ago
um so yeah just have become
much more sensitive to um causing harm
and so it's
yeah it's just I'm just so grateful to to have this practice because it
the more I practice the more I want to live ethically by the precepts and
be careful with my actions thank you
hi um there's uh somebody who caused me a lot
of pain a few years ago and um
and that I spent a long time working through it and I
I just I just decided that I I can't I don't want to and I can't live this
life with any hate in my heart for anyone and um
yeah I mean I I feel like um
I feel like I don't have hate in my heart for this person anymore not to say that it wasn't there once
um and I don't I can't really explain how that happened but um yeah I think it's
it's because of the practice very nice thank you
I'm noticing that I'm becoming very very sensitive to
concealing the truth to it's about the the fourth precept
that I sometimes don't even know like don't
know what I'm hiding exactly but I kind of this this like in a barometer
oh something is there and
and also I'm noticing um something completely different
um sensitivity to like when I'm buying food and there's a lot of plastic
uh riping so I just feel uncomfortable so
uh more and more uncomfortable so so what part of what grows is not just
necessarily inner beauty and treasures but inner discomfort yeah and that's
valuable too that's it can be a treasure it protects us from
doing something that we don't want to do thank you
so thank you those are wonderful comments is that enough and even unless someone else would like I'd love to
so thank you so um
and I don't know if some of you might be new to this all this so if this seems kind of strange
um the practice those bare wonderful fruits
and one of the wonderful fruits is uh an in strong interest even a commitment to
living an ethical life not because you're supposed to but because it's the hearts request
may your heart guide you so thank you