greeting friends greeting greetings and welcome
so [Music] today we are going to continue our exploration
practice first and our exploration of this profound teaching of karma
in in our practice in our um in our daily life in our understanding
and experientially not as a concept not as fate not as destiny that's been passed down
magically unexplicably from some unknown past life
but as an empowerment as a way that we can shape and form who we are
so so um
i'm going to start recording here one moment
there okay so technicalities out of the way so let's
uh let's start sitting together let's start sitting together and i'll
say more so i'd like to invite you to to arrive to arrive in your seat
in this moment in time
here
inviting awareness to be bright
to be bright
and expansive not as something you do
awareness is always on we don't do awareness
but as if
you're landing you're sitting you're resting
in knowing of what is here already
aware knowing your intention
in this moment why am i here
aware of this body
awareness infusing the body
all the nooks and crannies
and if and when the awareness knows sensations of tightness
holding it engages with the intention
to release to relax
to let go
knowing that a relaxed body allows
for a relaxed spacious mind
letting there be bright awareness of the breath
being received in the abdomen calming soothing settling
stabilizing [Music] connecting and rooting us to the earth
what kind of intention is operating in this moment
what kind of intending for the actions in the mind
and heart
and what kinds of actions of the mind and heart are actually being performed
and remember thoughts are actions
of the mind
and if we realize that the intentions or actions
of the mind in this moment are not what we really would like to create
for this being who is me what we want to create form
make form formations
our only chance is through awareness
through mindfulness to know to understand to see
to see and pause
and make a new choice
a choice that can shift and change this karma
each moment with each action
internally and externally actions of thought
speech which may be internal speech the body we form ourselves we shape
ourselves we fashion ourselves
in the future moments to come
if in this moment challenges are arising
can we be kind can we choose to be kind
can we choose to be accepting allowing non-reactive
spacious gentle
loving
loving to this body to this heart to this mind
and with whatever rises
gentle gentle
spacious awareness
loving releasing
forming wholesome formations
one breath at a time
if you find your mind has wondered
perhaps thinking about thoughts you don't really want to be thinking about
not in this moment not period
becoming aware and maybe dropping in the question so lovingly to
yourself oh sweetheart sweetheart what are you creating
what are you creating
what ossified patterns of the mind are you creating in this moment darling
let go sweetheart let go let's
create wholesome moments
wholesome formations
if you want to create patterns of kindness then be kind
if you want to form formations
patterns of wisdom then be aware
not sleepwalk
in this moment
as we approach the end of the sitting
can we connect with a desiring with a
with an intention for kindness generosity towards ourselves
without judgment for whatever rose or did not arise we've done our best
given the causes and conditions passed down previously
can we create wholesome karma in this moment
by being kind to ourselves appreciative thank you thank you dear me for showing up
for practicing in sangha doing your best
and really connecting with this mental act
of kindness and generosity relishing it
so many other things i could be doing with my life and this is what i chose to do with my time
yay appreciation
not attachment to outcome
and offering with generosity again connecting with generosity
our collective our collective practice our collective
goodness sharing it with all beings everywhere
all beings in all circumstances around this world
those who are well and happy
those who are in neutral state and those who are suffering
grieving in war zones etc
or any other challenges offering our goodness our care
to all beings everywhere including ourselves
may all beings everywhere
be safe happy
healthy and have ease may all beings everywhere
be free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you for your practice
so greetings greetings friends friends from around the world this blue
planet hi good moment good day lovely to be with
you if not in space but in time and if not in time if you're listening later
in heart space connect in the heart space of the dharma together
so today i would like to continue to share some reflections about karma and
i've been weaving some of the reflections in the guided meditation so that we can
experiment we can experientially
explore this teaching of karma again not as this magical
thing that has been passed down to us but as an empowerment as the way
we create we fashion ourselves in the next moment our future selves
so this teaching of karma as i mentioned
yesterday just a very quick review to remember because repetition helps us
remember three parts three intertwined parts of
the same thing karma being the decision to do something
number one number two the action that carries it out and the action can be
the action of the mind of speech and
actions of the body and these could be internal external and
the third aspect of karma is what is made what we make the result of the action
so the intention action itself and what is made
and what i mentioned yesterday is that [Music]
in pali this this expression
one forms formations one constructs constructions one fabricates
fabrications it's so powerful and to think this again in the
terms of a a potter in in the suttas
karma is like into a potter creating creating a piece of pottery so
that acts of creation intending to create to form to shape
and then what is made the pot that then is an ossified karmic relic i love how andrew
olenski puts this ossified karmic relic that's put in the kiln and we take forward it's
become who we are so what i like to add today well many
things but we'll see how how much time we get is um
one way one other way perhaps to consider this idea of karma is
is that in every moment of course in every moment we are shaping we are fashioning
ourselves so for those who have young ones or have
had younger ones in your lives children cousins
nephews uh nieces the younger ones you know when you care for them you want to send them
into the future you want to send them into the future with the best possible gifts
so imagine your future self your future self as your child
as your most important precious child this being this being who is you
whose care is entrusted in you first and foremost
you need to care for this being for their well-being for their body brush their teeth comb their hair
you know wash their body feed them take them to the dog you know really
really take care of this being wouldn't you want to send them into the
future the future version of yourself
equip them give them the best gifts possible
don't you of course of course and the way to do that is what we make
what we make for this being who is ourselves what we make what
you know what sandwiches do we pack in their lunch box and send it into the future is it junk
food or is it wholesomeness is it wholesomeness what kind of food for the
heart do we pack for ourselves for our future selves and that's in the teaching of karma what
do we make what do we fashion in this moment with our intentions with our actions
again actions of the mind speech internally externally actions of the body in the world
and the relic what is made what is created that's sent forward
and western thought is often concerned about
what we do in the world with our actions to bring about external
changes that we intend whereas buddhist thought is equally concerned is equally
concerned with how we affect our own well-being with
the decisions we make how we are changed by our own actions and
this is profound how are we changed by our own actions
so karma is mainly about how we shape ourselves and how we
are shaped by ourselves through our actions
moving into the future and neuroscience these days of course
tells us that our brain is plastic our self is plastic
and just as the brain shapes the mind the mind shapes the
brain and we and our intentions are conditioned by our dispositions
and our dispositions in turn condition our intentions
our actions are merely a go between
our intentions and our dispositions
i love this this part especially i love how andrew olenski puts this that
that our actions are really the go-between because our dispositions again i'll say this
again it's so beautiful our our dispositions
[Music] our intentions and our intentions
condition our conditioned condition are
our disposition so they they both the intentions and dispositions are conditioned by each other by the past
uh dispositions and intentions so so okay so you might think okay well wow
okay how do we how do i change this how do i change this in the middle of this
and that's where awareness mindfulness becomes key
becomes key every moment of awareness we have the chance we have the option we
have the privilege to shift to change
so if you find yourself as i was guiding as i was suggesting in
the guided meditation if you find yourself wait wait sweetheart do you really want to be thinking about
this you become aware do you really want to be creating this kind of creation
form this kind of formation because it will become the tendency of your mind the tendency of your brain the tendency
of your heart use whatever frame you want this will become your tendency the more you think about this the more you
are this way it will become more and more so sweetheart again not with with anger because you don't want to be
creating you don't want to be creating formations of anger
formations of hatred for yourself you don't want to be doing that you want to be creating
formations of kindness oh sweetheart do we really want to be thinking about this right now is this really good for us for
our future software our presence no it isn't all right darling let's let's think about let's let's
change let's shift let's turn the
karmic formations let's create some wholesome karmic formations
the same not just in meditation but in daily life in the midst of
um whatever is happening say in a moment of anger
if it's acted out whether it's acted out it's verbalized or unexpressed and
seething you know we're layering a thin layer of anger
and and because and more angry disposition is being created
ossified
and a moment of kindness a moment of kindness to ourselves
in that moment of sweetheart you're having a hard time ah moment of kindness to ourselves the
moment of kindness to others can shift can shift at this position
can shift that disposition and little by little
we can reshape our character our very own character we can reshape our very own character
this teaching is so beautiful and so profound so empowering
the opposite of what usually westerners take it to be
it's so empowering so more to say
but it's time so so i'd like to thank you for your
practice for seeding wholesome for planting
wholesome seeds of kindness oh and also i'll say
last night as i taught happier i also brought in karma with meta
planting seeds of kindness meta as as shifting karmic formation so those
who would like more teaching around this you can find the happier on imc channel and listen to
it so so thank you so much for your practice be well and yes maybe as an invitation
for today if when you become aware please be aware
awareness in the midst of when you don't want to be doing something or thinking something oh sweetheart do you really
want to make this the pattern of your mind do you is this really what you want to send
yourself to the future with sweetheart and shift with kindness
not with judgment not with hatred that's important
but with kindness thank you all thank you for your care for your
attention see you tomorrow