all right let's do a sound check Tracy how's that sound the volume
yeah not not too loud not too quiet
or no okay back there in that corner great
um so we've been having the teachers take off their masks while teaching if
everybody in the Hall feels comfortable with that are you guys okay with that okay
makes it um easier for you to hear and for me obviously
breathing in talking so welcome everyone and nice to have new
people we are in week three of a series
um which is not a problem if you weren't here for the first two
the first week the series is called establishing a practice
so just sort of trying to cover a lot of basic things teachings that have really
been supports for practice and so it's teaching them but not in a detailed way more like a introductory
way and so the first week we talked about wise understanding and and wise
intention um and the second week we talked about
mindfulness on and off the cushion and the five hindrances and sort of um
five common things that interfere with our ability to be mindful
this week I'll be talking about establishing actions that support Dharma
Joy so I think that they're all Standalone I
think that you'll be fine you're not going to get lost at all it's just sort of all the pieces that um
they're all different pieces that that support I think give us a foundation for our practice like the first week is
really about how to practice with suffering pretty important stuff so you can listen
to the recording if you want pretty much everything I've said in the talks will be on that handout so if you
sign up for the handouts I'll email them to you you can read it and you'll have all the information
that I shared okay all right so
um so you know
Joy I want to talk about Dharma Joy tonight and sort of
invite this idea that Joy arises as a result of actions
so Dharma Joy I'm not talking about Pump It Up try and make yourself happy
I'm talking about the joy that is a natural Joy sort of more of a a subtle
well-being Joy that comes when we feel good we feel
like that was nice or I did a nice thing or somebody was
kind to me it's a joy that is like sometimes
described in some ways as the Bliss of blamelessness
so that feeling of no there's no burden right that we did our best kind of thing
so Dharma Joy I'm trying to emphasize here we're not talking about simple happiness
right not just like haha funny joke or I'm happy because
you know I have enough money in my bank exactly it's a different it's a qualitative
difference it's not based on external things it comes up it arises from our
own actions and sometimes from the actions that we witness or experience around us
so with that in mind let's take a a little short set
maybe even inviting yourself during the sit to just I'll just drop in this question you can
see what comes up just is there something that comes up that you did that you can remember in
the last day or two week month year however
where it was an act of goodness an act of kindness an act of non-harming it
could even be carrying a spider outside instead of killing it something like that so just if there's
something like that causing extra long for somebody to walk across the cross
walk moving really far to the other side of the lane for a bicyclist
just an act that was really intended to avoid harm to create more safeness
just bring it to mind small is great
and just maybe appreciate that act and the intention behind it
may be consciously breathe in a few breaths to that to whatever it is you
can appreciate and connect with taking a little bit more time with it
than you might normally
and then if you'd like you can just just sort of check in take a few breaths
connect with your body just arriving here
giving yourself permission to put aside all the activities of the day
thank you and feel free to stay inward
do you all feel like you'd like a few more minutes to meditate the room got very nicely quiet I'm happy to
take a little more time any thumbs up on that one everybody's is that a thumbs up major
okay let's take five more minutes let's just sit for five more minutes
foreign thank you
foreign
[Music]
thank you all welcome
so this Dharma Joy
and and this connection is to um you know the ethical actions
which in in really in Buddhism is about non-harming
non-harming and so Gil wrote the Buddhist emphasis
on harmlessness is explicitly directed both toward oneself and others so we
don't leave ourselves out we should not intend to harm ourselves
not intend to harm others or both
rather we should intend to benefit ourselves benefit others and benefit both
for the whole world really so the ideal of harmlessness is
literally referencing the absence of harm and you know concern for ourselves and
others so that's one part and I'll talk about
some of the specific teachings that Buddha gave for these non-hirming ethical actions
another part that I want to talk about and I'm going to start with
is that it's really healthy and and really nourishing to connect with joy
it's like we need it we need to feel okay we need to take in the goodness
and my experience that's not always easy for people to do
I think that's partly because the negativity bias in the brain
is oriented our survival is oriented toward noticing threats potential danger
or what we need to go and get so Rick Hansen he's a Buddhist
psychologist and neuropsychologist and he coined the the phrase
the negative sticks like Teflon or sticks like velcro you know how sticky
velcro is in the brain it really grabs on to anything that's negative
and the good slips through like an egg on a Teflon pan you just
right on through so the good stuff the subtle Dharma Joy can be more bubbly and can be very
subtle it's very easy for the brain to treat it like that fried egg
flips in and out of the pan gone bye-bye out of sight out of mind
so part of the invitation I'm going to be kind of inviting you tonight to think
about is to make a commitment to take in the good to take a make a commitment to accept
receive and nourish the joy
so um ethical actions really support Joy
arising because of like that idea of the Bliss of blamelessness when we haven't done anything wrong
and we know we've done things in a way that we feel okay about
we don't have to carry a heavy burden we don't have to second guess we don't have to spend a lot of time trying to make up
for things it's just lets us walk through life a little lighter
so it's um the Buddha kind of taught trainings around
three areas in particular speech actions and is a general category
and livelihood that support our walking through this life without feeling a lot
of blame and um
he he taught these things because they made him happier
they supported him and with everything that the Buddha
offers this is um not a commandment so anybody who has any
kind of connection to some religious traditions where there's
a lot of like sort of authority and you have to do this and you can't do that
the Buddha approaches this really differently the Buddha says come and see
engage with these practices and see for yourself what happens for
you so paying attention to the impact of operating in certain ways and how that
impacts your sense of well-being your mind States your heart States
so you know well I'll share the guidelines the rules the ethical actions he
recommends but it's really important to hold them in this way of
I'm being invited to see what happens if I act in this
kind of way and to notice the impact on myself and others
to notice how it affects my sense of well-being my sense of feeling comfortable and close with others how
other people respond to me how I what happens when I sit down in my
meditation yeah okay
because I'm not going to teach them unless you agree all right
so the first is why speech and why speech I'll go into more detail
later but just very simply it's speech that doesn't cause harm
is truthful it's kind and it's Timely
so we don't we have to be thoughtful about when we say things
right um wise action is another category
and there are three things to avoid three actions to avoid and those are not
killing not stealing and not causing harm through sexuality
so it's not you can't be sexual it's don't cause harm through your sexuality
yeah and then the third category is wise
livelihood and essentially the Buddha taught that it makes a
difference what we do for our our employment and our livelihood and some of us are
lucky we have more choices and more options and sometimes we don't so again we'll we'll practice on the
Continuum with doing the best that we can but ideally we don't work in an area that involves
making weapons right making and selling of weapons
things that cause and kill cause killing and harm um
it means um I wrote the I have the wrong list in
front of me um so Butch like being a butcher and stuff
like that we try not to do those things you know not having to to do to kill
either animals people and the trade of people sex trade
or other ways of smuggling people like those are the kind of big categories that we want to avoid and then you know
we each will come into our own work environment and you know there's a whole Continuum of
harming and non-harming that happens in work environments and what what a company does and how it affects the
environment there's a lot of subtleties but the big ones are just you know not
not contributing to the killing or the ways to kill right or to trade or harm
people and animals does anybody want me to say any more
about those things right now or does that feel like good enough good enough yeah great
so one of the big supports for walking through life in a way that's non-harming
is being mindful pretty much there isn't anywhere we can go there's nothing that we can do that
we won't be supported by being mindful the opposite of mindful is being in
automatic pilot being checked out right just on sort of go and and not pausing
and checking and noticing how we're doing and how we're showing up right and
some of the the in some ways the trainings around why speech and wise
action help us bring and grow our mindfulness because we start to especially speech right internal speech
too you know like what are we saying in our heads how are we talking to ourselves
how are we talking about somebody else even if it's silently like we can really start to practice observing that with
mindfulness and with this commitment to not wanting to harm we can start to see how when
we're talking in our own minds even if we're not saying it out loud but we're thinking you know in harsh ways who
feels the harshness we do the person that we're upset with or the
people they don't feel that we're feeling it I mean maybe if we're around them and
we're exuding hate Vibes you know people pick up and that's not good but we're still
hurting ourselves when we're doing doing that and they're feeling it right
so um mindfulness strengthens it's like a muscle that helps us kind of be able to
respond instead of react in life and you know sometimes different
situations call for different kinds of responses so it's not like there's a a blanket way to be in this world so we
need to constantly be present and be assessing and viewing what's happening
so we can respond or restrain ourselves or or act sometimes it's actually the
opposite it's like we need to get ourselves to do something because we see something that's happening that's
harmful and we know we can do something to help and sometimes we're afraid but you know
if we if we if it feels safe enough and we can we need to help ourselves take
action all right
so that's kind of the summary of the kind of teachings
and now I'm going to shift to kind of talking about more practice tips and then I want to spend some more time time
talking about why speech so it's a big one and we'll do breakout groups and I'd
like to kind of review for you mindfulness of speaking and listening and you can practice it when you're
talking to each other all right
so um I mentioned this earlier but one really important thing that can help us and
reinforce our efforts to be mindful and to to practice non-harming is to take in
the good like to literally say okay it's like okay I'm gonna make myself a
nice cup of tea it's really delicious here it is my favorite and then we don't drink it
you know like so it's like we gotta we're gonna make the tea non-harming tea
and then drink it like enjoy your cup of tea enjoy the benefits of your effort
and that's what will reinforce it that's part of what helps us kind of
recondition ourselves if you will recondition what is Habitual often
reactivity irritation impatience you know consuming into more thoughtfulness
more pausing more reflecting more caring more open-heartedness those kinds of
qualities so um
there's a if I can this just the free association
to my mind but there I just got this invitation to our Workshop and it's something like you know resting
or napping is the ultimate Act of rebellion right I really like that you know it's
like it's important to rest Joy is important being at ease is
important taking your breaks at work is important very important
you're not you're not doing anybody any favors to not take your breaks here because you're just going to Tire
yourself out you're not going to be able to be really present for yourself let alone anyone else
so take in the good take it in another thing it's really reinforcing to
um take and notice moments of Choice versus reactivity
it's it's so easy to walk away and think I should have done it even better
if I'd only done it differently or or oh that was no big deal you know like no no
no no no no every time we consciously choose to do something we're you know with this
intention these intentions of non-harming these intentions of being Mindful and we we come into a moment
where we get to choose like we say no it might be to the extra cookie or no to
you know maybe the next you know click link on the
internet or um you know just the the little ways in
our lives that we stop and we say no I don't need to keep chasing this you know where I don't need to ask this
person for another favor right these are all choices um
or instead of lashing out at somebody when they say something to you you don't like
take a breath and you pause and you wait and you wait till you're not feeling
motivated by the anger right so that you'll speak more differently or
choicefully choice is a superpower
there's a there's a woman called Molly Doodles or
something like that she does she does Buddha Doodles you can find her if you Google Buddha doodles
and she sends out these emails with these little Doodles and she says she has a little
Buddha with a superhero cape and her cartoon says choice is a superpower
it's really incredibly true it's a huge huge power for us to have
choice
another tip is um to you know I have I wrote the word
celebrate small benefits the small changes the small things that you see the small movements okay so you know
this week you sat five and a half times instead of five great right like
um just you know oh I I was able to pause a little bit longer I didn't speak
quite as harshly great great we can get so fixated on being
critical and thinking we didn't quite do it well think about this
our attention that is like the most precious commodity
we have our attention what we pay attention to
and what we pay attention to grows in US
so if we spend our time criticizing ourselves for not quite doing it well
enough we're focusing on the negative parts
instead of on the useful helpful beneficial parts
yeah okay this is something I do a lot so you'll probably have heard me say this before but if I tell you not to
think about a chocolate chip cookie don't think about how they smell taste
don't think about what kind you like soft or chewy just just ignore me right can your mind help but know what I mean
and start to think about chocolate chip cookies
not really right it you know and and try not to think about them now Focus really
hard I'm not going to think about what they look like we're giving all of our
attention to something we don't want to be focusing on Instead This is the idea of like okay
well let's bring our awareness that's precious commodity that we have
and let's turn it toward what we do want to grow in ourselves
give our awareness to what we want more of what we appreciate what's beneficial
very very important very important all right
um one other thing that well one other thing to talk about before I move into talking about why speech is
emotions how do emotions impact your ability to
be responsive versus reactive all right where's the microphone I want
to hear some examples of how emotions impact and so
um thank you Sage who would be willing to say something
about how emotions impact the likelihood what kinds of emotions
impact the likelihood that you're going to harm somebody else let me put it that way
come on people's
like this can you hear me yeah yeah um
if you just let your emotions get to you you lose that pause and it's really easy
to just react uh oftentimes negatively to something someone says or does or
just something that's around you but it's pretty hard to not be emotional about things oftentimes right and that's
not the goal it's not the goal to be to not be emotional emotions are incredibly important part
of our lives they're what makes our lives rich and full and it's part of what creates a lot
of meaning but to not be ruled by our emotions
is what mindfulness can help us with right
and and so it's the you know maybe you're talking specifically Brian to how it's you know you don't want to get
angry but you get angry and it's going to happen right and then it's really
hard you don't want to get angry because you don't want to say mean things or impatient things or whatever
so let's one of the things I'll do for the guided meditation later is a practice to work that can help us work
with emotions so they're to give ourselves some skills and tools so those of you who are familiar it's the raft
practice so we'll do a guided raft practice but um
we need to learn how to be with them recognize them earlier rather than later
hopefully you know before they grow in us and get stronger and stronger
and how to relate each of us have to learn for our own selves how to relate wisely with different emotions some of
us have more comfort and less comfort with different emotions we're all unique right we have different patterning
different Role Models around what emotions trigger what kinds of things so we got we all have to come and see for
ourselves but working with emotions is huge and and being able to not harm
ourselves and not harm or others anybody else want to say anything else
about how emotions what you notice about how they can impact your movement toward harming
more a question um so
if you're mindful enough to realize that there is a difficulty motion
seems to me that it's maybe it's wisest at least to just
stay away while that emotion's strongest rather than be in touch with
situations that you can cause harm say more Mitra like when would you
decide that that seemed like a good idea and what might you do I should stay in my room and not come out
stay in your room and not come home and when would you decide to stay in your room and not come out before I say
things before I come out and okay so so you have an opportunity so maybe you're in your room and you're seething you're
upset about something and you can see yourself rehearsing mentally you ever do that planning I can remember I'm gonna
go but I'm going to say blah blah blah right yeah it will it's not always that easy I mean I I do have to come out
eventually that's right yeah yeah absolutely
so sometimes you can and sometimes you can't just take more time let's say you
don't have very much time what could you do that might help you
when you do walk out
I mean the only thing I can think of is be so close
in touch with how you how I feel
so I don't react yeah there's something beautiful about
what you said there Mitra about be so close to what I'm feeling there's a you're not just talking about feeling
your feelings but there's a maybe like an intimacy with yourself
like witnessing and caring about how hard
your how it's feeling right now inside of yourself yeah but on at the same time keeping and
um keeping in mind that my goal is not to harm beautiful
that's right and I never do that I can now say it
well that's not true that you don't ever do that it's not true okay
I can't lie to you I can't lie to me and remember notice are you doing when you
say it like that right are you following the negativity bias yeah for sure right
and so you're gonna grow witnessing and stomping in that land and do you want to
do that no but I never knew about that I mean read still the last few years yeah
great thank you anybody else want to say anything yeah good Caroline
uh I was just thinking about what other people had
said but there's also I find myself uh
meeting the emotion that I'm getting approached with sometimes and getting reactive there yeah because it's
you know although maybe I have some training to be like okay pause for a second before you respond maybe
um but when someone is coming at me with anger or fear or whatever it is it's really hard
to not just automatically get there and become reactive that way that's a
tough one thank you okay and I think that's really true emotions are communicated they're contagious you
could call them right you can feel it when somebody comes into a room sometimes they'll change the vibe you
know everybody gets you know really feels it yeah so number one knowing that that
happens is really important and so you know practicing mindfulness might be oh look at I'm recognizing what's happening
and and then for me there's a boundary exercise of like okay that's not me
that's not how I was feeling right before like okay this is their
feeling they can have their feeling that's the other part it's really easy to want them to stop
and you know we don't get to control that we we you know so we get to work
with ourselves like okay I don't need to own that I don't have to become that and sometimes that's enough and
sometimes it won't be enough because it's you get attacked maybe you know somebody says something harshly to you
um but staying close this the whole point
of mindfulness is to stay close to our experience to keep witnessing so that those we don't just get carried out and
we might and then we come back and then we might and we come back just don't stop coming back don't give up
don't ever ever give up it's always possible to come back always
and over time with the practice people get better at
it it gets easier part of it is um it is really like a muscle right that
we grow we get better at knowing our emotions emotions are
motivational systems they want us to take action you know that so we our body
starts to move so this is where that mindfulness the growing the power of mindfulness we can start to be that
close to what's happening that we don't get carried out before we see it
yeah so okay to shift
just to talk sort of start moving into getting ready for the breakout groups
and um yeah I think I'll just go through this kind
of quickly because I'm a little behind and I want to give you time in your groups
so part of non-harming is when we come into
these groups and we share with each other we the idea is to like agree that we're going to keep each other's what we
say in confidence so you know that's just a kindness that
we offer each other right so this is just an idea of how do we bring this practice into like active
use in the space so maybe you learn something a tool you
want to share but maybe you don't share about a person in particular and what they told you about that's personal
about themselves another thing in the small groups is to
consider that um if somebody wants suggestions they can
ask but that are we're not here to give advice we're here to witness to listen to
support if somebody asks for advice speak from personal experience like I have found
this helpful right these are ways of again just another way of trying not to
harm being really conscientious about your language and avoiding
avoiding things that can make somebody feel uh like their identities are being
called out in some way or another like you know our we have you know every
somebody who knows what is attached to somebody's identity but when we start to call out people's
identities we can easily move into territory that um can cause somebody to feel unsafe
unwelcome or even if it's their own story in their head about themselves
so just being super sensitive like we're just people like if people you know like
I want to put it like that how can I put this just let people share what they want to
share and try and take it in and be as respectful
with it as you can does that make sense okay
um let's see when you have
um when you're talking if something comes up that you're sharing that has to do with a trauma a very significant
difficult experience in your life use headlines kind of like I had this really difficult
experience as a kid but don't go into the details and the reason is
because you can trigger yourself going into the memory and you can trigger somebody else who maybe has similar
stories so the headline idea is you can reference these things but to to keep
yourself regulated keep it simple keep it simple
all right so um I think it would be good to break
into groups and then I'll give some more tips but I think it feels like we need to
like shift s movement a little bit so how about groups of three to four and
you can just cluster if you know people I encourage you to get in a group with
different people um you don't have to but that's the encouragement okay so find three or four
people just kind of cluster and when you're settled I'll offer more
over here
nice work oh look at that okay there okay
oh and we got somebody else come on in just join a group we're just getting started with the small groups
all right so um I'll invite you to introduce yourselves in a second
um but to practice mindfulness of speech know you're talking when you're talking
kind of oh I'm talking as you're talking and when you're listening know you're
listening I'm listening
um it's easier to stay mindful if you talk a little slower
and quieter it's easier to stay connected to your body
and easier to know what you're going to say before you say it as you're you know
like I don't mean planning I mean as the
words come out does that make sense okay pay attention to feeling of relaxation
or agitation just being mindful like keeping whether you're talking or
listening always keeping like 50 of your awareness internal
always keeping enough mindfulness with yourself even when you're listening to
track what's happening in your body
and noticing the impact of what's been shared after you speak or listen just just
letting yourself oh you wear a little bit like a bell you know
things come in and they resonate they move around us they affect us
so can you feel Can You Feel the vibration and the impact all right
so um what I would like to invite you to do is um I'll give you all these
instructions before you start one please share your names or and where you live
or something simple your favorite color maybe those three things
um and then um one at a time I'll have you go around in
the circle and share one to two sentences at a time
like not a paragraph and the question that you'll be discussing is what are you inspired to
do to support more joy of all the things that we've been talking about and maybe things you've heard elsewhere having to
do with this idea of non-harming and taking in the good
what are you inspired to do what would you like to see yourself doing differently yeah
any questions great so go ahead and start with just a go around with introductions
and and then you can one at a time just pop put in the circle like your one or
two sentence idea and then you can add more when it comes back around and then add more and let
yourself be impacted and inspired and changed by what you hear along the way
okay please begin
why is when I do the things I need to do and
letting goes like and then you know do the same thing but
relax
building inspired to invite is
doing as many expectations
thank you please
together
yes appreciation
just to write down a couple of appreciations for this selfish Ness
how is it feeling does it feel like it's a one more go around or you feel you're
good you feel like you shared the most important things you got it you got it absolutely how
about one one more minute okay
go ahead and finish your sentences for sure yeah
yes
and maybe bow to your mates I heard some you know I didn't get to hear very much
but I heard some good ideas so you know maybe just thanking yourselves and each
other for the generation of Good Vibes and energy and ideas
and um and then we'll we'll go into a guided practice so get yourself situated
for meditation and we'll do the rough practice many of
you have done it with me before some of you maybe have not um you know typically we use the raft
practice with difficult emotions but tonight I'm actually going to invite you to use how you're feeling something that
came good that was inspiring for you during this little practice tonight and sharing and connecting
and the handout has the instructions don't worry you'll have plenty of
opportunities to practice with difficult emotions later so if if you feel so inclined my
invitation to you is to choose to savor and focus with this practice on
something you know some level of joy ease relaxation validation Comfort Care
Connection all right so
coming into your body so we've been listening and sharing certain amount of our awareness energy
goes out so let's invite it in invite it in
and with each breath you might just invite more and more of a settling
I often feel like I'm a snow globe I'm all shaken up and then I set myself
down and I all the little snowflakes start to settle
maybe take three longer slower deeper breaths
ah [Applause]
and just sort of almost like you're looking around in a space taking it in
sort of look around and recognize what emotional tones and energies are
present in your heart right now and your body
and sort of just maybe gently naming them lightly naming them
and when you find one that you want to work with tonight in this practice invite it to come sit next to you
so the first part of the practice is are recognizing
really just the simple practice of naming recognizing kind of like this little bow
I see you to the feelings
emotional state Energies
the a in raft is allowing allowing space for these emotions
and our tendency is maybe not to give enough room to the
good ones to the Joy to the ease
so if it works for you creating space a sense of allowing
whatever you decided to work with
allowing it to be felt be seen be expressed
the F in raft is to feel it find and feel the emotion in the body
how it's expressed is it vibratory
if so it might be subtle or it might be coarse
does it spread or is it like a solid and a block
is there warmth or coolness associated with the
feeling in the body trying to tune into the felt sense of it
not the story around it
in a sort of open-handed way a receptive way
emotions emote they want to move
a lot of times when we don't want to have a feeling they get stuck Frozen
so when we're practicing in mindfulness with emotions we're not trying to
suppress our emotions we're trying to be generous in giving
them space trying to take good care of them
to let them know we feel them to let them touch us
as we breathe in and we breathe out
when we're doing the raft practice when we move from the F to the T
the t is about teasing apart
and this is when we start to maybe work with more of the mental activity
the stories the memories the associations
the fears the hopes the beliefs
and sort of try and disentangle things often when they're difficult
if you're working with a pleasant emotion a positive feeling
it might be that you want to sort of see invite yourself to see and name what
thoughts beliefs approaches supported the arising
the well-being just honoring the conditions
if you're working with something that feels more tricky and difficult I like to imagine a huge table
with lots of chairs and the different parts
that are happening the story the memory the belief the fear
they can each have their own chair at the table and you can put the ones that are
difficult at the far end of the table you don't have to have them close to you it's okay they can be there there's lots
of room
so we're we're just sort of um taking our experience and letting it
be seen piece by piece thought by thought memory by memory just allowing
it all to kind of unravel in a way to loosen up
for each part to have its own space
and when you're ready the next part there's another T and that's the trust
and this is this is the part where we say what can I trust here
is it can I trust my knowing can I trust
that feelings come and go do I trust a sense that by paying
attention to things I'll have more choices
do I trust that emotions are natural they're part of The Human Experience
and finding something to rest in that you trust
so we'll sit together for another five six seven minutes or so
and you can keep working with the raft practice or you can just simply practice with mindfulness of breathing
or sensation or sound open awareness practice
whatever whatever is right for you right now
if you want to do raft again with something new just it's recognize allow
feel tease apart and Trust that's the process
[Music]
is anybody willing to be the microphone microphone Bearer Mitra so
Sage you don't have to jump a Mitra will do it
oh great we can maybe have two of them
so um what did you notice what did you discover in the The Practice
the raft practice what what came up for you what did you
see differently what you have questions about great and
and Rose hello good evening everyone I think for
me what came up was just the feeling of you know to quote brene Brown am I enough and
everything and whether or not what I'm doing is is it good enough and do I have
to do more should I do less and like I tried to tease it apart like
and I think it was self-doubt insecurity I have to do more to to Showcase that
I'm competent in what I'm doing and it's it's a lot of pressure and suffering
that I've that's self-imposed and I know I could not do that but
and having that awareness of that is is very it's very liberating but at the
same time it's like I I know that I have it but how can I just be with it and not
try to control it because the other emotion or thing that I was feeling was the need to control and have everything
a certain way and yeah when it's not my way I'm like um yeah in it so yes that's
it thank you thank you so much for sharing and um I
mean you know sometimes we just do this one minute at a time
it sounds like you gave more time to these parts than you have
right letting them kind of letting yourself see oh and I get to choose
yeah yeah and it really kind of the way the
mind works is it's always doing this stuff right it's always doing this stuff so it's it's like each moment we're just
gonna keep coming and trying to notice and keep finding
ground choice it's a process
and the as you stop automatically doing all of those things all the time
it's like um my theory is the way they talk about
neurosynaptic Connections is you know a neuron you start and it
has a bunch of branches where it can make a bunch of connections and
where you don't make connections where you don't reinforce them or keep using them they they go away
they just fade it's by not using them
that they lose their power or capacity to make connections
so it's a lot of it is about restraint
and that's where the other part of Shifting toward what do you want to do
instead is helpful redirecting instead of trying to stop something
we just let it be try not to engage in it and choose something else to to do
sometimes so thank you
Ben thank you so I'm not sure how much of what I what
what is what's happening to me is related to this class or or the all the classes that I've taken prior to this
but uh one thing of uh come to conclusion with
that is this idea of being present
I don't know if there's anybody who's always able to be present so I've given
up on that but I'm aware I'm not present that's uh
that's the only thing that I think is my takeaway so I am
I'm figured trying to figure out the best I can
be at the same when I'm not present which is pretty much most of the time anyway
um so let me just make sure I I I got you right Ben
so you kind of are reflecting that it you don't know anyone who's constantly
always 100 of the time present that people too now they drift off they
get distracted that people aren't always 100 present yeah
okay I think that's the case yeah yeah yeah
and um and then I think you said and so you have so did you say so I want to be
available did you say something so what I'm saying is that I've accepted that it's not gonna it's
not gonna happen don't have to be perfect it's just not gonna happen it's so
but try to be aware that that's the case beautiful beautiful and you know there's
things that we've been talking about that we can do to start growing more and
more of those times that we're aware so like we were talking I think it was last week about like choose an activity
a daily life activity like brushing your teeth or making the bed or making coffee where you normally
wouldn't be very aware but you start you make it a practice that every day okay I'm going to be
super aware when I'm doing this and you get you grow it and you start to
do it automatically and then you might be ready to add another thing
I was um I'm doing this week I've been playing with setting my meditation timer
for like 10 minutes and doing my daily life activities while
the timer is going trying to keep in mind the timer's going and so that it's not like this one thing but it's
whatever's happening in that 10 minutes but with that kind of
hopefully remembering that I've got the timer going I'm being Mindful and then the Bell that will ring
so there's different ways to kind of grow and there's ways to give up
you know there's certain things that are going to make you less and less Mindful and that's important to pay attention to
too what makes you tune out more what makes you less mindful
um yeah thank you so much Ben anybody else
willing to share great Nathan
foreign
had some parts of me that you know tend to vex me you know throughout the day
and it's interesting how they don't show up at the table when they're doing this
and I wondering where are you guys yeah you're safe to be out here come on you
know so um this is a recurring thing for me and
when I come to The Meditation Center usually I'm perturbed by a lot of things out there but when I come in here it's
feel safe you know everyone's nice here and so I settle and it seems too easy in
here and it's like okay well I'd like to use this space to
kind of engage with this stuff at the same time and it's sort of hard to
get the rest of parts of me along in the program I guess well what might be
intelligent about what's happening what what might there be some wisdom at
work here I don't know but I'm I'm wondering
so how often in your life do you feel like you're around really nice safe kind
of cozy people in a room where you feel like okay you know like there's something
special to me about coming to this space and knowing people's intentions here and
that they're wanting to be awake and non-harming that's pretty sweet right
so maybe maybe when you're here it's really good to let your system relax
maybe we need that maybe we need that
and and then maybe maybe as you do more of the practice or I
don't know what you'll it'll show up when you're out there and you're being vexed
or you can invite yourself to practice when you're vexed
I don't know is that resonating at all Nathan I hope so eventually it'll show
up yeah okay the good you know I don't know I
just taking in the good when it comes up when it shows up
it's a gift so I know you want to do your work but
maybe this is the work maybe it is letting yourself have peace
and ease for a little bit thank you
yeah great
um something I've been working on is creative creating a sense of safety for
myself especially with regards to um
challenging bodily Sensations that I feel a lot of aversion to and so
um yeah when I'm not feeling safe in my body noticing that and um
um relaxing and feeling the feeling the effects of the practice and appreciating
that I'm like creating this safety for myself and appreciating that safety that
I feel um inside myself it sounds like a serious practice
um trying yeah beautiful it's very inspiring
thank you for sharing that
um what you just said really resonates with me too I feel like I invited worry in and feeling the sensations in my body
and I know I've been really working on trying to also feel safe in my body and just that idea of allowing the places
where I feel worry in my body I've had this tingling sensation in my hand and my neck and just allowing for that and
letting it be okay and my mind went to I want it to go how do I get rid of this
and that's like my tendency I think is to not want to feel those things and so
that became a wearer I became aware of that and how I kind of drift away and then
come back into my body it was like just being a witness to that whole process that I went through wow that's
great that's great learning how to stay
so maybe we'll no one's jumping up maybe we'll just do
a our final little sitting before we end for the night
so finding your your meditation posture
sitting up for yourself for your own experience showing up fully
right in this breath
and taking a moment to
reflect on any of the benefit any part of the benefit from being here
tonight and taking it in letting the good in
and imagining that good moving through you
to someone else and it moving from them to somebody else
and just it's spreading the goodness of our practice may be a
benefit to all beings everywhere
thank you