so welcome to IMC and those of you online welcome
to our Sunday morning program and um
for today I would like to talk about the role of posture in this practice
that we do the and I want to start with an analogy
of driving a car some of you might have had this experience
or maybe didn't have some of what I'm going to describe you're driving a car maybe in a from the freeway even fast
and lots of traffic around you and you remember
that um you forgot to return an important phone call while you're driving
so of course you know the thing to do then is go oh both hands oh no when how
could I have done that oh this is with we don't do that do we drive
oh no you keep driving right you don't give up the posture for this tragic
realization because more tragedy will come if you do
uh you lose something if you go oh no and collapse on the
steering wheel you lose your attentiveness you lose your care for everyone else
there's a lot that you lose in that process if you're sitting there in your car and
you know and there's you know traffic's going along but a good clip but not fast enough for you and you're kind of
annoyed with it all and you don't just kind of like sit back and put your hands like this
well in that case you know again you maintain
a certain posture when you're driving you don't collapse you don't pull back
you don't shrink you maintain a certain you might have little variations if you feel a little bit something but you
maintain a posture so you don't lose your attentiveness
now outside of something as important as driving a car people do all kinds of things with their
posture they do collapse they do cross their arms and sit back they do kind of raise their fists you
know all kinds of things they do with their posture and it might say people might feel well
like you know darn it I should be free to do whatever I want I feel free when I
do these things you know but we lose ourselves sometimes and how
and it represents our loss of ourselves how we succumb to posture sometimes
if we sometimes are so filled with desires that we're free to act on
desires but we lose ourselves in the pursuit of those desires addictions for
example or intense and neediness like I have create you know like clawing neediness the way I want something
and we lose ourselves in that process not just our attention when we kind of like ahead of ourselves
if we get uh you know into a very angry situation and we're really angry and we
feel I should be damned free to be angry if I'm angry but there's also we lose something about
ourselves if we give ourselves we lose ourselves to the anger and we lose the capacity to pay
attention to be a present and just like if you lose yourself into anger really lose yourself you know rage when you're
driving this is usually not a good idea you know not good idea for either the
drivers probably not a good idea for you so we lose ourselves all too easily in
all kinds of emotional states motivational states that we have
sometimes we lose ourselves because we freeze we get all rigid and hard sometimes we
lose ourselves in wanting to blame and fight you know and to criticize sometimes we lose ourselves in
in uh in our restlessness we get so activated and agitated that we don't
even know you know what foot to stand on
you might feel that way when you're driving but I suspect that when you're driving you don't succumb to the
restlessness you you kind of like within my within reason you're maintaining your posture
and uh because you have your life depends on a little bit so what I'm suggesting is that we lose
ourselves we lose ourselves to our emotions sometimes through our posture
by how we relate to it we give ourselves away to it sometimes
and it's not to deny that we are this way but we don't have to give ourselves away
to it and one of the ways not to give ourselves away is to maintain a balanced
posture in the midst of it in the flow of it all
and this is what I think the Buddha recommends this is what I I see the statue we have
here of the Buddha that for me that it represents that
the Buddha's posture is balanced upright he's not pulling
away like folding his arm and say who are these people you know who are come here you know
and you know they're not monastics so what good you know what good is this
you know he's he's present he's not pulling away he's not leaning forward into the world
he's just fully there he does I don't know if you probably can't see but he doesn't have his eyes
closed but he's not staring he's seeing but he's not caught in what
he's seeing in the world the Buddha is um [Music]
sitting in a strong way balanced way and he's available to the world and he's
available to himself for all what goes on and so when the Buddha before he was
enlightened there's a story he tells that he was meditating in the forest
jungles by himself and it seems that he will get scared the
Sounds in the jungle even he says even the peacocks walking around and maybe at night or something he didn't know what
it was and he would be scared and um and so he decided that his
practice was going to be whatever posture he was in
he would continue the way he was so if he was doing walking he said he
would keep doing walking meditation sitting he would keep sitting if he was standing he would keep
standing if he was lying down he'd keep laying down recently I was reminded of the story by
a trauma therapist and he loved the story he said this is exposure therapy
you know they just could I just expose yourself to something and then find your way until he said in his language until
you get deactivated until you can relax and um so I don't know if that's the
wisest to things to suggest always but but this idea that he would stay in his
posture and and the idea is a dignified balance posture
and what's the advantage of doing that of doing that until the fear passes
one is a balanced posture is one of the best places in which to
um monitor yourself with what's going on to not lose yourself but to gain
yourself to increase your capacity to know and be
aware and to hold whatever is happening for us without succumbing without giving it to
it giving up to it losing ourselves to it and also not running away from it not
distracting us from it so there's this wonderful combination of benefits from a posture which is in your
way the equivalent of what the Buddha is doing in your way it doesn't have to look as nice as his after all it's a
metal stat it's a metal statue it's just just an artist who made that one
but that uh that you would sit and not Lose Yourself
monitor yourself well and keep noticing the tendencies
to Lose Yourself notice a Tendencies to start tapping your fingers you know
because you're impatient the Buddha doesn't tap his fingers not because it's wrong to do that but that
is kind of a way of losing our ourselves distracting ourselves or getting caught up in the impatience perhaps
there's nothing nothing necessarily wrong with that but
is it is it the best way to process is it the best way to really
be present for what's here and have a certain be in the driver's seat of your life rather than the
passenger seat or rather than just kind of you know giving up or something losing yourself
there's something very powerful about being careful with our posture so the
posture can reveal better to us what's really going on
so if you're sitting meditating this way especially I'm talking about meditation it transfers a daily life as well
but you're sitting this way and um and you know you remember that
you've you know you didn't make that important phone call in meditation you can feel the power of the arms the the
power of this the collapse that wants to happen the arms that want to go like
this they collapse but you're committed to not doing it not not as a repression
but as a way to feel the energy to feel the sensations feel the motivations to
collapse wow my collapsibility is huge right now
I had no idea collapse could be so powerful in convincing and authoritative I had no idea the collapse could be come
with all its lawyers arguing it's a case that this is why you should collapse
wow this is quite something but I'm not going to collapse not in meditation
but I am going to be present for this I'm going to know this see it
until I see it through until I get to the other side many years ago I love this story that
someone told me what he had learned to do I think he was maybe an alcoholic some
kind of serious addiction and someone told them that when he got the urge to drink
he should go find a nice comfortable chair to sit in and not move
not leave the chair no not moving wasn't it not don't leave the chair no matter what
and he said it was hard the the power of addiction is oh it can
be overwhelming for people and um and uh very convincing very hard
to resist but he was he had this PR he was told to don't leave the chair
and what he discovered that it would be like the rodeo than a wild Bronco
that he would stay there and actually they uh they're their analogy he used
was that of a wave cresting he would and the wave would get bigger
and bigger bigger more and more powerful and at some point it would crashed and he'd find himself on the back side of
the wave and everything would settle down and he said that was a turning point for
me I felt so empowered he felt so capable I felt so like oh this I can do this at
least and that was a real turning point for him and his addiction when he learned to
not move from the chair so to learn to feel fear to you know you
know the mountain lion's coming don't just stand there but in meditation to learn to feel fear
anger depression sadness all kinds of things
that can come that normally we would sink into or give and give ourselves
away to and we do it in our posture unconsciously
but here to keep the posture that's dignified and balanced
and see it through to the other side if possible and what does it take to do that it's
not an easy thing sometimes what I'm start describing but we have all these instructions and mindfulness about how
to bring attention careful mindful attention to the body
to the feelings that we have to the impulses the Mind states that are operating
the desires and the aversions that operating and as we start teasing apart the package looking at the component
pieces of it rather than one big wave it becomes easier and easier to sit
there and that which can relax has a chance to relax and soften
and and something can begin shifting and there could be a sense of
empowerment or inner strength that can arise from being able to maintain a posture
through the difficulties we have so we have in this tradition the
teaching on the five hindrances and this is the place to practice this with
the five hindrances are divided into kind of three different areas
the first area has to do with our relationship basically with our relationship to what's external to us
kind of we're looking outward to the world of desires and the world of uh hostility of ill
will what we don't like in the world and what we want in the world and uh and uh so that intense way in
which we want things we lose ourselves in that wanting
and some people lose themselves with the carrying the banner of freedom
I should have this some people lose themselves in hostility
to the world blaming others some people live in the world of externalizing their life
desires what I like what I don't like blame not blame
Proclaim praise and then some people externally live in this world of hostility and it's
everything out there has to you know fit the way I want it to be or something
it's sad to lose yourself in this way but to sit to learn to hold a posture
and sit and see that movement to feel it within us is really powerful
the first hint I had about this you know it's not that big of a deal I suppose
but the first hint I had of myself doing this when I was practicing in Thailand
and we didn't eat much food there like we didn't have no food in the afternoon so lunch was a big deal
and lunch was kind of you know down a hill and through the jungle he had to go walk there for a
five minute walk or something and um I'd be ravenous
and I noticed that um my center of gravity
would be about a foot in front of me because I was kind of like kind of like all my concerns were up ahead
and I could say oh wow what a gill what are you doing out there and I would kind of take a deep breath and kind of bring
myself back to myself and and then I'd within a few seconds I found myself
and that was like the Seesaw reclaiming myself and losing myself just because of
lunch and um so
um so beginning to see how this operates and see it clearly because we're not
giving in to the impulses because we're standing here we're kind
of staying keeping keeping what we're doing in a sense the posture we're in
again not to repress it so we can see it really clearly
we see it with the kind of clarity we can't see if we give into it come back here come back here
and also a balanced posture is a posture not only you can be balanced in a sense but also a posture with a tension that's
building up has a better chance to relax and soften and some of the lawyers are I think the
lawyers are they're they're they're they're they're they're commissioned their what they get paid the lawyers of the mind is intention
the more you pay them attention the more they work for you
but the lawyers of the mind don't you know that when you if you're relaxed they tend to kind of relax too
so the so to begin seeing how we involved with the external world the
first two hindrances being caught in desires caught in ill will the second uh the next category of the
hindrances after those to do will we get caught in our internal world
the usually the next the next one is usually called sloth and torpor but it
turns out the word that's translated sloth in Pali means becoming stiff and rigid
so it has I think it's much more valuable understanding because we freeze
we get do we we get numb we get all kinds of ways in which we kind of stop or get
stuck in our inner life and we do kind of interpre sloth and
torpor what is torpor I think it's also kind of a here it's kind of a numbness a
kind of lethargy that comes from resistance we kind of pull in and collapse into
ourselves and so that's easy to succumb to with a nap
isn't that absolute right thing to do is it uh do we want to stay frozen and stiff
this posture can't take a balanced posture where
you're breathing doesn't freeze your breathing doesn't get tight the breathing has a chance to notice if it
does get tight and maybe you can adjust it and change it work with it and keep it soft and so
some of the the stiffness the rigidity the freeze doesn't get too locked in
Maybe and then the the second one or the second category that's internally
focused is um uh restlessness agitation excessive
activation we're running around excited not really you know
or filled with regrets with remorse with self-criticism with you know just
something is terrible here I did the wrong thing and and um and this also is something where
people lose themselves in this inner world of agitation and
one of the best really fun meditations I've had is being really restless
in meditation and just sitting still and imagining my body is like a big
I don't know big room with walls and uh and the restlessness is a ping pong
balls that are bouncing around inside when I used that analogy it was kind of fun to sit there and and feel the
restlessness it was certainly better than the alternative was to believe the
restlessness or be a victim of the restlessness or feel this is wrong or bad or feel the Authority or the
restlessness like this means that adding you know this means that or something
as opposed to oh this means that ping-pong balls are going wild in there
and that was fascinating to sit there just watch they all kind of move and it was when I had that analogy it was the
first time in my meditation where I had the experience of not being caught by the authority of
the restlessness but just allowing it just to be there freely but not losing myself to it so this kind
of moving around bouncing around and then there's that doubt there's the
fifth hindrance but I think doubt is too tame of a word just to call what it is it's a little bit too intellectual
cognitive I think it can be uh you know being bewildered
perplexed lost not an understanding what's going on
and that can be really hard for people and sometimes maybe it's even reasonable
it's things are so confusing but is that a reason
to collapse is that a reason to
pick up the other hindrances and blame or want something
you know want some food that's going to solve it for me or comfort me
but to sit or to stand or to lie down or to walk
in a posture that's balanced some of these things I'm talking about that can that are posted that catches
our posture and and changes out we do and how we are
really powerful difficult and I've found what's useful is to go
walking but and so it's the in the walking the movement the it's like massaging
everything and giving there's kind of a um I've done walking meditation really fast
when I was really pissed off and it was only it was only the fast
walking that kind of allowed me to hold it and gave me the capacity to be with it
without getting all being bottled up or something but to do walking meditation in this
balanced way and then from there with a posture of a balanced walk walking fast if you need to
then monitor yourself and notice what's going on and and be with what's going on
and and maintain that and see that and let that be the place where you look for balance rather than collapse or whatever
it is there's lying down
I think it's a it's called one of the four dignified postures in Buddhism so sometimes the wisest thing to do to
get balance is to lie down but don't lie down in the fetal position
nothing wrong with it I do the fetal position when I have a migraine I have no I have no shame
about doing so it seems like the best thing I can do I put my head under the
covers I get in the field position and I have my practice then I practice with the migraine
but uh but you know if you were talking about this kind of emotional stuff maybe a fetal position is really good
sometimes maybe that's the best option sometimes I don't but but the idea is
um with this kind of balanced approach I'm trying to suggest today is find a posture that allows you that's the
middle way the balanced way to be with it all not for not against not losing
yourself not collapsing sometimes lying down uh is the way that then you can
kind of track and be with things and and discover how powerful these forces are
and discover how to relax with them discover what they see them more carefully what they are
discover what's underneath them what's driving them or simply discover how to have a larger
capacity to hold them to be aware of them
and this is a I think an undervalued part of this practice
many people come to this practice to fix themselves to make something better and to solve
their problems and be you know but sometimes our problems don't get solved
but rather our capacity to be balanced and open and free become so big
that the so-called problem now just becomes a little detail
I have all this anger I have to deal with my anger oh the anger is still here but it's like
a book on the bookshelf in a big room as opposed to the book you know that
just this is the whole thing so kind of letting the awareness the body become larger or the felt body the
experiential body that can hold it and be with it the Mind becomes bigger the heart becomes bigger
so how to uh so this the role of the body the posture
I would encourage you to practice this within reason you don't have to go around all the time
but look for opportunities where you can take a balanced
posture upright aligned posture that works for you you know your body your situation
that is your your posture where you feel like this is a posture right of not
giving in and I'm not pulling away and that's a coming and I'm not
resisting I'm just there and that'll look very different for everyone what that looks like because of all kinds of
issues but find it for you and then breathe with it be with it
meditate in that see what goes on what you learn and what unfolds and how maybe
you'll learn the difference between being in the driver's seat
and losing and not being in deceit get you know giving yourself giving up to some let it putting your emotions in the
driver's seat which what happens for example when we collapse or we act out and react
so here present with it
and you might discover all kinds of interesting things you might discover
that some of the things that you're troubled by emotionally for example
Maybe are not so strong if you don't give in to it with your
posture I saw that many years ago when I was in college
and I had some kind of I don't know
you know this is a you know I don't think it was so serious degree of depression so I want to
preface of that so I don't know what else thinks that has to be like what happened to me but I had college student
depression whatever that is for me one day
and I was just kind of miserable and depressed and and I came home and
to this Barren house that we had hardly any furniture and it wasn't a particularly inspiring
place to be but there was a couch so I sat down the couch and I don't
think it was possible to be more of a slouch in the couch more than I was
I mean my I think my shoulders were in the crack between the backrest and the seat you know
[Music] they were so dramatic
and so I thought so I was so dramatic I noticed wow Gil this is quite something
and it occurred to me out of the blue Gail why don't you sit up straight so I sat up straight
and ninety percent of the depression kind of like this kind of vanished
instead of taking that posture it seldom that easy who knows maybe you know I'd ask someone
for a date and she said no some you know maybe it wasn't more more than that I don't know what it was but
but uh but um I was so impressed by the role of
posture that a posture can make that kind of difference and I'm not saying it's that easy
but posture is a very important part of mindfulness practice the Buddha when he taught mindfulness
he taught mindfulness of posture and he taught the mindfulness of those
these four postures and everything in between but he named specifically
walking standing sitting and lying down
and later in the tradition it's called the four dignified postures
and um practice in those and when the time sees time seems right
do the same thing that the Buddha did if you're afraid or angry or something
don't change your balance posture stay with it and see if you can what
happens if you stay with it without giving into it but but respecting it respect everything
about yourself respect these feelings and the difficulties and all that but
stay in the posture until
the wave crests which someday it will
so mindfulness of posture so we have a few minutes we can take a
few questions here or comments here and then uh at some point we can go outside
afterwards and so as you would like to stay we'll put some chairs in a circle in the outer in the parking lot those of
you who want to take off your mask and take it off and we'll continue discussion out there but for now if I see a hand over there
oh I didn't know have announcements first yes
no and uh next Sunday the 20th we will have
for the second time it's a monthly group that has restarted for kids it's called
Dharma rocks and we meet here at 11 15 to 12 15.
um each month on on a Sunday and uh it's approximately third grade through
six we had an eighth grader last time that was fine mature second graders also fine
um we have a great time we did mindfulness of spookiness we'll see what comes up um you know this coming month
next Sunday
thank you so I have a question about
so my reaction to things has improved you know I feel like there is space your
your reaction so um I'm just going to remove it more briefly
um so you know before I was always reacting right and I would say I would finish it
you know I have something smarter to say or you know I'm mad I have to tell that
so that has you know has slowed down and have become more patient I feel good
like you know there is no rush like you know I don't have to really tell the mean things I feel about
anything I guess so but when you know previously it would be like I'm saying
stupid stuff means tough but I feel like that is the greatest thing I have to say
and later on it's like oh why did I say it right so how come you know when we
are in the in the thick of the action the mind is so numb that in a in a way
it's like we say stuff and then we're like oh God I didn't mean it I do like them you know I Ruled around my aunt or
you know I was mean you know there is Rush of emotions but afterwards you know
so why do we do stupid stuff great foreign
well I probably don't have a good good answer it's a good question I probably
don't have a good answer but one of the reasons is because we lose ourselves in our emotions we lose ourselves in our
desires and we get pulled into it and you know and one Buddhist answer to that
question is because of the intensity of our desires our Cravings so we then
suddenly that those take over and what I was trying to teach today is a way of beginning to learn how that
that operates in us because if you take a posture that you're not going to succumb to things but but watch it and
find your freedom with it um the better and better over time you'll notice that tendency from the
inside before you do it and then you have the capacity not to give in
yeah thank you thank you yes maybe then over here first and then you can do it
yeah hi oh yeah um I have a heard that in Zen Foster is
extremely important in Zen I'm going to turn it up the volume okay go ahead hold that horizontally
like this horizontally flat yeah I've heard that
in Zen posture is extremely important um can you please talk a little bit about
and then posture is really important and uh
and there's a number of there's a number of reasons uh one is that this kind of posture you see here with the Buddha
it's a yogic posture and so you get yogic benefits especially if you can sit in full Lotus
and so but it's also a kind of a crutch I used to use full Lotus as a kind of a
crutch because I would get concentrated quicker and I would fall asleep I
wouldn't fall asleep so much because you get a really good energy going like the chi goes much more easily
but to rely on that rather than building it up from the inside out but to have it from the posture I don't think it's
really the so wise for what we're doing mindfulness practice where we want to really meet ourselves and be with and
see what's going on and not have some kind of you know yogic kind of effect that kind
of makes us concentrated or have the energy flow but anyways the yogic posture also some
schools of Zen they have a very very different philosophy and world view about
meditation and Buddhism than than Indian Buddhism has and so this posture is
considered people take in Zen sometimes Zen is a ritual
it's a ritual of being a Buddha and so you take a posture of a Buddha
and then over time you grow into it but it's more like a ritual enactment of
uh enactment of buddhahood rather than you know a path to buddhahood or something
and um so those are some of the reasons
posture that is is it a person that is unique to sin that you always practice
Zen with something like that or is it today concerned well depends where you practice then
uh you know if you practice Chad and in the Chinese and they they have a whole
different attitude towards it um in Japan some in some schools of them they have very strict attitude towards
it then practitioners in the United States have learned um that not everyone who
practices Zen are 22 year old men
and uh where in monasteries in Japan the real training Monastery most of them are
uh 22 years old like or you know in the early you know mid-20s and um
and so what we're capable of doing with this body is changes over time and circumstances and uh classically and Zen
there's very little tolerance for people who have disabilities you know if you can't sit full Lotus you know you can't
be here you know it's very strict um and uh they gave some when I was in
Japan Japanese monastery they um they gave me some tolerance they
didn't expect me to be in full notice but if you go into full load it's been expected I don't know if I can do it
anymore but that if you do the Japanese did it full Lotus and and there was a
there was a kind of like a hazing to go into the monastery and so you had
to sit there for hours you know in full Lotus and they would come with a kind of a stick and if you come underneath their
hips here like like this if you take put the stick all the way through like this if you're sitting in full
Lotus you won't hit anything but if you bring your foot down
the stick would hit and so uh
so it was a little bit some some so little bits you know
strict and I think some of the strictness
wasn't exactly the essence of Zen it was something else
they're going on over there so so it depends so that was a long way of saying
the you know it depends but Zen does rely a lot on posture and it's I think
it's part of I learned a lot of the benefits of a good posture through Zen I think it's one of the strengths of Zen
that they focus on posture but it can be overdone
yeah so two questions on uh movement the first one uh during meditation itself I
know some people are very strict on not moving at all um they film themselves and make sure
that over an hour they haven't moved by a millimeter how important is it to be completely still even if you sense some
discomfort so that's the first question the second question would be outside of meditation if you find yourself getting
you know frustrated drumming your fingers something like that I imagine you'd want to approach it with curiosity
and to relax but should you try to stop the drumming or how would you deal with that
um you should do whatever whatever it feels right to you
okay [Music]
but what feels right has something to sometimes I have something to do with what your practice is what you want to
see happen if you want to really get to the bottom of what's happening for you when you're
drumming your fingers and you want to study it like what's that what I'm going to make it object of
mindfulness maybe sometimes it's good to keep doing it you're doing it anyways I'm doing it what's going on here so let's keep doing it and and then that
gives you access to what's happening another today you might decide I'm not going to even begin I can feel the
impulse now let's see what's going on so it what's right depends on what you
want to do if you're trying to make a message to people be really clear that what what feels right is letting them
know then keep doing it if it's you know unless you're insulting them or
something I mean there's all it depends what you feel there's no shoulds here but in
terms of practice sometimes it's good to um
um like in terms of not moving uh uh there's advantages to not moving
sometimes it allows the Mind get calmer and quieter the more we move in
meditation the more we kind of activating the mind so a lot of movement keeps the Mind activated
and so it can get quieter more concentrated for some people when they don't move it can feel really nice as we get more
stellar and Stiller to keep that Stillness of the body it feels more more natural than
and uh and sometimes it's the wrong thing to do you know we're we start uh
you know we start having pain now it could be that you say you know I keep having pain I always avoiding it I
think what I'm interested in doing today is to stay with the pain for a while to see what I can learn maybe I need to
learn a little bit about my reactivity to pain that feels right today
um and then after a while if you feel the painful I think I learned a few things about myself but now it's getting
grueling you know I don't think I need to do it now you know how I don't want to meditate again ever again
I think I overdid it I won't I won't stay with a pain that long I'll move sooner
so there's all you know all these choices you can make but you do it out of what feels right with the criteria
that you've with the criteria that's appropriate for the occasion yeah very good thanks and that's where
you have to use your intelligence yep so it's a matter of being the right attitude with it to it basically mindfulness maybe that Curiosity and uh
and to relax into it yeah and also the criteria the intention the motivation you have what what what's the purpose of
this what's the purpose of being still what's the purpose of um you know moving and going along with it and and I if you
say I'm going to sit still what's the purpose of it I'm gonna I know I've done this so that's I'm not saying it's you
but it's me what's the purpose of sitting still to look really good
you know everybody you know I'm the last person sitting still you know I'm that
good you know so thank you so let's let's start
oh it's tea today oh today's tea okay so we won't have the circle outside then but we'll hang out and talk yeah anyway
so every we have tea today outside and what that means is that there's uh some little snacks some tea some snack things
to drink and uh we can hang out in the parking lot and chat and talk and you
know rather than having a discussion around Circle discussion and um so that should be very nice I
look forward yes suggest that you get your cup of tea before you go outside and
everyone is welcome to that yeah yeah so that the the hot water
urn is here on the counter in the kitchen so make your tea and and outside we can take the masks off they're
optional you can do whatever you want but we can't take them off if you want but Amy you come back in the back into
the building to go to the bathroom or get more tea please put your mask on again
so thank you all very much