so good evening everyone and welcome and what i'd like to do is um
talk about ethics it's uh at the heart of
buddhist practice living ethical life though there's no word in buddhism for at the
word ethics the english word ethics so you can argue maybe there's no ethics in
buddhism there's something else that looks like ethics so if you if the word ethics doesn't quite work for you
and the um the let's see
if the um um so what i'd like to do is start i
mean part of it is also this integration many people one of the wonderful questions people ask me
people meditate or go on retreat this is all meditation's fine it's fine but how
does it apply to our life you know it should apply to our life you know just not by just sitting peacefully
by yourself well this topic of ethics is about how it applies to life
and and it's not like ethics is secondary or it's
it's not like it's the foundation so because so we can meditate it's the fruit of meditation it's the
expression of it the manifestation of it in our life so that's kind of a little bit introduction
but i thought uh the way i'd like to start here is is uh
i'd like to wear a relatively small group compared to before the pandemic
we can take we have the luxury of maybe you could all go around and say your names
and will it be okay if you could
does it work yes my name is veta
hi my name is beverly herbert
and laura
my name is sage sally
my name is sue
my name is jamie
hi bill good evening everyone i'm anne rose
hi my name is kristen hi i'm malvika
i'm caroline
mike april
wonderful and also we have some people online it's a little hard for them to say their names but
and uh you're all included so uh
that was really nice nice for me it's also now a way that we're more
connected a little bit each of you had your voice in here and so there's more sense of being
somehow in relationship or been recognized something about you as a human being now has been
seen or recognized and as opposed to some of you i didn't know your names and
nameless people who come time c and maybe you wouldn't speak otherwise they wouldn't hear your voice
but there was some contact or some knowing and in a sense that's an
act of mindfulness that you know paying attention noticing what's here
and um but something else happens in that noticing now you're more
you know maybe you'll forgive me for saying it this way because probably not exactly to the point
or i don't know what but you're more human you're more yourself there's more
feeling for you there's a easier for empathy there's a like now you're you're
somebody rather than someone more amorphous or uncertain or and now
um for me i care for you more there's a sense of care there's a sense of you're
you have an emotional life you have an inner life you have a history you come you know you have something brought you
here an interest that maybe we share and so so that there's a deeper recognition
and i'm touched in some way it's not you know i'm sure i can be much more deeply
touched if you told me a little bit more about your life but uh i feel a little bit touched too
something moves inside of me that's different all of that
changes how i'd like to live with you in a sense um i'm i'm much less inclined to want to
hurt you to harm you more importantly i'm much more
interested in to have care for you and and be concerned for you i'm much more
ready to notice that if i have some kind of harsh or mean or
angry kind of hostile kind of thoughts that i've noticed that when i do that it
hurts me that it isn't just that why would i do that to you now that i know you
but also if i do that do it i'm now going to be a little bit
i'm hurting myself i'm kind of diminishing myself undermining myself and that's the movement of what i'm
calling ethics this is how ethics can come out of buddhism because of this practice or mindfulness
because we're paying attention more we're connecting more where people around us have a different role
and place in our lives than they do if we don't know them at all
and we know ourselves more through this practice we're much more sensitive we recognize the quality of
our thoughts the quality of our speech the quality of what we're trying to do our intentions
and it isn't that we're it's ethical in the sense that there's a should and shouldn't way of being
but rather we there's an ouch factor it's like oh that hurts why would i do that
why would i close myself down we could continue going around the room
and do this and i think the the sense of connection and things would be deeper
and not only to each other but also to ourselves so i'd like to ask we do that
and and maybe you can pass if you don't want to say anything it's completely fine
and in fact that's also a way of knowing you in a nice way it's a kind of
expression of who you are and that should be respected and and it's not uh
you know there's lots of place for that but this is the this is the it's something very brief it could be a
phrase no more than a sentence not a story
but it has to do with the story in the story of your
inner growth your caring for your inner life your growth of wisdom of compassion
of healing your story you know the story of your life in terms
of your inner growth healing spirituality
maturity where does meditation fit in that for
you does it is that part of that story or is it just like you know
you know you deny any difference in going home and doing this watching the shopping channel
how does it fit so let's put you on the spot but just it's just something it doesn't have to
be brilliant just some little phrase or idea
meditation's a foundation is what foundation foundation nice
thank you um this is the first time i've done a 45 minute sit since before the pandemic
and it was horrible [Music] [Laughter]
i would say meditation is the way to slow down and
get closer to attaining balance nice
um for me meditation is a way of bringing loving awareness to everything
around me
uh deepening quiet
meditation brings me closer to myself and to others in my life
it's what i do
um i would say meditation is something like the beating heart of my ethical practice
um i found that my daily practice is like
ironing out the wrinkles
i like the freedom of finding here
meditation has allowed me to just become more aware of the treasure of each day
today what i'm thinking about is meditation gives me the awareness
of what's happening in my mind so i have more choice about how i respond to that
i don't know whether it's the meditation sitting or meditation in daily life but i'm more
aware of what's going on in my body and what that's doing to my mind or vice
versa maybe more vice versa
meditation's had a changing role in my life and it's becoming more and more foundational
these days
meditation is a place of rest for me and it's how i find myself
nice very nice thank you so it was lovely to hear as well
and from hearing all that from myself i hear
a sensitivity in each of you that probably
would make you more ethical if you stayed close to it if you stay close to what you described
that probably you're not going to go jump up out up up sitting here and
and yell at me for wearing the wrong color shirt you know like how could you a dharma teacher shouldn't wear blue
or something you know i i'm just making something silly up but but uh you're probably more likely to make some space
i felt you know to listen or be a present and and
come out of that somewhat more caring for each other you could do a different activity
tonight and would come out of that activity the opposite
what you choose to do has a big impact on the tendencies of the mind and what we want to do
and and so coming to meditate and engage in the dharma in some kind of way
changes us in the direction of wanting to be more kind
wanting to be more connected or more sensitive to ourselves and to others the quiet
that some of you discussed is something that makes us more available
to feel and sense what's going on here and it makes a difference
what we do and so one of the things that comes out of that is this very i think important
recognition that we don't really don't want to harm anyone
because that harms them why would you
also you don't want to harm yourself one of the reasons not to harm yourself
is that that's a way to create the conditions to take remove the foundation that's important to have
that would make you a kind supportive caring person people who are very critical themselves
and living under that kind of stress are much more likely to snap and been
angry or or be shut down or insensitive to the world
around them and so as we practice
there's a tendency to become more sensitive to ourselves the impact we have
the impact we have in others the impact we have on ourselves and as that becomes more sensitive
then people will naturally want to live a little bit more ethically
which in my vocabulary means a life that avoids causing harm
in fact the very idea that we would harm someone intentionally or unintentionally
it just feels completely like no that i don't want to do that there
becomes a more and more a life of living for the for the benefit of others
for their care not because it's a should not because
that's what buddhists do and you've got you're a buddhist so now you've got to go figure out how to be kind
but it arises out of this mindfulness out of this practice out of this the deeper connection we
have to ourselves and the world around us so
that's one of the reasons why that's like so the connection to ethics and the integration of mindfulness in daily life
is inherent in what we're doing however
it's easy to overlook it it's easy to get distracted and busy it's easy to not appreciate fully that
this is happening so then we give dharma talks so we study buddhism and they say you know
it's good to live by the precepts it's good to be ethical and be kind and be compassionate and here
are some ways of developing compassion here's practice of loving-kindness i know that the precepts are hard to
practice but they'll really create the right conditions for you so when you do go sit
and meditate you won't feel regrets and upset about what you've done
so so there's all kinds of logical ways and doctrinal ways that we can get the
instructions to be ethical
sometimes those can put people in the wrong direction i've seen people try to be ethical
and they get all tight and they become a judgmental of other people
but i've also seen that people get inspired at some point
to want to learn about how to be ethical it's to learn to study about it think
about it to reflect on it to do practices connected to ethics
because they value that ethical sensitivity
growing inside of them that this is a good direction to go this is a way that i want this to be part of
my life and so some people then say you know if they say that that the five precepts
are what supports this or the expression of this and that there's a feedback loop between
living by the five precepts and this beautiful thing is happening to me having it grow
then i'm going to live by the five precepts and that's a very different feeling
than having some kind of strict moralistic idea that to be a good person you have to
follow the precepts it's something something that's coming from the inside out now
and but what i'm trying to say one thing i'm trying to say here now is that you don't have to leave it to chance
you don't have to let it this ethical sensitivity this care to be something that you just let
arise and develop kind of naturally out of the meditation practice as it does at some point you can begin recognizing
that you're being changed this way and want to support that
encourage it to develop it further and then it becomes something you take on intentionally
but the motivation from it for doing it comes from within the motivation is an expression of
the practice that's maturing as opposed to you read all the books on buddhism and that book say this the
manual say this is what you're supposed to do so this is the transformation
that this is the way that this practice becomes our life
and the idea that how do i bring this practice into daily life
i feel a little bit i feel very happy when people ask that question and i feel a little bit sad
and the sad part is because it sounds to me sometimes as if there's two things
their practice and their life and as long as there's these two things
then there can be a challenge or you know then you know sometimes habits
sometimes don't you don't but to really feel there's not two things it's your life we're talking
about it's how you live your life how you experience your life how you
how you inhabit your life that we're talking about and so it's not so much um
and so um um it's a lovely way of talking about this
is that you don't bring your practice into your life you bring your life into your practice
and why that's a wonderful turn of phrase is that
if you bring your your practice into your life it might for some people prioritize life
you have to live your life and do what you're doing and then you bring you integrate you bring in the practice to
it and that's certainly a valid way of seeing but to say
what um how do i bring my life into my practice puts the practice at the center
like that's the most important thing and you know where i go shopping and how
i drive my car those are all him that is my life
but my the practice is more central in my life because the practice is what i'm discovering is this deeper sensitivity
this deeper sense of foundation this deeper place of quiet of peace of compassion or care
this is where i want my life to be based on that's portable sometimes i'm driving my
car sometimes i'm shopping sometimes i'm doing whatever having breakfast and
and rather than prioritizing that
prioritize this place of practice as if that is who you are that's life
and then see how everything fits into that rather than how your practice fits into
into your life and because then you're always in practice is always always kind of the
forefront some people who don't know about this inner change that happens
can feel like now you're just being told to do get more busy to add something on top of your life now
i got to do a less practice on top of the dishes and making breakfast and all that
it's actually in some ways you get to do less because the practice becomes who you are
not what you do and that's the direction where this integration or this how this practice
goes more and more ethical when the practice becomes you you become
the practice it's not something that's apart from you you don't have to come to imc to do the
practice at some point it you carry it with you it's kind of
the nature of your heart it's who you are the um
the uh in the ancient language they talk about this in terms of entering a stream at
some point you enter the little little literal meaning of this word is not stream but entering the
current of a river and if you find the current it'll carry you along
and um and uh the um and then when the buddhists are
asking what is the current we enter into and it's the eightfold path
that we have become so the eight practices that are the eightfold path are not not meant to be
something you're adding to your life but something arises out of your life
so the challenge i'd like to offer each of you if you're up for a little challenge
is what is it about this practice that we do the meditation practice the dharma practice
that flows out of you that when it flows out of you
is looks like you're now an ethical person you're living an ethical life
what is it can you identify something have you recognized something in you what is it that flows from you
that maybe sometimes it gets forgotten gets over
or you know overwritten because of the busyness of life but what is it that flows out of you
and if you're willing to do one more round i'd love to hear some of you again you can more than welcome to pass because
this is a little more difficult question to answer but if um if some of you would like to
offer some words about what is it that flows out of you that
would someone else would look at you and say oh that person is inclined towards to be
ethical but you're not ethical because you're not thinking in those terms you're thinking about just
how to let the sensitivity be expressed in your life does that make some sense what i'm
asking yeah good enough
i have two things that come to my mind
i started trusting my kids to start trusting my kids my peers
no my kids i really trust them you know this is a big change and
and i conserve water i think about it all the time and
i really focus on this nice nice
and no specifics came up but just an attitude that i i recognize that's changed is um
is just coming from a non-harm perspective
as opposed to maybe more of a protect myself or something kind of a perspective
i'm not really sure i would say maybe caring being more caring of others but
i'm not sure i'd answer your question
i think i would say something like tenderness
it's become more and more part of my life and i think that comes from
meditation and the recognition that like you know all beings are
sacred and important
for me acceptance of myself of other people of things that are happening in the world
yeah
i think right mindset for me because thinking critically of myself and others
and being very anxious has always been something i've struggled with which you know putting that into putting
practice practice into my life has allowed me to um kind of
influence how my actions affect myself and others
i think equity equanimity really helps
that's onward leading
yes
i'm i have a little less tendency to be angry at people and
i understand my anger more when i have it
ah love
um i guess more acceptance of myself and
also when i see somebody really struggling
i find myself having a respect for them as a person
and and and caring concern which is a different place than i have been in the past
say care and the more i'm in the present the more
i uh have the ability to be attentive for others
which i work towards
what came up for me was gratitude and reverence when i feel that spring up i'm
more likely to not hurt others
i'd say compassion and connection just seeing myself in them and them and
me
meditation has helped me recognize when i'm angry to not get triggered and to
see that i'm angry and to observe it and not react so much
and like one of my girlfriends said i don't understand why you're not just jumping up and
you know defending yourself and i didn't have an answer at the time but
i think that's why
yeah where i work you sometimes hear people say it's better to seek forgiveness than
permission and i turn that around i'd much rather ask for permission than
you know get it cleared up front
very nice thank you all so i hope that the theme of today the
connection of this practice with ethics or something that looks like that
you know it was somehow addressed in a nice way and inspired something in you or touched something in you
i don't have much more to say today do you have anything you want to say or
any questions or comments april use the mic please
a colleague of mine was on the ethics committee and i asked him because i've
always wondered what's the difference between ethics and morals i don't know if you have an opinion
about that oh ethics and morals i think that's probably a very
individual thing how people would answer that that the difference between them is kind of like
you know some people would say they're synonyms some people i'm sure there's people who will have definitions that are different
um the um uh i think that uh morals
uh i i associate more with
guidelines by which people live and ethic is an abstraction it's more like almost like philosophy of ethics
it's the the wide field of how people might make decisions how to live their
life and and so morals are closer to the heart ethics is more can be more abstract
though i never use the word morals i use the word ethics in english so
um so that's the best i could come up with
the as i said the there's no clear word in in the buddhist
language about that matches our word ethics but many people say it's the word sila or sheila
but that word literally means a conduct and it refers to kind of some people now
translate as virtuous conduct ethical conduct
but usually we think of ethics in english as something something deeper in us
than only what we do it's also the source within us for how
we do it and so the word that's a better fit for the
english word ethics is kusala a word that can mean both wholesome
which i like is a wholesome word and also has the meaning of has three meanings that can mean
virtuous and it can mean skillful so do something skillfully with some
so this ability to that to do something with skill that is for the benefit of self and
others and uh and what's uh repeated often in the teachings of the buddha
is live a life that's for the benefit of oneself
benefit for others and a benefit for self and others
and i love that last one itself and others because i don't we don't know what it
would have meant but how i interpret it is that um it's the we
it's us in community and so it's not just the ethics of individuals now it is for me or the
impact i have on you but it's also the impact it has for us as a community is in a relation in
relationship to each other and so we want to care for that relationship as well
and so the carefulness is in how do we have a relationship that is friendly that's
warm that's connected that's that's supportive that's carries some of these values in the
relationship itself and so um so this so-called ethics
is uh in buddhism is very relational as well
so i love that that uh it's all of us in it together so thank you for being together here
today i really appreciate it a lot that we could come here and meditate and that you participated with me rather than
giving a classic traditional kind of dharma talk but to hear from you and
do this together and um so thank you very very much and i wish
you well