so to start introduce or start this meditation
there's a kind of a teaching story of a school
where on the wall in the classroom there's a sign that says in this school
we place the teachings on your heart
and so someone asked why do you put the teachings on
our hearts and the teacher said only uh
we only put it on your hearts only life can put it in your hearts
we put it on your hearts and when your heart breaks open then they fall in
so this idea that um to be receptive
or to have our hearts open not necessarily only break open but to open
to be receptive enough open enough transparent
enough wide enough so that we
something can touch it deeply something can fall into it and one of those things that uh
is awakened in that process as the life touches our deepest heart
is a sense of care a sense of
kindness Goodwill a sense of wanting to nurture and
nourish because what's deep inside of us
is both nourishing and nourishable and this wonderful reciprocity the very
same place that can nourish the world nourish ourselves
is also the place that can be nourished it's almost it can nourish itself this
wonderful reciprocity and one of those qualities that come
from this place is compassion a a and as I've been saying there's many
different forms of compassion different ways that different people experience it
so you have to when someone teaches about compassion you have to translate it into your own what into your own words
your own sense your own experience
but a place of tenderness tender that place that nourishes
and is nourished nourished
the place that wants to nourish care for a young child or a kitten or
even a plant when I was a gardener in the monastery
I had very strong parental feelings for the plants in the garden and how to walk
around the garden when the morning work period began and just kind of gaze
up on all the plants for quite a while just go around and look at them check them out as if they were kind of like my
children to see if they were all okay and how were they and I had a kind of tender feeling inside
this place of nourishing and being nourished
and so to um and to feel this nourishing and being
nourished surprisingly enough in the presence of suffering
the presence of knowing and the challenges that we have and other people have
knowing perhaps it accompanying people
being a companion and suffering and their challenge is sometimes one of
the greatest supports we can give someone as they want to find their own way through it
and a wonderful feeling of being available to help
wanting to help if the help is wanted in this feeling of being open and
available without a need to help
without forcing ourselves on of other people to help them
be available if the invitation is there if it's clearly wanted
so all this points to a place inside a sensibility a Feeling
and intention in idea and Imagination
thoughts of Good Will and compassion
so taking a posture assuming a posture
and as you assume a meditation posture do it kindly and compassionately
this body of ours is where there's a lot of challenges
and to dip into our bodily experience
with care and assume a posture for meditation that
is right for you
and gently closing your eyes
and perhaps if it's available to you
to connect to your way of
being tender or nourishing or caring
whether it's a feeling or thoughts an image
and with that sense of care tenderness to
gently take a few long slow deep breaths
as if these breaths are the most important valuable caring things you can do
and exhaling a long caring relaxing breath there
as if the exhale is emptying you of your difficulties
can as if the exhale is connecting you more fully solidly
to your body here
and if it's comfortable for you taking a deep breath in
exhaling a slow and long breath and then lingering at the end of the out
breath maybe releasing more fully
for a moment in the end of the out breath allow yourself just to be
maybe you can even feel the physiological
drive to care for yourself that is
to begin breathing in again
the process of breathing
is sustaining your life it's a way in which your body cares for
you
and then to
let your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale relax in different parts of your body
release the holding
but as you relax through whatever degree you can
maybe do it with a generosity of caring
not foreseeing not even expecting things to relax
but offering your body a chance to soften and relax
especially if you can do so with a caring attitude
and then simply being with your breathing
perhaps with a feeling of relaxing or softening all around the inhale
all around the sensations of your body they come into play as you inhale
as if receiving those Sensations around it is a field
of softness of caringness
and if as you exhale the sensations are returning
to a place that invites that's inviting the exhale
a place of tenderness place that is both nourished and
nourishing
and to continue breathing and maybe you're breathing with
compassion with
care
The Compassion which includes the feeling of generosity
not expectation not anything required
this place of tenderness
in place of thoughts of well-wishing
as if the experience of the body breathing are like waves of compassion
the inhale it's like waves walking washing up across the sand
the exhale the waves returning to the ocean
waves of compassion washing over you
relaxing the thinking mind quieting your thinking
compassion a place of inner nourishment
inner nourishing
you might very gently as you exhale
say to yourself the word compassion
or care or tenderness
both to let their thinking mind become quieter
into be reminded of this place within
to touch in again to this place within of compassion
perhaps allowing a sense of generosity to come with the compassion
the generosity that allows you to do this just the way it is for you
how it works for you or that it should or needing to make it look like something
just whatever way is easy for you to touch into
your capacity for Compassion Care
saying the word compassion and saying it like you're dropping a
pebble into a lake middle of the lake
in the ripples concentric ripples radiate outward
across the lake so let your compassion be the pebble and
dropping into your heart and concentric circles of warmth of care
radiate out from you out into the world
maybe with each breath each exhale
dropping the pebble compassion each inhale
the radian spreads outward into the world
and as your compassion radiates beyond the edges of your body
Beyond those edges of your body your compassion is no longer about you
compassion becomes free from self and self-concern
and appreciate that freedom of compassion that simply radiates
in a way that's no longer about you it's free of self
just the radiance
and then to feel perhaps how
the radiance of compassion that sense of warmth or goodness
caringness that somehow spreads beyond the edges of
the body
is nourishing for you
because it comes from a place that's both nourishing and nourished
and how beyond the edges of your body it's not about you yourself
free of self and how preoccupation with self
diminishes this nourishing place of tenderness of care
compassion as it radiates Beyond out into the world
can be a form of freedom from self freedom from
self rumination self preoccupation
freedom from self-criticism and self-belittlement
the simple generosity of compassion
the compassion for others is a freedom from what diminishes us
with self-preoccupation and to see if you can now turn your
attention out into the world of people who
struggle who suffer maybe the people struggling with covet 19.
the people who are sick some are dying
the medical staff and other caregivers
for those who have coveted and to allow your radiance
of Good Will of tenderness of care of compassion
spread out to all the people touched with covet 19.
and let your compassion touch them as well
as if all you need to do is to
know them and know their suffering and challenges
be a companion in a Ally
wishing them well
may all beings all people who have covid-19 and
all people who are caring for those with covet 19.
may they be free of suffering
may they be free of fear
may they be free of any hostility whatsoever
may they receive the care the best care available
and more so may they receive the best love and care compassion
that we're able to offer each other as human beings
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings be free of Oppression
may all beings be free of hatred
from others and from themselves
may all beings be at peace at ease
may they be nourished by the goodness that exists in this
world
[Music] foreign
so this is the last talk on compassion
and
the Buddhist concept of karuna the word that often translated as
compassion in the early Buddhist tradition
the reference point for this karuna is meditation practice meditation
where we become free of the hindrances where we become free of clinging and
hatred where we become free of preoccupation
and with that the free free of obligation free of idealism
free of all these things that keep us kind of locked in or limited or
or close down or agitated
and so what is it that gets born out of that that has to do with caring for the
suffering of oneself and the suffering of the world with that reference point what is the
flavor and the character of compassion that has a quality of Freedom within it
and certainly if we can have the X many of us can have the experience of being touched in a compassionate way in
a caring way for others and to feel in the very movement of
compassion a kind of something opens up something different than self-concern or
the usual reference points for me and you and yourself and other operate
and uh I don't know if this story touches this for you but it does for me
the story of I don't know if it's a true story but maybe that doesn't matter
it was in Washington DC on a very uh beautiful spring day with
some of the great trees flowering big white beautiful white flowers and
beautiful blue sky and crisp and clear air and
any kind of everyone kind of delighted by the freshness of it all
and a person uh who goes to work every day walked by walks by a man who sits on the
sidewalk with a begging with a cup a blind man
hoping for some change Spirit change and on that day the person that was
walking by noticed that there was no money in the person's cup
and so the passerby asks can I make a sign for you
and the blind man said yes so he wrote a sign and put it propped it
up against the cup and went on to work and coming back at
the end of the day the man was still sitting there and now there was money in the cup and
and he stopped and said How's it you know how's it going and the blind man said oh it's going great I've never
received so much before what did you write on the sign
and um Pastor by said I wrote
today is a beautiful day and I'm blind
and for some people our sense of common Humanity our sense
of empathy and understanding of what that means that here
many people who have sight are really enjoying something special and unique and vibrant and alive and something
which is a uplifting a beautiful day and the person who's blind maybe can
smell the freshness of the day but can't see the Blue Sky the flowers the
I can see it touches something in US and that and wanting to extend ourselves
for such a person to support such a person to write a sign to offer some support money maybe
something something in about that movement is not no longer about self
especially if we're coming out of meditation and we're not so busy and
self-preoccupied and caught up in ideas and thoughts what should be and shouldn't be there's something that that opens in US
oh of course you know I feel for this person or I
have compassion or I'm with this person I'm
and that movement I would like to propose and to care for this kind of situation
someone else like this for it to be karuna this coming out of
kind of like out of meditation or the similar places that way is nourishing for the person
that's offered to and it's nourishing for the person who gives it
that nourishing and being nourished are the same thing and to have that as the reference point
for compassion and so we're looking for that or we're being careful if it's not
that if we don't feel nourished then we're probably operating under
obligation Duty big should a kind of maybe even a harshness inside you Gil
you're supposed to be compassionate better do it now and otherwise you'll be you know somehow a bad person
but to but to feel to really recognize and know in oneself deeply what it's
like to be nourished and nourishing and that can be for oneself
but also in our relationship to the world around us to be generous and that
be a kind of a nourishment for ourselves to be have Good Will and have that be nourishing for ourselves and to have
compassion and not be nourishing for ourselves so this karuna then has a very close
relationship to Liberation or freedom in Buddhism the more free we become in
meditation or in other ways the the more we have a reference point
for understanding the Simplicity and the clarity the beauty of compassion
that helps us become happy a certain kind of happiness
when happiness is not really the appropriate or what because the
tragedies of the world are so big there is a response to that tragedy maybe we
don't feel happy but we there's a nourishment in it there's a Radiance of goodness that's there when we don't
get caught up in the thoughts of horror or dismay or or anger agitation or or it
lands on this place of self like oh I have to do something and I'm confused and what should I do it's simply this place that always
today is a beautiful day and I'm blind oh that's something in US opens oh oh
let me offer something here let me share something with this person
so um so compassion practices I think Diana
guided you taught you yesterday can be a formal meditation practice as well
so we don't leave the cultivation or that our compassion to chance we can
actually cultivate and develop and let it grow and it's been one of the great gifts of my life is to watch and develop
my sense of compassion I had no idea when I started meditation that it was such a fantastic thing to have
compassion be awakened in in me so possible to do that intentionally and
develop it it's also then one of the great important parts of that is the way in
which compassion both is becomes a form of freedom
and it also it teaches us more about freedom freedom from self freedom from clinging
freedom from hatred freedom from essential desires and comfort freedom from our opinions and
stories freedom from self preoccupation self-attachment
and so this deeper we go with this meditation and compassion and being
nourished by it we're experiencing a nourishing alternative
to the pursuit of central pleasure a nourishing alternative to being caught in stories of whatever
stories we have opinions we have an alternative to self-preoccupation
and it isn't that we let go of self-preoccupation and have nothing we have this place of tenderness and
nourishment Within so the deeper our compassion stronger it
becomes uh it and the more concentrated we become
it then itself sets the stage for the deepest Liberation that Buddhism offers
or points to and that is when the mind is really peaceful at ease settled on itself
then the experience that there can be insight into the nature of things
including the insight into the nature of compassion the insight into the even compassion is
impermanent and inconstant and changing even compassion is something that arises
out of the constructing forces of the mind and the Heart and there's something that is beyond the
constructing forces of the heart and the mind something which Beyond um
uh outside of you know kind of what's in constant and
impermanent and that which is beyond and outside of it is not a thing
but it's the absence of all clinging the absence of all self-preoccupation are
such a radical radical radical absence that it really gets her attention
and really wow it's possible it really is possible after all to experience to have to live
this life without any clinging attachment whatsoever
it's a phenomenal thing to know that and that freedom from clinging itself
clears the clears the dust in a sense from our hearts from the windows of our
hearts that now it's so much easier to have
compassion it's so much easier to have love because there's no there's no smudges
there's no there's no dust there's no nothing in the way of that tenderness
that warmth being touched by the world and the heart touching the world
and so we find that there's a whole new level of what compassion can be after
some really deep Letting Go it happens so compassion can be part of the path to
letting go because it really is supportive and helps us relax and and
can be very compelling to really kind of settle into a strong sense of compassion
and then it can also then be the the stepping stone for a deep releasing that
goes on and for the Buddha then once a person has experienced deep release
and then the heart is open and compassion is awoken in a greater way
then the Buddha's instructions is go forth for the go forth out into the world for the welfare of humans and gods
for the welfare and happiness of all beings in other words live
caring for this world live for the welfare of the world and not because we should
I feel it's because that's what the heart wants to do and that acting on the compassion is
extremely important thing to do not act on our compassion impulses is a
kind of restriction is it kind of closing down is it kind of diminishing or even sometimes even a kind of a
wounding of ourselves that if we have an Impulse for compassion act on it
it's a it's a feedback loop there too that the more we act on compassion and
this is pure compassion as we can the more the compassion then feeds back to us and supports us
and um just the idea of compassion and the thought that I am compassionate
just that only the meditation and compassion it really short changes us it's in the enactment of compassion that
compassion really comes to fulfillment to completion
so um and if you and sometimes the practice of
compassion is to practice acting as if you have compassion knowing very well
you're acting as if but sometimes acting as if evokes and
awakens up and clears the space for an innate compassion capacity of compassion to grow and develop and and catch up
catch up to what we're actually acting out
so the Brahma vihara of compassion one of their great
gifts and Treasures of this tradition of practice of the Buddhism and may it
be that you treasure whatever capacity for compassion karuna
that you have hint so that you have touched into treasure it value it make
room for it may it take may it have a strong place in your life
and may you benefit from that and may you benefit all beings from that
thank you