wanting they want to respond any thoughts that you'd be willing to share you need more time to think or
great
up nope there you go hello yeah okay hi i'm steve i'm been in redwood city for a
long time watching you know gill for maybe three or four years and haven't made it yet
okay i usually watch the second half of his lecture and kind of don't do the meditation in the first half
and i've done a lot of meditating but it's something called intuitive medicine where you do like chakras and clearing
and grounding and symbols and all this active meditation stuff okay i just kind of wanted to
just enjoying gil for so long see the other side of just a real still quiet buddhist oriented meditation and
learn it and just be more proactive with the group awesome thank you
somebody else willing to grab the mic yes
thank you um my name is nancy and uh
i've been coming here for a while um and uh
i guess i've been meditating for a few years consistently but sometimes i still feel like i don't know
what i'm doing so it's always great to um to uh
to come to an intro to meditation class so i'm pretty excited you guys are offering
this great nancy thank you so much for being here
hi yeah it works my name is sveta and
i've also been following along with gail and the imc for a number of years now
and i'm here to support my friend who is here and
i'm just i don't know it's an excuse to come to the imc and i love this course i
love intro and i think as gil says um if you're not
how does he put that an intermediate or advanced meditator is
just a good beginner yes that's very beautiful yeah thank you thank you for
doing it thank you so i'm just asking people if they'd
share a couple words about why they're here what they're hoping for
hi um my name's nadia and i'm i'm sveta's friend
so it's my first time and i'm here and i've just been doing a
little bit of meditation here and there mostly just for my mental health so beautiful yep and so you've been
practicing vipassana nope nope okay great what kind do you
know what kind of meditation you've practiced um i've listen i did this five-week series thing
through imc um just listening to the audio dharma i'm not quite blanking on that name
of what it was but yeah well if it was through here it was vipassana okay yeah that's probably everything yes
great anybody else willing to share great
thank you hi i'm linda hi linda i'm here at the invitation of my daughter i was
here once before um i actually used to meditate um daily
and then for some reason when i moved to a different apartment i just got out of the habit of doing it
interestingly enough i didn't do it at all during the pandemic which i probably should have anyway when
she invited me to come i decided it was the nudge that i need to get back to doing a practice beautiful here i am
thank you and did you do this kind of vipassana meditation in the past i did it
with deepak chopra on on a video great yeah perfect great okay anyone else
i'll just say great i can go hi i'm carlin linda's daughter hi carlin
and i have really picked up mindfulness meditation
over the course of the pandemic moving forward i honestly started with an app
on my phone and started a practice in the mornings as i was working to help
with the stress related to the pandemic and this past january i had the pleasure of
going down to baja and doing a retreat a seven day retreat where we did a mindfulness practice
every morning with a gentleman who told me about imc
and and so i had uh just a wonderful experience there and then came came back here and wanted to start
to incorporate more into my practice and it's taken me a while to actually get here but um was able to do a session with with
gil or a sit with gil a couple weeks ago and heard about this intro and great was happy to to come and learn more great
beautiful and then richard can you just check the youtube chat to see if anyone on youtube has a particular
reason they're here that that you could read out loud for us
okay okay great all right so
any other kind of different reason for being here
and maybe there'll be more time for those questions and answers or things to be brought up so
i guess i should kind of shift into orienting and starting i'm tanya weiser
i'm happy to be here really grateful for your presence it feels pretty a significant shift actually for
imc to be opening back up and starting to offer the intro class again and
and i'm really really excited to be a part of that and hoping to support
more of it and more community um and uh
just a heads up too that there's a couple other follow-ups we'll be offering um
a day long for intro will happen in september on the 10th and then
there'll be a second series following this one about establishing your practice so we'll we'll just sort of keep building
and see where we go but i'm glad you're here and um hope that it supports you right um
making it real i think you know the connection real the song gorilla and
so i want to just say a couple words about imc insight meditation center so
you know this is a buddhist center in vapasana tradition
and within the kind of origins of vipassana all teachings are offered by donna
meaning generosity so this whole center because of our founding teacher gil franztal is
completely devoted to everything being offered freely
so there is not a single employee of insight meditation center no one gets paid to do anything here
and at you the community has paid for and pays for everything
all the costs of insight meditation center so it's completely because of people's
generosity and time and love and finances that we exist
you're a part of it if you want to be a part of it there's no membership other than that so
i think it's pretty profound i actually just feel a sense of shivers in myself because it to me it is such a profound
thing to be a part of and to offer so i invite you to be comfortable
there are restrooms there are cushions there's kodo is going to talk about sitting
posture and you can use the equipment here so please make yourself comfortable
and i hope you feel welcome totally welcome
included part of so
um yeah maybe
maybe now koto you could say a few words about just introducing yourself and yeah
yeah sure thank you tanya can everyone hear me okay if you need as we go along there are
hearing assisted devices just around the corner if that's useful for you um
yeah my name is kodo coto conlon i live in san francisco so i i travel
down here to be with all of you i take a lot of joy and insight meditation fibasana practice
this tradition i've been practicing meditation for about 20 years
and that has added up to a lot of hours a lot of wrong turns which turned out to
be right turns i hope we all have such good fortune
i think the thing i want to communicate at the beginning just to echo something tanya just said
is yeah inviting you to be comfortable in the space whatever that whatever that takes for you
um finding your way being comfortable in the body while we're here together because i think that supports
us being together in community and i think uh one of the one of the benefits to all of us being here
together and being here online is that we have other people we're going through this course with
and uh connecting starting starting to make those relationships as we want to
so i think that's all for me great so i'll just say a couple more
words and then koto will do posture um
so you're here to learn mindfulness practice
mindfulness meditation so it is from buddhism
buddhism cannot exist without mindfulness but mindfulness can exist without
buddhism so there's no requirement for you to be a buddhist to be here or to practice
you can have any other spiritual or non-spiritual beliefs and practice
mindfulness okay so permission you don't need to agree
with it you know any philosophy or approach it's about a
practice and it's a direct practice it's a practice that supports us in
connecting right and connecting with our inner experience with more depth
and our outer experience with more ease connection depth ease
and the practice helps us gain choice
and reduce our reactivity so the invitation as much as possible is
to be comfortable to allow to know what's happening as it's happening
so this is why we're emphasizing you know this idea of it's okay to be in
your body it's okay to sit however you need to sit it's okay for whatever thoughts and
feelings to come up and we're practicing being with in a connected and non-reactive way to our
experience so that's what will grow it's kind of the big thing will grow
all right coda you want to guide us on sitting posture it might be helpful if i use the earlier
switch big invitation as we go along discovering uh the
posture for the next 10 minutes if you need more supplies you probably saw them on the way in we have cushions
blocks benches right around the end of the what was probably a stage here
and of course cheers so as i'm talking if you if you discover something that will support you in uh
finding the posture to help you stay alert and comfortable
for a stretch of 20 minutes 30 minutes then yep please get up and feel free to get
the supplies so a basic definition of mindfulness
to start with is a clear stable
non-judgmental awareness that's attentive
attentive to what's happening now clear and stable
not entangled at all and there's something actually that we're going to we're going to express
that with our bodies we're going to express clarity stability and balance
a couple of different ways we can go about the finding the basic postures i'm going to talk about sitting on the floor
sitting in a chair and i'll even i'll mention lying down practice which i i did for about a year
so maybe let's say something about uh the sitting on the floor first since
i'm here so have what she needs
great great um well there are certainly some some
benefits to sitting on the floor and then it lowers your center of gravity and can give you a wide base
i want to say before i begin talking about sitting on the floor perfectly
perfectly wonderful to sit in a chair for meditation i love that the the images the mythology
of the future buddha he's sitting in a chair so you're in you're in good company if you're if you set meditation in a chair
so regarding regarding all postures the most important thing
is an alert spine an upright spine that's both
energetic and allows the body to relax there's really something about
having a having a spine that's balanced on itself in such a way that the body is alert
that all the the muscles can start to balance and let go and release
so some particular pointers i'll be brief with the the time that we have
sitting on the floor everything starts with the base everything needs a foundation for your
spine to be upright and alert we have something like a tripod down here
but uh one point is the the sit bones on the cushion if you're on if you're on a
cushion sitting on the front third can be helpful to get the spine to align the in a comfortable way
there there are any number of cross-legged postures but uh a balanced one we recommend is
one leg in front of the other called taylor fashion or burmese fashion uh this can this is this both helps to
be symmetrical and also doesn't put too much torque on the knees or on the hips
and i invite you as we go through to feel free to play around with these different postures as we go through the five weeks like really spend some time
finding what works for you something i'll say if the hips and the knees are really tight
in order to help lower the knees it can be helpful to raise the hips so sometimes i'll sit on two cushions
and it raises this situation or
sometimes a knee doesn't want to come down but we need the we need the weight of the leg transferring to the floor so
put something underneath if you're going to support if you're going to support a knee
something to exp something to experiment with or something to make note of is that you you want to try to have the
the hips above the knees if the uh if the knees are above the hips it makes the back of the
the low back sort of turn out i love seeing everyone moving moving around and trying this out so yeah
please feel free
i'm going to show you another posture and then we'll move up from there so
great you're welcome to grab these two yeah
great crepe
so
i appreciate that so much so
finding a finding a a way for your lower body to be arranged such that
the spine can be upright and alert
it may be cross-legged let me show you another base posture before i sort of build the rest of the posture up and
that is you may sit kneeling like so where you turn
one of these cushions up like a wheel and sit like sit like this
that may be that may be more balanced
experiment please do yeah this will take some time
so finding finding the base finding the base that supports the spine to be upright
the shoulders can roll back
the hands we say can do can do anything where they're symmetrical a lot of people will
do palms down on the thighs palms up is fine
very traditionally we'll have one palm one hand on top of the other with the thumb tips and fetch in front
of the low belly whatever works for you something you want to look out for when
placing the hands is to to not place them in such a way that your shoulders get pulled forward
trying to maintain that front back balance is really important otherwise a real strain a real strain comes to the
back so this can help with that
resting your hand on a pillow nice [Music]
so from here one way you can really get into an upright position is once your base is settled you can sort of lift
yourself off the seat and let your spine grow nice and long
and then lower back down and doesn't your spine feel just a little bit longer
straighter the chin we say is just barely tucked
another way to think about this is putting some space in the the the last vertebrae under the skull so
the chin is tucking just like this to give some space up here
in this tradition we sit with the eyes closed if you're comfortable if you've trained in another way with eyes open
that's fine too mouth is closed um
i like to say relax the tongue i keep it uh keep it at the
uh the contact with the pallet the top but soft soft
i find if there's tension in the mouth there's all this tension in the face and the neck that can develop
one thing to check as you're establishing the posture is does your head feel balanced
like feel around is your head square on your shoulders or the ears line are the ears lined up
with the shoulders in such a way that your your back muscles can relax
wonderful so a thought or two about sitting in a chair
oh sure yeah yeah go ahead
how important is it to sit without back support oh that's fabulous thank you for the question
um i can say it's it can be really helpful
to sit without back support in the sense that it helps support the the attitude
of uh independence self-reliance
i it may be good to know that i uh i sit with a back injury
so very often can i have your support cushion very often i'll need a little something
in my at my low back so on a chair still try to keep try to
keep the feet flat on the floor if you can have your knees a little lower than your hips or right at the
same level but sometimes i'll tuck just a little support back here it really helps the really helps the low
back i try to minimize how much i lean lean on this so if i if my back feels
healthy and i don't need the support i'll actually sit on the edge of the chair
or something like this that feels really comfortable if you need back support all the way up
which sometimes sometimes that's necessary you can roll up a towel or
put one of these in half and put it along the spine such that the shoulder blades can still
relax back so i hope that responds to the question
on youtube
so those are some of the basics of posture the upright alert spine
having the sitting base established hands not pulling the shoulders forward
everything sort of aligned and opened love this hillary hillary's helping with
a posture clinic of sorts if at any point as we go along or in any of the breaks if you have questions about your
posture we can we can certainly address them it's really well worth investing in the time
to determine the posture that works for you it can make all the difference in uh establishing a practice in a a
more useful way yeah so i think with that go back to tanya for a while
you feel comfortable right now where you're at in your postures
okay and uh i think i'll just say one more thing about posture which is um
you know it's it's okay to be a little bit uncomfortable
and it's important to respect your body right
so if you're if you have an injury or if
you're afraid you're starting to hurt yourself just take a breath recognize it's important to move
and move with consciousness with awareness to change your posture
don't make yourself stay because you're not supposed to move
meditation we're teaching and in this environment it's like a gym right to grow and
strengthen our mind and our mindfulness but we want to do this in all of our lives really to be more aware
so it's not that we have to not move we don't want to hurt ourselves it is possible to cause injuries to ourselves
if we overdo it in a posture so nerve damage can happen
it's not common but i've known people who've had it happen so it's important to
to not feel like you have to you know sit through pain a lot of pain okay
we'll talk later maybe when we do the body about working with pain
to support people who do have injuries or just physical pain
so now i want to shift and talk a little bit about how to prepare the mind
because we're preparing our bodies which is also supporting and preparing
our mind but when we come to practice when we come to practice meditation
it is helpful to do things to orient the mind to prepare the mind
before you actually begin to formally sit so some of the things that i'm thinking
of naming you know for you tonight is just
number one please give yourself permission to have any and every experience you
have tonight so whatever thought comes up whatever
mood whatever feeling please give yourself permission
to to know it right to have it that
it's not about sitting down to try and create an experience
it's about learning how to show up for the experiences happening does that make
sense so i asked earlier about kind of expectations or why you were here
and so just take a moment and just maybe reflect a little more deeply
and you know a lot of times people start to practice because they're suffering
so maybe one of the reasons you're here is that you don't want to be so anxious or you
don't want to be so depressed or because you don't want to say stupid things
anymore or you know you or maybe you want to be free you maybe have a deep aspiration
for freedom so those things are all really important
um they can support your practice held in the right way
no but no mud no buddha right no suffering no freedom
you know we we can use all of our experiences to help support our awakening
and if we sit down with an agenda we will suffer more right if we're trying to make
ourselves be different have a different experience
we're not going to find much peace so
our our minds works in a way that
it weaves together all of our different sense experiences that are happening in the moment coupled
with our memories from the past and the learnings that we have and our beliefs and perceptions all of the stuff
in our mind is a weaver and it weaves it all together
so much so that you know if we uh are often going along we don't we don't
we're not even aware of all the separate pieces and things that are that are feeding the experience
we're having we might not even know that part of the experience that we're
having is actually based on past or expectation instead of what's really happening in the moment
we may not even know that so one of the ways that we go about learning
to practice mindfulness is that we break apart
parts of our experience so the first and we start to learn more about each
part we get intimate with it so that we become much more familiar
with how that flows in us how that shows up for us how it influences us
and over time we become increasingly attuned to these different aspects of
our experience this week the first week we start with mindfulness of breathing
as our primary kind of investigation
next week it will be body and so the work you do between now and
next week will be on breath and that work will lead and support
working on body awareness and then the third week we'll start to focus on emotions
so the breath and body will support your ability to be more mindful of emotions
fourth week will be the mind for thoughts
and again we're we're building we're building and we're also helping ourselves
get intimate with each aspect they're all interrelated i don't mean that they're not interconnected
but we can attune more finely to each one independent from the others
so tonight this week it's going to be about the breath
this thing that our bodies know how to do the first thing that we did
when we were born and the last thing that we'll do
on this life is to exhale in this world it's our longest companion
and it's a changing experience and it's much easier
for the mind to tune into something that's variable than to try and
pay attention to something that's unchanging relatively unchanging
so when um when you're doing certain kinds of uh
there's something called emdr a kind of therapy and you're stimulating the bilaterally
the brain if you have this stimulation it might be a tap
tap tap if it goes tap tap tap tap tap
same speed doesn't take very long for the brain to absolutely ignore it
it stops being input because it's no longer
causing the mind to pay attention to it because it's been figured out and it doesn't need to be attended to
so i say this to emphasize how important it is
to be tuning in to something that has some degree of flow and change in it that that's part of what helps
our minds stay connected just because of how we're wired
just because of how we're wired
so i just want to we're going to sort of glide into a meditation here as i'm
offering these instructions you might notice i'm slowing down am i talking
invitation is to sort of let things come to more of a stillness
so finding your body maybe acknowledging okay here i am we're
at imc oh whoa fast forward we actually have gone through the posture introduction we're gonna meditate
okay a couple of deep breaths can be a nice
support nice reset for the start of a meditation
feeling the support of your feet if they're on the floor your bottom if it's
on a chair
and if it's comfortable you might try shutting your eyes and if
it's not no problem you can gaze
typically we say a few feet in front of you on the floor or it's some sort of
blank bland object so your eyes can just sort of gaze there
so just taking a second to see what you can notice here
as you just receive your experience
maybe making the breath the star of the show
a little spotlight of awareness on the experience of breathing
noticing if it's long or short
fast or slow
just being curious curious about the experience of breath
noticing if there's a difference between the inhale and the exhale
and we can feel the breath in the body in a lot of different places
maybe noticing first how you experience breathing in your
nose
noticing perhaps in the throat
the chest
and the belly
receiving the language of the body which is sensations
receiving the massage of the breath as it comes in and goes out
and then just seeing where you are most aware of the breathing where it's most natural for you to feel the breath
and wherever it's easiest just sort of resting in that space
maybe relaxing a little bit more
you might think about yourself as a naturalist
somebody who's very committed to non-harming and
observing nature not there to make anything happen or
change anything but to be a beautiful witness
to take in the beauty of the nature the life
with this reverence with this sense of respecting
the life which is what we experience with breath life
so with the mind and the heart of a naturalist
just being attuned to breathing as it's occurring
in this body in this moment in this place
and how this breath is
and the next breath
and when because it will be a win when the mind
maybe catches you and carries you downstream in a thought
there's a precious moment when we recognize that's happening
when awareness is aware of thinking
we don't need to go anywhere we don't need to change anything or try and chase the thought away
see if you can't breathe with it
breathe through it and in time maybe the breath will become
in the center spotlight again being patient and kind
breathing just breathing
breathing with
and if it's hard to stay with a breath
it can be helpful to think about maybe a three-breath journey
just seeing if you can stay connected to three breaths in a row
feeling the beginning of the breath the ending the in-between
the new breath riding it like you might ride a surfboard on a wave
just three breaths little journey
and we're coming to the end of our practice not leaving it but but coming to the end
i invite you just to see how you can gently
feel intimately your next few breaths
i'm just resting as you hear the bell no need to quickly change
allowing yourself a slow and slow re-including of other
experience
just just noticing if anything has changed
just tuning in to feel of the vibration level the
energy the mind the heart what what feel what do you notice
is it different are you more connected are you uncomfortable and need to move
your body please feel free to take care of yourselves and we're going to shift into
a mining and question and answer looking for
the invitation to share a little bit about your experience what you noticed and
as you do it's an act of generosity to share it helps others
find and feel into their own experience so please take a little stretch
yeah maybe i'll take a drink of water
okay so we do have the microphones it is very
very helpful if you'll use them these talks are recorded and we are on
youtube right now so it's uh for the benefit of others that are listening that we speak into
the microphones and um yeah first maybe
what did you notice you were a little naturalist
in the wilderness of breathing what can you tell us about your
observations there's a microphone right
there thank you so much
my name is isabelo campo and
i for for a long time my life i've been trying to find a practice
and i did find myself meditating some years ago but then
i just move on into different things and things are fine in my life
but um again i've been questioning myself every day of
what am i doing is this ad is there more to my life
and i'm very grateful that i'm here today
and for a long after so long i was able to
just be just breathe and i did notice that
i had the need to take this really deep profound breath
and it was like coming from my heart it was i feel relief
[Music] this is my experience beautiful
anybody else thank you anyone wants to share
just
um i noticed how active my mind was beautiful nancy
and then after a while it was kind of like the the rhythm of the breath was
primary but the mind was still you know active more in the background
so i didn't necessarily feel
i don't know calm necessarily in the moment but after
the bell rang i noticed that i felt really calm i guess like i felt
my body was so still and i didn't realize that it happened
during the meditation so that was nice so great that you were able to
stay long enough right to feel that to notice that
yeah there was a share from someone online
that said sometimes i feel paralyzed at the end of the meditation is this normal
thank you for the question uh without being able to have a back and forth it's hard to know just what you
mean just just what the specifics are of what you mean by the word paralyzed
but to say something um you know paralyzed can have connotations
of fear also have a feeling of actually
physically not being able to move which may last for some time and
i wonder how long it lasts if i could talk to you that's one of the things i would ask
and what do you notice what do you notice about that transition
paralyzed can also have this other connotation which we just heard from nancy which is stillness
which may actually be something really wholesome so it's it's hard to parse without the
without a little bit of conversation um
i would say i would suspect that uh there's a there's a gradual coming back into sort of full contact with the body
that's that's happening and uh it's perfectly perfectly normal for
some of the machinery to start to power down while we meditate
and then it's good to be in touch or in contact with a teacher or an experienced meditator who can
help just gently gently keep you safely on the path that's what i would say to that
thank you um
i am going through some airway issues and breathing issues so it's been interesting um
it's extremely hard for me to do it which is a little bit upsetting but
you know want to keep trying yeah and so um and some people have
you know paying attention to breathing is triggering so you know that's where we'll
be talking about the body and so this week if it's just too much to do the breathing
just just tune into your body and we'll talk more about that next week but sensations move too right there's
there's ways to find that like the breath right because it's moving is a good object but you can pay
attention to the sense of sitting to feeling the sensations in your body
yeah
hello thank you der sanga my name is holly um
okay so when i first started my practice 11 years ago
i was so restless i couldn't focus on the breath i couldn't do mindfulness of the
breath so i had to learn love and kindness meditation
and samadhi with like visual objects i think they're called like nemitas or
something like colors or a candle flame or so i haven't even
bothered with mindfulness of the breath until today and now that i've calmed myself through
so much samadhi and loving-kindness [Music] i've finally
experienced the richness of the breath meditation but that's also to say that you don't
have to focus on your breath that's right beautiful and focus on
love for others visual objects yep
yep and so respecting respecting our each of us our own path
right whether it's we have body challenges breath challenges
you know all kinds of things so listening listening to what you know
what what will work talking asking questions there's a question from youtube that
i'll read and then we'll we'll start to shift into a second set
of instructions but boy this was so rich i wish we had more time right
do you feel so much benefit of hearing people share their experience
tremendous tremendous and so we'll also be around after the class formally ends
we'll hold the container but if there's anything else that you want more support around or want to
share afterwards we'll be here okay so
this this is a question thank you from youtube it's reads in zen students work with
teachers closely one-on-one and do such regular meetings happen in
mindfulness meditation and so the answer to that would be probably the simplest
answer is to come to day-long retreats where it says
there will be discussions with teachers to sign up for
there is one i mentioned scheduled for september 10th and we will be offering
you know discussions with students during that time
so day long's half days with gil or other teachers here on wednesdays is a
time to get to talk to a teacher about your practice they're short
10 15 minutes you just kind of go in you have a particular thing like
you know that you're struggling with and you get a little bit of advice for practice and you go practice
retreats are set up so that you get um and you know group and sometimes
individual um discussion times with teachers so within this tradition those
are the primary ways that you get that kind of guidance and feedback and
coming to a class like this where there's question and answer as well yeah okay coda i'm going to hand you this
little handy-dandy little microphone thanks
as we do a transition if you want to stand up again and shake it out or if you're comfortable you're welcome to you're welcome to keep
your seat but just want to give that as an option because we've been still and seated for a long time
all right
so there's this old teaching story
speaking of students and teachers this old teaching story of a student going to a teacher and asking what's the
essence of the practice and the teacher writes on a piece of paper
one word attention then holds it up shows it and the student goes is that all
and then the teacher takes the paper back and writes attention attention it shows them the shows them the paper
actually attention over and over again
again this uh this basic notion of mindfulness that's going to travel with us across the weeks and through our
practice to notice
just what's happening while it's happening
just to notice if it's pleasant or it's unpleasant just to notice and for this week
establishing and nurturing this connection between attention
and the breathing body the attention and the sensations of breathing
and this doesn't um it's not limited to our cushion what we're going to talk about right now is establishing a daily practice
finding your practice at home
something that experience tells us is that in order to develop the skill
of paying attention to what's happening while it's happening and to sort of experience the pleasures
that come through the practice and the sense of integrity and healing and goodness
or getting in touch with something really deep in ourselves it's very helpful to to do the practice
daily so the encouragement the encouragement for
these five weeks is to sit each day if you can um i want to talk a little just give a
couple of things for you to consider as you're establishing a daily practice one
can be really helpful to do a conscious reflection at the beginning and at the end
particular way that we're going to suggest here at the beginning
very very helpful to enlist the whole mind and body by saying
or saying or thinking to yourself deliberately setting the intention now i'm going to be
attentive and mindful for this period of time it's really remarkable how much that
sort of aligns the system just by making that simple intention for yourself
and then um along with that intention making the intention to for the for the time being
for the say 20 minutes of your practice i'm going to let go of my preoccupations
the important ones will be right there for me when i'm done right there or they'll or they'll
accompany me during the during the whole set but at least i have that intention
so that's the beginning of the setting at the end of the sitting
very helpful to to take half a minute just to reflect on how it
went just to reflect on what happened it's not a it's not so much a time to evaluate or criticize or or anything
like that but just to take the moment to sort of knead the water back into the
dough this is what happened this was the mindfulness that i had this is how this experience went
in addition to that just like we were hearing in the in the
q a a few minutes ago everyone has their their path that's unfolding for them
through their own body and mind all of us also have
our own home with its unique
characteristics your context is going to present its uh its own little its own little challenges some of them we have
in common um
i mentioned the home because it it it's ideal to have a place in your home
where you always do your sitting if you have the space have that one spot kind of out of the way so
people aren't walking by you it's pretty quiet if that's possible so that when you go to sit down
you have the best chance of being not disturbed for that amount of time
um i have found it really helpful to do
meditation in the morning there's something about the machinery of the mind starting to click on if i if i get
involved with the phone or i start reading the news or if i get into the first activity of the day
where it's actually harder for the mind to collect into mindfulness so i i try to do it first thing in the
morning if i can other people have a different system where it it's almost like the the mind
and body naturally coalesce into mindfulness or collectedness in the late afternoon
or in the evening so feeling to feel into what's going to work for your own circumstances
let's see something i would like to emphasize
is that it uh if there are other other people who live in your household this is true for many of us
i find it really helpful to have a conversation to sort of in not not enlist them to
hold you accountable or something like i don't want someone saying did you meditate today
but it is really helpful to to let them know of your intention you know i think i'm gonna i think i'm gonna for these
five weeks i'm going to try sitting at such and such a time it would be helpful if we could
if i could have your support in that i found that particularly helpful
so the place the time the intention
i think the one of the takeaways i want to i want to emphasize here is that
[Music] this is a process of experimentation a little bit of trial and error in terms
of time of day and the sort of the sort of um context in which you're practicing
try something out see how it works give it a go make adjustments
and maybe we'll learn something about learn something about how to sustain a practice at home
after five weeks of trying that
we're going to move into another guided meditation
so if you'd like to find your meditation posture again
welcome welcome there's questions if you want to grab a question
yeah go ahead we're just about to do another
so
yay people taking care of themselves
all right finding ourselves again
with an alert upright spine supported by the sitting base
alert spine relaxed wide shoulders
tucked chin and softly closed eyes
returning to this practice that we're emphasizing for the week
sustaining contact between attention
and the sensations of breathing
awareness noticing
and the felt experience of breathing wherever it's most predominant
maybe the nose
maybe the sensations in the throat standing out
maybe it's more easeful now to feel breathing in the whole body
or to let go of the breathing
and be attentive to the sense of sitting just where you are
to sustain contact
one support can be offering
[Music] a very very soft note or a label
that coincides with the breathing say on the inhale in
perhaps on the exhale out
or if you are noticing the breathing in the chest or in the belly
you may note rising with the sensations of rising
falling with the sensations of falling
it doesn't have to be the right word
but just a very simple very soft thought
to help keep you here
in this particular practice
to be attentive to the breathing just as it is naturally
to be a naturalist of the in-breath whether it's long or short
a naturalist of the out-breath long or short
just as it is
so
whether the experience is pleasant or unpleasant
just to notice is enough
and with this support the very soft whisper in the mind
rising falling
or if you're aware of the whole body maybe sitting
sitting
in this last minute of this sitting
checking in with yourself
tuning in to just how how much effort is needed
to sustain contact here and now
so [Music]
so when you're ready you can open your eyes
so we we introduced a very very uh well-known tool
in this tradition during this sitting some traditions will count the breathing
to help sustain attention and uh this tradition emphasizes using a tiny little
note label almost sounds too substantial to say that it's like can be like a little
puff a little in the mind very very soft
and there's a way that um it enlists the help of the thinking mind
the mind that uh really wants to veer off into its preoccupations
it's like you're you're making an ally of the thinking apparatus
to help you be here and now and attentive
so we have another 10 minutes for sharing questions comments responses
anything that came up
when you started you kind of shared all the recommended postures almost again like the most holistic postures but i noticed
myself fluctuating every minute and is it more important to like just to be comfortable
versus kind of still and regimented in a certain posture sure sure i think both
of those things have their time there's a there's a time for
practicing and cultivating a sort of skill in stillness and
it's really important i think to like ease into that ease into that
um you'll notice when we when we were doing the posture instruction i was sort of delighted when i saw people pop up and
get cushions and move around a little bit like i said it's very very well worth
the time to sort of invest in finding the right posture for you
and i would suggest being very gentle as we move in if your body needs to move
let it move um we're pretty um i'll speak for myself only can be pretty
wound up and there's a lot of unwinding that that has to happen so please please take care
holly has a hand
oh it's okay you've got your mask okay thank you tanya thank you kodo for
this and thank you and um very grateful to be here as well i sometimes i find
that when i'm sitting or i'm trying to meditate i'm just emphasizing on the the effort
rather than being present yeah and as many people noted sometimes it's
posture that i'm thinking about or being comfortable or thinking about things and from
the past or worries of the future that kind of become my problems for right now
so i just sometimes i don't know if my practice is going anywhere
and but i i still persist because i know it's important and i i feel like i have
i have a heightened sense of awareness now but in that awareness i'm like oh gosh
here i go again i'm like let me just try and breathe but then
i know the thoughts don't go away and everything but it's just being okay with it
and all that stuff so thank you everyone can i ask you something yes
you said um you know what's important how do you know
how do you know it's important you know i know it's probably not important and
it's the stuff in my it's the narrative that i've told myself over the years and now i
in the effort of trying to sit with my thoughts and just like just try and see them like passing
clouds i just i get confused because i don't know if it's
my own thinking or the make-believe yeah yeah
yeah you want to say something
sure unless you have a thought you want to give right away go ahead yeah
um what i feel inclined to say one is i saw a lot of heads nodding
i think there's a lot of relating to the kind of experience you're describing um
certainly wondering is this is this going right is this going anywhere
uh but i mean look what's going on in here one of the one of the
one of the paradoxes of mindfulness practice is that as as we begin to be established in
mindfulness we become more aware as we become more aware
more is revealed it may well be actually that things are getting more still for you
but there's more visibility now
possible possible subjectively it may not look that way
i also wanted to highlight that mindfulness of thinking
is advanced practice mindfulness of thinking takes a lot of
practice and i think i think if we if uh
sort of follow along with the instruction and sort of invest the time in each week
having the base of breathing the base of the body the base of mindfulness of emotion which is often
what's fueling some of the thinking then we're in a much better position to be able to relate to thinking skillfully
so uh maybe i want to i want to encourage you and i think um
i think you're coming here was was uh just the right thing
thank you so much the first half day retreat i attended was with judy cannon oh yeah i was
so excited because i was on summer vacation and and i was just like a little hesitant because i'm catholic and
i i practice every week and just you reiterating that it's okay
mindfulness and what was it buddhism don't you can still buddhism needs mindfulness
is required but but mindfulness doesn't need buddhism yeah and i'm glad i can still you know
align myself with both so thank you yeah okay i'm tempted to say one more thing
because there were so many nodding heads and that is you know you don't have to decide if those thoughts are important
or not while you're meditating you don't have to agree with them or disagree with them you don't have to
make them go away um just like respect them
let them be and like gentle like with respect like
as much as you can just okay that and breathing
and breathing oh in this breath just
so that there's not this power struggle yeah okay
say one more thing yeah and then we'll move on i promise
rather than um let's see what can i say there's a there's a possibility
of thinking about breathing in the foreground and letting thinking move its way to the
background without the thinking necessarily having to stop it can kind of be
say if you're sitting sitting next to a stream and you're watching the stream go by and that's your breathing
there can be the sound of the birds are the people walking by behind you on a sidewalk
or the wind in the trees these are the thoughts most of your attention is here in the
foreground and it's okay it's okay the birds don't get in the way of the stream
maybe time for one more and then we'll have to transition
hello again thank you everyone um so i was going to say something about
pain but now i want to say something about my wrist the restlessness thing it was mine pertained to thoughts
and i found some advice from jack cornfield helpful to just say label it
wandering and just patiently go back to the breath over and over no matter how many times it took
and get a new thought wandering and another practice was i'm just labeling
them pleasant unpleasant or neutral thoughts i don't know if that's a good idea or
not but i think he said that was a good idea sure and then
i always talk about pain as if anyone has chronic pain i have it too and what i noticed today
from finally practicing mindfulness of the breath again after so long um
was that the changing postures and changing where i felt the breath allowed me to almost control the amount
of pain i was perceiving from my hand sure so i don't know
it's just an observation it's not like a lesson or something thank you holly
let me okay i can't resist find your big toe with your mind
just bring your awareness into your big toe you don't have to wiggle it just just as much as you can
and if you can't find your big toe find your thumb whatever you can with your awareness
just see what you can sense whether it touches another toe or finger or
coolness or warmth can you feel where the toenail fingernail is versus the bottom of the
toe okay now take a deep breath in and let go of
the toe and feel into your belly
bring your awareness as much as you can into the experience of the belly
see if you can relax it let it fall over your pants
feel the breath expanding in the belly
soft belly
all right in the next exhale let go of the belly
and find the top of your head with your awareness like where that soft spot is when you're
a baby see if you can feel the hairs the individual hairs on your head
your scalp just bringing your awareness there
okay and let go of that what happened to the big toe
when you were paying attention to the top of your head were you aware of your big toe
it disappeared but it didn't so this is the
the commodity that we're working with if you want to call it that is awareness and we can choose where we focus our
awareness that's the practice
right partly is learning to direct and that's why
you notice maybe less pain when you're paying attention to the breathing in a different part of the body we're just
redirecting the energy of awareness what we're taking in
yeah all right koto love it thank
you so to bring us to a close our last couple of minutes
um again tanya and i will be here afterwards if you have something more to share another question comes up
no class would be quite a class without a homework assignment
and we've mentioned most of these already
it's perfectly fine leave the class tonight
don't think about meditation for the whole week perfectly fine and
the way the class is built sequentially you can get a lot of benefit if you practice practice in between as we go
along so we recommend a daily practice start with 20 minutes this week
i'll have to confer with my esteemed colleague about progressive increasing but we'll
talk about that so 20 minutes one time a day
and focus on mindfulness of the breathing as we practiced it there's a there's a handout that's
available online and there are a few there on the end of the stage also that have instructions and also review of
some of the major points second thing
is to choose some routine activity that you do during the day
could be brushing your teeth could be washed washing the dishes walking here or there
and experiment with doing that with a little
mindfulness careful attention so um don't have your radio on in the background
conversation going on just that one thing just this well well it's time to do this
take nothing i think loved washing the dishes
and then the third thing is that similar to the second
extending this mindfulness practice off the cushion because the boundary is arbitrary
between the cushion and everything else in your life tuning into the sensations of the body
while you're doing any normal activity for about half an hour i could try doing that once this week
and see how that goes um
and then after after after tuning in for that half an hour just check in what
happened how was that kind of like the reflections we recommend at the end of the settings is there any change that i notice is
there any bit of well-being here am i more agitated than i was at the beginning
if it's not what you expect that's the path if you're aware enough to notice
you're doing the practice whatever it looks like
i want to extend my thanks to all of you i am really delighted
so nice to be here with you at imc i'm looking forward to getting to know each of you a little bit as we go
um tanya is there anything you would like to say to close you can't do it wrong
okay okay thank you thank you so much
you