okay so hello and welcome everyone to this
rendition of happy hour so so today's happy hour um
i'd like to invite us to consider bringing a perspective of
and the practice of joy to bring more joy into our lives
joy is a very important practice it's it's not
a luxury it's not um oh it's reserved for some and also if
i'm a serious buddhist practitioner oh no i would be really serious i wouldn't have so much joy quite the opposite
actually joy happiness bliss are parts of the path as the buddha has
taught this the path leading to nirvana to liberation to freedom
the steps along the way actually you require the happy heart happiness bliss joy are part
of the path when they're happy when the heart is happy when the mind is is
joyous letting go letting go becomes easier concentration settling of the
mind becomes easier so so um it's actually good for our
practice and also it's good for our humanity joy gladness
is is good um it's good for all of uh for for us and and for others too as we show up in the
world as we serve others and practice is not supposed to be this grim duty
and there is a line that i heard actually recently in
a documentary that i saw i wanted to share with you and the documentary was excellent by the way so highly
recommended the name of the documentary is um is uh jazz fest and new orleans story i
don't know if any of you have seen it yet but i saw it on the plane when i was coming back so whether or not you're
interested in jazz it was a really wonderful documentary about new orleans
and also the challenges that new orleans has had with hurricane katrina and
and also the joy of music and and
musicians creating and there was this line that really caught my attention one of the musicians was saying
that and i forget whom so i can't give him credit life is to be enjoyed not endured
life is to be enjoyed not endured and
that really landed for me especially the word endured because i think sometimes maybe
our perspective or it becomes one of enduring like okay all right suffering or i'm gonna endure
this some more i'm gonna be really loyal to my suffering i'm going to endure
this life and yet we forget about joy we forget about enjoying how can we
bring more joy and and it's not just about hedonic pleasures so that we
we um distract ourselves into oblivion just
enjoying enjoying and not looking at at uh at sorrow and suffering but the
balance is needed the balance is needed not just trying to endure
but also bringing joy gladness and that's what we do happy hour we do try to see
feel into the suffering of course it's there but we bring care we bring love we bring gladness we bring joy we do we do
that so this is a practice we do already but but this is another way to
um [Music] to really look at it you know from from this perspective of this quote
not to be just endured not to just be endured um
but but to have joy to to to cultivate joy so
so with that as the as the frame
as the frame for this practice let's meditate together let's meditate
so i'd like to invite you to to arrive to settle in your seat
arrive in your body
ah to settle here here whatever has happened
all the busyness has come before to let it go
and just arrive here in this moment
here here
here here if the mind is flighty
just with the simple words here very kind
well here sweetheart here just here just here
with this body with these sensations with this breath
just here darling here
you can rest please rest please rest
taking a fume and it's just rest there's no doing to be done
let the heart be quiet and peace at rest
the body just being breathed
the comfort the comfort of taking refuge in this moment
letting go letting go letting go of thoughts
if they come saying thank you thank you not now
as if the breath is the pleasant loving lullaby that's
calming your heart calming the body in this moment
oh dear body to your heart rest rest
rest sweetheart relax it's okay it's okay
it can all wait really
and when you find the mind is wandering thinking
ah smile and relax the body some more let go some
more lean into this moment
with [Music]
ease as if you're stretching you're stretching your arms your limbs like ah
yawning ah landing
arriving stretching into this moment more fully
here here here darling
tell yourself just here
this meditation is not to be endured it is to be enjoyed
see what happens when you drop this reflection into your heart into your body not your head not to think about it
just to drop this in as if you were taking a drop of
color and dropping it
into water ah
let this drop of color imbue this perspective and view your
heart this meditation is not to be endured
it is to be enjoyed see what shifts in your heart and your
body your mind with this
this meditation is not to be endured
it's to be enjoyed to be enjoyed
not to think how it can be enjoyed don't think just drop it in
your mind your body knows what to do just trust just drop it in
and rest and trust
your heart will find its way let yourself be surprised
no thinking or planning just be breathed
can you enjoy being breathed
the breath moving through your abdomen chest your limbs
a sense of solitude delicious
with the breath just here knowing simply knowing this
simple yet sublime
drop in the reflection into your body this meditation
is not to be endured
it's to be enjoyed
having time to yourself precious time
to be silent to be breathed
the support of sangha community
caring caring for yourself
all aspects of care
let yourself enjoy the goodness in all of this
at this simple moment
can this breath this breath be enjoyed
this in-breath this out-breath not just endured
let your mind find the way don't struggle
your mind knows how to do this relax
can the sensations of breathing in the body whatever sensations are arising
even if some are unpleasant can they still be enjoyed to have a body to sense to feel to be
alive
i just endured having a body
can it be enjoyed this process of sitting
sensing glistening
feeling touching
even if you're tired or hungry can all this be enjoyed not just endured
shift in perspective shift in perspective
can this moment of your life right here
simply sitting being breathed meditation
can the heart open to the sense of enjoyment of this moment not just enduring
this moment trying to get through it to get to the next
what if we let go of that way of being way of seeing just enjoyed what is
if there are challenges a crowd of sorrows can we open up to them hello life hi
this moment what a smorgasbord
not to endure but to enjoy what is
this impermanent impermanent life permanent moments not to just endure
them they pass through quickly all
and too soon but to enjoy the fleetingness
not in spite of but because of its fleeting nature
and if there's a challenge arising in your sphere experience right now whether it's
pleasant sensations in the body fatigue
anxiousness even whatever is happening right now can we have a really spacious
perspective not just endure it but can we expand our perspective
ah expand her heart breathe around it
let the fact that this is at all whatever it is here
can it be appreciated even enjoyed
that anything exists at all
even if it has unpleasant feeling too
and maybe a sense that can arise when the mind
settles could be that there is just enjoyment there's just delight there isn't me and
mine i want this i don't want that person to me or mine it's just enjoyment
delight gladness knowing itself
being known not owned
not claimed without ownership
for the last moments of this practice period
can we enjoy that we sat we practiced
no matter what arose or did not arise doesn't matter let the judgments go
you showed up you did your best you planted seeds of wholesomeness yay
yay can you enjoy that yes yes
wholesomeness planted watered yay
enjoying your own goodness
let there be delight
yes i am here i am here
sharing this goodness with all beings everywhere
may my goodness my cultivation
and taking delight really recognizing this goodness made me cause and condition
serve as a cause and condition or goodness in the world
all beings everywhere may all things be happy may all beings be free
including myself [Music]
thank you friends thank you for your practice
ah so we have a few minutes for
reflections questions comments anything that might have arisen
and please raise your zoom hand because if you raise your physical hand i will not see you
and you can also type in chat if you type to everyone i'll read your name
if you just type to me i won't read your name but just your reflection so i'll be private
and i see claire yes claire
thank you this gives me a chance to tell one of my all-time favorite stories my whole life
i was listening to the radio many years ago and they were interviewing an actress who
was like doris day somebody who always played really happy parts and they were asking her about her life
and it went on from one awful story to a worse one it just was
her life was miserable and so the obvi the interviewer finally interrupted the interview and he said
you know i've got to ask you with the life you've had how could you possibly play the parts
you do and she paused and she said well you know at one
point i realized that i had a choice and i chose joy
and that's has stuck with me my whole life and i i go with it um beautiful
yeah exactly we have a choice happiness is a choice you make beautiful thank you
claire that's lovely yeah such such wisdom right it can arise in so many places so many ways and atlanta you have
a choice we have she had a choice and we have a choice every single one of us
thank you claire so may we choose joy may we choose joy not a perspective of
have to endure another moment another day even if it's challenging as as it is
it's human life we all have our challenges welcome to being human
thanks claire so any other reflections
questions comments richard says gratitude works for me yay
any other reflections was there i wonder here is a specific question as i was inviting you to um
to really try a perspective of especially if there was enduring like
there's a sense of enduring like if you shifted towards towards enjoying enjoying versus enduring did
you did anyone play with that did did it open up something for you in the practice that it wouldn't have was is
there a moment in your practice like okay another meditation practice ah breath in i was like oh can i enjoy this
any of you have a shift that opens something up for you would love to hear
or any other opening
again for the benefit of everyone to share that fuzzo please
just thought of some things that you know i have to do that
i'm not particularly excited about it's like well maybe i can approach it from a different
perspective great great awesome yeah thank you for
that yeah beautiful yeah yeah i was also reflecting on that myself there's like a few things i need
to do that i i need to do i have just like like what what if i really enjoy doing it
so susan i see your hand please yeah that was a great reminder about the
joy thing i definitely got raised and then my life as a consultant you know it really
reinforced you know work before play kind of thing you know
like you know and is the to-do list ever done right so um this is great you know it's like
oh yeah just enjoy you know and um two days ago i learned that a dear
friend of mine had just had a massive stroke and so i was pretty upset yesterday and then today i started
getting where okay you know more accepting it and then you know it's like okay i think it's
still okay to enjoy that i'm alive and not having a stroke you know
just how as you said how precious and fleeting and fragile it is and even more reason to enjoy it
yeah exactly beautiful beautiful he said thank you for bringing that reflection in susan how it's a lie for you yeah
we're here it's it's to be enjoyed to be grateful for not to focus on all the challenges and yeah i'm alive i i don't
have x y z a stroke being one of them and and also when you pointed out um
chuckling like yeah this this always worked before play you know always have a to-do list the to-do list is never
gonna end we're all gonna die with an unfinished well i'm gonna die with an unfinished to-do list i know that so
we're never done so that's sweet thank you susan thanks for those reflections
[Music] yeah okay avi has a reflection here i'll read it's a long one see
related to enduring it engaged my identity clinging so to speak
i'm in joy and a small internal tension toward fear of the idea of just enduring
and then the moment of awareness around my fear of unhappiness i'm also grateful
for finding silver linings much like the actor's story that claire mentioned with
pain or suffering finding the space there to learn i guess
so thank you so very much i get curious about equanimity around abundant joy
finding the balance and even background joy of neutral neutrality
question mark i think i'm a little unclear about the question at the end abby if you want to raise your hand and
clarify the question at the end i see you i have a curiosity about equanimity
uh of abundance well maybe i'll say something if i if i don't address it um
so so you know um
equanimity you know which was the sense of equipoise and unevenness of mind
in the face which is not falling into nor nor pushing away so with joy you can
absolutely enjoy joy enjoy and have delight as long as you don't attach to it like i
want more of this i want this to be the rest of my life like oh this is great yum yum yum it's
like kissing it's it's like this um this this poem uh
um forgetting the name of the poet they'll come to it's like kissing the joy as it flies you just kiss it as it
flies and there is the equanimity it's like oh yeah you kiss it as it flies instead of like trying to catch a
butterfly and pin it and kill it's like no let the joy be so that's the way
equanimity can can be coexistent with abundant joy yeah
great thank you for that yeah
yeah yeah i see if i see your comment here
sometimes i could cry or i could laugh um i see this as a comment i'm not quite
sure how to reflect on that so i'll let that sit as it is so uh many reflections on
on um [Music] youtube here
uh i'll pick a couple not a moment but i'm coming out of the practice time in the mode of enjoying not enduring yay great
morty and um thank you sid
you listen to my conversation with sam harris and inspired by my life story
story may it be of service made serve you thank you marty also says die with a completed
bucket list but incomplete to-do list sounds a okay oh to me
oh that's fine so so so okay dear ones the time has come
for us to to practice to practice sharing our joy sharing our kindness
in small groups so we've done it now in silence in in our meditation and now we
get the chance to enter the sandbox and practice relationally so create the breakout
rooms and as always the invitation is uh be kind to yourself be kind to others
you're invited to just offer a nugget maybe just a word you know just say not another word just a sentence
um of what what was this practice like for you and you
can also offer silence and say pass and hold kind space for
yourself and others the next person will say something and then the third person
and it will come back to you so please don't take the entire time the long monologue just say one
short nugget and and give time make space for others as an act of
kindness as an act of generosity and care for everyone may and may not be appropriate to give your whole life
story in the monologue just a little nugget just as an act of kindness to yourself
and to others um so and let's speak in reverse alphabetical order
and um and again just speaking from your own experience not managing
the group just showing up with with humility and kindness so
i'm opening the rooms take care of yourself take care of each other and be
kind and enjoy enjoy each other enjoy here we go
okay all the rooms are closed everybody's back and it is seven o'clock so
um okay well we had wonderful reflections before i'll see one quick question
follow up from abby so i'll just respond to it and basically it's what she's following up on is about
choosing moments of neutrality instead of joy or enduring um
i would investigate whether uh there is a um whether actually
the there is a masquerading of choosing neutrality is actually pushing something away whether it's pushing joy away or
pushing so that i'm hearing some masquerading there so i invite you to to
explore that because ah opening up to it is very different than choosing new valley there's some
pushing you away there so watch out for that all right dear ones thank you so much
for your practice for your cultivation supporting each other supporting
yourselves and i see gratitude for your group there and
at least in the chat i see that may all beings be well may all beings be happy
and free including ourselves here we go
thank you all take care i'm teaching oh i should i should have mentioned this earlier i forgot maybe i'll ask neil if
neil you're still here to send email to the group to um
i'm teaching a concentration retreat at spirit rock on land for the next 10 days so there's still spaces available if you
happen if you want to do a retreat last minute come there's space usually this this one is
by lottery only but there's some last minute cancellations and there's also another program that's starting in a
couple of weeks and that's mindful leadership training it's a five-month training program so so
um so i'll be away for the next 10 days and actually next two weeks teach you these two programs
and i look forward to seeing you when i get back and we'll send more information to the happy hour google groups alright
thank you all take good care