okay all right so welcome you all welcome everyone wonderful to see you
always happy making to come together um with the Sangha to practice so
for tonight's practice um the theme I'd like to invite us to practice with
um has been requested both on Friday when we had uh our happy hour at the end
I stayed a few minutes extra for those who were here and and a very important
question and conversation came came about about how to hold uh compassion
Equanimity with these hard practices with very very challenging times in the
world um if you're in Ukraine for example
um how would you how would you go about that how would you hold that in your heart and the same time also um another
aspect of what I want to bring in tonight is is a uh uh one of my students
sent me an email and actually I wanted to read part of their email asking
um and and as many of you know I am Iranian I was born in Iran and the very
challenging times right now in my uh in my country of birth so so they wrote in
your kind the student wrote and asked in your talks could you kindly suggest ways
for Buddhist Iranians and ukrainians who practice Metta how to use their daily
practice to bring more peace and love for themselves and
others around them during these challenging times also how to approach
activism with meta I so appreciate these questions because
this practice that we cultivate we do together five times a week it's not just
about easy times it's not just about sitting and wishing well it's also
irrelevant important or perhaps even the most important practice in challenging
times whether our heart is breaking with the news of the world
or if we are ourselves in challenging situations
um with with Injustice etc etc so so both how to hold it
[Music] um enabling transcription there somebody
asked you to enable transcription and I just did that um so
so with with this with I want to say a few words before we get into our
practice tonight and I so appreciate these questions and and the care that has has come
um with with the interest of how do we engage how do we engage so two aspects I
wanted to address very briefly before we get into the practice one is
this concept of compassionate activism compassionate activism
and activism with anger can be corrosive
and this is something that many activists in the world know anger can can bring up a lot of energy can can
bring up a lot of energy to do a lot in the world but it's also corrosive however being an
activist out of compassion it brings people together it it sees all
sides not to condone the harm not to condone the pain not to condone the
Injustice and the harm that's being done but one gets to see the humanity of all
sides again not to condone but compassionate activism
um is is is a way it really is the way
through this and just to say a little bit about my own reaction as I read the
news for example as I was reading the news from my homeland early earlier tonight
from the country of my birth um I was grieving and my heart was broken I
was grieving for hearing how peaceful activists in an elite University in Iran
were were um beaten up were taken away with a lot
of violence and what I noticed both in in what was
coming up for me was grieving for the pain of the people who were who were
hurt as well as grieving for the perpetrators for their karma for the pain that they
are causing so there is grief with compassionate activism there is a sense of grief and
sadness compassion for all sides it's not as separating of us against them of
course not condoning the harm and there there is action there is action but it
doesn't come from a place of hatred it comes from a place of and of course the
action might be this is not right this is not appropriate stop as a way of Defending
um and not allowing the harm to happen however it comes from a place of
of love for everyone involved not a place of hatred and I acknowledge that this is a very
very high bar to set and yet this is a high bar that
the Buddha sets in the um in the sitter
the simile of the saw where he says and I'm sorry this is very graphic uh
description but he says that if the bandits are are cutting off your arms
and legs still if you are following my teachings you
will have compassion you have Meta Even in that moment for them so for all sides
again you'll protect yourself you you won't be a you know oh yeah just do
anything you will protect yourself with all your might so compassion doesn't mean that you
become a wet noodle or you become submissive but that act of protection
that act of resistance comes from a place of of care and love
and similarly as one Witnesses what is happening with a sense of grief
and a broken heart with compassionate activism also comes the sense of
um a a need for holding oneself with with care because if if if you're
watching and you are off kilter
um there's there's not much that you can do you can't do your activism you can't be a force for the good in the world you
will be wallowing in grief you will just be lost in in grief and turmoil so there
are wisdom needs to come in to bring some Equanimity to hold the
compassion so that there is some stability to to have to be able to
engage in compassionate activism
so there's a lot more to say this feels
like such a brief and it might even bring up more questions than answers
but um I want to make sure we have enough time for our practice tonight our well
this is practice too listening to the Dharma and sharing the drama and yet I do want to make sure that we have time
for for meditating so let's let's turn to meditation and we'll have time for
discussion for questions afterwards okay so so I'd like to invite you to land
okay in your body
In This Moment In Time and this impermanent Moment In Time
Landing arriving letting go of thoughts letting go of preoccupations for this
moment just so that you can settle
so that you can have an anchor so that you can have stability
to respond wisely compassionately to what arises in
the heart and in the world so for the benefit of a wise response
we choose to let go in this moment of of all thinking preoccupations
there's nothing wrong with thinking with planning
but in this moment we give him away and settle
In This Moment feeling the body stable well rooted
upright
a sense of Integrity in the body
the feet well rooted to the Earth connected to
the Earth as the Buddha said
with the gesture with the Earth mudra and the night of his Enlightenment as Earth be my witness
I am here I belong here
claiming reclaiming your place on this Earth
and letting your torso be upright
sense of Integrity ceiling sitting tall like a mountain
even if there's sadness if your heart is breaking
there is stability in the body to hold it all
stability in the posture
letting the breath letting the breath move through calm settle
nourish nourish your heart if you are not nourished if you don't
have calm
stability
you cannot be of support to anyone
so calming calming the heart calming the mind
as much as possible with the breath feeling nourished
In This Moment
taking a bird's eye view
of humanity
of all the comings and goings of generations
at this moment this experience this breath is part of
the stream of humanity can it be a breath can it be a moment of
calm of care
not of anguish
to support more love to support more care in the world
less hatred more stability more friendliness
less othering
can this breath this moment of this experience here my experience
be an offering be an offering of peace
of care to All Humans all beings
may all beings everywhere whoever they are whatever their
conditions seeing their Humanity
seeing that in there value system
they're doing the best they can
wishing clear seeing
wishing a compassionate heart for everyone may all beings be awake to see each other's Humanity
may all human see that we are not so different
we all want to be happy
to be free not to suffer
breathing peace as if with each breath
we breathe in peace into our heart the moment of peace and offering of peace
and breathing out peace unto the world
if only are breathing breathing out peace and
goodness could calm could soothe
the pain of the world
bring peace ease let me share with each breath or
wish for peace
and as if our heart could transform the pain the Injustice in the world
each breath breathed in
as if the challenges the pain the suffering
okay fog breathing Into the Heart Center transform This Heart
of Good Will This Heart of care for the world
breathing out Goodwill for all beings everywhere
especially the places in the world where there is Strife right now
there's pain there is war there's unrest
to all sides not condoning the harm not condoning the
hurt
the perpetrators are also harmed
they're harming themselves it's so painful
harm others it impacts one severely
so compassion
for everyone for all sides not condoning the injustice
that needs to stop and be stopped
and with each breath not with anger but with love
transforming transforming the pain
in the world each breath in
the Heart Center as if the pain gets incinerated gets
transformed into a soothing light of Good Will compassion
breathing in breathing out cool calm
love care
and if this practice of breathing in or letting challenges be breathed Into the
Heart Center transformed and breathe out seems difficult this practice of Tong Len
and it's okay to breathe in peace and breathe out of peace
breathing in peace breathing out peace
if only this breath bring peace to those who are
suffering right now wishing well with each and every breath
so many people suffering
sharing care kindness good will compassion feels both the suffering but
and meets it with good will it's not just empath empathetic distress
breathing in peace breathing out Peace Love care
imagining that each breath is bringing Comfort soothing
hope restoring
soothing calming
all who are hurting
and if at any point it seems too much and the practice of compassion has
veered into empathic distress and it's no longer compassion but just feeling
the pain it's okay to turn to your own heart
with compassion with care
feeling peace with each breath a sense of stability equanimity
expanding your view expanding the view of your heart
the bird's eye view of humanity
all the challenges all the goodnesses in this being human
comings and goings
touching into equanimity offering this moment as a gift of peace
stream to the ocean of humanity past present future
we have come a long way as humans we still have a long way to go
can we cultivate this moment
to be a moment of Good Will kindness peace
as a gift as an offering to so many moments
of Human Experience
the tide has been turning
of regenerations towards more compassion and wisdom
Humanity at Large is Kinder
historians philosophers tell us
tide is turning slowly slowly let this cultivation at this moment
of good will for all beings everywhere
be an offering to turn the tide
if we hate if we hate if we join in hating
we are not so different from those whose ways we want to change
don't give in to hatred
wishing well wishing well-being freedom from pain
sorrow for all beings everywhere including this
being that is yourself
with each breath
with each breath offering may all beings everywhere
be free from suffering all beings
may all beings be well may all beings be free
may all beings including this one the being who is me
be well
be happy
have peace
be kind
be loving and wise
wishing well wishing peace with each breath
as if our hearts our good will bring comfort and sucker
could bring comfort
to all beings
foreign radiating out
our Goodwill
radiating all beings will come in contact
with the beams of meta Goodwill
may they be calmed May their hearts be touched
May there be a moment of lightness ease
May their challenge be enlightened
feeling being touched by the power of
this radiating compassion Goodwill
ryokan said oh if
my Monk's robes were wide enough If Only They were wide enough
to cover all the suffering beings in this world
as if our robes our cloth was wide enough to cover to comfort
it's a wide blanket of meta
Corona compassion bring sucker to all the hurting
beings in the world
as we bring this practice period the sit to close
wishing all beings everywhere especially those in
War zones
living under oppression and strife wishing them ease freedom
happiness may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
thank you
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
appreciate all of you coming together and practicing in this way
not turning away not turning away
so do we have time for Reflections questions
discussion conversation you can raise your Zoom hand please
you can also type your Reflections your questions your complaints in chat
you can type them to mean privately or in which case I won't read your name
only your question your reflection or you can type them to everyone in which case not read
your name also um easy says thank you from Malaysia thank
you easy for practicing joining on YouTube any Reflections questions
Radha
um first of all I just want to say thank you so much but uh um guidance
um and something that came up for me during it was
um this story that I remember um
of uh like from the Philippines kind of during the
um Marcus dictatorship um there was like this kind of Turning
Point in that um in the kind of overturning of the
dictatorship where um there were these sort of hundreds of thousands of women gathered
um kind of facing these soldiers and it was mostly kind of mothers of that age
and um um yeah they were facing these soldiers
and they just started chanting I love you to the soldiers and
um yeah it brings up a lot of emotion for me um and those
that was like a really big turning point in in um what happened kind of after that was
that the soldiers actually um Marcus actually lost support from
those soldiers um after that happened and um yeah the rest is history as they say
um that um yeah I just kind of found that coming up for me
I think during the meditation I was feeling a lot of kind of empathetic distress and
um I found kind of that energy of those mothers and that quality of the strength
of just you know just I love you um I found that kind of gave me a lot of
strength um so yeah I just wanted to shout out thank you so much Radha for sharing that
the powerful story and the turning point I'm so touched thank you also sharing
what what came up for you with this sense of feeling the
all sides both sides and really that sense of I love you and and that
can be the Turning Point may be the turning point I'm so happy to hear that was the turning point
when Marcus lost power and may be the turning point for what's happening in my
country of birth may it be so through love not through hatred thank you Radha
Jamie please
thank you for this Nikki um boy just such big topics
it you know it actually is was fairly easy for me
to extend compassion to an oppressor or someone perpetrating violence because I
know there are conditions that led to their actions which makes me much more hopeless
actually because I don't I don't need to counter that person I need to counter the
conditions that led to his or her actions and that seems a lot more complex and a
lot harder it actually isn't and I'm so glad you raised this Jamie this is
fantastic because the cause and conditions that game rise to
what happened are three things greed hatred
and confusion and confusion delusion not knowing any better not knowing that you
know not knowing what causes happiness what causes goodness in the world so it's really these three right
and and I'm reminded of Joseph Goldstein who was watching um who who at some
point in one of his teachings shared that um watching uh uh documentaries of the
world wars it came up for him that really it's it the world wars all the
aggression all the killing and dying it's all the expression of these three
roots of greed hatred and delusion in individuals in individuals So when you say hopeless actually it makes me more
hopeful because here you are practicing love and and here when you see oh yeah I
can I can love the perpetrator I can see the conditions you're already changing the conditions in you
so you're already dispelling greed hatred delusion and
that is Hope right there it's one person at a time I I'm not at a point right now
where I can see how those you know those three things um cause
all the all the um pain in in the you know that is
inflicted on people um it's um it just seems to me like a lot of the time it's
out of love for a parent who modeled Behavior
that was you know internalized and became embodied
with without ill intent necessarily yeah so I don't know what to do with that
so so I I have to admit the long uh chat came through and and there was a Crux of
something that you said that I missed so so repeat that I'm gonna it's hard to handle everything at the same time so
forgive me Jamie repeat tell me what is that part right and I don't want to I don't want to take all this time from
other people no but I do want to to hear the the um well I just think of um
uh let's let's take a soldier in in in in Iran who's who's you know beating a
protester um his actions might have been a result of
the love for his parents who had very strong uh beliefs and a certain set
of behavior that he took on board and emulated and internalized and I don't see how that is
read hatred or delusion yeah yeah it is delusion and let me thank so thank you
for repeating that so so this is what the delusion is the delusion is is
um not seeing the common Humanity that is a delusion when you don't see
that people the person you're hitting or beating is just like you but you're
beating them up and not seeing and not being able to take their place not being able to empathize and see and listen to
them and and othering that is a delusion
the delusion of othering in the fundamental sense list so thank
you for that Jamie thank you ah yeah
let's see okay Hugh says compassionate activism equals
non-violent resistance as taught by Martin Luther King Mahatma Gandhi and take not hot yes
and Dave says thank you Nikki it's tempting to
direct our gaze over there and point the finger of blame at an other especially
when the media are full of Stories of the official enemies du jour
but uh let's see but as as the land
acknowledgments remind us we are in the U.S are are seen as the perpetrators of
genocide genocidal violence before we accuse others let us take a look at
ourselves yes it's everywhere absolutely it's everywhere David's it's
um there is I I think once something that
your point points your note points out and I was also trying in taking perspective the big perspective of this
moment is a moment in The Wider Humanity in The Wider Humanity of of so much
perpetration of violence Etc which has again as historians and philosophers
tell us we've become Kinder as humans and of course we still have a long way to go
and yet yes let's not turn our gaze there's there's plenty
um uh Karina what days do I teach I teach Monday Wednesday Friday and there was
one other question that came through let's see and I wonder actually it's 6 51 whether tonight given this topic it
makes sense to stay in the big group that's actually my feeling right now that we stay in big group and tonight we
skip the small breakouts and um that's my feeling if what's if let me know if
if you like the idea of staying in the big group give me a thumbs up or something and I'll count the number of
thumbs up if not yeah I'll see lots of thumbs okay we're going to stay in the big group tonight okay
uh so it'll take more more [Music] questions and Reflections
um I do want to go back to the question that was put in chat what should we wish for the knowing perpetrators of violence
and suffering oh I think in a way that was already handled I uh that came through Jamie's question so I appreciate
the person who wrote that it's really wish that they get to see and also it was reflected in radha's uh reflection
that they get to see that they're they are loved and they can love they see the common Humanity this is what I wish for
the perpetrators of violence past present and future
um a couple more messages gosh let's see I agree Stanford group thumbs up okay I
see that uh one person says thank you thank you I was able to do tanglin
tonight when in the past I couldn't great delighted to hear that Jerry I see your hand and then I'm gonna go to to
um actually let me read Jamie's comment maybe the delusion in the example they gave in the delusion example I gave of
the Iranian Soldier is not seeing that they have other options than the ones their parents and Role Models gave them
yep that too that too there's so many ways to see our common humanity and let lovely Jerry I see your hand please
just a comment I read in one of the new Services uh when the initial War started
in Ukraine at least in February was that um the Russian soldiers were finding it
hard to attack people that spoke their same language so this issue of course for me as a
psychiatrist is because they see them as human beings and they're not speaking gibberish to them because they're
speaking the language of Russian that both of them overlap and so it did get
to me about your question your comment uh about well the delusion is is that
they um it helps that you don't you to dehumanize the person that you're
attacking so that's my only comment exactly and yeah that is the the
delusion of the humanizing of of othering they're different they're bad they you know whatever uh different
narratives right and that's how um anyway it's it's happened so often in
the history of of humanity unfortunately one group the human incises is the other
or maybe the people empowered to to that do that to stay in power
um a couple of comments from YouTube and I see Serena and Charles Lee's hand um John says on YouTube the challenges
that are so real in the northern hemisphere seem a long away from New Zealand so thanks for guidance to be
there now with love for all the people there and here thank you John for joining from New Zealand really
appreciate um so Serena I'm gonna ask you to unmute
please
yes thank you it was really difficult I have to say that to be honest with you
was very difficult tonight's meditation was very difficult for me
and um what I'm really very aware of is that
um it is really tough to deal with suffering
and in any shape or form you know I
I'm having you know it's like um yesterday I had to go and visit my uncle
well I chose to do that who is in um in a nursing home type of facility he
hasn't been doing well for a long time and um
I had to really get my courage up to really go and visit and to be with
somebody who has very little control over over his body and to be there for him
so um so what I'm trying to say is in my own
personal life I'm just having difficulty just being there for other people who are
and you know suffering or are in very very difficult situations and
um and honestly you know like for example when the war and in Ukraine uh happened
I was really activated I sent things I you know medical supplies Etc but it's
just like it's hard I get your I get your questions Serena so so in the benefit of time given the two other people also have their hands raised I I
hear you this is hard this is hard people are suffering and as you said it
already takes a lot of courage to be with suffering which is close that is
close to you people you care about close to you and and and so how to it seems
It's all it seems overwhelming right so so this is what I recommend as a
practice for you to have to build that courage to build that stability for you
to all to both be with people who are close to you to show up for them and yay
for doing so and people that are far away is to when it starts to feel
overwhelming to back into or to um to to
um support yourself with Equanimity with expanding your view get your balance get
a sense of stability and that's what we did tonight and I know it was a hard practice and I went back and forth
between Equanimity stabilizing on the Equanimity and then when there's a sense of okay peace is yes and then opening up
again titrating and again oh this is overwhelming going back to Equanimity that's the way then you can expand your
capacity Serena to be with suffering it's not going to happen overnight but little by little you're going to expand
your capacity and it will both serve you as a in your own humanity and serve
others thank you for raising that appreciate it thank you thank you thank you Charles Lee please
oh hi yeah thanks Nikki thank you again um I guess what what stood out for me
during during practice was really the comments about
um I guess or the rejoinder about uh myself
um you know may may others you know not have suffering um or all beings not have suffering and
you know including myself and I just uh really felt it uh uh this evening and
just uh just a good reminder um to
um I guess to in some ways be selfish but not in a you know in in a skillful
Wholesome Way allows me to show up um a lot better for my family and I've
had to tell my kids you know Daddy needs to eat something before he can help you
give him five minutes to get some calories it'll be a much nicer Daddy
beautiful beautiful I love that thank you charlesly thank you so much for
bringing that into the space it is so important um it's wise selfishness let's call it
you know or maybe another word I it's it's wise
it's wise taking care of oneself I mean really you have to take care of yourself before you take care of others and in
this guided meditation of course you need to be included compassion is 360.
specially if you feel that oh yes this over well means too much okay come back calm sweetheart it's okay it's okay it's
all right calm soothing because if if you don't have the capacity if you are
uncapacitated you can't be available for anyone so of course you have to take
care of yourself so thank you so much for highlighting that and that's so important in compassionate activism and
just caring for others caring for your family beautiful thanks again and Diana
it is seven o'clock so please say say it and and needs to be brief
oh never mind I can't be that brief so oh okay so tell you what we're going to
respect people's time closed but I'm going to stay extra extra afterwards to hear you out okay all right so I want to
thank you all thank you so much for coming to happy hour to practice
compassion care for the world for ourselves turning
the tide little by little by little one breath at a time thank you so much may you be well
may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music] thanks everyone take good care