hi everyone it's lovely to be with you hmm
so so the season of holidays in in the U.S
if you are in the US have started you know with Thanksgiving and Christmas
is coming and you know all that so holidays also you know the the perhaps
made the they're both stressful and and they have
lovely aspects they're lovely and they're stressful both you know we can focus on one or the other but it's both
and in some ways it's not so different from the rest of life it's lovely and
it's stressful right both of those we can say about life thank you so so what
I wanted to to reflect on tonight um and invited us to practice with is
the fourth Rama vihara the Brahma viharas again as a reminder are the practices of
the heart meter loving kindness being the first one Compassion or karuna the
second one third one is mutita vicarious Joy the fourth one is equanimity or
opecas this beautiful expansion of the heart to be with whatever is with with
stability with care it's not aloofness it's not oh I don't care you know listen
you know talk to the hand I'm not listening it that's not Equanimity we know that already but I always want to
remind us um Equanimity can be more nuanced can be
more nuanced compared to the other Brahma viharas and yet it is the Brahma
vihara is the faculty where the other Brahma vihara's rest on it's
um loving kindness compassion and vicarious Joy rest on Equanimity because
if they don't rest on the stability on the open-heartedness
and the spaciousness of equanimity they can rear into the
opposite meta loving kindness can become clinginess or compassion can become a
grief or or or distress or say
um would detail vicarious Joy can Veer into either Pride or it's opposite into Envy
if it doesn't have this open-heartedness this open-heartedness of equanimity just
open-hearted spacious stable it's just such a beautiful
quality to have and it's not cold it's not aloof at all otherwise it wouldn't
be part of the Brahma of the hearts right all the Brahma viewers we have metal right we have love there so wait
how are these in the same family oh okay so Equanimity isn't cool after all it
has care in it of course it has care in it has care enough in it to be stable to
be present to be with what is so I'd like to invite us to consider to
relate to Equanimity tonight as we practice um a spaciousness of the heart just
complete spaciousness of the heart spaciousness of the Mind for our own sake
um especially say if if challenging emotions if difficulties arise
there is a sense of equanimity there's a sense of peace and ease
um which which again can Veer into meta can Veer into for others can Veer into a
vicarious joy we can Veer into gratitude for ourselves it can Veer into
compassion if there are challenges so so Equanimity is responsive Equanimity can
be quite responsive so we start with Equanimity and under different flavors
different places we can go whereas again the loofness is oh you're not paying attention it's like whatever uh whereas
Equanimity really faces it's open opens the heart and faces
one last thing I want to say before we start practicing is that
it's such a beautiful quality of the heart and the more we expand our heart
and the more we make our hearts our minds spacious through Equanimity the more we can
contain the more we actually surprise ourselves
as to what we're made of right what we're made of we can just surprise
ourselves wow this I can be with this too this too I'm not losing neither my
confidence nor my temper I have a sense of spaciousness to meet to meet what's happening to meet what's
happening with with appropriate response so So In Praise of equanimity In Praise of
equanimity this beautiful spacious quality of the heart [Music] um
yeah it's glorious glorious Equanimity economy is really glorious it's it's
such a Sublime State really such a Sublime state to uh
um to cultivate a spaciousness of the heart it's very
generous Equanimity also is the ground
for generosity just being with all there is so all right I can talk a lot more
about the joys and the Perfection this this beautiful quality which is actually
one of the Perfections um as called one of the jewels and um
and put his practice but let's just practice together let's just try it on for signs cultivate enjoy a taste of it
for ourselves and if if there are areas when tonight Equanimity does not arise
or the opposite of it arise clinging or aversion not a problem not a problem
use the opposite of equanimity which is aversion or clinging as a pointer oh
there's Equanimity lacking here oh it's oh can I be with the lack of equanimity
present here because then you can bring in Equanimity to lack of equanimity and
that's like an Aikido move in practice so all right let's do it let's practice
together ah
so arriving arriving
arriving in this body arriving In This Moment
sitting with Integrity upright
and making space for whatever is present right now that could be fatigue there could be
boredom there could be resistance it could be Joy
anxiety whatever is present hi everything hello
Bring It On open your heart spacious spacious
stable this body connected rooted everything can be here just as it is
connecting with the breath
foreign
your sit Bones on the cushion on the chair hands on the lap
relaxing the body resting connecting to the Earth
let the in-breath be received in the abdomen the lower abdomen
priority of thin breath the paths between the in and out
breath the out breath entirety of it and the pause
calming soothing each breath
foreign
The Joy the joy of just being breathed nothing to do nowhere to go
taking refuge in this moment just be breathed thank you foreign
foreign foreign foreign foreign
foreign
your body is a boat on a lake
that is still a nostalic
foreign
it's floating
letting your body relax soften
it's a nice day maybe it's sunny warm Pleasant
this body this boat floating in the water
foreign [Music] meeting the circumstances
loading floating
your body can relax the boat is stable
let yourself enjoy this sense of relaxed
ah relaxed stability
moving on the water
foreign foreign
foreign foreign foreign
foreign
[Music] foreign
steady exploding on the water
your body breathing
relaxed and this image enjoying the day warm sunny Birds coming sitting
and the boat leaving
that there is some wind there's a little bit of wind
and there are some waves some waves on the water
and the boat meets them foreign
waves of life
your body be relaxed yourself to your your breath soft
foreign
no fear no worry
this is just how things are
conditions of life is to have some waves Renditions of the
water just to have some waves
perhaps the energy of the waves actually bring a sense of aliveness
energy into the body into the mind
vitality
riding the waves
in your boat in your raft
still enjoying the Sun the birds and the waves
spaciousness of the heart spaciousness of the heart
calm openness not contracted
interfere but open spacious
foreign
another boat that's floating and
coming towards you
and maybe you see this boat coming right towards you
and maybe at first there is some concern or worry or fear or anger
about the other person it was driving the boat right towards you until
you realized there's no one in the boat
it's an empty boat
it's drifting
it's moving towards you is born of causes and conditions it's impersonal
foreign
and perhaps you realize that this bird foreign
moved by the currents the wind
it's also so much boring of causes and conditions
so much of it impersonal impersonal it's impersonal foreign
no need to take it so foreign
concerned contracted
maybe the heart can relax be more spacious
appreciating the interdependence of all things
the wind the flow the waves
energy of life ah
yard relax in the midst of all of it still meeting it with kindness with
wisdom with compassion foreign
state of contraction
spacious
appreciating that foreign
moved by part of all these cause and conditions
not permanent not personal [Music]
not inherently satisfactory
and yet miraculous amazing foreign
this whole being filled with all
you'd be a part of it no matter how it is how the waves go
foreign
the heart to relax with the comings and goings of things with the waves
as we float
the meanings and goings of whether random boats on the water
enjoying the sun on your face and you're alive you get to foreign
these waves how amazing
thank you
foreign you can imagine maybe some challenge
that's happening right now in your life is as a wave in the water
in a way that comes and goes yet another wave here it is
it's okay foreign
be spacious
calm relaxed or maybe even joyous writing's way
floating through it
Your Vessel is stable sturdy
foreign
just waves it's okay I've been through a million waves in
your life
you've grown and experienced in wisdom how to write them
more ways
may they help me grow and kindness towards myself towards
others growing wisdom
foreign
having kindness appreciation for yourself
you've showed up you've done your best if there are a lot of waves during this
practice period it's okay let your heart be spacious and kind
bow into the waves it's okay a brightness a brightness in the Dharma
In This Moment a sense of Clarity and a brightness and offering this goodness
co-created together in this practice to all beings everywhere
our lives are intertwined with everyone else everything else
amazing wow may we be of service
May our lives are breath or work our thoughts
are being alive may be of service
the goodness in the world and ways we cannot even imagine
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice foreign
[Music]
[Music] way for us to explore this practice of equanimity we had never done it this way
on this at happy hour with this kind of a guided meditation with
with waves just a different way to explore it and maybe there is a nugget of something
in this in this visualization and the way that we related to it that worked
for you great keep it keep that inside keep that weight worked and maybe it didn't no
problem you tried it on for size you can let it go it's all good
so so [Music] um
yeah questions comments Reflections what did you notice
um what was it like for you what happened
it was also a little uh invitation there with with anata and
insight and there if you caught it but anyway Jerry I see your Zoom hand please
oops you got muted again that's on Mewtwo please oh you're still me
what happened still muted um there we go there good thank you uh
I guess um I know in Buddhism intention is very
important um and certainly I I don't question your intentions Nikki but I guess
um when uh you know there's uh in the
lay presses I would call it um gaslighting is a popular topic
nowadays and uh one of the things that you mentioned was
don't take it so seriously which is often a term used by people who may not
have good intentions to try to undermine another person just don't take it so seriously like in other words that
you're not in touch with reality and uh it can be a form of bullying
and I know that wasn't your intention but and I didn't take it that way but when I heard that word don't take it so
seriously I wondered um how that fit and I understood the
intent was to have yourself maybe look at what's happening and what's coming up
and is it yeah actually I want to pause you for a moment Jerry because I I remember saying don't take it so
personally don't take it but I didn't say seriously
so that's different that's very different in the dharmic so I want to pause you here because
not taking it seriously that's different I can appreciate how that might bring alarms but not taking it personally
that's dharmic language and I'm using that very specifically
thank you do you hear the difference yeah I I hear the difference uh
and uh I get it it's coming from the die I knew your intentions were good but it
just it's just sort of twigged a bit where if someone else is using IF
yourself is using it like the person and asking them to question it uh that's but
that's very different Jerry so I want to pause you because I I do hear that there's something happening here uh with
with with both the language and also the you know there's something that has happened you know with gaslighting Etc
but I just want to be very very clear with the intention and with the distinction here so pause so stay with
me for a moment Jerry okay thanks so so with with not taking it seriously that's
different that's like that's uh not going there but not taking it personally
is the concept that we're working with here and the concept of anata
impersonality impersonal and governable not self not me myself nor mine and
there is a sense of impersonality which is really a deep deep wisdom teaching in
in Buddhism and I trust that you're having practice as long as you have you
have had insights into the impersonality of the body of the thought process that
there's there's so much impersonality so taking your thoughts personally for
example you're taking your body aches personally it's not personal it's or or
things that happen rise and like oh pers just we take so much to be so much
personal and we suffer because we take things so personally so so that's a
that's an invitation not to take things personal because they aren't personal and and there's a lot of loyal and right
now I'm talking about the kind of the shallow level of this inside but they're very very deep deep levels that even
this being who is me is is born of causes and conditions it's not personal
it's really not so that's what the teaching is and it's a deep teaching
um and the invitation is not to take things personally yes oh you got muted again you're
welcome to say anything or just let it be uh it's very helpful thank you thanks
thanks Jerry yeah okay Steph please
so I just want to say I was pretty distracted but I think it was because I
didn't meditate this morning like I usually do I usually meditate on my own and or in a group and I've had a bit of
a stressful day but you know the practice was really useful but um I had
to keep returning trying to return my mind to it try to return my mind to it so if I really always appreciate it when
you lead a practice so much so thank you beautiful thank you Steph thank you for
saying that and and as you know well that's what I would say is that's perfectly fine distracted Buddha just
say oh yeah distracted Buddha just need to bring back and come back and come to the center and that's perfectly fine
it causes the conditions of the Mind are not always the same and that is impersonal because of what's happened
through the day or didn't sit like oh yeah it's impersonal it's like of course it's it's it's busy right now oh
terrible me I'm a bad person it's like no just like this is what happens like it's impersonal it's born of causes and
conditions this busyness of the mind and then you you and then you work with it with wisdom you work with it with wisdom
beautiful thank you thanks Steph lovely and Claire I see your hand
thank you um I raised my hand for two reasons one is that I loved your metaphor of the
boat on the water I thought it was absolutely spot on for me all right
the other thing though was a question that came up I have for a couple of years now use the concept of acceptance
to deal with complex situations um and is that similar to Equanimity do
you think slightly different slightly different so so so the idea the the
concept of acceptance is is when we accept what is instead of resisting what
is so it's not um again uh about acceptance It's not acquiescing
and it's not giving up so that those are important things that you already know but heard the benefit of everyone so
with acceptance your sense of accepting yeah it's for example my back is hurting right now by hating it by by being upset
about is like accepting the truth of the moment is acceptance there's an opening of not resisting it whereas Equanimity
is more about um so so Equanimity includes acceptance
but it goes beyond acceptance it includes the opening and not denying what's happening but then there's this
ah attitude of neither attaching nor resisting
so it goes beyond it does that make sense yeah there's a more equipoise great thanks thanks for that and Gene
you're the last reflection please thanks Nikki I actually just had a
question um I I I did really appreciate the guided meditation and the um the way you
defined Equanimity is open-heartedness I never understood it that way and it was really lovely and the wave metaphor
um but I wonder repeating yourself if you could just if there's anything else to say about why
it is we suffer so much when we take things personally um I find myself you know sometimes
saying why me like why did that happen to me and I I can kind of understand that that makes it worse but I I don't
know if there's any other dots you could connect there thank you yeah yeah thank you um
so so there are a lot of reasons why we suffer when we things take things personally like it's a longer Dharma
talk but I want to come to specifically what you just referred to which is why me and then let me just say something
about that because it's it's a particular example of the bigger bigger case like why me that that if if that
arises and you know and it arises for many of us in many different times so so
not to have judgment because that's why me arises that's number one but but if it if it arises
um the there is a sense of of excuse me
it's it's um as if I've done something wrong so it's
it's belittling I'm separate like everybody else is okay everybody else has it figured out but but I'm less than
I'm worse than I there's something special but especially in the negative
way and that is the delusion of separateness it's the Deluge it's denying our similarity in humanity
everybody you know everybody has challenges in in this life it's the
unsatisfaction is is a characteristic of being alive we just don't see it our
minds are are often focused on me me me me me right and my life my body my this
like that's just that's how we operate evolutionarily yes oh sweet sweet dear human being you know this is how we
operate and yet when that happens why me try to open that up try to open from the
country constructions of of me and what happened to him to like oh just like others
instead of why me just like others just like other human beings I'm having a difficult day right now just like other
people just like others just to to to take away that that separateness yeah
so okay I spoke a lot and looks like we have less time today it was gonna be a
short um uh short groups so so let's um let's
turn to them it's always sweet to to have to be in small groups so so here's
the invitation I have today um or the group so the invitation is um
as we get together in small groups of three is and since the topic is
equanimity is that the The Prompt is what supports your Equanimity what
supports the sense of being with um the waves that arise what supports it
and maybe what challenges it if you wanted to explore what what supports my Equanimity and what what challenges it
and maybe what supports it is contemplating the Dharma meditating being calm eating a good diet I know
sleeping well whatever it might be what helps my Equanimity what challenge is it and suggest uh going in in circle in in
you know round robin fashion each person will say will offer a reflection the
next person the next person Etc so uh take care of yourself take care of each
other each person will just be offering from their own experience and this is going to be pretty short tonight so
um yeah we'll probably just be what less than five minutes in groups here we go
it's gonna be gonna be lightening round all right take care of yourself take care of each other here we go looks like
the rooms are closed no everybody's back welcome back everyone this was a pretty
quick short uh yeah so it's uh seven o'clock already so I will um respect the
time and let's just dedicate the Merit of our practice together may all beings everywhere be safe happy healthy and
well may all beings be free including ourselves [Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice may you be well may you be
call me you have Equanimity may your heart be spacious may you have a
wonderful weekend