okay welcome uh welcome folks um yeah welcome to you
all um so we'll uh we'll sit yeah and
um yeah and it occurred to me just to say in case it's not already clear that
some level I the way I approach these morning sessions is that already received some instruction on how to
meditate uh there's something you can do that you're familiar with in one way or
another and um these are explorations of of technique and so um yeah take
whatever uh whatever value there is in them uh and add that into uh what you
already know and do so uh so let's uh find our posture
and uh and see what's uh greeting
us today
it's both so familiar and so
fresh kind of dense web of assoc
iations of the Stillness and the
silence almost as if it cues our
body and of awakens the muscle memory of of steadiness and silence and
release but it's also so fresh
who knows what this moment will feel
like where the body and mind is
today where the next Insight lurks
Laten
e
e e
no matter what phenomena the moment brings
there's some Dharma posture some
gesture of awareness gesture of the heart
that serves our long-term welfare and
happiness no matter what's
arising there is goodness that can be cultivated
and
e
e e
we we're so often looking for signs of our progress
signs we're doing it right signs the dark is quote
working and so we look for concentration we look for insight we
look for
tranquility but the mechanisms of healing and Awakening
are not usually evident to us
then fold in ways we can't actually
see and so sometimes it's okay to lock stop stop
looking for signs that we're on the right track to
stop orienting towards some
trajectory we uh imagine is the right
one and we just settle back into a certain kind
of faith and
awareness trust that the Dharma is working its way
through
us and then our job description
as a practitioner becomes a lot
simpler
e
e e
so there's relief in learning that we don't have to
engineer the
moment that the seeds of
Awakening are already
here
e
e e
we listen very
carefully or the the thread of uh wisdom
compassion we tuned to that as best we
can and then
rest e
for for
so Dharma pleas um we
think that um the practice is about uh about the
Peaks yeah and and meditation teachers are no doubt partially to blame in so
far as we talk about somat and the enjoyment of
Stillness or talk about insight and those moments
when um chunks of suffering just cleave
off and we talk about love and the the
possibility that it might um radiate yeah radiate out in all
directions and so we get the sense that um
the practice is about uh about the Peaks and that the the valleys are kind of
intrusions or sort of um pit stop before another
Peak but um the point of practice is not the Peaks the point is the ascent the
peak The Descent and the valley the point is all of that because at each
point along that ride we grow different capacity
and strengthen qualities of the heart that are relevant for our own process of
waking up and um
the The Descent and the valley is
they they have one of two tastes the
taste of suffering or the taste of
purification the taste of suffering or the taste of purification it's there aren't other options as far as I can
tell yeah and um and so uh today's theme is uh the
pleasure of purification when I
um tried coffee as a kid um
I thought it was just like inconceivable that any member of my
species could prefer that to um
say red Gatorade
yeah but um as is said some tastes are
acquired tastes yeah and um the pleasure of purific ation for sure is an acquired
taste but um we come to appreciate it and it becomes very
rich and um on this path uh we we do have to come
to to enjoy enjoy this taste to appreciate it to become a connoisseur of
the the whole wholesome unpleasant yeah the wholesome
unpleasant the forms of discomfort that um are onward leading
rather than the sign of injury and
um um practice can unknowingly recapitulate our resistance to anything
uncomfortable it it's it's so deeply conditioned you know everything in our
body kind of just says no even to small
discomforts and um and we have to uh
that's we're working with that conditioning you know uh that runs so
deep in us and much of the the path is
about breaking the links of suffering yeah the links of suffering
the way this came up last night in in the conversation like the way that acting
out are clinging partially delivers
yeah the way that acting out our clinging partial we say oh clinging is
suffering clinging is suffering I think Ain cha said to somebody like is it really do you really believe that yeah
pointing to the ways in which we have some fidelity to clinging and we have some Fidelity to
clinging because it and this is the tragic part it partially
delivers it's an it's an impoverished form of pleasure but it's a pleasure
nonetheless and to actually interrupt the Cascade of
dukka means that we have to move against the stream against the the cycles of of
reinfor en forcement that that acting out our clinging brings us
yeah and so um to move against against
the partial satisfactions of clinging brings with it a distinctive
flavor and it's a flavor of discomfort but it's a disc comfort that
has this kind of other other hint yeah
of um another taste the taste of relief
the taste of purification many many years ago I was
um getting physical therapy for an injury and um the uh the physical
therapist uh who I loved would cause a lot of pain and um sometimes it'd be
working like in a hamstring and um and I remember he say ah it's very ropey you
know and then uh kind of lean his weight
into the tightness yeah and uh that that
brought a um that was not we would say comfortable
that that is an acquired taste maybe but you can taste the release in it that
this is not the pain of injury this is the pain of uh
healing and this is um my
uh my teacher one of my teachers shinzen Yang
um uh says um the the taste of pure purification is very hard to describe
but in essence it is a kind of joy you may be in great pain but there is a deep
Joy because you feel the blockages being worked out each time you greet the pain
with equinity you can feel how the energy in the pain is wearing away the separation
between you and your spiritual Source you sense that Holdings from the
past are being grounded up digested
metabolized by the peristaltic vibratory movements of
impermanence the grinding and digesting is both painful and liberating at the same
time this is the taste of purification
the options are often the taste of suffering the taste of
purification and uh in that taste of
purification you can feel something is being softened yeah like your heart is
being needed needed like dough
and we get out of the kind of conceptual
world of this this hurts I don't like this how do I fix this and instead we
surrender to the flow of an N of impermanence sense of um the the
movement of any given moment the movement of any given
moment and we just in a sense take take refuge you
take refuge and let
anicha wear down the forces of
clinging we keep noticing um the the bracing that which kind of you know the
ways we kind of subtly brace you know and um we keep noticing that that that
quarantines the pain in some ways we brace for reasons it quarantines the
pain it actually amplifies the distress and then maybe there is a kind
of surrender you know like okay
Sensations okay heartache you can have
me can have me I offer myself up to
you and in this we're we're
so kind of awake that it it's it's almost like we're we're
feeling the exposure therapy that is purification working Moment by
moment it's you know it's like I think last time I I did last month did
something and sort of alluded to the ways that uh that Dharma is in part an
exposure therapy um and it's it's like the in
this purification we can like feel it we can feel it working Moment by moment
uh I'm habituating to the discomfort I'm I'm habituating to the wholesome un
unpleasant and that hurts it's an acquired taste for sure and you can
taste the freedom in it and there's um something that
um this kind of willingness breathes a very easy easy mind state in the wake of
purification it breeds a very easy mind State and so when you get up after a
kind of and have actively chosen the taste of
purification um the forces of clinging the cesas the forces of
suffering just seem very uncompelling very uncompelling hate
so obviously a form of self harm so
absurd not it's not like we have to Marshall our energy to put it
down the dead end of greed so
obvious and in the wake of purification you really don't need much stimulation
at all to feel very
fulfilled and
uh it's a whole other topic but um it feels to me like one of the the
byproducts in this cauldron of purification is also uh
love that um we've experienced suffering with such
um Exquisite Poise and uh such vivid
ways that um the The Human Condition itself
becomes more poignant the predicament of our own life becomes more poignant not
frenzied but poignant there's pleasure it's a weird
pleasure but it's pleasure are nonetheless so I offer this for um for
consideration and uh please pick up what's useful leave the rest
behind Okay team I'll
uh stop there and uh yeah May uh may
your day be filled with uh much goodness and when it's not
and when there is energy may we uh may we have the taste of uh of purification
rather than Taste of suffering okay see you uh see you
tomorrow good to be with you