so hello everyone and welcome back
continuing this theme on the Insight pentad theme of the week
and um and one of the
powers of insight is to see things in a new way
and I'd like to suggest a new way as we start the this meditation
we often start with relaxation and that's still I think a very good
thing to do and that kind of goes along with the Buddhist teachings too to relax the body relax the mind
it's kind of his beginning instructions for meditation and um but um
another similar movement at the beginning and throughout meditation
that's also very powerful is rather than relaxing
uh directly is to um
stop resisting stop resisting
whatever it is you're bracing yourself against holding yourself against or protecting yourself against
in the context of meditation so um
to take a part of the significance of taking a
a careful posture up upright dignified posture
or other postures but the idea says really take a posture that works well for you and then to hold it
stay in it don't don't collapse don't give in to the emotions the feelings the
beliefs the desires to do something else
and um with your body so it's quite significant to feel all
the movements in the body to move to to shift to collapse to pull back
but more subtly there is all kinds of ways in which the tension
we hold in our body it can be a resistance resistance from feeling fully
resistance from resistance holding ourselves against having to feel what's really happening
sometimes it's uh what motivates us with our desires might not might not be the
desires themselves but the discomfort that can come with strong desire and we're trying to resist
that discomfort by by maybe acting out or doing something
or pulling back a lot of the resistance is a kind of attention but uh relaxing the body is different
than releasing the resistance um and because even things which are
maybe things you're protecting yourselves in the moment the feelings the sensations the beliefs to release
them to free them while we're sitting still and upright so we're not giving
expression to them we're not acting on them speaking them but we are not holding them in check
and we're allowing some kind of full relaxation of the body that comes from
releasing all the resistance we have so if this is relevant for you or
understandable for you and how you are maybe at this meditation we can begin or
focus on releasing resistance
and this is one of the characteristics of Freedom that The Liberation that
Buddhism is looking for is Liberation from all tension including that of resistance
and then how to live wisely without this embodied physical emotional mental
resistance that lives in US that is the great art
so assuming a upright dignified posture
or the alternative for you
and gently closing your eyes
and feeling into your body
feeling the tensions the Holdings in your body and see if any of it might qualify as
resistance pulling back from life
protecting ourselves from something
and as you exhale release resistance
release the way that we're physically bracing ourselves or
holding ourselves pulled back
fending off for avoiding
any resistance release it and let what's behind the resistance
have breathing room have space just to be
in the Simplicity of sitting upright
and might there be any resistance to be found in your breathing
in any part of the inhale maybe the second half do you feel anything holding the
breathing back
and if so if it's easy enough let go of that
holding back let go of resistance
and if it's not easy to let go of
content yourself with feeling inhale
stretching against that resistance
any resistance in the exhale
and he holding back maybe at the end of the exhale not allowing it to release fully
foreign
thank you
if you sit quietly and still but let go of resistance
in the body the heart the mind what releases
what becomes larger or more evident
make room for it breathe with it Let It Be Free
while you're free from acting on it
thank you
foreign
here
x three exhales let go release
give up resistance to what's here for you make room for everything
and then imagine that the room of awareness expands outward
out into the world nothing's required of you
but you're able to include people in your awareness
remember people those you know and don't know those you
will encounter and work and communities and stores
and to let go of any resistance to being present
taking people in taking them into account
and caring for them
may we carry with us to stay enough
free time in our minds where our mind isn't not so preoccupied
we don't have time to register or take in the presence of other people
and may we gaze upon them with appreciation and respect
with love care
may we imagine them happy safe and peaceful and free
and maybe this be our wish that they have a wonderful life
happy and safe
may all beings have the Good Fortune to experience
great happiness may all beings
had the Good Fortune of being saved
may all beings have all the benefits that come with
peace and may all beings be free of affliction
tensions attachments suffering
and may our freedom our lack of resistance
be the source of our care for the world
so my friends we come to the fourth talk on the insight pentad
and uh it's the five
kind of uh movements Evolution's growth in the practice that flow from having insight
and the word flow suggests that it's not something we do or construct or make happen but something that as we see
clearly more we see clearly what we're doing what's happening in our minds our beliefs or our attachments our desires
our aversions our resistance as we see it more clearly really clearly
and we see deeply into its nature its impermanent changing constructed nature
that we begin to let go we begin to be disinterested or we start
changing our relationship to it where we're not so wedded to it or invested in it and there's a disinvestment process
that goes on and a fading away of the desires the
attachments that keep us caught that keep us from being free and the consequence of this is greater
and greater calmness peacefulness ease and so the reward is that there is a
reward it isn't just simply being left somehow
in some undesirable state of destitution
as as with this fading away of attachment fading away of clinging happens
it leaves us Freer and Freer and uh and the freedom The Liberation
that comes is uh why it's significant why it's part of this Evolution this
growth this flow is it's not something we do it's not a letting go it's not something we find the key that we turn
it releases something the lock and we the combination and we finally free
but rather it's a the uh the result of
this fading away calming relaxing not resisting not asserting not tense
wanting a real radical trust to really just be here fully fully fully present
in a calm relaxed way allowing things to fade away
and that at some point something inside of us releases it's uh there's a something that we're
not doing let's go stops ceases
and sometimes it can be a moment shift like a like a quantum
flip in the mind where something in the mind just stops and uh and now it's just everything is
so clear and open and free it could be in the heart finally settles
in his openness at home in itself and the Heart finally has lots of breathing room
and the heart just feels like it's it can sing and it's so free and so light
and so easy but the operating thing here is not something we do and we can't exactly
take responsibility for it in terms of making it happen we take responsibility for setting up the conditions for that
freedom and a huge part of this Dharma practice is creating the right conditions for
allowing something the Dharma to move through US allowing release opening development to move through us
and and that begins right at the beginning of the gladness pentad that
what precedes the insight pentate that we have it begins with enough trust and
inspiration to start being present for our experience in a non-reactive way
and finding that this presence it feels good there's joy and happiness that comes calmness that comes
until we see more clearly and we can start kind of get calm enough still enough to see deep enough
and then this process is fading away process that a lot of the we look sometimes
we're looking for I used to look for sitted meditation kind of like a like a
cat that a mouse door waiting to see if I can see the Letting Go happen the
releasing happening finding out where the magic was the magic point was where I could finally kind of penetrate
something and everything would let go and I found out over and over again that
there was this process of fading away and ceasing and things disappearing but I didn't always see when that moment
happened and if sometimes the meditation practice set the conditions for it to happen and
then after meditation is when the releasing happened and I didn't see it happen but at some point I recognized oh
it's gone the resistance the desires the clinging the conceit the things I was caught up
with wow they're gone isn't that that's phenomenal and um and so this uh setting up the
conditions for the fading away for the calming down for the centering for the settling
uh not for its own sake but so that uh that which is uh
the suffering inside of us that comes from that comes from some tight clinging or holding or resisting
has a chance to melt away to thaw into this process of fading away that I
talked about yesterday sometimes I think of it like thawing or being really cold and just kind of
slowly warming up melting dissolving it's a process of slow change
that we allow for and so if we're in meditation we have to sit in meditation
long enough still enough regularly enough that we allow for this deeper process to
happen it's a meditative process where some deeper deeper kind of fading
settling releasing can happen for most people much better in Daily than in
daily life and any other kind of circumstance um
and it grows the more we sit the more we meditate and just learn to sit still
letting go of resistance letting go of clinging letting go of tension
and trusting how things are fading away fading away settling quieting quieting
letting go of our thoughts coming back letting go of our thoughts coming back letting go over thoughts coming back in
a gentle quieting way setting up the conditions that allows something to feel at ease to feel peaceful to feel
comfortable and um and so it becomes uh invaluable
to learn to have a mindfulness awareness that's non-reactive an awareness which
is not for or against anything that's not despairing or upset or
resisting anything that's not critical of when the mind wanders off
and keep going back to this non-resistance awareness that is kind of gives the space
for things to release to settle to calm to open
and at some point you'll uh recognize
that what encumbered you with the inner movements of tightness and fear and resistance and
holding on and expecting wanting projecting that you do you'll find wow
it's not there and that is the kind of liberation
in the teachings of the Buddha he describes a whole list of the I think
the 17 18 things that he lists a number of times things a very particular things
that people discovered now it's gone wow and uh it's interesting things like
greed and hatred but Envy avariciousness um conceit
um disrespect disrespecting people
um it goes on all these different things but what I'm emphasizing here is he's very he names particular mental States
that fall away that stop so it's not a generalized kind of like
some general vague idea of what Liberation is he specifies different
states of Mind different emotions and things so it's very particular psychologically particular oh look at
that my Envy is gone look at that my resentment is gone look at that my remorse my desires my
greed my lust my um
my self-criticism is gone so it's these particular psychological states that he
says oh liberated liberated liberated and then that Liberation can grow
into more and more and more complete and
to be but to recognize it ah look there it's gone and I was struck when I learned about
this part of the Buddhist teachings many names particular psychological States that um
that was kind of eye-opening for me because I I kind of had just I realized only then that I had some vague idea
that there was some great experience of Enlightenment out there that I didn't know what it was but it certainly must
be good and certainly desirable and certainly going to free me from all my suffering and um and I don't even then when I
spread there's like 17 different mental States psychological states that the Buddha
each one talked about seeing how it's gone I said oh let's appreciate the
specificity of what is what Liberation I have what are the things that I and let's not
be held kind of captivated with the idea of some Grand
Big Bang Theory of Enlightenment that somehow is vague what actually happens
there uh begin appreciating the liberations of
particular things that have bothered us memories Stories We Hold On To
relationships we hold on to and to see although I'm free of that I'm
free of that and so this process of fading away and then discovering oh it's not there
anymore wow uh appreciate the not theirness
of suffering of painful psychological states that were there
but when they're you're free of them that is a nourishing that's really important to see ah now it's gone
so having insights seeing clearly enough
to start becoming disenchanted
to then have the fading away of the psychological drives that
kept us Enchanted and then having that fade away enough that we feel free of it
it's a wonderful thing and that this is a natural process to do this
it's not something we have to make happen it's kind of like natural means it's kind of built into who we are it's
almost a consequence of uh ending doing the unnatural things
and what I mean by the unnatural things the things that are the artifices of our
own mind that we create that make and and construct
and the interstates that are not the artifices like that freedom
so thank you and one more day on this insight pentad
and um so you might go through the day today with some homework and that is to notice
the times through the day notice the absence
of difficult psychological States suffering clingings desires resistance
that you have had at some point in the past earlier in the day yesterday last week
but notice the absence of them and take in how good that is
that something was difficult before is not here now you might have other difficulties now
but appreciate the ones that are no longer here and see what happens to you when you
kind of feel that absence so
thank you very much