everyone let's go ahead and [Music] start our day together
our time together so
settling in for meditation finding uh
your usual posture for sitting or whatever feels appropriate for you today
and if you're comfortable doing so you can close your eyes
and just having a sense of turning in or settling in
to your own experience of your body how it is now your mind how it is now
[Music]
feeling balanced where you're sitting [Music]
today the meditation will be on mindfulness of breathing
in a similar style as is taught by vikku anaglio
so it comes from the suta on mindfulness of breathing the anapanasanti suta
which has many interpretations
so as you settle in to the body
having a sense that you are in a secluded area
probably or you found a place where you can sit that's a little bit removed from
other people in your house for example and just enjoying that sense of
to whatever degree of seclusion you have at this time
tuning in to the sense of straightness in the spine
could be that you're sitting upright or it's also fine to feel the straightness as you're in the lying down posture
and just passing the attention through the spine from the bottom to the top
feeling each vertebra relaxing and aligning
the spine
you can go kind of slowly
so having the sense that you're supported by the straight and relaxed spine
and then bringing to mind some motivation
for practicing it could just be your specific motivation for this sit
it could be your overall inspiration to practice
it's nice if it has an altruistic dimension to it connecting with your
your inspiration
and then establishing in the mind
mindfulness so bringing the awareness of the present moment
to the foreground
and actually taking a deliberate period of time to sense what it feels
like when there is mindfulness in the mind what does mindfulness feel like for you
right now perhaps clear and sharp
or soft and warm
broad and spacious
what is the flavor of mindfulness right now
and then gently turning the attention to the
sense of in and out breathing
you don't need to feel the breath at any specific place
but for now just maybe a general sense of knowing when you're breathing in and
when you're breathing out in whatever way it's easy to connect
with that
so we have the sense of mindfulness the sense of in and out breathing
allowing that to fill the attention
if the mind feels drawn toward other concerns at this time
you just gently say not now i will definitely get back to you later
for now staying with the
in and out breathing
and now we draw the attention a little bit closer to the breath
in order to know the length of the breath
all that needs to be known is whether it's on the longer side or on the shorter
side the in breath and the out breath
so we have to pay attention along the whole length of the breath
and then the whole length of the out breath
just generally knowing is the in-breath long or short is the
out breath long or short they might be different
natural breath
we may find that as we watch the breath gradually gets
shorter release the active part of the breath
there may be a longer gap
[Music]
and then opening the awareness now to feel the entire body breathing
we don't change the breath at all just change the breadth of the attention
so that we're aware of the whole body sitting and the breath occurring in the body
no longer needing to notice the length
and when the mind feels connected throughout the body
still paying attention to the in and out breathing
we incline the mind toward tranquility
in the body
it helps to physically soften [Music]
areas of tension
it helps that the simple repetitive nature of the breath
can act as a an anchor for the mind
allowing other feelings of busy energy in the body to settle out
search tranquility throughout the body
and when the mind gets distracted as it surely will
we just smile [Music] and gently return
to the sense of the whole body in and out breathing
[Music] and an invitation to
tranquility of the body
it's a soft invitation not a our narrow focus
on the breath
points toward ease
a simple sense of being present with the body and the breath
as the body becomes even slightly more tranquil
the bodily activities are calmed even a bit
we can recheck the posture maybe a slight shift would help the body
feel more balanced
it's natural that as tensions release some adjustments are helpful
just balancing with that sense of in and out breathing
and as the body becomes somewhat more
calm it's very natural that a sense of joy
can arise so opening the mind to the possibility
of a kind of inner joy that comes about because of being in
meditation
it's often felt in the body feels like a almost like an inner smile
emerging from that ease
but even if it's very mild or we don't even feel any of that joy
we can also feel in the mind just a sense of contentment
content that we are mindful at this moment present for
what's going on in the body and the mind
the joy the slight joy of mindfulness can be this
contentment
if we can feel the happiness of presence it's actually a happiness that's always available
anytime we're mindful
so allowing the mind and body to feel this inner
joy or at least contentment
mindfulness does not always have to be a neutral noting of
exactly what's happening we can incline the mind
toward this kind of inner well-being and pleasure
just allow that to be there resting in that
along with the body and the in and out breathing
it's natural that as we feel even some degree of this joy
happiness of sitting of breathing that the mind will become calmer
we see that busy mental activities of wanting or not wanting
are less enjoyable than simple presents
resting in awareness we can watch the movements of the mind
slowly settle out as we watch the agitation in the body
slowly settle out
such tranquility available
we can get a sense that peace is possible
pretty close to our daily life something quite different is available
when the mind is able to be present and still
and although the conditions will change in a few minutes
we might consider as we go out into the world
change our way of being our level of consciousness
what are we willing to give up our peace for
this peace that we feel
what is more important than that as we get out into our lives
is it worth getting tangled up in a conflict or in anxiety
or in pursuit of something
is there a way we could just carry this into our interactions
into our work into our errands of the day or our tasks
and to see what a gift that is for others maybe they too would feel just a bit of
that
gil often says there's no way to practice just for yourself
it has to help others even in these very simple ways if we carry the
practice forward from meditation into the world
foreign
[Music]
hmm
so yesterday we talked about two sets of three two triads
where one is unwholesome and one is wholesome and the two sets are
sense desire comma ill will and cruelty on one side and
renunciation which is nate comma or letting go of sense pleasures non-ill will and non-cruelty
on the other side and we learned that in buddhist teachings these are applied to
intentions and thoughts and perceptions such that we might say that renunciation
or letting go is an attitude that we can bring to our life
and it's skillful which means that it leads onward on the path of spiritual development
so i didn't get to quite all the sutas that talk about this triad and i want to read just one more a little excerpt from
just one more because it points out that these same sets of three
are important in relationship and community life so
the buddha says in one suta i am not even comfortable thinking about
a place where people argue quarreling and fighting continually
wounding each other with barbed words let alone going there i come to a conclusion about them
clearly those people have given up three things and cultivated three things
what three things have they given up thoughts of renunciation good will and harmlessness
and what three things have they cultivated thoughts of sensuality ill will and
cruelty and then of course the converse i feel comfortable going to a place
where the people live in harmony appreciating each other without quarreling blending like milk and water
and regarding each other with kindly eyes let alone just thinking about it
i come to a conclusion about them clearly those people have given up three things and cultivated three things
what three things have they given up thoughts of sensuality ill will and cruelty
and what three things have they cultivated thoughts of renunciation letting go as
good will and harmlessness so non-attachment to
various pleasures of the senses helps other people it helps us live in harmony
just as much as will and non-cruelty do
so caring about relationship and communal harmony is one aspect of what i've been calling
this week the more elevated human desires and the happiness that these kinds of
desires bring could be called the happiness of letting go which is kind of our topic for today
the happiness of letting go so we talked previously about how the
buddha emphasized the disadvantages of sense pleasures in rather stark terms i read a
bunch of those images a couple of days ago and i know that they were maybe a little
bit surprising and how strong they were you know things like
a dog gnawing on a meatless bone and not getting any satisfaction from it things
like that and i pointed out that probably he wanted to wake us up from our
dream world of trying to secure our happiness through getting things that are not very
reliable and not really in our control but the good the good news i mean that's
good news too that he wanted to wake us up like that but the other good news is that uh the buddha had kind of a dual
strategy so he talked about how ultimately unsatisfying sense pleasures are and he
also talked about the happiness and bliss that come from these more elevated
pleasures and those pleasures become available when we are willing to give up material
and sensual forms of enjoyment and that doesn't mean that we're not going to have them and we give up the attachment
to them right so but it's you know we we're so entangled sometimes it's hard to see
where the attachment is and where the direct pleasure is but so it doesn't mean you need to get
rid of all your stuff and you know live in grim austerity but we have to give up the attachment to those
things or we can't experience these higher forms of happiness so it says in the dhammapada
if by giving up a lesser happiness one could experience greater happiness
a wise person would renounce the lesser to behold the greater
do you agree so the word here for that's translated as lesser
uh is a not a very clear word exactly what it means and it could also be interpreted as material
and some translations actually say it that way i read gil's translation so whether or not that word literally
means material i think that's a fair interpretation of the meaning of this verse
so that material happinesses are lesser and then you know say spiritual happinesses are greater
so you know it's it's not a difficult trade-off which is the greater happiness
getting some kind of food that you want or creating a good relationship with your partner
some kind of material gain or being honest you know when when the choice is made
then the trade-off is made that way it seems obvious so one of the things that we start
seeing as we cultivate beautiful qualities of the heart and mind that is when we value them when we
desire to increase them there is desire behind cultivation
so one of the things that we see is that sensual happiness has a kind of built-in
limitation to it so let's say i i'm enjoying an apple
and if i eat that apple no one else can eat that apple that's just how it works
in the material world but if i experience the happiness of say
being honest it doesn't interfere with anybody else's happiness there's an
infinite supply of these kinds of more elevated pleasures
which is a good thing you know it just works differently in that realm right
so let's move on to some other aspects of these elevated pleasures
the buddha was a teacher of the full eightfold path and he also highlighted that the
happiness of meditative development is a much deeper kind of happiness than
various sensual happinesses sometimes the ordinary pleasures that we
experience are called the five chords of sensual pleasure that's just the phrase
that's used in the teachings so things that are enjoyable sights and sounds and
smells tastes touches and there's a teaching i'm reading a lot from the
pseudos today it seems where the buddha says should anyone say
the five chords of sensual pleasure are the utmost pleasure and joy that human
beings experience i would not concede that to them why is that
because there is another kind of pleasure that is loftier and more sublime than that pleasure
and what is that secluded from sensual pleasures secluded from unwholesome states a practitioner
enters and abides in the first genre and then it goes on to other levels of concentration so that's
referring to deep states of meditation but really it could be any state of meditation where the mind has let go of
wanting and not wanting somewhat like what we did in the guided meditation
so it's interesting that it says that the precondition for meditative composure of mind let's say
is seclusion from sensual pleasures and unwholesome states
so once again we have to give up those pleasures in order to experience meditative calm and unification
and in that case on wholesome states refers to the five entrances
which are a different list so one of the other uses of this term
necoma that we talked about yesterday the word that's usually translated as renunciation but could also be letting
go is giving up distraction in meditation that's another way that it's used in the
buddhist teachings so that the mind can find ease and calm
letting go of stories and rumination and thinking about our views
is also part of renunciation as the buddha meant that term
there's a story of a man who comes to the buddha and he says that he understands he's a practice long time
practitioner and says that he understands that great and hatred and delusion are the main problems in the
human mind and he definitely wants not to go in that direction but that he
still gets overcome by desire for sense pleasure sometimes and he asks the buddha why that is
and the buddha says oh it's it's easy it's because you don't know a better form of happiness
so it happened that that that practitioner had not deeply experienced any alternative to
sense pleasure so in that case you know the buddha didn't tell the man about all the dangers and
terrible problems that come from sense pleasures he didn't give him all those images that i read the other day
he simply said there are better forms of happiness but you haven't cultivated them yet so of course you're not willing
to give up sensuality so he he points toward the toward the positive and sense toward the
other forms of happiness so this makes sense humans are not going to give up
happiness we're very strongly drawn to happiness and we have a natural desire for
happiness if i could say it that way so the buddha used this desire for
well-being and peace and freedom that we have and we wish to be free of the pain of
great hatred and delusion he used that to encourage us on the path
he encouraged creating harmonious relationships being ethical being caring
and developing the mind and meditation and all of these are these loftier forms of pleasure
so we're actually meant to experience to fully take in this happiness that is not
sensual we don't need to be just neutrally mindful all the time
it's good to feel joy and contentment and ease and peace to whatever degree they're available in a moment and even
if the moment is unpleasant you know even if we have a bodily pain of some kind or in a
situation that's challenging it is always possible to have a slight
joy in the mind simply from being mindful of that i know i've experienced that i've had
the sense when mindfulness was there of wow this is really unpleasant but
i'm glad to be knowing it i would rather know it than not know it
so another quote this is the bliss of renunciation the
bliss of seclusion the bliss of peace the bliss of enlightenment
i say of this kind of pleasure that it should be pursued that it should be
developed that it should be cultivated and that it should not be feared
how about that the buddha says this kind of bliss should not be feared head straight into it
the bliss of renunciation and the bliss of peace and the more that we experience these
higher forms of happiness actually the less attractive sensual pleasures become we look back at those
from some other place and we wonder why we invested so much in them
so our desires shift over time over the course of the path
more and more often we find ourselves wanting ease peace harmony awareness
wisdom sometimes people are a little bit surprised that something that used to be
enjoyable for them now feels a little bit coarse there's a
refinement and also a lightening up of the mind it's actually a bit of a relief to let
go of the more stressful forms of pleasure and this is also a way of healing you
know healing of the mind and heart we live with more well-being and we're
more often able to care for others more fully when we've started to let go of these
busier more stressful forms of of pleasure so the happiness of letting go i would
say is one of the great discoveries on the buddhist path and it draws us along the path further
and at some point we will feel the desire to move on even from these
states of well-being because the deepest stirring in the heart is the desire for complete freedom
which is what we will touch into a bit tomorrow so thank you for this ongoing journey
and i hope to see you then