and good morning
all yeah how's the sound yeah
great so we'll start with a sitting is it a little
high thanks good thank you yeah we'll start with a sitting
let's um welcome ourselves to the
seat beginning with reconnecting our bodies
to the Earth this companion of ours
that's always with us
so first inviting the attention to the
point of contact with the
Earth sits bones low
body finding your stable base for
and upon that stable base little bit by little bit allowing
the spine to grow long and
Tall all the way up through the crown the back top of the
head
as the spine grows long you may find your body adjusting
itself you may want to roll your shoulders back and let go of any of the tensions in the upper body
and the invitation and for this half [Music] hour is to let the
upright steady alert yet relaxed
body guide the attention
bringing our attention to this breathing
body
for
for for
and as we settle into contact with this breathing
body you may notice you may notice tensions or
contractions build up over a few
minutes and with an easy deep breath full inhale and exhale
just letting those
go and renewing the
posture
for for
for
to accompany this breathing
body with our simple straightforward
attention in its textures and temperatures
and when the inner Worlds the images
fantasies have the
attention the moment of recognition oh fantasy
and then gently releasing the thought the idea like a
helium balloon letting it float away into the
sky
e
for
for for
to accompany this breathing body
releasing any of the tensions the
Holdings that build up or
accumulate easing
into a simple settled awareness
Here and
Now
for
for for
and in our last minutes of this
sitting the invitation is to
release relax any
effort in the meditation relaxing the
body relaxing the mind to sense
into in your experience now if there's any any hint
of the wholesome qualities of settl or ease or collectedness that have
Arisen just a minute to appreciate
those and if there's no hint of that in the experience
is continuing to accompany the breathing
body for
[Music]
so again welcome so nice to be with you and my name is
cotto it's such a pleasure such a pleasure to be here I I have um a lot of appreciation and respect for
the the practice at the IMC and IRC communities here and in Scotts
Valley I feel a very very strong connection to this place so uh it feels
wonderful to manifest that here with you um and a pleasure to sit together I
mean to spend a Sunday morning sitting in meditation sharing in the Dharma talking about the
Dharma in this bit of relative Stillness which I'm not sure for you but
stands in some real contrast to how the attention can be during the week sometimes I feel like a caffeinated
bumblebee moving around from flower to flower it feels quite nice to just
simplify and settle the attention on the on the body and the breathing so the theme for today is joy
and the first Noble Truth and the perspective that I want to
I want to discuss this morning is that there's a way of looking there's a way of understanding this path of
practice of course emphasizes this first Noble Truth of Dua which I'll unpack a
bit but step by step there's also joy happiness pleasure in different forms
all the way all the way along so of course of course many paths
in Buddhist practice and many of them emphasize this teaching of dukka the
first Noble Truth dukka suffering unsatisfactoriness
now why why is that emphasized so much and just what is
that let's start with the why and then we'll talk about the what so to illustrate this I'd like you
to imagine um let's say you have a little bit of an injury let's say you've twisted an ankle and it doesn't seem to
be getting better maybe you have a sprain you have decided to consult a
doctor so you make an appointment you make your way there uh you make your way
to the second floor uh you wait a little while and then it's time for you to see the
physician as you as you make your way to the examination room usually they're empty but you see the doctor is already
in there and you think huh okay you take your
seat and before the doctor can turn around before they can ask your name
before they can see your ankle before they can feel look talk to you ask any questions for the sake of this example
they have no information they write a prescription and they hand it to you and send you to
the pharmacy how effective can we imagine that remedy
might be compared to one where there was an examination and such maybe not so
maybe not so effective so it seems pretty natural as
a principle that to have an effective remedy we have to understand understand the ailment and that the more fully we
understand the ailment like deeply really the
better so it's just like this so similar in our Dharma practice and this this is
one reason that the teaching of dukka this teaching of suffering is emphasized so
much it's the ailment that we study it's the the condition that
Buddhist practice mindfulness practice aims to
address emphasizing this point the Buddha is often quoted as saying in the past monks and also now I teach
suffering and the cessation of suffering in the ancient text one way
that the final goal of the practice is described is as the full understanding
of dukka the full understanding of suffering that then in turn liberates
so this gives us a sense this gives us a sense of why this is focused on so much the
liberating potential of understanding Dua and the metaphor to be healed to be
freed of the ailment through full
understanding and how about the what just what do we mean duka ancient
word apparently canotes a wheel that's a little off kilter clun clunk duka duka
clun clun and in brief the teaching points to
this entire spectrum of experiences uh of suffering and stress
everything from these maybe we can relate to some of these like the the the fiery grip of ill will the stress of
that or something as profound as the grief of the loss of a loved one
all the way to something quite mild the stress of mild physical discomfort that comes along with having
a human body and then the very subtle stresses involved in the simple acts of
perception and knowing very
subtle and then back out to the most profound things we all share like the stresses of Aging illness and death at
some point in our life I say those three quickly but I as I say them I notice I
kind of want to slow down and appreciate that it's something that we all
share so this entire Spectrum from the gross to the subtle to the profound of
suffering and stress in brief that's what we mean by
dukka and for this talk what I really want to emphasize is that with with a working definition like this
our understanding of Dua deepens and grows wise as we practice
with it as we practice the recognition of stress in our lives and its
conditions and its release not just wise mentally but our
heart grows wise so where do we begin with the
practice of duka first Noble Truth
first important principle I want to bring in for the practice of dukka is that we don't address suffering in the
abstract duka doesn't doesn't address a suffering in the abstract but in
fact it's presented to address specific stress this specific stress for specific
people that's
us and just as the skilled doctor doesn't address the concept of the twist ankle they actually get in there and
relate to your own body your own ailment in this sense the teachings of
dukka point to point our attention to our own direct experience our own direct
experience and I think that welcomes us to pause at any time and say oh how is this for me now what's here
now is there is there any any level of suffering and stress here how is it and
just as we were doing in the meditation feeling in what are the textures here what's the temperature the particulars
how is this manifesting in my body my heart and impulses and in my
mind and this way of looking at dukka
uh very closely related to our practice of mindfulness our sitting practice our
practice of awareness what is it I can know and understand
directly through my experience so it applies whether we're
seated applies whether we're walking whether we're talking whether we're working this careful attention this
mindfulness and this skill of discernment what's going on here begins to reveal more and
more layers and subtleties of duka and this uh this growth of understanding
is the trajectory of our practice so in my own experience and
also talking to other people there there are certain things that begin to reveal themselves as we practice mindfulness as
we practice mindfulness of dukka mindfulness of
stress and one is it won't take long before we before we encounter these sorts of stresses that
we all share that I paused to appreciate a moment
ago we all go through the the sufferings and stresses of birth presumably though
I I don't know how many of us remember um those of Aging when my my
body stops working the way that I relied on it for
illness and eventually thankful to our
very sophisticated Minds able to know that someday we will
pass so simply our practice of mindfulness with dukka again it
reveals uh it reveals these sort of universal experiences in their particular
manifestations and all of their Dynamics and all of their shapes and
structures and again this in itself is the path and there might be something in there
there might be something in there where uh we have these we have these experiences of duka and mindfulness
meets them and maybe there's just a touch of relief maybe there's just a touch of a
touch of ease that comes in through a practice of awareness maybe something in the heart
begins to grow easeful and still and wise this can start to hint at the
relationship between Joy
Anda another thing that might begin to reveal itself in uh in practice of mindfulness
of suffering and stress is the pars this practice of how is it now how
is it manifesting now how is it shifting changing great example is while we're
meditating physical pain physical pain I don't know about for you
for me it often arises as a a single uh monolithic signal it's like a big
no in the mind no thank you but you know mindfulness practice
getting a little closer both to that big no thank you and into the actual
Sensations this phrase is really coming up for me this morning text and
temperatures how hot is it is it moving is it pulsing is it sharp is it
soft mindfulness of stresses begins to reveal these
particulars it's true in the in the in the world of physical sensation it's also true in our emotional
life when anger arises as a big no thank you advanced
practice what's the constellation there the constellation of Sensations thoughts and impulses that I call
anger so again practice of mindfulness begins to
reveal through discernment the actual situation and because Dua is Shifting
and changing and it's not just one thing actually that's one of the most
hopeful hopeful points of the practice because these experiences rely on conditions the conditions can also
fall away so as our discernment
deepens another thing that begins to reveal itself is the importance of clear discernment of the experience
itself and our relationship to that experience the experience itself and our
relationship to the experience and how a how a skillful or unskillful relationship to experience
can either compound the stress or maybe the word
undermine undermine to illustrate this I want to tell a little
story it's a story about two phone calls um when I was uh when I was
younger when I was younger uh first phone call I received and I learned about the
passing of my grandmother I remember hearing the
sound I remember the shock and I
remember the the following days kind of actually just being numb because it was so much for me it was so much I couldn't
feel much and the grief took a really long time second phone call some years later
I received on the very last day of a Meditation Retreat I'd been sitting doing
mindfulness of the Body for 10 days and I got this important
message Cotto there's a phone call for you phone same ear almost the same sound
cot your grandmother has passed away other grandmother had passed owing to the state of the mind
and my relationship to experience at the time what happened this time
heard the sound go in I felt the body register the body really registered the
experience and it was it was amazing it it was like a uh bubbles from top to
bottom it just and within a couple of minutes the
the sensations had actually passed I hadn't um I hadn't suppressed or pushed away the experience it fully
registered and it was entirely clean such
that uh after after my body processed in that way I was able to completely be
there for the person on the other end of the phone two very very similar stimuli very
similar news over the telephone wildly different experiences in terms of compounding the
suffering or not and I want to take care here it was through no fault of my first version of
me that the suffering was compounded those were the conditions of the
moment but just to say there's the experience relationship to that
experience and how it can either compound or not compound suffering one of the things that starts
to reveal itself is the practice of mindfulness and discernment grows in US
so this development of mindfulness and discernment in relationship to
suffering on this path toward full understanding of suffering and stress
this full understanding of duka it happens gradually of course of course just like the other other ways we grow
in our lives right um but I often find myself coming back to this quote from the Buddha
describing this saying that just as the great ocean has a gradual shelf a
gradual slope a gradual inclination with a sudden drop off only
after a long stretch in the same way this dhma and
vinia this practice this way of life has a gradual training gradual performance a
gradual practice and I find that encouraging because a practice that's
that's uh that so emphasizes mindfulness of suffering and stress um especially on the mental level
it can hurt can really hurt so it's encouraging me to know to me to know
mindfulness and and discernment they develop gradually gradually gradually
even if it doesn't feel so good as we're
going and of course course there is good news one of the next things that we
begin to discern in uh mindfulness and discernment
practice is how duka and jooy happiness well-being they
accompany each other all the way along the path all the way along and I find this
so interesting um that's that uh if I zoom out if I
take any particular experience if I view it wide enough both elements are there
that's fascinating to me and and isn't it more complex and aren't there instances in our lives
where of course there are the joys and the pleasures and of course there are the sufferings and the stresses and how
they mingle I think this is this is a very rich area for
practice I think of maybe something many or all of us remember remember do you remember the
pleasant anticipation of the ending of shelter in place like oh I'm going to
see people I see Hands going [Laughter] up and I don't know about you but that
was followed by a real awkwardness and over stimulation it was
so easy to be over stimulated the joy and the stress right there
together or in terms of work um I can imagine a sort of the
joyful direction of working toward a project or a promotion or something
coupled with the stresses of overwork or even Leisure a day at the
beach and then there's the sunburn these are just some everyday
examples at a sort of Broad View that incorporate both and then of course we see we see
this close relationship between dukka and joy in the
teachings I think even of the first and second Noble Truths Dua and its arising duka and
its cause sometimes real emphasis on the
difficulty the stress and then the third and fourth Noble Truths there's cessation the path to the
ending of cessation the relief of release the joy happiness wellbeing represented by the third and the fourth
noal truths and I really appreciate how how close
they are how close they are what the relationship is I think this is well represented by a a Zen
phrase in front of the Cliff of dead trees flowers and plants are always in
spring so to look further into the teachings I think we can see that that
Dua and some form of skillful happiness whether it be Joy or gladness or well-being or happiness is associated
with the entire path in terms of the three trainings the
trainings in CA the precepts virtue the training in concentration Sami
collectedness and the training in wisdom Liberation and letting go
in terms of the training in CeeLo one of the great pleasures of the ethical
training is called the Bliss of blamelessness the Bliss of blamelessness
where the the mind that's free of remorse knowing that it has not harmed a
being knowing that it has not harmed a being such joy and settledness in the
mind and it has a very close relationship to understanding how we
create Dua for ourselves and others through our actions very close relationship that
actually encour encourages our restraint and gives way to this sort of
pleasure and then of course in terms of the training and
somadi this very deep settled joy and well-being that comes from a unified
mind very closely related to developing the discernment of the stresses and the mental
activities that actually get in the way of the Mind unifying the real discernment full
understanding and then the training of wisdom Joy is a factor for
awakening uh of these seven factors that when they're fully mature issue in a
full understanding of dukka and Awakening
another teacher put this puts it this way there's no scarcity on the path of beautiful
scenery the flowers know how to laugh and the birds know how to
sing another interesting interesting twist here is that the same practice of
mindfulness and discernment that we we apply to dukka also applies to our Pleasures our Joys and happiness
very generally very roughly speaking we might begin to see that there are ways of relating to our
Pleasures that bind and Fetter and there are ways of relating to Pleasures that
free and liberate and again here it's the relationship it's the
relationship to the pleasures of course there are there's
this teaching of the five chords of sensual pleasure that are are said to Fetter or
bind and uh venerable saruta one of these Chief Disciples of the Buddha in
the in the time of the early s when explaining this someone had a really good question for venerable saruta and
said these experiences we get tied up with these five chords of sensual
pleasure the eye and sights ear and sounds nose and smells tongue and tastes the body and tactile
Sensations venerable saruta is it the eye that is the issue here or is it the
thing is it the sight is it the ear or is it the sound
nose or the smell tongue or The Taste venerable saruta give me a clue I want to I want
to learn how to be free and he said oh in fact it's neither it's not the eye it's
not the sights it's not the ears it's not the Sounds in fact he says it's the craving
and cing linging that arises there that fets this is really good
news really good news sometimes I don't know if this ever arises for you but
sometimes practitioner will get the notion that oh I'm not supposed to see hear taste or touch
anything venerable saruta is saying no it's okay for you to be a human and live
a human life to have these sense experiences and the thing to see the
thing to become intimate with is there a relationship of craving and
clinging relative to the these senses if so binding
fettering and these of course stand in contrast to these um maybe what I'll call liberating Pleasures or liberating
forms of happiness that we we talked about a minute ago this Bliss of blamelessness doesn't tend toward
generating craving and clinging the mind is in a wholesome State doesn't tend to develop that
relationship same with the pleasures of a collected mind and the happiness of Letting Go
moving in the opposite direction so a simple question a simple
heuristic as you're going going uh going through your practice of mindfulness and
discernment relative to Joys just as relative to Dua relative to
suffering and stress what is it here that's Arisen what is
this experience and what's my relationship to it is there clinging here or is there
Freedom you can let that let that be information be
information I find a lot of inspiration when I ask myself oh just how far can this go how far does this go which is a
little dance step to me thinking about really practitioners and their
qualities um there's this book written by Douglas Abrams called The Book of
joy you hav't seene lovely cover Archbishop Desmond Tutu and the Dalai
Lama smiling I think somewhere maybe on the back cover they're dancing they're
dancing together just fabulous and the one thing that really
stuck out to me about uh Douglas Abrams comments about being a part of these
conversations was how much the Dal Lama and the Archbishop laugh they
laugh someone like the Dalai Lama who has known such
profound difficulty and the
Archbishop and still This Joy this laughter I find that so
encouraging I hear the same thing about um Suzuki roshi Who was the zen teacher that founded the Zen Center if you ever
read transcripts of Suzuki Roshi's talks he'll get like halfway through a sentence and he'll
laugh oh just love it there's a levity there's a levity along with this
intimacy with suffering and stress there are these beautiful joyful heart
qualities and these folks that have dedicated their lives to to to practice
in their own way
so just as duka is conditioned so too is Joy so too is
joy and this opens a doorway for us this opens a possibility in our practice that
that um we can through our observation and discernment uh start to recognize or
deepen our recognition how did this come to be not always an intellectual exercise
though that reflective exercise is helpful but even on our even on our meditation cushion just abiding there
with the body and the breathing as suffering and stress
arises and passes away as Joy arises and joy passes
away and through keeping a a contact as continuous as we can even if the mind
doesn't recognize oh this is how Dua was constructed this is how Joy was constructed the heart knows something
the heart has watched it happen I um one of my teachers really
likes to remind me that something maybe even more than three qus of communication happens
non-verbally through the body I haven't seen this anywhere but I
like to apply that principle to mindfulness practice maybe three4 of what we learn
isn't through intellectual understanding but something even if we don't hear it
think it something is is
recognized one more encouragement and then maybe a
story and that encouragement
is something about something about holding joy and Dua joy and
stress close to one another recognizing that they can be aspects of one EXP
experience what this opens up for me is that it it's not necessarily like there's an onoff switch oh it's just
going to be 100% dukka oh it's just going to be 100% Joy but in
fact in fact there can be this mixture and actually I can influence this
process there can be these little moments of wholesome qualities little
moments of mindfulness tiny moments of discernment tiny moments of recognizing oh this is
this is wellbeing just a moment and just like in the DAP drop by drop the jar
gets filled the jar gets
filled developing our full understanding of dukka and just filling
our bodies and hearts hopefully over time in this direction so we'll be dancing like the Dal Lama and the
Archbishop so a story to
close this is from the
udana in the time of the time of the Buddha there's a monk venerable
badia a former King who became a monk and he's been practicing the Dharma as
he does going on alms round and then he'll finish his alms round and do his love this phrase his day's abiding his
day's meditation at the root of a tree and the um the other monks
nearby overhear the venerable Bia in his meditation exclaiming what Bliss what
Bliss and the monks think in their compassionate hearts and their wish for well-being uh-oh the former King is
thinking about the joys of kingship I think he might be about to run away
from the training we had better go tell the Buddha such compassionate ones good
friends in the Dharma so they report this to the Buddha
and the Buddha invites Bia to visit and says
this oh the other way venerable Bia goes to the blessed one to the Buddha as he's
sitting there the Buddha doesn't assume anything I love this too he says is it true
Bia that on going to the Wilderness to the root of a tree do dot dot you repeatedly exclaim what Bliss what
Bliss yes pante yes doesn't assume anything the Buddha
what compelling reason do you have in mind like why why why are you doing that
when you go to the Wilderness when you go into meditation why is it that you repeatedly exclaim what Bliss what
Bliss and the venerable Bia gives his answer and he says
before before when I was a king maintaining the Bliss of
kingship every every luxury he said I had guards
posted inside the Royal apartment outside the Royal apartment
inside the city outside the city just layers of guards and he says I dwell in fear
agitated distrustful and
afraid but now when I go to the Wilderness when I go and do my days abiding my days
meditation I dwell without fear I dwell without fear unagitated
confident unafraid unconcerned
unruffled living on the gifts of others with my mind like a wild deer
which sounds very pleasant
so joy in the first Noble
Truth in Sun our path
our practice of mindfulness and discernment of comprehending fully
suffering and stress practicing with that I'll say it will not be without its
Joys and our path of joy and well-being it will not be
without its stresses so may it be at those
times of joy joy and in those times of stress and those times when it's very
clearly a mix May these practices of mindfulness
and discernment support this onward leading
path toward a full understanding of dukka and complete freedom for ourselves
and for all beings without exception
wonderful so we have um we have just a few minutes if if there are any
questions does that seem like that will
work it's on it's on okay hello thank you for your talk and
the meditation um my question comes in I I love this
sense of the suffering and the joy being present at the same time I feel that's
true in my experience and resonates very well this
um the opening or the release that allows you maybe to shift towards
feeling Joy more fully and a little bit less compounding of the suffer
suffering I guess the the the question becomes you know how how do you remember
oh how do you remember that oh this knee is caught right now oh let me release
that knee or oh there's somewhere else that I'm unaware of that I'm holding even as
I speak this question and feel mostly released but a little bit of energy that
I'm the center of the attention of the question sure sure thank you for the
question I imagine this resonates for many of us um it's mysterious isn't it
remembering we can ask a similar question when we're when we're practicing meditation and say the the
Mind moves into a distraction oh feel free thank
you how is it that all of a sudden there's a moment of recognition it's not like we we didn't
do that we didn't put it there we didn't put the recognition
there there's uh for me I think there's there's comfort and
confidence in knowing that we can trust Our intention for the
practice as I said as I said that principle of of maybe 75% I'm making that number up of communication being
non-verbal I think we can can trust our trust our sense that we have invested
something in the practice and the body and the mind know and that intention will manifest in
the moment of of stress and you'll see oh there it is and this begins to mature or or
deepens uh through repeated practice as a this this phrase I kept
using of the heart growing Wise It's almost like it's almost like
the system or the heart begins to recognize sooner that it's in a it's in a a bind
or a stress or a tension or something sometimes begins to recognize
sooner and then as we through trial and error skillfulness skillfulness in
releasing grows so for me the question uh is um
how to keep supporting that intention and then it will work on
us how to how to support that intention yeah um I I think it's
um all sorts of ways we do this all sorts of ways consistency in the
practice good Dharma friends good reminders a sticky
note um I get personally I get a lot of support from the practice being
regular so if it if it shows up in my day at a certain time it's like all of
the forces of the mind and heart coales and we we're doing this we're doing this practice and something about doing it at
the same time of day um builds it into the system and that really helps the
intention and then of course there are explicit ways that that you can do this you can you can write about your
intention um friends of mine who practice at the beginning of a sit and at the end of a Sit will give one
sentence of their intention for practice just to remind themselves and let that
let that guide those are some ideas yeah thank you
sure maybe time for one more great hold it like a
rockar so you were talking about anger kind of like being say um like saying No
thank you to mindfulness right like that was and so a question is
like when um when you have that feeling of anger it's often hard to control
yourself oh yeah like um be because like you're just just really upset it's hard
it's really hard tool in that moment so like how are you able to be able to
control that and just bring it back to okay um and just kind kind of lower it
to okay I'm upset but like the level where you're all where you can use
mindfulness in order to just recognize that Dua and the joy that comes along
with it wow fabulous thank you for the question um what's what's your name Aviv
Aviv Cotto nice to meet you um two things come to my mind yeah
well one three things one is like this upwelling of appreciation for the question that that is a that is a
difficult thing to to develop that skill maybe we'll
call it impulse control where the compulsion the compulsion from anger is so intense or can be so intense and it
almost comes along with like this promise of yumminess almost oh if I act this out this is going to feel really
good there's something there's something that balances that and that is actually
recognizing after the impulse has made its way out say I've acted on acted on anger the balance to the Yum is actually
recognizing how how it hurts how it hurts someone else and how it hurts you
and paying attention to that is very very skillful training of the mind and heart because you have you have more
data and like I said the heart starts to grow wise oh if I if I take this yummy
feeling step by expressing my anger oh look I've actually I've actually hurt someone and I can feel how that's
hurt that's one that's one approach and then there are sort of practical things that uh that we can do to support to
support impulse control one thing is just like over time practicing it but
I'm certain uh whatever you can do and maybe you have some ideas about this whatever you can do to slow down the
momentum if you if the if the impulse is there uh if the anger is coming up and
really wants to express itself in some kind of way that that may harm someone what can I do to slow down the
process classically one of the approaches is to to um feel the anger in the body feel
its heat and sort of let it sort of Let It radiate out when you're doing that you're not
harming anyone you're not suppressing it or pushing it away or saying oh I'm not angry
but you're also not causing causing harm something that I like to do when I get when I uh when I feel that impulse I
take my oh this is a gill phrase I take my anger for a
walk I let the body move because often this be the the last thing that I say
the body gets charged with it and and the charge is
reinforced by all the sort of chemical changes that happen through anger and it needs a way to move through the system
so I take my anger for a walk do a little stretching do a
Sprint uh or occasionally I'll go into my room and I'll uh I'll grunt I'm not
I'm not I'm not grunting at anyone but I'll make like a and that seems to really help so
basically try to just like feel that ink the heat without really doing anything
and just let it slowly um radiate out until um in until your until um the
anger is out enough that you can that you can just then that you're that now
like you have have done enough impulse control that allows you to um be able to
like recognize the upsetness well said and as you reflected it back I realize
there's one more point and I know we're a minute over but it feels important to say
anger you can one way to relate to it it's really good information this can mean that something
important has just happened or like something's happening that actually I'm uh my body is signaling that I or
someone else is in danger and the information that you receive once um once you have sort of
processed anger in the way we're talking about so far then you can take a wiser
mind that's not under the influence of that emotion as much and actually
discern is there is there harm here is there something is there something I should do about this that I can do
skillfully that uh won't harm another won't harm me and can keep us all
safe how's that sound to VI yeah that makes sense thank you very
much great we've come to the end of our time again my appreciation
for you and your practice and your kind attention I am full of joy and I hope
you enjoy your Sunday we'll see each other again soon