greetings greetings dharma friends greetings from mountain view california
and seated oloneyland and lovely to sit with you this
friday morning morning my time different times for many of you
and this week i've had the delight and pleasure to
support you as gil has been traveling and for us to explore
the energy body or the mind's body and the different ways
that paying attention to the body can manifest in different experiences open
up insights support practicing so
so today we'll conclude we'll bring it all together and
uh and without further ado let's uh let's start practicing together let's
start sitting and um
yeah let's give ourselves let's give our hearts our bodies our minds
to this practice
let us arrive let us arrive and again and again and again
every moment a new arrival
in this body in this heart in this moment in time
releasing the body releasing the weight of the body
ah landing
so many sensations
this body alive pulsating breathing
let us invite our attention first too
land to feel our hands sensations of the hands
our fingers thumbs
palm of the hand the back of the hand
and especially
fail are able to feel a lot of sensations
so start here let's start here
as if our mind was in the hands feeling sensations
of coolness warmth
maybe the back of your hand is cool
maybe your palm is warm or not
contact pressure hands touching each other or your lap
maybe there's tingling
sense of movement
really taking the time to rest settle with the sensations of the hands
it's one of the most sensitive areas of the body and the rest will become easier if we take
our time here
letting the hands be relaxed giving their weight to the earth
notice notice if you really relax the hands
it feels like more sensations are felt
ah as if releasing allows for more
awareness to rush in
to be aware of the sensations
at the end of the out breath release some more
and no know the sensations
letting the wrists relax
the elbows feeling sensations
the wrist elbows lower arms
and upper arm
this amazing body incredible body alive
sensing knowing filled with sensations
contact pressure heaviness and lightness
warmth coolness
pulsating
let the sensations of the body the hands
arms let them have primacy
not thoughts right now fully fully inhabiting
the body and being curious as to what might arise what might shift in
this way of paying attention be curious
interested not the same old same old routine
letting the sensations in your face be sensed
the forehead
the eyes resting in their socket
your awareness you naturally want to move down to your cheeks
the muscles of the jaw
sensations the nose the upper lip
the lips touching each other
the tongue
resting so many sensations
wow
the chin [Music]
maybe even the ears sense of coolness worms
back of the head
brushing it with awareness
the entire head face
any tension has crept in to the eyes or the forehead or the jaw relax release
and sense some more
notice that as you release
more sensations become present available to be known
or is it that the mind becomes awareness becomes more available to know
doesn't matter right now
moving down to the neck
and shoulders simply knowing the sensations
for some there might be tightness or tension present
get to know it gently kindly without judgment or aversion
it's just a sensation
just a sensation we slap everything else on top of it all our reactions not
liking just get to know
letting awareness feel the sensations in the chest
what is most prominent
the chest the upper back as the breath moves through
so many sensations
moving down to the abdomen
lower back
letting awareness know the sensations and the sit bones on your bottom
contacting the cushion the chair
wow so many sensations
notice as you turn your awareness to this part of the body or any part
this part right now feels like it comes alive with
sensations wow so much pulsating
movement points of contact internal heat
external coolness perhaps
letting the mind move down to the upper legs
underneath the legs over the legs the top
center
the knees
let them be relaxed released and sensed
lower legs
and feet
so many sensations known from the inside
not the control tower of the head
the entire body all the sensations now this whole body
as the sensations reveal themselves to you
felt from within as if the sensation is sensing itself
that is how
you might feel in this moment the body the mind the heart
and appreciating the seeds of stability
of groundedness peace
that have been planted to nourish wisdom
and kindness because we're more stable available
here embodied spacious
and let us offer the goodness co-created together all
these goodness seeds planted
offer them from our heart generously as a
gift of our life our presence
to all beings everywhere including ourselves
may all beings everywhere
know their own goodness cultivate their own goodness
we all beings everywhere including ourselves
be wise kind compassionate and free
greetings greetings greetings friends and thank you for your
practice so
this week we have been exploring the mind's body or
the energy body some aspects of it there's so much more to explore so much
more to explore a lifetime the worth of uh practice is the
material to explore and yet and yet we've been exploring um them this week
together and um today i like to bring it all
together and also share some more teachings
so so as we started at the beginning of the
week with with the intention setting our intention
why are we exploring this and anguttara nikaya 4 45 the buddha said
the end of the world can never be reached by walking however without having reached the
world's end there is no release from suffering
i declare that it is this that it is in this fathom-long body
with its perceptions and thoughts that there is the world the origin of the world the cessation of
the world and the path leading to the cessation of the world so our our exploration of
course the body energy body is
for the purpose of awakening
path leading to awakening so it's not just fun and games even though
at times it might be it might appear so especially with some of the teachings i shared today which might seem sound a
little more esoteric but actually it's what naturally arises
then we explored together
the different locations of paying attention to the breath on on tuesday we
did that at the um abdomen in the abdomen chest and
nostrils and the pros and cons of each of those especially with
relationship to the hindrances on wednesday we explored a different way
of paying attention that that
can actually lead to insight uh to not self anata
that in this and we talked about the bahia sutra in the sensed only the
sensed only the sensed being in this sensation only
the sensation being known in and of itself in the body there's no self needed it's
and again there's so many layers layers to that teaching if you feel like you've
you've got it great and yet know that there's so many more layers to still know and explore
yesterday thursday we explored a sense of verticality in the energy body
as well as uh this bellowing in the orb and and um
spaciousness body without boundaries completely expanded and spacious
and how that might feel and also how that can be a support for for practice
of meta for pervading kindness and just really both physically
connecting to the heart can be a lovely practice and today in our practice in the guided
meditation i led us through a body scan and if you noticed often body scans
typically start from the feet or the head ends of the body but actually i think it's even though yes those are the
ends of the body seems you know makes sense and yet hands feel so much more sensation in our
brain there is a lot more area devoted to sensations of the hands so it makes more
sense actually with respect to neuroscience and knowing what we know about our bodies to start with the hands
to really settle the sensations of the hands and then move to the rest of the body
so just a note there and um and many many
um ways to do body scan many uh uh gifts that arise from it and
something that uh i was hoping would arise today with a
sense of stability sensing these sensations the groundedness of the mind
in the body and again different way of relating to the body this mind's body
this energy body i was hoping that the andy would feel um
you would sense wow so much sensations here and their sense of calm
a different shift it's hard often hard to put these in words but but i'll just leave that for your own
experience um exploration there's so much to explore here but one thing i do want to say in terms
of the teaching i want to add today is that
um well with with mindfulness of the body especially
in different ways that when paying attention um
and also different practices um samadhi concentration
can arise the sense of really the mind calming collecting
becoming stable stabilized and also what are called
um uh jonic factors can arise so the particular genic factor
and their five genic factors i think i've talked about them before here when i've subbed
for gail before when i talked about concentration for the whole week but today i want to talk specifically about
the the factor of what's called pt or rapture because that's really one way
that the energy body the shifts and movements in the energy body really show up
and a lot of times for practitioners when pt arises pt
translated both as rapture and also as joy there are many different aspects to it
when a rapture these the and rapture can show up pt let me just call it peach because
there's so many different ways that it can express and practitioners often get surprised like
whoa what is that and that's really the energy body or the mind's body shifting
moving different ways as if energy channels are opening
so gosh very little time left but very briefly there are five different types
of pt and these these are from the visudi maga uh path of purification
teachings so this is a practice manual a thousand pages long
and deep the first one is minor rapture which um can feel like hair standing on
end you might have had that experience of meditation um and
or or maybe tears flowing and minor rapture actually occurs for some
not all practitioners could happen in rare occasions some
people might experience it regularly and and some not experience it at all
the second type is called momentary pt and this can feel like a um like
um insects crawling on on your on your body and and i know that when i was a
beginning meditator i would open my eyes and look like wait something crawling no nothing and over time i realized oh
whenever that happens it means my mind is getting really really settled oh then
i would never i would open my eyes it's like yeah that's what that means so so it could feel like that it can feel like
uh maybe something cobwebs brushing your face or or
body jerks jolts movements of the body that are not
intentional like wow what is happening and sometimes practitioners get spooked out if this ever happens to you do not
get spooked out it's just energy body uh opening and moving and it will go through it will be a phase
the channels will open and then they will settle again so just there's so much about this body we don't know so
uh the third type is called
showering or flood it's like a showering uh pt
and it's a stronger it's like it can be a stronger shock of electricity sometimes it can feel like wow
electricity bright lights like bursting and bursting in the body
electricity way or or waves breaking on the shore and also sometimes it could be a lot of
movement and people feel like they're being rocked back and forth repeatedly being
tossed about and sometimes people can consider this uh blissful
and not and sometimes not blissful actually not pleasant like okay enough already
and again just letting it pass um the fourth type is uplifting joy or
transporting uh transporting pt which the mind can feel the body feels fluffy
light as if you're walking on air you um and supposedly this is how yogis
levitate i haven't experienced or witnessed that but supposedly this is this is the
energy body that supports that but but you can actually and i've experienced a lot of lightness just like walking on
clouds this body is fluff so again different aspects of the energy body and the last
one is um all pervading pt
which the sutas talk about especially with respect to the third genre
which is pervading and this one is actually this this pt this fifth kind is
is very blissful and it's just it's
joy bliss radiating all over the body it's a an extra ecstatic feeling
um that doesn't leave any part any cell of your body untouched just completely
drenched in in this the sense of of of of
of bliss and joy of this kind of energy body shifting and moving so
so i wanted to share these with you just in case they come up but but but also don't want to share these with you to
bring any sense of wanting because like i want to experience that well
if you practice give your heart to the practice dedicatedly end and
they will arise if they need to arise it's not about fun and games it's about
awakening and being kinder being more generous being more
more wise for our own benefit and others and these are some aspects that can come up in our practice
because we all have bodies we all have bodies so
so thank you all for for joining this week
for your practice for your dedication for your exploration it's been a delight and joy to support
you to share these teachings that are dear to me and and i hope they've been supportive to you
in in your practice and your awakening in your life as service
to yourself and to others opening your heart opening your mind to this amazing
body of ours this this mind's body this mind's body the
energy body so thank you all and let us dedicate the
benefit the goodness of our whole week of practice together to all beings everywhere
including ourselves genus generously may all beings
may all beings including ourselves be free be wise be compassionate
thank you all take good care