so hello everyone and welcome
so in the journey through the sati patana sutta through the buddha's teachings on
developing a heightened awareness in our lives
we're now in the second foundation and from here on out the second third and fourth
the practice that's emphasized is knowing
is to know what's happening in the earlier exercise there were other things that for the
first foundation there was knowing there was experiencing there was relaxing the body
there was clear comprehension there was a the use of the imagination
or reflection in order to connect to the part different aspects of the body
and but here on it just to understand or to know kavodi
translates it understands i like to translate it as to know one knows
and and knowing is really kind of at the heart of
sati of mindfulness and when we know we emphasize the
knowing uh sometimes it's easy to get lost or
focused too much on the thing that we're getting to know as if that is uh
the important thing and it is important and i don't want to diminish its value of really seeing clearly
but there's another side to knowing and that is that
knowing does not interfere with what is known knowing is a very simple
practice they're just knowing without judgment without a value without
criticism or without desires or aversions just know and but that that and one of the reasons
that's important is that knowing makes room in the mind for something new to arise
and i'll explain it this way that most much of the days that we're living
we're acting in reaction or directly in
the input the data the senses the experience that's coming we're reacting to it without a lot of
forethought or without a lot of reflection or so for example if i'm
if you're sitting or sitting uncomfortably in a chair many people will adjust themselves without thinking about they feel the discomfort and then
there's kind of an automatic to adjust themselves or we hear a sound and automatically turn towards it
without any kind of even awareness that we're we're thinking about it or
choosing to turn towards it or we have a pain some place in the body
and there's immediately with the in the in the wake of that pain there's aversion
we have pleasure in the body and then there's an automatic response of ah this is great i want more of this
so reactions are the actions that come kind of almost
automatic almost like they're triggered by the experience
and this can happen in the mind as well we have a particular thought
and certain thoughts produce a reaction and
so we have another thought another thought and much of our thinking is in some ways reactive it's it's uh it's
prompted it's catalyzed by the thought before or there's feelings internal emotions
and feelings we have so for example anger anger is a reactive emotion it's
it's it's an activity of response to uh something's been some things
happened that triggers it and uh so i think about something that uh someone was unkind to me
and i have a thought about it and just a thought itself it's a trigger for a reaction of i'm angry or indignant
or something and in that when that reactivity the
reaction the response is kind of immediate catalyzed by the input that comes in
there's no room for some deeper wellspring deeper flow
of our life the the free flow of our inner life flowing out
like a wellspring fountain kind of water flowing out from deep inside the earth into the into the
fountain into the spring and and so the knowing
helps us to know what's happening we see what's happening helps us to know our reactivity
but the knowing in its simplicity is making starting to make room for some wellspring something different
something to emerge from within that is not reactive
that's radically different it's almost like a pair a parrot a paradigm shift
in how we live our lives from being reactive responsive to the input that comes in all in all kinds of
ways including from the mind and emotions and rather than responding to input
we're we're allowing something to emerge
rather than being customers of life we're being producers of life
that and that's independent or free from the input that's coming all the time
so knowing allows for space for the emergence
of something inside which we don't make or create
that is not a catalyzed by the input that comes in from anywhere
but rather exists in a certain way independent of our judgments or ideas or theories or
memories all kinds of things so taking a comfortable alert posture
a posture in which we practice
knowing perhaps a knowing that's not only cognitive
but also experiential the the way the body knows
gently closing the eyes
and without any special breathing familiarize yourself with how you're
breathing right now
at the end of the exhale let there be a ever so small pause in the exhale
so you can feel the emergence of the inhale
that's what the body does it breathes in
if you pause at the top of the inhale you'll feel the body's desire
to exhale the exhale emerges
and perhaps if you feel your body you feel where the body
has a almost like an urge to soften and relax
in the face shoulders the belly
and then centering yourself on the body's experience of breathing
seeing how you could no breathing no inhale no exhale
so you know the breathing itself you experience it you feel it
and in the knowing there's lots of room and there's
room for a kind of allowance allowing the breath to breathe itself
if there is attitudes connected to knowing agendas
see if you can relax the thinking mind
relax
kind of like clearing a windshield a window so you can see clearly
clearing the window of knowing
so there's only knowing of what is here
knowing of in-breath knowing of out-breath
and then as you're sitting here
what might be if you're aware of yourself globally
is your global experience of being here more on the pleasant side of things or
the unpleasant
in whichever it is take some moments to know it simply
know how you are pleasant or unpleasant or neither
as if it's you have permission to be this way
there's no need to be any different just feel how you are and recognizes it
generally pleasant or generally unpleasant here
and whichever it is do you react to it
do you have thoughts ideas judgments concerns
if you do you're making less room for something deeper to emerge
in this space that knowing creates
the space that awareness provides
can you find a way of being that is not reactive to anything
that allows whatever is just to be in the space of awareness
um
and if you look around your body and mind can you find some place
where there is pleasantness or pleasure
goodness that might be emergent
that arises as they're independent of
whatever you're experiencing not a reaction to anything
is there a place within of quiet of calm
some degree of peace
some kind of pleasure
that's not part of the world of reactivity of thoughts and stories and
what's happened to us or will happen
the place where there's feeling at home
here and now a place of pleasantness pleasure
however small
maybe if there is such a place you can gently breathe through it breathe with
it knowing it as you breathe
just knowing with the knowing that gives room in space
for the emergence
of what flows from inside the wellspring
letting the thinking mind become quieter
the quieter the mind becomes the more space there is
for this deeper emergence
of what exists free of reactivity not dependent on the inputs that come in
is there within you some place of
comfort or peace or warmth calmness
that seems to be independent of the world around you
maybe even independent of your ordinary feelings and thoughts
is there a pleasure within
that's not dependent on your ordinary sensations of the body
if you're quiet it's a pleasure that can be there even when the body is uncomfortable
a quiet pleasure that's in some ways more satisfying
than ordinary sensual pleasure
a pleasure that's better known or easier known
when there's some degree of calm and subtleness maybe near the end of a meditation
hmm
and as we come to the end of this setting
appreciating that certain emotional states
have its origins in the deeper wellsprings within
love generosity
kindness a love of honesty
that's easier easily eclipsed
by the reactive emotions and feelings fear and anger
greed
perhaps we can celebrate treasure
the emergence of the goodness within when we're quiet and peaceful
and may in this relaxed place of pleasure within the emergent
may we turn our gaze outwards
out into the world with its suffering and challenges
war and poverty
and not lose this place of love or care
generosity gaze upon the world
with love and kindness generosity
not eclipsed by fear and anger distress
maybe look upon the world with kind eyes
concerned with the welfare and happiness of others
may we in our each individual ways contribute to the welfare and happiness of this world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so continuing with the topic of the second foundation of mindfulness
and repeating a little bit what i said in the meditation
so the the four foundations of mindfulness
when you get to when we get to the second foundation the practice the activity that this
being instructed is that of knowing paganity
and uh and uh and it's and the way it's described how to know
is to just know the simplicity of the experience itself so if if there's pleasure
know it as pleasure if there's pain unpleasantness know it as unpleasantness
if there's neither know it that way and we'll see as we go to the other foundations it's that simple just know
whatever is arising know what's there and know it for itself without adding anything to it and so the
judgments we might have the preferences we might have just to know
and this knowing is a very significant act
just to know and different people know different different ways some people are more cognitive some people are more somatic
knowing kind of experiencing it but whatever way you have of knowing that knows it
allows each thing to be itself without the agendas and the preferences and the
commentary just to know as if
as if you're allowing a flower in your garden to just grow and be there
or you allow a tree to just be there and just look at the tree you enjoy it you appreciate it
but it you don't say well that branch is too crooked or too many and you know something or other just a
tree and allow it to be the tree so the same thing with the natural these
are all kind of natural phenomena whatever happens to us inside and just see it as that of the moment
but the knowing is not only the purposes of knowing something
the knowing the purpose is also to discover this place in the mind that can be that simple
that that sometimes we're very accustomed almost habitually
to be reactive to the inputs to the thoughts whatever's going on being for and against searching how to be safe in
every situation searching what can we get here and how can it benefit me or how does this relate to me myself and
mine and my self-concept and there's a constant searching wanting getting
making planning reviewing that goes on that's a part of
this reactive mind that we live in and um and so this part of this wonderfulness of this
knowing is that uh we're putting to rest that that way of being we're emphasizing
we're inhabiting a different way of being in the world which is just to know
and that can create a tremendous amount of calm and peace because we're putting energy into the
knowing not energy into the reactivity this knowing has also the quality
of uh kind because of this allowing just letting things be
the knowing then begins to have feel qualities of spaciousness or peacefulness or stillness or
or acceptance or some kind of nice qualities that i like to think of as begins making
room for things and makes rooms for that which inside of us which is shy
or that which is easily eclipsed the by what is loud
so what is loud oftentimes is is desires greeds fears
aversions resentments envies we have all these afflictive emotions
which i think of as being surface phenomena and surface because they're reactive to the input that we get the
input from outside but also input provided by the mind the mind has imaginations and thoughts and memories
that it drums up and then there's the reactions to those and because it has to
do with the reaction to input it's more surfacy
but it's louder maybe on the surface it covers over the hindrances are things that cover
over their wisdom that's inside and and so what's quieter maybe shyer in a
sense is that which gets eclipsed by the surface emotions the reactivity
and it's that which is not reactive is that which exists for us
that is independent of reactivity of the input coming in
and so imagine for example that you um you
cut yourself somehow maybe your finger gets cut and maybe you're gardening and you're
putting manure in the garden and somehow you get cut then there's dirt and manure on your finger and all that and
but then you just keep on working and working and then you go into the compost pile and you go in the outhouse to clean
that out and you don't take care of your your cut and so it's faster as it gets infected
and gets worse and worse but if you can stop all the doing
and clean it well and maybe cover it and protect it then something emerges from the whole
physiological system we have to heal the cut and it's a lots of things get marshalled together
inside of us in order to heal a cut and it's not a simple phenomenon this is
amazing how complicated it is so in the same way if we can
not keep adding input from the outside all the time but clean
ourselves clear out uh the all the reactivity and
this junk the gunk that's there and keep it clean that allows a
huge beautiful complex inner world to emerge and take care of things
it's not like nothing's in there within us we have as a rich inner heart we have a rich inner life
that give it a chance will bubble up and begin to do with the work it does
it's healing and liberating and all kinds of things and so in this second foundation of
mindfulness the buddha goes first he says first if i'm i'm interpreting now uh well
first it says no what's pleasant as pleasant know what's unpleasant is
unpleasant know what's unpleasant neither pleasant nor unpleasant just learn to make those distinctions learn
to recognize that once you've learned to recognize that that allows you to and if you get more
settled to know that which is uh pleasant because it belongs to the reactive world
and that which is pleasant because it belongs to this pla this other place that's the non-reactive it's the
emergent word world from deep inside and
and so as many people are so oriented when they sit down and focus on their body and their breathing
on the sensual world and the central world is always the uh the world that responds to input
the temperature the comfort the physical sensations that go on and
it can be wonderful and profound to do that but there's another world within
which is not it doesn't require input in fact it's almost like the less input
we have or the more the ground is cleared the more
something can grow there and so farmer clears the field so the
plants can grow so what is it that can grow within us when we don't have input
and that comes when we're quiet and focused and calm it's primarily in buddhism associated
with meditation practice doesn't have to be only there maybe because of the strong meditation
tradition that as we begin meditating and get calmer more settled more concentrated
that which is uh more quieter that which is not reactive within us but that which is
emergent can begin to flow can move through us and so at some point we want to be able
to recognize that that's happening and so for the buddha this was called
what is that the the pleasure which is not of the flesh
and the unpleasantness that is not of the flesh and i kind of like to translate it as
worldly and spiritual though us some people can say physical or
spiritual or one translator has worldly and unworldly
which reminds me of some other location that's not even here the astral field or something
but they call it unworldly but it has to do with something that
is really valuable
as we move along the path of insight path of mindfulness that something we begin to be attuned to
is something that's usually eclipsed and hidden in our reactive preoccupied mind
and so if we're always trying to navigate negotiate the reactive mind the mind that's all about input and
rearranging the deck chairs on the titanic you know everything's being has to be right and fixed and made just right in
the world and then we're missing the opportunity
to become aware of some deep these deeper wellsprings and these deeper wellsprings then become
the reference point for um for this path of liberation that's being
described in the four foundations of mindfulness uh these deeper wellsprings of the
emergent of the not the spiritual of the non-uh
sensual uh in the said non-sensual in that sense so it's impacted by
the sense stores are impacted by input from the outside um
there's this then it creates a a reference point a foundation for the
last two foundations of mindfulness so we have this switch now
in the four foundations of mindfulness and the pivot from the mindfulness of the body
mindfulness of the sensual body which has a lot to do with input like even if you you know dance which is beautiful
sensual thing to do the dancing is providing the input and
so i don't want to you know say that the sensual is somehow less than or something but it's
different than this deeper more spiritual place or so here we're having a switch in
from that which is of the body that which is the physical sense sensuality
to now focusing on um something that some people might call the mind if the
mind the cheetah which is you know the whole inner landscape but something deeper and more intimate
and and
that is helpful for appreciating the path to freedom from suffering
so i hope that this discussion about this distinction
between of the flesh and not of the flesh is uh uh gives you enough ideas
uh so you can kind of search on yourself maybe for your own terminology or this distinction between these two
um and your own way of finding uh something inside that
is not dependent on the conditions of the world or the including the conditions of your ordinary body
but belongs to some the heart the spirit spiritual center it belongs to
the cheetah the mind belongs to some the well springs within where the
deep reservoirs of peace and happiness can be found
so um thank you and uh so next week i won't be here i'm going
off on retreat at irc and um very happy to have nikki mergaforee
coming back and she's done this a few times now and i think people have really appreciated her and
i appreciate your your welcome receptive perception of her for your appreciation of her that i've
heard from many people and so i'll be back on the 7th of march
and then we'll do start with the third foundation
these uh chitta this mind states or this inner life that
we're now beginning to point to so thank you