hello everyone
I appreciate the opportunity to be here with you and to offer these words and
to have a sense of so many of you who are participating have been doing so for a very long time and
it's a I feel like it's a wonderful thing we share here and thank you for the opportunity
so some of you most of you know that when often usually when I start these
guided meditations I put some emphasis on relaxation
if I one of my preferred things to add is that we relax with a posture that has
some uh expression of alertness
and um and there's many ways of doing that of course and we have to have a posture
that works for us but even if you're sitting back in a chair or for example
um maybe you can put your hands in a place in a way in your lap on your thighs
in such a way that like it it kind of expresses I am here
but the emphasis I want to make today is I often start with relaxation
and there's a way of understanding Dharma practice
that uh it involves a con ever deepening process
of relaxation of loosening dissolving Letting Go
releasing and that relaxation is just one way to describe this
and so rather than dismissing relaxation as being kind of um you know
a beginner meditation or something simplistic or
maybe to appreciate that it actually contains within it the profundity of the Dharma
it uh all we're doing in a sense is ever deepening relaxation until the final
relaxation is an opportunity to let go of all ways in which we hold tight that
were caught up that we are preoccupied that we are attached
so I say this as a way of appreciating the beginning appreciating the
relaxation there's something about it in it with it
that has a goodness to it that has a ripeness that has a pleasure
trust that take time to feel that let that be a guide for you
so taking an alert posture even if you're laying on your back you
could maybe stick your point your hands up to the ceiling with your elbows on the side resting in something
but the forearm pointing up
and then to gently close your eyes
and take a moment to feel your body before doing any relaxation at all or doing anything
as a way of respecting yourself respecting your body
respecting this moment take a few seconds here just feel and sense what is here for you
and then taking some long comfortably long inhales
and relaxing the body on the exhale could be the whole body or particular
places
and then letting your breathing return to normal and I'll guide you if you want to follow
with relaxing different parts of your body
and even if all you can do is soften around that part rather than relaxing something
see if you can appreciate whatever pleasure goodness a sense of this is
right that comes with that relaxation even if the relaxation reveals some
discomfort maybe there's some rightness to it knowing it to feeling it rather than
ignoring it so on the exhale relaxing the face
maybe relaxing around the eyes
the eyes themselves letting them rest in their sockets
not looking with your eyes at anything
the looking can rest
the back of your eyes
relaxing the shoulders
and even if they don't relax maybe your shoulders appreciate
care that relaxing expresses
on the exhale relaxing in the chest
relaxing the belly
relaxing the thighs and down the legs
relaxing the arms down to the hands
and then again relaxing in the shoulders but this time
as you do so also relax the relaxing
the way that you relax let it be relaxed
without expectation without needing the relaxation to happen
an impulse and signal to relax that is very
relaxed itself
and then doing a relaxed way relax the thinking mind
if there's any tension or pressure or preoccupation around thoughts
relax any tension or pressure associated with that
and relax the Mind as a whole so the mind is
calmer or Stiller
without needing to be directed anywhere just here
in in whatever degree of calm the mind has
allow the inhale the experience of inhale
to show itself in the mind to be known in the mind
so the mind doesn't go to the breathing the experience of breathing comes to the
mind
receptive available
and then on the exhale relax with the exhale release let go
anywhere in your body and mind where it feels good to do so
it could be just in the breathing itself in the exhale itself
relaxing on the exhale giving yourself over to the relaxation
so at the end of the exhale that your awareness is more ready and
receptive for the inhale
taking a moment to feel your mind
if there's any ways in which to feel tight or contracted
Hard Solid tense
as you exhale
let it dissolve let it soften
maybe first it softens on the edges
if you are involved in thinking
that's a sign that something within could use relaxing softening
and then as we come to the end of the sitting take two three four breaths
on the exhale to relax as deeply in your being as you
can maybe if it's a long little longer than
usual exhale to Exhale from the surface of your body all the way to the Core
and then from whatever feeling for relaxation that you have
feeling of being softer perhaps
to open your awareness
to take in the room you're sitting in the building
neighborhood
wider community your attention goes out receptively out
into the whole land the whole continent
the whole world
and letting that open attentiveness to the whole world around you
be the medium for carrying your good will
you're well wishing for the world
a simple idea that it would be wonderful for people to be happy and safe
free and peaceful how wonderful and
that you would like that there is a wish for you
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and even if such a broad Universal wish could never actually be
accomplished it makes a difference
to have that wish
for many people it makes a difference for them to know that there are people who care
enough to wish them well may all beings be wished well
may all beings know of people who wish them well
may we be well wishers
[Music]
thank you
so hello and to the second talk
on these five wholesome States
of receptivity of softness of these are five areas of inspiration
that are considered wholesome mental states to develop to evoke
and um and these are the kind of focused of states which are self-protecting
meaning that as we cultivate these they protect us from the opposite
so yesterday that team was a Readiness a receptivity
that if we try too hard to be ready strain or something to be receptive
we actually diminished the receptivity the Readiness the Readiness has to have within it a
kind of letting go of a certain kind of straining intense unwholesome effort
so today the topic is the wholesome state that are really helpful for this
process of the practice and even listening to the Dharma
preparing ourselves for the deepening today's wholesome
state is malleability sometimes the word is sometimes is
translated as soft so becoming the
the beeswax become soft enough that it can be made into something shaped into
something and I love telling the story so some of you have heard it many times I apologize
but the when my son was in kindergarten once a week they would make little
animals with beeswax and the beeswax that they were going to use was up by the shelf and when they went to get it
it was always very hard and you couldn't really shape it and
they instructed to hold it in the palms of both hands kind of hold the
the beeswax between the two hands and then the teacher would proceed to tell a story
and by the time the story was finished the beeswax was soft enough for them to
malleable enough to to make into something beautiful little animal
so same with our mind if we can hold it in the Embrace of awareness of
mindfulness uh without reacting without forcing without doing but just really stay there
our whole being will begin to relax the mind will beginning to relax
and relaxing the body is a way of softening the mind
so it's very important not to undervalue the relaxed body undervalue relaxation
itself we want to become acutely sensitive in this practice to attention to strain to any kind of
stress involved in how we practice so it can be relaxed and soft but not so relaxed that we fall asleep
or that we are become kind of complacent there is a Kind of Wonderful balance between being
upright being alert physically and mentally and letting that alertness
relax letting that kind of soften not collapse but kind of settle deeply but
staying alert and um so one of those qualities of this kind
of wholesome mind is a malleability softness it's sometimes often in the Buddha's
teachings it's paired up with a word that means workability
sometimes translated as a wheeledness but uh the ability to make something
with the mind um the word the words come from the word Kama to make
and um and so there's a time in meditation practice where the mind is so
ready peaceful we're so present we're here and there's a feeling oh no I can start
a kind of applying my attention with more freedom with more ease it's not a
struggle there's not preoccupation uh you know or a strong Tendencies to be caught up in thought now I'm really here
and with because I'm here there's a the mind the attention the awareness there's
a a wildiness it's a workability it can be
applied it can be engaged there's some kind of way in which the home mind
becomes malleable and uh the example I I like for this
malleability is in my early years being a Zen student
we would sit in a very particular kind of posture very upright very straight
and and very balanced posture kind of a yogic posture almost
and we got up very early in the morning sometimes like before 4 30 in the
morning we're awake in the monastery and we went to bed at maybe nine o'clock
so you know I would people are often tired
and um but uh there was a custom of teachers to walk around and adjust people's postures
during meditation you know just in case it wasn't just lined up it was leaning or slouching or something
and um and uh we would be you know the teachers would
come from behind we were sitting and what they would do is uh gently put their hands on the back of our shoulder
one shoulder just to let us know they were there and then they would proceed with both hands to kind of usually from the back
the shoulders or the back to adjust it and all done silently
during meditation and there was an interesting phenomena that if I was preoccupied in my thoughts
during meditation and I felt that hand on my shoulder I would startle
um and it was like a physical startle reflex but if I was really present I was not
preoccupied in thoughts and then it would still be just a surprise to feel the hand on my shoulder
I wasn't expecting it I didn't it would just come out of the blue but it would touch my shoulder and
immediately my whole body would become softer and a receptive and it would be this
kind of softness that they're just like almost like I was already soft and just ready to kind of flow and move with that
whatever movement the teacher wanted to put on me so I learned from that the impact of
being preoccupied that when I'm preoccupied in thought and concerns that I don't become so fluid so
flexible I become inflexible I come fragile I become startable
and so to learn to uh to not be preoccupied
is a very important part of this process and it helps by taking time not to
dismiss being preoccupied and caught up in thought but rather to see it as a
valid area to be mindful of do when you do feel yourself really caught up in thoughts and ideas
is to start feeling the Mind feeling the body to feel how it might be tight how
it might be tense how it might be assertive or there's pressure in it or
um stress in it all these things that kind of would be not malleable not soft it's kind of the
thing is something is hard and we get to know that because if you know it that's like taking the beeswax
off the shelf and holding it in your hand so take the hardness of the Mind
and attention the pressure and don't make it a problem but make it something that you are willing to kind of hold
with the warmth with kindness with receptivity with the very thing we're
trying to develop this malleability this workability this receptivity see if you
can bring that to the places in your mind where you're not that way
see if that will soften it if it's easy enough to relax it relax
many people will meditators will learn to let go of thoughts without learning
to relax or soften the underlying pressure to think
and so you can let go of thoughts all you wish and that pressure will just pump out more thoughts
so we take time to soften and begin to appreciate then the softer
mind the receptive mind the malleable mind the mind that something surprising happens and it's the mind is not stunned
or shocked or or Frozen it's like the mind can just go with whatever's
happening oh okay like that um you know I think that certain uh
activities we do like maybe sports or playing music or uh maybe taking a walk
in nature being outdoors within a reason reasonable way there's
there's a way in which new things arise and it can be folded and included in this malleable wieldy a soft receptive
mind and it just kind of included as part of the whole so this uh cultivating and developing
and appreciating a soft mind a malleable mind a wieldy mind a workable mind
and to know that this is a radical difference between a hard mind and a
soft mind an unreceptive mind and a receptive mind a
and be inspired by the possibility of a soft mind a malleable mind a workable mind
um attention awareness which has that quality awareness that maybe is like
mine may be a little bit like um soft butter and whatever happens it's
just like a knife going through soft butter just no pressure is needed or maybe as uh your hand moves through
water the water doesn't really offer much resistance and it's just there kind
of to softly there's softness and water to let the hand move through
so in the same way the awareness in the mind let that be soft for things to
happen and occur um being ready for anything surprised by nothing
um just kind of available and um
and part of the theme for this week is that these are states of inspiration
something that's a beautiful qualities of mine
that um so is there some way that you can be inspired by these by the softness
some ways you can cultivate it so appreciate it so I'd like to propose for homework
today that um that uh all of you assume
that into some degree you can evoke a softer mind than you
have in any given moment you can make it more malleable softer and more receptive
and take some times through the day to make it so
don't think it's dramatic but what it requires is pausing it requires taking
some time to do this and I know for some of you taking time to do something like
this is very expensive it really is interrupts the efficiency of doing a lot
of things and doing the things that you're under pressure to do but uh I think it's well worth the
investment to take the time quality time to just even if it's just
like two minutes to uh see if you could kind of soften the mind some and uh and get a sense and
feel of even small movements in that direction because in the long run
we live our lives much more effectively with this soft malleable mind that's
receptive and it's a more creative mind and um
so I hope that this is something you can have some feel for and some ability to
tap into and this would be a great day to do it so thank you very much