so i want to begin this morning with a fable that i think is uh
as a good fable uh is a is a
great story to kind of kind of interpret in all kinds of ways
interesting ways but yeah start with the fable
so there were these two people who were going to be sentenced to the dungeon
and they were sent down to the dungeon and put in the room and before the door was closed
the guard executioner said
you have 24 hours to figure out how to get out of this dungeon
if you don't if you figure it out you can go free but if you don't figure out
its death for both of you so with that
he handed a little rusty nail to one of them and slammed the door shut
and they were like wow 24 hours to figure out how to get out of here so they looked at the door
and there was an amazing array of locks on this door
some of them were combination locks some of them were like big padlocks maybe that was what nail was for to get
in their padlock and try to figure it out some of them were elaborate kind of puzzle-like
bars that closed the door so then stakes were high death
and so one of them immediately got to work the other one just sat down against the
wall quietly just looking at the door
and the one who was working on the door worked away sweated away hard and at some point turned over
and said to the ones sitting around why aren't you doing something this is
like um you you're not that you're not going to do anything is
the death going to be the death of us and the guy on the wall said personal dewall said
maybe but maybe you're trying to do something it will be the death of us it's kind of a strong statement
so the person on the door kind of through went you know
got completely absorbed and trying to figure out the locks and as the 24 hours started to come to
the end it was got more and more frantic and was speeding between the locks trying to figure out what the way out was
sweat was pouring down and the person sitting against the wall
just sitting there peacefully quietly and then about five minutes before the
24 hours was over the person in the wall just got up
walked to the door and pushed it it had never been locked
the one who was searching and trying to fix that you know was was you know thrown off by all the locks they never
bothered to see if the door was actually locked
so what dungeons are you living in and what
locks are you trying to undo to get out
that maybe don't need to be solved
maybe what's needed is to sit down and do nothing for a while just sit there
and so the one who was sitting against the wall that person's
wonderful spiritual principle was the principle
just don't do it don't do it so why is that a significant principle
just don't do it some people in america the united states have heard the principle just do it
it's like i think of it a little bit like a carpe diem there's latin thing that
sees the day you know like what you're supposed to go out and do and
claim and assert yourself and you know don't have anything stand in the way and
so this idea just don't do it it's phenomenal but it turns out in our practice of
meditation and caring for our minds and our hearts in that domain
just don't do it is actually a very significant teaching very significant practice to do
so what are some of the dungeons we can live in one of them some of them have to do with
are how we see ourselves how we define ourselves and how we try to get out of that
dungeon so just a very kind of abstract kind of vague kind of way
someone might think that they're a bad person
and that's the dungeon that they have to get out of and so then they try to be a good person
and being a good person is kind of a lot of work there was a time in my life where i
wanted everyone to like me and i had a job that was almost impossible for everyone to like me
because i was kind of like the one who had to tell people you can't do it that way
and um so i got to see this strong desire to be liked and all that i tried amazing
amount of social gymnastics to try to make it work and it was just got was really stressful
it was a monastic job and it was like in the kitchen i was a kitchen manager and kitchens are pressure cooker places if
you haven't even have any of you ever worked in a kitchen a commercial kitchen or something
and the legends of that kitchen monastery kitchen was that in the 1960s there was
a uh ed brown who was the um wrote this famous tussahara cookbook some of you
know he was working in the kitchen then and at some point he threw a knife at someone
you're laughing but you can only laugh because it didn't hit anyone
and it's a pressure quicker place right so there i was trying to make everyone like me
and so so sometimes we you know or to have the
idea that you're a wrong person and then you have to be the right person
and then we try hard and sometimes just trying hard to do the opposite
it's just a lot of work and sometimes it doesn't work someone
who may be is very insecure will overcompensate
in such a way that people pull away like if you're really needy and trying to get
everyone to like you for example then actually maybe fewer people will like you because you're trying so hard
and it just makes people uncomfortable and um
so uh if when i was uh we were raising our first
son i know he was you know when he could start understanding words sometimes he
would be doing something really fun and nice and i would say oh i'm good boy
and my wife explained to me one point you know you shouldn't say that that way because that's reinforcing an identity
that he's supposed to be a good boy and then he has to do things to live up to that his father's idea of a good boy
and that's just the recipe for challenges as he grows up
so what i would say instead was wow you're having so much fun doing that
and you know that that probably is a problem too but
because you know you can't really be a parent without causing problems
but hopefully it was much less of a problem just oh that's fun
enthusiastically and so
when we sit and meditate and we see that our mind is doing funny things
a few of us have funny minds and and so doing funny things
and then think oh i'm not i'm kind of mean i'm kind of mean in there and angry
or harsh i need to be kind and then we kind of bring out the start
cranking up the kind gears and like i got to get the going you know kind gears and kind of
you know and you know trying and pumping them out pumping them out and until we're exhausted from the
you know doing those gears and and then we're even more irritated and harsh about everything
so instead of so it's true that we might be harsh or mean in our minds
but to swing the pendulum to the other side and think because of that i'm supposed to be a kind person
if we're a bad person supposed to be a good person if i'm a wrong person supposed to be the right kind of person
that sometimes is going that just staying in the same game
being caught in the same complex instead
what we can do in this practice again the domain of our practice our mind and our hearts there
is just simply stop doing the unhealthy thing
but don't try to do the healthy thing it's enough just to stop
you don't have to compensate or swing to the other side as if that's how you're going to be a good person
and why this works in the mind and heart with meditation
is that when you don't do something there's some settling that happens
we're no longer asserting effort to do something and accomplish
something we're no longer preoccupied in something and something begins to open
settle relax and then we have access to some other
way of being some other source like if they feel like you're
you're just really a mean person all the time you're not supposed to be kind just stop being mean
that's radical maybe that's enough some people just think oh it's so nice
to be with you you're not trying to do anything i just like i can relax and just be myself and
i know these people who are trying so hard to be kind i remember the first time i tried to be kind to someone when i was
18 i think she must have gotten sick of me
i was the member talk standing there in college talking to her and like being so saccharine and sweet and just like over
the top and later i walked like that was that was weird
i didn't ever never occurred to me how to be kind or friendly or nice or something and so it looks like i never
talked to her again or she never talked to me again
and so um but just to do nothing maybe i'll make
space there's a very famous uh quote from
henry now and a kind of a christian theologian united states that talks about
creating a friendly empty space for the stranger
so someone who you don't know stranger someone you don't know but to receive them in a friendly empty
space as opposed to crowded well you know trying to do things and being something
it allows people to be who they are and just let something evolve and develop
and this idea that there's something deeper in us a deeper place of wisdom of motivation
is integral to this dharma practice deeper than the kind of surface
preoccupation surface reactivity the surface pendulum that swings from
one end to the other because you know if we think we're supposed to be you know we're mean so we think we're
supposed to be kind but it's a lot of work to be kind so we get exhausted in that exhaustion we're back into the mean
and and so then we try again and it just kind of becomes a lot of work and a lot of kind
of gets stuck in the in the polarity and the duality of it all
if that's what we think is supposed to be there but if we can just stop
then something deeper can happen and the example i'd like to offer you is maybe some of you had this experience
i've had it certainly of being engaged and trying to figure out some problem
and um thinking about it a lot trying to figure it out and probably that part was needed
but then going away going on a bike trip or going going on a hike taking a shower or doing
something completely different where the mind is no longer thinking about it and then suddenly wells up inside the
solution the answer where did that come from it came from no longer being engaged in
it so as we stop and maybe the earlier thinking had to create the momentum inside
but still there was something some deeper place that's processing our life that's not that conscious place in the
mind where reactivity can occur so in dharma practice we're trusting
this deeper place of what wells up and what comes and
in another way of saying it we're trusting a peaceful place the more
we don't do the more peaceful it is now this can be challenging of course
but one of the other thing that buddhist psychology teaches which i think is fascinating for this whole
enterprise is that certain states of emotional states that we have states of
mind it's very easy to assume are fixed this is how it is this is how
the universe is and in buddhism we see them all
as processes of the mind activities of the mind so to give you one example
boredom people will say this is such a boring situation
this party is boring or this you know this person is boring it's a horrible thing to say right
and uh and so it's you know blaming the situation for being boring
there is no situation whatsoever in this universe that is boring
boring is an evaluation of the human mind your mind or maybe not your mind but
people's minds and in an evaluation of the mind or a reaction mind activity of the mind a
process of the mind as soon as you realize it's an activity of the mind and action of the mind
it's possible to calm it down it's possible to settle it
these activities of the mind are not inherent they're not required
we don't have to be involved in this reactivity as i have one teacher who says that
boredom is a sign of being separated from your experience so you're holding yourself apart so
that's work to hold yourself apart and then you know some kind of evaluation judgment
so when we people who meditate can learn can notice over and over again repeatedly as they meditate how things
states of mind and activities judgments that were seen to be
inherent melt away in meditation
and i've certainly sat in meditation and thought this is boring this meditation boy is this ever boring when is it going
to end they should ring the bell and then i said wait my gail you know
maybe you should try just maybe counting your breath and getting a little more concentrated
and so i do and then as i get more concentrated that level of activity in the mind
that's evaluating boredom quiets and lo and behold
without that activity it's actually quite i'm quite content and happy to be here
there's nothing boring right now because i'm not evaluating as boring does that
make sense so it turns out there's a lot of things like that and i don't want to go through
too many examples of it but
certain forms of sadness even depression might be
part of this evaluative active mind sometimes because things are confusing
distressing there's been great loss all kinds of things can happen and i don't want to
just diminish the sadness of loss for example but we have to appreciate what the mind is doing
and sometimes there's a way in of drop of quieting the mind stealing the mind just don't do it
that's very respectful of our inner life because we're not overlaying
so much stuff on top of it and we allow the heart to just show itself in some deeper way
and if there is sadness that sadness that needs to be processed sadness can be very healthy and healing
things to feel if we get out of its way and when the mind is busy and thinking
and reacting to all of it judging it or clinging to it then it doesn't allow for this deeper thing to
happen so um so so one of the little
quotes you know quotes that i hope you'll carry with you and use it at the right time
a little saying is um just don't do it
that simply stopping as opposed to having the pendulum swing to the other side
rather than compensating and like not to do it but just stop trust yourself trust it's
okay simply not to do it you don't have to prove yourself you don't have to be a good boy or whatever
that um you know all you have to do is stop and then make space and let something show itself and get to
know yourself and and with time learning to trust
a certain way of not doing not always reacting fixing
running away but saying okay okay here i am this is an un uncomfortable situation
just don't do anything with it just be with it and see what happens
and with time what we learn is to trust the peaceful place and what arises from that peaceful place
and this is a very challenging thing sometimes to trust there's a lot of messages are from from
our society that we're supposed to be a certain way we're obligated to be a certain way
and if you're not probably angry properly distressed probably properly something
then you're a bad person you're wrong you're somehow aloof or indifferent or
or somehow you know part of the problem
maybe you are but but um but if you can trust this peaceful place
maybe there's a very different way to respond a healthy way an appropriate way
that doesn't involve anger and distress fear
you know all these kinds of things that i i propose that oftentimes maybe
people expect from each other that's the vehicle in which we kind of prove that we're right if we're angry at
something then we understand there's a problem and we're it's kind of then i'm you know then at least i'm not
you know you know the more i can be angry the more i know that i'm just kind of made a claim that i'm i
know what's right you know and i'm on the right side because that surely is the problem
and i don't know if it's that that division that anger anger makes i don't know if that's healthy
so i'll venture into dangerous territory maybe in in
making some more examples of this the um
so there is a teaching in buddhism um
that there are three kinds of conceit and generally we think of conceit as
being something not to do not to be conceited and the kind of
in fact in buddhism also since conceit is seen as a form of suffering people have conceit or suffering
you know without you know in addition this whatever suffering they cause others
but there's three kinds and the first kind is one here in the in at least in english-speaking world we
often most clearly associate with conceit and that is i'm better than others
some form of that but in buddhism there's two other forms of conceit
the other the second one is i'm worse than others
and some people what that's conceit um
it's conceit because it's a over preoccupation with our own status
in relationship to other people so i'm worse than others and so we're still caught and then in
the grip of this self-definition and being someone not being someone
and then the third one which is particularly evocative or
concerning for people in the united states given some of the value some of the important values that
are touted in the united states the third form of conceit
is that you're equal to others in land we're supposed to be you know
equal that's like what's wrong with that we're supposed to be equal and
and so the reason that the problem with the equality conceit
is when it's still a conceit it's still a comparison holding on to an idea
of something so then the question is well what's left
and what the alternative to those three is not to do the comparisons
not to place yourself in comparison to anybody else just to be yourself in some way
without that playing the comparison game and so when conceit falls away
we are who we are but we're not piling on top of it judgments and
comparative thinking there's so much suffering in our society tremendous amount
from all the different ways that we live in comparison to each other so it's a radical thing to stop doing
that and at the same time we have to be very
careful with this kind of teaching because this teaching is only meant for again the domain of your heart and your
mind don't play the comparison game for yourself the conceit game
because we do live in a society where there is inequality
and not to see that not to recognize that is to not to recognize the tremendous
suffering in our society we do live in a society where there are people who
hold themselves superior to others and keep other people
you know pushed keeping them down there are people who feel that they're inferior to others
they've learned that and they're struggling with that so we live in a society where those
things exist so when we say in buddhism you know don't play the conceit game and no
superior inferior equal that's why this really has to do with what's going on inside of you
we should use our wisdom to recognize what's happening in society
but when we see the inequality in our society which is immense
are we supposed to get angry are we supposed to be distressed
are we supposed to be afraid
there are people who expect us to be if you're not probably angry or upset or guilty or something
then maybe you're part of the problem maybe you are it depends it's complicated right
but um but the um but in the in the dharma
trusting that peaceful place inside
just stopping just stop something stop that judgment stop the
anger but pay attention to the world don't shut down
don't avoid the world what's going on but if what happens if you trust the
peaceful place inside maybe that peaceful place inside is not
aloof is not removed maybe there's a very different source of
motivation a source of stepping up and trying to improve our society and make things
better that comes from a very different place maybe comes from compassion maybe it
comes from generosity maybe it comes from a deep sense of
shared humanity and caring for each other maybe it comes from inspiration maybe it
comes from joy one of the ways to improve the world
is to whatever you do to do what brings you a sense of joy and delight so that can be inspiring
to save the world while you're miserable does that save the world
that doesn't really convey so in buddhism there's a lot of emphasis
on how we do things and there's important things to be done for our society in the world
but how do we want to do it and where is the source of the motivation from
and and i'd like to propose that it can be from this peaceful place
inside that we discover when we've learned
just don't do it just don't do it
and what i'm referring to here is just don't do a lot of the preoccupations reactivity
of the mind the the the pendulum games were caught in
settle down be here trust yourself trust this peaceful place and if it comes out of the heart
just do it then do it maybe
and maybe it's easier to do when one of the things has been settled over time
is fear one of things has settled is inhibition
but inhibition without coming from a deep place inside can be disastrous
you know i'll say whatever i want to say but you know so just just don't do it
as a vehicle as a means as a practice to discover
this peaceful place inside that's not participating in the games
the mind has or the pendulums or the reactivities of the mind
where maybe it's radical enough it's powerful enough
to learn to stop doing the things that are unhealthy for you
you don't have to then compensate for that and do you know become a saint
it's enough just not to do that you know the you know the harmful things the
difficult things the ways your mind is kind of you know caught in these things
and i think that's a radical message it's enough just to
stop some of the things you're doing and i think it's very respectful of
ourselves because we're learning how not to have too many cooks in the kitchen
you know in our kitchen of our own hearts and minds and letting getting out of the way and allowing something to rise and
surface learning perhaps that it's okay
just to be alive just to be alive and breathing is plenty
we don't have to prove ourselves we don't have to compensate for ourselves or we don't
have to prove ourselves in any kind of way
but it is wonderful to learn to trust that peaceful heart
and learn trust how we come how we respond to the world from that place
that's a radical thing there's lots of people in our society who are responding from other places
but i think it's good for our society for people to start learning how to actively respond to the world the
needs of the world needs a family needs of friends colleagues anything
from this place still quiet peaceful place inside
that may be the fast way to discover
is just don't do it that little practice
easier said than done but maybe
i've given you some perspective that you can try to use today or use and explore
and and see maybe if some of you are in
your dungeon you'll stop trying to pick the lock
and try something else so thank you
and we have a couple of minutes if any of you like to make any comments on this or
reflections or questions
yes
um gail my question goes to um
like if if somebody has a habit of course it's not i'm not talking about myself here
but if somebody had a habit of being very judgmental to
stop to learn how to just not do that is a process i'm sure yeah it's a process and so
could you say a few words about how to how to navigate that process and i
suspect part of it is uh awareness bringing awareness to when when i i find myself judging
um and also to maybe meditate more to get more into
this peaceful place but anyway that's my question yeah so i think that
certainly meditation can be a great help if the meditation allows the mind to quiet down enough
so the judgments are not there so every time you can do that and drop into a deeper place it's kind of like
you're massaging the mind and you might have to do it repeatedly but slowly something begins to give and
your mind learns the lesson oh there's another way of doing this and it feels good
and uh having that contrast of a place that feels like a better alternative is a way of
reconditioning the mind so i wouldn't you know so that's that's if you have that ability in meditation
if you don't then uh follow some of the instructions we give on mindfulness of emotions
so you would look at the uh you want to get your bring mindfulness to the judgmentalism
and study it in a more careful way what's actually going on in the present moment not where it came from in your
life but what's how how is it really going on here and now and
the um so the um and so what is the emotion that's behind
it and if you can discover what the emotion is can you sit quietly and just breathe
with the emotion and feel it maybe that emotion needs your attention more than their judgments
the judgments might just be the messenger don't kill the messenger and the message is not
what it's saying the message is uh that you're hurting in some way you're afraid you're lonely or
something you know feeling inadequate or there's a conceit maybe maybe you feel
i'm not saying it's you but some people judge a lot because they feel inadequate in themselves
and judging others is a way of feeling adequate if they're bad then i know i'm okay
but it's kind of the conceit game and it's kind of funny way so you know stop and take a deeper look
great i think over here
and then okay maybe i'll tell you two more than you
so gil um thank you for the talk um i'd like to make two points one is that boredom is
considered the lack of focus because if you're focused you're not bored the second point is
you stressed several times in some of your talks that it's
dharma teachers just say oh just let go do it don't do it but it's
it's also not proper for dharma teachers to say such a thing because
there's a lot of these innate fears and things they have such a great grip that it's very
difficult to let go and then in one of your talks on um janas you said
the buddha was a very wise teacher which is why he substituted anxiety with
pleasure so when you trade it's easier for people to change the focus on something else
than to just let go so that is one way for personally for me
um a lot of the stress and anxiety the way i was able to let go was by
tuning into these sensations in the body and then you go on to find something
deeper wonderful thank you so then over here last one
thank you hi gail uh thank you so much for the
talk i really appreciated it um i just wanted to say i guess
one thing that i thought i i think it was i don't know if it was from a book i read or from one of your other talks i
talked about how there was 113 different emotions
and i was thinking about how sometimes it's easier to kind of embrace whatever
you're feeling when you can recognize that emotion but 113 is a lot
so i don't know if you've heard i just started reading this book and i thought it was really helpful and they did or
she did make some references to buddhism it was called uh the atlas of the heart
and like 87 different types of emotions and so it was really interesting because it kind of showed how some things could
be similar but how they're different and anyways i just wanted to bring it up i don't know if that would be something
that would be helpful or anything that you'd ever want to look into but i really liked it so far and just wanted
an update yeah i think developing emotional literacy is really helpful
and knowing the range of emotions and the distinctions between anger and
irritation and ire and rage and annoyance and be able to separate and
really see the distinctions and becoming you know more and more familiar with it all some people have never
really developed much emotional literacy and it's just like a vague sense of you know i'm feeling lousy or something
so i think it's a great thing to do yeah thank you okay so we should stop so we can have
our tea and um and it's time for us to stop and so you're welcome to come up afterwards now
if you want or meet outside for tea so you're all welcome to stay and so the idea is we the reason to get your tea in
indoors hot tea is that there's a hot water
dispenser on the counter there and there's tea in the drawer there i guess or i don't know how it's set up
and then those of you who want to stay will meet outside and chat and say hello and i hope all of you stay so thank you