hello everyone and
welcome and um hello
everyone a few words for introduction to this
meditation
where for these last uh few months now we've been doing
satiana the practices for establishing awareness and uh the Buddha calls these
practices the practices of cultivating awareness to be a heap a
mountain of wholesomeness of
skillfulness he says that um the five hindrances which are one of the things
we've looked at in this these weeks is a heap of unh wholesomeness
unskillfulness and this idea that mindfulness and what we're cultivating here is what's skillful what's wholesome
what's nourishing what's healthy serves as a very useful guide
for how to practice mindfulness how to evoke and bring
forth uh a clear and clear awareness of the present
moment we do it in a way that is uh skillful wholesome it feels healthy
feels like welcoming for us to do to chase after meditation out of
greed to use meditation to try to get rid of something we don't like
that's that's using mindfulness that according to the five hindrances we just
brings unskillfulness it brings uh poor
results so as you practice this practice of mindfulness one of the things to be
attentive to is the quality of your practice the
way in which you practice is it open-handed is it
openhearted is it open-minded to what is here open-handed
meaning uh you're just here to experience what is here in a generous
way openhearted means that uh your your
care your kindness is available you're caring for yourself in
this approach and open-minded means you're available for whatever the experience is
you're willing to be present for things without expectation without agendas just
present and um maybe we take it on faith initially that this is for the Buddha
this is one of the most healthy skillful things psychologically spiritually healthy things a person can do is to be
bringing forth this Clarity of awareness to the present moment and I think part of the reason it's considered so healthy
so skillful is that it's a magnet for so
many other good qualities it's almost as if um awareness
clear awareness of the present is making open space
for uh in which uh other skillful States other wholesome ways of being can
Surface and come into it and that open space face holds that bay or doesn't
make room for doesn't really help th help the hindrances Thrive the
hindrances Thrive when we're not paying attention when we're not creating that open space where we don't have clear
awareness so in these all these ways of talking the word
open is emphasized open-handed open hearted open-minded open
space so may as you sit today you be attentive and
careful that the way in which you practice how you bring forth present
moment awareness feels has a good feeling for
you and it's a kind of way of being a friend to yourself perhaps or just that
other people would be attracted to you in the goodness and the clarity Simplicity of being of how you are with
your experience so other things
come so to begin maybe caring for yourself
by your posture you
take maybe taking the time so your body feels that you're attending to it and
caring for it a posture that the best of your
ability seems like a good posture for meditation for your body to be
in and gently closing your eyes and maybe with the eyes
closed before meditating just to let your attention roam around your
body with an open awareness of this is how it is this is how it's feeling
now being careful with how how your attend how your
awareness can just be with yourself for a few moments here maybe just to
discover to be receptive to recognize how your body
is and maybe how you are in an open-handed
openhearted open-minded way
and gently gently a little deeper breathing
than usual so that when you exhale maybe you exhale with a little
bit of relief relaxation here now
a gentle little deeper breath than usual maybe with the
inhale infusing awareness with more clarity more
openness awareness becomes a little more expansive or receptive
and on the exhale the awareness rides along with the exhale
letting your breathing return to normal and anytime your mind wonders off
and it's time to begin again with your breathing in the present
moment see if you can make the beginning be enjoyable or Pleasant
friendly and as you stay with the breathing or stay with your
experience stay with it in a in some manner simple relaxed
manner that is friendly or feels
healthy so that it feel you you have the feeling oh this is good to hang out with
this kind of this kind of awareness here and
now and whatever you're aware of body feelings mind
States thoughts
reactions the how you're aware is important
for
e
for for
remember to be aware in an open
way where awareness is an
opening awareness opens
itself
e
for e
for
e e
as we come to the end of this sitting to
consider what you know about being aware being
attentive in an open way without expectations or demands
without pulling away
or wanting something just aware open handed open-minded
openhearted almost like as you're aware you're making
space making a room and to
think about doing this for other people that you
encounter how I'm being aware of them a little bit not too much a little
bit it's like you're making room for them
space you're with them in open handed openhearted open-minded way
and if you're not can you be aware of
that and in being aware of it can you try to open up a little bit open clear
awareness of others what would it be like to be with others that
way and it is healthy wholesome to apply what we learn about
attention in meditation to how we can attend kindly
to others to be aware of others without the
hindrances getting in the
way may through this practice that we do may we support the
possibility for all beings to be happy for all beings to be
safe for all beings to be peaceful
for all beings to be
[Music]
free
e e
so so we've gone through for these last four months the four foundations for
awareness for awakening awareness
and um these four awarenesses four areas of
developing awareness and can work together cooperatively support each
other and um they make a very interesting um uh perspective very useful
perspective for us to um bring to our
lives so often when when we uh pay attention give attention take
in perceive the world around us or the world inside of us it's all too easy to
do it with uh preconceived ideas uh preconceived
agendas um being oriented to certain areas certain things that we think are
important and not to automatically dismiss those even if it's a useful way
to look at things the way you look at things um sometimes it's it can be useful to
find a new way for a a fresh perspective for our uh for perspective uh for our
perception of the world ourselves and um so these four foundations four areas are kind of
interesting to keep them in mind use these perspectives when looking at our life so if for
example uh some people might be oriented towards uh what's in it for me what is
it what what am I going to get out of this experience in satiana we wouldn't do
that instead we would say what is the physical experience here what's the
feeling tone that's here what's the Mind State that's present and what are what's
the Damas what are these processes of being caught or being free that are playing out as I practice
here it could could be that uh when we look at the world we look at the world
through what we don't like what uh what frightens us or what's unpleasant for us
and um and we we react to that from that point of view and um but instead of that we can
ask this you know how does it physically how is it feeling tone how is it mind
States how is it with the Damas it could be we um there's a lot of
uh uh self orientation going on instead of that we do the four
foundations so these are like going through the scales we can ask ourselves
given what's happening now maybe let's look at them from these Vantage Point these are the these are
the four Vantage points that the Buddha offers uh for the path to Awakening to
Freedom a path to everything that's wholesome or skillful a heap of
skillfulness heap of wholesomeness for the Buddha this is phenomenally healthy and beneficial to
cultivate this kind of awareness and so so and the vehicle he
does this or the medium is not through orientations that are about me myself
and mine of course it's about you in a certain way but that's not the orientation which with which we're
looking and analyzing understanding the situation rather he's saying for the
purposes of cultivating this open awareness that's liberating that's freeing healthy and
wonderful um notice how it is in your body notice your
body notice uh the feeling tones of How It's taken in and registered as pleasant
unpleasant or neither notice the qualities of the Mind the state of the mind is it contracted
is it expansive is it filled with the um uh intense desire or intense aversion
or is it not is it does a mind feel caught does a mind feel
free and those categories have no self in them it's not
like saying am I caught am I filled with greed am I aversive am I
contracted um there's there none of the instructions in the saatana involve the
perspective of me s and ey it can be such a relief it can be a
challenge because of the how common it is to have that perspective but to uh
put it aside or evoke a different perspective the advantage of that is the
perspective of looking at things from the point of view of me and myself in mind what's in it for me and how am I
being seen and what's good for me and how I am is that that's a magnet for all
kinds of of um unskillful unhealthy attitude states of Mind situations it
tends to one where the other it tends to close the space inside of us around us
uh it tends to uh reduce the open-handedness the open-heartedness the open
mindedness and so instead of going that direction like you know what's what's
happening to me how am I doing how are people treating me what's going on here for for me and um how am I improving am
I'm getting better uh am I getting worse I'm a meditation failure all these
things you can say with the word I or me um uh see if you can put them aside
and bring into play a different perspective the four foundations and so what you've learned
about mindfulness of the body um you know there's all these we talked about
um you know go back and read some of the exercises so or listen to some of these
talks about mindfulness of the body and cultivate this greater connection to the body it is you but you don't have to
think about it being you of course this is who you're paying attention to you're paying attention to
your body it's you're paying attention to yourself but um it's uh extra to put
that idea to operate to to analyze to react to the situation from the study of
Me Myself and mind especially when we're meditating so just the body the Simplicity of it the feeling tones the
Mind States the dhas and um and then the orientation also is not
to get anything of it or understand or analyze situation but to begin tuning in
waking up to that uh the changing nature of experience the flow of present moment
experience the River of Life that goes through and things are always changing always moving and to do it from the
perspective of these four foundations and um so there's also a different perspective the perspective of
change things coming and going and um and to do that with an
openhearted open-minded way and this is another this is a um a very helpful way
to loosen the grip of attachments to just rest or float or or just keep
opening to um the flow of change the flow of experience that's only
available or best available when we're centered in Awareness in these direct
experience of body feelings mind States and the Dumas let it all just
flow teaching us how not to cling not to grasp the five hindrances are forms of
grasping forms of clinging that diminish the freedom that diminish the clarity in which we can see
things and for the Buddha diminish our wisdom when you're caught in the five
hindrances bring forth the the U the four foundations when you're caught in a
hindrance how is set in the body what's the feeling tone of it what are the Mind states that are there and then just be
really present for each hindrance in and of itself as it comes and goes letting
go of it and this uh this referencing back
then through the four foundations applies also to the way in which we
practice the way that we meditate and from time to time it's good to go through the
these steps the scales the four Foundation scales and to
see uh in relationship to how you're practicing how you're being mindful how you're meditating how does it feel in
your body how you're doing it are you straining is it tightening up are you
resisting uh are you sluggish are you collapsing are you um are you kind of
draining in your body because you're not really in it how what's happening in your body what's
happening with uh feeling tones is what's the feeling tone of how you're
practicing of how you're doing mindful um is it Pleasant or
unpleasant is it is it something it feels good to do or not what is the Mind state with which
you're doing mindfulness is the mindful is the mindate with greed or aversion or
delusion is the mindset expansive or or is it liberating or is it settled what's
the Mind State and then in the way that you practice the five areas of the fourth
Foundation are the hindrances that play even subtly are we entangled knotted up
in anything uh are we caught in identity Me Myself and mine around the five
Aggregates or are the seven factors of Awakening kind of peing their head up as we're
practicing are they kind of nearby or potentially nearby are they creating the space where those wonderful
factors can begin to grow and in the how we're paying attention is it we seeing in a way
that's allows us to see the four noble truths which is another way of saying
seeing the changing nature of things so um how so to bring bringing
these together these four foundations and when we sit down to meditate uh
different times we might choose one of the foundations more than another Foundation because that seems to be a
Salient one it seems like the good one with which to develop awareness I find it's really useful to come back to
breathing over and over again the first very first exercise uh stay in the body I find be
really useful and then the other ones as needed as is helpful and sometimes I'll
go through the four just okay what how's it this area how's it here in relationship to whatever is happening in
the moment so this is a way of bringing the four foundations together and and
cooperating them and how they are mutually supportive of each other and how this works as a whole the unified ho
there's a unified way bringing together all these practices um for the purposes
of open awareness openhearted open-minded
open-handed attention to ourselves and the world so thank you