so good morning uh good uh good afternoon evening to some
of you um
okay you know uh you know the deal here
so um find your uh find your posture
so breathing in such a way that you
that helps you land here now
a kind of subtle ripple of relaxation of the exhalation
conscious effort to release
tension
whatever tension might remain willingness
to tolerate that
you're not responsible for experience
you're not responsible to manage and mold yourself
you're not responsible for awareness
which does itself
you're not responsible for generating insight
engineering samadhi
concentration
to the extent we're responsible for anything
we're responsible just for the seed
of sincerity and willingness
the willingness to offer our heart up to the dharma
and then trusting having faith
in the logic of the path
we drop beneath the the layers of meaning
into more and more simple intimate
experience of what's here
maybe the breath or the body more broadly
maybe the realm of feeling
pleasant unpleasant neutral
maybe sound and silence
maybe the darkness behind your closed eyes
we just give our attention to something
and let that simplify distill out
more and more of the meanings the sense making
until there's less and less to say about the moment
but more and more urgency to know it deeply
our compulsion to extract something
from the moment compromises our intimacy with it
and so there's a kind of receptivity
willingness to be softened by the moment
when we give ourselves the freedom of not needing to accumulate
anything
you just keep surrendering in awareness
with faith in dharma
[Music]
they uh researcher
psychologist mcadams we are
the stories we live by but we should not forget
that there is no good story that is free of struggle and
tension there is no perfect life narrative just
as there is no perfect life
the dharma is made of thoughts
and arrests arises when thought ceases
it's made of thoughts and arises when thoughts he says the buddha has given us
so many thoughts so many useful ideas um
decoding suffering with such brilliant distinctions and categories and
you know if you if you try to like parse experience like what is expect if
you had asked me matthew what's experience before i started practice i would have made like some wild
hand movements and i don't know what i would have said but it's confusing it's very confusing
and so to begin to actually make some sense of it with
brilliant distinctions this is so useful
the path is about the most beautiful thoughts you know
like is there an image that is more beautiful than meta
loving kindness pervading the entire world
and this path is about a deeply
meaningful way of living a way of living that
makes life feel complete a way of living where doubts about
purpose doubts about meaning really fall away the dharma answers are
quest for meaning and so the path is about meaning and the
path is about stepping out of thought putting down all
meaning all compulsion to know
and to make meaning and there's a kind of dialectic between
this meaning making and stepping out of the realm of meaning
so much of our thought so much of our thought has a kind of
almost a defensive quality like it's necessitated
by fear our meaning making is necessitated by
fear very innocent that it is such
actually some some
neuroscience the organism's survival depends on high
fidelity predictions the computationally efficient solution
to this problem is for the brain to prune its models kind of
somewhat akin to beliefs to prune its models using
prediction errors by processing the difference between a
model's predictions and sensory input the organism can indirectly quantify the
accuracy of its predictions and improve the models that generated them
an organism that does not aim to minimize prediction errors over time
would not survive for long
meaning making revolves around
this kernel of fear you know
the need to know we're contending with deep forces you know just
we're small creatures amidst big forces
and sometimes i'll see you know just look at a like a bird
in a on a branch it's so fragile and like so many
head movements just looking everywhere alert to sounds and movement
kind of like vigilance you know
and um we're vulnerable in some of the same ways and
the way to deal with that is to conceive to make meaning
and we often come to come to practice drowning in meanings
you know so we don't even know how utterly spellbound by
our models our interpretations the kind of house of cards of our
views and opinions our meanings
and when our thoughts feel real
our life feels surreal when our thoughts feel really real
our life takes on a slightly surreal quality there's a kind of alienation in
it and so gills concentric circles of like
the most elaborate fantasies out in the kind of farthest circle and we get
closer and closer to here
the more intimate we get with experience the less
we perceive as being there the less substantial life seems to feel
we make less and less meaning and this compulsion to like always be saying
something about experience that starts to fall away
the compulsion to like talk about our life to talk about this moment
to make meaning out of this bit of sense data that starts to fade
and experience itself when we're not making so much meaning
not conceiving in such dense ways it starts to get thinner and thinner
experience starts to get more and more run through with space
questioner asked the buddha associated with what do appearances
disappear how do pleasure and pain disappear tell me this i'm motivated
to know how they disappear the buddha's
response appearances disappear when not conceiving concepts not conceiving false concepts
not non-conceiving and not conceiving disappearance
this is because conceiving is the basis of conceptual
differentiation
as the more elaborate structures of meaning
making of conceptual proliferation falls away
what is known gets quieter and quieter less and less uh substantial it's both
more there and less there at the same time
the field becomes less and less differentiated the lines we draw between
this experience and that experience between self and world all of this gets more
and more porous and so
we we practiced letting go of meaning and the need for meaning
letting go of the mind's desperate attempts to make conclusions
to land on a conclusion moment by moment
sometimes i'll give the instruction and meditation like come to know conclusions
don't be satiated by any conclusion it's just another
conceiving moment
and then from the silence and the stillness from that we make new meanings
yeah we don't it's like we don't find our meaning in stories
but in the intimacy with experience
like the building blocks of our stories is just this very intimate encounter
with no way knowing in this really pared down simple way
and so the building blocks of our stories don't come from they come from this like encounter
encounter with experience and we tell new stories
about experience new stories about who we are new stories about what means what
new stories about goodness and new stories about what matters
and our autobiography our autobiography becomes a dharma story
a story of dukkha and delusion and clinging and
release and love
and meaning and meaninglessness coexist
but the stories that come out of the intimacy of this experience
they're infused with space infused with space they feel different
than other stories yeah we make meaning out of experience
we tell stories about who we are and what we're doing we tell stories about the
freedom of heart but the urgency and
entanglement with our stories that starts to dissolve
we become more circumspect about our lives our plans
all the meanings we make the stories we tell there is space
everywhere there is space everywhere even as we live
a committed life
so meaning and
meaninglessness dialectic
offer this uh for your consideration
and um yeah
appreciate the chance to be with you today may uh
yeah dharma blessings rain down upon you today and
well we gather 23 hours so
thank you