greetings dear ones i so appreciate this online sangha
although unfortunately i can't see the chat during the sessions but i
do enjoy uh looking at it after the talk is over
and seeing many familiar names from far and wide
so today is our fourth in the series this week on cultivating
peace and the expression of peace we'll explore today
is letting go into unification
so as we've been doing this week we'll begin our meditation by making the
conscious choice to leave all of our concerns
agendas worries and responsibilities well outside of our meditation area
for the next half hour so the invitation is to take a moment to
carefully put all your concerns in a safe place on the other side of the door
with the commitment to leave them there you can always come back to them afterwards
now closing the eyes
getting settled we will practice
breathing in open non-reactive
peaceful awareness breathing out letting go
and as uh we did yesterday we'll begin our meditation by bringing awareness
our friend sati to the fore we know that what awareness is strong
it opens the door for us to seeing when unskillful states arise
and we can make the choice to not pick them up
with saute mindfulness in the forefront
we can bring a strong clear awareness to our posture
balancing and aligning the whole body
feel your physical and energetic connection to the earth
with roots going down deep from your sit bones
if you like you can invite the grounding energy of the earth
to flow up into your body through your seat gently moving up the spine
providing physical and energetic alignment to the posture
and then letting this energy exit through the fontanelle the small
energetic opening in the front of the crown of the head
in the vedic tradition this soft spot is called the infinite
chakra in sanskrit so maybe
you can imagine your energetic connection to infinite space
in qigong this soft spot is where we can absorb the energy of heaven
and draw it down into the body to be clear
drawing on this particular way of connecting to our our energetic body to
heaven and earth is not the teaching of the buddha
excuse me
but it works well for me although it may or may not be helpful for you
if it doesn't work for you no worries just come back to your normal posture
the buddha did however in his teachings on emptiness teach dwelling in the realm
of infinite space
so the idea is to have a posture that is both
grounded and spacious as a way of encouraging the mind to also
be simultaneously stable and open
breathing in normally and out normally do a quick scan from the head down to
the feet relaxing letting go or just softening a little bit
any tension or holding and as you
do this relaxing scan breathing in
contented awareness breathing out
letting go we are cultivating a healthy balance
between being alert and being relaxed
breathing in contented awareness breathing out
letting go
settling in with the eyes closed
breathing in contented awareness breathing out
letting go
if the thinking mind becomes active we whisper
in a kind and loving way come back be here
breathing in contented awareness breathing out
letting go
breathing in contented awareness
breathing out letting go
now we're going to transition
from having
generated the condition of peaceful contentment
to the unification
the buddha teaches that in one who feels peaceful contentment
the mind becomes unified and the mind state
of unification the buddha is pointing to is like
coming home coming home to a place where we feel
safe and where we can really be ourselves
so over these few days we've put in place the conditions for the arising of
samadhi the subtle joy of resting in awareness
tranquility and peaceful contentment
and is what is so nice about samadhi is that we don't have to be perfect
to let go into this unification what a relief
in the unified mind there's room for all of us warts and all
nothing has to be different than the way it is including ourselves
so continue practicing now breathing in
quiet contentment breathing out
home to safety
breathing in quiet contentment
breathing out home to safety
you are home in your sacred seat of awakening your bodhimanda
knowing that everything is okay and all of you
is safe at home
breathing in quiet contentment breathing out
home to safety
as we come to the end of this sitting let's bring to mind the people we will
come into contact with today strangers as well as people we know
and making the wish the aspiration of offering them
our example our example is the very best way
to give these teachings to others
so through our example
we model and offer the ease
the happiness and the safety of being at home
with a mind at peace with things as they are
we have room to be just who we are
and we offer others the same freedom to be just who they are
and this is a beautiful gift
may all beings ourself included first of all be safe
may all beings know peace
may all beings be happily contented
may all beings feel at home
in their true abode of a unified mind
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
welcome dear sangha it's lovely to be here with you all
some of us have been part of this online community since it started over two years ago
and i treasure this international sangha so i thank you for your presence
today is the fourth day in our theme this week of cultivating peace
and yesterday i appreciated the kind and thoughtful comments about my loss
when my little sister died she became ill 12 years ago and died
seven years ago and to be honest
i no longer experience her departure as a loss she's still very much present in my
heart yes i had been grieving intensely and
constantly for about five months before being able to in a retreat
setting dive into and then swim
in that ocean of tears and that was transformative
to abide in the lucid awareness of my pain
and finally to let go of wanting or needing a different reality
and this was profoundly healing
as i said when distress and loss give way to peaceful acceptance
then we are in a much better position to radiate our peaceful contented
abiding so that we can better offer support
to others who are suffering
and this ability to remain peacefully contented with whatever the dharma has on offer
for us is the condition that makes possible
the last of the necessary conditions for abiding in samadhi
the state from which the liberating insights of awakening
can arise so the expression of peace that we're
exploring today is letting go into unification
samadhi is usually translated into english as concentration but personally
i have a strong preference for translating it as unification
because in pali the word samadhi literally means gathering together
we are happily composed not needing anything to be different in
our present moment experience
for me the english word concentration has connotations of
maybe coming from the control tower which may suggest effort
and it's interesting that in the vast pali canon with so many teachings
there are no instructions that the buddha gave on what to do
to enter into samadhi rather
he taught that what we must do to advance on the dharmic path to awakening
is to put in place the conditions that allow for samadhi to arrive
spontaneously effortlessly those conditions of course begin with
living ethically and with generosity
and then in order to step out of the bonds of samsara the first thing we have to do
is to establish receptive awareness sati
this is the foundation of our practice both inside and outside of meditation
yesterday we spoke about living in awareness with satyapathana
evoking a metaphor for the mind of living in a messy house but one that
has a quiet living room now when we begin the dharmic path
clearly seeing dukkha both in our own
unskillful mind states and in the world around us
we see the mess and we know there's work to do to clean out all the other rooms of the house
and this work starts with our commitment to practicing continuous mindfulness the
best we can and as our mindfulness practice develops
we begin to get a feeling sometimes for resting
in present moment awareness
what i'd like to offer today is an instruction of
how to encourage these beautiful mental states
like sustained mindfulness so when
awareness arises and is
strong the instruction is to notice
appreciate and relax
into the experience of strong mindfulness
and we do this with all of the conditions that allow us to enter into samadhi
so we begin with the subtle joy of resting
in this clear awareness our gladness to be on the dharma path
also naturally allows for joy to arise so when joy is present we see that
we notice it we appreciate it and we relax into it
and then joy gives way to tranquility and it's important
to notice tranquility when it's there and then noticing it
can we appreciate the moments of calm can we relax
into the coldness excuse me
and we've seen that when the mind is calm peaceful contentment
naturally arises and so we repeat the practice of noticing
appreciating and relaxing into the beautiful feeling of being content
with things just as they are this practice helps us to become more
familiar with these wholesome states and with familiarity
it becomes easier to enter into them but we do need clear awareness when
dwelling in wholesome states because sometimes it can be tempting to get caught
in chasing after these beautiful states of mind but we know that they're conditioned
they come and go so if we can stay
soft and relaxed in the well-being of contentment
the door is wide open for samadhi to arise
and now i would like to read to you from a beautiful teaching by gil that
he taught when uh
he was teaching a course at the institute of buddhist studies in berkeley
on um samadhi
gil says to allow yourself to settle into a state that's broad
expansive it helps to be relaxed to have faith
to have some modicum of stability and it helps to be mindful
part of mindfulness is that we start noticing how we're tense stuck
how we have concerns and we find a way to live at peace
conflict-free with whatever arises
and we heal the urge and the wars
that exist inside us mindfulness sees all this
and perhaps is able to meet it with kindness friendliness
as our attention settle we settled into being here
and we start to feel like it's actually more interesting to be here
than to be elsewhere so part of the movement of mindfulness
and samadhi is a clarifying of our interest
if you try to settle on the breath but you have all these thoughts
is that you're more interested in your thoughts it's not easy to convince the mind
that it's more interesting to be here distracted thoughts might arise
and we let them fall away and it becomes more interesting to keep
the focus on the safety of the harbor that we're going to
it means that we gather together all the energies and there is a phenomenal sense of
safety to be found in the state of samadhi
we keep coming back letting distractions go and just
settling in with the simplicity of being here
and contentment arises the mind is fully engaged
and we have uh the encouragements of joy and happiness
that help us to stay on track it begins to feel so good to be here
and this is very healing work samadhi can move toward deeper and
deeper states of equanimity
so we can develop somebody into a very deep equanimity
where being here and settled is so strong and safe
that the mind does not really react to what is going on
it's not something to be believed this process
it will be revealed to you when you've entered the temple under the tree on your riverbank
and it brings wisdom for how to be in the world
doing this deep work and truly being here discovering this samadhi of just being
here transforms us into peacemakers in this world
it's not an escape but a sacred preparation of caring for each other
in this world we live in so thank you to gil for this
samadhi is the condition for liberating insights to arise
and we begin to trust the supreme safety of dwelling
in a unified mind where no part of us is left out
so for the next 24 hours it would be nice
to experiment with these
wholesome mind states that allow somebody to arise and when you see one of them
whether it's joy or tranquility or contentment
take a moment to notice to appreciate
and to relax into that a little bit and in this way
um you'll become more and more familiar with these mind states and they will
arise more easily
so thank you very much for your attention
and thank you for your practice