so hello everyone
the um i'm feeling happy looking at the greetings in the chat
thank you for those of you who'd takes warm greetings every morning and
i take the greetings in the chat from to be representative of
kind of the warm greetings the goodwill
that exists in this extended community that's participating
including the people who are not chatting so i want to thank all of you for this
so um i want to uh
begin a little story from the sutras this morning before the meditation and
i'll continue it tomorrow so hopefully you'll forgive me and
there is a some kind of celestial being that comes
down to visit a young monk who's starting to meditate and the celestial being says um
you're young in the prime of life you should go go out and enjoy sensual pleasures
why do you abandon what is immediate and directly visible
here and now for this dharma practice and the monk says
no it's not not the case i'm not abandoning what is directly
visible here and and and immediate now the dharma is directly
visible the dharma is directly present now immediate and it goes
through it like this and then there's the deity sit that says well
explain yourself and the monk uh can't explain himself so i'm new so you have to go talk to the
buddha so that's the part for tomorrow but the end of the buddha explaining all this to
him to the to the celestial being the celestial being um summarizes
the teachings the summary it's you know the answer to all this
and that's what i want to read um
oh no yeah here here it is okay
one should do nothing mean in all the world
not by speech by mind or by body having abandoned
sensual desires mindful and clearly comprehending
which one one should not pursue a course that is painful and harmful
one should not that's why i wanted to read to not pursue a course that is painful and harmful
so this practice that we do the way that it's immediately beneficial
visible here and now to be seen for oneself
is a practice of non-harming we see something about the dharma when
we harm ourselves and so the dharma is seen there if we see it as dharma so we see it as a
teaching something to learn from something to practice with so suffering and pain and discomfort and
despair that we might feel in the dharma we don't have to see it as unfortunate
we see it as the dharma oh this is this is true this is what's happening i
see it clearly now and we practice with it and we learn the practice of non-harming
thorough non-harming radical non-harming
non-harming in all directions including not harming oneself and that's when we really discover
that this dharma is uh
is visible here it's now immediate
it is
it is onward leading it is to be experienced by the wise
and it is um so um so that's what we'll do today maybe that
can be a orientation for your meditation
the practice of non-harming and there's a way in which
letting the mind be distracted lost in thought while not directly harming
is a little bit stressful it's a little bit of a tension it's a little bit away from the place of freedom and peace
and so this guideline to sit with non-harming
quietly and if you do harm yourself it's with being mean or being
something um don't add harm on top of that
see the dharma in it don't believe it
but dharma it don't don't don't participate in it
but see it clearly for what it is and then you're seeing the dharma
so with that we'll sit quietly thank you
as we come to the end of this sitting
maybe to take a few moments in your own way
to appreciate that the heart of the dharma
that is visible here [Music] now
that you're invited to take a good look at that is onward leading
and something to experience to be experienced by the wise to experience by yourself
at the heart of this dharma is non-harming
non-harm not harming ourselves not harming others
not harming self and others not harming the various communities
groups were part of and not harming the entire world
and may it be that as we end this meditation that the meditation serves as a basis
for a better understanding of harm and not harming
that we see the dharma
or to see the dharma in harming means we don't believe in the harming
anymore the activity of hurting someone
we know there's another way there's non-harming
the entire dharma can be discovered on this path to
fuller and fuller manifestations of non-harming
may we live for the non-harm for the benefit
for the welfare of this whole world
may others experiences experience the blessings of non-harming
may others experience the safety of non-harm
may others experience the peace of non-harming
and they may others be free of all forms of harm
may all beings be happy [Music]
thank you
so today we come to the fourth characteristic of the dhamma
the dharma and that is that it's up
and most commonly it's that's understood as it's onward leading
and i like this translation of the word
there are other meanings of it the ancient commentaries they discussed
some of the different meanings they can have these days uh bikibodi the great
translator of our suttas he's translating it as applicable applicable
that the dhamma is something that you can immediately apply you can use it's usable
and which is also a very nice idea it's immediately used you can use it
and so and another meaning of it is that um
is that the dhamma is something it's immediate and now
and approachable something to be to approach something that's nearby
something to be close to stay close to um we're guided close to it
so these kind of different meanings so the idea of onward leading i'm very
fond of because when we practice it's not a static thing that we sit and
practice nothing to think of onward leading as something that has almost a natural quality to it it
moves along without my effort so if i
float on top of a current in this river it's onward leading it carries me along
if i stand on a conveyor belt you know that these walking i don't know
sidewalks that they have at the airport i see them at the airport um you stand there and just carries you
along you don't have to do the walking so this idea of being carried along unfolding by the dharma
and the you know it's not the mystical or strange thing i like to understand it
very simply that the dharma is to see the dharma to be
it's visible here now just really see it to take a good look at it what's happening here now
one of the things we start seeing is the tensions we hold the holding patterns in the body and the mind we
start seeing the strain the stresses we carry with us and
and there's something about showing up and being really present for tension for stress for holding for that
um something begins to release it's hard it's a sooner or later it's
hard for the system or psychophysical system to
relax uh to to hold on to keep being tense
under the gaze of mindfulness of awareness
it's kind of like we can't do two things at once we can't be fully present
and fully tense and fully engaged and holding on and clinging and so
as we devote ourselves to being present to being aware that part of us there's less energy
available to be tense too tight to hold on to be to cling
and so then it begins to relax and soften sometimes we see what we're holding on
to and we let go of it and something relaxes and that relaxation of the system mind
heart body is onward leading because it heightens heightens the sensitivity
to recognize more clinging to recognize the remnants that what's you know what the next layer of tension
or strain that we have it heightens our attention to notice when we bring in more strain again we
get tense again and now you can see that in meditation sometimes very clearly where they were
pretty relaxed and at ease and then we have a certain thought or memory and we
feel tightening up someplace maybe the whole body or we brace ourselves in some way
and we can see we're getting involved in an idea a story and the effect it has
and sometimes it's it's in seeing it so clearly it's possible to let go of it say i don't need to be involved in that
story i can let go of those thoughts and let it go and the body relaxes a little bit
and so um so sometimes it's a practice that we do
because of this heightened sensitivity that we get more and more aware of it and so as we relax we're more sensitive
as we relax there's a momentum towards greater ease towards greater letting go not clinging
and our whole body begins shifting uh they say that with a lot of stress
a lot of stress that are uh biochemical
makeup inside of us changes there's more cortisol stress hormones and different things
and they're not good for us but as we have ease and de-stress the system moves towards kind of a homeostasis of health
and well-being more or less and so there's this onward leading towards health to spiritual health
psychological health even to some degree his physical health that can happen through this
and so at some point this movement towards letting go uh begins to feel like it's happening on
its own and it feels like we're kind of on the gentle slide or in a current that
all we have to do is stay out of the way don't interfere with it and with the whole system moves towards greater and
greater ease greater relaxing letting go opening up and it's remarkable to feel this it's
almost impersonal it's almost natural quality to it
and it's kind of very inspiring to feel this not selfhood of this process of the dharma unfolding within
us we have our role for sure but that we can't engineer it we have to
kind of enable it to allow it and and stay close to it
and uh so this dharma that we stay close to is one of the meetings of panayako
something to stay close to and i love this idea that we stay close to the dharma
keep it close in stay close remember it
it's the most important thing for our life because it's more important than anything
not because other things are unimportant but because they sit at the center of a
really healthy way of being with things that are important in our life the important things in our life if
they're worthwhile stay important but with the dharma being the most important
we actually have more to offer the other important things we we have in our life
and with the dharma being most important there's a quality of freedom that comes
with how we connect and be with people we people we love we can still love them
fully maybe even more so but there's a quality of freedom of non-expectation of
non-demanding maybe a non-neediness that goes along with it
so onward leading um then pick a body now as i said translated as applicable
so as we see the tension the holding that we have
we see it clearly that shows us what we can do what's useful we
see where we can let go of and sometimes we can't let go of the tension the holding itself but we might
let go of our self-criticism that we might have
oh i'm such a terrible person i'm bad buddhist because i'm clinging
maybe that can be let go of and we're still holding on to something but we're more at ease with
being tense more at ease with our attachment and it doesn't mean that we're
condoning or celebrating and participating wholeheartedly in our attachments
but it does mean that we're not adding more suffering on top of it and this is a beautiful quality i think
of dhamma practice of this kind of acceptance this kind of non-uh
movement would be not being troubled by all the challenges we have all the
faults that we have a few of us have a few faults uh inner personal faults and
i kind of like to think that every human has it it's not even personal it just comes with being human being
and so to to not be troubled by that and the same time to see it and to know
it and not to cause any harm because of it and as long as we don't cause harm
it's fine to be who you are no harm to yourself no harm to others
that's it's profound because it's an alternative to how much harm is being caused in this
world it's phenomenal the amount of harming that goes on even in the most subtle ways even among
people who love each other there's harming going on and it would be a radically different
world if we stop that so even for one person to come to that place of not harming
is just an amazing thing close to that so
upanayako this onward leading quality of the dharma
also means the dharma is applicable it's something we can apply ourselves to
we can apply ourselves to the stream that carries us to greater and greater freedom
and it's something to stay close to stay close to the stream stay close to this practice stay close to this thing that
can be visible right here that is now
that is a good to take a deep look at it yes look at it deeply
stay close to that so that you can experience what the wise
experience to be experienced by the wise and that will be the topic for tomorrow
so thank you and stay close so today
stay close to non-harming
and and if that means that you're seeing clearly the way that you harm
try not to be troubled by that and don't participate in it
see it clearly don't add problems on top of it but to explore this world of harming and
unharming stay close to that and you'll find there you'll see the dharma there
that's where the dharma can be found so thank you very much