greeting friends greetings and good morning good afternoon
good evening whatever your time zone might be it's lovely to be with you
in this day in may and i'm delighted to be able to support
gil while he's teaching a retreat and also to spend time with you sharing teachings and practices together
so my name is nikki murgaforie for those whom
uh we have not met um so without further ado let's uh
let's start meditating together and i'll introduce the theme
for today and um
whatever whatever is needed later so let's just arrive together let's arrive together
let's arrive let's arrive in our bodies
let's arrive in this moment
and releasing into the body
releasing thoughts releasing plans preoccupations
it's okay we'll return to them
afterwards taking this time
to take refuge to take refuge
starting is always starting with our intention
connecting with the intention
what is my intention right now why am i here
what is my bigger intention big picture intention
and what is my moment-to-moment intention for this engagement
letting your intention be felt not in your head as a thought but in your body
in your heart as a conviction [Music]
as a bright light
as an inspiration that lifts you up keeps reorienting you every moment when
you get lost in thought there is your intention yes i do intend
to be here to be present to be kind to myself and others
when i'm lost it's all part of the training
connect to be
to inhabit the better angels of ourselves
this angel is here available to be inhabited
with ease with ease letting the body relax
ah letting
the muscles be soft
the forehead releasing
our face our jaw
the cheeks the ears
neck and shoulders
putting down their weight
the chest unburdened
releasing softening
whatever emotions are present is okay
it's all okay
nothing is a problem in this moment to be treated as such to make space to make space
the heart more expansive than we realize
releasing releasing the abdomen
your upper back our lower back into the sit bones
releasing the weight of the legs the upper legs lower legs and feet
here this body this entire
body
soft alive
relaxed as much as possible
breathing breathing
breathing on its own we don't have to consciously breathe
trust trust the body
and at any point if you find yourself lost in thinking it's okay
it's really okay
become aware in that moment with a smile towards yourself towards the thinking
mind
thank you thoughts thank you please come back later
now let yourself let awareness
reconnect with your intention
to be present in this moment to train your heart your mind such
beautiful intention to be kind
and settle back in the abdomen settle back
the sit bones receiving the breath
calming soothing breath
it is helpful to reconnect with our intention now and then
here here let the intention be the guiding
north star
and yet right here so close in our hearts inhabiting
this better angel here and now in this moment
not too far
the angel out ahead is closer than we think it's right here
stepping into and inhabiting
in this moment
are better angels
just a mind moment of intention away right here
what is your intention in this moment
what is the intention of the heart not in a tight graspy way at all
but in a beautiful loving perhaps even devotional way
what do you want to give your heart to in this moment of awareness
right here
what do you want to cultivate in this
short human life in this moment of it in this passing moment
it's already here just recognize it
with relaxed easy
soft gentle heart mind body
and one invitation for an exploration
for some the word intention is just fine
and for some it might be too dry too heady
you're welcome to experiment in your heart and your body with an alternative
how about the angel within
aligning with the angel within
or whatever frey's idea is embodied and inspires you
physically see how this might shift my invitation
if you like it how it might shift something for you open something
inhabiting inhabiting the angel within
hmm
maybe so you sit a little taller a little more with ease
vibrations of warmth goodness kindness
reverberate see for yourself
and as we move to bring this sitting together
the sitting to a close together
let the inhabited felt expansive angel within
to appreciate that you showed up that you have practiced
and for them to let go to be kind towards
anything that quote-unquote you didn't like
sleepiness distraction it's all okay
it's all okay
this angel within is forgiving kind wise
appreciative grateful
to have sat with sangha in this moment in time
they don't take it for granted to have sat with other angels
in this moment in time oh so much goodness
so much goodness co-created together
so much goodness each of us
and with generosity we open our hearts and offer
offer the goodness the merit of these moments
of beauty of presence share it
it to all beings everywhere
all beings may all beings everywhere
be free including ourselves
thank you for your practice
so
hello and greetings again dear sangha
so lovely to practice together so lovely
not taken for granted it's i have this image of
us in different places and so i so appreciate the
the words and chat coming through and the different places you are in the world
so we appreciate feeling your presence all of us together
powerful powerful thank you
so so today i would like to
speak about
this teaching this concept this
practice that's often misunderstood in the west
not perhaps so much by buddhists but maybe by us too at times
but it this word has been co-opted this teaching has been
co-opted by the popular culture and misrepresented misunderstood so
so this teaching i'd like to talk about today is the beautiful profound teaching
of karma karma so
in the west it's often thought of as
an inheritance and it's often bad like oh what have i done or what has
this person done in their past life that they deserve this or they must have
done something terrible or i must have done something terrible and
basically using the um the teaching of karma
as as flagellation as a way to flagellate
either cell flagellate or flagellate others so
it's not a helpful and it's not actually it's not a useful
way to use this practice to interpret this practice to to understand this practice
so i want to speak a little bit about that and actually to the profundity of what
karma means here and now for us and it's not this magical
um thing this idea that we don't quite understand and it's weird and it's in
some other dimension
so so not to think of karma as destiny or
as fate as it is often thought of but it's
again it's really a distortion to think of it as fate it's a distortion of the buddhist
teachings it's definitely a distortion and and i love the words of um
of andrew oldinsky
saying their name properly olensky who says
that karma is has unparalleled unparalleled profundity
and significance i love that unparalleled profundity the concept of karma in the teaching so
so let's do away with let's do away with this magical this weird thing that we
don't even know um you know fate destiny let's do away with that understanding all together but instead
consider first of all the word karma simply means action
and it's derived from the verbal root vector which means to do to make in pali
to do to make you already get the sense right to do to make is different from something you
inherit something magical and weird right so to do to make
and there are three distinct senses of the word here there are three
distinct senses of this word here and yet these three distinct senses which i will
describe in a moment are inseparable
inseparable aspects of the same process of karma okay so here are the three aspects
so the first one is the decision to do something
it's the intention is the decision to do something okay that's the that's
the leading edge the second aspect is the action
that actually carries carries the thing out is the action
and the third aspect is what we make what we make thereby
as the result of that action so there are these three distinct
aspects so let me repeat that so the first is the decision or the
intention to do something the second is the action that actually carries it out and the third is the
result of the action what we make
and karma is actually all three of those they're
inseparable they're distinct but inseparable not just the intention
not just the action itself and not just the results it's all three of them
which is so beautiful and profound it's right here right now
so the buddhist understanding is that these three parts are the same whole
so the intention being the leading edge of karma
which leads which directs the activities
of the mind speech and the body all of those are
considered actions notice that the mind thoughts are considered actions
in buddhism actions of the mind speech is considered action of
speaking of course and the body is considered action so all those three so
again intention is the leading edge of the karma of karma which directs the activities
which then which then on the trailing edge it
accumulates the karmic formations of the karmic dispositions karmic dispositions it's our disposition
if we just drop the word karmic it's our dispositions it's how we show up it's how we
ourselves are made up of those dispositions which also is the intention the actions
and the dispositions so
so in other words actions is preceded every action
the mind of action of the mind speech and body is action is already preceded
by some doing right by some doing and that doing
is where the decisions are made is the intention is the doing of the oh
intending the volition the aligning or not aligning it's that
there's some doing before the action and then there is a result in the making
in the making of our unique personality of our dispositions
so so the main idea behind karma is the
relationship between what we choose to do and what we
make of ourselves what we choose to do and what we make of ourselves
let me just pause here wow to me this teaching is so profound it's
not about faith oh poor me what have i got it's actually
a powerful empowering teaching of what we choose to do and what we make
make of ourselves so powerful so powerful i i
love this teaching and every time i'll just share with you
as i come to this and many teachings over the years over time there are more
nuances there's more beauty maybe when i was younger my early years of practice there was
some level of understanding and the more i come to these teachings there is
a newer level of appreciation for the beauty for the profundity
of these practices so i invite you to see them with their fresh eyes even if you're a
practiced experienced practitioner don't hear the word karma and go yeah yeah
yeah i know i've studied this appreciate it as if with fresh eyes
in your practice in in your heart and mind in this moment
so one last thing i want to say and there's more i want to say tomorrow so
there is this expression in pali
sankaram api sankarito sankharam apa sankarito
which are many ways that can be translated to english and again according to andrew olensky
could be translated as one forms formations or one constructs
constructions or one creates creations
one fabricates fabrications so
the an action both involves the activity as well as building something as the
product of it and an image that is used in the suttas
often is the image of a potter on a pottery wheel a potter is engaged
in the creative process of shaping forming the clay and making something to
his will with his intention with his desire with his actions so intention actions
is forming the clay forming the clay and then when the pot is done
it's put in a kiln and it's fired it's put in the fire
and then it's an enduring it's an everlasting artifact this pot so think
of ourselves our characters our personalities our very self quote-unquote self
as this again olenski puts it beautifully ossified karmic relics
ossified or rather as a gallery of ossified karmic relics
the accumulated residue of earlier dynamic processes of intention and
action i'll close by reading that one more time what we take to be our very self
is viewed in buddhist thought as a gallery of ossified karmic relics the accumulated residue of
earlier dynamic processes of intention and action
there's so much more here to say but just to end and say think of karma as an
empowerment as an empowering teaching that one we can change we can change anyway
we're out of time so much more to say but we have time together tomorrow well
maybe life is so impermanent and unpredictable but
if all maybe we'll see each other tomorrow take good care looking forward to practicing
together be well