hello and welcome
and here on Friday those of you been following these 7 A.M weekday sittings
for some time but recognize that often there's a unfolding a
pattern of kind of going more going deeper or
um by Friday kind of Step by Step taking a
step deeper deeper over the five days and today um
the simile that's going to be to I'll talk about later is um
very simple simile that on the surface is
just seems very ordinary and it's a simile for full Awakening
and so I want to highlight the ordinariness of it so when we do this meditation maybe
there can be for you um an emphasis on
seeing clearly what is obvious
what is ordinary here and in that seeing the ordinariness of everything
maybe something releases for you something relaxes the searching the wanting the not
wanting the fixing they're trying to understand
trying to have something special trying to recover some state of
meditation that you used to have just very simply a simple being with
what is so the simile is a person standing on the edge of a
lake the lake is very clear clearer than clear just
maybe so clear that you almost don't even know there's water there
and the person looks into that that Lake and seas on the lake floor
you see shells different oyster shells different kinds of shells
seize the Pebbles and the gravel that's there on the lake bottom
and see schools of fish both hovering still in the water not moving
and also gently swimming around
so the remarkable thing about this metaphor is the clarity of the water
but what we see in the water our natural phenomena
and maybe for that reason it's kind of special especially for people who are not connected to Nature so much
but very ordinary just the gravel at the bottom of a lake the shell that's down there the shells
and uh little fish in schools
swimming around peacefully so just to look at this
simple World natural world and let it be that simple
and what would it be like for this meditation where you are content
to be present here and now for what is obvious
what is it that obviously is clear
maybe what it is is you're confused you're not clear about that almost
anything except the fact that you're you are confused and you see that clearly
where things are not clear because you're agitated but what can be simple and obvious
is the agitation so
maybe with an emphasis on breathing what is obvious about breathing
what can you know with some clarity
don't worry about trying to see deeply or
don't worry about how you're not seeing clearly just be concerned about how you do seek
what you do see clearly would you feel and sense and experience
and let that be like looking into the Clear Lake
and seeing the simple natural phenomena that's there
the simile is a simile for awakening what is it about
this radical simplicity of being with what is obvious
independent whether it feels concentrated or feels like some great spiritual experience
what is it about just the clarity of knowing what's obvious seeing it as a
natural phenomena and letting it be that way what is it about that that's so valuable
so to take a posture for meditation
relaxing the Eyes by gazing down
and gently closing the eyes
and gently taking some deeper breaths
okay and longer exhales
relaxing on the exhales
letting the breathing return to normal and for a few more rounds of breathing
relaxing in the body relaxing in the mind
and then relaxing more deeply
maybe settling the attention on the body breathing
and maybe with breathing as a default where your attention lands and takes in
more than anything else for this sitting here
emphasize knowing what can be known clearly
what is obvious and appreciate the clarity of knowing
that if for example you're confused about
this instruction maybe what's known clearly is the
confusion
if it's a sound Outdoors that's known clearly
know that whatever is clearest most obvious
know it has a simple natural phenomenon
to emphasize the naturalness of it maybe you can have the little phrase
that goes along with it of course
of course this is what's here nothing to fight nothing to condemn
nothing to want just of course this is what's happening now
and in doing this way beginning to appreciate
Clarity simplicity directness of knowing
that is not encumbered by what is known
what is getting in the way of seeing what's obvious Here and Now
and if there is something getting in the way thoughts or something else
know that simply clearly as the obvious thing
whatever you're aware of how can you be aware of it as a natural
phenomenon where only what's obvious about it
in the present moment how it is in the present
not what you're thinking about but just thinking
not the story of what you're feeling your emotions in the present simple awareness of the
emotion whatever it is
what can you know how can you know it with Clarity and simplicity
as we come to the end of the sitting
to settle back release any extra effort you're making
to be mindful in favor of seeing clearly
knowing simply
being present for what is obvious
without any tension or straining or wanting
and if straining and wanting is the obvious let that be what is known clearly
and to do this to appreciate simplicity
clarity
the ordinariness of being aware
and imagine offering this kind of attention
to others
not being aware of others with your desires and your aversions
not judging or without bias Prejudice without
preferences just the simplicity
naturalness of seeing clearly
letting each person that you see be someone natural and simple and
expression of nature
into through the medium of this Simplicity
and clarity to gaze upon the world kindly
gaze upon others with good will
gaze upon others with simple care ordinary care
that you care for them you wish them well
May others be happy
May others be safe May others be peaceful
May others be free
[Music]
thank you so on this Friday I offer my
Fifth and final Reflections on the Buddha's assemblies for meditation
and the previous similes all came from the
Buddhist discussion about the four absorptions and um
the um today's will be
um he's a analogy or simile for awakening
often following the absorb absorptions and it's a remarkable simile because of
its ordinariness the four absorptions are states of deep
meditation that are very satisfying and people have a variety of attachments
to them attached to wanting to have it when they don't and being upset when they don't
have these states of meditation wanting to have it again and some
sometimes desperate way if they have it once
sometimes they're a little bit frightening because they're so different than ordinary life
the ends of people pulled back and what was that and
and sometimes they lend themselves to a feeling of great certainly Bliss Rapture
wonderousness amazement Delight they can be very healing there's lots of
benefits with concentration practice but they kind of are extraordinary
states of mind at least from the point of view of everyday life
in the middle of these uh some states of concentration if they're not too intense
it can feel like oh this is the natural mind this is a natural state
the Altered States Of Consciousness is everyday life of anger and desire and
confusion and all the stuff that goes on that when we're agitated in the mind
but the mind is settled and quiet and peaceful it can feel like this is that this is help this is natural
but in any case some of these states of concentration are kind of extraordinary in some ways
the simile for awakening comes back to something ordinary
and for all that Buddhism for all the ways in which uh Awakening Buddhist practice emphasizes not self
the the the assemblies for absorption
kind of involves a kind of Disappearing of the person and uh at deeper and deeper states of
concentration uh until the body disappears and
and um and they're kind of like the person is not quite there
not because discounting you as a person with meditation is just that the mind's
gotten so quiet and peaceful an assembly for awakening the person has
come back person is standing and the clarity it's in my mind of just
standing standing at a place here definitive location standing a person
standing upright and this person is looking into a very
clear lake and the person is looking into the lake and seeing
because it's so clear can look right down to the bottom to the lake floor and
the person sees there different kinds of shells the text translates that is
oyster shells that they're kind of in the in the water also sees uh gravel and Pebbles in the
water in the floor and sees schools of fish either swimming
around together or um or just kind of hovering still in the
water and these are seen clearly
so that's the simile and uh and there I think there's nothing
extraordinary symbolic that's supposed to be represented by
what these objects in the water because the emphasis here is on the
clarity of seeing and uh that when sees something so
clearly and so obviously that it seems like ordinary the mind isn't for or against is not
excited by it it's not uh you know making a self out of it not
congratulating oneself it's just the things there just the objects of nature
you know gravel and Pebbles you know we don't make much about them
shells maybe we don't make much of them but them unless we want to eat them and um and a little little uh I imagine
this in metaphor the schools of fish are very small fish so there's not you know any not like if
you want to fish them because you know they're way too small to to
um to eat so it's just kind of this the natural scene of in the water
and um and that ordinariness of Awakening
maybe there's something extraordinary about the freedom and the release of Awakening but uh of attachments but uh there's
also something amazingly ordinary extraordinarily ordinary
and that we're seeing nature we're seeing what's natural we're seeing what's here as part of nature as in its
naturalness and this is part of the release we're releasing all the ways we
want extraordinary all the ways in which we attribute meaning and purpose and self and and
philosophies and all kinds of kind of layers and layers and layers of building cathedrals of
ideas and stories and meaning and self around experience those get released and freed
and what are we left with and uh we're left with Simplicity very simple
just standing seeing clearly seeing clearly as if everything is in
the naturalness of everything so now I want to read the simile so you
with that background that I and this is biker body's translation it's in the
39th discourse in the middle length discourses it's also in
the second discourse of the long discourses and um
so it goes to bigger body's translation goes like this just as if
there were a lake in a mountain recess clear limpid and undisturbed
so that a person with good sight standing on the bank could see shells gravel and Pebbles
and also shows a fish swimming and resting
and is and he might think that person might think
there is this fish swimming about and resting there is this Lake clear limpid and
undisturbed there are these shells gravel and Pebbles and also these Shoals of fish swimming
about and resting so
exactly how we are supposed to interpret this simile for awakening
can you know there's different choices and ways and certainly there's much more to be said about this
but uh what I'd like to do by ending this week is to emphasize
the ordinariness of it the ordinance of you standing still and
quiet and peaceful at seeing and seeing the ordinariness of life
seeing the simple things around you without the mind
wanting and needing and avoiding and building and fantasizing and
making up a self in relationship to it in the simile the person does not
disappear because sometimes that is a
extra this idea I'm not supposed to be here I'm supposed to be empty I'm supposed to be somehow vanish and have
no self here or I'm supposed to kind of be have a non-dualistic relationship with the
world where I disappear or just the world and and everything disappears or everything
is somehow
I'm interpreting a simile is just you're allowed to stand and be here
but if you're alone and the mountain is kind of in a safe wonderful cozy place and
looking at the water the many people just kind of they're
the self the social concerns that exist in urban settings living around people
kind of disappear just here and not needing identity not needing to
approve oneself defend oneself assert oneself not needing to be anything for anybody
just standing there looking into this calm peaceful Lake and seeing the most you know ordinary
things in it and um gravel shells
small fish swimming around and um so what would it take for you
to have trust enough that it's okay to be this way
to stand tall and confident in a certain way
the kind of confidence that looks confident from the outside
but the inside you're neither confident nor not confident
just be willing to be as you are
and be able to kind of gaze upon everything the world yourself
content to know what is obvious
not searching for meaning not searching for what's behind it the cause and the history and
fault and blame and
there might be time and place for those things but what is it to just sit stand there and
gaze upon things as if everything is just a natural everything obvious everything's seen
clearly as it is in the present moment whatever it might be it's just seeing it
as nature no greater lesser value than
gravel in the lake bed or
small little fish swimming around a Marvel of nature but
not something to get to appropriate or be greedy about or to
hate or to not something supernaturally phenomenal
and fantastic that you can write postcards home and say wow I had this amazing experience it was so
far out and not to diminish the value of far out
experiences but
just the ordinariness of being here with clarity
so um so similes
so part of the value of similes is they can be interpreted under certain
different ways they can kind of uh sometimes like poetry maybe you don't have to always
understand the author's intent behind the similes but rather by exploring them and
interpreting them and seeing them on different days different months different years they might point to
something or speak to something or clarify something that is new and just
and sees the world in a new ways sees ourselves in new ways similes are kind
of have this wonderful power to reach deep inside of ourselves to understand new ways
and expand our senses and
because all of these similes have to do with meditation kind of the path of the Dharma
there is a place to try to understand what they mean dharmically what they mean as part of this path
and uh and how do they work together how do they unfold together
for the purposes of freedom a freedom that in the end
allows us to be ordinary
a glorious ordinary
where we're free from all the burdens that we carry
so thank you very much and um so as I said yesterday I want to repeat
the announcement that um it looks like I won't be here for the next four weeks
I'm teaching retweets three of those weeks and then I'm going away a family trip for Thanksgiving
and um and for the next two weeks I have guests
coming a wonderful it's a couple a wonderful
two people in the imc's teacher training
wise teacher trainees who are already great teachers and done a fair amount of teaching already
and um and uh they are I think they're the youngest
teachers in the teacher training or among the youngest and so it's kind of like the new generation coming along
which is kind of exciting and I'm very happy to introduce them to you this way and have them come and and
so I think you'll enjoy them quite a bit this coming week it's kodo Koto Conlin
and he's also a priest at San Francisco Zen Center so he has a similar background to me and that I was a priest
there and also trained to be the Persona teacher and um and then there's May Elliott who
is a long time vipassana student and also a student at San Francisco Zen Center and teacher there
um and um so and then the last two weeks I'm not
sure what's happening yet we're kind of a little bit dependent on having volunteers help with the technology for
broadcasting this and um we have to make a for people are not here at IMC we have
to make a zoom room for them and then uh had they they teach through the into the zoom room and
that gets uh transferred over to YouTube so it's not clear we have volunteers to
do that and um so I'll still wait and see if we if I have teachers if I don't find teachers
to come then there'll be um we'll do replace and um and hopefully make a nice choice
from this huge collection now of the 7 A.M teachings we've done over these almost
three years so thank you very much I look forward to
coming back in a month I think it's on the 5th of December and um
and I hope that uh you take good care of uh your your 7 A.M
Sangha during this month thank you