hello everyone and
welcome so the topic of today is this week is
different ways of experiencing our body and one of the purposes of this teaching
is to encourage you encourage your mind
to be less interested in its thinking
while meditating so be less interested in thinking about
anything else but just really what's happening here in the present moment in your meditation and then one of the
things to be focused on is the body
and some of what we'll become aware of is the karmic body the body of our
has a lot to do with our holding patterns our tensions that we
carry with us and um learning how to relax those and
release those and and if we can't relax and release them to learn a wise equanimity
a wise non-reactivity in relationship to our physical discomfort
not all our discomfort physical discomfort is karmic some of it is just
you know raw pain but we can develop a lot of karmic tension around the raw pain
so learning to be wise and work with this karmic body is part of practice
but one of the ways to go to support us to find this non-reactivity
to find equanimity to find a different way of being is to start becoming attuned
to the pleasures of the body the subtle ways in which
there's feelings of relief and well-being and
pleasure as we meditate dharmic pleasure so one of those pleasures is
the pleasure of relaxing the body the subtle subtle
sense of relief or freshness or openness that happens lightness that happens when we relax
and it's a kind of a release of energy it's kind of a release of potential to do that that's all bottled up in our
attention and there starts to be a kind of a little bit more of a flow a little bit more of an opening or a
glow or a warmth through the body that begins to knit the body together
tension holding in the body tends to divide the body and the release
of that tension tends to kind of unify begin unifying the body and the same thing happens if as we
learn to let go of our
undermining thoughts many of our thinking can be depressing can be discouraging
can reinforce the kind of tension in the body can reinforce a kind of
orientation to life into our body that doesn't make room for
the emergence the emergence of a sense of well-being and health and
healing through our body so for this meditation
i would like to direct your attention as much as it's available to you
to the feelings of well-being in the body feelings of pleasure in the body
not a discount or or pretend that there isn't discomfort
but maybe to bring our attention into a kind of balance
where uh we're not only focusing on our discomfort or only focusing on
the thoughts that about life about the world that are difficult
but we begin finding a refreshment through mindfulness of the body
so begin by assuming a posture
that is both alert but also gives you a little bit of
feelings of good energy or
vitality or even a sense of
appreciation to assume this posture
may be sitting a little straighter maybe relaxing in some way
and then lowering your gaze looking down at 45 degrees
so your eyes begin to rest not looking on anything in particular
and then gently let your eyelids close
and gently in a way that's nice for you
take a deeper inhale slow long deep
and maybe almost as if in your mind's eye you say ah exhale as you
relax the body and the exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
and maybe as you inhale see if you can find a place in your body
where there's any tension
and as you exhale begin the process of relaxing the tension
releasing it softening
and feel if there is any pleasure or goodness rightness
in the relaxation
as you relax on the exhale maybe also
calming the exhale itself the calming of the body and the calming
of an exhale
softening the belly
as the body relaxes when the body is tense the tension
kind of defines the body contributes to boundaries
in the body in meditation is to re-relax
the edges of the body begin to relax as well
as you exhale you might soften the edges of your body
the way you experience them
and perhaps feeling whatever vitality well-being
that might be present for you in your body
breathing with it breathing with that well-being
relaxing with it
another way that we diminish the free movement of our vital vitality
is with a lot of thinking reacting judging wanting
as you exhale if possible relax the thinking mind
calm the thinking mind
feeling whatever pleasure there is with the calming of the thinking mind
thinking also defines our body the boundaries of the body
thinking also divides the body
to relax into the body without thinking
quiet mind and feeling the pleasures however small
and minute they might be that exists in your body sitting here
whatever sense of well-being there is whatever feelings of pleasure there are
breathe with it maybe expanding it as you inhale
relaxing into it as you exhale
um
so
if there is pain discomfort emotional distress
it's okay allow it to be there
but see if you cannot be preoccupied with it
defined by it
be occupied with whatever sense of
well-being pleasure happiness joy
is found in your breathing is found in the humming of your body
on the inhale expanding spreading the pleasure the well-being
on the exhale relaxing into it
on the exhale letting go of your thinking so there's more room
to feel the well-being of the body
remember to feel the pleasure and well-being in the body
let it spread as you inhale
let yourself settle into it on the exhale
and might help to make a very small little
smile with the corner of your lips
see if you can move out of your thoughts into the
pleasure of your body the joy of your body the humming well-being
of a relaxed soft open body
where there might not part of the body where there's a glow in here
where there's an appreciation being alive in this body
and the mind is quiet and peaceful feeling that joy
when we are centered
a joyful body
body with well-being there can be kind of a glow
that spreads outwards from us
that's both kind of a protection a little bit like a force field
and also a channel for
our good will the more the well-being in the body
the more it's natural to feel kindness love
care friendliness for others
imagine what it'd be like to meet someone in the state that you're
in now to meet someone where nothing is needed nothing needs to be said
it's okay just to sit together like you're sitting on a park bench
companions companions and goodwill
and then saying these words to yourself in your mind
but as if they're messages that can float outward on your good will out into
the world may all beings
be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
so continuing the theme of this week the different ways we can experience our
body and because they're so can be so dramatically different depending on the circumstance the state
of the mind the
we can almost refer to them as different bodies refer to them as so yesterday there's the karmic body
and i think that's where most people live most of the time if they're paying attention to their bodies they're
experiencing the body that's much under the influence under the
impact of our thinking or wanting or not wanting or
fear all this kind of volitional
force that that is um
operating and that if used chronically irregularly builds up a very strong feelings of the
body sense of what the body is about meditation begins to quiet down two
things it quiets down the ongoing karmic formation the ongoing karmic
force that is shaping our experience of our life but especially experiencing of our
body and it begins to we begin to recover
from the legacy of that karmic shaping of what's going on and very simply
you know if you spend your days with your shoulders up to your ears because you're tense or afraid
there's a continuous continuous fear that's the karmic force
and then as we stop the fear the shoulders can relax but they might be so chronic that it doesn't relax all the way
and so then sitting and meditating slowly slowly the shoulders might find a way to relax more and more
and so the legacy of that karmic uh anxiety or fear begins to abate
that gets replaced with with time not automatically with a sense of
of pleasure or well-being or ease or lightness
openness softness in the very same shoulders and
it's easy then to go on to the next concern and not linger and pay attention to the
shoulders but it's possible also to feel how there's kind of release of energy there's a kind of a
way in which the tightness and definition of the shoulders softens and the
shoulders become kind of more porous or softer or more more kind of in in flow with the
rest of the body there's a release of energy and it might not be noticed at release
because you know it's not maybe not much but the opposite to stay chronically
tense is exhausting and and can you know really create a lot of
tiredness through the day exhaustion and weariness and without that tension our energy is
more available in a cleaner easier way doesn't get so tired
as we sit in meditation that uh and relaxing the body
relaxing the karmic body that there starts to be
available to us not only a nicer flow or glow or vitality of energy
but also with as we start getting settled in more and more um there can be uh uh pleasures that
begin appearing pleasant experiences that begin to show themselves they might be very subtle
but starting to pay attention to them and notice them uh allows them to grow allows them to
have a different influence on us than if we continuously continually take
in the the karmic body take in the karmic pain and the karmic thoughts and
the all the ideas of what's all wrong about the world or ourselves or our situation
these thoughts have a huge impact on us and if those negative thoughts are chronic they can have the karmic
repercussions on ourselves are huge it's not cost-free to spend a lot of time with angry
thoughts or or depressing thoughts or undermining thoughts
and so part of what meditation can begin doing is to quiet down
those all those thinking and thoughts and then if we pay attention to the subtle pleasure subtle well-being
it begins showing us a different orientation it shows us there's more going on
there's more to the story of our life than our challenges part of the story of our life is our
capacity for well-being for feeling of a healthy body a flow of a body
and even if there's illness even if there's injury and pain in the body it's possible that the container that
the overall atmosphere of the body that holds that pain
um is one that's soft and pleasant with pleasure and joy
and this sense of pleasure and joy that can be there it makes it much more interesting for
the mind to want to be present here and now and and it supports the mind to want to be
here in the present moment with the body with the breathing and so there's it starts to be this
unification process of gathering together process and maybe around the breathing around the
mindfulness practice the mind is less scattered less interested in other things it's kind of
our interest becomes more and more centered here and there starts to happen
and it creates a kind of breathing room creates space for something to begin to emerge
the karmic mind is a reactive mind and the karmic mind a reactive mind
doesn't make room for the well springs within to flow
freely and emerge the emergent quality of of healthy emotions and one of the
emerging qualities that begins to arise in meditation is a feeling of joy
uh a feeling of delight the feeling of kind of uh i i liken it to that of um
of a child letting go
sliding down the slide and uh and is squealing and so happy now
they we're squealing in meditation but letting go into breathing into our experience here
at some point there does feel like there's a little bit of momentum and joy and and kind of pleasure from that letting
go that's a little bit like the letting go into
this sense of well-being that can be here and
there's also some there's also some way in which mysterious way maybe not so mysterious of people who
know the neurochemistry of the brain that as we begin to
get concentrated and settled and focused here there's there starts to emerge
as a wellspring from within more and more joy more and more happiness
and over time and might be years for some of us this happiness and joy and meditation
begins to suffuse the body begins to spread and until at some point
it it kind of dominates over or
my experience is that somehow it lifts me out of the karmic body
and then when the concentration is no longer there i come back into the karmic body and there's as it lifts out there's a
pervasive feeling of well-being a glow a warmth a joy a lightness
that can have all kinds of different intensities from a mild pleasant intensity to
sometimes quite strong but the um but we start feeling a whole different
feeling of what the what the body is and this sometimes is called the joy body or the bliss body
and it's the emergent experience of the body that is a paradigm shift for the mind
it's kind of like wow is this possible is this my body um it involves almost a shift of identity
where the boundaries of the body are not so strong where there's a sense of safety and confidence where there is
a sense of safety openness
joy um and we start experiencing ourselves in a
very different way than the karmic body will ever let us know later
and if we only have the karmic body as a reference for how the body is to be experienced
we think the karmic body is their real body remember these are the bodies that we experience they're not the corporal body
the physical body their body that's being experienced in all experience of the body is mediated through the
activity states of the mind and as those states of mind shift
the experience of the body shift and one of the ways it shifts is into the karmic body that's just one
more way in which the mind manufactures or predisposes us to experience the body
it's not any more real than the joy body the bliss body
and um they both have their place they both have their value and um and so to begin settling into and
relaxing into the sense of pleasure sense of joy sense
of happiness that uh maybe at first there's only hints
only we have little traces of these going on but these are things to relax into
to open into to allow form to have as a
supports as a toehold in the present moment
and so that toll can grow and grow inevitably people who experience this
something like this this joy and delight pleasure in the body
that inevitably people will become attached to it prioritize it try to make it happen
again and try too hard and of course there's no crime in doing this
maybe it's a developmental stage to do this and maybe most people have to go through this
and i went through that and uh until i realized it wasn't working
and so uh and so we have developmental stage to go through the attachment clinging the
wanting trying to make it happen with too much force too much expectation and
attachment and and then we start seeing that then we can begin working with that and
letting go of that and because if we don't if we stay with the attachment
and the expectations and the demands it should be a certain way we're just contributing to more of the
karmic stream and where the karmic body gets gets reinforced
so chances are if you start opening up and experiencing in meditation this joy
body you will get attached you've been warned so that now you can be mindful of that
and not be so caught in it and hold it lightly and find your way through it
so i certainly understand that
this teaching on the joy body might be very distant from some of you it's no
idea what i'm talking about and it feels maybe even a betrayal or as a
as a offense to the challenge difficulties you have with
your body and however
there might be something here for you even so and maybe through the day today
give yourself extra time give yourself pauses through the day maybe put yours
your smartphone on a timer or something and every 30 minutes every hour or something
have a real you know extended pause
the only purpose of which is to feel embodied physical pleasure
and joy go for a walk sit and have some tea look out the window and relax and see if you
can touch it as a touch to have a joy or delight or pleasure in your body
be a touchstone for a few moments and and see what happens through the day
touch tones um check-ins to your body's capacity for pleasure joy
and happiness may you have greater well-being today
than you would have otherwise thank you