hello everyone and welcome
I've spent time among the Redwoods trees lately
large Majestic trees it's kind of inspiring to see how straight they are how tall they are
how solid and strong looking up at a giant Redwood is quite an impressive sight
and the redwood tree has a very small seed I don't know if it's the smallest seed
among trees but it's a very very small and the small seed grows into a big
dream imagine that you have a seed you want to
plant a redwood tree and you go find a place in the forest
that you think might be a good place for it near your house perhaps and you take survey the territory and
understand the challenges the dangers the the
conditions that are there and in the middle of that you find a spot that you think given all the
conditions that are here uh here's a spot that I will plant the seed
and in this environment I will care for it I will water it and feed it and
until it becomes well established and then it can grow on its own
so in the same same way we are planting a seed for joy
and it can be a very tiny little seed
and uh and that seed can grow strong and big and tall
and we plant it by first taking into account
the feel the territory the forest where we'll plant it so all of ourselves
that kind of uh survey and understanding Clarity wisdom
about all of ourselves is included in this practice of mindfulness
The Good the Bad the Ugly the wonderful and the difficult
and it all has a place and in the middle of this large field of
our life we have this little seed of joy that we plant
and then we support it we nourish it with the nourishment the water of awareness
of the sunlight of awareness that shines on it so it can grow
and the particular um joy that we're interested here today
is not that being joyful about anything but the joy that comes from engaging in
something the activity so for example some people would find a
lot of joy and dancing or joy and singing or joy and
going for a walk or the joy of meditating
just the opportunity the possibility of that engagement there's some joy that can come from it
if we give ourselves to the experience
we turn our attention away from our concerns preoccupations
away from the weeds and the bushes and the vines that are growing around
to hear now maybe the breathing
and engage in it like you would something that brings you Joy just in
the activity of doing it the feelings of movement and freedom in
the body that feeling may be of like a dance all
of us who are included
and there that Joy this little seed that we want to plant so maybe there's we can
find that seed during this meditation so to
assume a comfortable alert meditation posture
where in assuming the posture there's some care given to the posture
as the beginning of this stance beginning of this entering into
her experience fully all of ourselves included including the body
it was sitting in a way that kind of you feel like you're really here in your body perhaps both feet planted
on the ground if you're sitting in a chair
you're feeling a solid connection to what supports the weight of your body
gently closing your eyes and here
here in this body at this mind at this time this is the field of practice the forest
where we plant a tree
to relax this body
to begin a wholeheartedness
by entering into this embodied experience of Here and Now
taking some deep breaths as part of the stance of with yourself
of being present
maybe the inhales like the lead dancer and the exhale is going to Follows
breathing in deeply and relaxing fully
and letting the body return to normal
the body the breathing returned to normal
and then finding your way to a place in your body
where you can feel connected participating
with the body breathing
maybe almost as if breathing is your partner and a dance
and being aware of the fullness of the inhaled fullness of the exhale
aware with the body
and what would it take for you to be present mindful of breathing
so the engagement with it the immersion with it
Devotion to it has some joy in it
some Delight some enjoyment pleasure
and if there is a little hint Joy Delight in the engagement with the
breathing gently water that
by being aware of it including that Joy
in the experience of breathing out in and breathing out
if your mind wanders off in thought don't despair
instead be glad that you're able to
gently bring your attention back to the breathing
it's an amazing good fortune to be able to begin again with breathing
it's amazing good fortune to practice mindfulness of breathing
the same practice the Buddha practiced
feel the joy of that engagement
The Good Fortune participating in the dance of breathing
in and breathing out
foreign
sometimes in Dancing with a partner there's a joy that comes with
surrendering to the dance maybe surrendering to the partner who
leads maybe there's a joy in surrendering
to the breathing following along participating being
carried along breathing in and breathing out
and then coming to the end of this sitting
breathing in and breathing out
breathing in and feeling whatever Joy however small
you might find Within maybe with a small half smile on your
lips breathe in and feel the joy
and breathe out imagine sending it forth out across the lands
that you share your joy your well-being
your inspiration
The Winds of your joy carrying your good will for the world
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so hello everyone
and this is the second thought uh talk on the gladness pentad
and as I said yesterday the remarkable thing about the gladness pent head
is that it's a natural phenomenon that just like a seed with all the
conditions are in place will grow so when the seed is planted in US
and nourished and supported that this amazing natural process
unfolds it requires the momentum of practice
so it's really supported a lot by having cultivate developed some modicum of
concentration some ability to really dive deep or be really present in one's
experience mindfully but that momentum and the practice then
um um picks up this good energy this good feeling and a
lot and it's real if it's a practice grows we allow this to grow it transforms
and um the um
And So It Begins this pentad with something that inspires us
and the classic thing in Buddhism is our faith confidence trust in the practice
sometimes it's our own Integrity our own virtue
something about our virtue that we feel happy about and inspired by it can be someone else's virtue that
really hits Us in some deep way and moves us it can be inspired by another person who
maybe has a lot of maturity a lot of wisdom a lot of Joy themselves Dharma
Joy and so that inspires us whatever the inspiration is
as we practice that inspiration can first lead us to gladness
which is in which is a reflection that of how good it is to do this to be
involved in the stands to be involved in this practice feeling the Good Fortune of it not many people have the chance
and even though it's hard it's a phenomic and Buddhism is considered phenomenally Good Fortune to be able to
do any degree of practice so feel the contentment or that kind of happiness with that
as we allow for that contentment that happiness that Delight
as the practice develops the momentum of practice kind of begins to carry that along and into and transforms it into a
joy in the engagement and um and uh so the Joy or practice the
joy of waking up the joy of being aware of being mindful this is phenomenally Good Fortune it's a
great thing but it's not so much reflecting on The Good Fortune now it's more like
almost like we can surrender ourselves to the practice give ourselves over to
it fully and the fullness fullness which we give ourselves over to it
is where some kind of Joy begins to rise up
sometimes it's me quite strong when all of who we are
is absorbed or connected to the practice that we're doing
and uh this the immersion in the activity of practice
so there's we're not daydreaming we're not thinking about something else we're not preoccupied with an itch we have or
on it something or other we just really fully present
and even though that kind of language fully present is kind of you know Grand language
as we approach that as we kind of give ourselves for the into that purpose there can be this Joy Wells up in the
engagement that is like the joy of giving ourselves over to a dance maybe surrendering to
our partner surrendering to our breathing it could be the joy of singing The Joy
of playing um playing with children or being a
child and just being delighted and squealing and playing so much fun just to be active and moving
the joy of exercise some people feel so whatever it's some something that
kind of we give ourselves over to and fully there and that so it's kind of pleasure and joy and wholeheartedness
and kind of surrendering to that activity and partly because we're not caught up
in our usual ruminations and preoccupations and so the importance of this in Dharma
practice is that it it supports the Dharma practice
um to have joy in the practice itself uh sometimes what we're mindful of what
we include in our practice is quite difficult um there can be a lot of difficult
emotions like difficult physical Sensations pain all kinds of difficult
circumstances that we're practicing with but even with all those difficulties
um if we have recognized that the joy of giving ourselves to the practice trusting the practice
as if the practice is more important practicing with the difficulties is more important than the difficulties
um it isn't like we're practicing to overcome the difficulties we're practicing to be present with the
difficulty like there are dance Partners our difficult dance partner but it's we
can give ourselves fully to that too that dance um it's a kind of very different
perspective than how people most people live with their lives where we live kind of preoccupied with problems and wanting
things and not wanting things and the path of this meditation practice is different than that uh it's the
engagement in the practice and the mindfulness and being really showing up that is where the dance is where the
where the play is where the immersion is to experience so it's a shift of where
we're looking for our well-being and the advantage now of making that
shift is then we can learn to get out of the way of the natural growth of This Joy
and a big part of a Dharma practitioner's job when we start kind of getting in the flow of the present
moment is to get out of the way and allow this present moment to do its thing allow the joy to grow for example
but we have it helps if we recognize that it's there and when once we recognize this there
then it's we have a little bit more incentive to not get distracted
a distraction is kind of like putting as like night time coming and so the sun
can't shine down at uh on the on the plant that's growing
when the directions go then it's like the clouds are parted the sun is out and
then the plant can grow on the sunshine the sunshine of awareness and so uh
uh important part of practice is is to make sure that there's a space and
clearing for awareness to shine on our experience to shine on the joy and the
Delight of engaging mindfully with the whatever is here This Joy Dharma Joy should not be the
primary thing we're focusing on it's kind of an adjunct it's kind of like the music or something of the dance or it's
part of the the kind of what comes along and the Art of this is not to get
attached to it or try to Pump It Up but to allow the natural process of it to
grow and develop by staying present making room for it allowing for it and
staying with the practice we're doing like mindfulness of breathing keep with the breathing
and um so why do we do this why do we give ourselves over to uh the practice so
that we enjoy it so that one reason is it's a lot easier to be with the difficulties the
difficulties aren't the whole show and everything the difficulties are just part and parcel and of what's happening
and uh and the other part maybe a bigger part is uh our mindfulness our awareness
that just feels great to be active with and be present with and
so it grows and um so this this uh gladness pentad
is something to do that we allow to grow with a growing concentration
until the fifth uh the pentad we'll talk about on Friday is concentration itself
and that sets us up to see things as they are so gladness Joy
Tranquility happiness samadhi is the sequence
and then the instructions are or the the unfolding is to become aware of
suffering if we're suffering
the that can Inspire us to practice that can motivate us
but we're not really ready to address and work with suffering directly when we first come to the
practice and so part of it is being motivated by suffering but not
being too concerned about it it in beginning let it be motivating
let it support the faith the inspiration to practice engage in the practice for a
while as if you're tilling the soil you're repairing the ground for something different to grow and
develop and at some point when this gladness Pentagon moves
through and so there's enough well-being enough stability enough
concentration then we're in a whole different uh place
to see or suffering in a new way A New Perspective
and um so in that sense the joy
is pragmatic is practical it's very useful so it's not joy for its own sake
though it almost is and because if we get involved with trying to make it happen and make it
grow for other purposes it kind of gets interferes with the dance with the play
with the kind of giving ourselves over fully to the activity at hand with our mindfulness and our awareness
so I just realized this morning that we're
doing this gladness pentad which ends with concentration
and that that is uh then the the practice continues next step is seeing
things as they are and um and which is seeing suffering
seeing having insight and uh I think it's kind of coincidental on
Saturday I'm going to do a day-long retreat on the four noble truths on
suffering and I think that you'll be in a much better place to understand and follow
this day along on the four noble truths if we're building on this gladness pent
head if that's the background support for then seeing suffering in a new way
so um gladness Joy
tranquility happiness
samadhi these are the five topics for this week
and for today is if you want to do some practice in daily life
look for opportunities to do something maybe physical to do it wholeheartedly
as if it's a dance or a game or a play or like you're like you're playing a
game or a child in the playground is just so delighted to be in the sand making sand
castles so just give yourself over to see if you can find the enjoyment of
the activity when there's no resistance no distractions and ruminations about
the challenges of life just there for the activity it can be in cleaning
washing dishes cleaning the house doing laundry
it can be driving it could be going for a walk it can be
you know anything that's physical see if you can discover the joy
of giving yourself fully to just the activity and doing that doing it in your way
the way that works for you and your body and your circumstance but whatever way it works see if you can find the joy of
giving yourself to it foreign so thank you
very much and and I hope you enjoy your day