hello and this Monday welcome happy to be here with you and
some of you participated in this Saturday morning a Saturday day long and
so there's maybe perhaps more continuity in that practice
between the Friday and the Monday that you carry with you and um
and um
one of the things I said uh Saturday about practice of mindfulness is there's a
comes a point where it's kind of a paradigm shift we see things in a different way than
we usually do and then I want to emphasize that here as we begin this meditation
that there's a natural I think tendency enough to focus on if we're in the present moment
really with the experience with what's happening to be concerned with how things are
and so the that expression how things are focuses on the present moment existence
of what's Happening and if you ask you know how are you
there's a lot of things that might contribute to that answer
but if you try to explain it you know really how you're feeling sensing what you're
experience is here you might say something definitively
with the Buddhas uh but that kind of focuses on the on a kind of a static the
things as they are as little but can be seen a little bit static unchanging
the Buddha's way of saying this um and then what he emphasized in terms
of inside practice was not how things are
but how they come to be how they become
how they arise and it's a difference between
uh is focusing on the static part of our reality to the
dynamic to focus on how things are arising appearing in the moment that being
present right there at the Edge of Time the edge of that time keeps arising appearing is
here with particular experiences that arise that they appear
certainly some things persist but um but to be a little bit kind of like
on the front of a boat just watching the boat move through the water as opposed
to being in the back of the boat or being at a large ocean liner where
you're not even looking at the water because you're maybe inside in some
some big room but to um to be kind of right there with how
things appear how as the water comes and meets the boat does the both meets the water
so things as they as they come to be and we can begin this with um
this paradigm shift with our breathing if you say how's your how is your
breathing you might say my breathing is tight my breathing is loose my breathing
is fast it is slow and those are all accurate but how's the breathing
arising how's the breathing the breathing coming to be Moment by moment
and now we're into the process seeing the process nature of our
experience not the static kind of stepping back and generalizing oh the
breathing is this way is that way as opposed to how is the breathing come to be
and then now we're focusing on how it's coming into awareness how it's coming into experience
the beginning of the in-breath the arising of the in-breath expanding of
the Torso perhaps the beginning of the exhale and how it what happens the cascading sensations of
exhaling has the sensations come into being there
at the beginning of experience so hopefully that's uh clear enough
so to assume a meditation posture
that's stable rooted grounded
so that you can sit the bow of the boat
without being tossed around too much by the waves that keep coming
and if it's if your eyes are open gently lower the Gaze
and then with a gentle relaxed gaze if it's comfortable you can close your
eyes
and then to receive the appearing of an inhale
the whole process of breathing in taking a long slow inhale
they're coming to be of an inhale
maybe that and then at the top of the inhale there's the coming to be coming
into begin it's beingness its appearance
the beginning of an exhale long exhale it's not just a single thing
it's the unfolding of a process of the body Contracting
diaphragm lifting
in a sense breathing the body of breathing is not a thing
but it's a dynamic process of change
we're constantly something new is appearing
something new is growing fading
relaxing into the breathing relaxing the whole body
as much as you can a tense body is kind of stationary
static her relaxed body has room and space
for change for movement for
breathing to be unencumbered
chances desire that if the mind is preoccupied in thoughts
it's concerned closer with how things are
what kind of relating to thoughts as things as Concepts
as opposed to the process of thinking the coming into being of a thought
every moment things are coming into being
this is the place where the meditation becomes settled
focused relaxed
allowing things to come into be moment to moment getting out of the way
letting the physical mental experiences arise and pass
as if there is a lot of space for things to come into being
and that you're ready and available for the next and the next
like an open window is available
for the wind that blows through it
sometimes what arises
elicits a response within us a reaction
that is just another arising another appearing
another thing that comes into being stay there at the edge of things coming
into being allowing them to fade away
from attention so you can be there for the next arising
we've got a bow of a boat that meets the water and then lets the water just slide off
the side
even within the in-breath and the out breath
being available for the process of what comes to be
in breathing the constant process of change
thank you
okay
to be at ease with the ever-changing nature of
experience to be available ready and opened
to Ride Along with how things change
as they're always changing in some way or other
to do so is to let go of fixations on anything
and without fixations without dwelling on anything in particular
there's more possibility for being with what's ever happening in
a friendly way in a kind way
with generosity and care and
as things come to be
may we meet it with our care
may this meditation teach us encourage us Inspire us to meet
everything with open care kindness
so that this meditation that we do can benefit the world
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
foreign
so hello everyone
we will um so today being Monday we start kind of a new theme
and kind of because in some ways the theme this week will continue last
week's theme last week was What's called the gladness pentad
and these five qualities of the gladness pathetic gladness Joy Tranquility
happiness and concentration also appear in a longer list
that continue the pattern continued the flow of the practice
and for five more qualities and these can be called the inside
insight pentad the five factors that arise in the wake
of insight so this is Insight Meditation that we do
and here in this teaching last week the idea is that there's preparation done
for real deep insight and the ins insight into suffering into insight
into the into constant nature of our experience some deep kind of paradigm
shift that the first insight the part of the insights pet Tad is
seeing things as they've come to be knowledge and vision of things as
they've come to be and uh the often we this the poly expression
y-a-t-h just means like as
BH long u t a and and this is a past participle it
means that not things as they are but things as they come to be things as they have come to be
and the focus here is not an insight into how things are
as things things as things but rather focus into that the process
things as processes things as Dynamic and changing
and it's very easy for us to be concerned with particular things ideas
experiences sometimes we hang on to an experience for a long time carrying our resentment or our desires and around it
our regrets and we maybe carrying some fixed idea of
that what happened somewhat fixed and but we're kind of focusing on that as
opposed to the process of thoughts arising memories arising the thoughts of
regrets are rising and um and if we're settled enough we
see that these are actually a relatively inconstant process in the sense that it's repetitive that keeps
reappearing and reappearing but there's a kind of a it's not a static flat
preoccupation be concerned with the mind is constantly regenerating
itself in terms of uh what it's focused on what it thinks about
but we get enamored we get caught in the ideas the ideas of things being a
certain way they're fixed they're this is how it is and um
and uh the alternative offered by the Buddha is this nothing is everything is
a process of becoming everything um is unfolding
so that there's always a possibility for change always a possibility for something new
the the world is not a you know are suffering our personality are not static
big icebergs that don't change they are more like water that is
constantly moving to the degree to which we live in an iceberg we live as an iceberg
the the gladness pentad is a process of thawing of relaxing the places of
tightness and holding the places where we're caught the places where we're
fixated on things and this the practice of the pentad the
gladness pentad is to free the fixations of the Mind the fixations of the heart
so we're available ever available for What's Happening Now what's happening
next what's happening in this moment and if we're able to see the constant
arising and passing the constant things as they come to be then we live in a world that is is full
of potential full of possibilities that grow the less we fixate
the possibilities the potential of how we meet any situation becomes not only becomes can be more and
more creative and more and more varied it becomes a meeting reality with freedom
a fixation focusing on really tight this is how it is it has to be this way
is not a space where there's for freedom for freedom of the heart the openness
the availability the Readiness for something but if we see it oh this is not how
things are this is how it's coming to be then the the fascinating and Powerful
question is given that's coming to be this way and again it's uh let's see and how we
can shape it how we can let it pick come something next be something else
how do we respond creatively how do we respond with newness to allow
things to keep unfolding in a good way to take everything that appears
as not a fixed thing but as a platform or means or a condition
for responding in a new way so if
so for example if someone offends you it's easy to get upset and angry
and then this person has offended me and that offense has become a thing ecstatic
but if rather we see it as a process an ongoing process
then we ask ourselves oh that was a that seems offensive that hurt
given the flow like the flow of water how do I now navigate in this to make it
better how do I navigate this to Res to understand it better to myself be better
with it and maybe respond to the person in a better way if I meet it with
resistance then I'm stuck maybe there's less flexibility
but if I meet it with something fluid then maybe something different can become and arise
so I I can't do this necessarily so well but I know people who will meet offense
with humor and it de-escalates it quickly it kind of changes the whole nature
I know people who will meet offense with curiosity what's really going on do I
lean into the person what's happening here for this person I know people who meet offense with
letting people know well that that's that's happening to you let me tell you
what's happening to me I feel hurt I feel afraid I feel concerned I feel
angry given what's happening and so we're kind of expressing talking
about what's happening in the moment as they come to be and so maybe saying wow
uh this is how it's come to be wow this is a difficult situation that's come to
be here given that that's what's come to be what's next for us
given that this was difficult to hear what you had to say um what should be next how do we go
forward from here so always this movement how do we go forward where's the dynamism where's the
movement that it's more difficult to happen if we're dwelling fixating on
this is how it is so things as they come to be
in meditation can be a meditation becomes a dynamic
place of change everything is just coming into being Moment by moment we don't dwell anywhere
sometimes this isn't Buddhism is called non-dwelling awareness non-abiding
where we kind of float on the River of change and time be being the change
being the the changing flow of the present moment we become it
as opposed to think about it be something step apart from it
is this easy not necessarily but uh the um the ability to kind of be
in the flow of the dynamism of things coming into being
is built on a continuity of the gladness pentaton the teaching from last week
so if we can't do this then we step back and we go back
to the beginning where practice is maybe we go all the way back to the place where we're fixated and suffering and
challenged and we hold that with kind non-reactive awareness
may be feeling glad that we have a practice to do so and then we with that gladness we can
engage in the practice of really trying to see more clearly being practicing more non-reactive awareness which maybe
brings the kind of warmth to it all that begins to bring some kind
of ease Tranquility maybe begins to thaw the iceberg of how we're Frozen in
some kind of concern or preoccupation and when the when the whole Iceberg has
melted then uh it's we're resting in this wonderful pond of water
Lake of samadhi which from which we then can kind of be with the fluidity of the
water the changing nature of it meeting at the meeting meeting the
currents meeting the changes as they come to be as they flow
so this is one way of talking about the insight into impermanence
the Buddhist language he literally said insight into inconstancy how things are
in constant motion constant change and um and one of the purposes of this
deep Insight is to begin Letting Go begin resisting letting go to begin
Letting Go letting go of resistance letting go of clinging letting go of fixation now this is how things are
nothing is this is how the things are it's always this is part of a process of
change this is a part a part of a things coming into being
and when we see it that way then it may be easier
to be interested in given this how this is coming into being now
how do I participate in this for the greater good how do I step into this changing River
of phenomena and contribute to something really wholesome
valuable wonderful beneficial into the mix
our job is to let go
and contribute what is good let go of our clinging and flow along
letting the current be an expression of our goodness
so um this is the Insight insight pentad and
then as we start having this insight into change Shifting the orientation from things as they are to things as
they change as they come into being this has an impact there's a con there's
a con that's a condition for something to begin to thaw to change to move and that's a topic for tomorrow
the way that ins how we're affected by the deeper and deeper Insight that
comes from this practice so thank you very much and um
and I look forward to our time together tomorrow