hello everyone
and I'm happy to be able to share this week on right effort
I think it's a really an essential area of practice
and easy to overlook even easy to think of effort as being somehow
effortful in a stressful way but there's also effortless effort
effort and uh so for uh today for the meditation
I would like to um emphasize
um that when we're going to do something
encounter something engage in something make some effort perhaps to do something important
if it's important enough we prepare ourselves for the event and um
someone who is playing a sport might
warm up first and prepare themselves for it a musician might do the same thing prepare themselves for performance
someone might going to give an important speech they might breathe deeply or calm
or be quiet for themselves for a while to gather themselves together to prepare themselves for what they're going to do
so this idea that we prepare ourselves is a common part of human life
and maybe in part a big part of meditation is uh especially when we start
but is preparing ourselves so that we are available
for what available for life
the alternative to being available is to go ahead log into our desires or wanting
trying to make something happen trying to assert ourselves and but to be available is a little bit
to get out of Our Own Way little it make room beyond our
opinions or ideas what should be how things are supposed to happen
to be available it's a very different stance or a way than to assert ourselves
and one of the things we can become available for is um
we can become available to um what wants to emerge
what is arising here and in particular
be attuned to what feels healthy what
feels good what feels wholesome what feels beneficial
what is it that arises if what Rises when we're available are difficult things difficult emotions
that might need to arise there can sometimes be a sense of goodness or rightness in allowing them
space and that availability the wholesomeness is the receptivity The Compassion the
care in which we open to receive what's difficult Within
but also what can arise is something really good and maybe the goodness the rightness of
just being available is so wonderful the energy of availability
so this being available is the theme of The Meditation today
so assuming a upright meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes and to prepare yourself
for this meditation or to prepare yourself for an encounter
a meeting with a phenomenally important person
and that person is yourself but to prepare yourself as if you're an
important and valuable and someone that you care for and love
how would you make yourself available to sit and be present with this
important person
so maybe you would take a posture that's not collapse not receding too
much but really showing that you're here and present
that your posture of being available
and with the eyes closed to take some long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale see if you can let go of other thoughts
and concerns that might get in the way of being available
for what's here
letting your breathing return to normal
taking a few breaths to continue the preparations
by relaxing your body
the more the body is at ease
the the more we have to be available with
greater sensitivity attentiveness more space to feel
the fullness of our life
and then rather than focusing on breathing how would it be different
if you your awareness was available to the experience of breathing
to be available
and when the mind wanders off in thought in that wandering off
we're no longer available for our immediate experience of breathing a body of Here and Now
when you notice you're wondered off in thought re-establish
a sense of being available with your awareness with attention
not to assert yourself or require something to happen
but to see what emerges what wants to come what's here
allow things that are good to come into full awareness
but don't get lost by them don't get caught by them
so that the sense of availability to what's next
is eclipsed keep staying open available
with awareness available
might there be some feeling of wholesomeness goodness pleasure
in the sense of availability itself
available attention which is available
for the present moment
a sense of awareness available to experience
can be supported by imagining there's lots of space
here in awareness
for things to arise where the difficult things
are easier with all the space around them
and the beneficial things have space to grow
allow the wholesome to spread out wide and fully
and then as we come to the end of the sitting take some gentle deeper breaths
is a way of expanding or returning
to a sense of being available to our present moment experience
whatever it might be
in the availability sense of availability that does take some kind of effort
but maybe it's closer to an effortless effort
that an effort effortful one
and then to bring this meditation to an end
if you're care and connection to others
arose out of the sense of availability
where there's no resistance or no assertion
no obligation no protection
just available for oneself and for others
what would the nature of your kindness your care Your Love be
in such a circumstance
and perhaps with that as a reference point to give some thoughts
think about it in your own way of Goodwill
well wishing for others who do you have good will and well
wishing for
how do you want your Good Will and well wishing go out into the world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may my good will be available for all beings
thank you
up so for this last talk on right effort
I would like to emphasize how incredibly important this topic is for anyone doing
Buddhist practice all the Buddhist practice could be summarized
as the practice of discovering what right effort is
and and kind of refining and maybe purifying
effort so the effort is completely wholesome
and has no attachments no pressure no resistance in it there's a
freedom there's a ease there's a peacefulness in the efforts we make
and finding that uh you know the right effort the right way is in some ways a constant
adjustment that we're making finding our way and over time it becomes second nature
just like riding a bicycle after a while becomes second nature even though you have to swerve around this way in that
way and make different kinds of effort depending on the grade you're driving on
or driving on a freeway in a car um we might you know kind of
conventionally say we're going straight down a lane but there's ever so small little movements left and right to the
car that we're constantly making uh adjustments for but doing it almost an
automatic so it's so it's second nature so the same way with the effort
but as we understand the difference between a wholesome effort and unwholesome effort wholesome mental
States and unwholesome mental States uh to really be able to see those and
see them for what they are that the unwholesome drain us the unwholesome diminish us or stress us or are painful
and the wholesome ones do the opposite that's a powerful Insight powerful
really to see that and then to have confidence and this is
an important thing real confidence that it's not worthwhile
to engage in things which are unwholesome to engage in unwholesome ways
if we want to live our lives don't make the effort that's unwholesome that's debilitating that's stressful
to have confidence in the wholesome and it's hard to find that confidence in this kind of funny way many of us have
confidence in the unwholesome like that's how we'll be saved That's How we'll take care of ourselves that's how
we fulfill our responsibilities but in fact it does the opposite
and to as practice develops we have more confidence in the wholesome or to say it
may be more more kind of to the heart of it and the confidence and the unwholesome withers away
and so we're not prioritizing it anymore and we're left more with the wholesome
but also we can prioritize it as we value the wholesome that we make space for we allow for it
we um not willing to sacrifice it we don't give it up for the unwholesome
for the stressful uh so this idea that it's important to stay close to what's wholesome and
beneficial uh is part of with this Buddhist practice and what are some of these wholesome
states that we stay close to some of it is just being mindful staying present
some of it is as simple as being Mindful and Discerning and really
connected to have wisdom operate some of it is to be non-reactive
to have a certain degree of calm to be kind to have compassion
some of it might be to have a sense of uh pleasure or Delight or joy
in all the different 32 Flavors of joy that can happen in practice that we
begin making room more available for this kind of sense of well-being that
can begin to be here and as we feel the well-being that's a reference point a support to
highlight when we lose it because of the unwholesome it's kind of a gives us the early
warning sign oh I'm going to lose this don't hold on to the wholesome
then we're doing something unwholesome the holding on so we're always looking always kind of
you know the Wholesome Way of investigating is this very simple thing what's is it
wholesome it is it stressful or is it uh unstressful is it beneficial is it
useful and any effort at all including the effort to investigate that
the effort to be mindful the effort to let go the effort to stay with the wholesome
effort has to be under the lens the frame of reference of this right effort
it's a powerful protection for us that the very way in which we practice
Buddhism is not going to be stressful for us that's not going to be detrimental to us
it's also a powerful way of of
discovering what freedom is because in the end to be able to live
the right effort with ease and choice and really stay close to that place where the effort
itself is almost effortless so easy or it doesn't carry the weight in this the
stress of conceit and self that is a kind of Freedom that we have
so the in the Eightfold Path right effort is the sixth Vector the
seventh is mindfulness and the the how they're related is very
important here in the in the list that uh once we understand right effort
then the mindfulness we develop and gets to get stronger
um then can gives us more information in order to practice right effort
so the heightened awareness of attention that we develop we're more attentive to
the subtleties in which right effort wrong effort to operate within us
also but mindfulness itself then is protected by right effort if we're
usually we teach people mindfulness without teaching them right effort first and then for some people and then the
first long period of time in my doing practice is discovering how to be mindful in a useful way in a healthy way
in a Wholesome Way but if we remember if we taught right
effort first and we really know what that is then when we start doing mindfulness practice we're looking at
the mindfulness efforts through the lens of right effort is how
I'm practicing mindfulness right effort am I practicing with greed or with
aversion that my straining am I pushing am I being assertive in a way that's not
wholesome or am I engaged in a nice way the way that brings ease and peace and
dedication do what I'm doing so in the background of all this is
um that's a part and parcel of what the Buddha talked about when he talked about
each of the four steps four kinds of right effort he talked about the generating desire
and um and here he's talking about wholesome desire
and as we go through and learn about this right effort this is one of the gifts the treasures
is to learn how desires can be wholesome it can be beneficial no stress involved
whatsoever in having a desire no compulsion that the desires themselves are
beneficial for us human beings constantly have desires some of them are
really unconscious and we don't really see we have the desire we don't call it desire
you know so you know I'm lifting up my arm to be a
little bit more emphatic as I speak there's a kind of desire to be emphatic to make a stronger point to desire to
move my arm that kind of is almost second nature so I could do it without thinking about it
and even without it consciously intending it but there's a desire there's desires all
the time human beings are kind of a stream of desires if you look at it
as we become aware of these desires aware that the choices we make
letting those desires flow out of the wholesome place
we're cultivating the wholesome we're becoming the wholesome where
transforming ourselves into being available to be filled with goodness
filled with the wholesome the beneficial and then this miracle happens that the
desires we have come out of that wholesome place and the desires no longer seem
necessarily that their my desires even because the identification the attribution of self to it gets in the
way but at the same time we're tracking the desires to really know that they're
wholesome that they're beneficial and we're tracking a little bit the impact they have in the world around us
so that it's beneficial for them as other people as well
so um to generate desire
to prevent the arising of unwholesome
to care for ourselves enough to live a careful life to not carelessly live a life that the
unwholesome begins to take over to live a life that when the unwholesome
we recognize the unwholesomes in US we have a careful loving way that we try to
put it down or abandon it or at least not believe in it then go along with it
that we value the wholesome The Helpful The Beneficial and we make
space for available for it to recognize it and support it and we rise to generate the desire to
maintain it to stay close to it to not lose it easily and once it's there
all of this generating desire done with ease with non-attachment
non-clinging non-resistance
the desires that way the effort is that way and this is a good treasure to find our
way to this way so I hope that this has given you
something to look at and consider and practice with
and um and for this weekend you might want to see maybe prepare for
next Monday when uh in the next series is
um I know this maybe someone's teaching I'm saying might be difficult and challenging and you have questions about
it or just seems too much or something but instead of dwelling on that
see if for you can kind of frame it and understand this that it's inspiring for
you that it helps you feel more prepared for practice more ready and receptive
more confident uh more inspired yes
this is a key this is important this is valuable and that would be your homework for the
next uh today in the next couple of days is uh to really reconsider consider this
topic of right effort to the point where you can have discover
some degree of confidence and inspiration and and gives you the Readiness and being
prepared for for something and maybe you have a chance to talk to
friends about this right effort thing and Journal about it listen to these talks
again read about it whatever whatever it does for you so thank you very much I appreciate it
very much and to be with you at this turning of the year and we'll be together a few more
days before the end for those of you going on vacation and for others
um I wanted to tell you for a while now there's uh you know we end in November
IMC sent out a end of the year fundraising letter and some of you might not have received
it there's a link to it on the YouTube page for this for today just underneath the photograph the underneath the video
and also on the what's new page for IMC there's a fundraising letter I wrote
and um if some of you are interested in supporting IMC that would be very wonderful and uh
so thank you all and look forward to our next time