hello everyone and
welcome welcome to our meditation
session together and the idea that we're doing it together so many of us from around the world
for me is quite meaningful it's always been meaningful for me to practice in community meditate and
community i've done a lot of it and i probably wouldn't have practiced as much as i
have if i hadn't had a community around me sharing the meditation i probably wouldn't have learned as much
and i've learned a tremendous amount sitting and together with other people in meditation
so we have this way here now with him through the medium of our
electric electric electric communications to have a chance
to meditate together thank you
and um
sometimes when there is a particular practice buddhist practice that's given
and it's offered not as a universal practice do this all the time or if it is offered that way then we do
it for a while and we forget and then it's just always there and we might do it and
it might not but the alternative way is to have a practice that we do for a very specific
time and maybe even a short time this is what we're doing now
and what i'd like to suggest that for this next you know 29 minutes now
or so of meditating together that the primary practice
be letting go and
maybe you know let go and let go into your breathing keep the
thread of coming back to your breathing over and over again and it's a way of highlighting what can
be you can let go of anything that takes you away from the breathing gently lovingly kindly
maybe even slowly let go release it
thoughts let them float away like thought bubbles
and it and we're not letting go of things per se what it is is letting go
of our preoccupation with them our concern with them
so is not a judgment or a statement about the value or the lack of value
of anything it's just the value of not holding on
the value of having a heart a mind that's
not concerned preoccupied involved with anything at all except gently
concerned with the breathing letting go into the breathing
being with a breath and any kind of extra effort straining pushing judging and commentating about
how it's going let go let go of your concern with it
let go of your interest in that kind of thinking let go of giving it authority or value
just let go and be with the breathing be with the breathing
so to assume a meditation posture that
maybe provides you with a certain kind of little bit of strength a little bit of dignity
a little bit of of uh
presence here and now
if you're sitting in a chair or sitting in a cushion perhaps you can
straighten out the back of your neck a little bit so the last vertebrae of the spine
there's a gap between the last vertebrae the spine and the skull and as you kind of lift up and open that
part at the same time maybe open your chest a little bit
not puffing it out but just letting the shoulders maybe roll back a little bit
and feel where the weight of your body settles on your chair your cushion
wherever you are what do you feel the groundedness
there and taking a few long slow deep breaths
on the exhale releasing yourself into that support
while staying upright
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and it's a lot easier to let go if the body is relaxed
so in whatever way that's possible but not more than that
relax the body on the exhale relax the muscles of the
face
maybe when you feel the muscles of the face you can get a sense of how much they work
speaking smiling communicating
responding to the world meditation let your face relax
taking a break from all that
relaxing or softening around the shoulders
you carry the burdens of the world the things we're preoccupied with
the preoccupation is maybe held or expressed in the shoulders
for these minutes now putting everything down
letting the shoulders relax
and the belly
maybe anxiety fear is chronically held in the belly
and if there's fear or anxiety it's hard to let go of our
mental preoccupations even for a short while
softening relaxing the belly
feeling the weight of the belly as you do so
and finally you can also relax the thinking mind
the energy the pressure the
tightness associated with thinking
maybe in the head maybe somewhere else
as you exhale maybe a little longer exhale than usual
relax the thinking muscle the thinking mind
and then breathing normally
noticing how the body experiences breathing
so you're not so much in the control tower as you are
in the experience the body has of breathing the sensing the feeling in the
body
either maybe feeling more fully or a little bit like
placing a a flag in the sand
say here this is the place where the attention will now
reside come back to
and any other concern preoccupation of the mind as soon as you notice it
let go especially let go on the exhale
release your preoccupation let go of your concern your involvement
whether the thoughts you're caught and go away or not that's secondary to releasing
your interest in them your involvement with them
so that you're deliberate or conscious
interest returns to breathing over and over again
let go of everything else but resting gently with the breathing
let go let go of the layers that get revealed
as you let go release
release your concern your involvement
it's not that you're so much letting go of what you're thinking about
just letting go of holding on being involved
and let go into your breathing
let go into knowing breathing
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
sometimes the practice of letting go in meditation
where there's no need to be thinking about certain things or being
concerned with things in the moment no inherent need
we start seeing how much our desires our thoughts keep
us from the task at hand
and sometimes when we're with other people caring for others
caring for ourselves
we get hijacked pulled away by our thoughts our judgments our commentary
and learning to let go can be a learning to really be present
for others present for ourselves in a deep friendly way caring way
kind way
may it be that what we learn about letting go
supports us in caring for self and others
for a focus on supporting the welfare and happiness of
all beings may letting go
wise letting go be a be
give us the ability to wish
and support happiness safety
peace and freedom for everyone may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so the practice of letting go is a powerful teacher
learn to let go and you can be available more fully for
our life for compassion for
wisdom to arise practicing letting go
starts revealing all the ways in which we hold on all the ways in which we
cling grasped hold on and it's hard to see that in daily life
often but in meditation we can see the subtlety of it the consistency of it
how easy it is for the mind to wander off into some kind of concern and it might seem innocent enough some
of our preoccupations but it still involves some part of us is interested in our thoughts our fantasies
our imaginations the past the future and that interest is involves some kind of desire
some kind of wish that can be mild innocent enough it could also be
strong and intense if there's a anger about something
sitting in meditation and the mind just can't drop thinking about what happened and what
someone said and and the intensity of holding on being
concerned about is so strong but one of the things we learned is the consistency that how subtle how
thoroughly we're always always holding on or something and in daily life we don't see it so
clearly the minutia that ongoingness of it um in some ways we are
being um led around we're being hijacked we're
being um uh directed by our desires
and there's a lack of freedom we're not we're not directing the show our desires are
and um so in meditation we can learn how this works and learn to let go of it
we can we can start to cultivate um we can softening the
the muscle of holding on and clinging the intensity the energy behind it
some of the mental um uh orientations that leads us to to
cling and to hold on to things the inclination to give authority to our
thoughts to the the inclination to see everything to the filter of me myself and mine
the the orientation to have opinions that
we need to have we have to have all kinds of things we can see
and and so in meditation we can it's a one
laboratory to discover what it's like to let go of it all let go let go let go
and uh mindfulness practice uh you know if we as we go through this
uh there's been no real discussion about letting go at this so far
and um and so the only thing is at the very beginning it talks about relaxing the
body but otherwise that's the closest it gets to actually instructing us to let go
the the phenomenal power of the satipatana is that we don't we are not the agent
for change we are not the ones who are doing the change we're the ones who are knowing showing up for experience
knowing it well and then the letting go happens in a deeper way
and that's how the suta is but it can be very wise to let go if you
know how and um it could also be unwise there's unwise letting go letting go of the
wrong things but what we're focusing on in buddhism is not letting not the things we let go
of we might let go of some things but rather we're we're focusing on
the letting go of the clinging to things the holding on to things
and for this regard it's helpful to make the distinction between holding on and holding
so i can hold on to this striker and i can also hold it like this with my
hand flat so we can hold things in the softness of our hands
and now we're holding it lightly and if it's something that needs to go or is naturally going away then it goes
we're not holding on to it if it's something that temporarily needs us to use it for a
tool or something then we can grasp it and do something and then we return to holding it lightly
and so we don't necessarily have to lose things and letting go
we lose the grasping the holding itself the holding on
though we still might hold and so why this is important in looking
at the second the uh four noble truths is that
the um probably the most popular and common modern interpretation
of the four noble truths is that that the second noble truth teaches that
craving is the cause of suffering
that's a craving somehow grasping is somehow
responsible for how we suffer and in this interpretation if the grasping
goes away then that suffering goes away
it's possible to argue this and say for example not all suffering comes
from grasping and clinging some suffering some pain sadness grief
is just a natural part of life a dear loved one dies the fact that we feel grief and sadness
doesn't have to entail any grasping clinging they're just a natural state of
losing something that's important to us but there can in the grief also be
clinging and attachment and the issue for in practice is how to hold something like grief
without holding on to it and when you hold it then grief
kind of knows what to do if we hold on to it we limit it's working it's unfolding
so it could argue it's possible to question this whole thing about that the suffering comes from craving
that's why i like to turn this interpretation around and that's and say that if you crave
you will suffer so it's not that saying that all suffering comes from craving but
rather craving is a cause for suffering and part of the reason that i'm i feel
confident in saying this is that craving itself is a form of suffering it's a form of
stress on our system and so even regardless
of what we're crave the thing we're craving the act of craving is suffering
but the act of craving also uh creates habits in the mind creates karmic
momentum in the mind that will come back and sometimes
make things more difficult in the future so
so then learning to recognize what's called craving clinging
is important and i like to think of it as having as being desire
as being compelling desire desire which we seem to not have any much choice
about because it's so compelling it's so forceful it's so insistent um
put it down it immediately comes back sometimes try let it go go over and you can't let go of it sometimes it has us
complete control over us the intensity of the addiction desire that we might have
and and so um so
some people find it phenomenally useful this simple idea that craving
gives rise to suffering and if you let go of the craving that particular suffering goes away
suffering that's there that's not because of craving that's a whole other topic
but and this is one of the great i think
teachings of modern buddhism is this focus on craving and clinging
and letting go that allows us to really release a lot of the tension the stress
the suffering that we carry with us in our lives
and so to see that the second noble truth to understand it as
um so the first one is the truth of suffering the second one is the truth that
craving is the cause of suffering and um and some people in the modern world also
like to say that in this regard suffering is optional and
pain is not emotional pain not comes with life but the suffering suffering is the
the in this in the buddhist language is suffering is the pain
that arises because of the clinging so there's pain that has no clinging
it's then it's uh it's uh it wouldn't be called dukkha it wouldn't be called this uh this we
wouldn't use the buddhistic word suffering for it
so learning to let go and and there's two ways there's
dropping something and there's letting go of the holding onto it
and one way some people love to do this letting go practice
is not to let go per se but rather to let be and this is closer to what we're doing
in sattipatana is a practice of letting everything be
and then just seeing it for what it is knowing it and if we think of the knowing of
mindfulness as a letting b practice i think it adds a richness
to an adapt to the mindfulness that i think is very very significant
so letting things be so letting go of the holding on to
wanting expecting measuring ourselves how are we doing wanting it to be different
wanting it to go something to go away there's all these compuls compulsive thoughts ideas that
can weigh us down when we do mindfulness practice and the idea is to come to a very
free or easy or satisfying place of mindfulness where we
let everything just be and in the beingness we know it
we let it be and we know what we're allowing it to be so whether it's
experiences of the body feeling tones mind states the hindrances the seven factors of
awakening a lot of it is just letting it be and knowing it well
and what we discover over time is that the act of this clear full
knowing while we let things be it doesn't this has an impact
it it sets in motion something begins to unfold and to move
and change i don't know if this is a good analogy but if you take
carbonated water a bottle of it and maybe shake it first and then remove the lid
then just removing it letting go of how the lid is holds on and clings to the top of
the bottle then it releases the pressure of the carbonate carbonation
the gas and um so sometimes just letting go releases
something free something sometimes it allows something healthy to
flow and move our psychophysical beings are processes they're not things
and so the holding on interferes with the processes the the dynamic nature of this life that we
are and so letting be is not that doesn't really let things
stay the same letting things be allows a process dynamic process to
unfold which is not under your direction and so there is a kind of letting go of
direction with giving direction is another thing to hold on to
so um so you might want to look at um
what behavior you have today that's compulsive what thoughts what words you speak
what activities you do that you find yourself doing without deliberation without
care and attention like something inside of you is kind of taking the ball and run with it
where you're not free and what do you need to let go of or what you need to
not hold on to so you come back to a place of freedom of choice
of agency knowing what you're doing without compulsion
getting in the way so stop through the day take a good look at
this and you'll learn a lot
so thank you all and tomorrow i'll offer a different interpretation for the
second noble truth that relates to the third noble truth thank you