so hello everyone and
and as we begin the meditation I want to suggest that um
especially when we're this week considering fear
that meditation is meant to be done
in a location in time when it is safe
it's not always possible of course but ideally
that here and now is a safe place
and that are safe enough that you don't have to solve
anything that you're afraid of you don't have to fix it you don't have to figure out how to deal with it
and that's true for almost anything that the meditation is the time when it's appropriate to not need to think about
the rest of your life about even big issues or small issues or
what you're you know what you're going to have for supper or anything at all
and it doesn't mean you won't do those things it doesn't mean you won't have fear or have
concerns that are not here but because you're clear when you sit
down and you look around the place you're at that here and now nothing is needed
it's the opportunity to look upon what's happening in a new way
and that new way for some of us would be to not fix anything
not analyze it but per se not judge it
um but also not to participate in it to be able to meet our inner life in a
new way and the new way that Alexa suggests today is maybe not so new for some of
you is to meet yourself meet whatever is happening
with a silent mind with a quiet mind a Calm Mind
even if you can only manage it for half a second but the idea is to meet and encounter
your experience in a very different way and this Quiet Mind is not meant to be
disrespectful but rather respecting what's happening so you can
hold it and be with it in a new way in a different way
and what I like to do I like to refer to it sometimes that there are times in
life when it's appropriate for us to be quiet because the situation has called
upon us to support or to meet or to attend or to
receive what's happening in that silence sometimes uh you know the big turning
points in life that way young children putting a child to bed a young you know
a toddler to bed and be or when they're napping and getting really quiet going into a library
going to a funeral going into a Sacred Space someplace and
we allow ourselves to get quiet going into a majestic place in nature
and we allow ourselves to get quiet to feel it and sense what's going on
to maybe sit and have tea and look at the full moon
so there's many things that allows us to become quiet and um so to become quiet
to meet whatever is happening with a quiet mind maybe a maybe the silent mind
or maybe if the mind could not become quiet and silent
become aware with that form of awareness that attentiveness
that is quiet so if this makes sense
we'll start and we'll see that this ability to
attend to meet to hold to be present for things
with a quiet mind or a quiet attention opens a door to a vast
wise deep way of living Our Lives it's not
superficial it's not truncating experience it actually allows something really profound to begin happening
so in this sitting perhaps um
the um maybe experiment C
where can you sit how can you sit with whatever is happening with a quiet mind
and maybe it's just for a moment and then do it again and I'll guide you
a little bit here at the beginning so to
take an upright posture literally or metaphorically
and gently closing the eyes
and the right off the bat taking a
caring respectful scan through your body
to feel and sense what's happening for you and seeing you if you can do that
with a quiet mind a silent mind
the kind of Silence it maybe allows you to be more sensitive to what's here notice
more the details scanning through your body feeling
what's here for you
and within this body taking two or three deep breaths and
relaxing as you exhale
and then letting the breathing return to normal
hey
and as you exhale let the Mind become quiet let go of your
thoughts especially near the end of the exhale
let all the sinking mind becomes still and quiet or feel the Stillness and the quiet at
the end and then with that whatever Stillness
calm quiet you have feel what's happening for you
on the inhale feel the sensations of your body your
emotions just feel it respectfully
with as much of a quiet mind as you can
thoughts might return on the next exhale
let go of your thoughts and that's the Rhythm
Here and Now nothing you need to think about on the
exhale on the inhale feel more fully
as if you can listen deeply in that silence
to your breathing to your body your emotions
to your mind let go in the next exhale
so there's a rhythm of Letting Go and feeling letting go and knowing
gently repeatedly
letting their thinking mind become quiet on the exhale
and whatever you're supposed to feel on the inhale operate as if that's the only time it
needs is that moment those moments of inhaling
you know doesn't need any more just this
and then let go and the exhale
and if it's there again on the next inhale that's okay it's like a new time
and with the repeated doing this maybe you'll get into the Rhythm
Letting Go quieting and then respectfully feeling and
sensing what's happening without thinking much about it
maybe staying close to the quiet and the calm damn
and if anything troubles you or is difficult
or activated
in this gentle way of practicing letting them thinking by and become
quiet on the exhale and feelings with the body
what's here let what troubles you
feelings the sensations experience the direct experience
help it feel safe let yourself be safe
a safe place for what is
actually happening in you
the emotions the sensations
just the quiet the mind so you can work
feel what's happening letting it feel safe
it's okay for it to be there during this inhale
foreign
huh
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to
now on the exhale
let go into the world
as you inhale take this world in
its Joys and its sufferings challenges
and its wonderfulness take it all in and then in the exhale
let the breath be exhale
be your kindness
your care your gentleness take in the world and breathe out
kindness care
love compassion
May It Be that as our awareness our attention
spreads out into the world that we're able to meet it
with our good will may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so my internet here at IMC started being a little bit
not working uh during the end of that sitting and but I think that this all
worked on YouTube anyway so it seems to be working again now
so uh see all the greetings and thank you so I'm assuming that it all
worked fine for you and I'll start in a minute again
okay
so
so what I said at the beginning of the meditation is quite important
or quite useful say it that way that meditation is a Time
to experience our life ourselves in a new way in a different way than as usual in
everyday life and um so in everyday life kind of the maybe
generic version of it is we're doing things thinking about things taking care of things fixing things avoiding things
concerned about things and and many of that stuff is purposeful
is sometimes thinking about the future thinking about the past trying to change
something in meditation the idea is to have a very
different way of respecting our life as it's being lived it's not to deny anything but in a
sense to be present for it in a new way and maybe a radically new way
and so as we learn this new way of being present for experience we have available to us all kinds of new
possibilities new possibilities of understanding of wisdom of Investigation
of questioning our life in new ways and new ways of allowing a deep deep
much deeper processes within us to heal us to unfold us to grow Us in new ways
so the new way which is an ancient way
I think it can be represented by this idea of meeting our experience with a
quiet mind maybe a silent mind meeting our experience to be present for
it in a full way with a quietness of a of a clean window
a dirty window you maybe can't even see out but when the window has been cleaned
then the window itself is silent but the window enables us to really then
see clearly what's outside the window so as the awareness becomes quieter it
also the idea becomes clearer and we can see more fully what's here so in relationship to fear
to be to really be able to find a wise way in a creative way to be with fear
and find our way through fear and um this kind of new way of seeing is
really useful and important the so when we sit to meditate
I ideally we're sitting in a place where Here and Now is safe
so we don't we're not the building is not burning down um
people are not attacking us it's just nothing's going to happen within reason
um now sitting here it's relatively safe and the reason to have that clarity about the safety of Here and Now
it might not be safe if you leave your place where you're sitting it might not be safe in an hour what you're going to
do but in the where you're sitting and uh
it's uh you become clear oh this is safe right now here and now
the advantage of that is then you can see notice that if there is fear
it's not about Here and Now and so in a sense it doesn't have to be
figured out rather we want to meet it
fear is something that is we want to respect with our mindfulness something
we want to be present for not avoid not fix not try to attack
but to it's a very worthy focus of mindfulness for living a Deeper Life a
fuller life and so we want to be able to turn our attention and when fear is Salient if
here is the main is a strong experience or important enough to learn to bring the attention
mindfulness to feel the fear and it might be that you're sitting in a safe
place but for 30 minutes you're doing mindfulness of fear
and it might be time very well spent many people don't really stop and look
at fear the bumper sticker now would be um I break for fear I stop for fear
really stop and take a good look at it what what is this here
and the principle that I think is very powerful or the practice we're very powerful we're trying to do with fear is
when we're able to stop and really feel our fear feel it in an embodied way
that we're trying to help our fear feel safe
so there might be a real cause for the fear it might be a real fear out in the
world in half an hour there might be something happening that's dangerous But Here and Now in this safe place that
we're in uh how can we help the fear feel safe how can we allow it to be there
and now and so it doesn't have this sense that we're it's wrong or it's bad
or we're trying to run away from it or trying to attack it and fix it like we're supposed to doing the
practice in order to get rid of it um the uh if you're if you're doing the
practice they get rid of it if you're going to anthropomorphize your fear a little bit the fear is not going to be
happy it's not going to be comfortable it's not going to feel like it's has a place it's going to feel unwanted it's going
to feel unrespected and so the idea to help the fear feel
safe means to allow it to be there as if it now has time time in the sun of
awareness as if it's uh someone's never lived in the sun it's always been in the dark and
they finally able to come out in the sun then um you know it's like oh now let me take it in let me
you know receive it and so the son of awareness so that as if the fear has never been
seen really really not gotten to know the task is to get to know the fear to
recognize it to see it help the fear feel seen help the fear feel like it's
being known just like maybe for you if you're really anxious one day or really afraid a friend might come sit next to
you and see and say I see that you're really afraid I'll sit here with you would you like a
companion I'll just you know clear the friend is not fixing you or judging you for being afraid but they recognize it
and they're going to sit and be a safe person for you we then just be there with you and can accompany you and
having that company makes a world of difference so this new way is to accompany the fear
to be with it for a while and what this does is it allows the fear
a room to do what it needs to do to unfold to relax something begins to
shift and change when we give that kind of permission to for the fear to be there
and um and to give that kind of permission for the fear to be there and be known to be accompanied
it does help if we have a quiet quieter mind it doesn't have to be completely
silent but a quieter mind that's not ruminating and repeating stories and
judging and criticizing and all kinds of things that the extra things of mine doing the thinking mind is just almost
like they're saying they're there I'm here with you I see you
I'll be your companion here now let me feel you where the thinking mind is very
gently saying where do I feel this in my body where does the fear lived
because one of the ways to help the fear feel safe and really be seen is to
recognize where it's being most activated in the body is it in the belly is in the chest and
the hands uh you know in the jaw where might it be
and and then bring a careful loving attention to that area
and the image that I like to use for that is cupping the hands together and holding something for underneath
that's just holding so holding the fear so sometimes I'll imagine my mindfulness
my awareness is like this two hands that are coming together underneath wherever the fear is located in the body and
holding it being with it as if it is allowed to be there forever
and uh so it's this is a radical different way of being with fear than most people know
if in doing that we start to panic it gets very uncomfortable to fear then it's not a
useful thing to do and then maybe we need to do something to settle the fear the quiet the fear maybe stop meditating
and and do something else but if that you're able to do that to
come and sit and be with the fear this allows us now to as I said allows
the fear to process itself which is often wiser than us processing it
more often than not the thinking mind is reactivating the fear and perpetuating
the fear so for the mind to be quiet to allows a fear to process itself
and then it also then begins helping us to do deeper mindfulness into the
Ecology of fear the different elements of it that are important to also pay attention to
besides just the direct experience of the fear and that'll be the topic for the next
couple of days and I'm hoping that this will also give you kind of a a new angle
New Perspective in which to look at fear because the old perspectives often keep
us trapped keep us caught in fear and um and fear anxiety can follow
someone along for decades and um and so to learn a new way is a
can be phenomenally useful so you might try over this next day if
you if you have some anxiety or fear pay attention look for it if it's easy
to find great then you're on track if it's not easy to recognize then maybe you have to be extra sensitive so you
recognize where it might appear and um and so to and then see if it's a
situation allows for it to just stop and pause for a while and maybe sit down and close your eyes
and and see if you can spend some time helping the fear feel safe
you have to find where it is in the body to bring attention to it carefully and then maybe almost like you're
breathing through the fear with the fear as a way of accompanying it and helping it feel safe
it's almost like the breathing with it is kind of like it's okay now you're safe now you're safe here with me
and then see what happens to it with this kind of uh helping the fear feel safe practice
so um thank you and uh with that as a foundation I look forward
to what we'll be doing um the next couple of days thank you