okay so welcome welcome to you all uh good morning
afternoon wherever you are um
yeah so my name is matthew brent silver and um happy to be with you today
gil asked me to step in for this week as he's away teaching a retreat
and um so we'll we'll um we'll sit and i'll
offer some reflections after that um
as we we begin i i just uh looked to see what what gill had done on
friday he was talking about two two bodies the body
of which we're aware the body which we're not aware the thinking mind
or that is uh aware and not aware and um
yeah so we settle into awareness we just kind of just as we begin
subtle but enormous difference just to bathe the circuits of body and mind
in awareness so just
settle in in this way
so we relax whatever can be relaxed
area around the eyes or the jaw
shoulders or the belly
relax our hands and open
the hands energetically
relax whatever can be relaxed and any tension that remains we permit
to remain
sometimes i'll give the instruction to stop try
to stop being aware
whatever aspect of awareness you can't stop
just rest there
part of practice is directing our attention
why is attention appropriate attention
so we direct it to the breath or the body to feeling or sound
but sometimes in in our choreography of the attention
we miss this dimension of awareness that
we don't hold up and we can't stop
that which doesn't require your effort to arise
whatever can't be stopped just rest there
suffering typically requires that our attention be glued to something that we be
[Music] identified with something
so we start to discover that whatever is the case whatever our life
is in this moment when we are aware awake
something else is always also true
in this space
this space makes uh all the difference
subtle but also dramatic
just to know one's life
as winds blowing through the space of awareness
all the familiar ground from which we
strategize and fret is just folded into awareness
and just keep folding our life into awareness
it's good to sit with you
so um this is uh
maslow 1961 and a short
reflection on peak experience so he wrote
the goal of self actualization seems to be simultaneously
an end goal in itself and a transitional goal
a rite of passage a step along the path
to the transcendence of identity this is like saying its function
is to erase itself its function is to erase itself self
actualization self-cultivation points to something greater in other words
it erases itself it erases itself and it points to something
maybe [Music] maybe we even say enlightenment
erases itself and points to something
what might it point to i think it points
to love when um
when the self is not a preoccupation what is left
is everything else what's left is everything else
and in that context love becomes a much more natural
we're we're really we're developing a practice a way of
being that feels very very natural love feels natural renunciation feels
natural samadhi feels natural the awareness feels natural
and that's important yeah this practice is meant to feel natural
it may be hard it may be rigorously hard at times but it's meant
to feel natural and we hear so much about choice in in
mindfulness to choose a response rather than a reaction for
example and i
honestly don't notice that i make better choices
it's more like my options are much better
it's more like i don't find myself kind of backed into karmic corners where there's
duke in every direction suffering in every direction
this is not a um a state based practice it can sound that way at times like
we're trying to engineer create state states a momentary state of something
but we're really developing wholesome traits
traits don't need or effort to be maintained
that's what i was pointing to in a way in the kind of that quality the
effortlessness the the dimension of awareness that you can't turn on or off
don't it doesn't need your effort to be maintained yeah
we're in the same way we're developing traits that don't need your effort to be
maintained i would say we're developing a trait of love
a trait of love so where where does the mind rest you
know what what's the what's the default position of our attention where
it's kind of like asking where do you live where do you live where does your attention live when you
don't need to [Music] do your life where does your mind go
and it tends to be a heavy mixture of self-referential thought
curating the image that others have of us curating the image we have of ourselves
i am this not that it tends to go to
the future which is gripping and
we predict and simulate futures we try to strategize
a way through samsara a way through this realm of the realm of threat and
opportunity and in that kind of that little
bubble of self-referential thought strategizing it feels very much like kind of little
little me contending with big anisha you know big uncertainty
this enormous intimidating world
and some of that strategizing and prediction
and simulating is adaptive no doubt but we probably go quite a bit overboard
where else might we live where else might the mind rest
yeah to what baseline might the mind return
what might become the kind of default position of our
attention
buddhist suggestion is that perhaps it's the the brahma viharas
the the divine abodes uh the theme for this this week
so love and kindness kind of warmth compassion shared joy equanimity
these places for the heart to rest all expressions of
non-clinging facets of love
i think of love as um
like um like our our uh like our nervous system just longing
for the dharma
yeah when i really consider okay what what is um what does the dharma feel like what does
this path feel like to me just me it feels like relinquishment
and in the wake of that relinquishment kind of quiet love
and so we have these four brahmaviharas these facets of love
and if i had to propose a fifth brahma bahara gil has not authorized me to do
this but if i had to propose a fifth if that was my contribution to uh
american buddhist discourse the fifth brahmavihara would be
something like um puttering i think like oh yeah before that pretty
much takes care of it but i just i need one more just
puttering sometimes that's the place to rest for me
so these um these places of dwelling they're meant
to be varied enough so that one of them
one of them is always a good place for the heart to rest one of them
no matter what's happening in this moment one of those forces is medicine
the warmth the compassion the joy the joy the equanimity the peace one of them
yeah is is a is medicine a birth a death
um a marriage or a divorce a war or a peace
one of the brahma vahras has your back
there's no there's no control in these mind states
clinging is painful and um
trying to control it's it's painful and it's really important to get that in
our bones like clinging is is painful we can kind of take that on faith we
hear that in dharma talks but we actually have to know that for ourselves we have
to sort of run into the dead end of clinging enough times with enough vivid
awareness that we sense the pain associated with it
and that doesn't mean that doesn't mean that the best medicine is always to let
go it doesn't mean the best medicine is always to let go but clinging is so
painful we get worried you know if i don't cling
maybe i i won't get what i want
and maybe that's so but you get what you actually
need just peace
so metta um loving kindness this is this is love in
the face of goodness maybe we'd say compassion karuna love in
the face of suffering mudita sympathetic joy love in the face
of happiness and upeka
equanimity as love in the face of the ungovernable
endless nature of samsara this realm
when when you consider the state of sentience you know
just pleasure and pain the waves of pleasure and pain being human is like this
uh love becomes just one of the most plausible responses
to that predicament and as we'll see some some brahmavihara
practice highlights love and sometimes the practice highlights
everything that is not love but needs love
and just to bathe in this kind of this love that is not
born of clinging that is not seeking to control
but just that is deeply hearing really you know it um
sometimes it just takes a moment of abiding in that
to pierce a day or a month or a year or a life of
pain
so michelle michelle mcdonald
a beautiful teacher on this uh in this realm of of met uh
um she once um described this yogi who a
long time dedicated practitioner and and
and loving kindness for herself just felt impossible just so remote you know like
just just like bizarre thought to actually express this kind of care for oneself
and trying over not months but years of practice right
years of practice and then during uh
one session of a silent retreat silent retreat in the silent hall
this yogi suddenly yelled out i could feel it
i could it was so sweet i could feel it for myself she yelled it out in the hole
right um
you're not allowed to yell it out in the dharma hall as sweet as it is
but um we can uh we can all yell it out on youtube yeah
i can feel it for myself
so this week i'll start i don't know what i just said but we'll start tomorrow with meta and
compassion joy equanimity for each of the four remaining days
happy to uh to be with you this week and
i wish you all a good day