good morning good day everyone and um
one of the things that we are doing in doing sati patana practice practice
of establishing awareness is
learning to not only pay attention to
the details of what's happening the moment right now we're doing the body breathing
body activities but we're also beginning to
understand the other half of the equation the awareness part how we're aware
and um and in a sense uh the the the activities we do can be a
mirror to how we are to and also how we are aware
it's possible to be aware in a contracted way in a tense way it's possible to be aware in a
complacent you know hardly committed way
and it's possible to be aware with a very relaxed open but
engaged awareness so for this purpose i want to do a small
exercise with you and and that is uh if you would open your
eyes and find some spot maybe a small object or something
and uh if you would kind of uh fix safe
look at it but really kind of stare at it fix your attention there in a one-pointed way
and just look at this look at the object without wavering just you know lock onto it and just look at
it and and don't let your eyes kind of waver or shake or anything just hold
your attention there so very focused very intent
and as you do so notice what's happened to your
breathing notice what's happened to your body
notice the quality of your mind
so now uh relax maybe take a moment to close your
eyes and breathe deeply and relax
and then open your eyes again and look at this object
but rather than fixating your attention on it let your your eyes kind of float in your
eye sockets and just look at the different parts of it maybe trace the contours of it
uh kind of look at then what's what will be the bottom of it the top the sides
just let yourself kind of wonder and aim your attention so you're still kind of centered on the
object but you're kind of floating swimming around your attention
on the object or with the object there
and now notice your breathing
notice your body how it feels notice
what your mind your awareness is it the awareness
tight or contracted or is it more spacious and loose
and so i don't know if this exercise worked for everyone but generally
when people fixate their eyes to focus on something it tends to create tension it's kind of
an unnatural thing to do to hold the attention fixated like that
and it takes effort and work and certain kind of tension what's more natural for the eyes is to
kind of constantly be on the move gently relaxedly
maybe not so much we don't necessarily realize that my eyes are kind of dancing around slightly but what's nice
is for the eyes is to have the eyes move so it takes in the object of
attention from different perspectives different angles different parts of it so the eyes are not fixated the eyes are
quite loose and soft and flowing around the object
as the mind gets tense as the mind gets fixated or preoccupied
or afraid or angry or desirous the mind tends to lock up or become
tighter or fit more fixed like the fixed eyes and um
and in uh with mindfulness mindfulness awareness the mind that awareness gets loosened up
and we allow awareness to kind of certainly focus on the breath on different objects but we are kind of
floating with it then taking it in in different kind of angles and ways and
and um so just with the experience of breathing for example uh you don't we don't hold the attention
on the breath rather we place the attention in the area where we experience
breathing and we allow the different sensations that come into play
to do their dance to appear and awareness kind of floats between it
and moves around it it's all with the breathing but the awareness is kind of
as loose and relaxed with the breathing maybe a little bit like a
like a uh if you were floating maybe on a rubber
mattress or you know boat or something on a just floating and relaxing laying on top
of a of the ocean with gentle waves coming up you're right there with the waves but
the waves come and go you're not fixating on the ocean you're allowing the waves to lift you and drop you and
you're feeling all the different contours of the wave as it moves through your body
and this kind of attention allows for hopefully a deeper sensitivity
to our experience and as we continue to do this practice
we are actually looking for or or awakening a deeper sensitivity
to our sense experience the physical experience of what's happening
and beginning to allow the awareness to rest on it or
stay present but in a way that's soft and relaxed it kind of floats
on top of the different things that appear and disappear
so to gently
lower your gaze with your eyes still open
and lower and have your eyes kind of looking down at about 45 degrees
not looking at anything in particular
but just gently letting the eyes kind of subtly move and roam and
be relaxed and not trying to see anything but just kind of
maybe things are even a little bit out of focus that's okay so you're not fixating on anything
and now if it's comfortable gently close your eyes
and now with your awareness let your awareness float around your
body in whatever way the body calls whatever way
awareness wants to travel whatever just gently slowly relaxedly
the awareness is centered on the body but loose and relaxed
just floating between different sensations and experiences
and as the mind the awareness floats around if you notice any tension
if it's easy enough without fixating the mind
the relaxed attention
maybe allowing awareness to slide
down with the relaxation along the relaxation
and then settling your awareness on your
breathing the sensations of the body that come
into play as you breathe whether it's the movements of the belly
the chest sensations in the nostril
or some broader global experience of the body breathing
rest in those sensations in that area
and let your awareness gently almost not
out of choice isn't like you're doing it almost as if the natural tendency for
awareness to float and move it
floats and moves within the experience of breathing
so the mind is not fixating on the breathing but orienting itself on the breathing
as the sensations of breathing change so the
awareness floats on the change
as awareness naturally loosely
floats it sometimes floats between sensations
maybe there's no rhyme or reason of which sensations you pick up at any given time
but be oriented to the sensations of breathing in a relaxed loose way
perhaps allowing for a growing sensitivity
for how the body feels experiences
the details of breathing
floating on the sensations of breathing as if you have all the time in the world
no hurry
oh
if the mind wanders off in thought notice if the mind is fixated or tight
if it is relax the mind if you wonder often thought innocently
kind of floating off into some kind of thinking
then float the mind back to the breathing gently
settle back in again
awareness resting on the waves of sensations
developing a heightened sensitivity to the body's experience of breathing
you
as part of this meditation
while you're still sitting quietly
i would like to read this section of the text
that we're studying this week and the reason to read it while you're
still meditating is that the primary way down through the
centuries that people have encountered this text is not as something to read and study
but something to listen to as it was chanted
or something to participate with by chanting it and chanting repeatedly the same
passages over and over again has a very different effect on how we learn and how we're changed
then studying so because it's closer to this chanting
way of taking in the text i'd like to read it now as the end of the meditation
a practitioner is one who acts in full awareness
when going forward and returning who acts in full awareness when looking
ahead and looking away who acts in full awareness
when flexing and extending the limbs who acts in full awareness when wearing
clothes and carrying their plates and silverware
who acts in full awareness when eating drinking consuming foods
tasting who acts in full awareness when defecating and urinating
who acts in full awareness when walking standing sitting
falling falling asleep waking up
talking and keeping silent in this way
one abides observing the body in regards to the body
internally externally and both internally and externally
when abides contemplating the body and its nature of arising its nature of vanishing
in its nature of both arising and vanishing
or else awareness is established there is a body
just to the extent necessary for bear knowledge and lucid awareness
and one abides independent not clinging to anything in the world
this is how a practitioner abides observing the body
in regards to the body
and may it be that each of these activities we do that they're infused with an aspiration
and orientation to do so for the benefit of the world
that somehow we're developing ourselves cultivating ourselves to be
caring people for this world somehow we are also
orienting ourselves to a life of caring for self and others
and making this a better world for for all beings
may all beings be free and happy
[Music]
thank you
so the direction that this satipatana practice goes to
is the ability to have a loose open clear awareness
that is able to wisely float and be around to all aspects of our human
experience and whether it's the body or the feelings mind states mental processes
the experiences of the world our thoughts and ultimately it's not a matter of keeping
it limited to some particular domain of our life
but able to kind of take it all in as a because awareness is starting to become free
loose relaxed open receptive and um
and so uh in different circumstances then uh it will the mind will sometimes be aware of
thinking sometimes the body sometimes feeling sometimes emotion sometimes sounds what's around us
to some degree going along with the call of whatever is happening to some degree also having
some choice about where it's important to bring attention an orientation
an aspiration maybe based on compassion or healing or
you know what's beneficial what's fun all kinds of things that we might choose to and
so there's a play between choice and non-choice with awareness is
something we become wise with and something that we begin enjoying even to to do
in the beginning of sati patana it's often a strong emphasis on the body
breathing in the body with kind of limiting the orientation to that because if we go too quickly to the full
range of all the different things we can pay attention to floating through them that more likely the mind simply gets
hijacked and held hostage by the thinking mind and the thoughts
and and so we're kind of cultivating the ability of the mind to relax
it's thinking the grip of thoughts the grip of preoccupation by coming back to the breathing
and it's very important to realize that's what we're doing it isn't so much that we're we're developing the muscle of
concentration which to some degree we are but if we can be over emphasized and people can
get tense and tight it's a big part of what we're doing is um decreasing
the the the impulse the attachment that
sometimes addiction the the strong kind of orientation fixation
on certain limited parts of our human experience it could be a lot often into thoughts
ideas memories planning it can be our emotions and feelings
even sometimes it can be the body work we're stuck on we're learning to relax that
and then as we relax it more and more then it becomes a whole different game to be able to
settle in and to be with the like the breathing or the body and um
and so this this is part of the field in which we're practicing this this this
and why i want to bring it up today is that i want to talk about a particular activity
to which to bring full awareness to and which mentioned in the text
and that is eating mindful eating where meal time
is meditation time meal time is mindfulness time
and it's one of the real wonderful places to cultivate mindfulness and well
use it as a kind of case study for bringing mindfulness into daily life
so um not few people eat uh an automatic pilot
they eat with lot not a lot of a careful attention as they're eating uh maybe they're if you're eating alone we have
uh you know listening to a podcast or watching the news or watching something on the screen
listening to the radio old days would read the newspaper
maybe with eating other people it were absorbed in the conversation and hardly
noticing that we're eating and what we're eating sometimes the eating is done quickly i'm
i'm a kind of not fast eater so i know that well and um so
it's so quickly that we you know are not really taking in the experience of eating
and when the eating is kind of automatic or in this kind of way that gives often free reign to the mind
to do whatever it wants to do and the mind has a strong tendency to be fixated or preoccupied by things
or to be given too much freedom to kind of travel down its highways and byways
then we actually live a truncated life a limited life and even though it might seem like it's
unlimited because we can think about unlimited number of things it's really a small domain
of our life and so to sit down to eat and
from time to time it's really wonderful to have a chance to eat alone or to eat uh quietly without speaking
so that you can just be you can just be eating and nothing else
and um the um the uh
you would um um you know and and so if you just with the
eating and then you're really kind of floating your attention with the experience
giving means you're not in a hurry you're there just to be with the experience all the different pieces of
the experience with full awareness of the body it's all the physical things that come into play
as you're eating one of the things that i found really nice to do around eating especially when
i'm eating alone or quietly in meditative kind of way is to notice
the first moment where i feel the hunger is no longer there and i feel
the simplest form of satiation i'm not full uh there might be a
in my mind in my in my situation kind of a desire in the mouth
in the tongue for more um there's me i don't know if it's a maybe a pull for pleasure or something
or the mouth and the tongue get the news that i'm full last and so there's still this drive to want to eat
and and but i try to pay attention the first time when i basically no longer hungry
and feel kind of the simplest satiation and then stop eating then and then notice what happens
notice that there might still be desires the desires for pleasure or that pull or the impulse
and sit and it's fascinating sit and watch it and see what howard morphs and changes when we don't give into it don't
reinforce it but make room for it to feel it it's not exactly the same as denying
ourselves it's actually something more like allowing
an impulse a desire to be there in its pristine glory
without giving into it and to allow to just feel oh there it is practicing mindfulness with that desire
one of the things to learn from mindful eating is how mindless we eat
and that's fascinating to notice maybe you know are we eating in a hurry are we eating uh in order to
um you know what you know are we are eating too much are we afraid is there anxiety
around food as we eat is there a greed as we eat
is there a lot of confusion around food when we're eating it and and then
take time to feel and be with that give a second and third and fourth look
at those feelings that are connected to eating some of those feelings do not have to be
present or not in don't inherently have to be present as we eat
and some of those feelings limit our natural capacity to be attuned to the body's own
intuition about what to eat and how to eat and and how much to eat
and i've really appreciated uh as i became more sensitive
to uh feel that the body kind of had an intuition on its own about
how to eat when to eat what to pick up at different times out of the plate
and um and uh and there's kind of a deeper knowing the body has that we can tune into if we
develop this deeper sensitivity of mindfulness
it's also a great pleasure to eat mindfully to eat in silence and be kind of
just absorbed in the pleasure of eating and just kind of taking it all in and
enjoying it but so fully that the thinking mind gets quieter
because it's not such a big part of the experience and it's possible to eat a meal i mean
especially if you eat in silence eat a meal and feel clearer and more relaxed and
more open by the time it finishes i've known some people who really enjoy
eating mindfully and will spend actually quite a long period of time
um uh just taking their time to eat generally it's best to do that alone if
you're eating socially because even in you know that you don't you have you know other
people are long finished before you're done but take your time to eat
i've done that i've done that in a lot of different ways taking my time to eat and sometimes the sense of pleasure
meditative absorption absorptive pleasure around it has been quite strong
the and sometimes because you know i said i'm sometimes a fast eater by you know
since i was a child sometimes in order to cultivate this greater mindfulness for me
i have eaten with my non-dominant hand
and and that just kind of brought an interesting kind of more attention to what i was doing
and when i've really gotten into it really enjoyed it and really kind of felt like i was doing it slowly
i would actually put my utensil down between bites and i would
put put a a fork full of food in my mouth put it put the fork down and then just
be with the chewing and when the chewing and had and after i swallowed then i'd pick up the fork
again and that would certainly be for me would be a little antidote to
the habit of putting food in my mouth and then while i'm chewing
digging in for the next bite you know it's innocent enough but to really kind of be present for the
experience to put the fork down so as we do this
the activity of eating is a mirror for our attitudes and our approaches and our what's going on for us
and that's part of mindfulness practice to really see that and if some of those attitudes are not so helpful for you
um what's important part of mindfulness practice is to the degree to which you're able to shift that to let go of
it in a relaxed way do so the degree to which you can begin to have some choice about their attitudes
of the mind you want to exercise that choice but don't be worried if you can't or
don't force it and then and also as you're doing this you're
also becoming aware of how you're aware is there a fixation that the mind and
awareness and can the awareness be soft and loose maybe if this metaphor works for you can
be floating around the whole experience of sitting there eating and being with the experience of the
the food of the arm lifting up to put the bite in your mouth
the experience of the food being taken into the mouth and the movements of the tongue and the taste and the chewing
just really be there for it and then over time as the mindfulness
gets stronger then the attention can float between all these different areas
it's not necessarily fixated or not fixated but not necessarily settled or centered only on the physical experience
of eating but it's centered on the wholeness of who we are as we eat that includes the eating
so i offer you this before this will be the last talk on mindfulness of activities and i offer it
to you to you as a case study to explore and and
and maybe to uh to use over this weekend maybe you can take a couple of meals
that uh you sit quietly by yourself or maybe you're with someone who's a meditator you can ask to eat the meal in
silence together and and and explore uh
what the benefits are and what the richness is and what the challenges are in uh eating mindfully
without a hurry just eating so thank you
and i want to make a couple of announcements that might interest some of you one is that periodically imc has a
mindfulness circle for black identified practitioners
and if you are or know some black mindfulness practitioners who
would like to join the circle um it's a little bit of meditation a little bit of teaching instructions and
a chance to be in a in a zoom circle uh to be in discussions around mindfulness
and so the next one is starting a week from saturday i believe it's the 12th
of uh february and there's information about that on imc's website
and on the homepage on the what's new and the other thing is if some of you
would like to come and sit a retreat that i teach then i am
you know i teach number of them at irc but they're sometimes difficult to get into
the insight retreat center i'm also teaching one in april at spirit rock
and i think probably it's easier to get into the retreat there and teaching it with
four wonderful co-three wonderful co-teachers and um
and uh so you can look at i think it's april 16th maybe
and you can look there for the schedule so thank you and
i hope you enjoy your mindfulness and enjoy mindful eating thank you