so hello everyone and
beginning of the week for some of us and some places in the world it's
already tomorrow
so um happy to be here and i want to start right in with um
the teaching to get oriented around this practice of
mindfulness of the elements or the physical properties
such an important part of vipassana practice
no sound is it other people not having sound
let's see let's take a moment to see if there's uh people hearing
usually there's a whole stream of no no sounds if that's the case okay great thank you
so i wanted to start right in with
this important area of mindfulness mindfulness of the physical properties or sensations that we have
they're so fundamental to our experience and there's something very valuable about
being attentive to the fundamental layer of our experience where consensual begins
and so here's an example that i could be sitting here
and i could feel there's tension in my shoulders that's an ordinary thing to experience
but then i start wondering why am i tense in my shoulders
oh it's left over from yesterday yesterday i was waiting to for a car to
pull out of a parking space and when it pulled out someone else
zipped their car into that space and i felt indignant and angry and how
could they and and i got all tense and since then my shoulder has been
tense and um why is the world it's a such a an unjust place and
there's been so much injustice and and now it's with the cars and
and maybe i should really do is buy a small car or even buy a bicycle they don't have to deal with this
problem and where do i get a good bicycle and on and on it goes and in the meantime i have departed very
far from the tension in my shoulder and no in a sense no longer in touch with it
an alternative way of not going into stories and interpretations about our sensations
is to just feel the sensation of tension and let it be just tension
and no past no future just tension no cause there might have been a cause
but we're not concerned with that no resolution of the tension just tension
just to offer mindful attention to what is as if what is is allowed to stay there
forever this is okay but what that does
it creates a kind of a mental space or room the attention to something gives it room
and something like tension then has room to relax there's like space
that there's almost an instinct in the muscles themselves to relax
if we're not feeding feeding it more and more stories and ideas
and and so this idea of just holding the tension and awareness keeps it
gives it space to begin to not be reinforced by the stories and
and make space for it to relax some things at this elemental level
that are pleasant sometimes actually get stronger if we hold it in awareness
but if we bounce off of it into the world of stories and ideas we might lose touch with even the what
feels wholesome and good so the this four element meditation
is to drop down to the elemental or the fundamental sense layer sensation layer
of experience and then give lots of room for it and not kind of
get pulled up into stories interpretations past and futures and this allows for a very important
process and so the art of this is whatever happens
during this meditation whether it's physical sensations themselves
whether it is emotions or even if it's a lot of thinking
locate the way it's being manifested in physical sensations
and keep it so simple that you just stay with the sensations that are part of it
and letting this physical sensation the body compost it letting the body process it
not your mind not your heart just the body just the sensations themselves
and to help with that to keep focused on some sensation which
is predominant is that you can breathe with it breathe through it
if there is no predominant something that grabs your attention
that then you refer to the body to feel it just stay with your breathing
and there's something profound that happens when we give this kind of breathing room to the sensations of breathing
just the sensations each in-breath has its own sensation seat algebraic breath has a sensation
and that's the focus of meditation just whatever is happening
how is it felt and experienced in the body as sensations
so sitting assuming your meditation posture
and to settle in taking a few long slow deep breaths
letting your breath return to normal and continue on the exhale to relax your
body settle in your body will be the meditation hall
for this meditation
and then check in with yourself and what is the predominant
experience of the moment for you within you
and how is that felt in the body
what sensations in your body are most pronounced
that feel like it would be good to just hold it in awareness and noticing
what sensations are there tightness
looseness pressure
weight softness
warmth coolness
movement expansion contraction
hardness pulling
twisting
opening
keep coming back to this fundamental elemental level of experience before stories and
interpretations just the sensations for now
breathing with it being with the sensations
making room for the sensations
if you're in your thinking you're probably not feeling the sensations
but if you're thinking a lot are there any physical sensations
associated with that and if so
let those sensations be the place of mindfulness
whatever's happening refer it back to the body
see how simple you can be with it simply feeling the sensations
associated
to be able to step away from the incessant thinking mind
to relax and to be settled in
the body in the body breathing the body sensing
can be a place where we can find
some peace peace from the incessant thinking
from time to time it might feel like a vacation like a place of safety
and may it be that all of us find a way
find our way to be at ease and safety resting in her own physical
experience and her body so the body becomes a home
a place of rest and ease even if the pain the body is difficult
it's possible to find place within
to be at ease and at peace may it be that all of us
each individual one of us and all the people we know and out into the world
may everyone find peace with their body
rest in an ease and comfort in their body
may there be a freedom
from incessant thinking and reactivity and meaning making
just breathing simply just being alive is enough
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and on this valentine's day may it be for all of us
a meta day maybe there's a way that everyone can be
our valentine
who we look upon with kind regard
may we have meta for all beings
so this part of the discourse on the foundations for awareness
is the simplest of them all it's a simple description
instruction it simply says in this body
there is the property of earth the property of
water the property of fire and the property of air wind
and that's it uh it does give an analogy i'll mention the analogy the simile tomorrow
but the instruction that's all it says so there's a recognition of each of
these properties as they appear within us and and so it so simple that it might be
overlooked it might not be understood how profound it is that it's actually one of the central
ways that vipassana practice is practiced is a really delving deep into the level
of the sensations of our experience so it's easy to not be in the sensations
to certainly it's possible to have sensations of some kind or other and then start interpreting it have
stories around it reactions to it it's possible to not be connected to our sensations and all at all and be living
in the abstract world of thoughts and ideas and feelings that are disconnected from our body
part of mindfulness practice is to awaken the body there is one
mahayana sutra that says that we are awakening and light enlightenment happens through the body
the buddha himself said that there is no awakening without mindfulness of the
body what we're doing and partly this dropping into the sensations just
feeling the sensations that they appear is that we're beginning to expand our awareness throughout our body
so more and more of our body starts uh being we feel connect really connected to it
start feeling embodied it does a lot of wonderful things for us to do this
one is that the body to the body itself can process so much
of our life so much of our difficulties and our emotions and our thoughts and our
concerns our tensions partly because when we're not in the body
we're often in the reactivity in the thoughts the interpretations the stressful ways of thinking
that are reinforcing the tension in the body if we drop down into the body
then there's room for things to unfold there's breathing room for things and even things which and some things
will just naturally unfold and resolve themselves like tension for example oftentimes
some things don't resolve themselves maybe there's chronic physical tension in the body
but there's an art to just feeling the tension without adding any second arrows to it
without adding any tension extra attention to it and um and then delving even deeper into
the pain so we're no longer experiencing at the conceptual level
and what i mean with that is we'll take pain as an example
the word pain is an abstraction it's a umbrella term
for sensations which are quite intense and those sensations can be varied
there can be intense burning stabbing there can be intense twisting
there can be intense um um you know stretch pulling and tightening
going on there can be intense exhaustion of the muscles it's really aching
and so the um those are those are the particular sensations
that what we call pain and two people can say they have pain and they have very different sensations
sometimes when we call things pain we react to all the ideas and notions we
have about pain rather than uh and and it's the abstraction we're
reacting to what it means where it's going what's going to happen in the future rather than just dropping into the pain
itself and feeling that particularities of the sensation it's possible at the level of calling it
pain it just feels like it's constant when we drop into the level of sensations we can discover if we're
really focused that the sensations are not constant they're
inconstant they come and they go they appear and they disappear um you know there might be i've had you
know when i was first a new zen student i used to bring my attention to feel
the pain in my knees which i had a lot of and it would be sometimes just to be reduced to a little square centimeter
and in that centimeter there would be this dancing of of intense sensations sparking
sensations of stabbing and tightening and different things and it was kind of fascinating to watch
the dance and flicking around that there was no one sensation to hold on to or
react to because they are constantly moving in this little square centimeter
for some things the that ability to just feel at the
sensation level gives breathing room for it to resolve itself to unwind to dissolve
and for other things which are pleasant and enjoyable there's breathing room for it to grow and expand
and some of the great uh feelings of well-being that come with practice that
we want to have come with practice are much more accessible if we can feel it more fully in the body
the more we're awake in the body the more the body body's is a field of sensations that we can
feel so much of the happiness and joy and well-being it can be felt in embodied way it's more
stable it's more fuller it's more coursing through us if we can really feel it through the
body so this ability to drop down and feel the sensations increases our capacity
for experiencing joy and happiness dropping down and feeling being embodied
with our experience referring everything back in the body and let the body hold it
and the body wakes up and becomes more expansive in a sense with sensations not that we're living from the neck up it
also turns out we have a lot more capacity for being with difficulties
that the mind doesn't have actually sometimes a lot of capacity
in its stories ideas reactions beliefs memories projections in the future it can get
very claustrophobic but if we can be centered and grounded and
stable in our body making room to feel the sensations letting the sensations come and making
room for them then we have a much bigger capacity to deal with challenges
much bigger a much bigger ability to be uncomfortable so that we're not knocked over or pushed
around or we become reactive or we get tense or we get we feel like our boundaries are being
pushed because we we have all this capacity to hold it and be aware of it
kind of like um the analogy i like that if you put put a pyramid
on its head on the point it's not very stable and maybe it can maybe get just perfectly
balanced for a moment but someone just taps it then it just falls over but if you turn the the um
the pyramid upside down i mean right side up and so it's not sitting on its base
then you push it and it's not going to tip over so easily and or at all
and uh so there's something about being stably centered inner physicality of our
body sensations of body that we don't easily get pushed over or
thrown off balance by events of the world so this simple exercise
i mean not maybe the exercise is not simple but to do but always but the
simple instructions opens up to a vast world of possibility
the world of our body being centered ground in our body embodied in our body
letting the body process our life letting the body be the place we just compost things into our body
when i have difficult emotions uh i just find it so valuable to sit and meditate
and just feel those emotions in my body just let them trust the body cut like the body's composting them and
then i just kind of put put them back into my body in my body and feel it in the body
and it's so relieving to realize that the
the wisdom of the body knows how to take care of things sometimes much better than the mind
that's trying to figure it out or trying to navigate negotiate
mediate bargain with reality
so um so [Music] to begin increasing your vocabulary
for sensations you might want to draw up a list and maybe ask friends to add words to
them and of all the ways that direct sensory experiences is
felt and the greater that vocabulary list the great maybe the
the more you have to enter into this world of sensations and feeling them
entering in so fully that at some point you start feeling the dynamism of it the dynamic nature in
which it changes and moves and flows and comes alive more and more as we rest in
the body as way that awareness is embodied so i would i offer you that one
as an exercise to do supporting this sensation meditation
is to draw up some a list a long list of all the words in your language that
describe sensations twisting pulling heat
hot cold heavy light you know just go on and on
um itching and whatever it might be and uh and they and maybe um
get your friends involved with it and maybe they have different words than you do and you get your vocabulary increases
and as the vocabulary increases perhaps your sensitivity also increases you're able to identify the differences between
some of them that otherwise would have been missed
so thank you and i hope that you'll come to a day
maybe today that you come to love your body
much meta to your body may your body be one of your valentines
thank you