so hello hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour lovely to see you
to be with you so so for today's practice um
i'd like to invite us to work with the theme that
i've introduced in the past and tonight again we'll we'll work with it from yet
another angle from another perspective and that is to treat ourselves the way we would treat a
beloved other the way we would treat a beloved other
we're often kind to people we're kind and loving to the people we care about
we maybe we cook for them with just an additional sense of care kindness
maybe we we are considerate of them oh how are you doing
you know just very very caring very loving of them uh we honor them
we recognize them we you know the way we treat a beloved other with care
with love with respect we give them our time we give them our time
we sit and listen unhurriedly we don't go okay are you done yet are you done
being sad now are you done being whatever like okay i gotta go there's a
sense of i'm here for you i care for you your pains are important well your body
is hurting what can i do for you so the sense of care the sense of love
the sense of affection so what if what if we treated
ourselves like a beloved other we treated ourselves like a beloved other
and the guided meditation i will invite that perspective and also for our daily life
which you know this practice is also for the daily life um what if we brought that same perspective
to tonight when we take ourselves to bed
uh when when you are putting yourself to bed what if what if
it were as if you're putting this beloved others imagine you had this child this precious precious child and
you're putting them to bed how would you tuck them in how would you perhaps even plant a
little kiss on their forehead or maybe if you're brushing their teeth you wouldn't be doing it like
okay let's get this over with i was lovingly laughing like oh here sweetie i
don't want to hurt you here i'm doing this to take care of you to take care of your teeth so what if we all brushed our
teeth choose one one thing you do tonight or tomorrow maybe you make
yourself tea or coffee let's talk about brushing teeth you do it lovingly really
caringly just as
taking time for yourself so
so so yes our practice will continue not just in the sitting but throughout the
evening or whatever your time zone might be i see marie christine it's morning there afternoon there's whatever your
time zone might be so for the rest of the day for the rest of your day
so i think that's all i want to say to
frame to frame right now and let's just land in the
practice space together and give our heart to ourselves
so so i'd like to invite you
to arrive to land ah in this body
at this moment in time
letting go thoughts of concerns of whatever has come before
and just arriving here i'm here
and for the first few minutes of our practice together as usual we
will just arrive with the breath with the body connecting with the breath and the
abdomen in breath and out breath
relaxing with each breath
and as thoughts arise as they inevitably will
it's okay it's okay
treating the thoughts yourself with kindness hello thoughts
ah thank you and not now
i'm landing in a moment of refuge here in this quiet
sense of peace within connecting with myself
in this moment
connecting with the breath in the abdomen
appreciating the fullness or the shallowness however it is
appreciatively connecting with the breath
here here now
inviting the body to relax release let go
the next out breath release
ah then release some more
here now here now
without judgment without yanking [Music] smilingly
taking refuge here now yay yippee
now i'd like to invite you if you wish to consider these invitations
as support for your practice in whatever way they may serve
now let's imagine there is this beautiful
magnificent
child that's entrusted whose care is entrusted
to you this child is
very special so much goodness so much potential
you really look into the eyes of this child you see so much goodness
you see they're put in nature you see the divine
just this beautiful magnificent
child that you're supposed to take care of
you're supposed to brush their teeth comb their hair [Music]
feed them cook for them feed them
bathe them put clothes on them keep them
comfortable support them
if they're in pain if they cry to comfort them
and you want to it doesn't feel like you should you want to
there is a connection with this child
they're this tender vulnerable
tender and vulnerable and yet beautiful
and full of goodness being you want to protect them
be patient with them teach them help them grow
imagine yourself in whatever way support it
at whatever age is supportive with this child
this magnificent being [Music] seeing their butt in nature
their inner goodness their magnificence their bright light and their vulnerability at the same time
if it feels okay maybe they can sit on your lap
or next to you they need protection and support
maybe they're scared maybe they're tired maybe they're sick
being human is hard enough especially when you're a child
see how the expression of meta love care
your mind's eye can express itself towards this being
maybe you're holding them in the blanket if they're cold just holding them
maybe rocking them
and yes as i mentioned the introduction
tonight this child is you is yourself
this beloved child
full of goodness beauty light
divinity and tender vulnerable
maybe even hurting in some ways
is you
what is a physical expression in your mind's eye of your care of your
love for this being let yourself be created
if you're imagining a blanket of comfort let it cover both of you
notice if there any words or phrases i want to be said
to this beautiful being maybe the simply the words i love you
i care for you i love you just as you are
i appreciate your goodness
i'm here to love and protect you whatever feels right for you
as an expression of meta
what if you imagine yourself in your mind's eye taking care
of this being with patience
see yourself brushing your brushing their teeth
patiently lovingly
appreciatively playfully
as if you had all the time in the world
to care for this beloved beloved being
and now what if you imagine brushing your own teeth looking in the mirror
of this beloved being this being
so much goodness with the bright light of goodness
divinity but then nature in them bright and their tenderness and vulnerabilities
having all the time in the world to care to care
oh sweetheart
maybe if you like imagining imagining feeding
this beloved other this child first living all the time in the world
one bite at a time nourishing them is important
now if you imagined taking the spoon and feeding yourself
with love in your heart
may this food nourish you nourish me
it's an expression of care my love of meta of self-care
and now maybe imagining putting this
beloved other this child on a swing
pushing them up into the skies on the swing [Music] it's an expression of love taking care
delighting in their joy
having joy delight is part of caring part of love
it's not only grim duty
and now what if you were the one on the swing
feeling your body on the swing
moving into the sky up up ah
the joy the fun [Music] of play
taking care of yourself
letting yourself play
notice what something that brings joy to this
child maybe they like to splash in puddles
you join them or whatever else it might be squealing with delight
maybe
play on a see-saw
let yourself play
it's an act of love and care with this beloved child
both of you playing running in the grass rolling whatever it
might be
maybe lovingly tickling the tickle attack and being tickled back
let yourself have fun the meta can be fun
joyful
and for the last moment of this practice period
let yourself hug let yourself hug this beloved child
hugging lovingly in your mind's eye and
letting the child be you become you be inside you
embody you you embody the child the child embodies you
and just before we end and open our eyes take a palm of your hand
put it on your heart center middle of your chest connecting with yourself
with this beloved other i'm here to take care of you
your care has been entrusted to me i'm here
i'm here for you to love you to take care of you
as best as i'm able
may all beings everywhere no they're all magnificence
love themselves fully which then translates to loving the whole world
thank you all thank you for your practice
so so we have some time a few minutes for
reflections questions comments
and please know that whatever you offer is offer is you're in the invitation for to
offer for the benefit of the sangha you can type them in chat i'll change
the settings if you change if you type them to me alone i won't read your name
if it's typed to everyone i'll read your name also you can raise your zoom hand especially if you haven't spoken for a
while or if you're new please
so what did you discover any aha moments any challenges
susan please
thank you for the invitation to play i'd forgotten it was just i just was feeling it in my
body that's the joy of playing what a gift
thanks susan i'm so glad that that lit up for you that invitation just lit up
from i can see in your face it's lovely it lit up for me too i was having a
great time on the swings and running around it was just yeah just
such an expression of meta it can be play yeah thank you for that
yeah another reflection in chat privately thank you for the loving guidance of
deep self-care yeah thank you thank you
any other reflections one more a lot of tenderness and tears
in the midst of a health flare-up the spaciousness of being held and loved
ah thank you for sharing that a lot of tenderness and tears
thank you and holding you holding you dear
with spaciousness and love in the midst of your health flare
[Music] up and morgan
please i have a little conflict nikki
it's all welcome oh thank you so much i am during that i was so i got so aware of
there actually not being a self and that my emotions and my thoughts
were just conditioned experiences that were part of nature but weren't
a part of a self so i and it was
it was not disconcerting but it was
like what do i do with that knowing
that this is a conditioned experience just the result of causes and
conditions and then how do you relate to the the self and the nut
yeah yeah yeah great question i'm so glad you brought it in yeah
wonderful question how do we bring both of those insights together how do we
yes it's it's um it's a both and it's at both end
absolutely at both end so
so there you know there are so many levels of seeing
phenomena reality understanding and one does not negate the other
i think that's the thing i would encourage you when that comes up say oh i see you
thank you you know when did not self arise it's like yes but that doesn't negate it's not like it's a that is
better than this see that that is where the dichotomy or or a false
understanding can come in that somehow the ultimate reality view is better or
super or better place to hang out than the relative reality both have their values
both are this just as important and there's a time
that's important to to rest in the ultimate and there's a time that's
wholesome beautiful important to rest in the relative
does that help thank you yes it does thank you yeah thank you morgan that's lovely
thanks so much yeah one more
couple more one reflection from jerry it was lovely to hold myself as a child
with my arms wrapped around myself very caring that's lovely thank you and one
more reflection privately my child self was very upset with me that i haven't been taking good
care of myself i had to hold a lot of her rage during the set yeah yeah and that's okay too
thank you for bringing that up because it's all welcome it's all welcome sometimes it is that rage and what i'm
actually really touched by in this share is that you held a lot of her rage you you're
like oh done with you like oh sweetheart okay yes i i hold you yes you're angry it's okay sweetie it's all right it's
okay and that is a part of of re-parenting re-parenting ourselves
so thank you for sharing that and thank you for hanging in there with with the rage of the little one
that's important too that's really important yeah yeah take heart
and melissa i see your hand this will be the last reflection before we transition into small groups please
i just wanted to thank morgan for her uh question because um it helped me to like when i
reflect back i feel that um you know i was able to imagine and visualize my child's
self but it just didn't hold as much emotional charge as that time and i
think the way you spoke about both like i could see what morgan was
saying and i can see what you're saying and yeah just you know you know what i'm
saying like time has passed and it doesn't feel as charged as yeah it's as
as that time yeah you know like a lot of healing has happened yeah which is beautiful also
yeah and to hold that with respect and also holding this adult self that is in
a different place yeah yeah thank you melissa
thanks for being here and thanks to everyone for being here and your practice and reflections so
so i'd like to invite us please now to turn to turn into
um a little bit of play play in small groups so
i like to invite tonight for for there to be of course always care always meta in small groups but also
what if what if these younger cells were showing up together just kind of maybe a
little more playful why do it show up oh what just be curious about it again with
a lot of care a lot of love but but it's a little lighter a lot more playful a
little more playful so so i'm about to create
the rooms and here we are okay they're created i'm going to open them take care
of yourselves and especially take care of each other okay here we go
okay the rooms are closed and everyone is back welcome back everyone
and we've got just about a minute left um so if there any
reflections questions um burning please
anything that needs to be said or asked to feel complete with this
session
okay feeling complete yeah jerry says i'm going to play more great
oh yay i love that i love that yay may all of us play more so
so that's a fantastic note to end our happy hour it's happy hour it's playtime
so um yeah oh yeah melissa says thank you for the play inspiration thank you melissa
thank you all thank you for your practice for showing up cultivating your
heart your mind ah for the benefit of yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be
happy may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thank you