okay thanks Martha I appreciate it um
yeah welcome welcome to you all um happy to to be sitting with you and
um yeah welcome to the the folks uh out there and
we'll have the the usual form I'll lightly guide us uh until the top of the
hour and then offer a talk and maybe we have time for some dialogue we'll see
and um yeah so please uh settle settle into a
posture that feels sustainable
foreign
just making your mind a welcoming environment for
foreign people trickling in
welcoming environment for the intensity of having a body
maybe exploring ways of breathing
that help you arrive
maybe it's a deeper Fuller breath that reaches into the
belly
and just ever so gently Smooths out the the energy of body mind
there's also often a sense
as the Winds of phenomena blow through the sensations of our body of affect
of sound thought
it's almost as if our bracing against phenomena
is it an attempt to protect some kernel of our being the center point
of self
sense that something inside of us needs protection
from phenomena
but our practice
to let the Winds of experience blow
and trusting that there's nothing inside that will be blown over
it's nothing more than Pleasant and unpleasant
oh
no Winds of grasping and aversion
an opportunity we Sense on the horizon
the unpleasantness of sound or sensation
we let those winds blow too
uh held in the the openness of awareness
foreign
the Dharma never asked us to pretend
to pretend we like what we dislike or a neutral about what we like
asked us simply
foreign s and
the openness of awareness
thank you
foreign
almost a sense of our heart being massaged
by the collacers forces of suffering
greed and aversion
in the sense that something is being softened in the the openness of
this awareness
foreign
so uh so welcome
um
so I I don't usually do talks on lists
um sort of because I I like how the lists
interact with each other or the facets of the list interact with each other
but um today a talk on a list yeah
and um it's almost like we we can get
um we almost get too familiar with the list over time I mean when we're new it's
different but as we practice over years we sometimes get so familiar with
Buddhist list that we almost lose track of their Brilliance and um
and I was was uh talking to a friend a colleague of mine
who said something like that she she just basically assiduously followed
the Eightfold Path deep into her practice you know the
years into practice just assiduously followed that it tried
to implement that in all spheres of her life and it changed everything yeah and
it's like not that shouldn't have shocked me kind of right but there was something about
um understanding her mind the potency of her mind and then just to say like yeah these kind of
um this this list yeah meant everything
and so uh in our own practice we apply these uh we we pick up these these
themes these teachings at greater depth and nuance and
they come to me and more and more to us over time and what we hear in a list the
first time we hear it is so different from the 100th time we here at
there's really a different list
the the Dharma generally revolves around what's to be let go what's to be
released and the basic architecture of the the view is that in a sense suffering is our
only problem yeah that to relinquish suffering
is not a trivial thing and in its wake leaves just many species of goodness
it's not that we let go of suffering and then we have to create some other kind
of positivity yeah um and so quite naturally the the
attention goes to the untangling deconstruction of the the
sources of suffering um but then what what is actively
cultivated what species of wholesomeness are actively cultivated
and one of those those
lists what's actively cultivated the the goodness that helps us keep going
the sometimes celebrate as a kind of like the anti-hindrances
the seven factors of Awakening and so the Buddha says I do not even see
even one thing that when developed and cultivated leads to the abandoning of things that
Fetter so effectively as this the seven factors of enlightenment
the seven factors are both a kind of um the path and the fruit
it's often how these teachings are they are both the path and the fruit the practice and the culmination
the um the work that we do
and the fruit that is Harvest there's a story of the Buddha somewhere
in the sutas being sick at night and asking
one of his disciples to almost like as a
kind of the feeling that I had of like a kind of bedtime story yeah
of um o o kunda
bring to mind the seven factors of Enlightenment bring you know speak them
to me in that state of sickness at night
in you know our practice um in meetings practice discussions
interviews on Retreat for example um
so much of the time there's some form of suffering that's being some people are
seeking consultation on one way or another but what happens when they're not
yeah what does the teacher do when there's
no report of of uh active course suffering
mostly we just say keep going yeah um but sometimes sometimes we say uh
let us examine you know like uh the these seven factors to see the relative
balance of the energizing side of practice and the tranquilizing side of
practice uh because a lot of this path is the kind of uh
it's a kind of dialectic between um between different forces a lot of this
practice is a dialectic between the absence of suffering and the emergence
of new currents of suffering sometimes deeper layers currents of suffering
and so um this these um
states are the as we get more and more free the
Mind states are increasingly characterized by a kind of some balance of these seven factors of
of uh mindfulness as a kind of balancing point
of the energizing and tranquilizing factors
of investigation energy effort
intense Joy rapture on the energizing side and Tranquility
samadhi the unification of mind and and Equanimity on the the tranquilizing side
and um said something like the the first the
first it said something like um mindfulness
investigation energetic Vigor effort
these are the causes and every the others are the the effects yeah which is
an interesting formulation they have complex relationships with each other
and so um in a way
we uh even though
the the characterization of the Tranquility fact decide as being the effects yeah not something we do
we sort of have to begin you know with a little bit of Tranquility otherwise
um there's no room to digest the impermanent the the impermanence and the
imperfection of experience if there's no tranquility
yet to try to let go to try to open to try to soften all of these things uh are
very difficult to do in the absence of some modicum of Tranquility
and so there there's um a lot of relations between these
different facets in our in our practice
um so mindfulness mindfulness is uh
it's a word that's been used in so many ways one of my mentors said we just have to throw it out you know
it's just been so it's like a pocket into which so many things have been put
that the word has sort of lost all meaning Integrity something like this
and sometimes in fact the way mindfulness is used
is a kind of umbrella term for the seven factors yeah if you actually hear the
way it's used in popular culture it's actually it's not Sati in the narrow kind of
sense a lot of other beautiful qualities are smuggled under in the back door kind
of to this this umbrella term of mindfulness and I'm not blaming the wonderful John
cab it's in for this but John cabotzin did say this yeah
yeah this is 2000 2011.
um said mindfulness-based stress reduction which which uh he is the
developed this eight week program that's been a tremendous blessing to many
people and my life no doubt is a function of the kind of efforts uh his
efforts and many others um said mindfulness-based stress reduction was developed as one of POS of
a possibly infinite number of skillful means for bringing the Dharma into mainstream settings
it has never been about mbsr for its own sake it's always been about the m and the m is a very big m
we use the word mindfulness intentionally as an umbrella term to describe our work and to link it
explicitly with what I've always considered to be a universal Dharma that
is co-extensive if not identical with the teachings of the Buddha the Buddha
Dharma um
that we do need a word we do need a word to
try to convey the depth and the beauty the richness of the Dharma
and in this case mindfulness was chosen yeah
and um and there are consequences there are
definitional consequences to that decision yeah and so what do we mean when we say
mindfulness we can talk about it in these sort of
more pared down ways or more Grand ways um and
in a sense to for mindfulness to
to really it's never been described as
a single it's always conjoined with other factors yeah in the way that a big
umbrella term kind of implies and so I
do actually link mindfulness with with uh
the kind of um an awareness that lets go
an awareness that is just already conjoined with other factors
an awareness that um is
aware of the movements of suffering of the movement of greed of an aversion
um but is uncompelled by them that sense of like I was alluding to
this in the sit sense that the the awareness is a little bit bigger
than the forces of suffering and that when awareness is present no
matter what suffering is there something else is also true
and it's a subtle move this gesture of awareness but it's radical
and sometimes it just just uh just that that sense of knowing
suffering in the clarity and the openness of
awareness does not erase all of the unpleasantness
or something but it's enough that our life all of a sudden feels quite
different than it did one moment ago when we were fully identified with the
phenomena of suffering
and so we usually talk about mindfulness as a kind of
what rescues us from our habits particularly the bad habits yeah the
sense of that there's without some metacognitive awareness we are just living in obedience to our
habits and um that's fair enough
but um mindfulness also
becomes a habit and helps us develop good habits
and this sense of that we have often early in practice of like okay I'm gonna leave here and I'm gonna go have my day
and I've got to be mindful I gotta remember
that's not that's not how it feels I don't think as we continue practicing
it's not this sense of mindfulness is this this um this kind of thing we like the on the
grocery list like I have to remember carrots you know
and you know when you kind of do a bad shop you sort of like
get discombobulated or whatever I can kind of feel it at the register like I
just I messed up you know I'm forgetting a
lot you know like and and we're gonna have this sense of like oh yeah I could just keep forgetting the mindfulness or
something like this and it's okay to try to motivate like explicit cognitive
control or something but to some extent what we are actually training in is the
elevating the trait level of mindfulness the mindfulness that exists in the way a
habit exists yeah that we actually don't have to remember
in the same way that we're more mindful when we're not trying to be mindful
and that's important because we'll never be able to remember enough consciously
[Music] um
investigation which is of course enabled by
mindfulness and investigation
investigation to me not not about um
some X kind of um top-down cognitively trying to figure
something out trying to figure out like sometimes investigation and rumination
the line is thin you know like how did I get here
why do I feel this way where am I going and those questions can kind of like
masquerade as deep existential inquiries but there actually have a kind of
ruminative obsessive feel to them and um
an investigation is not kind of loosely looking for some
answer out of The Ether or something it's a kind of sustained attention to
the the unfolding of experience the connection between moments
and um I Associated a lot with curiosity which
is really kind of the lifeblood of this practice I don't know where that where if it's in
a list somewhere and you know but I you know investigation is like very
closely linked to curiosity and the truth is there's no cure for a lack of
curiosity and there's nothing a teacher can say to keep you engaged unless you find
something that you get interested in like I want to understand this
I want to know why I keep doing this I want to know
um some facet of my mind
I want to understand something and
in a sense when there's curiosity present because it's so agendaless it's
not like I want to get happier even it's like a very deeply trustworthy
intention for animating practice I want to understand more and there's a
kind of patience in it
and there's um a sense of
it's not even the point to get to some answer there's like no Final Answer
there's just deepening and refining and nuance and and more
curiosity and we find Our Kind of cruising altitude in our autobiographical story
of who we are of what we are of what the path is of where we're going of What happiness is
and then that rug will be pulled out before too long hopefully
yeah and that ignites a kind of new sense of curiosity a new round where
we're no longer satisfied with the stories we've been
feeding ourselves
the somewhere the Buddha says that we have four options when in pain
blame self blame others despair or investigate
yeah that's not a hard multiple choice question you know
it's like okay what is happening here and we do develop a kind of
uh Faith really in the looking of faith
not that everything's okay or anything like that but a faith that
uh maybe we just say a faith in wisdom
faith in love a faith that the more deeply we look
the more Dharma we will find the more the more the Deep more deeply we look
the more reason there will be to uh to love
and so we're not so afraid of what we'll find yeah
hmm
energy very uh this is among the most emphasized
themes in the suttas and um I think because this path is against the
stream uh genuinely against the street in some ways it's with the stream in
other ways it's against the stream and it's against the stream in the sense that Neurosis is
often the path of least resistance yeah like my neurosis
is just like so happily floating down a stream you know strong current at my
back you know like Gill has the in some of the way he talks about Satya batana I
think I picked I remember slides from Gill where it's somebody coasting down
the water just relax the effortless of mindfulness that's not what I'm talking
about I'm talking about the the stream of neurosis where it takes zero energy
for me to act it out right and we all know those moments where it's like
for sure like the easiest thing to do right now the absolute easiest thing to
do is to express the forces of suffering and my own bad habits you know
right
so what are we gonna do yeah um what are we gonna do we're going to
mobilize energy effort
sometimes not always sometimes we really are in the Stream of goodness and the
goodness and the awareness and everything feels effortless but that's often a function of Prior
effort yeah and so we Marshal our energy because
growth is hard it takes energy you know it's like
when kids going through a growth spurt and they have to like really rest or something it's like that
and um
so we're we Marshal some effort in order not to
obey the dictates of greed hatred and delusion
and um this path is a
it's a renunciate path in the sense that it is not a something for nothing path
and sometimes we get the sense that just because
the awareness is is so powerful and that the this most simple gesture of it can
sometimes bring incredible relief we get the sense that maybe maybe
if I'm making effort I must be doing it wrong it is we have some sense that the
lure of something for nothing you know is deep in US
but um but it's not we are we're not giving up things for no reason
we're giving up it's lesser forms of pleasure for deeper forms of satiation
um and uh and
uh Rapture Rapture a Rapture born of letting go
doing really badly on time here
yeah sometimes sometimes this is this is translated as
um as Joy but it's sort of more and we want
to make the definition accessible but it's more energetic than the more effervescent than that more compelling a
kind of like just the the attention just sucked into the flow of this
and um because it's so normally our thoughts are the most prominent thing
and experience by far by far but
that can change and a sense of um of
um PT of rapture that becomes
more compelling than anything else and this usually experience usually
pleasant but sometimes not pleasant and at some point even that you know as
unimaginable as that might be Rapture as pleasure isn't that why I'm here isn't that what I'm
in you know why I'm doing all this letting go and whatever you know for Raptor's pleasure even that gets old
yeah even that gets old but it is significant
in so far as it does confirm that this path is not a con
yeah it's not another shell game and when we start to see like I didn't
know that I could feel this way
I didn't know that I could settle into the moment in this kind of rapturous way
you're like okay this induces faith and it's a sense of like
um there's something here for me and the power we actually sometimes for
some people it's the first deep glimpse of the power of our mind
which we have underestimated forever
[Applause] this kind of delight is said to give way
to come yeah which is a little bit the reverse
of what we think about we think we get calm in order to then become happier but here
is kind of reverse it's happiness and then we get calm we get settled we get focused we get you know
um but uh but come um this pivot to the tranquilizing side of
uh the path and the ways in which our nervous system is
just Longing To Be unstimulated just Longing To Be unstimulated
we think we're always looking for pleasure or something
but we're usually looking for pleasure to balance out the intensity of
something else and peace this Tranquility maybe the beginning of
that is um in a sense our deepest longing I almost
think of it as the nervous system longing for the Dharma to be at peace it is
as far as I can tell the only thing that does not fatigue the heart
peace
and so to begin to settle to begin to settle to
find ways of breathing to find signs anchors ways of attending that bring
some measure of Tranquility in is necessary in order
um in order to do the work of Letting Go you know
it's like if we're trying to uh trying to to let go and open to
experience from a very untranquil state it just feels like it makes our mind
more brittle there's no more space it's filling a cup that's already overflowing
so we learn ways of of bringing in some calm and over all the years of practice
now it it's almost like even no matter what's happening in my mind my there's
like such deep associations with the posture and with the sense of the the
breath and the sense of gravity that something you know it's like this kind
of cue that just induces a measure of Tranquility and then there's more room to bear with
the imperfection of samsara
when there is um Tranquility less agitation there's less
of a a kind of um searching and foraging for for food for
the mind to medicate our agitation yeah that sense of like
we're we're often kind of just scanning the realm of our own thought world as a
way to um to medicate to medicate the
the sense of of um threat and the sense that of of un
acquired opportunity and so
this Tranquility when that begins to settle when there are not alarm Bells
going off in our system Moment by moment what else is there to do other than just
pay some attention and so we settle into to somebody to the
kind of unification of the Mind and um
and samadhi linked of course with
Rapture rapturous Joy samadhi is what um
what turns the Dharma into something more than a philosophy
yeah the Dharma is really it's a good philosophy but it won't save us as a
philosophy you know we have to it has to become real yeah
has to become real uh it has to be be realized yeah
which which yeah one uh credit literary critic you know Eve
Cedric said like oh yeah to the difference between knowledge and realization is in realization something
becomes real as real as this very room and for the Dharma to become real it it
requires some measure of samadhi otherwise it's just kind of a appealing
set of ideas that we sort of clumsily try to apply to our life but until we actually
start to hear the Dharma from a place of
unification of steadiness it's um it's not so useful
and so we we come into alignment it feels like all the all the
pieces and parts of us all of a sudden start moving in the same direction
and the kind of ambivalence and the sense of Being for the fragmentation of
the self um just recedes and we are all all of us
is moving in One Direction it feels more and more natural just to
rest the attention with what we decide is relevant
and um we get so um
so um [Music] we kind of use uh
the level of discursive thinking as the barometer for our samadhi and for our
practice generally we sort of take the surface layer of the Mind very seriously
and we use that to measure how still we are but the truth is there are processes of
Stillness that happen outside of the the realm of discursive thought
and that's why when people have been sitting in retreat for example for a few days or a couple
weeks as have people have been at Insight retreat center now yeah
um even if their minds are
still florid with thought there's a deepening that's happening as
some kind of silence is setting in and I associate samadhi with the unification
of mine but also with the plasticity of mind the its sense of depth and this
it's it's How Deeply impressionable it becomes
yeah and so the mind the the mind that is stabilized is a very is a deeply
impressionable mind and whatever we learn under the conditions of samadhi
has legs yeah the insights That We Gather the
understandings that we cultivate the realizations that we have under
conditions of samadhi that has legs it stays with us we all know the sense of
the the light of some insight or some understanding fading over time
oops Insight developed under under conditions
of the unification under conditions of samadhi have legs yeah stays
and um in in the experience of samadhi of Piti
of of the kind of delight of every part of us moving in the same direction
um uh we
we
have a kind of the the movement of the heart is not towards the intensity of
pleasure but towards the neutrality of
uh of of equanimity of a kind of
the the heart mind like utterly
unstimulated by The Winds of phenomena
a sense of something in US is a Longing To Be
unstimulated by The Winds of phenomena and we say we
this is as as OPEC uh Equanimity deep ends
there's a sense of um
at least first it's a sense not of the absence of preferences but the absence
of the compulsion to enact our preferences that distinction makes sense the so it's
not that that there isn't preference but the sense of like the compulsion to
bring our preferences into being to make something happen and all of the
agitation and strategizing requiring to bring clinging to fruition that starts
to fade huh
and um but in that process
um something in US is being softened it's like I think I said something like the
chalesas or softening or hard or something like that which is a weird
formulation and I'm not even sure it makes sense but that's how it kind of
feels to me it's like the forces of clinging when they're met in the the kind of
openness of equanimity it feels like something is being softened
foreign called Equanimity the primary cathartic
factor of mindfulness yeah of the path the primary cathartic
Factor this being alluding to the sense of
um of release that happens the softening that happened when when the when the
forces of clinging actually soften rather than Harden our heart
um
I think it's said that Equanimity when it really ripens is the
the closest approximation of Awakening
but the amidst this like radical okayness
in this non-interference with all phenomena with the Winds of samsara
we don't actually lose the poignancy of our life of life itself the poignancy of
of suffering the suffering world
um love is only a kind of stone's throw
away from peace and the mind that is that is stable that
is tranquilized that is gathered that is equanimous
um just just one kind of drop of love
flavors everything
so I offer this for uh your consideration yeah
and um seven factors yeah
so may they uh may they be the practice may they be the fruit yeah
and um yeah please pick up whatever is uh
useful here and ignore the rest yeah like for real you know you this has your
path and you have to be the the kind of Judge of what is what is
useful and you sort of test things out and um uh you see yeah you're patient
patient but you test them out and um and this is the way our path unfolds in
our very idiosyncratic way yeah so uh so thank you thank you for your
attention and uh thank you to uh the crew on YouTube and to to you Martha
Kevin yeah thanks for saying hi to them for me okay chat Chatham they know they
should still be able to hear me but thank you Kevin um okay folks you uh you'd be well and
um yeah we'll uh we'll see you see you around the Dharma campus somewhere so