good morning everyone or good morning here on the west coast
and good day everywhere
wherever you are and thank you for those of you who are joining the zoom page
somehow i find it easier to talk
when i see faces in front of me
i haven't quite mastered the art of being animated
just looking at a screen that doesn't have a kind of
a human response
so thank you who joined the zoom and i haven't quite mastered
having a zoom and a youtube channel both open at the same time i hope too soon
but i haven't yet
so yesterday i was offering the notion of
our practice in in a variety of ways
is an expression of wisdom and compassion
i think of them as the yang and the yin
the wisdom being it is what it is
each moment each experience pleasant or unpleasant each interaction
pleasant or unpleasant it is what it
and the is you know each one of us navigating
our life each one of us exploring what it is to flourish what it
is to bring forth the qualities of being
that make a life enriching rewarding and
vibrant alive
and that these two interplay
and and together as we connect to them
they they bring an extraordinary extraordinary quality
to our human experience they enliven it
they give it depth they create within us
a capacity to be
each moment create within us a capacity to trust the human process
it's not an affliction it's a great gift
and of course when we're just holding that as
an admonition for or a
transformative notion and that can inspire us but when we
taste it when we become it something in us
is deeply nourished
so as we start to sit if you can just
remind yourself of what it is to be aware
in the midst of the human condition
usually what's most dominant for us is some
state of mind maybe with a persistent contact
or maybe just a disposition
and in the midst of that disposition reminding ourselves
this is about meditation it's about calling forth
the qualities of presence that enhance
and support the human experience
rather than some food more quality
of taking this time to nurture our being
discovering how the very process of being aware
as our singular activity can be benevolent
it can be supportive
as we engage our body
can we find within our relationship to it within our posture
within our somatic being can we find that benevolence
expression of physical aliveness
maybe just tuning in to the physical sensations in the body
you give them an expression of aliveness
unless you tune in can you let the body teach you
through its physical sensations what it is
to inhabit it fully what it is that helps it to open
it helps it define a quality of uprightness
equality of balance
what it is that helps the chest open
and soft
quite literally what is it to be heartful
and almost
as if you didn't know how to breathe just noticing
the inhale and the exhale how they move
through our body
physical movement of breathing in
the physical opening to what's happening in the moment
taking it in
sticking in the physical sensation taking in the thoughts
taking in any ambient sounds
taking in any mental dispositions
emotions it is what it is
and let the eyebrow release
everything changes it's dynamic
it's a constant flow
the exhale
maybe if your experience feels a little tumultuous
the exhale can have a quality of a sigh
not dismissing or rejecting but just finding a way to be with
do not grasp
and then
pretending to the stream of consciousness
that flows with this body in this breath
this constant engagement
in living this life
this amazingly complex event
that's happening in our being all the time
creating emotions creating memories
creating thoughts
creating openness creating contractions
can all light be embodied and breathe through
okay
uh
and when you notice that your awareness is wandered
just pause let the moment rediscover itself
the body rediscover itself
remembering we don't make the moment happen it's always happening
and as we move towards the end of our sitting
imagine the bell has already run
whatever doing has been happening can be allowed to fall away
and just being without any
agenda without imposing consequences
no no
[Music]
martin luther king said the challenging experience
can be educational and transformative
each of us attempting to navigate our life
with all the challenges of it internal external
or sugar in as we read
and hear certain pieces of news about our world
the task of balancing all the things in your life
how to take care of them how to
decipher the most important thing at any particular moment
that they may be educational and transformative
that they may embody wisdom and compassion
the marvelous thing about mindfulness
is that it draws us into an activity a process
it allows the very things that we would normally grasp
or push away to just be moments of experiencing
moments of discovery
sometimes as simple as oh
my shoulders are tight can i listen to that tightness
and be educated can i listen to the tightness in my
shoulders and discover
how to shift into letting something be more
open something be more
accepting of just what is
can i find within that moment a benevolence
a compassion
but that's a completely internal process or whether that's
how we're relating to another person a group of people
and can we track that through our day
you know yesterday just offered the notion in in an intentional way just a
single notion of it is what it is
and it's asking for compassion
okay can we continue
mindfulness through all the things that the day presents
and when we can frame mindfulness
as a benevolent act as something enriching
something nurturing then it's like we're attracted to it
and as we can act on that attraction and rediscover
how to shift situation by situation interaction by
interaction to shift into a benevolence
it's not that our grasping and aversion disappear
it's more like they're not the only thing that's happening we bring to the moment
a compassion for even our grasping and diversion
this is me doing my best effort at being alive
discovering happiness and suffering less this is this other person
being their best effort of being alive discovering happiness
and that benevolence as we explore it
it's an experiential learning it's educational in an experiential
learning way
and experiential learning is somewhat supported by
mental learning conceptual learning but in some ways it's radically
different it's like it has
a tangible engagement to it
it's palpable we feel it in our body
our emotions it
so as we engage mindfulness through the day you know can we keep checking in with
that what state of mind is it creating
what emotions are coming up along with it
and can we remind ourselves to be benevolent
this person that i'm annoyed with is just
making their best effort at making their life work
it finding happiness and freedom
from restrictions can i remind myself of that
can i check in to this experiential learning process
can i notice when the mind is contracting or the attitude is hardening
or the emotions becoming more negative
or judgmental in what's being evoked
and as we do it we moment by moment
we're introducing a transformation
just think of how many conversations you've had in your life where it's they they felt combative
and then when something in you and hopefully the other person lets go
and there's like a sigh an exhale and then something
simpler just listening to who this person is
you're just hearing them express the truth of what they are in that moment
and you express your truth in that moment
something quite different from combativeness can happen
this is the transformative quality of awareness of mindfulness
so maybe today you can explore
in the world that happens for you
in the self that happens you can explore it
and see can there be an experiential learning ah
what is it to be present like this
what is it to be skillful with the mind and the heart
when it's contracted when it's separate when it sees other
as a difficulty or an opposition
what is it to practice with that is it helpful to feel it in the body
just what is the impact of that is it helpful to acknowledge and note
the emotions that are strong for you or the attitudes with which you're
addressing yourself or someone else
our practice in seated meditation and our practice in the interaction of
life they balance each other
they teach each other
in this capacity this opportunity
to let it shift from its usual patterns
and can something in us remember the benevolence
that this is a gift this is not a burden this is not the should
that's demanding and
burdensome this is the gift that opens up possibility
so maybe you can reflect for a few moments on
helps me remember that
it helps me to remember the things that
the teachings that have touched my heart
the quality of sati the root of the word
it is remembering coming back
so thank you and i got the chat message that the sign was a little low and i will
endeavor to either speak louder or find a way to put on my lapel mic
and have a great day thank you