whoa that is a little loud
yeah i was testing the mic oh that's better thank you so much
okay let's test this one it's not very loud is it loud enough
not quite yes tracy is it loud enough yeah okay
are any of you concerned about um exposure if i take my mask off while i'm
talking okay
all right well it's 6 30. um
so i'll just do a very brief review of where we've been
just to help remind the mind like you know what what we've been practicing
so first of all just to say what we've done with this series is
we've taken what we normally experience as
you know our how we normally perceive and we've invited ourselves to
kind of focus in on different parts of our experience instead of having it
all be clumped in together right so it's not that everything isn't still happening
we don't ever stop breathing when we pay attention to mindfulness of the body but
rather we're working on choosing what we're focusing on
and giving more of our awareness to that thing one at a time
to help us become more familiar with that part of our experience
so we started with mindfulness of breathing
and we talked about establishing an anchor also with that first week and many people usually we talk about the
breath as an anchor but it doesn't have to be the breath an anchor can be anything that helps you
stay present stay aware so sound can be a really great anchor and bodily sensations like
the feeling of of sitting right your your the weight and the support and the lift
of the spine so we spent the first week really kind
of getting intimate with breathing and with establishing an anchor in the second
week we talked about mindfulness of the body
and for me i like to this idea that the body is a gateway to the present moment
when we're caught up in thinking and things that are going on and we're having a hard time
bringing ourselves into the moment by tuning into the experience in the
body because sensations are only happening in the present moment right touch only happens here
right so the body is such a great doorway
out of the mind and into life i'll put it that way
then the third week we talked about emotions and we practiced with emotions
we talked about being the riverbed and allowing emotions to move through us
like the water moves through a river and sometimes we are a small riverbed
sometimes we can be wide and broad and allow pretty much anything to flow through us
but to practice with that and the idea that emotions are you know if we measure when they measure
them and they look at the biochemical makeup of an emotion it lasts for
60 seconds 120 160 seconds something like that is about
the lifespan of an individual emotion it's different than a mood state
moon states are more prolonged but individual emotions unless we feed them and refuel them
re-trigger them they have a short shortish lifespan i can hear my
muffledness is that any better yeah okay
and we talked about you know practicing with you know tal how much we can tolerate practicing
letting different experiences move through us like that riverbed and maybe we can't do it for a long time
but for short periods of time trying to just practice letting things flow through
letting them move then last week we brought up thinking
mindfulness of thinking and we talked about that there's different
ways of thinking there's a narrative thinking where we're
talking to ourselves some people actually see words
some people think a lot in images some people
have sort of mini movies playing all the time where they can see a lot of stuff playing out in their imagination
sometimes our thinking is more uh subtle
um more a little bit of a background hum a little bit of a
you know like there's this feeling of something's working in us so sometimes our thoughts aren't
so visible or clear or audible depending on how we think
and there also can be a way of thinking that's like holding a view or holding a belief
like i should be doing something right now
so if we if we're kind of walking around with this idea i should be doing it better i
should be doing something it's a way of of thinking that can generate a lot of activity
and if we think we need to be doing something it also can proliferate into a
lot of other thoughts about what i should be doing yeah
another thing that we talked about is that um i'm not my thoughts
it's part of our experience just like sensations just like sounds
just like emotions things come up and come into our experience
and that it's possible to know these experiences to be the knower
instead of the thought or the thinker
another thing we talked about as helpful is using a light noting practice
so if we're trying to attend to the breath in
out would be an example of a simple noting we also might think about
naming oh planning so we don't want to get elaborate in our noting we want it
simple we don't want to get caught up in the noting thinking we just want that oh there's a there's a
human kind of thing there's a thought oh and if it has a lot of energy
uh last week in the meditation koda talked about the ships right this idea that
we've got this warship you know and then we've got the the
dance ship and the you know all these things these kind of big thoughts that come through and so you
can just kind of name the theme of them right and see them
koto is there anything you would want to add to uh our last session summary of
yeah that covered a lot of ground i think one thing we've emphasized a lot
that bears repeating is that all aspects of experience
can be included in mindfulness practice at its best
with mind with mindfulness practice nothing needs to be left out nothing that has arisen has gone wrong
and a corollary of that is that mindfulness practice is impossible to
fail at yeah yeah just practicing over and over
in this this simple capacity of attention in all the ways that tanya was talking about and we've talked about over these several weeks
but everything gets to be included and that's a great segue to tonight so
i'll say something and then we'll go back to this but this idea we've been breaking up our experience
and what we're attending to but it's not that everything else is stopping
right we're we're just trying to kind of get more intimately uh connected to the
certain kinds of experiences and that they're all kind of actually distinct in some ways and then they get really
kind of tangled up together and so tonight we'll do a practice that
invites you with this idea of having that anchor to step back and once you get kind of
settled to let different things come up and to be mindful of them and not to be
working to just track thinking or emotions or the body or breathing
so before we do that we want to give some time for reflection on your homework your practice this last week
what did you notice was there anything that you know came up
you know as you were working with thinking that you know you were able to pull up some of the stuff that we talked
about in class and have it support you anything you struggled with i'm hoping you were sitting even if it's
a little bit you know most days so
does anybody have anything they want to share or ask
great
i wanted to share um that i feel grateful
sort of yeah okay
hello okay much better thanks um i feel grateful that um
that's um another tool that i've been conscious of using is
being mindful of my thoughts or noticing if i'm thinking
and i think that um it's helping me to feel more free because uh when i notice that i'm
thinking then i can go back to a space of just
feeling the feeling in my chest or feeling feelings in my heart
or my torso and yeah i feel like it's peaceful
and i can be free from thinking at least for some time so yeah
i appreciate you teaching us that great
great i always i this happiness happiness is here
that's great anyone else it doesn't have to be great
news you can also share what's not working or an instruction they were like tanya what were you talking about
you know it's oh it's all welcome
so very close oh because of the mask i guess
i noticed that
i don't meditate with a mask on very often so i notice that it's a different
experience with the whole focusing on the breath thing and having it feel warm
against your it's just different so i'm
appreciating the opportunity to learn
other things to focus on other than just the breath because of course that's the first thing we learn
right is focus on the breath but focusing on the breath can make me feel hot and
you know uncomfortable so i i am appreciating
learning how to use other things to focus on
great what have you found helpful tracy is there something else that you've you
know so uh number one opening my eyes makes a difference and
and that just seems counterintuitive to everything that you're taught about meditation but what i did last week when
i was feeling that way is opened my eyes and focused on this sky and trees and window
which helped me feel less warm and
i don't know it's it's a strange thing for me to meditate with a mask on let's just put it that way yeah
thank you tracy
anybody else
anything you want to say before i move to the next
okay okay so um i'm going to
talk about a couple of things leading into kind of how to
work with open awareness practice
and we talked about one of the things that we talked about when we talked about mindfulness of the body was
um the idea of watching like a football game without a narrator turning the
sound off right so this idea of how to be with our direct experience without doing a lot of
adding perceptions and narrating kind of trying to be more simple and direct
right and that's very helpful um it's very helpful to do that it keeps
everything a little bit more simple um but you know our minds
our minds construct things so i i um i brought a flower to share with you
tonight and um you know it's a it's it's a pretty
enough flower right and um you know just sort of get to enjoy this
beautiful little flower yeah and just take it in for a minute see what you notice about it
how much you like it or you know yeah
so i have this flower and
i also have this flower
so when i bring this flower up how does it affect how you see this
flower does this flower become more beautiful
less beautiful does this flower become a big flower and this one becomes a small flower
right so how you know the color oh that's a vibrant pink that's kind of a dull pink
whereas this was just pink before right
yeah and then
i also have this flower
and so does this flower still seem big when i have this flower it might am i not
all of a sudden maybe this flower seems like oh it's just a lot of little flowers
but it was big before and this seemed quite vibrant perhaps
and now maybe it seems muted
so this happens automatically and all the time
and if i just brought this flower up and shared it with you and talked about how beautiful it was you probably would
have just been right along with me for the ride yeah and now
seeing these is it a little bit hard to be excited about this one
you know not because we don't want to be but it it's when we start to cluster and
compare the mind is automatically creating little hierarchies and valuing this more
than another and having these thoughts and oh well this one where you can see it's kind of all you know all of this
extra extra stuff so this is a an example of
that narration that happens in the mind and how much it can really change our
experience of the same thing one minute something can be
remarkable and then next not worthy of any attention at all just
because of a subtle shift or a comparison or a narration a way that we're talking about it all of a sudden
and describing in our own minds so
the opposite is just trying to be with a direct experience in this really simple way
that's why it's so good to just do the simple noting coolness
warmth sound instead of annoying car alarm
going on out there how dare they do that what's the sound pollutions going on right
it can just be sound or it can be this whole other thing
and if we can let it just be sound it there's probably a lot less suffering
certainly less aversion and if it was sound that i liked it might be that i'm not i'm not having as
much greed or desire right there we go high sound
sound arising
all right so um with this open awareness practice
let's see i'm just needing to orient to time here
okay let me talk about a few things first more things
so when you you know you've been coming
now most of you right everybody's been here
and you've been practicing and uh
do you feel more mindful than you did when you started yes does anybody feel like you're not sure
sometimes we feel less mindful and do you know why that might be
we're actually more aware of all the extra stuff that's happening
we're more aware of all this added chatter and stuff that's going on
and we're trying to be mindful and so we're struggling and or maybe we're judging and all this stuff makes it even
kind of we get to see what the mind the gymnastics the mind does when it's you
know comparing and wanting this instead of that
okay so
that's one part that we've been working on but trust me you are you're growing your strength
just coming here if you come here and you try and do the guided practices and you you're trying to track even if
you're not practicing formally during the week you are you are being changed
you are you are growing something inside of yourself because it's it's in us anyway this
capacity is innate we just need to grow strengthen it learn
it tune into it create more room for it and sometimes when we practice open
awareness it can feel like
you know we're i'll just tell you now so this there's a here's a great image for
this practice which is to imagine a small little cottage one room cottage
with a door some windows no fancy anything just a chair in the
middle nice cozy chair recliner a little bit not too cozy you fall asleep but you
know something solid and that's all that's in this room
and the practice of open awareness is like sitting down in that chair
and letting things come up like things come
up to the window like you see a bird flying by but you stay in the chair you don't get
up every time you see a bird out the window you stay in the chair and you're aware
of bird thought emotion might come to the door
and you stay in the chair and the emotion might come in and leave
but the idea is kind of letting things pop up visit come and go
while you stay in the chair does that make sense
so when we're doing this practice it might feel like there's just one thing after another after another
every window and doors being you know popped into and or it's just you know
it can feel like that and that's still the practice and it also can feel like
there's just this huge vast open space
and you know it's like it's just this is going
this is over here like it can feel like there's just lots of spaciousness not much is
happening can feel like you know one can feel like oh that's a squirrel oh there's a bird
oh it's a bluebird the other one can feel more like oh there's something flying
you know just it can be very different our experiences so it's not like there's
any right way to be aware with this practice
okay they're both fine
all right how do you feel about doing a little practice
so we'll start by finding an anchor we'll start by
getting grounded in our bodies and
that that will will give ourselves time right to just just settle let the mind
quiet slow down a little bit if it wants to
so taking your time and richard maybe the air conditioning you want to bump it
up a little bit so it's not too too cold yep i see a sweater going on
so yeah getting comfortable need your sweater on off you know
how do you want to be sitting now we're going to sit for about 15 minutes
so finding a posture that you feel comfortable that you can sustain feels awake
but settled like a chair where you can sit back in a
little bit you don't need to lean forward you can just sit back just a little
and let experience start to become more clear
and so whatever your anchor is if it's the breath if it's sound
if it's just gazing just getting connected to your anchor
just noticing if there's a tension any stress in the body
maybe even a holding and you might need to okay i gotta lift my shoulders up i need
to roll them back i need to take a few conscious deep
breaths we're gonna support ourselves in settling
that's part of the work of mindfulness it's a gift we're giving ourselves to
take the time feeling our feet
our bottoms is tuning in to what it's like to be
here right now in this body right here
is there ease and dis-ease and if there's dis-ease it's okay
give it permission to be here just take care of yourself
if there's ease can you rest into it a little bit
you might just do a little brief body scan
feeling into or breathing into places where you might be holding a little
invitationally invitationally inviting a softening or relaxing
if that part feels so inclined
taking as much time with each each place that you can encounter as needed
it can be helpful to just notice the forehead
jaw these are areas we hold a lot of tension
sometimes we just need a little bit of a awareness a little bit of an invitation
to like oh it's okay eyebrows you don't have to pinch together
well that's my efforting to try and be a mindful okay all right relax a little bit if you'd
like
and when you feel maybe settled enough maybe tune in to the experience of
hearing sounds
you might be able to hear the air conditioning a fan
a car driving by
you might be able to hear the sound of someone else breathing or even your own breath
sometimes there's the experience of even hearing our own heartbeats
just receiving whatever sounds arrive in your ears
sort of sitting back and allowing them to come to you
maybe bringing your awareness back to whatever your anchor is if it's not sound
attending to sensations
wherever it's easiest to stay present with them
maybe even just thinking about like three breaths in a row just this sort of
a a the breath feeling
or sensation or if you're using sight it might just
be you know the subtle moving of leaves
and if the timing feels right if you feel a little bit settled
you can let go of the deliberate energy of attending to your anchor
if the breathing is still prominent great that's fine
but it's the letting go of the deliberate focus
it's that sitting back a little bit into the chair
broadening the awareness a little bit to allow
the mind to just sort of witness the awareness to witness things as they arise
and pass away
whatever is most clear just allowing that to become
the primary focus
it might be a sensation or sound an attitude
there's no one kind of experience that's right or wrong
awareness can meet each experience as it arises
and mindfulness can know it directly in that simple way
we talked about directly knowing
and then as whatever primary experience is happening fades away
something else may become more prominent and you can allow your awareness to
receive that everything can be included
knowing it simply just allowing the awareness to be
easeful receptive that's sitting back in that chair that
feeling of resting back
and if you find yourself getting lost in thought or fantasy or planning
or maybe the mind becomes vague kind of sleepy
it can be helpful to return your attention back a little bit more effortful way to your
anchor just establishing a little more clarity a little more connection
or you might just try the mental noting just see if that helps with a little
more clarity
there's two minutes left in the practice and i just sometimes it's helpful to know oh
can i just sit back and relax for two minutes and allow or two breaths
and just allow the little things to appear and disappear being simple
allowing whatever arises to arise
everything can be welcomed and known
just as the night sky is spacious
the moon can appear stars come
awareness can be like that too a vast field holding it all
[Music]
so
i'd love to hear what happened inside your mind
anybody willing to share
hello good evening i just felt like my brain and my thoughts were just like scattered marbles and
just everything was everywhere and then just trying to anchor
you know go back to the breath to anchor everything but it was just so many things going on and
and then you feel kind of feel i was feeling kind of defeated by this practice not from what we've been doing
just just for myself like oh i let this get to me again or i'm letting other people's thoughts
invade my own and i don't know who to listen to or if i should it's just
so if i just feel so defeated right now no but it's okay it's okay
oh yeah thank you for sharing thank you for sharing who of us can't say we've been discouraged
um yeah i heard i heard there's a there's a
lot happening mentally a lot of mental activity um
sort of two paths of inquiry come up from you one is like that could just be a really full day
yeah it could be a lot going on and then um
what's our relationship to that what's our relationship to um the the mind being like a bubble machine
pop pop that's something else
something else that comes to mind to share with you is that as we um as we start to practice i heard
i recently heard this liken to like polishing a floor if you never mop the floor i don't know
if any of you have gone through phases like this i did when i was in college i didn't mop the floor very much
you don't even notice when you drop something on the floor you can't even see it but if you frequently
are polishing the floor you'll see like the tiniest thing so we decided so we as a group have
decided we're gonna sit down and be aware and be attentive of what's coming up it's like we're
polishing the floor and then we see so much more so much more
anyway my my heart is with you please um borrow some of my confidence if you need it
thank you very much sure
so the idea of mindfulness practice is something you
can't do wrong i think i can accept that but there's always this part of me that's
thinking well i'm not doing it wrong but you know i want to
i'm not getting as much of a fruitfulness out of it like you know i think it could be better it
could be worse so i see that judgment coming up a lot so it's like yeah you're not doing it
wrong but you're [Music] still kind of wasting your time here you know it's just like it just
this bypasses that and just i just start thinking like you know you know
i could be doing this more fruitfully and that's the thought coming up a lot
i got an idea great um
yeah my first impulse is to normalize the uh the i think part of what you're describing
like doubting doubting if the practice is working or like am i doing it right or like what am i getting
out of it it's so normal that there's like there's a
particular buddhist name for it it's like so it's so common to the meditative experience that
the name of doubt has been given to this this whole collection of like
oh maybe that maybe i didn't understand the instructions or um who are these people telling me about
this anyway and you know all of these um this sort of like
b-side track that's going on next door to attention that's telling us about how the practice isn't going right
um the you've got a couple ways that we can practice with this one i mean the first
one you're already so attentive to it like you you see that it's happening clearly i know it seems counterintuitive but
that's a moment of mindfulness it's like a moment of clear recognition
just like we were talking about a couple weeks ago could be interesting to could be interesting to like follow the
follow the path back and see if there's something in the body or some physical sensation or emotion
underneath and see if you can experience it on that level too
i think what you'll find over time is like the that b side track may still continue to
be there but you've also got some other information about
how things are developing or growing or changing yeah thank you
i'll just i'll just add the flower story right
so you you describe mindfulness a flower
can you just be with the experience without comparing it to the other flowers
right it's too much i'm not you know like i'm not getting it's not good enough
can it just be the flower that it is without all the added
does that make sense yes
so what i noticed was that
my body needed attention once i was quiet enough to listen yeah i
felt like my head had been scrunched up all day and my neck and my
my shoulders needed some some attention and i wouldn't have
noticed that unless i was sitting quietly and paying attention
that's what came up for me thank you thank you for sharing could i ask how did you know how to
what language did the body use to let you know uh
i felt this is going to sound strange i felt like i had a headache in my face
once i was quiet enough i think you said something about the forehead
and i realized that i feel like i was scrunching up my forehead all day and
then once i finally said you're scrunching up your forehead and you know
just try to breathe into it and relax then i realized oh and and your neck is
also a little tense so being quiet helped me to focus
enough to hear that my body needed some attention
yeah thank you so much some really really good uh clear attentiveness there and and in
addition to clear attendance like the instinct of care that is such a thing to appreciate
instinctive care for yourself thank you thank you
um so at the at the risk of having sort of a
bummer comment um what i noticed uh during this practice period
was the closer i got to like open awareness or what i'm assuming is open awareness
the more i also felt like a kind of rising level of fear just kind of like
what happens like when you have like open awareness or like what other things come up
so that was my experience
how did you work with that i just kind of
stuck with it i guess i i remember from like the uh
emotions um meeting we had it sometimes you can just kind of like stay with it like how does
it feel like what are the like i don't know contours of it look at that helps but
fear is so powerful right and um
we just it's almost like we're afraid of fear itself so it can
it can grow quickly in our our minds you know
so um i i really still like that idea of
having the what are the name of those shoes with the big thick soles
no um doc martin doc martin oh yeah yeah you know like you know just remembering
that awareness is like the doc martens and if we stay grounded you know that
the electricity of fear doesn't have to kind of keep pulsing through us
you know and it sounds very skillful to direct your awareness toward the sensations
because it's so much of the what feeds fear is the story
you know that what we're imagining oh no and uh
so it sounds like you worked with that really skillfully and um it's also common for fear to come up
just to say it's not you know like it's a good thing to start to practice
with
any i don't know if there's anyone on youtube writing in comments richard no okay
all right anyone else want to share anything or
we're good to move on great
so i one of the things i appreciate about
having time for reports and q a is that we get to share with each other this whole array of experiences
it's like uh it can really at any given time it can seem like a wildly different experience it's happening
this person's sitting next to me but something that it highlights or emphasizes to me is
um sometimes our attention is directed to an emotion sometimes it's directed to a thought
sometimes to the breathing sometimes to the body directly the scope is so broad
and when we're practicing this open awareness practice you know sometimes it feels like we can
get a little scattered and as tanya was saying we come back to the anchor come back to the anchor
steady ourselves center ourselves calm ourselves
and when we think about extending the practice further same sort of motion applies
the the meditation seat can be our anchor
it's the place we come back to steady ourselves settle ourselves
and the line between the edge of your meditation say matt if you're on a mat or a chair
and the rest of your life it's pretty arbitrary isn't it
pretty arbitrary uh the the line between meditation
and applying clear attention in the rest of our lives it's pretty fuzzy it's
pretty fuzzy what this opens up is that we can open up we can open our practice we can extend
it we can move it into the rest of our lives really common for uh people starting to meditate to
ask the question okay kind of getting getting a hang of this meditation thing maybe
what about the rest of my life so just a few a few thoughts about
practicing in daily life first thing i'd like to share is that um
in the spirit of softening the the perceived boundary between your meditation seat and the rest of your life
is that your mind and your body go with you wherever you go when you're seated you're practicing
with your mind and body it's that same mind and body in a manner of speaking
in another buddhist manner of speaking we might say it's a totally different mind and body every moment
but the same mind and body gets up off the cushion and extends the practice
i think what's important here to emphasize when we're on the cushion so to speak
cultivating attention cultivating clarity and these other wholesome qualities
and those same qualities don't disappear when you stand up we can keep practicing these same
same qualities of clear attention open-heartedness letting go
steadiness kindness
yeah very commonly meditation is associated with sitting it's like the icon the icon of
meditation as a silhouette of a meditating figure
um [Music] and there are good reasons that meditation is associated with sitting
like that we we've seen over the course of these weeks like how
stillness cultivates our attention so
strong i think that's like a strong endorsement for seated meditation practice or still
meditation practice and
the practice extends to all we call four four noble postures
sitting standing walking
lying down um
to give you something of the flavor of like how old this notion is of all the different activities you can include and
mindfulness practice there's this text that that's something like the the foundational instructions
for uh insight insight practices that we've been doing and there's a section called the section
on full awareness and it says something like
practitioner acts in full awareness when going forward and returning
acts in full awareness when looking ahead and looking away
acts in full awareness when flexing and extending the limbs
acts in full awareness when wearing robes carrying the robin bowl
or eating drinking consuming food and tasting
acts in full awareness when defecating and urinating acts in full awareness when walking standing sitting falling
asleep waking up talking and keeping silent
i wonder if we left anything out is there anything we left out
surely something but yeah i hope i hope you can get a sense of like
the scope we can apply it we can apply this mindfulness practice
everywhere so some of the ways that we start to work that skill
it's like as we're uh as we've been talking about one of the central metaphors for these weeks is
this notion of concentric breathing in the middle body emotions
thinking open awareness if we extend further
some of the things that can be really helpful is uh trying out little by little
if we uh if we have the uh have the idea okay now this today i'm gonna be completely mindful from the time i wake
up to the time i go to sleep and i'm not gonna miss a moment i'm probably gonna maybe get frustrated if that's my karma
or disappointed if that's my karma or my tendency
but start small one of the ways that when i was living in monasteries one of the ways that this
really worked well was that there's a right after right after meditation often there is a very
short period of silent cleaning it doesn't matter what the activity is it could be cleaning that's so great for
mindfulness but the idea of getting up off the meditation cushion
and rather than going straight to the phone or straight to a conversation do something silent
with your body and be a body be a body doing an activity and there's a way that that can help
bridge stillness and activity another way to do extend mindfulness
from the cushion into daily life have some other activities that are particular throughout your day that
remind you to be mindful um one thing that i will do is
before i cross a threshold in a door oftentimes i will i'll pause just for a second and feel
it's a moment to check in with my body and feel how i am in this room and then i step through and i feel myself feel
again so i get two check-ins back-to-back and there's something about something
about that that works for me you might have other cues like you could
set a timer to go off at random times throughout your day if you want to do that just a pause and have a brief moment of
mindfulness take not han of course is well known for
for um talking about the the practice of mindfulness while washing dishes
there's so much so much tactile data to sink into
and be there with the warmth and the suds and the dishes he used to say just do the dishes to do
the dishes instead instead of taking that time to plan or
think about something else just be there i think in a nutshell when it comes to
finding little ways to practice in daily life we can do a little better than than the
old slogan of be here now finding tiny moments to be here now in
your day
so the noble postures
sitting standing lying down i'm going to get up off the cushion and
where i'm going to demonstrate walking meditation here in a moment
the reason why we want to introduce walking is that um maybe you've noticed as we as we've gone
along how the continuity how the the momentum of the tension sort of builds
you might notice this in a sitting it can be a nice thing to do if you're looking for ways to
help establish your practice further you're sort of inspired by what we've been doing here one of the things you can do is set aside some time to do a
period of sitting followed by a period of walking followed by a period of sitting if he
wanted to do that but walking meditation bringing
bringing this full attention and awareness to the moving body in the same way that we do when we're on
the cushion um i find i find actually sometimes i get
even more concentrated doing walking meditation than i do with seated meditation
something about the rhythm of the movement keeps me here the sensations that i'm that i'm tuning
into um
walking meditation can also be useful to balance our energy there might be times where it's hard to meditate more
really sleepy walking meditation can be a nice alternative
to bring up the energy a little bit help balance i also find it's a really useful
transition practice sometimes i'll just do maybe five minutes of walking before my seated
meditation and there's a way that um there's a way that for me if especially
if my mind is busy say the at the end of the day my mind will take to walking meditation
more easily for a few minutes and that can be like a way to coast into sitting practice after settling
just some thoughts about that uh so let me show you how we do it in
this in this tradition luckily i have a walking meditation path outlined in blue right here on the floor
you'll see this
yeah pretty simple what you want to do
choose your path ideally maybe 30ish steps at least 10 or 30 feet at
least 10 steps and i'll start on one end
and i'll pause and set up my posture see if i'm aligned i'm steady
take a few deep breaths and let myself know oh here i am i'm here i'm standing
and then it's simple it's just as simple as it sounds
once the attention is established in the body beginning to walk
and we're not going anywhere can be little steps some people take
really little steps some people take a longer step
the pace can vary find the pace the backup
find the pace that encourages the feeling of ease for you
for now and that will change interesting thing is the mind gets more concentrated sometimes the body tends to
get smaller or like the steps get smaller and slower
so start at one end do this thing that this thing that is probably common to many of our day which
is walking just attending to the body as the anchor
once the attention is in the body let this let the let the sensations of the feet and the legs be the anchor
and then we meditate in just the same way that we have been if something more compelling comes up and draws the
attention away you can pause attend to that thing
feeling emotion thought and then when that's finished come back to your anchor which is the walking body
a couple more things about the form so walking along nice and easy come to the
end of your walking path just pause stop i turn around
pause i'm taking ev the pauses i'm taking every opportunity to come back into my
body because uh there's a there's a way that the attention can drift
you know walking is so commonplace for us and often it
when i get to the end of the path and i pause it brings me right back yeah simple enough so
turn walk back at the pace of ease
and again some people do hands in pockets some cross their arms or behind the back anything
works think that may be all i wanted to say about how to walk
yeah
sure
thank you how's the volume is that okay great
how about how about now great
okay so we'll have some time uh if there are any questions about walking practice
we will have time for that right at the end but i want to i want to carry on with this idea of um
a question that a lot of us come may be coming up for a lot of us as we come to the close of the these five
weeks what now where do we go from here um
yeah maybe maybe actually what's coming up in my heart is to pause and appreciate that
uh that we have come to this point in the in the in the class the course together
it feels really good i feel like we've done a lot of wholesome activity together wow i'm appreciative for the
the attention and the sincerity and the the work that's gone into it and my
my hope is that something useful has come into your life
as a result whether that's meditation or you found something useful that you heard that is
uh framed your experience in a way that you appreciate
so from i mean taking that taking that that wholesome wholesome sense
what do we want to grow with it so some of the some of the ways we can grow some of the ways we can grow this
where do we go from here um is we have so many activities at imc
so many opportunities for practice there are these um
we're all pretty savvy online i imagine and can see insight meditationcenter.org
for the full array but some things i want to highlight there's the
sunday morning talk it's a sit and a talk it's a little bit longer than we've been sitting here
35 minutes and then then a dharma talk something i like about these is
community they're available online but they're also available here and many of us know
the benefit of being together sitting together talking together plus the the informal things
that happen after monday nights longer sitting
probably silent 45 minutes sitting
it seems like a really long time when i say it something i found myself saying
frequently recently is that i remember it took me a long time before i could even before i could sit 20 minutes and
that felt like a really big milestone and 45 minutes felt like no way no way ever
but just little by little you know a couple minutes at a time yeah
so the difference sits sunday and monday um some of you may be familiar with the
the sittings that are happening on youtube in the mornings yeah gil gil does a lot of them uh 7am
7am sitting 7 30 talk it's usually like a 12 or 15 minute talk and it's usually on
a theme for the week these are so good great way to start the day i
find myself doing it around the time that i'm making breakfast
there's an afternoon evening sitting on usually on zoom happy hour
loving kindness practice or brahma-vihara practice he's like so such nourishing heart
practices in the spirit of sangha or in the spirit
of community something i want to say is you'll notice on the website that there are a number of groups
i love the way that that the mindfulness communities sort of like weave into
weave into these like subgroups and then weave into each other grow and shrink
but there's there's any number from support groups to affinity groups
of other types uh buddhism in the 12 steps that happens on sunday nights
there's an lgbtqia group that meets um
there's a support group for folks who are practicing with life-threatening or chronic illness
so there may be something you don't expect that's available online so
check out the list uh oh the 20s and 30s group at home in
the world that meets on sundays and zoom with max
so where to go from here in addition to these like one-off events and community
something we've emphasized a lot already is the the power of daily practice
the the wholesome power of daily practice if you've got three minutes
if you have five minutes 10 minutes 15 minutes this is a wholesome thing to do
i had a friend who was um he had played the guitar for many years he was a fabulous guitar player and he
said he had a commitment i asked him how did you do this how did you grow so much
skill on the guitar he's like every day didn't matter if i if it was only two minutes i picked it up i put it
in my hand and over over the years i became became a
skilled guitarist i think we can do the same thing in meditation i find it's helpful to have a consistent
sort of schedule for myself so i don't always have to wonder where is this going to fit so having a 40-minute sit such-and-time
in the morning or maybe you're an evening person
something that daily practice does is helps to generate mindfulness of course
and it also helps to develop our powers of concentration and you'll find as the as concentration
and mindfulness grow together then all sorts of openings of the heart start can start to happen all sorts of
wholesome letting go can happen and uh i
i'm sure tanya used this analogy of concentration as like the tripod
that allows the telescope of mindfulness to see clearly the night sky they work really well really well
together to reveal what what's actually happening here
along with daily practice you can start to look toward retreats of all lengths we do a half day
retreat in the mornings on wednesdays day longs are often offered tanya will be offering one the
beginning of september september 10th september 10th and then we'll do another one on the first of october
um and then from there it just grows uh four day retreats oh
there's a whole retreat center associated with the imc called irc insight retreat center near scotts
valley retreats in length from four days to now three weeks
can be quite a quite a powerful experience to
dedicate your time to mindfulness practice i find even
even just the benefit of setting setting aside most most or all of my normal
concerns for a week is so nourishing to the system
because we we don't write we don't read we put away our phones and
we dedicate our dedicate ourselves to being attentive as much as we can just little by little
so there's all that if you like this series format tanya's
about to launch another one called establishing a practice aptly which begins on next thursday
you don't even have to change your schedule
and then the last thing i'll say is there's um it's a literature counter this is what i'm calling it
along the back here the flyers and events uh you'll find these online if
you're listening on youtube also here uh in the building section for books that are published
through the sati center in the corner here that are offered freely and then by the door one
of my go-tos that i go back come back to again and again is gil's collection of essays the issue at hand
also available online too so i hope that gave you
maybe more than enough as far as places you can go places you can go routes you can take to
deepen the practice from here it probably goes without saying that
i think this is a really worthwhile experience in itself
and a um it's a practice that can that opens up all sorts of
beautiful qualities of the heart so i i wish that
we've got some time now for for questions if you want to ask anything about walking or if you have specific
context about like oh my life is like this what can i do to deepen my practice now
or anything else that's coming up across the whole course and let me give you this mic back
oh sure here i'll turn this on
so um i procrastinate like a lot of people do and i am noticing this past month doing
this that um i'll talk about today i um
you know i took the day off from work today because i wanted to iron out a bunch of stuff for you know
a job transition and i just didn't i just wanted to focus on that and i was so unproductive today until like the
last hour before this started and then i think in like panicked focus i got it done
but i just couldn't wait to come here like i just there's more i need to do when i get home but i'm just like i just want to get here and you know not have
to do this and i get to sit and do nothing isn't this great you know and so um
yeah i just was wondering if what you all could speak to that because i think
there's you got there's stuff you got to get done and you just got to do it and you know i i can kind of see
myself using this as a excuse to avoid as well
could i defer to you sure great uh one thought that came up is um
you could alternate sitting and doing so uh you know if you enjoy coming and
doing nothing right or being the the doing of awareness
um you know you could make a bargain with yourself that if you work for half an hour you can sit for
you know and alternate in your life to give yourself maybe a little bit of a
more of a sip experience of getting things done with lots of little
breaks um does that feel like anything within
reach or not at all it's okay if it's not
i don't know i think but i making a deal with myself that might be
i might try that i don't know yet the other thing is um you know you really can practice while
you're doing and that feeling of
for me when i can just sort of settle in right and be
uh with my breath and my experience there's something i don't know really peaceful
uh soothing pleasant joyful for me about it but actually if we um
[Music] there are lots of things we can do that way in our life if we it's it's a it's
how we're doing it it's the polishing the floor with care
sorting the papers with care like oh noticing how it feels smells
you know just being present for it i think a lot of it a lot of
we kind of disconnect with our to-do's we just want them to be done but
what does that really mean what are we disconnecting from that we could stay close to
so i'm offering also just a whole nother approach to
to doing life i guess so
now do you want to say anything else you have another idea that sounds great relationship to what's happening
thank you oh i had another idea
so um another thing you can do is um you you can look at speaking of
relationship to your experience like okay i oh i don't want to do this
i'm having a lot of resistance and you can kind of start to be mindful
of the resistance and get more curious about that what is it about it and start to kind of
watch the filters and the mind and the associations and the
wanting to escape if that's what's coming up so
kind of being more curious about why why don't i want to do things
why do i want to procrastinate what is that about for me so like just but you got to watch it's not like a thinking
exercise it's a it's an observing exercise so aversion desire
escaping you know looking at that
can you go into more of the difference between sure observing the thinking
sure okay i'll make something up here
so it's you know nine o'clock this morning i've taken the day off work
i've got my list of things that i need to do
and i find myself on the computer watching youtube videos
and um an hour and a half goes by
and i kind of notice what time it is and i'm a little bit hungry
and i get up go get something to eat come back go right back to youtube but then you know let's say 12 o'clock
i'm starting to feel the pit in my stomach starting to feel sick like
i have all this stuff i have to do so that at that moment it kind of gets more
pronounced right i'm not in the distraction but i'm in between and i can say okay this is uncomfortable
i i feel uncomfortable what's going on for me um
and just simply noting it sometimes like yeah i guess i'm
escaping but is it helping i actually don't feel that great right
now um i feel like i need to do this stuff but
i don't want to do it just sort of like i'm just sort of naming okay there's a lot of like
there's a lot of energy and avoiding actually i'm trying to avoid but i'm it's not very pleasant
and kind of get really clear i could go back
to the youtube i could go back to the computer and do more of this
or i could decide to see what happens if i go clean the bathroom
and stein try and just do one thing and see how i feel afterwards right and practice
kind of working with myself in this way so i don't know if that was a good enough
example okay great great so that you know one of the classes i'll
be teaching at some point won't be for a while but is the five hindrances we talked about doubt which
you brought up aversion not liking not wanting greed wanting desiring
restlessness and worry where you know there's the mind is spinning and we can't be still
sloth and torpor sleepy no energy in the body mind is diffused
these are five hindrances that are very common in our practice they hinder our practice
normal human experiences been around since the time well before the time of the buddha i'm quite sure
so it's also helpful to notice what's going on which of these hindrances is
present and then you know if you see oh it's a lot of
aversion okay so how do i turn that around instead of
putting all my energy into not liking something how can i shift
right what's the antidote if i've got a lot of greed and i want a lot of pleasure
you know pursuing the pleasure it's helpful to notice that well i've
got a lot of greed around watching and doing the computer but it's actually not pleasant how it's feeling right now
and so noticing that that there's unpleasant with that so soft and torpor it's
opening the windows making it cold standing up you know doing the opposite of the energy that's happening in the
mind and body so there you go hey thank you yeah
this may be our this may be our last one how do you like calm yourself
in the midst of things like just to remember especially if something's really feeling chaotic like what do you
say like i know gil said i noticed that i'm feeling
like that just just continue to do that but then i then i find that my emotions
like i feel like i'm suppressing them because i'm trying and so oh
oh i see so you you um you're feeling you're feeling an emotion
there's a lot going on you you use that sort of sentence stem i notice i feel
fill in the blank and then there's this there's this second thing that comes in which is
um [Music] sort of like judgment that you used the tool
it's like you you're suppressing suppressing the feeling by by looking at it or like me pretending
to be mindful like i'm i'm aware that i'm feeling frustrated so let me try not
to be frustrated and then something happens and then i just
double over and then
but then it's maybe it's more so my response and my reactivity to things
and it's something that i need to be more mindful of and just being still though in here was helpful because
you're right the work day was crazy and yeah just you know but thank you both tonya koto
thank you so much yeah yeah um
just to pause for a second is there anything you anything you would feel okay sharing about what's happening in your body
right now oh maybe a bit of trepidation thinking about tomorrow
all the all my actions of today and what i did prior to
i just it's just building yeah it sounds like it sounds like that was a thought
anything in your body that's going along with those thoughts oh or anything you're feeling in your body now i can't really say i can't
really identify oh i it's just i feel very relaxed though just sitting
here it's just the mind that's racing oh oh i wonder i wonder how possible it might be for
the relaxation the that sensation to be a little more in the foreground and
let the mind have its have its space in the background is that is that a possibility
also like transferring my focus oh because it's like things become
what you focus on it becomes what you i see i see yeah
oh yeah okay maybe something so simple and then as the maybe this would be the
last thing i'll say if that's all right and if there's if there are more questions or more comments we can talk after
something to keep in mind as we go along with the practice is that the uh
the effect that we're expecting uh it can really easily flip over into a
demand where um where i end up i've had this happen before where i i suspect i'm like
okay i'm i'm frustrated i'm gonna watch my breath for two minutes and that's gonna calm me down and that's the deal that i've just
made with myself and then my frustration doesn't cooperate with me and i do my i do the practice
and actually i feel the same i feel the same so something has gone wrong and clearly i
did it um it's simply the fact that the
the the web of conditions that's making up the current state is so dynamic
that we we can't like flip it off with a switch let's say but we can feed something wholesome into the system
that over time is nourishing but but we're not we're not we're not 100 in
control so just some things to to keep in mind as as you go along
if it's unpleasant it doesn't mean that anything has gone wrong
okay thank you so much that was very helpful thank you i really appreciated you being here these weeks
so it's time for us to close i think i will
i'm so glad i gave you a long appreciation earlier because that's what i'm feeling [Laughter]
um yeah full heart
full heart deep appreciation um it's a wonder it's a wonder that we do
these things together and it's a wonder that everything that imc does is done is offered completely
freely completely where does that happen um
if you feel like you had got some benefit from this from this practice and you feel inspired in the direction
of the deep joy of generosity there are ways to do that the kiosk over there and
a place to offer donations over there but let's um let's keep this field of like freely
given freely given teaching freely given field of generosity let's
uh let's keep that and nourish that i'm i'm really happy is there anything
you would like to um just there's a practice of um
dedicating the merit that maybe would be nice to share
those practices that you know whatever benefit that we this is out of the
generosity spirit whatever benefit we got from a coming here
may that benefit be shared with others so as each of you leave here tonight and
you encounter others in your life maybe you're leaving a little bit calmer
a little bit more present and you can share that with somebody
and then it's a gift that's been given from you to them and then hopefully they can give it to somebody else and
hopefully it gets spread to all beings everywhere
so thank you thank you for your time and kindness and
willingness to share
can i ring a bell yeah i think we need to we should [Music]
thanks everyone
you