so hello and welcome everyone good to see you
good to be with you especially nice to see you as last time um
for those of you who are present on monday um internet was down where i live and
and and neil kindly opened the room and facilitated and i called in i was on the phone so it was kind of fun
not to see you but uh but to lead and practice together nevertheless that was
that was fun and interesting
ah so so today is particularly nice to see you
and it was nice to just be with you and actually that was quite fun too i was uh
i'll share with you that i was uh because i had to keep my phone plugged in and also keep it close to the outside
so that the few bars i have with the reception anyway so it was was interesting set up for me but also in a
minute that i was able to lie down on my back and and guide you whatever while i was lying um down which was
uh which is a nice way to practice especially metta is you're not going to fall asleep there's just a sense of
nourishing to the lie down practice i don't get to do that when i'm sitting
here in my chair and then guiding but so that was a gift in disguise so i do
welcome you to try the lying posture especially if you're not sleepy can can
open things up for you perhaps so so so for today's practice um
[Music] you like to lead us in just this simple session of meta i
always say it's a simple session of meta but you know there are always surprises
maybe maybe having talked about the lying posture again if you're not going to
fall asleep maybe i will invite you today to explore
the lying posture um yeah why not
why not let's let's do that and if you're sleepy then and
you can continue to sit or even stand but maybe i will i'll invite you to explore that and at any point
during the guided meditation if you're feeling sleepy it's okay to open your eyes
yeah maybe that's what i'll talk about today okay so so
lying down posture that's it so lying down posture so um
the buddha taught four postures from meditation
sitting standing lying down and walking
and it so happens that in the west for our western minds especially we
privilege to pre we privilege the sitting posture as
as that's how we're gonna get enlightened that's where it's at whereas actually
all the postures they're wonderful posture there's an awakening is possible in each
and every one of them and um and personally i've done
a lot of my practice a lot of my quote-unquote serious practice you know
three months of silent meditation retreat uh most of it lying down on my back i've
had a lot of back issues a lot of physical issues pain etc so
and yet what i discovered was that actually um the lying down posture
was a gift it's so much easier to relax and release the body
the tightness the holding that that
rises in the body and and when the mind the body is relaxed
released the mind can relax and release
so especially if you haven't lied down before and if you've thought about it as a lesser
um posture i really encourage you to try it
out give it a chance um as i said i've done a lot of my practice
especially the jhana practice the concentrations and states of some samadhi
uh that way so i still do so maybe in maybe the title of today's meta
practices in praise of the lying posture is in praise of the lying posture
it can also be very um comforting and very soothing and very
appropriate for meta practice because sometimes when we're practicing meta
and compassion practice karuna practice
hurt me there's a body that's hurting so imagine if you have back pain and
you're sitting and you're trying to have you know trying to do compassion practice meant to practice for your for
yourself well hello the first the first thing to do is to actually
physically have compassion for yourself and the way to have compassion is to lie down to
take care of the body to to not be let it be in such a state of of pain
so so a couple of things i want to say about the lying
posture one is that um [Music] both in praise of it that the the body
can be more relaxed at ease and the mind can be at ease
there could be a lot of care and in fact you can there is a beauty in it because we can
think that oh um sleepiness can arise or maybe because it's so similar to lying
in bed that i can fall asleep but at the same time maybe cultivating the sense of kindness towards oneself
it can become more accessible when you're lying in bed at night going to sleep
actually it becomes your default and and it's interesting i'll share with you that for me it's become the default
whenever i lie in bed at night the the words that go through our mind my mind are safe
happy healthy ease they just get evoked it just comes like oh yeah this is this
tape or rather now it is i should say this mp3 that just keeps playing in the background
so so that can actually be a gift that it becomes more readily available
this meta when you're lying down in bed and maybe the times that you're sick instead of
kicking yourself oh you're sick there all these things you need to get done and you're not getting them down it's like oh
sweetheart may you be well maybe happy so it could be accessible in
those times maybe also say something about um
if you notice and i'll give much more guidance of course as we're going through it but
but some people um [Music] decide to lie on their side for some
people that maybe it's not the way they sleep so it's not they don't fall asleep but as readily
but also uh another thing you can do is to have your arm if you're lying down say if i'm however long
you can have your arm at your elbow bent at 90 degree angle so that if you fall
asleep you will fall down and and wake you up or you can be all the way straight up and if you fall asleep
you will fall down and wake you up so those are a couple of things that people can do with the lying down meditation to
support themselves so so with all of that i think i've said plenty to set the stage so let's
let's get ready so if you want to try to lying down meditation you're welcome to try it now you can
turn off your camera if you want or let it be on doesn't matter it's all good
um and i invite you to give it a try
so [Music]
lying down lying down lying down
letting this whole body rest on the earth
feeling the entire underside of your body connected to tears
release thing your feet yourself feel the contact point of the
feet and the ear
releasing the legs
your bottom [Music] your back
and neck and shoulders your head
your hands could be resting on your belly or on your side or one of them could be straight up
or bent at the elbow
if this posture isn't familiar to you [Music]
bring awareness bring awareness to all the cells
even if it's familiar regardless
bring awareness to all the muscles
releasing the muscles
release release release
now let the breath let the breath move through received in the abdomen
expanding contracting and releasing the body more
slowing down posture as a sign of care as a sign of meta
the sign of care for this body that is yours
there is restlessness the lying down posture can be grounding
can ground a whole body connected to deer
if there is pain fatigue present
can be restorative this lying down posture
meditation is a practice of the mind
let the mind be alert let the mind be alert
the mind can be upright the body can be
horizontal
maybe putting a hand in your heart center you're lying down or sitting
and feeling sense of care for this body
this body that works so hard
this body that is you and not you it's yours and yet it doesn't so much
belong to you
it's kind of a mystery or relationship to this body
that we take to be me and mine as if it were a beloved other in this
body wishing it well
wishing this body well especially in this expression of
lying down posture sitting posture
may this body be safe fully knowing that
complete safety clinging to the idea of safety is not
possible but yet we wish it as a gift
for ourselves
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy may my life flow with ease
just offering these wishes simple expressions of our goodwill towards
ourselves our friendliness towards ourselves
simple meta
may i be safe from inner and outer arm
may i be happy and have joy in my heart
and may my life flow with ease
you're saying the phrases for yourself doesn't quite connect
see if you can perhaps shift perspective and say may this being who is me
this being who is me be safe
or maybe wishing it from the perspective who from the perspective of someone who loves you
cares for you or who has loved you maybe a grandparent
or a compassionate being
or kanye or any other archetype
may this being may this being who's me
be safe
just receiving just receiving safe
happy
healthy these
in order to better connect with these wishes for yourself if you like you can see yourself maybe you have four
different tabloids the tableaus may be one with safety
seeing yourself in a safe environment
may i be safer
may i be happy seeing yourself happy with joy
laughing doing what you loved
people care about
may i be healthy seeing yourself healthy
maybe outdoors maybe doing [Music] some activity you love to do
signifies health for you
may my life know these may i take my oh take care of myself happily
again some image some vision signifies
ease for you ease in your life maybe lying in a hammock
feeling comfortable all is right in the world it's all okay
with each tableau saying the phrases
safe happy
healthy ease
filling our own cup so we don't need
our cup to be filled by others filling our own cup with care with
mental
as we bring this practice period to a close
offering kindness to whatever rose or did not arise
but let this be a moment of cultivating kindness meant to yourself
especially if their judgments arising oh you were distracted you're sleepy
it's okay dear you did your best
let it go let it go moment of kindness
and trusting there is kindness cultivated goodness nourished
and together we share we give our goodness our song
of peace to all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere
including ourselves be safe
happy healthy and happies may all beings everywhere
including ourselves be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have some time for reflections comments questions
and you can raise your zoom hand if it's your physical hand i may not see you
if you type it in chat if you type it just to me it'll be private i won't read
your name and if it's time to everyone it'll be public
thank you for your good wishes the person who sent me the chat thank you
i appreciate it so what did you notice
offering your
your aha moments your challenges maybe something that opened up as a gift to
others maybe for those who tried lying down or maybe you didn't try lying down
specifically or anything else
any reflections
as a gift to others
for those who might have tried the lying down meditation did you notice anything different
ah chinese says good way to re-enter the world being in hospital after being in
hospital welcome back ginny welcome back [Music]
welcome back glad you're back with us may you be healthy and well
[Music]
yeah lie down meditation has many gifts
another reflection this one privately i look forward to waking up every night and doing method
practice yay yes exactly yay
that's what i do if i wake up in the middle of the night especially in the middle of the night
this this body this being needs it's a lot of meta at that point for
whatever reason you've woken up yeah so great thank you for that reflection
very wise
reflection on on youtube thank you you guided me to ease you are most welcome
thank you for your practice it's more appreciation also showing up on
on youtube from our friends thank you for joining us on youtube
community
met is such a soothing balm for the
heart both energizing soothing
whatever you need it to be marianne says thank you for the best
part of my day oh thank you marianne
what a gift what a gift you give to yourself and you give to everyone else marianne was here showing up
this meant this happy hour would be very different if i was just the only one showing up here
so thank you for being here and practicing
so you aren't yes
yeah it's another comment that one of you finds
listening to dharma talk while doing yoga helpful to stretch the body and stretch the mind at the same time taking
care of the body and taking care of mine that's sweet
so if there aren't any more reflections then maybe we'll save time for
reflections at the end so i invite all of us invite us to
to practice in small groups and
in small groups of roughly size three just offering one nugget about your your
own practice what was this like for you just lying down or choosing not to lie down
and um each person will offer one nugget and then the other person another nugget and
then another nugget just speaking from your own experience not acting as a facilitator
and if your turn comes and you want to say pass that's perfectly fine you can just hold silent space with meta with
kindness for yourself for others um nothing needs to be said it's all
okay it's just showing up showing up with presence and kindness what is it like to
be in community with presence and kindness so that's the invitation so with that
i will create the rooms and invite you to be kind
kind to yourself kind to others and
here we go opening them up enjoy time with community
okay the rooms are now closed everybody is back welcome back everyone
so we have a few minutes for any request questions
comments there's one comment on youtube thanks for bent elbow idea
i easily fall asleep yay so that that worked for someone i'm glad to hear that
so so many things that came up for you today
okay catherine
um i did kind of drop into sleepiness but what i
what i felt in that state was that i was in a hypnagogic state where i was
really processing like stuff that's been going on and it and i rem it it reflected back to me the need
that i have to to take a moment like that during the day so that i can do a little bit of that
processing it's really really helpful for me and i sleep way better at night when i do that um
so it felt like a really helpful and i have been wound up today
i was like oh yeah like because in our culture it's not like cool to just be like i want to go take a
nap in the middle of a weekday but it should be cool because it's the coolest
thing and i'm bringing it actually is yeah yeah i'm so glad you said this katherine
that's lovely that as you're mindful aware aware and that's another
thing i want to bring bring in so so glad you brought this in so with down meditation
it's also okay if sleepiness comes in becomes a different kind of training so we get to
actually work with sleepiness as you said with the hypnagogics because we're aware or where okay where or where
and then we can decide okay hypnagogic state then you can go multiple places
one place is just as you said oh yes stay with the hypnagogic state okay
yeah we up that's what's happening i'm about to fall asleep and sometimes actually it's wise to decide to fall
asleep and not to fight it because a lot of times we we you know we're meditating
all of us have had this experience like you're fighting you're fighting you're neither sleeping you're near your norm
are you meditating it's just a mess it's like you're right it's just like it's a fight it's like a whole 30 minutes of
conflict so if you actually if you're aware and mindful and and let yourself fall asleep
for a minute for a few seconds for a minute like yes and then you can actually be mindful the
moment the second you wake up mindfulness can be present and it can be so refreshing that 30 second one minute
nap is more refreshing than like hours and i say here yes yes you're you're nodding so you know
it's and there's a different relationship to sleepiness to rest hypno it's like awareness awareness awareness
awareness it's just it's lovely instead of it being an enemy so thank you so much for bringing that in and then also
sometimes if it seems like okay um hypnotically no today i'm going to open my eyes i'm going to stand up move and
this is where i need to go to then one can make a decision at that point but then you have choice right it's
so it's beautiful thanks so much for bringing that in catherine so delighted that's great
jamie i see your hand yeah hi nicky thank you for that that
was wonderful i i had this really really sent
you're caught up
yeah now we can hear you we lost you for like that sentence well um the tableaus you know thinking of of
these little you know scenes was uh that was that was really pretty rich um but it you know kind of put me in
karuna for a minute um i i thought to myself that all the all the scenes of of
happiness were from a long time ago and i thought gosh i guess i haven't been that happy
in a while and and so i did a little you know it's okay dear i know that can be hard
and and after that i started thinking all these wonderful happy moments from like last
week it took was a moment of corona oh oh
i'm so touched thank you thank you for sharing that jamie that is
so sweet oh that touches my heart all it took was a moment of karuna a
moment of compassion to open the heart to appreciating goodness
present here beautiful beautiful profound thank you yeah
and deborah says thanks for the permission to do this and reframing how to do meditation the right way yes
they're right i love that so so thank you all thank you all
um let's see one more comment here from pat on youtube thanks
for the discussion of near sleep states i've been wondering about dreams yeah there's more we can talk about dreams
about dream yoga and and actually lucid dreaming which is
being aware and mindful and conscious while we are dreaming but anyway
we'll save that so this has been rich thank you so much for your practice thank you
to all of you every single one of you for your own sake for the sake of all beings whose lives yours touches
directly and indirectly may all beings be safe may all beings be free including
ourselves [Music]
thank you