hello greetings friends greetings hello wherever you are in the world
lovely to be with you in this moment and um to practice together it's so lovely to see all the hellos
and greetings all these expressions of metta people are expressing from around the
world it's very sweet very sweet warms my heart this morning here
i'm nikki margofouri in mountain view california on seated oloneyland a few
miles away from imc the virtual background of imc so we feel
we're at home so today speaking of being at home
we continue our exploration of the mind's body not just the body as
we take it to be this fathom-long body
but the mind's body the way that
this physicality this experience of
having a physicality in the world or a perception of a body
is impacted by the way we pay attention
and vice versa the way this mind's body or energy body
impact supports our awakening
especially if you tend to always do the same thing or pay
attention the same way to your breath to your body these sessions are especially for you
to explore to open up different pathways different ways different impacts
so so today in the guided meditation
um i'll intro i'll invite us to explore
the impact of
attending to the breath being mindful of the breath in different places the difference
between paying attention to the breath in the abdomen the chest the nostrils the whole body
these all have different impacts and at different times different
practitioners would be invited to explore so [Music]
let's um [Music] let's explore together and
all you need is sense of interest curiosity
for your own mind body laboratory so here we
go so let us settle let us arrive
finding our seat first and foremost
feeling our sit bones
feeling ourselves connected to the earth
sensing feeling your feet on the earth
your legs
your bottom on the cushion lower legs let them land let them be released
connected connected to the earth a stable base
stable base
turning your attention your awareness intentionally to the sensations of
contact filling out filling out your legs your
feet your sit bones your bottom
relaxing the upper body releasing the upper body
the jaw forehead
neck and shoulders
chest abdomen arms and hands
and noticing noting turning the awareness fully
wholeheartedly to the lower abdomen to receive the breath
the breath is being breathed on its own
so no need to make it into a project you don't have to breathe intentionally
it's already happening it's already happening
so all the doing that we do if there is any doing
is to receive is to receive with our awareness
the breath
in the abdomen it's just turning adverting our
attention
a gift is given every moment this breath
this gift that keeps us alive is air it's oxygen
receive it receive it wholeheartedly
the lower part of the abdomen
let it ground you
let it be enjoyable
this knowing of the breath here this part of the body filled out
full [Music] bellowing
notice something about attending to the breath receiving the breath in the abdomen
how it manifests in the body
what happens in the heart and the mind and you may have never noticed before
be interested in this laboratory
make sure you're relaxed
now with the same ease in the body
ah feeling relaxed releasing
[Music] thoughts muscles
now turning attention awareness to receive the breath
in the chest area
as if the breath was being received from your heart center the middle of your
chest entering and exiting
awakening your heart
this moment in time with each breath
giving receiving to the world
perhaps your good wishes your kindness
notice how different it may feel to receive the
breath in the chest the heart center
compared to the abdomen
is there something different about your state of mind now state of your body overall
and now receiving the breath at the nostrils
not inside the nostrils but outside the nostrils at the upper lip
noticing the coolness of the air the warmth
could be more subtle
let the body remain relaxed
noticing the breath outside the nose that the upper lip could be
quite subtle see how the mind the body adapts
notice
you notice any differences in the state of mind and the body
receiving the breath at the nostrils
do you find yourself more distracted perhaps or not
or thoughts arising or perhaps
more concentrated see the difference
and letting go of attending to the breath of the nostrils
ah settling into the whole body whole body filled out
the entire body especially if you were practicing
yesterday the outline of the whole body
the whole body filled out sitting whatever your posture is in this moment
head shoulders arms trunk
sit bones legs feet
entire body this entire body
breathing as if you're breathing through all your pores
this whole body billowing
if the body itself was breathing through the pores
not effortful it's happening on its own just bring your attention awareness to
it
perhaps even [Music] considering that your body extends
just a tiny bit beyond the border of your skin
and the breath moves through
in and out with ease porously
settling settling into the whole body breathing
imagine the whole body bellowing
being breathed
your hands are breathing your back is breathing
and as we bring this period of sitting to a close
dedicating sharing our goodness our cultivation
our engagement our energy our effort
as a community as individuals and a community
offering it offering our collective cultivation to all beings
everywhere including ourselves
may our cultivation or knowing or
awakening walking on the path towards awakening
made serve may be of service
not just to ourselves but to everyone those we know those we don't know
may all beings everywhere be happy
may all beings everywhere be free including ourselves
thank you for your practice
uh hello greetings dear sangha
lovely to be practicing with you
so as we are exploring the mind's body this week
this particular invitation today in the guided meditation
was to explore the impact of attending to the breath
turning awareness to receive the breath either in the abdomen
the chest nostrils or the whole body there are more ways to tend to the
breath but given limited time
and and recently i was talking with a dedicated practitioner who's
practiced for many years or decades actually set three-month retreats at ims multiple ones etc
and we got to talk about um the breath and i started to share about
the different impact that attending to the breath in different places has and they said i had no idea no one has ever
shared this with me before why why why don't other dharma teachers ever talk
about this and um and i thought ah this is important to
talk about this is important to talk about and um and i also i i'm appreciating
seeing the comments about how breathing into different areas really are shifting the energetic
feelings for people how you're exploring and seeing that that's wonderful makes me
very happy to see that um so so
a couple of things one is dharma teachers in i may or may not have heard this through my own practice maybe for
one person or not but but it's also something that i would say that i've experienced on my
own and discovered on my own and there are other writings anyway it's
the so this is part of the canon this is important it's knowing how to work with
the breath can also can support you can support where you're in your practice can
support the energetic feeling can support you with hindrances so so let's dive in let's dive in
so attending receiving the breath um
in the abdomen let's start with the abdomen the sense of ease relaxed
receiving of the breath again not intentionally breathing yourself because that could become very tight
it can become like a chore i'm breathing but the breathing is already happening but receiving it in the abdomen
so the abdomen especially the lower abdomen that's also where
mahasi sayadaw a prominent teacher in the um
in theravada tradition in burma
that's where um and mahasi said i was a teacher to
many of the teachers who came to the west and brought vipassana to the west
about 50 years ago or so so so attending to the breath in the
abdomen can have the uh impact can have
um [Music] the the the um the result of the the
mind feeling settled the fee the mind feeling grounded so
the abdomen can be perhaps one of the most grounding places
to attend to the breath and especially if you are a practitioner who tends to be very
heady tends to be very heady in your work in your life you tend to think a lot
then bringing the the gra the the center of gravity of the attention down down
down in your physical body to your abdomen and noticing the breath receiving the breath
in the abdomen can be really grounding can be really grounding the image
to have is like a balloon if you have a helium balloon and it's light and it's just wants to
get away you put a weight you put the weight on the bottom of it and you put it on the earth
so put a weight on your helium balloon of your thoughts that i want to go with here there
everywhere if you notice there are a lot of thoughts bring the attention down down down to your abdomen
receive the breath in the abdomen so the abdomen is
generally i would say the best place for beginning practitioners if you're relatively new
or still exploring the abdomen or even if you're an experienced practitioner the abdomen is
it tends to be a one size fits all has many many advantages
um and there's also a grossness to the sensations of rise and fall that can be
again something for the mind to grab onto all the sensations on the sides of
the belly on the top of the bridges there's so many sensations everywhere so that can really
ground and settle the mind the mind's body
can be really comforted soothed settled
with paying attention to the breath in the abdomen
especially if there is um the hindrance of agitation
if there's the hindrance of restlessness worry bring the energy down
lower lower abdomen sense the um the breath there and it will calm it
will soothe it will settle it will ground um and sometimes even your sit bones can
that can be helpful it's really low really feeling your your breath low
the the chest the chest [Music]
can also have different impacts different uh ways of the energy moving shifting um
sometimes the the the advantage maybe i'll say one one advantage of the breath here
sometimes feeling that the breath is entering directly into the heart center and exiting the heart center you can
open the heart it can have a a meta quality to a loving kindness and
and especially if you're practicing meta this heart center breathing can be jasper it can be just so lovely
um can synchronize your meta with even if there are no phrases but just this feeling of kindness breathing through
your heart for the whole world for yourself there can be a sense of calming and soothing
their um the chest however
can bring up some anxiety if if you're having anxiety or restlessness worry etc
can can kind of bring the energy up a little bit in your chest um so so you can
knowing that you can bring it down if that happens you can bring it down to the abdomen
again all of these places have a lovely uh both you know
the right time the and what's not helpful um the nostrils the nostrils can be very
subtle and the nostrils can be very subtle and i do not recommend the nostrils uh for any beginner or even
intermediate practitioners um thanks for exploring it this morning so
if you're new it's okay the nostrils the the beauty of the nostrils can be is that it can be the
breath can be so subtle here that the mind can really get concentrated but
only after you've been you've experienced many many years
of practice and and even decades and you really know your way around the energy bodies and concentration practices
the challenge with and and never go inside never go inside the nostrils do
not feel the breath inside the nostrils that's bad habit do not do it
can cause a lot of problems down the road with worth practicing but outside here this is called the
anapana spot on upon the spot here the
mindfulness of breathing spot here i've been below the nose and and over the the uh the lip
uh this ridge here so um the disadvantage can be that again
it's very subtle so it's so subtle that um you you don't feel it at all
you lose it you become really tight like where is that breath you become you become so tight that you
you uh trip over your own shoelaces and practice and and uh not helpful
it can also uh bring a lot of bring the energy to the head area so one
can be distracted a lot more easily um so
so again all of these have uh these with so um let's say we're practicing at at the
nostrils um it is how my teacher the parks parks iodine
for the deeper level of genres this is where the point but again after a lot of experience has happened a lot of
experience on the path etc so um
um and and also to say the the abdomen as i talked about being the generally
wonderful place to go if you're feeling a little sleepy if you're sloth and torpor
and you're feeling very uh sleepy then it might be helpful to
actually pay attention to the breath in the chest or at the nostril just to bring the energy up to wake you up it
can have an uplift have an uplifting the energy body can kind of uplift instead of being settled
and down so if you're feeling sleepy it's okay for for some time to feel the breath further up
and the whole body breath the whole body breathing
which we tried very briefly can again be very comforting soothing grounding
uh this whole sense of the energy body and can feel spacious can both feel
conf confined in a good way sense of secure
here i am in a cocoon i'm being i'm being breathed and can also feel very spacious again if
we add the spaciousness there's a lot more may um
say so i i didn't include all of that because in 30 minutes there's only so much you can do and besides this was a
really quick tour i would recommend that trying all of these for longer periods
of time on your own and really exploring in your own energy body wow this shifts i mean
five minutes is just not a lot enough for each of these uh stops um it's like
a whirlwind tour of our breath and then there are more practices etc etc
um so there's so much to share with you about the mind's body uh
so i knew this was going to come up i there are lots of chats lots of questions i haven't seen them all but the one that i
see is why the sensing inside the nostrils is not good so if you just practice a little bit
here and there inside the nostrils is not going to impact you but inside the nostrils
if you go on a retreat or if you practice a lot it
the sense of solidity the earth element is it is said the sense of solidity arises inside the nostrils inside the
head and and if you do it over and over for a long time especially on the retreat then it feels
like they're bricks in your nose in your head and it can completely mess you up um i've worked i've
known practitioners where this has happened you forget how to breathe you can't even breathe it gets tight it's it's it can become very painful so do
not develop these bad habits that later you have to undo if you um
practice more um so so i'll leave that
answer to jane's question okay so so much in this
mind's body to explore and share i hope this is supportive to your practice knowing how to
shift and turn and change if there's sleepiness if there's anxiety if there's
need grounding subtlety and there's a lot more
to share i look forward to practicing with you for the rest of the week
take good care be well
you