so hello and welcome
to this third day on a series of the gladness of pentad
and the middle one here today is um tranquility
is specifically the Tranquility of the body
but we can also consider it also a Tranquility of the Mind
and meditation is often associated with calmness and people will do meditation to become
calm but I'd like to propose that the calmness that we develop through
meditation is not only for its own purpose
but for the benefits that come with calm and one of the benefits
is um that are body and mind
becomes organized it self-organizes in the calmness
when we're not calm when we're we tend to be disorganized
we're scattered fragmented agitated sometimes jumping around sometimes their
thoughts are buzzing or pop uh you know jumping back and forth between things
sometimes the body is the can't be still sometimes the body just has to keep
moving and and and because being still is too uncomfortable
and the constant movements of the body the constant movements of the Mind
can very easily become a disorganization process that it's scattered divided fragmented
and as Things become calm and there's a settling and that's settling things begin to shift and change and become
organized the classic Buddhist the way of talking about this is that Things become a
unified but unified it doesn't suggest the ways in which things
cooperate or coordinate that may be organized does
and as we become more calm and more organized more settled
it allows the mind and body it allows the mind about it to heal to settle to
come alive in different ways and most importantly it allows for a cleaner more
direct Opera operating of our intelligence our creativity creativity
and our Focus and to bring our intelligence
and our creativity to becoming focused in meditation to being really here in a
wholehearted way a whole a wholeness
that is also a wholesomeness
so to be calm and perhaps by mentioning these benefits
from becoming calm maybe you can you'll give this a
give it a try as we sit here and maybe a little bit more intentional
way than you might did meditation so assuming a posture
that is an organized posture organized for
the purpose of meditation
just like a maybe like a
a painter on a canvas will bring the whole body into
being really present the body's organized as gather together
for the purposes of just being really there precise with the brush of the stroke
or the way they cook might be slicing making a beautiful slice
of some vegetable to Adorn a dish
be right there precise focused with the body gets involved and
connected and this organizing the body taking care with your posture
so that it's a posture that begin feeling that
as much as your posture as can can in a relaxed way
is cooperating participating in the meditation
maximal participation of the body
in being intentionally present Here and Now
and sometimes sitting up straighter will allow for a much deeper relaxation
of the body than leaning back and slouching in a couch
initially it seems like it's more work but over time
and a line body can let go deeply
I read once that the two postures that allow for the deepest relaxation of the
body is the yoga posture called The Corpse laying flat on your back
and the other is sitting cross-legged with a spine Direct
not slouching gently closing your eyes
so the eyes are not doing looking at things they're different than being here in the meditation
and one more time with the eyes closed making small adjustments to the posture
almost as a ritual of getting the body organized
and participatory in the meditation in being alert
and then taking a few deep inhales
and using the expansion of the rib cage the Torso as you breathe in
as a way of deeply connecting to your body
the stretching the opening feel it fully
and then the long exhale soften and relax
long exhale settle into this body
taking a really deep breath that expands the Torso
gives the Torso a chance to reorganize itself as you exhale
refined itself
and then to let breathing return to normal
and with normal breathing
relaxing the different parts of the body both to relax them
and also just begin this process of
reorganizing the body to be a Cooperative whole
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
softening around the eyes
exhaling and relaxing the shoulders
feeling the weight of the shoulders
releasing
softening the belly as you exhale
maybe there's a way of relaxing the belly as you inhale as well
and then in the next few exhales the inhale and the inhales feel your
whole body in a global way and the exhale relax your whole body
release any bracing you have bracing against
life releasing any momentum forward into time
to do to worry whole body softens
and then relaxing the mind maybe also in the exhale
a gentle softening of the thinking mind
a gentle quieting of the thinking
any pressure or tension agitation in the thinking mind
let it relax and let the weight of it settle it quiet it
so the fragmenting forces of the Mind begin to quiet down
and the mind gathers together in a subtle place within
and instead of now focusing on breathing
from the control tower looking down or imagine that there is a kind of a canal
or a tube from the brain down into the belly
and as you exhale all the thoughts and mental activity
awareness itself moves down that
Canal down into the belly and rests there
settles there together to experience the movements of the belly
as you breathe
where everything is allowed to organize itself around the
movements of the belly
if the Mind wants to be at peace
you can support that by having the Mind rest in the belly
come on
relaxing on the exhale and perhaps feeling
how the scattered parts of ourselves gather together settle down together
fit themselves together in an organized whole
Letting Go relaxing allowing everything to settle
around the breathing
if you're inhale your exhale is your paintbrush as an artist
and you have to be precise with the brush stroke
let your attention get gathered and settled and focused
on each stroke of the breath as if it's the most important thing of
the moment the last Strokes that finishes the
painting without messing it up
and then to end this sitting imagine that every thought
is also like a paintbrush stroking painting a picture
maybe painting the picture of the world that you live in
and every thought of Good Will and kindness it's like painting it
with a friendly color and so to end the sitting with
good will for the world for others
saying to yourself these kinds of words as you paint the world
Infuse the world with your good will
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
then may we be organized
in our hearts and minds and bodies
with kindness compassion and love
[Music]
thank you
so we're now at the third Talk of the gladness pentad
and this is uh Tranquility specifically it's Tranquility of the body
and but it I like to think of it includes calmness of the mind as well
and um here the language is not that we are calming anything but rather there's
a calming that happens from the momentum of the meditation of the practice it's
like if you sit still and upright when you're really tense the body just wants to relax and settle just kind of you
find yourself settling without intending to do so and so the same way for the mind there's
a way in which things are allowed to settle they're quiet if we get out of the way if we don't perpetuate our
busyness our activities so being still and it turns out that
that deep relaxation of the body is supported by gladness and joy the
first two steps of this gladness pentaton it's kind of like with with the
gladness and joy there's a contentment there's a sense of well-being
that it just feels safer to relax and let go it just feels kind of warm and cozy to
be present so that the body wants to relax more kind of like it's been tight
and shivering in the cold and then it stands in the Sun the warmth of the Sun and soaks in the warmth and something
begins to relax so when in meditation we can help with
the relaxing calming and when we allow for it as part of the art of meditation
meditation is often associated with becoming calm and tranquil and uh
it's a very useful quality of meditation but it's very it's not so often talked
about how the calmness the Tranquility that brings that we create that comes
along is a not for its own sake many people feel that's enough I mean I was so
stressed out it was not nice to be calm that the calmness begins to allow for a
reorganizing of the mind and body especially I think of the mind getting
reorganized maybe a mind that's disorganized is all too often our
experience in life and you've only realize that when we sit down to meditate and see how much the mind is
jumping around or fragmented or preoccupied in a way that
you know so distracted we don't even know we're distracted so preoccupied we
don't even know that we're preoccupied until we sit down and see it and um
and so the um um to begin uh
and to be present and awake and clear and see what's happening in the mind that begins allowing the mind to settle
it's kind of like making breathing room for something to settle and then we could also participate in
that relaxing sometimes and just kind of kind of being with the breath and
relaxing it being with our our mind and softening the mind
and the more that we're both awake attentive and relaxing
the more the mind will self-organize it's like the self-healing properties of
the our body and mind that are not enabled if we stay scattered and
stressed it's kind of like we're keeping ourselves away we're interfering with
the self-healing self-settling self-organizing aspects of our mind and
as we get as the mind gets more organized more less fractured more
gathered together the the purpose as I said is not just to be
calm but to so that our intelligence our creativity and our Focus can operate in
support of the meditation and because the idea is that the calm is
not an end of itself but allows for a deepening of concentration of settling a
greater sense of settled concentrated wholeness not another fragmentationary lasers
focusing on something and pushing everything else aside but rather everything is allowed to settle together
nothing is left out nothing is held at Bay nothing is repressed or denied but
the self-organizing everything comes together and then can find a way to work together
cooperate to coordinate for the purposes of meditation
um I I was told recently about a game that uses some kind of Technology
attached to the head that can measure I guess the brain waves whether a person
is agitated or calm and now apparently it's a game where there's a ball between two people and a
table or something and that's somehow uh connected wirelessly connected to
these headsets people are wearing and so um when we relax the ball moves away
from us towards the other person and so it's a competition to see who can get
the ball into the other person's goal or in the other person's side of the table and but what's required is to be relaxed
so you can't strain you can't be competitive in a forceful straining way
um and the person who wins is the one who is most relaxed which probably also
means the most unconcerned about winning and um but I imagine that you don't win
by falling asleep um you know you don't win by kind of spacing out you have to be present
very present to notice uh if the mind is you know if the boat
which direction the ball is going and whether or which direction you know is the mind now more stressed more agitated
or is the mind now is it more places you can settle and relax quiet the mind
and so learning this art of Being alert present tracking what's going on with
intelligence and keeping it relaxed at the same time
many people only know one or the other but to do both and then to use the uh our intelligence
our creativity to gather more fully and focus more fully just here in our
meditation so in this last meditation I suggested the idea that
um you know as an image is a creative image of you thinking of attention like a
brush stroke and like you're a painter painting something and that every inhale and
every exhale is this is a you have to have the very precise and clear relaxed
Focus of an artist who's putting the finishing touches on a very refined detailed
painting that's maybe exquisitely beautiful but uh you want to put the
last little thing in it and not mess up and so very present
maybe there too if there's stress or tension in the artist's hand it won't it won't be quite right it has to be very
relaxed but very focused and so that every exhale is a brush stroke every
inhale side brush stroke of this painting and this metaphor is not uh partly
borrows from the ancient Buddhist language Pali that in one of these coincidences
accidents of the language that the word for mind chitta
is the same as the word for painting they have different uh they come from
different Roots so that technologically they're not related but somehow in the way the language is kind of evolved over
time the accents the pronunciations they came to have the same pronunciation so homonyms
so but it's kind of a wonderful coincidence that um you know that the word for mind the
word for painting is the same because maybe there's a way in which how
we're present how we engage in attention is a way of painting
the Mind painting our experience painting ourselves into being a whole
organized gathered together everything working in harmony
and so how do we harmonize mind and body and part of the way is to allow it to
harmonize by being calm by being settled and so some of that we can do ourselves
we can relax the tensions in our muscles while staying alert
in the body to what we don't want to do is relax and
become limp limpness is not the Tranquility that the
Buddha was pointing to it you know the most limp person would end up you know
like a a cooked piece of spaghetti just kind of you know
call you know not no no tautness to holding it up so
we don't not possibly we're not supposed to become limp we're also not supposed to be tens
and uh so some kind of tautness some kind of Vitality energy that keeps Us
Alive Keeps Us upright and engaged but also something it allows for a very deep
relaxation of the body and the mind it's phenomenal that what can happen in
meditation so I offer all all this all this to you
is a is a
as a suggestion
or as a ideas to encourage you to lovingly relaxedly
participate and support this organizing self-organizing
de fracturing movement of meditation that part of the reason to settle the
mind is so that the if we can become more
intelligent and creative and present for our experience for those of you who have mine to jump
around a lot some image might be helpful
so the image for example that the as you exhale it's like you're you have the
focus of you know a painter with a paintbrush just right there with the
every little step of the exhale you're painting it you're right there tracking
it or maybe you know really present for
um I don't know it's a
the um you know what's the attention you need to if you want to
um some fruit like a mango or maybe avocado where you put the knife down you don't
want to cut through the skin you cut it in half you don't cut through the skin but you know from the half from the
inside you're you're slicing it down to the skin so what's that Focus right there
for that cut that you need to do maybe you have other images that you
like that works for this a um maybe an Archer and you know just really getting
the whole body organized settled connected they're also an Archer can't
be tense but the Archer has to be taught and everything is organic whole body is organized for the purposes of the shot
and then you know that kind of the mind everything takes its time to really be
there to to hit the target and um so
to org meditation as a organizing practice
that is supported by tranquility and the more we have gladness the more
we have joy the more that it's just natural for the body to feel cozy content and feel like
it can settle and relax and and participate in this reorganizing
from the disorganization of stress stress and and
resistance and you know agitation
so um
look for opportunities to be tranquil you know we'll set in a park bench for a
little while and said look out the window and have tea look for opportunities to relax your
body standing in a shopping line don't read the magazines that are there as you're waiting or don't be you know
judging what other people in front of you in line have bought you standing there is a chance to soften and relax
your body maybe relax your mind look for opportunities today to relax be tranquil
not for its own purpose but see if you can notice if in that Tranquility in
that calmness if there's a way in which your body and mind kind of comes together kind of becomes more whole
becomes more organized or gather together or Unified
so um thank you and may you have a tranquil day
and and not just because you're tranquil but
because your whole system starts coming into harmony you'll be better prepared for tomorrow's
topic which is happiness so thank you very much
oh and I wanted to mention that yesterday I talked about the day long I'm teaching on Saturday
that could be seen as a continuation of this series this week
it's a day-long meditation teaching and meditation on the Four Noble Truths the
information for that is on the what's new section of imc's website also it's
being offered through Insight Retreat Center so if you go on their website for
a day long under day lungs online retweets you can see it it's a zoom
Retreat so so thank you very much