so good morning everyone and welcome to imc and mostly we'll sit quietly this
morning and uh but i would like to
uh one of the central meditation aspects of this
vipassana tradition is to be aware of the four elements
and here we're kind of this is the sunday to celebrate
earth a day and so the four elements are earth
water fire and wind and uh
and in this tradition the pipasana sometimes will focus on
the ways that these are found in ourselves as particular
qualities of experience the earth element is
they often say the earth element is everything that's hard and solid
but itself i often experiences that which is offer support
the water element is
everything that's fluid moist but the quality the way it's experienced is it
it's that which holds things together cohesion
and uh the fire element is all the everything that's animated in us
everything that's energized within us the energizing forces of life
which is basically all their sensations and then there's uh the fire the uh wind
element and that's the movements everything that moves as we sit the
movements of the chest the diaphragm the belly anything that moves just the wind element
so to sit quietly here and to feel those four
so to gently close your eyes
and to feel the support
of the earth
the earth both is what we rest on
our bodies the earth element it supports us
and to feel the contact of your body against your chair your cushion
the floor in a sense would hold you up from the
pull of gravity
in your body there's a support of your lower torso that holds up the upper torso
the neck that supports the head
and a water element the cohesion
that can be exaggerated in all the feelings of
tension that we have the holding together the tightening
pulling in and to gently
as you exhale exhaling the wind to the air
to release some of the extra tension holding in
your body
relaxing in the shoulders
the belly
in a sense releasing the tension that pulls the muscles inward
and allowing your muscles to fall outward away from this bones
where it can be held by the skin the cohesive holding
property of the skin can hold us
and the fire element of everything that's animated energized
within us energized sensations every sensation you experience
is there because of the animated energy of
the nerves the firing
the energy behind thinking this is the fire element
whatever you're feeling emotions are an expression of that animated
life energy of the buddhism likens to fire
and that fire element can come into harmony like a candle
frame flame without any wind everything burning everything alive
animated held in awareness
allowed to burn allowed to be without our
preferences our likes and dislikes our wants and aversions
pushing them around
and then the wind element gently
as you breathe in and out gently feel
the movements of the body as you breathe
so
maybe treating the breathing is something delicate fragile
tender that you want to hold or receive gently in awareness
with no forcefulness just a soft receiving
of breathing the movements of the body
touching awareness
and so we sit here
aware of the natural
elements found within us
that are found in the natural world
and we sitting here in a certain way are continuous
with the outer world in the inner world here
now
nature
here and now
okay
this
as we come to the end of this sitting
i'd like to use the analogy of a light
that goes on in a dark room
then if the light is on a dimmer and it gets turned on at the absolute
most lowest setting
the room might just begin to come into view
just a little bit but as a dimmer goes that's turned up
higher and higher more and more comes into view until the whole room is filled with light
so we come to the end of a sitting and we dedicate our practice for the welfare and
happiness of others it might begin with this
the light of care the light of compassion light of
our deep connection to others maybe it's turned on that just a little
bit and our wish to benefit others can be a small wish
but it can be the beginning of that light getting brighter and
brighter until it fills the world
may it be that our care for others and for this world
can grow steadily within us
and may it be that the benefits that come from this morning's practice
is dedicated some way known in unknown ways
for the happiness safety and peace all beings
in this world of war and environmental degradation
poverty and hostility and hate
may we be a light in wishing and working for
possibility that all beings may be happy
all beings may be safe
all beings may be peaceful and all beings
be free
and may that wish be a light that grows stronger and stronger
[Music]
so [Music]
so before i
before the talk i think
one of the nice announce announcements especially since we're celebrating earth day today a few
days late but we do it on sundays usually is that the imc is
starting up restarting its earth care group
that is a group of people here at imc whose
meet to talk about earth care activities studying earth care issues together
and considering what imc might do
in this wider world for caring for this earth
and i think they're going to start having regular monthly meetings and they're going to be a lot of them will be on
zoom so it means that people who are imc connected people far away could maybe participate
and the first meeting will be next saturday at 1pm and uh
ram who's here in the back those of you here raising his hand in the back he's one of the people organizing it
and he went through the sati center's buddhist eco-chaplaincy program and now
he's deeply connected to this whole world and shawnee here also who's here she's also went through the
buddhist equal chaplaincy program together with ram so anyway so that's the
so if you're interested there's more information on the website under what's new it's an announcement for it with the
zoom link it's also also in the imc calendar and or if you're here in imc you can talk to
ram and probably shawnee too
so
so to talk about her this day earth day
i want to uh adapt a story that i'm fond of i've told
before but adapted for this occasion and the story has to do with uh
in the village there was a a couple who were going to give birth to
their first child and she was born and this beautiful little baby girl
and uh some wise elder of the village
or from the neighborhood the area came through town and looked at her and said oh very nice
however it's her destiny that she will die on her wedding night
oh well so the the couple had the baby then raised his
daughter and were kind of hesitant to have her be married but at some point she couldn't they couldn't keep her from
becoming married and they didn't want to tell her about the prophecy
so she was married and then there was that that evening a
big party and everyone in the village came and it was a big celebration and party and
to celebrate this wedding and um the parents of course were a little bit worried what this meant
and everybody was involved in the party and then but then someone knocked on the door and it turned out to be this very old
lady who lived on the edges of the village and people had kind of forgotten about
her no one really quite knew whole she was but
she had lived there for her whole life and she had given birth to a number of kids
she cared for and she took care of her grandkids
even took care of her great-grandchildren but because people had children when they were quite young in this village
after she had grandchildren and great girl she stopped having the energy to take care of them that she was old
and as the generations proceeded she was forgotten that some of her kids
and grandkids had died and great-grandchildren had died and so the people left this old old
lady she couldn't take care of herself anymore and people left her alone and
what you said anybody of an old lady and so she was hungry and poor
and so they came to the wedding knocking on the door to ask for some food
and the guests opened the door said i'll just shoot her away you know someone that poor and old you know just
just not so not so nice to have a wedding party we're celebrating they shoot her away
and but then the bride saw this
so she went out and asked what is it it's so i'm hungry
oh let me bring you some food so you brought her a big plate of food and may i sit with you while you eat and she
said yes and now when they had finished eating her meal the old lady said to
the bride
you know i've been here living this village for a long long long time
and i have a lot to teach you for the sake of your children and their
children and their children down the generations i know things that people have forgotten
i know the seasons to plant and harvest so that the soil doesn't erode away it actually keeps the
soil healthy and fertile i know how to harvest things from the forest
trees and everything so the forest regenerates i know how to care for the lakes and the
rivers so that pollutions and sewage and all kinds of things don't destroy the life there
i know how to have fires in the village when to do it where to do it how to do
it so that the children don't grow up with asthma
if you come visit me i'll teach you these things and the bride said sure i'll come
and uh well she went by went back to the party it was celebration
the bride and groom do what bride and grooms do and then they uh the next morning
the bride was still alive so the parents were kind of like what
happened you know so they went to the person who had prophesized about her death
and they said well there was one thing i couldn't tell you there was one thing that would allow her to live
and that was she had to be selflessly generous
but if i'd said that she wouldn't it wouldn't have been selfless so she would have wouldn't have been real generosity
and she did that selfless giving to this old ladies and that's that kept her alive it saved her
and uh and then more than and saved her she got a gift back
from it and offered to come and study and learn
and this old lady her name was in different languages in
our buddhist language he was bhumi mata the earth mother
terra madre in italian in norwegian it's you
and the word yo mo means earth mother it also is the norwegian word for midwife
which is kind of nice you can probably make all kinds of connections from that interesting ideas
of that our earth mother is
also gives birth to all that we have here supports it and brings it forth
and uh so here we are on earth day and uh we have this wonderful earth
that has been supporting us for generations cared for
you know the earth has cared for human beings since the beginning of human beings
provided abundance of often in order to survive or to make it down through the generations
and here we are and uh and what's going to
what's going to save us the earth is struggling it's under assault
the people of the earth are under all kinds of intentions stresses and
that are pretty awful with climate change and things now what what's going to what's going to
make the difference what's going to keep us a lot us alive well from the story it's an act of
generosity to be generous and generosity can't be forced
can't be an obligation that has to really come from us
which to say that or to hear that some people will protest
say no no we have an obligation we have a responsibility to
work to save this planet save and mitigate the problems of climate change
not only for the sake of the environment but for also for so many people who are going to be harmed by all this
some of them are the poorest of the poor and of course we're obligated especially
here maybe some of us in the united states where the united states has five percent of the world population but produces thirty
percent of the pollution so you know so don't then you know that in a sense you
can say the privilege to you know should actually use more of the resources should be more
responsible so of course be the responsibility and we bring up our finger and we shake it
you know like you have to do something and you're responsible and obligated
but obligation and responsibility and chastising like
that is not generosity
but of course we're responsible for going well if you like
obligation if you like the idea of responsibility if that's your thing
then from the buddha's point of view we have to turn it around and say well
we have an obligation then a responsibility to learn selfless generosity
so that from selfless generosity we can do we can support the world and
the people of the world so there comes with a joy a delight so
we're willing not just to so we can sit down with everyone and learn from them and be friends with them
not be divisive there's a kind of poison that comes along all too easily
if we act from obligation duty like you have to
it doesn't lift us up it's kind of obligation is like a burden
and it it kind of i don't think there's much hope for us as a planet if everyone has to click you know gear
up their obligation and like okay we gotta you know but can we do things
with gender selfless generosity maybe tirelessly maybe do a lot maybe give
ourselves over to it but come from a motivation that
that is inspiring that's nourishing for ourselves and for others
then i think there's hope and possibility then it's contagious if we can figure out how to do this
and uh and i think that's one of the contributions buddhism can make to all this buddhism hasn't had a
particularly particularly history good or bad i would think
of caring for the environment people who are environmental and buddhist environmentalists will kind of
squeeze out of buddhist teachings teachings that support caring for the environment so you can find it there but
i don't think that you have to kind of like you know really search for it and you
get small little hints here and there and then they put them all together in one big package so it looks nice
but buddhism hasn't had a lot to say about this but buddhism has a lot to say about generosity
about care compassion those are important
and so when we see suffering around us then the idea is to generously care for
that generously inspiringly with love and kindness and friendliness engage in doing something
and how do we come to that place so that we don't have to fall back on obligation and
or defensiveness or war to care for ourselves
well this is that's the strength of buddhism is to bring forth those in an inspiring
way in a delightful way and so we learn how to look at
our attachments our clinging we like to look at the ways that we create divisiveness and hold on tight and
create a sense of self that that contributes to divisiveness contributes to selfless selfishness
and to learn an alternative to learn to settle deeply and open up and discover
layers and layers of inner freedom layers and layers of joy and happiness
that dissolve selfishness dissolves self-centeredness
helps us to feel more and more deeply connected to our others to the world
like when you know like when i from the first years i was practicing
i was in college and i took a botany class
and uh maybe literally because of my meditation practice by that time there was one day when the
professor was on the board and speaking at the amphitheater class and
i was talking about i think the photosynthesis for the synthesis and this you know the
cycle of you know all the cycles and oxygen and carbon dioxide and the
cycling of all this you had all these diagrams of how the cycles through nature you know the simple like cycle is
that we produce carbon dioxide and the plants
converted carbon dioxide to oxygen so we can breathe without the plants doing it
there would not be enough oxygen here for us to be alive so then i left the class i was kind of
absorbed in this whole discussion very still and i and so because i was so kind of absorbed
in it in the mind everything distractions and kind of fell away when i went out and stood in the
courtyard of at the college where there was huge old oak trees
around us i stood there and i kind of became under frozen's right word but completely i
couldn't move i just started looking at it and i felt wow
i could do without one of my kidneys without a arm and all kinds of parts of
my body i can manage fine without but i can't do without these plants
and so where do i begin and where the plants end you know where is the separation if i'm i'm so dependent on
them and i stood there this kind of world of separation dissolved and it
felt this beautiful inspired sense of the mutual support and connectedness and
how we don't we're not born from the the earth from nature
we are the earth we are nature we're no we're not revisiting this planet visiting life
we are the life of the planet we're inseparable from it
and so from that to be generous is your right hand generous when it
helps when it washes the left hand and the left hand is it being generous when it washes the right hand
you could say yes but it's it's selfless you know it comes together then you know
it you know it is it's because it's you know they're connected or we don't think of that way because it's just
caring for what's here can our the way that we relate to the world around us have that kind of
intimacy like it's almost as if it's part of us or there's no there's no sense of
it being an obligation to care or no sense of it is um required even
but it's just of course we do it of course that comes out of us
it doesn't even come out of us of course it comes out of the world and this is kind of the beauty and the
mystery and the wonderfulness of settling deeply into buddhist practice is discover this
beautiful source of motivation this beautiful source of energy and engagement
that is kind of selfless kind of we don't want to we can't claim it to be
mine me myself and mine but it's it's available and or connected or it
lives in a mutuality with this wider world and then
there can be generosity that's the selfless generosity that's the heart that's what makes the
heart sing and smile that's what nourishes and supports the
heart so what is that generosity
how can we learn it how can we enact it how can we
uh give ourselves permission to do wonderful things to turn on the
light of that generosity that care that love that compassion turned on so that
it's those wonderful things for the world around us
and not because it's an obligation i don't know you know
i'm gonna miss my netflix
but rather why would i watch that why would i watch netflix when i can do these wonderful
things when there's something in flow of this flow of the natural world it's aliveness
and goodness can just flow and be here and and i feel more alive and everything is
kind of free in this generosity and in this doing in
the world so uh
so this mutuality and this intimacy with the world that's possible
i think for me is represented by the emphasis that buddhists will have on
finding the four elements within us these four elements are
said to be earth water fire and air
and what this means is that um there are certain characteristics sensations sense feelings that we can
have that are identified as being somehow this behaving in the same way within us
as we can find out in the natural world so the the finding the quality or
characteristics of earth within us is to find where there's support
what supports us the ground supports us
and uh and in us there's there's things that are solid and heavy and
supportive that hold us up and allows us to sit upright for example and and uh receives the weight of our body
and provides support i kind of little bit delight in the this idea that if
how important it is that we have this earth to support us because without it
we would just be like floating around in space i see sometimes photographs of the
astronauts up in the space station and they're just kind of floating around up there
and i guess there's a small enough space they probably push themselves off the walls but imagine if the earth wasn't here we
couldn't get you know we would have to find our way back to the earth to push on something you know and we'd probably just kind of
like be helpless from the air but the earth has gravity that pulls us
down it keeps us and then and supports us just enough just the right amount so that we don't float away
but we don't get crushed by too much uh gravity so the earth so everything else is the
same thing and then there's uh the uh water the water element is said
to be the characteristic of water that we can feel they say is cohesion like water droplets put next to each other
they stick together they get more and more of them together that cohesion there's also
that phenomena where water goes up a little bit on the edges of a glass that's holding on and sticks
capillary action and plants that pulls up the water of the tree of these big redwoods we have here imagine that
redwoods because of the nature of water properties of cohesion and water it pulls water to the very top of our
redwood tree it's a big tall tree there so this cohesion and so so much of what
we are we're held together we're held together by the skin the muscles the tendons
all the stuff that holds us here together and if we didn't have the cohesion
you know we all our particles would just kind of float away but we're held together
and these are natural phenomena that somehow has evolved over time not of the cosmic soup
and the fire element and they say that what you how the fire
element is is that everything that's animated within us and uh so you know it's
all the energy that keeps us alive every sensation we have is an expression of something energetic within us the firing
of the nerves firing nerves is a kind of a fire and uh and they had all the energy we
have that keeps us alive and going and some way or other has originated from the sun
and you know sunlight comes down and the plants turn it into photosynthesize and turn it
into you know carbohydrates and we eat them and and now or something else eats them and
then eventually if we eat the food and and we transform it into
somehow or other into energy and and then you know
so in a sense we're a con there's a continuity of that energy from the sun that keeps us going and so we can feel
that continue the energy the aliveness the vitality it's part of the net it's not only the natural of this earth but
at the of our solar system i think it's so cool
and then the air element is is uh they say it's the quality of movement
and uh we're moving beings we're not plants rooted down we can we can get around we can walk
around we can move our limbs we can move our chest our diaphragm to
to so we have this exchange of oxygen and and carbohydrate
carbon dioxide and so this idea of kind of feeling
within ourselves characteristics or qualities or aspects of what we can see outside
makes it so that suggests that there's not actually such a strong line between self and the world
around us we're all sharing so much of the same material
it said that each of us is made from recycled materials
how's that recology you know they're going to do a line of business
you know that they were all just all recycled i mean we're all the material that we built of has been
in many different places and times and oh you know down through the millennium
and uh it's possible that each of us is breathing in now at least one particle
of air that the buddha brave breathed because there's so many you know billions little
particles that of water and air that go into us to the way it's statistically the way it
spreads out this is a good possibility we're breathing in something that would have breathed so
long ago so this kind of feeling of you know this interconnectedness and interdependency is phenomenal thing to
feel and to feel it in such a way that we want to be generous
and we want to learn before it's too late learn from the elders learn from the people who are
studying it learn how to use it to live in harmony with it
how to enjoy maybe the sacrifices that we need to
make sacrifice meaning making sacred
maybe the lifestyle that some of us are living is not sustainable for this planet
and is there an alternative lifestyle that we can enjoy that we that delight
us and this again i think for coming back to buddhism buddhist practice the
possibility of learning how to enjoy life without needing the latest and greatest
technology without needing a lot of consumer goods not needing a lot of
doing things that require air travel and even car travel just like just to feel
the delight and the joy one of my delights on sunday morning
uh is to walk down here so it's about a 30-minute walk from my house
i enjoy it so much but what a waste of time right i mean i
i mean i could have been 25 more minutes at home you know it takes only five minutes to drive here and
i'm sure i could have spent 20 good 25 more minutes checking out the news again
you know or reading we're looking for more websites and just kind of searching you know i mean that 25 minutes could
have been you know productive and useful and all kinds of things i could
have done with netflix but i actually enjoy the walk act like
some of my you know just a beautiful wonderful thing to walk down here and
and so the example is supposed to be the example of how can we this practice of
ours it's mindfulness attention being present how can we let that bring forth these
beautiful potential that we have this phenomenal potential we have so that
we are inspired we're delighted we're happy to live a radically different life a
radically selfless life where of course we want to
live differently different lifestyle it's not a sacrifice i would say that if i had decided to
drive down here saved you know so just five minutes to get here rather than 30
so that i could to do more web searching or whatever i do
that that would have been a loss that would have diminished me
is the walk that enhanced me so i don't know if that example works for all of you but there are maybe you
have your own examples i hope when i die i don't look back in
life and say yeah
you know i think i should count up how many websites i visited you know probably you know and then and
celebrate on my deathbed yeah i visited 232 000 websites over my lifetime
what a great life
or look back and say actually the feeling of joy delight well-being
grandness i had from what these walks i take that is a good
visceral memory that to die with wow that is good or the people that i
touched or i was touched by remember those these deeper connections and love and that's something to have
so earth day mother earth she's knocking at your door
she's been forgotten she's starving him
what do you do send her away saying continue the party
what do you offer what do you have to offer
and what do you save what life do you save by stopping long enough sitting down
with her long enough to offer your generosity and to learn and study from our
great parent the earth parent
so let us appreciate this wonderful earth that we have and all the inhabitants
and care for the earth and its inhabitants equally they are inseparable
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
and may the earth thrive in this wonderful
way that the natural world lives in harmony and homeostasis let us support this harmony and homostasis whatever way
we can thank you