some many of you have been practicing for quite some time I can kind of tell
right by how quiet the room was uh during the sit that was very nice thank you
and so you might not remember but at the
beginning of our practice and maybe this still arises but in the beginning of practice it sometimes feels like our
difficulties are getting worse like we started this practice thinking it's
going to make things better and yet we start noticing all these Troublesome
experiences and things that aren't quite right and
so it seems like our suffering is actually increasing
and part of us recognizes that because with practice we are no longer hiding
from the difficulties no longer hiding from ourselves
no longer like constantly distracting ourselves with a
whenever something uncomfortable arises you know just trying to do whatever we can to not experience it
and of course a big part of mindfulness practice is also learning to become tuned in and maybe more sensitive to
what it is that we're experiencing you know all of our experiences not just the pleasant ones
so for all of these reasons sometimes in the beginning of practice and maybe this continues with practice too we start to
feel like wow there's a lot of stuff here that doesn't feel so great
maybe you know I did have somebody a student say to me ignorance was Bliss
because I just didn't see some of this like maybe the deeper difficulties and you it's true right
when we practice we start to see things that we hadn't seen before
and not only that and this is true with anything any Endeavor we want to do
if we want to learn to sew and we get the fabric together in the sewing machine if we're using the sewing
machine and we start to see like oh my goodness it's so hard to get the lines
that go straight and the tension right and let alone reading a pattern or anything like this right
so we just start to notice oh all the ways in which sewing is difficult
so of course in the way in which we practice and if we have this idea that
we want to have more freedom more ease we just start to notice everything that
isn't Freedom we start to notice everything that isn't ease
this just naturally happens whenever we're trying to learn something new or we have a
expectation or a goal or a direction in which we're headed of course we notice that everything that
seems to be going wrong that's preventing us from going that direction or achieving that goal
so we start to see some of our limitations Maybe
some of our for in meditation practice maybe some of our fears start to come up or some of
these inner conflicts that we might have or confusion or
sensitivities that we might have so then
we might when that when this arises when these things arise of course
we fall into some of the habits that humans have when they meet some of these
difficulties blame it's got to be somebody's fault
sometimes it's our own fault and we have a whole story of somehow why we are inadequate or if only we could do X Y
and Z better if only we had ABC experiences right the list is endless
we blame ourselves or we blame others right right well we right we have a whole like
media is all about who can we blame right there's so much kind of like
societal support and pressure for just let's just blame somebody
let's just blame somebody and that kind of like distracts us from the discomfort of when we see
frailties or fears or sensitivities that we have
maybe we don't we have the sense of frustration or maybe I don't need to go into all these long lists I think many
of us are familiar with them without my having to list all of them
but just this recognition that we might have some difficulties maybe it's we have an idea of how we want our life to
be or who the person we think we want to be then we see a gap
between how our life is or how we are feels uncomfortable
maybe we blame somebody and then we don't even notice like the blaming itself is uncomfortable this
first maybe it feels good right we get to have this righteous indignation and
how dare they and I can't believe it and they should have done this and but then we're not
noticing as to like how our hearts and our minds are just getting smaller and smaller and
constricted and there's no Freedom there you set up a me versus you US versus
them and that's not where the freedom is
so of course when we discover that things are uncomfortable man it just starts all over again well
just this uh uncomfortable feeling we have this reaction trying to push them away get rid of them or just go distract
ourselves and have some other pleasant experience
laughs so difficulties part of the human experience of course
and maybe we can make a gross generalization and say that there's two
types two types of difficulties and this recognition that every life every human
life without exception has periods when there are a lot of difficulties no exceptions we all think and hope that
our life will be but it's not the case and so
two types when we have these periods of difficulties or seasons of difficulties
one we might say is some difficulties are clearly problems that need to be
solved so there's something we can do and we fix them
maybe there's some situations that call for some compassionate
I had anemia for quite some time and I just didn't know
it wasn't you know until blood tests I don't remember exactly what the occasion
was and like oh Diana you are anemic like oh that explains a whole lot
okay I can take iron supplements this is a problem you know there's a
solution and this is what I do I take iron supplements right so there's those kind of problems that are kind of
straightforward and maybe aren't too complicated and there's some action that we can do
but many of our problems aren't like that
so many of them are some of what I've been pointing to are problems that were
unknowingly creating for ourselves don't mean to
of course not but maybe there's this way in which we're
insisting or struggling or wrestling with life and demanding that it be different than how
it is that's painful
it's uh can be never-ending this trying to
make things be different than how they are in this way in which we're kind of like shoving things aside and
insisting that things be different or maybe there's a way in which I kind
of getting so caught up in our point of view and not seeing the bigger picture or not
seeing the harm that we're causing ourselves let alone that which were causing others
okay so I talked about some difficulties maybe maybe it'd be helpful to talk
about what can we do
the Buddhist you know uh for Noble Truth the first is there is suffering
so sometimes it's just to recognize okay what are some of these difficulties that we are creating for ourselves partly by
insisting that things be different than how they are
so one is we can find Freedom
in the midst of the difficulties of Our Lives
I know for a long time I had this idea like okay my life is going to be better as soon as you know all these other
things are taken care of or okay I'll be able to meditate properly as soon as I'm
no longer Restless or tired or filled with desire or filled with the aversion or don't have any confusion
soon as this as soon as that and then you know
of course those situations don't arise so often
we try right we are trying to create all the conditions so that we finally can
meditate or find Freedom but we don't have to wait
in fact it's such a for me it was such a radical uh turning point in my practice
and part of it was when I was helping gilfron still guilt probably all of you
know who he is um create this book called unhindered and
it's about the hindrances and I have to kind of create that book and edit it and so much the whole book
essentially is about how to be with difficulties
and the answer was if I can sum up this book
just be mindful of them as best we can
but this openness and spaciousness so
we can just bring awareness to our difficulties I'm not saying this is easy
because right I've went through all this beginning of this talk talking about how we're trying to push things away and we
don't want to see them and we're trying to make them be different but this mindfulness practice kind of
like bringing our attention back to our breath again and again and again
quickly the practice that we need to help not turn away from difficulties
to help us be with them as best we can as best we can
so it's often we have this idea there's only two ways to be with practices or be
with our problems is to suppress them and deny them or try to insist that they
be different or this maybe there's this or maybe I could
say sometimes we have this idea where you should like just all our difficulties yell and express
them and you know make sure that everybody knows how
unfair or it seems to us or angry but this is pointing to this third one that
this third alternative for being with our difficulties and there's this story that Jack
cornfield tells in one of his books that I really like
and it goes it's about the poison tree so this poison tree a tree tree that has
like poison fruit and Jack in his book tells this story I don't know if he created this story or
if it's he got it from somewhere else but that when some people when they first discover this tree they see oh my gosh
this is really dangerous this is really dangerous this poison
so we've got we better cut down this tree before anybody gets hurt
so they get out the chainsaws and cut it down and this often is our
initial response to difficulties like we got to get rid of it and we're trying to create whatever way that we can and so
it's too difficult I difficulties I talked I'm sorry two approaches that I talked about just a moment earlier is
either deny or repress it or let everybody know about them you know so
often they're using one of these two approaches with this poison tree
but there's some other people that have maybe journeyed a little bit further
along this spiritual path And when they see this poison tree they realize oh
let's not cut it down and said let's let's take care of the
tree take care of ourselves take care of others let's put a fence around it
and we'll just protect people we'll allow it to this poison tree to be there
and but we'll just protect ourselves and maybe that this is a compassionate way
to be with the difficulties or to be with the poison and so this
in some ways is a profound shift in art practice instead of I've got to get rid
of it to like no no it's okay it can be there and we'll just kind of like build a
little fence around it but then there's a third type of person
maybe he's gone even a little bit further in their spiritual path and they
see this poison tree and they go ah a half stick here's a poison tree
exactly what I needed it's perfect just what I was looking for and they take out
the fruit and they work with it and they use turn it into take the poison maybe
extract it and add it to some other things and they turn it into medicine
some things that can be helpful huffle for themselves and helpful for
others as an aside I'll say maybe this is
probably the reason why I like this story is that back when I was a biochemist at one of
the Laboratories down the whole they were working with Cobra Venom Factor as they were taking a cobra Venom
and extracting one particular kind of like the active ingredient and we're using it and did turned it into medicine
that can help people so this is you know this is sometimes what people do
but is there a way in which when we see poison fruit that we can pick the fruit
maybe not eat it but investigate it look at it look at it its properties and
treat it with respect and some understanding and use this as a way to find more
freedom for ourselves and maybe we can help others too
so what are some ways in which we can maybe get a little bit more tangible or practical
about how can we pick these poison fruits quote unquote and
help them to be medicine and support for our practice
some of you might know that here at Mcgill and Tanya Weiser they came up
with this acronym r-a-f-t raft
something that can help us cross over some choppy Waters something that can help us get to the other side where
freedom is so r recognize what's happening
this is a poison fruit this is a difficulty this is a difficult emotion
this is not what I wish what were happening
but is there a way that we can bring mindfulness to the experience
this is sadness and it feels like this
this is loneliness and it feels like this this is anger
and it feels like this sometimes just recognizing and even
using the label is hopeful because then we're not tangled up with it as much
there's a way in which there's a little bit more distance between ourselves and the experience
there's also a way in which when we label it or give it a name and just say
okay this is you know what I don't even know what this is but I feel out of
sorts and it feels like this there's a way in which there's a
honoring and respecting our experience honoring and respecting ourselves
instead of like being dismissive like we often are or instead of like blaming others or blaming ourselves
but just to recognize this uncomfortable experiences here
and of course this is the first Noble Truth there is suffering
this this second letter A is for allow is there a way that we can make space
for what is already here it's already here we're already
experiencing it is there a way that we can allow it to
be here kind of soften the pushing away
that we habitually do this is what humans do of
course we do we want to push away what's uncomfortable and there's a way that this kind of allowing
even the intention to allow is a way that we can interrupt the momentum this
habitual momentum of push things away
there's also a way in which mindfulness you know just recognizing being present
for it and allowing it as best we can as best we can there's a way in which it
can have a restraining quality maybe restraining is too strong of a
word so we like I kind of want to point you that's kind of like interrupting the
momentum so stopping the flow of some
maybe like some emotional experiences for example like anger
so is there a way that we can rather than
having this nature creaction of getting rid of it maybe we could just ask ourselves is
this something that really needs to be dealt with right now
is this something that needs a response right now
that we can allow it to be there and by allowing it to be
there we can understand it better if we want to work with something if we
wanted something to shift in our lives some difficulty it helps to understand it better
there's a way that also is kind of respecting ourselves respecting this is
what's happening and I I have the capacity to hold it in such a way that maybe I can
understand it have a little bit better
understanding of what this experience is like what are the conditions that help
it arise what does it feel like
when we come into contact with and allowing this experience and maybe feeling it is
maybe some compassion arises depression arises for ourselves
this warm-hearted feeling this warm-hearted recognition of yeah this is suffering this is difficult
that's coupled with a with this warm-hearted wish for it to be different
and this wish for it to be different is not the same as shoving it away it's
more compassion is this more warm-hearted quality
so allowing allows us to understand it respecting ourselves respecting their
experience some compassion to arise and allowing it increases our capacity
to be with difficulties this is definitely something that's a
skill that we have to train with it's natural that we don't want to be
with difficulties so it's a skill that we can train
we might ask well why would we want to train with something like that
guaranteed that in our lives there will be difficulties that
do not quickly and maybe never end
people that we care about people that we love have illness or die
we have illness or die we will die
we don't know when and we don't know how maybe there's you know world events that
we have no control over and just really affect us
so there will be large difficulties in our lives that we can't control so
just practicing with some of these simple ones learning how to allow even
the minor irritations that arise when person in front of you that's driving is
going way too slow when the line at the grocery store is
going away too slow when the person nearby is talking way
too loud on their phone this these mild irritations is fantastic
place to practice okay this is an irritation
and it I'm going to just allow this irritation to be here as best I can
r a f feel in the body
to the somatic experience of this often frustration anger sadness
loneliness all these things there's a lot of stories associated with them and
there's a lot of like we might say baggage associated with them my kind of and it's easy to do we of
course it is kind of get lost in the conceptual worlds or we kind of like generalize
like this is terrible and it's always going to be terrible and I'm always going to feel like this
and the best way to interrupt that to kind of cut the
stream or cut the cord or I don't know what the expression is stop the Train on
the tracks is to feel it in the body there's
frustration and it feels like this maybe my foot is tapping or maybe there's my
shoulders are going up towards my ears because I just want it to be different dang it
there's sadness and it feels like this of this real heaviness in the shoulders and the
maybe this knot in the stomach or the lump in the throat
for all of us it's different we don't all have a physical
association with these emotions aren't always the same
sometimes we're not even aware of what the bodily experience is
physiologists tell us that there are physical experiences that accompany
emotions so this is part of mindfulness practice is just to tune in and to be able to
experience them and it's a way to maybe stop the swirling
that's associated with difficulties and to just feel them in the body
and there's this way that by bringing them into the body that interrupts the flow
and by interrupting the flow you know the train of thoughts or the swirling that might happen there's a way
in which we kind of like keep the experience we might even say in check
so it's not continuing to snowball into getting something bigger and bigger
and Tom Jeff right he writes that getting to know the emotion including
the bodily experience is a like trying to know the currents of a
river like that this emotions do have this you know this momentum
and so even though like the surface may seem Placid and calm
of this emotion when we start to feel it in the body and
then we can flicker interrupting the the flow that happens
in the mind then we start to notice oh for a river we don't know how strong the
bottom currents are until we try to Dam it and then we kind of bring the awareness
to the body have like want to interrupt the flow of
the emotion then we really start to see oh there is a real strong momentum and
there my all of a sudden all this rationalization might start to arise
so bring it into the body not only interrupts the flow but it might also
make it more clear like what are some of the ways in which we
on some of the underlying maybe experiences that are supporting this
emotion for example
so RAF recognize allow feel in the body
tea to tease apart The Experience we're having the
difficult to experience from the reaction to the difficult experience we
might be filled with anger and then we don't want to think of ourselves as an angry person so we have aversion to the
anger and this aversion in some ways is getting all tangled up with the anger and it's kind of like
fueling the anger this is so common
so common in my role as a retreat teacher often when practitioners come in
they're sharing how things are going in their practice whether on Retreats you know they're seeing new things they're
understanding themselves better their mind and their bodies are getting settled
but often they don't see it's not so easy to see like okay there's the aversion we can
see that but often we don't see the second beat the aversion to the aversion
or the third beat the aversion to the aversion to the aversion so is there a way that we can tease
apart and often it's aversion to whatever we
are feeling and this aversion is a way of Tangled that kind of um fuels and allows the whatever it is
to happen whatever difficulty emotion we're experiencing to continue
often what we don't see too the way that we might actually like the
difficulty in some kind of way that's certainly not clear to us at the beginning but
we might notice that there's something about feeling
enraged feeling angry that we kind of like makes it feel powerful and
makes us feel like we have a purpose and we have this gives us license to say and
do whatever we want because we're angry we're not noticing now what it how
taxiness is and what a toll it takes not on us but on those people around us
so we're not noticing the aversion and we're not noticing the way in which we
might like it or there might be a way in which we're feeling like really uh greedy want more I need more I need more
and but there might be the way in which we actually feel attracted to not only
the object of whatever we're lusting after wanting greedy for
but there's this way in which we feel attracted to the feeling of really
wanting something because it distracts us from something
else or again it gives us a purpose or gives us a direction I need this okay I
just have to get this and we're not noticing how
this constricts our lives there isn't Freedom there when we just feel compelled to go after something
or the same way with anxiety maybe we of course you know nobody's
going to say they want anxiety but maybe there's a part of us that believes that
okay if I just worry enough I can make this problem go away maybe
this is like underneath we don't it's not clearly in our minds but
we might lose to get rid of this belief that worry isn't helpful because
we don't know what is helpful we don't want this uncomfortableness to
be there so
to work with some of these difficulties raft recognize allow feel in the body
and T support the experience from our reaction to the experience
I'm offering these in this order because it makes a nice acronym
doesn't mean we have to do this in this order we start Where We Are
maybe we've already recognized and we're just allowing or
maybe we're just filling a lot of aversion and we just are teasing apart like oh yeah this is a version and I
have a version to this aversion or whatever it might be
but there is a way in which we can take these poison fruit
and turn them into medicine I'm not saying this is easy
I'm not saying this is fast I'm not saying this is a linear path
do step one two three and you'll be finished
but I think you wouldn't trust these teachings too if I were to say oh just
do this and everything will be fine easy peasy right I think we know this
from life that undo habits
to undo some lifelong beliefs to undo what societal Society pressures
us to do not easy not fast
but it's possible it's possible and maybe it's not as
difficult as you think
maybe it just starts with a mindfulness practice
just being aware of what our experience is
starts there start Where We Are and I can start with that simple that
simple so I think I'll open it up to some
questions or comments if everybody has something that they'd like to say or
hi Diana I
really appreciate you talked about the raft again I heard several times
but every time I heard it is there different
reaction I have today is so clear
that everything makes sense but before I get to the last one
I want to tease apart but a lot of time
like you said the version the version of the Virgin the third aversion
it's like really fast slip and slope it's just few happened at
all at once so when look at that
usually I'm just it looks so solid it's just one thing
you know I I don't know what would be the skill to tease it apart
for example um this is probably not a good example but
one thing I'm struggling with is after the retreat
I realized my life had so much leakage of the time
you know so much leakage yeah it just suddenly the time is gone
but because of doing things mindlessly
then I thought well there's a fine line
do I treat my life as a project of improvement
or I really have a purpose I want to have a
dedicate most of the time as much as I can something I think it is
towards my life you know there's a fine line there
so so to tease it apart
again I don't know how to tease that apart
so you don't know how to tease apart so there's a fine line between your life as a it says you're leaking
time and that the uh it's a self-improvement project right that kind
of idea and it wasn't quite clear to me what the other part was
other part is whenever I have ideal situation like in the retreat
see my life is so clear you know I know what I want to do
I know what I shouldn't do in my daily life what I don't want to
waste time on I see that when I come back home
I would fall back to that then I don't want to represent myself
to harshly because I still have to live I see
yeah so while on Retreat you have some clarity and some inspiration and
motivation and then when you come back after you've been off a retreat for a while
then like what what happened how can I keep this clarity
yeah right this is a great question
so you were talking you said about teasing apart so to tease apart
I didn't I'm sure I understood to tease apart the what was hap your the leakage of time or
and and your wish for to be
using your time to as a support for practice
I would say you're going to teasing part anytime we're teasing apart
if it feels like oh wait this is too complicated I don't know I'm getting I can't figure this out I don't understand
then we could just say oh frustration it feels like this
instead of having to tease it apart we just say oh we could recognize and allow
frustration or recognize and allow disappointment recognize and allow confusion or
something like this and then there you are right in the practice again
and of course you know life outside of retreat isn't the same
as on Retreat right we want to we want to have some of the same benefits or yeah yeah
so helpful yeah thank you Lydia thank you
just wanted to share a joke I'm used to rain yeah for dealing with
the five hindrances yeah I'm not is it raft or is it rained and then I thought maybe it could just
be rafting rafting rafting
r-a-f-t-i-n refton apostrophe nice we just need to come up with a G what
would be G IV nice
recognize allow feel tease apart investigate nurture and give resting
I love it thank you very much how many letters is that was eight
letters that eight factors of working with hindrances or something like this
nice thank you
thank you hi thank you for the talk
um so I like the idea of raft and I've in
cultivating my my own mindfulness practice I do a lot of sort of inner exploration and things related to Raft which is
helpful um I also recognize the sort of therapeutic value of like
venting at times or sharing and I kind of heard elements of that in like the types
of people who tell everyone about the poison tree like maybe I'm not gonna
turn it into medicine but I'm gonna tell everybody about it to keep them safe and
I just recently I've had a hard time I've I've like felt this desire to sort of like
not quite shout my problems from a rooftop but you know sort of share or
like put them outward and not explore inward as much on my own but I also know
that there's like a there's like a healthy balance like Sangha is important and and support
and so just any words or ideas on sort of balancing this
inward light and then outward yeah yeah Dynamic here are some ideas and I
appreciate that you said that uh Sangha is important and sometimes we do connect kind of like with our shared
vulnerabilities right if we said like here's some difficulty that I have and it allows us to connect with others and
allows for some intimacy there's there's some release so yes and there's some release also
right and maybe others have you know some even just being recognized by others can be really supportive
but I think the Buddhist teachings are pointing to that just uh
allowing or let's say there's a recognition that we have habits of mind
and that if we feed habits of mine they're just always going to stay so there's value also in interrupting them
as we can so the Buddhist teachings would be opposite then of some go into
like there's some therapeutic uh modalities that suggest going into a
room and like hit pillows or something like this they're saying oh actually you're just increasing the amount of
Rage or whatever it is is happening so and that's not connecting with another
person that's just venting you know or something like that so they would make a
a distinction is this helpful yeah um and so when you say habit of mind
that that some people may have this habit of Mind of this desire to share their problems that's what I understood
or no I was thinking about a habit of Mind of like being angry and so if we're
just always expressing the anger her then we're just fueling The Habit to be
angry it's just easier and easier to be angry if we're always expressing it and
that's but sharing it with somebody else or you know connecting with somebody else about this is not it that would be
um not that's different you're talking about the anger you're not being angry
towards somebody yeah right yeah thank you thank you
okay so we're at the top of the hour so thank you thank you for your kind
attention and for your practice
and if you'd like to speak or come up to me you're welcome to do that otherwise I I wish you all a
wonderful evening thank you