so good morning everyone and
welcome to our sitting and and thank you for also for
welcoming back and nice to be back with you all after be gone for two weeks
and so for the meditation today
i want to evoke for you
one of the experiences that ideally
you would be inspired to enter into to really be interested in and
dedicated to as you meditate and that is
that experience which can be experienced
here and now that which can be seen and felt and
heard here and now that which can be known
only in the present moment that the past
doesn't exist anymore except in the thoughts
about the past and those thoughts are in the present moment and so to know and recognize oh
this is present moment thinking about the past
the future doesn't exist except as a prediction
certain thoughts and ideas but those thoughts exist and can be seen
and known and felt perhaps even if there's tension associated with them
or emotions they can be known and seen and felt here and now in the present moment
to really enter into the world of our inner life
that it's only here in the present moment to enter the world of our emotions
emotions in and of themselves only exist now
and to stay here to be inspired to value to
be interested in what can be visible here and now
this is where the dharma opens up this is where practice opens up
and it's hard to do because of the tremendous pull into
past and future fantasy thinking about things
these are important things that human beings do we don't want to dismiss them
but there's something very radically different that happens if we are clearly grounded
in touch with how those things are happening in the present moment
that we're not blinded by thoughts about the past to not see that all these are happening now
in a sense anything that you experience anything that
is occurring for you occurs in the present and this is where mindfulness
finds its grounding finds its center finds its opening
for us to meditate so to
assume a posture that hopefully
gives you an embodied experience of being grounded
centered here and now if the posture is too casual
if the posture is just too much you know slumping against the back of the couch
it might be more difficult to feel an embodied involvement with the present moment
to have your body support you and encourage you
into here and now
and to gently lower your gaze
and gently close your eyes
and one of the reasons we focus on breathing in meditation
is that it's a rhythmic
experience that is continuously in the present
moment here and now and to ride the rhythms of breathing
to begin by taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing on the exhale
becoming centered or grounded in that relaxation
by settling into your place
here and now
and then letting your breathing return to normal
a bit more on the exhale relax throughout your body
and as you exhale relax the thinking mind
the more there is pressure in the mind agitation in the mind
anxiety or desires in the mind
the easier it is to slip away from the present moment
to be concerned about other things at other times in other places
but to relax the thinking mind soften
to gentle the thinking mind
um
and then to settle into your breathing again
the breathing being part of your lived experience
to call it a lived experience is another way of saying that which is
happening for you here and now right here and now
the only place you can experience your vitality or
whatever way it is for you to experience being alive
eh
and it's here in your direct experience
where we will discover what the buddha was pointing at the dharma
you don't need to look for it
but to remember how valuable and important it is
probably the most important thing at this moment is to be here
with your present moment experience not pulled
and lost in the world of thinking but pulled into the world of direct
experience breathing
um
so
perhaps after these minutes of sitting
you are changed a bit maybe calmer or settled
or maybe more sensitive
in being so you can better settle into your direct immediate
experience
independent of the future and the past
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
our capacity to care for others to
have good will love kindness generosity
are all
things that exist only as we're doing them
only as they're present for us within us
to be centered grounded here in the direct experience
gives us the opportunity to know
connect with whatever degree of goodwill we have for this world
that we have for others that we have for all the creatures in
this world
and here in the present moment that's so important
it is the location place time from time to time
that we can give expression to this care for the world
and to take whatever benefit we've received from this meditation practice
and dedicate it for the welfare and happiness of others
at the benefit you receive you don't have to give it away
but you can
dedicate it use it
to support others may all beings
benefit from this meditation
may this time that we've meditated together support us in bringing
welfare and happiness peace safety to others
may this practice of the dharma be for the welfare happiness safety and
freedom of all the people and creatures that we
encounter may all beings be a beam
[Music]
so [Music]
thank you
so warm greetings to you all and for this week
i'd like to take the theme
the dharma the dharma that the buddha taught
and there is a ancient
teaching about this dharma that the buddha taught
that describes how someone understands the dharma
when they have a confirmed confidence
in the dharma in the buddha in the practice that we're doing
and this idea of confirmed confidence means that we've we know something we've
experienced something for ourselves that we know what the dharma is about
we know something in the dharma that there's a confidence a
deep sense of maybe maybe faith maybe trust
but the most common way to talk about this is a confidence which is peaceful
a peaceful confidence and
this and so to practice to come to an enough
to have one's own personal experience that from that experience one feels oh
this dharma this teachings of the buddha this world of practice
is something i know for myself that well enough that i have confidence in it
and one of the kind of tests for this confidence is
if someone comes along and like for example i came along and came down sat down one of these
7 a.m sittings and i said well you know something
i was completely wrong that all this dharma stuff that we've been teaching and doing you know it's
not really you know right and and
you know there's probably better things to do with your life and you know i recommend you to kind of give
it up and when one has a confirmed confidence because one has experiences the benefits
and the transformations and the and the freedom from this practice
that it doesn't matter what i say because you would know you know well i'm sorry
for you guild you might say but i know for myself how much i've benefited i know for myself
the value of the dharma this practice that i do and i'll continue
and um because i know for myself and and so this idea of this really knowing
it and having this confidence so how does one come to that kind of
confidence and so the the five there's a five part description
of what this well proclaimed dharma the welcome proclaimed
we could say teachings of the buddha but the dharma is not a teaching in the abstract like a set of a creed or a set
of prophet propositions the dharma is
is part of our lived experience things that when we discover in our lived experience
that shows us a way to live a wise and
and good life so what is it about dharma that provides that what do we see what's going on here
and so there's a five-part description and of what we have confidence in and what
we know and and it's possible in a sense to do kind of reverse engineering
to understand these five parts and and this will tell us what the dharma is
um in some kind of deeper way so as opposed to just some abstract teachings of the buddha or some kind of
vague i don't know principles or
natural forces that we connect to it's um you know we really discover it for
ourselves and these five qualities of the dharmak five characteristics
are frequently chanted when people do in a terrible tradition they chant
and the english goes like this the dharma is well proclaimed by the
buddha by the blessed one it is visible here and now
immediate inviting inspection
onward leading and to be personally experienced by the wise
so i'll take each of these days we'll take one of those and look at it more deeply
so the first one is that um it's called uh san ditico in pali
and um and it has it refers to the fact that it's directly visible
the dt here means to see what you can be seen and and we often say in english for this
phrase visible here and now the here and now is not in the word just
like if the word is to be is it's seen uh it's known
and uh the only thing seeing always happens in the here and now and so by adding here and now it's
really emphasizing the immediacy of the experience and the immediacy of the knowing of it
and it doesn't have to be only with the eyes it says the word is visible but it's
visible with the mind's eye with all the different capacities we have for direct attention
we can sense so we can hear we can feel we can know in the mind directly what's
happening and so this is so the dharma that well complained
proclaimed by the buddha is not something that you have to believe or find in a book
it's something that we can see for ourselves and in fact sometimes it's said that
everything you need to know in buddhism can be discovered by your own powers of observation
all but you have to look carefully and maybe the what that the teachings do when the instructions do
is to point us to how to see in the present moment so that we that dharma really comes alive for us
but so for today that is the value of our direct experience
and to see it clearly when the buddha wanted to explain a bit
further what this means san ditiko that the dharma is directly visible here
and now he referred to our psychological states
that we can feel we can know we can see experience directly
that there is kind of unhealthy states of mind present there might be
greed or hatred and delusion there might be jealousy or envy or there might be
avariciousness it might be lust there might be
anger now there might be you know resentment all kinds of things
might be in the mind conceit one can know it directly that is
and there's two things that can happen without direct seeing this that
in the clear seeing we if the seeing is clear enough strong enough
that we are not then identified with those states we're not involved in participating in those states it's
almost like we can instead take a step back and observe what's happening
rather than being in the middle of the fray and this is a powerful thing to do
for all the kind of difficult states of mind activities and forces that exist within a human being
to not be invested in it not be caught by it not be reactive to it not be
struggling with it but to step back step back in a sense open up open up in a
sense so there's an over overview of it with mindfulness with awareness there's a clear sense
this is happening in the present moment this is here and uh and this is what it feels like
and this is what it's like to know it this is what it's like to step
back far enough or step get the overview high enough
so oh this is what it's like and then we're not caught in it and involved in it
and if we're not caught or involved if we really discover how to see it that
kind of way then the these unhealthy states of mind
have much less or maybe no power over us and to see the and to see that
to see the presence of unhealthy states of mind clinging and grasping and resistance and
hating to see it there and then see
ourselves being
unattached to it unentangled with it to see that we can clearly know it
without believing it or being pushed around by it or this is a phenomenal thing to discover
even more phenomenal is to see that these unhealthy states of mind can disappear
for some people certain kind of chronically unhealthy states of mind
can be so deeply ingrained with we don't even know we don't even know we have it
or we don't assume that it's always this way this is part the universe was built this way to have these states of mind
but to have these drop away to have the experience of
life without them can be life-changing for some people to know
that there's another way wow you mean i don't have to always be
afraid i don't have to always be aversive i don't have to always be
critical or always kind of
fighting for what i want it's possible to find some peace in a different way
so when so that's how the buddha kind of elaborate on this idea that the dharma
is visible here and now and and so what it means is that we want to
be able to see clearly what is happening for us here and now
and what is can be quite marvelous wonderful and wondrous
is we discover our capacity to see us unhealthy states of mind
within us and and not to
believe in them or react to them or to use them as a basis for criticizing ourselves
all we're asked to do is to know it directly for what it is
and then we can start seeing the freedom from it the ways in which we can kind of know it
so clearly we're not caught by it so so to see that over and over and over
again to see that to develop this capacity to be here and now
is can be a that's kind of the direction that's going
so we're cultivating and developing our capacity to be in our lived experience
the experience of here the experience of now and the stronger that capacity can be
the more we're interested in this the more we decrease
the drive some of the unhealthy often unhealthy drive that pulls us into the
world to the past pulls us into the world of the future pulls us into the world of fantasy and
and rumination and and as we do this
we get to appreciate the richness and the
texture and the and the all the different
heightened opportunities potential that is available here in the present moment now
i think of the being fully present here and now as like a
like opening a door into it into a multi-dimensional
experience of life that is not available if we spend our days in our thoughts past future
fantasies desires whatever they might be so the dharma that the buddha taught
is something that's directly visible here and now and i'd encourage you for this day of
practice that stay that you have before we meet again tomorrow
that maybe you can begin
not begin but kind of make it make it a task make it a
a real activity of the day to really be present
in a relaxed calm way
with what can be experienced directly here and now
the dharma is visible here and now
thank you