so good morning everyone good day and uh
we're coming now to the
we're coming now to the in the very end of this series on
on this and um
and it's uh there's a practice that is offered by the buddha
for the purposes of ending sorrow lamentation suffering
distress for the purification of beings for the attainment of
nibana or liberation it's uh designed to address some of the
most fundamental existential issues of that humans can have
and while it's sometimes taught in the modern world mindfulness at least is thought for stress reduction
this satibatana discourse is really being taught here for the highest
realization of the end of suffering and in this regard it's often
and traditionally this practice of sati patana is considered to be the
best practice to have as a person is dying so to learn this practice well and have
it close at hand and then to just as as we're dying to have this
available to know to value it to be able to do it with some yeas not
as a forceful practice but as almost as a natural expression of
life as we're dying and there's a teachings the buddha gave to his son
that he said that if someone cultivates mindfulness in this case he was talking about mindfulness of breathing
that a person will know their last inhale
and last exhale as it ceases as it ends
the tradition says that this means that the person will die calmly
but i believe it's deeper than that that there's something about being calmly present
for one and really present for one's last breath without being afraid without being angry without being
distressed is a phenomenal opportunity phenomenally
wonderful and important way to die and
and so the question for this meditation for you is that what is it
about being present for the end of especially the exhale but
the end of the inhale the end into the exhale as if it's once last exhale
once last inhale and that one follows it all the way out calmly
and what's available there in terms of letting go in terms of peace
what is it and that's kind of the question i'd like to leave you for here
for this meditation is that as you settle down and are present
what um what might there be there with
riding tracking the ending of the inhale the ending of
the exhale that is invaluable
at the time of dying the ceasing the letting go the releasing
and perhaps during this sitting with all that we've done now these months on sativatana and
being present for experience maybe there can be this question that you and did you engage in with every
exhale every inhale what is it
um what is it about that exhale what happens there what's available
there what's the possibility there what's what is it that is is uh
so important so valuable that the buddha is pointing to
and i suggest that if you take this up as a way of being present today this
question that you don't answer it analytically you don't answer it cognitively so much
that might come as a byproduct but rather
in the stillness of the mind the answer is in the stillness and the silence and the peacefulness
but have a question and see what what comes
and then we'll just sit here today quietly and you have
had lots of instructions here and guidance and today
you're left here with yourself and your own breathing
so
sitting here as if each exhale will be your last exhale ever
being there fully for the exhale
and the letting go
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
what place of quiet stillness is available for you
at the end of the exhale or any place at all
that be a valuable way to sit next to someone who's dying
to be present for them with care and
value and kindness with love
and as their about to take their last breath
and to use the analogy of the last breath maybe highlights the preciousness
of life the value ever present value
of showing up and being present for what is here for the people in our lives
not distracted not caught in the hindrances
maybe not caught up in judgments and projections
but to be able to be present really present with a quiet heart quiet
mind at times is one of the best deepest ways
to find our
deep connection to each other whether
we know it or not we are in fact deeply connected
and perhaps this satipatta practice can help us to
sit freely and peacefully intimately
with that connection free of clinging
and with care may we care for everyone
all the people suffering all the people going through this human life
may it be that they are happy
may it be that they find safety
may it be that they find peace
may it be that they find freedom
may we pray we live for the welfare and benefit and care
of everyone we encounter
[Music]
so good morning and we're coming to the penultimate
talk on satypatana
and after all these months now over four months of going through it slowly
and coming to the end and we'll all come to an end at some
point and this sativatana practice
is considered to be one of the greatest practices to do as we're dying
and the
you know if we if we wait until we're dying to begin our practice
we won't have we won't have developed our practice we want to have the practice won't be there as a strong
resource for us at those times and
the what i've learned through this sativatana practice
um and been doing it doing this practice for now many decades
it uh generally gives me a very uh positive feeling about dying my
relationship to my death is if i'm lucky to die
consciously and without dementia or without too much
pain that um i just anticipated to be being one of the great
things to be present for and this letting go that undoubtedly undoubtedly undoubtedly
happens there as we're dying is one of the best things going really wonderful thing to do the experience
that i've had of letting go deeply and deeply deeply i now kind of associate that also with dying
and so i don't feel that dying is so much an end as it is a
a releasing and letting go and letting go into i don't know but
they uh i don't it doesn't matter so much to me what we're letting go into
um maybe nothing but just the letting go is so so wonderful so peaceful so
happiness so freeing
so to to consider this practice we've been doing all these months
that one of the purposes for it is uh to come to terms with find our
peace find our our center in our freedom uh in relationship to some of the
deepest and most challenging aspects of human life and this is why i think
you know this is kind of represented by how the text begins
and how it uh it ends in the end it goes
um so this so it was with re reference to this
that it has said this is a direct path for the purification of beings for the
surmounting of sorrow and lamentation for the disappearance of pain and grief
for the attainment of the way for the realization of nibanam namely
the four foundations for awareness and um
so in some terrible countries or you know temples or
often there's a practice of of reciting this as someone is dying or after they've
died because of its this associated there's a very close association with the practice
of satipatana as we're dying one of the ways to appreciate this is
that you know as we're as we're dying that all kinds of things no longer are
that important and uh when you know we're not in the last our last breaths we're not
uh concerned about whether or not we need to buy more socks or not or you know what are we gonna have for
supper what is all kinds of things that and
and you know and to be able to let go of concerns and thoughts which are not relevant at that
time to be able to let go of fears desires distress
to really kind of not have that get in the way of the fullness of the moment that
the opportunity of the moment and to this practice teaches us
that we have something better to do than be distressed something better to do than being afraid something better to
do than being lost in fantasy and thoughts and projections and ideas
not that we can necessarily put all those things aside but our our life and interest the energy the
attention doesn't go there anymore we can let go of it and and focus on this practice of sati
patana practice of being aware and being awake being present that that is the better alternative than
so many of the ways our minds can go and uh to practice at the patara this
practice of mindfulness a lot uh helps us to see over and over again in a deeper clearer way
how it's the better alternative how it's the this is where life is found freedom is
found peace is found more often than what else the other things the mind is doing
and the compulsion to uh of some certain
our thoughts and certain ones of our feelings and attitudes as much as they might seem important to
us through this practice we see that there's something better to do
there's something much more freeing much more peaceful some much more alive much more satisfying
to do than um uh thinking about our resentments
thinking about wrong how other people are wrong thinking about
regrets we have over our lifetime i mean all those things can have a place in
life but to realize that they're not the best alternative they're not the best place
the most valuable place to be do not invest so much in so many things
which are uh to our detriment that diminish us that our wind drag for us ourselves
and to know what where what's the best alternative to see that
being awake being aware being present is the best alternative going
even even at the very beginning i mean at the very end this last breath
that we have what's the best thing to do at that point would you would you know that do you
have a fa feel really feel this is how you want that last breath to be
i hope it's not you know wondering how many you know who's going to get your socks when you die
i hope that it's uh you know there's really something there and then maybe there's a letting go of
the world around you even and the relationships at that for that breath maybe there's a letting go into being
awake into being aware letting go into release letting go
and um and um
so to so that all these months so we've been doing satyapathanam
uh it comes to this that um it's really about some of the most
essential deepest aspects of our life and death represents that but there's all kinds of suffering that
human beings have um that the human realm is filled with suffering and
challenges and how do we meet it how do we address it
how do we find our way through it and for the buddha
this is the unified way this is the direct way this is the way
and i think of it as the simplest most uncomplicated un
way all the way through to to freedom to liberation
so um well thank you and
we do our last talk tomorrow and and i look forward to
our time thank you
you