okay and it's the audio okay all right so hello and warmly welcome to
happy hour everyone lovely to see you lovely to be with you
ah so so for the theme for for today
this morning this evening whatever your time zone might be
um the theme is um
self care self love self forgiveness just it's a blend of those it's a blend of
those it's really an invitation the theme tonight as an
invitation for examining how we often respond
to when we make mistakes and when mishaps happen and of course we're human it's error to
be human we say things that later we think ah hmm
that was not very skillful or we do things that um are
not helpful or or maybe even hurtful to ourselves or or to others in
intentionally inadvertently um and in those moments when we or when or
we even do things i don't know that later it seemed like they were not the best decisions in retrospect and so do
we kick ourselves do we berate ourselves oh you are
fill in the blanks stupid terrible mind mindless gosh do we berate ourselves how do we
treat ourselves in that moment oh you should have paid more attention you
should have could have should have like oh oh oh oh how do we treat ourselves in those
moments in these moments there may be plenty of them because again to er
is to be him with these timings not huge mistakes not but just tiny little
mistakes throughout the day or mishaps or or decisions that are not
ideal if we had spend more time etc so so how how do we how do we what is our
the way that we hold ourselves what if what if in that moment because we've already you know been hurt say by
our decision or our lack of attention or lack of awareness or or whatever it might be we've already been hurt right
it wasn't an optimal decision like oh what if we say oh sweetheart sweetheart
oh i'm so sorry well this is hard for you i know this is hard it's okay
it's okay sweetie this is hard yeah this is it's okay it's okay i still love you
i i accept you it's okay and it's all right let's
let's learn from it let's move on and i forgive you it's okay it happens it's
earth it's it's human to earth to er is human it's really okay
do we extend that acceptance that love that sense of forgiveness
to ourselves and in the guided meditation i will invite you to try the different perspectives on
and see how they feel physically in the body how do they feel in the body in the mind
and see for yourself which one is more conducive um
to to actually both recovery and also learning and also
um maybe more mindful behavior later there are some research results also um well maybe
i'll share the research results as i'm sharing uh as i'm sending the space right now
but there is there is a couple of very interesting studies one is um
that for people who actually have um who have made
some kind of mistake or maybe transgression in this study was a moral transgression that they tested
if they um if they were primed towards
self-compassion towards care for themselves they actually took more responsibility
instead of taking less responsibility because there was a sense of oh yes it's okay i it's just it was a mistake was it
um but i'm not wholly bad it was not the sense of throwing the baby out with a
bat or bath water it's the sense of it's okay i made a mistake and learning
from it instead of if you don't have that cushion of
self-compassion then there might be pointing the finger to
others oh it's their fault that's why this happened right because there's no kindness towards oneself when there's
kindness compassion towards you you can accept that yeah you screwed up it wasn't optimal and it's it's okay it's
really okay there's that cushion to take responsibility
whereas when there isn't that cushion when there is the harshness of you should have done better you idiot
then then somewhere deep down inside that we don't want to take responsibility because if
we do then we're bad we're awful there's no recovery right so then people point
fingers to others oh it's their fault it's they dated their you know right
yeah et cetera whereas actually kindness to oneself
um allows one to to uh take responsibility so so
um and one last thing i would say is that as you know compassion towards oneself
and towards others it's not it's not just the sense of care and
warmth and and um uh softness gentleness it it does have
those aspects to it but also there's an uprightness there's a sense of power there's a sense of
goodness there's a sense of fierceness yes yes there was a mistake and it's
okay it actually makes you feel stronger in your
morality in your intentionality so it has the both softness the gentleness
as well as the sense of uprightness and the the energetic uh fierceness in it so it'll hopefully
all become more clear as we practice together all right i've said plenty to set the stage
so let's begin let's begin let's begin as i like to invite you
to land in your body
to arrive to arrive in your body
here
and allow yourself to feel your feet
planted rooted in this earth and this precious earth
this precious body and this precious earth
it's okay it's okay
releasing releasing
whatever the body is holding energetically
unto the earth through your feet
through your sit bones onto the cushion or the chair
releasing your shoulders your neck
as if you're releasing the burdens that you have been carrying around the proverbial
weight you've been carrying to release in this moment it's okay
taking refuge taking refuge the simplicity of this moment
it's okay it's all right
releasing any tension [Music] in your jaw
your eye socket letting your eyes rest
deeply
letting your forehead relax
your cheeks your chin your ears
inviting your heart center your proverbial heart center inviting you to relax
center of your chest whatever emotions are present it's okay it's all right
they can be here just as they are releasing any tightness or
pushing away or clinging to it's okay relaxing all of that
relaxing releasing the abdomen
sit bones upper legs knees lower legs and feet
as well as the arms and hands this entire
body bringing awareness relaxed
spacious awareness to the whole body present
pulsating sensing [Music]
breathing the whole body breathing
this miracle of nature letting the breath be received in the
abdomen lowering lowering the center of gravity
and we'll spend a few minutes just
letting this body be breathed bringing awareness receiving the breath with
awareness in the body in the body
this
calming soothing breath one breath at a time [Music]
and if the mind is wandering resting on thoughts
it's okay it's all right simply seeing
observing noticing it's arising
with a smile as if it's a beloved puppy that has
wondered
about our beloved child you won't beat them up it's okay
it's the nature of puppies and little kids to wonder
gently ever so gently call them back come back sweetie come back
ah releasing it's okay
and finding ease comfort seclusion of the mind that's nourishing
healing just here with the breath
in the body
can awareness be imbued with appreciation for this breath in this
moment
the breath being known in the abdomen
a kindness with a smile greeted with a smile
inner smile
now i'd like to invite you if you want
if it feels okay
to gently bring to mind maybe something
that recently
you considered a mistake
something you did or said [Music]
that later you wish you had done differently you regret it you were upset you were
disappointed
be very gentle as you call this into your heart not into your head so much we don't want so much of a
story bringing the memory back
maybe a misstep oh stepped off the curve
twisted your ankle oh i wish i had looked or had been able to look more carefully
whatever it might be
see in your body what the habitual response might feel like
just to just to explore what does it feel like to have
the habitual response you tend to have of course we're bringing compassion in
the moment to compare but for now
is it disappointment sadness anger
whatever it might be how does it feel or maybe it's too hard to bring it up
and so don't don't try too hard it's okay it's all right see what's available
just recognizing just tiny bit of it is okay the tinge of that reaction reactivity
or i wish it hadn't happened or how could you whatever it might be
and notice how tight that might feel sense of tightness contraction
physically that that brings perhaps in your heart center
center of your chest
maybe in your belly too maybe in your jaw maybe in your shoulders
and see where you feel it forehead maybe see where is the contraction for you
around the i could have would have
just to feel it i know it doesn't feel good so we won't linger here too long
just to get a sense comparison
and now opening opening the heart wide as if
there are these worn arms that are embracing you holding you
lovingly acceptingly compassionately sweetheart it's okay
ah maybe putting
a balm in your heart center or wherever there's a contraction the balm of
acceptance of recognition of forgiveness it's okay sweetie
yes yes it's okay this was hurtful
to you you've already been hurt dear you don't need to add
to injury don't need to add
salt pour salt and a cut it's okay
it's alright sweetheart it's already hard enough
this injury this
suffering this pain this difficulty as a result of the mistake you don't
have to add to it it's okay holding holding yourself
as if you're warm gentle accepting embrace it's okay
to err is to be human you're only human
family just like anybody else
where you see you hear you cognize you decide with limited information you
process it's all limited it's okay
it's a part of being human dear it's okay
it's all right it happens
it's okay letting yourself feel held
acceptance with forgiveness and if you need if you'd feel supportive
actually to put a hand in the middle of your chest as if you were putting this ball
[Music] was this this arm putting this hand putting balm
[Music] soothing accepting compassionate balm in your heart center please try that see
what that feels like experiment with it for a moment can be powerful
self-touch can be quite powerful
give it a try even if you've tried it before see what it's like in this moment
it's okay
you did your best you did your best in that moment
you've done your best if you could have done any differently any better you would have of
course you would have of course you would have there's no doubt you would have
given all the causes and conditions in that moment
internally externally so many different
the things and conditions gave rise
to it happening the way it did
if you could have done differently you would have
so trust trust and forgive
yourself and the causes and conditions that came together
forgive those two and the part that you played it wasn't
just alone you [Music] there's other things too
so recognize those recognized
the causes and conditions
forgiving them forgiving yourself
holding yourself with care with love you're already hurting
you've already been hurt not kicking or hitting
yourself as if it beloved a child or a little
puppy it's okay
you've done your best
letting go of the contraction
releasing there is no use there is no use
to feeling contracted
especially if there is shame or challenging emotions no use we can have
remorse learn
from what went wrong in
a sphere of compassion this fear of care
just holding yourself with care with kindness
you are both mother and the child there's the sense of power uprightness
forgiveness courage grace
that you can extend to yourself both give and receive
both the mother and the child sense of
energy fierceness uprightness powerful love
that holds the hurt and holds the tenderness
it's okay sweetheart it's okay
and as we move closer to the end of this sit together
releasing letting go or whatever rose or did not arise
letting there be a sense of appreciation we showed up we did our best
so many causes and conditions can we forgive can we hold with care with love
this being who is us doing their best
we could do any better could have done better we would have it's all okay
appreciating appreciating ourselves and all
who are practicing with us in community appreciating them
their goodness
and this way creating wholesome karma if we bring love care
forgiveness to what might have been challenging or
difficult or unskillful at least we're planting
wholesome seeds kindness forgiveness wisdom
instead of more anger aversion disappointment
self-flagellation and sharing this goodness
sharing this goodness with generosity with all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere all us beings all us humans who make
mistakes may all of us
be happy be healthy [Music] be safe
may all of us have ease may all of us be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes for reflections
what you might have discovered what came up and you're invited to share
whatever you would like to share for the benefit of others for the benefit of sangha
um offering a gift your offering gift through your reflections
your questions maybe what went wrong what didn't work it's all okay
and you can [Music] raise your zoom hand if it's your physical hand i will not see because
there are multiple pages on my zoom and and uh you can type them in chat
um charles lee says thanks thank you charlie thanks for your practice
you can type them to everyone in which case i'll read your name or just to me privately
um in which case i won't read your name it'll be private so
so gifts from the sangha discoveries
did you notice a shift what was it like at the beginning with the habitual way that you
respond to the mistake um versus when you brought in the
embracing hugging arms and the balm did you notice the difference
what happened
and holding space of silence is perfectly fine in this community we know that
so it's all good
i'll share something with you as i wait not wait but as i hold space for any
reflections that might come up from you um for me as i was doing this practice yes
there's definitely it's so interesting just a little bit of contraction and for me it's more in the heart center like oh
i wish that didn't happen and then oh sweetheart it's okay it's okay and then there's a sense of
strength and uprightness really is as i lead you guys of course i'm i'm in
that space with you i mean that space with you elaine says i appreciated taking the
time to be gentle and have deep forgiveness with myself thank you lilly and jamie i do see your name for your
hand please um well if i want to thank you for the
invitation to both give and receive a mother's love
um i i hope i'll remember to revisit that again
um you know cis man and father i've never given a mother's love before
and it was it was really amazing to try it thank you
thank you so much amy thank you for for sharing that so beautiful
yeah thank you for exploring that and and that lighting up for you as as you said
as this man as the father beautiful thank you i'm so touched yay
yay made support you and your journey
as a human being as a cis man as the father beautiful
sarah says i like that notion that the more self-compassionate we have for
ourselves the less we need to blame others yes yes isn't that great
isn't that wonderful and see it for yourself just the study is pretty cool
and and i wondered if that came up for you experientially also in this practice
like oh it was their fault they should have done it this way or that way maybe like oh well it's okay it's all right
right it's okay i didn't see or something like that so
yeah pretty cool so [Music]
how about we turn into practicing
in community in small groups of three on zoom and
holding each other with compassion with with care
um and as always we only speak from our own
experience or you can be silent you don't have to say anything you can hold space when it times your turn you can
say pass and be present it's perfectly fine and
you're invited if you like to share what came up for you what did you discover and even if you fell asleep or
distracted that's okay too no problem that that's what you can practice with in the moment well usually
i would beat myself up because i fell asleep but no it's okay sweetie you didn't get a lot of sleep last night
right can you practice in real time with these instructions with these invitations
and so in small groups the invitation is
one person will share one nugget of their experience and then the next person and then the next person and
they'll come back to you and then we'll go around and round until they're the time is up
and and again please only share from your own experience
authentically as much or as little as you like to share silence is fine and
not managing directing probing others let let them have their
own experience just holding space this is part of the practice holding compassionate space
for all of us humans we're doing the best we can doing the best we can so
so with that i'd like to create the rooms the breakout rooms which i haven't
yet created here we go and um [Music]
let's see if there are any invitations that i usually give which i forgot and i think i think that's it so so here we go
i'm going to open their rooms be kind to yourself be kind to each
other what a fantastic way to practice
in sangha here we go
okay the rooms are closed welcome back everyone
and we have just about a couple minutes if there are any reflections questions comments um
after having practiced in in small groups so katrin please
um i was really grateful for this practice it's very very apropos for me um
i've had this question and maybe you can't speak to it in this short amount of time but it really
troubles me which is like the thing if we could do if we could have done something different than
we would have and but like how does that work in the present moment when we are
trying to make a decision it's not a philosophical question because it's really like
how do i make a decision if if that is the case i feel responsible
but but then it couldn't have happened any other way yeah yeah part of a greater issue of
decision making for me but oh oh it is yeah yeah i appreciate yeah it is it is
um given the 30 seconds left i'll try to do it justice here he goes a big
philosophical question think of it this way or feel into it this way
that you know there are a lot of causes and conditions there are external internal and think of it as
probabilistic right because really the question you're asking me brings in the question of freeville free will do we
have free will or do we not have free will like if i can't do any different like why am i uh but i do feel like i i
have intentionality i want to have intentionality so all of those really
come together um it's it's really the weight of and the idea of
karma is it's not deterministic karma isn't deterministic or causes and conditions aren't deterministic it's
just that the problem the probability is kind of stacked this way right it's stacked this way but if you
really work hard and you know you just you can shift and change it but it's if it's
really stacked in a particular way like oh yeah that's the way it would have gone it would be really hard to change
it in that one but it doesn't mean that i can't keep trying and shifting and
setting the intention so that it becomes more likely so in the example that i gave with you know stop stepping off the
curve and getting it you know uh sprained ankle like oh yeah you know
maybe you know glasses were up from wearing a mask it's like all these causes and can be like
oh yeah okay and yet and yet i know i can change the karma like okay
now i know wearing the mask like this is what happens like i will change it i can but in that moment that's the best that
could have happened because this is just a simple so so there is free will in well anyway
that's a bigger question i don't want to say that but anyway i'm just uh does that help
hold both of those uh for you both the past and then present
yeah and it's a yeah and it's a forgiving perspective that's like um that's evolutionary it's like oh yeah
like things change like yeah it makes me think of life as that you
know sort of a practice and an experiment versus like a constant test of getting things right right hey i
appreciate that beautiful i appreciate you putting it there exactly it's just
just always yeah with kindness forgiveness we're going to keep trying keep intending turning turning keep turning
advertising changing the the stream keeps trying to change the stream and yet when it's there's so many forces
it's okay it's okay sweetheart so yay what a rich hour thank you all for your
practice thank you for your practice hanging in here thank you all beautiful
dedicating the merit may all beings be well may all beings be forgiving may all
beings be free [Music]
thank you take care be well