so welcome everyone and to our sunday morning here at imc
and uh today is juneteenth day
which is a one of two independence
holidays that you have here in united states freedom holidays
and perhaps for those who meditate while we're meditating
it's uh the call to freedom can begin in our own hearts
movement to be free within ourselves
of ourselves to be free of the tremendous
pull and influence of our attitudes our ways of thinking our greed
our clinging our attachments our fears and there's something in our hearts that
here's a call that sends forth a call
for that freedom and for that freedom to begin with ourselves
then perhaps we can hear the call for freedom in our society
that we can support so perhaps in this sitting today
maybe what can guide you inspire you
encourage you to really be present be here in this experience of the moment
is your own heart's impulse
to not be limited to not be defined by thoughts and
attachments and clingings distractions
maybe you can be inspired by your capacity to step
beyond through all attachments all clingings all
inner oppressions that we live by so the heart can be free
here and now so to take a meditation posture
and there's a history of in buddhism there's a history in buddhism of
this meditation posture representing either directly or symbolically
a certain kind of dignity nobility in
claiming or or establishing in our posture
a certain kind of freedom and independence
that might help enable the greatest freedom of heart
so what would your posture be if they had your posture express that
and if you're comfortable with it to gently close your eyes
and if it's comfortable for you to take a few long slow deep breaths with the exhale settling in to
yourself
with the exhale letting go into your depth
letting go into your heart or your horror
a place of grounding stability
here and now
letting your breathing return to normal
and in the center of all things there's a welcome there's a call
come here here
you're being called to freedom in the midst of all things your
breathing your body your mind
here come and see
freedom is to be freedom is to be found
okay
and as we come to the end of this sitting
to practice with the buddhist
bridging of our practice to the welfare of the world around us
we dedicate the merit we dedicate the benefits of this sitting
and may it be that any of the benefits the welfare
the insights the freedoms that we recognize or intuit
through this practice may we
consider think about how we can apply them
to benefit others and we can wish and hope that in fact
directly or indirectly consciously or unconsciously
that this these minutes of meditation
serve for the welfare and happiness of all beings may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may we contribute to that
possibility
[Music]
so
so good morning everyone and welcome to imc and
here in person and also online and uh
so today is the anniversary of
the delayed emancipation of african americans here in the united
states some two two and a half years after abraham lincoln lincoln signed the
emancipation proclamation it took that long too for
some of the slaves in this country to and slaveholders to finally
realize that freedom from slavery in texas
in uh 1865.
and uh it's now that it's become the
national holiday it's this it's the united states now has two
independence days and uh the first one marks a certain kind of
independence and also represents in many ways
an independence that was only partial independence that ended up legalizing
the enslavement of other people so a freedom that some people attained
but which institutionalized or
sanctioned the lack of freedom for others
and it took almost another hundred years before
legally that freedom became much more complete in that
slaves were emancipated and as probably many of you know this
the history but that's been celebrated every year first in galveston texas
and then it spread to texas and to other places over time and uh
until now it's a national holiday
and uh the people who mostly celebrated until recently have been
black americans who were most impacted by this and it was a certainly a celebration for
them over their this freedom from slavery it was also a
remembering of the horrendous oppression and suffering that their
ancestors went through and it's good to remember
and then there's uh but also many african-americans have used the time
as a celebration of their achievements their perseverance
how far how brilliantly some of them have worked through their
oppression including the challenges they've had over the last hundred and
sixty seventy years since emancipation
and uh and uh you know it's remarkable how much
african-americans have contributed to this culture not just contributed institutions to help make it
with uh some phenomenal achievements and uh highest levels of government and
military and science and literature and music just goes on and on
so this day is is also the celebration of this the tremendous drive its creativity and
capacity of this population of people who who've been so oppressed
and for me personally i'm inspired very much by by this perseverance
this the degree to which so many of them have not given up have not
turned around to to
reject this country but really have stepped up in a powerful
way to claim their place as citizens of this country proud
citizens of this country and have met with oppression and violence and murder and
all kinds of things some of them with persevering and insisting on the truth
insisting on asserting or finding their freedom but also
many of them maybe partly from their christian background but a message of forgiveness and love
it's phenomenal to see how this has worked that someone was so much stacked against them so much
horrible things done to them have kept showing up showing up showing up over and over again
and excelled in so many different ways including in the capacity to love
i've met a number of african-americans who are been practitioners some of them have become teacher buddhist teachers
and have learned a little bit about their personal story and how challenging it's been growing up in this country and
and what they've had to face but that they came to buddhist practice
in order to deal with their tremendous pain that they carried with them
and their tremendous rage their anger and how difficult it was to sit
in a room full of mostly white people and retreats and uh and sit there and sit there and
but they use this practice in order to somehow resolve that and work with it and heal it
and came out the other side with a dignity and confidence
and a capacity because they had healed their rage and their woundedness
a capacity to still be in the fire of racism in this country but to be able to look at it in the face
with strength and confidence and with a certain kind of love sometimes a fierce love
and sometimes i met these african-american practitioners and had been it's kind of in awe of them
and kind of like it's well inspired by them and kind of felt wow
i hope you know what would i be able to do that would i have been able to manage with that level of challenge
like you would hope so but i don't know so a day to celebrate
you know the amazing amazing accomplishment of what a free people can do
and to recognize there's plenty of people who are not not yet free enough there's still oppression in this country
there's still still limitations and things that undermine that lots of people not just african-americans but
that's what we're celebrating today and uh that keeps
lots of things that keep them from excelling they keep them from
living a free life keep them from fulfilling their capacity
in beautiful ways so what i'd like to do today is to
teach you what the teachings of the buddha are called the four great resolves the four
things the word resolve here and the quality word is aditana
which kind of etymology of the word means something like a higher stand and where
you take your stand so it's not just a resolve which can feel like where you're headed resolved to get
someplace but this is where we take our stand like this you know
this is what we're committed to and we're going to find our way and these four resolves or four stands
are uh wisdom truth
relinquishment and peace so i'll say a little bit about them but
mostly what i want to do is use this as a as a structure to read some quotations from
african-american writers activists people and i've chosen different quotes that
kind of fit into these categories and that might kind of give a different uh
application or orientation in order to kind of consider these four stands
i think many for in the context of this buddhist meditation practice
that these four resolves uh are often understood in terms of our own in practice
it's like uh turned inward towards ourselves how to practice them and that's actually very significant to do
that and that's what these african-american practitioners in some ways did in order
to find their freedom in order to be able to go out and after that afterwards some of them are
kind of activists now so there's a place for that but we tend
to limit ourselves too much our freedom in being internally focused sometimes in this buddhist practice and so to
hear these these quotations in the context of these four resolves might be interesting too for a reflection and
also a way of kind of honoring this holiday
so the first one wisdom and there's a number of definitions of
wisdom in buddhism but the one that i find most inspiring
is not that of wisdom but of a wise person so how a wise person thinks is their
wisdom and the buddha says a wise person
is someone who considers their own welfare consid the welfare of others
the welfare of both self and others and the welfare of the whole world
this is different than what most people think wisdom is in buddhism or many things that are defined as wisdom
sometimes it's you know people point to emptiness or the four noble truths or
to uh dependent arising all kinds of things kind of other things but
to front and center put was put define wisdom and have wisdom be connected to welfare
and for that we have to know what is welfare what is the well-being
and we have to for that to be concerned for the welfare of others we have to know them
we have to know something about them we have to be able to meet them with a lot of respect
and understanding and so to have buddhist practice that part of the context for it
according to the buddha is this mutual
welfare and uh when he says the buddha says self self self other
self and other and the whole world i unders there's no explanation of what
these three four categories are but self and other i understand it to be the
we the relationship we have what happens when we come together the interact interrelatedness that we
have and uh that gets created in our mutual contact with each other
and then the whole world just i just take it to be you know our scope or the care of a wise person
it is 360 degrees nothing's left out nothing is outside
the purview of what our care is so
uh one of the really one great
african-american historians in this country was w.e.b de bois
amazing man who uh you know there was about a century
from the time of the end of the civil war the emancipation proclamation
to uh the civil rights act in that hundred years he lived 95 of
them he was born in 1868 died in 1963 a year before the civil
rights act which he he championed and you know worked for
and what a what a lifetime to live through jim crow and
cooper's clan and you know world war one and world war ii and
the civil rights movement you know just kind of you know there's so many powerful things that happened
and uh and he studied it he wrote about it he
commented that he was a prolific writer and one of the founders of the national
association for the advancement of colored people so he wrote
herein lies the tragedy of the age not that men are poor
all men know something of poverty not that men are wicked
who after all is good not that magnar men are ignorant
after all what is truth nay the tragedy is that men know so little
of men a little hard to read when we don't use gender inclusive language these days but
this was the language of the time the tragedy of we don't know each other
and so one of his summations of all the suffering that he's seeing in his
country in this country in his time uh and this quote kind of zeroes in on
it we don't know each other well enough and what happens when we really know people
there was a african-american jazz player who uh
made it his mission to uh convert or
disarm members of the ku klux klan and he would go around to ku klux klan
rallies and he would befriend the people there become their friends get it invite them
out for lunch invited to their houses for lunch and uh and these clan people they never
had friendship with a black person and they got to know him and they realized that their beliefs
their vision of you of what a black person is was wrong and they left the clan some of the high
wizards left the clan that he has a whole collection of clan uh robes that they gave to him as kind
of uh to mark this they're leaving the clan and he collects them he has a big you know
closet full of them but what a remarkable thing to do i mean that kind of sounds a little
crazy you know in principle to me but uh you can read about him there's lots of articles about him
and uh forget his name
alice walker healing begins
where the wound was made healing begins where the wound
was made so here also this wisdom of knowing you know being concerned for
the welfare of others but can you know about the welfare of others without knowing the wound they
have the suffering the challenges they have and one of the principles of wisdom and
buddhism is the wisdom the importance of being attuned to suffering and being
attuned to pain the wounds the challenges of ourselves and others
not so that we are oppressed by it or suffer even more but without understanding or suffering
with understanding or societal suffering there's no hope to move move through it
and find the freedom on the other end healing begins where the wound was made
james baldwin wrote for a while the tale of how we suffer
and how we are delighted and how we may triumph is never new
it always must be heard there isn't any other tale to tell
it's the only light we got in all this darkness so we have to the wisdom of facing this
to be able to tell the story and or to recognize how we suffer how we're delighted
and how we triumph and that's what you know this holiday is about part just not only freedom but the
triumphing of those african-americans who have really pushed through their oppression
and excelled in so many different ways
and malcolm x a man who is a little controversial perhaps for some people but
many people have come to appreciate him more and more as the distance of his time
we are not fighting for integration nor are we fighting for separation
we are fighting for recognition as human beings in fact
we are actually fighting for rights that are even greater than civil rights
and that is human rights so
fighting for recognition hey we're here we count we're important
this is you know i think it's a wonderful wonderful rallying cry and a teaching in its own
right the slogan black lives matter and because there's been so so much
resistance to this slogan in this country surprising
that anybody would resist that slogan i wonder sometimes whether we add one
word to it whether that would help black lives matter
also because who could argue against that
so wisdom recognition seeing the wound recognizing
other people recognizing the humanity of others and uh
you know is part of this whole wisdom tradition so here not just for in ourselves but now
looking outwards into this world so the second resolve is truth
and this is central to buddhist practice we practice mindfulness to be able to be present for what is most true the truth
that's liberating and for personal liberation it's a real
deep look inside and through the depths of our hearts for societal liberty liberation there
has to be some study and recognition of what's true out there
and uh and avoid lies
complicated issue in some ways but uh certainly we have examples in the
contemporary society where it's not a question of what is true and what's lies because it's
freely admitted their people are lying but they're doing it anyway tremendous costs to our society
uh so nicole hannah jones who's one of the
one of the main originators of the 1619 project to study racism in this
country she wrote
if we here at the united states if we are truly a great nation
then the truth cannot destroy us
this is a powerful statement in my mind so here they're trying to get to come out they bring out the truth of the
wound of what's happening here that so many people are resisting and not wanting
thinking somehow it's going to do something terrible but the truth can never destroy us
dubois said the cure
isn't simply telling people the truth it is inducing them to act on the truth
so to act to live the truth to act on what's true so you know part of the danger in
buddhism where we have in our practice at least where we're having insights and understanding and wisdom
is that it uh they're powerful for us maybe to see the truth in some ways in our practice
but then we don't take the next step which is to understand how that
influences or or inspires living a different way let go of
attachments not so that we can watch more netflix and not have to worry about anything
because we did our own spiritual world work but to discover how to be let go of our
attachments so that that we can step into the world
in a free way dedicated to freedom i sense i'll go on absolutely
so then there comes relinquishment relinquishment is a fascinating word because it also the
pali word chaga for relinquishment also means generosity
and the fact that relinquishment letting go in some deep way can mean generosity it kind of gives a
different twist because some people think relinquish by just kind of giving something up
but the word giving up originally apparently suggested offering
something up on the altar giving it's also the word giving is in it and though sometimes in colloquial
english giving up feels like a kind of a hopeless surrender or something but what
if giving up is a powerful act of of independence and freedom and
he you know that it's not surrendering something
but rather stepping in letting go to step forward
in a free way so again dubois
there is in this world no force as the force of a man determined to
arise the human soul cannot be permanently chained
the human heart cannot be permanently chained
the uh uh here's our soul the human soul cannot be permanently chained and for me
i translate that as heart our heart does not want to be held in
check doesn't want to be repressed or held down there is in us a call to freedom
a yearning for freedom to be set free and i believe that once we do mindfulness practice or meditation
practice that lets the mind quiet down enough from all its distractions all its
preoccupations and we can feel listen hear ourselves more deeply
we'll hear that call for freedom the way in early in the buddhism that's expressed
is the word which means come and see
there's a call there's a call to come and see come and look here freedom is found here come and look for
it one buddha is saying a chinese buddhist saying is that
freedom beckons us in everything there's a call to freedom the heart
wants to be free the heart doesn't want to suffer and one of the simplest kind of maybe
rational maybe even mechanical ways of understanding this
call to freedom is that it's a call to let go
of all the ways in which the heart is contracted or tight
fisted up and it's a lot of work to do that
it's a lot of effort and if you really if you feel into a fist which is all contracted and tight
you feel kind of a call in the fist to relax it doesn't want to be that way you
have to assert the mind over and over again to keep the hand fisted up there is a call in the heart
for freedom for release the human soul cannot be permanently
chained dubois again the cost of liberty
is less than the price of repression
that's a powerful statement and i don't know if you can reword it for
the cost of freedom is less than the price of
attachment the price of craving and clinging let's say so if you want to do the
economic analysis of this practice it clearly comes in favor of us doing
the work to become free
dubois again i believe in liberty for all
men the space to stretch their arms and their souls the right to breathe and the fight to
vote the freedom to choose their friends enjoy the sunshine
and ride on the railroads uncursed by color
thinking dreaming and working as they will in a kingdom of beauty and
love working as they will and a kingdom of beauty and love
don't we want to live in a kingdom like that a world like that do we want to contribute to that
do we want to be someone who contributes to beauty love and freedom
i think that it's actually if you learn how to do it it's actually less
less work than the alternative
then a colleague of uh dubois was a man named carter woodson he was actually the main founder of the naacp
lived around the same time and uh
he wrote history shows that it does not matter who is in
power or what revolutionary forces take over the government
those who have not learned to do for themselves and have to depend so solely on others
never obtain any more rights or privileges in the end than they had in the beginning
so this is where buddhist practice comes into play because this is a kind of specialty of buddhism
i think that has to contribute to all this we those who have not learned to do for
themselves and have to depend so solely on others
buddhist practice is leading us to becoming independent
there's a certain kind of the buddha was explicit using this word not dependent to live a life not dependent on anything
and not dependent on others is that possible psychologically in certain way
it is possible and and to the degree to which this the heart can become independent
without that woodson doesn't believe it's possible to
have any other freedom so then in terms of this freedom
living a life of beauty living a life of love
tony morrison has this beautiful quote
if you can't imagine it you can't have it
if you can't imagine it you can't have it so some of you maybe don't feel like you
have freedom yet full freedom don't live life of full love and all the context
that you'd like to live it maybe you even have the but imagine that it's possible imagine
it have a vision for it the first experience of liberation and
buddhism is often called a vision then we have a vision of what's possible
the first experience of liberation is not the end but it's the beginning because now we kind of we can imagine it
as so the four resolves wisdom
truth relinquishment and now the fourth one is peace and for the buddha
in terms of the kind of emotional experience of liberation what it
actually feels like he has two concepts that he presents
one is peace and the other is happiness peaceful happiness happy peace if you
put him together so peace is kind of like the one of the goals of the buddhist practice
and malcolm x said you cannot separate peace
from freedom because no one can be at peace unless he
has his freedom no one can be at peace unless he has his
freedom so we don't want to live in a world where people are denied their freedom
dubois what a world this will be when human possibilities are freed
when we discover each other when the stranger is no longer the potential criminal
and the certain inferior it doesn't really mention peace but this
is where the quote got to put the world of human possibilities
tony morrison don't let anybody
anybody convince you this is the way the world is and therefore must be
it must be the way it ought to be this is a unusual quote for buddhists in
our scene ought to be different we keep emphasizing you know you have to
see the world as it is yes
we see the world as it is so that the social world
can become what it ought to be we see the truth of what's happening
things as they are in our hearts so that our lived life in this world
can be as it's possible as we can imagine it if we only accept
things as they are ourselves as we are
nothing's really going to change and is there really a freedom
to be found by simply just accepting things as they are
i'd say no things have to change
to the degree to which buddhists practice acceptance it's only so that we get to know them
better more deeply only so that our reactivity and our
attachments don't get the upper hand but not we don't accept so that we
permanently accept we learn how to be present to see things as they are
so that we can let this growth into freedom
happen that's what our heart wants that's what the heart
the ought of our hearts there is a possibility for a different
life there is a possibility for a different society whether or not we attain it in this
lifetime in this century and this millennia one of the most powerful
ways of freedom gets enacted and lived is
we don't we don't limit our freedom our enactment our
by the short-term possibilities
what's important and even by the results what's important is we act in free ways we act for freedom
we become someone who wants to live expressing our love
our care maybe a certain beauty
and freedom so we can be free
and the love in our hearts can be set free so that we can be
attuned and supportive of the freedom and
love that others can have the possibility of freedom and love
between self and others and to contribute to a world
where freedom and love are recognized
appreciated valued and celebrated and may it be that on this day of
the juneteenth that's a day where we appreciate
value and start to live more fully dedicate ourselves
to the advancement the freedom the happiness of
everyone including and maybe with some priority
the african-americans in this country they've been forgotten ignored
oppressed for centuries and so
there's a little bit of a reckoning that we should do and care for
and to support a real change continue the change that's happening in
a good direction on this juneteenth day so thank you
wisdom truth relinquishment
and peace so uh
we will stop and then for those of you who would like we'll take some chairs folding
chairs outside the parking lot and we can sit there and have a little discussion and check in
and whatever happens we can take our masks off if you like you can keep it on if you like
out there and that's nice you're all welcome to come it's nice to have chat and one of the things i'd like to do maybe at the beginning of that gathering
is to talk a little bit about some of the thinking about how what kind of changes we might enact
of for the covid protocol for coming here on sunday mornings in july
is maybe not a lot big change but a little bit of change one but one of them is
maybe to stop using this whole registration system we have
to have it be an honor system that people are vaccinated still wear masks but uh maybe also not uh
limit the numbers and see what happens if it just you know if
with that uh so we haven't decided we haven't decided what to do but i thought
at least to give you those of you who'd like to stay and have some discussion about it we could begin our conversation out
there with that so uh thank you
very much and uh
this holiday continues tomorrow so it's really a two-day holiday so so
so keep uh keep this the whole idea i suggest you keep this whole idea of
juneteenth day and enough in the forefront in your mind that you read about it study about it
and kind of learn a little bit more about african-american history thank you