okay well I think we'll go ahead and get started as people continue to arrive
nice to see everyone so this week the theme is called meeting
life well five Dharma resources one could say that Dharma practice is a
series of encounters we sit on the cushion and we meet the state of our body and mind in detail and then we go
out into the world and we meet other people situations in our life and amid
all of that we have our own minds reaction going on also so there's a lot
going on in the human life and as we encounter our life
on what resources do we draw in order to meet it well and to respond well
are there supportive qualities or assets that can come forth in particular when
things get challenging or surprising or unfamiliar of course I think we all know that
mindfulness is essential so we might call that the foundational resource
what the Buddha also named other qualities as forms of inner wealth or
fortitude and there's a list of five items that I like to call the five Dharma resources
that's my term not the Buddhas um what you'll see as this week unfolds
that these five when they're readily available for us can serve as highly
helpful resources to meet life well and the first of them is confidence
so we'll see the others as as we go on but let's go ahead and start sitting
so finding a posture where you can be upright and relaxed
or at least have a straight spine just allowing yourself to settle into
a position that's relaxed and alert
perhaps sensing the contact points where you're sitting or lying down maybe
some of you are standing so feeling your seat against the cushion or chair
your legs or feet against the floor or your body against the surface
and just feeling the support and groundedness of that
allowing yourself to be supported
you may find that as we connect with and Trust what's supporting
us there's kind of an upward surge of energy allowing the body to be drawn
upward just allowing that also
as we softened down the body straightens
and softening the muscles of the face the eyes and the eye sockets
the jaw
softening down through the shoulders allowing the shoulder blades to slide
down the back which tends to put the chest just a bit
forward leaving with the heart
allowing there to be ease in the arms and hands
and down through the Torso
softening the rib cage front back sides
sensing Into the Heart area just allowing that to be as it is
down into the valley
just connecting in and inviting any ease
through the belly area
and then down through the hips the inner thighs
the knees and all the way down into the feet
just connecting in with the whole body however it is right now
and inviting ease and if there are still parts that are sore or tense
or you couldn't feel them very well that's fine can just have ease in the mind also
about how the body is right now
and gently turning the attention toward the sensations of breathing
toward the breath
and if we can we want to connect in with the very basic Elemental sensations of
breathing so rather than an idea or even an image
of our lungs or something I really feel the touch of the air on
the nostrils or the upper lip
some sense of expansion and coolness as it moves through the air passages
maybe there's a shift of clothing against the skin as the chest inflates
maybe you feel it even into the belly
and then at some point the inhale ends and there's a shifting
feeling as the exhale begins
the lungs soften and begin to release and there's
a different movement of air maybe warmth
so it's all part of Wrath but there are these minute simple Sensations that we
can allow attention to just flow along with
and all of that is in the service of establishing the quality of mindfulness
being in the present moment
this is the foundational resource for us and a five that we'll talk about this
week all rely on some degree of mindfulness
and as we get used to the being with the flow of the sensations of
breathing we can of course be aware of other Body
Sensations there's also the Sensations in the legs and
maybe you have other Sensations coming forward there's the sound of my voice
or other things in the room or the house where you are
and we can just breathe along with those
there may also be some emotion or mood present for you
it may not be prominent or it may be you know we may have sense of tiredness or
sadness or ease Joy
irritation could be anything we can read along with
that also
and it's common also to have thoughts going on meditation is not about eliminating all
thoughts but we can simply be aware when there's
thinking going on so if you have some thoughts present
you can try to breathe through them or along with them
let them be kind of in the background like a radio playing in the background
not trying to shut it off but also not turning toward it
thank you
I know in the mind has wandered away it's fine to just
gently reopen to all these objects when
awareness returns just start again with the breath or the body
being with what's present just being simple
anything in our experience can be touched or known by awareness
anything actually
service May generate some trust in this quality of knowing
as the initial foundational way to meet life
foreign
so I'd like to drop in just some very brief reflections
and then we'll keep sitting in silence after that
so please recall how you first encountered the Dharma
or meditation or mindfulness how is it that you somehow came into
contact with that
and then move on to recalling what kept you going with it
even if you're quite new or if you have started and stopped a number of times
what is it that in the heart that wishes to practice or
that keeps you with it keeps you coming back
and then if you can kind of feel underneath the specifics
if there's some kind of quality like trust or confidence
I really might even call it faith and what you're doing with this practice
it doesn't have to be anything you can name or explain it's more like the underlying feeling there
let's see if you can tap into that
and perhaps with a bow to our heart we can just go back to sitting with the
flow of experience perhaps infused a little bit with this
sense of trust in the process of meeting it however that feels for you right now
gently bringing the attention to the body sitting
just in these last few minutes just touching in again to the upright
posture particularly centering into the chest
area
breathing in and out of that space following the shoulders to soften
are to be forward a bit the way it is on our Buddha statue
with a rupas are meant to express confidence in a certain way
through their posture
there's a way in which our own sense of trust and confidence in the practice
is conveyed even silently
definitely doesn't need to be overt or verbal
when I first attended a Sangha just a local sitting group
I was struck by how it just seemed like the people who were the more experienced
leaders of the group they just seemed comfortable with themselves
that was what I noticed because I was not at that time
so is there a way that whatever your sense of trust in the
Dharma or in mindfulness might somehow just be part of your being
as you go about today with the hope that
somehow that will be picked up by others not even in a really a conscious way
but our way of being does subtly influence others
the world needs people who are confident in being present for whatever's happening
may that be something that we can offer from our practice
[Music]
foreign
so someone wants to ask the zen teacher possibly Suzuki roshi
um what is the essential teaching of Zen and the reply was an appropriate
response so we'll be talking this week about five
Dharma resources that support our ability to meet life well maybe to
produce an appropriate response in the moment their inner strengths that can rise up
to meet the moment and they come forth in happy times as well as amid suffering
but they're especially useful if we encounter something that is confusing or
alarming or painful or just outside of our typical experience
so I'll name them all first they are confidence
virtue or ethical conduct listening and learning
generosity and letting go and discernment
so this list of five is actually from the sutas it appears in a variety of
sutas in Bali Canon at least 10 that I counted and to name them in Pali the these
qualities are SATA Sila suta chaga and panya
which we'll go through this week so in these various discourses they're
not always applied in the same way let's say the Buddha called them
types of wealth ways of fortifying the mind modes of spiritual growth
accomplishments and Inspirations that's kind of a range
but I like to sum up all of those diverse terms into the single term Dharma resources so resources from which
the heart draws to respond well to situations both on and off the cushion
and we can strengthen these through practice and we can also observe how
they might naturally arise to meet situations if we're mindful they all have the basis of mindfulness
and the stronger that they become in our heart then the more readily available they are
to meet life So today we're talking about confidence
SATA I just watched a new film
that was made about the founding of the Insight Meditation Society IMS which is
kind of the mother institution of insight practice here in the west I think it's fair to call it that
we have several long and long-standing institutions now but IMS was the first
that was aimed at training laypeople in the practices that the founding teachers
had learned in Asia and it was formed in the late 1970s
so those founding teachers are Joseph Goldstein Jack cornfield and Sharon
Salzburg and also Jacqueline Mandel was involved at the time so
um and then Joseph is kind of the you know the one who Joseph and Sharon remained at IMs and are the kind of
grandmother and grandfather there so what's striking about the film is how
much trust and faith and confidence were needed to create IMS and the Insight
Retreat form that we have when there was really nothing like that in the U.S
before these were young people in their 20s and
you know they've just come back from Asia and they were buying a huge Catholic
novitiary for a lot more money than they had really dealt with before and they're you know they came and look
they've been looking at a bunch of different places but they saw this one one morning and they were pondering well
is this the one because it it seemed to meet all of their needs although it was really a lot bigger than they expected
but they thought about should we buy it and so they they went into the Town Square in Berry Massachusetts which is
where IMS is located and they were kind of hanging around and they noticed that there was a statue in
the middle of the square that had the town motto on it the town motto for Barry is tranquil and alert
so they thought perfect perfect for a meditation center let's go for it
so they they tried to you know they went forward they signed the forms but they
didn't have all the money for the down payment yet so they did some fundraising but they were still short eventually by
fifteen thousand dollars which was a lot of money in the mid 70s and it was a lot of money for a group of essentially
hippies in their 20s so you know how to get fifteen thousand dollars no clue but
um Joseph at that time was teaching at naropa in Colorado and he was there for
an extended period doing some classes and living in an apartment there and a
woman came to his apartment who had been to one of his classes and she said I'm wondering what to do with some money
that I inherited it's about fifteen thousand dollars what do you think I should do with it
and he said well I have an idea for that so you know it kind of
appeared for them and then of course so then they bought the building I have a lot of stories
today by the way um once they had the building they were learning to operate it and keep it going
and they found that it had three massive oil tanks in the basement 60 feet long
and it was not even possible to remove them from the room where they were
but it turned out as they checked them that only one out of three was actually working and so the facilities person was
a little worried about this uh you know how to three three tanks only one functioning
can't even really get the manner out so he was a little bit at wit's end and
he said to Joseph what are we going to do about these tanks and you know what if this one doesn't work anymore and
Joseph simply asked him well is it working now and he said yes Joseph said
not to worry there will be a way something will work so people repeatedly in this in this
film referred to Joseph's faith in slowly growing IMS to him it was just
doing the next thing doing the next thing and somehow it all worked out of course there were many problems along
the way but you know this kind of just meeting the moment this kind of
sincere confidence is often behind institutions that actually endure and
evolve over decades or longer and we can see some similar things I think in the
evolution of IMC where where this where we're based here just one small example
maybe is the financial model at IRC Insight Retreat Center that's associated
with IMC and the financial model there is that the you know there's no registration fee and the Retreats are
offered on the Donna basis and the donations that people make somehow pay it forward and keep it going
and I've heard people talk about Gill's faith in this regard it's it's not really a common business model in the
world to you know not charge for what you offer and many people said that it wouldn't
work and yet yet it does so
this is yeah this is meeting the moment as it says in the comments and this is
you know I'm talking on an Institutional scale but it can work on a personal scale too I'm remembering uh talking
with ayatata Loca who's one of now the very senior nuns in the coonies in the
western world and she you know way back when she was thinking about ordaining
very young in her 20s um she was going back and forth should I ordain as a nun what should I do with my
life and she happened to be flying back home to which was in Portland at the
time uh Portland Oregon and she got off the plane and that was in the time when Nike
had their um their slogan just do it and there were all these ads in the Nike
airport in the in the Portland Airport from Nike that said just do it just do it and then she walked off the plane and
saw these um signs she said okay I think I'll ordained just do it
so there's a way that honest openness to the Dharma connects us into some larger
flow I've heard Gill call this hidden Pathways that we don't know are there
and sometimes this approach of Simply having confidence is a way to meet the uncertainties of life
and it's not even that we have confidence or trust in some specific thing that we could name
we just have trust there's a saying the Dharma supports those who support the
Dharma and you know this has to be done with some
sincerity and humility we can't rely on it from a purely cognitive perspective
or we can't have a demand or an expectation
um in in following that that maximum in our life
and it's useful also to remember that we might not get the exact solution that we
were imagining but there will be some shift that addresses our problem you know if we take this approach of meeting
life confidently so here I want to give a somewhat pointed example that I heard
from another Dharma teacher in a Dharma talk and I found it striking they were
saying suppose a person has the problem of wetting their pants when they get
nervous in public and they desperately wish to end the suffering of this terrible condition and
so they Place their trust in their Dharma practice but instead of
stopping the wedding of their pants what they find is that they become equanimous
about doing it so either way the suffering subsides I mean it's kind of a
humorous and somewhat overblown example but it points toward the idea that we
can't quite demand how the issue is going to be addressed but we can have
confidence that the Dharma will find a way to ease the suffering maybe things
change or maybe we just learn not to be so concerned or any other of a myriad
possibilities it may not even be about a you know we
may not even use this approach just for problems per se I know somebody from a
asanga in another location who was sometimes asked to give Dharma talks
when the teacher was away and one time she was asked and she said no because
she didn't really have any ideas for a talk um but so that's one approach
but another approach is to just say yes and trust that because the talk is on
the calendar an idea will come you don't need an idea for a Dharma talk when
there isn't one coming up on the calendar but as soon as there is then maybe an
idea will come so I don't know do you have my examples
of this from your own life if you want to say ask that as a question for your
contemplation have there been examples of that that you've seen
there's even a story from the sutas about this Maha kasapa who was one of
the Buddha's Chief disciples he knew from an early age that he wanted to
ordain as a monk but his parents wouldn't allow it and he ended up marrying he ended up
married he didn't want to get married but he ended up marrying turned out a woman who really wanted to be a nun but her parents wouldn't allow it so they
did their best to being married and running a farm to make a living but
eventually the calling to the spiritual life was too strong for both of them and
without even having met the Buddha you know he the possible had never met his teacher but he just knew he wanted to
ordain he wanted to live that life so without having met the Buddha kasapa and actually also his wife they just put
on the yellow robe anyway kind of effectively ordaining themselves and set
out on the road and the Buddha had sensed at that point that a great disciple was in the area and was coming
and he went to meet Kosovo but gossipa couldn't have known that when he set out
so this quality of confidence sadha
Sometimes the best approach is to just go forward sincerely not knowing how it's all going to work out but trusting
that we'll be able to meet it whatever comes may be pleasant maybe unpleasant but we trust that we can meet it
so confidence becomes a Dharma resource when we have some clarity in our heart
about what we're devoted to or what we're following or what we're aspiring
to we have some clarity like we want to build a Dharma Center in America we want to orient our life around
practice we want to find a way to meet a terminal illness something and then we
step forward and we need the next moment and the next we maybe have a big picture in mind but big pictures come about
Moment by Moment by moment and there's a way that we can bring our
full heart to that so may you find that confidence is a Dharma
resource for you today and and broadly in your life
thank you