hello friends hello and welcome hello and welcome to happier hi
good to see you all good to be with you and as always we start by saying hello
warming the space so i start by saying hi i'm nikki i'm
in mountain view california unseated olonyland who wants to say hi
or by the way is rather chilly for a change and who wants to say hello who wants to say
hello welcome to unmute yourself for typing chat
as you wish hello i'm dave from whidbey island and
it looks like you got your hair done i got a haircut yes shorter
[Music] yeah easier to take care of hi
who's this from columbus ohio hi welcome good to see you hi
and there's jesse san rafael billy dallas sarah from snowy flagstaff claire
in new york city ah just makes me happy to hear all the hellos
or read them your voices anybody else wants to say hi hi i'm laurel from seattle hi laura
welcome hi it's linda from utah hi linda from
utah and i noticed your hair too nikki
looks lovely thank you you're very kind thank you yeah
yeah it's fun these it's you know hair like this body right it's
ours and also not ours you can cut it off and you're still you and there's a part of your body missing right
interesting these reflections we can take them to interesting places
kelly says hi from memphis tennessee hi kelly terence from squim washington
sweet so let's get started let's get started and hi gabriel from montreal
hello hi we're international so let's uh let's begin
let's begin formally and i changed the settings at this point so
that if you are uh if well i ask you to to mute yourself i
think you're already muted i'm going to change the settings so that unmuting would go away for the duration and also
change the chat settings so that uh the chat will only come to me if there's
anything urgent that needs to be communicated like the sound drops off otherwise let's can keep
that channel quiet otherwise it can be distracting while i'm giving a guided meditation or a talk we can we'll open
it afterwards and last but not least turning on recording for the sake of
audio dharma our friends will join later here we go
so hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour
so for our practice today um [Music]
i'd like to invite us to explore in our meditation together
a couple of different concepts that i want to bring together
one is the concept of practicing loving kindness meta
which has so many different dimensions it's both a cultivation practice and
it it makes us kinder happier
in how we feel externally relationships there's so many different
aspects to this practice so many different aspects but of course we've spent many many
sessions tapping into all these different aspects relationally internally etc
and one one aspect of the practice of meta
is that it's also a considered a unification practice
it's a practice that calms the mind that pacifies the mind
that steals the mind and it's like petting it's like petting the mind if you're petting a kitty like
so this practice if we gently gently pet the mind with this practice over and
over again it starts to purr starts to purr there's a sense of ease
and and contentment and goodness nourishment nourishment of
loving kindness for ourselves that just fills the heart fills the body
which is so healing can be so healing so that's the aspect i'd like to invite
us to tap into and if you've had a long day or a hard day
if this sounds like good news that this is what we're exploring then yay because
it is there is an aspect of healing calming and for this for it to build up there are various
things that need to be in place and one again
it's a much longer conversation and as we've covered many aspects but one thing
i like to lean into so just saying that this is not a complete description of everything that's needed
but what we'll be leaning into today for our practice is
is an embodies embodiment so we keep bringing back this meta to ourselves to
the body again and again
and again and when the mind wanders off for a thought or plan or tomorrow
yesterday it's like oh sweetheart it's okay it's okay come back to the body
come back come back and if we feel oh i've had this i'm done
with it i'm bored like oh stay stay stay stay just keep petting you
just you hang in there and one concept i want to bring in here
is in psychology this is called the very technical term of risk response
inhibition response inhibition which is this in one description of it is
refers to the suppression of actions that are inappropriate in the given context and that interfere with
goal-driven behavior yeah that's very psychological but the point here which is actually this practice it's
really um i mean this idea of response inhibition is when you stay you just
stay you kindly gently i know it sounds really clinical but it's also another
way to feel into like you know it's like oh i've had it okay it's been whatever 20 minutes okay i want to go and watch
netflix and i've practiced you know i've done it like stay stay
stay can you stay and the more you stay the more like okay i want to just fix it and and grab my
tea and drink it in the middle of meditation and fidget and like scratch myself how would if i stay
what if i gently stay again not in a harsh way i'm not suggesting that but
can you gently train yourself to stay keep petting
petting the kitty and see what happens see what happens at the end right
if you don't interrupt if you don't go after all these distractions of thought or mind just see
if the sense of nourishment again you need to be very gentle with this it's not a harsh thing to do just
lovingly oh can you stay sweetheart can you stay okay
so that is the frame for tonight that is the frame for tonight and again
gentleness ease its nourishment being nourished and healed
is our goal is our destination so if anything if you find yourself becoming
too harsh or too tight that's not the way let that go it's okay
just breathe breathe with ease breathe with ease
and kindly kindly turn to whatever is arising as if you're petting the kitty
so that's the frame i think i've i've said all i wanted to say to set the
frame so so let's begin let's practice together
so so let yourself be comfortable for this
practice especially for this practice let yourself be comfortable
sitting comfortably it's good if your spine is straight
there's a sense of integrity in your posture lying down is fine lying down is
okay if there be a sense of integrity in your limbs and your spine
ah let your body be comfortable and landing landing landing arriving
arriving here
embodied embodied turning the attention to the body ever
so gently and inviting the body to relax
to let go might be tired
might be hurting [Music]
release can you release
ah can you release into
release into all the nooks and crannies
of this body that haven't got attention today because you've been too busy the mind
has been attending to the proverbial to-do list
here
relaxing relaxing releasing into the body
letting the breath be breathed
gently kindly
each breath with each in-breath connecting
the awareness connecting with the sensations of breathing in this
moment and with this with each out breath
releasing into [Music] say your toes how are the toes really
we feel our breaths release into the toes and the sensations in the toes
then the feet
and the lower legs
relaxing same way that image of us
petting the kitty
let the breath embrace
different parts of the body
the feet the out breath now [Music] i'm bracing the lower legs the knees
the upper legs
being petted embraced with the out breath
sit bombs
each out breath released released
felt notice when you release each part of the body
as it was being petted by the breath
is there more sensation that's available more ease that becomes available
the entire lower legs lower part of the body and the sit bones
petted with the out breath kindly there's a sense of kindness gentleness
in each breath the meta is infused in with each breath
it's not separate
then lower abdomen
your time
the lower back
released into the chair into the cushion
the bed with each algebra
the chest the area around the heart center with
each outbreath
released
as if the breath is lovingly petting a kitty
here here here here dear body dear kitty
the in-breath bringing awareness bright awareness to this part of the body
the chest bright awareness the out breath letting go releasing
notice if you're getting sleepy might be helpful to bring attention the
in-breath to the aliveness
to the brightness in this body part
down the shoulders arms
elbows lower arms hands
with each in breath bringing awareness bright awareness
with each out breath ah releasing letting go
the kitty being lovingly pennant
the neck and shoulders
a face the cheeks
the forehead
tongue the ears the jaw muscles
and the proverbial thinking muscle of the brain
in breath here bright out breath released
relaxed into let thinking be relaxed
or release to let it be released
and now the entire body
the in-breath sense of awareness brightness here
knowing the body is breathing
ah the out breath release relax let go
kindly lovingly as if the breath the out breath
specially
is petting the kitty of the body lovingly it's the metta
the meta in breath here now
i'm here i pay attention to my dear self dear body this dear being who's me
ah the out breath release with kindness here
here sweetheart maybe you even have an image of the breath
petting the whole body maybe the body starts to purr after a
while receiving all this loving attention
let yourself be surprised
as to what levels of peace nourishment healing
might be possible
through continuity consistency with this practice
and the thoughts arise pet them and release them too
coming back to the body
the nourishment of the breath wrapped in matter
releasing releasing letting go the other side of the coin of mitta
release into peace
release into love loving each part
each and every part of this body with the breath
can there be meta wrapped with each breath in each breath
breathing in and out for this entire body especially if any part
is having challenges
let the breath imbued with kindness be nourishing
healing to your heart your mind to your body
breath by breath
here here
as thoughts arise can we release them come back here this body with metal
here here this body
each breath breath of kindness
and for the last moments of this practice period releasing releasing
with the out breath whatever rose or did not arise for
releasing any judgment any criticism and allowing there to be meta
appreciation care for yourself for this body for this heart and this
mind you showed up you did the best you could
and offering that to yourself and to others
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone
[Music] ah
i have to say i don't feel like talking so much but i don't know if
if how it was for you i'd love to hear it at any point it was feeling like
per you know this purring was petting the cat with the breath metal infused with the breath the sense of purring
like oh yeah this is good i want to stay here this is good i can hang out here
even if for a few seconds you felt that yay what how
nourishing how nourishing for for us to rest
in this wellspring of this wellspring of contentment
in the heart another way we could see this practice
we did together was the merging of mindfulness of the breath
mindfulness of the breath with the practice of meta infusing the two together
so that's another perspective can hold this practice so so
some time if you want to share any reflections any thoughts
observations um
you can type in chat
typing in chat would be if just to me would be private and i won't read your name if it's to
everyone i'll read your reflection if you wish or you can raise
your hand yeah i see greg
i really like the the idea of taking something that's a tactile process
and turning that inward it seems really novel to me and uh
i do this thing or i have my whole life with my horses where i palpate down their spine when i
think there might be problems and then watching their spinal column
relax and then radiates out through their whole body and i was just sort of doing that to my
own guts [Laughter] based upon your suggestion so thank you for that
i love that greg i love that you were doing that to your own gut and did it have the same impact as you
observe in your on your horses actually it really did it was just sort
of the idea of a gentle sort of massaging of you know
you know the abdominal area and you know just like i noticed a sort of sometimes a
short-term contractile response in which the horse will elevate their spine and then they let it down and you see
you see like the arc of the natural arc of their spine drop as they relax and i had the same sort of
internal reaction to that so it was a beautiful little experience for me it's a really food for thought
yeah it's great it sounds like it opened something up and a couple of other things i wanted to bring here thank you
so much for sharing that greg i'm loving hearing about the horses and their you
know the rhythmic uh the petting and and and their releasing
and and one thing also comes to my mind is you know this idea of petting the horse out of care out of concern with
meta for them so it's the same movement of the heart that you're doing it's not just a physicality right there there is
that sense of care that you're also bringing and so i wanted to highlight that also which is what
really helps this release there's a sense of safety and care that makes it happen so that's lovely
thank you for that reflection beautiful and glad yay something opened up for you
may it continue may it continue to nourish you
in the other reflections [Music] richard on youtube says
beautiful metta dash four beautiful metaphor and reflection thanks richard i like the
playing with the words metaphor yeah sweet any other reflections
discoveries you made surprises there were things that didn't work it's all okay
it's all good thing to share for the benefit of
yourself to be a held witness or for others
and for others
especially if you're new yeah melissa
thank you so much i just wanted to express gratitude i'm having a really hard day today
and having this space to come to in the evening at the end of struggling so much
is so wonderful and i just wanted to express my thanks
to the song and to you thank you thank you melissa thank you so much for
for voicing that that care that appreciation the nourishment of of having this
uh sangha having this practice community to come to after a long hard day
holding you yeah yeah as we all come together for practice
hugh says meta flows out on each breath that's lovely yeah what a beautiful
metaphor to experience lovely
so let's turn given that uh last person who spoke called the
the nourishment the nourishment of being in sangha being in sangha this wonderful
group community that we have become practicing together caring for each
other even if you're new completely new this is your first time please stay stay
and just meet a couple of other human beings on this planet on this earth who are
cultivating their heart towards kindness and then hold them with your kindness
and let them hold you with theirs just meeting each other meeting each other hello fellow
humans so i'll create the breakout rooms now let's
start with 15 seconds of silence as always just silently
holding each other that's kind gazes then you can share as little or as much
as you like um in about your practice questions
comments you know whatever might arise so
so um let's see i will
oops that something just happened here with the room so what's going on here
something funky is happening hold up i'm in trouble with the rooms bear with me come on so we can do this
let's do this ah okay i think it worked all right great so i'm gonna start open the rooms
and here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other
oops
uh oh you're back okay i think we had some trolley oh my god
all right we had some trouble let's try oh what happened okay you oh gosh all
right let me try jesus we're having some technical difficulties tonight guys hold on
let's um oy vey [Laughter]
oh this is funny all right let's see um [Music]
how can i do this break out no i just oh that's so funny i have to wait 30
seconds well let's do 30 seconds of metal have to wait 25 seconds for the rooms to
close in order to reopen them again so
technical difficulties i'm having tonight
so all right the rooms are going to close in 10 seconds and then i can open them
up all right here we go
okay so everybody's back now hello everyone hello welcome back i'm going to um
recreate the rooms there were some technical difficulties tell you what i
mean okay sorry about that open the room close the rooms
all right let's try this again hold on recreate the rooms okay i think we're
good all right i'm gonna open the rooms now all right here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other here
we go there
and the rose will close in about five seconds
we'll wait until everyone has come back okay
all right rooms are closed properly this time not prematurely hi welcome is back
welcome back everyone any uh last minute reflections we have
about a minute left if anything you'd like to share that has come up for you especially from
being in groups a quick reflection
going once going twice ah i see lots of smiles so i'll let that
stand as as the reflection as a standard for a reflection of spending time
together in sangha so thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for
doing this cultivation for your own sake and the sake of all those whose lives
yours touches directly or indirectly may all beings be happy may all beings be
free including ourselves [Music]
thank you