okay so hello formerly hello and welcome
to happy hour lovely to see you lovely to be with you
i have missed you i'm delighted to see you all in the sangha
so for our practice for today i'd like to invite us to um
sit with and reflect on and of course as always i'll offer a few words and then a guided meditation
on the theme of inter-being
so inter-being is one word that the late take not han
used a lot um in his teachings the sense of
inter being that our being that my existence depends on you
depends on so many causes and conditions
so it's not as if i'm an independent being going around in the world as we as we perceive often or wrongly perceive it
to be it's an inter being an interconnectedness interdependence that
if we stop and pay attention we get to appreciate appreciate and really
be in off this concept of inter being is also
related to another concept that i want to bring in tonight which is
the teaching of the concept of ubuntu
which is um i am because we are i am because you are
and and the concept of ubuntu is one from africa it's a beautiful concept in
africa and in fact there are a series of articles that showed up recently
uh on lines or the leading buddhist magazine one of the
leading buddhist magazines and in fact tell you what i will um i will put the
pointer to the articles uh a little later tell you what yeah
when we come back from um you don't you don't have to look for them right now i'll provide them but but
the idea here is similarly is this sense of um
i am i am because you are and and also as as in
uh in many african countries it's part of the greeting part of the greeting which is how are
you for example the question to how are you is i am well if you are i am well if you
are and wow what a beautiful way of yes my well-being is interdependent
with yours and another greeting also as you'll see these articles beautifully talk about
the sense of ubuntu i am because we are
there's this greeting of when people greet each other um now i'm
escaping on which country it was but i'll remember later
the greeting is i see you and the answer to that is i am seen
i am seen what a beautiful greeting what a beautiful way to have this sense of oh
yes my using me is is dependent on me being seen is is
another consciousness that's holding me the sense of inter-being i am because we are sort of the sense of
independence that we all often have in the culture it's in the zulu culture thank you now
in the zulu culture so so with these as themes i am because
we are and let's actually think about it bring it home right now
i am because we are i wouldn't be here
if you were not here happy hour my being here is dependent on your being
here and your being here is dependent on me and others being here i am because we are
it's as simple as that it's not independent but it's dependently
co-arisen how we are is dependently co-arisen and
we often forget that it's this this um
perception that we have it's this delusion of independence this is delusion and what how beautiful
to lose this delusion now and then and realize how interdependent we truly
truly are there is a tenderness there's a beauty
to this interdependence of all beings not just all us humans but all animals
and the planet earth and beyond and when i say beyond it's like wow
blows my mind to think of all the galaxies and stars
and yet it is true i am because we are we this all all of
this all of this i am stardust i am because we are
because the big bang happened at some point so so many directions
this contemplation can go and yet there's a particular way that i would like to
invite us tonight to sit with it and let our heart to open to this interdependence with care with metta
with love with appreciation of holding because you are not alone even if you
think you're not alone you are not alone you are being because everything else and everyone else is so
to bring that in our consciousness to bring that so without further ado would like to
invite us now to uh start meditating together so
so let us let us land let us land in our bodies
ah let us land
in this body in this moment letting go of all the
words that have come for the purpose of arriving
for the purpose of settling here
here
just simply here this breath
sensations of the body not complicated
just here
inviting the body to land to arrive to relax
to give its weight to the earth
filling the soil of awareness by arriving settling
connecting with the in-breath
ah connecting with the opera
[Music]
ah to the body to the seclusion of this moment
into the seclusion of this moment this mind-heart
moment of refuge
do
and if thoughts arise as they will arise it's okay
no need to chastise yourself or yell at yourself
it's okay simply simply notice what the beloved puppy of the mind has
gone after it's okay it's all right sweetie it's okay
smilingly smilingly smilingly petting maybe even petting as
if you're petting wandering mind okay sweetie
let it release let it release the juicy bone
let it release the juicy bone ah noticing [Music]
that being here with the breath with the body
taking refuge is juiciest of all
what a gift here now
this breath this body
do
just this breath
ah this body here
here
now i would like to invite you
if you wish you can stay if it feels calming soothing
[Music] to stay with the breath and the body
and if you wish
consider to open your heart not so much your head
your thinking but drop in this contemplation
as if dropping a pebble in a pond
the person you are how you are
everything you have done and do [Music]
the past and let's say in this moment
it is co-dependently [Music] arising
with so many other factors other beings
so many other beings your life
in this moment
is intertwined
is completely intertwined
with so many other beings lives that it could boggle the mind
could be one of the imponderables as the buddha shared
you really contemplated it so we don't want
to get too lost in thought but just to touch into
touch into this contemplation
maybe bring one aspect maybe the fact that you're here right now
practicing listening
intertwined intertwined deeply embedded
so many other beings actions
you are you don't exist or feel or do independently
not possible
just letting your breath to breathe in this contemplation into your heart into your
heart center a few breaths with sense of awe without
words
it might help for a moment to step out of yourself
and see yourself [Music] from a third person perspective
this being who is you their life so intertwined
so many other beings in this moment let's start with this
moment the present moment
as if you're watching the movie of your life
yes you seem to be the protagonist the star of the movie
and yet there's so many plot lines so many
heroes is not an independent one
let yourself appreciate the richness of the tapestry the tapestry of all these threads
of all these threads interwoven yours is just one
interwoven see your thread deeply
interval with
each breath interwoven
each thought interwoven
each emotion each sensation too interwoven it's not independent
allowing your heart allowing there to be appreciation gratitude all meta
whatever flavor shows up for you good will for all these
threads all these threads interwoven with yours in this tapestry
of being human of life
as you wish well for your thread
may all the threads be well may all the threads travel in safety
and happiness in health and ease
knowing that as you wish well-being through all the threads your wishing well-being for
yourself it's inextricably connected your thread to
the others
so there is no difference really you
wishing well for others and wishing well for
yourself at the ultimate level they're one and the same
one and the same i am because we are
here
may all beings be well
i am because we are
i even have a sense for the threads those you care about those near
and dear in this tapestry
and the threads of those you don't know
so many threats and the threats of those with whom you
have or have had challenges inter-being
i am because we are all of us
opening your heart to care to love
with the entire cloth even if you don't understand it
you don't have to understand it we don't have to understand
and it's possible to share to spread
our goodwill our appreciation for the vastness
of this interconnection
the
they all pigs be well
i am because we are all of us because all of us are i am
i'm part of the cloth i am not a independent i'm not alone
i am i am because we are
both power and humility in this
the
okay
this body is this being is this here
i am here now because we are
okay
and maybe if you wish the last few minutes of the practice
can fill your heart with those who have touched your path
you are because they are they have been
with appreciation and meta with each breath
notice what arises when you bring few of these beings to your mind to your
heart your might heart i am because we are
i am because we are dear one
may all of us
may all of us practitioners all beings everywhere
may we awaken to the grace
the magnitude the beauty
the awe of our inter being
our interdependence
that we are not alone we are deeply deeply embedded
with and for each other
may all beings everywhere
be well may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
i am because you are
so so we have some time for reflections
comments questions reports from the field
for the benefit of the sangha and you're welcome to type in chat
and if you type to me alone i won't read your name it will be private if you type
the chat to everyone i will read both the chat and i also see a reflection here oh yes this is a quote
let me share this first this is from martin luther king jr from
a letter from a birmingham jail we are caught
in an escapeable in an inescapable network of mutuality
tied in a single garment of destiny whatever affects one directly affects
all indirectly beautiful thanks for sharing that i'll read it one more time such a beautiful
quote from dr martin luther king jr we are caught
in an inescapable network of mutuality tied in a single garment of destiny the garment
yes the garment the cloth whatever affects one directly affects
all indirectly can i see your hand please
yeah hi nikki um i've i've noticed for a long time that when i
try to send loving kindness out to other beings that i end up sitting in a puddle of
love and kindness whereas this time having the connections out there
already just feeling loving kindness just automatically went out
those those strings to other beings so that was very nice thank you oh that's
lovely thank you for that report from the field ken that's lovely let me
reflect that back it's what you were saying in the past as you were sending loving-kindness to other beings
your heart yourself would be filled with loving-kindness and here what you noticed was
um with this practice automatically with bringing to mind
this um sense of interconnection with all beings already this this thread
the um bringing the sense of uh meta loving kindness already became became shared it
already went out through all these networks so it's just a different way of being and it's it's lovely right to
experience a practice in different ways right thank you beautiful thank you so much that's lovely
thank you thank you ken any other reflections please
kristen please hi um
[Music] so i think that so right now i'm in the
process of applying for jobs and like waiting to hear back um
and so it struck me as we were meditating um
that part of what feels so hard is kind of just like this vulnerability that um
it's it's other people's decision like whether i'm gonna get a job and what my
life is gonna be like um
and i noticed that you said that this practice um
sort of brings like both humility and power um and i was able to feel the humility
with more ease so i really appreciated that um
and i wonder if you could talk just a little bit more about like the power
that that you see coming from this yeah yeah thank you so much for for sharing
kristen and um and also your question um
this and also where you are in your life right now with with uh looking for a job
applying which can feel vulnerable of course it is one it can feel vulnerable and yet
and yet to feel that actually the places you're applying they depend on you right there is a dependence on
your skills on your gift on what you give to the world
and um so the sense of humility comes from wow yes as you experience there is such a
sense of oh yes interdependence and then their sense of power is the sense of agency that you
are part of this cloth you're an important thread in this cloth
and everybody else is because you are because of what you offer and finding
giving your gift to the world in whatever ways might be appropriate and show up but you
may not know you may not see right now you might be attached to one idea but maybe life has another idea for you how
to show up and share your gifts your agency your your beauty your goodness so that is the
sense of power i am part of this cloth yes i am part of this cloth of humanity i
i am i am wow
how amazing is that
yes and you're welcome to comment or you can let it go as you wish yes yeah yeah yeah helpful
thank you thank you kristen and jamie please
let this be the last comment nikki um
um i think we all know that trauma can radiate out now you know lasting effects
on ourselves and others um you know i'm thinking especially about adverse childhood experiences where there's just really
great research that's been done on the long-term mental and physical health impacts
and you know there's growing research about those being transmitted down generations um
so i was just thinking about that so a lot of compassion during that exercise too yeah
yeah i appreciate you bringing that in yes there are so many causes and conditions and interdependence
and i also really appreciate how your mind
is holding all of that with compassion it's it's not a way to be distraught like oh so
much trauma it's interesting generational etc radiating out but yes
trusting in the power of goodness that is bigger um in humanity the power of
compassion and wisdom to hold um all the all the traumas
as as we navigate this human being human together
towards towards more wisdom and compassion um
yeah i'm reminded of of the the book the um um [Music]
i think he's called the better angels of our nature uh it's and the author is
escaping if any of you know it's uh it'll come to me but the this research
this idea that actually humanity has become stephen pinker thank you melanie yes
that that humanity has become so much kinder and less cruel over over ages and
ages and that's the direction we're going so that gives me hope that gives me hope i share a couple of reflections
in chat before we turn ko says even donald is one of the threads in the tapestry of
my life now how to be matter of fact about this compassion compassion compassion
we are yes because we all are there's so many reasons why
every being is the way they are jerry says it was very helpful to see
your power and agency coming from everyone including yourself i am because you are yes power and
agency exactly beautiful so so we have time now to turn
and and have a sense of inter being in small groups with one another small groups and
and here's the greeting i'd like to invite us to to share with one another and the greeting when you get into
groups together tonight to share the greeting i see you and there will be three of you so you
can you know one person says it and the other or two people will say it back and then you maybe you
take turns so i see you and then i am seen or we are seen
i see you we are seen and let yourself actually be seen be held by the other
being and see how powerful it could be to see someone and let yourself be seen
by them and then take take turns and maybe the first person with uh alphabetically uh just to
make it simple first name closest to the beginning of the alphabet start and go around and do
this and do it as a practice see how it feels and then of course you can share as much
result about your practice these groups these small conversations can be so precious they
already know this this is song guys it's a special sangha so i'm going to create
the rooms now and here we go
okay all right so take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind
and here we go opening all the rooms
okay all the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
nice to see your smiling faces after talking together it's very sweet
and here is the link to the article about ubuntu
in lions roar and we have maybe just less than a minute if any quick reflections or comments
you like to share perhaps about being together and sharing together um it's welcome
otherwise we will
yeah i think maybe this is enough so i'm just seeing the smiles and i'm so
appreciating the smiles that i see yeah heartwarming so
so let's dedicate the merit of our practice together may oh yes dawn says
such joy oh that's lovely what a lovely note to end on such joy
ah may may our practice together be a cause and
condition for for freedom ease joy for ourselves for
all those whose lives are ours touches and all beings everywhere may all beings
be free may all beings be happy
thanks everyone be well