so warm hello from Redwood City
and happy to be here
and as we begin
the theme of this week is compassion
and compassion is one of the great ideals the ideals that people try to live up to
but sometimes it's more useful to focus on not the ideal
but what gets in the way of the ideal and there's a number of reasons for this
one is that if we try to live the ideal well there's something blocking it
then mostly the ideal is the idea of the ideal it's kind of a little bit surfacy
or not really deeply rooted inside of us
and also because uh if we're if we're
operating and we don't really understand What's blocking an ideal but we're still acting it out
uh we're not we don't really understand ourselves very well and we can do all kinds of Mischief if
we don't understand what's going on inside of us and finally
while the ideal any idea might be ideal might be seen as being great
uh it might not it's not always the best response and so if we if we can remove what
blocks what gets in the way of the ideal inside of us then we might discover that without that
blockage there's actually something else some other wholesome movement that wants to come out something else that seems
appropriate and um so
uh one of the so so compassion has a lot to do with
how we are in the presence of suffering our own suffering and the suffering of
others and one of the things that blocks karuna is compassion that Buddhism focuses on
is if there's resistance to suffering resistance to experiencing
and feeling it or contraction or closing down in relationship to it
and so in mindfulness practice we want to be very aware of how we resist how we
close down contract um or get involved in attacking they're
pushing away our own suffering or any suffering that we are aware of
and uh and so what is it like to experience you're suffering however small it might
be without any resistance but also
without any solid place inside hard place inside
that receives it picks it picks it up
because what resists suffering is often can often be ways in which we hold on to
other ideals or ideas about who we are or how we should be or
or memories or past and suffering is you know is difficult
for sure but the mindfulness practice is a practice of learning to be wise and
and with suffering and learning over time it's very important to understand it's
over time so we can be caring and careful with our suffering
but over time to learn how to have no resistance to it and in that way
to to not be struggling with it not be defensive to it and not be the
victim of it but certainly we feel it but in a sense it's it's uh it it doesn't limit us it
doesn't diminish us it it's like we're a wide open field wide open space in which
suffering has space and room to be there as well but we're not troubled by it so much
so as we sit this sitting um from time to time you might find that
there is some suffering some dukkha some something which is stressful or
difficult for you that happens and we might you might spend some time exploring
the resistance you might have to it or the blockage or the contraction and what it might be like to open and
have no resistance and find some degree of spaciousness and freedom
with the presence of suffering so taking a
comfortable upright meditation posture
and upright being metaphorical depending sitting in the way that's right for you
but with your heart and mind upright present
gently close your eyes
and as you're sitting here now is there already some resistance
to something is there some blockage some holding back
a sense of bracing yourself or pulling back
and if there is that itself is the suffering
can you be aware of the resistance without resistance can you be aware of contraction or
pulling back without pulling back from that
and then maybe quite gently taking a slow long deep in breath
gently slowly long exhale
breathing in deeply and then letting go with the exhale
breathing in slow and deep and full
is something which is gentling or Tender kind
moving through your body
slow long exhale as a kind exhale soft movement
carry movement within the Torso
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale softening the muscles of the face
the muscles do not need to be held close to the skull
they can ease away
relaxing the shoulders the shoulders do not need to be pulled
up towards the ears
shoulders can relax down towards the ground
relaxing in the heart area
in the chest
and maybe even the back rib cage can soften
and then relaxing the belly
and breathing naturally normally
for a little bit attend to the rhythm of your breathing
to the cycle of breathing in and breathing out in how it's experienced in the body
the physical Sensations
and as you're sitting here is there any form of
emotional discomfort any form of suffering or stress that you
might feel or any physical pain
discomfort
and if so how are you relating to it how are you
with it is there any resistance
or is there an openness even a willingness to let it be there
not so you can suffer better but so you don't make it worse
with resistance and contraction
if you do feel anything that could be suffering
see if you can breathe through it
or if there's a resistance breathe through the resistance
don't struggle with the resistance don't resist resistance but hold it in Awareness breathe in
awareness with it as if becoming aware of it carefully
is the only thing you need to do know it intimately
and if your discomfort your dukkha is not too strong
experiment with opening up
to receive it
in the way that you would receive a refreshing Breeze of wind
on a warm day just to open
or the way that the air receives the wind
the way the dry ground receives a raindrop
the way your pillow receives your head
experimented with letting go of resistance and just being with it
as if your Duca has permission to be there and that you will receive it
and if that's not possible then be aware of the resistance
breathe with it feel it
as you exhale also let go of your thinking
the more you think the less it's possible to be receptive
and open to dukkah
foreign
and if you're able to not resist suffering
to really allow yourself to feel it freely and openly
perhaps it touches something wholesome within you
perhaps it can allow for something inside of you to expand
instead of contract something inside of you to open instead
of closing and allow something inside of you to
become more tender soft and sweet
instead of hard and challenged and maybe even bitter
the point is not to be without resistance for its own sake
but to be without resistance to suffering so the suffering can touch something
much more deep inside something wise and
caring
a place may be of tenderness or softness someplace that feels intimate
and valuable
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn your heart towards this world around you
perhaps through the suffering both the small and the immense suffering
in our world and what would it what is it
um what is it like to open up to it without
any resistance
as if there's a deep place inside a place of wisdom of care of compassion
that's worth feeling having it feel be present for
his suffering of the world without resistance
almost as if you're a one-room house with two doors one in the front and one
in the back and the suffering the world of the world comes in clearly comes in
but it blows out the other end the other door back door
not to dismiss it but once you've received the message it
doesn't have to linger the wind might keep coming
but there's no blockage for it
and then to
end this sitting with actively thinking about having thoughts
of wishing hoping wanting
suffering of the world to decrease to be alleviated to come to an end
thinking happily how wonderful that would be
thinking about how wonderful the end of suffering would be
as if just know if others just knew that you had this wish
it would benefit them just knowing that there are good people
who are care and concerned about suffering and the end of it is itself
medicine for this world
and then maybe you can also consider how you might act on compassion today
are there small acts of compassionate care that you can offer
to those local and those far away
compassion grows when we act on it
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings be free of Oppression
may all beings be free of hostility
may all beings be free of danger
may all beings be safe
and may all beings
live in peace and freedom may all beings be free
here
so these days that beginning talks about compassion
I feel a little cautious or want to be careful here in talking about it because
I don't want to assume that there's compassion is only one thing and that whatever way I talk about it
that's the true Compassion or the right compassion I think that maybe I think because
compassion is such an integral part to many people's lives it is uh something that's very important
and sometimes lays at the center of you know what is that what's most valuable
for them um I think each person will experience it very personally and in their own way
and um and so you know certainly want to be careful
and one way to do that is to appreciate that maybe compassion whatever it might
be for you or for anybody maybe it's not a singular thing
but rather it's a kind of a compound thing it's made up from different aspects of it and it's possible maybe to
to tease apart and look at some of the particularly important component parts
of compassion and maybe that helps us to look at it more carefully and or find
our own way with um with this important topic
and so one of the elements of compassion I believe is that it involves a contact
with suffering and it that can be the word suffering sometimes in English seems like it's a
really big word word only big things counter suffering but in Buddhism
can also be very small forms of discomfort or stress
that we might feel and so compassion has something to do with being in the presence of of
suffering um and uh that's one of the component parts that's is that's for some people
that's an important part of it and I say sometimes because there might be an exception to this as you'll see as we go
along and so uh and so to uh be willing to
know be wise about how we are in the presence of suffering our own and other people's suffering
and one of the component parts of I think's uh compassion at least the karuna that uh comes out of Buddhist
Meditation practice is uh having no resistance to suffering
it doesn't mean we don't have a strong protest to the suffering of the world or strong idea that this shouldn't be there
or things have to happen but in the heart in our inner life that there's no resistance to
experiencing and feeling that suffering and this is what happens as a
consequence of meditation practice that we learn in meditation practice that the contraction of resistance the hardness
of it the close the closeness of it is itself a form of suffering
and that uh it's kind of unfortunate to do it and we want to be able to relax it and let go of it and um
and to be able to let go of the different ways that we cling and just to be present in an open way
for the suffering it's one of the great gifts and this is one of the things that I learned in my first early years of
Buddhist practice when I had a lot of suffering um I the meditation practice was a lot
about just sitting in the middle of it and just allowing it to be there but just being open to it and not being
reactive to it in any kind of way or caught in any kind of way just present okay it's kind of an unconditional
acceptance of the present moment with a suffering and that was transforming
transformational for me to uh it was hard but uh I was kind of like uh the
meditation practice was a tenderizer for hard meat and my heart just softened and softened
um by just this showing up and showing up to Suffer Without reacting to it or
closing down to it and it might seem counter intuitive to do this because it hurts that you know
it's kind of painful but it allows something to soften it open
and the idea of having the suffering we experience be something that touches us and rather
than Contracting us or closing us down or making us hard it actually expands something inside us
something becomes more open or something kind of suffuses us so I often think of
this as being tenderness myself tenderness softness of words that
I like for this kind of inner feeling and epitenderness has no boundaries it has no walls or sharp lines where the
tender is and to experience suffering and have this openness suffuse pervade
without boundaries this feeling of tenderness somewhere in the chest somewhere inside
is a beautiful feeling a wonderful feeling even though the suffering kind of hurts at the same time
so to meet suffering without resistance this is uh if we meet it with resistance
then it's easy to be distressed to be upset dismayed frightened angry all
kinds of other things but to learn the capacity to receive it without resistance
and again the reference point for this is meditation practice um where you're not expected to do act
on the suffering you're not expect it to go help someone um you're expected to just learn how to sit and be really present
and and in that kind of context to discover in that process this place of
Freedom inside this place of softness and tenderness that gets uh evoked in
the context of suffering it's a very strange idea for people who've never experienced it because
suffering is you know feels awful and why should I feel awful and bad
I've known people who've gotten angry when they said you suggested when I
suggested they should sit in mindfulness and open to their pain or open to their suffering and really feel it and know it
because their whole life was about getting away from it and fixing it and doing something so part of compassion is this Tender Is
this place that's touched inside that when there's no resistance kind of an
opening a tenderness and then the second part of compassion that I think of is uh caring for
whatever that suffering is even either for the suffering itself or caring for the person who's suffering or the being
that's suffering and the word care is a kind of a special word
it doesn't necessarily mean that you were going to act to help them
alleviate their suffering that you're responsible for their suffering it means
that in some contexts it's enough just that we have the capacity as to just
care oh I care about your suffering it's important for me and that you're that
you're suffering it's important for me because I care about you I want to know that I let you know that I care I
sympathize I'm with you I'm I'm your companion I'm your ally I'm your support
I'm here with you in your suffering and I've been the recipient of that from
people where I really felt that in some ways they cared for me in my suffering and um
and uh I didn't feel like they were asking anything or doing anything or expecting anything from me and it wasn't
like they're actively involved in trying to fix or take away my suffering but
just knowing that they sympathize that there was this wonderful care and warmth
and love and recognition and appreciation of me as I as I had my suffering it kind of helped things
relaxed and softened and feeling the human warmth and connection to someone else
so part of suffering is not is just simply the caring for someone that
kindness the openness the sense of shared Humanity independent of wanting
to do something to alleviate it but another aspect of compassion is that
motivation to do something about the suffering and this is where we have to be a little
bit careful because what kind of motivation and I like to
think of this when we're in the context of suffering there's two Dharma motivations that can arise out of it
one is in fact wishing and wanting to help the person
so they don't suffer anymore hoping for them not to suffer and and in offering
something offering help and support and um being a compassionate so a
compassionate action the other action responds to suffering
is when it doesn't make sense for us to act on the suffering to help them out or
to do something to change it or give a helping hand um the experience of suffering in the
world and our own suffering can motivate us to practice more diligently to be
inspired to practice and really get to the bottom of our own suffering really find a deep peace find a deep place of
non-resistance and and wisdom and deeper compassion
to go on the path to practice and this is a very important part for me because there's lots of suffering in the
world that breaks my heart but I'm not going to do anything about that particular kind of suffering not
directly just I only limited what I can do but so I put my energy into another
Direction One Way is I devote myself more to my practice
and now that I'm a teacher I also devote myself more to teaching because I'm not
necessarily helping somewhere else in the world but I'll just put more inspired effort into making a difference
where I can make a difference and so to have the contact with
suffering give birth to motivation of different kinds I think sometimes it's
very respectful for our own hearts there's something about acting and being motivated by something that moves us a
lot that is actually uh keeps freeing the heart or developing the heart not
acting sometimes is a kind of a causing
more suffering causing more harm to ourselves but um and the more the bigger they're
suffering is that we experience like in the world the more important it is for us to respond and to act and to do
something but remember it doesn't have to be we respond directly to that thing it might
be we do something different so for example 911 had a big impact on me and when it
happened I felt I have to be I have to change I have to be a different person by that to be changed by this experience
how do I want to be changed by it and so I decided to start a to train people to
become Buddhist chaplains so I acted in the world I felt like I had to do
something different and so I had to create this program that still exists has been going on now for about getting
close to 18 years or so um I am trading in Buddhist chaplaincy
so the idea is um what can we do and not be burdened by the idea we have
to do something that's uh you know directly related to suffering if it doesn't make sense for
us to be involved so the non the tenderness that comes from non-resistance
the simple care and caringness that doesn't really involve doing anything but it's a deep care
and the third is being motivated to do something and being wise about what direction we
go through there but again the reference point is deep meditation practice
and to have these component parts come forward they come out of us without any
obligation and we can feel in meditation that any sense of obligation is a resistance
there's a heaviness there's a burden there's a closing down is not really healthy to do it out of the of a sense
of Duty I'm obligated to be compassionate um you can't be obligated to be
compassionate because it's then by its very nature it's something that's deeper than any obligation you get manufacture
it and enact it out it's something deeper and so this uh to
not feel obligated to be compassionate but to be motivated to be compassionate
to be motivated to develop our compassion to because something deep
inside us wants us to be I want a different person wants us to be someone who can respond to the world in
effective and useful ways um so no obligation to be confession and
I think for some people this is a maybe difficult lesson and a very important one to learn
um I feel at least because then the compassion can be clear stronger and
come from a deep rooted place inside that hopefully makes it more effective
and more meaningful for the people who we encounter and for ourselves
so you might have different component parts of compassion but because there's so many different
kinds of compassion different people experience it different ways maybe just a principle that it's your
compassion is made up of different parts it can help you to look more deeply what goes on with you when you have
compassion and that's something I think sometimes very helpful to write about or talk to
friends about to kind of really start teasing apart what goes on for you and you feel feel or act with compassion
so thank you very much and um