so uh hello everyone and welcome
and happy to be here with you and i love coming down here in the morning
i live about two kilometers from imc
and uh different times of the year i enjoy different parts of coming down here and
now it's the early morning light that's here and
the sun is beginning to show itself a little bit through these big windows we have in the room here and
i think they'll probably have the shadow play
the wall again so
at some point as people continue meditation
practice and continue doing buddhist practice or just continue with life experience
they'll have a significant experience
of maybe i shouldn't make it that dramatic a noteworthy experience of
letting go of not holding on to something putting down a burden
and it could be you know something as you know retiring and no longer carrying
the burden of work it could be finishing school graduating
from school and no longer having to stay up late at night studying and having the anxiety of tests
there's many different things that we kind of put down and we get relieved of sometimes we let go of them sometimes
they leave us and we can experience something like a
state of peace a state of relief a state of
well-being of emptiness of the kind of a delightful
emptiness like now i'm free and no longer have this filling me
so for this meditation we're going to do you might want to consider sometime in your life
where you've experienced the degree of peace or calm uh or freedom or ease
to whatever degree that's accessible to you it doesn't have to be dramatic it could have been something mild that
happened yesterday or it could be some big event in the past in your past
and and then is there a way that that can be
a reference for you for the meditation
not that you have to attain it again but rather is there
a memory or is there a not so much a memory of the event but a
memory or a embodied memory of
where that sense of peace was in you or how it was or the taste of it the feel of it
maybe that still lives in you someplace maybe there's something that you feel
still to this day that is a remnant is a little hint or trace
of that experience and if so
can you call on that as a way to support you
in being present for your experience during this meditation almost as if
that experience of ease or peace or letting go
is a is a beacon or a guidepost here this is the direction to go
as your present with your experience here this is the way to be with being mindful
like this so sitting upright
in an alert comfortable posture
gently closing your eyes
and to settle in to this spot here and now
to remember that to really go
into this practice it's to realize that the mind and body
are being brought together so that they're cooperating in harmony here at this
moment now in this place the mind is mostly a task of the mind
coming here in the same place as the body
when the mind and body are cooperating or connected
in the same place at the same time then the dharma can begin opening up for
us
gently taking a few long slow deep breaths as deep as is comfortable for you
and on the exhale relax and let go
softening your body as you exhale
preparing your body to relax as you inhale
and then to gently return your breathing to normal
and as you exhale relax your body some more
go through the different parts of your body wherever there's holding
see if you can soften the holding
all an exercise that brings the mind into the body engaging the body
and then bring to mind a recent or distant memory
where you let go or you relieved of something that was
agitating or difficult and in it going
you experience some peace some ease
some freedom some calmness
and remembering that experience in your body how did the bot feel in the body for you to be
at ease
peaceful do you remember what it was like in the mind
maybe in the next few exhales continue to let go relax your body
as you exhale but relax into the feeling
or the memory feeling of that extent of peace
ease relaxation
and maybe on the inhale if there's any feeling in your body in
your mind of that experience and you inhale
see if you can let it spread and grow
on the exhale settling into it more
and might there be a way that a memory or a
leftover feeling of peace might
guide your mindfulness
instruct you in how to be present for your breathing
letting your mindfulness be based some
orient some peaceful orientation
some peaceful way of being and even if you're agitated
the mindfulness the awareness itself of the agitation
can be peaceful
letting peacefulness be a guide of support
for being present attentive here and now
one breath at a time
and then as you meditate perhaps the near goal of the meditation
just a moment or two away
is to be present to be a little bit more peaceful
to be present to touch into
the aspect of the present moment where there is peace
peaceful attention to breathing
remember the place where there's peace
even in the midst of agitation
and as we come to the end of this sitting
there are times where
some modicum of peace letting go
can allow ourselves to be ourselves
we like oh we shed the ways that we are put on a mask or not quite honest or
putting doing things which are not really who we are
and sometimes meditation is a homecoming to ourselves
and when we have some reference to peace and being peaceful
our peaceful attention of others is a way that
we allow them to be themselves allow them to just be
and relax and maybe even come home to themselves
may it be that whatever calm and peace and understanding we have from this
practice may it support us and our good will for others
so that we bring a generosity a kindness
a good will for the welfare and happiness of those we meet
and a friendly peaceful presence
that allows them to feel and sense who they are in some
deeper way may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
so today's topic is the fourth noble truth
and how we understand that depends a little bit about how we understand the second noble truth
if the second noble truth is the cause of suffering
then we may or may not be able to let go of the suffering but we understand the cause
and knowing that maybe some attachment is the cause some clinging is the cause some belief that's
unhealthy is a cause and then we look for a practice that
helps us to become free of that to loosen the grip and so the fourth noble truth is the
practice to do that and
and so we start cultivating a way of being in the world that creates the conditions for us to let go of the cause
and so we practice right view we practice ethical life we practice meditation
practice so that we can uh [Music]
experience or attain the degree of subtleness the degree of non-agitation
the degree of integrity that allows us to
uh or the system our mind our hearts to begin to soften and release the
attachments we have if we know the cause of suffering and craving
or attachment and we have a very clear release of that craving a cessation of
it that's dramatic then we know oh this is the way forward
and and so if the eightfold path can be this is the way to
do this again this is the way to develop myself and grow myself so that these are the practices
so that i put myself in a better position to let go even more and not cling again
if the second noble truth is the arising of suffering and the fourth is the cessation of
suffering we see it coming and going all the different shapes and forms of suffering that we have of stress we have
and and we see that in the arising and passing there starts to be freedom
then the um then the eightfold path can be seen as a path to can do this more and more
support that deep seeing but if the cessation the third noble
truth is a definitive clear dropping away the bottom drops away in some
wonderful inspiring way and then we realize oh this is
freedom this is
peace this is the profound sense of well-being that's possible i had no idea
then the eightfold path is still the practice to do it becomes a practice to
two things to move into this experience of peace more and more
but it also becomes a practice that manifests that peace
and in the teachings of the buddha we find plenty of times where the eightfold path are eight ways of being in the
world which are not practices to attain
peace they're not practices that now we understand this is what we should practice if we want to deepen and deepen
our peace but there are more expressions of the peace
so i don't know if this is a good example but um
the an open hand might feel easeful
and the expression of the open has hand is eased expression of open hand is being
opened the expression of open hand is being its sensitivity available to the world
the expression of the open hand is it doesn't it's not creating a fist to hit someone it's just
an open hand so when the letting go is deep
full enough and we have a it becomes it can become a reference point and a
source from which we then live our life and the eightfold path then
is not a prescription for how to practice further so we can
deepen our practice or experience more liberation but rather the eightfold path is an
expression is a description of how we start living
so um if um um
if um so especially how are they so at some
point we have a clear sense that it's really good to be at ease to be at
peace to be have a sense of well-being and then when we have forces within us
that want to go in a different direction we would say why
why give up something good something useful for something is not so
good it's not a matter of practicing the hateful path but rather it's a matter of
not doing those things that take us away from the eighthful path
someone who is deeply practiced becomes the eightfold path they don't practice
the eightfold path and then becoming it they don't do the things they don't allow themselves to do
things that that take that away or they lose touch with themselves this
home of who they are and
so at some point in this four noble truths practice
the eighthful path becomes more and more interesting either it becomes we understand that
this is useful uh to do this all eight of these practices to create the conditions to
involve the tr to move into a kind of transform who i am transform my feelings my
my sense of being my attitude how i am in the world so it becomes easier to let
go more and more or there has been a transformation from a deep letting go and now it's a matter
of growing that transformation letting it become spread and become bigger and bigger
and and the eightfold path is then both the goal
the fulfillment of the goal and the means to the goal
so the eightfold path are eight sets of ways of being sometimes they're called
eight practices uh which is true when they're understood to be a means to liberation
but they're uh but they're eight ways of being when they're understood as being an
expression of our awakening so these are right view
right resolve right speech right action right livelihood
write effort right mindfulness and right concentration
and the right concentration ends with right concentration and right concentration is so the middle
ones right speech right action and right livelihood they're ethical how we behave in the world and how we
relate to other people how our actions affect others and
there's a kind of an orientation to an ethical transformation not to follow rules so much
but to follow these guidelines these these ways of being that are the ethical guidelines
um so that we begin to be transformed it's not about following rules
only it's about living this way so that we start being ethically transformed we
become someone who has such a sense of integrity or peace that of
course we wouldn't do the unethical things that would
obscure that or harm that but with the right concentration we're
talking also about a transformation concentration is not just a matter of having a lace not just a laser focus of
the mind it's having a unified sense of peace and calm from having let go a lot and practicing
concentration practicing stability and steadiness and
this is one of the primary ways that the tradition buddhist tradition has for preparing ourselves for the
deepest kinds of letting go we can do we're kind of becoming softer more malleable
more resilient more less distractible
and in that state it's kind of like we're ready for just something to be put down that we've
been carrying for a long time so there's some kind of inner
transformation that happens and part of that inner transformation is an experience of peace
and um and at some point that piece
becomes a reference point becomes a seed
that we can water and grow become something that a plant that kind of grows and
blossoms within us and and the eightfold path
is the represents that blossoming that fulfillment of it all
so if you not familiar with the eightfold path
there are really marvelous things to learn and study
they um once you kind of get the idea study them enough so you understand the basic idea
of what it is each of them then once you understand then you can start feeling your way sensing your way
understanding how these eight these eight waves of being
are not only practices they're also inner
wellsprings of being at home ill inner expressions of being settled and at peace with
oneself and this piece is not doesn't just doesn't start off doesn't
have to be dramatic but there might be little hints of what that is like
and then as we orient around that piece it can grow
there can it's possible to have very small degrees of peace in this life that we overlook
the mind is so concerned with his preoccupations that uh we just keep thinking them and
we have one preoccupation finished and we just jump on to the next one and the next one
and there's no space what we learn in this practice is to create a little more
space and attentiveness to the subtler places of well-being subtle places of
peace that begin surfacing through the practice and then
touch into it periodically regularly through the day find the little seeds
and recognize it water it with attention let it be a reference point let it be a
guide let it be kind of there to support you as you go through your life
so for this day you might study the get a book or
something or go on online and read about the eight noble eightfold path
but you also might look for the seeds of peace the little hints of it
that or ease or that you that might be
more part of you more available than you allow yourself to feel
it's pause stop take a break
check into yourself see if you can find is there anywhere within you some modicum some even the smallest
degree of peace and well-being and if you stay close to that for a little while
breathe with it what happens to you and what do you learn about peace
being an expression
and not a practice so thank you for today and
we'll have one more talk on the four noble truths tomorrow and
and we're almost done with this thank you