so hello hello nice to be with you
come to practice together so
so like to um i'd like to share something from
take not han book tonight um and
he has so many wonderful beautiful
um books and one of my favorite ones is peace is every step and
all these short vignettes and i randomly opened a book to a page and
it opened to a passage that i love and i thought oh okay i like to share this tonight with the sangha so so here we go
so from take nothing this is uh this section is called real
love and for those of you who may have the book and later want to look this up it's on page
80. so take note han says about real love
let it wash over you can close your eyes i'll read it slowly
we really have to understand the person we want to love
if our love is only a will to possess it is not real love
if we only think of ourselves if we know only
our own needs and ignore the needs of the other person
we cannot love we must look deeply in order to see and
understand the needs aspirations and suffering
of the person we love i love that needs aspirations and suffering
of the person we love this is the ground of real love
you cannot resist loving another person when you really understand them
i'll read the other couple of paragraphs and please think about
this love that he talks about not only as romantic love of course not it's
love of any kind love of any kind even
when we have friends colleagues a sense of love and care only if we think of our own needs so so or people elsewhere so
think of it as an expansive vision of love he continues
next section is more about people we know but again we can take this principle and make it
general so next section from time to time sit close to the one
you love hold their hand and ask darling do i understand you enough or am i making you
suffer please tell me so that i can learn to love you properly i don't want to make you suffer
and if i do so because of my ignorance please tell me so that i can love you better so that you can be happy
if you say this in the voice that communicates your real openness and understanding
the other person may cry that is a good sign because it means the door of understanding
is opening and everything will be possible maybe a father does not have time or is
not brave enough to ask his son such a question then the love between them will not be
as full as it could be we need courage to ask these questions
but if we don't ask the more we love the more we may destroy the people we are
trying to love this is so profound
if we don't ask the more we love the more we may destroy the people we are
trying to love true love needs understanding with understanding the one we love will
certainly flower what a beautiful teaching
[Music] so so both in terms of
close relationships when
there's someone near and dear to us could be a friend in this case a child
or a relative or even friends colleagues
and the idea also i want to bring in here is that we can love people without even liking
them it is possible to not necessarily like someone but to
love them and in this way to care for
or understand appreciate how take the perspective of their needs
their suffering their aspirations their wants
so as we've practiced together in the sapi hour in the past with
um say with the neutral being with the person we don't know where very well and
we bring this sense of common humanity or just like me taking their perspective
just like me as a human being who wants to be happy so this idea of real love
can be both in terms of people that are near and dear to us people we care
about in our lives friends and if we try to possess if we try to just take their
time try to take their resources that's not real love it's real love is
not just about me me me my needs my needs what can you give me dear friend dear teacher dear i don't
know whatever me me me me me so so a sense of
um especially in close role or children like
to saturn my need to be loved uh what is what do they need what what is their
need and as as tikhnathan puts [Music]
we must look deeply in order to see and understand the needs aspirations
and suffering the people we love this is the ground of real love
one last thing to say it is said that understanding
really understanding someone else clear understanding is equivalent to loving them when we
understand someone when we really understand that the heart can open
from this perspective of self-centeredness just being centered on
our own needs to having a wider perspective a bigger perspective it's
not just about me then service actually love can become an
act of service so i think i have said enough for
setting the frame for our reflection for our meditation today so i'd like to
invite us all ah to land to arrive
in your body in your posture if you need to move
to sit your cushion or lie down this is the time
entering a posture that's going to be comfortable for the next 30 minutes or so
and landing arriving in this body here
here
connecting understanding
opening up to the sensations in this body in this moment
not try to control but to open up to ah to relax into
can we have real love for ourselves for this body
even if there are pain there is pain there are challenges
now try to conquer but to open up to things as they are
this breath this sensation
with openheartedness
as always let us arrive let us settle first
with the breath
as it moves through the body the sensations
wherever they show up
expanding touching knowing every cell of this body
as if greeting breath greeting internally
gently kissing each cell inviting you to relax
to be just as it is
awareness awareness aware awareness knowing
the breath the sensations just this
releasing thoughts plans just being here relishing
this moment
and i'd like to invite you maybe first turning turning to ourselves
turning to this being it was me as if it were a beloved other
yes take not han recommends in this passage real love
asking ourselves these loving questions first
asking yourself sweetheart sweetheart darling
am i making you suffer am i making you suffer
please tell me so please tell me so that i can
learn to love you properly i don't want to make you suffer
and if i do so because of my ignorance please tell me
so that i can love you better can we ask ourselves this question see
what arises don't think about it drop it in drop the question in
into your body
as if a pebble dropped into a pond
resonating the water resonating reverberating
how can i love you better sweetheart darling
maybe the answer is wordless maybe just asking this question is enough
or something to be unleashed opened up internally
like to experiment with putting palm in your heart center your chest connect with yourself
physically more fully your own heart darling sweetheart how can i love you
better am i making you suffer
help me see help me now
how can i love you better
and this is not a chance to self-recriminate or self-judge just
meeting yourself with love with understanding in fact it's a time
not to do any self-judgment or self-criticism if any of that is coming up
let's drop it
not needed release
not a time for self-judgment or shame just loving
caring as best as we're able to
and now i'd like to invite you to bring to my your mind's eye if you wish you want to stay
with yourself if it's been a hard day and lovingly stay with yourself that's fine
and if it feels appropriate to move on that's okay also see what your heart
needs right now what is the ultimate expression of care
if you like you cannot bring to your mind your mind's eye someone who's near and dear to you
someone you love care for their well-being
so with with whom you have an easy relationship perhaps
wondering and in your heart your mind asking how can i understand you better
dear my dear what are what are your needs
your aspirations [Music] your hopes the ways you suffer
how can i understand you how can i understand you
better not to possess
not to satisfy my own needs but to understand you
to step out of my limited perspective what i me me i want
to see you from your complicated complex beautiful
perspective of the uniqueness of you as if i were gazing through the world
through your eyes as much as possible
how can i love you better through understanding you
see for a moment as if you were stepping
behind your eyes looking at the world what does it feel like what do you see
how can you love them better
for their sake not your sake
their needs and wants
in this way love can be service love as service
serving their growth serving their goodness their beauty
how can i serve you better how can i love you better
and you can stay with yourself if you like as a beloved other
or a spare being
a dear being in your life you want to try a bit of a stretch
maybe bringing someone to mind that's different from you
many ways different maybe you've had some minor challenge with please don't choose the hardest
most challenging person for you just
tread lightly someone maybe who's been complicated a
little bit in the past
just a tiny tiny bit challenging does the touch challenge
where there isn't much energy and if no one comes up then go back to your dear person or yourself
and can you see this person this being
from their perspective their hopes and dreams their aspirations
the way they suffer they suffer as if you're looking into the world
through their eyes and trying to understand them you could
have been born as them they could have been born as you this is so random
the bodies the circumstances the parents were born into the family
background upbringing what if you were then
even if you they're areas of their personality you don't like or you disagree can you love them
meaning can you understand them better just a little better
doesn't need to agree with everything there's just can you understand them just a tiny
bit more from this perspective
and we offer our love to the world
stepping outside of ourselves from ourselves as a beloved other too
[Music]
just dies this short lifespan of being human
with hopes aspirations intentions needs
sorrows sufferings here being us
we love can we offer our love to the world
our care
our warmth our service services love love and service
true love true understanding
may all be everywhere all things everywhere
know real love love themselves appreciate their own goodness
may they offer their love to others the generosity
may all beings everywhere
be happy may all beings everyone be free
thank you for your practice everyone
said who passed teaching by taking our time
so we have time for reactions
and i hope that my internet is a little unstable i hope you can hear me
my i know i might be freezing but you are welcome
um hopefully you can still hear me so ah see some reflections thank you though
paul that was lovely you are so welcome thank you for your practice
so i like to open up the space for reflections what did you discover
what came up especially if you haven't spoken for a while offering your insights or
your questions or your confusion as as an offering to serve both
yourself being held being witnessed and for the benefit of others if they're aha moments
you can type them in chat if you like if you type them to the group
then i will read the reflections if you type them to me alone
it will be private you can also raise your hand and if you cannot hear me you can type
it but i think my my image is frozen but i think audio is still working so i hope it's still good
so any reflections any thoughts you'd like to share from this practice
questions comments
deep gosha thank you you're welcome thank you for your practice
see private question coming i have quit meditating for
many months now the reason being every time i sit to meditate
my mind wanders and i become enraged with hatred for people who have done wrong to me
although they are not in my life anymore so instead i chose to concentrate on hobbies hobbies
that require concentration like learning to play an instrument and learning a new language
how can i get engaged in regular meditation again thank you thank you so much for that
question yeah beautiful question um
and very apt the invitation the recommendation i have for you
is first and foremost as you engage with practice to practice
self-compassion compassion and love and care for yourself because you are the one who is suffering
anger when we're angry we feel like oh yeah we're angry at others but it's like
picking up a hot coal that you're trying to throw at someone but who gets hurt when you
pick up a hot coal well you get hurt first of course so
feeling holding yourself with compassion when the mind goes to they they they just bring it back a sweetheart
sweetheart they're gone off they're living their life they don't even know i'm hurting right now just hurting
yourself as if you're holding a young child a younger version of yourself just
holding this young child letting it have a tantrum letting it cry letting it be
angry just hold it sweetheart it's okay you're safe you're safe you're safe it's
okay just holding the child
as long as it's needed for it to be angry with love with love
not thinking about others others but just yourself so that's a way that's a way
to to re-engage that's my invitation and you're welcome please come back and
send me a little report and tell me how it went you can also send me an email through my website
tell me how how this practice i'm inviting but you really have to hang in there you really have to let the whole
the younger version angry version of yourself be and just with love with love
with love maternal love just stay stay it's going to take a lot of courage which is great
because it both brings up your own strength and courage to be with your own
suffering with love so it's a courageous practice it's really
a um a a loving warrior practice it's a loving
warrior brings up a sense of strength as well as love so that's for what i invite you
go away see your hand is up please
uh yes um well uh
the only near and dear self that i have is myself
and um it's been a difficult number of days and so it was
a big question to ask myself how can i better understand
myself because
i don't have to look very far to find a very complicated person as myself and um
i don't find it easy um at all i i i can i can accept
myself uh even when i'm full of resistance
but that's about all i can do is just is just accept
accept my resistance and i don't know why i'm maybe feeling so much resistance
yeah yeah that's the best i can do is to accept
that and um just figure that i i may be the best thing i can do is be
patient yes there is so much wisdom ko in what you just shared i want to
applaud your inner wisdom that is beautiful that is
pure wisdom acceptance you may not understand it that's okay but can you
understand the resistance oh dear sweetheart there's a resistance here okay i can't be with that i don't
understand it and i don't need to probe was it my childhood my mother does it's okay i can just be patient and
hold it with kindness there is so much wisdom in that to allow it to
to be and unwind and show you the answers because when we let our
confusion our resistance our anger feel safe when we offer safety to these
complicated emotions without needing to necessarily understand them so yes let's back up from that word understanding i
appreciate that he's using it here let's back up from that understanding of that word and yeah using this acceptance
allowing um that that is deep wisdom thanks so much for bringing that in co
appreciate it a couple of other reflections here and
before we go quickly into groups
yeah another reflection wonderful loving practice seek first to understand before
being understood quote from stephen covey another reflection thank you nikki
the invitation to ask myself what i need how i can love and support this being was timely and moving thank
you and dave says compassion and meta for the russians were suffering absolutely
yes absolutely yes so many beings we all suffer in so many
different ways especially people in thai areas of of war right now in this world
love as service you for bringing them in and the last
week i offered every session compassion and meta
bringing in the people in ukraine especially and and now bringing in russia
and tonight we're staying a little more personal but of course it's
practicing love as service is not a selfish aspect serving all beings
so i'd like to invite us now to turn to engaging
in small groups together and can we can we hold
patiently each other and just listen or share as little or as much as you need to let's
start with maybe 10 15 seconds of silent meta for one another and then share as
little as you like or maybe just hold with for one another maybe that's a way of
listening and holding an understanding or maybe sharing what you're feeling is about real love this understanding as as love
love as service so so the rooms are created i'm opening
them up please take care of yourselves take care of each other speak only from your own experience here we go
okay welcome back everyone and
gosh it is seven o'clock so we have uh more time i think earlier with
with questions and reflections so um so why don't we dedicate the merit and
close our practice together thank you all for practicing and made
the goodness of our cultivation together may be a cause and condition
for goodness for for real love for care in the world may
all beings be well may all beings be happy including ourselves
[Music] you so much
you will