hello everyone and welcome
there's a classic image or metaphor that's used for meditation
and that is to sit like a mountain and um it may be a little bit easier to feel
that when you're sitting cross-legged when you have this triangular shape but
i bring it up now today because um learning to be firmly grounded
in the place that you're standing sitting for your being kind of be there solid like a mountain
it implies that you're not leaning forward you're not pulling back you're not contracting
you're just there in a very stable
way that the winds of the mount the mountain winds the stormy
winds doesn't move the mountain the mountain just stays
so to learn this the ability to have this kind of stability is really helpful
when we are in the world of anger whether in the world of other people's anger or our own anger
to not to give in to any of it not to be caught by it not be unduly influenced
by it and one of the and and to have developed a capacity to be stable
in meditation can translate into finding that stability in times of
great difficulty in times it may be when there is anger directed at us or that we directed some
other place and so with that in mind maybe in this meditation
we can take some care to have to feel like a mountain
whether you're meditating in a chair or sitting cross-legged or maybe some of you are
standing or if you are lying down
maybe there's some way of feeling stability strength
unwaveringness in the face of whatever is happening and to
have the body your physical body support you in this groundedness
so to begin
giving some care to your posture maybe adjusting things
so that there is more stability if you're sitting in a chair make sure there's a there's a feeling of
firmness underneath the soles of your feet that uh if you're sitting with the feet
on the floor like they're there firmly some of that stability comes from the
feet if you're sitting sitting uh
cross-legged on the floor that
it feels balanced to you that the your the way your lower part of
your body is against the floor and your cushion
is there's a firm support feel the firm support or whatever
underlies your body's weight
and take time to feel the support feel the way your weight
comes down and rests against your chair your cushion the
floor your bed
and to really feel that grounding
you might sway back and forth a little bit
forward and back and to really feel the contact
of your body against what holds up the body's weight
and then as you exhale to exhale into that contact point
like you're releasing yourself into the that support
and then to feel your torso arising out
of that support and it works a little better if you're sitting upright that
imagine you're sitting here like a mountain with a wide firm base
if you're sitting using a backrest if it's possible to
sit up a little straighter maybe even not using the backrest
even for a little while
and with and taking a few long deep breaths into
your rib cage deep in stretching opening on inhale
almost like you're becoming more full or substantial or
strong as you breathe in a little more deeply than usual
and exhaling and settling into the stability
of this body of yours
and uplifting movement as you breathe in
and a rooted feeling as you exhale let go and become rooted in this body
letting your breathing return to normal
and whatever allow yourself to feel whatever global stability
there is in your body global steadiness
and as the torso breathes
perhaps you can feel that steady stability
the breathing arise out of that stability return to it
be part of it
entrust yourself to your body
trust the stability the steadiness the weight of your body
as it's rooted like a mountain here
in the thinking mind thoughts are like clouds or winds at the top of the
mountain
releasing any tension or holding associated thinking
letting those thoughts begin to
evaporate
the energetic wind of thinking begins to
quiet down and calm the mind trusts resting in the stability
of the body
mindful of breathing as if breathing is
intimately connected to the stability of the body here and
now
maybe gently saying to yourself the word
stability stable
as if that word is being said out of the stability of the body
becoming grounded in the stability of the body
stable
with the reference of being stable or
maybe you can notice the movements away from that stability
and then noticing them return to the stability
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
consider how being stable
can be a support for being present for others
maybe when others are not stable
maybe as a way of
letting our friendly friendship or friendliness be more evident and present
perhaps from a base of stability
wishing well on others has a very different
feeling than doing it without stability
trusting the stability of being trusting the stability of the bones
your weight the contact against the ground
the stability of gravity as you sit here
and opening your heart wide
to offer your good will your well-wishing your compassion and care
out into the world
you as a champion for the welfare and happiness
of others may others
be happy may others
be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and may we contribute to that without losing
our balance our stability and our wisdom
[Music]
hmm
so here we are at the fourth talk on anger
and today i want to talk a bit about speaking when we are angry
it's one thing to be able to be by oneself and to meditate and and
process the anger that way it's another thing to
manage our anger wisely when we're in relationship to other people and you need to talk and work and
do things with others and certainly i hope that
the whole mindfulness approach with emotions with uh with anger
uh and this kind of deeper looking at it uh is supportive for
how we engage that in the world when we are anger angry
so the mindfulness approach to anger is an alternative
to expressing the anger acting it out venting it
catharsis venting anger is usually not very helpful
it's helpful for people who have very deep repressed anger and never get a chance to have it come to the surface
then maybe going to a safe location like in the forest and you know express the anger to a tree or
something where there's no one or alone in your room and just to kind of finally get it up to the surface so
you can address it but generally venting and anger and cathartic expression of anger
more often than not tends to strengthen the anger give more make more of it and make it grow
and that's why venting anger to other people that you might feel
is usually counterproductive because it tends to put fuel in itself
the classic buddhist um teaching around anger is that anger is a fire that burns
the person who has it and um so with venting you know
the the external externality of the venting sometimes doesn't allow the venter to
feel uh the cost the burning but in fact it's tremendously costly for the person who's
venting anger it's not really a relief release of pressure
and then so then one end you know expressing the anger or venting the anger
is usually not suggested repressing the anger is also not uh
healthy this can create tremendous amount of problems and usually it's counterproductive and sooner or later
there may be an explosion or or the anger the resentment kind of sees out in unseen ways
so the alternative i'd like to suggest for today between expressing anger
and repressing it is managing the anger
so knowing that we're angry and finding the tools how to be with the
anger that we we have so that it doesn't need to be expressed
and it doesn't need to be repressed and what we can do is we can learn to
interact with other people [Music] having the anger somehow helpfully
managed so one of the things one way to manage the anger
is uh not to automatically give into it but have an alternative
place a way of being with anger than giving into it and one of those ways
is to be rooted grounded stable in ourselves to have cultivated a
habit a strong skill set in being connected to the physical body
to be able to be grounded in the physical body to take a stable posture
in the physical body to learn how to manage the agitation of
the body the restlessness of the body
the pressures emotional pressures that arise in the body to be able to hold them in the body
and this is phenomenally useful that we are learning through mindfulness practice to expand
our capacity to experience difficult emotions if the capacity is small then the
difficult emotions spill over or explode or become detrimental
but we're learning steadily in this practice to expand our capacity to hold more and more difficult emotions
including anger and one of the ways to hold it to be with it is to really
drop into the body feel the body feel the stability of the body and let the anger be felt as part of the body
as opposed to we becoming the anger identifying with the anger and
which is a very difficult state to be in if anything we identify with the body
and the anger is a subset of it and then uh as we manage this um the
anger if we have a little bit of ability to
investigate to look inside to understand the characteristics of the anger
is it something that's really unique to a current incident
or is there a long history of resentment of complaining of indignation of
of stress connected to how we're feeling now this is just a continuation of a long pattern in fact there might even be
a kind of a continuous chronic feeling of the irritation that weak
annoyance that's there regardless if we're with others or not and it's just that that annoys a chronic
annoyance irritation resentment has it sometimes now it's getting kind of
a big wave is being formed of it though the little wave is always moving across the ocean
and um and maybe it's going across a shoal and now it's being raised up and really big
if it's chronic we might relate to it very differently than if it's just in the incident in the
moment because incidence in the moment is where maybe there's real danger
and so if anger is a symptom of a danger of
some so there's a problem going on that then if you recognize what the problem is
then maybe there's less need to be angry then we can maybe find ways to address
the problem and this is where mindful speech is phenomenally useful
to learn how to speak mindfully and one of the ways to speak mindfully
is again to be rooted in the body to have the stability of body as we speak
so that we can track what we're saying we might even be able to track what we're about to say
it's because we're managing all this not to repress anything but so the best parts of ourselves come out it's really
managing ourselves so we can stay free not managing ourselves so we bottle ourselves up
it might feel like you were free or if we just vent our anger and just speak spew out what we're feeling but that's
not really freedom that's really a loss of freedom even though there's a release and kind of a
ease in which things are spilling out of us the managing is to to stay close to that
place where there's a deeper wisdom that's free deeper connectivity deeper choice is possible
and so to learn to speak connected to the bodies being aware of
what's happening here the other is if again if there is
an opportunity to to pay a little bit of attention and this becomes second nature the more we
are mindful of speech in ourselves is to is to be careful why you're speaking
what's the motivation what are you accomplishing with a speech some speech it's only a dagger as we're
throwing at other people to hurt them some speech is to
try to solve the problem some speech is to try to give a message to someone that what they're doing is
not acceptable but it's very different been letting them know in strong terms you
can't do this versus some kind of statement that says you're you know a terrible person using
some horrible language to say that you know kind of attacking them and throwing you
know swear words at them perhaps um so what's the purpose of the language is
it to hurt the person is it to problem solve is to be able to let the person know what we're feeling
and then the content of what we say is important and one thing that's very helpful
is at times is to learn the art of i statements
i was once many years ago i was a ta in college
for a for the chair of the department and
he was treating me in some kind of way that was not appropriate maybe as a servant and something and
asking me to do all kinds of things and putting pressure on me and demands that were unreasonable
and i got furious at him but i had enough sense no this is not a
person to yell at or be angry at and so uh but i didn't want to repress
it i felt this needs to be addressed so i went to him and i stood there and i was kind of shaking because i was so
angry and and i made i statements i said things like
what i'm experiencing now given what you said and what you're asking me to do is i feel really hurt i
feel really upset and it was obvious that i was i wasn't saying anything about him and
what he did i was just saying the impact it had on me and that was all i needed to do he
backed out he understood the impact he understood what he had done and then the whole thing became a lot
better and the and so to sometimes sharing the impact
sometimes it's powerful to tell people when you did x i i know i feel afraid
now some people kind of when they realize what the impact they had like that they switch and change
as opposed to yelling at them and then they yell back and then the whole thing escalates
and the idea is to learn how to speak in ways where the speaking de-escalates our own anger
whether it diffuses it and they're wonderful i like maybe slightly pronounced differently but the two
meanings of diffuse is to kind of
settle out spread out so it's weaker thinner less concentrated and to take
the fuse out of a bomb to diffuse we're defusing our anger
we're tracking ourselves so we know we get the feedback that we're actually maybe speaking in a way that's
increasing the level of the anger rather than decreasing it i've been angry at someone once
some years ago and and i asked to meet with a person privately so we did
and we talked for a while and then i said after after a while i could feel myself getting even more upset
and so i asked if we could have a time out can we just sit here quietly for a few minutes um and the person was a practitioner so
that was apparently easy enough to agree to and then and then when the
you know after a few minutes of breathing and being present then i was ready to continue the conversation
i was not in a good place to have the conversation until i had had a couple of minutes of silence
so to track ourselves to manage ourselves to uh to be able to
manage the conversation and find the balance and find how to speak and what to speak
how not to attack people when we speak which is so easy to do when we're angry
but to speak in ways that try to get the job done that needs to be done that's appropriate
to be careful that we're not spilling over things have nothing to do with them
chronic resentments chronic hurt that we're carrying with us
can bring a lot of pressure along that way we're not really taking
care of the situation at hand as we're somehow giving expression to age-old resentment
that we're carrying that we're frustrated with and is coming out so in these few minutes i have those are
the the ideas that i'm offering so here the primary one i want to leave
you with is two ideas one is manage your anger
and manage it with discovering some stability within always look for the stability if you can
and the other is uh start being exploring and being wise about how you
speak because sometimes we have to speak when we're angry
and maybe today if you have an occasion to be angry or irritated or annoyed
or you want to complain don't complain don't express annoyance don't
send barbs to people rather consider what you can say
that's maybe an i statement that may supportive in the situation that's appropriate for the situation take care
of something that takes care of you and the other person if the person hasn't done the dishes one
more time don't kind of yell at them just kind of say wow
here we are again the dishes aren't being done what's happening or it's very discouraging i feel so
discouraged to see this thing full of dishes again and leave it at that see
what happens something mainly the point being find ways to speak
when you're angry develop the skill and the wisdom to be able to do that so that your speech is healthy and wise
in circumstances when you're angry so thank you
and we'll have one more talk on anger tomorrow i think