so good morning everyone and good day hello
and we're coming here to the last week of the series on sati patana
and my preferred translation of the word
sati is awareness and awareness
maybe is a little bit ambiguous term for some people it's a
multivalent term meaning it can have different meanings for different people
and one of the meanings that it has for me that
pertains to my practice and understanding of this text we're doing
it is a form of awareness form of
attentiveness that when established
has an effortless quality to it
there might be effort to stay in the flow of the river
if you kind of go off to the side and get caught on the bank on the left side you
maybe push off or you kind of paddle a little bit to stay in the middle of the the current
or if there's um some boulder in the way as you go down
on the left you kind of you know make sure you stay in the middle and so there's a little bit of
effort involved but it's clear that the effort involved is not to be aware
the effort involved is letting go of what interferes
with awareness and some of the things that interfere with kind of a crisp or clear awareness
really feeling we're present is there's a lot of thinking and thinking is not the problem
in a sense thinking is the distraction from that awareness
we don't have to then condemn thinking or stop thinking the art of it is to kind of turn it
around and let that discover that awareness
return to that awareness being aware of the thinking
and so it's a little slight of hand you're preoccupied and thinking then you know you're caught in your thoughts
and then rather than doing anything against the thoughts judging them or
or or trying to get away from them or do something it's the
discovering the kind of knowing of thinking
the awareness the recognition that has a kind of ease to it a
quietness to it a naturalness to it maybe an effortlessness to it
effortless in the sense that it's not something that we do
but rather it's something that is done by our psychophysical system
something that's done by maybe we say the mind it's as if it's the awareness that you
can't turn off you can only be distracted from in waking hours
it's always operating and
and luckily it operates when we're distracted sometimes because
um you know you might being lost in thought but you have just
something something has just enough awareness to see that as you walk down the sidewalk you're about to run into a
person pushing a stroller with a baby in it and somehow that comes into awareness enough that the system takes it into
account um but you weren't really seeing anything but you know consciously
but somehow that awareness was there so
i don't know how accessible this will be for you today but perhaps for the sitting today
maybe there can be little moments where you can appreciate this little moments of maybe being in awe of
it inspired by it that we have this capacity
or maybe there'll be moments where you can't understand why this is a big deal
why is it so important because we have important things to think and to
do and and we have to get on with it and just to do something that's so
uh we're not applying ourselves can seem like you know
what's the point but we do apply ourselves mostly to get
out of the ways to stay in the current to place ourselves back in the current
and then allow this awareness to be there and to carry us and maybe it's the
current the river of of our present moment experience
or maybe it feels like there's a river of awareness itself that flows through experience of the
present moment something like that
so assuming a meditation posture
and just as you're here even before you close your eyes if they're not closed
what comes into awareness effortlessly
what you become aware of that you're not directing your attention to focus on or
it kind of comes into peripheral vision
maybe what comes into awareness that there was no plan to have that be there
just there without planning or directing attention and
a sound
a particular body sensation if your eyes are open in particular
sight object
it's possible that almost seemingly immediately after something comes to awareness
unexpectedly and effortlessly the mind kicks in with effort and
directedness and reflection
that's okay but see if you can even for moments
recognize and appreciate when awareness seems effortless or
undirected as it knows something
now you might gently close your eyes
and with this kind of under on kind of receptive open
maybe seemingly effortless awareness the closest you can to doing it
without doing anything more or fixing anything or changing anything
become aware of the tensions in your body the places where you're tight places
that we usually relax during this meditations but don't relax them
just let them be in this field of awareness
and let them appear in whatever way they want to appear in the different parts of the body
maybe without attention centered on any one of them
but just gently in its own way floating between them
notice any tendency to want to relax the body
and that that desire to relax the body let that just be one more thing that
awareness knows without needing to do anything
awareness does not need to do anything at all except be aware
if you need to do something experiment with just being aware of the
feeling of that need letting it just exist in a
field of this effortless awareness
and maybe as if you're pulling the curtains on a window and now see the landscape outside
kind of like you're pulling the curtains for your breathing
the landscape is the body breathing
and what a part of breathing experience of breathing comes into
awareness effortlessly unplanned
the particular sensations of the in-breath and out-breath don't last
when one ends
what's the next sensation that comes into awareness
you're watching the river of experience in the river in the breathing
it's like watching the little waves on the top of the river
that go by watching all the different sensations
putting aside needing to do anything accomplish anything
in favor of
appreciating whatever way there's a naturalness and
awareness in whatever way once in a while
it seems that awareness operates without direction and without
you doing the awareness just aware
yeah you don't have to give any concern
to how you're not doing today's practice not managing to do it
only kind of begin again noticing how it is working
maybe it's a most clearest time is when a sound or a sensation or a thought
arises uninvitingly unplanned
is just there in awareness in that first moment
it's there effortlessly
and what happens to the naturalness or the effortlessness of awareness
if you make a very small half smile with the corner of your lips
resting in awareness as you would rest in an
easy chair rest in a
back into a soft mattress is resting in awareness
and then whatever way you can appreciate
the naturalness of awareness the effortless quality that can be there
the way that awareness could operate without directing the mind or doing awareness
and in that natural awareness
is there any in and of itself within itself not within you
is there any attachment
any fear any aversion or
clinging is there a place of awareness
a way of being aware that is absent of clinging absent of
attachment
absent of being for or against
and what we're focusing on here is the awareness itself not what awareness knows
the awareness might know attachment it might know clinging or
but the simplicity of that awareness which
is there even when you're not trying to be aware
in and of itself is it free
of attachment and fear
and those of you who can sense something like this
take one last moment here in the meditation to appreciate
knowing a place within free of attachment free of clinging free
of fear
and to the degree to which you can be aware without attachment without fear
without
asserting yourself let that attention move now towards
the people in your life in your neighborhood
places of work family friends strangers your
people in stores you go to
and perhaps this simple natural awareness
can be a clearing a clarity through which
your kindness your
love your friendliness
can flow outwards to them
may the clarity of awareness allow us to love more
freely and in that love
as an expression of that love may we wish well for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
thank you all
and while i drink my water if some of you would like to write what the meditation was like for
you or how well or not well you could tap into this idea of
natural or effortless awareness and i'm sure that some of you it didn't
work and that's those comments are just as valuable as those that it
was useful for and then those comments maybe will help me kind of know how to direct my
little dharma talk
so thank you all for the comments i'm seeing and the ones that are still coming
i'll read them all um at the end when we stop here and so i
appreciate looking at them then but for now i'd like to say a few words
so we're coming to the end of this many weeks
teachings on sati patana the sati patana which the title of which i like to
translate it as um the
ways of establishing the four ways of establishing
awareness the establishments for awareness
and the emphasis what we're trying to do here is not understand
so much these areas of our life that's certainly part of it
but we're also establishing awareness when and then we're abiding in that
awareness and and that awareness isn't uh
involves a clarity involves being able to remain in the present moment
that ability to remain centered in the present moment is often associated with
concentration to be concentrated and focused here and now but often with
concentration there's a for many people they assume that um
that concentration is kind of a laser focus or a tightening of focus onto something
and the way that i understand somalia here is that it's an undistractedness
in the present moment where all our our whole being starts getting gathered together
to be aware here and now without the distractions
this is to do this well uh comes at the end of a long period of doing sati patana
practice and um and it might for some people it they might get the hang of it quickly
some people it might take years and years you'll see in a moment it might take
them seven years to develop it to some degree but one of the nice qualities that
happens is as we get some sense of the naturalness of awareness or the effortless of awareness
or the the the way that we can um
practice letting go of the distractions from awareness but then abide in awareness awareness not something we do
it's something that we allow for something that we stay in
and uh and and avoid it's like staying in a current in a river
and you're floating down the river and um and i i said this earlier but
this recording is will might live differently from what i said
so floating down the river and you can stay in the current but if it looks like you're going to veer off the
current into an eddy or into the side of the river then you make a small adjustment to come back into and then the river carries you
so the effort at some point becomes not an effort to be aware but the effort to avoid being distracted
being caught in something and then come back be here come here
at some point uh there starts to be a recognition
that in this awareness this awareness itself in an in and of itself
there is a kind of freedom there is a a absence
of attachment of clinging maybe fear anger
hostility even desires are absent in this awareness
even healthy desires we can still have them all these things still exist but we start
taking up residency in the awareness we don't have residency in our anger
residency our fear those things can still exist to some degree but we're not prioritizing them we're
not giving them undue attention and importance
they can be there and we can take care of them wisely but we realize we're we're not those we're not identified
with them and if we want to identify with anything we identify with this awareness that we
can't do that just is there but more importantly though is that we
start seeing how this awareness is free of clinging and knowing that this exists that this
possibility is there is a fantastic knowing oh it is possible
to be free of attachment amazing
i get a glimmer of it i have a hint of it but wow it's possible to be free
of jealousy of judgmentalism of cynicism of
of craving of avariciousness of
um all kinds of things that are absent in that place
and it's possible to live in the world effectively established and abiding in this place
to know that is to know something really important so now i'd like to read
the last part of this text that we were doing all these weeks and
it's kind of the conclusion to it all and
it says so that the buddha says practitioners
if anyone should develop these four foundations
for awareness in such a way for seven years
one of two fruits results could be expected of that for that person
either final knowledge here and now or if there's a trace of clinging left
non-return so if a person does this practice seven years
they can expect one of two results final knowledge here and now to in this
lifetime here to attain final awakening here's called final knowledge
and and what it's a knowledge of it's not knowledge about the cosmos and the inner
workings of the mind or you know the details of you know
physics or something final knowledge is a knowledge
that the mind is without clinging wow and really know this wow this bind
here has no clinging in it amazing
and what i was pointing trying trying to point to today is we can get a
early hints of that possibility so we know it's possible some as we develop awareness as we
find ourselves more and more aware and
and don't confuse it with having clinging it's a part of you
that is free of clinging it's a part of you that's for your fear and it's found in the awareness itself
and then it says either after seven years you'll have full awakening final knowledge here and now
or if there's a trace of clinging left non-return non-return means that when you die
you in this old idea of rebirth i mean the common buddhist idea of rebirth that you
will not return as a human being but you'll do the final work the final liberation finally letting go in this
liminal space somewhere beyond your death
and um and um
and in seven years so i the usual interpretation of this is
that this means seven years that this is the primary occupation a person is
involved in doing this practice so classically it's someone who can do this would be monastics and
really give their life over to it and that seems pretty phenomenal but the buddha goes on and says
let alone seven years if anyone should develop these four foundations for awareness in such a way
for six years they'll have have one of these two
fruits or for five years or for four years three years two years
for one year one of two fruits should be expected
either final knowledge here and now or if there's a trace of clinging left
non-return let alone one year
if anyone should develop these four foundations for awareness in such a way
for seven months for six months for five months for four months
for three months for two months for one month for half a month one of two fruits could be expected
either final knowledge here and now or if there's a trace of clinging left non-return
let alone half a month if anyone should develop these four foundations for awareness in such a way
for seven days one of two fruits can be expected
either final knowledge here and now or if there's a trace of clinging left non-return
so it seems pretty you know phenomenal to do this inner work in seven days
they're probably you know in the billions of people that exist in the planet there are people who can uh
probably are prepared and have a certain kind of capacity potential that maybe they can
drop into a deep state and find their way all the way to to the end
for most of us it's uh this is not if you don't attain final knowledge in
that this kind of speed but uh it's possible to have
knowledge of this recognize that it becomes part of us
it's not complete it's not the final but it's we're well on the way we've had an
experience we know this possibility of non-clinging and to have confidence in it to feel
that it's value no it's valuable it's one of the most valuable things a human being can can do with this lifetime
is to discover this place within this this place or this
possibility or this i don't know if it's within it's just once you're in the in awareness there's
no insight and outside where there's a freedom from suffering
then our compassion for the world knows how it's
how fully it's possible to help support people to become free of
suffering to have compassion for people who suffer and provide them with
band-aids is great if there's a wound i mean i never want to
not offer band-aids that are needed and i celebrate the people who do
and to really know how thoroughly people can be
freed of their suffering is to have this knowledge in experiential knowledge inside of
ourselves of this possibility then we can be a beacon then we can point people and then we can support
people to to the full potential to become free of suffering the very
goal of compassion the text goes on a little bit more
and then we'll stop for today so it was with reference to this
that it was said this is the direct plat this is the direct path for the purification of
beings for this amounting of sorrow and lamentation for the disappearance of pain and grief
for the attainment of the of the of the way for realization of nibana namely
the four foundations for awareness this is what the buddha said
the practitioners were satisfied and delighted in the buddha's words
so that's the end of the text and um we'll have the rest next four days of
the week to kind of also finish up this whole text and suta and
and so thank you for today and
during this day of your life maybe you can
try to have a heightened attentiveness to when awareness operates
without you directing it you making it happen the awareness where
your ordinary self is not the agent for the awareness you're just aware in a natural way
so thank you and i'll see you tomorrow