so hello and welcome and today the
theme in this week's series is happiness a particular kind of happiness
that um in a sense has no reason
external reasons isn't that we've won a prize or some wonderful things
happening in the world um but rather
happiness that comes with doing the practice
that mindfulness the meditation practice a kind of contentment a warm thing
that uh the pleasure that comes from the
from being immersed in the practice itself without any
distractions without any reference points of other things that we want or that we don't want that should happen in
the world or our concerns about what's coming or what's happened before
the immersion Here In This Moment's experience
so um I'd like to say this that
um what the mind what attention focuses on
can have an influence on the mind what the Mind feeds on
affects the health of the Mind the state of the Mind so if the Mind feeds on a lot of horror
movies then it might be not a surprise that we
spend a good amount of time being afraid if we spend a lot of time with friends
who mostly are angry complaining cynical and that's what we focus on and there's
no surprise then that then that gets reinforced that happened to be that way
if we spend a lot of time on advertisements no maybe no surprise that then we end up
strengthening our desires if we focus on genuine or healthy
happiness that affects and influences the Mind differently than these earlier ones
and so what we focus on is food or effects or is an influence on
the Mind itself if we do it regularly and repeatedly what we think about same thing
so it's helpful in meditation to lower the bar for what we think happiness or joy is
maybe it's a very subtle contentment or a subtle sense of pleasure of Simply
sitting here and being here and to include that in the focus of
attention let that be a food that would that be what the Mind feeds on or grows
with now mindfulness practice is often about being present for what is whatever is
predominant and so what I'm saying might seem contradictory focus on something gets
subtle and ignore the predominant desires that I'm caught up in or the
anger that I'm involved in it's a little different in that
we definitely want to be present for what is but we want to notice that the being
present being mindful being aware and here I use the word
being as a kind of deliberateness a kind of yeah conscientiousness or kind of
conscious presence and awareness that deliberateness or that engagement
of awareness that way of being aware
it's possible to find happiness pleasure in that so if we're being mindful of our anger
being mindful of our greed or whatever it might be or
um the way not to have the anger and the greed be fed is to uh
step away from being from participating in these unwholesome unhealthy mind
States and in stepping away look at them be aware of them watch them
and appreciate the watching appreciate the awaring of them the awareness
appreciate feel the feel a contentment a joy a kind of happiness
in being aware as opposed to in participating with
so as we sit here today as you bring up your mindfulness to being aware of the Present Moment In
your experience with a very low bar very low standard of what qualifies
see if you can be aware while there's a pleasure of mindfulness
the pleasure the contentment for being aware maybe a delight Maybe not something
you're actively thinking about too much but just the nature of being aware the nature of mindfulness
contains within it some pleasure some goodness something that feels this is good
this is valuable this is um this is this moment is content to be
aware this way to bring that along with your mindfulness then that is what feeds the
mind that's what influences the mind it's a protection from being influenced
by the greed or the anger or whatever it might the unhealthy mind States mind activities
while being aware of them at the same time so hopefully that's clear so
assuming your meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and slowly and deliberately bring a sense of gentleness into your
body being gentle with what is not gentle
being gentle with the tensions the agitations
the emotions that might be in your body a gentle awareness of them
and if you find your body being muscles being tense
almost as if you're not doing anything but being aware of them the tension
allow the tension to release if it wants to release
allow your body to relax if that's what your body wants to do
and then allow awareness to gently
be with the movements of the body breathing
wherever that movement of breathing Sensations or breathing
are the easiest or most enjoyable to experience
and as you're aware of your breathing maybe also aware of any tension and
agitation in the mind
and if that tension wants to be to relax
allow it to the mind to soften to relax
and then again becoming aware of breathing more fully
where there's a light touch in the body
the light touch between awareness and breathing
and awareness touches the experience of breathing lightly but broadly
not the fingertip touching but the whole hand of awareness
making a light contact with a body breathing
awareness floating on the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
if you find yourself thinking it isn't so much that you let go of your
thoughts as you let go of your interest and involvement with them
so you can be more interested and more involved
in the contact between breathing and awareness
and then as you're aware you might be aware of breathing thoughts
are rising sounds Sensations emotions all these things might come into
awareness see if you can also include
be aware of that a contentment a happiness a pleasure
in being aware what you're aware of might not be
pleasant and happy but some way that being aware
deliberately consciously knowing what's happening as it's
happening lightly gently
openly whatever way that that feels
comes with happiness contentment
include that as you're being aware
maybe you can let there be a happiness
in The Knowing in the awaring
instead of giving yourself over to your thoughts give yourself over to being aware
here now
sensitive to the slightest pleasure or happiness
that comes with being aware
foreign
anywhere physically emotionally
is their way of lightening up gentling on how you're aware of it
opening up the awareness so that awareness of it has a contentment or
pleasure or happiness or a feeling of rightness this feels
right to be aware this way
foreign
thank you
so then as we come to the end of the sitting imagine
that how you're aware of the world is offering medicine or food for the
world that if you're aware of the world if you know the world
from fear or from Anger from greed or lust
you're putting into the world something very different than if you're aware of the world with
contentment and happiness with joy pleasure love kindness
at least the kind of pleasure or contentment that can come from being aware itself
the awareness that allows us to see clearly and honestly what is here in this world
without being entangled in it
to be aware in a way that is
the awareness itself contains a joy a happiness
a pleasure the joy of non-clinging
the joy of being present
to be aware in this way provides a healthy food medicine for
this world that we live in may we bring the joy the happiness
of mindfulness into all our encounters even the ones
which are unpleasant even the ones that we have other emotions
but at least we have the subtle pleasure happiness
of mindfulness itself May our mindfulness
be a healthy influence on this world that we live in may it contribute to the welfare and
happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
thank you
so this is the fourth talk on the gladness pentad
and the fourth of these five qualities is happiness sukkah
and because sukkah is sometimes translated as pleasure the um there's two conclusions about the
kind of Happiness we're talking about one is that um
uh pleasure is something we mostly can feel through our body there's a physicality to it
and so this is a happiness which has us sublime or Pleasant pleasure
somehow in the body it's not excited it's so something gets settling and quieting
and the other is that this sukkah this happiness is not to be happy about anything
but rather it's the happy in doing in the inactivity
so to be immersed in an activity that just the immersion the absorption the
giving yourself over to it the I like this like giving ourselves
over to to really be there not to forget ourselves not to disconnect but to real
in mindfulness to really give ourselves over to this immerse ourselves in this
world of practice and and as the practice the strength of
it builds that immersion in the practice is not something that we will that we you know say okay now I'm going to do
this but rather something we enter into we settle into that opens up for us with
the strength of our practice and our ability to our strengthen her in
not being caught in thoughts so there's a momentum that builds
through practice that begins with faith with trust with inspiration and the practice itself
so that we want to practice and so we sit down we're glad to be able
to practice we're glad something that we're glad that wow I'm glad I I've been busy running around like crazy all day
and it's so good to finally sit down and sit quiet and and not be so busy or wow
you know I've been this is so important for me this practice and and I do it every day but this is like the center of
how I want to live my life is what comes from this practice so I'm so glad to be back here at home in this practice
so for each of us it's going to be different but there's a gladness and that gladness is a little bit of a
encouragement a cheerleader and a to start really giving ourselves to doing
the practice the um you know we sit down to meditate and we find ourselves interested in the
challenge we have a look with a local neighbor and her local neighbor is not being right or
you know being unfair or something and that might be an important topic but uh
we sit down and that that's not what this meditation is about you're finally
here at home you have something you love doing and you're so happy to be able to
do it the concerns with the neighbors can wait for another time so
there's a momentum then being glad to do it and that gladness that we start doing it we start feeling we start feeling
hooked in or or plugged in to being mindful that being mindful is
you feel like there's a life of its own the practice it's doing itself for us now it's not constantly coming back
constantly coming back constantly applying ourselves but there's um there's uh you know we're kind of
like now we're on the conveyor belt like okay now we're kind of coming along and and that conveyor belt feeling of being
in the practice in the engagement um the engagement itself starts feeling
uh kind of a delightful Joy um a uh a a kind of a very subtle
Pleasant maybe thrill or a little bit of excitement oh yes we're here we're present and that's a feeling that maybe
is felt in the arms and the chest um sometimes in the face it feels like
maybe something's vibrating or something's uh energized or something there's a lightness or a Clarity or a
tingling or a a sense of flowing pleasure to that immersion
and then we're so happy to be doing it something relaxes and let's go oh I'm
here I can trust this I can now relax more fully
and so there isn't need to apply oneself so much in meditation something about
the attention of application relaxes and the body relaxes and settles
and with that settling of the body quieting tranquilizing the body then that the gladness and the joy transforms
into a kind of Happiness a kind of contentment a kind of embodied
um pleasure that is not kind of hidden hedonistic
pleasure it's just feels so satisfying that it doesn't feel right to call it
pleasure maybe it feels better as kind of a kind of a happiness that that feels
light that feels quiet that feels still it feels more subtle than gentle than
the the joyful immersion that came earlier in the practice
so so this momentum begins happening and this is one of the great things about practice to find ourselves on the
conveyor belt of practice and some people at this point in practice will talk about it isn't that
they're doing the practice but they are being practiced it's almost like a practice is doing us
rather than we're doing the practice and so in a big part of the practitioner's role at this point is
making sure we don't mess it up we don't get in the way of it we don't get caught up in thoughts or control or trying to
make it better or fixing it or holding on to it it's mostly just kind of stay out of the way
like you know there's too many if there's too many cooks in the kitchen it doesn't work and so the extra cook is
you and so you have to kind of stay present for sure but you mostly have to kind of stay you know out of the kitchen
so one of the ways of understanding this pleasure to make it more accessible
perhaps because it might seem a little bit much this idea of being on the
conveyor belt and being carried along is to feel it uh very be content and
happy how subtle it can be how small it can be and one of the ways of doing this is as
we kind of cultivate mindfulness practice and get used to it and being aware and being present
being in the moment Here and Now recognizing what's happening offering
our presence our attention to what's happening here if we're drinking tea eating food opening a door
being with our breathing listening to someone that there's a kind of a kind of a
heightened attentiveness a feeling of kind of deliberateness of being present and receptive to what's
happening and then to begin feeling recognizing
that there is some pleasure some goodness something healthy some
Happiness joy in being aware of self some of this might be evaluative like
all these different uh steps of the pentad it might be that the happiness of
being inspired I'm getting to do this practice look at me it's like Ma look riding the bicycle with no hands
um look at this I was aware of three breaths in a row look at this I was
listening to my friend my friend said something difficult and I didn't habitually kind of lash out or my
usually I just stayed and was present wow this is good so that's a valuative
gladness and then you keep listening and it just feels good to have this ability to be
attentive and open and you see that your friend who's complaining about something that something shifts in them because
you're just present in a non-reactive way and you start appreciating your non-reactivity in a deeper way
and then it allows you to relax into it and then in that relaxing you feel that
there's a little you're there's a subtle in the awareness itself not evaluative
that evaluating it but rather in the tone of it and the texture of it there
is some happiness some contentment some pleasure
and to stay gently aware of that to pleasure
that goodness that what's healthy about that kind of awareness is very useful
because what we pay attention to is what influences the the the quality
and texture and state of our mind and heart and if we're only aware of and focus on
what's painful difficult with our anger and our grief and our sadness and our
conceit and our discouragement and all kinds of things like that if we could
get kind of too absorbed in it without being aware
then that is cyclic it influences the mind and heart and we feel worse and then we
become more aware of it we're still we have to step out of the loop of these
things affecting us negative negatively and one way to do that is have enough awareness
that we feel the goodness of being aware the goodness of being not lost in
something or or influenced or in the grip of something
and to and to feel to just subtle this kind of keep the bar very low the subtlest forms
of contentment happiness joy satisfaction that is comes along with
being aware if you're aware if you're aware of something difficult
if you're being mindful of something difficult and while you're you know the difficulty you also know the
satisfaction of being mindful then your practice is really getting
strong because then you're not somehow glued or being influenced by the difficulty
you're actually starting to become in it's actually the mindfulness is protecting you
from being influenced by the difficulty the difficult mind States you might have and um and uh and not only is it
protecting you from being influenced by difficult mind States it's also um feeding you in with this the goodness
of the practice itself the happiness the satisfaction of the practice itself of
being mindful and um and even if it's very very small
it's a fantastic food it's fantastic for a heart our mind our body to appreciate
and feel that so as you go about your day
you might experiment a bit or notice
there might be one or two times during the day would you get really absorbed in
something some irritation some anger some desire some fear about something
and um and maybe it's not imminence like not right in front of you the thing it's more like a the Mind projecting and
thinking about the future or something that's something or some person somewhere else and you find yourself you
know caught involved in that in a strong intense way turn your awareness to
the way that you're caught in something like this that's the kind of you know that you
could theoretically have very negative influence on you if you imagine you're being fed a diet of this
turn around and be mindful of it really know that's there and see if you how
clear the mindfulness has to be how much you have to step back or open up an awareness to really know this is what's
happening I'm really angry here I'm really afraid here and how until you
come to that place where there's a satisfaction maybe the satisfaction of not being
caught there's a joy the joy of having this wonderful practice to do that's an
alternative to being caught or the happiness that can come which is
a kind of you're so content wow this is so good that I'm being nourished now in my
mindfulness even though I'm present with a difficult state so it's a homework assignment and
noticing the difference between being immersed in something and lost in it and in almost like
influenced it or stepping back until you find the happiness of mindfulness
and some of you maybe uh won't know until after it's over that you were really caught up in something
and um and it might be interesting too even when you finally notice of reviewing the day
there might be a way that in the reviewing of the day that maybe you can do the exercise there
and I find where that happiness is so um
so thank you very much and I look forward to
the conclusion of this pentad tomorrow