burmese style and if i could make a suggestion from here
i would suggest maybe two things oh yeah go right ahead
one is you may end up needing that support cushion to support your right knee but actually the first thing i would suggest
you try is to bring your body forward on the cushion so that you're sitting on the front half
front third of the zafu if your right leg's falling asleep
it may mean that some circulation is getting cut off here yeah because if i lean back far enough i can feel the
blood just yeah then then i think what what you need to do is
experiment with a way to sit that's gonna that's gonna free that uh that uh vein that artery so it can
flow and it may like tiny adjustments will be will be enough
if you're if that didn't work or if your knee is floating which now
that you've moved forward it seems to be down the wedge would be to put underneath the knee
you don't need it though yeah it doesn't and then what i have noticed helps
and i know i know you mentioned this last week that it's probably not so good but if i just go like that sure what is
that what is that uh what effect does that have for you i know
oh yeah the um what you're sitting and now i know is quarter lotus and that's a great posture if it works
for you um it it's it can be a little hard for folks who are sitting sort of early in
their practice it's hard for me to do now um because it puts a little extra torque on
the knee and on the ankle or it can yeah one other thing i might suggest that not
a change that you have right here um do you alternate betw which leg is forward between sittings yeah
yeah that would be a that would be one thing yeah thank you so much you're welcome you're welcome
yeah so this is a time for questions and comments about uh the practice as as we were talking about
it last week maybe something you noticed in your meditation on the breathing maybe
something you noticed in the homework of your mindfulness during daily life or
your attention to posture throughout the day
um hello good evening koto and tanya i really liked uh what you said about
setting an intention first or sometimes like prior to the 20-minute sit
at least for me it was two 10-minute sessions from the calm app that i wanted
to that i kind of was following so i was just like okay
let me at least focus on the breath or or something focus on the breath and then after the session
i reflected on how i how it went and it was pretty good
i think doing the 20 minute meditations mostly guided has been very helpful for me i did try to do a 10 minute
meditation without anything and it was it was kind of difficult
just for focus and stuff thank you that's great i i usually tell people
you know 20 minutes is the goal if you can't do 20 do 15 if you can't do
15 do 10 you can't do 10 do 5. if you can't do ten
do two so and breaking it up if you need to break it up works
so good for you and maybe if 10 minutes was too long to do without guided try five unguided
and if that's too long you know back it up but find how long you can do an
unguided for and practice every time maybe either before maybe
experimenting before you do your guided sits or after
try practicing with whatever where wherever you're at whatever makes sense to work on the breath or the body is
this week to build up your capacity bit by bit
yeah great
great so when we're talking into the microphone we want everyone in youtube to hear ya
and everybody on the recordings who listen for posterity stake and so speaking into the mic is great
thank you anyone else have any reflections from
their practice or questions or if someone from youtube has
any comment or question we can address that too
hi um i wanted to talk about laying down like i know you mentioned last week that
there was a little bit of time where you practiced laying down and sometimes i feel like my body just
really really wants to so what are the pros and cons and
benefits yeah sure have you had a chance to try it out yet
what laying down no but last week during class i like
i was really uncomfortable but didn't want to lay down you know so i
yeah yeah yeah the um maybe talk about the pros and cons
and then we can move in a little bit the
practice of mindfulness uh as tanya was just pointing to
meets us where we are and that includes all bodies
and sometimes say an injured body for example is uh better served lying down than it
is sitting up the downside to lying down meditation is
probably exactly what you would imagine it's easy to fall asleep very easy to fall asleep so
a trick or a tool that i i learned from andrea fayla one of the teachers here
when she does lying down meditation she does it so you imagine me flat on the back she was with a an arm straight up like
this that way when she falls asleep she knows it
and it wakes her up  and holding the holding the hand up
are two hands two hands straight up like this elbows elbows
it takes just enough energy to keep you up until it doesn't and then
you wake up so um there's always a there's always a
measure of discernment uh if it's if it's sort of everyday variety discomfort
that's motivating me to lie down then i you know i i try for a little bit longer to stay
stay up if um if it's actually an injury that i'm trying to trying to meet and serve
then i'm i'm more motivated to lie down more quickly
maybe time for one more and then we'll go to uh next thing
i'm just curious if you could just raise your hand if you practice this week
fantastic fantastic thank
you nice work nice work
yeah wonderful to be on the path together i think uh that was probably a good time
moving to a little bit of a little more formally at the beginning of our session here tonight
so there's a teaching by uh pikuboti who's a translator scholar
practitioner really good news for all of us
for this path just two things you need
you need to start and you need to continue
last week we started and today we have continued so we have everything we need
everything we need we started um we started this
sequential unfolding of the practices of mindfulness meditation
presenting them in a sequence as we do here beginning first with the breath
mindfulness of the breathing centering ourselves and mindfulness of the breathing
and then we'll continue today we'll talk about the body mindfulness of the body expanding our
awareness to include the body more deliberately in our experience and our attention
next week we will continue further mindfulness with emotions really important part of human life
um often a sort of challenging or vexing
curious making part of the practice how do i how do i practice with emotions
and we'll get into that next week after mindfulness of emotions we'll continue into thinking and then in the
fifth week we will tie it all together starting
continuing just to review a couple of the key points from last week
this practice of mindfulness has everything to do with the skillful use of it of
skillful use of attention nothing more mysterious than developing
our capacity to pay attention in the present moment
there's a way that what we're doing here unifies the mind and the body
in the here and now this present moment experience
if we are daydreaming about
uh say dinner tonight or something in our work tomorrow
our body is here our body hasn't gone anywhere it's right here in the present but our mind has
left the premises our attention has left the premises for now so in the practice we're just practicing
again and again bringing attention back so that the mind and the body can both be here
together last time in addition to talking
something some about attention we covered some of the key points of posture
of course one of the most important points is the alert upright spine that's well supported
if you're if you're seated either in a chair or on the ground well supported either by
the balance from your seat to your knees or your seat and if you're in a chair down the legs
into your flat feet if it's okay for your body sitting sitting with uh the back free and
independent long balanced spine so that the body can
relax relax and loosen around the spine
so along with attention and along with posture it was mindfulness of breathing
mindfulness of breathing so important uh i love this metaphor of
the human being as concentric circles and the center of the circle
we can think of as the breathing center ourselves on the breathing
and the other aspects of our life they're included in the in the circles
but they're all connected here in the center grounded here in the center of the breathing
so we think of course we think but have the thinking connected to the breathing
important distinction we brought up last week was direct experience this here and now the
felt sense of breathing for example as compared to our concept of the
breathing our idea about the breathing or idea of the breath another way
direct experience compared to our interpretations of what's happening
the comments or the layers we add on to the direct experience
and we introduced this this traditional tool this traditional helper
very soft note very soft label
if that's helpful for you maybe the in on the in breath out on the out breath
very soft just to help keep you here with the body
now
i think maybe just to highlight one more of the important principles we covered
the experience may be pleasant it may be unpleasant while our attention is directed to the
breathing may experience this as pleasant or unpleasant
that is not the indication that it's going well or it's not going well
if there's if there's attention enough if we're attentive enough to notice just what's going on as it's
going on we're doing the practice we're doing the practice
so for example if if we're breathing and some say uh say a sensation in our
body becomes predominant it's okay to let go of the breathing and be with that
if we're attentive we're doing the practice
maybe the last thing i'll say in this uh in this journey we started last week
and that we're continuing over these these next several weeks the trajectory or the arc of this whole
thing is that we include more and more of our experience
such that we are learning to be more and more skillful including everything
every bit of us gets to show up for mindfulness practice
so i think with that i'll i'll hand it over to you
does anybody have any concerns about my taking my mask off no
okay
i am i think it's worth just taking um i'm kind of going to repeat some of the things koto said maybe um
and some new things but one of them is i just want to kind of build back on this idea of
last week we started with attending to the breath and we talked about we used the word anchor
right so this idea of a reference point or
something that kind of holds us close to the moment right like an anchor would a boat
in the water right to keep it from drifting too far away
and i last week i mentioned something about how the mind sort of it's a weaver
and it weaves all of our experience all the data that's coming in together
and incorporates past information
probably even anticipatory information so this weaving brings all of these
parts of our experience and creates sort of a more what feels like a solidified
whole or how we are seeing things
and so what we're what we're helping ourselves do with this practice is to sort of try and pull this apart a little
bit to make ourselves a little bit more connected with the different
threads of our experience does that make sense so tonight
we're adding body we don't need to stop being aware of breath
right and the invitation is use your anchor if breath is your anchor
now if your breath is not your anchor right because it doesn't work for you
because it's triggering or just there's something else like sound or the body
can be an anchor good anchors so start with your anchor right when you
come into meditation use that anchor put it down drop it in get it hooked in
there and then the invitation is to open up to
noticing the body now guess what
do you think that that means that the mind is not going to offer thoughts
no and that it's emotions aren't going to come up
no so there's no expectation that your mind has to stop thinking or your heart has
to stop feeling so i just want to give you permission to
have your experience but to highlight
maybe use that noting practice that we talked about within out like
oh feeling emotion or thought just real simple
not we're gonna we're doing this sort of trying to loosening the pieces right
so we don't need to get in there and get tangled up in the thinking or the emotions trying to think about that
when you're working with strands of a yarn right like sort of how do you let
the pieces relax they can all be there and they don't have to kind of get caught up together and if they do
just sort of gently try and give them their own room
so we'll start with the breath with our anchor if it's not the breath
and then the invitation is to invite the mind to be interested in what's happening in this body
and one simple way is the whole body's breathing really
we can just start to kind of expand the awareness of the breath
start to notice it in many ways that maybe we don't usually notice it usually notice it more in this
the center area so just sort of
trying to create a sense of non-conflict for yourselves right
with what comes up and just kind of like okay and we're gonna try and be a little bit more
curious tonight about the body and what's happening in the body
so as kodo said the body is not thinking and ruminating he didn't use those words
but essentially the body's in the present moment right it's here
it's always here it's always in the present moment
it's our thoughts about the body that aren't right
it's our memories or our wishes or our fears
but the body ex itself is such a present moment anchor
such a present moment gift
so it's a very supportive very foundational part of our practice
it's mindfulness of the body it's it's uh
can be quite delightful to get really centered and connected
with our experiences in the body it can also be difficult if we have pain
or other things come up so i don't mean to say it's going to be all rosy
but even connecting with what's difficult there can be a beautiful connection to
the present moment right if we have pain sometimes it still can help us
stay here in a way that feels very wholesome nourishing even
even like a break from the mental activity
if you think about what we're doing maybe one metaphor would be that by tuning in and feeling the
sensations in the body the body has a language
and the language is sensations and by tuning in and feeling we're
listening the way of listening to the body is to feel the sensations
so the body doesn't have a narrative it doesn't ruminate and think
and so maybe a simile or a way to think about this we're trying to bring a mind that's more
simple to the experience of these sensations that are happening in the body
and um a simile might be
going to a sports bar people are
watching huge monitors with narrators not narrators what are they
called the the announcers right who are play-by-play talking about what's
happening on the screen people are chatting and commenting and
there's a lot of activity around this tv screen
right or the sports that we're watching
and imagine no sound in that environment
no more commentators room gets quiet
and just watching the game unfold without all the commentaries
without the stories about the players or comments about how great this was
or how unfortunate that was
just seeing the motion in a way this is what we're working to
try and experience is to be with our body and what's happening in our body
without all the mental comments all the interpretations all the judgments all the liking all the
not liking
is that a picture you can imagine yeah
voice is a little soft i think i start to put people in a little bit of a meditative space when i'm just talking
yeah so it's great i'll try and just keep
going with it we'll move into the guided meditation shortly
so maybe back to this scene of or the simile
of the quietness
and just sensing into maybe seeing yourself in nature
in the sense of intimacy that one can have with your own experience when we're in a a quieter
simpler space
kind of connecting in this deep listening which is
the receptivity to the feelings and the sensations the life
really it's our life energy
our life being expressed through movement through breath
so we're growing our capacity to be intimate and
connected with our with our present moment experience
it it has certainly felt to me
like a coming home it can feel like a coming home
finding sort of just this this familiar comfortable
centered space
and sometimes it's a coming home to a raucous place too
like going home to a lot of things happening but it still has that quality of coming
home that sense of really feeling like
embodied yeah
so now another simile is thinking about the body as a gateway
a gateway to the present moment to connecting with the present moment
sometimes it's hard when we're busy in life and our minds are racing
it's hard to find the present moment hard to feel connected to it and so the body is a way a gateway to
help us find it it might be as simple as noticing my heart is pounding
yeah and that starts to help us connect more fully more richly
so in the practice we want to invite ourselves to
be at ease as much as we can right
and to be curious curious about what arises
paying particular interest to the breath and the body sensations and maybe
curious but in a hey i see you sweet little thought
is it right here kind of way so it's not pushing it away
you know it's not arguing with it not saying you can't be here but just like okay yeah
there's room here to come over here and play
and it you know we're we're applying a gentle but persistent
energy to stay present it's so easy to get carried out to see by our thinking
so easy and you will and that's gonna happen it's not a problem the moment you
recognize it you're already back so there's nothing to do but notice that
you're back that's it oh i'm right here again
i'm right here right here there's nowhere like sometimes in instructions you'll hear somebody say
and bring your awareness back to your breathing i don't think it's necessary to kind of
quite go that way because what we're doing is cultivating knowing awareness aware you're aware
right as soon as you recognize you were thinking you're aware and the awareness is what we want
that's what we're building that's what we're growing so we can just okay
like just hold and sit with the awareness and then the breath might start to come back into
a present awareness or sensation right just sort of allowing the awareness to
start to connect in that way
and just a reminder gentle reminder to respect your body respect your edges
right so not push too hard if you're
ending up in pain or you think you might be hurting yourself or
you know you're trying too hard try and soften up or change your posture so
respect your edges all right so let's go ahead and
slide more fully into a practice
taking a moment to find a good posture
supports the spine its natural lift
maybe moving forward on the chair trying that out instead of leaning back
experimenting you can always move it's okay to get up and get cushions or things to put
you know i find it very helpful as well to have something right down near my lower back
just a little bit of support helps me
and so then just sort of see actually i have a preference my personal preference is to
lift my shoulders up toward the ears kind of squeezing the ears
and then rolling the shoulder blades back toward each other and really the elbows squeezing open
squeezing together the elbows right and it opens the front chest and then driving the shoulders and
elbows down the side so we've kind of really stretched and opened the front body and then you can
just sort of rest your hands on your legs
one hand on top of the other thumbs touching
or just palms down on your thighs or palms up it's all good
and for me once i do this i notice the body wants to take a natural big breath
all of a sudden i've created a little more room in this chest for breath
so just inviting the body to take a few longer slower deeper breaths
and another image for me is you know as i'm doing this as i'm taking these deeper breaths
my eyes tend to naturally want to close and they don't have to be closed we can
gently gaze a few feet in front of ourselves
but as we as we settle it's almost like putting a snow globe down
and all the glitter comes to the floor of the snow globe and the energy
in the body can feel the same way as things come in come down come settle
come home
and then there can be more room for the breath this anchor or whatever your anchor is
i'm going to just say one thing here which is everything i'm offering is an invitation
you are welcome to change the language i offer so that it feels more comfortable
for you in any way
you are welcome to disregard something i say
this is part of also respecting your edges and knowing
and tuning in to what's happening inside of yourself
there is no reason to deny your own truth
deny your needs i offer
guidance and you follow in a way that works for you
so feeling into this experience here
breathing here
and for purposes of kind of orienting toward the body and paying attention to the
language of the body i'll invite you to pay particular
attention to your feet
maybe getting a sense of the whole foot
not creating a picture of the foot in your mind or looking down or touching your foot but
but feeling and sensing the feet from inside the body
so we're not the commentators in the sports game evaluating the feet
but just in that simple way feeling feet
these feet and this moment
and so what is the language of these feet
sensations that might be like tingling or vibrating
buzzing pressure
temperature
you may notice that there's parts of your feet that are cool and other parts that are warm
you may notice there's parts of your feet that feel hard and
others that feel soft
just holding awareness of the feet in a kind and gentle way
whatever you're feeling and sensing is okay even if it's uncomfortable
maybe just saying it's okay
just being present for whatever is being experienced
by being with our feet in this way we can see how it's possible
to explore other areas of our body
how we might be able to feel into the body with curiosity and sensitivity to whatever is present
so from here you can let go of attending to your feed
and just allow your awareness to go back to whatever is prominent for you the breath or the sensations
maybe noting thinking or emotion just
kind of getting clear
and seeing if you can't find your anchor feel into your anchor in the middle of it
bringing the same curiosity
to whatever you're sensing now
breathing in and breathing out
maybe noticing a cool breeze on the skin
or other sensation that calls your awareness to it
providing a sense of ease of intimacy and connection
just this just here
the body is a gateway to the present moment
feeling the sensations as a way of listening deeply
to our experience
and just for fun as we come to the end when i play the bell
see if you can feel the sound in your body
[Music]
so
just noticing what you're aware of now
staying close to your experience and we'll we'll open this up for some comments reflections and questions and
including from youtube if anyone has anything richard will check the chat in a minute
and a reminder to use the microphone
so is anyone willing to share anything about your experience
i was able to feel my feet being warm
and i'd never been able to actually get in touch with a particular body part
but somehow the way you explained it i was able to feel it from the inside
and i always have cold feet so it was very interesting to have
warm feet maybe your feet liked being felt
um so i felt well my mind was wandering quite a bit and i
had to call it back a few times so
there's that thank you
how was that for you if i may ask
yeah and the the process you described right um i try to just use one word like
wandering or daydreaming and then bring focus back to
my breath or to feel different parts of my body just kind of going through the whole system
so a little distracting but overall good we're doing the practice
trying yes um now that you mention
the thought process that you noticed i also remember how i always have a
running narrative of what i'm thinking about it's like right now i'm thinking about
my feet now i'm thinking about something on my hand so
would you like to make a comment or should i go ahead sure um
now i'm thinking about my feet now i'm thinking about my hands it it sounds like the thinking was helping you to
stay present that's one of the um
one of the the bits of logic behind using a note
is that we're noting what the attention comes into contact with it's using a thought to keep us here
skillful use of the uh the mind that can stay active
and then uh it it is possible over time the body will settle down breathing will
settle down and the thinking will for a time maybe slow its tempo
but we'll see thanks
um i had what i thought was a very cool experience and that you had mentioned uh trying to move away from your mind's map
of what you think your body looks like and i sort of like felt into like some
like neck and shoulder pain that i have and i was just like i wonder like what this feels like from the inside and like
was so different than the like shape of like anything it was like sort of weird and
like felt like almost like symbolic like uh if that makes sense yeah yeah
but i just thought that was cool thank you uh that's going to be
um we're going to touch more on that shortly when we talk about talk about pain but isn't it fascinating how the
the sensations we're presenting maybe in a shape or a form or a texture or something it was
different than your idea of the neck and shoulders yeah thank you for that observation
okay so i have um a question that's kind of difficult and i hesitate to ask it
but um so i have a rare pain and maybe we'll talk about it when we
talk about pain but i have a rare pain disorder where if i focus on it it becomes a feedback loop and gets magnified
so if maybe in our pain discussion if you have any ideas about how to break
a feedback loop of pain perception i don't know it's a difficult one so that's a big question so
it is it is um i think we would be really well served why don't we spend a few minutes
together at the end of the session that's something i can say now is um
and and i'll talk i'll i'm actually going to say exactly this the experience of pain as you all know
is like it's composed both of both of nerve
information and the recognition up here or recognition where the recognition
happens yes oh this is this is danger yes and there's a way it sort of gets
stuck it can get stuck in itself when i was working with this injury
there came a time where i ended up actually talking with my pain and saying something like oh thank you
for the information i'm safe i the you've done your work
and um um we're safe here now and actually having that conversation
sort of let the metaphorically let the pain know it had done its job
and somehow for me helped undermine the loop but we can we can connect more no yeah
thank you for reminding me that because that's exactly what my pain psychologist says for two
different points so i don't know why it didn't occur so yeah
maybe one last thing about that i realized i went straight to process and the first thing is like that's
really difficult i'm recognizing it it's
it can be really challenging to work with consistent pain so thank you thank you for the practice you're doing
so i have a chronic illness and fatigue is a significant part of that
so i actually dozed off during that meditation and i noticed that i did that
earlier in the week as well when it was later in the day and so i'm not sure sort of how to
work with that knowing that that's probably going to be a challenge for me so any any just
comments or thoughts you have about that would be great maybe i'll just say something and then
you can pick up and take off on the next part um
maybe you're just learning the rhythms of your body right so um
something to learn to know about yourself and maybe it's perfect to fall asleep a little bit
in the evening because you're tired so just to to not make it a problem
to have it be information maybe have it help inform you about
when you practice and um
yeah and um it's great great you know you fell asleep and
hopefully you got a little rest [Music] i did
good yeah maybe i'll i'll add this briefly and then
segue into our our next section um
gil will often mention at the beginning of a meditation retreat how a great a great many of us are perhaps
sleep deprived and maybe could benefit from an early night's rest and a secret of the first
night of a meditation retreat is we always go to bed early and then the the other thing is that um
someone who's who's close to me has has made it a practice of
being like very uh acutely mindful of the state of sleepiness and has
discovered all sorts of interesting things like where it's living in the body uh and how it moves and functions
so just to just to say that that too can be part of it that too can be part of the practice
you know while we were doing the guided meditation i was really taken by this this uh image
of the anchor and because we uh we live so close to
the bay i was thinking i actually saw in my mind's eye i don't know how many of you had this happen an anchor in the
ocean and i was seeing the sort of sway of the seaweed and imagining the little
little sea life floating along the temperature of the currents the different aspects and i was thinking how
all of those all of those parts of the sea are right there with the anchor
they didn't disappear so our whole life in the same way
is right here with the anchor whatever it is the body is right here with the
breathing the emotions that are right here with the breathing our states our thoughts
and as we're as we're bit by bit
uh practicing with one aspect of our experience and then widening practicing with the breathing widening to the body
widening to emotions thinking learning to include more and more
so for now keep it simple our practice is with the breathing
our practices with the body sensations of the body i appreciated how
the the attention can be both directed as it was when we were feeling into our
feet we can direct the attention to the body to really feel into
sense into from the inside out what's going on in a part of the body
can also be a receptive attention that maybe takes in the whole body globally
can also be [Music] a mix of the body and the breath let's
say our our anchor is the breathing
say there's say there's a sensation that arises in the body that's calling awareness
it's more compelling it becomes predominant letting go of the breathing
attending to that sensation while it lasts while it's compelling
and then when that fades going back to the anchor
the movement from object object not a problem attend like going along with attending
in the sense of going along with the attention we're still doing the practice whatever the experience is
for many of us and especially especially i think in the beginning months and years of practice there can be a lot of
discomfort in the seated posture or in the whatever meditation posture
you use so you may be experiencing sensations that are predominant
those two get to be included and there's a way that there's a way that whatever needs to be
experienced will come up for you in the course of meditation uh i have a
i have a faith that we can trust that so the fact that a discomfort has come
up not a problem
not a problem how do how do how to engage with that in a way that's caring
and gentle and clear
so the discomfort can take uh take any number of forms and sort of be part of a spectrum
discomfort can be very mild it can be very intense it can come up in the form of agitation
it can come up in the form of pain this pain is a very
very interesting part of practice i think for all of us that comes up sooner or later
so i appreciate something tanya said earlier to respect your edges
we're going to talk about practicing with pain and very important to emphasize this for me
respect your edges stay in your choice choose how much you're going to practice
with pain for now there's a time and a place for sort of
strong determination with pain that can be a good teacher and there's a time and a place for being
very gentle so then you'll have to discern
to bring in another image i did something but right before the session i did
something i haven't done in a really long time i was sitting out here on the bench i was enjoying the trees the breeze in
the trees and i looked up at the sky and i watched a cloud just watched a cloud
who knew who would think and i was watching its shape
just really just slowly drifting slowly changing
some of it kind of fading away yeah it was so relaxing just to be there and watch the cloud
and it occurred to me this is perfect this is the perfect dharma for this is the perfect teaching for talking
about pain clouds just like pain
they're composites a pain is not one thing
the exp and experience of pain is not made up of one condition it's not just a lump
it's interesting though because our perception says if we hold pain at a distance it's like
oh that pain is solid it's one thing it's over there it's pain
but really interesting just like the cloud actually it's made up of a cloud is made up of
some sort of particle it's made up of uh a sort of mist in the sky that's
condensed around these things the right temperature things have to be just so and they're always changing
and the same with pain it's always changing and if we get close to in the same way
we're practicing with our feet earlier if we get close to if we get into we
feel pain intimately
maybe say at an appropriate distance if it's too much there's a way that it reveals itself
there's a way that it um it the threads that make up pain start to loosen tees apart
it might be that what we think of as pain what we think of as one pain if we get close to it it
might be that it's a combination of say pressure or
and heat and maybe a little bit of tingling or this particular pain might have a
feeling of twisting involved in it it could be any number of things
but the very same curiosity that we bring to sensation and bring to breathing
we bring to pain and it can reveal itself
what's very interesting about this is that as we tease it apart you might notice this any given any given
sensation pain included when we tease it apart it has a tendency to start breaking up
it might reassert itself very quickly but then it breaks up breaks up breaks up or changes
one of the things that keeps pain maybe seeming unitary
is the interpretations it's the uh it's the things that are that aren't actually physical sensation
but are other parts of our being kind of like the glue so say
i feel i feel a sensation that's unpleasant in my hip while i'm sitting
the thought oh that shouldn't be there um
i think this me this means that uh i'm i'm i'm not going to be able to walk
pretty soon i'm pretty soon i'm like three four steps down the line from the physical sensation in a in a narrative
so just the same way we were talking about the difference between the game and the commentary
there's a way of relating to pain that's similar where we can experience pain as the physical sensation
and notice also what's what's added what's it what's the commentary what's the interpretation
and that can support this teasing apart process
i can say it as the as that practice starts to develop
and pain starts to reveal itself there's a way that there's a way that actually you can be
there with pain totally with pain and be independent of it
and actually uh totally unexpected maybe even relaxed some of the time
the big qualifier with all this some sort of talking about pain
in a general way working with working with our our own pain
it's particular we can use some of these same strategies but they're you know we never want to we never want to like
exacerbate our injuries by with this good dharma mindfulness
advice please take very good care of yourselves and follow your wisdom
follow your wisdom the practice we introduced of
uh maybe offering a note can help us to tease apart what it is
that's making up an experience of pain can actually let the mind register and recognize oh this is a comment
pain pain heat vibration comment
oh fear there's emotion anyway that can help with this parsing
process
so in the practice that includes our whole life this um
this whole spectrum of discomfort will very likely begin to show itself
and can be a rich a rich field in which we discover more and more about
freedom of attention and awareness
it's not all pain of course we have great pleasures and meditation that can come forward an independence of
awareness and attention one
aspect of experience i want to note before we go into a guided meditation is
say the body is in some level of discomfort and you've discerned that oh this for
now for me for now this is too much this is too much
moving is an option a good one tuning into something neutral
is a good option i've also heard tuning into sounds
tuning into sounds if the body for now is too much opening up opening up to mindfulness of sounds
and we'll explore mindfulness of sounds a little bit in this guided meditation
so why don't we find our way back to our meditation posture
feeling the steadiness
the sensations of a upright balanced body
maybe even renewing the shoulder roll that we did earlier
the spine both alert and relaxed the chest open
belly relaxed
can lengthen give invite a little space in the top
vertebrae with the top of the spine and the neck she may find that tucks your ten your
chin just gently
greeting the body your companion for life
and connecting again with your anchor
be that sounds or awareness of the whole body
or the breathing
allowing a soft breath to be a soft breath and a full breath to be a full breath
just enough energy
to sustain contact and curiosity
and for the sake of an exercise
letting go for now of effort to stay with the anchor
opening up to the sphere of sounds
in a wide receptive way
receiving the sounds as they come in
and letting them pass right through
if the sound sparks a thought sparks a comment
to parse to discern to tease apart the sound
just the sound comment just the comment
relating to sound in this way
pleasant or unpleasant the sound does not
request a response
so
pleasant sound is just pleasant sound
passing right through
unpleasant sound is unpleasant sound
and again as i ring the bell
can you listen with the whole body
[Music]
and when you're ready you can open your eyes
as we transition
into a few last minutes of q a given our conversation of
sound and commentary and pleasant and unpleasant today i
found i came across the perfect quote
from the founder of zen center suzuki roshi
you may have heard this before it says teaching on sound versus noise
and i think he was a tassara he says when we hear the bird
actually i'm not listening to the bird and then very cute he goes peep peep
peep he says when you are reading something you may think
the blue jay is on my roof but their voice is not so good
when you think in that way that's noise and then he says the most important
thing when you're not disturbed by the blue jay the blue jay will come right into your
heart
when you're not disturbed blue jay will come right into your heart
so maybe you have some uh some something you'd like to share or some
question
i think for the second half of that meditation where i actually tried sitting on the floor for the first time
i tried not to be so disturbed by feeling uncomfortable and then i
felt comfortable it was really strange i was just like oh wow i'm not trying to move i was just
and i i wanted to hold on to that but i'm like wait if i hold on i'm gonna get attached to it so
i kind of just let it be and i'm like wow it was really cool so i think yeah it was nice thank you
wonderful thank you thank you for sharing i love that you you tried it out and
had that experience or had an experience
that's a great example of um losing the commentator
right like we add so much to our experience with our comments and
reactions so it's like turning that tv volume off you know nice work
i um paused to give people time to ask questions and now i'll go ahead but um
okay so that really helped the um the visualization with the pain this is
holly again um the visualization that you mentioned
code of the of letting the sound pass through you and being expansive like having an
expansive perception so it was like i gave space to my body and became like the size of the entire soundscape
and i think gill has talked about um imagining yourself as
more space if you have a lot of thoughts bouncing around like ping pong balls nice and it did the same i think it did
the same thing as with the pain signals or the pain whatever pain ruminations
it gave them space and also provided a little distraction
um while still maintaining that anchor of mindfulness in the breath or the body
so yeah that seems like a pretty good antidote i'm happy to hear it so it sounds like
during the meditation on sounds it opened up your perception of space to be broader
and that gave more room for the the pain signals to have have some have some space around them or
inside them or yes yeah instead of being focused in one area kind of like you mentioned
earlier it wasn't so much pulling them apart it was just giving a ton of space to
a concentrated location wonderful wonderful thank you
anyone okay great
um i was just wondering if there's a way to be like entirely like with sound uh
in the absence of kind of like associations and emotional charge that comes with it because uh
unfortunately i got a lot of emotional charge so um yeah i find that i can
fall into a place where i'm thinking about the feelings that come with specific sounds and oops
feels counterproductive sure i like actually sound meditation great i
like it a lot and one of the key things that helps me
is not to be imagining what's making the sound
because then i start to create a lot of mental fabrications and stories
and i like to um see if i can feel because i i really sense the vibrations
of sound you know like there's a car moving and you can feel oh it's shifting where
you feel it in your body so receiving that's another word i like is
receive the sound we don't need to go out and find the sound it comes to us
so more of a receptivity and
you know if you have particular associations with particular sounds that are very strong it's
it takes a long time right so maybe that there are certain kinds of sounds or things that are triggering
that have a lot of impact for you and so knowing that and then bringing compassion maybe to that
um is that helpful yeah you want to add anything
i was thinking i was thinking if um say the breathing is generally a more
useful anchor for example if that is true for you and you're exploring the world of sounds
one way to do it would be to ground ground yourself in your anchor and then decide okay now i'm going to open up to
this thing that i know is a little more stimulating for me and let's just see what happens let's see what happens and let's do that
for however long a few minutes if you want and then come back and settle and that
sort of back and forth so you can you can have your meditative resources about you
and then again if it if uh say meditation on sounds encourages a
response to note that response to be attentive to it you're doing the practice
thank you okay so we're about ending so i'm just
gonna um if you didn't pick up a handout there on the stage as you come in over
by nancy thank you nancy and so
the homework for this week is to continue to practice 20 minutes a day
you can't do 50 20 through 15 can't do 15 to 10 can't do 10 to 5 right and
break it up maybe so you get your full 20 if it's possible
and there's an invitation to take two hours during the week
to do a devoted mindfulness of your body practice in daily life
so you know yoga swimming going for a walk those are all easy
places to kind of practice for a sustained period for more broken up one of the nice
things one of the practices i grew for a while was
every time i got up to walk somewhere practicing mindfulness of the body
moving so that's a nice way to build in something into the daily life is every time you
get up and walk somewhere it's practice [Music]
you know we're talking about the body so we've talked about sensations and then we just added sounds because the body
does hear the body also tastes and smells
so this week you're invited to have a mindful meal to spend a whole meal or
start a whole meal as mindfully as you can it can be very
[Music] fun to do eating meditation like sometimes
a raisin or an orange you know so smaller bits
like that but really taking time smell it before you taste it listen to
it you know notice that you start to salivate there's so many things you can feel your body wanting to swallow you
know there's just so much to notice so you might do a smaller eating experiment with a little piece of fruit or
something like that and then see if you can how much of a meal you can pay attention to
you can try putting your fork or spoon down between bites that can help
then you're really aware before you pick it up again wait till you're swallowed you know
so but one meal have fun with it see what you can notice and the fourth invitation for this week
is to be curious about the things that take you away that distract you
there's a lot of information there particular thoughts or
reactions or fantasies or you know just be curious what what is it
that that kidnaps my awareness what kidnaps me
what happens you know just just noting it and paying particular attention being curious about
it so thank you so much for being here and your practice and
if you have questions afterwards we'll be here and hopefully we'll see you next week
thank you thanks so much
you