so warm greetings for this tuesday
morning and for our second talk on the third
foundation for awareness and we are trying to steadily
through this sativatana to cultivate a heightened awareness a heightened sense of
knowing attentiveness presence
and and
in a sense there's a path through these different foundations beginning with breathing and then
mindfulness of the body mindfulness of feeling tones and then now mindfulness
of the mind it's uh sometimes considered to be more refined or more subtle or more
um more accessible through a
settled mind and so the beginning of this process begins with mindfulness of
breathing so in this meditation i'll lead you through
kind of a quick trip through this first two foundations a bit with the button breath the body
feeling tones and then we'll open up to the cheetah the mind the mind state
so assuming a meditative posture
one that allows you to have a combination of being alert
and relaxed at ease
and you might lower your gaze to about 45 degrees angle looking down at the floor
and kind of loosening the focus not looking at anything in particular and
letting the eyes become kind of soft and relaxed
and very gently slowly closing the eyelids
and then perhaps letting the mouth drop drop open a little bit
the teeth apart so the mouth is a little bit more relaxed
and then gently float the teeth together so they're almost touching or touching
so the jaws are a little bit more relaxed
softening the belly letting the belly hang forward and down
maybe in softening the belly feeling the weight of the belly and
so the belly almost kind of settles into the down towards the pelvic cavity
maybe beginning with a soft belly as you inhale
letting the in the belly expand the chest expand
maybe taking a long slow deep breath
and a leisurely a little bit longer exhale
on the exhale relaxing the face
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders softening in the shoulders
adjusting your hands and arms a little bit if that helps the shoulders
and again softening the belly
breathing normally letting your breath just be let the breath breathe itself
and become aware of the thinking mind
is a lot of energy or pressure contraction tension in the
thinking mind
restlessness
maybe on the exhale a little longer exhale again
settle the mind quiet the mind
almost as if as the on the exhale the mind spreads wide
spreads horizontally wide and peaceful
and then settling the awareness into the body
breathing
and it might help you not to struggle
with anything if you think of the breathing not something to be
exclusively focused on but something to
allow to be at the center of all things as if the experience of breathing
is the center of your world
and your job is to sit at the centers be with the breathing
and allow everything else to be in the periphery
as if for a few minutes at least breathing is the only thing you need to do focus on
just breathing
and then knowing how the body moves as you breathe
the movements of the chest the belly
maybe the shoulders
even the back rib cage
maybe as if you're flowed and peacefully floating on waves gently coming and going across
the ocean gently resting
floating on the movements of the torso as you breathe
maybe being being aware of breathing in the middle of your body
the peripheral attention as a global awareness of your body
that receives the experience of breathing receives the inhale
settles on the exhale
and as you're aware of breathing is any of the breathing
is there anything connected to breathing pleasant or unpleasant
maybe there's both going on at different parts of the cycle some are pleasant some are more
unpleasant
see if you can be equanimous but pleasant or unpleasant and breathing
just know it that's how it is as if you're breathing through the
pleasant through the unpleasant
breathing with it
and in particular [Music] feel the pleasant part of breathing
and let yourself feel it more fully like taking in
drinking or receiving the pleasure of breathing
even if it's just a small part of the breath
and more broadly in your body beyond the
experience of breathing are there any pleasant feelings of your
body that you can breathe with
or that you can allow to accompany the experience of breathing
so your attention to the breathing is supported
by the pleasant sensations of your body
and notice if there's any pleasant or unpleasant sensations of the mind
breathe with them so your attention is more with the
breathing than reactive to the mind just breathe with how the mind is
whether it's pleasant or unpleasant
perhaps relaxing any agitation or tension in the mind
as you breathe
um
breathing in and breathing out centering yourself on breathing
and with the peripheral attention gently without
too much effort or focus see if you can know something about the
quality of your mind your mind state
maybe as if you're breathing with or through your mind your mind state
knowing it for what it is equanimously
whether it's pleasant or unpleasant whether it's agitated or peaceful
aversive or kind
strongly wanting something or being content
whatever way it is breathe with it
breathe through it know it
kind of as a peripheral phenomenon as you center yourself on your breathing
and then letting go of your breathing
and see if you can directly know your mind your mind state
and now let that be the center of attention
see if you can simply be aware no be present
for how your mind is the attitude the state the mood
the energy and see if you can know it
with a knowing that's peaceful equanimous
not troubled by how the mind is not desirous for anything being
different just knowing
and as you know it almost as if you're roaming around in the mind
to feel it know it in different ways different directions
and then coming to the end of this sitting
whatever the way that your mind is calm or equanimous
or even if it just wishes it was or assumes you have some
considering the suffering of this world
equanimously gazing upon it kindly
gently as you would gently touch
or clean a wound on the knee of a child
to cause the least amount of pain for the child caring loving the kid
so look out upon the world of that kind of soft kind gaze caring gays
as if having compassion for the world
should be done with respect and gentleness and
tenderness
and for all the people who are suffering in wars and poverty and oppression
all the people struggling can we from our
quiet whatever quiet and peace of the mind we have
wish well on this world may all
beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so continuing on these talks of the third foundation for awareness
which is mindfulness of the mind and so it's
building our capacity to be aware by knowing what's happening in the mind recognizing the mind
and the mind is important because whatever the mind is this inner mental state heart state
whatever the heart is the the there's the intellectual emotional
center for ourselves that's the location
for our primary experiences of suffering and for
happiness we can have physical pain and physical pleasure
but the places where the mind is the location for that which is existentially much deeper
and impactful and important for us it's a location for where
suffering occurs and whether you call that place the mind or the heart or some other name
the mind is that inner mental emotional landscape
that we have and you can define it for yourself it's more important how what you're experiencing than that you
experience some buddhist idea what the mind is
and um it's also where we can feel happy deep abiding happiness
deep peace and even the experience of freedom is something that belongs to the mind
this cheetah so the task
that as is described in the text is simply to know
the state of the mind in the way that it is there's nothing in it about
judging it making commentary about it wishing it would be otherwise being
aversive to it trying to fix it trying to make it into something else it's simply to recognize it as it is and
as i've said that simple recognition does change begin to change it
tends to change it in a wholesome direction because the clear mindfulness of it
is now is not feeding anymore the unhealthy and the unwholesome mind
states if we're not really mindful the mental energy can go into the
stories and the ideas and the resentments and all kinds of things that support this on wholesome mindset of
mind but as the energy of the mind goes into being to being a mindful
into a kind of clear knowing oh this is what's happening now i see i see
the mind is desirous the mind is full of wanting something strong
and that's what's going on in the mind it's almost like you can have that conversation with yourself oh that's
what it's like or it's full of aversion or resentment
or hostility or irritation that's what the mind is like
right now the mind is like this if it's confused agitated
full of doubt full of delusion to know this is what it's like
this is a delusion delusive mind mind that's spinning stories and fantasies
and so the um to know to simply to know it and this is kind of the the center of
this exercise of the third foundation is that how simple can you simply know
the mind mind state makes a huge difference to do that
because chances are if we're not just simply knowing it if the mind is caught up in desires or
aversions or confusion delusion those come along as baggage carry on luggage
for how we do the mindfulness practice and the mindfulness itself will have
awareness itself would be somehow colored by that desire leaning forward grasping wanting
uh or by the aversion of pushing away or being hostile or looking you know meanly at it
or it's just confused the awareness itself is not very centered or
clear and calm because it's agitated confused not going with knowing which way to go
so the more we can just let the knowing be very very simple the less carry-on baggage it comes it
comes along with and then it just see lighter and easier and easier
so the way the buddha words these instructions he says when a mind when the mind state or the mind when the
cheetah is with desire it knows the mind is with desire
when the mind is without desire one knows the mind is without desire
sometimes translators have translated this as if one knows that the state of
mind is desirous a desiring state of mind
or an aversive state of mind but literally the the pali it says uh
mind with desire with the virgin and this is a very significant uh
distinction because as mindfulness is a clear awareness it recognizes something
clearly for itself as that becomes stronger
the desire and the aversion is not part of the whole mind it doesn't color or
shape or define the whole mind awareness the clear awareness begins to
expand the domain of the mind so it's no longer wrapped into
desire or aversion and so with clear mindfulness
desire is not the whole mind it's just a part of it the mind is coming along with the mind but it doesn't define the whole
mind and so um part of the this is why it's this practice of the
mind is so powerful when the mindfulness can see oh this is in the mind
and one place the buddha talks about the mind having
visitors the visitors that confuse it the visitors that defile it
the visited visitors that obstruct the mind and decide well lovely idea that greed
hatred delusion the hindrances are visitors to the mind not
inherent to the mind and we start when mindfulness becomes strong enough
then we start kind of prying ourselves apart from these difficult mind states
and we start seeing oh there's more going on but the buddha also talks about not just
seeing a desirous mind with desire but also seeing a mind
that's without desire this means positive states of mind
generosity is a state without desire without greed
for example and and so it's also positive states of mind but here we're asked to notice when
there's desirous in the mind and when there's not when the mind is colored and shaped by desire and when it's not
and it's of course part of the mind that sees it and um and so the three kind of three
root fundamental kind of forces of the mind that underlie all unhealthy states of mind according to
the buddha greed hatred and desire one knows a mind with greed with greedy desire
as such when knows a mind without greed as such when knows a mind with
aversion or hatred or stillie as such one knows a mind without it as
such and one knows a deluded mind or a confused mind
as such someone knows a mind without that as such and
and so becoming more and more familiar with this and then becoming familiar what's that like
so it's not just knowing it but knowing the felt sense the experience of it
uh recognizing um there's a clear recognition oh when the mind is full of desire it's leaning
forward it's searching when the mind has aversive it's
stabbing or you know attacking or blaming or or pulling away or it's getting the mind
gets narrower contracted it gets restless it gets a kind of maybe a phonetic
energy if that goes on the mind maybe the the mind is more up in the
head rather than in the heart and the body the location of the mind shifts and
changes depending on what the mind is caught up in at the moment
and when it's caught with great hate and delusion chances are it's there's some kind of locus
center of the mind where it's coming feel it's located that might be different
than if the mind is filled with compassion and love and peace and wisdom
and so to look around and explore what does it feel like in the body what does it feel
like in the mind itself what's it what impact does the these different states of mind have in our
clarity of mind and our ability to stay focused and balanced
so we begin kind of um familiarizing ourselves with all this but this is a third foundation of
mindfulness so to do this right away from the beginning
maybe it means that um we get rap we get just more confused by it or wrapped up in it or reactive to it
or it lends itself to a lot more thinking about it all but to think of this third foundation of
mindfulness as as having the first two foundations
as a support for it the mind is already able to get somewhat calm present stable
in the present moment the mind is starting to come strong in its mindfulness
so with that calm ability to be calm and centered and not being distracted easily
without and knowing something about this non-reactive awareness and just knows
very simply when that is all in place that's a good time to start becoming
aware of the mind state if that's not in place then it's good to go back to the beginning just go back to
just breathing and beginning of the whole satyapathanam until it all settles in again
and then we can kind of begin opening to the mind state and the mind state can color mindfulness
as i've said and color how we're mindful it's like carry-on luggage we bring with us so has become clear and clear about the
mind state that we have that um we have less and less of this luggage
and the mind becomes clearer brighter more free in a certain kind of way
in a couple of days we're going to look at the second half of this third foundation where that is looking
at the the what it grow how the mind can grow and develop when it's no longer in the grip of greed
hate and delusion or fear or agitation or contraction and
and what we'll see then is that the discussion goes from talking what the mind is with to talking about the state
of the mind itself and when these beautiful states arise they can coexist with mindfulness with
awareness it's almost like they are awareness but that's for in a couple of days
so um thank you and um in the next 24 hours or so when you have
a chance going about your daily life you might uh in daily life start doing a little bit in inventory
of the state of your mind is it a mind that with desire is it a mind with
hostility or hatred or ill will aversion is it a mind that's confused or delusive
and just notice these will probably float through and arise and pass in different circumstances when you're hungry for dinner
you might feel that desire mind is predominant when you've eaten too much a verse of
mind is predominant when you wonder how to do the dishes
uh when the dishwashing machine is completely packed and you might notice this confused confused mind or
you know just notice it comes and goes it's like kaleidoscope in small subtle and big ways
start tracking all this and when when there's no desire notice what that's like no ill will notice what
that's like and just kind of explore and and get to know and become familiar with it texture
the smell the feel for these mind states and see what happens when you recognize them
more and more i look forward to
i'm introducing the next talk thank you