so really warm welcome really warm welcome again to everybody
what a pleasure it is to be here practicing with you all
i'm with our friends on online
so tonight i wanted to say a few words about
i think all of us probably many of us have this experience that the more we practice mindfulness the
more we practice meditation and
maybe there's something that we learned the hard way that maybe i learned the hard way
is that an orientation an attitude a stance
of kindness is so helpful
i might even say mandatory because right as our meditation practice
we start to see all the little movements of the mind
which we're not so kind to ourselves in which we might not be kind in our
minds to others and then we can just kind of get snagged and
stuck and especially with the unkindnesses towards ourself we can
i can really you know grow and end up really being
so that meditation practice is so uncomfortable and
maybe even unhelpful
so mindfulness i know like uh jack cornfield now he talks about mindfulness he talks about
his loving awareness as this way to emphasize kind of this
the warm-hearted quality that's associated with mindfulness practice
and maybe we hear this in drama talks that we should have this
maybe non-judgmental we use this kind of language or uh available allowing accepting or
something like this to help uh point to this attitude that's so helpful with the
mindfulness practice so today i'd like to talk a little bit
about another doorway in another doorway that can really support our meditation
practice support our mindfulness practice and that is loving kindness practice
meta practice some people
have a lot of resistance have a lot of reluctance pushback
i do not like this practice loving kindness practice it's not uncommon
i certainly did i thought like okay i don't know what that living kindness practice is but it
sounds sappy sentimental
ooey gooey sticky i don't know i just didn't even before i
even really had done the practice just the whole idea of it for me felt like okay not not so
interesting
so maybe i'll just say a few words about loving kindness practice here is this
it's the uh cultivation of the intention to have some warm-heartedness and i like
this language warm-heartedness because it's kind of vague
and i like it because it's the opposite of cold i mean kind of have an idea what it means to be cold you know to give
somebody the cold shoulder or to um be you know off putting that somehow to
be cold just to not be welcoming so i like this idea of warm-heartedness
warmth or warm-heartedness kind of bringing in the heart quality but maybe we could even just say warmth
so loving-kindness practice is not so much that we have to or it's insisted upon that we
generate manufacture engineer create some warm-heartedness
but it's more about intentionally creating the conditions in which that might arise
no guarantees that it's going to arise but we create the conditions
with the understanding that giving the heart and the mind i'm making
this distinction which might even be artificial but the
understanding that the being this psychophysical being
if we can allow it to rest
abide in dwell in experience some warm-heartedness
that it just becomes easier and easier to access that warm-heartedness when we
need it it becomes easier and easier for this warm-heartedness to
be a support in all areas of our life not just
loving-kindness in fact it's most common that the effects of metapractice
first really show up in one's daily life before they might even show up in your
meditation practice you might be doing some meta practice and it might
feel dry and stale and a little bit
forced maybe and feel like i don't i don't know why i'm doing this but then you just notice
that you start to be a little bit nicer to the other drivers on the road
you start to be a little bit nicer to the neighbor that doesn't put their garbage cans away and
time or you know whatever it might be
probably everybody knows this but i'll just mention that loving kindness practice is kind of done
systematically classically it's done there's lots of different ways you can do it but
one way is systematically starting where it's easy and then expanding out to where it's
more and more difficult and it's often not always done with
repeating phrases so don't worry this whole talk is not
going to be about living kindness practice i just wanted to introduce it and
and i wanted to talk a little bit about some of why we might have hesitation around it
and one particular place which i think it can be really a great support for us in our regular practice
i know that um there's some years ago there was this expression no pain no gain
and uh right we hear this for like uh physical activities
and i hadn't heard it for a while but then i just heard it today like no pain no gain
and there's so many ways i think that we often bring this idea to all areas of
our lives including our meditation practice
and so there's a way in which we might bring this to thinking that meta practice loving kindness maybe it's not
so useful because it doesn't seem like it's painful enough or
it doesn't seem like you know to have this warm-heartedness like what benefit can
that be when we when you hear me say this or it sounds a little bit ridiculous
but there might be a way in which in the back of our minds we have this little bit of a an idea about this
so that might be one reason why people have this hesitation or reluctance around loving-kindness
practice is it might feel too sappy or sentimental or it doesn't feel like it's
strenuous enough or difficult enough or something like this but there's another
reason too and that is because sometimes
loving-kindness practice when we start it it might bring up a lot of
difficulties from our hearts might bring up a lot of
pain in a way that mindfulness practice doesn't to be sure mindfulness practice
can also but loving-kindness practice might get at some of the
other aspects of our experience and bring up some of these difficulties
and to be sure that sometimes what it brings up is the exact opposite of loving kindness
whenever another dharma teacher tells the story of
that uh so now i can't remember if it was this dharma teacher or if they were talking about a practitioner
that shared with them but nevertheless the um the person was doing walking
meditation and doing with meta practice to kind of repeating the phrases
and they found themselves saying these phrases i hate meta
i hate meta you don't just kind of this you do just these things kind of
floating up right and uh the opposite and then when you realize oh my goodness what's happening i've had similar things
to you happening may you be happy and then beep like i would say like you know some
so it's can be surprising and then of course none of us want to think that we have hatred inside of us
or ill will or something like this so really doesn't conform with the ways that we want to think about ourselves
so it's can be really uncomfortable
and jack cornfield has this expression that i really love i appreciate when he
talks about some of the difficulties that might come up with any kind of practice but i'd like to say maybe
specifically with meta practice and that is the unfinished business of the heart
so whatever it is some of those pains and difficulties that
are recurring that maybe um are deep in
some ways they show up in so many different uh they manifest they show up in so many
different ways often this could be a sadness or grief
or anger or some hatred even
and of course some of this unfinished business of the heart might even show up as some bodily pains
maybe we don't recognize it at first but or maybe just part of the difficulties
or bodily pains too you know sitting in meditation it's not
the most comfortable certainly at the beginning when one's practice
so that's the second reason why sometimes loving kindness practice is we can have a hesitation towards it is
because we might have tried it and unknowingly just the difficulties came
up the third reason and there's actually some clinical data
on this where they had some group of individuals doing some mindfulness practice and some
individuals doing loving kindness practice and asked them you know a whole bunch of questions before during and
after you know these uh being trained to do these different meditation styles and what they learned
was that at the beginning if you were to compare mindfulness
practice and loving-kindness everybody prefers mindfulness because loving kindness feels way too
complicated and you have to remember these phrases and who are you going to do it with and you know there's all this
maybe it just seems too busy or it just felt like too much effort
but then through i think it was like eight weeks after eight weeks that had uh switched where after having
done it for some time everybody preferred loving-kindness practice over mindfulness practice
partly because it felt like you know it was a way to be kind to themselves and
they could feel some shifting happening and the way that they were viewing
themselves and others no guarantees right that this is going to happen but i just kind of want to
validate if there's something like this initial resistance it just feels too complicated i don't want to do it
so one thing i want to talk about is
how is it a maybe how can we work with some of these difficulties that arise with a
loving kindness practice but not only that
how might while we're doing mental practice doing
practicing loving-kindness how might it be especially suited to
work with certain types of difficulties that show up in our lives that show up in our mindfulness practice
so can we if we're doing mindfulness practice sorry meta practice
the encouragement of course is if we can can we just
expand the living kindness to include the difficulty
just in the same way that we would with mindfulness right we would just kind of bring whatever that difficulty might be
so for example if we're saying phrases may you be happy may you be healthy
can we also include the sadness that sometimes arises
sometimes when we're wishing people may you be happy what comes to mind is all the times we have not been happy
all the times they have not been happy maybe may you be happy and then we start to
think and maybe it's just for a flash we start to think like no wonder you're not happy it's so many terrible things are
happening and off we go right in this kind of a mindstream
so if we discover that oh yeah there's some sadness
can we in some way be acknowledging the sadness but still
saying may you be happy may you be healthy safe may you live with ease
sometimes with loving-kindness practice there may be a real sense of boredom
we're saying these phrases it's the opposite of sadness right which is juicy and feel like we have to work with it
and but what if there isn't anything particular happening and instead we're just reciting phrases
having this intention of cultivating loving-kindness
can we just be bored be saying these phrases
that feels dry sometimes not forcing ourselves not
tightening down and drilling in but can we still may
may i be happy maybe we feels like a little bit of suffering then and we can bring a little bit of compassion
practice in for ourselves but sometimes there can be some anxiety that
arises just thinking about happiness and health
so can we just make space for that while we are
continuing to do phrases is one way we might work with difficulties that are
happening this way we let the practice be
inclusive instead of kind of like insisting that things
be match our preferences and we're more relaxing or softening in all the ways in
which we divide our experiences between this is okay and that isn't okay
it's like may you be happy and to notice yeah there's there's sadness also
i'll talk a little bit more about what to do if there's some real sadness but there might if there's some twinge or
some um recognition of some grief there
can we allow our loving-kindness practice to be inclusive
so then maybe we can think about our loving-kindness practice be
less about befriending ourselves befriending others
and maybe more it's about just befriending each moment
and is there a way that we can meet each moment with kindness
instead of trying to shove it away or having an aversion or
grabbing onto it so tightly whatever it might be
so i want to read some words by rosemary trauma
she's this i think a very beautiful poet
and part of the reason why there's a number of reasons why i like this poem it's very short
is that she talks about blue herons and i just love blue herons they have
this majesty about them for those of you don't know they're you know they're they're big birds maybe
that's what makes them seem so majestic they can be like three or four feet tall and their wingspans are like you know
six feet and and i often go walking in a place where
i can see them i have an uncle who's
lives on the east coast and he's often he's a
professional photographer and he also likes to go for hikes and stuff and whenever he sees a blue hair and he
always like sends it because you know it's just there just have this majesty about them
so here's this poem by rosemary traumer
nudged by hope the heart rises from exhaustion
it's like the great blue heron i saw this morning flying up from a wasteland
on broad gray wings with strong slow beats
for a moment charged with grace
before did you see this heart
it chose to land again bringing all its beauty
to the desolate place so we can imagine that it starts here
that uh this great blue heron leaves this wasteland like this like there's nothing
here it's a wasteland and going up with this kind of graceful way and then
deciding to come back down
i love this idea that some ways like loving kindness practice maybe is like
this right this beautiful bird she describes it as bringing all its beauty
to this desolate place there might be this wish initially to leave like okay i don't want to be with
this difficulty maybe taking a few beats and then landing again
so we keep coming back to the practice whether it's mindfulness or loving
kindness but just this idea of keeping coming back
increasing our capacity for a living kindness and
i started talking about loving kindness as warm-heartedness and i was appreciating
the vagueness of it but maybe that's even too
ambitious warm-heartedness maybe it's helpful and supportive to
think about it as not dwelling in aversion
not dwelling in aversion
so maybe it's warm-heartedness maybe we don't even have access to that but to
just uh orient the mind in the heart away from ill-will away from aversion a
will away from insisting demanding in our minds if not
actually that things be different
so bringing all its beauty to this desolate place in this poem
it's a way that it transforms the place so that it's no longer desolate so it's no longer bleak it's no longer abandoned
but instead we choose to stay
as best we can as best we can
maybe we're a great blue heron and then we turn into a crow that is
crying making sounds and the birds that's is very different and
then maybe we are a great blue heron again i don't know but
and to be sure sometimes it's really skillful to drop the loving kindness and to bring
mindfulness to the difficulties but can we meet it with acceptance and
kindness maybe this is uh where working with
difficulties while doing loving kindness practice
really helps us with this very thing to meet difficulties to meet
all the ways in which we might get stuck with some warm-heartedness or not
dwelling in aversion and just having that experience of doing
that can help us in our daily life certainly but also in our mindfulness practice
so probably all of you know there are these five perennial ways with practice in which our
clarity gets obscured in which there's these forces of distraction or agitation
that arise or whether it's in our mindfulness practice or in our meta practice
it's called the five hindrances of kind of like five types of
things that get in the way i'll just mention them here i'm not going to talk
about all of them but just so that we recognize that oh yeah sensual desire
ill will sloth intorper restlessness doubt
so many of our things that get in the way with like i'm using this
language get in the way but that was sometimes we it's not actually in the way it is the practice but we
feel like it's something like hindering or not not uh supporting us
and of course these five it's a natural part of every human experience they are
not personal failings when they arise during meditation but
how often do we think that when they do arise oh
i'm doing something wrong i'm not a very good meditator this meditation practice is not going well
probably that person sitting next to me is doing fine but look at me i'm having all this aversion or
i'm feeling so restless or whatever it might be
but instead of personal failings can we just see them as part of our practice
and there can be a way in which because these will arise during meta meditation as well as
mindfulness meditation if there's a way in which we can make it a point oh yeah what meta
and i see these hindrances i feel these hindrances arise this is such a great way
to practice with hindrances precisely because we might
if we're doing mental practice maybe we're less likely to naturally fall into
these ideas of oh i'm a terrible meditator
i can't meditate i'm hopeless it can be an opportunity for us to say
i'm a terrible meditator and may i be happy
i am hopeless and may i be peaceful
this is terrible i can't do this and may i live with ease
so just to fold it in with the phrases that we're saying
because part of what meditation practices is to help us i think all of us know this about you know
we rewire the brain and it's amazing right how much this
inner critic shows up and how much this inner critic telling us that we can't do
it we shouldn't even try or everybody else can do it or
whatever the however it shows up or whatever words it uses for you
and it can be really powerful this inner critic it can really undermine our practice our lives
but to work with it while we're doing mata makes it very so much easier to notice
the inner critic and to counter the words counter these phrases with
when may i be happy so that there's a way it's like oh if this word come if this sentence comes
up oh you're a terrible meditator and then to say may i be happy kind of
like takes the the authority out from this idea may i i'm a terrible
meditator maybe it helps soften the
the blow so to speak that it might even become familiar that we haven't even noticed
but with loving-kindness practice we can start to
undo or rewire some of those neural circuits that might be such a habit that we don't
even notice a second way in which
it can be really helpful and fruitful for our lives and for our meditation practice in general to be working with
hindrances to be working with difficulties while we're doing meta practice while we're doing loving kindness practice
is because there might be some repeated patterns that we have probably all of us have repeated patterns
of difficulties that arise in our lives and of course arise in our meditation
and one way to work with these some of these repeated patterns is to just do a very gentle inquiry
what is asking for acceptance what is asking for
some warm-heartedness what is asking for us to not be dwelling
in aversion with regards to it and if we
have been practicing loving kindness and have this intention to have this warmth
or to have this openness or spaciousness
that might be just be creating the conditions in which it might become clear what is asking for
acceptance and to be clear i'm not talking about doing a very like type of archaeological
dig or you know discovering exactly what it is that thing that happened when you were 80 years old and
you know whatever it might be but there's something about asking the question
it's not so much about finding the answer it's about asking the question what is it that's asking for acceptance
what is it that's asking for kindness what's asking to be loved to be seen
within us so if we if we're in the doing
loving-kindness practice there might be a way in which the conditions are such that there might be
some new inside some new understanding that becomes available
because these repeated patterns they remain because there's some level of resistance right there's something
that's not being accepted there's something that we continually are trying to push away or
not acknowledge and so in the scheme of
not trying in the scheme of uh practicing kindness
that might be just the conditions in which there might be some new understanding
and so this also asks you know that this um
asking us maybe what's to be asking for acceptance is our fear our judgments our aversions
not always easy to see this in ourselves
sometimes it doesn't match the image we want to have of ourselves
but this process of gentle warm-hearted
investigation can be transformative
in such a way that maybe there isn't a big shebang and everything gets resolved and we live happily ever
after but there can just be a little bit of a shift by
having practice some loving kindness to be seeped in that and to ask what's what's
need for acceptance there can be a little bit different understanding
so maybe one last thing here that i'll talk about with working with difficulties in
the context of doing loving-kindness practice is
when there are difficulties whether it's emotional difficulties physical ones or
whatever ones they are whatever they might be there's a way in which
our attention can shrink and the only thing that we notice is
what is difficult at that moment if we have this
pain in our knee then it just becomes all about can i move my knee now should i wait to
move it or it's i shouldn't have uh walked that extra mile this week or
i thought i would be better maybe i should call the doctor you know whatever it is there's the all of our attention tends
to be about the knee or if it's this repeated patterns i'm talking about some of these emotional ones
for example there might be a repeated story i'm just making this up about the divorce of our
parents and and over and over about what happened to which child or and when or you know
something like this and then we might have this uh maybe this memory or this thought that
just shows up repeatedly in the context of a loving-kindness
retreat or this shows up is there a way in which we can
expand the field of attention earlier i talked about when there's pain
in the knee it's always the knee but now i'm talking about maybe there's this thought or this memory so it's more a
bodily experience so can we expand it so what do i mean by that
this idea with the let's say the story that happens with the divorce of the parents and there's
this pain or is or there's this memory that keeps on coming up
that's a that's more like a mental event a memory to expand is to say oh how does
that feel in the body to bring in something a little bit more
than just that difficulty how does this thought feel in the body
what is this oh i might recognize oh there's some tightness in the chest and the diaphragm and a
lump in the throat and with that just expanding this area
of awareness already that has a little bit of a shift so we're not completely consumed
with this with uh the memory and with that little bit of shift there's a little bit of space
just a little bit of maybe a little more breathing room
and then we might also ask ourselves maybe maybe it'll be
skillful maybe not something for you to explore for yourself if it seems like the appropriate thing
to do but we can then with this expanding our awareness and
now a little bit more space we could ask ourselves is it true
and of course we're going to think well yes it's true i'm thinking it so it is true
or we might think well that's kind of rude to ask right there's this
of course it's true feeling but again this just kind of dropping in this
gentle warm-hearted inquiry makes space for something else to unfold
something else to arise something else to happen
in the context of it when we're doing meta practice
this warm-heartedness you know is it true might allow for
well part of it's true but maybe not the magnitude or maybe even just the answer
is i don't know so there may be a time in which it's not
helpful to ask this question is it true but there might be a time in which it is
supportive and is wise and so that's all of us to find our way
with this but if we find like we're really stuck and if we're doing loving-kindness
practice and just find that we can't connect or we can't
do the loving kindness practice this is a way in which we might be able to
find a little bit more ease
so our difficulties are often found you know in the body the pain in the knee and the mind memories about something
that happened emotionally or energetically or something like this but
this idea that can we be expand of our awareness can we become aware of another
dimension of it of this persistent
visitor we'll use that word visitor so beyond what's the obvious beyond
what's the most prominent way it shows up because
this release or a shift or a type of letting go only can
if we find that we're stuck a release can only happen if we kind of are shifting our
way that we are with the difficulty what i mean by that is the way that our stance our perspective
and so often the easiest way to do that is to if we find it's a mental thing to
go to the body if we find it's a bodily thing well to go maybe to a neutral place in
the body or maybe to hearing but to shift a
little bit our our awareness what we're bringing to our attention
and then of course this expanding our awareness helps us to become a little bit disidentified with whatever it is
that's causing the difficulty and that
can open up space too recognizing what else is here
if we've been practicing some loving kindness there might be might be some of this residual this
residue that perfume maybe of some warm-heartedness even if right then
we haven't there might have been uh easy access or easier access to that if
we had just been practicing it earlier and it might be a way in which
that we can orient towards the
warm-heartedness as a way to make space and disidentify with
difficulties so tonight i talked a little bit about
why there are difficulties even starting a loving kindness practice there's a number of different reasons why people
have a hesitation a reluctance to
not even do loving-kindness practice and then i talked about
some of the ways in which we can work with difficulties while we are doing loving-kindness practice and
a way in which it might be um a really fruitful place
to work with loving i'm sorry with difficulties of course mindfulness practice is very
skillful in a way to do that too but there might be some ways in which
in the context of living kindness practice to work with difficulties can be really helpful also
there's something about reminding ourselves of
the goodness the warm-heartedness that exists in everybody
ourselves and in others that can really make it
it can be transformative and can be really powerful practice as an alternative to
maybe just feeling stuck or feeling like we can't find our way
forward or in a way that doesn't feel like it's supporting our
life or our practice so that we can show up for our life and
our practice and show up for others in a way that is
supportive helpful uplifting
so that all of us can find more freedom more ease and more peace
so thank you
i also want to say thank you again for coming and just think to jim and nancy
and their volunteers you know when i'm here by myself right it doesn't require so much
volunteer energy i just show up and give a little talk so and and
for the website and sometimes we have recorders so i just want to kind of like bow to this whole community
sometimes we don't see them all that helps makes this happen
and i'll stay up here for a little bit if uh some of you would like to
talk or ask a question or something like this but as always thank you