okay good morning or afternoon or evening let's go ahead and start with
the meditation today so just allowing yourself to settle in
for this period of practice finding your spot
if you're comfortable doing so allowing your eyes to close gently
it's often good to begin a period of meditation with just a
quick check in with the body and inviting some ease
so sensing the body in the sitting posture or if you're lying down
or standing whatever posture you're in
just sensing the orientation the disposition of the body
allowing the attention to come inward
just so that we have that connection with ourself right now
sensing the place where you're sitting your seat against the cushion or the
chair
sensing how it supports you the stability
and maybe taking a moment to feel balanced
where you're sitting so i sometimes even rock back and forth a little bit or forward and back
just to find that center point or close to it
where the body feels as balanced as it can
typically that will be a feeling of uprightness
almost as if the head is being drawn upward
by a string even at the top of the head
and just letting the body soften around that
letting the shoulders release maybe the shoulder blades slide down the
back
letting the arms rest hang down comfortably from the
shoulders
letting the hips and the legs soften
and then inviting ease even inside the body so inviting the
eyes to soften in the eye sockets even letting the brain relax
if that image makes sense
sometimes if i've been thinking i imagine that my brain has gotten a little bit
compressed and i just allow it to expand to fill the whole skull
and down through the chest and torso area
maybe also feeling some release and expansion let yourself fill the body
from the inside
and bringing some attention to the mind how is it right now
does the mind feel a little contracted
a little excited is there some mood or emotion that's prominent
it's all fine we're just checking in to see what's there
so the invitation is to touch into whatever
degree of contentment you can feel right now
things are as they are can we have some mental ease
around the current conditions of body and mind
at least for this moment you're sitting quietly
touching into the sense of it's enough for now
to whatever degree that's present
it's often helpful to give the mind an anchor maybe the breath or the body sensations
or for some people sounds are relaxing anchor
just something to orient around
seeing if you can connect with that and just rest with it for a few moments
when we have even just some degree of stability and ease
in the mind whatever degree it's present
that can serve as a a reference point
for feeling the ways that the mind and the body
kind of pull away from that
maybe there's a leaning toward wanting
more peace or more ease
or maybe there's a compulsive thought that keeps coming back we keep wanting
to plan something for tomorrow or we want to
review a conversation that happened yesterday
figure out what would have been better to say
and sometimes we fall into those and get on that train and that's normal
or maybe we really are wanting something to eat or
to be outside right now so just taking some time is a simple mindfulness
practice of just resting where we are in our seat and noticing the
the pulls of the mind toward various things
if there are any
and if we have been able to see some of the ways that the mind
wants things or wants to move into things or move toward
things or pull things into it
all of those are part of this movement of desire that we're exploring this week
and it's also helpful to see the relationship that we have to that
sometimes in meditation we react to wanting by not wanting it
oh if only my mind would stop doing that
so it can get a little complicated if we begin to put wanting and not wanting under the lens and then we combine it
with wanting or not wanting those things those movements
but it's also helpful to see the the way the world of wanting and not wanting is
complicated so the invitation is to let be
so not to get entangled but not to try to resist if the mind
is pulling this way in that what if we could just let those
movements be let them be as they are
if not wanting arises we can let that be as it is too they're really just different sides of the same coin
we always have the that reference point of
whatever ease or contentment we have at this moment
it's okay it's just sitting here
just let it be
the breath that comes in and goes out
it comes in without us wanting it
goes out without us wanting to get rid of it
many of the movements of the mind come about without us really wanting to bring them into existence
if we just let them be they will eventually end also
just resting with the direct experience that wanting and not wanting
are only partially related to what's actually coming and going
yes we're able to tune in more often
to a place of rest in the mind and heart and body
even if it's just a little bit more than what we had before
there can be a very slight feeling of joy
of happiness of being simply being in the present moment
even if what we're experiencing is somewhat unpleasant
suppose our back has gotten a little sore sitting here
well we're just not feeling well today or
any of the myriad things that occupy the mind and body there's something about just
being there for it knowing it letting it be that has a very subtle kind of joy to it
the joy of being present for her life
that's very helpful to tune into when we're able to feel it
because it encourages the mind to stay present
and to allow the various wantings and not wantings
to come and go and to not have so much hold on the mind then we would have a choice
about whether to act on them or not
we may begin to sense in our life that that
centeredness that we can rest in that presence
where it's okay for there to be wanting and not wanting and we have a choice about
acting on it that's a gift to the world that little space that we can open up
through our awareness
so that we can begin to more often make choices that will be good for us
and for others more often the things that we
we can choose among the things we want the ones that will be beneficial
we can choose among the things that we feel not wanting toward
we can move away from the ones that are actually
harmful and help others to do that too
far from being self-serving contentment and ease
and ability not to want and not want is a huge gift
so valuable for this world that is so busy rushing here and there
so we bring in a beautiful kind of desire into the mind
the wish for happiness for ourselves and others
the wish to be free of the grip of unhelpful wanting and not wanting
may it be so on this day as we go forward into our lives a little bit
later or tomorrow if we're going to bed soon
may we bring our contentment for the benefit of the world
[Music]
okay so this week we're talking about
desire and letting go and we learned yesterday
that desire has a lot of different manifestations in human life
it's a big part of life and just to review the vocabulary for this
week i'm we're using the word desire as a general term that just means
our mental movement toward something that we want to move toward and it can definitely be unwholesome
lust for power lust for sex addictions
but it can also range into just the needs of the body hunger wanting to eat
and all the way up into aspirations and good intentions and even the wish to awaken so i'm
calling all that kind of this space of moving toward or desire
and you know we can feel in ourselves that different kinds of desire feel very different
and that's important you know we need to gain some understanding and also some
strength of heart around handling desire so it's important area
of buddhist practice and today we're going to look
particularly at the pali word for it is comma
which is the realm of the senses and just to be clear that is a different word than
karma which is also called comma in poly this one has a long a
comma i'll try to be clear on that so this word comma
it has two different sides it has an objective side where it
represents the sensual pleasure or attractiveness that's out in the world or that we think
is out in the world and then has a subjective side that's related to the
sensual pleasure and also the attachment that we generate the sensual desire and also the attachment that we generate in
our mind around sense objects so i'll mostly probably call it sense desire or sometimes sense pleasure but
it's kind of multifaceted like that um and i should probably keep repeating
this all week which is to say is all desire bad no no it's not
but some are clearly more wholesome than others and then as a refinement of that we also need to check if there is attachment
coming along with a certain wish this is a little bit of a refinement so you know it's totally fine to wand a cup of tea
and head into the kitchen to get it but if our partner has finished the last of
the tea and we get there and there isn't any do we get angry about that
so the desire was fine but if there's attachment to it then there will be suffering if it's not fulfilled so we
have to watch that particularly in the realm that we're talking about today
so comma sense desire or sense pleasure
sometimes this refers to the five physical senses seeing hearing smelling tasting touching
i.e pleasure at any of those scent stores or desire for pleasant experiences there i think we're all very
familiar with that and sometimes it also includes the sixth sense in
buddhism the mental sense so like wanting pleasant ideas or having a desire for
pleasant thoughts and we have that too you know we we sometimes spend time
honing our views or philosophies or creating appealing stories etc
um the buddha just used the word comma differently and
on different occasions so sometimes only the five senses sometimes all six um
but when we relate this to the different types of desire i talked about yesterday
it isn't just one of the five it connects into several of them so
just as a review the five that we talked about were tonha which is grasping desire
and then the second one was our basic bodily needs hunger and thirst
needing to pee and then the wanting the various wantings associated with living a human life
and then the elevated wishes for well-being and peace and the fifth is the aspiration to
awaken so when comma this sense pleasure is very strong it's
part of that first kind of desire when there's a lot of attachment to it the grasping desire or tonha and then when
it's milder it relates more to the next two to the simple bodily needs of wanting to keep the body comfortable
and then the wanting associated with creating a human life so wants around
livelihood and family and community and so in those latter two cases that
are more in the milder form we tend to regard sense pleasure as very
important and useful and justified and um
and of course we have to do those we have to create our life but it's very
interesting to see how the buddha talks about kama in the teachings that we have from him
so i i thought it would be honest to uh to go over some of those and so to put
it frankly comma does not come off well in the buddhist teachings um
as we read and study the teachings we have to acknowledge that so um he gives a series of very stark
and graphic images for sense pleasure in a number of different teachings and i i won't even
go over all of them but because there's a lot but just as an example
one of them is that it is a it's like a meatless bone that a dog who's very hungry comes to
gnaw on the nose and nose and gnaws but it doesn't get any nourishment from the meatless bone
another image is a bird that has found a scrap of meat and
it picks it up and flies off with it and then it's attacked by other birds because they see that it has
something good and so they attack the bird that has the meat
and if it doesn't drop it it's going to get hurt another image is uh
going against the wind with a grass torch so if you go if you go with the wind
then it will you know it will blow away from you but if you go against the wind the smoke and the fire from the grass
torch will blow right onto you and maybe i'll just give one more
um which is that it's like uh since pleasures are like a dream world where
we imagine lovely parks and lovely groves and beautiful streams
and then they they they go away like poof when we wake up
so there i could go on but i think that's enough to get the idea
we say wow that's pretty stark i mean each one has a different uh focus right each one highlights a
different aspect of sense pleasure that is painful or troublesome
so you know meatless bone shows unsatisfactoriness
in the end ultimate unsatisfactoriness the bird with the meat shows other people's envy
you know when we have a lot of nice things that can be a problem in human life
um a dream world is like there's something kind of deluded about
thinking that these things are so wonderful and maybe we've had that experience of thinking that something we
were going to get was going to be really really wonderful and great and we get it and maybe we like it for a little while
but then you know we realize it isn't quite as good as we thought
something like that so i think you get the idea so you can ask wait a minute whoa why
why does the buddha do this you know why is this the most common way that he talks about karma
is it really so horrible to enjoy a good meal a sunset
my comfortable bed and of course the answer is no i'll have to keep saying this
it's not horrible we don't want to replace pleasures that we're that we like
with aversion or with guilt that doesn't help
so then we're left though with the question you know what is the buddha doing
i think the buddha makes a big deal out of the underlying unsatisfactoriness of sensual enjoyment
because it's so hard for us to see it you know we often have not just the simple enjoyment of these pleasures but
we have attachment on top of that and we don't really want to see
the other side of these it's fine to enjoy things when they're present but if there's the attachment
then we start getting into these problems so he's getting our attention the buddha wants to wake us up for a
moment so that wisdom can come in the buddha actually knew that it's hard
for us to see the disadvantages of sense pleasure because even he had a hard time
this is also in the suttas you might remember if you know the story of the buddha that he had a wealthy
upbringing he had plenty of sense pleasures and in one suta he actually says
that he was intoxicated he uses that word he was intoxicated with youth and life
and health and hence he just got lost in all the pleasures this was before his awakening
and then at some point still before his awakening he realized that it would be
good if he weren't so infatuated with sensuality but he still couldn't give it up
i'm reading a quote now of the buddha speaking even i myself before my awakening when i
was still an unawakened bodhisattva thought renunciation is good seclusion is good
but my heart did not leap up renunciation it didn't grow confident
steadfast or released seeing it as peace and the thought occurred to me why is it
that my heart does not leap up at renunciation doesn't grow confident or steadfast or released or see it as peace
and then it occurred to me i have not seen the drawbacks of sensual pleasures
i have not cultivated that insight this is the buddha before his awakening so if he had to he
had to actively look for the difficulties behind sense pleasures
and if that was the buddha i would guess it's going to be the same for us so he gives us these things these images
for our contemplation so that we can become more wise so that we can back away from the attachment and the idea in
our mind that these things are the whole point and if we just get enough of these
that's what life is about um i think we know many people who come to
meditation have realized that that isn't quite enough just to have all
the things that society tells us we should have it doesn't feel quite satisfying in
the end so um we're pointed you know we get pointed out to us these are temporary
and they're also not really controllable you know we might have gotten lucky and gotten a bunch of them in our life or
enough of them at least but and that's good because that's supportive
but do you really have complete control no we don't and so
and then they can also cause problems with other people sensual desires lead to all kinds of conflicts
so they're bound up with all kinds of unskillful mind states and it's hard
i acknowledge that it's hard for us to see this hard for the mind to see this because we feel like we'll be left with
nothing if we have no other source of happiness besides comfort and material pleasure
then it would feel terrible for those to be taken away
so it's understandable so the buddha is is being careful but also
pointing to the truth so he i did slip a word into that quote that i read you might have heard it it
was renunciation that's not a good word in western
english understanding um so we're going to talk more about what
that word really means in the buddhist teachings it's actually quite a positive word we have to let go of some of our
associations so maybe just for now we'll just substitute the word letting go as something better than
than the word renunciation for us until we've had a chance to explore it but i want to end on a practical note
today so you know what does it mean for our life if we start to question the value of
just pursuing sense pleasures if that's all we did what would happen if we started to
question that and i think i would guess that many of you have already done some reflection in this area
because it's common for people who are interested in meditation to also be interested in some degree of
material simplicity you know some understanding that getting more and more stuff isn't the
answer to happiness usually simplicity is somewhat valued in our lives
and so one you know one realm for simplicity that we can have is material simplicity the physical stuff in our
life and we can begin to realize that stuff takes effort to get and to
maintain and to organize and to remember all of that stuff
and so we start to realize ah it would be easier if we had less so i'll offer a little reflection
is there something that you have that it would be easier if you didn't have it
something that you have to manage or look out for or deal with in your life something
and what would it be like to let that go it's interesting letting go often brings
kind of an ease to the mind and when it's a clean letting go you know when we actually were ready to
release it there's peace in the heart there's no sense of deprivation
we need so little really so tomorrow
we're going to talk about this willingness to let go of things that that we're genuinely
ready to let go or that genuinely aren't necessary in our life we don't have to let go of things that are necessary for
our support and for our nourishment i'm going to go so far as to say that
letting go is a hard quality and that the ability to let go of
sense pleasures that are not necessary or even that are causing harm is a heart quality and something that we can do out
of wisdom and out of care so that's the focus for tomorrow and i hope
to see you then be well