okay all right so hello hello everyone lovely to be
with you welcome if you're new welcome if you're an old timer
welcome if you're returning after a while lovely to be in this space and time together and also
welcome to folks on on youtube who are joining us uh because this is live
streamed also so so
so so practicing practicing kindness practicing loving kindness
practicing meta and the other brahmavihara is the other
practices of the heart so the theme i'd like to bring in today is this
[Music] realization is this realization that
when we practice when we uh create
ourselves others and also what arises in our
heart in our mind emotions maybe even challenging emotions fear
anxiety etc when we treat everything with with
with gentleness with kindness instead of pushing them away instead of being
aversive towards them hating them if we
share kindness if we share meta if our attitude is one of meta
then then it feels like the world is responding to
us with meta because we form our own perceptions we
form our own world the world that we live in it's similar to when say someone is
angry or or or upset and goes through the world
uh feeling upset and angry at everyone and they they feel that everybody is angry at
them and this is a very hostile world so creating our own reality
with not with all of our actions quote-unquote actions and in buddhism
this is fun actions also refer to actions of the mind so
thoughts are actions of the mind speech is actions of speech and of
course actions in the world what you do but your thoughts the way you think the way you re react the way you
frame something or refrain something they're all actions actions of the mind
the mind door in buddhism so so however we act quote unquote act
again actions of the mind however we act in the world um for every action there is a reaction
right there is a sense of how we um if we are spreading if we perceive if we
are sending or sharing or have the perspective of
of aversion anger fear anxiety all of that and of course
that's how we perceive the world to be we perceive the world to be a very
unsafe and unfriendly place whereas with meta it we
live in a world in in our we perceive a world that is kinder because we are
being kinder to ourselves first and foremost and kinder to others
one last thing i want to say to set the frame today is um the story of why the buddha or how the
buddha started to teach metta many of you may know the story but i like to
bring it again tonight so it is said that a group of monks were sent by the buddha
to a forest to practice diligently
on their own and the tree spirits were very upset to have their
peace intruded upon by these monks so they
scared the monks away and they created ghastly images and and smells and the monks were terrified
so the monks run back to the buddha and say oh buddha please send us anywhere
but not that forest it's a scary scary place trembling
and the buddha the sense of humor he says well actually i'm gonna send you back to the very same
forest but i'm gonna give you the only protection you need
and that's when he taught them the story goes metta the practice of mittal
sharing loving kindness good will so they trusted the buddha they came back
the monks came back to the forest and practiced diligently loving-kindness
good will kindness for the tree spirits and the story goes that the tree spirits
after a while they decided they actually liked the monks they started to care for them
protect them and they lived happily ever after so
so whether you take this story to be an archetype the point here as an archetype
the meta as an antidote to fear meta as an antidote
to fear the perceptions and also you can think of an the archetype of the story is that the
monks in their mind they were creating the sense of lack of safety they're afraid this world is a dangerous place
ah this forest is awful terrible gosh this is awful then they come back
with a sense of meta for the tree spirits whether or not they exist but just sense of meta and
kindness good will fills their heart and they feel happy and practice happily so
so we are not so different from those monks so i think i have said enough of a frame
for our practice today so ah like to invite us all to settle and
settle in our chair
to arrive in our seat
and whether you're sitting standing lying down
turning your gaze inward to this body and inviting it to relax
inviting it to soften [Music] when the body relaxes the mind can
relax can you invite this relaxation in the
body into stillness not moving not moving
as an act of kindness to yourself to invite yourself to be still
when the body is still the mind can be still
the body keeps moving the mind keeps moving
turning the gaze inward and connecting with the breath in the
abdomen sensor refuge
in kindness and goodwill
and whether your body is tired or
sleepy or anxious however it is
can you open up wholeheartedly to this body however it
is right now
offer safety and kindness oh dear body
relax it's okay it's all right
just be breathed
this coming to practice together
for your own sake and the sake of others is an act of kindness
in the space of practice every breath
is an act of kindness
taking refuge calming settling
connecting with your intention
for cultivating goodness
i'm going to start our eyes as they pass
can we meet them with kindness not with judgment
same way that say beloved little puppy has
started to wander away you notice
it's playing [Music] in another field you don't kick
it maybe you're kind gentle you laugh
with good will oh sweetie it's okay
it's all right
come back here and settle [Music]
come back settle on my lap where i can pet you
let there be the same sense of kindness gentleness
to your thoughts to your heart your emotions
even if they're challenging ones your body and your mind
can you offer them safety
invite them to sit on your lap so you can pet them it's okay fear it's right
anxiety it's all right sweetie it's okay you're just doing your thing
hello backache
mm-hmm
if judgments arise or doubt arises am i doing this right is this the right way
[Music] this is correct invite the judgment or the doubt also
to come [Music] sit on your lap and be petted it's all right dear it's okay come
it's all right offering it safety
non-judgment kindness letting your body
your heart be relaxed
whatever arises
treated with kindness
and if nothing is arising it's just the breath just quiet
imbue the breath with kindness
each breath breathing in kindness breathing out kindness
simple
no need to make it complicated
my
let there be an attitude an attitude perspective
of good will the actions of your mind
your heart as much as possible even towards
what is difficult even if you have aversion towards something
can you be okay aloud
offer grandmotherly patience and kindness even to the
aversion
say when the child is cranky and
upset or crying the wiser older grandma
doesn't become perturbed but understands that the kid is tired
maybe or is hungry or is hangry there's patience there's love
knowing the causes and conditions have given rise to this so let there be grandmotherly mind
you may not know you don't need to know all the causes and conditions
what's arising in your heart and your mind and your body but you can have kindness
grandmotherly mind towards whatever
is arising
and whenever you're ready let there be a sense of expansiveness
in your heart your body expanding
this grandmotherly perspective pervading all around you
permeating through your life
all the aspects of your life
kindness patience good will
all the people in your life
sharing your grandmotherly metta grandmotherly mind
the goodwill of it with them whoever comes to mind is welcome
and if thoughts are arising can we be kind
to everything everything
as we bring this practice period to a close
can we offer kindness safety grandmotherly mind to whatever rose
whatever arrows or did not arise no judgment
no judgment we showed up we showed up as well as we were able to
and to offering generously this goodness trusting there is goodness here
cultivated within ourselves there is goodness offering it to all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere know their own goodness
may all beings everywhere including ourselves be happy and free
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so so we have some time for reflections if
there are any questions comments complaints maybe their aha moments
or anything can raise your hand or you can type in chat if you type
uh to everyone in chat i'll read your name and if it's just type to me
it'll be private so what came up for you what happened
hello lars on youtube from sweden it's a very early morning for you ah
anything that shifted for you anything that you notice perhaps especially with the in between
the grandmotherly mind
was it easy to offer grandmotherly mind did things shift
private uh chat may all beings everywhere everywhere know their own goodness
lovely refrains the situation yeah thank you
cherry [Music]
so um it was difficult
initially and then it's interesting how a word
my grandmother was had
many children and thus even more grandchildren
i think at numbers close to 30. and so grandchildren so i was one of them
and the younger ones that the much older ones for some of them it
could be my parents but she had a term that she used
and it was pet and i would ask something oh pet do you want some juicy fruit gun
and so that um word pet just like oh there it is i haven't
thought of that word in many years and it was like
oh that's warm that's that's kindness you don't have to yeah whatever else
comes after that it's um so it just it was a a click of a
switch but until then it was seemingly um i guess a little back academic
uh but i got that word and i thought okay
i'm i'm here so hope that helps others oh that's very
sweet jerry it brightens my heart and helps me connect that's so sweet oh
hello pet you know just it's just so sweet just one word has so much kindness
in it that's very sweet thank you that's lovely thanks for sharing that katrin please
um i was having a uh in daily life practice because i wanted
to be meditating outside in some grass and their people were loud everything like
and it just felt like oh this day has been so hard already and i just wanted to meditate on the grass and now there's
these people and i was really mad at everyone and mad at myself and just feeling so bad i was like i should
be meditating right now instead i'm walking home and i've like i'm ruining my one chance to get calm
of the day and on my way home so i was like kind of hustling home to like
i was like i don't even want to be inside but i'll go meditate um and this i was passing a neighbor and the
neighbor smile like smiled and waved and i just stopped and i like took out my
air pods and i asked her about her tomatoes and she was like they're actually this
guy's tomatoes and then he came out with his 10 like 18 month old and the mom
and suddenly we were all having this really sweet conversation about tomatoes
like three generations of humans just connecting um and then
and the rest of the night that felt so good and then and the rest of that walk everything
changed like everything that had been like dark and like icky just suddenly like
opened up and felt so beautiful and transformed everything and it was that
choice the choice that was a hard choice for me to make to stop and just say something kind to her
and then allow that moment to open and to receive the sweetness of the of the connection
so i didn't quite do the practice but i did a different practice and i wouldn't have
been able to do it without the teachings in my ears so thank you
thank you catherine that is so beautiful oh what beautiful practice you did in
this session thank you that's so gorgeous it's meta and so in all of
its beauty and it's the jewel the action that you took the action of the mind
saying something nice opening up the the perception right the perception is the
same evening same walking home same where everything the perception just shifted like
it's it's just one moment oh that's so beautiful thank you that's great practice love it
gene please i what what i was thinking of is that um
i felt like your guidance was helping me maybe start to build a muscle that i
don't have already and i was kind of challenge channeling my
kindergarten teacher he used to hold me in her lap and rock me and um
i've been dealing with you know trying to deal with chronic pain and a lot of fear around that and kind of
um grief and remorse and it's really hard you know i definitely resisted
so i think this was a good um kind of first step but it really does
feel like a capacity i have to build but i'm not sure i would have had the courage or opportunity without that
beautiful guided meditation so thank you thank you thank you so much ian for
sharing that and and also sharing that there's something here that's opened up for you there's
this possibility of oh yeah here and there's this memory of this kindness of
this teacher and the visceral this the feeling the physical feeling of being rocked
under lap that what a gift that you remember that and you have that available to you to
to reach into and support yourself with that and just the kindness just that
level of gentle kindness um really with with you know metta is not
so much a hammer like oh may you be happy maybe oh sweetheart just rocking gently so
that's exactly it gene i applaud you recognizing that and and opening up to it more and more thank
you lovely yeah it's a couple more reflections let's see
um jennifer says very very peaceful for me thank you
you says i'm reminded of the vase that quan yin carries it is said that the jar
contains a never-ending supply of compassion yeah thank you you says
michelle for that reminder about kuan yin and one more respect uh uh one more reflection privately fits
with diana's guidance from last night may this uncomfortableness be held with kindness and ease yes oh lovely
beautiful one more one last reflection pat on youtube a nice smooth quiet
session this evening after an active day thanks nikki you're so welcome yeah
quiet tonight yeah very quiet very peaceful just just gentle it was a
gentle rocking of the breath one more reflection uh privately at work
today i had a difficult conversation with an old friend and was still feeling the effects i was able to release it
during the meditation thank you beautiful yeah powerful powerful to have
this this space of gentleness so that challenges can be released can
can soften so so dear community with the same
gentleness with the same grandmotherly mind we're all invited to uh to join
each other in small groups of roughly size three
and the invitation is to share one thing about how this practice was for you
and [Music] then the next person will say something
and then the next person will say something and i'll come back to you just one nugget and again from your own experience not
asking not directing not managing the group just showing up how you are just offering what you have if
you wish with uh to be held to witness and you can also offer
silence when it comes your turn and say i pass right now i'm just holding compassionate space for everyone
that that's okay you might change your mind in the next future rounds so take
care of yourselves take care of each other and really enjoy take advantage of the
support of space this beautiful community that this is i'm gonna open the rooms and
you can join them here you go okay
the rooms are closed everybody is back and i see some smiles which is wonderful
it's always nice to see smiles when you come back from a room so so we are at time we have
lots of wonderful practice reports before we went into the room so we'll
we'll close now together and appreciating the time that you have all spent cultivating kindness and
grandmotherly mind gently gently gently with all the memories that have
popped up for you i love a couple that people share it the word pet and the being rocked on one's knees
very sweet so thank you all thank you for your practice for being here cultivating your heart
the benefit of all beings may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves