so hello and welcome to the beginning of
this week in this week's series meditation and dharma talk
and
i remember last monday coming here after the retreat and
not quite finding my words or
or kind of feeling quiet inside
so to start this meditation
i'd like to ask you maybe a little unusual question for
setting the stage for meditation and that is
for you for each of you individually
what comes to mind as you hear this question there's many possible answers but what
gets evoked in you as a response to this question
or what does this question point to in you
so for you what is the opposite
of hostility
within you your body your heart your mind your emotions
what what do you see at this moment is the opposite of hostility
it could be love it could be generosity it could be peace peacefulness
it could be kindness friendliness it could be care caring
compassion
it could be a calm a stillness
it could be confidence
stability is a wide range of things that it might
be and if you close your eyes
and if something come up came up as the opposite either something specific or just a
vague sense is there any place in your
body that that opposite lives any place in your body that you
associate with that opposite opposite
it could be anywhere at all and if there is such an association such
a place or you can maybe just choose a place
to to hold the opposite
take a few long slow breaths breathing through that place
almost like it's a balloon that you're blowing up on the inhale and
letting it peacefully relax on the exhale
or like a gentle wind that flows over the surface of it refreshing it
taking deep breaths and as you exhale relax
your body and as you relax relax into that place
like you're settling into it
letting your breathing return to normal and continue relaxing your body
but maybe it's possible to relax into the opposite this opposite of hostility
to this place where that
lives for you even if it's not present now
if there's a particular state that is for you that is the opposite of
hostility very quietly in your mind for maybe three or four times gently slowly
repeat the word for this state
drop the word into your body and let it
spread outward like ripples
in a pond
and then to let your thinking mind become a bit
quieter as if you're approaching this place of
the opposite of hostility you're approaching it with respect and care
attentiveness to feel and sense make
room for it
and then to continue now with a quiet meditation
perhaps
breathing with this opposite or letting your mindfulness your
awareness somehow be informed
by this quality
letting the opposite of hostility
be what nourishes your practice during this meditation
so
and then to bring this meditation to an end
to consider the opposite of hostility
and to offer that sentiment
out into the world to consider how you could
meet other people today with this opposite
consider how they can be the attitude which you think about people
consider people especially if you end up feeling hostile
remember this opposite and perhaps you can live the day
with part of you oriented towards benefiting this world leaving
the world a little better place by the end of the day by the friendliness the kindness
the smiles the generosity that you offer
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
so hello again and on this monday morning
and um for those of us those of us in united
states it's a holiday juneteenth day holiday
um the second of the two or the first of the year of the two
um independence holidays here in the united states and i gave a talk about this
holiday yesterday so
so last week we i talked about emotions and offering five different perspectives
on emotions for support and practicing with them and this week i wanted to take some
specific emotions and like case studies and go through them
and i decided that that would start with anger and when i considered anger i considered
that um there's actually a lot to say and maybe it's more useful to
spend the five days on this topic rather than just doing one day and be done with it
so that's what we'll do and maybe this the title of this week can be respecting
anger anger of course is a very important
emotion attitude motivating force in our society
and uh tremendous amount of harm gets caused through anger
and one of the i don't know if it's fair to say that any one particular harm of anger is
worse than others but what comes to mind in the moment is the
tremendous influence it can have on young children if they grow up with anger
or they grow up afraid of unexpected anger coming
at them and also uh
anger is a protective device anger also some people motivated by
anger will protect other people protect their children protect society
some people with their anger protect themselves and set up strong
boundaries and strong no and can be ferocious sometimes in in
in that protective movement some people by their anger can
[Music] put a tremendous amount of energy into a cause a good cause because of the
energies is forcing them so anger has many different expressions
in our society and um
and um but in um one of the it then it can be confusing
because sometimes anger is treated as something that's wrong or bad
painful and sometimes it's treated as something that's necessary and important and justified
and in buddhism
whenever there's a discussion about anger in buddhist english the discussion is
implies that anger has hostility as part of it
so if that's how we see it then we have to come up with another
word for something like anger or anger which has no hostility in it
there might be a very strong expression of displeasure
that will look like anger but there's no hostility in it
there can be very strong movement ferocious movement of protection of a strong no
but there's no hostility there's no desire to harm anyone it's just setting up a very strong
statement of asserting a certain ferocious uh ferocity of
purpose ferocity of of negation something
and and so a very useful way of looking at our
anger is to look and see is there any hostility in it
and if there is be careful the hostility
i would like to suggest is never necessary never appropriate
ferocious boundary setting ferocious
standing in front saying stop ferocious sense of displeasure at this is not
right that i think can be very healthy for ourselves and for others
and the first time i saw that was when i was working in the kitchen i was a kitchen manager at the monastery of the
zen monastery and i don't remember the details of how what led up to this what i did but i was
of kind of the the manager managing other people in the kitchen and the kitchen was kind of a
pressure cooker and an older man who was in the kitchen were standing next to each other on the
big table and and he just stood up straight and turned
to me and with ferocity said to me don't ever say that to me again
and so it was quite ferocious but what uh was amazing to me
was uh the moment as he said it i could uh he's he turned
it off he it was he was then he was back to being kind of clean and clear just
present doing his work and uh i i i then i was so surprised
because i only experienced before that people stayed angry people were upset that they
would stay and there'd be a kind of a conflict and a fight and he had this
clean anger it was completely clean it was just like don't do this again and he said what had to be said and he
wasn't carrying it he wasn't being continuing with it it wasn't like i was forgiven
but i didn't need to be forgiven uh it was just like i got the message and he wasn't holding on to it he wasn't
carrying anything with it he just made his ex said what had to be done and and i was so amazed by this that you can
take care of yourself this way but regardless if anger is as
is only defined by as having hostility or it's anger that's a kind of ferocious
ferocious uh boundary setting or displeasure uh it's helpful to see anger always as a
messenger always is something to study and get to know better
that anger is a tip of an iceberg of something deeper inside of us
that uh probably be useful to get to know well well to understand well
part of the challenge of any kind of anger is that it tends to be directed towards something it's with
such uh strength of directionality even if it's in towards something inside
of ourselves that we don't see the bigger picture and we don't see where the the
anger is coming from it's directed outwards and we don't look backwards to see what is happening there
what's going on there and and that's what the practice is about
very broadly in broad strokes kind of there are four stages that buddhists can can be point
to around anger one is unrestrained anger
you see it sometimes in a young child where they're just completely consumed by their anger and
i've had it with my child my child when was a toddler and
i was carrying him through the supermarket aisles and
having a temper tantrum about something and probably i just assumed that people at the store thought that i was just a
horrific father and i know that other parents have had this experience too where the child
you know just unrepressed pure volcanic anger at
something that maybe it was that they saw a toy that they wanted but it
wasn't really the time to give them a toy in the store buy it for them
and the um um
so the first there's un unrestrained anger where it's explosive uh freely
given uh you know felt like every anger is justified and
and then very broadly then the next kind of stage is um
holding anger in check sometimes repressing it
denying it hiding it and because it's dangerous to express the
anger or something and some people as they grow up and they
learn they learn that growing up sometimes they learn it on with that about the violence done to them
that they express anger and they're hit or attacked or something and so they learn
that they can't they can't express any anger and they bottle it up or turn it off somehow
the third is what we do in this practice we respect it we attend to it
we study it we get to know it better and we get to know it without shame
without further anger towards the anger we get to know it because
it is an expression of our life force it is an expression of what it means to be a lie alive
and it arises out of some it's not just anger that's happening it's the
something deeper and fuller about who we are that's in that anger our values our
emotions our fears our desires our loves um our past sufferings and pains and
wounds a whole bunch of consolation of things come together
some of them which is part of our beauty and wonderfulness and some of it is that which is what we're trying to let go of
in practice to let go um to let go um
of conceit the self-centeredness
intense self-centeredness is often a recipe for intense anger and hostility
and so that kind of anger we don't want to allow give free reign to but we don't repress it either
what we want to do is turn around and really look deeply what's going on here
and meditation is one of the best places for this in meditation you're committed to being
still not moving your body you're not going to punch anyone out or screaming anyone and to give
when you so you might even try it when you find yourself having anger
go sit down to meditate and let the anger be a volcano let the anger course through you and just feel
it make room for it let go keep letting go of the thoughts the stories
and let the body compost the anger let the body hold and process the anger and
sit there allowing it but being present for it feeling in the body
and see what happens this is very respectful of anger it allows it to be there but we're not fueling it and
feeding it with more and more activity and stories but this is a place to really get to know it
and then the fourth stage of buddhist practice at least with anger
is that anger doesn't get triggered partly because we've learned
other ways of responding other ways of boundary setting or protecting other motivations that get
what needs to be done done and partly because the attachments that we have the
clinging the conceits that are part of the triggers for anger
are no longer there and there might be strong displeasure but no
hostility at all so that's kind of an introduction for
this week we'll spend the week looking at anger and
and as a little homework assignment for this next day or for as you go forward here
see if you can learn to be comfortable or to be
empty or to be non-reactive to other people angry at you
it doesn't mean that they're justified in the anger or they should be angry or or hopefully you know it's a safe context
for this to happen don't do anything unsafe but if you can learn to be present
and stay relaxed and breathe when other people are angry this will go a long way
to your ability to do that for yourself so whether you're angry or you're a
recipient of anger see if you can practice mindfulness in the middle of it it's invaluable
so um so this is what we'll do this week and
uh it's a difficult topic and hopefully i'll do it in a way that is respectful for all the different ways
that people have experienced anger been angry been harmed by anger
and that that each of you will maybe hopefully find
some usefulness in what said this week thank you