so um so the war in ukraine is very much on my
mind and it seems that one of the interesting or important topics is how does our buddhist practice
relate to such international events that have such a big impact on all of us and we're all
all many of us are trying to figure out how to relate to it and live in a world that
both is unfolding in front of our eyes a new world a new whole kind of maybe
era in human history that people will write about and for centuries to come that
and um and we're living it and how do we live in this change and how do we relate to it
so i want to begin by to go back to the
time of the buddha that the buddha was sometimes referred to
as a teacher of action quality word is kama baden
and so of all the different ways that he could be represented as you know his stance his
approach there were times when he was called a teacher of action
and uh and why is that and what's so important about action that he that's his his teachings and is
associated with action as being so important and i would like to say that probably
action is one of the core aspects of what the buddha had to teach and so to understand why action is so
important and why i think is to understand the kind of the kind of the essence of the buddhist practice and how we practice it
and given the war in the ukraine and given this emphasis on action i want to tell a little story
that from the 1950s that is kind of circled around
western dharma circles had to do with a early western kind of a dharma teacher named
paul reps he wrote this book zen zen bone zen's flesh then flesh then bones
it's a collection it was done in 1939 a collection of wonderful little zen stories that have been quite evocative
for many people and probably introduced many people to zen in the 50s and 60s
and there's many there's many uh versions of this story
i'm sure it has some basis in truth but exactly what the you know the version that's accurate i
don't know but it has to do with paul reps um going to the consulate consulate in japan
to in 1950s during the korean war to get a visa apparently a visa to be
able to stay in japan for another year and he was told that there was problems
getting a visa he had to either wait a long time and or it could be that he couldn't get one because of the korean
war that was a difficult time for east asia and
and so um but he was given the application but you know it's not going to you're not going to hear back anytime soon it'll be a
month or months or something but he needed the visa so he filled out the application and he
sat there in the kind of applica waiting room and maybe he apparently had a thermos with
him and he had some green tea and then he handed back the application
but with a note on it and the note said drinking a cup of green tea i stopped
the war and it was like i think a haiku which he was he knew japanese he wrote in
japanese and and maybe haiku haiku is kind of you know mean a lot in japan so
so he handed the application back for the visa with that poem and that person looked at it and said
okay come back tomorrow and tomorrow and the next day he got the visa
and this is this little because i think a little saying that many i've heard quoted recently
with people saying drinking this cup of tea i stopped the war do you really stop the war with drinking
a cup of tea is it isn't this ridiculous to say that isn't it somehow
diminishing the horror of what's happening to in your comfort of your own kind of
life drinking you know a nice cup of tea and saying that i stopped the war how could that you know
what is this what's going on so partly this talk will be a kind of an
exploration of this very topic so action
this has to do with what we do with our bodies the activities of our bodies activities of speech what we say
and also in buddhism it's what we think and uh and all these are consequential they
have meaning and they can be done in different ways we can act in ways that are stressful
and we can act in ways that are peaceful that are non-stressful calm
we can act in ways that uh express anger and hostility or greed and
we can ex we can act in ways that express our generosity and our love and our care
and and this can be done in uh as the medium or the
the way in which we do things and so we learn through practice to pay attention to how we do things
so something as simple as sweeping the kitchen floor
if it's one more thing in a long list of things that have to be done for the day
one more thing that interferes with uh
being anxious about tomorrow when whatever is going on
sweeping the kitchen floor might seem like just something to get over quickly and finish and just grab the broom
really tight and just you know speed through it and don't don't worry about the corners no
one sees it anyway and just get it over with and and then when it's over
if you paid attention you that person might notice that uh it was actually kind of tiring
it was a little bit stressful to do it because the tension and the hurry and one more thing one more thing and
but you might not notice it because that was stressful because you have one more thing to do and you're already on to the next thing or four things later and
you're so distracted by your distractions you don't notice the impact of how you do things is
but if you start being mindful you might discover that there are different ways of
sweeping the kitchen floor you might do it in a way that's stressful that adds the stress of the
day continues the stress of the day there might be resistance there might be resentment why do i have to clean the
floor and the resentment is stressful it uh
there might be a conceit look at me i hope everyone notices that i'm the best kitchen floor
sweeper in the world and they better know it you know and so there's no you know figuring out ways
maybe put a you put a you know now a camcorder a camera in your video camera
in your kitchen so you kind of broadcast it on youtube so people can see how good you are and
it's like all this kind of strategies and things but itself it's stressful
or you could do the sweep the floor and just sweep the floor in a simple direct peaceful way
so that the only thing that you're really doing at that moment is
physically sweeping the floor engaged in it wholeheartedly
maybe that's what your thoughts are about your thoughts are organized in harmony so that they're actually involved with that too as opposed to
being someplace else and uh and so you start to gather
yourself around the sweeping and you discover that there's ways of
doing it gripping the the broom your posture
the speed in which you do it there's ways of doing it that feel just lovely to do feel harmonious feel
peaceful and there are ways to do it it adds a little stress in how you do it how you grip the broom and how quick you
do it and all kinds of things maybe there's resistance those corners you know you can feel as you get close
to the corners there's this like like pulling back and like well navigating and negotiating and
bargaining and bargaining and like okay i don't have to do everything and it just doesn't feel peaceful it
doesn't feel nice and so as we kind of notice the impact of how we do things is
on ourselves we might learn there's a there is a peaceful way of doing it so that at the
end of doing it we actually feel more settled more calm more present
than we were before it feels good and uh and we learned that
how we do things not just what we do but how we do things is actually consequential
and so when people say you know buddhism is about action some people get exhausted just hearing
it like one more thing to do you know give me a break i thought actual buddhism was but just being
and you know i just sit down to meditate and and just kind of like finally i don't have to be racing around doing
things i could just be in it buddhism gives me permission just to be
but that's not what buddhism is really at the heart about
but maybe it's closer to this idea of how learning how to do
so in the doing we enter a kind of harmony or peacefulness or non-conflict or
non-stressfulness so the very doing we do is nourishing
supportive creates a kind of a beautiful environment
internally for ourselves physically mentally emotionally so how we do things
so how do we learn this uh for some of us uh certainly for me one of the primary ways of having
learned something like this had to do through meditation where it looks like you're doing nothing
sitting there still but sitting in a good meditative posture
is a kind of doing is an activity it's an action itself and then while i'm not doing anything
i'm just being present but being mindful is an activity of the mind we're acting
as we start paying attention noticing how it is and what happens to us as we meditate as we get more settled and calm
and we see more one other thing it isn't just about becoming calm
what's more important than becoming calm is beginning to discover and track
the different ways we are in meditation to notice
when we are for example calm and when we're agitated or where we are in that spectrum
and begin feeling well being agitated is kind of stressful being calm is better
so maybe by accident you find yourself calm in meditation one day
and you're very familiar with your agitation that comes out of thinking about certain
things and so you start noticing yourself starting to think about those things
and leaving the calm and at some point in practice as the practice matures it
gets you get to the situation where you see that transition happening
and you're able to say no thank you because you see
that you're better off being calm than being agitated starting to stress out it's clearly it's better that way
as we settle in and become more present with mindfulness and mindfulness
at some point mindfulness is staying in the present moment with present moment experience
and we start seeing that the mind leaves to her thinking about something else
maybe something really important maybe the war in ukraine
from your meditation spot in california
and you can feel as you do that that you're getting angry
and then becomes you say is this really am i better off being angry or am i better off
being present with mindfully with what's happening here where is where am i taking up residency
am i taking up residency in the anger or residency in my peaceful state of
mindfulness of being mindful at some point
what we begin to discover that mindfulness and presence
peacefulness calm especially mindfulness is what are the best alternatives going
if someone asked me you know when should i be mindful
i would respond when it's the best alternative available
and how do i know is that as people become mindfulness get stronger it's really clear that staying mindful
is the better alternative to any state of being non-mindful
because tendency when not mindful is it's a stressful state
to be distracted caught up in thoughts preoccupied is not a really a healthy state to be in
and so we start seeing that we have mental actions that we have
some choice over we have a choice about whether to stay
with the action of being mindful or going along with the actions of being
stressful being agitated being worried being anxious being angry being greedy and
wanting and it's fascinating to watch the impact
different states of mind different chain trains of thought have on us to
see and feel it physically emotionally psychologically mentally
that some activities of the mind are clearly kind of
not so beneficial for us there may be stressful or even harmful
they perpetuate harmful ways of being it habits of being
and that there are other ways that are clearly beneficial that clearly brings sense of harmony
peacefulness subtleness that helps us be connected to the best parts of who we are
rather than disconnected from it but then the lawyers of the mind come into play
and so one of the lawyers will say you're not being responsible for the world situation unless you get angry
or how can you take care of yourself without being greedy for the next thing
or wanting something you're supposed to want things i mean that's what all the advertisements have been telling us some
of them say you deserve so i'm supposed to go off there and so in one way the other
some of us will have very strong ideas beliefs
that we're supposed to be or it's good to be angry
anxious greedy conceded
with what we do i deserve it you know it's all of me and you know it's about of course i'm supposed to be the best
kitchen sweeper on my block and i've been let you know i make sure people know that because if
they don't know that then how will i get my just desserts about if people don't know how important i am
as a sweeper so so we have to contend with these lawyers
these beliefs we have but the beliefs we have which are subtle sometimes subconscious
can become known and it's possible to recognize the impact those belief just having those
beliefs have on having us chances are those beliefs are not just kind of floating through peacefully like
gentle cloud and empty sky and just kind of like you know coming and going they're a dime a dozen
no problem they come with a force they come with a grip they come with an insistence that's kind
of stressful if if we're having some choice about the
actions we've engaged in do we have a choice about whether to go along with those beliefs
allow them to take over allow them to influence us participate in them
or do we have the choice to be mindful at their happening
look at that there's a belief wow it's just another cloud it's just a dark
one but it's just a belief but i'm mindful of believing
and then seeing what the impact is of that mindfulness
and learning how to be mindful so the mindfulness itself doesn't add to the stress
the mindfulness itself adds to a kind of peacefulness a kind of a kind of something that feels
nourishing and pleasant sometimes the buddhist tradition talks about states of mind that are beautiful
so it creates beauty inside but isn't that self-indulgent
well the alternative is worse the alternative of being caught up in these things and preoccupied and
listening to the lawyers that say that you have to be a certain way and have to be anxious and upset and angry or yet
let get let people know about you know how right you are and
all kinds of things why sacrifice your peace why sacrifice
the best alternative available so as we sit and meditate part of the advantages we start learning
have a reference point for a healthier and healthier way of being in the world
and at some point we realize it's the best alternative going why why diminish yourself
undermine yourself uh in the old habits maybe of
how you usually be it's a it's a navigation for many people
negotiation or kind of to discover that it's okay to have an inner life that's peaceful
sometimes our society doesn't doesn't appreciate it you're supposed to be a worried
you know if you're if you're not worrying you don't love me if you're supposed to be angry if you're
not angry then you're not really concerned with justice the more angry you are the more you're
proving yourself interested in you know justice in the world
and the more angry you are about what's going on the more you're showing that you're one of the people who is
believing the right things or doing the right things so there's all these reasons why people feel like they're
supposed to be angry or they are not okay to be peaceful and
present but as we start learning this this new reference point
through some like meditation or mindfulness that new reference point becomes
a teacher for us and shows us what is healthy to do and what is not healthy to
do and then we keep choosing and buddhism we keep choosing a healthy alternative
and then this teachings of action that the buddha has is sometimes
encapsulated in four kinds of action that
there's a four four ways of acting everything can fit into these four categories
so it makes action simple it's more has to do with how you do things than what you do but it can be what you do too
and they're summarized like four words a little bit my own
version of these four it's to prevent
to stop to start and to protect
prevent stop start protect so the first is prevention an ounce of
prevention is better than anything else so
live a life that prevents sets up the conditions so you avoid
getting caught up in states of mind habits thoughts activities
which are unhealthy for you detrimental as we have stronger and stronger
reference point of peace within it becomes more and more subtle
understanding how to prevent so if we are living
stressfully it's very easy to not pay enough attention and have old
habits take over one way to prevent getting lost in
unhealthy states of mind and health activities is to be
is to stay calm not don't allow yourself to get stressed out easier said than done but
that's the game that's the that's what we're trying to do here to prevent maybe there's things you
should avoid doing entirely maybe you should avoid drinking alcohol
it seems innocent enough i can do it no problems
but it turns out that whenever you're doing alcohol the next day you're not quite up to your usual self
to your full self or in a good way and you tend to say things you later regret
because you get more casual or you're kind of tired or something and so there's a lot of things we can
pay attention to what can we do to make it less likely we succumb to
some of these unhealthy tendencies so for example one of the great
preventive moves activities for meditators is to meditate
to have the kind of presence of mind the attention the calm that comes from meditation
sometimes has a lingering effect through the day if you meditate in the morning
and uh maybe you're less likely to get stressed out or get caught in preoccupations or less likely to do
something mindlessly or you're more in a frame of mind frame of heart
where you're connected to what's the best in you so meditation is a preventative
you know just like brushing your teeth every day meditate every day just as a good preventive mechanism from getting
cavities mental cavities mind cavities
so to prevent you know prevention the second is so is to prevent yourself
to prevent yourself from getting involved with things which are unhealthy for you in body speech and mind the second is to
stop and learning to stop is
fantastic what it means here is if you find yourself doing something which is unhealthy
stop if you have a train of thought which is not going anywhere useful it's actually
going some detrimental way learn the capacity a healthy capacity to
stop doing it to avoid it to drop it to let go of it
but to stop but you know it's my mind it's just what it's doing and it's that's repression if
i stop it or that's kind of like not allowing things to be or that means that i
you know i deserve i'm supposed to think that way and i'm supposed to include all of who i am and what's just buddhism that says i
can't do this kind of stuff yeah i mean if you argue like that i
just probably just get quiet maybe it'd be kind of like saying that um yeah yeah when i have a cut in my
finger i should still be able to do whatever i do and you know put my hands into the compost pile and
clean the sewer and not have to worry about anything you know putting a band-aid over it or keeping it clean or putting a
glove on while i do those activities and that just seems like i'm being limited and i i want to just be myself fully and
and i happen to have this cut on my hand and i just wanted you know okay well if you say that
okay well you know maybe i'll take you to the
emergency when your hand gets infected let me know so
to start learning how to stop but to stopping it
itself to do it in a peaceful way the stopping itself is an activity
so how do you do that activity so that it supports the best in you
so it supports harmony beauty peacefulness calm
if you uh i've had it i've had you know there's a there's an expression whack-a-mole
that's applied to meditation and uh which is kind of like every time something
like a thought arises or some kind of negative thought arises and kind of like hit it over the head to
knock it down you know knock it down like kind of this angry aggressive form of mindfulness
and uh when i was a new meditator i sometimes imagined i was playing pinball machine
you know it's like knock that thought out of the way or and uh
but how to stop in a way that feels peaceful and not repressive not angry
not attacking anything just kind of like that's enough no thank you
i don't have to do that anymore and how does mindfulness a clear
recognition of what's happening how is that a kind of a stopping
and it's a kind of a stopping if your life energy goes into the mindfulness
so it's not so much available to continue trains of thoughts and ideas and motivations
that don't serve you stop
so the third is to start there are things you can do which are healthy that are beneficial supportive
you could start your mindfulness practice you can start kindness
you can start generosity you can start looking more closely what's going on here investigate
sometimes you can start joy you can start
a calmness you can kind of take a deep breath and relax and relax your body
you can take a couple of moments you know to take a little walk
maybe just maybe just uh 20 paces enough to get a little bit more settled and calm and connected
start means to get involved and start doing the things that you've learned are
supportive and helpful there too how you do it is important
if you're desperately doing it holding on for dear life maybe that's not the most conducive to
being you know get the best out of it if you're doing in a greedy way
you know like i'm going to get these really good states of mind and that's what i want to have
and then i can go be the best meditator on my block and i'm going to let everyone know
or you can do it as a way of avoiding it can actually be a form of anger or aversion hostility
i'm going to get rid of that bad states of mind but getting those good states of mind here and overcoming it
those are all actions of the mind always in buddhism we're looking at the
actions of the mind the actions of mind body and speech we're looking at those actions
and evaluating them is the way that i do anything
the way that i respond to anything happening in the moment or anytime
is the way i'm responding beneficial or not beneficial
and then we have the fourth one which is protect some things are worth protecting
some states of mind some ways of being some activities of mind they're worth protecting
if you finally after a lifetime of being anxious you're finally calm or settled or at
rest then it's maybe that's good to protect
but how do you protect it not by resistance not by
stressfully holding everything at bay but maybe valuing it taking time for it
not rushing off to all the other next things we could do so we forget about it
protect what's good protect what's coming along the beauty
all of you have tremendous potential for inner beauty all kinds of ways in which there's
something really a treasure inside of you as you get hints of it
that sense of it through practice or other ways it's worth protecting
protecting it is another action the question is how do you do that action so it is beneficial it's healthy it
brings harmony to the situation well you protect it
by preventing unhealthy ways of
protecting stopping unhealthy ways of protecting initiating healthy ways of protecting
and then protecting yourself from that doing that there's always a self-referencing back
and as practice deepens and deepens and matures for people there's a stronger and stronger and stronger reference
point of well-being of ease of peace of happiness
that gives us a clear and clear understanding
of how valuable these four efforts are these four actions are
preventing stopping starting
and protecting as we go along with this
then when we encounter the world and all the
horrible and beautiful things that can happen in the world that reference point is available
so if we encounter the horrific
war in ukraine
why sacrifice your own inner well-being
at that in relationship to the war why sacrifice
your peace your harmony so that you can be angry
so that you can be distressed so that you can be
afraid you know so all these things we do
that we in choosing to do those and we do choose this is the kind of the
challenge of buddhism we don't necessarily see the choice being done but we choose
why choose these stressful ways of being why not
stay with our peace one of the reasons people choose to let
go of their peace is they feel like then they won't be able to be responsibly
involved in making a difference in the world
for those of us here in california is your being angry you're being
despairing going to help anything
why give into despair when you're sitting quietly and you see that
moving into despair is a choice it comes with beliefs
that are evoking the despair why give into it
and this teaching i'm giving here i think is most suitable for people who do something like mindfulness meditation
and who really be able to settle and see there's this choice there's a reference
point for some kind of place of being it's okay
and in fact not only is it okay the world needs people who know
how not to give into despair how not to give into anger how not to give into
fear how not to give into greed because if there's going to be any
chance for world peace
it has to come out of that that somehow world peace
the greatest wonderful goal that is begins with each of you
i can't begin for you i can't begin anywhere else
they can't begin anywhere else if you want to do something for the ukraine
stop the war in your heart find peace be that way
does that mean that you ignore what's happening in ukraine no
my my trust is that if you find the healthy peaceful freedom that's within
the heart will respond as is appropriate and there are many ways of be of
responding some very local some indirect some direct
it all depends on our circumstances but buddhism is about action
so how will you act don't be a couch potato that's that's
not a healthy action how do you act
so that the very acting responding feels nourishing and beneficial for you
how do you maybe change your lifestyle like i can imagine there's going to be a call for us to
change our lifestyle because it seems to me that it's be pretty beneficial for the world
for those of us all over the world but in this country to consume less gasoline
for all kinds of reasons it would be beneficial but this is an exact religious idea in the united states it's a way of getting
voted out of office if you if you say it
but how to do that change how we live and live in a way that
contributes to the world rather than detracts from it how do we do it so we feel nourished inspired gladdened by the
very doing that's the art of this not so that we feel diminished we
actually feel enhanced we feel more beautiful we feel more happy
how do we make a donation to save the children not because you know
you know gil is expecting it of us and you know then it's kind of to be diminishing that kind of undermines you
for that kind of motivation but is there a motivation that comes out of a subtle peaceful place that's
inspired that makes you sing this is great to do that it's tragic it's heartbreaking what's
happening in ukraine but here is a beautiful activity that i can participate in it feels good to do
this
and then my hope is that as we learn how to stop the war
drinking a cup of tea sweeping the floor
talking to our neighbors whatever we're doing that we'll set up the conditions
that when what we have to offer the world
to save the world comes in front of us we'll act
accordingly that we when we understand what's needed
when we understand the situation and what we have to offer that we will be
people who contribute to a better world not just because we're peaceful
but because that peaceful place is empowering
action empowering engagement in a way that's appropriate for each of
us in our own way so that that engagement
is beneficial for us not harmful to us it enhances us
doesn't add to our stress and our burdens and diminishes us the buddha taught action
was a teacher of action and how do we act in such a way
that the heart can live in this world actively fully participating in this
world so the heart is at peace
so the heart the heart of the heart is sweetly
still sweetly unagitated unmoving
and here is where buddhism emphasizes not doing
the place where the heart is sweetly not doing
peaceful still while we
act and speak and think in beneficial ways for ourselves and for
a whole world may this practice that we do
give us the inner reference point of peace of stillness non-agitation
that allows the best of us to come forth into the world
that's for our own benefit and the benefit of the whole world may this practice help us be peacemakers
for this world thank you