foreign whether you're joining us on zoo many of
you are and also those joining on YouTube Hello greetings welcome to this
rendition of happy hour so
so would the theme I'd like to invite us to practice with
um today is um relating to meta relating to
warm-heartedness offering safety offering Good Will
offering goodness is is
how a sense of enoughness just bringing a sense of it's
enough it's enough it's okay no it's enough this is enough
I'm enough in this moment just showing up is enough maybe you've had a hard day
it's been a long day and just showing up sitting
in Sangha or or maybe if you're listening to the side of your leader uh
on your own just showing up making an attempt this is enough this is enough a
sense of comfort of not always driving ourselves uh ragged more more
and more but it's okay opening up to the enoughness of this moment
enoughness of this amazing being who is ourselves and is doing their best
this is enough and maybe through this acceptance of
the enoughness or rather the plenty of this moment
we can appreciate and see and really touch into this care the
sentence of care the sense of holding of ourselves this non-judgment it's a sense of
enoughness actually is the opposite of self-judgment because self-judgment is not oh that's not good
enough you're not good enough this is not good enough you should be doing this that or not be doing that's okay
sweetheart it's okay dear heart it's not a sense of Solace calm
So Meta warm-heartedness loving kindness showing up in this other
wearing the the clothes of it's enough this is enough it can be a very soothing
calming um meta not necessarily very energized
or energy energetic law so as you know by now you're maybe you're getting to
know that meta loving kindness can show up in practice
in so many ways it can wear many many many different beautiful guises so this
is one way I'm inviting us to explore it it's not very energetic but very calming
it becomes more similar more um
um expressive uh of itself similar to Equanimity this is a calming soothing
because of course Equanimity opeca is a practice that's one of the Brahma viharas one of the pr or Heavenly abodes
meta being the first one Equanimity being the fourth one they're related of
course they're related so this way of us is enough it's okay it's okay it's all
right it's it's expressing meta expressing itself
um its similarity or its its relationship with Equanimity in this way
of showing up and this nuanced way comforting way of showing up so that's
all I want to say to set up the space for our practice together
so so let's let's meditate together let's meditate so I'd like to invite you
to land in your posture whether sitting
standing lying down and if it's comfortable for you to close
your eyes
softening relaxing this body foreign
[Music] opening up to it
feel out of energy present there could be lack of energy fatigue perhaps
the end of the day maybe there's achiness
present in the body
maybe there is excitement about this period of practice taking Refuge together
allowing the breath to move through foreign
showing up in the abdomen
and wherever there is tightness
maybe lower back
or your forehead foreign
foreign
to move through and calm soon
like a soothing ointment
ointment do whatever might be tight in the body in the mind and the Heart
foreign
s do
offering that oh sweetheart dear mind this moment is plenty there is so much
here really no need to try to entertain
[Music] the thoughts of the future past regrets this moment is plenty
it's enough let's rest Dear Heart let's rest
foreign Let There Be kindness
not judgment not kicking the mind for thinking
but inviting you to appreciate how much goodness there is here in this
moment of just sitting being breathed
being silent contented such Exquisite training
such exquisite
way of being simple
enough
foreign
noticing the mind the heart wants to wander is trembling
Dart here and there again with kindness oh sweetheart it's okay
okay this moment is enough see there is so much here
this moment is more fulfilling
with kindness with spaciousness
then darting to the past future
rest dressed be cared for
Dear Heart your mind right here with the Lullaby of the
breath
foreign
comforting the mind the heart at this moment is enough
there's so much here and comfort
in Refuge
can also bring in bewitch thank you
that just showing up however you're showing up with your intention
that this is enough that's showing up is enough
if you're knocking on the temple door it's proverbial Temple door
repeats ease Awakening just showing up is enough
the body of ease be relaxed and soft
the breath soothing calming
connecting you to the present moment desperate
breath can anchor into the ocean of now
foreign
drop in the word enough are plenty
this is enough this is plenty
this right here whatever this means showing up
this being who is me this moment this body this opportunity
all these gifts of the present moment
Let There Be kindness
as if your Fairy Godmother is showing you the
enoughness of your heart enoughness of everything with kindness
and if the mind or heart the body at any time becomes petulant the Fairy
Godmother is caring loving
eternally patient this is enough
please see shows you
all the things maybe you haven't seen
or taking for granted
foreign
foreign notice the mind that feels scarcity
this is not good enough do something
or you're failing your mind is wondering this is not good enough notice that mind
and love it
offer it kindness safety it's okay so
your mind that wants something else
the Fairy Godmother of this moment loves
everything that's arising even the mind
of scarcity
offered kindness
goodness
let it relax
not feeling pushed out
foreign
there is a particular angle of insufficiency they're about yourself or
present or what you have what you do
you can try the different incantations of
enough sufficiency
I have enough or I do enough
I am enough foreign
s my wholeheartedness my goodness to really turn the mind to see the good
again how to practice of complacency but to
really see sufficiency sufficiency
which can still leave room for aspiration but let's turn towards
efficiency see the Plenty
so that the heart feels replenished in its plenty
this is enough this is plenty
foreign
nourish your heart for just these few minutes insufficiency
be curious what might happen can always go back to insufficiency but
just right now what happens foreign
[Music]
foreign
this period to a close foreign
did not arise during this practice period it was enough more than enough
can we see it can be appreciated with gratitude for whatever it was
ah exhaling into sufficiency to completeness
I've done my best trusting that seeds
of contentment have been planted of kindness
they will flower
the time that we least expected may all beings everywhere may all beings
everywhere know their own goodness their own sufficiency
may we too may we wake up
to our goodness our completeness our fullness together with all beings
everywhere
[Music]
thank you all for your practice ah
we have time there are questions reflections
reports from the field
you're welcome to type in chat if it's just to me private I won't read
your name it's to everyone I will read your name also you can raise
your Zoom hand if it's your physical hand I will not see you
and you're invited for to offer any Reflections any
aha moments any challenges anything that's a gift
as a gift to others one one of you says thank you fairy
godmother
you're welcome and all your fairy godmothers are welcome yes Fred please
thank you Nikki I find it relatively easy to think
certainly I have enough in the material side of life and in the many ways that
that plays out [Music] but as I
come back to feeling am I am I enough now am I sufficient in
my aspiration and my um my efforts to be as I want in the
world to be more open to be more loving to be engaged in useful ways you know
the answer is no I'm not and um I I think you're asking us to
simultaneously maintain two contradictory ideas that to not let go
of aspiration and effort but perhaps to also say well
you know that's one can Aspire and still
feel some peaceableness in the present effort
exactly Fred right on and you put it so eloquently thank you that's exactly it
and don't mute yourself just yet it's um it's like the Suzuki roshi famous line
you are perfect as you are and you can use a little Improvement
how is that that's exactly the intention because there needs to be a sense of
because the you need a little Improvement alone it brings tightness in
the heart and the mind as you know and there's a sense of insufficiency and lacking and and envy and or shame or
whatever it's like it's not conducive so there needs to be a sense of I'm enough or there's enoughness there's a sense of
sufficiency gladness goodness that the heart can feel settled and rested in so
that it can be so that it can aspire
for further goodness exactly yeah right on okay thank you
thank you not easy to do but thank you it's not and yet I so appreciate that you verbalized the you you really
brought out what what the intention was here so I really appreciate you for doing that thanks red yeah
um a couple of Reflections here let's see Christine who says enough these few words are
enough if not these words this breath if not this breath is sitting here this
opening to life we have refused again and again until now until now David
White oh yeah beautiful I love that poem actually I think I've seen that poem
before had I remembered I would have brought it in but thank you for bringing it in this is perfect Christine thank
you but that's lovely and and maybe um Neil would also share that poem later
um in the um in the Google uh
uh mailing list Goku groups uh fossil says thank you for that
question Fred that's been on my mind yes thank you Fred that's great
um Pat says such a relief for the practice of just enough after a long
involved day yeah sometimes it's yeah appreciation coming
thanks red thanks Christine I think you sent that just to me not to the group
this was private so if you want to send it to everyone you're welcome to ah Nadine I just saw your hand please
yeah so I just something kind of funny happened
um when I'm you know pushing thoughts away and just being present the thoughts are always kind of words in
my mind or I just I'm talking to myself and suddenly my mind just shot me a
picture and I thought oh sneaky mind what a sneaky mind it's like you're not
talking to you shot me a picture and I I could push that away too that was the first time I had my mind ever tricked me
with a picture hmm that's interesting it's it's cute it's
many Minds do that so here's here's an invitation I haven't had Dean so so when all the thoughts come and also
if pictures come again now that the mind is you know presenting people that's not unusual
um see what happens if you shift your position from pushing it away you know
your hand gesture was also like this pushing it away instead of welcoming it
see what happens if you do that oh hello dear mine hi sweetheart you're calm sit
down calm see there is so much plenty there's so much goodness here so so see
if you just shift it around see what happens be curious does that make sense what I'm suggesting maybe it'll send me
a pretty picture thank you it's all just bring it here come come here it's okay because that
that pushing that that movement of the heart that movement of the mind which actually you represent it beautifully
and um that that can actually
create more involvement in thinking that that energy so I'm inviting you to bring
more just more care more attention more love to that movement it's not needed make it
this make it yeah and it's not about giving into thinking and ruminating but
it actually shifts the dynamic then I invite you to be curious about that
yeah thank you you're welcome thank you so
um one last reflection um this one is private thank you Nikki I
have been in a lot of emotional pain over the past 24 hours many feelings of worthlessness and inadequacy this
practice really helped to soothe me ah thank you for sharing that
yeah may it provide comfort and to see the goodness within your hair you're
practicing there's so much goodness here already so much goodness so
so dear ones let us turn our attention
to practicing in small groups in small breakout groups
so roughly size of three and here are some invitations so please listen up
especially if you're relatively new to happy hour
so the invitation in the groups is you speak only from your own experience you
don't ask questions you don't direct you don't manage the group you just offer a nugget
from yourself and also pay attention to what is appropriate to say or not to say
oh it's too much to say um and you're also always welcome to say
pass and hold uh silent space that's okay too and then the next
person will say something and then the next person and they'll come back to you so make your your piece pretty short
just one nugget of thought it's not a long monologue it's just one nugget of thought that the next person the next
person come round and round and be kind to yourself and especially kind
to others um holding each other with care with appreciation
um with meta these are your siblings in practice take care of each other take
care of yourselves and let's speak in Reverse alphabetical order tonight
and I'm gonna open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other
here we go okay the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone and I realize
it's exactly seven o'clock so we're right on time and uh since we had such
lovely Reflections before we went into the group um if there are any last minute
Reflections feel free to type them in chat but otherwise maybe we'll bring our
our session to a close um thank you all for your practice thank
you for showing up um and may we all know recognize our
goodness our enoughness that we're perfect just the way we are and that we
need we can we can use a little bit of improvement may all beings be well may all beings be happy including ourselves
here we go
thank you all be well