all right so hello hello and welcome everyone
lovely to be with you to be in community uh warms my heart warms my heart
to be with the happy hour sangha so
so so for tonight or this moment whatever the time zone might be you're in
i'd like to um invite us in a practice in the reflections and in the guided meditation
um to consider karma and meta so the theme of karma is something that
by the way i've been i've been subbing for gil of those of you who show up to the 7 a.m yes some of you are here i see
you and this morning i talked about karma and um
i wanted to bring that in to in the spirit of happy hour the way we practice
with with meta and the whole all the hard practices so i want to say
something first briefly about karma
that it's not really it's not a teaching about
what we've inherited from the past magical life or
or somehow explain why you know we're having poor fortune here i must have done something terrible in
my past life where this other person must have done something bad in their past ouch ouch
not a helpful way to use this profound profound teaching
so it's unfortunately co-opted in the west and misused really misused in these very
painful ways that's not really helpful it's not appropriate it's not serving it's not really a
practice it's just a baton for for or it's for self-flagellation it's a um
rod for self-fragilation not at the top but anyway so so instead one way to understand um the
teaching of karma or the way really to understand is
is that there are three aspects to karma
and they're all intertwined one aspect is the intention the wanting to do an
action the second part is the doing of the action but the
action could be action of the mind actually no speech action of the body so
a thought is considered an action of the mind or okay that's number two
number three the third aspect is what is done is is the result is the result of
what has been done is the is the is the karmic uh disposition that we're left with that
we are left with so all of those aspects both the leading aspect which is the
intention the doing and what is done that is karma that is what we are left
with that's what shapes us and we are
product of our quote-unquote karma because of the actions of the intentions
we have taken all these moments of the doings we have done and
the the results of those actions and it's also concordant with neuroscience so
not going to too much detail speak more about in the mornings if you guys want to show up
but how i want to relate it to the practice of metta for us in this in this community is
if you want to be kinder to yourself and to others
then intend to be kinder right lead with the intention have the intention to be
kinder do an act of kindness part two an
act of kindness again could be thoughts of kindness could be words of kindness
could be physical acts of kindness towards yourself towards others right that's
part two part three part three is that you are left you will be left with you'll be
shaped you'll be shaped little by little
to have a kinder disposition wow
pretty cool hey karma is powerful
we can produce our own karma it's not this magical thing we produce our karma
moment by moment by the way we think the way we intend
the way we act and what and the result that it's we're left with and then we tend to do those
more and more so if you find yourself not being kind okay just pause
change just shift a little bit shift shift and probabilistically speaking
the accumulation over time you will be changing your karma you'll be you'll be acting you'll be going down a
different path that'll become your habitual way of being in the world so
karma is profound especially when it comes to practicing loving kindness so
so let's produce some good karma
for ourselves really and in that way i'm not again with the definition i've given it's not
something magical but let's intend towards kindness with our intention
let's engage in thoughts words and actions of kindness oh and see what
kind of a result we are left with and we are we will be left with a different karma
with with wholesome karma wholesome karma instead of unwholesome karma
so such an empowering teaching such an empowering teaching is karma
it's not a you know matter of fate or destiny oh
poor me it's like no i can change my karma i
can so all right well let's produce some
wholesome karma together so so with that i'd like to invite us all
to land to land in our seat to land in our chair or cushion
ah if you need to shift and move to be comfortable
it's okay this is the perfect time to do it
and arriving arriving in this body
at this moment in time
landing landing landing landing
oh dear body i intend to be kind i intend to be kind to you
oh dear heart their mind fear me
i intend to be kind in this moment
in this moment of creating producing wholesome karma because i can
i'm alive i'm awake i'm here
i intend to be kind and thinking thoughts of kindness
care towards ourselves let's start with the body
oh sweet dear body you have worked hard today
you have worked hard today you have digested
you have kept me safe from viruses as much as you've been able
to you have been working as hard
as possible in ways i can't even imagine thank you
thoughts of kindness appreciation towards this body
an act of kindness ah releasing letting go of any unkind
thoughts any judgment thank you judgmental thoughts
thank you you're not needed right now i'm intending to be kind
it's powerful practice intending to be kind
engaging in thoughts words
actions of kindness
letting the breath be received letting the breath be received in the
abdomen gently kindly with appreciation
maybe with a smile as if your
belly your abdomen your cells the cells of your body are smiling with kindness
we're bowing to the breath thank you breath giving oxygen to us
such a wholesome beautiful exchange
this
and if you notice thoughts arising challenges in the mind and heart
connect with the intention to be kind towards whatever rises
the intention to be kind whatever rises whatever
whatever arises
radical radical kindness
intention for radical kindness experiment
see what happens if you're radically kind [Music]
it's your mind to your heart when you notice it's been
distracted thinking if you're kind do thoughts become less
sticky
do they release more easily in the heart
that's spacious with ease with kindness
experiment
and can we to engage and can be to engage
with thoughts of kindness for ourselves
perhaps with the metaphrases
may i may this person knows me
be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may my life unfold with ease
offering these words of kindness to yourself to our songs
as a gift without any expectation
not clingy karma we don't want to produce
clingy expecting wanting karma but one of generosity
may i may this person who's me may they be safe
happy healthy have ease
as if you're offering blessings to a good friend
words of kindness wishing them well on their travels
not clingy or tight spacious and generous
let yourself enjoy enjoy the phrases of kindness
to yourself
resulting producing wholesome kind karma
intention to action result
in this moment right here
offering yourself the words of kindness either in the phrases of meta
or however is appropriate for you right now maybe holding yourself as if you're a
baby with kindness in your mind's eye
a physical action physical movement of meta of care
and now if you wish extending
the intention to be kind to another being in your mind's eye
someone who's dear to you you have an uncomplicated relationship with them
greeting them your mind's eye with kindness
i intend to be kind
loving generous
in your mind's eye with this being
could be a person an animal a pet a child
maybe see yourself doing acts of kindness
be active speech maybe you're telling them
kind encouraging words or maybe you're sharing the words of metta
the phrases of metta in your mind's eye
or seeing yourself caring for them maybe patiently listening to them
sharing acts of generosity kindness
without attachment to reciprocation [Music]
without attachment to outcome without attachment
not producing clingy karma just generous karma
kind spacious spacious in the heart
in this moment and in the next moment
may you be safe from the inner and outer arm
dear ones
may you be happy and have joy in your heart dear one
may you be healthy and strong as much as possible dear
and may your life flow with ease dear one
it's okay to use your imagination
see yourself in acts of kindness and care or maybe simply holding presents
patience patient presence
an expression of kindness
you can stay with this dear being or extend extending intention to be kind
to more beings many more beings
may all of us may all of us be well
including
yourself letting your body be soft be relaxed
and if thoughts challenging difficult thoughts emotions are arising
can there be kindness
as a response not believing
not falling into the judgments the grief in this moment
i just hold it with kindness
even if a thought is annoying or if someone comes up
the landscape of your mind doesn't you're annoyed or displeased can you
still be kind to yourself to this being who doesn't know any
better
who's acting out of confusion delusion
having dust in their eyes lack of wisdom
planting planting seeds of kindness planting seeds of kindness
planting seeds of wholesome karma
and for the last moments of this practice period
can we be kind to ourselves
kindness in this moment for whatever arose or did not arise we've done our best
to be kind to this being who's me here and now we've done our best
to cultivate good will for others
whatever came up or did not come up
it's an unfolding it's an unfolding of causes and conditions past thoughts actions karma
it's okay you can forgive it let go forget
and intend in this moment to be kind one moment of kindness
infinitely more powerful than zero
moments of kindness
may all beings be
may all beings be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice and planting all these moments all these
seeds of kindness together wholesome karma what a beautiful field
[Music] so
so if you wish you're welcome you're invited
to uh share reflections questions comment
richard i see your hand
am i unmuted you are well i i wonder if you could help me
briefly uh i guess for a long time to this moment i sort of think of the
brahmavir as warm and squishy and bare awareness is neutral and chilly and
dry and some i i think that's causing a split
down my personality yeah yeah well well said you're not
alone richard it's so well said yes meta warm comforting nourishing
pipasana or or awareness or open awareness as neutral
cool yeah it's and and then this feeling is split
in your personality so well said so was it i think you already know the answer
yourself no no no okay all right i think you do but okay all right so um
so um yeah so you know the sense of
kindness gentleness it has to be imbued it has to be part of
our awareness when we do vipassana when we do inside practice when we do open
awareness if that kindness isn't there it becomes so dry it becomes
can become a grim duty it's it's lacks it's just gentleness i
i often quote joseph goldstein i love what he says he says
wisdom wisdom practices and open awareness is a wisdom practice wisdom without
metta wisdom practices or vipassana you know fill in the blank without meta is like riding
a bicycle without air in the tires so richard please put air in your tires
please bring kindness gentleness in every mind moment it can be imbued and
and i'll be in higher teachings you know the sense of kindness gentleness there's
this goodness imbued in every moment of of of awareness of mindful of sati
so um they are not separate and so many here's my personal opinion
my humble opinion um that many practitioners practice for
many years i'm not talking about you but many practitioners practice for many years without
um fruition without um
getting well i don't want to say getting somewhere but you know without just uh
with with a lot of challenge let me put it that way i'm feeling a lot of challenge because there isn't enough
meta and care and ease and gentleness imbued in vipassana so i'm so grateful you
brought this question up it is so important and it's not so difficult i mean you
you know how to practice meta it's not just you know here's a problem
that i'm going longer this is not a short question because it's such it's a short answer because it's such an important
question see that the problem arises from westerners often thinking of meta
practice just as the phrases may i be well may you be well that's just one
expression of meta practice as you know because you've been coming to to this practice um
to the to the happy hour for so long the way i offer and teach you sometimes
a lot of times it's without words it's like resting the feeling resting in the care and the gentleness
in you know when the thoughts for example come just smile at them be kind to them all of that is meta all of that
is bringing meta into awareness practice so there is the infusion i hope that
helps richard thank you you're welcome thank you for that very important question
invite me to reflect for the benefit of many beings
catherine says i was one of those practitioners the dharma only started actually landing for me when i opened my
heart to meta practice it has changed everything yay
yay thank you katman thank you so much for sharing oh it's beautiful that makes
me so happy it makes me so happy apparently others do i see hearts
so so any other questions reflections about
today's practice as we engage together
nima yeah um i really appreciated this
because i had never looked at it from that angle that um the way you explained it it is
empowering it's not like i'm a victim to my own ignorance and not knowing
what karma was it's it can change today like right now like this practice and i
didn't never i never looked at a meta and coming to happy hours planting seeds
of that karma to change my whatever causes and conditions of
yeah my constitution of how i am or whatever um so this was a really uh helpful way of
looking at the practice very soft very
tender kind yeah thank you thank you mima so well said yay i'm
rejoicing in your insight and in the beauty of your
expression of your insight thank you thank you for that gift that's so lovely
yeah indeed yes we are changing
our karma every moment through every action every intention
thought action it's powerful it's so powerful empowering
yeah empowering and yes happy hour a way to to shift to plant seeds
any other reflections you like to share
you can also type them in chat if you type them to me
privately i'll only read the reflection if they're typed to everyone
[Music] i will read your name also it'll be public
um silence is always welcome too
the complaint's true questions if something didn't work it's all welcome
warmly welcome
tell you what let's shift and turn and engage with each other
in small groups and the invitation today the invitation
for the small groups is um you know you can share it by your
practice if you wish you can say a word about any insights aha moments challenges or
maybe about karma and metta this relationship of exploring
karma in this new empowering way so um
again as always you're asked to just share from your own experience not
serving as a um um what's it called facilitator for the
group just speak from your own experience just ask your own experience that's it and let other people speak
from their own experience or say pass people can say pass and hold presence
it's all okay they can be silent perfectly fine
no one is forced to say anything you can hold that with kindness hold that with kindness
so each person will share one nugget let's go reverse alphabetical order just
for the fun of it according to your first name say one nugget the next person the next
person and back to you next person next person etc and be kind to yourself be kind to each
other you're planting seeds in the small group remember you're planting seeds
of of karma in the small groups so
so i'm going to create the rooms be kind to yourself
be kind to each other and
here we go [Music]
okay the rooms are closed and everybody's back so we've got just about a minute
um if there are any insights anything that came up from the
group i'd love to hear especially if you haven't spoken um jamie says it was wonderful you want to
say more jamie please raise your hand because i don't or anybody else i don't want to put you
on the spot anybody wants to say just one word what a rose any insights
going once going twice
you can also type in chat
oh oh i do see hand i guess i miss the hand sorry i see lots of hands now oh my
goodness all right we're gonna let catherine i wasn't seeing the hands before
catherine please oh just that um i'm recognizing it's not
just seeds of loving kindness that i water here but also flowers and
saplings and big trees sweet
thank you catherine that was beautiful and and poetic and given that you're outside and i see all the saplings and
the victories behind you that is so sweet thank you fred please
well two of us in our group had identical thoughts um during the meditation we we were both
thinking that well this is what we want to do with the rest of our life you know however long
it might be we we want to be kind we want to find
the means to do this in a persistent way as though this was now
our post-career career it was kind of wonderful to think that
the same words went through both of our heads it was a nice communion together
sweet thank you for sharing that and now i'm lighting up hearing that from from you
both yeah vicky quickly
oh you're still muted still muted
third try there we were saying that you are a wonderful model and um that it's humanly possible
maybe because we see this um shown to us with you
oh thank you thank you you're very kind
and it's i think what comes up i is i want to say it's not me not mine
it's the practice yes so it is it is possible it's it's the practice
it is the practice i have definitely changed over the years and the decades so so yes
and continue to change this this is what i love to do to keep cultivating
for the benefit of all beings including myself so thank you you're very kind
yeah thank you yeah and mary says gratitude one word gratitude and there's a longer
thing dave says let's see um our karma is always subject to revision
yes yes can always choose a wiser perspective
thank you dave indeed yeah so and that was
oh that was from peter hershak east-west center in honolulu
yes beautiful so thank you all we have gone away over time my apologies but these were such
rich and beautiful reflections tonight it was just lovely to hear
all about and share and revel in the planting of seeds and seedlings
and big trees so so take good care thank you all for your practice thank you thank you thank you
for the benefit of yourselves and all things everywhere may all beings be well may all things be
free
thank you all