let's see where was I I was introducing myself my name is May Elliott and good
morning uh here we are in the midst of a week-long study on the foundations of
vipassana meditation so yesterday we focused on the breath and today we'll be talking about the
body so these are the basic instructions meditation instructions one receives
that Insight Meditation Center and many of the western the pastina centers in
California and around the U.S so I'd like to begin our sitting with a
quote and we'll have a little more silence in the sitting today than yesterday my quote goes like this this is from
Kate Johnson the language of the body is sensation
and feeling is the way we listen the language of the body is sensation
and feeling is the way we listen
so let's begin our meditation with a stable upright posture
foreign upright and energetic space to be in an
energetic spine perhaps maybe some lifting in the
neck and pairing that with some relaxation
some ease
you might start by connecting with your primary anchor that might be the breath
a global sense of the body or a sense of sound
for the Simplicity of the instructions we'll just talk about the breath
so go ahead and connect with the breath where you feel it most predominantly
maybe in the chest the belly or the nose
thank you allowing the mind to collect and
stabilize
foreign in order to support us in learning the
language of the body we'll spend some time exploring one particular area in the body
and we'll do this with the hands we'll go ahead and choose one of your hands
and bring your attention to that hand and see what you notice
because the body speaks in the language of Sensations
you might feel tingling
for temperature
buzzing or movement
maybe there's a global sense of the hand there's the whole hand being
not a picture of the hand and the mind but a felt sense of the hand from the inside
and as we feel the hand we're not trying to make it any different than it is
we're not judging anything or telling stories about our hand
just feeling foreign
between their fingers where the skin meets the nail beds
just exploring the territory
feeling the Flesh of the hand
the muscles and feeling the bones
if the sensations are Pleasant that's okay if they're unpleasant that's okay
it's just observing with a kind and gentle awareness
foreign
you can move your attention to your other hand and explore in the same way
seeing what you notice
foreign
s in this way it gives us a sense of how we might feel into Sensations elsewhere
in the body foreign for feeling
temperature pressure tingling sharpness softness
Etc so we can now let go of our focus on the
hands go ahead and return to your primary anchor
coming back to the breath
foreign
so from here the way that you might incorporate more of the body into your meditation
is by staying with the breath as the anchor but when something else feels more
predominant maybe a sensation in the knee tightness in the shoulder
coldness of the toes and something else becomes predominant you can allow your attention to let go
of the breath and to go to that Sensation that New Sensation
the mind can feel that sensation and when it begins to lose predominance and
we return to the breath so the breath is still our home
but the awareness can venture out to other areas of the body when they call
for our attention and then coming back to the breath
you can go ahead and try that now through the meditation
foreign
you can add a soft mental note when breathing you might make a quiet
internal note saying in and as you breathe out
okay oh
and then as another sensation calls the attention we might say
tingling or pressure
foreign
[Music] out
it's just a light mental note with the majority of the attention on the
sensations being felt
foreign
thank you
as we sit attending to our primary anchor the
breath can we apply our attention to the breath
and maintain contact with it aiming and sustaining
the taka and vichara
staying in contact with the full length of the inhale
and the full length of the exhale naming and sustaining contact
foreign
when another sensation arises heaviness
lightness length
whatever it is allowing the mind to connect with that New Sensation
and feel it completely
then returning to the breath
foreign
foreign thoughts and emotions may still arise
but for now we allow them to fall to the background letting them go
dedicating our attention to the breath and the physical Sensations
foreign
thank you
by practicing mindfulness of the body we can learn to be more present in the
world the body is always in the present
we can become more able to be with things as they are
to live with less greed hatred or delusion
and when we're able to do that we can be more available more kind more
generous and more compassionate with others
so may the goodness of this practice benefit all beings everywhere
so they may be happy healthy safe and free
thank you
oh good morning again everyone so nice to be here with you if you are just arriving my name is May
Elliott and here we are in the midst of our week-long study on the foundations of
the pasana meditation so yesterday was on the breadth today
we're talking about mindfulness of body so there was an experiment done by the
University of Iowa some years ago where they made a gambling game that consisted of four
decks and each of the cards in the decks either awarded money or detracted money
and the task of the player was to make as much money as possible
so unbeknownst to the player some of the decks provided great gains
but even greater losses so in essence these were bad decks and the only way to
win the game was to pull from a good deck
44 40 to 50 cards of sampling from all the different decks
before a participant caught on and could consciously avoid a bad deck so about 40
to 50 cards now during the game a participant would
be hooked up to electrodes measuring Biometrics and this is where the study
got interesting um so despite not being able to identify
the good deck until about 40 or 50 cards the participants bodies showed us stress
reaction when they hovered their hand over a bad deck only about 10 cards into
the game so this stress reaction happened long before the player consciously recognized
that the bad deck would would produce a losing hand so 10 cards Ted cards in the body reacts
40 to 50 cards in the player can consciously name the pattern so somehow the body was exhibiting
stress signals some some sense of risk or danger associated with that deck 30
to 40 cards uh before the thinking mind caught on
so for me this points to the wisdom of the body the body is giving us signals all the
time and what what could we learn from the body if we really trained in listening
to it it has so much to teach us
thank you again the quote that I shared at the beginning of the meditation the language
of the body is sensation and feeling is the way we listen
and it's hard to listen we're so often distracted I I used to live at tasahara
a secluded Zen Monastery in the ventano wilderness and in the valley where the monastery
was located um instruments would play to call the residents to the meditation Hall
so when we'd hear the Han this wouldn't block being hit we would know that it was time for Zaza for meditation
and one of my friends would often remark at the sound of the Han oh it's time to
go to the movies uh and I thought that was at because sometimes sitting in meditation can feel
a lot like sitting down to a fantasy film or maybe a drama or a horror film
or if we're lucky maybe a romance and our habits of rumination are a lot like
watching blockbuster hits so when we sit down to meditate
often it's hard to to attend to the language of the body it's hard to actually hear it because it's drowned
out by the films of our mind as we become more settled then we begin
to enjoy the peace and ease of simplicity
the peace and ease of resting in the body we realize that's a blockbuster hits no
matter how enjoyable they seem to be are actually pretty agitating
being lost in thought replaying these movies is a little like being out on the
tiny limbs of a tree being blown about by a storm and this is an analogy that
Gil often shares it's like we've we've lived our lives on the tiny branches
and as we learn to be still and present it's a little like coming off the tiny branches deeper uh closer to the trunk
of the tree it's a little more stable we're blown about less and eventually
we can come we can come right into the Heartwood
where we're not blown about by the worldly lens and we don't need to be blown by them we
don't need to be blown by praise and blame gain and loss
Pleasure and Pain Fame and disrepute the more that we live in the thought
world the more we lose touch with our life as we experience it through the filter of
our thoughts and our perceptions so we end up lacking a sensitivity to our experience so given that we then seek
greater intensity and we want uh louder and bigger and tastier
experiences we need that greater intensity in order to feel anything so without training in being in the body
once we get what we've been seeking we don't really know how to be present
for it and the Buddha stressed over and over
the importance of the body because of because of course the body is
always in the present the mind with its many distractions stirs up a lot of trouble but the body
is always here so our practice is just learning to land in it learning to make our home in the
body in this practice you'll often hear teachers talking about letting go
but what are we letting go into we're letting go into the body
letting go into the body so how do we do that how do we feel it
it starts by making contact just being here learning to love the
simple ease of whatever is seen or heard or spelled or tasted or touched
and to do this without getting lost in commentary about the body is difficult and it can help to be
curious this is something we talked about yesterday when talking about mindfulness of breathing the way that
curiosity is like glue for the present keeps us connected to the present
if we can get interested in Sensations and how things feel we can think about
it like being a scientist kind of like being a scientist exploring the inner world
so uh in the early 90s there was this cartoon on TV called The Magic School
Bus and in it Miss Frizzle the teacher the zany science teacher would take her
students on these unlikely field trips inside the human body where she would do this by shrinking the
school the school bus down to the size of a peanut miniaturizing the students and then they would drive the bus into a
bowl of Cheetos or something like that and then poor Arthur the one student who
always missed the school field trips would grab a handful of Cheetos
and inadvertently ingest the school bus so from there the field trip would begin
and all of the kids in the science class would learn about the anatomy of the human body while literally coursing
through the digestive tract or riding on a blood vessel being pumped through the
bloodstream or something like that so so that's all to say that I sometimes
think about mindfulness of body as a little like being on a field trip with Miss Grizzle and so when we're exploring
the body from the inside I sometimes think of it like I'm one of those miniature scientists exploring the
inner world and like Miss Frizzle when we sit and practice being in the
body we actually are within it we're entering into the human body and
exploring it from the inside they're like wow you know the jaw feels like this when it's clenched or when the
stomach produces sensations of hunger feels like this or this is what it's like when the mouth
feels dry so can we bring the same curious clear
non-judgmental attention that the scientist has to our
exploration of the body
now sometimes when we're investigating the body we encounter something difficult
we encounter something painful so I want to say a little bit about working with unpleasant
Sensations as you practice in the body you may notice that some Sensations are hard to
view it or that there's pain and this is a natural experience of course and our job isn't to reject or
hate the discomfort but rather just to be aware of it you know can we practice being non-reactive to that which is
uncomfortable I think so what's so powerful about that practice is that in doing so we grow our
bandwidth for being with the full spectrum of of difficulty of human life
without being unskillful in our reactions to it and we grow our ability to be with what's uncomfortable without
reacting unskillfully so when unpleasant Sensations arise
we might bring our interest to the pain we might explore the sensations that
make up this idea that we call pain sometimes when we explore closely we
find that there are only moments of aching burning pressure or tightness it's kind of a kaleidoscope of
Sensations and that there isn't actually something there something fixed called
pain just a kaleidoscope of Sensations and sometimes I can
unlock some of the rigidity that the Mind holds around our idea of what the pain is
so if the discomfort for that's a great practice to do if the discomfort isn't
too extreme but if the discomfort is really intense you can also allow the attention to go elsewhere in the body
somewhere more comfortable to rest to a more neutral sensation so this is a way
that we can resource so say if the back hurts we might allow the attention to go
to the breath maybe go to the breath in the belly or go to the feet or such somewhere that
feels neutral or another place that we can go is if there's discomfort in the body we can
pay attention to sounds as our primary anchor and give ourselves a little spaciousness
and of course it's really important to know the limits of our bodies and to respect those limits and not pushing
ourselves to sit in or hold postures that might exacerbate an injury for
example so so it's always okay to consciously choose to move to shift postures to
readjust during a meditation period doing it mindfully doing it with
awareness um such that we can be present and also that we can be compassionate with
ourselves and of course unpleasant Sensations aren't all we find in meditation
we can also experience incredibly Pleasant Sensations you know the body can be filled with
lightness with ease with relaxation or spaciousness
so if an area of the body feels Pleasant you can allow yourself to enter into
that sensation to feel it fully and to be nourished by it
our renunciation practice doesn't mean that we can't experience what's
beautiful so um suffering comes from clinging
right from craving not from meeting what's Pleasant so you can enjoy a
pleasant sensation there's a pleasant sensation in the body you might enjoy it kind of like sliding
into a bath and just allowing yourself to soak there and really take it up
allow your attention to rest in the pleasantness and then of course when that sensation
goes because it will not clinging to it not grasping after
so I think I'd like to end by just doing a little review of how you might
continue practicing with the body this is what we talked about uh what I talked about in the meditation
so we start when we sit down to meditate it can be really helpful to start with mindfulness of breathing we're directing
our attention to that sense of inhaling and exhaling and then from there we expand our
meditation to include other Sensations in the body so the breath is still our
primary anchor that we can begin to include Sensations elsewhere as they present themselves so
we still are have a preference for the breath but when something else becomes strong in the body then we allow our
attention to go to that sensation we feel it until it's faded away and then we return our attention to the primary
anchor of the breath so that's a little bit of what your
um your practice could look like at this phase of the instructions so
I hope that these teachings have inspired you to let go into the body
uh to let go of the narratives of your minds and maybe I come in off the branches off
the tiny branches and enter into the Heartwood of your life
so I hope that you all have a wonderful day today and I look forward to seeing
you tomorrow for a discussion of mindfulness of emotions thank you so much everyone take care