hello everyone and warm greetings
from inside Meditation Center in Redwood City
I say that with uh particular kind of happiness
that I'm back here at the IMC I've mostly been gone for the last month
certainly gone from YouTube and all of you here and uh
and that's nice to be very nice uh to be back and
being able to be have this kind of contact with you and the kind of contact it is for me is that
uh you know I get to share my heart share my my practice my sense of the Dharma
and and it's a I feel very grateful to
be able to have this opportunity and and to be able to share what I have
loved and delighted in so here I here we are
and uh and I'm certainly delighted and glad
happy to be here and I want to use that as a jumping off for our meditation
that there is a role at times
for gladness for Delight for
and maybe as we settle into our meditation here
there's a variety of things that we can settle into or be inspired by or
kind of Welcome us kind of make a welcoming kind of place within
to be present that we want to be present to these good
feelings that can arise Maybe and there is a gladness maybe that comes
from simply sitting in this meditation
posture if you've been doing this for a long time it might be a kind of homecoming
fortunate to be able to have a posture to meditate in and to have that
and you can maybe be at a certain degree of gladness or Delight
that you have these minutes put aside where there's so much
of your life that you don't have to take care of at this moment or you've chosen not to take care of or be engaged in
and it's kind of a vacation a Sabbath stepping away
and maybe there's a gladness for this little bit of time and maybe a modicum of peace and subtleness
peace of not having to respond and react and do and accomplish and prove yourself
and just to be here
and maybe there's gladness and having a mindfulness practice
gladness in her practice where we with time can find our home here in this
body in this space that there's a kind of safety
that we find in being aware being attentive
so that our reactivity doesn't get the upper hand
just to be here breathing and so there is maybe a variety of
things you can be glad about happy about this opportunity to meditate
you might have a lot of challenges you might have physical pain you might have emotional
difficulties that are not very uncomfortable not to deny them or try to
override them but maybe
for these minutes here in the middle of them in this present moment
maybe there's a place where your heart can smile
maybe there's some some things that are
that allow your heart to have a smile and in that smile
to welcome you and to be here and present
so gently closing the eyes maybe closing the eyes so that
that part of you which has the smile or the gladness can be felt more
gently taking some long slow deep breaths gently
three quarters full inhale
and perhaps with the inhale and exhale breathing with
the smile breathing with the gladness
letting your breathing return to normal
and sometimes it's useful to notice the location in your body
from which you're aware from where you'd practice mindfulness
and the seat of awareness
can be changed is variable
without denying how you might be otherwise can you let your awareness
come from the place where you feel a delight or gladness or contentment
quiet well-being
like you're sitting into a nice comfortable easy chair
from which you can gaze upon the world
letting your awareness says take a seat
in the smile of your heart and from here
be aware of your breathing
be aware of your body
be aware of your experience remembering always to know it
in there from that seat Within where there is some well-being
resting there
awareness resting so awareness does not work
foreign
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to consider sitting here quietly
what you might be glad for grateful form
during this sitting perhaps the meditation has has its
challenges for you maybe your body now is uncomfortable
from sitting this long but is there somewhere inside
something that you can are content or happy or grateful for
this chance to meditate to be together
is there some feeling of relief
or appreciation
a smile in the heart
and may whatever appreciation we have from this practice
be a source from which to who appreciate others
whatever ways that we have benefited from this meditation in ways that we know in ways that we
don't know may it translate me would Inspire us
to for greater care and respect for the people we encounter and relate to think
about
may it be that sitting quietly in meditation
has value for how we live our life
may we contribute to the welfare and happiness of others
while doing so for ourselves may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings everywhere
be free
thank you
foreign
um hello everyone and here we are in
and new Monday a new week
happy to be with you and in a sense I bring with you a little
bit of The Last Retreat that I was teaching on that the inside Retreat
Center and ended yesterday and it was wonderful to be at the retreat center in person
and um even more more wonderful to be meditating there and kind of being in
the flow a very very relaxed flow of the practice of
the schedule of the whole life there at the retreat center
so I come here happy with this and also I come here with little bit the theme of
The Retreat and what I'm inspired to share with you this week is what has been come maybe locally been
come to be called the gladness pentad
and I probably thought about this before certainly parts of it and these are five
inner states qualities that can grow as
we develop practice and the way the Buddha presented these five
was not something that we generate or create or construct for ourselves make
happen like we're the in charge and we're going to make kind of pump this up but rather something that emerges
and uh and then begins to flow emerges and begins to flow into each other one
after the other and the role of the practitioner is to know it allow for it they groom for it
and not interfere with the process we interfere with it by getting lost in
thought part of the value of learning how not to be Wonder off in thought and be caught
up in preoccupations is that when we're really here that is
that those thoughts those preoccupations are a dampener they limit they close the doors through
something flowing and moving something can happen that when those are not there
it's kind of like you you know if you're on the on the radio
and you turn onto the channel of the news as horrible as the news might be
and you're going to look um you missed the you know you're tuned into a
different Channel and but you turn it back to the channel where maybe there's some really uh
inspiring music that really kind of touches you and opens you and delights you and and it helps you to be in the
present moment and so uh when we stop being distracted
and mindfulness has developed so we're really here it's a new channel and it's a new
something new can flow and move that can't move if we're distracted
and um and that's part of one of those descriptions of this is the gladness
pentatonin so this is gladness itself that's the first First Quality gives it
its name Joy Tranquility happiness and samadhi
concentration and and one of the Salient features of
some of the description of these is that it doesn't say that the meditator makes
these happen but they from one the other arises the other flows from one to the
other and this idea of flowing or arising flowing is kind of maybe the I think
maybe one of the preeminent ways in which the Buddha talks about the growth the expansion and movement of healthy
states of mind and uh the number of places he uses the
metaphor of uh of uh water flowing in a river
flowing in a stream and um or water flowing
um from an underwater spring into a large peaceful Lake the flow of that
water from the inside out um or really finding the current of the
river and then flowing in the current um or as the rivers go down the
Mountainside and combined they get bigger and bigger and bigger so as these good qualities kind of come together and
grow something within us gets bigger and bigger more expansive and this idea of
the of um of becoming expansive is uh part of what the Buddha talks
about as practice develops so instead of flowing the alternative to this
is uh uh is what uh we uh we could call
reactivity and the reactivity and the kind of in my
language but their activity and the kind of what the Buddha points to is very
different metaphors to describe it here Mr garbage it has fire that burns you he
describes that as a Barb a kind of an arrow that you know pierces you uh a sickness that comes from the
outside and maybe a virus that comes from outside that is not the alien
little bit to who you are but makes you sick um a a tumor
which is also kind of you know not you it's something that's extra uh sometimes
he calls it a burden so there's something outside that's weighing you down like a heavy thing you have to carry
and these are very different kind of uh two different ways in which we can go
through life one which is a burden which is we kind
of afflictive and the other which is uh we're being carried along something's
moving within us that we make space for and allow for this movement
towards freedom and so the way the Buddha describes this
gladness pentad it begins by something that inspires us
and uh sometimes it's the faith or the trust we have in the Dharma and the
practice sometimes that has to do with some experience of of Freedom that we've
experienced not necessarily the Big Bang Freedom that the Buddhism might be emphasizing
but it's just a small ways in which we learn to let go and experience ourselves independent of our reactivity our
preoccupations our our kind of ways in which our rumination is
self-afflicting we kind of repeat the same kind of self-critical kinds of thoughts over and over again and it is a
kind of a burning fire that singes us to have this over and over again
and so to have that stop or cease or quiet down enough that we have a
different experience of ourselves and we're inspired that it's possible
what's remarkable I think for many of us is how we can go through a life growing
up and good part of our life thinking that how the mind is our mind is operating is
normal that's the way it should be and if the mind is involved with reactivity
and what I mean by reactivity is that there's a habitual
uh mental emotional activity that gets triggered by some event outside or some
event inside so you know if I sit here quietly and think about
um you know that um
you know I I haven't had my car oil changed for a while now it's time to do
it and and so that's just realizing that
or there can be a reactivity to that inside like Gil I tell myself
um you're a really lousy terrible car owner you don't really take care of that
well this is a thing that should be cared for and respected and how could you and I get angry with myself and if
that that's an automatic pilot that kind of criticism and anger that's reactivity
and um and then that reactivity then can produce more reactivity so once I get
angry with myself so for being a a you know a lousy car owner who doesn't care
for his car then I remember then I start remembering
um you know that I'm supposed to be a mindfulness teacher who doesn't have reactivity perhaps you know and now I'm
really kind of a bad person because you know I'm at you know now I'm a lousy teacher in addition to it and now that
I'm a lousy teacher then um and talking about it to all of you that you know just I just get caught up
in my reactivity my embarrassment my conceit my ideas and it's possible that some people
that's all they're living in it's just reactivity triggering more reactivity triggering
more reactivity and just swirling around and it's so normal that the mind doesn't
think that anything of it in a sense this is what life is and the reactivity
has some truth to it the the messages from it
to have it all quiet down enough to experience ourselves without that
reactivity where one thing doesn't trigger another harmful thing another little
fire that singes us or a Barb that pokes us but we experience the mind the heart
unpoked unsinged kind of becoming relaxing softening
opening wow this is possible and that and for that to give rise for
the Buddha this this kind of experience gives one of the sources for gladness
for this kind of it's kind of an inspiration oh okay and whether the word is should
be gladness it's the word is and um I kind of like the word delight
um I kind of but we can't say joy and happiness because those are coming maybe kind of a joy it's evaluative in nature
it's the kind of sense of joy that comes from evaluation a realization understanding oh this is a good thing
so it does require some engagement involvement to reflect on oh yes take
the time to reflect on to think about oh this is a good thing this is this I
appreciate this is valuable the nature of reactivity is that it goes
non it can go non-stop it never takes a vacation and so we just go from one thing to the
next to the next to the next and there's no room to pause and stop and just
appreciate the present moment appreciate what can live within us that is not
reactive and the non-reactive life
where something begins to flow has movements to flow is one of the things
that Dharma practice is moving us towards um where we get out of certain our
reactivity gets out of the way so that the current
of goodness that is a ve that lives within us as a potential can begin to flow
and to begin getting an inkling of this possibility and feel it within us
and take the time to appreciate that is allows us to begin feeling a gladness
and appreciation a certain kind of joy that's important because when that
becomes strong enough or present enough in this non-distracted state
of mindfulness that becomes the the seed bed or the the
the the river that grows into a stronger one bigger River and that's for that
grows into Joy from gladness there arises Joy says the
Buddha he doesn't say from gladness now make yourself joyful
The Joy just flows the current so um
so perhaps today you can take a little bit of extra time
here and there through the day to see what it's like to be undistracted
in the present moment to allow yourself to find a way to appreciate
just being present Here and Now and see that if in that kind of letting
go of reactivity and thoughts enough not that you have to stop thinking but enough that maybe you can find some
kind of bubbling up flowing up some little hints within
of of something that wants to flow radiate move
that is good maybe a beginning of a smile
an inner Smile Smile of the hearts
so thank you and uh I'm very grateful to all of you that
you're here to keep me company
as uh we engage in the Dharma together this way thank you