welcome welcome and good evening
it's nice to be here to be with you all
we had a tbd on the calendar for some for quite some while i wasn't sure who
is it going to be who's going to be the mystery speaker turns out to be me [Laughter]
that wasn't the initial plan but i'm happy to be here
so last week gil max ernstein and i finished teaching
this eight month long course that we called the equivalence of ethics
and enlightenment ee 3e
so 8 months 15 homework assignments you know of reading and the students were writing as
well once a month and getting in small groups and
we gave them some prompts to talk about
and so you might think like ethics oh my goodness [Laughter] that sounds so boring why would anybody
do that that sounds tedious it sounds uh i don't know just not something necessarily
one would want to spend so much effort and energy on
but it's turned out i mean it's not a huge surprise for us teachers
but even though i've taught that course before a few times actually that
it's so rich there's like something that's um even having taught it before to
really look at the role of ethics or the way you know and to broaden what does it
mean to be ethical and to broaden it to include just the way that we are in the world
so monday being the last class we spend a little time kind of reviewing some things and
and i kind of combined a few different elements and kind of made up a little bit of a
new way of thinking about the dharma this with having had this experience
because you know we have this expression the dharma and for those of us who
taken refuge quote unquote we take refuge in the buddha dharma and sangha but what does that mean really what is the
dharma and what does it mean to take refuge in it and
is there a way that we could explore this question
that we could investigate by using the perspective
of ethics and i actually would say rather than ethics harmlessness
this idea of not wanting to cause harm
and not exploring what does it mean to not cause harm
and what does it mean to cause harm
so this idea of dharma can we look at it explore it using this as a as a lens
so dharma of course is one way we can understand it is as the teachings
of the buddha so maybe like the the doctrine or the words of the buddha
this recognition that the buddha and some of his senior followers senior disciples
these wise compassionate people that left instructions that left teachings
so that others could find the same way that they have
so we can be inspired by them so we can learn from them
and they're certainly lots of teachings right for those of you who have studied the sutas or the nikayas you know that
there's a whole lot of them in there i myself kind of like enjoy reading them
and looking at them and studying them i for myself getting inspired
and uh here's one verse that's in the dhammapada
it's a collection of verses it's probably what's been translated the most i think there's over 20 different
translations available translations into english let alone all the other languages
and you know what sweat up i feel like that the volume is just a little bit low so i feel like i want to strain my voice
just a little bit to that be a tiny bit tighter i let louder so if i'm just
talking like this can we have it just a tiny bit louder is maybe just a tiny bit
more louder so it's so is is it okay for you guys you want it
to go up or is that an okay sign or a go higher sign
okay thank you that's it i felt like i was straining my voice just a little bit trying to be a little bit louder
okay so in the dhamma part of this collection of verses there's some like there's some really wonderful and pithy
little verses in there and this one goes like this
doing nothing malicious engaging in what is skillful
and purifying one's mind this is the teaching of the buddhas
so kind of just a summary of all the dharma all the teachings is doing nothing malicious
engaging in what is skillful and purifying one's mind
i kind of like this straightforward way and it brings to mind i don't know if
it's exactly the same but it brings to mind the path of practice as silas
samaripanya the path of practice is first
doing nothing malicious sila that is being ethical not causing harm
the second engaging in what is skillful samadhi
samadhi is mental development and meditation concentration and certainly
that's skillful but we could also say skillful is ethics so maybe does it not a perfect match
but the third verse in the dhammapada i'm sorry the third line is
purifying one's mind this could be also considered maybe part
of wisdom is the contents of the mind or the way that the mind thinks
that could also of course be concentration or mental development
but i think what i'd like to highlight now is this first line
doing nothing malicious two other steps this is the teachings of
the buddha i remember when i was in graduate school
studying buddhism i was in a class and i was the only student who was a practitioner of
theravada everybody else was a mahayana practitioner mahayana is the leader buddhism
and the teacher the professor now i don't remember what point he was
trying to make but he asked this question okay so if you could
could you just use one word to describe the dharma
about his teachings and i thought sure it's easy it's just harmless and it's like do no harm that's
you know three words three monosyllabic words this is really simple
it turns out it's not so simple right because we had a classroom and every single person there in the classroom had
a different idea and the mahayana people some of them i didn't even know what they were talking about
so even though that i'm it's we might want to simplify it
doesn't mean that everybody would agree but for me this idea of do no harm
even if it's not i don't know the absolute fundamental
i think it's a fantastic provisional fundamental teaching or a way to be like
why not because do no harm sometimes we think about doing no harm is like you know treating
others with respect and not cutting them with knives or shooting
them with bullets or something like this but it's also about ourselves
and so much about this practice is we start to see the subtle ways
in which we harm ourselves the subtle ways in which the inner
critic criticizes us or the maybe subtle ways and sometimes we
abandon ourselves when difficulties or maybe the way that we don't take care of
ourselves even though we it's good for us to eat well and sleep and exercise and
meditate you know it doesn't mean we always are doing those things and it's not because we're intentionally
wanting to cause harm but part of the practice is just recognizing or becoming sensitive to
oh yeah this way isn't the way that leads to the greatest
freedom the greatest ease the greatest peace
so there's another in the suttas also there's a way in which the dharma is described
and it's described as this is part of the teaching that the buddha says and
it's when other people are describing the buddha they say oh he's one who teaches the
dharma that's beautiful in the beginning beautiful in the middle and beautiful in
the end i feel kind of inspired by this that's
something that's beautiful through and through and so we might think harmlessness too
also has this beauty maybe this grace
something about it that you know that where we can be safe and others can
be safe maybe there's something beautiful about that
so the dharma as the doctrine kind of summarizes some of the teachings
of the buddha and of course of course one of the key teachings is
the four noble truths many people would say that this is the
key teaching of the buddha we can consider these as
pragmatic perspectives that help us guide us in the world and
understand the world and concerned with suffering and the end of
suffering and i know
for me the very first time i heard this was not when i was expecting that it was a
in a yoga class i had no interest in buddhism i didn't even really know what buddhism was
but the yoga teacher said turned out to also be a dharma teacher i
didn't know that that didn't mean anything to me at the time this person had a lovely accent from
minnesota and i just uh so have this warm-hearted feeling towards people i have a really
thick mint i can't mimic it but a minnesota accent
acknowledging that there is suffering
and well all these years ago sitting there on my yoga block i feel like
oh what a relief that somebody's actually talking about
something real and not pretending that everything is okay or
saying how things should be or aren't really
there's a cause for suffering things arise for a cause they're not
magical and importantly there's an ending of suffering the third noble truth
and of course the fourth noble truth is the eightfold path there's a way
leading to the ending of suffering it did occur to me what would it be like
if there was not this fourth noble truth oh yeah there's ending but
there's no way to get there like it would just be very different right it would be uh
this practice this would be more just about faith or something
but maybe we could just boil all this down to if you stop doing something that causes
suffering the suffering ends pretty simple pretty straightforward
and so of course in the four noble truths and all these different ways in which we talk about suffering
in this buddhist tradition this is a a word that stands in for such a wide
range from just the acute physical that's suffering that humans can experience the
cute emotional suffering anybody who's ever had their heart
broken knows this or a left one die knows this kind of end of the spectrum
but also the other end of the spectrum this feeling like there's something that's just not
quite right and i don't know what it is
but it just doesn't feel completely satisfying or doesn't feel quite right
so suffering is this isn't a single word for this whole range
but what if we use this word harm instead of the word suffering
and if we considered the same thing whereas suffering has the flavor of maybe of
something we experience and harm as more the flavor of something
that gets done either done to us or we do to others
but this same idea of tuning into the presence or the absence or what causes
harm and the same way that the four noble truths or
these pragmatic perspectives
of using the word harm instead of suffering there is harm there's a cause for harm there's an
ending of harm and there's a path leading to the ending of harm
there's a way in which we might interact or engage with the formidable truths in it
and maybe a little bit different way and acknowledging that harm so often is
unintentional sometimes we think about it primarily as
uh being intentional if somebody is willfully
harming others but to think about kind of the unintentional
highlights some of the ways in which we harm ourselves that are
not so easy to stop these habits
these compulsions these
just simply not being present for what we are doing and recognizing that harm
causes from that
and these habits and these compulsions and not being present can be an expression of the clinging or the
craving which can be a cause for suffering of
course and because of harm for ourselves partly because we're not present for what's
happening or we don't have [Music] the capacity when we're really clinging
on tightly to stop the momentum of the mental habits to stop the
momentum of the emotional habits that cause harm
so to tune into and recognize the ways and that we might
be causing ourselves harm not because we want to give one more reason to
beat ourselves up or to feel like we're failing or not doing it right
but just to recognize that sometimes when we recognize that when
there's harm arising there can be some compassion there can be some tenderness
like oh yeah this is this is dukkha this is some harm is
being caused by my holding on so tightly to a particular
idea or a belief or
recently i was at a um
a group of where there was a group of people and i showed up having this idea that you know okay i have this
particular role and i'm gonna behave this particular way that's you know appropriate for that
role but i didn't realize that nobody else thought i should be in that role
and it's quite something right as long as i uh i was hanging on to this idea of like no no i'm the one that does this
and you guys are the one that do that and you know what this is how it's supposed to go but
you know it just was a misunderstanding but uh just this recognition like oh just let go
let go diana of this idea that you had and that just was really great it was
such an obvious way to see like how many times am i are we are people holding on to how
we think we should be or what's expected from us and then our environment and how
other people behave doesn't necessarily match and the suffering
the harm that's caused and of course the four noble truths have
the fourth noble truth as the eightfold path
and if we look at the eightfold path we can see that four of the factors half of them
have a concern with harm the second one right intention
includes with it non-ill will that is some not causing harm not having
hostility and causing harm towards others
right speech right action right livelihood all three of them are associated with ethical behavior
which are you know one way in which we don't harm others
maybe we could stretch it a little bit and say some of this right mindfulness and
right concentration is a way in which to help us not cause harm to let the mind
and the body to settle down
so the eightfold path is a way in which we can consider as a
in through this lens as uh to help us not cause harm
intentionally or unintentionally
so one way we can understand the dharma is as the teachings and includes the four noble truths and
includes that pithy little statement from the dhammapada but another way we can understand the
dharmas not just as some concept or some idea
that's you know existing out there in the ether somewhere just as language or
thoughts intangible but the dharma is also something the way that we show up in the world the way in
which we interact with the world
through the way that we live because
there's a way in which with certain skills or intentions
the way that we that we are allows the dharma to be expressed
allows the dharma to have a role in our lives
so not so not only is a dorm as a concept but the way that we show up
and here's another quote from the dhammapada
goes like this not by harming living beings is one a
noble one by being harmless
to all living beings is one called a noble one
so to be harmless the word here is ahimsa of non-violence so to not have any
violence to be acting with harmlessness is to be a
noble one that ties in with the four noble truths
maybe some of you know that there's a number of ways we can translate that expression that's often
called the four noble truths but it could also be the four truths of the noble ones
that paulie allows for that translation as well
so the noble truths of the or the truths of the noble ones
and the noble ones are the ones who are harmless
for noble truths can also be the four enabling truths
there is something ennobling about being harmless
the uprightness the
the steadiness the clarity that's associated with not
causing harm right the sensitivity enabling
but with our as we practice the dharma with our spiritual maturity if you will
our sensitivity to harm grows it increases
and we begin to notice it in subtler and subtler manifestations or
and we become more sensitive to that contraction to that tightness that a little bit of
sense of something's not right here when we're considering causing harm
or when certainly when harm is when we harm ourselves or somebody else has harmed us
as well and then particularly that gets heightened uh highlighted when
as our practice develops we also become aware of the spaciousness the ease and
the increased freedom that's available as possible
and so as we notice more spaciousness we can notice like oh the contrast with the constriction that
happens that's associated with harming this constriction can
be also expelled i'm kind of like a tightening but it also can be felt kind of like as a disconnection from others
or maybe even like a disconnection from ourselves
and as our practice deepens not only do we we become more sensitive but we also become more
motivated we start to see and experience and
acknowledge what's possible
as we start to touch into some areas that have more peace or start to have
greater understanding about ourselves or others then we feel more
motivated to not cause harm as the maybe the goodness that's inside
of us the goodness that's getting cultivated that's getting tapped into with a dharma practice
as this opportunity to get expressed in the way that we are showing up in the world
so we can also understand the dharma as something arises with our interactions with the world and
and with the harmlessness the way that we show up
not wanting to hurt or harm ourselves or others
maybe a third way that we can understand dharma is
kind of as a natural law or as a truth or as the way things are
and part of the natural thing or the way things are or
something that all humans experience if not all beings is a wish to be happy
i wish to have ease and peace and freedom
and certainly the dharma is about this
and so this wish to be happy gets supported by one of the
buddhist teachings about the bliss of blamelessness
of not harming others
and this knowing that we haven't intentionally caused any harm
gets expressed in this excerpt
one accomplished in ethics sees no danger in any quarter with
regards to their ethical behavior so seeing no danger in any quarter that
means not in the north not in the east not into the west or not into the south
so the way they're talking just no danger anyway
instead they experience a blameless bliss that comes from maintaining this
noble virtue this feeling of safety if okay i haven't
done anything wrong and not only the safety but the
confidence that that gives to somebody
to know that you don't have regrets or if it comes forth that somebody
was harmed or something unfortunate happened as a consequence of your actions or something
you said or something you didn't do or didn't say
what a good feeling to know like oh okay that was certainly not my intentions
that was just i wasn't aware i didn't know i misunderstood whatever it might be
but this bliss of blamelessness kind of helps support the
dharma law of uh humans want to be happy
and also there's a one more quote here from the dhammapada
goes like this always awake are the disciples of the buddha
whose minds day and night delight in harmlessness
again this word is ahimsa so somebody is talking about
that the minds of those of the followers of the buddha are delighting in harmlessness
this kind of uplift that can happen that it knows when we're
not harming so what's really important about this is
this idea you know i'm talking about non-harming and the dharma
reading quotes from the nakayas and it could be
one way to interact with this which i think like okay i have to never cause harm and
if i do that means i'm a terrible person or something like this
it's so important that the manner in which we engage with these teachings be consistent with the teachings
it's not helpful for us to set up a impossible standard
and to chastise and beat ourselves up when we don't meet it that's not what the teachings are the
teachings are about being present for our life
being present for our experiences having that intention having the motivation to
not cause harm and when we discover that we have caused harm we
make amends we do what's appropriate and we go on to the next thing
we learn from it and we go on rather than carrying it around with us
and beating ourselves up that helps the that kind of carrying it
around and ruminating and getting stuck with
it there's a way that kind of doesn't allow us to learn what we need to learn
and move forward instead there's a way in which we get
stuck if we turn it into a story about being a
bad person or being inadequate or unable or something like this
but instead this harmlessness maybe another word we could say is good
will care warmth
kindness so can we have this for ourselves
and for others a key part of the buddha's teachings
right is this open-heartedness this warmth warm-heartedness
and certainly that's harmlessness let's care
so can we have that for ourselves as well as for others
i can have that for ourselves and it's the way that we're practicing the dharma
so no matter how we define the dharma it's whether it's the teachings
whether it's the way that we show up in the world whether or not as getting expressed
through humans in the world or whether it says kind of the natural laws and one of them is that people
beings want to be happy i tried to express it in terms of harmlessness maybe it was a little bit
of a stretch but in some ways how is it not
how is it not is the dharma as being in harmony
not in conflict with what is and with others
and in this way we can take refuge take refuge in the dramatic refuge and
not causing harm and may our doing so
be a support for not only our greater freedom but
for the freedom of all beings everywhere
thank you
so i'll stay up here for a few moments if somebody would like to ask questions otherwise i wish you all a really
warm and safe evening thank you