there okay so so hello and welcome everyone hello
friends it's lovely to be with you um it's so comforting and really soothing
and happy making to come together in the sangha and and practice even
if you've been away for a while or your first time warmly warmly welcome
so so so for today's practice um
[Music] i like to
to offer a practice of returning to our center returning home
returning home returning to our center with metta
so returning home returning to our center
to [Music] especially this especially important
when we lose our balance whether
challenges of the day challenges of the environment external
internal whether they're challenges or other events when we feel like we've
lost our balance we've lost our equanimity we've lost our meta we've
lost that our center so the way
i'd like to invite us to practice with the practice of meta loving-kindness
today for ourselves and for others is a way of studying is a way of studying nourishing
nurturing the heart um and bringing this aspect of equanimity
it's bringing this aspect of equanimity so
so that is the invitation and there is not much more i'll say because whatever you need to know will be offered to you
in the guided meditation so whether you're new or experienced
as they say relax and enjoy the ride and whatever
arises whatever arises is what needs to arise given all the causes and conditions of
our heart of our mind of our life and as long as you have kindness
towards whatever arises even if it's a crowd of sorrows that bring up
or distraction or sleepiness as long as you bring kindness
to what's arising that helps you cultivate meta cultivate stability
whereas if you get whipped out of shade like oh i'm trying
to meditate here and i'm distracted ouch that's that's even makes you even more uh unkiltered
um so whatever arises as long as you bring kindness to it it will help you
find your center find stability and peace right here right now so that we
can be of service to the world to others to ourselves this person knows me just be of service it's
much better place to be in place of stability to serve
our life others than a place of reactivity so
i think that's all i want to say to set the stage for our practice today so so with that i'd like to invite us all
to to shift into our meditation posture
you need to lie down that's okay you need to sit up straighter
or stand up or anything that this body needs in this moment in order to be comfortable for the next
30 minutes or so the guided meditation
so landing landing in this body
landing in this body in this moment let's find
[Music] let's find the center of our gravity
checking in with the body
let the center of the gravity be lower
not in our head in our thoughts but lower lower lower
maybe in our abdomen ah
in our sit bones
and from our sit bones from where we are sitting and let there be a sense of verticality
a sense of uprightness
as if there is this centered
the centered pull that
goes through [Music] that touches our sit bones our heart
our head connected to the earth
all the way energetically maybe it's just this
brightness the sense of ah
settledness
and again let the center of gravity be low releasing relaxing the body
maybe for a few minutes we'll just sit
with the breath that's moving up and down through this axis this vertical
axis connecting our heart
to our head to our gut to the earth
finding our balance finding our center
let the breath move on its own along this axis
freely if it needs to be if it needs to hang out in the sit bones
area let it relax release the sit bones
your seat maybe it needs to hang out by the heart area
to release relax the heart the seed of the emotions
or if you're feeling sleepy at this point maybe the breath
gives a sense of uplift opening the heart the head the mind
through whole body sense of vitality uplift
more wakeful energy
and if there's anxiety present or nervousness then
let there be more attention given
the lower part of this axis vertical axis your sit bones your feet the earth
grounding grounding settling [Music] finding your center your balance your
grounding ah touching the earth
let the body be relaxed released it's easier to be at our center
the body the heart the mind is at ease we naturally
naturally fall into our center
stop stirring it up
just being breathed
maybe like the buddha sitting under the bodhi tree
when mara distractions doubts challenges
we're assailing him he touched the earth this earth be my witness
i belong here i'm here
sense of groundedness stability centeredness home
let your whole body touch the earth your heart be connected
through this vertical verticality of this axis
and as we let our heart our body be breathed
one breath at a time
with each breath
we return home we find our way home we feel at home
at our center
in our humanness with our goodness
our intentions to grow to learn
to love to serve
to continue to be better versions of ourselves better angels of ourselves
with each breath connecting
to our heart to our center of being
our center our home
goodness kindness good will as her home
place to rest are tired mind our tired heart
our tired bodies
and welcoming kind place
this chamber a safe chamber
and if challenges arise sadness
or self-judgment anything arises in this while your
home in this chamber of safety in your heart let them feel safe too it's okay
oh self-judgment oh the statement it's okay rest
rest ah rest in the love
the care and the warmth the complete acceptance here
in this home [Music] this chamber
this refuge of the heart
feeling nourished feeling calmed
it's okay it's okay sit rest
rest be breathed reconnect
be held
with kindness
aspiration
goodness love
the essence of friendliness for yourself
for all of your life
can you welcome yourself wholeheartedly
this lost beloved who is you who is yourself
as if reunited with yourself welcome
or have you been sweetheart rest relax
feast on your life feast on the goodness
that is here
holding yourself as you would hold a dear dear one
with care with appreciation if you're tired
if you've been working hard invite yourself to rest
in your arms holding it's okay sweetheart it's okay
it's okay what do you need
welcoming yourself home
what happens if you really welcome yourself home
with kindness with complete acceptance for just a moment see what might happen
what might open up
with kindness acceptance just as you are
in this moment
welcome home sweetheart there's nothing you need to do or be
it's hard enough just rest
may you know that you're loved and accepted just as you are
let your heart be nourished
uh
safe safe in your own heart
a place of refuge kindness acceptance
maybe even forgiveness
if it's needed
and can everything else feel safe in the space the thoughts
distractions perhaps aches pains
random sounds it's okay this place of refuge
everything touched with kindness
with an open heart embraced
home kindness metas are home
healing soothing centering centered in kindness
in generosity for others for ourselves
centered in aspirations
home centered
home
by coming home connected oh maybe a sense of trust arises
sense of stability trust
confidence
emerges
and as we bring this sit
too close together connecting to your heart again
[Music] to your body
to the sense of alignment verticality connected to the earth
rising up to the heavens expanding aspirations
with open arms and offering generosity kindness to
whatever arose or did not arise this practice period
you showed up you did your best it had to be exactly as it was
given the causes and conditions and together offering offering our
practice offering our goodness as if
we're spreading confetti over the whole world
joyously offering this goodness to all beings everywhere including ourselves
may all beings everywhere feel
centered feel at home in their own heart bodies
mind feel soothed nourished
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
be free
[Music]
thank you all thank you so much for your practice
what a gift what a gift that you show up you show up
you show up again and again for yourself and for others what a gift
what a gift
the buddha says that the gift of the dharma is the highest gift
and some people think of that as just teaching the dharma or dharma gifts or books and
but actually this showing up this practice that you show up this is a gift
of the dharma this is the gift of your practice is the highest gift it's the
highest gift that you make of yourselves you offer yourself up
so beautiful so beautiful such an expression such a beautiful expression
of your humanity so so we have
time for reflections if you like to raise your hand to share your reflections as a gift
to the sangha you can also type in chat if you type it to me privately i will
only read your offering not your name if it's typed to everyone then i will read both
your name and the offering debra i see your hand please um i've been typing a lot but today i
just want to gush um i had
i just want to say that tonight's practice i was just so present to
this balm for the soul that this practice offers and that you
offer and it was particularly
um strong for me because i've had dental surgery
and i i went off the pain meds this morning but whenever you finally lie down you
realize the pain and so i jumped up at the beginning of the
meditation and i grabbed a tile and all because i realized oh it's coming back and then
as you were speaking i just like held my my jaw
and i hadn't i hadn't gotten down to that level of realizing like
i've hurt my body you know this really hurt my body and so i sent all this loving
kindness there and yeah
just was like a balm thank you so much and i've searched in other places you
know i used to go to green gulch and i always felt like
i wanted to find a loving prep a loving buddhist practice and i
hadn't experienced this until i started coming to the insight meditation center which
i'm sure it exists elsewhere but thank you
thank you so much debra for sharing ah beautiful thank you
yeah and and surgeries just trauma to the body it's it's hard right it's
and when we sit we realize oh this sweet poor body you're traumatized it's just it's not just the jaw or the teeth it
affects the whole nervous system yeah so welcome home deborah welcome home
yeah soothing bulb thank you thank you so much
jesse please thanks yeah this was a really amazing
practice i love the imagery of coming home and uh
your you mentioned self-forgiveness and coming back to center
so timely for me um my mom mentioned to me about eight days ago
she's bringing up some end-of-life paperwork my mom's 76 years old and in
good health i'm really grateful that she's being proactive about it but i just felt um clenching and tightness
in my chest and just feelings of overwhelm and grief and uh just this whole idea of coming
back to center coming home and self-forgiveness for any duka or suffering
that arises and you know this is why i've been practicing all these ideas about impermanence and recollection of
death you know are coming to bear now and i i just also want to share another gift
i have right as you said something like you know can you accept yourself as you are
some type of ambulance emergency siren went by which is unusual
for my suburban neighborhood and these dogs started howling and it's just there's just this
evocation of impermanence you know it's like yeah this grief and this overwhelm this arises and it passes away just as
because you also mentioned sounds you know random sounds at the same time so wonderful practice and thank you for
getting tonight um thank you jesse thank you so much so beautifully beautifully said
thank you [Music] thank you for your practice
[Applause] balm for the soul mima
hi nikki thank you um i think this practice tonight was like so rich
um i was like like um initially um i've been learning how to rest i i've never
known how to rest and so tonight when you were talking about resting um
and i've been learning how to do that it was like oh my word this is like so perfect for me right now
and what i really appreciate it was when you mentioned that about even inviting judgment to rest like all of the the
things that could come up you know to allow it come here let's rest let's just be right here and the kindness of about
how we approach it how we we can approach it with kindness and it reminded me something about um tiknon
han something i heard this weekend was you don't have to know what it is is treat it with kindness whatever it is
that comes up treat it with kindness so i really felt like it um it tied in a lot for me
that um i was able to even turn it on myself and my heart just welled up i cried it was
like yeah be kind to me be kind to me i i'm tired i am tired and i need to be
kind and it just like released my tears and i was able to rest in that and let it go so thank you tonight was really
really rich thank you thank you and and thank you mima thank
you you thank me and i thank you and everyone in the sangha for their practice thank you so much for your
beautiful reflections and sharing your practice yeah yeah and we're often tired we're often
life is life is life right
in the past i've said that we every one of us deserves a purple
heart medal for being human it's it's not easy being human this human realm
it's not easy for every single one of them i mean of course of course there's they're joys they're 10 000 joys and then there are
10 000 sorrows and challenges yes sweetheart you are tired sweetheart yes
yes yeah yeah beautiful thank you mima thank you
so dear ones uh bill has asked uh was this coming home exercise the
same as concentration
not necessarily not the same they're not equivalent
there is an aspect of coming home keep coming back keep coming back that could be a part of a practice of shamatha
samadhi concentration but the way i was leading it today was
was more coming home to sense of rest heart ease i was
emphasizing that that aspect of it so um so there was a little bit of i think
with with practice concentrate there is a sense of coming back resting so there's a little bit of that but they're
not the same there was a venn diagram there's some overlap with the practice tonight but
but uh not not the same yeah yeah so
yeah um so dear ones dear sangha
dear happy our family whether you just join for the first time you're part of this family you're here
so the invitation we have at this point is is to connect with a couple of other
members of this sangha with kindness it's where the rubber meets the road
um so just offering kindness to yourself offering kindness to others
and um and the soothing balm can we all rest in
a soothing ball can we all rest in a soothing balm together and the invitation is in the small
groups to offer maybe one thing about yourself how the practice was speaking
from the first person experience one nugget then the next person will say
one nugget and then the next person will say one nugget and they'll come back to you so not a long monologue but just one
nugget knowing they will come back to you and just from your own experience not
asking questions or directing or facilitating just offering europe offering your own humanity as a gift to
the sangha here i am and also if it comes to your turn you can say pass and just hold silence
that's perfectly fine too if you want to offer witnessing and kindness
kind witnessing to the sangha so so with that as our intention for
practice tonight i will create the break breakout rooms take care of
yourselves take care of each other be kind and enjoy enjoy the few minutes of
conversation with sangha it's precious so here we go
okay all right the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
so we have just about a minute for any concluding reflections or
comments from practice to night or or sharing in sangha tonight any
any last reflections you like to share or questions or challenges anything is welcome you can type in chat or raise
your hand
dave hi nicki thanks i was trying to remember
there's a phrase you used for the pilot you know
so when you make a mistake like i just did in clicking the leave breakout room
button when i didn't mean to you you then you start piling on yourself
and injuring yourself there's a phrase you've used it's much more succinct of uh how you hurt yourself after
hurting yourself ah um self-flagellation i don't know or or a
selfie second error yeah that's it thank you oh yeah yeah yeah second error it's not my phrase
it's the buddha's teaching so he gets all the credit i'm just repeating it back but actually there's a whole sutta
about the second era it's a beautiful teaching it's a beautiful teaching about
how we engage and it has to do with the teaching of vedana actually that beautiful set of vedana being the
feeling to unpleasant unpleasant neutral when there's something unpleasant we just pile on and we we add the second
and third and fourth arrows so yes it's the second era and yes rada
and deborah and neil all of them are jumping i love it i love it this song is jumping in with with the
answers i love it i love it this is so sweet yeah thanks for bringing that up dave that's great
second arrows yeah beautiful well thank you so much all of you thank you for
sharing for your practice for showing up um may you be well may you be happy may
you find your home when it's been lost come back to the center with care with love
thank you all let's dedicate the merit again may all beings be well may all beings be
free [Music]
thank you all take good care i'm going to stop the recording i'm
going