head gopal in Sunnyvale hi Papa
hello hi Nikki it's BRAC from Mill Valley oh
hi Brack you were just at the retreat didn't you yes yes wait welcome to happy
hour thanks sweet
I heard you welcome great oh no wait I I think I think what just happened I
started a live stream and I hadn't muted myself and I heard EU Bupa one more time through my earphone never mind it's the
funkiness on my end and bunch of people are saying hello in Chad hi Bill and
Wayne and Christine and hi Katrin and and Amy and Claire and Bruno and
goodness Pat from Seattle and Jamie from his car I love it I love the locations I
missed a lot of the locations but thank you everyone and hi Don you're back in Pakistan ah it's what time is it there
morning no what time is it there
7 A.M good morning to you Don great great lovely that you're joining us how
sweet how sweet wow well the Sangha has assembled I feel the song assembling it
warms my heart welcome to everyone whether you are an old-timer
or um or if it's your first time at happy hour welcome welcome and hello Marcella
as well and thank you Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google Groups if you are new to happier
we have a Google Groups um where information is shared quotes
are shared it's low on traffic and high in heart I like to say so
and um and Neil just posted the the link um so hi welcome you're welcome to join
if you like to be like a part of this community well if you're already part of this community so now we transition
after the hellos after warming the space uh with our hellos it's a way of
um yeah warming a space with our meta saying hello and greeting bringing our greetings is is really for me it makes
my heart Happy like oh yeah all of us are coming together new faces
oh familiar faces spaces to be familiar all of that so now we do a formal
beginning form will start and before I start the um uh recording for for Audio
Dharma and I change the settings for chat it will only come to me I ask you to mute yourself if you're not muted
and I change the mute settings and um and also even though uh the chats can
still come to me I ask you to not send any chats during the guided meditation
and um and the uh the the darmet because it can be very distracting for me but
after a result change the chat settings and and Reflections are all welcome so
so last thing I do is I turn on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
here we go okay so welcome welcome to happy hour
I've missed you all I've missed you guys um and and I've been
not far I've been steeped into Dharma last week I was teaching a residential retreat at Spirit Rock on befriending
mortality unmindfulness of death which as many of you know is a topic that I love
and death these are the two topics I love to teach about and many other ones but these two special especially so
so the topic I wanted to bring in for our reflection tonight in in meta in
loving kindness is um is perhaps inspired from the retreat but
is also um inspired from some Reflections I've
had in my own life um uh recently today um and that is you know with when we know
our time is short and with uh the practice of of meta is one way to
beautify our mind a way to Glad in our mind for us to learn what it means to
Glad in our hearts glad in our minds both in Daily Life as a resource and
when we have challenges when we have difficulty when we have pain when
um and of course a death bit too but but really it's it's it it's a support for for our life learning how to beautify
and glad in our mind through meta and kindness for ourselves and others
and also the way that this other reflection of brevity our time comes in is is
um as you reflect as you as we will do in the guided meditation together with
mindfulness of the body and the breath as we will settle in um but the practice of you know life is
short what's what's happening right now in my mind stream what's happening am I stressed am I worrying am I having ill
will feelings like if this was my last moment in life so it was my last breath
is this what I want to be spending my time doing worrying or or
planning Ad nauseam and and um you know how do I want to be spending
this precious time if this were my last moment How would is whatever is happening right now is
this how I want to be spending it is this what I want to be cultivating and of course menta thoughts of kindness for
ourselves for others love forgiveness um vicarious Joy all the Brahma viharas
Equanimity are all these beautiful states that both beautify them the mind
and heart both for any moment where there's the last moment of Our Lives
last breath or also as we as we create our own Karma as we weave the future
moments as we precondition the future moments so if we if in this moment we
have a kind thought a generous thought a thought of forgiveness Etc all the beautiful hard qualities we precondition
ourselves to have more of those feelings and thoughts towards ourselves and
others in the future moments whatever thoughts you have now precondition you to have more of those in the in the
minutes hours days years to come so
so lots of ways to relate to this to the to the beauty to the to the value
of practicing the Brahma vihara's meta um meta loving-kindness compassion
karuna muddita vicarious joy and upeka and
um so so I think that's all I want to say for
to set up to set up the stage for our practice tonight and then let's just practice together no
let's No More Words let's let's well there'll still be guided meditation boards but no more darn it let's
practice together so
I like you I'd like to invite you I would like to invite you to settle in
your posture for practice
ah sitting
relaxantly sitting upright allowing your back to be straight
as if it's pulled up by an invisible string
sense of Integrity sitting up like a mountain
letting your feet be stable in the earth touching the Earth
creating your sitting bones sitting belts where what you sit on
connected to the Earth via the chair or the cushion
and releasing releasing the weight of your upper body releasing
on to your sitting bones foreign
a few minutes just feel the bottom of your feet and the Earth the bottom of your
sit bones connected connected
where does the Earth beneath my feet begin
and my toes end
feeling the weight
we might have seen helium balloons that are lighting and Light
go up in the sky and often there's a weight there's a
weight attached to the helium balloon
to bring stability to it let your body be that weight that counterweight
that stabilizes the helium balloons of thought
distractions your body it's a wonderful counterweight
let yourself enjoy the breath
enjoy the breath moving through this body
when the Mind enjoys what it's doing when the heart enjoys
the practice it relaxes like a baby
who's well cared for ah well fed
Let each breath be nourishing filling your body with
Sensations
thank you
foreign
balloons keep drifting it's okay no problem no problem
maybe you can untie some of them and let them float free
it's okay that's right release them
back to the body to the breath ah so calming soothing enjoyable
nowhere to go nothing to do
just enjoy appreciate
being here being breathed
thank you
foreign
spend another couple minutes just settling releasing releasing the body any tension the body
forehead ah jaw neck shoulders hands chest
abdomen set bones legs feet
releasing releasing with each Opera
we become grounded present before we turn to meta
a couple more minutes
foreign
[Music] the feeling
stability especially as you release
ah like this holding grasping
[Music] taking refute
in yourself
and the Infinity of this moment
and the Buddha nature of this being owes me and the Sangha
community year year
and now let's turn our hearts our minds our
attention first gladdening our heart our heart mind our chitta in poly translated as
heart nine
gladdening via reflecting our own goodness on our own goodness
to hear a city seeing yourself externally
from the outside this person knows you
you'd be reflecting on something kind of generous we've done recently or some time ago it
doesn't matter maybe an act of forgiveness or generosity
however small doesn't matter or maybe you
said some kind words to someone or to yourself
maybe you did something nice for someone help them out
and maybe you're kind to yourself
and give yourself a hard time about something very gentle forgiving
reflecting on the goodness of any of these
as if it were your best friend you're appreciating
and let it in let your own goodness in
and appreciating also now your intentions your intentions for cultivating kindness
compassion wisdom
generosity all the any values
that are important to you any beautiful values
friendship support
etc etc integrity
virtue
let yourself see this recognizes goodness
from this place of goodness let your heart your mind your heart mind be uplifted
aspiration aspiration for goodness uplifts the mind uplifts the heart
thank you
foreign
goodness wishing yourself well
may this goodness Within Me increase May the aspiration for goodness
made increase may it never rain
may wish myself more goodness I wish myself well
and similarly bring to mind
someone who's dear to you may be a good friend
a benefactor anyone from whom you've received kindness
you appreciate them their goodness and appreciate their goodness
their inner beauty their kindness their wisdom
let yourself feel uplifted that such goodness exists
in the world such kindness such friendship such care
such a brightness virtue whatever it is
appreciating appreciating this this being this person
their goodness
whether present or past doesn't matter
there has been this goodness in your life on this being exists or has existed
let your heart be uplifted
uplifting the heart
and from this place of goodness appreciating goodness wishing this person well
or letting feelings of gratitude arise for them
uplifting uplifting your heart your mind this is heaven
this is heaven this is the Brahma viharas heaven on Earth
and now maybe you get to see your own goodness through this person's eyes
how do they see you how do they see your goodness your values your inner beauty
let yourself see your goodness through their eyes don't shy away
who are you to get in your own way
however they see you appreciate you respect you love you let yourself be seen
as if reflecting through these mirrors them seeing you you seeing them seeing
you let yourself appreciate your own goodness through their eyes
what they see in you
let your light shine Let It Shine
by letting our light shine
the goodness in us not belittling it
but by seeing and appreciating appreciating it it's not an act of ego
but seeing goodness helps goodness increase
brightening the heart and mind
feeding feeding the goodness the brightness
thank you
and from that perspective wishing yourself well
may this being who's me
may they be well and including the person this this dear
being whom you're including wishing them well too
May both of us may we let our our light shine onto the
world our goodness
may we support each other in more goodness in the world if possible
and if you as if you were witnessing observing lots of points of light
lots of points of light on this planet Earth
lots of points of light so if you're an astronaut from the space
all these points of light all these beings all these human beings
beings with their values with their intentions
so many beautiful intentions
let your mind see the good let your mind open up to the
wholeheartedness to the good so many beings who care
for each other on this planet they care for loved ones family
at so many so so many acts of care so many acts of care across the globe
and if your mind goes towards but but there are challenges and
cruelty yes I know we know but in this practice right now
returning towards the good to uplift the heart and mind
the other practice can be a practice of compassion another time right now
seeing the good yourself
in the world many other beings so many
blessings so much goodness so much giving and receiving
so much generosity from this place wishing wishing all
beings well may all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere be well
may they wake up just as I wish to wake up may all beings wake up to their own
goodness
may all beings letting myself appreciate how brief how brief our life really is on this planet
how little time we have to
act in goodness
make a change even if it's just small change for one person
may we all wake up to the preciousness
and the goodness enormous
you all before I open the space for reflections
I wanted to share a little uh story that my co-teacher Beth shared on the um
Retreat we were just teaching and I paraphrased it um it's a Zen story
and it goes something like this but um incense stories there's
often there are two archetypes there's the um the warrior archetype and
um and a monk archetype so in this story there is a a samurai a warrior but
um that is very full of themselves and uh goes to a monk
and says you know something like um tell me
everything you know about Awakening tell me everything you know about
Awakening in the Monk [Music] um
says oh to you something like that I might be
paraphrasing but the punch line would be the same so bear with me so so the the
monk says what to you so it doesn't really show the samurai the respect that he feels he deserves so in the ramp
Samurai gets gets really oh yeah I think the question was tell me everything you know about
Awakening in heaven and hell maybe something maybe that was the question hey I have to look up the the but anyway
the punchline will stay the same so so the summer I will get really really angry and and
um he pulls up his sword and is about to to
when wants to cut the the the head of the monk off and the monk still with a
lot of equanimity stands and says Ah that's hell
and delighted at this Insight oh yeah this is a state of hell I'm angry and wow how
quickly that happened and I don't want to be angry so a sense of a smile shows
up on the face of the summer I haven't gotten the wisdom the Deep wisdom oh yeah that's that's uh what what hell is
and so he smiles and the monk goes that's heaven
so such a simple description of heavil
Heaven and Hell in this realm in this body and the Brahma viharas it the
gladdening of the heart our Heavenly States and when we're angry and and
upset or blaming or self-recriminating or so many difficult states of mind
that's hell that's hell so it's helpful to just call it that sometimes if you
find yourself in this hellish states of mind like oh sweetheart this is hell
this is hell do you really want to be in hell do you want to be perpetuating states of hell
um drop it just drop it and turn you have a choice turn the Mind towards wholesome
States wholesome states of Mind towards Heavenly states of mind
forgiveness kindness um so I'm sure there are many questions that
can arise but I'll just leave it at that and open now for for reflections
well what came up for you in the meditation question you can either type them in chat or you can raise your Zoom
hand because if you raise your physical hand I will not see you there are many of us but if you raise your Zoom hand
then I can see your questions comments uh complaints it's all welcomed
okay so any Reflections from the the guided meditation
Stephanie says great meditation thank you Stephanie oh and I see Katrin raising their hand Catherine
um hi hi great to see you again thank you
I was just on a retreat and the practice was so much about being with whatever
arose without judgment and so I wonder about like the third punchline of that
story because he asked three in the way you told that he has three things so then what is Awakening oh yeah I didn't
tell it well very well I think he might have just asked about heaven and hell or maybe he just asked about Awakening
there was no a third punch line I appreciate I feel good in myself
[Laughter] being like um that and I don't know if you would
agree but that Awakening is is holding Heaven and Hell as maybe all one or or being in
Equanimity whatever's arising and how that's not contradictory to cultivating
uh wholesome states of mind
yes yes and I think that is beautiful yes um yes and
I think Awakening holds that includes that but it's more than that it's not just that
it's not so I wouldn't equate Awakening with Equanimity I think Equanimity is a
um uh something that arises is is something arises from from Awakening and also
Equanimity leads to States a week but they're not equivalent so I wouldn't say that Equanimity is Awakening yeah but
yeah they're definitely definitely related but I think the point you're really trying to make is is not
um to to um yeah so so so yes there is and I think
it's an important one and I expected someone to bring it up and I'm glad you have Katrin which is the sense that yes
these whole unwholesome states arise and by shaming ourselves and pushing them
away it doesn't really help and yet in our practice we do try to cultivate wholesome States and yet on wholesome
states are going to arise so how do we work with them skillfully and one way to work with them skillfully is through
Equanimity and there are many other skillful ways to to work with them but I think the point you're trying to bring
in as from The Retreat that you just saw it is not to shame ourselves because of the negative states of mind and
absolutely that's an important point yeah but to work with them skillfully
with wisdom with mindfulness with with vipassana and also with compassion so I
think that that point stance yeah two more hands I see Jesse please
oh yeah thanks for this practice today um yeah I wanted to ask about I think normally this works pretty well
for me in this practice um but what was coming up really strongly for me today well I wanted to
ask about pre-practice attachments this experience came up for me where it's kind of cute I
think when I was four years old I had a balloon tied to my wrist and it flew away and I lost the balloon and I was
really sad and you know so at the time I was like I'm four years old and I really wanted this
balloon it was really important to me and but that was coming up now today in this present moment experience and I
just I didn't really it didn't feel appropriate to be talking about Duca and letting go to
this four-year-old child so I was just wondering you know about when memories come up you know from
childhood you know that that are you know pre-date you know my Buddhist
practice like how to practice compassion in those moments yeah yeah yeah great I appreciate I
appreciate that and and it's and maybe it came up because in the invitations I was sharing um
uh you know the the image of you know let the balloons fly away and maybe that
that helped bring in this memory that you had many years ago in the sense of grief and then the Letting Go came up so
so um um I I think there are multiple things
you're what you're asking again and and just to be brief I think one is when there is a four-year-old well there's a
four-year-old that you couldn't talk to or couldn't be talked to about letting go and just things things come and
things go but but now that four-year-old within you you can't talk to them there is an older and wiser Jesse who
understands things arise and pass away so that's part of reparenting ourselves with kindness with compassion so it's
actually quite a gift that this came up because there's something in there that
can be a younger version of you and that those deep memories to to re learn
yourself with kindness with care uh the truth of impermanence
beautiful thank you thanks Jesse Fred please
thank you um welcome back Nikki it's it's great to have you back thank you uh
as I was picturing the people who I
in envisioned being purveyors of kindness and uh and other good things
um I feel them very richly and uh with a lot of detail and a real felt
sensibility there's nothing theoretical about it when I return to myself it's not as though I'm I feel like I'm
um I'm not skeptical of those virtues in myself but I don't experience it with the same richness as I do looking at
someone else and when I tried using the eyes of the other person to see me like
that didn't quite pull it together for me either and I wonder if you have a yeah
yeah thank you thanks for sharing that um I wonder when you tried the eyes of the
other person instead of just your own eyes directly whether that was any more effective even if a tiny bit
more effective in saying your own good tiny bit tiny good tiny bit is better
than zero yeah that tends to help actually that tends to so so
um I would say Fred hang in there with that with seeing yourself Through The
Eyes of another but really really taking their perspective like letting go of your own perspective completely and
seeing really doing perspective taking and it can take a little while and and
this was a relatively short meditation but really taking a while to do that perspective taking from their
perspective something kind that you just and then really feeling into it yes they
really see me as kind or generous or thoughtful and that thing I I did for them yeah that really made a difference
to their it's a really lean into the perspective taking and can take a little
while but but don't make it just black and white because I think we just did the graphite a little black and white drawing but really pull out the
watercolors and and make it as as as um as Vivid as you possibly can okay
thank you thank you Fred thanks so much there was one and one last oh we should go into to practice
if it's too late but one person has asked about how people confuse kindness
for weakness which not true because kindness really uh includes ourselves as 360 degrees so
um it's that that often comes out with a sense of confusing kindness with with weakness and and maybe I'll talk more
about it next time but it's um you know kindness is 360 degrees and includes
yourself and when you are kind to yourself you're not letting letting people um take advantage of you so so we do we
need to I turn to small groups right now otherwise we'll have no time for the
breakout groups folks so so thank you for Reflections thank you for um everyone who's spoken so I'm going to
make the groups and here is the invitation the invitation is that we will um
um speak about you know something about a goodness some some other person's
goodness having seen their goodness what does it feel like when you see someone else's goodness how does that how how
does that light up your heart when you reflect on and really appreciate someone
else's goodness um and and I think through that we can
um yeah I think that's what let's just say that's prominent actually I realize that practice me the small groups are
going to be pretty short tonight so it might be just a quick round going around and again just speak from your own
experience and the next person then the next person will go alphabetically not directing not asking questions it'll
just be a 30-second monologue no reflecting on someone else's goodness what came up for you in this practice
um so I'm going to open all the rooms take care of each other take care of yourselves here we go
foreign
thank you
their rooms will close in about 15 seconds we'll wait until everybody's back
okay the rooms are all closed everybody's back and
it's seven o'clock we had lots of Reflections and and
um so I think respecting the time let's let's close let's close now thank you
all for your practice for joining to Gladden your minds and hearts in service
of both yourself and all beings it's when our minds are uplifted
um and filled with goodness when we see our own goodness we can be better Force for good in the world
better than serve better anyway may all beings be well may all beings be happy
dedicating the blessings the Merit
thanks everyone take good care