greetings friends greetings good morning good afternoon good evening
whatever the time zone might be delighted to be with you to
feel your presence spread spatially
but the same temporal time um the same same same temporally same
time but spread in space so today uh day two of our exploration
of the refrain of sati patana which you've been studying thoroughly
and systematically with gil so
what i'd like to offer today and invite us to explore is the uh so yesterday i
tried to set the frame a little bit i set the frame a little more today but the importance and the significance
of the um the refrain and then we'll explore the
first sentence of it and i'd like to invite us to explore this first
statement this significant first statement in our practice together also
so [Music] so the first
sentence in the frame is in this regard in this way
in regard to the body one abides contemplating the body internally
or one abides contemplating the body externally or one abides contemplating
the body both internally and externally
so i will decode that i'll talk more about that in
the dharmad but in the guided meditation i'd like to bring in some invitations
for us to explore this invitation of internal external
together uh in in one aspect not not every
teaching of the sati patana there are so many of them but one of them or maybe a couple of them to have a taste of what
this might this might feel like and what might mean so
so without further ado let's let's sit let's practice together
so let's arrive let's arrive in this body
in the seat landing arriving comfortably
arriving in our seat in this body
releasing releasing
releasing whatever is not helpful right now we're supportive releasing thoughts
releasing plans for the future
or preoccupations from this morning releasing releasing
[Music] releasing
not out of it should but releasing
because of love because we love to do this we love to practice
we love to cultivate our heart in peace
and kindness for ourselves and others
to cultivate insights
so out of love releasing
ah and relaxing into the body relaxing here
this body [Music]
when the body is relaxed the mind
can relax more easily so relax the body
is there any if there's any tightness or holding anywhere
ah releasing
with the out breath
and taking refuge refuge in this moment
the simplicity the beauty of our intention here here
in our hearts here
let's take a few minutes to arrive in the body
releasing relaxing taking refuge together
when the thoughts arise entanglement arise so release
release and return release and return to this moment here
no need for self-judgment
beating yourself up oh i was gone for so long no need no need just release
release and come back to the refuge of this
heart in this moment begin again begin again
relax into the body
feeling the breath in the body internally
this life-giving breath
the entirety of the in-breath the palms
the entirety of the out breath the pause
the entirety of the breath felt sensed clearly known
clearly known clear comprehension
in this body without making it effortful
let it be known let it be known
the breath
this breath internally
the breath internally this life-giving breath
throughout the body nourishing
bringing life the breath being sensed unknown
taking one more moment to really grok to really
know let it be known capture the sensation of the breath in this body internally
as if it were your first breath
or your last breath
the breath known internally
now relax release
and bring to mind let's first bring to mind someone maybe who's near and dear
to you you have an easy relationship with
and let their breath be known this external breath be
known to you they breathe just like you
as human beings
as you know your breath internally
knowing this breath externally by this other human being
life-giving breath
how it might feel for them you can even perhaps in your mind's eye
imagine them breathing seeing them breathing deeply shallow
shallowly
and now expanding this external knowing
of the breath to as many beings as you wish in your mind's eye
many humans all breathing
the breath known externally
and if it feels overwhelming then just stay with one other being another human
or animal breathing
externally
and now exploring the instruction [Music]
of knowing in the body internally and externally
as you know your own breath this breath being known
the body the mind be relaxed
and knowing also externally
this other being in your mind's eye
the breath known internally and externally
known thinking analyzing just simply let it be known
as if perhaps you and your friend
were breathing together both breaths known internally and externally
continuing to know the breath and internally and externally
maybe at some point the personality of the breath drops out
and is just a breath not me not mine not
internal external it's just breath breathing happening
internal external just breathe
don't try too hard just
let it be known first internal external the insight might reveal itself on its
own when the time is right
my breath breath
their breath their breathing
may just become breathing
breathing internally breathing externally
internally and externally
as we bring the sitting to a close
may the goodness of our practice together all of us
in this moment in time
it's coming together different places
and all the breaths all the moments of awareness
all the dedication to goodness cultivating goodness
gifting dedicating offering this goodness
generously to all beings everywhere
who just like me just like us breathe
depend on this breath to keep them alive
especially those who live right now in areas
that are not safe in war zones
wishing them safety ease and breathing in peace
may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so today day two of exploring the refrain of the
satipatana which in some way
is i don't want to say more important as important is very important
so just to remind us
of the refrain i will put up the uh diagram from yesterday again this is
from piccolo nalio's book page 17. um the name of the book is sati patana
direct the direct path to realization and it's also i put this up
on audiodharma associated with this week's teachings actually with yesterday's teaching so you can look it
up so the refrain shows up this refrain
this important refrain shows up after every teaching after every teaching
shows up 13 times and just to say a little more about the
significance and then focusing on the internal external that we've done today is um
so this refrain as i mentioned yesterday it both
talks it expands each teaching it does three things after each teaching say
after breathing after um postures after activities anatomical
parts elements etc it it both
adds a spatial aspect which is internal external and it also adds a temporal
aspect which we'll discuss tomorrow when because the the refrain talks about
arising and passing and arising and passing so it brings a temporal time
aspect to the study of the phenomena
and and also what another thing that's significant about this and i'd like to point point out about the refrain
is that it is worded um not with respect to the individual
content so after the section about say breathing or actually let me put up this
again so you can get a sense of it here we go okay so like
in the there are six sections in for the body breathing postures activities etc
after the teaching especially on breathing the refrain
goes back to the body says the body it talks about the body after postures it
doesn't say postures it's the wording refers to the body
so so as i read in this way in regard to the
body one abides contemplating the body it doesn't say you know one abides like
so there's something about oh the bigger picture the bigger picture it invites us
to to to and um contemplate the bigger picture so the idea here is
and let me stop the share here some commentators say that what is
significant here about this going back and forth is that in each teaching we
focus on the content but coming out the practitioner is invited
to to study to be aware to be mindful
of the general characteristics of the experience and when we become aware of the general
characteristics not the detailed not the not the thing itself
but the fact that it's internal external it's everywhere and it arises and past
it we shift from a content studying the content to studying the general process
and when we study the general process that's when insights about anitcha
du ka ananatta impermanence unsatisfactoriness
and impersonality not self pop out and that's something i was
gently inviting you to explore this morning if it perhaps maybe for a split second popped out for you
and if not no worries when the mind is ready the heart is ready it will be seen
the insight will will reveal itself so so i quote john engler in this regard
who says his opinion not mine but i think it's interesting to see it this way the
reason he says the reason western meditators tend to progress more slowly than their
eastern counterparts is the tendency to become absorbed in
the content of awareness rather than continuing to attend to its process
becoming preoccupied with individual thoughts images memories
sensations etc rather than keeping their attention focused on the essential characteristics
of all psychophysical events whatever the content a tendency to
confuse meditation with psychotherapy and to analyze mental content
instead of simply observing it and you know this many of you know this
already it's not so much about the content is it the process it's the arising and passing
and also this internal external which is often not taught
or emphasized so i want to focus now after taking more time to set the frame the
importance of of the refrain
um left over from yesterday what i wanted to say today i want to now
speak more about this first line about this practice of internal external which again
comes in after every teaching in the satipatana pretty wild right
so so the the internal external
can be applied to every aspect and in fact in the commentaries in um
in the vesude maga in the path of purification commentary especially um
the the it is taught in the um uh internal external
for every aspect of the satipatana so it could be applied to the breath to
the postures internally and and oh just to say internal here of
course means our bodies external in this case means other human beings or other beings other beings
so observing our own breath their breath our posture their posture our bodily
activities body theirs body parts elements the cemetery
contemplation internally externally um [Music]
vedana mind states as well as the aggregates and i'll share you a share with you a
personal story here since we're talking about this um the first time i practiced this
internal external i didn't even know this was part of the teachings years ago when i practiced with
with my um teacher park sayada who teaches very very detailed vipassana
from the abi dhamma and the visudi maga and my instructions for days
was to to contemplate the body part the the
32 body parts internally first internally first you do it internally
until it becomes really really really clear
and then and then really clear until actually one feels that wow this body is
just body parts it's like sack of grain it's just sacko grain
rice and this and that it's just body parts and then the instructions were to okay now
externally externally all other beings not just humans but where i was practicing their
their uh chipmunks and things like that oh externally the instruction was
oh all beings internally externally all beings too body parts just like me just like me
then start to see all beings walk actually body parts starting to walk around which is very interesting way of
seeing the world we we usually don't see that way but it is
just as valid to see any other way just as valid to see in the other way there are all these body parts moving around
and then internally externally something pops out wow the impersonality
the impersonality of the this body these body parts
so so when we start satipatana as i read
this line starts with contemplating the body internally so first we do it
internally to establish to really get a sense to establish also um
some mighty concentration the body the mind settles and then it has the ability to go externally and and investigate
uh or see the same phenomena externally
and and it's also said that external also could
for these various aspects see observing other people's postures their
facial expressions their tone of voice when you get to feelings and state of mind for example uh the
the next few weeks uh you'll be studying say state of mind and
and uh and the dhammas the aggregates internally externally
is a suitable practice for daily life is a suitable practice because one
perhaps one issue that some people point out or maybe they feel when they they do a lot
of internal practice is they become too internalized like oh i'm just interning
like don't bother me i'm just practicing internal whereas the instruction
is internal external internal external internal external so so that we don't risk becoming
self-centered uh and only aware of our own self
and what's happening internally but also open aware of other people's
feelings of body behavior and and how our actions how our
words actions our internal state affect other people's
state of to become more aware of our impact on the world through this internal
external practice internal external so the external practice is so important
as here laid out as the second step first internal then external observing
the world others other beings their state their state of mind their state of
breathing etc and then the third step and um this is so
important i want to say it again the the third part uh the third phrase when we're
invited to to um uh the the wording is uh let me get the
exact wording one abides contemplating the body both internally and externally one
abides contemplating the body both internally and externally
and some commenter commentaries say since we can't do it at
the same time you go back and forth okay that's one way but another way what happens actually is you notice yourself
when you do internal and external when you try to hold it together and even go back and forth
wow a sense of objectivity arises it's just
a body is just a breath the sense of objective the sense of subjective stance
drops out and an insight towards not self towards
this universality of whatever phenomena we're observing
the universality of the phenomena pops out so it's not just the thing
itself anymore it's the universality of it that that arises
i cannot emphasize how important these practices are the the refrain
the internal external so today my invitation is as you go
through your day through your life daily life practice external
mindfulness practice external awareness both internal internal what's happening
internally externally what's happening externally for other beings internal and external
and see what a different shift in stance that can be
and tomorrow we continue with the next sentence in the refrain
which has to do with impermanence with arising and passing away which is quite
profound also so thank you all thank you for your kind attention for your dedication for your
practice may you be well and may you practice internally and
externally see you or feel you tomorrow
be well