okay so we'll go ahead and get started now good to see everyone i think you all
know that um gil is on retreat this week so i'll be here for the five days of this
week and i'll be continuing with our you know the the theme for a while now
has been the sati patana suta and so that's about mindfulness so um
we'll take a little interlude this week to look at mindfulness as a
protection and in particular we're going to look at some images from the suttas the sutas
are totally rich with images for mindfulness there are so many similes so many
metaphors and i thought we would just look at some of them this week
with this theme of mindfulness as protection protection of ourselves
protection of others we'll look at different aspects of it throughout the five days of the week
there's so much protection that comes from seeing clearly which is
the function of mindfulness you know for example we don't get swept up by strong
feelings or high views in our daily life we probably experience that ourselves
also when we have some clarity and clear seeing we have a choice about how we respond to
what's going on in the moment and you know we can see
and feel quite clearly the harm that comes from unwholesome states and so
then it's natural to choose the wholesome becomes much easier ethics become clearer when we have mindfulness
and also we have some wisdom that comes with it we can allow things to just arise and change
and pass thus essentially freeing ourselves from them
through mindfulness and then we can also help others by being stable and calm and
present that automatically brings some benefit to others around us even if they aren't practicing themselves
and you know getting to the greater matters of life mindfulness allows us to
meet aging illness and death with some presence and clarity these things that
we know are inevitable for us as humans so that's a wide range of wonderful
benefits that come from protections really that come from having
some presence of mind so that's what we'll be exploring this week different aspects of that day to
day so why don't we go ahead and sit
so finding your meditation posture
allowing yourself to settle in [Music] perhaps closing the eyes if that's
okay for you
maybe taking a long slow deep breath and allowing the body to soften and
relax on the out breath
i'm just feeling into the stability of where you're sitting
proceed against the chair or the cushion
your legs or your feet against the floor
and just taking a moment at the beginning of the sit to
sense the alignment of the body so you can even rock back and forth a
little bit or forward and back just slightly to really find that middle point
sometimes in front of the computer screen we tend to lean forward a little bit so you might particularly pay
attention if you need to settle back at all
and then just allow yourself to be supported by what you're sitting on
and gently softening the muscles of the face the expression
on the face
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
down through the neck and the shoulders letting the shoulders release
imagining the shoulder blades sliding down the back
and softening down through the chest area the heart the lungs
rib cage
the belly
down to the hip joints
and the arms and legs letting go of any bracing or tightness
so just inviting some ease in the body
and then turning the attention toward the sensations of breathing
just however the breath is coming in going out
for many people breathing is something that feels safe
and so we can consider the breath to be kind of a home base
for the mind and if for some reason that is not the
case for you you can also consider the body posture
just the sitting posture and the feeling of that as the home base
i'm just having this sense of resting
sometimes the resting of the body can encourage the
mind also to find
some some degree of rest
and when the mind inevitably gets lost in thought
there's no need to criticize but we can just bring
back awareness of the breath with a sense of returning to safety
sense of now i'm home again
so the mindfulness is mostly staying with the breath or the body
just a simple breath meditation but we can notice that the
mindfulness is protective in the sense that
it will notice when the mind is moving off the breath
so the mind is moving out toward getting in trouble
often and so it's actually the awareness that
is doing the protection
but we just use the breath as the home base to help us have that protection
and as we settle in a bit farther
and there's a bit more mindfulness even just a bit more
we may begin to enjoy this sense of protection
we maybe begin to feel that the mind has a little bit of strength or resilience to it
and that has a pleasant feeling and it's fine to enjoy
that sense of mindfulness
even if what we're mindful of is some pain or
even a busy mind we know that as long as the awareness is there
we have some protection some benefit even
often when the mind wanders it's going off into the territory of
wanting or ill will
or confusion
and even just knowing that it's already protection but we may find
that bringing mindfulness to wandering thoughts
they naturally just fade
there's something about noticing them that
them
hello
this mindfulness that we cultivate on the cushion [Music]
carries out into our daily life
likely we've seen that
as we see it as a protector
it will continue to serve that function throughout the day
so it can be helpful still to have some kind of an anchor or a home base
as we move about the day i often use uh the body
so the general feeling of my body
wherever i am that's certain to be in the present moment
so that can be the place to help orient the mind to
and then having that awareness is what is the protection
so when we're there in the present moment and aware of how the body is
we're less likely to get caught up in what someone is saying to us
or in extraneous concerns letting the mind
wander off into anxiety or excessive rumination
and then we can enjoy that sense of knowing that we're in the present moment
where it is really the only place we can be safe
even if what's happening is not to our liking
we know it's safer to be there [Music]
and somewhere that isn't so real
and we still have a choice about where to put the mind within the present moment
but you might consider that as you go about the day how is mindfulness protecting you
serving you like a good friend
and this will automatically help others we'll talk more about that as the week goes on but maybe for today just
staying with the sense of it as protecting yourself
[Music]
so this week we will continue to talk about
this wonderful quality of mindfulness but the theme will be different aspects
of mindfulness as protection and
in fact i wanted to show you you can see on this wrist i have this red
cord on this one i have a little white cord these are called protection cords and
you may have received them at some retreats or other
other buddhist event and i'm remembering that um one time
the teacher uh i think it was john travis asked was he when he was receiving one so what is this protection
from and the monk who was giving it to him said it's protection from yourself
and i've i found that to be a useful idea in some sense they're just pieces of
string but we can conceive of them as protections from our self and i think as
we practice we come to understand that that is useful
that's a useful image so speaking of images this week we'll be
looking at images or similes from the sutas that relate to mindfulness
and there are a lot and you know as i was sort of looking through and collecting up the various
images it was clear that that protection is really a theme and
different aspects of it so maybe i'll just talk for a moment about
the value of these images and similes that there are in the sutas i don't know
how many there are but there are certainly well over a hundred different images used
for various qualities and experiences in the teachings it's clear that the
buddha was a kind of a a teacher who liked to evoke that
aspect of us you know the images the feelings
the our connection to them and often the images relate to things
that are quite accessible in in life you know images of
simple feelings that we have or well of course many of them are agricultural from you know his time but
we can imagine that fairly well still and they're meant to be i think quite
experiential you know we're meant to have a sense a really a visceral sense
of what that image is pointing to and that may speak to a different part of our heart than
just hearing words or or having ideas so that's one of the reasons to look at
them carefully they speak maybe to the non-rational aspect of us
which is not the irrational aspect of us but the non-rational hopefully you can
see the difference and it's possible i have found that
these images maybe i read them at the time and i think oh yeah okay that that makes sense i can
kind of feel that but sometimes they can really bubble up during a sit you know the mind will we
read something about fear and then um and it's nice in the moment and then during a sip maybe when fear comes up
that same image will suddenly have meaning i've found it's like oh that is what that was referring
to that's exactly what it feels like wow and so i hope maybe you'll take in some
of these images um and consider just store them maybe store them somehow in your mind or your heart
and see if they come up for you sometime
so each day has a theme which is some aspect of protection and we'll be looking at these images sometimes one
sometimes more than one each day that relate to a certain theme so today's protection related theme
is called guarding the scent stores and so that is it's about mindfulness as a
basic protection for our self and guarding the scent stores means
taking care with the eyes ears nose tongue body and
mind such that inputs to those senses don't overwhelm the mind
in buddhist teachings there are six six cent stores those ones that i named
so one basic image that's used is
the image of six animals that are bound together by a rope and so the animals are a snake
a crocodile a bird a dog a jackal and a monkey
pretty different kinds of animals and so you can imagine that
what happens is each one wants to go in its own direction each one tries to go toward its
natural place and when he wants to go up to the trees and the bird wants to fly and i think it says the snake wants to
go to the ant hill but anyway they're all going in a different direction and if you just tie
them together with a rope and let the rope go uh the strongest animal is going to win
and they'll all have to go that way and so this is the the the idea here the
metaphor is that the six animals are the sixth sense faces that each want to do
something different our eyes are going somewhere our ears our mind and so if we're just you know
willy-nilly let that happen what kind of whatever is the strongest is what we'll end up doing
and that's really not so helpful but that might be kind of how we go through our day when we're not mindful
so then the contrast is to have the same six animals bound with a rope but they're tied up to a stake
and the stake is put in the ground and so then what happens is the animals can't actually go
and eventually they get tired and they lie down so the image says and so the same thing
is if we have mindfulness of our senses then our sense doors
then we don't get drawn off and they're not running off in different directions you know we can just hear things but we
don't start thinking about that and worrying about that or being angry about the thought about the sound and so
eventually things will settle down quiet down we can maybe see this sometimes in meditation
also applicable in daily life when all of our when we have all six senses operating
so then um so that's maybe one way we can think about how mindfulness guards are sent
stores prevents them from running off but i want to also talk about another
nice image that's more specifically for the sixth sense store of the mind which
is the one where we often get in trouble i think we can see so this is one that's from um
mn19 uh a suta about thoughts about different kinds of
thoughts and so when we have many different thoughts in our mind that are related to the
hindrances um actually the suta says they're related to sensual desire ill will or
cruelty but we could probably include all entrance related thoughts since i know you just talked last week with gil
about the hindrances and so when we have a lot of thoughts like that
it's a kind of a drain on the mind and if we keep track of what we're thinking
with mindfulness then we can kind of redirect those unhelpful thoughts
and the image given is that of a cowherd who is trying to handle a pack of cows
does it ever feel like your thoughts are like a herd of cows going in different directions
you've got to try to kind of keep it together so the image is like this it says just
as in the last month of the rainy season in the autumn when the crops thicken
a cow herd would guard his cows by constantly tapping and poking them on
this side and that in order to check them so the idea here is that it won't be good
if the cows get into the crops and eat them and so the cow herd stays close to the
cows i'm kind of poking them this way in that and when the mind has a lot of these thoughts then in the same way we
have to kind of guard our mind carefully by doing a lot of noting practice for example or really paying attention to
those thoughts each time they come and maybe one thing to note also is that
the cowherd is not angrily beating the cows to get them back in line
he's just tapping them gently but firmly and so if we do that in our mind and we
gently but firmly you know note okay nope not gonna go off into anxiety no
not gonna ruminate about my housemate etc uh as we do this the mind will tend
to settle down the same way that the six animals get tired when they're bound to the stake and eventually settle down
and then the nice thing is that we don't need to be checking so actively with the with
the mindfulness the mindfulness also can change and so there's another image given in
that same suta again about the cow herd and it says
just as in the last month of the hot season when all the crops have been brought inside the villages
a cow herd would guard his cows while staying at the root of a tree or out in
the open since he only needs to be mindful that the cows are there
so it's a whole different image right the cows can just be
you know out in the field because there's no crops left that they're going to eat and so the cow herd gets to just rest
under a tree and just kind of watch that they're there and in the same way if the mind is in a
more skillful place having thoughts of non-ill will non-cruelty
um thoughts of generosity uh it's fine just to know that those thoughts are there
or maybe it even settles down enough not to have very many thoughts and then we can just be calmly present
so this this protection that's called guarding the scent stores
could be quite active or it could be quite relaxed it depends
on the state of the mind and what sort of external inputs and internal thoughts we're experiencing at a given time how
we need to be mindful of them in order to guard our senses so over time
we'll find that we can be with more and more challenging situations mindfully
so the mind gets less reactive overall and so we'll find that the
the nature of guarding changes throughout the course of our the long
arc of our practice as well as you know the short-term arc of just how the mind is right now
so the hope then is that during this week we'll
build a picture out of different images of the many ways that mindfulness serves as a protector
and today we looked at this idea of guarding the scent stores of not letting the mind run out
in the same way that seems like the images are about animals the same way that animals kind of wander off
if we don't uh keep track of them so i hope that's a helpful
image for you to get started on today or maybe it's later in the day for you
but consider maybe consider today what it would be like to guard the scent stores with mindfulness
and to see mindfulness as our our simple protector
so thank you