there okay so welcome everyone welcome to this
rendition of happy hour lovely to be with you lovely to be with you
ah so so for today's practice I'd like to
invite us um with a practice that I want to call
seeing ourselves as whole seeing ourselves conceptualizing seeing
accepting loving ourselves as whole or list or for just for Simplicity
seeing ourselves as whole and
not not that we go around the world and always the first conception is that
we're broken in some way but sometimes there could be a sense that either there's some either physical
challenge we have or or maybe there are some ways that we are um
um highly say um [Music]
we we self-flagellate we are judgmental of ourselves because of oh you talk too
much or you talk too little or you love too much or you love too little or you're too this or you're too that just
all these things you know the self-judgments um and
and in some ways maybe we don't see ourselves as whole sometimes there is something not quite maybe there's some
challenges or or say trauma there has been in the past so and if any in any
way we don't see or conceive or of ourselves as whole or if say there's a
back pain so we see our limitations we focus on the limitations of this back pain or or this physical condition or
our aging right oh yeah I don't have as as much energy as I used to so all these
ways that maybe we don't see ourselves as full as whole
as whole what if what if we tune what if we choose intentionally not to be
pollyanish that's not the intention at all but given that the Brahma vihara is
the the practices of the heart are cultivation practices or cultivation
practices where we cultivate a particular way of seeing a particular
way of saying we cultivate to see through the eyes of kindness Through The Eyes of Mecca compassion
gratitude these this is what we cultivate little by little by little so
these are cultivation practices whereas with mindfulness with inside practice with a vipassana we see things as they
are but then again one I argue and it is true that we're still seeing from a
particular perspective we're seeing things from a particular perspective even though we're not we're cultivating
to see from a particular perspective
um with non-attachment with with Equanimity with with ease with curiosity
with non-judgment so there's still some cultivation is going on in Insight it's not just seeing things as they are we're
staying in a particular way but anyway I digress especially in the practice of the Brahma
vihara as the practices of the heart meta compassion
vicarious Joy Equanimity we are cultivating a particular way of seeing
particular way of being in the world and what if we actually choose to tune
into to tune into what is whole
what is whole what is beautiful what is strong what is lovely our own loveliness
our own strength our own goodness or this particular way
of seeing as a way of cultivating yes again not
condoning that yes there is work to do and there's cultivation to be done and
yet by turning to see what is good what is whole what is whole
and this way of seeing what is whole can be about are our goodness our
wholesomeness our kindness and mouse could be about or the way we show up in
the world this the physicality of the scent just the way we sit because sometimes actually not sometimes but
they go together our phys our embodiment goes together with our state of mind our
state of our it's [Music] um there's a lot more I can say about that
I'm going to tease myself bring myself back so that doesn't become an R long darn it but um our physicality or
embodiment is so important in the way that we show up in the world it affects our embodiment impacts our way of being
our way of being impacts our embodiment so both of these are important so so as
a way of working with that I have a particular invitation that I will bring
in tonight so um and it's it's inviting the embodiment
of the Buddha um or the Quan Yin the the
icon of compassion of the to bad
embodiment that's seeing ourselves as that or we can choose any any being
living being alive or passed away maybe the Dalai Lama or Martin Luther King or
Gandhi whoever really speaks to you that sense of oh yeah seeing yourself as a whole seeing yourself as whole as good
as as complete as as as loving physically
in your heart so those are some invitations I'll bring in little by little so that's that's the that's the
uh perspective we will cultivate tonight so
all right without further Ado let's practice together let's uh
ah let's land in our bodies let's arrive
in our seat together foreign
feeling or
bottom on the cushion our hands our hands on our lap
the sense of uprightness of the Torso
been releasing relaxing releasing any tightness or holding
connecting with the breath let the breath move through the body
now the beginning is always we always take a few minutes to settle with the breath with the body before
turning into invitations of cultivation just arrive
just enjoy being breathed take refuge and
a moment of non-doing just sitting not doing being breathed
let the breath be sensed known in your lower abdomen it helps to calm
and settle the mind
letting go of thoughts of whatever has happened today what might happen later plants
just quiet enjoying the silence
as much as it is available Within
foreign
foreign foreign foreign
letting the breath enter your body as if a song as if a lullaby
your favorite tune maybe an Arya
or Whatever It Is song of birds
connecting with goodness connecting with beauty
with wholeness with each breath foreign
foreign foreign foreign
foreign
foreign of sitting be a refuge Let It Be
nourishing
nowhere to go nothing to do and to just
sit here and be nourished by the breath
it's quite simple
foreign
center of gravity the center of gravity of your awareness be dropped down down down into
your lower belly not your head
ah maybe that will release your shoulders
your jaw might be a release with this
releasing into your belly to your sit bones
foreign
feeling your body feeling your hands your feet
your sit bones your belly
dropping down
dropping dropping everything that's extra in your mind just drop drop it
gently dropping not needed
foreign
and while you stay embodied feeling your feet your legs
abdomen your hands with each breath
invite the Buddha
[Music] Paragon of compassion kindness or any
other being Living Earth
no longer living
invite them invite them into your heart
invite them or as if you are actually entering their body as if you're entering their body
sitting here as if
there's the embodiment of the Buddha on this question on this chair
foreign
merging connecting with yours seeing yourself as whole
seeing yourself as kind
those qualities of you that are kind of the goodness in you
goodness of the Buddha
as if you're practicing yes the Buddha or konyen or any other being you have
invited sense of stability
so if you're looking out of their eyes though your eyes are closed but you have
their perspective their perspective unto the world unto yourself
foreign
whomever you've chosen is not accessible either you can spend a
little more time feeling the breaths merge or to somebody else it's okay
maybe someone more accessible Maybe someone kind someone you admire
a teacher your grandmother
try sitting tall like whomever you've chosen
tuning into the wholesome aspects if you've chosen a
human being Maybe there's some aspects of them that are complicated you don't have to tune into
those tune into what's good until it's wholesome
foreign what do you aspire to
thank you
have fun with this practice have fun with it find your own way
foreign
doesn't have to be a lot of thoughts actually not a lot of thinking in this practice but a sense of embodiment
just corny and sitting and breathing here
kindly compassionately
tune into the embodiment not so much the conceptualization
keep it simple foreign foreign
foreign foreign foreign foreign
foreign
being bravest as whole as kind as loving
as wise whatever qualities
you admire you're aspired to
feel their embodiment feel their embodiment with this
invitation of a deity or another human being
foreign foreign
foreign
thank you
foreign foreign
foreign
tuning into the aspects of you that are whole are kind
maybe you had the phrases I am kind
I'm whole I am well
tuning into the wholeness kindness
fullness of your being
without the phrases that work for you foreign
foreign
together
and appreciating appreciating our own goodness our own wholeness
in our hearts bowing to the
human being we invited or or the archetype
for their support and with generosity sharing
the goodness of our cultivation trusting there is goodness here
trusting there is goodness we showed up we tried we've done our best
trusting there is goodness sharing that goodness with all beings everywhere
there is a little more goodness in the world as we practiced even if we deem it
distracted or sleepy there are moments awakefulness so
appreciating ourselves and dedicating that to all things everywhere may all beings be happy
may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you for your practice everyone
I'm changing the chat now there's opportunity for sharing your Reflections
if you like with everyone or with just me privately
in chat um or you can raise your hand your Zoom head is your physical hand I would see
you maybe share any Reflections what would this what what was this like or
any challenges and your humblements
what did you notice
was it easy was it challenging what worked for you
what didn't work for you
well since the song goes rather quiet tonight
yeah yeah let's uh transition well I see some
Reflections coming when the person says it felt very soothing
Brian says after feeling a sense of enoughness I started to visualize my piece my business in a very different
way the money we generate being something that flows in and out nice I
like that nice different relationship to Dharma in the world yeah
one of you says let's see it's been sent to me private I showed up I tried I did
my best thank you for that I felt that truth for the first time in a long while beautiful beautiful yay
So Beautiful to connect with that another person says uh very peaceful
yeah foreign something that we don't own yes
money exactly flowing in this and say Yes Brian who was talking who was sharing the
reflection of visualizing money going in and out yes the flow the flow generosity
nothing is ours really just passing through this life for a limited time we
don't take it with us we didn't come with any of it
similar for businesses it's all a flow it's all a flow
in between all beings flow of generosity
resources yeah beautiful thank you for those reflections
so I wonder what do you aspire to in this practice as you were practicing as
you were coming together as you were sitting and inviting a an archetype or a being and seeing
yourself in the in the ways you aspire to what is your aspiration what are your
values that would be something lovely to
to reflect on and also to hold yourself with to let yourself be held witnessed
by others so that is the prompt for our breakout groups which we'll go to in the
moment after Neil says what he wants to say oh Neil you disappeared where'd you go there you are
yeah um you know I I really like this practice
you know I just find it you know I find in picturing someone and then like
becoming them it's a strategy that routinely works for me I use it often you know and I I just found myself just
being very very generous and caring with myself it was it was very sweet and
tender for me thank you thank you thank you for the practice
report a reflection knew so sweet sweet and tender with yourself lovely and I
applaud that you have practiced and you you know the the routes that work for
you and to to keep keep cultivating this way yeah
thank you so soothing yeah me too so so calming so loving so generous yeah this
practice can be beautiful so dear ones
um with respect to the pro the um practice and uh the practice the the
breakout groups um what we'll do is roughly groups of three
oh we'll see how the size ends up but let yours is so beautiful to let
yourself be held witness when you speak when you say your aspiration your
intention your goodness this is what I aspire to I aspire to
or truthfulness I find myself telling White Lies We don't have to say that
part no I aspire to be truthful or whatever it is it's so beautiful to be
held witness and share share your aspirations share your goodness because that's the sign there is there's a lot
of goodness here aspirations so you can share your
aspiration if you like you can say something about the practice or you can
just say you know pass when your turn comes it can say pass maybe in the next few right when it comes back to you
maybe you'll say something maybe you don't maybe you just hold the space so
so um so let's go the order of
um of um first name alphabetical order just offer a nugget the next person will
offer a nugget the next person will offer nugget or silence then you go around and round a few times and it's
lovely to be with Sangha to be generous with others to hold them it's so fun to
to offer generosity to others and and also receive generosity so
so enjoy this practice it's quite sweet and take care of each
other take care of yourselves I'm opening the rooms now here we go everybody's back welcome back and we've
got a few minutes for Reflections for comments questions what did you discover
in the groups what was that like
especially if you're new we'd love to hear from you Richard
well my aspiration is is to be focused in what I do with with whatever I'm
doing you know whether it's reading or playing music or whatever it is and I guess that's the the concentration
part of the Eightfold Path am I wrong there no that's that's good that's it yeah
yeah that is a concentration part yeah well actually it's um
it's partly concentration uh on the Eightfold Path it's also uh
I would say a little bit of it would be uh wise
so so part of it is also wise engagement or energy Viria so
that's another way of you want to be engaged in a in a fruitful and wholesome
way so I would say a little bit of it of that is there too yeah thanks Richard
yeah bill says I found that when I directed my attention to my breath I
tightened up constricted oh it's interesting ah it's uh how was this different from
practicing other times Bill do you want to say you don't you don't have to say anything but if you want it you're
welcome to I don't know maybe I was just more conscious of my breath this time out but it's it's not like you know when
you're about to fall asleep and your breath is just very much at ease it was it was definitely not that it was it was
it's just like it by paying attention to my breath there's something about it that seems to where I tighten up with
the breathing and it becomes more constricted so it's interesting because I I know that this was happening for you
some time ago and then you've been working with it and there's a lot of ease and relaxation that has this hasn't
come up for a while I haven't heard you mentioned this for a while so it's always different it's interesting for
you to explore right yeah what made this different to to after having worked with
bringing your center of gravity attention all of that down it's interesting yeah I'm not entirely sure
well I can't say is that my battery is running low so if I if I if I wink that's what's happening great thank you
thanks any other Reflections or any quick ones from from the groups from being held witness or holding other
people witnessed with their aspirations was it did you find it inspiring or not
just so that I know whether this is a good prompt for next time feedback
Katrin um yeah I liked it it's challenging for me
that but I really liked your emphasis on embodying these beings as opposed to
like thinking about how I might be like them because then I'm like well then I'm super not living up to that
um so and I've and just the invitation to connect with Kuan Yin was really
lovely so yeah I think that feeling like in my body how because
my body is like there's nothing wrong that's where there's nothing wrong so and my body knows about face of goodness
beautiful natural state great thank you Catherine I love the the embodimentification embodiment and and
fossil also says I like the prompt and so does Amy I found it sweet and lovely too beautiful and I saw another person
give a thumbs up for the prom okay so that's that's fantastic thank you Diana I see your hand but it's 701 already so
so yeah yeah so I'm happy to to pause to to stay at the end you're good like okay
so you're like it's all good it's been covered freaking so thank you all thank
you so much for your practice for showing up for cultivating this practice
for yourself for the sake of all those whose lives you touch directly and indirectly may
all beings be happy may all beings be well and free including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone