so um as I prepare to give this talk
it occurs to me to ask for your patience and your forgiveness
for what's going to talk about because I'm going to talk about something that I don't really think I
know much about and I'll probably say all kinds of
things which maybe are not maybe not even accurate and some of you will know more about this topic than me
and if I could shake your head and or you have particular perspectives on this topic from your particular studies
or something that what I end up saying might not fit that perspective and you'll shake your head
but the uh for all the mistakes I make uh my wish from giving this talk is to
provide you with a heightened attention to this topic and to be able to think about it spend
time with it talk to friends about it maybe see if there's other perspectives for this topic that might be useful of
how you live your life so uh the topic is time
time what is time I don't even I don't even know how to
answer that question very well but I I live in time all the time
I suspect some of you do as well and uh it's possible to have many
relationships with time it's possible to be time rich and time
poor and just to say it that way suggests that time can be a wealth
and that's independent of material wealth it suggests that there's something very
valuable potentially about time that may be many of us live
in impoverished in time in how we live our lives
what would it like to be living time Rich to be wealthy in time
you have to wait until you're well and retired some people who retired find themselves
with even less time so that's no guarantee
and then uh I was reflecting about how we have all these terminologies around
time that we use and two of them that I'm thinking about is
taking time and giving time to something and you know taking time I mean that
seems kind of acquisitive once I started thinking about it we were taking time
for myself I take time for myself where do I take it do I keep it do I share it
what do you know what does it mean to take time exactly and uh but more more
importantly you know it's just an idiom but uh but you know it has other
associations to it taking time that maybe it goes along with certain kind of
self-centeredness what about giving time being is it
possible to have a generous relationship with time and uh and you you know it's and does
that provide a very different relationship to the world than the notion of taking time for something
many people say that uh time is really a useful resource to have time for
something allows healing to happen sometimes healing psychological healing
requires amount of time to for it to happen time is useful for processing Our Lives
digesting our life the time is a really important quality if you want to be a wise person
I said I would suggest that um that if you don't have a lot of time
you're probably not going to have a lot of access to wisdom and one of the one of the
characteristics may be a foolish way of being in this world is to not
give enough time for what you do to do it well and then
you have to do it over again which takes more time there's a traffic sign here in Everett
City I don't know if it's still up that um that says something like late with the
question mark um you'll be later if you get a ticket
and so um so you know so
you know this rushing that people do is it really beneficial
you know or is it you know in the short term it seems like it's beneficial but what happens in the end I saw a car
accident in the freeway the other day and and I wondered if the person responsible
was in a hurry and
probably the person was going to be late now if the person was even alive there was
some question about that as I drove by so
a wise life is a life that has time for time
and what does that mean what does it mean to have time for time
there are some people distinguish between a physical time and psychological time
and so we could do that I that might be useful to think about cultural time
and spiritual time so at least you know four categories of time and physical time has to do with some
physical event in the world which measures the duration of
of time measure some duration for measure for some way of measuring change
sequentially and so
there was a time when people measured the months by the sequence of the moon
lunar time and now we have this Roman time that it was kind of made up by the
Romans in some kind of funny way that we're still kind of trying to Grapple with
and uh and it's very confused time because September literally in Latin means the
seventh month October is the eighth month but for us these are the 9th and
tenth months and um and then you know so November is the
ninth month and December is a tenth month but you know so like we're just confused
and um so so
um physical time so we have um uh you know the calendar time
that we live in and uh for example the year and the year it lends itself to kind of
a cyclic idea of time but also we have this linear idea of time that from the
past to the Future the there's atomic time that's used now for measuring things and so it's all
kind of physical time is something where we can measure psychological time is the time that our
mind somehow calculates or lives in and works in and it's amazing that our mind can in
certain kinds of ways measure duration of time between events
and apparently they have never discovered any place in the brain that is the time keeper it's some kind of an
intuitive sense maybe a way of looking at patterns of things that the patterning of the Mind as it coordinates
can get a sense and so for example the time it takes for a beach ball to reach you
is very different in the time for a baseball to reach you when you're at that
and so in a you know baseball player has to have a very acute sense of how long it takes for that ball to get over over
home base and if you don't have the right timing you've missed the ball
and a beach ball flies through the air and sometimes you can just keep your hands in your pockets for a second or so
because you know it's like taking its time to float there to you um but you know the volleyball that
comes over the net you better be on it you know quickly so that somehow you don't you don't pull
out your stopwatch and calculate you know and you're you know you have smartphones now so we can probably do
all kinds of calculations there's no time to do the calculations and let alone figure out the physics of time and
weight and mass and all these things that have to be calculated to figure out when the object's going to reach you
and is it going to reach you it's going to reach you on your left or the right or higher or lower
and the mind has this amazing capacity to have a sense of the duration it takes
the time it takes for things to come without any us consciously calculating
it so the mind has a capacity for for you know figuring out something about time
and um and uh and also they say that people can
have a spatial sense of time and uh what's interesting is that people
at different peoples in the world cultures have very different ideas of what how they imagine time spatially
so for example I think in most English-speaking books where they're going to do a chronology of History
it goes from left to right the the old times is in the left and you
get you know into the future and then maybe if Arrow that's pointing to the right for the future
in um then maybe that makes some sense because we or we read from that direction
cultures that read in the other direction they actually see time as going to the
left and and I heard that what what do you mean to the left that can't be
and um and uh and what's interesting about also about this is this is the reference
point for this image of time is personal it has to do with your phys your body
left and right kind of there are some cultures who don't use the left and
right which is a bodily personal reference point but they used things in nature there's
places in the world where um uh islands and people live on where
the the future is it up the mountain
Where the River comes from and the past is the ocean where the
river goes to and so it's the source it's the source of everything is in the future in a
certain way and uh and then it goes to a place where there's a big repository you know the big repository for the past the past
contains so much have you noticed that and and you're contributing to making it
bigger and bigger and um so um so that's kind of interesting that
so so no matter where you are on the mountain whatever Direction you're facing they always have a sense that you
know if they're going to talk about the the future they point up and um
and uh in some of the aboriginals in Australia
um you know I think for many of us but some of us if we were given a whole series of
photographs of ourselves over our lifetime and were told to put them in chronological order
many of here in the in America at least in the west would probably do it uh you know for again from left to right baby
pictures on the left and you know whatever age you are lately closer to the right
and um yeah apparently some aboriginals in Australia are just they're asked and
they always do it from Westie from I think it's from east to west
I guess where the sun comes up and it goes and then it goes down and so no
matter what direction there's wherever they're sitting whatever Direction they are uh if they're if they're sitting
pointing south or they're putting North they always have a sense of where East and West is and they'll lay out the
chronology in that way so these people with the mountain and the ocean and and the East and the West
sense they're not measuring time from the personal reference point
that people in the western cultures are often doing the right and left which is always personal in some way it has to do
with the body and our hands and how we see things does it make a difference
that we have this anthropocentric Centric idea of time uh directionality
for time spatial idea of time and or having some some reference point in nature that's beyond our anthropocentric
concerns I don't know if it makes any difference but it does show it does show that we
have different senses of slime ideas of time concepts of time
I asked a friend recently yesterday about this thing about left and right
you know where does she see time and she thought to me no a time comes at me it
kind of goes through her from the future it comes directly at her and through and and one way I think of time is as an
hourglass and I think sometimes that time comes from above and goes through The Hourglass this big funnel and then
it goes out again at the bottom and I'm sitting at the neck of The Hourglass and I'm sitting that's
what I watch everything going through the neck of my experience
so um psychological time but psychological time is also related to cultural time
and we live part of the burden we have in living under time is had a lot to do
with our cultures we we we're living in the legacy of in the industrial revolution
there that's when really strict ideas of time through the day really became institutionalized
and from uh because they had all these shifts in the industries that were being
built as huge manufacturing places and they would have these horns that would blow and people would know when their
shift stopped and started and they had to show up all at the right time and and so it became much more regimented than
it had been before before there was just big Industries and big groups of people to organize and then from what I read is it from the
industrial example of how they organized time that was translated or applied to
the school systems and I don't know if before the Industrial Revolution how time was at
school but um certainly at the time of the Industrial Revolution it became clear to
the industrial countries that it was important to educate people to make them prepared for this industrial world that
we were growing into so then there was massive movement to educate people and they borrowed you know very you know
again we know some some of us know this very regimented idea of time that the students have to live under
is that healthy to do that is that useful to do that I met a kid up in Islands outside of Vancouver some years
ago who had never been to school and he'd lived on a farm and his parents
would never required him to go to school and and I don't think they made any particular efforts to educate him either
and uh and he just kind of roamed around and worked on the farm a lot and he seemed very smart and knowledgeable and
engaged and seemed like a really fantastic lovely person but had never been put under the
pressures of this and you know regimented time that so many of us I believe have probably
lived under I've lived in different cultural times a
fascinating time for me was I lived in a Zen monasteries that used a Time system
from long ago in Japan maybe China which was a five-day week
and and so it was measured by the days of the month so there were there you
know there was the one days the two days the three days the four days and the five days and you know and um
so one two it was right for nine days uh I think we worked one
two three four I think we worked three days and then the fourth day was off is that right that works and then uh five
six seven eight no no I think there were zero days right so there was four we worked for four days uh then we had a
zero in it uh and then one two three and then the fourth day was off and then
five six seven eight and the ninth day was off so we would talk about four or nine days
like some people talk about weekends we would talk about four or nine days so rather than having two days off we
would have one day off and then go back to work for four days or to beat the monastery schedule
and it was fascinating to live in this alternative sequence of time and I lost
touch with what days of the week it was days of the week were irrelevant and I didn't know it was Sunday or
Monday or you know because I just knew that the date because it was all by the date
foreign so that was interesting and then I've done long retreats where I had no idea
what day or month it was you know just that that kind of concern just completely dropped away
I I lived on a farm for a while and I loved living on the farm for a number of
reasons but one of the reasons was time wasn't regimated
the work time and off time and play time were kind of flowed kind of seamlessly
between each other we would go out and work in the fields or take care of the cows and then we would have time off and
do something but it was never planned it was never um
you know strict but rather has a wonderful organic feeling just flowing
between what we were doing um the only thing that was a little bit strict was uh
um by Dawn you had to have milk the cows and by dusk you had to have brought them back to milk them but that was you know
following the light um and um
so to have that experience or this fluidity of schedules between personal
time and work time and having it so porous was really a fascinating thing for me
and then we have spiritual time and what is spiritual time
I think that you know there's a kind of a common
story of going to some wise spiritual person and
saying you know what's the most important time and the answer is now
now is the most important time and we have a spiritual practice this
Insight Meditation practice that is really based on being firmly rooted
grounded in the present in the now an important part of that practice of
attempting to be in the now is to discover how difficult that is
and how difficult it is because of concerns about other times the the concerns about the future
concerns about the past and and how difficult it is to be
resting or or or alive or feeling a sense of
real kind of um uh attentional vitality
to this moment here without a need to leave it behind without a leave to kind
of lose track of it by our distractions and our thinking mind or are rushing around
and um and so we start discovering how for that challenge we have with the present moment
and some people attribute that challenge to the challenge of a distracted mind
some people have the challenge of having a full schedule of things to do or a
long to-do list but it's also a challenge of
um you know our relationship to time and maybe not understanding how valuable
the present moment is how much is available here I think of uh you know if we have the
time being a timeline where it's it's a line from at least here in California from left to right
that a line is impoverished it's just a very
thin narrow and rather than the present moment being a DOT on that
um the present moment is not even an axis that goes through it that makes it
two-dimensional the present moment is three-dimensional or there's maybe there's more Dimensions
I don't know but um three dimensions it's it's you know as opposed to there's
something about the past and the future that maybe fits into a line but the present I think is
three-dimensional it's a difference between going from a black and white movie to a a color movie
it's you know that dramatic if you're old enough you remembered Wizard of Oz going that direction
suddenly it's alive and um so um
so this spiritual time I propose has a lot to do with our
relationship to present moment time the time that's unfolding Here and Now
and that that's the three-dimensional which means that it's never a DOT
little pixelated dot that you you know you've passed through quickly that spiritual now
is has a duration and how long is the duration
of the now if you're relaxed and present and really embodied or inhabiting the present
moment without any indicate any uh varying away into the past and future or
preoccupation fantasy but really here to experience this moment kind of in its fullness
three-dimensional fullness what's the duration of now
some of you probably never considered seriously how long is it now and how long is the moment is it is it
just like Snap the finger that's all it is a famous American philosopher
psychologist named William James I think it was him who talked about the Saddleback of the present moment
and the Saddleback means it's kind of like a u-shape and so the present moment somehow is in this you know maybe if
there's a timeline the present moment is like this u-shaped dip and um that uh you know that saddled
back that's it lasts for a while but how long is that while
and then we have spiritual people who want to talk about the Timeless now
what is a Timeless now and what good is it because if it's if it's timeless
if time measures change how do we deal with change if we're if
it's timeless well maybe time and Timeless can coexist
but what is this present moment that we have that we live in what's the duration of now
and it's possible by getting a sense of the
present moment now then this moment
that then we can start living in time and the expression living in time I
think has two delightful meanings one meaning is like comes from music
you know the music is in time I'm in time with the music and so living in harmony with uh with
time to be in time is not just to show up on time but to kind of be in harmony
or to be in the flow or find a rhythm with time as opposed to missing the
present moment I suspect most of us here have missed a lot of
moments they went by without us noticing and noticing them
and and so to be in time in harmony with time but also to end time is kind of to
inhabit time as opposed to living under the weight of time
to live in time is more like a floating on the water
to to be in the water for most people is they're floating on the surface right because unless you're a scuba diver or
something or diving down for a few moments but uh to be in time to be floating on
time maybe time is weightless
as opposed to the weight of time what do we really weigh down by when you
talk about the weight of time because time is I think it's weightless last time I tried putting on the scale
and if time is weightless
and we have some intuitive sense of time the Mind does kind of construct a sense
of duration of time and a sense of time and but if it's weightless
and you're somehow can you feel that or sense that does that make a difference
or are is the preoccupations of the mind so strong that you're pulling away out of this
moment that you don't have time for this talk even I mean this is such a silly talk ridiculous
when you could you know probably be
figuring out what stocks to buy tomorrow or today I don't know if they've opened in the weekend something's open the
weekend to buy but um but to be in time
and uh and then in time and be present for the duration of the present the
moment now and how long is the moment for you sometimes I've thought that my moments
last about as long as I say it takes to say the word now
sometimes now is the duration of how long is to happen how long it is for me to have an in-breath
that's that's duration of a now and and
sometimes I have a sense of some Timeless now Timeless presence but generally doesn't
last in theory it lasts outside of my being aware of it
but it is there time is there timelessness if we're not aware
is there does the tree that falls in the forest make a sound if there's no one to hear
it is there time if there's no one to be aware of time
and uh and I I think not at least spiritually there's a way in which we
could talk about awareness time where awareness and time are inseparable
they kind of arise together and so this richness this three-dimensionality of time
awareness time what is it what's the time in which we're aware
what's the awareness that exists in time the awareness that exists in time can
only exist in the present your awareness which such an important
part of this practice cannot exist in the past it's gone there's no there's no awareness the only
awareness of the of the past is our memory and we're aware of the memories
the only awareness we have of the future is our prediction
and and forecasting the future which again is the world of we can be aware of those thoughts and ideas
but to be aware of time is to be here and what are we aware of
it's fascinating that it's possible to be aware of the recognition of now
I'm in now I'm now I'm here and it has a beginning
and has a middle and that has an end
and then you do it again and again that somehow an act of awareness a clear
concise distinct recognition of the moment has a duration
that appears it's there for a while and then it disappears
what happens to time when you've the recognition of it has faded
away physical time you can go look at your watch and know exactly what happened
but um but this spiritual time the time that has spiritual time is time
that has time lots of time it's spacious time
that's where time becomes a richness a wealth
here where the mind is not rushing off
is not preoccupied where the Mind senses and feels
what's here is available for something that's different than what
we're controlling what we're directing what we're wanting
that doesn't fit into industrial time doesn't fit into even this kind of idea
of time that's very personally the spatial sense of it is very personal from left to right or right to left
to feel the time here now
what is it to not live under the burden of time the pressures of time
what is it to live in a luxurious time and this is such a these are such
important questions for people doing this meditation practice because at least when you're meditating
that's the time to give yourself over to time
to live in time to live in the the time of this moment
here where awareness and time are coterminous
awareness and time arise together no separation
where there's no hard and fast measure of time requirements of time
where we can sense the comings and goings even of time in a sense the awareness of
time and um it's almost as if
you know there's a vast ocean if time is not a line but a
vast ocean two-dimensional surface and maybe the present moment is a wave
that somehow gets energized gets lifted up and has some prominence for a moment
and then the wave passes and and settles down again
and so what is that wave what is this coalescing or coming together or Rising
of um that happens here and now and this time now
what do you feel what do you experience what's available for you
when you're living in time in the moment Here and Now
so I hope that these ideas and we'll give you something to think
about and to reflect on how might you have a new relationship
what is your relationship to time and is there a new way of seeing it and is there such a new way of
engaging in time when you're meditating
is there a way of living in a spiritual time or luxurious time a generous time
when you're meditating and what would it take to do that to have a sense of that to be in there
and um
and so
and I hope that this will support your meditation practice in a dramatic way
that kind of kind of opens up a new dimension of it that maybe you don't know it not so well attuned to because
we don't really give a lot of time to think about time
but to give time for Time Imagine That
give time for time so that's what I have
and maybe if some of you stay now for a discussion outside maybe we'll find out
if it sparked any interests questions Reflections on this topic or anything
else you want to bring up bring up so thank you all very much and um