so
what's on my mind on my heart a bit is a might seem initially maybe a little bit
of an interesting topic I hope I can make it interesting and and that is the the
sixth factor of the Eightfold Path which is right effort
and maybe one thing that will kind of maybe pique your interest around this
topic of right effort is the first time many years ago I was over 25 years ago that I gave a series
of talks on the Eightfold Path one of the most important teachings of the Buddha
and I did it you know I was going to do it one factor for every evening and so I was going through the factors
and then it was time to do the factor on right effort and I without any comment or explanation
or recognition that I was doing it I consciously skipped it
and no no one asked me about why'd you skip it and uh and um the reason I skipped it
was I could I wasn't really behind it I couldn't quite get myself inspired by it
and some of it had to do with my background in Zen where in Zen there was a really clear
teaching admonition to not do any not strive not have any goal orientation not
try to make anything happen not try to attain particular states of meditation
but rather the instruction was to wholeheartedly fully be present for what
is and um and so so uh there was a lot of physical effort
that went into into zen you had to show up early in the morning in the monastery like at four o'clock in the morning you
had to wake it up and to get up to do no effort at all
and then you had to uh take a very particular posture sit very straight and upright there's a lot of effort that
goes into the posture and um and then they ring the bell and then you have to do a walking meditation
to ring the bell you to come back to take this posture to do nothing in and so there's kind of nothing you do
but kind of a lot you do there's a lot of effort and in fact when I was practicing in the monastery in Japan
um I was admonished when I didn't make enough effort and they would say in Japan I had to do things with Zen
nochikara and that means with Zen power so so it was a little bit you know kind
of how I learned then and how I understood it was very peculiar maybe to myself but
um but it was clearly not striving not goal oriented and not trying to make anything happen just and I loved Zen and
I I put a lot of in retrospect I realized I put a lot of effort into it but it was kind of like the effort to
show up but the Mind wasn't trying to do anything it was almost like it was a
physical effort to show up for the present and physical was very important for me
because a lot of it was the embodied awareness that came in the embodied showing up
and the mind was just trying to be present but nothing else so no effort there
so that's how I defend myself a little bit or explain myself a little bit for skipping right effort
but um at some point I started appreciating as I kept studying day 12
path and looking at right effort and appreciating that actually I put a lot of effort into it and uh and I love the
effort I made and uh even when I went to uh Burma to practice vipassana there
there too the teacher made teachings about you should strive and some people really did themselves in
really suffered a lot because maybe with kind of Western acculturation striving meant stressing
and so people with stress and meditation which was not healthy and there were people who were kind of basket cases
from that approach but because I came from the Zen background when I heard strive I mostly
just Shrugged It Off and then I did that anyway in retrospect I wasn't striving to
attend anything but again once again I was really trying to wholeheartedly show up and be present for what is
which was the instructions and in the background it was for attaining something but I wasn't there
exactly to attain something I was there to show up fully and it was really wonderful for me the very detailed
precise instructions that I received in Burma in vipassana for doing this Zen
thing show up really precisely for the moment but in doing that it's set in motion an
unfolding a growth the development in practice that led to some of the states
that they're pointing to what you can attain but it wasn't like attaining it
wasn't the point for me it was kind of a byproduct so I felt I felt very lucky to have had
this background in Zen when I practiced with this Fierce uh teacher upadita in
Burma because I was protected in a way that a lot of other vipasto students
were not protected from the striving element that he had and um so uh so it took a while for me
to get my handle on this uh teravan of early Buddhist kind of idea of right effort
so to give you maybe maybe to kind of you could appreciate a little bit more the challenge I had to get behind it
um so right after it is made up of four different kind of practices or efforts
and whether we should call it effort or Endeavor some people translated four Endeavors the right Endeavor and maybe
that feels a little bit more relaxing I don't know but um it has to do with
recognizing the distinction between wholesome states of mind and unwholesome states of mind
unwholesome states of Mind are reactive qualities of the mind when we react uh
compulsively addictively to experience with anger with greed with hostility
with delusion with fear the unwholesome states of Mind are
always contain some degree of suffering of pain in them and that's what
qualifies them as a as unwholesome is they are detrimental to the person who
has them so uh so if you have anger which is not detrimental to you then it wouldn't be
considered unwholesome but the that's the definition of it in this tradition
so we have to be able to recognize what's on wholesome what's stressful what's detrimental and then there's what's wholesome which
is healthy and beneficial for the person who has it and these are mental States activities
of the mind that we do and so uh if there is an Impulse for generosity that has no conceit or no
greed or no ill will in it then it's wholesome but if it's mixed with these
unwholesome ones it kind of makes the generosity unwholesome as well so to be able to be generous to be
loving kind these are all kind of just part of many
many wholesome states of mind that we can have so that's the distinction in right
effort and um there's uh two two uh practices of
that invoid unwholesome states of mind and two for
wholesome the unholesome has to do with um first
if there's nothing unwholesome if you're not being in a reactive mode not caught
up in wholesome States then prevent them from coming occurring
so do what you can so they don't arise if they're if they have arise
then abandon them let go of them so the same distinction happens for
wholesome if there are a wholesome states that haven't arisen
evoke them if they've Arisen if they're there
then maintain them so that's the kind of a simple explanation for it
but in each of these four steps this is what you're supposed to do
and it is repeated for each one you should make effort arouse energy
exert your mind and strive to do each of those
so maybe now you can sympathize a little bit for my skipping right effort in my talk you're like what I mean this
is a little bit strong right now whether the English translation is accurate is uh you know you've always
questioned like the word strive is that really the right thing but anyway that's you know just four
words you know for for doing this so what but when four words are being used
like this what it does indicate is that for the Buddha
making some kind of effort is super important this is the Dharma is not for lazy
people the Dharma is not like you know to be easy going I'll get around to it
eventually and you know then I'll get I'll do some of it um and in particular for meditation
you know to sit down in meditation well I'm sit here for a while but I'll get around to being presents you know maybe near the end you know you know I have
some good I have some good fantasies I have to get through first they're mostly reruns but still I'm
gonna I want to go through them and but the idea I love the word word
wholehearted and for me the summary of all these powerful Expressions here is do your
practice wholeheartedly do it holy put yourself completely into it
but don't don't stress and then and uh and I'll talk about that
some more about this but don't do it wholeheartedly the Buddha really wants you don't be lazy be wholehearted give yourself to it
give yourself if you're going to practice give yourself over to it when you're practicing so like meditation
there's a peaceful way of giving yourself over to it a way a peaceful way that it doesn't cause more stress or
tension a wholehearted way that actually because the nature of the practice supports de-stressing
Letting Go relaxing tension so um so uh in in sometimes sometimes
these four right efforts are summarized by the four words
um prevent abandon evoke and maintain
that's nice nice thing to remember Maybe but it's uh but if you then if you look at the instructions a little bit more
carefully there's a I find this is fascinating and this is where that kind of came to realize the last few weeks
as I've been kind of seeing the teachings of the Buddha from a new slat the things that I overlooked before
and so sure enough it says um for unwholesome states that have been
arisen prevent them from arising and for ones that have Arisen abandon
them just so each one pages is one word but um
and for um for uh
for evoking wholesome states that have not yet Arisen it just says evoked them
bring them about bring them up somehow it's just one word but this is what I find fascinating is the fourth one
there are five words
to describe what you do here not just maintain so in this translation
it's Contin um make the effort for the continuance the
non-disappearance the strengthening the increase and the Fulfillment
by development by cultivation of those wholesome states that are
present that's a lot of words so the other were other I have just one
word but this has a so there's a kind of like wow now if you're chanting this in
the ancient world people chanted this it has a rhythm to it it has a heartfelt that has an embodied feeling to it that
I think has a my guess is in the ancient word had very different impact on people who sit down to read this and start
falling asleep because of these words of the repetition I mean these a lot of this Tech these
ancient texts are not very engaging to read if you're not if you're a novice
but um but if you're chanting it and you get the rhythm of the language and you're being carried Along by the Rhythm
I can imagine that this language of um it kind of almost suggests energy
suggests kind of a embodied feeling of kind of excitement or and then if you've
chanted it a number of times and you heard it a number of times and you can it's like a refrain and you can get behind in Janet yourself there's
something that happens in chanting and communal chanting that there's a concentration and a location a deeper
resonance inside of us for what's being talked about so one awakens effort
uh for the continuance for the continuance
the non-disappearance the strengthening the increase the Fulfillment by cultivation
so by cultivate so anyway I don't know if this you get a sense of this Rhythm and the energy behind it and how it
might be conveyed in the ancient way in the way that this was originally meant to be presented
but what strikes me is that a couple of things is a
I think it's fair to say that this Buddhism thing that we do
is often associated with letting go isn't it kind of like non-attachment and
you have like you go to a you know a block party and people's you know it's kind of like the Hebrew Buddhist you're
doing Buddhist practice and you know that's like kind of party pooping you know just it's just about letting go and
you know it's about letting go and not attachment this non-attachment is overdone and you know my my wife when we
had a little baby went to an organization called um that Bay Area attachment parenting
so we're setting my you know parents my you know my wife and my son my little baby was going through this attachment
you know place and but attachment has a very different meaning in Psychology these days where
it's a healthy kind of sense of bonding and connection that's a very important and but to boot for Buddhist attachment
is all bad in Buddhist English and so so that's we
have Buddhism has that reputation but it does does not have the reputation
for what we're supposed to do with these wholesome States um and the you know to increase them to
strengthen them to expand them to develop them once they've Arisen make them have them
grow and we find out and elsewhere in these ancient texts where it actually uses the
word to to grow the wholesome States to the point that they're abundant
that we Thrive with them that uh we're filled with them they fully flow through
us the word for fulfill kind of actually means to fit be filled out by them
fully and that's kind of dramatic and then you know the Zen person in me
the way I was taught then kind of reacts as well wait a minute we're supposed to be prioritizing certain states of mind
we should just be with the way things are and accept it for what it is and the idea that you prioritize certain states
of mind you know that was kind of like you know if you go to your Zen migrant to my zen teacher and say you know wow I
just got really concentrated or really felt peaceful or filled with joy in my
meditation uh we I'd be lucky if the teacher said something like well just one more thing to let go of
and uh and then sometimes it was worse and uh in Zen they have something called
makko I think it's makio which is um
you know anyway it means delusion it just kind of you know it's just illusion
don't bother with it and so this dismissing of these beautiful wholesome States makes sense
in a certain cert in the in the in the um in the approach of Zen I want to be
respectful for it it really makes sense in the grand totality of what's in practice is about It's very effective if
you really understand the purpose and the background for it but it also when I it lends someone like
me to read these kinds of texts and be dismissive of it or not be interested but at the same time when I did
vipassana practice how do I do it these beautiful States arise
and they're allowed to rise they're supposed to arise sitting in meditation and allowing
yourself to feel deeply calm deeply content deeply at home being here right now in
such a way that it's kind of an embodied at home in this feeling that comes sometimes with delight and
joy and happiness and a settleness of the mind gets really
stilled and unified and peaceful their mind gets the I was really
surprised to discover the upwelling in meditation for the first time of a very
powerful states of loving-kindness of compassion of equanimity
that arose and so these things are supposed to be allowed and grow and develop
and and some of the faults were not recognizing this early on is that the a
lot of the early English translators flattened the Pali language into English
they kind of made it I think they maybe they were distrustful of a lot of emotionality and you know flowery kind
of language or evocative language and so some of the more beautiful and inspiring
discuss words like thriving uh the word
thriving became increase and uh and abundance became
uh like you know frequent or Lots or you know something
you know you know has very different emotional tone or feeling the words you choose and I think we kind of flattened
it in these English translation and um and so but when you start getting
this language of abundance and thriving you get a very different feeling for
what fills us what can happen what's possible it's also possible to hear these and
compare oneself and say well these aren't happening to me so then I'm bad or wrong or it's
supposed to be different it's also possible to think that you know well I have to strive now to attain
these and huff and puff and try to hold on to it and so there's a lot of detrimental reactivity that can come
into play when we hear about these things but that's why these four right efforts are needed together
and we need to understand them together because if we mix wrong effort
with right effort we end up with wrong effort and so if you hear that you're supposed
to develop qualities of joy and happiness and practice that that's supposed to come up
but we do it with with the clinging and attachment then it doesn't help it
doesn't work so um so one of the examples I like to
give for the kind of proper striving if you were into that kind of thing
is strive to be relaxed thanks
and if you try to if that's you strive to be relaxed that's a protection
because you can't strive with tension and relax at the
same time if the purpose is to relax the striving has to be wholehearted has to
be diligent it has to be kind of continuous really stay on it on top of it
but in staying on top of it it's you're saying you're getting more and more relaxed you're discovering the places within where there's tension just to
relax and in fact elsewhere the Buddha talks about the first stages of meditation has
a lot to do with relaxing calming our reactivity
and the in the kind of stages of meditation that he gives
it's not until there's been a fair amount of relaxation of reactivity
that we begin getting into the realm of maintaining cultivating and maintaining
and growing and with these wonderful positive states of mind that can arise
and um and so we learn to relax the body that Buddha said the reactivity that's
stored in our body for someone who's new to meditation this is one of the first
things that's really useful to do really really find a way to sit and meditate so the shoulders can relax the
belly can relax that the muscles of the face really work on sitting upright or
the equivalent for you and let let things really unwind
don't be in a hurry to jump over that stage of a practice
and then uh and then the second instruction is to do that for the mind for the mental World whatever is a
reactive intense in your mental world that's important to come to try and make
tranquil to settle to relax and so this is a very important
protective measure in this practice is to remember how important it is to relax
so then we take this instruction here which says
you should make effort arouse energy exert your mind and strive
to relax
do it wholeheartedly really give yourself to it but you know don't if you
do it give yourself to it wholeheartedly remember to do it as a way of relaxing
and then at some point with enough relaxation and enough being fully present here and this is not an
easy thing to come to and many people find meditation phenomenally beneficial just because it
gets real helps them relax 10 percent of their attention and they're 10 more
here and more wiser because of it but at some point when there's enough relaxation of our reactivity the
reactive world that we're caught in and living in these beneficial States the wholesome
states begin appearing on their own they're not something we have to manufacture or require but rather
there's kind of like almost like the nature of who we are is waiting inside of us
are our our states of calm peace generosity
care love Equanimity wisdom
joy happiness that are just kind of like in the you know
you know just off stage just waiting for a chance to come on stage when just those reactive
actors can just get off but you know that the reactive actors
are there all the time and so they never seem to they think they have an endless encore
and um but finally when they settle away and there's room on the stage of our mind our heart
there's all the stuff that can arise and what this teaching here means for me
of you know support the continuous the maintaining of it the strengthening it the development of it the abundance of
it has a lot to do with allowing it to do so
getting out of the way and this is one of the things I learned from this way I was practicing was how
useful it was to get out of my own way and kind of make room for these things I'll make space for them which comes
from appreciating them and it took a long time for me to appreciate these positive states of mind
that can arise out of meditation out of Buddhist practice they Rose for me but I kind of shrugged
them off or didn't pay any attention to him because of this Zen background where we weren't supposed to
and but eventually I learned oh you're this is okay to appreciate these
it's okay to make room for them and value them because doing that is the very thing that supports them to grow
more and more and more if you don't appreciate them they don't grow
if you get attached to them they don't grow if you tie them if you connect them to
your self-worth they don't grow just let them be let them be there and
support and grow and develop and don't make them complicated get out of the way for them don't interfere with them but
then do the things that support them and some of that that supports these is
the wholeheartedly showing up and being present for what is and when the host of states of Mind
begin showing themselves maybe as small hints at first to be wholeheartedly
present for those in making room for them gives room for them to grow and develop
and um and then we come to a point in practice some point not an easy thing but uh it is kind of
the North Star that we kind of know that's possible is that we come to a point where the
thriving the sense of abundance and sort of thriving that is possible uh embodied
thriving embodied abundance body sense of wholeness of nourishment seems to
begin having a life of its own it seems to be welled up and be present and support us in being present and it
creates a context a background a foundation
for being present for all kinds of things including our reactivity including what's really difficult in
this world that that is such a powerful support
to be supported by deep relaxation by Joy by Happiness by a sense of calm so
we can address the difficulties of this life of ours is very different than
meeting the difficulties of this life from that place of reactivity from the place of unwholesomeness that many
people are caught up in so with all that I want to read an ancient poem
and it's a what's here
I think it's written by a disciple of the Buddha from the ancient world rather than by the Buddha
so in sense what we're talking about today is the distinction between also between wise and unwise attention
so unwise attention doesn't know what to pay attention to properly and also pays attention to ways that
maybe involve attachment or clinging or resistance or aversion um
so this poem begins with a sentence from unwise attention
your thoughts eat you what do you think of that none of you of
course there apparently the the Pali word might literally mean chew you up
I'm building more than just a little more dramatic than eating so this ancient uh it's a text you know it's
very poetic and powerful the words they have been kind of flattened in English and so sometimes you know even the
negative ones are very kind of but you see
from unwise attention your thoughts eat you giving up what is unwise think wisely
basing your thoughts on the Buddha Dharma Sangha and your own virtue
you will no doubt obtain gladness joy and happiness
then with abundant gladness you will make an end to suffering
so here you see a shift from language here from something unwholesome
unhelpful unwise attention we learn how to pay attention wisely
and to think wisely so that our thoughts don't eat us up don't you know pull us into their Whirlpool of
preoccupation and then basing ourselves on the values
the orientation in life that the Buddha Dharma Sangha represents
and virtue your own ethics you will no doubt
obtain gladness joy and happiness so here's the emphasis on these
wholesome healthy qualities of Mind our hearts and then here it talks about abundance
with abundant gladness imagine this language of abundance is used
sometimes kind of another way to talk about it they talk about uh
inner wealth that faith is inner wealth
uh vigilance and kind of careful attention is an inner wealth
loving kindness is an inner wealth so the idea of becoming wealthy abundant
likes of spilling over you have more than enough you feel completely you know content and happy
and then you will make an end of suffering
maybe your suffering won't come to an end until you've figured out a way to
relax deeply to allow some really beautiful qualities of heart to arise
and so you can really then from that point of view address the root of the suffering that you have in your life
so that was a little plug for right effort maybe trying to make up for 25 years ago
and when I skipped it so thank you and um so we have a few
minutes if some of you would like to ask uh questions or comments and you're welcome to do that
let's head north over there yes
thank you uh thank you very much that was very
provocative for me many things swirling around inside me I want to add
that in that place as I've acknowledged
over time the wholesome thoughts if you will the positive States The Joy the the
higher vibration if you will I feel very much that I work with that
idea of what nurtures it what how do I resource it because we're also in our
human being bodies and um my profession is a therapist so as I
was listening to you it was diffic it was unavoidable to not
think about how we live out here externally
practically what do we do what choices do we make to feed those states of mind and just the one thing I wanted to share
that got me very excited was when you spoke about how do we grow those
wholesome States and what came to me was express it create service Love Love More
here and here and so thank you you fed me deeply today
great thank you that's very nice yeah I think if there are these wholesome
Tendencies or qualities that are in US they grow by expressing them
especially if we express them wisely you know not just you know inflict
people with them but uh the wise expression of it and and
the relational are so important because one of the most common if someone you didn't ask me correctly but if one of
the someone asked me you know how do you make these grow or these wholesome States the most common answer the
tuition gives is um has to do with how we live interrelationally with other people they
say you should be ethical you practice your ethics and generosity ethics is all
about how we live in relationship to other people and others other things and
generosity is same thing it's an interrelational world that we're that is so important for all this and and
sometimes because it's a meditation tradition we had and we close our eyes in our
tradition even right it just seems like it's so self-focused internally focused but but a lot of this work also happens
interrelationally in just ethics and generosity is the beginning of it
so someone else
um thank you for your comments and um
the session today I wondered if
you have tried to teach or you have taught meditation to four to five year
old students to you know the and what your
ex I mean to more higher ages maybe 9 10 to 11 12 13 14. I've been trying to
teach like five minutes meditation when I have been teaching last few weeks and
just to see how they absorb being able to close their eyes and feel
you know the generosity and the wholesomeness of relationships
um I don't haven't had a lot of experience a lot of I haven't had a lot of experience with four to five year olds
and I think that for that age and for even older some of the ways of being
that adults want to see them adults want to have kids kind of
be positively influenced by meditation so it can be different in some kind of
way but I think some of the ways we want them to be different or be changed or be supported or be guided or I don't know
something there might be better ways in trying to get them to meditate
there might be how how parents conduct themselves slowly over the you know
regularly becomes a model for how they learn to be present and be relaxed the
parents are anxious they learn that the world is a scary place if they alert If
the parents are happy they learn the world's a happy place to be so how the parents are at that age is
probably more important when my kids were that age there was one one I have two sons and one of them did
a lot of meditation with but that wasn't because um you know I you know I thought it was
I don't know how to say it the main reason for doing it is that um uh he was
kind of a hyper active kid like you know not that kind of and
um and so uh and the more tired he got the more activated he would get which
wasn't healthy for him because that he couldn't sleep and so getting him to sleep was a big issue like it was a little baby we could
only get him to sleep if we carried him or drove him in the car you know for naps
and so I started doing guided meditations for him going to bed at night and that would help him go to
sleep and um and so I did a lot of creative imagine
visualizations or imaginations for him like imagine that he was a sea otter on
its back on the ocean on top floating on top of the kelp and the gentle waves are
coming and lifting you up and down and and so your breath up and down of the waves and he would lay there and imagine
he was a sea otter or a bird or I did all these animals you know it's like every evening was a
different animal for a long time and that would so he had that and what How Deeply that went into
him I don't know the other thing that we did with the kids were that young is
um uh we had cookie parties
and a cookie party was uh a time where sometimes we did it because it was it
was with two kids at home things were you know I didn't know that people literally bounced off the walls
I thought it was just just an expression and so there were times when it just
like was you know not only bouncing off the walls they're going to bounce through the window soon so we we need
something here so let's have a cookie party and uh and they knew what that meant so
we would they would get involved in setting it up and we'd set up a kind of special kind of rug on the floor and and
they get a little kind of flower or centerpiece maybe a Buddha and then we put zuff who's like we have here sitting
on around four of them for the four or you know in each corner of a kind of a circle and then we get cookies out and
put them on a plate and maybe some milk for the kids and then we would sit there my wife and I would sit in meditation
posture and they would sit on those offers in the way that they do and everything could calmed down
everything's settled and got peaceful and there was no meditation but there
was a Ambiance the tone the how the kids felt and what was going on for them maybe they I don't know what was going
on when they were activated but when they but they you know they and then after they had this cookie party they
were so calm and contented and cozy and it was such a you know it you know
whatever a parent wants a four-year-old to get for meditation
we got from cookie cookie parties so that's a I could say more but that's
enough for now and uh and I think adults do well maybe not cookie parties but now we call them
tea ceremonies it says are just looking at our
teammaster so um
okay so thank you so if some of you would like to meet outside now in the parking lot we can take some folding
chairs out and we can take the masks off there and have more discussion for a little while and be nice to hang out and
otherwise thank you