great great so so today I'd like to
invite us to um engage with
um asking for help as an expression of meta
for ourselves and for others so
so let me say a few more words about what I mean and how to how to think
about how to consider this this asking for help asking for support
so so asking for help sometimes it can feel
like a um an admission of weakness or or or putting a burden on someone else and
we you know we could have this um delusion of Independence that we can
do it all by ourselves instead of a sense of healthy interdependence so
so to shift our perspective or or invite ourselves to consider that asking for
support asking for help is not just good for us but also good
for others and for the relationship so
let's start with others we're inviting we're asking others to to be generous or giving them our the
opportunity we're giving them the opportunity to be kind to be generous to
share their resources to share their time their attention their affection
[Music] um so it's it's wonderful to be able to give
to support others and if if we don't give others the opportunity we're we're
closing ourselves off like an island I can do it all by myself similarly
there's with this sense of you know if we consider our own thinking about not
you know needing help but having a hard time asking for help there could be many different
um thoughts about that one is oh I should be able to do it by myself well really
is it helpful to to bring the shoulding should all over ourselves
um also it's there is strength There Is
Power invulnerability in sharing
in allowing um
others to support us and this is an as is an expression of care not just for them but care for ourselves so in that
way it also shows as Meta Meta for ourselves so if you were your own best
friend were very caring say benefactor caring mother father whatever works for you
your own caring best friend your own caring benefactor and you saw that oh
yeah actually support would be really helpful right now support would be
really helpful right now is an expression of meta to reach for that
support for that help in whatever way
um it would be would would support us so it's an expression of meta for ourselves and also as as I mentioned earlier as an
expression of creating relationship it's it's giving and taking acknowledging our
interdependence in the world that we have resources to give and
others have resources to give so it is this acknowledgment of giving and receiving instead of feeling that we're
an island we can do it all by ourselves because we can't none of us can
we all live in this abundant generosity
of the universe and generosity of others helping us supporting us us helping them
supporting them so making this both more visible
and opening our heart opening our minds to uh to this giving and receiving of
support that can make more happen back in part of the cause and conditions of
making more possible in the world so In Praise of asking for help and one
other thing I want to also bring in here is when we ask others for for help we're
acknowledging we're giving them credit that they have
resources maybe we're reaching out to a friend for their time for their care for
their wisdom um for their
um know-how for their skills we're acknowledging them we're seeing them we're letting them be seen and how
beautiful it is what a gift it is to let someone be seen and of course in this
way of asking for help and support there's a lot of wisdom that comes here
that in to to be appropriate with our request not to be overwhelming with our
request but both to ourselves but to others it's also the other aspect of
generosity as the Buddha teaches about generosity to give to people
um appropriately not to tax ourselves not to be um
Not to cause ourselves harm or other people harm when we are being generous
right similarly the other way around when we're asking for help to keep those in
mind right to keep um to ask for support and help in the
wise and caring way um so so as to acknowledge
of both others limitations and in some cases actually we can let them them decide so it's anyway this can be a much
longer discussion uh because there's so many caveats here but but but let's
let's um let's consider reaching for support as how can it be
what are the areas in our lives that we don't reach for support and it would
behoove us and others to actually acknowledge our interdependence and and
ask for support so so
I think I've said enough and let's I'm gonna do a guided meditation I'm sure
questions Etc will arise we'll we'll discuss at the end but for now let's not uh invite
our minds not to get into all the caveats and oh what if this what if that and and try to stay with with this
simple with the Simplicity of these Reflections in ways that you know can be
supportive for you you know if there are areas that it's not supportive for you
it's okay let it go you don't have to get stuck in those what ifs right now
but see the ways that it can be supportive and nourishing for you okay
all right so so uh let's practice together so I'd like to
invite you to get into your meditation posture
ah to arrive to land in this body
In This Moment
feeling the presence of this body a sense of the weightiness of the body
the weightiness of the body sitting
present here
feeling your uprightness and sense of agency this fullness
of heart fullness of your presence
and relaxing softening
letting your feet your legs
be released their way to be released unto the Earth
feeling here
stably rooted to the Earth
feeling your sit bones
of the cushion than the chair
we're releasing the weight of your upper body and to the Earth
and letting your heart letting your heart center the center of your emotions
ah you're releasing
letting there be flow as if there's a flowing river
flowing electricity ah
so you're grounded connected to the Earth let this flow
Let There Be flow not stuckness
therapy flow through the body with the breath
rest through the abdomen through the chest
releasing the upper body releasing the shoulders the neck
forehead the face
and letting the breath move through
with each and breath and not breath relaxing calming
and energizing each in-breath energizing
deepening your sense of presence
the major out breath relaxing
feeling more here connected to this present moment
engaged training your mind
your heart to be engaged
with what is here right now
letting go of thoughts preoccupations plans
let this moment be a treat let you're engaging with the Simplicity of the breath
this breath then we'll be present let it be a treat
in order to go nothing to do how delicious
Justice an act of care
thank you
engaging with each breath each and every breath
an expression of care for yourself in this moment
you are showing up taking the time taking care
engaging with the breath
a sense of presence right here right now letting go releasing
oh it's judgments preoccupations as much as possible
this showing up as an act of care it's meta it is meta
says if you're wrapping yourself in a blanket of mitta
Goodwill for yourself by just showing up
engaging as best as you're able to and not judging yourself that's enough
feeling your feet on the earth your sit bones feeling embodied
here
supported by yourself supported by your own care
how awesome is this
and if you like you can drop in this question Into Your Heart Center into your body
not into your head this is not something to think about but to feel and to see what comes up
dropping this question
acknowledging acknowledging my own resourcefulness my own power my own
agency My Own Strength
feeling your rootedness to the Earth your sit bones your brightness
acknowledging my own resourcefulness
as well as my own vulnerability areas that I feel challenged
I need support to fulfill my full potential my
potential in my Humanity
dropping in this question into your heart
is there a way that I can support myself that I can better support myself be a
better friend to myself if I were asking my dear self for help
for support
what would it be drop it into your heart don't think about it
an answer might come up and be known in your body or nothing
might come up it's okay let your body be a tuning fork
how can I better love and support myself
nor does the support I can ask for myself and I can offer myself
after dropping the question Let It Go don't well
Just Breathe and listen
with your heart
it works better if you don't think if you really let go let yourself be surprised try it
soften the body soften the Mind release release ruin these
just receiving the breath with care appreciation
thank you
and letting this not be an opportunity to judge yourself
find out all your shortcomings but
a terrible your strength the gifts that you have the wisdom that
you already have your own inner wisdom and compassion for yourself
foreign
not dropping the question into your heart still feeling embodied not in your head
feeling your feet your sit bones your hands foreign
areas there's something in my life something that
I do need support with help with and maybe I have a sense of
shyness to ask for help or feel vulnerable or whatever the reason
but
it would really support me and others that I serve and support
if I reached out for support in this area
what if what if I opened up
acknowledge my interdependence
opened up what it opened up to this River this flow of
giving and receiving and invited asked for support ask for
help
realizing that not only would this benefit me but
likely the person who will be seen recognized acknowledged
for the goodness for the capacity to support me and this co-creation goodness good support
could help others it's bigger than me it's not just for me
what's beyond me I have the support
I can be more available support others better
it's not just about me
dropping in this reflection into your heart into your body and yourself let yourself breathe with
it hard thinking with it but just breathe this is not the thinking exercise we've
already planted the seed of the reflection now just breathe let it seep into your
cells not your head but yourselves cells of
your body to receive the breath
appreciate the breath relax soften
let's go
even though it's so juicy to think now let go you can do it let's go
foreign
asking for help or support it's not just about me
it's not a selfish Act
and allow us be more to fulfill our potential
to serve others to be available for others
it's impersonal acknowledge being part of this
low of giving receiving [Music]
receiving gifts giving gifts needing
meeting others needs be beautiful acknowledged to be vulnerable in this
way
it's both personal and not personal
asking for help oath helps us another is fulfilled
calling our Humanity
the all beings everywhere recognize acknowledge
that we are part of this expansive
interdependence of giving receiving giving help receiving help
asking may all beings everywhere
be supported
support others ask for support
towards fulfilling our full potential of our weakening may all beings be free including
ourselves [Music]
thank you so much for your practice everyone thank you
ah so we have a few minutes for Reflections questions comments what you
might have discovered realized aha moments challenges can raise your Zoom
hand you can type in chat if you type to everyone I will read your name if you just type
to me it'll be a private comment and uh what did you discover or what did
you realize ah
any aha moments more challenges for the benefit of everyone
and as I wait I'll maybe share with practice reports something that came up for me which is
um a sense of there is a sense of empowerment in recognizing areas that
that I shy away from asking for help or support and how actually it's impersonal
it's it's not about me asking for help supports me support others it's such an
interesting realization it really expands the heart expands my heart
um into into seeing that that interaction Madison please
yeah um I had like a reflection and then a question
um the reflection was similar to what I'm gonna lower my hand okay
what you just said of I've never thought about the fact that like when I look to
myself for help it's like a way of recognizing that I
have resources to give myself and I I just really want I really
appreciated that that perspective so thank you for that nice thank you
and I I'm wondering so I love this framework around asking people for support because
it's it's a way of giving them like you said an opportunity to feel their own value and to be connected and
and do a generous Act um and I've been struggling with a few
family members who have become very greedy
um with like around money and
I and like in the same way that I've asked for support and locked from
through lots of forms like I think asking for money is the same thing um it's a way of
giving them an opportunity to be generous so I'm I've never really dealt with someone like
yeah I just wanted to know if you had any advice on how to work with that or
just be patient or just continue to like give them love I don't know
um but I was stuck with that yeah thank you Madison thanks for both of these Reflections and really also
want to acknowledge again the first one just this sense of oh yeah empowerment I
have resources to give myself a sense of empowerment it's yeah there's wonderfully and there is strength wow
such a beautiful realization I want to celebrate that and really highlight that and um
this asking for for support for help and especially when it comes to financial
support um it's it's so interesting that money can can bring up this this this not
um uh for for many people even if they have the resources but it you know if
they don't have resources that's another thing but if they do have it it can be complicated and yet it's such a great
area for practice it's such a great area for practice for everyone so so for you
as as you brought it in it becomes a practice of of um
asking or inviting them giving them the opportunity to to support you uh giving
them the opportunity to be kind to be generous so it's an invitation from your heart
with that perspective and to be very clear in your heart as you are asking
them that you are going to care that care for them love them no matter what
but that you need to be clear in that ask it needs to be part of your practice
um so that's the part I invite for you and maybe even say that as you sit with
it as you practice with it in your invitation that this is the way that your support your help will support me
and I care for you I love you it's not going to impact our relationship either way so so you really need to be clear
that in your own heart in your own practice and then you give them the opportunity
with with it they'll accept it or not or they'll get entangled and that becomes part of their practice right
um and but as long as you have this Clarity of intention and Clarity of Love
um for you that can be this this ease yeah yeah I think the this ease is like
my like heartbreaking over there their heart clothing
but I think yeah just connecting to like the love is probably a good way to ease
that feeling yeah yeah exactly and connecting to the love and also connect to the compassion especially if they do
have the resources um and and they're getting tied for and for you to have compassion for them
really connect Like Loving them so much that ah loving their their karmic
potential you know you know what they how should I put it there's a sense of um you know your heart not closing if
they are getting entangled loving the the pain they are going through
loving them even more with compassion but they're getting entangled
right it's so taking a bigger perspective does that make sense
yeah thank you so much yeah thanks for bringing that in Madison
yeah um Claire I see your hand and
um asking you to unmute and I see he who says one B cannot create a honey Factory it takes a hive I love that
um no I just want to thank you very much because this is an area that I have been working on and continue to work on more
I think I've mentioned before I'm an only child and I grew up fiercely
independent and self-reliant um and as life went on and I started
meeting more life experiences unpleasant life experiences I started to learn a
little bit but I forget to ask for help at the point but what I discovered when I started to do it that I really wanted
to share with the others in case anybody hasn't tried it yet is that there are a heck of a lot of people who really like
to help and it makes them happy when you ask and it was it's such a pleasant
experience when that happens you know I don't do it frivolously but there are times that I really do need help and you
know I'm now very comfortable with you know if I ask the right people there
it's going to work and they will be grateful for having been asked and I'll get one you know the support that I at
this point need so um I think it's a great topic thank you yeah beautiful thank you so much Claire
I love it I both love that as you share it you you've you know you grew up as an with a sense of Independence and I'll do
it myself and not asking for it and then you've taught yourself to oh yes to ask and how beautiful that is that learning
that re re reteaching yourself loveliness you're you're teaching yourself it's like if this poem flower
teaching itself I'm totally messing it up but maybe somebody will type the who remembers the poem the flower that
reteaches itself its own loveliness or reminds itself of its own loveliness there's a sense oh yeah oh yeah teaching
yourself of your about your interdependence and then what you what I so appreciate you highlight
is is yes people love to help I found that too it's it's it's beautiful that
people are happy to help and and I know that for myself when somebody asks me for support I'm happy to support them
yes I'd love to so it's it's such is so powerful to to acknowledge that yeah
yeah thanks Claire it's so appreciate you bringing that in yeah such a delight okay well it is time
to turn to um small groups and here's the prompt I have for us to play with uh the The
Prompt is what are the ways what is there an area in your life that you can
um you could ask for support that you kind of shy away and and it would help you to ask for support either from
yourself or from others and in the group you can say a nugget and that next
person will say nugget next person will say nugget go around and round where you can offer presents and silence and say
pass like don't have something yet and um just um share share your presence and
um what else do I want to say about the groups yeah any other Reflections you want to
share with each other inspiring supporting how can you offer
support and Care uh to each other so so I am going to create the rooms now
and uh hold on I said yeah okay the rooms are created
[Music] and I'm going to open up take care of yourself take care of each other
and uh here we go okay all the rooms are closed
everybody's back and it is seven o'clock I wonder if if you have any quick last
minute comments oh okay 30 second quick round
and you haven't spoken tonight you're welcome to share something came up in the practice
discussions
any takers lightning round
I see enough okay nav please
whoops wait he got muted against her accidentally try again oh
I think I muted you there okay
um so in our group we had this um exploration of giving others the
opportunity to give through asking for help which which I love that reframe it's sort of uh it's not asking for help
it's giving someone else an opportunity to give love it beautiful thanks so much for
bringing that into the space and what a lovely note to end on ah thank you all
thank you so much for for being here and uh and through your presence creating
the opportunity for me to be here to share the teachings so thank you so much
for your practice may all beings be well may all beings be free including
ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone take good care bye [Music]