good morning everybody good morning it's a joy for me to be here
this morning to be invited to come and join you here
at insight meditation center i've spent some time
in this space while being with the
sati buddhist chaplaincy training program but i've never had the chance to
come and practice here on a sunday morning so
i was a little bit nervous about being in a new space with new people
and now that i'm here i'm feeling much more relaxed so thank you for welcoming me
thank you when i um was talking to gil
about being here this morning and i was asking him you know what the order of events was
and i said to him well will i should i ring a bell at the beginning of the meditation
and gil said something along the lines of oh well we're not nearly so delineated
there's there's no need for a bell thing the meditation just starts and flows in
and you know i started thinking about that you know the ways in which
we bring ourselves into this space you know whether it's
just by some simple sound a bell i thought of
a poem that's very dear to me by the poet david white called the bell and the
blackbird where at the beginning of the poem he says
the sound of a bell still reverberating or a blackbird calling from a corner of
the field asking you to wake into this life
or inviting you deeper into the one that waits
so i thought well there could be a bell or there could not be a bell or perhaps there'd be the
sound of a bird what is it what is the little sound what is the cue
that brings us here
so the place where i practice which is cannondo zen center in mountain view
like many other zen centers we have outside our meditation hall
a big block of wood called a han the name of this is a han it's a big block
of wood and there's a mallet that comes with it and then
before every session of meditation the wood is struck
in a particular way with often with great force depending on the size of the
the center and how far the noise needs to travel and over the years
many hands begin to become indented and they'll sort of have a big sort of
splintered hole in the middle of them that attests
to the amount of energy and effort that has gone into striking them calling
people to practice and often these hands have
like a a poem um inscribed or rather painted on them
and the exact wording of the poem differs
um from one place to the next that's not always exactly the same
but usually the words are more or less to this effect
it goes something like great is the matter
of birth and death quickly passing gone gone
awake each one awaken
don't waste this life
so this message is conveyed often in this
very definitive sound of the wood being hit with a mallet
and the invitation is well whatever we're doing in that moment whatever activity
we're involved in best to wind that up as quickly as
possible and try and get to the meditation hall in time for sitting
and well it's part of my personality that i'm not always very good at being on
time for things and often i'm running i often in my head
i associate the sound of the wood with great effort being exerted and being out
of breath and trying to get to a place on time
and sometimes i think oh you know what's my what's my motivation here in
my hurry what am i worried am i worried about being in trouble sometimes i i get
flashbacks to being at school being late for class you know am i going to get shouted out by somebody
is somebody going to think less of me because i'm late am i going to disturb somebody else's
practice if the meditation hall is quiet when i enter you know all these very sort of
self-centered thoughts that arise very surface motivations also but
they're they're the first ones that come up for me in my hurry
so then i think well what are the deeper motivators
what's the what's the more fundamental source
of motivation for practice and i find this a very rousing question
for me it's a driving question
in the zen tradition we refer to the mind of practice
mind of practice and we talk about giving rise
to the mind of practice
which is something like allowing our our true nature our original nature to
emerge to flow freely
i think of a river flowing freely without impediments
not a river that's dammed up or that has been prevented from taking its natural course
but the energy of that flow that has has found its natural direction
and it just goes
and this kind of image is helpful to me for thinking about the sort of effort
and energy necessary for spiritual practice
because fundamentally when we at least when we start practice and
even in the day-to-day practicalities around practice
we require effort you know we talk about effort
just showing up here today
getting here having found a teacher maybe you know
having put that effort in to open towards a tradition and a teaching
to learn maybe even reading a book or two
on the subject
and then the efforts that we put into meditation itself you know
it can be very difficult at first just to just to stay put
and put yourself there and
perhaps when we're first starting out we might have been sitting for a few weeks and
then think uh but i don't know what's changed my brain's
still ticking over i'm still having all these thoughts i feel
so distracted and that can feel very demotivating
i can feel like ah what am i doing wrong
am i doing something wrong maybe i'm not trying hard enough
maybe i need to try harder that's what i need to do you know
maybe i'm not dedicated enough
and so we try harder and
maybe that can bring us some difficulty too working with these
levels of energy is a skill it's a skillful thing
that we we work with as our practice develops i kind of think of it a bit like you
know salt and cooking a little not enough or too much can
you know totally ruin the deal like knowing just how much
well there's a skill in that
so there's a story that came up for me when i was thinking about this maybe this is a story you've already heard and it reads a
little bit like a joke in fact so there was a
a martial arts student who went to his teacher in great earnest
and asked his teacher he said you know i'm really i'm really devoted
to studying this system i really want to learn everything you can teach me
how long will it take me to master this how long will it take me to get to where you are
and the teacher thought about it kind of casually just threw out an answer no
10 years and the student
very impatient and shocked and answered but
no like i need to do it faster than that i want to you know i have enthusiasm
i will work very hard i'll practice every day i'll i'll do this for 10 12 hours you tell me i'll be here the whole
time if i do this how long will it take then
and the teacher thought again for a moment and replied
20 years
so as that story suggests um sometimes the harder we try
the further away we get to where we think we might want to be going
and the late zen teacher from who was a teacher here in the area shinryu
suzuki who was a teacher up in san francisco
he used to say that the right kind of energy is very important
and if there was such a thing as bad effort um he would say that well
that's the kind of effort that moves in the wrong direction
so that would be something like maybe moving against the current
you know the wrong direction direction that requires
more effort so i think about cycling sometimes i like to go cycling and
sometimes it gets very windy around here and maybe some of you have had this experience but i like to cycle
over by shoreline and the bay lands some beautiful trails there
and some days i go and i'll be cycling north and there's a southeasterly wind of like 18 miles an
hour and it's really hard it's like like pushing against this wind and it
i get horribly frustrated and you know i start to feel myself you know wishing
wishing for something else you know wishing that it be different like ugh i'm expending so much energy and
i don't have that wonderful feeling of just you know moving gliding on two wheels which is the part that i love
about cycling
so then when we apply that to practice that image what does it mean
when in our practice our efforts move in the right direction
so another another prominent figure in in zen teaching and
in soto zen teaching specifically was a a monk and a teacher from the 13th
century called hey dogen and
on the subject of effort in practice he he provided some images to his
students to to take away and to think about to chew on he said to them think about the kind of
effort that would be exerted by a thief trying to steal a precious jewel
well think about the kind of effort that would be that would arise for a warrior
about to fight a formidable
enemy or maybe the kind of energy and
effort that comes up in the heart of somebody who's in love
and wants to get the attention of their beloved
that sort of rich boundless energy that would be in somebody's heart
at that moment
and so i think what he's trying to say here you know not necessarily encouraging us towards you
know theft and violence but that the the energy that's present
in all of these examples it's inherent it's it's already there
it's not something that needs to be forced it's something that can be used
tapped into
so maybe in in some ways we can we can all relate to this on some level
that kind of focus when
we move towards an object of desire you know maybe something that we really want
a beloved person an activity that we become
fixated on survival you know whether it's just our
own survival the survival of someone we love
i'm a parent i um i think about
the kind of attention and energy i put into being around my
daughter when she first started to walk or when she first rode a bicycle and my
heart was in my mouth being next to her just every wobble like
you know and there's not much that would have distracted me at that moment
you know i absolutely feel like by how i have this biological
programming as a parent to you know
have her at the forefront of my attention
especially if there's some danger in the air
so the effort's already there in abundance and i think the way that i
understand master dogan's teaching you know the way that he talks
about energy in this way is that there's an encouragement here to
try and find a quality of effort that can be sustainable
um that would be healthy and not and not be depleting
you know if you spend half an hour
cycling against the wind you won't get very far
and you might end up feeling very frustrated and tired physically in your body
if you turn around and point your bike in the other direction it would be a very different kind of
experience
so how to bring that quality or even that intensity of energy
[Music] into everyday life into practice
into moments that are not necessarily exciting or fraught
you know maybe especially starting out in practice we may just have a
a moderate sort of idea that oh this would be good for me this is a good thing to do
seems good people who meditate they seem to be
happy happier maybe maybe not but you know maybe this is a direction
i'd like to move in or maybe i feel very strongly about this today
but how will i feel next week or next month or next year like how could i sustain this
over time how to really find an authentic
motivation in myself in the midst of distractions and tiredness
or maybe just too much comfort safety you know
or just moments of feeling disengaged how to do
that so what master dogen said
he said well you can't just make this up you can't just will it into being
or think about it you know do it this is not an intellectual exercise
it's not something that can be done by some temporary method of contemplation
instead he taught this he said that in order to arouse
this mind of practice we need to try and tap into what's
already there we need to
prime the ground so that it can appear so that it can rise up
and his recommendation for this you know he said what what we can all work with
is we can all practice with impermanence
impermanence
so what is it about impermanence you know
this is something that's very core to buddhist teaching
but how can practicing with impermanence you know
give rise to this kind of energy well at least when when i think about this
you know the most um the first example that comes up for me is you know thinking about death it's very obvious
sort of stands for it seems to be the first kind of image of impermanence that rises
up for many of us through various points in my life
especially as a young person death the idea of death has been quite a
fixation for me
on the one hand it's it's generated a lot of actual sort of physical fear you
know felt sensations of fear in my body this idea of extinction
this may be a very natural response to the prospect of
extinction is a kind of a bodily fear
a kind of panic as though i was already you know facing a very hungry tiger or
something sort of a flight or fight energy it can be a very strong kind of bodily
energy so that's you know that's one thing that i experience in the face of
impermanence
and then there's a more kind of mental reaction that comes along with it too
this is a you know perhaps um
in the face of of death or in contemplating death in an intellectual way we sort of arrive at a bit of an impasse
sometimes it's something that's very hard to understand i think for me
in contemplating impermanence in this way it was sort of hard to understand how
we just carry on with our daily lives and
not be addressing this very urgently you know day by day
so this was this this question that came up if you know how to live in the in the face of impermanence you know for me
this generated a lot of energy um in wanting to well find an answer find a solution you know
and there's a wonderful um little student master exchange in the
zen tradition that i heard recently that i just thought ah yes the student asked the master one day
what is the direct way to obtain buddha's wisdom what is the direct way
to obtain buddha's wisdom and the master replied there is nothing more direct than this question
think that's it you know the question's there and you're off
they say the question's there the way opens
i was with a friend recently who sadly lost
their their pet you know they just lost their pet and
we were talking about this and you know what a what a traumatic experience this had
been for this person and they'd actually been
in the vets with their pet when the pet was put down
um and then they were administered i suppose an injection and
you know they were holding the animal and then one moment the animal was alive and the next moment
they were gone and this this friend is a fellow
practitioner and he said to me you know i um
and excuse me i'm paraphrasing him but this was how i understood what he said to me he said
you know i i've come to through my practice try and understand impermanence
on some level and i can try and understand our
interrelatedness as human beings and as as all life forms in the world and
there's ways in which i can understand birth but he said i can't get my head around
this i don't understand this death i don't understand
where this member of my family has gone
it just it created a you know a kind of a wall for him and he said i'm you know
i'm trying to look at all the teachings that are out there but there's nothing that's resonating with
me right now
and what i noticed was it it gave rise to a kind of energy in him almost an anger that seemed very
motivating what he wasn't saying was like so you know having having had this experience
now i'm just gonna pack up and not try anymore you know it seemed to want to push him forward
into something and what that is isn't necessarily entirely obvious
at first
so there was a another zen master in 17th century china called wu yi yuanlai
who's also popularly known in japan as master boshan
and master boshan would be very happy with this situation with my friend he would be very happy because he he
would he like to hear his students express this kind of situation for themselves
he he very much felt that this was the door that would open and lead students into practice and lead
them toward awakening there's a there's a phrase that says great doubt
great awakening that's the idea great doubt great awakening and
master yan lai said he said if you genuinely inquire
you rouse this doubt and you wield it as a razor sharp sword
whoever comes in contact with its blade will be annihilated
that strong a wonderful image
so i don't know um how many of you are familiar with the rinzai school of zen i know myself i'm
only very faintly familiar but one of the things that some people know
about the rinzai school is that they they practice with koans the koan
is a kind of a situation or a sort of a puzzle that's given to a student
and it can you know it's something that just stays with you and it's something
that doesn't make sense and maybe sticks with you and
eventually it challenges a student's sense of the world you know to the extent where
they might start their paradigms of the world would start to shift
you know they would start to be a fundamental kind of change
so this was a great insight i think from from the rinzai masters that something
that gives people energy is problem solving you know it's very hard to sit
with a problem and just let it go like we have this we have this
desire you know to find resolution a lot so this this is harnessed in some
practices so in summary
um you know thinking about the different kinds of energies that arise from
the practice and contemplation of impermanence they can be any they can be things like
fear or even anger doubt
longing puzzling problem solving
or joy
all responses that come from different parts of ourselves maybe
different different personalities for different people maybe some of us are more driven by
questions maybe some of us are more driven by fear maybe some of us are driven by a sense
of longing a sense of wanting to connect with something we don't even quite know what it is
and to address the the last mention of or
and joy i think of mary oliver's beautiful poem wild geese
in which she says you do not have to walk
on your knees for a hundred miles through the desert repenting
you only have to let the soft animal of your body
love what it loves you do not have to walk on your knees
for a hundred miles through the desert repenting you only have to let the soft animal of
your body love what it loves
she's talking about trusting ourselves and trusting what
arises whatever it is that's bringing us here
letting the soft animal bodies love what we love
fear what we fear long for whatever we long for
because first if you're thirsty you'll get yourself to water
and if you're hungry you'll get yourself to food right if you're tired you'll you'll find
your bed eventually and so what is it in you that's bringing
you here what is it that's fueling your spiritual practice
what are you responding to
and i'll finish with um a quote from another late zen teacher called cobenchino
he said when you realize how rare
and precious your life is
and how it's completely your responsibility
how you decide to live it how you manifest it
that's such a big responsibility that naturally
such a person sits down for a while
it's not an intended action
it's a natural
action may all beings benefit from practice
may they be happy may they be joyous and may they be safe
and may every river run into the sea
so we have thank you we have a couple couple of minutes left
i think on the clock if you have any responses reflections even questions
yes please if you live with joy the way you
described it and wisdom the way buddhism describes wisdom
what is the state of awakening that might come
at some point could you repeat the question sorry so
you said that the joy well you uh you mentioned that if you
live naturally and let the the shelby say the
the better part of you the loving part of you to manifest itself in real life
and and have joy be the driving force
how does it lead to awakening
in the moment when true joy
is manifest true joy as a response to
life and the understanding
of this conscious being
just that moment itself is awakening
thank you very much thank you thank you for that question
thank you yeah i was um hurrying to a retreat once and this bit of doggerel arose in my mind
something like i'm late i'm late i cannot wait i must hurry up and
meditate [Music] anyway
and uh so thank you for mentioning doubt and uncertainty it's interesting the interplay between
doubt and confidence trust
um and another thing is that you know another translation for a nietzsche is
uncertainty so anyway if you have any any comments
what was the word you used the translation that you translated
the three whatever they are
is um uncertainty or impermanence anata is not self and
is suffering pain
and how do you how do you experience them as interrelating
so the the theravada term for those is the three characteristics of existence
and so they uh there are fundamental
things that operate in our in our existence they're
demonstrably true yeah thank you
yes please bill i just want to thank you for early in your talk
raising [Music] the question of noticing how
those thoughts will persist during meditation and
then wondering can i do this or am i not dedicated enough or is there something
wrong with me so i i know that's
the persistence of daydreams during meditation is a very common
still it's helpful to hear that even teachers
sometimes have that experience too thank you
sometimes even more than sometimes i didn't want to say that
thank you thank you all so much
thank you i wish you a good day and a good
continuation of your weekend