so hello everyone and welcome
and this
mindfulness that we're exploring and discovering it's always a discovery
this dharma that we're discovering here and now
is always a discovery it's always a feeling that
not a feeling but all that we never go we never bother
never go to the effort of thinking
that we've seen it before we never have to
have the mental the neurons firing that's saying this is not interesting or
this is too much this is you know not what i was hoping for
all those kinds of ideations are not needed in the simplicity
of just here and now as something to be known to be
experienced to be felt in its radical simplicity
and yesterday i offered this teaching about this the ouch and the ah
without needing to analyze what the ouch is or what the eye
is or think about its past and its future and what to do about it keep it that simple
the other sim very radical simplicity of this practice
is to be with the experience the ouches the ahs the knowing of it the ex whatever
the experience is even if it's not out your ah but to
be with it as with in the changing river of time to be with it in the current
of how things are always flowing past or through
it's kind of like a little bit like we're standing in a
river and maybe we're not we're not we're standing
but in the moment right with us the the water is always flowing by
and to stay in the flow of the present moment as it comes from the comes from the past in a sense and goes
to the future comes from the future and flows back to the past whatever your metaphor
might be just right here in the changing nature and what's interesting is that this
principle this being grounded as best we can here and now in the changing flowing nature of it
is that what we discover is the ways that we
freeze the moment the way we resist the change the way we step out of that flow
by thinking by wanting something different by remembering the past or the future
reacting to something wanting to analyze it figure it out these movements out of the river of time
out of the river of change and movement and flow of what's happening
and that flow of change that we tune into is both the change of experiences that they
come and go and use new new experiences come that weren't expected maybe and they're there for a moment and something
else comes but they also involve the changing nature of the knowing itself
knowing is a little bit fickle knowing knowing jumps around and
and um uh and um
and so to kind of be there so like if you're with your breathing and then
you're with some kind of thoughts about the breath or about yesterday's breathing then um
the knowing the awareness has shifted to something else and there's a sound outside the knowing
shifts to the sound and is it a knowing that shifts and moves is it the sound that moves that
comes to you is moving what is it that's you know the constant moving of the mind of awareness
of experiences not to be straining to look for it that that's just more
kind of freezing in the flow but relaxing into the very simplicity
of the experience here and now to know it for oneself
so to assume a meditation posture
a posture of confidence that yes
maybe with a yes yes i will sit here
in a sense standing in the ground standing in the middle of the river
of time yes here's where i'll sit be present
with confidence taking a few long slow deep breaths
and on the exhales closing the eyes and
settling into this spot here now
and letting your breathing return to normal
and continue on the exhale the inhale to feel your body feel where the holding is
maybe holding tension is a little bit of an ouch
feeling that on the inhale and the exhale letting your
letting your body relax soften
and then quietly peacefully calming the mind
relaxing the thinking mind
and as you're experiencing your breathing the breathing itself the way it's
experienced in the body is a changing experience
to some degree it's a change that repeats itself
but it's still a changing experience
and spend some time now centering yourself from the changing nature
of sensations connected to breathing
and as you do so become aware also of the changing nature
of what you know of the knowing itself
that you might know the breathing the mind might move if awareness might
move to know something else my voice and then back to the breathing
stay centered on the breathing the changing nature of sensations
but be aware as well of where the knowing is and how the
knowing might come and go and where it goes
it too is changing don't worry about the change if you can
just know and see the change
maybe with your breathing maybe some other way
know how your experiences in the moment now here
are changing and be aware of
how your knowing itself shifts and changes
these two exchanging things their experience and our knowing
relax back into that awareness alertness
that can allow this to flow along in the present moment the shifting changing nature of
experience and of knowing
both are in the flow of time
what we experience is changing shifting
the knowing is changing and shifting
both the known and the knowing
come and go and change
calmly being aware of change
change of what we know and the knowing itself
and if you're aware of all this with a kind of
background awareness or overviewing awareness
they can know what's happening with your knowing
that awareness
is maybe where freedom is found
being aware of change
the shifting moving in constant nature of our experience
being aware of it and resting in that awareness
kind of like you're not standing in the river but floating in the river of change
carried along in the current
that's where freedom is found
where that is where you can feel that you're resisting or
change or stuck and not moving along with change
as soon as you know clearly that you're stuck clearly not in the river of change
that moment in a way you're back in the river
if you trust it if you allow for it it's just another moment of knowing
that has just arisen
and as we come to the end of this sitting
the end is just a continu continuation of change and comings and
goings just another
moment in the river of time that's
we only connect to in the present
and to be at ease in this river
to not freeze it or be stuck in some way
not hang on to the branches on the sides of
hanging over the sides of the river
to be available for the changing nature of this world
where the present moment is not static but dynamic
to be available and open receptive
and to see that that it can be at that stance that way
of being can be a gift for how we are in the world
certainly many of the other ways of being is not a gift
but to be present and available aware and
attuned to how things shift and change
and to be present to feel it to sense it is a way of connecting more deeply to
other people into our life
may it be that the freedom of our awareness
our ability to be aware freely with freedom
allows for a wonderful channel
of our care and good will to flow into the world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may our ability to be mindful aware here in the present
contribute to this possibility
[Music]
thank you
so we come to the
fifth and last talk on the characteristics qualities of the
dharma the dhamma that has been well spoken of by the
buddha so to some degree it's talking about his teaching and what is but it's also talking about
what his teachings what is dhamma is pointing to what the dhamma is is the truth
that we're discovering through this practice and it's also
the the the way we discover it the means by which we discover it and this uh
combination of the means of what we're discovering and what we're discovering
speaks to this intimacy certainly of mindfulness practice
but also the intimacy of the means and the goal that the goal to be free to be
aware and open free unrestricted way
that not doing it completely but in partial ways beginning to to live that goal in the
means to practice being present in a clear direct full way
here and these uh five qualities of the dhamma that
i've been going through this week is to
is the dhamma which is visible here
that it's now it's immediate that it is
inviting inspection inviting us to see come and see so this coming to see opening to see
here now seeing here now that's kind of at the heart of what
we're doing here and if we enter this world of seeing knowing being present here and now
then we find that something opens for us the an open door
or an open current of what's onward leading we can see a path we see a movement
towards what is wholesome and healthy where the eye is we see the ouch
and we can see how our clinging and grasping and hate and
delusion and ambition is a freezing of time
is a being stuck outs you know without being in the in the free flow of time being free in the time in time
in the flow of here and now and we feel the out show that
and as we see it and be with it there's a at some point we see or intuit
or feel there's something an alternative to that and that alternative we get a sense of
it is the ah is the possibility of non-green non-hatred
non-delusion non-conceit non-reactivity just here in a relaxed
open way and something begins to flow and to move where we start
flowing in the flow of the present moment we start being carried by this wholesome healthy direction
of practice of and and that this is to be experienced
this dumb must be experienced the last quality is the dhamma is to be experienced
directly actually the languages this dhamma is to be
personally experienced by the wise
so personally experienced by the wise so we're talking about something that in a
sense only you yourself can really experience know for yourself
so i don't know if it's the best examples but um maybe only you
know that you're hungry only you know you can tell people and maybe you can give the symptoms of
it to people but it's a the experience of hunger is internal to oneself
the experience of having an itch people might not know you have an itch but you certainly can know it
you have to pee that's something we experience for ourselves
so certain so there might be better examples for each of you rather than what i came up with but they did some things only we
can experience for ourselves and so there is a way in which this dhamma
is to enter into that world which we can only experience we ourselves can experience personally
and the way there's ouches and oz is really something we experience
experientially we can know that for ourselves and we can know for ourselves
whether things are stuck or whether things are flowing and moving maybe other people can intuit that
looking at how we behave but this is something to be experienced for oneself really so this is almost
internal or this deep very personal very intimate involvement with the present moment with
here and our direct experience and what we can experience most valuably
is not complicated so this is not an engineering job it's not some
sophisticated analysis it's not remembering causes and understanding why things happen or
planning out the future and what should happen it's rather than
there's something extremely powerful and freeing about keeping it radically simple in the
present moment the only place where we can really directly personally know for ourselves
how things are shifting and changing moving how they appear and disappear
their inconstancy their impermanence and
and not to be straining to see that but more like resting back into it
and seeing the changing nature of so this uh
personally experienced by the wise the experience wise that the wise person
um is mentioned here and and now my favorite definition that the
buddha gives for a wise person a wise person is concerned with the welfare of self the welfare of
others the welfare of self and others and the welfare of all beings i think
it's such a beautiful definition of wisdom because it doesn't require opening up all the dharma books and learning all
the lists and all the teachings it's more of an attitude it's something
that arises within but as a practice deepens a wise person
part of the reason a wise person is interested in the welfare of everyone including oneself
is because in the direct experience of the moment we see very clearly
this um ah and ouch we can feel the movement to the ah to
what where welfare is where well-being is where peace is and
and that comes together with seeing impermanence and change
because when we don't see the changing impermanent moving nature of reality
we're probably locked on in some way we've frozen we've gotten contracted or caught or
in some way on something some preoccupation and maybe trying to think about how things
can things really be in constant and changing so much we start thinking about that we've kind of removed ourselves
from the experience the directness immediacy of what's changing and we can feel that movement we can
feel the ouch of that maybe very very subtle but a little bit of strain or attention
and we can feel that there is a way in which the ah comes from coming back into the river of change of flow and movement
and and all that and to see this uh it's not an easy
thing i'm talking about so you can't just decide to sit down and do it but as a practice deepens and as we
settle in more and more and feel more confident and more at ease and more able to stay
mindful of the present more continuously at some point this opens up for us we
start seeing the changing nature of our experience the changing nature of our knowing of
experience sometimes we're more aware of how experience is changing like the
breathing sensations are changing sometimes i'm more aware of how the knowing of it is a changing moving
phenomena that the knowing is cooperates a little bit sometimes independent of what we have
chosen to know because if we start thinking we you know the mind is kind of no the knowing mind
knows different things there's a sound outside and now we know the sound rather for a moment rather than for
the breathing there's a thought about how much time is left in this meditation
and we know that and then we're back into the breathing we might be
knowing something about the breath and then we notice that now next what we know is we notice that
there is some sensation that does in that area of the chest where we're doing breathing but you know
it may be not directly connected to breathing how did you shift how did the how did the knowing move that knowing
changed and all this no all this knowing of change
uh is the at the heart of of uh
you know what uh some people are called and translate into what's called vidja
in pali and vijaya some people translate as true knowledge vija is liberating
knowledge the liberating understanding or knowing vijaya is the opposite of avijja which
is ignorance so if we use ignorance in the opposite in english i guess would be gnosis
but knowing understanding seeing and so a wise person is
is a vin vinu is the word is connected to this word vidya
and so someone who knows what's beneficial what knows what welfare is is concerned
with it and can see that in the direct moment of being attuned to
the changing quiet flowing nature of phenomena and in that awareness of that
not looking for freedom but in the awareness of all that
freedom is revealed letting go and non-clinging is revealed
to be personally experienced by the wise to know for yourself from the inside
that the mind is not clinging to anything attached to anything holding on to anything at least for a short period of time
trusting that finding that being that is
is this art of this dhamma that the buddha is talking about so
uh so we have at this uh the dhamma
uh spoken by the buddha
well spoken is the dhamma of the buddha it is
visible here it's immediate now
it is to be see it is inviting us to see deeply
it is uh onward leading and to be personally experienced by the
wise and in pali this is often chanted in pali and my pali chanting is not so
great but i'll offer you my best effort for it
so you have to kind of be generous to the chanting but that's the poly
so so thank you and i hope that
this kind of teachings about the dhamma can give you some deeper
trust and confidence in the mindfulness and don't be so concerned about
how far you practice or whether what i'm talking about today this week is exactly where you are in your
practice but have confidence that doing this practice it's onward leading
and you don't you're not necessarily responsible for the onward leading nature of it
we are setting the conditions for it by being present and mindful
and then when the time is right the dhamma is onward leading within us
and may you become a wise person free liberated
and concerned for the welfare of all may all beings be well
thank you