so hello and welcome to happy hour everyone
lovely to be with you to share the space with you to practice together
so so for today's practice i want to invite us to um
explore the practice of of gratitude it's nice to explore
gratitude on on a friday or for some of you it's saturday already um
like mario christina in australia and maybe others will be listening to this on audiodharma later
but the practice of gratitude just to brighten the heart and uh
as you know as always we take different um approaches to practices um
there's so many different ways to practice meta gratitude each of these practices
there's so many ways in so we'll find our way in in a different
way tonight in the way of of appreciating having gratitude
for not just what's what's good and easy and wonderful and things that we're
typically grateful for but also for challenges gratitude for challenges
um [Music] i'll share with you that i've been contemplating this
as [Music] and as as
quizzical and as paradoxical as it seems um [Music]
although illness is hard sickness is hard and i've been down with a bad cold for many
many days over a week and yet
and yet what i found in my heart is and of course not that i like being sick
i don't like being sick i don't wish it upon myself you know so this is not a masochistic way of being in the world in
the head when when it is when things are the way they are when
sickness when lack of health lack of energy is there can i be grateful for
this too can i be grateful for this too what are the gifts
that this thing that i don't like i don't wish it upon myself but yet it's
here and it's not pleasant it has unpleasant faith enough
can i be grateful for it are there things are there gifts are they gifts in this darkness
and that's something that i'll lead you in tonight but just to share for me i am
grateful i have been grateful for my illness because even though there are
many things that was on my to-do list and i didn't get to do and accomplish or
come and be with sangha and teach happy hour but it forced me to slow down which
is a gift it forced me to be in bed it forced me to spend all those hours
being with this body that wasn't feeling well at all um to meditate to to be aware of things as
they arise and pass when the mind doesn't have the energy or the the
the uh uplift to even read to even do to even watch a movie but just enough
energy to just be aware just be aware that is a gift that's
that's a tremendous gift so illness in that way is a gift becomes a gift
hence having gratitude for illness or anything that seems to be difficult or undesirable so
it's a nuanced practice and yet with a little bit of creativity
i trust i know that it can be available to all of us
so that's the setting that's the way i would like to set up
our practice the inspiration the framing so
so let's explore together friends so let's explore together so like to invite you
this time this moment to turn to change to shift
into your meditation posture
you may need to move from the cushion to a chair or from a
chair to a cushion lie down stand up see what this body needs
to be comfortable as comfortable as possible
but yet alert and awake and landing arriving
arriving in this body in this moment
letting the breath be received in the abdomen
ah by the entire body not the head
but the sensations of the breath be sensed by the body itself
let there be awareness let awareness pervade the entire body
parts that are tired achy
heavy parts that are comfortable
pleasant
warm
the parts that are energetic energized
are there parts in the body that are all of these and more at the same time
can we rest let go release
release release release more holding more tension
aware of this moment whatever is arising in this moment
in this body with curiosity and interest oh yes look
at that there's achiness there hello achiness you're welcome
to be just as you are
or hello [Music] lightness
comfort coziness in some other parts of the body
hmm you too are welcome [Music]
to be appreciated and relished
what's present in the body not thinking about it but letting it be
felt
all these sensations all these sensations
even if some are unpleasant can we have
gratitude for the unpleasantness for the pain in the body
because after all [Music] sensing pain means that our
pain receptors are working
that our spine is not cut off
it's actually the system is working it's sending the signals we may not like
the signals but can we be grateful that they exist
what if we refrain the unpleasantness in the body
the fact that we have a body that has sensations
can we appreciate and enjoy the breath
the opera
can we enjoy and appreciate this moment of quiet
sitting and practicing simply being aware
so much gratitude for the simplicity of this moment
of being able to sit just be
expanding expanding and knowing from our heart
middle of our chest sense of presence connection with
ourselves can we be grateful for this moment
simply being and here being aware
here i'm here
can i love be grateful for this moment just as it is
not needing wanting it to be any different
appreciating relishing the normalcy
in some ways and maybe in some ways it's not normal
of this moment just as it is unfolding even if there are many thoughts arising
or aches in the body or distracted or sleepy doesn't matter
it doesn't have to be perfect can we appreciate love it just as it is
just this
what we consider to be normal boring
[Music] not good enough not exciting
someday we will look back someday when the present moment
is the long it belongs to the long past
history by god this moment would be part of the good
old times ah when life was like that
which i took for granted
can we not take it for granted look at this moment from the perspective
of the future looking at this moment
in the rear view mirror ah the good old times
when so-and-so was alive when i was at that age when that was
happening which maybe was challenging but oh looking at it looking back at it all
wistfully visually can we appreciate it now
before it's gone while it's here relish it really relished
this life these circumstances
the safety the shelter the people in our lives
the opportunities the challenges
the full catastrophe the full beautiful catastrophe of our
lives can we relish it appreciated be grateful for it
not needing it to be any different in this moment
as if we are opening our arms wide and hugging just hugging embracing
ourselves our life just as it is in this moment
savoring it beautiful the challenges all of it
all the goodness and yes the challenges are part of the goodness
embracing embracing our lives
the arms wide appreciating loving
what is here staying embodied not thinking about it not
planning
let it be a reflection dropped into your body stay embodied
the feeling of appreciation gratitude love for what is
this amazing mysterious thing called
my life
the whole enchilada
and from this perspective can you embrace the good as well as the
challenges it's a part of this beautiful complex
painting [Music] this play that's your life
this piece of art
is there a recent challenge maybe you had earlier today or this past week
that you can include
see the goodness of it
maybe how it helps you grow
in compassion and care and wisdom in ways you wouldn't otherwise
the opportunities
hidden in challenges
the gifts
within the challenge
maybe life isn't all about getting what you want but growing through
getting what you don't at times
grateful for it all let the body be relaxed
let the body be relaxed and receptive
receiving receiving your whole life in this moment just as it is
with an open heart open arms
one breath at a time
looking at this moment from the perspective of a future
the same way you would look at the moment from your past from this perspective oh
yes i remember oh then oh yes oh the good old times
when i was at this age oh so-and-so was in my life
what those are my challenges ah the sense of perhaps bittersweet
tenderness looking at this moment
of your life with the same perspective
and for the last minutes of this practice period
holding yourself with kindness for whatever arose or did not arise
can i appreciate love whatever happened
in this practice period even if i was it was sleepiness or distract
distraction
just as it is just as it was
and sharing our goodness the goodness of our practice of our
heart our intentions
generously sharing it with all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere
know cherish
appreciate the gifts of their circumstances
whether easy or challenges
to support them support us all to grow may all beings everywhere including
ourselves be happy may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes if
there are any reflections you have you'd like to share them you're welcome to type them in chat
you can if you type them to everyone i'll read your name if you type them just to me
i will read the reflection but not your name so you'll be private you can also raise
your hand invited to share for the benefit of all beings what did you discover
what was interesting what was challenging any aha moments
claire says have been told that gratitude is wanting what you have yes
exactly exactly not having what you want
which actually can put us on a hedonic
treadmill keep wanting keep keep wanting
keep keep having what we want keep going after what we want whereas it's the other way around
exactly gratitude is is wanting what you have yay this is what i have yay so
actually wanting it appreciating it yes thank you claire
david on youtube says what if we refrain the signal in quotes i'm hearing the hiss of
mindfulness loud and clear thanks to you and the dharma deep house thank you david yes it's reframing
so much about reframing in the other insights
and the other aha moments
um one person says having joy for surviving my injury yeah
yeah [Music] and what gifts there can be in the
injury actually none besides surviving it but actually the ways that
maybe maybe it slowed you down maybe it gave you more time to be with
yourself with others or whatever else what other gifts there might have been
i'll take another pause for any reflections that might have come up
the aha moments anything you noticed when you looked at your life from the perspective of the
future your challenges
hugging your life how was that with eye with arms wide
open merry christine says grateful for the awareness this practice brings me
yes indeed can't run nice in your hand please
yeah um is it this kind of exercise has always been really hard for me because i
try and understand it with my mind and then and then i just feel guilty that i haven't
been appreciating my life and and i can't quite grasp it um and the same with chat like
appreciating challenge it's like i i've i've done this like unconscious
exceptionalism where i'm like okay other people can get that but not me and i just kind of listen and like
keep it at arm's length but lately because of loving-kindness practice and and
deep embodiment practices um i have i have recognized like oh my my body
understands this like or this like unified wisdom that is my whole being
understands things like this about like how i can appreciate my life now imagining the future or how i can feel
um grateful for challenge and it's just like this the shift of like
letting my mind take a little bit like of the back seat and
open to like this greater wisdom that understands all this and that i am deeply grateful for
yay catherine i'm celebrating this i'm getting chills as you say this beautiful
thank you so much for sharing your insight your wisdom for the sake of
others is so beautiful to go from this place so that's beautifully described
trying so hard understanding and then feeling guilty like ah it's like oh the sense of trust
the body the embodiment with kindness there's there is opening to wisdom of the body
and the mind the embodied mind that gets it and deep deep gratitude for that as
you said beautiful i so appreciate you sharing that brightens my heart thank you
oh sweet sarah please
hi thank you first of all and kind of to piggyback off of that i feel
like well i was experiencing during the meditation
just this experimentation with moving the locus of how i understand me
from my head into my heart and like as if i had eyes like in my
heart because i think that's a lot of where vision
like i see out of here so i'm located here but trying to drop that down into
my chest and i it's the first time i've ever tried that like living from an awareness here
instead of here it's just it was interesting for me awesome
yay thanks for sharing that that's beautiful i love that and and
actually i'm going to ask you if it's okay for you to have mute again oh lost you where did you go raise your hand
again oh oh i wanted to ask you to yes there you are thanks to uh and was there
a was there something that arose and then just and again if there are no words for it
don't feel like you're on the spot but if there's anything else i'd love to invite you to
um reflect on it out loud yeah i think
it got less judgmental immediately
and it felt really challenging too i will have to say because i it's so
habitual to live from my eyeballs and my brain um
and in some ways i'm like can i like re like plastic surgery this these days is
it good enough to bring my eyeballs down here i don't know yeah yeah yeah that's beautiful thank
you for saying that that's lovely yeah so so that both it is challenging because habitually like yeah we
associate ourselves our our perspective with our head
not from our heart and yet as you said judgments drop there's a sense of oh
heartfulness so one thing that i would so so you've discovered this yay
beautiful keep exploring keep experimenting and also if others wanted to experiment
with that i would invite actually this is an improv
exercise or practice i've done when i've done mindfulness and improv day longs which i
haven't done for a while thanks to the pandemic but anyway um you can imagine
that there is an orb there is an orb of light there's just an orb of light which
is compassionate and loving and and and imagine that's in your chest and i
was like oh yeah you're bleeding with that you're leading with your chest into the world not with your head not with
your hips actually you can try all of those ways of walking in the world but you're leading with your heart you're
leading with this orb in your heart and you're just you're looking around look at this orb this light is looking around
uh in the world so so i invite you to to check that out
so so it's time to turn towards small groups i want to make sure we have enough time
for them claire i do see your hand we're going to come back to you at the end so so i'd like to invite us to
to practice in small groups to take these insights
to take this way of being together um to the way of we have been alone
uh with and actually let's practice with this orb of light in our chest actually
let's let's let's take this um let's take the show on the road so as
you enter the small groups try this on for signs and it might be clunky might be challenging as just reported by sarah
or might actually drop the judgments like oh yeah there's this sense of brightness my heart there's the
brightness in my heart i trust there is this brightness in my heart this goodness this
meditates it's there it's just there and that's what's shining when i'm talking just i'm shining i'm talking from the
center of my heart so and then practically speaking
we'll be in roughly groups of three and each person will have
a nugget they'll share about a nugget and then the next person will share a nugget and the third person round and round
so it's not not a long monologue but just one nugget you're sharing from your own experience not
managing asking others about their experience but just staying close to your orb to your orb of
light of goodness shining and receiving others receiving others with care with
love see what that feels like i'd love to hear your report when you come back to see what this this
improv so we're doing this improv experiment right um see what this improv improv experiment
is like so so with that i'm going to open the rooms
take care of yourselves take care of each other and here we go okay
the rooms are closed everyone's back welcome back everyone so um
even though we're at time i'd love to hear maybe one person perhaps maybe they would share quickly what was it like
experimenting with this orb of goodness of light in the chest
which was inspired by sarah's report anybody would like to share that please raise your hand don't
be shy did you experiment with it what was it like
going once you can also type in chat if you're shy
any experimenters i don't see any
okay i see sarah again all right sarah you get the last word
i actually was gonna defer to vicky had wanted to raise her hand oh there's vicky okay vicky
oh you're muted still vicky
okay i had an experience because i was so in the middle of this i think you just
opened your eyes as my cat knocked off something that came crashing to the floor
and so after and i grabbed the cat got the cat off and and didn't have time to see what it
was but spent the rest of time trying to forgive myself for being reactive and then in the end it was a light bulb
and so i i had a lot of experience to say well coming back to this it really
didn't matter it was the cat was playing cat
yeah yeah the cat was playing cat
just the fact that it was a light bulb when we were talking about bringing light to something and
oh my gosh nikki's gonna think i'm the most reactive person in the world in the middle of meditation completely involved
with what you were saying and then reacting and then just that's hilarious i didn't even notice
all this story all this papancha this story of what will nikki think of mean i'm a terrible meditator
i didn't even know that i didn't even see anything oh my god but i was compassionate for the cat
because in the middle of my meditation it's gonna hurt its paw so i have to get out of my
presence here so it was an interesting meditation [Laughter]
i appreciate that i appreciate actually you know what i'm going to say one last thing and then to wrap it up the fact
that it was a challenging meditation and then it actually the there's so many
lessons in the quote-unquote the challenges of the that the mind was creating right there were so many chunks
like what what what is she gonna think like oh i'm real it's like oh it's just
the cat was doing its thing it's just like it's okay it's all okay and it's
much to do about nothing right and that is the point right that's that's
so gift for this the gift of this challenging meditation that's just beautiful thank you vicky that's great
lovely and kitten says the light often shines way ahead and not in proximity
and what keeps us from keeping the beam close are constructed
emotional concepts of fear or anger very well said all right dear ones oh my goodness we've gone way over time
tonight thank you for your patience and humor wasn't my intention but it was juicy gratitude for challenges so take
good care may all beings be well may all things be happy and free including
yourselves thanks everyone
take good care