so hello everyone and welcome to our monday morning
meditation time together and um to introduce the meditation today
i want to evoke the idea that over these last
you know i guess it's been maybe close to 10 months we've been going through the sati patana
sutta the discourse the buddhist teachings on the four foundations
for awareness and
if we take this text uh to describe a journey of deepening one's meditation practice or
if you don't like the metaphor of deepening uh i'm very fond of the idea of clarifying
meditation becoming clear in our awareness awareness becomes clearer and clearer cultivating greater
clarity and so if as we develop greater clarity in
practice so we get quieter and stiller as a line as a mind is less caught up in
its preoccupations there's a new opportunity in practice
and as we come into the fourth foundation um it's best i think it's best to think
of this as building on what's happening earlier or building on a mind that is
has the ability to be quite clear or quite still calm
concentrated or deep or whatever whatever way you like to see this for yourself
and um and so then we start to see at some point this if so for example in the
in the third foundation we talked about the expanded mind the mind that awareness and the mind kind of
coterminous where awareness becomes quite expansive
then we can start because of seeing that and knowing that we can become aware of how the mind gets
contracted how the mind gets tight or narrow again or the more clarity we have the more
sensitive we are to how movements of the mind uh causes us to lose that clarity
how we become more uh things become more obscure or or
hidden or difficult to see if we like the idea of stillness the
mind becomes stiller or calmer that we see how the mind gets activated again agitated
restless so whether mind gets constricted or restless or
obscured we don't see that the clarity as the ma as the practice continues at
some point we have a reference point for seeing these movements of the mind
that take us away from our best interest to take us away from
the continued unfolding of the practice and uh it's one thing to be constantly
caught up in for example sensual desires and desires of all kind and hardly know we're doing it
but it's another thing if we're still enough quiet enough to be able to see
the mind getting caught in sensual desires and desires
and wanting things and it's a very different perspective
very different vantage point to just be lost and trying to find your way out
to be able to see it that has a particular mental phenomena activity of the mind
desire there it's coming i can see the impact it has on me i can see how it's
hindering or obscuring the clarity of the mind the wisdom of the mind
and and it's almost easier to see it if we have
if we have some kind of either direct or memory access
to what it's like to have a mind that's free of say for example sensual desire and we can see it oh there it is
it's a particular phenomena it's not the whole universe it's not i'm it's not
that i'm living or identified or caught completely in this universe of desire
look at that it's desire that sensual desire
and then it's a whole different game a whole different way of being it's moving towards freedom
so uh we'll sit a little bit and the first hindrance is sensual desire desire for comfort
a desire for sensuality sensual pleasures and
and so at some point during the meditation i'll introduce to you the idea of noticing
if there is essential desire essential desire arises and for you to see if you can see it
with whatever degree of clarity or stillness or calm that you have so you see it for what it is
as opposed to be it or you know enter into that world of desire it's
almost like you the mind is not bigger or wider or stiller and you can see oh their
essential desire so taking an alert posture
and gently closing your eyes
and perhaps as if it's your body's wish and you're following through in it so
it's arising from the inside let yourself take as deep a breath as the body wants
it's taking as deep as breath as the body wants and then
exhale as long as the body wants
breathing in deeply relaxing
the body maybe even relaxing
following the lead of where the body wants to relax
soften
as you exhale let your breathing will now return to
normal
and then as you exhale letting the mind become
as quiet and still as it might want
in the depths of the mind in the place where the mind can rest
let the mind become as quiet as it wants
and then following breathing
the simplicity of the body breathing
and perhaps as you breathe following the in-breaths the out-breaths
follow also
the path in front of you to becoming quieter and stiller
through the path within you with each in-breath and out-breath
supporting your inner life
to follow the the invitation the welcoming
to becoming quieter and softer quieter in thinking
softer in the heart
gently following the call the welcome
to that place of greater quiet and stillness
letting go of thoughts as you exhale
maybe at the end of the exhale allowing yourself to come to a quiet
place
and then as you continue sitting notice
if there is or is not the presence of sensual desire
the desire for comfort
for pleasure even in the meditation itself
if there is notice what that's like
if there's not notice that absence
and if there is the arising of sensual desire
notice what it's like to see it appear
if you can let go of it and be quiet for a moment and it reappears
see it as an arising phenomenon just something coming like a sound outside
and if it goes see it go
if you can let go of it let go of it gently
and if there is no sensual desires
appreciate that absence
and as we come to the end of the sitting
as much as you might value sensual pleasures essential desires maybe are
innocent
there's also a clarity and a simplicity in a freedom
that comes with the absence of sensual desires sensual cravings
concerns with pleasures of all kinds
and that clarity and simplicity and freedom
is a medium in which your good will can travel
unobstructed
and to whatever degree you can be free right now of
concerns with desires of all kinds sensual desires desires for comfort
can you allow that space to be filled with your well wishing for this world your
care [Music] your love your compassion
may it be that these wishes of
well-wishing may it be they somehow touch others
seen in unseen ways may benefit them that you wish may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so good day this monday in march
and so today we're beginning the fourth foundation for
awareness fourth support for developing a heightened
sense of clarity awareness that
begins to move us into our potential for liberation and freedom
and all along this is kind of the direction that the satyabatana this mindfulness practice is going
it's going to greater clarity so that there's really clear mindfulness
i like the expression lucid mindfulness that it's not simply just you know a simple
knowing and experience there's something about the knowing which has qualities of
clarity lucidity stillness freedom non-reactivity equanimity
something that's really special about the knowing the awareness itself
that comes from being settled to being concentrated getting calm and having a stress heightened capacity
to be aware almost like awareness and knowing is a muscle that gets stronger
and also that comes from being less preoccupied in our attachments less preoccupied with
our concerns our preoccupations and
and then the natural capacity for knowing for awareness
can shine can be there and to have the naturalness of it there's almost a spontaneity of it or
the simplicity of it just arising and being there without a lot of agency
is one of the stepping stones of developing mindfulness at first
there's more agency and then over time it's more a matter of the agency is more about getting out of the way and letting
go and so then we come to the
fourth foundation of mindfulness and like the second and third
there's a journey through this where at the beginning it talks about the
hint the different three different ways that the mind gets caught up gets attached gets
entangled with experience and then it talks about two ways in which the mind moves towards
disentanglement towards freedom and so there's a kind of a journey from
being attached to uh to becoming free and that journey goes first through
what's called the five hindrances then it goes through what's called the five aggregates
then the five uh fetter the six fetters the six ways that we get entangled or
fettered knotted up in in the experiences of the senses
and then that's that's the ways we get caught up and then the freedom has to do with the
seven factors of awakening um and then the the four noble truths
and so there's a journey through this and uh i love it that we start with the ways we get caught up and
hung up and get caught because we will understand that the idea is to become wise about this
if you're feeling like you're supposed to quickly get to some beautiful state wonderful state
it might be that you're not going to take the time to really know yourself in a deep way and know how you get intang
gold or know the entanglement itself so that in the future you're not going
to get tricked by it if you know it well you won't be tricked and be pulled into its orbit and make
mistakes and all that so taking our time so this week is the
five hindrances and uh we'll do one day on each hindrance
but today a little bit introduction for it um
the in the teachings of the buddha the hindrances are often
paired with the seven factors of awakening these are beautiful qualities of mind
that arise as we practice so mindful awareness itself mindfulness itself
investigation effort energy joy tranquility
concentration and equanimity and many texts the buddha teaches he
puts these together where one is the problem one is what we're overcoming and the other is what grows and develops
as as a result as a instead of that
and um so these two have different uh impacts on us the hindrances
uh are uh cover over our wisdom make make wisdom difficult to have
access to it they contract the mind they limit the mind
the seven factors of awakening allow for the functioning of wisdom allow for an expanse of mind
open mind a free mind and so one one kind of uh pulls us down
and one lifts us up in a certain way uh an image in the suit is used for this
covering over impact effect of the hindrances is that of a tree growing in the forest
but there's a larger tree that's covering it over so the small tree doesn't get any light so
it's stunted it doesn't really grow and develop and the hindrances are that stunting
that covering over that keeps the light of awareness from operating clearly when the light of awareness is free then
the tree of bodhi the tree of awakening can can grow within us
and that tree is this the some people call the sap of that tree
are the seven factors of awakening and and so then the light of awareness
really kind of lets it grow and develop and so the idea is to
uh let go of or be free of these obscuring qualities of
of the hindrances so that something uh beautiful can grow and develop instead in that space
and that clearing in the forest so um
the um
so the the first hindrance is uh in the sutta essential desires
in this in the teachings of the buddha sometimes it's alternative thing is called
avariciousness wanting the thing wanting things so the first one is the usual one is
sensual desire wanting desires pleasure essential pleasures of all kinds
and and then and the alternative is wanting things to acquire things more and more
stuff both can be a big entanglement
and sometimes people just call it desire the second first hindrance to cover all
those things but the problem with calling a desire is not all desires are problematic the desire to be free of the
hindrances may be really healthy and appropriate and um
but sensual desire and wanting things wanting sensual pleasure and wanting things
there are innocent versions of this kind of desire it's innocent to want something i run out of toothpaste so i would like to
have a new tube of toothpaste it's an innocent uh maybe beautiful ways
of having uh desires for pleasure that are you know it's simple and easy and
and um so you want to cook your broccoli just to the right
you know tenderness just to the right way so that when you eat it there's pleasure eating
it it feels nourishing and delightful and and and fresh to eat it
it's it can be innocent but um but then what is not innocent
is desires that were grabbed by were caught by were
preoccupied by and there's a kind of a become sometimes a strong enough kind of biological
uh force within us uh behind that like sometimes it's strong enough to be like
uh propellant fuel for a a rocket it's so powerful some form of sensual desire
that you know it's almost like it's hard not to kind of follow along the strength of it
and um and for the purposes of sati patada it's not like it's immoral or bad or
wrong to have sexual desire it's just that it just happens to be
that they uh it makes it difficult for this clarity of awareness to grow
this openness expanded mind to grow to this quiet stills place of freedom
to show itself and since that's what the direction we're going we want to learn how to
be mindful of sensual desire so it supports that direction it doesn't support freedom to go along
with essential desires spend time in meditation thinking about sexual fantasies thinking about food thinking
about trying to make meditation as pleasant and enjoyable as you can like to recapture a
past meditation experience where there was all kinds of wonderful
you know uh bliss in meditation and the desire for that bliss again is
just another desire for sensual pleasure and so but what we do is rather than
negating them or condemning them it's just a very clear and purposeful
and dedicated mindfulness so this essential desire essential desire is present
and then getting to know it feel it i find it very useful to feel it physically there's something about
feeling the physicality of desire that for me is very quickly shows me the
downside of it and and that the other the way in which the body is
not really it's not really pleasant to be caught in the force of sensual desire
even sensual pleasure might be pleasant the force of this drive for it
is not it's kind of a loss a kind of alienation for myself in having it there
and um and then know when it's absent there are times as meditation deepens
that there's no essential desire at all and this is actually very important to register that to take that in
and get to know what that's like to know that benefits the way there's clarity and freedom or ease or you can
breathe more easily or you're not being pushed by some kind of inner force
so the instructions are know when it's present and no in its absence as we know the absence of it
that gives us a new possibility and this is really getting down to the heart of what
the insight of the whole purpose of of satipattana and that is to see
and be present enough and still enough or clear enough to see how any phenomenon at all any experience at
all see it arise see it appear nothing is there all the time when
anything that be qualifies as an experience is in perception for a while
it appears and then it disappears and when the mind is quiet enough and not involved in thoughts
you can start you can start seeing this arising of sensual desire and you might see its passing
and seeing their rising um there's a easier to have a very
kind of a different freer more disentangled relationship with
potential desire when you see it first arise then if it's already there full blown
and so to be right there and see there there it is then it's easier just leave it alone
and it's easier to abandon it to let go of it
and this exercising of our capacity to let go let go of the clinging the wanting
the reaching for is a wonderful thing to cultivate and develop
and so the way that buddha describes working with sensual desires one knows essential desire is present
when it's present one knows it's absent when it's absence one knows that it's arising when it
arises and one knows the abandoning of it letting go of it
when it's let go of and then if that's thorough enough and deep enough then at least can lead to a
deep freedom where we realize that the sensual desire is no longer there
and is not going to arise again maybe at least in that meditation session there's such a clarity of
fullness of such full clarity such peacefulness such subtleness such
something that it's like wow this is so good i'm essential desire is not going to arise
in this context because it just feels so free the freedom is so good
so to become wise about the hindrances to
become wise about how the hindrances obscure wisdom
and the buddha said a fool who knows fools who know their fools to that
extent are wise so to use that
practitioners who know they've lost their wisdom are starting to become wise
and so for the next 24 hours until we meet again
i'd encourage you to notice sensual desire desire for sensual
pleasures desires for comfort that might exist for you
and there's lots of them through the day for most people and to see if you can notice when it's present when it's absence in particular
see if you what happened what happened what's the opportunity what happens for you when you see it when it just arises oh
there it is that's a fascinating place so hopefully you'll get
wiser over these next hours around essential desire and then we'll continue tomorrow
thank you