so warm hello welcome to this meditation
and i think it's fairly well known that
buddhism doesn't think very highly
of the kind of desires that have to do with craving or
clinging and grasping what's less
known is that buddhism has a lot to do
with desires that can be characterized as aspiration
uh inspiration even but i like the word aspiration
and the distinction between those is that the ones that buddhism
thinks poorly of the ones that bring suffering are the ones that one way or the other
close us down contract us tighten us
limit us or oppress us even
and aspiration are the desires that open us up and the word aspiration is derived from
the word in latin that's connected to breathing just like respiration is to breathe it's
our breathing system uh and um and uh so the idea of um aspiration that
comes from the opening breath the expanding breath the breath that kind of the breathing
that helps us become whole or full and so i think of aspiration as a
movement towards wholeness aspiration is for me is very much about
a desire has more to do i think for me
with the focus of desire the object of desire and aspiration has a lot more to
do with the source of inspiration inside the source of openness
inspiration creativity possibility the the something deep
inside that wants to kind of emerge and blossom come to fruition
and so to uh in buddhism we aspire to becoming free
aspire to becoming whole and the path to that is to be whole
and to allow the aspiration of being present to really help us to fill up
into the present moment and added to that is the aspiration for what is beneficial
what is good uh what is um happiness and delight
and that comes together this kind of ability to focus on this wholeness of happiness wholeness of goodness
that this place of aspiration can if we can connect to the deep inside and let it
emerge maybe with each breath that each breath is
it carries the aspiration to fullness aspiration to connect to
that which is good in us of course there are challenges we have of course there are all kinds of other
things happening within us and not to at any kind of way push them away or
or somehow dismiss them offhand but to
have this aspiration there's a growth to presence to
mindfulness that becomes full where there's lots of space for all of who we are
and we don't get fixated on the parts that are difficult they are held within this wider whole
of what is beneficial and what is good so to
take a meditation posture and ideally you take a posture that
there's a room or for becoming cold
where in a way all of ourselves is included one of the reasons to sit cross-legged
if you can is that a little bit more of a kind of i think it's easier to have a feeling of all the whole body comes
together then when we're sitting in a chair or at least when i've sat in the chair i often feel like my lower part of my half
my body is not really as connected to the upper part but cross-legged it all comes here
and but even if you're lying down maybe there's some way of laying
that um the body is symmetrical or the body is
laying on its back so that the chest a little bit is open and exposed
to be and then to gently close your eyes
and if what i'm about to say makes sense for you great if not don't worry about it
see if you can bring yourself to the source the beginning
of breathing where does your breathing begin
where in your body is the first indication first little hint
that inhale has begun
is it a little movement in the belly a little movement in the chest
a little tug or tingling the nostrils
and from that beginning point of inhale
the inhale grows if you're breathing quickly it might
grow very fast if your breathing slows down
you might have a sense of
leisure space time
to really feel the growth the expansion of the fullness
of the inhale
and after when you get to the top of the inhale
maybe you can feel the letting go the releasing
the settling of the chest the belly
as you exhale all the way to the end of the exhale
to the last sensation that represents expresses the exhale
maybe it brings you back to that place where the inhale begins
where the exhale ends and the inhale begins
and as you inhale and feel the your lungs fill with oxygen
maybe you can feel a little sense of growing fullness of awareness
maybe a fullness in your whole body or your torso your rib cage
and as you exhale letting go of your thoughts and concerns
in a way the more you can let go of your thoughts and make space in your mind
that space can receive more fully the your fullness of being
okay
and then as you breathe in see if you can have a
almost almost a silent aspiration
for well-being
an aspiration that recognizes your potential for a sense of well-being
maybe because once upon a time you felt that way
and i used the word well-being to encompass many possibilities of
happiness and joy and satisfaction peace
whatever you're inspired by
and have an opening aspiration
for your own well-being
and as you inhale
let the expansive and the fullness of the inhale
carry and spread that wish for well-being
out into the body where maybe you can feel
in the wholeness of yourself some hints some traces of well-being
letting your mind be quiet as you exhale so breathing
fullness aspiration
for wellness
connects you more and more to the present moment
to here and now of your experience here in your body
this is the place in the present
where your wholeness your well-being
can arise on the wings of your aspiration
the wings of your breathing
breathing in inhaling inhaling in such a way
that it opens you up from the inside to the present moment
it opens you up from the inside
to your body's experience of the present moment
re inhaling with an aspiration for well-being
as a potential possibility here now in this body
the opening aspiration
aspiration is itself a form of well-being
aspiration has a goodness in it and so when we breathe in
when we inhale and let the chest expand the belly open up
becoming whole with oxygen full
let that also carry the goodness of your aspiration for well-being
for wellness for happiness and let that goodness of aspiration
be carried by your inhale throughout your
body the body that expands as you breathe in
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
maybe as you inhale and feel the chest expand
the lungs fill imagine
that your aspiration and aspiration for the welfare of the world
rises and spreads out from your in your inhale to cover the whole world
as you breathe in you your expansion of the body
spreads your aspiration for the good will to the whole world
and as you breathe out you might say may it be so
an aspiration for the welfare of all beings is itself a wholesome and
good beneficial state to have for oneself
there's goodness in it and as you breathe and spread your
aspiration for the welfare of all beings maybe you can feel
maybe physically maybe in the heart the goodness of that
the wellness of that the kind of aspiration that's opening
expansive from a place of inspiration
and may it be that our collective
well-wishing of the world for others spread from our meditation community
out into our neighborhoods our towns our lands
to the people we somehow rather encounter or learn about
or communicate with today
may the goodness of our aspiration spread across the lands
by how we speak and how we act and how we think of others
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be free
[Music]
so this is the second talk on this week's theme of lovingkindness
as one of the divine abodes immeasurables
and so the the word for the pali word the buddhist word for
loving kindness is metta m-e-tta and it's a cognate to the word mitta
which means friend and so part of the connotations of
metta is friendliness and friendliness is a basic attitude of
respecting people being kind to people appreciating people
being open to to kind of a friendly exchange a kind
exchange with people and it's possible to be friendly
with people who you don't really like or who are challenging in variety of ways
and so the word loving kindness which is i think a beautiful concept and word in english
for some people might not really represent meta as fully as other english translations
some people the idea of love has a very high bar and
to have loving kindness kindness which is filled with love
it's hard to do like for people who are challenging for us maybe there are people who we find difficult to love
because they're just you know maybe doesn't have to explain why but
there are challenging people that exist in our lives and we encounter and uh
and so to love them might be you know unreasonable and
to hold ourselves up to some kind of standard we're supposed to love everyone might not be
realistic but it is possible to have good will for everyone to be friendly for everyone
and and friendly towards the strangers friendly a sense of hospitality
for anybody that we encounter and so uh it might be that a
word that translates meta more appropriately into english is the is the word good will
where there's a uh in an aspiration an intention a willingness
um to spread our goodness to extend our goodness
uh to others so they feel safe with us they feel
happy with us they feel that we have their best interest in mind we have their good interest in mind
we're there to support their welfare not there to support their their ill we're not there trying to undermine them or be
critical of them or diminish who they are in some way
and the um
so good will i like also like the word kindness as a
as a translation of meta because kindness has like uh for me
implies more than just a feeling or an attitude kindness has connotations for
me of you actually something an extension towards other people uh there's expression of you know we
have kind words we have a kind gaze we have a kind action that kindness is good will can just be
that you kind of radiate a sense of well wishing for someone but kindness implies a little bit more
action for me and so i like the word kindness just simply kindness as a translation from metta
in the ancient buddhist texts metta is described this way
the primary characteristic of metta is to promote the welfare
of all beings to promote beneficial conditions for others
so this idea of wanting to benefit wanting things to be beneficial wanting and it says beneficial conditions
so it doesn't necessarily mean that you have to be the one who provides them with those conditions but there's a
genuine wish that may the conditions of their life be such that they have happiness and well-being
may they experience welfare and well it's a you know big difference
between simply wishing that and doing something for it uh we shouldn't underestimate the
tremendous value of having good will for others i know i've been the recipient of people's
simple goodwill and it makes a difference something inside of me kind of opens up or is buoyed or inspired by
just just knowing that people are thinking well of me
the um it says that the uh that the core
of loving kindness is focusing on what is beneficial so it requires some sense of what is
beneficial um you know if simply to uh wish someone
win uh a very big lottery ticket and you know to get really you know amazingly
wealthy uh is that really for their benefit as i i've said enough times that there's
been studies made that people who win big chunks of money in a lottery uh a year after winning it
they're less happy than they were before they won it so uh you know what to really wish
people what's genuinely beneficial what's really supportive for them and nice for them and
it might not be wealth it might not be status it might not be
material goods it might be that uh you know sometimes it can be so simple
some of the simplest things are some of the most fulfilling and happy um
i think that uh learning how to breathe within with a breath is just easy and easeful breath
is a phenomenal wealth the buddha said that for a monastic who
is not monastics are not supposed to acquire money does not have money or wealth he said that
wealth for a monastic is meta is loving kindness is good will
and and this is a wonderful kind of kind of juxtaposition that
having good will for others a wealth for oneself
there's so much goodness in that aspiration that the goodness of the aspiration kind of benefits and
feeds or nourishes something in us and this idea
that uh so that we're focusing on that beneficial both for others and for ourselves it's kind of this mutual way
and this is where i really love this english word aspiration as i've said earlier that
aspiration is a beneficial desire that buddhism champions aspiration is a good
thing and um and that it's a desire which is opening desire
which is freeing desire which helps us feel more connected one that it contains within it
beneficial seeds beneficial goodness in it so that when we breathe with
aspiration inspiration that we get filled with something good
it nourishes something there for in ourselves and so they have the aspiration for others welfares we're benefiting
ourselves as we're benefiting others the
we know the the description goes on and says the manifestation
of metta is the removal of malice the removal of ill will
so you we know that loving kindness is present in a stable strong way when there's
absolutely no ill will there's only a good will that's there
um and its proximate cause
is the loveliness of beings what a great expression
that the approximate cause the approximate condition that brings about this method is seeing the loveliness and beings
so to how do we see the beauty in other people
i think that one of the things that requires is slowing down
taking the time to pay attention to that if we're we could be our minds go fast
they pay attention to all kinds of things we have a lot of desires we have a lot of wants with a lot of preoccupations concerns fears and so
when we encounter someone sometimes all these different things are swirling around and
and making the mind fast or caught up in things but to stop
and take time it doesn't have to be anybody notices your pausing that long
but to learn to appreciate the loveliness of beings
the beauty of other people everyone has loveliness
everyone has it and to begin to tune into that and that's what again if we go back to
meditation practice as we discover our own loveliness
as we start sitting and opening up to our beauty beauty within the capacity
for integrity and wholeness of lack of conflict lack of ill will
lack of hostility lack of greed this beautiful place inside that where
this kind of whole other way of being lives is with us and we recognize the beauty in ourselves
then it's more easy to see that in other people it's there and if we don't see it in other people
one principle you might want to consider as a principle not as a truth
is that maybe just maybe you don't see it in others because you
haven't seen it in yourself and if you really see it in yourself you'll see it even even in people who
are quite difficult you'll see there's the seed maybe it's hidden even from them
but it's a seed it's a potential it's something something lovely to appreciate
in others and and it says then the last part of this
description is that meta uh fails
uh when it leaves leads to uh the translation here is a sticky
affection so affection for others which was a neediness and wantingness and a graspingness
so that's not meta meta is open-handed
the hands don't grasp don't hold on to anything with meta just like a freely offered things are just offered freely
and here you can have it you can have my good will and and it's offered freely and i'm not
going to hold on and demand anything in return
and so
and meta is an aspiration you know for all the emphasis we do in mindfulness about being in the present moment
that it's not really the full story of a full liberated life
that there's also a place for having a sense of potential and possibility for others
and wishing that for them certainly wishing it for them to have it now but a sense of the possibility they
can grow into that and may it be so may it be
and so that aspiration i this is what i would like
my wishes my heartfelt wish my wholehearted wish is really that other people feel well
and happy you don't have to tell people that you have this wish for them
you don't even tell people you have good will for them sometimes that
some relationships are such that it's too complicated if you tell them um
and because they'll there are people with sticky affection or people who will you know are even mean sometimes and all
kinds of difficult ways of being so the wonderful art of metta
is knowing when to do it privately and but just to have good will for
others and i've had goodwill and i've heard stories of people say that they have very difficult person in their lives and they
decided to just have good will for them kind of privately sometimes they do hold them in their in their loving kindness
when they're not together and when they are together they're kind of like just kind of reflecting on their well-wishing
for that person and nothing special is said nothing special is done that expresses the good will but just
that attitude seems to change this circumstance and the person seems to become kinder or
less threatening or less you know difficult to be with
finally uh this this brahmaviharas this practice of loving kindness
it's both a an expression that can be in
present moment just to express to live with loving kindness and goodness and
well-being wishing well-being or friendliness to others but it's also in a
as i keep saying an aspiration and an aspiration is a choice
and uh and it's possible to marshal together a choice a decision a wish
yes i would like i want to be kind here i want to be friendly here i want to wish
this person well i see what's beneficial i see their loveliness
and to live that life where we choose to have that aspiration to be part of
what rises out of us and opens us it doesn't mean so what it means is you
don't have to feel loving kindness you don't have to feel friendly
maybe that those feelings will follow in the wake of the aspiration but the wish is something deeper than a
feeling and we do have some choice over that so don't wait to have the feeling
to have the wish and if the wish is an aspiration it'll carry with it goodness it'll carry with
it welfare and you'll benefit from having that wish if it's sincere
may all of us have the sincere wish to benefit ourselves and others
and may we be carried and expanded and come to fullness
in our kindness and good will and may you for this day that we
next 24 hours until we meet again why don't you take some ex do some
experiments take some risks and see if you can make a little bit of
this meta-loving kindness good will a kind of a theme you carry with you through the day
and uh reflect on it think of it expand extend it to others and see what
you learn about loving kindness that in the next 24 hours that you didn't know
you don't know right now so thank you very much i look forward to
our time tomorrow
you