anybody else kelly in san mateo hi kelly
fred in oakland hi fred steven houston hi steve
swim hi mark inscrim
hi it's dan in new york hi dan welcome thank you
nick in berkeley who is that it's nick in berkeley hi nick welcome
and i see a bunch of hellos now that i've started the youtube i see bill is saying hello
from dallas and maury christine says hooroo from
from australia good afternoon to you both larry from seattle
hi from claire los gatos michelle ecuador hi we're definitely
international lots of times though so sweet ozil from chicagoland neda from redwood
city hi neda and welcome and amy from oahu hi amy hugh from san
diego jill from san luis lots of hellos and also welcoming our friends on
youtube whom are just joining so okay the sangha has assembled and the space has been
warmed we all are hello so so let's get started so i am going to uh
ask you all to mute yourselves if you are already unmuted
and also i will change the settings so that accidental
unmuting will not be possible the space will stay quiet thank you neil for posting information
about happy hour google groups at this time if you're new to
apr google groups is a nice way to keep connected and also
that's where you receive the resources quotes and all of that and i changed the
settings so that um uh chat will stay quiet also uh
you can still send me chat but please don't unless it's emergency my sound drops out it can be very
distracting to get chats while i teach so let's save all
that for the very end i thank you for that okay and last but not least let's turn
on recording for the sake of audiodharma
there okay so so hello hello and welcome
dear friends it's lovely to be with you practice together
all of us coming together from different places in the world
so so for today's um practice what i would like to invite us to
consider in our practice
is um is both how
how compassion how suffering how challenges how ouches
are both personal and also impersonal
um i was having a conversation earlier today with a practitioner
but um since has been inspiring to me so i wanted to share that with you this
these images these ideas that
but a lot of times you know our confusion our sorrow
our pain or those of others
can feel so personal are i'm sorries like oh i'm sorry oh i'm so sorry ouch
ouch or they i'm sorry that other people have for us
i'm sorry that they have i'm sorry i didn't treat you the way i would have liked to treat you i'm i'm
sorry i wasn't there for you or maybe the i'm sorry is that we have the sorrows
that we have i'm sorry that i wasn't the person i wanted to be or
show up the way i wanted to i'm sorry for myself or for others these these
expressions of of of perhaps
sometimes um [Music] regret that can turn into shame that can
turn into shame what if we heard what if we really allowed ourselves
to perceive to hear these expressions of i'm sorry
whether it's for ourselves or others we heard it as an expression of sorrow
not one of shame or blame but one of expression of sorrow sadness suffering
and what if as if we listen to it
with the ear of kuan yin ear of compassion the same way
that kuan yin this embodiment this this paragon of
compassion it is said that kuan yin listens to all the cries of the world all the sorrows of
the world so what if you had this image of say a conch shell and listening
listening you know the way it seems like when you listen to a conch shell you hear the sound of the sea you
hear the sound of the ocean all of that you're like one year you're listening to all the
the sorrows all to all the i'm sorry both yours others
all of humanity's both yours both the
sense of personality in the um how personal these sorrows are the i'm
sorries are and also how universal the human condition how challenging it is
to be human we can't be perfect none of us we all make mistakes
all of us everyone ourselves others mistakes we've made for
ourselves we've let ourselves down we've let others down other people might have
let us down all these sorrows all these stories all these i'm sorry listening to
them through this conch shell with the ear of compassion
as if the buddha or the kuan yin so in this way
hearing the impersonality both the person the personhood
the particularities as well as the universalities not taking it so personally
ah the heart can relax the heart can relax when we realize that this is part
of the human condition these sorrows i'm sorry are part of the
human condition and can open up our heart
to compassion and care for ourselves for others
wherever it's needed it's the human condition after all
do we know a single person who's never been sorry who's never made a mistake
no oh of course not that's preposterous right what a silly question is she
asking of course but often we think we're the only person oh my goodness
i'm the only person ah or this
say if if there is a mistake somebody else has made oh it's it's just this
relationship that's entangled so so that is
that's the basis of the guided meditation i like to offer
tonight which is both recognizing the humanity the particularities as well
as the human condition in all the sorrows all the sorries
becoming sorrows deserving of compassion not shame
not finger-pointing wherever there is a sorrow
right answer is compassion self of compassion so
so i think i have said enough so [Music] i'd like to invite us into a guided
meditation and whether you're new or you've been practicing for a while all you need to know will be shared with you
so so um let your heart relax so i'd like to
invite you to get into your meditation posture whether you're sitting whether you're
lying down standing and landing
arriving in this moment arriving here
here
in this body however the body is
inviting the heart to relax
inviting the body to relax being gentle
a time to take refuge
in ease and care not setting too many expectations up
and after a lot of expectations be kind to yourself
dear soldier if you expect yourself to march on with
compassion have humor i have humor of gentleness
ah connecting with this body the sensations
of sitting first and foremost
connecting to the body
feeling your feet
you're sitting in a chair at the bottom of your feet if you're in a cushion your legs connected to the earth
aha rest for oh dear earth dear earth
let your self your feet relish this connection
the richness of the sensations
in this moment
there's a whole world [Music] of sensations
greeting you
inviting you to luxuriate
and this connection sense of connection to the earth
as if this is the most important thing no need to move on
as if your feet your legs are giving praise
thanking the earth for holding them for holding you
this is it
and let your weight also be released onto your sit bones
the entire weight of your upper body your eyes your forehead your jaw
back and shoulders hands arms releasing
ah
nowhere to go nothing to do in this moment
you are home
home in this body
feeling the breath welcoming the breath
like a soothing lullaby the abdomen
the sit bones your legs your feet
in-breath this out-breath
and let's spend just a few minutes to till the soil
with the breath in this body to settle to arrive even
more before we turn our hearts the practice of compassion
if your mind is wandering with faults it's okay
know that this is part of the human condition minds wonder can you be kind to this
mind oh a dear mind
like so many other minds
releasing gently default balloon letting there be another minute
calm spacious settling
now i'd like to invite you if you want to continue to stay in the body
connected with the breath
feeling your abdomen let yourself feel in your body not in
your head let there be a felt sense of
maybe something that the words or the feeling of
regret or the words i'm sorry has come up for yourself maybe there's something
you really wanted to get done today or the past week and you're just not getting to it
so there's a sense of oh sweetheart this being it was me i'm sorry
i'm sorry i know this is important to you
could be anything else
offering this i'm sorry gently to yourself
letting yourself feel maybe the ouch or the sorrow
sorry sorrow and sorry
not in the form of shame or blame but
ah this too is true
the river the ocean of
human condition it's not always the way we want it to be
what if you're listening to it listening to this i'm sorry that you've offered yourself
through this conch shell
listening to all the i'm sorry the sorrows of humanity all
the beings who are in the same situation or have been numerous
part of the human condition
it almost some of you might feel joyful
it's like music oh this is this is part of the music of being human
it's not that heavy or morose
it's just part of being human
my voice added to so many listening to it
as if kuan yin the buddha was listening
taking heart taking heart that you too you're part of
this amazing mysterious ocean of humanity
you're not separate you are uniquely you
and yet so
human see if your heart and open can open
to holding to hearing this with kindness
maybe forgiveness if it's needed it's available
maybe sense of strength it's not just you
no need for shame or blame sense of power strength
in recognizing your rightful place
it's okay you're fully human
fully beautiful fully imperfect
it's okay
you're doing the best you can
and you've done the best you can given all the causes and conditions
of your unique humanity could have been any different it would
have been each breath
i think there'd be ease care
warm-heartedness for yourself this ocean of humanity
and now if you like you can stay with yourself for the rest of the time
if this being who is you
needs the most holding compassionate bearing witness today
for those of you who like to offer
some bearing witness someone else
in your life who recently might have offered you and i'm sorry
you can listen and follow [Music]
these suggestions invitations
to bring someone to mind
or maybe recently
offered i'm sorry in words or
in actions to you
again not going to the most difficult challenging person or situation
something a little lighter that is not going to unsettle you in this moment this is a
gradual practice easier later to more challenges don't
choose something easy let yourself sif again picking up the
conch shell listening to i'm sorry this expression
of sorrow [Music] sadness that they didn't live up
to their values who they want to be the care they have for you
the respect they have for themselves
as much as possible listening with the ears of compassion the ears of
kuan yin or the buddha this i'm sorry this expression of sorrow
both uniquely theirs offered to you
and one of the sounds in the ocean of humanity ocean sounds
we are not perfect we do our best we often fail
is it appropriate in this case especially if the person who's offered
the words i'm sorry has a lot of shame or guilt
especially to offering them this gift of hearing them out listening to them
with the ears of kuan yin the ears of compassionate being
especially if it's someone we care about
maybe in this way of hearing we offer it back to them it's a different way of being in the
world not with so much shame or blame but taking heart
and trying failing learning forgiving
and trying again
and for the last minutes of this practice period
picking the proverbial conch shell again and listening to all the i'm sorry
sorrows
yours included the sound of the ocean of humanity well as
the other person you thought about all of them
so many intentions expressions of goodness
imperfections imperfect causes and conditions
listening to it all as if kuan yin heart of compassion listening
to the cries of the world tenderness
with appreciation sound of the oceans like this to be
human your joys also ten thousand joys ten
thousand sorrows it's like this being human
it's heartbreaking and it's beautiful at the same time
this kind of listening bearing witness can extend our capacity
capacity of our heart for ourselves for others for all beings
how mysterious and amazing to be human to hold witness
be conscious
contain infinitives infinitudes
more than we realize we are capable of
offering our ear our heart to the world to ourselves to
others as a gift
or kindness
our ah as much as available
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
know the goodness of their uniqueness and
that whatever they're going through is a part of being human part of being alive
conscious this mystery
may all beings everywhere wake up
their eyes opening up their ears opening up to beyond their little shell
of their own life to how magnificent it is to be
to be swimming to be a drop in the ocean of humanity
thank you all thank you for your practice for picking up the conch shells
listening to yourselves others
all of humanity so we have some time for reflections if you
like to share you can raise your hand your zoom hand you can raise your
you can type in chat if it's just titled to me it'll be private
i won't read your name just your reflection if it's typed to everyone i'll read your name also
jamie please yeah um for some reason i i just got really
locked in to imagining
people in marginalized groups or who have experienced trauma who
have been conditioned um to feel sorry not for what they've done but for who they are
and um you know i felt anger but some of it was directed at the members of that
group you know it's like i wanted to say you matter but it i mean it felt like angry
i'm just wondering if you can comment on you know those those you know people in those
categories yeah
yeah thank you for sharing that thank you for what came up for you jamie um
something that i'm hearing actually here and what's come up is i would turn
i would turn the compassion first towards yourself because in what you're
describing you're the angry one right it's the projection of anger
it's it's it's an anger it is said that anger is like picking up
a hot coal right it's you're the one burning clearly here
so so that's the first thing to notice ouch there's there's suffering here ouch
they're suffering here um [Music] so when the mind gets
off kilter with anger in this way there isn't enough balance to offer the
listening year or even any support or the wise action what would be the wise
action you would take in in the real situation not just in your meditation but but in the real
world if if you are having actual interactions and and what you're hearing which i'm
taking has inspired what came up in your meditation to actually take the
the appropriate steps the appropriate responses not being locked into this anger
yeah how does that land no thank you and um
you just helped me uh see where that came from actually it's you know i need a little upeka practice i think because
it's a someone who really matters to me who who falls into the sort of you know
has experienced some unfortunate things in her life and um
you know i took it on in a way where when she uh didn't change because i wanted her to
i was frustrated with her so it's i think that's a carryover but thank you starting with compassion
for myself always seems to help yeah brilliant i appreciate the light bulb
going off and and supporting the person because through your equanimity then you can actually through conversations and
you're listening ear and bearing witness and letting them see through the
reflection your mirror that them blaming themselves
is not the solution here so yeah so yeah there's more i can say
but i think that there's the you can support them more by bearing witness actually yeah great thank you for that
yeah any other reflections you can also type them in chat
either to me privately or to the whole group
done um thank you so much and um two things
came up and then when you said at one point you said uh this is it and um and it is
very evocative for me and it's like it's sort of motivating and uh in a way it's
like this is it and the other thing is um
uh i think myself and and no doubt others are often at war with ourselves
and um the and and there's and i'm sort of interested in thoughts on
uh a practice to and i'm sort of thinking okay i'll try to practice for six months
or a year or just sort of try to melt this a little bit
and um anyway there's no doubt different ways to do this and one book that comes to
mind um i think it's called good morning i love you and and the author of the book pretty
much said you know i didn't believe this at all and and it's sort of the sort of the
fake it until she made it kind of thing anyway i i'm interested in your thoughts over yeah
yeah yeah there's there's a lot in what you're you're saying don um
so it's it's the faking it until you become it that's the other thing i like
actually it's like until you actually become it you practice it and yes
definitely there is this um you know i i i think i've said that before that i um dedicated about a year
of my practice primary practice to be mental and compassion and it was a beautiful wonderful year
um and i do recommend that to people actually a certain amount of time
uh to just dedicate themselves to this practice and see the potential of it
um and yeah being locked into just so many different states to so many different
perspectives so so instead of you know you know it doesn't happen overnight but little by little by little by little so
so basically i'm offering encouragement if you feel called to do this absolutely
yeah definitely yeah daily yeah in daily life and in sitting practice yeah thank you
so let's see uh
one request from one of the members if folks want to walk around and otherwise move around a lot maybe they could turn
off their camera please yes so yes please if you that's in general if
you're about to move a lot on zoom some people can get a headache um so yeah i think it would be wise turn
it off after you've been settled turn it on again as a way of kindness offering kindness to others
so so let's um who is the author of the book don
mentioned dawn that is a question for you if you would kindly put that in chat while i create
the uh the breakout room so the breakout rooms a size of three roughly and the
invitation always is to just share something from your own experience not managing
handling other people's experience just saying something that you want to say
from your own practice and you'll say you offer one nugget somebody else will offer another nugget
and then another person another nugget and they'll go around and round a few times
um [Music] and be kind be kind to yourself be kind
to others and i still haven't seen dawn maybe maybe when we come back from the groups
done we'll have that information or i'm sure we can find that by googling it also so it's not
if it's not here in the chat no problem all right i'm going to create the rooms
there it is shana shapiro good morning i love you great thanks so i'm going to open the grooms take care
of yourselves take care of each other again just speaking from your own experience not managing or asking
questions from others and if other people comes their turn they just want to hold silent
witness offer compassion and kindness that's perfectly fine always have the conch
shell of compassion for yourself and each other available tonight okay here we go
opening the rooms
okay waiting for everyone to come back
and the rooms are closed everybody's back and we just have about a minute
left um so are any questions comments
um [Music] burning to be to be witnessed to be
expressed please raise your hand or write it in chat anything you noticed
any gift to offer to others aha moment serena
oh thank you um what arose for me was um
that you know i can have compassion for someone's i'm sorry
but there's also the case of um the story not being the kind of story
that is a transformative kind of sorry but uh
a quick way to um try to eliminate the problem they have caused
yeah i hear you i knew that was i know that was going to come up when i was giving the instructions so i was trying to yeah let me say something very quick
about that so so it's it's really the difference between an authentic and inauthentic sorry that you're bringing
up and i was trying to be careful in the guided meditation to say we're not talking about the inauthentic ones like
well i'm sorry like that's that wasn't a part of this guided meditation but i completely it was more about the blame
and shame that some people have like i'm so sorry i really messed up that's what this was about yeah so thank you for
bringing that up yeah okay thank you yeah thank you so thank you all for your practice for your
sincerity for your working with us and picking up the conch shell to listen to
yourself and other beings may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you all and now