it's a [Music] quite a lovely place to sit and practice and
in this very powerful contemplative environment of the retreat center
so a gentle background like the wind
the uh you might be hearing the traffic we uh in the morning sometimes we hear the traffic of highway 17 not
over the hill and uh some of the windows are open because uh
having uh we have about 37 40 people living together here during covet time so
we're having windows open and so um so uh it's probably you're hearing
that uh so
the camera is out of focus no sound suddenly static stop when you started talking
uh so the camera out of focus
well we'll look at that tomorrow but hopefully
okay so one of the things i wanted to say about this
sati patana the knowing quality is that
one of the things where what supporting our mindfulness is having a very simple reference point
so for example if you are if the classic example
um is um is that of um
a white piece of cloth that uh or canvas or something
that if it's full of stains one more stain you wouldn't notice
but if that white cloth is completely clean and you put one more stain on it you will notice it
and or if you have a chalkboard that is uh full of
writing on it you might not packed full of writing you might not notice uh
that someone writes something else on it but if it's completely clear the blackboard then
you'll see clearly you know if someone scribbles something on
so if a person is really agitated
they might not notice that their mind is now agitated with something new it's just all the same
but if the mind is calm then they might notice that
that the agitation begins so to have a reference point we see ourselves better
and this is what this imp one of the benefits of this simplicity of knowing
um the um
so some simplicity of knowing and
and so just to know that you're sitting just to know that there is a body
which is one of the statements in the sativatan sutta they have knowledge just enough to know
that there is a body to know that you're sitting might not seem very profound
but it highlights when we can't do that when we can't sit still and we're agitated
and fidgeting we can't we it we notice that we don't just see the body we're caught up in our
preoccupations so this simple knowing of breathing
works the same way that we might not be successful at staying very long with the breathing
but we can if the mind we're more likely because of this reference point of breathing
we're more likely to notice if the mind wanders off and and then
we practice simple knowing of that and oh and when you and the simple
knowing is a reference point for when we have complex knowing
when we know something with judgments and evaluations and a lot of thinking commentary
so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and just a simplicity of sitting here quietly your eyes closed
does that highlight something about how you are that you may not might not have noticed
if you hadn't stopped
noticing how you are in your body and your mind and your heart
and how simple or how complex is your knowing of that
chances are the more complicated the knowing the more you're caught up in it caught
in thoughts and preoccupations the simpler the knowing
the more freedom there is
and then settling down into the experience of your body breathing
breathing in and breathing out
and if anything makes it difficult just be resting in the simplicity of the body breathing
know that
experiment with this to see how simple you can know it
and then whenever you're ready return to your breathing
or allow the experience of breathing to return to a simplicity of knowing
settling in relaxing into the experience of breathing
on one hand you can notice when it gets complicated
on the other hand as you simply know it the experience of breathing becomes more
intimate more embodied in awareness
with this as awareness gets simpler our perceptions can become clear
here in the present moment
how simple are you with what is
how complicated are you with what is
and can your knowing be simple
even if things are complicated can you in a sense step back
and just know complication
always returning to simple knowing
how can the simplicity of breathing highlight
ways that you're not simple
highlight how you enter into more complex worlds of thoughts ideas feelings
and when you see that you've gotten complicated
can you take refuge in a kind of simple knowing
knowing of the complexity that's all
knowing thinking feeling
whatever it might be how simply can you know it
and as we come to the end of this sitting
the simplicity of being simplicity of knowing can be a refuge
a refuge of safety
and when the knowing is calm and peaceful it's a refuge of calm and peace
there might be other things happening which are agitated even within us
but to take refuge in the simplicity of calm knowing
and then when we live in a world of agitation
a world of complexity where people are spinning out and
not really present for themselves
may our refuge and simplicity simple knowing simplicity of presence
be a support for others may we make ourselves a refuge for this
world as we found a refined refuge in ourselves
may we somehow be a refuge
a place of safety for those who meet us
encounter us
may we be a refuge that supports the happiness of all beings
maybe may we be a refuge that provides safety to everyone
may we be a refuge
that offers the world of peace a peaceful
presence and may we be a refuge
that supports the freedoms of others if nothing else
people feel that they're free from us when we're present with them
may all beings may all people be happy
and once again being in a new place
all the preparations i set this up i didn't get a bell close enough to hit
to ring so i will bow and end the sitting
thank you
so we've started the discussions of the second exercise of the satipatana sutta
the one that goes very simply instead when walking
one knows one is walking when standing knowing one is standing
sitting one nose one is sitting lying down one nose
one is lying down in whatever way the body is positioned one knows that
and so it's uh very easy to just skim over this because
most people can master this one very quickly to know they're standing when they're standing
and they're ready to go off to do something else but
to really center oneself in this knowing
has all kinds of benefits but the one i'm going to focus on today
is that how it can be a reference point for uh we don't want to be there in just the
simplicity of that where the momentum where the impulses are where the life force is going for us
in a way that maybe is not always healthy for us or doesn't
express a lot of our freedom so for example standing in the
in the market in line for the cashier to
just center oneself standing i know i'm standing
and to really know that and not only know it with words
but know it feeling wise know it and embody it knowing just just stand there and then breathe with that and be with
the standing and it could just be for a few seconds
and then you might notice that there's this really strong pull desire impulse
to read the front covers of the magazines that are standing that are there
for you and or maybe you're a very strong impulse to
look and see what other people are buying and comment on it in your mind or maybe you notice then only then how
impatient you are and you're actually crowding the person in front of you a little bit so because you're somehow you know eager
to get on with it and without the reference point of a simple way of just
i know that i'm standing we see that we can't just stand
we want to do more we're engaged we're this impulse is there walking
to just walk and know you're walking and that's the all you're doing
it might highlight how you're walking in a hurry you're leaning forward or you're tense
or you're you know it might highlight how you're walking or you might highlight the fact
that you're hardly noticing your surroundings or noticing yourself walking because you're in some kind of
reverie or in some kind of preoccupation or anxiety
and um and none of these things is wrong that we're doing
that takes us away from the simplicity of what we're doing in the moment but the prac the path of mindfulness is
to know it to be mindful of it so to really know
oh there's a desire to look at the magazine covers there's a desire to move forward
i'm impatient and to know that with the simplest clearest freest kind of
knowing you can and that becomes one of the kind of
premier reference points is a simple knowing can we allow ourselves a calm simple
knowing of what's happening or is the mind racing ahead wanting to do things wanting to pick things up want
to get involved it can't just stay centered and settled
and standing in line in a market you know it's not the end of the world to just
stand there and breathe and be present and so you can feel how that's not
there's lack of freedom and how we're kind of maybe crowding the other person
looking at that cashier trying to calculate how quickly they'll be done not going to change anything probably
for you to do that but but you can see the way we've been caught in it and
it has us in its grip that kind of concern walking the same way we can see what's
the complexity of it and the and that beautiful art of this is that no matter how complicated the
mind's preoccupation is no matter how complicated the situation we're in there is always some capacity to know it
in a simple way and one of the
labels and ways of knowing that i have is that covers it all no matter how
complicated it is i'll just tell myself knowing chaos
this moment i know that it's chaotic and i don't know the details of the chaos necessarily understand all of it
i'm not trying to evaluate or study it or fix it i just oh chaos
and that knowing of that keeps it really simple and then there are times when i've used
that knowing of chaos and then i then i take the moment then to because
i know it now i can take it in and perceive it more fully as chaos
and then i start seeing almost naturally without losing that simplicity
i notice some of the details of it i notice that the chaos is primarily physical agitation in my body
and so now it's knowing simply knowing physical agitation and as i'm with that in a simple way
then at some point it becomes clear that there's anxiety
and the anxiety is this and so it kind of begins to be more specific but not
because i'm investigating and questioning and wondering what's happening it's just that i'm relying on the
simplicity of knowing for things to become clear and if we have a simple knowing where we
just allow ourselves to be with what's happening then clarity begins to appear on its own
so um it becomes a refuge the simple knowing it's a way it's a reference point for
freedom because in the simplest knowing the knowing happens in a very free way
the knowing is independent of what is known
so you know if i see the magazine covers on the rack at the market
i can recognize some exotic
title of an article and and i can just know it look at that
there's a title and as opposed to being horrified or fascinated or
eager to kind of get involved or start judging and how could they um
and when i start getting that complicated i can notice oh i'm i've lost myself in the complexity
i've lost myself in the feelings the desires the drives that i have there's not freedom there
but to have the knowing be free then is a reference point so this teachings about
when walking no you're walking standing know where you're standing sitting no you're sitting
lying down no you're lying down can function this way that it helps bring
more mindfulness more attention to what's going on for us beyond the simplicity of it
of just standing and walking and if nothing more is going on if it's really easy just to stay close to
walking when you're walking sitting when you're sitting standing when you're standing and lying
down when you're lying down then just enjoy yourself just sit there and breathe and be there
breathing and walking and feeling and being connected to the experience it's a fantastic
pleasure to do so and and if you make it more complicated than
that know it that's the case and then with that knowing perhaps
there's also some wisdom where you realize i don't have to spend my
time looking at the covers of magazines when i have something better to do
i can just sit stand here and breathe and be present or maybe you realize
maybe i should get a magazine a friend of mine is ill i know my friend likes
that particular kind of magazine it's a nature magazine and maybe i'll buy it okay for my friend
that's a little more complicated but it comes from a very different place
so in the refrain that we covered the very end of it it said
one has one is mindful there is a body
just to the what's necessary for knowledge and lucid or clear
awareness and now here we have again this very simple thing there is a body
and the the text the suit goes from that refrain to the the second exercise where
it remains that simple and uh it'll get as we develop this then
um this simplicity of practice it opens up and we become aware of a little bit more
complexity but we hopefully have learning how to be aware of more and more complexity or
more and more kind of richness of the moment we know it in this simple way
and in this simple way maybe is not so cognitive always it
might not be a label or a word that we say like chaos or sound or something but it might be a
quieter knowing that is closer to kind of a just experiencing it
so um
i think that's my words for today and um
i'm enjoying going through this saturday slowly step by step and and um
so we'll continue and uh and take refuge in your knowing
experiment and explore what it's like to be simple a simplistic simplicity of
being with whatever is happening a simplicity of knowing with whatever is happening
and see what what shows itself see what clarity there comes and the reason to experiment with that
and explore that in the next day or day or two is that
the mindfulness will get a little bit more complicated a little bit more involved slightly
and and so having this ability to have a refuge and knowing and keep it simple always to keep back
to the simplest knowing simplest awareness of it all is such a powerful support as we go
through the entire satipatana so
thank you very much