so good morning everyone good day it's my pleasure to welcome you this
today to the insight retreat center in santa cruz i broadcast from here a few weeks ago on
a monday this week uh this week i'll do all the days here i'm here teaching a seven-day
retreat and um and i really wanted to be able to continue this series on sati patana
so i'm delighted to be here and to share this wonderful place with you you don't see too much of it but
then you certainly see the altar and and one of the things
that i could say just to get a sense of what irc is like um the altar was built by a
practitioner here uh a woodworker and beautiful altar that
he spent many months building and uh and that was his uh
his uh inspiration his generosity to the center and the buddha was a gift from um
practitioners here at imc and people who love the irc and
and so um this little little picture of you know how and you see the paint on the wall that
it's you know the color the paint maybe it's nothing particularly special but there were volunteers here and i was
part of a team the aesthetics team that was uh considering every color and what would work for meditation hall and
for retreat center so it's all there's all this
it imbued this place with this wonderful dharma dedication of many many people to
make this possible volunteer set so you get a small taste but if i look
around irc i see this replicated a thousand ten thousand times of all this wonderful things that support
that people have provided for the center
um
when we started this at the breath exercise in sati patana the
instructions are when breathing in a long breath no you're breathing in a long breath when
breathing out a long breath know you're breathing out the long breath and the same with a short breath
and i take that as being shorthand for when you breathe know the characteristics the qualities know
the experience of breathing and and the operating word here is to know
and the most common verb most common activity that we're instructed to do in the satipatana is actually to know
and one of the ways of understanding this that i like is that the knowing is a kind of
recognition and it's a moment of recognition
and there's something very special can be discovered in just a simple act moment of the
recognition and if you kind of spend some time experimenting with the act of knowing
this recognition knowing uh you might be able to find
that uh that there's a some quality of freedom clarity
spaciousness perhaps non-identification non-reactivity
in the simplest way in which we can recognize what's happening
so uh and so it doesn't take too long to uh you know the mindfulness doesn't
you know the idea that mindfulness takes a while you have to kind of do it for a while to um is certainly
true that there are benefits that come as you continue to do it but to have too much focus on the future
and what you're going to how it's going to develop you miss the opportunity to discover how wonderful it is just in a
moment of knowing of presence
excuse me so if um
you would just maybe for a moment close your eyes and as you are
and find some neutral but clear sensation
that's happening that you're experiencing it could be a sound it could be a sensation in your body it could be breathing
and and recognize it with a a word like
hearing sensing or touch warmth
coolness movement whatever it might be and and uh say that simple word
in a very simple easy going relaxed way but with some kind of uh
like this is what this is really what you're doing you're like you gather yourself around just the simple act of
verbal recognition in your mind in an easy pace
um either continue with the same sensation or continue with whatever sensation it
comes to you very very easily just like there it is and you recognize it
and um and experiment with having that act of recognition
feel free free ill kind of not sticky not
reactive to the experience not judging it and um
and the just just the clarity of oh
this is hearing as you hear my voice hearing
if the chest moves moving just really really simple but but see if you
can gather yourself so that you're not
that's what you're doing you're not kind of on the side in the background of that underneath it mostly
having commentary about it or commentary about this exercise and questioning it
just like give yourself over for one like a moment to recognize a sensation you're having
and see if you can find a way in your mind to do that recognition so that it's a
spacious receptive allowing open
maybe has some quality of the knowing
is free of what is known
and this might feel like a little bit of work if you've never done this kind of focus like this
but this is the direction that mindfulness meditation can go where
it becomes simpler and simpler more more easeful but it's a we're taking refuge or
resting ourselves in the mind's capacity to know
but not a knowing that's necessarily work it's almost like a natural knowing that
the mind does the natural recognition we're recognizing recognition
so that that becomes clearer and stronger and we start discovering the freedom
the peace that's in that moment so to start the meditation
to assume your meditation posture
and gently take a few long slow deep breaths
on the exhale settling into your core settling into
the center of your being
letting your breathing return to normal and continuing with a normal breath as
you exhale to settle into your body
maybe as if you're relaxing and settling into your core
and then as you're breathing
no you're breathing know if your breathing is fast or slow
know it to be long or short
no it to be deep or shallow
and without working too hard at it see if you can recognize
the simplicity of recognition simplicity of clearly knowing
the simplest recognition that has no commentary no judgments
a recognition that's light useful
if the mind wanders off in thought see if you can discover the simplest
possible recognition that that's happening the recognition that
has some quality of being free of reactivity
free of preference
and then begin again with your breathing
as you make the simplest acts of knowing of recognition
do you have any sense that your mind is pulling away
or leaning into searching
and maybe it's possible to have the mind neither search or pull away
the mind itself can rest
trusting the simplicity of knowing just knowing
knowing in breath out breath
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe giving us some contemplation
about what it's like when you feel really known by someone else
not necessarily they know everything about your history but even a stranger it takes five minutes to
get to know you and you feel somehow they really
knew you to the extent to which you were at those five minutes what is it like to be really known
and what's it like for you
to know someone else
if there's no words to be spoken and you're with someone
and you really know them recognize allow for some clarity of recognition of
the humanity of some other person
there can be an intimacy in knowing
the simplest and fullest knowing maybe has no barriers
maybe it has no judgments
there can be something clean about only knowing
but knowing well knowing clearly
and as we develop our capacity to know intimately clearly
may it be the channel by which we convey our
care for the world our love our generosity
our respect
may what we learn through this meditation practice
support us to be a
conduit of care and love and kindness
and may our good will spread across the lands
from person to person
a ripple of goodness out across the world wishing
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
and for this morning i'm not sitting with the bell anywhere nearby
so i'll bow and you can join me that can be the ending
of our meditation thank you
okay so so today i begin the next exercise in
the discourse on the four foundations for mindfulness for awareness
and um it follows the same pattern as the first one in this in in that
it's going to describe another way of
observing the body in terms of the body
ardent aware clearly comprehending having a put aside
uh greed and distress about the world for the world
and um so this is a relatively you know mature mindfulness
state to be in to be able to observe the the simplicity of the body in regards to the body
ardent clearly comprehending and aware
having put aside greed and distress for the world
some people practice mindfulness so they cannot be caught in greed in distress
so but that could happen and when it happens then the practice can go from there
so that's kind of like a little bit the goal and then these 13 exercises are the means
so that's why i translate this text the four foundations for mindfulness classically it's called
of mindfulness but it's it's the purpose is for developing this clear awareness
which i call mindfulness and so how do we do that well we can also do
this with a second exercise if you do the second exercise well
that becomes a platformer foundation from which to go through the steps of the refrain
to have this more awareness that's open both to external and internal
uh to have this ability to see the inconstant nature of the experience
and with the help of that inconstancy of impermanent nature of phenomena
experiences to
abide in a very simple lucid awareness where there is no greed no clinging to
anything at all so this is the pattern now the second exercise is very simple
and because it's so simple it's easy to overlook it's you understand it immediately you know and so
you might feel like you're ready to move on to the next thing because it's you know just four or five lines and
you're done and um so it goes this way
when standing one knows when is standing
when walking one knows one is walking
when sitting one knows when is sitting when lying down one nose one is lying
down in whatever posture the body is in
one knows that so it's so
you know um deceptively maybe uh
simple uh you know just to know you're standing when you're standing okay you can do
that in a moment and then you're on ready to do the some more important things
and um but here we're talking about to really know and it's the knowing
pacianati and pali p a j
to know this is the important verb activity in that goes through much of
the satipatana exercises there's a number of different
instructions of what to do the verb to what we're supposed to actually do here
and then but the most common one is to know so there's a few things that make this
uh exercise you know really rich one is in fact
this emphasis on knowing and uh and this idea of clearly recognizing what's happening when it's
happening in the simplicity of it the most simple aspect of it in the moment
independent of any relationship to anything else so
at the moment i'm feeling comfortably but i feel a little bit cool
the windows are open here in this room it's a little bit cool outside so i feel cool so i know that i'm cold
i could add on top of that why is the cold in the room maybe the windows are too much open
i wonder how long the windows have been open how long should i sit here being cold
and maybe i'll get chilled if i stay here too long and so all that commentary and questions which might be reasonable
in some circumstances but what it does is that
it can take us away from the most simple relaxed
present moment awareness of the simplicity of just being feeling a little cool
feeling cool coldness and and feeling it in and of itself as if
it deserves or to be respected for what it is in and of
itself you know it is in a sense also can be seen as a message that i should pay attention maybe if i
was really cold but uh it just um uh but to be just to as if it's worth
worthy of just knowing for itself because what we're doing here in
mindfulness practice is going in a different direction
than the mind usually goes uh so all those concerns i have why is the
windows open how long can i sit here um you know those kinds of questions
imagine that those are like um the horizontal plane of life
and the in the mindfulness is the vertical dimension in
a sense that it allows us to penetrate and go deep so the simplicity of just knowing
something like cool coldness in and of itself is a doorway to a deeper entry into that
experience to really penetrate and see deeply into the experience
until we start seeing something that's liberating and freeing in that experience
and so the idea is to really be there with that in a but not to when i use the word
really being there i can imagine some people steal themselves up and they're going to try hard but this is meant to
be very trusting the very simple relaxed knowing
so to know when you're walking you're walking
means that you're not distracted you're not thinking about all kinds of issues in
your life and problems you have or wonderful things you can contemplate
as well the mind thinking is a fine thing to do
but there's also something wondrous about the times we can go really simple
and just know i'm walking now the in the in the horizontal mind
that has many concerns and interests that can get boring very quickly
but in the vertical mind that can go really deep it opens up to something really special
the first time that i experienced that in my life was uh really experienced in some
palpable strong way was when i lived for uh was about 20 21
i lived alone for a week on a farm and i'd never been alone for that long
didn't talk to anyone for the week and or see anyone really um and um
and uh i wasn't meditating but it was kind of like uh
as the days went along uh everything started to glisten everything started to be
this clarity to it and i would see something you know i see an object and it was like it was
shining if i had a thought the thoughts were just kind of like
um like a wonder
to see if there's a thought arise it was a clarity to it that i'd never experienced before it didn't really
matter what i was thinking it was just this clear thinking and there was all this space i guess and stillness and
quiet around which i can just have this very simple knowing of each thing
and it was life-changing for me it's one of the conditions that probably led to me being here and teaching
was appreciating and valuing this intimacy and clarity and simplicity and
brightness and vibrancy of just being present in the moment for this little thing
and knowing it and so that felt like maybe deep
and um so um the um
so to know you're walking as you walk to know where you're standing as you stand
to know you're sitting when you're sitting to know when you're lying down when you're lying down
on on coming out of meditation when maybe you're somewhat settled
that could be almost second nature to stay that simple or it's not maybe not second nature but
it's a way of staying that simple as a way of continuing to live in some of the benefits and
in the practice of mindfulness before you kind of automatically or quickly get into the complexity of your life in your
mind but allow yourself to stay calm and centered and simple
one of the you know i talked last yesterday about tiknot han who recently died and one of the things that many people
remember him for is when he did walking meditation and people there was sometimes long
lines of people walking with him down a country road and he would just
go really slow and steady and there's something compelling about when you walk just walk
when you walk just no walking when you sit just no sitting
so um so i'll talk more about this second exercise tomorrow but for today i
wanted to emphasize um this the knowing quality and i'd recommend that if you can today
to um experiment and as if you know you you all know things
easily it can be almost subconscious that you know something and you open your front door
and uh you didn't have the conscious idea there's a door there's a knob
this is opening the door you know you're you're it's kind of done an automatic almost
but see if you can stop doing things those kinds of things that are almost automatic
see if you can uh just open up a little bit more mindful
of them and see if you can find a way of recognizing door handle opening
in a very rudimentary simple easeful way that you see that in the knowing itself
there is freedom and then knowing itself there's not entanglement with what is knowing
that there's no before or against it's not automatic the for and against
the entanglement can be so integral to the very act of knowing we can't tease it apart
but see if you can begin teasing apart and just just know eating just eating
hearing a sound just hearing a sound and see if you can find some places where you discover something very
precious and special about the the human your human capacity to
know to recognize because if you start appreciating the freedom the ease the
peace that's found in knowing then mindfulness becomes a lot easier
and and you start developing something easier to receive some of the benefits that come
from doing ongoing practice and i see that there's a note in the
chat about wanting to see a copy of the suta that i'm reading for
the reason i haven't posted my translation is i want to redo my translation for this and i
haven't had any time to do that a version that i did many years ago is on the imc website if you look under the
resource um menu and at that top bar and there's uh the writings and i think
there's a suita translations is one of the categories in the menu and there you find the satipatanosuta
and when i have more time hopefully in the next couple of weeks i can or soon i can
post my updated understanding of the translation
so thank you thank you for being here and being part of this and
um and as we go slowly and steadily through this i hope that this text
will become more alive for you and richer and more
engaging for your practice thank you