so good morning everyone welcome
and um
so today the meditation is about
knowing and not knowing
part of the challenge of meditation is all the meaning we assign the
significance the fantasies the illusions the ideas that we add on top
of our direct experience one of the ways is assigning personal meaning or personal
ideas about what it means for me and some of that's okay
but some of it is extra it's a lot of it can be delusion
and fantasy and one of the ways to meditate
is to meditate uh with part of what we do is
not know not try to figure things out not try to
explain them not try to assign meaning to them or ask why they're there
or how to fix them and um and so this commit practice with a
question just a simple statement what what what is this
but not trying to answer it almost like what
is the uh is what allows us to witness something
and see it fresh and see it anew and and really know kind of see let it
appear come to us so the to sit with a what
and then see what without needing to know the answer
to just sit with what's there not knowing what's there in a sense but letting it show itself to us
but not asserting or projecting our ideas on top of it
and this is so helpful for the living in our life to always to begin
with a question what and let the experience speak to you
rather than you you claiming the experience for yourself
so what so to begin
by assuming a
upright balanced posture
and entering into this posture as if you're not coming with a long
history of knowing exactly how you should sit exactly what's your way but to kind of
discover what the posture can be as if it's the first time
and then to lower your gaze
and perhaps close your eyes
and this what can begin right away
what is this experience of sitting here being present
when there's no overlay of shoulds or expectations or
ideas of where you're going in practice
just what to this experience
a willingness to not explain not even to know what it is but just to
feel and sense and allow it to be what it is
and to have this what for what's happening in
your mind thoughts the attitudes
the reactions and this what some deeper question
almost like what is here what is this mind about what's happening
here but perhaps not looking for answers
just being open to feel and see and cents
and then perhaps taking a few long slow deep breaths
to settle into your body to settle into your place
letting you your breath return to normal
and then relaxing your body a bit
the face the shoulders the belly and each time you relax
imagine that you asked the question what is this
as if you're discovering this part of your body for the first time what's happening as i relax
what is revealed
and then to let yourself settle into your breathing
the rhythm of breathing with a beginner's mind
with the best you can without
expectations or ideas of what should happen
what it's supposed to be like
just what what is this experience of sitting here breathing
where the question what implies a relaxation
of searching and looking it's just what and being open to whatever is here
open to breathing to body to mind
oh what a beginner's mind
that brings a receptivity and a willingness to just be here with this
not needing to make it into anything judge it
but just the what the question what that takes you away
from your discursive thinking
your fantasies
the what to what's happening now here just now
sitting with an attitude of what that it opens you makes you curious
to this experience now while at the same time
not needing to know not needing to have it understood in
words or just an open
curiosity to this
so
when the mind wanders off in thought what is this
what is the question curiosity that quiets the mind
in a process of this silent discovery
one of the benefits of developing a mindfulness practice
can be a comfort level with not knowing
a comfortable comfort comfort comfort level being present for our direct
immediate experience and not needing to
have something to say something to explain not needing to know what one's supposed
to do just present
accompanying the experience allowing the experience to show itself
more fully without the filter of our ideas and
explanations and certainties
to ask the question what without looking for an answer
just looking for looking seeing more fully
and in this way perhaps we can
know people in a new way
fresh way not see them through the old filters and ideas and histories memories
not see them through the roles and ideas
by not knowing who they are we actually can get to know them more
fully in some way what is known
when we don't try to know
and perhaps the quiet stillness of the mind of mindfulness
can help us to
have greater good will and respect for others
may it be that as we come out of meditation whatever
ability we have to be present without needing to know needing to explain
generates greater care for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music] so
[Music]
so good morning and um
today the sunlight is quite bright for me so
so the um
one of the things that bind us that keeps people in
bondage can have a huge impact on others is delusion
and confusion and it's a very powerful
powerful word the word delusion and buddhism is considered to be one of the
important forms of bondage and poisons and
one of the ways to be caught is to be caught in delusion and it can be particularly
harmful because when we're deluded we don't really see the situation clearly
and so even if our intentions are good we might be causing harm in the world around us
but also with delusion we can be misinformed or misguided
in whatever we think is important if we think
you know there's a classic teaching in buddhism that someone who wants a fire
uh goes and chops up wood looking for the fire in the wood because in that where fire comes from
but it's not just enough to chop it up you have to uh you know create the fire
in the old days by rubbing something together and or the idea that you can get grape juice
by squeezing gravel if you're trying to accomplish something and you're deluded about the means and
what ways to do it then you're not going to get much result
so one of the delusions that buddhism emphasizes is
the the improper pursuit of happiness believing that what is not a source of
happiness is a source of happiness thinking that pleasure will bring happiness
thinking that power will bring happiness thinking that anger will bring happiness
thinking that criticizing others and blame will bring happiness
all kinds of ways in which we kind of you know thinking that i'll only be happy if
uh you know and have some idea far in the future that we want to put everything in place only then if only that can happen
and and so the um part of the function of buddhism is to
overcome delusion overcome confusion and ignorance
and the last binding bondage that we'll talk about on friday is ignorance so i want
to save some of the obvious kind of opposites of confusion delusion
as but what i want to say now is that
in relationship to delusion and confusion
there's two things that can be kind of the the the
corollary the healthy wholesome corollary one of them is
a capacity and willingness to not know a willingness to
when we don't understand to not be confused and not to spin out
delusive ideas and theories conspiracy theories about how things are
but to be willing to not know to be comfortable with not knowing
and to be able to say i don't know and the
and so rather than not knowing and then becoming confused or adding confusion
and delusion on top of it by by coming up with theories and stretching
and and projecting ideas and solutions onto the situation
there's something very powerful about not understanding what's happening
and being resting and grounded in not knowing
and there's wholesome not knowing there's in some schools of buddhism emphasizes a
tremendous emphasis on cultivating a not knowing mind
sometimes it can be called a beginner's mind and and the value of this not knowing is not
that we become stupid and uninformed by things but rather that we see things fresh
we're willing to learn and see anew what's there so there's new possibilities
there's a great we're better informed by what's happening and we're not caught up
in suffering around not knowing it's not a crime to not know
i've met people who didn't was in a situation that was difficult they didn't know what was
happening they didn't know what to do but they said so and there was something about them being comfortable
with not knowing and not understanding that made such a huge difference to me
um like it inspired me wow you can do that you don't have to have answers you don't have to have solutions
and um just sit there and not know and take a take a stand in
in not necessarily and not knowing but taking a stand and not needing
to pretend it's otherwise not needing to rush ahead and try to
make things up or figure things out i think that it's a phenomenally
powerful thing to to be willing to not know
it's a protection from delusion from confusion i think there's a lot of pressure in our
society to know to have explanations to assign blame to um
to kind of live in a fantasy world of of what brings happiness and what is the
dangers we live in uh there's people lots of people who are spinning out
tales of where the danger is and who are the dangerous people that are it's elusive
and so there's this pressure to go along with that current of delusions social delusion
and to step back and not know be willing be comfortable with that
it's harder to get swept up in mass delusion or the collective delusion
of the people around us or the pressure to to to do anything and to do something
besides be able to not know but to not know can open doors to not
know can give us new perspective to not know can be freeing of something very profound within us
so as a healthy alternative to delusion
there's a possibility of not knowing the other a healthy
corollary wholesome corollary delusion is a commitment to building our life
from our lived experience in the moment that this is where the
where we discover how to live a wise life is a dedication to the present moment
because what we can start seeing here and now is
how we suffer how we create our suffering how we
get caught how we strain how we get contracted how we get resistant how we get caught in desires or caught
in fear any kind of cotness any kind of bondage and a commitment to hear
and then finding a way to be here without
believing that the way forward is through suffering
or the way forward is to do something that involves that brings suffering to us at the same
time so for example to be in a in a
challenging social situation and and then to use hostility
to clear the room to make everything kind of be safe maybe let people chase
people away maybe maybe it's effective for the situation
but the hostility harms ourselves to think that what i need to do
is to become wealthy and the pursuit of wealth the very pursuit of his engagement in a greed that is a
tremendous amount of suffering for our own hearts somehow the the opposite corollary
to confusion and delusion is to be committed to tracking and
seeing very carefully discovering how to live a life now here
that's not built on things that are causing in the moment suffering to
ourselves and to see that as a sense of purpose
that gives clarity this is important it's not the final answer to everything
but it's the foundation that's the beginning of our life is the place where we can sit and be present
and know now i'm contributing suffering to my life now i'm not
and to be committed to that in a strong and a powerful
way um when i was i was thinking this morning about how when i was 14
i met a 14 year old woman that i was attracted to
and all i knew was her first name and the street that she lived on
and and so a friend of mine with a friend of mine we went through the telephone book of
the town i from the fro front and he from the back uh and we called everyone who lived on
that street and asked for for the you know using her name her first name asking for her
until somewhere i think was halfway through the in the middle of the book so we were kind of two of us were coming to the middle we finally found her street
and her through that way and i say that because of the drive the
seriousness the dedication to really be focused at that quest to find that woman
if you used if you used to use one tenth of that kind of dedication to dedication
to track yourself so that you don't get swept up in
confusion delusion needing to know the suffering of needing to know the suffering of
straining to have solutions but dedication to
staying in that place where we don't succumb
to to movements of mind and heart that cause us suffering here and now
with that dedication with that movement
and letting that be where the life is built from and and everything can be built from that
and a wonderful life can be built from that but it's not it's not a life that's built on
delusion or fantasy or or expectations and abstract ideas
it's a life that's built um that doesn't know about
is willing not to know about so many things but it does know
about tracking and staying close to that place where we don't contribute to our
suffering so
may you not be caught in delusion and confusion
may you discover the wonderfulness of a not knowing mind so as you go through the day today
you might see if some of your ideas explanations projections
might might somehow have some tinge of
delusion uh confusion some tinge of uh maybe it's not quite accurate what i'm
assuming here and see if instead of assuming things
you can practice not knowing the kind of not knowing that
that it doesn't ignore what's happening but then not knowing that allows you to
gaze upon it look upon it with fresh eyes and see what's actually going on including
what's going on in you and so that you can but in not knowing what's out there
you're more and not being confused by it or caught up in it you're more likely to
see what are you doing to contribute to your your suffering
and that that exploration will probably save you from a lot of delusion
so thank you