hello and welcome and uh
so it's a time to perhaps be a bit quiet internally
sit and meditate and to bring mindfulness to our experience
to bring awareness attention and it seems that in the teachings of
the Buddha water is used as a simile metaphor for
awareness and when we begin practice
maybe there are capacity to be mindful to be consciously aware
are brief and maybe it's more like moments that we sprinkle into the situation
so sprinkling awareness into our life and and that maybe that's also kind of a
nice image that uh that is kind of
I've been in places where Buddhist monastics have sprinkled waters
on people's heads and is a blessing kind of sprinkling Awareness on our experience
as uh the as the moments of awareness become more continuous
awareness becomes more like flowing water and it flows over and through and around
our experience or our experience
um yeah it's kind of being washed by awareness or floating in awareness
and uh that you have flowing water it doesn't that's you know it doesn't stop
for anything if it's a dam it builds up to the top of the dam and Spills over
but eventually it finds its way downhill and it can be soft but over time it's
very powerful wearing a ray wearing away the hardest granite
wearing away the hardest attachments we have as we
let the water flow through and with and water doesn't complain about things
it just flows water doesn't attach to anything it just
flows and then at times water becomes uh
enters into a large large lake where the water becomes really still and quiet
and peaceful quiet transparent water
is how mindfulness awareness can become when it becomes well developed
when all those moments of continuity really come together and there's no more
um reinforcing or bringing more attention and energy to it it just the
awareness just there and to abide to dwell
in this kind of lake-like oceanic-like awareness
is uh also possible and so these in other ways as well the
Buddha uses water as a simile metaphor and so as we sit today
perhaps you can keep close by
the simile at the metaphor of water for the awareness that you
are evoking bringing forth for this present moment experience
water flowing along with the breathing
water sprinkled in water as the vast
space space spaciousness vast Stillness in which everything floats
everything floats in its own way
and when everything individually floats in the vast space of awareness
for the Buddha there's a lot of equanimity that comes along
and so being equanimous about all things so with that that's kind of the idea for
today mostly will sit quietly
and um so you might if you haven't already gently close your eyes
and if your mind awareness heart is
like agitated water taking a long deep
breath and in the exhale let it all settle
let it all settle
letting breathing return to normal
okay bringing awareness to your body
breathing if
sometimes intermittently like water or sprinkled in blessings on
yourself other times more continuous and flowing
moving than other times
everything floats allowing to be as it is
in a vast body of water vast body of awareness
if you find yourself agitated
or caught up in thoughts or feelings or Body Sensations
imagine that it's floating in an ocean a wide Lake of water
it's allowed to be there
but it's allowed to float all by itself
it doesn't have to influence you or affect you
doesn't have to go away but it's held in a wide
vast field Lake of awareness
as we come to the end of the sitting
to again give some thought or image to water
maybe and how if you put your hand touch your hand into water
the water doesn't resist the hand
but it does surround it in a sense the water touches the hand
completely thoroughly but offers no resistance
so when sounds come Sensations come feelings thoughts come
it's possible to have no resistance allow them to come and
the water changes its shape to receive
whatever comes into it at the same time
so your water your your your awareness receives
doesn't resist but it also can be intimate with everything
non-resisting and in contact
touching
and to go into the world without resistance but with a heart
that can shift and shift and change and adapt and
move with whatever comes
doesn't resist but doesn't
lose itself and remains in a certain way connected
connected at the heart
and may it be that this practice that we do teaches us
how to care for ourselves and others by not resisting
while staying connected teaches us how to be saved by not
resisting but staying warm and kind and friendly
teaches us to be peaceful
by not contending and complaining and grasping
and may it be that this what we learn
about being present can be a benefit for this world
may it be that our ability to attend to be mindful
is for the welfare and happiness of all may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
so good morning and good day so here we come to the third talk about
the Buddha's use of similes to augment his instructions or to provide
instructions in meditation and some of the instructions have to do with um
also describing what can happen as we meditate and so we can recognize it and somehow
in recognizing it Buddha talks a lot about abiding
inexperience in entering and abiding in this idea of abiding
resting in or dwelling in or living within I believe it's supposed to have
connotations of um being at ease being somewhat still
kind of just content and happy to be present for what's here as a place of abiding a place of
resting standing being and um so to recognize the states that
are useful to abide in and um and these abiding quality it's a
metaphor to abide or to dwell but I think it has a connotations of being at home in the experience being where one's
supposed to be and being at ease there and so by recognizing the these
experiences when those were to abide and to convey those experiences of
meditation the Buddha and to provide instructions the Buddha uses similes
and as I said in the in the meditation there's a lot of similes that the Buddha
where the Buddha uses water and in different similes water represents different things
but often in the context of meditation it seems like water represents awareness
and uh mindfulness and uh and so depending on how strong
the meditation is how centered we are um the mindfulness feels differently
when we begin practice mindfulness is awareness that we bring
to our experience might be intermittent and we might have a moment of being Mindful and then we want to draw find a
moment again and so the Buddha talks about sprinkling
water into maybe from the simile from Monday into
the powder but if they have sprinkling and as I said earlier I love the idea of
sprinkling because it's kind of a hot day it's kind of refreshing to be sprinkled with water to have a water
sprinkler kind of kind of touch you and cool you down
and uh or standing in a shower it's kind of lots of sprinkles pouring through pouring down it can be very nice to
stand there and in the shower sometimes or the way that the Buddhist monastics
will sprinkle water that's been blessed so they're doing blessings and
sprinkling it on people's heads it's kind of a really fun ritual ceremony that they do and so they're sprinkling and so you
know it's not just simply bringing attention back bringing attention back I wonder who I bring you back but it's
bringing it back in this nice way we're kind of like sprinkling our blessing
refreshing our experience with awareness the best we can as these drops become more continuous
and come together then the metaphor is that of a lake that
has a current flowing through it delightful current flowing through it from the under underwater spring
and here there's still activity and movement in the awareness where maybe still applying ourselves we're still
there's kind of an active way in which awareness is functioning within us and
and we kind of feel the dynamism of it maybe the dynamic quality of it
and then but then as the as the um we get more concentrated more settled
resting abiding more deeply in the experience then uh the um
the metaphor the simulated Buddha uses is that now still of a lake but this
time the lake has no current no movement in it so there's uh the lake now is
completely still and and I think of this lake is very clear
and very still very peaceful I've seen I've been Mountain Lakes early
in the morning before the birds are up but the light is up and um that Dawn and
and being on the edge of these lakes and before the wind begins and seeing the water the top of the water so still and
quiet maybe reflecting the mountains in a distance and there's something so peace generating
and by watching that I just love sitting there just looking at this peaceful quiet morning setting scenery where the
day hasn't begun and everything is so quiet and still so the Buddha uses this idea of a still
Quiet Pond Lake for how sometimes meditation can be
experienced and and so the mind has no sense of movement anymore
and awareness has no sense of movement and it's not being applied or brought to
anything or flowing through us and it just is and things occur within it and
the metaphor that Buddha uses for this the he talks about this still very still
quite like and he says that within it lotus flowers of different colors and he
specifies I forget white and red and blue and black and
I don't know what the colors are that lotuses can have but these lotus flowers are floating and not
just the top of the water but in his metaphor they're floating underneath the water so I don't know if lotus's flowers can
float underneath the water maybe it's the buds before they've opened um
but because the water is clear these lotus flowers are just floating there each one separate from the other kind of
just floating by itself in this beautiful body of water
and this represents the different colors represents all the different experiences we can have as we're sitting in
meditation that each experience each individual detail kind of is allowed to
exist there by itself each thing is allowed to be just itself
without any reference or tied to or caught up in the past the future about
comparisons to other things that are not it and it just allowed to float
and so agitation can just float there and be a lotus flower
sensations of the body kind of feeling just floating there and um
and everything just seems to float just each thing by itself and we're not doing anything with it or tying and connecting
it to anything else is just allowed to be itself and this kind of idea of allowing each thing to be itself the pristine self as
it actually is I think for me it gets conveyed in this simile of the lotus
flowers floating in this very still Lake the water here is not just awareness but
it's also awareness saturated or filled with a kind of joy and Delight
and so um if you have joy and Delight joy and happiness the
um they're you know their strong awareness that comes along with it and the distinction between This Joy and
delight and awareness maybe is not so obvious or maybe it is maybe joy and Delight is
some of the lotus flowers and but the idea is that the water the
water touches everything and the lotus flower
no part of the lotus flower is not touched by the water and in this metaphor the Buddha says no
part of the lotus flower that is not touched by the um
the peace the Tranquility the contentment The Joy the happiness
of um of that's a present in this state
it's not easy to just suddenly feel and experience the mind the awareness our
being as a stale quiet Lake but when it does happen
then the instructions are twofold is to abide in it rest in it and very gently
allow the the well-being The Joy the happiness the sometimes the Rapture the
Bliss that's there to allow it to spread and suffuse throughout the body
throughout everything so nothing that occurs is not touched by awareness by by
this well-being that can be there so um
so the Buddha provides these metaphors
these similes and and they're kind of pointing to
they're illustrating the kind of experience that can come as the mind
gets settled focused quiet still when we start living in Awareness rather
than having to only sprinkle awareness remind ourselves to bring more to it and more to it
and so um it is a kind of points to a possibility a potential we have that and
these beautiful similes maybe it's inspiring uh to think about this to the
possibility of abiding resting in awareness not contending with anything not
resisting with anything but meeting everything with clear awareness
and letting that build and develop over time of the sprinkles that we do slowly
increase the metaphor the similarly before was that of
you know the soap powder coming together and holding together another uh assembly that Buddha uses is
also drops is the rain falling on the Mountainside and if the rain becomes large enough you
know continues long enough and the water kind of sits on the surface of the soil
um it starts to roll and the drops meet each other and become stream little
streamlits and then the stream the streamlits become streams become Creeks becomes Rivers but as they go down the
mountain side they they first go into a small Lake and then a bigger Lake and
then the river goes into a bigger Lake and each Lake it gets bigger it gets
quieter and Stiller because there's uh you know uh the lake
is so big compared to the amount of water coming in until finally the water ends up in the ocean which is in this
assembly is the greatest peace most peaceful place if you go a few feet under the surface of the water
so uh so the sprinkles the drops drop by drop
we practice our mindfulness that's our job is to provide the drops and if we
keep doing it the drops join and come together and we start getting a sense and a feel for something vast and large
and beautiful so um that was my attempt to make these
similes come alive for you a little bit so maybe you can um
um see if something in your experience corresponds to these similes and that
maybe there's something about water that's evocative and interesting as a
simile for awareness for for mindfulness that kind of can change
the quality the characteristics of how you practice awareness how your practice
mindfulness practice as if you're bringing um moist
flowing what water to your experience where there's no resistance
to what is um but it's there's a flowing around and through and over and under
or or if it's not flowing maybe it's still and
just holds everything in the Stillness of a quiet mind
so thank you and there's more more similes that the Buddha gives so we'll
continue um tomorrow thank you