well good morning everybody good day and i'm aware that this is um being
webcasted as well and so there may be folks joining online so
we have to ima and kind of stretch our imagination to feel the
sense of kind of practicing together
english multiple forms
so we'll start um with a meditation
and this morning and i wanted to invite
in our meditation paying particular attention to the conditioned nature of our experience
so our offer some guidance and maybe particularly at the beginning
of the meditation maybe towards the end
and hopefully those pointers will offer something for you to explore in our meditation
so we'll begin our meditation by maybe just begin to pay attention to our sitting
position and sitting postures and if you like to close your eyes
feel free to gently close your eyes or if you like to keep it open that's fine
also
the first few moments arriving at our seats and our cushions
allow this arriving to be
just taking its time letting it take its time
maybe having some generosity towards this process of arriving
sometimes and there is a sense for me as if the flights are landing
i'm not completely stopped just yet and coming to our seats
arriving may feel a little bit like that
maybe our minds are still moving about thinking this and that
our bodily energy
can feel a bit bubbly
just by noticing that the arriving is happening
mindfulness is already here
become available to this process however it's unfolding
taking a few long deep breaths
maybe as you breathe out allow that sense of arriving
to settle even deeper
become aware of this whole body sitting
right here and right now
that's the first few moments of our sitting i invite you to rest your awareness
in the lower half of the body
what's the felt sense of sitting against the chairs the floor
pressure a weight
underside
maybe some sense of energetic settling downwards
supported by earth grounded
we can tune in to the stability aspect of the body
by resting in the felt sense of earth element
firmness of the bones
the stability of the pelvic floor
supporting the rest of the body
he's sitting like a mountain
you can expand to include the earthy
earthy feeling of the rest of the body
maybe the strength of the spine the weight
of the limbs
and steady
maybe you already noticed with the
steadiness as the backdrop
there is a movement in the body movements of the breath
dancing sensations of the body
receiving both the steadiness
and the movements
we can expand our awareness even further
to receive the movements in the mind the emotions of our
our dancing emotions in our experience
thoughts memories
so waves of emotions are ripples
including in our field of awareness
all experiences coming through our senses sound
smell
today i would like to invite you if you like
to pay particular attention [Music] on how experiences
arise and pass as a conditioned phenomenon
maybe the sound of my voice coming you hear the words
having some perceptions of it
and noticing what arises right after that
curiosity aversion too much too little
and there may be stories about it about yourself others
this comes through a conditioned
process
with a sense contact of hearing
evaluation and judging and
storytelling arises
and noticing how they pass away
i'm becoming really interested in the unfolding of your lived experience
right here and now not to think about it
trying to figure it out just sitting here
[Music] becoming available
to the unfolding of our experiences
so
if you find yourself a wandered away from here and now
it's never too late to simply return to the simplicity
of this experience right now right here
[Music] so
[Music]
hmm so good to see you all to be with you all
uh what's on my mind today to share as a dharma talk um
i'll continue to invite you on a kind of simplicity of a being as you listen to
this dharma talk and just you know bring your body along bring
your mind along and checking how you are periodic periodically
what i'm offering is not separate from it
so i want to start by sharing on a story and i recently read an article by
lama rod owens called do you do you know your true face
and in this article he wrote about after
his three-year dharma teacher training training program and he had a period of
his life that he felt quite uninspired and even used the word
breakdown you know it was challenging and so
he turned towards it and very quickly he had an insight into what was
happening and so this is those are the words um
that he wrote he said that my identity as a llama and a
resident teacher had somehow choked my identity as a
queer black man i was privileging the llama over rod
and rot this being and have many different needs different roles and different identities
and the rod got subsumed by lama and the resident teacher
when i read this i immediately resonated with it deeply
and and found much humility and
wisdom in what he said i think all of us probably have seen and
this version affecting ourselves um so in the pursuit of
our own ambition our hobby our passion or simply wanting to be who we wanted to
be you know really wanted to be very inspired for being this person
and um we may have joked
[Music] word or suffocated
as other aspects of our beings and so i want to share
a story of my own i remember some years ago in my work life i
was very busy and was doing very well and i got caught up
by the momentum of it and i remember there was one morning and that i had to get up to do a
presentation that happened at 5 30 in the morning to a very important client
and i had hoped that my baby boy won't wake up 5 30 in the
morning and he was very young and but you know what the moment i started
my presentation he was sitting upstairs mommy mommy
and so um but i ignored him because i got very
important presentation right now and i gotta go do that and i finished my
presentation and went up uh stairs to check him
and he was sitting by the stairs very quietly holding a piece of paper in his hands
and i looked at the paper and he barely was able to write anything at that time
and it said you are the baddest mom i ever knew
so that was a wake up moment so
just like llama rod owens and i was privileging
a scientist a career woman um over a mother a spouse and
in the rest rest of me
and so it's uh worthwhile to notice that uh in each of us
there's a whole community within us and there's a whole community community around us
um our dharma practice in what invites us to become aware there's a whole
dynamic of the different aspects of our being when we're not aware
it's very easy that we create favorites the ones that we really want to be
and the ones that you know rather they don't exist
and so this brings me to a short suta that i want to share with you today
called kachana this this is in samyata nikaya and
in the chapter around dependent origination
and so in the sutta venerable khachanon is asking the buddha
a question about how to define right view [Applause]
well many of you might be very familiar with the notion of a right view which is
the first path factor of the noble eightfold path and in this suture
and the buddha had a very specific definition for it which i want to share
but in answering this question the buddha first made a few quite
dramatic statements so he began by saying
this world mostly relies on the dual notions of existence
and the non-existence so this world mostly relies on the new
notions of existence and non-existence
then i'll unpack this a little bit and first by maybe unpacking the word and the word
world the world often
when the buddha spoke speaks about a spoke about the world the world is not necessarily something
kind of out there but the world is often defined as
our direct experiences through our sense context you know and our sixth senses
cite hearing smelling tasting touching and mental activities
and through this our subjective experience come about right we make contacts with
the sound with the smell and we can directly experience what's happening
and the broader world is kind of experienced through our senses as well
so there is in a way there is no world out there but through our direct experience with the
senses [Applause] so the world mostly
or by and large relies on the notions of existence and non-existence so what does
this mean and so existence non-exis existence um
in the chinese parallel i use the word becoming
and non-becoming some of you might be familiar with this and it's
often present in the suttas
but if we go back to the stories i told early on
we can see that sometimes we get stuck um the idea of
who we are our identity identities our roles
uh you know i am so and so and so i must do so and so
and when we have this kind of
ideas sometimes they're very deep and subtle we don't even know they exist
sometimes there may be very visible momentarily but when they really are in the core of
our being what happens is that we can orient and organize our whole
life around these ideas right and if you want want to be or you are a great poet
then your whole life activities could be centered around that notion
you know six o'clock in the evening you might forget about putting dinner on the table
or you know your child is asking to go out and play in the backyard no i'm busy you
know i gotta write this poem and and so this ideas can
become a basis or in this notion of we rely on those ideas
to live our lives and the opposite could be true also you know if some of
us may have parts of ourselves we would rather them not be there we have certain ideas that
maybe i'm just not this material you know i'm just not an artist and
and maybe that's something that happened very early on in our life
very young we had this ideas i'm not good enough for a certain thing
and that get reinforced by culture around us or
environment that we're in and then we have a deep seated ideas this is and then this is who we are and
and no we're just not that so um
and then with this kind of ideas what can happen is that
we also organize our lives around this ideas or maybe
organizing activities around this kind of activities
maybe we don't care about this part of us at all we may even be violent against them
when these parts of us show up and so there is can be this
sense of what the buddha is pointing to relying on non-existence kind of really denying
that and
and nama rod owens in this article uh spoke a bit about this and he said
to resist naming our identity locations is to commit a kind of aggression toward
ourselves and to further obscure blind spots that hurt others
others are hurt when they're not seen invisibility is another form of violence
and oppression and so this is not an existence in a way it's also pointing at
the invisibility that can happen
but because of this ideas [Applause] are not the reality of our direct
experience in our direct experience you know maybe we are
working on poems or doing some activities for a while
um being a poet but the other situation comes up
for caring for others and caring for themselves happens
then the situation change so can we
in the situational transitions can we recognize that is
happening and honor that that is how that is happening in our experience right now
when we don't we hand on to that idea of i am so and so
we rub against the reality of the situation and that
rubbing against began to create a lot of stress in ourselves and for others right this this
rubbing against so these are not mistakes that we blame
for ourselves but it's pointing to the fact that
when we're not aware um what is happening we can live our huge
part of our lives based on this kind of ideas and without us knowing it
[Applause] and we can also see that those are the ideas and that
can play at a societal level right certain categories of people may have
certain ideas about being more worthy of their existence
[Music] and others may have the opposite and you can see you know a lot of the inequality
and conflicts and injustice began to kind of bubble up from this
kind of ideas and they often can trace down to the notions of existence and on existence of
becoming a non-becoming so it's quite humbling to see those
ideas live and operate in us in quite deep ways
the buddha continues to point out the deeper phenomenon that exists behind
this notions i wanted to just point out for some of you who might be very geeky about this
the way that i'm i'm choosing to kind of express the unfolding of the
suta is based on the chinese parallel version they have a different order in
terms of how the teaching is presented in the poly canon
it doesn't it makes not a whole lot of a difference in um what i'm presenting here
but for me that ordering seems to make a little more sense in my own mind
the buddha continues to say that the world is for the most part shackled
by attraction grasping and existing
but if when it comes to this attraction grasping mental fixation existence and
underlying tendency you don't get attracted grasped and committed to the notion
myself you will have no doubt or uncertainty
that what arises is just suffering arising and what ceases is just
suffering seizing your knowledge about this is independent of others
and this is how right view is defined
so the first thing the buddha is pointing out and after he spoke about
the world in the world mostly by and large relies on the notions of
existence non-existence is that he's pointing out a deeper force
that keeps those ideas alive in this and that is the forces of grasping
cleaning craving attachments
it's through the grasping and attachments that this ideas are kept
alive in us i know um this is something for us to
see in our direct experience without grasping
you know the idea i am a scientist i'm a courier woman it's just momentary and
it's a thought comes from time to time and it goes just a thought
but when there is a craving to continue to establish this
i like those the translation word commit we commit to it again and again
now this idea becomes hardened in us more and more and can almost become a core of
ourselves because i am this person right i am
and so it's um what the buddha is pointing at is to begin to see
this underlying force of grasping and clinging and craving
in our meditation i also offered to maybe see this conditioned nature of
our experience directly you know those are some things that we can see
so we can even do a little experiment right now and then see
how the condition the phenomenon of existence comes to be
so i'm going to tell you all a little secret about yourself that you don't
know maybe you know but pay attention to what i had to say
and see what happens in your experience so i'm going to to say this
you are all such wonderful yogis
have anybody told you about this you are all
wonderful brilliant yogis see what happens in your lived
experience maybe there's some pleasantness in you
pleasant feelings in you some recognition
maybe sometimes there is that kind of a huff and puff kind of leaning in you know
boy wow i am a great yogi or some of you might say but it can't be
me you know that can't be me and so you can see
just by hearing something i said that can be different responses coming
out of it and sometimes the sense of itself is very obvious
and sometimes that sense of a denial is very obvious right and so this is the
um the direction that the the buddha was pointing at began to notice
that the leaning in or pushing against and you can see you know now if the
whole room is telling you the same thing and then watching this process happening
again and again no doubt i am a great yugi
there's no doubt and here it is you know a great set up before a
failure right somebody just shows up and mildly criticizes boom the whole bubble
bursts and so this commitment to this notion
keeps this ideas um kind of held up held up there
um
so you know the the notion of existence and non-existence can feel quite
abstract and high level and philosophical but this right view the definition of
the right view that the buddha is appointing to is really inviting us to see this
directly in our lived experience and i like that the chinese translation for
right view some of you may know this and also has a literal meaning of
directly see direct seeing the second half of the sutta the buddha
explained how this right view can be established through seeing
and so this here it goes but when you truly see the origin of the
world or with the right understanding you won't have the notion of non-existence regarding the world
so when you see how things comes to be you won't have this idea of
non-existence regarding the world and when you truly see the cessation of
the world with the right understanding you won't have the notion of existence regarding the world
so there are two things happening here and let's unpack this a little bit one by one
[Applause] a few key words here
when you truly see with right understanding right understanding here the pali term is sama
panya right wisdom a clear wisdom
when you see with a wisdom what do you see seeing the origin of the world
seeing how the world how the phenomenon arises seeing the condition the nature of
arising so for example we are all here in the situ situation or
in you know listening to a dharma talk and practicing together
and this isn't the arising of the situation but it comes with a whole host of causes
and conditions you all probably drove walked and
the schedule happened to be like this and you and i are all present here and
there's a whole host of conditional conditions that led to the situation we're in right now
right here and we can't just say this doesn't exist
we can't just deny no this doesn't exist you know this is all just a fantasy no
in our direct experience we experience this truthfully
there's a truth to this existence so when we know this the notion of
nothing truly exists all doesn't exist
that makes no sense right and so that's what the buddha was pointing at
when we see the conditioned arising of our phenomenon
non-ex nothing exists makes no sense
you know and then when we truly see the cessation of the world
when we truly see the ending of our experiences
and the notion of a permanent existence long-lasting existence
makes no sense and we see that the meeting ends um
you know the situation ends let the things
stop we can't just say oh this is going to go on forever you know that makes no
sense and so what the voodoo is pointing at is
in our lived experience when we begin to clearly see the arising and passing
and the conditions leads to arising and passing
we began to see for ourselves that hang on to this notions of
existence non-existence totally makes no sense
and we know this for ourselves and what that entails
is very simple direct awareness
and really being present for this arising and passing because what can happen oftentimes is that we
don't quite see so we just hold on to that notion in our head most of the time
in a way our meeting ended but we're still thinking oh you know this this would happen again and you know we just
kind of have ideas to keep things going so in this article
um lamar rod owens speak about this radical presence
that points to this particular dimension of being aware
it says radical speaks to a sense of remembering and returning to a simple
and a basic way of being in the world when we choose this way of being in the
world we feel at home in our own body with no desire to live it
because we feel at home in the body we feel at home in the world
this is a radical presence
and when we know this conditioned arising and the passing of our
our experiences what can happen is that
we grant fluidity to our identities it can float depending on the situation
we're in you know this moment we can be students and teachers next moment we might be buddies
and we can become fluid and we don't have to carry all these ideas along with us
and um and the llama rod owens had this sentence which
spoke to me deeply he said practice grants us as a space to allow this
shifting to happen and to call that shifting our home
so instead of relying on the notions that seems to be quite permanent and
persistent making that at your home and ground here
we rely on the ever-shifting changing of our direct experience and
calling that our home
and so i want to end by
um sharing the next piece of the buddha's teaching
which probably really need another dharma talk but i think we will just end with that um
and i'll do a quick summary after that and so the buddha went on
to give the teachings on the middle way and he says o exists katyana this is one
extreme o does not exist this is the second
extreme without a veering towards either of the six dreams the tatakata teaches the
dharma by the middle and this teaching by the middle
is not in between existence or non-existence but the teaching
by the middle is the 12 dependent origination
of the dukkha of the suffering and the dependent association of the
dukkha and usually this link starts with with ignorance as conditioned relational
formations comes to be with the volitional formations as conditioned consciousness comes to be
and then all 12 links all the way to how the whole mass of the suffering
comes to be and so that's you know there are 12 links of this
and then the cessation also follows a similar pattern but it says
something like this with the reminder list fading away and the cessation of ignorance comes the
cessation of relational formations with the cessation of relational
formations cessation of a consciousness and all the way to the cessation of the whole mass
of dukkha or suffering
maybe what's more important is not necessarily to kind of
remembering this 12 links but to begin to really pay attention
to our lived experience how the dukkha comes about
and how they cease began to see the underlying
conditionality in our direct experience because when we know this for ourselves and this
said that your this knowledge is independent of others
no one else can talk you out of it because you know this for yourself
and that began to offer a potential to shift
shift the perspective shift our behaviors
i want to end with this quote from
the activist um james botwin
and he said i am what time circumstances in history
have made of me certainly but i am also much more than that
so are we all and so when we see the conditioned
natures of our experience we can acknowledge
what is here what is here right now what is true
for ourselves not denying not indulging
but when we see this we also let go of the limitations of notions of who we are
and what this uh last line that he said point out to is i am much more than that
all of us are so there is a vastness of all of our beings
that is not defined by the limited notions and ideas and beliefs that we
have for that is done through our direct
knowing of what is happening what is here
so thank you everybody for being here and we we have a few minutes for any
comments and questions or sharing you have reflections you may have
and the floor is open
here we go just one second thank you
i appreciated and feel like
i got what you just said yet i don't i haven't studied and i don't understand
independent origination do i need to understand that to have
understood your main points today well you seem to have answered the question to yourself
yeah so you have a sense you know in your own being and so
this uh talk is pointing at really begin to pay attention to what is happening
and maybe when there is a chance to study we don't have to resist that also and
come along and that's good but it's not dependent on that
i think what is more dependent on is to begin to pay attention to what is happening
yeah do you have any recommendations for reading for
understanding [Laughter] there's so many
i'm sure even on audio dharma if you search on some talks on dependent
origination i'm pretty sure you'll find talks on this thank you yeah
um i have a personal question i heard that you started
your i guess path with buddha dharma it was mahayana buddhism but then you
got drawn to the theravada buddhist this is actually my first time ever in uh theravada
type of you know monastery but it's monastery so can you elaborate on like what uh
the difference maybe for also others seem like would be useful what the difference between mahayana and
theravada and why did you get get drawn to tiravada
yeah i um i feel a little hesitant to kind of um
i i don't feel i'm qualified to kind of do a real broader perspective i can talk
about my personal perspective and what happened to myself
and i've continued to hold both of the lineages with high regards and
deep respect and i happened to start with mahayana
first because i met mahayana sanghas
and i resonated with a lot of teachings there a lot of
the community that i really enjoyed and
but the particular community i was part of we didn't have a lot of
meditative opportunities and i was very caught up by all the
teachings in my head and i just i felt like my head was about to explode if i
keep on doing the studying and i really needed to know this in my own experience and so
when i began my meditative practice it was in the theravada tradition and
that's when i began to meditate and that spoke so much to me and so
today i continue to maybe
study and learn in different ways in some different
traditions but now i i kind of um i bring along kind of my lived
experience and the direct experience driven practice with me and
so that helps me understand a lot of mahayana teachings
i wouldn't say a lot but i understand the certain dimensions of a mahayana teaching
and this particular suit i coated it was sometimes recognized as a seed of
the mahayana tradition because the scholar and the practitioner on
nagarjuna um had this um
profound teaching around the middle way and this was the kota he uh this was the
suta he coated yeah so there is a maybe a deep roots uh
deep common roots yeah thank you yeah thank you
oh no just a little follow-up so you mentioned uh direct experience do you mean like
direct insight or direct to you i guess to clarify um
direct yeah you said like direct experience i guess meditate direct meditative experience direct uh or
direct insight like this is inside meditation i guess right that's yeah the the practice that i'm uh mostly engaged
in is the inside meditation process like noting or the on the mindful meditation
what's uh yeah that also changed and gifted quite a lot you know over the
years of the practice and i did a start with um amahasi sayadaw's tradition
and um and that kind of continued to evolve and this shift and change yeah
okay all right thank you yeah
i just wanted to appreciate your talk and your being here and to loop back to the beginning of
your talk with the experience of your child i i'm remembering
that my own young youngest child at one point said i'm going to go
on craigslist and find a better mom
i think all parents have been told this one we are another running their lives
yeah they're very honest untruthful it was great
to have a mirror coming back yeah they all
you mentioned the chinese parallel um uh scriptures um
this is just a kind of a technical point because i kind of interested in this
but what i've heard
is that since the poly canon is
in a language that's close to what the buddha originally
spoke that it must be primary or primal
and that the chinese versions of the polycannon must therefore be a later translation
and so we can just stick with the polycanon right because it's closer
to the original and and yet i've also heard that there are a number
of places in the chinese
versions that are clearer or make a little bit more sense
and that perhaps therefore the polycanon might be
a later translation from the chinese that didn't get the translation very done
very well so in other words it's just not entirely clear uh
if the poly canon is always closer to the original teachings
whatever they were does does that make sense or is this something you yeah i don't know about yeah yeah my
understanding is this is an ongoing kind of scholarly study a topic for sure
there is no definitive statement to say that the parallels are
later than the poly canon there may be certain collections that
one can make a little more definitive answer a statement than others
and so the chinese parallel comes from sanskrit collection so that's translated through
the sanskrit version but it's it's not totally uh clear
actually that there is a such definitive answer about which one is first and
which one is later and so um this you know this is ongoing
ongoing research still in this domain when i um
[Music] for me personally looking at the different versions
um not encouraged for those who have a different
maybe either mother towns or different language capacities
to do look at different translations and they do have um they can be quite
meaningful for me because i'm not i wasn't born uh here and and
i didn't grow up here i came when i became a young adult i had a very little
emotional association with english language and on
so the so is the translations you know and kind of like a lot of words as a
the emotional resonance with them is kind of learned you know a taste but what the chinese translations i have an
immediate sense uh oftentimes with what they are and in kind of in almost a somatic way
and so this is you know something for each of us to explore i mean looking at the different words
even the english translations there are different words um different
english words that translate on the same poly and poly term
and so um they may be helpful you know that's a helpful aspect of studying and learning
so yeah so thank you for bringing that up it's just a technical note but but
sometimes you know the question does come up and and maybe it's just best to
look at all the translations if you have access to more than one version and and just sort out for yourself what
what makes most sense to you yeah yeah yeah and i know that that may change
over time [Laughter] yeah i think we're almost time so
thank you thank you for your presence here for being here and studying learning and practicing
together with a delight and my understanding is those who are
online will have a online zoom out
and for those who are here in person we also have a handout
opportunity so we can go to the parking lot and there are folding chairs that
you can take to go to the parking lot you can have tea or just
you know chat a bit as a community and and that's just about 20 30 minutes
that we can we can be together yeah okay thank you everyone
yeah