hello and welcome to happy hour everyone lovely to be with you practice together
in this moment in time whatever the time zone might be for you around this uh
special globe of ours this planet Earth
so I'd like to invite us to practice with today is [Music]
um meta kindness good will
for The Human Condition for this human condition that we are a
part of we uh to have a mind we have a body we
are a Denizen of this planet Earth and uh
and being human has so many joys and so many challenges this Human Condition on
this Earth um both internally and externally and
internally of course there are the three poisonous Roots they're called The Roots
the um greed hatred confusion and uh it's
clinging to things that don't make us happy aversion that comes up even when
we don't want it to and and confusion about not knowing not really knowing any
better not in our heads but I mean our heads we might know that oh yes Lee what
might lead to happiness but but this this from our hearts not knowing any
better so internally there are oh I think let's see unable to join soon
what's going on I think the meeting is locked hold on oh the meeting is locked how did that happen okay all right thank
you for letting me know on YouTube that the meeting was locked hmm okay here ah
yes there we go okay I'm going to ah sorry guys I uh good luck today
unintentionally here we go all right well speaking of The Human Condition sometimes you lock the zoom room without
intending to intending to and and uh yeah so our minds don't always uh work
as we intend them to so here we go to air is human the perfect example right
here causing suffering for for friends who are trying to join but we're not able to so I really appreciate you
letting me know Fred and others on on YouTube so that's why I was wondering
where is everyone tonight ah So Meta for The Human Condition I
love that example yeah meta for The Human Condition here we are making mistakes internally and also externally
so much going on in the world um so much going on in the world
so much Strife challenges and so many different places in the world So So Meta
and compassion for The Human Condition or all these humans
we are part of this Humanity so I think that's all I want to say to set
the frame for it's practicing some meta some compassion whatever arises
um yeah simple simple meta compassion
for The Human Condition ourselves included in it ourselves included in it so okay well
let's uh let's practice together let's begin
huh so Landing Landing in our bodies
Landing
here here
letting go of any tightness tension holding
being here with whatever is arising
whatever discomfort in the body
whatever is in the body softening relaxing
are releasing releasing thoughts releasing
preoccupations ruminations ruminations [Music]
we don't have to be anywhere else than right here
an opening completely embracing what is here not as wrong not as a problem not
as something we need to fix or make better
no so if you're opening the door of your
experience and completely wholeheartedly entering
your experience whatever it is
fully embracing your experience in this moment
not avoiding pushing away and by fully embracing by fully entering
it ah this experience of being human in
this moment however it's showing up for you however it's showing up
it's part of The Human Experience you are not separate
this is part of Being Human it looks like this if it's messy confusing
not clean not concentrated it's okay this is this is what it's like to be
human ah what if you didn't try to fix it
change it entered it and just relaxed
relaxed opening your arms wide hugging embracing it all
even if you don't like it love it
it passes too quickly it ends too soon this is it
this is it
what if you didn't resist hoping for a better moment a better day better
this better that completely fully embraced ah this moment of Being Human it's like
this okay hello hi
it's your heart relax does your body relax something release
is wanting this Greed for a better present
this desire to fix
it enjoy embrace even if it's a crowd of Sorrows pain in
the body part of the human condition this mystery
of being alive
let there be the ocean of the breath
with its waves in and out waves
may not be perfect conditions
they rarely ever are it's that's okay that's perfectly okay
embracing loving the imperfection that is this Human Experience
and if the mind wanders don't make it into a problem part of the human condition too for
Minds to wander it's okay no need to judge
can you have ease with this mind the Wonders
make your heart a safe place safe loving place
the patient place and the mind will wander back taking refuge in the heart
making your heart your mind your body a safe place
place of Refuge
for all the ups and downs and challenges of this Human Condition
all the beauty too all the goodness that is your life
that is manifested in this moment
foreign
all these comings and goings in this heart and mind
this manifestation of The Human Condition can we hold it with care with good will
have a sense of perspective maybe a smile
especially what's happening in this moment whatever it is
noticing if there's any resistance to what's happening right now can we loosen
the resistance just a little bit soften it
and if needed re-enter our experience completely
blessings of all these experiences in this moment the breath the body
awareness even challenging experiences there might
be showing up
oh to be human oh to be human to be alive
to experience this moment of this passing show called our life
best moment fully completely
like a comment passing through the sky
daringly brightly
burning up
in the night sky
loving it fully
we don't have to like it like every aspect of it but we can love it
by fully opening to it
this opening can feel quite radical
let it feel like a radical opening embracing
the doors of the heart so wide so wide wider than usual lean into
a wider opening more than usual that's what I'd like to invite you to
feel into
opening more wide wider to this Human Condition In This
Moment
perhaps the same way that sometimes a cold shower at first there's
resistance ah Pleasant but then when we actually
embrace it fully open to it take the cold shower feel the coolness
on our skin really embrace it it feels refreshing
we feel enlivened by the energy of life
the fullness of it even if the water is really cold
freezing really
that kind of openness opening wide
The Human Condition In This Moment
maybe even pain if there isn't in the body can feel electrifying
I'm alive this body is alive it can feel wow
or pain in the heart I'm alive I feel
this is being alive being fully embraced
fully embracing The Human Condition
no part left out
it's also empowering so empowering and shift our relationship
challenges to difficulties
see for yourself
it's full Embraces an act of love his loving what is
it's a radical meta
it's loving what is with abandon it's not perfect it's
not as I wanted to be maybe thoughts come up love it fully open your heart
I'm loving what is this Human Condition In This Moment
loving the impermanence love it all
so fragile so tender
and as you feel the body feel the heart
kicking down the barn doors opening your heart wide wide embracing fully
completely Arms Wide Open
a human condition that's arising in this heart in this Mind Body In This Moment
as best as you're able
opening the hard wide to The Human Condition in the world
I'm going to make some invitations that may not make
sense to their cognitive thinking mind but see if you can follow them with your heart as best as you're able maybe
something will open up so here we go
opening opening your heart embracing this moment whatever is
arising the body and the mind and the Heart an opening wide spaciously opening wide
embracing The Human Condition for all beings on this planet
all humans all beings all sentient beings
so much goodness so much Beauty so much strife so much pain
when your heart might feel the pain it might
be weak and yet can we open the heart to love it all
even the pain the weeping
you'll love it all to love it all fiercely
even the pain the sorrow
even as our heart Weeps open wider with love
for this tender Human Condition this tender
condition on this planet to all its beings
letting the love be so wide so all-encompassing right
it's bigger it's wider than the grief
privilege of Being Human knowing being cognizant loving loving fiercely not turning away
even if your heart feels and meets the injustices of the world
loving all the sides
the humans the beings that are hurt and those who hurt all of them
completely
the ignorance of hatred
your heart feels so open
loving this tender Human Condition this planet
ten thousand Choice ten thousand sorrows
may we all all of us all humans and our beings wake up to
love
the Love's so radical so brilliant
that that it is enlivening all-encompassing
and it's who we really are may we all wake up to who we really are
and love completely
thank you all thank you for your practice
we have some time for reflections questions
or reports from the field especially if you haven't spoken recently I invite you first you can type in chat
you can raise your Zoom hand what did you discover what what was this like for
you offering your
insights to serve to support others your questions too
Gina says was hard to really welcome the pain but I kept trying yeah
yeah sometimes what it helps is to relax
is to relax because if we tightened and try to welcome pain as if trying is a
fist trying so hard sometimes it helps to just relax and welcome welcome that
way and I appreciate Gina that you stayed
it's there's it can transform back as I was leading the practice tonight I have
a lot of pain in my body and just opening up to it opening up to it and
the relationship gets quite transformed to challenges pain difficulty
this amazing Human Condition pain included
red please
I'm wondering how to open up to fatigue without just falling down the hole and
falling asleep or being just um completely scattered in the fatigue
thought process yeah yeah yeah good question so
so there's a difference between opening up to it and falling into it so
so let me uh try to to describe what I mean
so so when I just when I talk about opening up to it it's more of a spacious
perspective so there's fatigue ah there's fatigue in the mind there's
heaviness there's dullness in the mind and the body like ah can I
or put it open up and and be be bigger than it instead of being reduced to it
because falling into it is kind of being reduced to it like oh so heavy so heavy
it's like uh whereas not being reduced to it there's a sense of opening to it
it's like holding it there's much more here there's much more here there yeah
the fatigues there but there's a lot else happening too does that pointer help Fred what I mean yeah I I think I
understand I'll try okay yeah it's hard but I'll give it a try thank you yeah
yeah you're welcome and and one other thing that can also help is to to help let your breath be supportive a few
deeper breaths to make space because the breath can get a little tight and tinny
sometimes in fatigue and falling into it whereas let the breath be more spacious because if you're not opening space a
little bit great thank you thank you
one of you sent a reflection privately Randy Newman describes this in a song
titled it's the rest of your life so live it well yes that was one of the aspects I
was bringing in into this practice one aspect of it there was a lot more in the
practice but yeah that was definitely one aspect of it
thank you another reflection thank you for this meditation yes there can be openness
until I come into the picture yeah yeah that's right
that's right there can be a lot of weapons and it's okay the self it's fine
to bring the self into the picture actually I want to say that not to deny
your Humanity your particularities and I think that's really important I want to
make that distinction so the idea here is not to deny
that we have a personhood in fact this practice really works to open up to our
particularities we are human beings we have sufferings of course of course we
do and it's okay for the self to bring please bring the self into the picture bring the eye into the picture with this
practice so that it can be loved um this expression you need to love the
self before you let go of the self so really fully loving it
Jerry says the precious the precious of the life left for all
the preciousness of the life left for all of us was emphasized yes
yes indeed indeed
so if any other reflections and if not let's turn
I'm gonna make the practice rooms but if there are any other Reflections feel free to raise your hand
have time and um
yeah and and you know what tell you what let's let's make some time for when we come back from the room so I'll ask you
what your relationship was when you opened up to to loving the whole
whole of humanity with all maybe I'll ask you now if anybody has a reflection about that with all of its Joys and
sorrows and the heartbreaks anything arose for you
you like to share maybe what I'll share is with this
practice again it may or may not work or maybe might just work for one Split Second something might open up there's
this tenderness of loving it all loving both the
in all sides of conflicts EV everyone that it's it's a sense of loving and
grieving at the same time that can be so precious with this complete opening up
to humanity loving and grieving but love feels bigger can hold the grief it can hold
the so I see two hands so so now it's Jerry
and Mary and then we'll we'll go into the groups quickly Jerry thanks and thanks for correcting my grammar when
I'm just typing it it feeds in what I felt was actually
um uh following up on what you just said was this enormity of what's left uh uh
how precious it is for every one of us and who knows what's coming and so there was a sort of excitement uh about both
in both ends about wow who knows it's just this is just today uh so enough
thank you and today this this is exciting this is enough exactly this is
lovely thank you Jerry and Mary please
I would say just I thank you and um I've been dealing with a lot of grief
and a lot of physical pain and all this stuff and it is such a relief to be
reminded it's part of the human condition that for me is an Incredible
Gift to just know it's not my suffering all by myself it's part of the human condition and and
to be present to that in to myself but with others which is what is being
required right now for me so thank you so much beautiful thank you so much for sharing that Mary so appreciate your
reflection beautiful yeah to be reminded of that so helpful
yeah yeah so dear ones let's turn to hold each other
in small groups roughly size of three and an invitation what is it like when
you open your heart to the to fully love Embrace this human condition for the
particularities here and and ever for everyone
um what arises you can offer one nugget or you can also offer just space say
pass or offer your silence your holy presence and the next person then the
next person they'll come back to you and let's Go reverse alphabetical order according to your first name be kind be
kind just share from your own experience um not coordinating organizing directing
other people's shares but just offering just offering your own Humanity your
common Humanity letting others share their common Humanity make space for each other okay here we go
we have just about a minute if there are any Reflections that have come up from your
conversation together especially if you haven't shared tonight or recently like to make space
any questions comments oh
oh I see one of you got got kicked out of a group and I didn't see it early
enough to put you back in but usually you can go back in yourself if this happens again you're able to I uh
there's nothing on my end that I can do if you get kicked out
um so you can put yourself back anyway I'm sorry you gotta kick it out
anyway any any other Reflections besides that which I didn't see earlier
oh well it's time okay as as um Car Talk
those of you who are familiar with Carta Click and Clack the top and brother is not NPR you have wasted a perfectly good
hour cultivating compassion and love and kindness just kidding anyway thank you
all thank you for your practice thank you for being here and cultivating your heart for the benefit of yourself and
all beings in this short brief flash of lightening of Our
Lives May all being be all beings be well may all beings be happy
[Music] thanks everyone
[Music]