so hello again
for some of us it's a morning for some
events it's evening
wherever we are in the world welcome
uh wonderful to be together
so continuing this discussion of
the five presets
keeping us safely on the path
our third day
and
so this morning I would like to I would
like to talk about the third lay precept
for the sake of our training together I
undertake the precept to abstain from
sexual misconduct
and to discuss that in in terms of a a
teaching that I often hear at IMC about
ethical sensitivity
foreign
maybe for 1500 years or more
it's been very common very traditional
and
the teravatan Buddhist tradition and
other Buddhist Traditions to organize
the teachings into three trainings
and ordering them
as if first we develop Sila ethics
virtue precepts restraint
and then samadhi a second training
the training of the mind and heart and
collectiveness and concentration
and the third training of panya wisdom
discernment
very common to hear them hear them
developed in this order and what's
interesting is we as we watch the
development of
the Buddha Dharma
in the United States certainly
many many many practitioners first
encounter
meditation
the first encounter the practices of
samadhi and maybe
of wisdom and discernment before
um
finding their way into Sila and one of
the ways this often happens by seed
is that through our mindfulness practice
to become more and more attuned to
what's happening right here what's
happening right here in the body
what's happening in terms of
emotion that's happening in terms of
thinking and all the more attentive to
our action and how we're influenced by
all of these
becoming more attuned to this it's quite
a natural movement very often to start
to develop what we're calling ethical
sensitivity
so in terms of the third precept
to abstain from sexual misconduct
the it's noteworthy that the Buddha did
a lot of his teaching to monastics
and that the monastic rules very clearly
State about their practice
from an Aztecs was celibacy it took this
very seriously
part of what this means for us probably
most all of us as lay practitioners is
that we have to
we have the task
if we want to live according to a
Buddhist interpretation of wise
sexuality or to abstain from sexual
misconduct it takes some interpretation
on our part
how to apply this in our lives
foreign
my inclination is is to
um
is to explore or to begin looking at a
wise sexuality through
um
through the principles we've been
looking at so far in the precepts
if you think back foot to the first day
and we have this teaching of the Buddha
teaching venerable rahula to discern or
reflect before during and after an
action
is this actually going to do harm is it
not going to do harm
is this action skillful
is it not skillful
and to apply those understandings apply
those principles to this very very
multifaceted sometimes quite complicated
world
of our romantic life our sexual life
with the understanding that
um
mindfulness practice is fit for every
area of Our Lives
and
maybe to State it most Softly
it sure can't hurt
to bring our mindfulness
into into this into this realm of our
life
sexuality
so I think it goes without saying many
of us are aware of all the many ways
that we get caught
in our sexuality and caught up caused
suffering for ourselves cause suffering
and stress for others
so I think we do well to examine am I
harming am I not am I skillful am I not
of the one of the close
principles to examine when we're looking
at our own sexuality
I think many of us can relate to is uh
the difference or the distinction the
discernment between
short-term pleasure
and our long-term happiness
part of what's so fascinating about the
influence of sexuality is the way that
it can stir up
[Music]
the the roots of uh delusion or kind of
blindness
or the passions can get can get so
activated
as to influence us to operate out of
greed or operate out of even ill will
so we see how sexuality can be very
closely tied to these three
delusion
greed ill will
and these in turn can grow into other
unwholesome conduct
harmful conduct
it may sound a little
a little I don't know how you'll receive
this idea
um
but I
oh here we'll do it this way
can imagine imagine yourself
floating along in a river
in a river stream
floating along on your back just flowing
along
comfortable temperature of the water
carried along
and so long as you're floating
you don't notice
just how strong the flow of the river is
how strong the pull of the tide is
and then you decide as you're floating
there oh I'm gonna I'm gonna stand up
I'm gonna put my feet on the riverbed
and so you do you put your feet on the
riverbed and you decide oh I'm going to
be I'm going to stand still
here in the middle of the Stream
and when you plant your feet
only then do you see feel sense to the
utter power
of this River the outer power of this
stream the pushing the pushing of the
water and how much force it takes
to not be
um push Downstream
I think this can very closely be related
to the influence of sexuality on our
lives
or the the pulled toward how sexuality
can influence us
it's just amazing
that as uh as we float along in the
currents of say
um sexual impulse
or sexual behavior or romantic life if
we do it in an unreflective way
we can just be swept along
totally swept along
and not notice how powerful its
influence is
but if we if we take up a practice we
may plant our feet and finally see wow
look at look at all this look at all
this force and influence in power
that these impulses have on my heart and
my mind my activity
and one of the ways that we do this or
one of the traditional ways we do this
you might see it on retreat
say for a seven day retreat
we take up a practice for that set
period
to observe deliberate refraining from
any sexual expression at all
let me take a take a
we take up the practice for those seven
days
to take up celibacy
and to not ex not express
and sexuality it's not an evaluation of
sexual impulse or sexual behavior as
wrong or bad or somehow misguided
I think we can see in a Time such as
that
when you've made a decision a strong
resolve okay I won't be
taken away Swept Away
by sexuality for these seven days then
you can really see the currents then you
can really feel the pull on your life
and see it all the more clearly
and then as we see through mindfulness
practice
as we see more clearly
we have more opportunity to
decide to live in a wholesome
skillful
non-harming way
for our long-term benefit
for the long-term benefit of others for
the long-term benefit of the whole world
I think those are my Reflections on this
third precept
for the morning my sense now is why
don't we continue with our practice and
recite the five presets
uh and then we can even see what
Reflections or questions are coming up
in the in the YouTube chat so let me
share this and then we can chant
together
there we go
foreign
follow after me
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
harming living beings
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
taking what is not given
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
sexual misconduct
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
false speech
for the sake of our training together
I undertake the precept to abstain from
intoxicants that are a cause for
heathlessness
so they are reflections May our practice
consideration
of these precepts and considerations of
how we can live wisely with our whole
life
May that nourish us
support us support our Sangha
support the community
may all beings benefit
please take good care
until tomorrow