so good evening everyone and welcome to imc those of you here and
those of you online welcome and
i hope it was nice for you to sit for the 45 minutes in quiet
that's how we used to do it here on monday nights for years for 30 over 30 years but then with
pandemic when you started doing online we started doing the guided meditations
and when i sat down to meditate i thought it was so nice and quiet in here they wouldn't disturb it with
words so um
i don't feel like i have a lot to say today but what i have to say i think is
important so we'll see where it goes maybe we'll have some discussion
and that is um let's start with uh there's a very famous story
or in a story exactly but a teaching from the time monk meditation teacher
named ajahn chah teacher of many people here in the west and he said something like
if you get let go a little you'll have a little peace if you let go of middling you'll have a
middling peace and if you let go a lot you'll have a lot of peace
and so the emphasis is on letting go and many people that do associate buddhism in buddhist practice with
letting go and there's a lot of wonderful words associated with associated words like
there's relinquishment some people sometimes talk about renunciation
and uh the um what's interesting if you look at the
teachings of the buddha about relinquishment or letting go
it generally not about relinquishing anything
but rather it's relinquishing the grip the holding
so it's re-releasing the clinging we're not necessarily releasing or letting go of the things of
our life now so some of us might be doing things which are unhealthy
and uh it's good to let go of things which are unhealthy unethical and wise
but for the buddha they i think he was just so assuming people were doing this practice or living an ethical
life and so their focus was letting just letting go of the clinging the grasping
and and so i'm about to say next is one of the reasons i wanted this the thing i almost wanted to emphasize
um it's possible to hold on to something tight
hold on to it so this if you hold on tight it might be useful in the wind to hold on to your umbrella tight
but but if you do it all the time even when it's not windy
and you have really attached that umbrella eventually your hands might get all knotted up or
start cramping up or you know you can't do a lot of other things with your hand
so it's nice to not be attached to umbrellas and put them down when it's not raining and leave them at home
and so we learn to let go or release though we're not holding on so much anymore
but there's uh in english we can say that
if you hold once you're not holding on anymore it doesn't mean that you've dropped
something no longer have it it can mean you still can hold it
without holding on you can have your open open hand open
and you can hold something freely and openly in the hand and that's a world of difference
you don't have to let go of something give it up but can you hold it lightly
loosely not you know just just holding it burying it
this way with an open hand so if you were holding on to a little bird
it would probably fly away that's what birds do but
if i'm holding on to the striker you know it's not going to fly away
but maybe you have one of you has a really good use for this and asks me for it
it's really easy then it's almost like this is holding it this way is almost like an offering here
take it holding it like this it's almost like a fist
that makes a very different impression so what i'm proposing is that
we can learn to let go of the grip and then hold the things in our life the
people in our life loosely lightly
without any restrictions on anything about holding tight to anything
and then things will take their course things will unfold it's a bird it'll fly
away if someone wants a striker maybe you're ready to give it
if something needs to be comforted well it's nice and warm and soft in the palm of the hand so you're
there and but we're not limiting anything we're not saying you can't go away
and we're not saying you have to stay here but we are welcome to stay here
i'm available here so what are what what ways do we
hold on rather than simply hold one of the ways we hold on is we
identify with it this is mine this is mine so it's my striker so you
can't have it it's my whatever so you have to protect it
maybe it's appropriate sometimes to protect your umbrella if it's raining on you but not in someone else
you know it's a very narrow little rainstorm when i was in hawaii they had very local rainstorms
but but what about living a life that somehow holds everything lightly
holds everything without restriction holds everything without
keeping it trapped in the fist of our clinging or grasping or holding on
is that is it appropriate what happens if we go around with an open hand always
pick things up we hold an open hand we're offered something and we hold it
with an open hand someone wants it do we offer it many years ago i was uh
spending time with a monk named ajahn amaro englishman who was an abbot of a theravada monastery here in northern
california this must have been the very early 2000s i don't know exactly when it was but
he had a cell phone that was uh maybe a smartphone before
there were smartphones you know before i really had that name he had this it did all this stuff i think he
could do email or something but he did all this stuff that he was amazing what he could do
and so uh and it cost something like a thousand dollars
and so i said to him uh what are you a monk doing with this
big expensive fancy phone aren't you supposed to be a renunciant
and he said oh someone gave it to me and i figured it was okay to have it
if if anybody who asked me for it i would give it to them
so i thought about it not so much that i wanted the phone but
i wanted to test him i want to find it this this for real but i i didn't
and um but this you know he was holding it i think he i think he was pretty probably genuine
he was holding it this way he was holding it loosely and
what about someone you're in conflict with what if you're someone's angry with you you're angry
with them so then the gesture might be you know like this stay away go
but what about if that if you go like that also with the person who you're angry with
don't push them away but like here what what what
what does that mean to hold someone who's angry with you or you're in conflict with this way
if you hold them this way hold on to something then it's not very friendly but with the open hand
the gesture of fearlessness in buddhism it should be that people have nothing to fear from you
is to hold your hands up like this flat no weapon just a flat and open
so this idea the open hand open mind open heart
so it doesn't mean that we have to give everything up
unless maybe they ask you for it maybe who knows what you want to do it doesn't but it doesn't mean you have to
give things up but you have to but in in the dharma what we're learning to do is something
different we're learning to not hold on hold but don't hold on if it's
appropriate to hold hold it but don't hold on because holding on prevents the natural
flow of things that happen things come things go this is the master in san francisco who
started the san francisco center shinrio suzuki roshi
he said renunciation
um is allowing things to go when it's their time
when things go when things have time to go then then we let go so it's like he was quite happy to hold
but when it was time to go then the renunciation was letting it go
i think parents have to learn that at some age sometimes the kids are ready to leave
before the parents are ready for them to leave alco in all kinds of stages okay you
have to go you have to go remember when my son was i don't know he was maybe five
and he came out of the bathroom
dressed like a 1970s disco king
i couldn't believe what i saw i mean where do you find those clothes and where did he he figured out how to
slick his hair and it was like he had some kind of gold necklace i don't know you know what in
our house what did he find and i looked at him
and uh and i thought okay i mean this was like represented
something which i don't stand for it just was so different than anything that i could you know appreciate really whatever it
was and i looked at it and said well this is what he's done
who am i to say that he shouldn't do that just because i don't have a good association with that
it's not my place to tell him that he can't dress up this way and to figure it out so
so i have to i have to keep my hand open and he's going
who knows what direction he's going to go in his life but you know he he gave it at five he's
making choices and you know it's not my place to shape him in every possible way parents
have a role of course but but you know there was a it was a moment of like oh okay
i have to i have to let him go in certain ways
so um so this uh freedom of the open hand
and but is that a freedom that you're comfortable with do you feel safe or do you feel like you
lose too much or you feel safer and more comfortable holding on
gripping no not that it's finding fine for guilt to say that but he doesn't understand
you understand what life is about the challenges and i have to keep my things so i'm safe and
it goes on in all the justification but is it really
what are we trusting what are we not trusting we're not being asked to let go of
anything we're asked just to hold it with an open heart open mind open hand
and care for it i love this gesture i mean if i think when you put two hands together
like this and hold things then it's really supportive then it's just that love i love this as a metaphor
for mindfulness we take our attention and come from underneath our sadness or anger or fear and just hold
it like this but again it's open so it can go if it wants i'm not holding
on to it not resisting it so just hold everything
and maybe if it's time to for it to go maybe it's
okay maybe it's okay because the biggest gift we have the biggest treasure we have
is the open hand is the open heart is that freedom
to lose that by clenching from a buddha's point of view is
impoverishment even if i think that it's so important to keep the striker
the fact that i'm gripping it is a kind of poverty
if i hold it like this it's a kind of a wealth
a huddle like that and it goes away i still have the wealth
the freedom
so holding but not holding on
i think it's a very respectful way to live for life it's kind of like the middle way
the middle way between clinging and throwing things away clinging and
letting go of things
the middle way between accumulating and getting rid of things
just hold it like this and things come and go people come and go things come and go
all kinds of things come and go in that openness and maybe
it's a phenomenal form of respect
reverence care generosity to hold other people
in that in that open hand to hold on to other people maybe is not
respecting them to discard people is disrespectful but
that middle way hold but don't hold on
hold but don't discard
so that's the the thing that i wanted to say today
what do you think of that do you have any comments about that testimonials
protests questions
hi it's nancy um
i have some possessions but i have some possessions yes
that are very dear and nostalgic for me and i realized that
when i pass away my nieces and nephews have no interest in them whatsoever
even though they're family heirlooms and so um i've been thinking about it lately
about what do i do about these treasured things that are so dear to me
and how do i let those go when they're really going nowhere
i don't have an answer to that but what occurs to me is that in that open hand
you might figure out how to let go how to give it how to do something
but they represent something for you and so what they represent
is different than what the object is and maybe if there's something that's
something some way with the open hand to preserve protect stay close to
what what they represent in your heart that
will actually better allow
these memories or whatever it is to live in you than the object
maybe it's easier than to figure out a good home for the objects
and so maybe doing a ritual that maybe transfers
the memories or the associations from the objects to your heart
what does that sound like sounds good
how do we adapt to this way of thinking to our day-to-day life like i think the
the idea is great but i think just living life it's kind of hard to understand when you are grasping to the
object or idea thought whatever etc versus just keeping it open as you've mentioned
i don't know just like this because it occurs as an example happened recently to me
that in the last months where i went to a restaurant and there was something strange about how the credit card payment worked
and i didn't get any receipt so i wondered about that what's that
about am i in trouble am i going to be charged a whole bunch you know
and i wondered about it and so i did check my eventually my checking my credit card account online
but um but i i didn't want to i did it didn't seem i didn't seem
necessary i didn't want to do the usual things i would have done years ago which got me get anxious
somebody can take advantage of me i was like okay well let's see what happens and
what happens if they charge me twice as much than they're supposed to
do do i need to get worried or upset or feel injustice of that and
what should be my role so i didn't have answers those questions but those questions existed with me feeling like
this very relaxed about it is that appropriate or should i have gotten anxious should i rush back and
said hey something's wrong here i didn't get a receipt then i don't you know what's going on i also didn't
sign that little slip here goes aside when you do credit cards like what's this is unusual what's going to happen now
so um so i don't know if that answers your
question but that's what occurred to me i think it's a very different way of living
maybe it's a in one point in my life i would have referred to it as living a life of trust
but now i don't think of it as trust anymore i just think of it as freedom
do you have any suggestions for if you feel like you're the one being grasped like the person being grasped if you're
the person being grasped yes oh by maybe your family or your friends and
they sort of hurt you sometimes what do you do then yeah
ideally in my in my world ideally for me at least is that
you would uh have friends or that you can talk honestly with and if you can't have an honest
conversation maybe it's that's to reevaluate the friendship and an honest conversation what would be
maybe look like this you know i've noticed for some time now that you know you're really attached to
me or grasping onto me holding on and we have a friendship and i value you
and i can imagine you have a need for companionship or need for something
but it's also hard for me i feel limited and boxed in i wonder if we can have a conversation
about this and find a way together to works for both of us so some kind of conversation like that
um and that would be my inclination because i i put a tremendous
value on honest communication how does that sound that sounds good that sounds helpful
yeah good it's hard not everyone wants to have that kind of honesty and communications
it's difficult for people so for people who it's a foreign idea to have such open frank conversations you
have to kind of come come at it a little bit slowly and carefully and work into it rather than like let's sit
down and be honest but uh and and to be able to learn the skill of these kinds of conversations is
one of the great things that was this was my introduction to the spiritual life
was it was witnessing these kinds of conversations with people i lived when i was 2021 at the largest
uh hippie commune united states it was about 800 people
and then tennessee they called the farm and it was but it was a spiritual commune of sorts
but there's uh they had they had gotten their start in spirituality through lsd
but when they moved to tennessee lsd didn't work so you know taking lsd didn't work so much there
so they had to figure out something different something as powerful as lsd and the powerful thing they discovered
was honesty so when i went there and stayed for a while i stayed there because i saw the
amazing honesty between people who were there and how they worked all kinds of things
out and it was so inspiring to me and because it was kind of a spiritual community that was i got a sense of oh
spiritual life could be this way and that inspired me
yeah yeah i think that's really helpful i i've always believed in the honest communication i think i need to
slow my delivery
great thank you thank you
your first examples of the beautiful imagery of an open hand were very clear
to me i believe the very first one you gave was an open hand with the
striker and that seemed very comfortable because that's a neutral object to me
i may have one i may have two i can get another one easily so certainly i can
do this and it it may leave my hand and similarly with the bird
it wasn't neutral but it was the nature of the object that i had so i
it was the right thing to do to open and let it go but if something is so
personal not even high value perhaps like nancy if i may refer to that that this
is such a treasure an actual object of treasure but
something so emotional like the anger you would feel with someone
and the thought of opening up and expecting that to just leave
certainly no one's going to take it from me it's not very valuable to anyone else
but why is that feeling so different than the bird or the striker
do you have any ideas because it's a very personal question so i see if you have any for yourself
it's just the intensity of the creation that it is
from me but it seems to have high value and it may be anger on one day but it may also
be something about my my my self image or my
something that again it just seems to be a if it's such so much about me
yeah yeah so i mean so there's a wonderful saying in buddhism i've learned from buddhism that if um
if there's a gap between the ideal and the actual a gap between what's what
we ideal about to be and what's actually going on study the actual
so you've heard this teaching today this ideas today and now you're asking about how did you have this intensity it's so
important for you and so valuable study why it's valuable maybe that means that you haven't you
haven't really studied you haven't really looked at yourself what's really going on why is it valuable what are you trying to do what are you afraid of
and um and then and then so that's where you find the answers to yourself rather than um you know that's that's
that's where the answers come by so if the ideal is to be like this
you can't do it in some areas of your life that's okay but that becomes where your
practice goes then you discover something i can't tell you what you'll discover
but something useful that's lovely thank you
i thought at the beginning when you were speaking that you're going to maybe ask something else and that is
what if what i have is really valuable and someone asks for it
what do i do then i take that like this this spell in the striker we've had it here for now almost
20 years i remember very fondly the person who gave it to us was a gift and
we came to satire and was sat in this room for years and all that and so so for me i have this wonderful
association it's important the connection to that person and all the years we've been here it has value
so if you came and said you know i think i'd like that striker i'd say oh
well let me tell you a little bit before i give it to you you know this is this is not any old
striker this is actually has a lot of value because of the memories associations and
kind of the background here and so i don't know i mean i'm happy to give
it to you happy enough but
what if i go buy you another buy you a striker a different one would that be okay
or i would just say i explained to you that yes but this is what it means for me and then you'd say oh and i didn't know that
okay well then i don't want it or many years ago i had a zen teacher
he um we were facing each other i asked him
for a time to meet with him to talk about practice or something and um
and his reply his res back then people had date books and so um so his response to me facing
him saying you know do you have time to meet with me was he came around shoulder to shoulder next to me
and brought out his date book and put his date book between us so he could see his schedule
and and it was like he wasn't going to tell me i can't meet you in the next week you have to wait
you know he said let's look at this together and then oh it's obvious he can't meet
with me right now and it wasn't me versus him it wasn't oppositional why doesn't he care for me
just why is he putting me off two weeks it was like oh it was it was done cooperatively
and this idea of of doing things cooperatively uh you know letting people know what's
happening for you this is striker is valuable you still want it
do you still want it something so so that i thought that's where that was the answer i was getting
very getting ready to tell you you know you went you went someplace
else i'll try to be more careful no no no it's great no no you don't have to it
was great what you said i've guessed
gil i'm wondering if you can talk about letting go of one's self-identification
with one's work or whatever one's doing moving from a place of
like you said identifying the task um to
a place of um aspiration so is this an identity that you um
keep like this 24 hours a day seven days a week or is it what does it kind of wane and wax
through the week probably wayne and wax
so what is it like when it's it what is what are you like when it's most not there
hmm
open to more possibilities a little more relaxed so rather than you
could you could study the identification but uh but
another thing you can study is study when it's least there and see what they're what you have to
learn from that and that might be enough yeah think you have to change it and
shift it yeah thank you i'll try
um so it's a horizontal
you're like yeah okay um i want to say just uh
it's a little off topic but i haven't been here for a couple years since kovit and i
really appreciate being here in this space and
i've um i'm usually the one that doesn't speak so i think for me i've been uh holding
on to my it's interesting holding on to my fear holding my fear of not speaking and um
it feels good to say what i said oh fantastic and just and to describe your fear that's
here and do it and you're so i hear that you're holding your fear but not being
held by your fear to speak to speak this way yeah that feels accurate you're practicing what
i'm talking about already that was that was beautiful thank you
very much come practice more often i will yes
okay so thank you for being here this evening this was very nice and
i still find it very lovely to be with people and still even though the you know the
serious part of the pandemic of really being isolated is kind of over i'm still not actually spending a lot of
time with people directly like the way i used to and so anything like this i value and i think it's it's
wonderful to be together with people practicing together so i appreciate it and thank you for
being part of this and i hope to see you again i'll i don't think i think i'm scheduled to come
mondays maybe about once a month and diana probably
two to three times a month or something and other people will come through as well but uh lovely to be here
thank you you