okay so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to see you
wonderful to be with you always happy making just going around and saying hellos and
reading all the places uh in the country and the world that you're joining from where we're all
joining each other it just makes me happy just brings joy it's happy making for me so many people dedicating this
this time whether it's friday afternoon for a friday evening
early evening late evening middle of the afternoon in the middle of the day in
in saturday as the case is for mary christine uh joining us so uh that we come
together and practice together it just makes my heart happy and also folks are joining us from
youtube's to to to acknowledge them hi hello says nick
hi nick so all right so for the theme for tonight
what i would like to um share is um
is inspired by something that i read
from john keats the poet who [Music]
who lived who actually um just a little bit about john keats which
i didn't know he died from tuberculosis when he was 25 years old
and it was actually he also lived through a time
a time of pandemic there were many people in his family who were ill who died before him he
went through a lot of suffering and uh
and this is a from a letter this quote that i found it's from a letter
that he wrote to his brother just so beautiful so beautiful
so he says call the world if you please
the veil of soul making then you will find out the use of the
world i am speaking now in the highest terms for human nature
admitting it to be mortal which i will take here for granted of course he's talking from a particular uh perspective
from the christian perspective but let me um i say soul making soul is
distinguished from intelligence there may be intelligences or sparks of the
divinity in millions but they are not souls t till they acquire
um uh personality itself and then he ends
do you not see how necessary a world of pains and troubles
is to school and intelligence and make it a soul a place where the heart must feel and
suffer in a thousand diverse ways i read again the highlights the parts i
want to highlight do you not see how necessary a world of pains and
troubles is to school and intelligence and make it a soul so here
maybe in the words uh he's talking about intelligence so knowing awareness and that that all the pains
all the sorrows of the world are necessary in order to take this knowing to take this intelligence as a
human being to make us into a heart so maybe instead of the word soul i use the heart how to make a
mind and make it into a heart that that the suffering of the world is needed for
us to feel compassion for ourselves for the others
and he ends by saying a place where the heart must feel and suffer in a thousand diverse ways
so call the world if you please the veil of soul making or maybe i would
say the veil of compassion the veil of heart-making
so there are different ways different
teachings of course this is a teaching in buddhism that that com that
compassion arises suffering isn't just in vain
and and of course well here's another teaching and buddhism that comes to mind
that there are two types of suffering in buddhism there is suffering that leads to more
suffering and there is suffering that leads to the end of suffering
so the type of suffering that leads to more suffering is just ah why me this is
terrible why is it happening to them this is awful just more suffering just suffering wallowing and suffering
wallowing in pain wallowing in pain that's the type of suffering that leads to
more suffering and of course we all know that type right when the mind just takes
off and we're wallowing in it and then there is suffering
the second type of suffering is one that leads to the end of suffering and that is the profound
teaching there is so in that way it depends how we approach suffering
how we see suffering if we wallow if if
we get lost in it they're just piling piling on we're
suffering whereas if we open our hearts open our hearts to
compassion we cultivate compassion as keats call the world
in this world the veil of soul making he says i call it compassion
making making us into real human beings who feel who love who are compassionate
um fully inhabiting our humanity
and a compassionate heart has freedom there is freedom and compassion
there is strength and compassion there is beauty and compassion there is peace there is bliss in compassion
so the suffering as we work with it with compassion they
can open our heart for compassion towards ourselves and others and also there are wisdom practices when
we see when we see the unsatisfactoriness the suffering then can lead
to seeing the three characteristics which i have mentioned before impermanence unsatisfactoriness and not
self and again it's the end of suffering in the way that we're not impacted by it of course the
suffering still happens for us and others in the world challenges but there
is instead of saying we're not impacted by it maybe i should say um we don't wallow in it that's what i need to say
of course we're impacted because our heart opens up to compassion
when there is suffering of course our perspective changes
so that when suffering arises for ourselves or for others in the world
the automatic response is compassion is care and there's a stability there is a
beauty there's a goodness in compassion and
in the bigger perspective of equanimity holding it all holding it all spaciously
very very spaciously very spacious comings and goings again
we are impacted and yet we don't
wallow we don't wallow in it our perspective doesn't become limited to
just the suffering we don't just identify with the suffering for ourselves and
others okay that was a longer darmet than i intended to give but
that's the framing for tonight dear friends let's practice together
let's land let's land in our seat
ah if you need to shift and move so that you're comfortable
[Music] it's the perfect time
sitting or lying down or standing [Music]
and arriving arriving in this body
arriving in this moment in time
and for this moment releasing
out of care out of love releasing entanglements
just to stabilize just to cultivate stability
to arrive feeling each breath
in the lower abdomen [Music] let it be breathed on its own
feeling the bottom of your feet on this earth
earth on earth
the solidity the contact points
as if you're breathing through your feet as if the breath was being breathed from
mother earth into this body each breath nourishing
moving up from the feet through the legs
through the sit bones through the belly up through the torso
touching the belly of the chest
arms head
not in an effortful way let it let it happen on its own
connected to mother earth
energized and breathed by mothers
each breath soothing comforting settling your body
deeply settling unsettling your heart
each breath each breath nourishing settling being breathed through the feet
up through the legs ah
through the torso expanding through the body calming nourishing healing
stabilizing settling the heart and mind
bringing a sense of stability with each breath
both and stability
relaxed alert
tender the heart stable and grounded
now let us imagine [Music] if you will
the paragon the perfection of compassion this being
if you're not familiar with kuan yin you can imagine the buddha
either kuan yin or the buddha
whichever whomever with you have a relationship
imagine them
gazing upon you holding you as you sit in their presence
in your mind's eye they hold you with their gaze with a
compassionate gaze knowing your life knowing your history
knowing your sorrows sufferings
knowing your joys your goodness
the goodness within they see that more than even more than you see in yourself
they see all of you and so much
more than you can see yourself let yourself be seen
with eyes of compassion letting your body relax
continuing to be breathed through the earth being embodied
and maybe this is not visual maybe it's a feeling that you're being
held the energy of compassion by them
or maybe it's more felt sense you're sitting on their lap
being held maybe like a newborn
appreciating how their compassion
is stable it's powerful
it's a soothing balm they love
care hold all that you are
the ten thousand joys the ten thousand sorrows
expansively without being toppled into
your suffering they care and yet there's a stability
and now imagine that they so gently and lovingly set you down
[Music] and say to you let me show you how it's done
they invite you to see the world through their eyes
as if the buddha or the queen yen [Music]
you invite them to enter your heart enter your mind shining out
so it's your body but they're gazing out they're feeling
so you feel the sense of stability
looking through their eyes their gaze this unbounded compassion
for yourself and for the world
hearing the cries the cries of sorrow yourselves and
others included
others who are suffering and war zones
and you hear the joys also
being breathed through mother earth through your feet
the hard expenses looking through the eyes of ultimate
compassion
allowing yourself to be impacted of course impacted you feel
you feel of course
there is love there is caring and yet not toppled over
and holding the sorrows the suffering of the world
opens your heart more to compassion to the goodness of compassion
not empathic distress which is agony
but compassion which is soothing healing wishing well
for others for yourself there's care warmth
heart quivers with
feels with your heart feels with the sorrow the
suffering in the stability
the world is the veil of compassion-making
if at any point it feels as feels overwhelming as the badan kuan yin
is teaching you gently gently
let yourself be held in their compassion you don't have to push yourself
let yourself be held in the compassion in care and love
a gentle cultivation and training
and if there's any judgment arising i can't do this
this is hard my mind is wondering etc
it's okay it's okay you're doing your best let it
all be held expansively with compassion with care
you're doing your best let the judgment be held
with compassion and care and love with non-judgment
and as we come to the end of this practice period
allowing your inner quantity your inner buddha
to hold you and however this practice period was
what it was what it wasn't let it be held with care with compassion with appreciation
letting go of any judgment you've done your best
offering your goodness our goodness collectively to all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere
be safe have ease
may all beings everywhere including ourselves be free
[Music]
[Music] thanks everyone thank you for your
practice
so we have a few minutes any reflections
questions you can type them in chat if you wish if you type them
to me privately i won't read your name just the reflection you can also type them
[Music] publicly or raise your hand any questions comments
complaints everything is welcome
any aha moments anything that you discovered
did anyone discover realize that you had more stability than you realized
with kuan yin or neil i see your hand yeah but you just said what i was gonna
say you ruined it um i take it back neil you say it now
yeah so first of all that was a lovely practice right and it was you know you started and i'm like you
know why are we doing this earth thing you know i'm like whatever right you know i had nothing better to do so i
went with it you know and then you know funny neil i just want to say you're you're that constrained forward it's
classical i'll be playing here all week um you know and then you know and then you
know we started talking about difficult things you know and you know i found myself sort of flipping back and forth
in my head you know right when things got difficult you know i would like you know for a
breath or two i would like feel the ground inside of me you know and it was you know it was just
it was just you know it was a very strong stance if you will it was very nice
beautiful thank you neil strong stance lovely thank you i'm delighted yes
there is method to the madness aurora please
um i don't know if i'll be able to articulate this but i come from a
family of people who are always trying to save you know saviors right like and um
and i i feel like i could feel in this meditation like like embodying kuan yin or having kuan
yin embody me that like just how different it is to
be with versus to like jump in
you know and um and i think i understand that conceptually
but it was nice to feel it like in a bodily way it's a lot if there's like a coolness to
it that i was really appreciating
um and i feel like i could i could use more of this like
i don't know if you have recommendations for like my dear it's available to you it's your
inner kwan yin your inner buddha is always available to you call them up and they show up and they embody you
any moment yeah there's something about like that and that embodiment that yeah you know
because when i do a meta practice i i can sometimes just get like caught in
the yeah yeah closeness of things you know right so this is this is a method right this is a
method this is and and as you ask okay how do i do this this is available to you anytime right this this
could be your practice this could be ah oh yes
there is an image of quantian oh beautiful what a gorgeous image thanks for sharing that on my desk oh my god
that is so perfect that is silver maybe at the very end when we before we close
maybe we'll spotlight you and you can put hold it up after we yeah yeah that's awesome thank you that'd be
lovely uh yeah so just to say yeah this is another way of practice so it's available if it's clicked for you
use it any time in white coin yen let let her enter you you and you know
just this is it's all skillful means if this worked yes
great skillful means beautiful thank you thank you it's beautiful susan
please yeah um thank you for that practice um
i guess i've been influenced mostly by the chinese version of kuan yin and um
you know she's sitting cross-legged and looking very serene and almost joyful while she's being compassionate
so i and then when i invited her to be in embody us to embody her and look out
through her eyes i remembered her one of the translations of her chinese name is
the one who listens with ease to the sounds of the world and i was i just felt that like she's
just like so rooted in you know the present moment of
you know just the wholeness of everything or you know the non what do you call it the emptiness side
of things right yes he's so rooted and joyful in that and that she's unperturbed and there's this room for
this big heart to just feel the compassion beautiful yeah thank you for bringing
that in and the embodiment the ease also that you felt and her listening joyfully
it's true the the depictions are so beautiful she's listening with ease and
and also the this invocation of emptiness because she sees the emptiness
and and yet she is moved it doesn't mean like oh i don't care it's all empty it's all it's it's there's there is the
chance of of just to say just to bring this in since
we i just brought we brought emptiness in emptiness it doesn't mean that it's
pointless or or empty the word shunyata the empty translation is empty is kind
of funny a little bit but it's it's full it's
full of possibility there's so much there's so much it's both
it's um gosh i feel like i need to give a hold on no i'm just going to leave it that i'll come back another time
thanks susan thanks for bringing ease to this i cannot pack it in just a couple of
minutes thanks susan a couple of reflections and then we'll
go into groups steve says this was a new visualization having the passionate
one inside us the compassionate one inside us and seeing through those eyes
where did this come from something to do more of and get better at yes yes
um so yeah where did the i mean there's so
many skillful means uh and i've learned to so you know these
practices some of them i come up with on my own or that or they come through
me i can't say i come up with they come through me and and and this one is inspired by
something i learned i think i see now
i think jack cornfield has some version of this maybe i think or someone else so
that to uh where that that maybe this is where it came from some version of it
and then um in a private reflection i appreciated the earthing
breathing us the earth breathing us from the feet up usually i begin meditation
beginning from the top of my head down yeah yeah all these different ways of
experiencing that open up so for the practice small groups i want to
spend some time as i did last time to really set them up because i think that helps
the community um practice uh more you know better
together so so as we come into groups
small groups i invite you to speak only from your own experience
not comment on somebody else's experience not ask them questions and not serve as a
facilitator so only speak from your own experience for your own benefit
and you share a nugget from your own experience if you wish or you hold silence you can say pass
or you can and then you pass it to the next person instead of a monologue long monologue you just
share one nugget you pass it to the next person the next person maybe says pass
hold or hold silence or shares one nugget from their experience and then passes it to the next so he goes around
and around and staying close to the integrity of your own experience speaking for your own benefit
not educating or impressing anyone just sacred space and entering the space with love with
care for yourself and others as if three kuan yen's are showing up listening to
each other holding each other with care with love
okay everyone the rooms are closed everyone is back and we seem to be out
of time we spent wonderful time earlier with questions and
comments so i'll finish by reading one reflection that came earlier and that is
i imagined i was a lotus flower emerging from the mud of the earth with kuan yin sending me
all of her compassion then i could let that compassion move through and out of
me what a beautiful way to practice as a lotus flower being the lotus flower whatever works for the
skillful means so thank you all thank you for your practice
for cultivating your own inner konyan inner buddha for the benefit of yourself
and all beings may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music] thank you