all right
okay
did you catch the mic let's see how's the volume
okay not too loud and not too soft okay this this one is good
that sounds a little loud to me a little loud okay but you do get soft I yeah
maybe we should leave it right the way it is let's see yeah because I know my yeah and you're doing the meditation so
yeah yes
Richard
yep hi welcome Richard will be right there
this is like my favorite Dharma topic I'm so I'm very excited about engaging
with you guys tonight and starting this you know conversation and exploration
together about the four noble truths so um really
excited about it and you know happy to hear you're planning to come
for all the weeks and I don't know if you guys are you thinking you're going to make it for all four weeks there
might actually end up being five so um we'll we'll talk about that as we go
but what's that well the there's five five Thursdays in
December it's four noble truths I initially planned
we're gonna make up one and then yeah there's some scheduling
things so we'll wait for everybody to come into
the Hall before we officially begin but um I maybe in the meantime
um and Ben do you mind grabbing a microphone what would be really fun is to hear what
do you know about the four notable truths just a few words about how you're how familiar you are just you know what
your relationship is to it so
feel free to come on up you just got to stay one side or the other of the blue line
um does anybody feel like they would like to answer that question about
what do you know about the four noble truths and hi
Matrix great I mainly know the first one
I it's my expertise
but yeah what I know is that the first Noble Truth is that there's suffering yeah
and that there is a Cause
which is clinging or attachment yeah yeah and there is a way to get free from
that and there is a path that you can follow to get there that's right
yeah maybe just pass the mic and if you want to share anything the question is yeah Ben maybe Ben will answer any what
is your thoughts about the four noble truths you know you don't have to repeat what Mitra said is there anything you
would add or your relationship and if nothing at all
what brings you here I don't think what brings you here for
the series yeah um I got a
flyer or the the notification what's on there what what's the subject and but uh
I mean what resonated with me about
many of the talks and what I've learned over the years listening to different
teachers is suffering and attachments and how
attachments um the kind of it's like a
cause and effect kind of thing um I don't know what else I have to add
great and there's I mean we all have plenty of attachments
and some of them are oh I just this is how I do things
Etc yeah yes thank you Ben thanks so we don't have to
at this point I want to just kind of yeah let me just shift where and say
um just one or two things and then Sandra will do a guided meditation and
then we'll talk more about this first Noble truth but maybe I'll just say this
that um you know the Buddha this was his first real teaching
and it was right after his full Awakening and after he await you know
had this Awakening experience and this insight to how the mind works
um he first was like oh there's no way I'm going to teach no way like what's the there's too many no
people are not going to get it it's just going to be confusing and and then you know
so The Story Goes some Celestial beings came to him and pleaded him to teach and so he he thought oh you know he sort of
considered okay well you know maybe I'll do this and um
and uh and then he thought well but who should I teach to
if I'm gonna if I'm willing to do this who should I teach to and who will understand the Dharma who
will understand this and so you know he was having his own crisis really around
what to do next in his practice and his life and he remembered for five people
that he had done a lot of practice with and he thought they'll I can talk to them I can teach
them and so he did he went and he taught them
and they did understand and that is what they say set they call it rolling the
wheel of the Dharma set was set in motion that that was the beginning of this
wheel that we're we're benefiting from now is that very first his way of
understanding the mind which we'll talk about around the four noble truths and suffering and life and this Wheel of
Life and the way to Freedom so I feel grateful personally that um
that he was you know convinced to teach and that he had people that he
could teach who could understand so he felt like it was you know a Worthy
a worthy endeavor so
just to plant the seeds of inspiration and kind of the history and the the
poignancy of this particular teaching Sandra will you do a guided meditation
for us
so I'll invite you to find a comfortable posture I'm gonna do a
around 20 minutes meditation so just feel comfortable and
that you can really soften your body if you want to bring some movement first
the shoulders the hair just let your body move in the
way it needs to move before we settle down
I'm taking a couple of deep breaths inhaling by the nose
well I'm exciting by the mouth
and I'll invite you to feel the contact with the floor
notice the contact with the chair
the touch of your hands on the legs
and just really feel your body here
notice in the weight of the body
maybe going from head to toe
noticing the muscles of the face and with the exhalation
inviting to soften to release
allowing the shoulders to get away from the ears and maybe falling
a little backwards
perhaps breeding becomes a little easier
noticing the chest and the belly
and softening
noticing any holding
perhaps with the exhale inviting to
to soften to release
it may be that the breathing becomes more clear
and bring your attention to that place in your body we're breathing
is more clear to you
not about thinking about the breeding but just sensing it
in the body noticing what happens
with the in-breath
and how what do you feel with the exhale with the out breath
and it's not about kind of becoming a monitor of your
breathing bed resting on the breathing
relaxing softening with the breathing
there's nothing to do or nothing to change it's just resting your awareness
around your breathing in your breathing
every time you notice the mind is distracted
because it all happened
just bring it back it's an invitation to get back to the body
to the sensations of breathing
if the breathing doesn't feel right for you you could bring the attention to the
sensations in your hands
for the contact with the chair or the floor
when you get distracted notice what is your attitude
are you annoyed by the destruction or
or you like it very much and you just get lost it's so nice to get lost
just noticing what the Mind does
perhaps you're back to a discussion this morning or
planning for tomorrow
for some achiness in the body some worry
some fear
and whatever you find allow it to be there
you don't have to change it or fix it or ignore it just allow it to be there
acknowledge the destruction
the boredom the sleepiness
that little egg it's technology
there's nothing to change or fix
and come back to your breathing to your hands
and if the Mind feels concentrated
if it's easy to keep the attention on the
breathing enjoy that notice it too
and also notice that what was distracting you a few
minutes ago it's maybe gone and there's a new distraction now
just notice it
noticing your body
how does the distraction or or the concentration
expressed in the body
foreign
[Music]
thank you I think
and I wonder if there was anything in particular that came up to you
how did it feel were you distracted very distracted were
you very focused could you pass the microphone back
thank you oh good evening everyone hello again
hello Sandra um I noticed um I tried to have just the resting of
the awareness of the breathing and then I hadn't hadn't been to IMC in a while
so it's it's nice and cozy and I was I found myself I was going like this and
and then I'm like I fell asleep and then but then I was kind of not nice about it and I like okay well I
was dozing off so I just opened my eyes and but I you know I started this meditation
Journey with Tanya and never in my wildest dreams did I think I could sit
for 20 minutes comfortably because before in the beginning I was like I can't do this and then Richard showed me
how to sit like this and it's all coming together even if I'm dozing off a bit so
it's okay it's all good nice thank you very nice
something else did you happen to see your mind going
everywhere yes it was very much so and um the breathing just trying to focus on
that and not strain I still find that even doing this or at least trying to
dedicate every day to Twitter I found myself doing more five minutes it's
just but you know every day trying to be consistent and has just kind of upsetting when I still
feel like even though I'm like my body is comfortable in this position my my
mind is still very much everywhere else and it I can I I know what I'm thinking
about it's yeah I'm very much aware of it I just have to Let It Be and that's not easy and
softening like being comfortable yeah you can be alert but comfortable yes so
it helps yes ah so like you relax the body the mind also yes relax
yeah thank you thank you thank you for anybody else any any thoughts
and the observations hi
um for myself I noticed things are becoming a little bit more routine getting into the practice of the
meditation it's almost like a walk in the park whereas before I would try and hurry up the 30 minutes like are we or
you know 20 minutes or whatever like is it the time yet and now I'm more kind of
accepting you know 20 minutes or 15 minutes will pass when 20 minutes or 15 minutes past you can't have it fast or
slow um 20 minutes or 15 minutes but um every once in a while
I'll have thoughts come up and I'll push them aside that was embarrassing that thing that happened way back when or
something but um every once in a while something will come up that's kind of important oh I forgot about that I should probably get to that eventually
so those ones kind of um will hamper me a little bit more of what I call more
important kind of a just random thoughts but for the most part now it's not as
judgmental when things come up I just sort of brush them aside yeah nice yeah just oh look at that I
have forgotten about it I'm like okay I'll take care of that later but yeah I know that's very nice is the
attitude also that matters um yeah thank you
I would just okay for me to go ahead yes I think
there's just two two examples right here that I'll start with that exemplify
um creating a you know less suffering for
yourselves both of you the way you shared so the first Noble Truth is
and the poly term is there is dukkha and dukha is widely translated as
suffering often referenced to suffering but it actually when you look at the Pali word and you look at the different
ways to Define it it's it extremely broad range of experience from subtle
irritation stress to you know distress to
pain to agony it's this huge huge range of experience
and there's a a simile that the Buddha gave about the arrow you probably have
heard the simile some of you but in explaining suffering
one of the things that the Buddha pointed to was if you got shot with an arrow
would it be painful yes right now if you got shot with a second Arrow
would that be more painful let's imagine yes twice as much pain
going to be more painful and a third and a fourth right so
much of our suffering much of our dukkha is like the second third fourth fifth
two hundredth Arrow it's the it's the added psychological
stress that we put on ourselves so and Rose your decision not to trip out
about your mind wandering or falling asleep was an example of deciding I'm not going to keep shooting arrows at
myself that was a beautiful example of not
continuing to contribute to our difficulty and yours example of not tripping out
about fast slow things complete that of our control but we often try and control
that which is out of our control and it creates stress that might be a more subtle irritating
pressure kind of stress but it's stress and the experience the opposite
experience of just going oh okay well it's going to be 15 minutes or 20 minutes or whatever it is there's kind
of a freedom in that and that's the kind of Freedom that the Buddha wanted to teach us about
and um my I feel like my practice changed
completely when my relationship to do got changed
when my relationship to Duca changed the whole practice change
and Duca essentially became for me a very very useful feedback mechanism
I also liken it to a you know my relationship to using a compass we use the compass to help us find our
way we use the experience or absence of dukkha to help us know if we are on the
path if we are practicing
so if I look at a if I'm experiencing
that the kind of stress that is Duca the optional suffering right of the ways we
make things much harder for ourselves it's like looking at a compass and the compass says
keep going this way and you're going to suffer more right it's telling you right there this
is the way to more suffering you know so if you want to go that way keep going
this way and my option is to stop and reorient and sort of decide how I want
to proceed what the next step will be whether it will be toward more suffering
or away from suffering toward less suffering
um and feedback like it you know really
um what was I think oh pain okay so if you get a cut on your hand
and it hurts what does that mean to you how do you
relate to the cut hurting like in a really simple way like what's the
purpose of your hand hurting if you get cut
security there's the mic do you mind just uh
it's not on sorry Ash just for the body to know that this is something let it
rest let it heal leave it alone give it care right really uh pretty simple actually if we
don't know we're being cut we're not going to stop what we're doing that's causing harm
right like if it doesn't hurt haven't you ever been cutting your not
known that you were put doing something that was causing your body to be hurt if it doesn't hurt if we don't have that
feedback we don't know the body is going to get injured and so
if we if we are if we can see that the function of
suffering dukkha is the same as the function function of pain from hurting
ourselves we can start to be all of a sudden yes it's unpleasant but oh my gosh I'm
really grateful I'm recognizing this because just like I want to take care of my body I want to take care of my mind
my heart so it's feedback and that very same way
it's just that it's like how I think it's kind of a
miracle that there's some sort of internal system that gives us feedback when we
are moving in the direction of of harming ourselves or others
so the Buddha um
oh please thank you thank you what if you're like getting
feedback and it's constructive yeah and then
you know it's you know it's good for you like you get cut you have to rest your hand but
what if it's something that you have to deal with and
he like Let It Define you even though you know you shouldn't and it's like
especially with work dumb you know work stuff so
it's supposed to make you make me better but it sucks
in my you know well it all I mean I think um you know this is complicated right
relationships are complicated our relationship to work is complicated
um without the more specifics I don't know how to respond but I would love to
have that conversation with you you know um and hopefully we can flush it out a little bit more
here over this period of time that's yes bring your examples let's do it
um yeah so let me tell you just a few more key
points about the Buddhist teachings around this particular you know Mitra started she
named the four noble truths so just to remind you there is dukkha there is the
cause of dukkha there is the end of dukkha and there is the way to the ending of alduka
it's it's very much like a medical diagnostic tool right there's it's very
similar to how medicine works in terms of diagnosis and so the dukkha is like the symptom
that you go to a doctor with this is the symptom I have doctor okay the doctor
then says this is the cause of that suffering that whatever right and then
there's the ending of that particular illness hopefully if we're lucky right but this is for our working with our
minds and our hearts and with others in our life and our conditioning so
[Music] um his this is his first teaching this is setting the wheel of the Dharma
emotion it you know the do the Buddha and sometimes people will say I I teach I
only teach suffering in the end of suffering but I think the probably the real quote is closer to I teach duka and
the end of dukkha and it's not that that's the only thing he teaches but that is primary to what he teaches
many things he teaches but they're all in service really of the end of dukkha
so it keeps this particular teaching at the center of everything he teaches
sort of a very very center of it um
and another important thing about the way
the Buddha taught and about these teachings as well is that this is not like a Creed or something
that you're meant to like just believe in it really is is it's like you can
believe that it hurts to get a cut but it's that's theoretical
we have to pay attention to when it hurts so it's it's the same idea that this
this is a teaching to be incorporated to use as a guide for us and and everything
we do in all all forms of our practice all forms of our life
another way to think about this is that um
you know the their well I think I'll leave that alone
I think I'm gonna see yeah so let's let me shift to like
that relationship right to this suffering to dukkah like
so how do we start to be to welcome
when we recognize we're suffering and that's almost the opposite of what
our instinct is when it comes to emotional suffering physically not so much I mean sometimes
we do we override right some people more than others but when it comes to
emotional or psychological suffering a lot of us collapse
or just kind of kind of keep trying to go and ignore it
um kind of trying to like it's like almost like we wanna make convince ourselves or the world
that we it's not really happening and somehow we don't have to give in to this
like there's something really um weird I find it weird that that's our
relationship to suffering to hurt to pain to distress
so really starting to be curious about what what is your pattern what is your
relationship to noticing when you're having a hard time when you're having duka what is your
this is your conditioned the nature of conditioning right is you can start to notice
in your relationship to suffering so much about yourself so much about how
your mind has adapted and work is working and then in that space you can
start to like oh well I don't really have to do it that way
so one um
one way that I like to think about this is you know on 92 Highway 92 and 101
when you're driving on the highway actually on 92 as you're going into Half Moon Bay in the middle of the road
there's rumble strips and then along the side there's these rumble strips and rumble strips are those things that when
you drive over them your car goes it really vibrates and it's loud and it's
quite abrupt and so to me it's almost like that's
that's duka you know you we're on the path we're driving we're on the road and
you know we start we we wander out of our Lane
you know and and then you know it's like
the dukkah happens and sometimes it's really abrupt and loud and irritating
and you can be like oh I remember plenty of times driving on freeways and on the
sides feeling why is it you know like very irritated and that's maybe the natural initial
response it's totally fine but then like if we step back and we go oh wait a minute like I was looking at
the ocean instead of the road if I had just kept wondering I would
have been off the road I would be in the ditch and so can I be grateful
that that experience happened so that I and you know that it woke me
up that it brought me back to the path to paying attention to where I was and not wandering off
so um am I supposed to be done at 7 20 yes
okay so we'll say one more little thing which is that it can be very helpful to think
about um that there is biological physical suffering that that's just innate part
of life like you know we're going to adopt we're born we age we get sick we
die these are this is just kind of this biological fact of being a human
and then there's psychological stuff suffering and psychological suffering stems from our reactivity
to whatever is happening it's all about the reactivity the judgments the which
is a reaction the not liking it which is a reaction the wanting more of it which
is a reaction and
so it can be helpful to kind of think about suffering in those two terms and
we can go further into looking at sort of the psychological suffering and
psychological suffering that's based in identity Me Mine this is about me it's
personal um and it also can be about interpersonal issues
about you know our relationship to somebody how they're going to see us now
or what we really want them to be doing instead of what they're doing
that that's a interpersonal form of suffering and then you could also think about systemic suffering which is where
you might think about you know institutionalized racism things that are
kind of on a grander scale incorporated into a system or society that oppress
women in Iran in my view it's oppression right but of
course that's my view and I think a lot of women in Iran feel that way right now they're telling us so and that's been
institutionalized right it's become systemic um
so so there's different this this is said
to say it can't kind of trying to help you start to look at and differentiate
the ways that duka might be showing up in your life
I was thinking as you were speaking that the four noble truths is kind of the
Buddha deconstructing suffering so first you have to see it
then you understand where he's coming from you know that it is okay I can can
be there's an end to it and then it offers you not a recipe but a path to follow that
will help you with it and I think as you were saying if we
don't see it if we don't become aware of that we're suffering and the sufferings
can be kind of a strong word if you are annoyed if you are uncomfortable
if you don't notice it there's nothing we can do about it
I think it's in our biology uh kind of place against us in that sense
because we in our brain and and evolution and everything you we are
biased towards looking for what's Pleasant to what's good and it's just
plain survival um we're going to be aversive to things
that are make us uncomfortable that we need to look for food we need to look to be warm
we like to be in community and things like that and then it's like the suffering that we
Society impose over us the way we were educated where we grew up if you look at
the publicity for example you deserve it it's like be unhappy or
be unwell or be anxious or
feeling fear it's it's a big No-No like no like everything has to be perfect so
in a ways so we have the biology and plus uh all
the people that profit on us because it's human nature to suffer in a way
so I'm gonna maybe give you some tips that you could like practices that you
could do on your day-to-day um I mentioned during the meditation to
notice the attitude because a lot of these practices how we do it it's not so
much what we do but how what is the attitude that we have so for what I'm gonna invite you to do
at some point during the week when you feel like um is to bring
a very kind curious awareness
so like huh look at that I hadn't seen that before like I didn't know I reacted
like that all the time like we we have all those patterns and habits and we may
not like him when we start noticing them it's like oh I'm not I'm not a good person or think
like that we can go really to the extreme so the invitation is to bring
kindness and curiosity and curiosity like for example you go to
a place for a new hike but that you have never been before there's trees you have never seen before
the terrain is different so look you are really looking very carefully where you
put your your feet like uh or gonna climb there so you're very careful and
like watching oh I can't see that tree oh look at those flowers so it's like
let's check there's something new in ourselves so it's a visit it's an
internal hike in a way I think the the very first thing uh kind
of the uh oh the other thing is the exercises like
big suffering like somebody dies we have a problem at at work
um we are in an accident we twist our ankle those are like whoa you very
quickly realize that you're suffering but there's other type of suffering that they're not so obvious for the reason I
was telling you sometimes we just don't want to see it it's like you know I'm good I'm happy I'm well everybody likes
me um you're in a group with friends and you're all smiles and things like that isn't it so that is that little
suffering that little annoyance that we tend to forget and that's what I'm gonna
invite you to notice and it's because like going to the gym you're not going
to start lifting the 20 50 pounds let's just start with the three pounds the
five pounds and that's day-to-day suffering so let's say once a day you sit down and
the purpose is put 10 minutes aside and notice what am I feeling
what is making me uncomfortable and just like curiosity like
I just noticed for example that my uncle is my I just twisted my food several
months ago and he said oh my foot is still hurting like that kind of suffering because I am I Ever Gonna Get
Well is am I gonna be free of this pain someday like I started like going like
oh look at that that's too good um you have a disc you had a discussion with a co-worker a family member or
something like that and you're still running that scenario in your head and you're telling yourself I should have
said that tomorrow I'm gonna let them know and things like that that's okay so just sit down and see hmm let's see what
kind of things are going on in my mind and notice it no not with the intention
of going not fix it just see it like wow
and I think we all have the tendency we see something wrong and we want to go
and fix it it okay we need to do something here so notice what you do to
fix it to make it better to hide it
um sometimes we don't see the suffering we see what we do to cover the suffering
so notice that too like you're waiting in line what's the first thing you do
and you take your cell phone and start browsing like with no particular reason with no
purpose at all it's like notice that so notice the suffering or notice what you're doing to hide it and suffering is
a strong word here the annoyance the uh you're bored it's like oh my gosh do I
have to wait DMV for example things like that what do you do and then like why am
I doing this like you just start browsing look at your I don't know your Facebook or whatever social platform you
utilize so what what is why am I doing why am I doing this is I'm noticing
those things and again do it with kindness and like wow look at that I'm I'm just
I'm not doing anything I just took it out like automatically how many times do we check our email
like every minute it's like I I assure you there's no new email
and we do it over and on like so oh what is what is behind that what is it that
I'm trying to get distracted from and see what happens
um yeah the other thing is okay the more
noticeable annoyance discomfort like it's so
obvious that you're seeing it so first what I was saying during the
meditation relax your body take a couple of deep breaths like oh can I relax my
body it's not gonna fix but it's going to help you be better
with it face it and then maybe try to investigate a little bit
like the example the discussion that you have with a co-worker in the morning and
you're going over and over and I should have said that I'm gonna tell my boss
like we go into all these Loops yeah we had the second Arrow the third Arrow the
four arrow so when you notice that you're in that situation could you
separate what was like the pain what what causing you to be
hurt or be sad or be annoyed what was the cause and then what is what you're
adding on top of it can you separate the two things and again is observation what
the invitation right now is observe see what's happening and it may be that just by noticing
things tend to soften a little bit things tend to relax a little bit
what Tanya was saying too about these um
we we don't oftentimes we don't suffer in isolation so something happens and so
we have the event and then is because you really like that
co-worker you get along so well and then you got so that what they say to you was
so hurting and so terrible and it's also oh wow it's my relationship with this
person so don't look at yourself in isolation but oh wow is my relationship
to other people that really comes to play I think like family relationships
with our partners with our sons with our parents and those are complicated
relationships so can we separate what was that happen what is that I am adding
on top of that and recognize that is maybe that relationship that makes it very difficult
think yeah I don't I want to make sure we leave time for the small groups great
well that's a perfect warm-up for the breakout groups actually so um what we what we like to do assuming
you're willing is probably to break you up into two groups so two groups of four
and um and have you share in that in those groups
personal examples that you feel comfortable sharing so don't share what you don't feel comfortable sharing
and you don't have a lot of time so not all the details but just this kind of a brief sketch of some examples for you
maybe think about big suffering and then a small suffering
big dukus molduca and also maybe what is a psychological or what is an
interpersonal duka what's a personal duka like kind of can you come up with any
questions about those or examples of them and see if you can help each other kind
of identify by hearing from each other and sharing in that way are you in agreement
with willingness to do these great okay and so I tend to suggest people not go
into a group with someone they know well so you feel free to share and
um you know so I just leave it to you to maybe make a group on this side of the
room and a group on that side of the room um four people per group
go ahead and uh yeah that would be awesome
so go ahead and introduce yourselves maybe say your name and where you
where you live or some if you've ever been to IMC before