welcome to this
community of meditators Gathering
for what being California we call the 7 A.M sitting in Dharma talk
at the beginning of the pandemic the first months or two of the
Sheltering in place it was remarkable how quiet this local
city became and how you could hear sounds that I
normally didn't hear there were sounds of birds that uh
kind of like oh yeah there's so many birds here and normally those sounds are drowned
out and maybe you've been in situations
where you know something became quiet and you
could hear things maybe it's the quiet that happens when
the refrigerator hums stops and and you could somehow hear the quiet
or hear other things
or there are times when the haze or the smog in the air has
cleared out and here where I live we can sometimes see across the San Francisco Bay
and it's surprising how close the Hills are on the other side
when there is clear so in meditation
when the noise of the Mind quiet down
when the Haze and veils that over our eyes our inner eyes
our perception clears it's surprising what we can see and hear
and feel within ourselves
and so part of meditation is to see
the noise the thinking the the
attitudes the agitation all these things that make it difficult to see
but from time to time meditation supports
the humming of the refrigerator turns off
City in within us becomes quiet
and we can feel and hear and send something we normally can't
and what is it that we sense what is it we feel that's normally obscured by the busyness
the loudness of our ordinary life
and of course that's an answer for each of us to answer for ourselves
so to begin our meditation
to place your body in a posture
that might allow the agitation the busyness to settle
maybe there's a posture you can take that's relaxed
that maybe has some qualities of
being peaceful and settled
and in a peaceful way to lower your gaze
and not looking at anything in particular
slowly and peacefully letting your eyes close
and without doing much else
not changing your breathing notice
how it feels to be breathing right now
letting your attention roam around the Torso
to feel the movements of breathing
the sensations the Rhythm
and where in your body can you feel fixed
the body breathing in a tranquil and peaceful way
maybe it's not your usual place to notice breathing
maybe for a few moments it's to be aware of the movements in your back rib cage
or the very subtle movements of your spine
maybe there's a little bit of Tranquility or peace
for a moment at the beginning of the exhale
or at the end of the exhale
and as you sit here as you meditate is their beginning of a little bit of
calming calm or tranquility simply sitting here
feeling perceiving a global experience of your
body noticing where there's agitation and tension
noticing it with some gentleness
and letting the body relax as you exhale
and with gentle care be aware of any agitation or noise or
busyness in the mind gently caringly
be aware of it
and now on the exhale perhaps letting the Mind thinking mind
relax
and as you would let the mind be thinking mind be quiet to listen to a
sound faint sound in the distance but a thinking mind be quiet
so you can feel and sense
the dynamic flow and of Sensations in your body
maybe the subtle sensation is subtlest sensations of
the body vibrating humming
the deepest feeling of
aliveness
where your body both generates
sensations of
the body just being here
the background deeper Sensations always hear of
just being alive and the energies humming vibrations
and the Rises out of the body and is received by the body
known in the body
and in the middle of all that there's the sensations of the body
breathing
maybe almost as if breathing
arises out of and returns
from the subtle sensations of the lived body
gently writing the sensations of breathing
as if you're being lifted and lowered by swells of water that you're floating in
riding the exhale all the way to the last sensation
associated with exhaling
and from that last sensation receive the upwelling movement of
Sensations of inhaling
with a deeper hum or vibration or flow of Sensations in the body
like the current that moves through the river of the body
and the breathing his gentle swells
waves coming and going in that current
okay
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to let something within you become quiet
so that you can remember some experience in your life of care
someone caring for you in a peaceful way for you caring for someone or for some
animal
and what is care like what is love like
if it arises from the place inside that's quiet and peaceful
that maybe is only felt when
the mind is quiet
nothing flashy maybe love and
care that is free of Desire
a tender appreciation
and from the place inside where Maybe love or cares most innate or quiet
peaceful
to let your good will flow out of there out into the world
as if it radiates
and that it carries the words
out with it into the world may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe male beings
be peaceful and may all beings
be free [Music]
thank you
so this will be the second talk on the Buddha's use of similes
for providing meditation instruction
and I think that these beautiful similes the Buddha uses for his instructions
might not at first seem like instructions and in fact for me I think
in my early years of reading these early texts I was somewhat dismissive of that
similes and kind of maybe glossed over them
but now I linger with them and they seem to be quite enriching
and the mind the human mind often works well with images metaphors simile
some people say that human life is we understand ourselves and the world
around us is very much through the filter of similes
or metaphors and that sometimes we can understand things in new ways through metaphor
someone might be repeatingly
kind of angrily aggressively
um trying to fix themselves get rid of some
kind of trait or something that they have that is a you know causing suffering
and then they hear kind of a metaphor that
their approach to try to stop or
this tendency they have the approach they have is kind of like picking at a scab
and if you pick at a scab it doesn't heal so that metaphor
might penetrate more deeply be evocative suggestive have some truth to it that was scapped
it's true that um that might penetrate much deeper into
the psyche than simply saying you know just you know leave yourself alone
don't try keep you know you know getting rid of something that
you don't like and um so that you know so the metaphor there kind of somehow speaks to
something when my son was young
very young I uh he didn't fall asleep very easily
though he had a high sleep need and um so I would when I took him to bed
I would do guided meditations with him but I wouldn't sit next to him and say
you know be aware of your in-breath be aware of your out breath what I would do was uh paint a picture
of some animal in the natural world that was sleeping
and one of the most common ones was a sea otter
uh resting on the surface of the ocean with surrounded by underneath and around
all this kelp that kept the sea otter quite safe
in this in the image I was creating and that uh the CO2 just lay on its back
and gently feel the rising and falling of the swells as the the ocean
and those swells I would say you know very peaceful and gentle and quiet and
as you feel you're breathing maybe put your hand on your chest I would tell him or and just feel that rising and falling
of the swell and the otter kind of falling asleep you know resting there safely
and and with that he would stay with his breath he would feel the movement of his
breathing and he would gently fall asleep and I had a whole repertoire of animals
that I would use and one of them was a you know like a gorilla or a monkey that
had a little newborn baby that would rest on the chest of the
parent and and would feel the rising and falling of the parents chest as the
parent was breathing and that the baby would just feel that movement and and
then again I maybe have him put his hand on his chest and feel his movement and then you know and this worked very
well for quite a while and helped him fall asleep so this idea of kind of painting an
image a story something kind of allows the mind's imagination allows it's kind
of an emotional connection you know a little uh you know a little baby monkey
with its parent um the safety of being surrounded by kelp it was in in the story I made
um it kind of kind of touched some different aspects of Who We Are that allowed something deeper to connect to
you know the movements of breathing in doing this kind of meditation
and um and so the Buddha also used these similes and these similes then tap into
our imagination tap into how the imagination and the picture that's created reaches out and touches
different parts of our emotional being but different parts of our Concepts and
ideas and our ability to ability to visualize the way that supports what
we're doing and um and I didn't know that this was could be
part of meditation partly because both in Zen and they're in vipassana practiced started in Asia
it was clearly uh opposed to doing anything like that it was just kind of
sitting here present with the truth not doing anything trying to make anything
happen just a direct penetration of the truth of emptiness or something
and with the personal practice it was just directly seeing things as they are without the overlay of Concepts and
stories and images and similes there's something very profound about the way I was taught to end the way I
was taught to be possible but it's also was kind of an advanced practice and kind of assumed that people could
were already able to settle quite well and in fact in when I started Zen I
wasn't Envy Personnel I wasn't and so it took a while to kind of find myself
settled enough to do the instructions that they were teaching
and the Buddha but the Buddha when he gave his meditation instruction he made some very simple technical
explanation of what to do or what goes on but then he provided similes that filled
in the picture they gave a richer sense of what was going to happen within it's almost like similes and metaphors
sometimes evoke or touch or explain describe what
can go on inside better than just a simple statement and um
you know if someone someone could say to me you know I'm feeling pretty sad today
I would kind of care for them and wonder what's going on but I've heard sad songs
that made me cry there was one actually one children's song from my son that I don't think he
ever was moved by it but whenever it was uh by the singer called Rafi
um who made children's songs and uh and now to hear the song and now it'd get kind of teary and it was such a sad song
so there's there's something there's things that touch us and evoke us so similes so the simile I want to
describe today is the beginning stages of really
getting quiet and settled so that uh all the noises of the Mind
the business of the mind is no longer there and we're beginning to kind of settle into the present moment but
there's still a kind of dynamism there's still a kind of kind of the flow of energy that of life is kind of flowing
through us in a very nice way and um and so the simile is that of a
mountain lake that is uh deep deep Mountain Lake
and there's no uh Rivers flowing into the river into the lake so it's not
being replenished by Rivers coming in and there's no rain that falls in the
river so it's not being replenished from above instead this this particular lake is
being reply replenished by an underwater spring that's at the center of the lake
basin where it's uh flowing Waters coming out of the spring
into the water itself and Fanning out in all directions through the lake
and this water is explained as being cool and fresh
and in a hot climate like India cool and fresh water was very comforting very
wonderful for people and have very positive connotations and and so the city of cool refreshing
water I would say it would come out of the spring and spread throughout the lake so no part of the lake was not
touched by the this cool current of water in the same way as a person gets settled
and starts getting quiet and able to hear and listen more deeply what's going on
partly because they're starting to get focused on the breathing and the
thinking mind the distracted mind the discursive mind starts getting quiet and
quiet then the it starts to kind of be a
unification Gathering Together harmonizing of the energies of the sensations of
what goes on inside of us that there's kind of something as touch something uh
you know you can almost say something almost emotional something that uh something gets kind of
freed up and there's a flow of energy of delightful sense of well-being that
can flow through the body in the same way that the the water from the spring
flows through the lake this delightful kind of Uh current
flows through the body so that no part of the body is not touched by this
delightful sense of current sometimes this current is called joy and
kind of a joy and happiness I like to think of it as just kind of you know it's also all kinds of intensities of it
it can be um but essential well-being a sense of unification
that might be comparable to a craftsperson really happily absorbed in
the work they do uh or a someone reading a book or playing music or doing some activity
where the doing of it fully completely involved in it where there's we're not
fragmented all the energy is there kind of gathered to kind of in a peaceful way to kind of be involved in it some
delightful happy sense of concentration absorption has this welling up feeling
that spreads throughout the body and um and so uh that's the simile and so
as it gives a sense that as we can get concentrated as we get settled and
present here with a quiet mind there is something deeper that Wells up
that feels quite healthy and delightful and wonderful that that we can trust
that is supportive and that so the simile kind of gives a sense of feeling
that there's a current there's a flow there's a it arises maybe out of some place Source within us
the important part of the simile is that um the the source of the sensations of
delight and well-being that they're going on arise from inside out they rise
from within the body and they're not dependent on any of the rivers coming from outside any of the scent stores
being stimulated by sounds smells touch
sites they're not dependent of anything in the world and because there's no rain falling in
and the metaphor the rain is all our thoughts stories we make living in the kind of conceptual world
and none of that is influencing us we're not being impacted by the world or the
world of our thoughts uh this source of this well-being is not dependent on
anything in the world and that's a phenomenal pointing the story this kind of assembly pointing
that possibility can give a lot of inspiration oh I don't have to fix the
world I don't have to line up the world to be just the right way there is a place
of quietude or peacefulness where something begins some happiness can
arise and swell Love From the Inside Out and it can feel like it has no cause or
no reason though the cause kind of is being settled and focused and present in a
more continuous way that's kind of the cause but it kind of
like has no worldly cause and to begin having a sense of this that we carry with us this possibility
can free us from the idea that my
happiness is dependent on what goes on in the world and I have to fix the world get everyone to behave
properly then I'll be happy rather there is this
beautiful Deep Mountain Lake inside of you in which there is a bottom there's a
spring of freshing energy coming up and can flow throughout the whole body
the treasure is in you not outside
so thank you and um and um
and I feel a little bit apologetic that the guided meditations this week are a little bit long a lot of words but
hopefully uh it it uh conveys little but what I'm teaching here with these
similes and we'll continue again tomorrow thank you