so uh so welcome folks um
yeah welcome to y'all um
yeah happy happy to be with you this week and um
I hope you're well wherever you are and um
well um to that thing we do
um and uh and set
okay so uh yes it'll settle into a posture that feels sustainable
just let at the Dharma
tell you what to do
and let the muscle memory
of any no your prior practice
tell you what to do
let your mind and take its cues from the Stillness
the silence
and maybe looking for the the phenomena
where giving giving some attention there brings in
sense of Tranquility is
maybe that's the breath maybe that's
Sensations in your hands or feet or something
the body that feels vaguely Pleasant soothing
maybe that's the darkness behind your closed eyes
or maybe even amidst the ambient noise in your environment
you can kind of tilt the attention towards cylons
it's letting your mind take its cues
from these soothing objects of attention
the tranquility is a
healing in itself
and the tranquility um
makes more room for the imperfection
of the The Human Condition to be digested
so maybe we just uh what's a rising is um
some sense of e is quiet and we just abide
there's no project to be done
maybe the tranquility uh illuminates what is unfinished in the
heart or the transient aches
heartache
that which is uh calling out
to be digested
by awareness
so whatever is arising in experience
um there's goodness unfolding
and no matter how you think you're doing
you can rest well
in the wholesomeness of your intention
the goodness of the aspiration
to wake up
is connecting with that is also soothing
tranquilizing
we take a certain kind of Dharma posture
make a certain gesture of awareness
and then just let time pass
let time be your ally
nothing more needs to be done other than just making
that gesture of awareness
letting the logic of the Dharma unfold through you
foreign
so it's good to uh good to sit with you good to be with you
um yeah it's always easier actually to say hello and welcome after we all said
kind of deeper greeting in a way so um yeah I'll be I'm your substitute
teacher this week and um yeah we'll be be with you uh these days
and um I'll actually also do tomorrow night
um and and Thursday night do a zoom session an optional Zoom session for a
half hour that I'll post the info at the end um for you know we can sit for a few
minutes and um and have any questions or dialogue
so um
yeah I have this this friend um long time practitioner and
um and and he he is always working actively on something in his practice as
if he's like in the new phase of like intense excitement about Dharma practice he's
just like always there actively contemplating something
and um whenever whenever we talk
it's like he's living in a Dharma talk giving it to himself then giving it to
anyone who will listen really and uh he's extremely persuasive
and um one time we smoke and um
remember this conversation and and uh and he said you know we're
um we're always saying let go we're always saying open up to Anita open up
to unreliability uncertainty comprehend duka comprehend suffering
and he said it's too much it's too much we need to teach pleasure that's what we
need to teach and um and so this week the the theme is uh
varieties of uh of Dharma pleasure now Dharma pleasure is weird pleasure in
a way but it's pleasure nonetheless um
pleasure is not the same as satisfaction and
I I really associate ordinary pleasure with
um actually strengthening the patterns of craving
of craving seeking relief finding some kind of
brief seclusion from the pain of craving but
then the cycle continuing whereas maybe we say Dharma Pleasures
are distinctive insofar as they don't create thirst they actually
satiate they they are um Pleasures that leave
peace in their wake
so that's a theme and today the pleasure
of uh of having a path the pleasure of having a path
um we're we're all
um I I sometimes say we're all philosophers of happiness and we we
've all asked the question many times implicitly what is the good life yeah as
a philosopher might ask what is a good life and we're all in a sense tentatively
living our answer and
as a kid I was um Without Really knowing it but just
looking back or you know retrospect I I was asking this question
and was kind of picking up and ruling out many different philosophies of
happiness and a sense of like could this work no
could that work no I was so sensitive to suffering
and with so little Equanimity and I was just like trying out what could work
what could work and my conclusion was that
I didn't know and my conclusion was that adults the adults
didn't know that much about happiness either and uh
I kind of waded into this path years later with a great deal of
skepticism sort of unsure that this had anything new to offer really
and um many of the the tears that I would shed in the early years of
practice were tears of of relief and they were the relief of this
I found a path yeah not the path that
the path that everyone must walk not the one true path but I've found a path
this is a path for me and there is so much relief in that and
a sense of like my heart kind of interlocking with some vision of
happiness very
soothing um the the philosopher Nietzsche said
um one who has a y can bear almost any how
one who has a y compare almost any how and we need to be
convinced of our why but when we are convinced the why
wisdom and love when we do become convinced
the rest is just kind of details yeah the rest of the path how I'm doing where
it's going what I'll learn how much I'll achieve details
we have our y and I'm really alluding to in a sense
the arising of Faith a certain kind of the pleasure of faith
baklav Havel said hope is not the conviction something will turn out well but the certainty that something makes
sense regardless of how it turns out and uh
there's this kind of faith we relax we relax we're not
um compulsively looking for evidence that we're on the right track you know that
sense of just like pinging around within our experience just looking am I doing this right is
this right should I be doing something else should I be that kind of
um energetic state that that starts to fade
the the absence of faith we could say is a kind of this wobble a certain kind of
ambivalence of always looking for evidence that we're doing it the right
way or trying to sort out our place on the path we're comparing ourselves to
others rather than just actually feeling one's own belonging
within the Dharma
and the absence of this this kind of Faith
leads us to a sense of like grappling in the dark and never sure
exactly what's trustworthy where to look for data you know where to validate what
we're doing and um
and that Fades that Faith there's a pleasure in our faith we stop
guessing if we're getting it right because um we know we're just going to keep going
exploring learning growing
and the pleasure of this kind of faith is uh it's a it's a particular pleasure
I'm no no fundamentalist I'm really almost reverential about the the
permanent possibility of being wrong but um
at the same time my mind hasn't wobbled about the path for for a long time
and what that feels like is a very abiding
confidence in wisdom and love not more than the just the confidence in
the
Ken McLeod um a few times in my life I've been in
difficult situations situations in which I could not see any way forward
in my morning practice sessions I would to the best of my ability rest in the
confusion that swirled inside of me I suppose it was the years of effort
that made that resting possible even though all those years those efforts had seat poultry
an ineffective when I could rest in the confusion it
grew quiet and dark the quiet of a dark night with no moon or Stars
as I rested in that Darkness a Clarity would sometimes arise and with it a sense of direction
how or what discerned that Clarity or that direction I don't know but both
were there the clarity didn't illumine anything it
didn't make anything in the situation clearer
it just indicated a Direction where that direction LED or what I would
encounter I had no idea there was a Direction
nothing more
one of the measures of this path
is uh we have a Direction we have a Direction
and even when the confusion swirls
we there's solace in a Direction there's solace in
a kind of faith in wisdom and love that
that will matter that will matter no matter what unfolds that will matter
so I offer this for your consideration
and um we'll uh we'll keep going tomorrow yeah
new strange pleasures of uh Dharma practice Yeah
okay thank you uh thank you all yeah and um
uh post that the zoom info here for uh
a little bit tomorrow on Thursday let's see
um
okay uh
thank you thank you folks um yeah I wish you wish you a good uh good
day and um yeah nice to see your names here in the chat
uh I'll see you uh
see you in the morning yeah okay