so good morning a good day welcome
and the buddha said that it's likely to slight paraphrase
that tranquility supports tranquility
and this can be understood that if you let yourself become aware
of the tranquility that's here the tranquility can grow
if you ignore that whatever tranquility is here it doesn't support or the growth
of more tranquility and in this sati patana practice the first exercise with
breathing the tranquility that is focused on is tranquility of the body
and uh so some translations will will say that
the the last exercise is breathing in one tranquilizes the
bodily formations tranquilizes the bodily constructs the tension the holdings the
part the way the muscles are engaged very subtly
based on how the mind is breathing out
one tranquilizes the bodily formations
the bodily activities and and so there is this movement towards
tranquility in this practice that begins when we start just taking
the posture and see seeing if you can find a posture
that supports tranquility some modicum some minimum kind of feeling of
being the body is still but not just still
in a hell tranquility is a certain stillness that has a wholesome feeling to it it feels
refreshing or feels nice and
the deep tranquility of meditation practice is not kind of calm that puts us to sleep
it's a kind of clarity energized clarity that's very peaceful
and as the practice deepens awareness takes on qualities of
tranquility itself awareness becomes peaceful and the analogy i have for it is
being in some very beautiful wonderful sacred space
it could be some you know great cathedral in the natural world
of great big redwood trees or great mountains or
looking out across the sea it could be a one of the large cro the great cathedral where you go in and
it has this maybe the busy noisy streets are outside you go inside and
and uh there's a quiet and a piece that uh stillness
and in these spaces awareness is is there present without having to
work for it without having to search for it or direct or do anything
it's just somehow the space the situation just
allows for kind of a spacious open wide awareness that somehow is attuned or becomes part
of the peacefulness of the place the quiet of the place
and attention is not directed it isn't like awareness being used or to work
it's simply present it's there and
there might be other places that um in your life where just awareness is just there in a nice way
it could be that something as simple as waking up from a very refreshing nap
and you just feel like oh you're just aware you're not really focusing or trying to do anything with it
but you're just you're clearly aware and it's kind of a clarity or maybe
looking out across a great expanse of natural worlds being on a cliff or in the mountainside
and it just the situation just calls on awakens a kind of tranquil open
awareness but not searching for something not trying to focus on something it's just there the awareness is present
and so in this satipatana here in the first
exercise there is a gentle movement that takes time that involves establishing awareness
settling in on the breathing letting the settling on the breathing settle the mind settle the body
until it becomes easier just to relax the body more and more and make and help the body's body become
tranquil and appreciating the tranquility of the body and in when that's established
then awareness doesn't have to be directed so much anymore it doesn't have to be work it doesn't
have to be like f making effort to know what's happening or to feel what's happening
and it's not just feeling it's not just knowing it's this uh kind of broad or maybe it's the gestalt
or the harmonious working of all or attentional capacities
into a state that we might call being aware and then having this awareness
established or present and um and abiding in it
so this is a pro so i'm just describing a process and i'll say more uh later but
so for today let's uh focus a little bit more on this tranquility
and see if tranquility awareness can take on some of the qualities of
tranquility so assuming a posture
that will allow your body to be tranquil and still
but it should be a posture that also has some degree of alertness to it
a little bit teeny bit energized so the energy the alertness maybe the
uprightness can hold the tranquility
gently closing the eyes
and then noticing is there any hints of tranquility for you now in your
body your mind your heart
maybe it's even in your little finger or
your big toe or something but anywhere at all
and then you know in a manner that has some degree of tranquility or calm in it
calmly take some larger breaths
and then as you exhale calmly
soften the body
calmly relax your body
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and calmly taking your time as you breathe normally
search through your body for places that you can relax soften
and as you do so see if that can be a settling into
a degree of tranquility or peace
letting your breathing return to normal
and seeing if there can be a little bit of sense of tranquility or calm
in establishing your attention and experience the of the body breathing
breathing in and breathing out
perhaps if it's present if some tranquility is present for you
maybe that can be the
atmosphere within which you're breathing
an atmosphere that includes awareness tranquil awareness
if your mind wanders off relax something relax
any holding or tension in the thinking
any or in the body related to thinking
and see if you can settle back in
to a tranquil awareness it's more like the atmosphere
than it is doing but which
within which breathing is the center
a tranquility that makes room for the kind of awareness
that doesn't require effort
the kind of awareness that just is
some people might call it just being conscious
tranquil con conscious in a tranquil way
the effortless way of being conscious
breathing breathing
through that effortless awareness
noticing whatever tranquility peacefulness
is present for you now
and is that sense of tranquility shared in some way that it's shared
by awareness by being aware being conscious
and imagine that with whatever calm tranquility
peacefulness you have
that you're sitting together with someone you trust
someone that you it's easy and peaceful to be with
and nothing's required nothing needs to be said but see what it's like what would it be
like to sit there aware of them present with them
through this tranquility through this peacefulness
perhaps appreciating them perhaps having good will
care for them
nothing's required the care the good will don't need any nothing needs to be
done just let it be there in the peacefulness in the care
and with that kind of good will staying in that place of tranquility
expand your goodwill now out into the world
tranquilly wishing all beings well
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may my peacefulness
create the conditions that support them in feeling those ways
may all beings be free
[Music]
so the last step of the refrain for satipatanam
is one abides mindful
that there is a body just to the extent necessary
for knowledge and lucid awareness
being independent
of see dwelling independent not clinging to
anything in the world so
when abides again this is again a very important word when it rests when it just allows
at the abiding there's not a lot of work mindfulness because now has transitioned from whatever directedness whatever
efforts needed to show up and be present to allowing so just to be present
it's more almost like more of a being rather than a doing and when abides
um in awareness and but the awareness when abides
in awareness is present to this very simple recognition there is
a body so it's very simple it's you know just no judgment no complications
no analysis no that has to be different in any kind of way
it's just a simple simple recognition just to the extent necessary i love this expression just to the extent necessary
we're not looking for a really super high standard to do the absolutely the best we can but just the extent necessary so
awareness is established just to the extent necessary for there to be knowledge the knowing
a very simple knowing that's not work it's not like actively knowing but uh it's just kind of the
knowing like for example there is a body knowing that we're
independent not dependent on anything
knowing that we are not clinging to anything
and um and uh and so to the extent there's knowledge
and lucid awareness and this word lucid awareness is in in pali has the word
sati in it the word is often translated as mindfulness
it's uh has a prefix pati p-a-t-i so
p-a-t-i-s-a-t-i patti sati and it's a reflexive
prefix meaning kind of reflecting back on oneself and so it's here it's awareness that
kind of is aware of itself so i try and say this is a lucid awareness
there's a lucid because we know we're aware in a lucid clear way
and so the practice leads to this place where
there's a very simple abiding in awareness that's lucid
and is able to know very simple things including and that sets the stage for
moving into um this freedom of not being dependent on
anything in the world not clinging to anything in the world and what that means is not necessarily
that we don't depend on you know on shopkeepers having food for so we can
live but rather not the uh the awareness the mind the heart
is at rest in itself and the mind and heart don't need anything for suppressing a kind of
peaceful place and this uh last phrase
being independent not depending on anything not clinging to anything in the world
is one way of describing nibana the full
realization of practice so it's a you know you don't expect to sit down and just do that
quickly but it's something that grows over time and this idea of this practice growing
over time is inherent in this whole way in which satipattan is laid out it's
we're describing a path a process and um and so having a sense that
there's kind of an onward leading movement slowly over time but it's not an armored leading movement
that's linear that you can expect to just kind of steadily go make progress it's more like up and down back and
forth and our lives are so complicated the states of our mind are so different from different times but
slowly over time we're kind of moving in one direction and that direction is towards freedom
so there is this process there's this path a journey that unfolds over time
and uh so we don't get tripped up around that and caught up in striving and comparing ourselves and wanting to be
further than we are one of the principles that i love is the principle that
to go from a to b be fully at a
so for the purpose of mindfulness practice if you want to go anywhere in your mindfulness practice
don't worry about getting anywhere with the practice just focus on being fully present for what is
and that practice of fully present for what is is what is onward leading it'll it'll unfold the way it's supposed to
unfold if our our our dedication is not making progress but rather showing up
and being fully present here the progress makes that takes care of itself
um so the to summarize or to repeat kind of what i've said already to get a sense of this journey
that's described so far the buddhist talks about there's a
there's a path to liberation a path to nibana
and what is that it's uh observing the body and the body
uh ardent aware and clearly comprehending having put aside grief
and uh and uh covetousness for the world
so that's a high standard already to put put aside covetousness and grief for the world to stress for the world
to be you know and um so then he wants to say well how do you do that how do you practice this
practicing observing the body in terms of the body well you sit down to meditate sit
upright and you establish awareness and with awareness established
you use that first to become aware of your breathing and because the mind so easily wanders
off the tether to the present moment is knowing knowing the breath
and if some people will use the knowing or a practice of knowing with a mental
noting so as they feel the breathing they say in
out or rising of the belly falling of the belly or the chest
and that mental note is a little bit way of being emphatic slightly emphatic with the knowing of the breathing as you
know it and kind of as a tether to the present moment
as that practice deepens then we can become aware of our body and we just become aware of the whole
body at some point and then the onward leading movement goes
towards relaxing the body and this part of the process is can be
repeated over and over again um you know for a long time just getting used to it and knowing and feeling and
relaxing and some days one is emphasized more than the other sometimes we just stay at step one
uh barely stay there because the mind is so busy so
whatever you are just be fully at a practice with what you have that's what onward leading practice where you are
not where you think you should be but then as we settle in and there's more and more tranquility and we settle
into that tranquility then the awareness we observe we enter this phase of
practice where there's observation watching just this non-reactive non-interfering
perceiving of experience and we experience it um
internally and externally and one way of understanding that is that it's just open awareness is now open 360 degrees
and and we're aware of the body the full body in a simple relaxed way
and and as we settle into that further then we abide in a situation where a time
when awareness begins tuning in to the changing nature the flow of change the inconstancy of
experience and then constantly change things coming and going it becomes clear after a while
that it doesn't make any sense to cling to anything hold on to anything resist anything because everything is flowing
and if anything it's like we we surrender to that sense of flow in the body
that exists of everything arising and passing everything moving
and we see so clearly that we when we get up get involved in thoughts and concepts
that we kind of start solidifying our experience again
and so then we dip back down into that the flow of the river of life that flows through
us with all experience and because we're not clinging at some point then
what happens next is that we're just there present in the simplest possible way with a lucid awareness
awareness becomes freed from how it gets agitated or contracted or
cloudy with concepts clinging wanting not wanting it's just this lucid
awareness lucid consciousness that is not working to be mindful not
working to do anything it's more like something we abide in we rest in
we allow and that very still quiet mind
where we just allow things to be where we're not for or against anything is a very equanimous
and that allows for even a deeper letting go where we in that state
it's clear that our hearts our minds is no longer depends on its well-being on
anything at all there's no not that it's kind of self-contained or self-existing
our sense of well-being and freedom so it doesn't depend on anything at all
and then and not clinging to anything in the world
and and to have that experience and have that as a reference point for what's possible
it brings a lot of wisdom a lot of inspiration
probably you'll cling again probably you'll have a sense of depending on things again but you you'll have a you understand
there's a different perspective now different way of being and you'll you'll hopefully hold your
clinging hold your feeling of dependence much more lightly and you have a sense that practice is
moving beyond it to be free of all that so this is a journey
and so now we've done uh the first exercise of the sattipatana gone through with the breathing
into the refrain and now the same uh there's 12 more exercises
each with the same refrain that we just went through and um and so on monday i'll start with
the second exercise contextualizing a little bit and um and uh
and uh but we'll never lose track of the breathing i mean the guided meditations will often come back to the breathing
it's like this it's like the anchor or the foundation uh that supports this i hope
and but the other practices are also relevant and so if some of you don't care for the breathing at some point these others
might be more meaningful for you so um
thank you and i when i now we continue on monday
i'll be back at um um
irc the insight retreat center i'm teaching a retreat next week so i'll be film i'll be broadcasting from the
meditation hall there and so you'll see um you know that i'm a different location
so thank you all