so hello hello and welcome to happy hour delighted to be together
again um wherever you are in the world on this
planet earth and the only planet livable planet we have
so today being earth day i'd like to um
invite us to cultivate practice to turn towards mental kindness loving-kindness
appreciation gratitude all these different flavors um
with respect to mother earth this amazing blue planet of
ours as well as all the beings who live on it including
ourselves including this being here oh yes i'm a human being i live on this earth
this is my home it's not them they're talking about
it's me it's me it's this earth my home as i walk on the earth as i sit on the
earth as i eat my food from the earth
so so those are the reflections i like to bring in today and play around
with in our um guided meditation to honor to honor mother earth with care
appreciation and at times maybe sorrow or sadness might come up knowing
knowing how challenging the state of global warming is and and
and climate change is sorrow can come up and bringing
practice of compassion meeting sorrow our own sorrow and sadness with compassion and care
and and [Music] yeah many different practices we will
weave into tonight so appreciation joy meta compassion equanimity it will go to many
different places so are we ready to explore together dear
earthly explorers are you ready shall we shall we let's let's
let's so so with that i would like to invite you to sit
comfortably so that you can sit easily for the next 30 minutes or so and if you need to lie down
it's perfectly fine this body needs to lie down as long as you don't fall
asleep it's important for your back to be straight and upright so
let's begin let's begin landing landing in this body
arriving landing here here
here i'm here on this earth
feeling feeling our feet
on the earth might be on the floor but in lieu of the earth or sit bones
connected the chair to the cushion again in lieu of the earth
connected well rooted
as earthly beings that we are
arriving in these bodies
and turning turning our attention our awareness
inward there may be many thoughts
entanglements it's okay
nothing wrong with thinking
and for the sake of this practice we release
the thoughts right now we return to them later
and right now for the sake of this cultivation with friendliness
with a smile from our heart we say thank you not now
come back later please and we release
release trusting if they're important enough they'll come back
and we release the weight we also release the weight of our bodies
releasing releasing onto the chair the cushion
the earth supporting us always supporting us
offering our weight to gravity
and notice how your muscles your body
ah can feel opened up when you release
onto gravity hear gravity
i don't need to hold this up hold up the tension the tightness
allowing allowing the breath
just the right mixture of oxygen [Music]
nitrogen on this earth of ours
to enter this body to be received in the belly
this body knows how to breathe it knows how to receive the breath
let it receive the breath naturally
appreciatively
the gift offered a gift offered
we'll spend a few minutes as always just resting
with the sensations of the body releasing relaxing letting go
receiving the breath to calm and soothe the mind
settle the mind settle the heart
here
his thoughts arise not a problem [Music]
thank you not now smilingly turning the attention inward
it's so peaceful and delicious inward we keep mixing it up
steering it up so we can let go
ah and begin again every moment a new beginning
every moment a new arrival
not a problem
let yourself enjoy the breath
the movement of the breath
how it relaxes the body the out breath
each moment we're receiving a gift
a gift of this breath
can we receive it appreciatively
this breath
a gift from the mother of us all mother earth
this air we breathe
not to be taken for granted
in california the fire season
the air was so [Music]
polluted rich with smoke was hard to breathe
not to take clear clean breath air
for granted
can there be just a little bit of gratitude
and now i'd like to invite you
continuing to feel embodied rooted in the body
feeling yourself grounded stable
connected to the earth
to let there be appreciation
both for yourself first of all you
each of us this being who is me this earthly being
this earthly being
who is me
appreciating
oh this is my home this is this is the only home i've never i've
ever known and we'll ever know
can we extend this sense of appreciation mental friendliness
kindness to all the beings on this earth
all are siblings whether human
four-legged whether they have wings
swim in the sea
or they they crawl or slither or hop
all the beings
together with me all of us all of us interconnected
in calling this planet our home
inviting you for a moment perhaps to take on an astronaut's vision
[Music] many astronauts have said
it changes them it has changed them to see this blue planet from afar
how vulnerable
how complex how beautiful can we take on that vision we've all
seen images
to see to have this image of planet earth
our home
the home of all of us
can there be a sense of commenta kindness goodwill this is what we're doing here cultivating
cultivating this is the practice cultivating our heart
not in thinking about it but in tapping into an appreciation
a sense of care for all the beings
starting with all the beings including ourselves who call this planet
home a sense of tenderness kindness good will
and all the beings in the future those are who were born or
yet to be born the unborn who will call this planet home whether
human species or other species
it is said we don't inherit this earth from our ancestors
we do not inherit the earth from our ancestors
we borrow it from our children all the
children of all species from whom we're borrowing this earth
feeling our interconnectedness
and opening our heart to feel the tenderness
maybe some sadness arises that's okay let us sit with the sadness
let's not avoid it by thinking or getting caught up in stories let's feel
let's be open feeling the feelings
whether it's all the sense of amazement of the
interconnection we all have whether it is sadness
sorrow
for the damage mother earth
i was born
i'll let there be kindness tenderness if emotions arise can we be kind
can we allow [Music] can we love
let there be openness let it move through not fighting not resisting
not intellectualizing can there be a raw to soft this body can
it be soft the soft animal of this body
and a tender heart
appreciation appreciation for all the beings and for mother earth
as if it were a being a living breathing
sacred entity
that shows up its varieties and
it sings with joy through spring with leaves
everywhere it regenerates
nature rejuvenating regenerating
healing the complex
amazing ecosystems
very complex
just as we are an ecosystem this being who is me
with bacteria in the microbiome
different neurons
so many complex chemical processes
creating this being who is me
nature this earth too so complex
sublime
as an indigenous culture it's recognized as gaia this
earthly
being nature as a force
as a mysterious magnificent entity
can we have love can we love
mother earth
not in an extractive way but
a way of loving devoting caring
the way we would care for children
for tender leaves for tender beings
loving nature
our mother earth along with all the beings
all the ecosystems and the beings who live in the ecosystems
the ice worms that live in the tundra who knew
such richness magnificence opening our hearts with awe
with love can we care
how can we serve how can we protect what we love
what we value feel devoted to
not thinking right now about what letters you can write no not later
later but right now just tapping into a space of the heart
it's not a space of thinking [Music] it's not a space of thinking
the space of the heart let it be tender it's not a space of planning
not now with each breath just connecting to
nature right here right now this breath this body too is nature
it's connected to the earth
it is earth it is nature
and again if at any point sadness arises
with respect to nature mother earth
can we meet it can we meet it with compassion holding the sorrow
the frustration which is ours
can we hold it with care the way we would hold
a crying baby a lot of patience
they're there here here i'm here for you i'm patient resilient
loving
and here as long as it as i'm needed
knowing that our time on this earth is limited this being who is me
we're born and we will die
how can we care how can we leave this earth
better a better place a safer place a more nourishing place
for others
and again not to start thinking and planning but drop this question into your body
as if a quant drop this question into your body as a koan
as an aspiration
for the last moments of this practice period
holding yourself holding yourself with compassion with care
this earthly warm that each of us is
for whatever rose or did not arise during this practice
maybe your mind was completely distracted there was not a moment's peace
it's okay can you be kind to yourself let go
you've tried you showed up you did your best
can you have groundedness and meta love acceptance openness
in this second forget about the last 30 minutes
can you have it in this moment just this moment to accept yourself
just as you are
and to extend this kindness to all beings
to all beings in this community [Music]
all beings everywhere humans etc pushing all beings well all of us living
together on this planet and may our planet be healthy
be well made be free from the ills from the
pollution from the challenges may all beings
everywhere our planet ourselves
have ease may all beings be free
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so [Music] birthday appreciating the earth and its
denizens so i'm going to change the setting so that
you can type in chat either to me or to the group
and if you type it to everyone i'll read your name your reflection and if you just type it to me it'll be private
and bill i see your hands up please uh hi nikki
when you uh stated what the meditation is going to be about um
i i felt a lot of aversion uh in the form of anger and but underneath that fear because
this is an anxiety producing subject for me
i tried to stay with it but it was just it was hard for me to stay on track you
know but i can see the value of it i mean maybe more so because i i don't want to
do it that made maybe that's a little more reason to do it um
i'm not sure where i'm going with this i don't think i have a question just i was just expressing myself so thank you
thank you bill hold on don't mute yourself just yet um yeah thank you so much for for sharing
expressing um that a lot of anger and underneath that
fear and it's great that you have the clarity to know that and and ah just this pain of i don't want to
do this i don't want to do this and yet realizing actually because that's a sign that maybe i need to stay
with this maybe there's something here to open my heart to the pain because there's a lot of pain
so there's a lot of pain um and a lot of times when something is painful
or traumatic we are afraid or scared or angry when we push it away we
don't even turn to it and when there's even news on the radio about earth is like we just turn it off like i can't go
there it's just too hard it's just too painful right and we can't even do anything about it because we're just
blocking it off it's like not there just like it's just whereas by slowly slowly
actually attending to your own suffering to your own pain like this this is hard this is painful
and increasing your capacity to care but have equanimity by being
overwhelmed you're not helping anyone you're not helping yourself you're not helping the the causes you can support
um the awareness you can have so so i'm
i'm appreciating the um the wisdom of knowing that oh yeah actually i feel like i need to hang it
hang out here longer even it may be hard and bill you've been
doing this long enough my friend that i think you you can you are ready to gently gently
explore this territory with compassion yeah thank you
thank you thank you so much
other reflections
i see um see a couple of private messages can you complete the
mantra but i cannot solve your problems for you oh oh it's
it's not a mantra first of all it's the it's a compassion phrase so there are a lot of compassion
phrases like tonight i didn't offer any formal ones but so the compassion phrases i care for
you i care for you but i can't so solve your problems for you i can't make them go
away another reflection recently i too find myself avoiding experiences certain
radio shows podcast calls people because i fear adding to my sadness grief or anxiety i wonder if you can comment on
how to counter this tendency which limits one yeah yeah it's the
of practices i think what what supports the the balancing of that is the practice of equanimity so first is the
practice of compassion so and and again we don't go for the hundred pound weight we don't go for the
hundred pound weight you start with the 10 pound weight okay what's what's easy maybe in your practice maybe in your
daily practice you just bring a little bit of something that brings you sadness
about the earth or something else um and and
hold it with care with love again with this being with this vision of holding
your child that hurting which is you your own emotions with love with care
it's okay it's okay patience patience and through that
through that patience it can open up to equanimity because you can be here there's a sense of stability a sense of
equipoise that is built through the practice of
the through the practice of compassion
is that clear the person who asked a question you can send me a private chat
if you want i see a long chat that was sent to me while i was giving the
guided meditation which i don't read usually it can be very disturbing it distracts me so i'll look at this later
thank you um
so any other reflections you can raise your hand
okay and the person says yes clear and appreciate the answer you're welcome
thank you for your practice
yeah and pat on youtube asked practice equanimity first yes don't go in and
prepare it could be either way path we could start with compassion because that's where pain is we can start with
compassion and build and go towards equanimity or we can start with equanimity and then
build towards compassion it can work either way
yeah ram please and if you could also turn on
your camera that'd be lovely so we can actually see you
just give me a second so my question was when i used to practice meta
for when i used to think of beings that were close to me or let's say i i was able to feel that love
and kindness but today when i was thinking about now earth as a being i was not able to
resonate that feeling even though i am deeply deeply
interested in conservation and all these topics so i was
i was just thinking where did i you know go wrong yeah yeah you haven't gone wrong there's
there's not a problem so i'm so appreciative that you brought up this question so so sometimes when we practice meta we
have a feeling since there's a feeling of warmth and care connection right
and sometimes we don't have that feeling and it's okay don't think that you've
done it wrong trust that you're still planting seeds you're still planting seeds that might
flower later so later today or tomorrow the next day all of a sudden there might be a sense of tenderness you might be
walking and see trees go oh mother earth oh wow this earth like it might flower
then so it's okay don't expect results for your timetable like wait i didn't
feel the warmth i didn't feel the connection where is it patience patience patience and trust is
trust your planting seeds yes okay great great thank you so much
thank you okay all right dear friend so so um at this time we um
in at happy hour we turn to um small groups and it's just for six seven
minutes and it's where we meet other practitioners we meet other
practitioners in this space and please listen carefully to the instructions this is a very formalized
way of practicing it's not just oh go and talk amongst yourself it's not that
it'll be a group of size 3 roughly and each person is invited to share one
nugget if you have five or six nuggets just share one just share one
the next person will share one nugget or they can say pass and they can just hold kind loving
patient space for others you can do that too and then the next person says
something or they say pass and it comes to you again so you go round and round
in a spiral a few times it's not a long monologue it's just a
brief thing you share so you can have interaction and it's really it's not so much what you say you're not saying
anything to educate or impress others you're showing up with your heart with your care for yourself and for other
practitioners it's so precious these small group meetings to show up with
care how can you show up with care with your care for these fellow beings who
share the earth with you your neighbors this is the only earth we have
so can we show up with that kind of a sentiment for ourselves for each other and you can
share something about how this practice was for you tonight um
[Music] or again you can say pass again just hold it very lightly
with a lot of with a lot of ease so um so that's all i was gonna say to set it
up take care of yourself take care of each other be kind be gentle and i'm going to open the
rooms and let's go reverse alphabetical order according to your first name okay
enjoy okay the rooms are closed and we've got
oh maybe just a quick 30 seconds if there's any burning reflections or
comments you want to share something that came up in the group you can raise your hand or type it
going once going twice okay i'll stay a minute extra afterwards
so thank you all thank you earth citizens denizens for joining this
this edition of happy hour even though it might have been challenging but it's a good challenge it's it's an important
um place in our hearts and minds to to open up to to turn our attention to so that
we can hold with compassion with equanimity so that we can stay we can stay instead
of running away from from the challenges and also rejoice we need to balance the sadness with joy
because there's still so much to love it's not all lost it's not all lost so
please enjoy the sunshine enjoy the earth enjoy the greens enjoy the
fresh air the birds please please balance balance the sadness the grief
with the joy with the delight because what is precious is worth protecting so
so thank you all for your practice may all of us everywhere all beings
everywhere be free and well
[Music] thank you