foreign hello yeah looks good
okay I think we're good
oh so welcome I thank you for
coming today so this is
yes please so this is the uh our second class in
the series of the Four Noble Truth
um last week we talked about the first Noble Truth and today we're gonna go the
second um therefore no one truths are kind of
the the basis the
what we really need to understand and and see clearly our own practice our
experience our inner life our life in community
there is this a sentencing in the sutah so it's a sariputa to achieve disciple
of the Buddha he was talking to a group of monks and he said this
friends just as the footprint of any living being that walks can be placed
within an elephant's footprint so too all wholesome States can be
included in the Four Noble Truths for it's kind of from there we we start
and we go back and forth we may go deeper in other teachings and
things like that but the four noble truths remain kind of the of the basis
and you're listening to them now and maybe in the future to listen to them
again and something else comes up it's incredibly rich is a very
deep teaching it sounds very simple but there's a lot a lot to to reflect a lot
to learn a lot to understand in them so I would like to
to share some of the teachings from Sylvia Burstein the way she talks about
the four noble truths so she says we talked last week about the first
novel truth about Duca the suffering bit annoyed being stressed anxiety all
kinds different kinds of suffering different levels let's say of suffering
and she says life is challenging for all beings
everybody our bodies relationships all our life
circumstances are fragile and are changing we are accommodating all the time we
just yeah that's kind of the reality of Duke in
her words the second Noble Truth The Castle the cause of suffering is the mind's a
struggle in responding to challenge and we'll go deeper on that one today
the third Noble Truth the end of suffering a mind that doesn't struggle a
mind that is at peace that is is possible and therefore Noble Truth is kind of the
medicine what is it that we need to do to be free of suffering and that is the
the Eightfold Path so just with this short introduction
maybe we could start a meditation thank you Tanya
everybody okay if I take my mask off
that was great I just uh I'm just going to repeat those am I can
you make me a teeny bit louder I think how's the volume you guys is it loud enough
okay so
life is challenging for all our bodies relationships
all of life circumstances are fragile and changing
we are always accommodating
a second Noble Truth the cause of suffering
is the mind's struggle in response
to challenge so feel your body
will go into a meditation fill your feet on the floor
maybe lift your shoulders and roll them back a bit
make sure your arms our hands are resting comfortably
with the next inhale let your body Rise Up Lift Up stretch up
feeling yourself rising up to the present moment
to meet right here just this just the space
this body in this moment with whatever emotions and thoughts
and Sensations that are happening here
so with this idea that we're always accommodating
and that life is challenging
see if you can bring to mind some small way
that life is challenging for you right now small
so on a scale of one to ten a one or a two maybe a three not a ten
so there's the challenge
and then there's our struggle to be with that challenge
see if you can feel into the struggle
and as you hold that struggle just notice the way
that you might struggle a bit in response to this challenge
and see if you can feel that struggle get a feel for the pattern the pull
three patterns I notice in myself are a pattern of
puddling or sinking in sort of like a
this is hard and every bit of me just falls into this is hard
that's one pattern another pattern is
this is hard and there's a refusal
or a distancing feeling so it's not puddling it's maybe armoring in response
there's a distancing or a repressing energy
these are two extremes that embody that struggle with whatever
it is that is difficult and there's everything in between
so just with that as a reference see if you can't
stay with the same struggle or maybe choose another one again
three or under on the trigger scale not big
tolerable and be curious
trying to bring to mind that struggle like I have a broken leg
just in that simplicity and then there's the reaction to it the
oh and that means I can't drive the car
or I can't believe maybe I'll never be able to walk again
hike run that's the struggle with the challenge
let's see if you can't feel into the energy the dynamic
of how you're relating
to one of the many little struggles in your life
and if the struggle starts to become a floor or a five or above on the
trigger scale
and sort of Imagine bowing to it and saying
I'll come back to you I need to choose something little right now maybe open your eyes
maybe put your hand on your heart
this is hard
and notice that in a way sometimes the hard stuff is very magnetic
the mind just really wants to stay focused on it so just see that magnetic energy that
pull that draw the way it keeps pulling us back feel that
witness that without being it
and see if you can't soften just like in a warm bath softening
around all of this that's happening in your mind no need to bring up anything else I
think you've probably done well enough just focus on
how to be soft
around it
breathe in softness and breathe out with softness
breathe in caring
and breathe out caring
and let's do a little body scan starting at the top of the head
just above the head
just first standing with him
alongside the body taking it in
the sense of caring and Wise Eyes
and imagine a warm light
maybe golden like warm honey
imagine that the way that you are seeing and feeling the body is like warm honey
sweet gentle
sort of let it the awareness slowly
Glide down from the top of the head
down through the forehead and the side back of the head and the ears
the eyes cheekbones and jaw
ah taking some breaths down
and Chin the neck sides of the neck back of the neck
tops of the shoulders collarbone
down the front of your chest
down the back body
just taking your time
scanning touching with this warmth the body
moving as slowly as you need
down the arms
and with each exhale just invite a little bit of softening a little bit of
relaxing
and the belly and the lower back
the hips and the bottom
the thighs knees
shins and calves
ankles and feet
breathing into the whole body now feeling it expand with the inhale
contract with the exhale
and feeling the Earth under your feet a sense of groundedness
so being soft and relaxed but here
upright
and imagine in your mind's eye
what it would be like to stand tall and relaxed
next to whatever is difficult in your life
maybe imagine what it's like when somebody puts their hand on your shoulder or
just stands beside you with support
in this caring but upright way
in the sense that nothing needs to happen right now just being
and this way with whatever's going on is all that's
needed
breathing in
and breathing out
feeling the flow
the changing nature of your experience moment to moment
changing nature of sound
just allowing whatever comes up in your meditation now to come up
just witnessing nothing needs to happen
just holding this calm and upright presence in the middle of it all
letting whatever comes into the Mind move through in its own way
imagine there's nothing sticky nothing no magnetic energy
it just can slide through
nothing to hold on to
and then when you notice some holding some tension
ah hmm
what am I trying to hold on to
a Feeling a thought
the way I wish it were
a memory can it be held on to
maybe it becomes transparent dissolves
and feeling the breath and the body right here
foreign
the feet
the support of the Earth
and when you notice tension or stress in the body
in the mind in the heart
see if you can't stand at its side witnessing
with kindness and confidence
strength I can be with this too
right here right now in this moment I don't need to do anything
just be aware
and it's okay if it's not okay
here
everything's okay
it's done this moment
even the weird honking horn I'm just fine
so where does something I have alarm wow it's like a flat tire or something
again just noticing if there's any tension building up in the body
it just kind of keeps coming back in my body
the breathing in and inviting it to soften
inviting a little letting go with exhale
and over and over again just softening
allowing
and meeting standing up to meet whatever is happening
in the last few minutes of the meditation together
maybe just check in and notice reflect on your journey
you've all had a very different Journey than everybody beside you but you've all
been on a journey the different things that have come up The Feelings the energy in your body may
have shifted and changed see if you can't just sort of get a
feeling for where you've gone journeyed
what's different
when you think back to the difficulty you first thought of
the challenge
notice how it is to think of it now
[Music]
so we'll take a couple of minutes just to um reflect on how was that for you
anybody have anything that they're willing to say or share there's a mic there and a mic there
great
I I think I got hello Tanya hello Sandra good evening thank you hi Richard I was
very I was too comfortable obviously I never thought I would doze off so audibly but um it was um I have to say I
thought from last week's class to this week regarding the tone of voice that you had mentioned like what tone are you
bringing in I I am more mindful of that and I think throughout well throughout
my journey and or my meditation journey I find that I've been needing to I've been wanting to sit longer in the
morning as opposed to the evening because it helps me start my day because I feel
like my days are I'm just trying to get ready for the day and so
so that's been so that that's this sitting was nice and um
even with the car horn you know that's happened before at IMC and
just trying not to get bothered by whatever so but but that's yes thank you
thank you and Rose yeah great
thank you thank you for having us here
also thank you for your comment that all of us had a different Journey
and we are all here meeting at the same point um
there is uh some um poetry um
which I will try to make like a close English I mean essentially a couplet
um make a approximate English translation of that
the two hearts are beating but the
music is the same two hearts are beating but the music is the same the sound is
the same um and the
um um the the songs are different but thus
but the instrument is the same yeah so when you talk about the journeys are
different but the instrument is the same yeah so I just wanted to present that
thank you thank you
um thanks so much for the the meditation I was surprised at the
when you invited us to pick something that was just like a one or two and then I think the invitation was to like let
go of the struggle a little bit and wow I was so surprised how good it felt like a little struggle
and then also it was about my students that I work with and then just like
what came to me was just like I can let go and just trust that they're gonna figure out how to do this and that's so
much um it's just so much more loving than the other way that it could be of like this
like holding on we have to do it so anyway so thank you that felt really
good I also had this little thought pop in um about my family and I thought my gosh
there's such like worry carriers if that makes sense oh I love that term yeah and I love them all the pieces but um
but it's such a thing in my family to worry so anyway maybe when that comes up
that invitation to let go of the struggle could be a really good just a good place to go
thank you Sandra
Okay so repeating from the second from Simply
upper stains the cause of suffering is the mind's struggle in response to challenge
thank you for the meditation I couldn't find the two I went to 10
immediately like oh my gosh and I think it's the
the reaction to the struggle of the Mind is what they in Pali is called
tanha that literally translates as a thirst
is also translated as hunger desire craving
um thirst works very well for me now in this moment of my life
and and as you you'll find the
translation that relate that really expresses where you are how it feels for you
so we have the challenge the minor struggles and then that thirst
The Challenge and and in the three of them is kind of the way things are
really we cannot control the challenges in our life there's they're going to happen no matter what
the way our minds work link because we're just humans is we're going to
struggle and it can take different forms and also like that desire for things to
be well for we want to be we want to live in with ease at peace so it's that
that thirst that hunger in a way is kind of natural
um Gregory Kramer says that the the clinging the uh the grasping
is what makes the bridge between that thirst and the suffering
so in reality those three like okay that's the way things are that's the way
your brain works that's part of our human nature isn't it but is that what
comes after that that clinging that I have to fix this this needs to be well
and we can see it in many aspects of our life that's really what brings the
suffering um I for me it works like to break things in
pieces it's just I'm a scientist so I guess it's just the way my mind tends to
go um but yeah and
and what we want to be at ease to be well there's really
nothing wrong with it the problem is that
I personally am I'm a doer and a fixer every time my mind's a struggle I want
it to be like I that's my default to go
so we cling to things I wanted it to be perfect I wanted to be well I do I I
don't want to feel bad I don't want to be uncomfortable I don't want to be called things like that and we also
cling to what we do to achieve that
we cling we grasp even grasp the fear that we're
going to lose it when we get it and we even cling to the fear of not getting it
so it's a little like a convoluted so I'm gonna give you an
example I was thinking of how can I convey so I'm going to bring an example
of my life and maybe you'll find something in yours
when for me going to college it was very difficult we were in very tough
economical situation so it was it was very hard I had to work and all that
and then finally I came to this country and I was able to find a
good job and found economical stability and I wanted to make sure that my kids
didn't need to go through the same struggle that I had to so I worked 24 7.
I burn myself to exhaustion and but it's like yeah because uh I need
to make it right for them they they so they don't need to go through the same so that in itself that that I wanted to
achieve I think it wasn't two parties and eight I think we won to provide the best
but it became kind of um an addiction for me so I work it hard
and I work it on the weekends and I work it late at night and but yeah I have to do this so like I got
addicted to to the way I was trying to achieve that and the fear of
not being able to provide oh gosh like oh it's my motivation I
kind of let go of that oh and then the fear of not not being
enough not not achieving enough because then it becomes very convoluted and it
is not only one thing we tend to mix a lot of things I'm a woman and I need to show that I'm I need the validation I
need to show them that I can do this isn't it so I mean maybe a little too extreme but I
I can see like all these faces of what is clinging
um in in that part of my life
and then probably you you're gonna find your your own examples as well but I
think again it's not what we want that is wrong it's not it's the way we our attitude
how it becomes an obsession almost and um
we don't notice it very easily we because that's the way things are and
that there are much simpler things and we just simply don't notice
um like when I I got here earlier and for some reason the thermostat was 72
Fahrenheit it was like oh my God she's so hot like I started going where is how
is it I was trying to remember how to like wow this is what is it that we're
gonna talk today so we see it it's every day we see it in
the Small Things um so yeah it was kind of interesting
so the that thirst that we feel that um
the Buddha gave us three main big groups the first one is the craving the desire
for sense pleasure the next one is hunger for being for
becoming and the third one hunger for non-being for non-becoming
um so I'm gonna try to More by example I want to make sure I'm I have the the
right time all right um so decipher sends pleasure who
doesn't love a nice meal who doesn't love a nice song looking at a beautiful landscape and
piece of art a pleasurable touch like a nice warm shower
a pleasurable State of Mind feeling content and relaxed yeah who doesn't
love a nice relaxing meditation so it's kind of that sense pleasure
and again it's not in itself what the thing that we decide that is wrong that
is that we shouldn't be enjoying it or this sinful or anything like that it's
more how we relate to it that is gonna bring us that I want it I want and I
don't want to let it go and that's what bring us the suffering
um the I think something that's quite interesting is the desires is
usually the way we engage with the world we come here because we want to listen
we want to I don't know cultivate our spiritual life we when I come to this
community where we feel okay welcome so yeah that's uh that's kind of the way we
we go around in the world but is how are we gonna do it that is
um that really bring us the the suffering in itself
and then what what is also in in with their desires for some sense pleasure is the
aversion that we have for pain it's like if you have some work to be
done in your mouth at the dentist like that you're thinking for a week that oh gosh
that's gonna hurt like it it's also a little bit what's involved into that part of clinging
and now for the Hunger for being on for non-being rather than going into
um too much talk about it I'm maybe give you some some examples
so you get to work and you have been
assigned a certain parking spot because you're an employee of the month and then you arrive at there's somebody parked
there oh what the lack of respect and we're
goodness they they don't know that I am the employee of the month like that
desire to be seen to be known isn't it or
um you want people the pain of our personalities isn't it you're very good
at making jokes and things like that and somebody is not laughing at you joke at the comment that you just did like oh
wow that I I'm that person like I you need to laugh at my jokes or things like
that and even like we just had the elections in
November and you you think very you have very strong position about that
proposition and you voted against it and rallied your friends and all that and
the proposition passed wow like all these my opinion my
political beliefs my religions belief we really is and we identify so much with
those one that I found quite interesting first
one I when I came to this country is how some people feel offended when I
said happy holidays and not Merry Christmas for example he he was taken very personally it took
me a little while to figure that that one and then on the other end is
this desire for not being seen like that team building event and that
your all the group is invited and oh gosh it cannot end soon enough like you
don't like I I don't like those I mean I I end up enjoying it at the end but it
takes me like a week of preparation there's something about all those things I just don't want to be seen in that
context we don't want to be seen please Earth open up and eat me up is so is it
in a way is and I mean you can read more about it but I thought that maybe that
give us a little bit of a sense sometimes we want to be seen and it's part of our nature isn't it we
we live in communities we belong in communities we want not belong and
sometimes we don't want to um yeah sometimes we just don't want to be
we want to be there I want to be mindful of times
okay whatever yeah so what I wanted to see sometimes
when we talk about the clinging and thirst and the hunger and
all that it sounds like like addictions toward desires it sounds like very major
isn't it but it's not we see it every day it's in our daily
life is I don't like this chair I wish I had I
don't know what it's it's in it's the little things that sometimes
can make a difference in a in a daily life in a daily day in our life
um last week I was going the conference for work and I wanted to see the talks
that day and our water heater broke so and so when they fix it and then they
had to shut off the gas and then the area here the heating system in the
house just died so I couldn't go to my it was like oh my
gosh she's like that does can I bring my practice into that and I think I heard
them okay I was like okay I wasn't too miserable but it's in our daily life
it's every day is in traffic is coming here is going home all it's yeah
so don't don't think that because okay maybe I don't have those addictions but
think little think in the Small Things what bothered you this morning where is
where can I see those ideas those that clingy dancers what is
it that is coming from and what is the suffering it's not big big suffering still some I'm very annoyed by it and
that doesn't feel good so I'll stop there
thank you thank you so um one of the things I was thinking
about was um the what is clinging you know when it's
more subtle what does it feel like or when it's around something that's still sort of pleasant
right oh I'm gonna buy that thing and I you know
push the purchase button right and or I'm thinking about what I want to
buy right and it's that that you know there can be something you like and then
there's this like and you can oh it's pretty it's nice and then there's something that comes in
that's a little like sneaky and it it that kind of um puts you into
an automatic pilot mode I feel like I get disconnected from my
present moment when I get in caught in that kind of wanting something so there's there's the
hunger right for a piece of you know peanut butter rice cake or whatever it
is and I'm hungry and I need to eat and that's fine and that's great but
there's something then if I get clinging to it I get fixated on it it's like I the word that comes to mind
is like being in an elevator right like I'm no longer really connected to my experience I'm more like on a ride
does that make sense there's a way that we can get kind of
hot in it and we get disconnected actually from ourselves and from the present moment and even from the peanut
butter rice cake we might be eating it but we're not really tasting it because we're in this
craving right so um
I wanted to sort of you know talk about it in that subtle way too and how it
disconnects us you know when we get into that clinging we're we're grabbing onto
something and really there's nothing we can grab onto truthfully right we can't really grab make anything
permanent or stay the way it is or become what we wanted it will or it won't it's it's
sort of its own thing but there's that struggle that we get caught in that
brings us into relationship with the world that's actually really quite
disconnected from the present moment the world ourselves
so noticing what it is whether it's that
tension or tightness right in our bodies when we're clinging it's that's a huge
cue to me but it also is a sense of disconnection that is acute to me that
I'm clinging so that's inherent
that's inherent in the clinging so getting to know what how it manifests
for you when you are grabbing on um
so that's that's like get really curious about it in the subtle little Way start
to study it I think we all know pretty much the big ways I really want that job
damn it that was my car you know what it whatever it is like there's the big ways
we know that right we get upset about it and but the little ways are subtle and
Insidious and they can just permeate our lives and pull us away with our
my phone's not out right but this constant hold to the phone to the phone and then
there you know it's like oh I'm lost again right it's that word I'm using today is the elevator
feeling you get in an elevator you push the button and you're on the ride right and you're stuck but it's kind of like
that enveloping feeling of um being consumed by something and then you get
out you know okay oh okay I'm off you know so get to know what that is for
you and these small small ways not just the big ways
be curious curiosity is your is your friend when it comes to working with
duka with clinging it's the you know understanding the
cause of why we're suffering that clinging we've got to be curious what am
I clinging to it might be that I'm clinging to the idea that I'm going to feel better because I don't feel very
good for some reason or I'm anxious or I'm afraid right or I don't like myself today
so that's that part we need to sort of
you know get curious about and soften around be gentle with yourself
you're human and you know Sandra said this but it it is this is the condition
we wouldn't survive we wouldn't be alive if we weren't hungry
it's part of life all life is consuming all the time little amiibos you know
amoebas you know everything is consuming and that's that's part of it but how do
we be conscious consumers of life how do we be awake
and not try and get more than we need take what we
don't deserve or you know get in this battle
so a gentleness a softness a curiosity around it
seeing that it's normal don't make yourself a bad person
around us and um
really pay attention to the times your desire leads to well-being
versus pain or more difficulty that's a huge cue
to you to notice when we're kind of getting caught in an unskillful Direction versus a wholesome Direction
but but we've gotta stay awake long enough we'll get on the elevator we're in the
space we get off and then we're off to the next thing but don't run away so quick
pause check in oh how did I feel when I got on the elevator do I even remember
and what's what am I how am I feeling now do I feel better do I feel more hungry do I feel
disconcerted what you know what what's happening for me here before I run off to the next thing because it it is
relentless you know this
consuming energy so let me um
see if there's anything else I want to say
oh yeah I think that I'll just say moving away from suffering and toward liberation
requires us to let go of unskillful actions
unskillful thoughts and unskillful intentions
what helps us let go is seeing that they cause us suffering
that really helps us let go to see how it's hurting where it leads us
taking the path toward freedom requires us to take responsibility for
our thoughts attitudes and behaviors it's really helpful to ask is this
serving or harming myself or others is it serving or harming
whom in the last moment before we moved to
small group kind of conversation anything that I could say that would be
clarifying or helpful was I clear
yes and Rose just find a mic please
it's on so like the moment where you talked about Tanya the elevator like how
do you know when you're con because I know I'm I'm stepping into that elevator multiple times a day yes indeed you know
but I'd like to I'd like to get out you know yes
yeah so um I think that the the
so you're asking how do I know I'm getting on the elevator essentially like you're asking for how
do I stop myself from getting on the elevator yeah well I think for me it's starting
to wake up when I'm probably already on the elevator or getting off the elevator it starts late or not at the beginning
that's what I would say for me not all the time but over time it's waking up
and then pausing when it's happened giving myself enough space to the mind
to consciously acknowledge oh I just did it again
you know okay how does that feel okay and then in in when I have the energy to
even go like okay can I go back another step what happened right before I I got
caught what was going on for me and I may or may not have an answer but being curious
about it actually starting to teach the mind to pay attention
and so we start to grow our interest and our mind starts to just tune into these
things and then we start to combine and couple oh wanting this with the pain
afterwards because we've consciously connected the two does that make sense okay thank you
thank you that um
we we have habits we have patterns and yes we we have to
catch ourselves I don't know how many times when we're leaving the elevator but at least we're
catching ourselves and then maybe we start identifying like oh I tend to do this so in a way kind of
start making mental no like a little pasta that when I get there I know I
need to pay attention it's like right now um holiday season shopping
be very aware like you like you go to the websites
where you're gonna find your gifts it's like um order early because Transportation
blah blah I mean the world out there wants you to be
very thirsty and very clingy so okay so
I need to pay attention when these things happen and we need to get caught many times before we notice that's
that's the way it is that's the only way we learn oh yeah I like that
um when you were talking and something that you know a lot of people can relate to you're talking about like taking out
your phone and being kind of like addicted to it and stuff like that and it made me think a lot about like
just triggers and how we like deal with triggers and not necessarily like it could be
like big triggers or even just like little things that trigger us down this like negative rabbit hole
um I guess my question is around like in some ways you know the advice is like
we should remove those triggers so like don't use social media for example is like the obvious one that we hear a lot
or um I mean sometimes the triggers can even come from like books or like talking to certain people or like
watching certain TV shows and stuff and um sometimes it makes me also wonder like
is removing all triggers like I mean obviously in certain cases where
there's more serious effects involved like PTSD and things like that is it I would say a different scenario but for
like smaller triggers is removing them helpful or is like
being able to not go down the negative rabbit hole when you see that trigger
does that serve you better or is there like no right answer I don't
know yeah do you mind if I answer this one all right yeah it's a really important question
um so there are times but this call this
does call for discernment which is what you're pointing to there are times when removing the
triggers are possible and necessary but we can't do that with everything
it's not possible and and that one of the things that I
had sort of suggested in the guided meditation was
you know can we just stand next to something the trigger whatever it is can we
imagine being alongside it and not collapsing and not
rigidifying either and you know just sort of that's
something to practice and that's what we're doing in meditation we're we're cultivating the capacity to
to be uninvolved to allow things to come up and go and
move through us and just like realize actually it will all kind of come through and go on if I just can sit here
I'll be okay but it's getting up and running off and fighting with this and that and trying to do this and that that
gets us in trouble so discernment is necessary we can't get
rid of all the triggers in fact triggers aren't you know triggers are really just associations
and our brain is an association organ prediction organ it just that's what it
we've got this you know library of experiences that our brain pulls on to
associate and so it's not possible but let me say one more quick thing here
which is we can work on also adding what we're associating we can add things like
if we have a trigger we can start to build other experiences around that
resourcing experiences positive experiences empowerment experiences recognizing oh I can sit next to this
and it's not going to kill me kind of thing okay
so oh I'm sorry oh you talk about this clinginess and
the um the elevator uh experience
um have you come across people who
um like in that same sense about who try
to be like God like or
um like I can give an example that let's say who are always kind of in this
clinginess or elevator experience they are always measuring
that this person uh did a sashtang pranam to me sashtang
is essentially all it um you know
body parts touching the ground that is a way of like bowing to someone
whereas she or he did not even touch my feet or whatever that is like a one form
of salutation um so uh and like uh so like I said this she or he does not
love or respect or whatever whereas this person so constantly like you know in
this like how I view this this is like you know in the massive pyramid that's
like that low self-esteem like they're constantly evaluating in
this elevator sense or you know I I don't have this respect I don't have this that the
eating thing or thirst or whatever the constantly looking for that
satisfying that have I presented my question or the I think you're talking
about somebody who's hungry for being seen or feeling better or they're
they're constantly comparing and and judging yeah and yeah and it's like like
that you know it's like the uncontrollable tongue which is like
uncontrollable you know the speech speech oh
there are many ways that those things happen
like always trying to be very well dressed and very nice hair and the last
I mean there are many ways that we can express that and I think is
what we're trying to do ourselves we can do the work ourselves isn't it we
cannot do the work for others um and uh and it's hard to notice it it's
there's a lot of conditioning that has gone into that so I think the best we can do is do it
for ourselves [Music] try to teach it to other people I think
you need to be there at the right moment probably will happen it could happen but
um yeah it's like the person that doesn't want to be seen that wants to be invisible
and maybe I don't know so in some way I think we all may be
able to relate to that there's been moments in our life where we we just don't want to be there we don't want to
be put on the spot we want to be invisible oh so but it's hard to notice it it takes
courage to do it um yeah
that does that make sense yeah yeah well I mean it's essentially yeah I mean I'm
officially hold your makeup in smaller circles you know it kind of when we are
operating in a very small circle of people let's say we are like I mean we
are I guess we don't have a choice of
uh not being far away and which means that so I have to be I
have been in Bali so I am more Superior to this person I have been in seeing
this pyramid so I'm super well traveled and whatnot so it's
uh it's I just wanted to make that presentation I mean because I am unable
to uh comprehend sometimes that that thirst or
hunger to or that you know that
Godly status you know that it's it's really a
clinging to an identity you know it's just we all it's whether you want to be
dressed up Identity or you want to be smarter than other people's Identity or you want to be better because you've
traveled more places like it's all identity those are it's very and we're trying to
make ourselves create some self that's Elusive and vulnerable so it doesn't
really work so we but we keep trying right and so it sounds like somebody's you're describing is very uncomfortable
person and trying to make themselves better or trying to make other people feel bad to make themselves feel better
I'm not sure which way it is but it's it's uh clinging to an identity right
yeah and and also when we satisfy those
desires when we achieve those things the satisfaction the the well-being lasts a
little bit is not it's not the happiness it's just a
moment and when that clinging it's um
it keeps kind of reinforcing itself because we need more of it more of it
and more of it to be well so yeah
so should we yeah let's go to the well I think we need to uh
consider maybe maybe you want to choose you know one of these things that we can
just discuss it here yeah maybe because yeah we can't really do the breakout groups exactly okay so what I would like
you to invite so yeah you know that's a good idea Richard he just suggested having everybody
Circle up for this part yeah do you guys mind coming and we'll just do kind of yeah
this day off the Blue Line because that's the camera just yeah there you go
thank you all right so I'm gonna Maybe
read some things like ask you invite you to think of something in your life and see
what comes up and perhaps something that we didn't touch too much was
um about the satisfaction that we get out of it so
so think of a moment and try to maybe something recent today this week
um so you so now you can see in retrospect
that wow that was a moment where I felt that that thirst that hunger that
craving for something and you were able to get it you got what
you wanted things weren't on the way you wanted it like that's the way you cut it
so I would invite you to think about um how did it feel to get it
and did it last and perhaps did it open you for more it
didn't make you thirstier for more so that's that's one thing
and also so not to be so focused on the first part of the clinging Parts maybe
you can also think of a moment even a small thing where you were able to
let go to let things be to be content to
what was happening and how does that feel
even a small thing how does it feel how does how does it feel in the body
and like if you could contrast both
what do you see
and see so let's let's take those two if anybody would like to
anybody have an example I could share a little one I'll just to help you get started if you need the
help so I I need new glasses
and um you know my prescription changed right and um so
you know if you wear glasses it's like oh my God what frame what color what you
know the wheat you know plastic or the nose things all these things right
and so um I I last pair of glasses this pair have been okay I don't love them but
they're okay you know and so it's like and I've gotten a few pair that I really didn't like so I was like okay I gotta
really try a lot of different glasses here and then I ordered some try on at home glasses and I ordered some of the I
actually ordered them and I didn't like them and I took them back and
so all this like energy and trying on looking well taking pictures what do you
think of this one and then I was like you know I have this old pair of glasses
that I really like a lot and from when I finally settled on just
using that frame and getting new glasses it was like oh
that was contentment I was like such a relief rather than that seeking
the trying to find the right pair so I don't blow it again right and end up
with glasses I hate and hurt my nose or whatever but it but why didn't I think why why wasn't that the first choice I
don't know but and then I got there thank God
hmm anybody else wanna share something
great
um I don't know if I have an example oh sorry I don't know if I have an example for both um never mind but one thing that
um so recently I've been taking a break from working and I'm taking some classes one of them I'm taking is in Ceramics
which is something I love doing and is like um
it's been great and I definitely have felt like a new feeling of like I'm
excited to like wake up at 7am and go to class and on a weekday which is like I
don't think I've ever felt that way before um and so that's been great but I I think it's
something about what we were saying where it's like we have the clinging even when it's something good and I find myself sometimes like in
class and like this is what I've been looking forward to like all weekend and I'm here and then I just get into this mode of
like I need to like do everything and I need to like like you know get as much as I can done and I
need to like make sure I finish all these pieces and then I'm like oh my God like stop breathing normally and I'm
trying to get everything done on time even though it's like something I really enjoy doing yeah
um and I like don't let myself take a break and so uh I've been trying to be better about
that and like stop and be like I don't have to get all this done right now and I should like make sure I'm
actually enjoying what I came here to do um so yeah
I'm full of both you you notice and and he's like I need to enjoy this so in a
way it's like letting go so yeah that's that's very good thank you
yeah as you were talking I didn't I had that in you know in the airport they
have those flat escalators where you know you get on it's like being on that
thing right you're pulling your you know you're getting really fast and is that what you're describing right maybe
you're in this doing this great thing but somehow you're like crabbing reaching trying to get next next and you
lose it's like going by so fast you're not even there yeah you're not even enjoying
it anymore yeah because the mind this is where the mind that's why I feel like the elevator
escalator thing it's like we stop being here we get in this head we're imagining
things we we're imagining what we want and then we're relating to that instead
of what's this this yeah
it makes me think too of um the frame of mind so she stopped working in the
company because she wanted to go more into cultivating her spiritual life and such and it was so confusing for her
because um like she was saying it's like when the work we do is we are so overwhelmed
all the time than when we have a break like we all we only know overwhelm or
vacation we don't know anything in between so she would say like she didn't know
what to like I have time I I don't know it was very yeah
yeah and then like okay no little by little I mean it took time but yeah
it we we need to relearn to enjoy
maybe that was like also yeah that's also a good example we're like yeah when I left I was like I was not having a great time at the company I was working
at and I was like once I quit my life is going to be amazing like all my anxiety is going to go away and I'm just gonna
live like the best life ever and at least like temporarily you know and then when I quit I was like why do I feel
worse than when I did before because it's like now I have more mental space to worry about right all the other
things in my life that I was like probably not thinking much about when I was working so yeah
um I don't know if I understood the question correctly but I think the way I'm trying to interpret it is
um not taking so much um like catastrophizing of things and just noticing that there's no permanence
whether things are really horrible or really great you know that will come to an end and I'm like you know sort of
transfer to one one extreme or the other and just trying to be okay with going
through the motions and knowing that it'll change either for the worst or you know for the best again and just trying
to be able to like navigate that more more regularly and sort of contently
yeah it's to avoid the the addiction for it I mean the desire the one they have
in it and okay it's calm you got it enjoy it let it go it's gone like no not
fall into that cycle on that more and more like yeah so
sometimes I'll notice myself sort of going down like a spiral of catastrophe oh this is so horrible now now I'll lose
my job and my car will break down I'll end up on the streets and homeless and or something like that but I'm trying to
maybe more so find a way to if I have learned that behavior or mental way of thinking how can I become my best
cheerleader instead of being my my worst critic and trying to cultivate that more
into not having such a clinginess to either you know something catastrophizing or even something great
that is going wonderful yeah and I think it takes courage for us to face those
things because it probably is coming from something that happened maybe when
we were children's or something like that isn't it like okay why is that like
I know my catastrophizing I know like but it's taken me a long time to even
see in it like like why am I going like what where is this coming from and
getting curious what Tanya was saying curiosity and but with that kindness
with that softness isn't it where where is this coming from and like naming the dragon so it loses
its power in a way
I'm not sure it's on
you talk about the enjoying each moment or taking time to have be with each
moment and since you talked about that you are a scientist I also wanted to
talk about this concept of time dilation or sour like sometimes people even in
poetry they talk about you know time seems to have Frozen which means like if
people are having a good time then they say that you know it's like the time has dilated our time has just
stopped and they just want to be in that moment so I
um can give two examples um one let's say going back to the
mountains uh like Swiss Alps which reminds me very much of you know James
James spawn 007 and you know you're like Shelton and Lotter brunon and those
places and just I mean time I mean last the session before last I had also talked
about like someone like Gregory Peck of Indian Cinema uh like there are some pictures from
that though those places so when I have traveled to those places the time just
seems to have stopped I I like Zurich and burn and all those places you know
the uh I I still can feel that joy and happiness that I had
um and like in the immediate present uh I have to make some presentation for
some teaching some music talk about some music so
every small breaks I have so I I listen to some pieces
I will prepare some um and then you know maybe make some notes or something
ah for me those times you know they they just stop then and there it's like the time has
stopped that those uh pieces I'm enjoying so much that uh whether now or in in my sleep or
you know I'm I'm kind of enjoying that even if that moment of
presenting to my audience has not yet come but even while I'm being prepared
I am enjoying that moment so that comment about being happy in every
moment or essentially um dilating the
time even if the time is like only you know short duration
but it can be prolonged that it can be like eons or Aegis or whatever
so to to bring us to that conscious that is uh I don't know if I am ah that
is how I I want us to feel and I I try
to view things that way so I've given two examples one of like
you know the being in the mountains and
I I guess I would just say this uh you know it's a very philosophical
question but also time is a concept and there are ways of stepping out of
conceptual time to not be relating to life in that same
framework in the practice I think it's possible to have experiences but the main thing is
that I think the the the absence of clinging
the absence of clinging is a spacious feeling
everything there's so much generosity in it everything can just be
we don't want the tree to be closer or different or there's there's just so
much generosity and and so that also has that timelessness feeling so I don't
know how else to answer you but I think it's a great thing to question our relationship with time and and notice
how we're relating to what's happening affects our sense of time
does that feel like enough I think we need to shift it's actually about time to end so
um time to do our dedication of Merit yeah
so um so coming here together with definitely
I we hope that is of benefit for you but also to keep in mind that what we do
here benefit the people around us our families our
friends the people that we cross in the street we we get out and like we're thinking
about these things that has being here today has repercussions
and um it's not only we we don't only do it
because it's nice but really to maybe share this with other beings with all
beings um and a practice that Tania introduced me
to is we we forget it's easy to forget the the
pain the suffering that is out there isn't it and sometimes if we can bring
some of it into our minds and maybe offer the benefit of the
practice today to those people to those causes to those
countries to whatever it is that can open your heart
so I don't think we're gonna circulate the microphone today but maybe bring it in
in your mind and bring it to your heart and May
the benefit of our practice today be shared
with every being that everybody every being is free of
suffering and its causes and that every being may live
in his and peace thank you for your practice today
[Music]
I'm happy to try and see if I can answer more