greetings greetings friends greetings and welcome
it's lovely to spend this moment in time with all of you practicing cultivating together
and it's lovely to see your hellos greetings warming the space with
your meta with your heart from each other
[Music] so so today
we continue to engage and continue to engage
right here continue to engage with the practice
and with considering exploring the teachings of khan
as an empowerment in each moment
experience predilections what we pass down the stream
to ourselves in this life who we are becoming every moment when we are becoming
everyone we are making ourselves to be
[Music] so let us begin
by meditating together so i'd like to invite you to
arrive in your meditation posture
allowing your back allowing your back to be straight
allowing there to be a sense of integrity in your posture
and inviting your body inviting the muscles of your body to rest in this
moment to relax
to arrive to arrive here
in this moment in time
allowing awareness to be bright
as if awareness is waking up bright in each moment
expansive like the sun the sun in your heart the sun in your
body shining awareness this amazing beautiful
mysterious powerful
capacity of our heart and mind awareness
expansive through our bodies
aware of how this body's sitting [Music] breathing [Music]
ah effortlessly it's just here just like the sun shines
as if effortlessly it's there it's just there you don't
have to do much
similarly
similarly the sun of awareness internally spacious expansive
effortless knowing knowing this body knowing this
heart knowing this mind
each breath received in the body
and the sun of awareness shines
on the sensations of each breath
each sensation each thought each sound
each emotion the sun of awareness shines
warmly smilingly knowing everything
without exclusion exception knowing everything appreciatively
openly
not holding back its knowing or its warmth from any object
that is known in the space of heart and mind
whether it's tightness clinging
pain sadness it's all known pray the son of awareness
with warmth intertwined
goodness intertwined in the knowing
effortlessly engaged effortlessly
and with a sense of receptive interest
not judgment but receptive interest dropping in this question this inquiry
into your heart how am i engaging
with this moment
with whatever object is arising in this moment
what is the flavor of engagement
is it with greed wanting more attachment
is it with hatred i don't want this to be here
is it with confusion lost
with anger with fear
just knowing how are you engaging how is the quality
of engagement
with whatever is arising the object is less important
it can be the best news or the worst news it doesn't matter it could be pain or pleasure
what is the quality of engagement
relationships
to whatever is arising
is the son of knowing imbued
tinged with equanimity and kindness
or something else whatever object is being known right now
sensations thoughts sounds whatever
letting the rays of the sun of awareness
touch know the goodness
of having shown up having practice this morning as we bring this sit to a close
with reactions of appreciation and kindness gratitude for
yourself for the sangha for the causes and conditions
and with generosity both letting go
of whatever was difficult challenging
distracted sleepy it's okay it's all right
you've done your best and through generosity to all beings
sharing sharing our goodness our collected goodness
offering it as if we let the sun
of our goodness shine offering it throughout the world may all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere be well
and benefit from my intentions
from my orientation towards wisdom towards goodness kindness
may all beings everywhere including myself
in all parts of the world
be well be free
[Music]
hello and greetings dear sangha
so
so karma karma karma as as action
karma's action as these three aspects of action that
we've been discussing the past couple of days the
intention around it the leading edge what is done the action of the
thought speech and body and the trailing edge what is left behind what is created what is
what is made what is made so today i'd like to talk about um
what andrew olenski terms where the action is where the action is
so so there are um
two aspects to every moment's experience
one is the content what you're aware of it could be a sound
a thought a sensation in fact in buddhism there are
six um sense doors as you know you know they're the five senses the usual five
senses that we have with with smell and taste and touch and and hearing and seeing those
five and then the sixth sense door is the door of the mind so in any moment
you can choose to imagine
a beach you can bring to mind uh a
maybe a music that you love and play it in in your mind again it's a sound but you can play
it or you can um have a thought of say a happy thought or a sad thought you can
conjure it up so in the mind door everything can be chosen to be played up
so so there is the object there is the object of awareness there are many
objects either physical objects or or seeing hearing tasting objects of the
mind which again the mind can access all of those five objects even remembering a touch a sense of sensation you can
remember it you can recreate it in the mind or
which is pretty wild right it's pretty awesome being human like we can do all
this right recreating all these objects quote on objects of
knowing objects of awareness in the mind door in the sixth door
i thought this was pretty cool when i first learned about the sixth
mind door a sixth door sixth uh door uh in in um
or this in in buddhism whereas you know in western psychology we only have the
the five anyway so in every moment's experience there is the object of
awareness right which could be through the six cent stores the six cent stores
and then there is what our emotional response is
towards this object of awareness how we are relating to it how we are engaging with
it right so so as discussed as i just mentioned the
um objects of awareness um
they could be recreated in any moment in the my door
and and our mind body apparatus can really you know lurch around from
one object of awareness to another object of awareness
very quickly um sometimes it will sometimes seemingly
not it will right you're thinking about this and then maybe you're meditating you come back and then you're thinking
about something else and just so so these two both the object of
awareness and the way we relate to it the way we
relate to it our attitude or our reaction etc
it's called in in the in the buddhist psychology
this is called sankharas or formations this is called form rupa
the objects are called rupa with the five aggregates so those who are familiar with the teaching
of the five aggregates and if you're not don't don't be overwhelmed or scared like what five
aggregates wait a minute i'm just explaining them to you so stay with me stay with me
form is just the object of awareness and and uh also known
in pali rupa and then sankharas sankaras are the
aggregates is the aggregate of the way or the mental formations or also called
formations the way we relate the way we engage we react
in each moment and each moment in each moment these shift and change
even though we have this sense of permanence every moment it's a refreshing it's a refreshing because it can change every
moment right so so the sankhara is these these reactions these formations these mental
formations these the ways we react can shift and change every moment
so so what is interesting is that um
you know if we were perhaps an automaton a computer my background being in in
artificial intelligence you know just knowing just knowing an object is one thing right knowing but the sankhara is
the way we react the way we respond the way we
relate to an object in fact that's where the action is it's
that's where that is um the way we engaged within with an
object because just knowing an object oh okay all right yeah this is you know this is a pen okay this is just a pen
um but oh i i love this pen i don't want anyone to
take it like ah or oh i hate this pen this reminds me of blah blah blah that's a you know
difficult day the way we engage the way the sun car is the way we are responding
engaging with an object either physical object object of the
mind that is what shapes and forms the next moment's experience
that's how that's how we are shaped and formed
so a skillful healthy uh
way of relating to an object it shifts it forms us
into a more skillful into more a kinder a less deluded
um more equanimous person being in the next
moment so
so we could say that perhaps the harm that comes or the harm that we cause
ourselves isn't so much from the objects that we relate to again physical objects
i'm talking about the objects of the six cent stores not so much from the objects but the way
we relate to the experience the way we engage with the experience that's how
that's where the karma is shaped is through our experience
is how our next moment's experience is shaped and our next moments of
experience and who we become and who we are and how we show up in the world
so this is quite profound actually to see this in
buddhist psychology this teaching of karma which is this this way we engage and how
we engage that shapes and forms who we become who we are
because that's also what um western psychology and neuroscience
also not surprisingly
supports suggests you know it's not so much the moment's experience but but
those emotional memories those emotions that really fix
uh something in place some memory of something
becomes fixed in place because of the emotional engagement because of the
emotion that has been ignited that has come alive as we have engaged with
something that has occurred with an object in the six sense doors and you know this to be true
for your own experience maybe some moment of experience became really
etched in your memory in your heart and minds at the moment of experience in the past because
of the emotional response you had to it because of the anger you had or because of the love you
had or because of whatever happened and that really felt like a formative moment
and in fact in in um in a.i in neural networks that's called
one-shot learning when there is something so um uh
so important so so you know a pattern that's so um we give it so much weight
um that it becomes oh it's a one-shot learning is really shapes and forms
uh the shapes of the neural networks but again coming back to humans
so so the way we engage really that's where uh that's where the action is the moment
of anger becomes and and also it shapes the uh it also grows maybe a moment of
anger is a thought and then it becomes a striking blow or becomes or becomes a a um
or becomes a hurtful comment or becomes a nasty thought and then becomes an action etc etc and then they grow
so
so who we are who we are and and actually andrew odensky says
this beautifully who we are and what world we inhabit
actually consists of these series of of the series of these emotional responses
unfolding within us
so it's actually just these series of emotional responses
is who we are and we keep conditioning them for the future
so how we hold ourselves right now in this moment how are you holding yourself
right now in this moment how are you relating
how are you relating to the contents of your experience
how are we holding ourselves in this moment
right now is it with greed hatred delusion is it with the opposite generosity
with love and with wisdom how we hold ourselves right now right
here right here people right now is the key
to the next moment so it's not about what we engage with it's
how we engage with with the what it's the how
it's the how and that is so powerful we have so much
power to shift and change the way we engage in this moment in this moment
so then sitting on the cushion is important of course
is when we really learn and observe and and get to see our reactions with detail and yet
the whole day our entire life is our practice because every moment we
are shaping and forming our responses our reactions our karma
so time has come to an end so i wish you a full day a
beautiful a a wise a wholesome karma forming
day of practice thank you so much for being here for practicing for your own
benefit and the benefit of all beings whose lives yours touches thank you and see you
tomorrow be well