hello everyone and welcome to our time together our 30-minute
meditation and um
the theme for today is tranquility to sit with a tranquil body and mind
i think of it as a ability to sit quietly without being in
conflict with anything without being disturbed by anything
and it's a remarkable state to experience
because it can feel like one of the most
noteworthy remarkable forms of spiritual health
maybe even sometimes mental health even physical health at times
to sit with their whole system at ease
undisturbed but alert clear
it involves learning not to be preoccupied with the little thoughts we
have the buddha and talking about his own practice talked about not
running after the little thoughts i love this idea of little thoughts
they can seem so big our thoughts so huge and monumental and important
and maybe they're just little thoughts maybe thoughts by themselves are just floating
ideas and memories and plans and
projected fears into the future so to sit quietly and tranquilly
to relax all that can relax while all that can be alert
can be present and clear so
not easy to accomplish but the buddha said that
the nourishment the food for tranquility is tranquility itself
so in other words the ability to recognize is maybe at first just a hint
of tranquility and then build on that
uh feel the tranquility as an alternative to preoccupation an alternative to
being involved with the thoughts that are distressing or disturbing or
um react reactive to what's happening here
so assuming a meditation posture
and maybe wiggling your body swaying back and forth a bit
swaying forward and back straightening up and bending a little bit
until you find a posture that for you
represents a balance of tranquility
and alertness tranquility and attentiveness
and attentiveness alertness that's embodied
aware through the body
and then to
lower your gaze and letting your eyes be cool
ever feel any kind of coolness quiet that's possible in their eyes as they
rest in their sockets not looking at anything in particular
and then to gently close your eyes
and gently maybe not a full deep breath but a half
deep breath gently tranquilly breathing in more fully
and you might try at the top of the in-breath to gently hold your breath for a moment
or two so that when you do
begin the exhale it can feel like a letting go
a releasing letting go into a quiet state
and you might with a deeper taking deeper breaths pause for a moment or two at the end of
the exhale so that when you do inhale it's a
welcome attentiveness welcoming
the feeling of attentiveness alertness awareness of breathing
and here we have this wonderful the alternation between
releasing relaxing on the exhale
and aware and alert on the inhale
letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale
soften the body
a global softening
on the inhale as if the body expands the whole body expands and gets
larger beyond the boundaries of the body even
you know the exhale is softening settling
releasing
softening the belly
softening in the chest
releasing the shoulders
releasing relaxing the muscles of the face
and quieting calming the energy of thinking
relaxing the thinking muscle
and now see if you can find within your body
someplace that there is a bit of calm or tranquility
it could be in the torso the arms and hands and the legs
in the head in the back anywhere where there's some feeling of tranquility
calmness
it doesn't have to be dramatic just the place in your body where it's
most where it's calmest
and then see if you can breathe through
that area of calm breathe with it
there's a way almost as if you're gently blowing on a small fire
so that it grows
adjusting your mind so the mind is calmer
quieter
maybe even a stillness of mind as you're aware of whatever
stillness tranquility
peace there might be in your body in your heart
so
whatever is not come for you see if you can let that recede to the
background of awareness
not to dismiss it or to ignore it entirely or
but to give time to your capacity for being calm
that also it's important for that also to exist
for you in a strong way and so to feel into
calmness tranquility
when you exhale letting go of your thoughts
relaxing the holdings in your body
letting go into the place within that is still
quiet
so
underneath your thinking maybe you'll find a place of calm and
tranquility breathe with that place
breathe through it breathe out of it
let tranquility be the flavor
of your meditation
so
you might try having tranquility
come the feeling of it be at the center
almost like that's who you are if you're identified with your thinking
more as who you are switch to whatever degree of calm or
tranquility stillness you might have within
let that be who you are let that be the center
around which everything else orbits
taking refuge in the calm
and see if you can [Music] let your eyes be calm and
tranquil cool still
either with your eyes closed or if it's most tranquil to open the eyes gently
maybe gazing down 45 degrees let the eyes open slightly
and with a calm gaze relax gaze
be aware of the world around you the extended world out beyond your
where you are people in your lives people in your communities
people far away people you don't know gaze upon it all calmly
peacefully for a few moments not disturbed
not in conflict just a calm regard
as if calmness tranquility his medicine
for an agitated world
that your calmness his medicine for an agitated world
all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may your tranquility
be a way that you support the happiness safety peace and freedom of others
may all beings be a beam
[Music]
thank you
foreign
uh
hmm
so here we are
and the topic is tranquility and in the theme of the week of
different ways of experiencing experiencing our
body it's possible to have have the body
be felt as a tranquil body a peaceful body
and uh this is a remarkable feeling of health of well-being
that everything is kind of right here now
it's a experience of the body that comes when we're not disturbed by anything in
conflict with anything and we're not spitting out thoughts and
ideas it's a quieting of the mind
of the mental activities that's used to relate to the body
and because these different bodies i'm talking about have a lot to do with the state of the mind the activity of the
mind so i've seen diagrams of the brain kind of um
kind of diagrams where they're showing what parts of the brain are most biggest or most active or something
and uh and they show that um people who do the same activity over and
over again that part of the brain grows i don't know if it physically gets bigger or just more activated
so that someone who is um you know their whole profession maybe is
typing there's been a whole day typing that somehow the the brain centers having to do with the
fingers grow bigger and and so these brain centers that they're
involved with different parts of our body can grow and shrink depending on the
usage in which we have it and so as the activity of that center grows
then there's more maybe orientation to feel and sense and experience and know
that part of the body but if those mental activities if the mental
activities the mental centers get quiet and calm then the ways in which the mind
constructs remembers the body fades away as well
so you know we can have a very strong body image of some part of our body
the you know i recently i i clipped my fingernails and
and so i might be self-conscious that i didn't clip my fingernails just right maybe it's a little bit uneven and here
i am with a few hundred people uh you know watching me and maybe noticing my
fingernails and so my whole world starts thinking about my fingernails and so that fingernail part of the
center of the brain maybe gets probably other centers too becomes bigger more activated
and so in my mind i kind of have an image of my fingernails my fingers
um and i'm just you know oriented around the image of it and what the impact that has on other people
and so my my i have a i have a i'm operating under an image of
fingernails but if i let my mind become quiet and calm
that part of the mind that's busy and activated to think about fingernails to imagine what they look like
to to be concerned about you know their shape and their smoothness or whatever
that's all god turned quiet and in my experience
fingernails kind of disappear from awareness you know i sit here quietly meditating
with my breathing meditating my torso grounded feeling centered quiet
and the and that for 30 minutes i wouldn't even think about my fingernails then this in a certain kind of way
in experience they don't exist of course they exist but i'm not experiencing them
they fade away from from attention in the same way
as the mind gets quieter and quieter the body begins to recede from its defined
definitions from its image that we carry with us subconsciously we carry images and ideas
and projections and priorities about the body we're in conflict with the body we're
adjusting it we're reacting to the pain and pleasure in the body there's a lot of kind of sub
liminal subconscious and conscious activity going on in the brain
in relationship to this body that we have as that
those mental activities quiet down um the body begins to feel more calm and
peaceful it's almost like the puppeteer in the brain has taken a vacation and is not
pulling and tugging and directing and and awakening and and
being no no no nosy into all the different things going on you know something's going on in the
body the body is just left radically alone and this uh
not obstructing not interfering not activating not thinking about the body
leaving the body alone in a nice meditative way allows the body
to move towards a kind of health the body has tremendous uh kind of
movement towards homeostasis thesis uh to harmony to subtleness to release
the body itself just wants to relax wants to relax the tensions that are being held there
and and so as the mind gets quieter
our relationship to the body shifts and change and then the way we experience the body
changes and the body can have a very refreshing peaceful feeling to it
the tranquility can be a feeling of suffused tranquility
through the body or suffused coolness or refreshment that exists somehow nice
peaceful um it's a more peaceful state than the bliss body the joy body that we
talked about yesterday that um because that's still a little bit uh
activated compared to now that quiets down as well and um
and there's not exactly any place we can you know anything solid or too much
solid in the body it's more like a glow of peace glow of tranquility
of refreshment and it's a it's a very different way of experiencing ourselves
it's a tremendous gift to the body when we can you know no longer have the mind
preoccupied by it or reacting to it or defining it or having an image of it
some people find that the edges of the body begin to dissolve and there's no clear sense of the
boundary between the body and the air around it because the boundary itself that's the
shape of our body the boundary we have is part of the mental construct the ideas the mind does
that that based a lot of memory but if we so drop into the feeling body
without all the ideas and reactivities the feeling body moves towards
subtleness and peacefulness and calm it only gets activated if the puppeteer
pulls the strings if the if the cook stirs the pot
and if we're not pulling strings or stirring the pot the body can go quiet and peaceful
and it's a um remarkable to feel the
the um tremendous value the wealth in a sense that uh comes with this very deep sense
of peace and tranquility it's um
and uh from the vantage point of that state of tranquility and peace calm
it's possible to have a clear sense that many of the ordinary pursuits we
have in our life um especially if they involve tension or
anxiety or or ambition or greed
are so much less valuable the richness the well the
peacefulness the richness the texture of this tranquility and peace and calm that can
exist this doesn't mean that we have to kind of stay stuck and always be tranquil and
calm but it does mean that we have a lesson a dramatic kind of contrast between
different ways of being and we can begin appreciating how the puppeteer works
how the mind works in activating the body and prioritizing the body or
defining the body you're concerned with the body in such a way that um
you know that the turn quilt tranquility is lost
so um [Music]
it's a beautiful to really marvelous thing to have this
[Music] the the shift in the body from the karmic body to the joy body tranquility body
and where the experience of the body the energies the sensations the
these qualities of well-being and of tranquility seem to emerge from the inside out
and are not dependent on the ways that we relate to the body from
the outside in we have individuals families societies have
tremendous painful attitudes beliefs
behavior uh relationship to the outer body kind of how it looks
in terms of size and shape and color and race and
and all kinds of things that um people can have a lot of suffering over
but the body's experience of itself from the inside out from what emerges peacefully when we're
not tamping it down or constricting it with all these
outside-in kind of concerns and preoccupations and obstacles
what comes and emerges what flows what can be there from the inside out
is it can feel like it's really independent of the outside in concerns
if there's a liberation from outside in there's a liberation from the societal
pressures on the body and judgments and ideas just to have the body have its own
experience from the inside out where its own flow of energy's flow of sensations
can settle and open to joy and to tranquility is a powerful lesson
in freedom powerful lesson in an alternative way of living that's
not outside in it's not caught up in thoughts and ideas and images of
how the body is and what should be so tranquil body
so you might over this day see what you can do as through the day
to let the body be more tranquil maybe it's how you sit in a chair
you can sit in a chair in a way that the body is more settled and easier to relax
and in a tranquil way it's it's not necessarily
slouching in a chair i don't know if that gives us the most tranquility
um but where do you feel the most calm and subtle that we're settled and rooted and grounded
and as you walk as you do some work as you talk as you drive
look and look and see how you can do all these things with some modicum of calm or peace or
tranquility and see what you learn in the process and
and certainly what you can learn about what takes you away from the tranquility but maybe for this exercise today
what you learn about the benefits of living a tranquil life
so thank you very much and
and i look forward to continuing this series tomorrow