so uh the one announcement i want to make before we
i start the talk is that today's the last day then that we're going to do the fundraising for save the
children for their work with the refugees from the war in ukraine and it's kind of not very nice that so far
we've raised directly seventy three thousand dollars which is a lot of money for us the
community and some people have donated uh inspired by this and donated directly to save the
children rather than through us for their own reasons so uh
it's i think it's kind of powerful when a community comes together and does something like this and you see
the aggregate you see the coming together of shared
goodwill intentions desires to make a difference so thank you all those of you who've
contributed and i think the treasurer will kind of close
down the everything tonight and and send save the children to check
so um so the topic for today's talk
it can seem like some people roll their eyes maybe when i give the title
but hopefully by the end your eyes will have settled down and that is
meditating for peace meditating for peace
and so many people for centuries have associated meditation in the buddhist
context with the goal of liberation often for personal liberation
one of the remarkable things is that there can be other motivations
for doing the same practice in other words the same practice doing
the same thing can function for different purposes even purposes you didn't attend
and one of the purposes of meditation is to contribute to a peaceful world
and it turns out that if you dedicate your practice to liberation and dedicated to
your practice to your meditation practice to supporting a peaceful world you pretty
much do the same practice it's not that different except for the motivation
and uh but it makes a difference the motivation you do it and so and it's also possible that
dedication for liberation can remain
and and it can join with the motivation to contribute to peaceful world
and the benefit of that is there might give a wonderful and healthy and stress-free perhaps
sense of urgency for the meditation practice like the practice is important it's
valuable it gives it like and right now with the war in the ukraine
the wars in yemen and
it's different places in the world myanmar all kinds of horrible things the world's
doing but for many of us i think that what's happening in ukraine is so horrific and
so dramatic and seeing it so clearly with images and everything
that uh you know it's really something that and also it represents for many people
a real turning point in human history and our situation here things are
changing in such a big way it's going to affect the whole globe in a way that some of the other wars may don't affect it so dramatically
the whole the whole the whole globe
and so if we're meditating anyway
meditate for peace and how is it that meditating can
contribute to peace in the wider world that's the topic for today
and so one of the things is that uh what we learn how we how we're transformed
and what we learn about ourselves changes us into a person who can then
uh approach the conflicts in the world the suffering of the world in a more useful way
the very things we learn about being present for ourselves and plumbing to the depths of ourselves in meditation
is the is transforms us so that we can bring some of the same benefits into the world
so there's a number of things that meditation can do or is it it's about in our tradition
one is to be a witness for what is true the second is to heal what needs to be
healed the third is to liberate what can be liberated
and the fourth is to cultivate the best in us the best qualities within
us best best of our character and those those four things are being
cultivated when we meditate and it's powerful to do this
as we do it for ourselves and learn what it means to do it for ourselves
those very same things can be offered in how we attend to a present for the world
we can be a witness for the world witness of what's true
we can be a healer for what needs to be healed we can be
liberate help liberate what needs to be liberated and we can cultivate the best qualities
that are needed for this world so how does this work for in
meditation and so we part a huge part of what mindfulness
is is being honest but i like the expression of being a witness to what is true because it has
two qualities first is that um
we're you know we're trying to see what's really true here for ourselves in ourselves
and sometimes what's true about ourselves is not exemplary
sometimes it's not even things we want to share with other people because we feel embarrassed or worse
sometimes what's true for ourselves something we don't even want to admit for ourselves
or we have trouble understanding it or seeing it the truth of it because we don't know how to be a witness
so the other aspects of being a witness for the truth is witnessing and one of the things we're doing in
this practice is learning to be a a clear
calm open available witness to what's there
to be a witness before we're a judger to be a witness before we're a fixer
to be a witness before we're an escaper getting away from it all
that we have cultivating the ability to be present and witness even the most difficult
things that humans can needs to see sometimes and we're doing that with ourselves
now some of you might have completely might be saints and so maybe that's what you get to
witness but for most people there are parts of ourselves that are not necessarily what
we're most proud of and difficult challenging
and so part of meditation is to learn to be a witness to what is hard for us to
witness to witness how we're attached to witness how we're afraid to witness howard
have caught in the grip of desires or preferences
judgments how we operate with hostility we're all saints beautiful calm and peaceful
until the unexpected happens and then it triggers all kinds of
frustrations and angers and things these poor computers that some they've
been recipients of so much frustration and anger some people like i want to throw them across the room you
know but you know but to learn to stay keep stay calm and work
with it so uh to be to see what's going on to be
a witness in ourselves which means to witness all those things the anger the frustration the desires the fears the
the judgments and to be able to witness it in a way that we're not automatically approving
it not automatically participating in it we're kind of stepping back and being
the witness of it it's a powerful thing to witness
and there's something healing about witnessing it to say it could be honestly seeming
space in room thought this is what's happening and for some people what we get what
we're witnessing is the inner wars some people live with all kinds of conflict within themselves
so people live with sides of themselves parts of themselves that they don't want to admit don't want
to accept they want to push away they want to deny they're angry at hostile even towards part of who they
are and uh and don't even want to talk to those parts or relate to them
maybe because they we grew up and thinking we're always supposed to be strong and so there's parts of us that are weak
maybe it's because uh parts of ourselves uh uh is uh
you know is uh afraid and we're we don't wanna accept the part that's afraid and tender and vulnerable
maybe uh you know there's parts of ourselves that
we want to deny or we feel like is wrong or or maybe there's parts of ourselves that
is that that is from which we've been hurt in the past and we don't want to ever look at that
again we don't want to admit that we're hurt and so sometimes there's these inner
wars or two sides of a person even and that so to be a witness to that war
to be witness to that conflict sometimes uh
it's uh you know just it's not so much like we're split but sometimes it's just like you know we're horrified or upset
or embarrassed by parts of who we are in this mindfulness practice we're
trying to show up to be a witness and be honest oh this is this is a truth
there's inner conflict there's inner challenge of who i am i'm not kind and calm and reflective
about what's happening for me i'm actually trying to avoid it or trying to push it
away or repress it or deny it and uh
and you know it's certainly not something i would admit to other people so we sit in meditation to be a witness
the good the bad and the ugly to really see and it can be hard to to
to accept the possibility of just witnessing because we're supposed to fix we're supposed to
be different we can't we can't just if we if we just witness it it's like that means i have to admit it or i'm making
room for what shouldn't be but slowly we're learning
to discover to trust that it's it's actually quite powerful and useful to be
a witness to see the truth witness to the truth though this is what's happening
and learn to overcome or to recognize all the ways in which we avoid the truth
so that we can become a witness of the truth those don't things don't get in the way
and then there's healing what needs to be healed so sometimes this divides within us
it's not so much a matter of making what making what we don't like about ourselves to go away
but when there's a war divide or split within us is to heal that
bring bring bring together bring and bring into our hearts in a deep way
the things about ourselves that are difficult and challenging to hold it kindly to open to it
the heart that knows what to do the heart the inner life knows how to
unfold and heal itself if we create the conditions for it to heal
or we break the conditions that help it heal we bring kindness and compassion and love
we bring honesty honesty is powerful just more truth and really really say it
we bring uh making amends sometimes we have to kind
of do something only by doing not just the meditation sometimes by doing it does something have a chance to
be healed maybe we have to apologize to people maybe we need to
engage in the world in a way that informs the heart
that there's a new we're under new management so something can begin to relax and just
heal sometimes there has to be expressions of gratitude
for what was there's a beautiful powerful for me story
i've told this many times now i'd like to tell it again when i was a growing up
in los angeles we get the los angeles times and periodically in the 1960s there would be
this little article in the newspaper about uh japanese soldiers from world war ii
who were still fighting world war ii uh in 1960s because they had been sent into the
jungles in the philippines by their commanders to be kind of guerrilla fighters or something and so they were told to stay in there
and fight the war until we come and get you the war ended but they weren't no one
came to get them and so they continued living there dutifully
and they were stealing chickens from local farmers somehow they managed to make do for so i think the last one was
like 25 years later and uh and
so then they were found and then brought back to japan
the story that i've been told about how they were brought back to japan that's what's so significant
is that uh the japanese would bring out a very senior military officer still alive from
world war ii who'd put on his best uniform and maybe the samurai sword as
symbolic and would walk to the jungle in japanese calling out for the soldier to come out
when the soldier came out the first thing that the officer would do was to do this deep
balance that they do in japan and offer gratitude thank you for your service to
the mother country i'm here to bring you back they put them on the they go together on a boat they
had to go back to japan just before the
soldier was going to get off the boat to step onto japanese soil the officer would say again thank you so
much for your great service to the country and then maybe with a lower voice would say
and by the way the war is over
for some of us the wars we're fighting are long over they've continued from childhood
and what's significant about this story is the great is the gratitude
sometimes the wars we've been fighting the struggles we're against and the ways we're you know fighting against
ourselves even were ways to try to manage to survive
in a horrific issue so situations growing up and we're survived we're here and maybe
that was needed that's what's what that's how we managed
maybe there would have been better ways to do it but as a child you didn't know what it
was and you this is kind of kept you alive and so this idea that we have these
so-called you know unfortunate unhealthy sides of ourselves that we don't like or is difficult or embarrassing
who knows why they're there maybe they were an attempt to try to take care of ourselves at some point probably it was
so maybe before it can be let go or put to rest to express gratitude thank you
and once the thank you has happened imagine that thanking your fear or thanking your
greed or thinking your anger what a different relationship
appreciating that this was a attempt to try to take care of yourself
and then reminding yourself oh by the way the war is over
it's okay so that's an example of healing
and the connection between truth and healing is quite important in california now there's a council a state
age state created a council called the truth and healing council
that is a start i think i don't have started i think in the last few months that it's going to go for two years
two or three years uh just similar i think to what the truth and recon conciliation council in
south africa did but with the indigenous people of california the native americans
there's never been a time when the state with its important role
that is going to really take in the truth of what happened to the native americans in the state which was
horrific it was kind of genocide and uh
and uh and to really hear it take it in and then heal
it's interesting that the word is not reconciliation but healing
i'm not sure why they chose that but it's maybe he has a different does something different
and so here you know so there's now a meeting you can go to those meetings they're online and
as a state kind of gathering information hearing the truth in preparation for some kind of healing
so so if we as we learn to be a witness for the truth in ourselves
then there can be healing in ourselves as we learn to be a witness for
ourselves we can learn to be a witness for what goes on in the world
if we can be a witness what goes on in the world we can maybe contribute to the healing of the
world we need people to be witnesses of it so
you know as some of us are figuring out how much to learn about
what goes on in ukraine what to look at and what to take in
part of what we're doing is being a witness for it it's important that the world has witnesses for this that we
don't deny it or don't overlook it or don't go asleep
it's very important for people to know the truth of it
to bear witness because without that there can't be any healing there's not going to be any healing it's not going to be any movement in a in a good
direction at some point how much can we bear being a witness
how do we bear witness and so the best qualities of who we are are summoned in that witnessing
we don't get despair we don't despair we don't get angry we don't get you know all these other things that might get in
the way of a deeper full or productive healing
witnessing i'd like to suggest that that's one of the things we're learning through
meditation as we witness ourselves how do we witness the truth of ourselves
so that we don't succumb to more anger more conflict more fear more
hostility all these things we're more overwhelmed and so we're
developing this muscle of being a witness in ourselves we're learning about how what goes on inside of us and what gets
in the way and so we're ready when those when that
what happens in the world happens that we can be a witness
i think it's so important and then to liberate what needs to be liberated
so we learned how to do it in ourselves we learn where we're holding on tight where we're attached
where we cling where we resist in some deep way where the heart is contracted or it is
made dense and small and we learn to open it we learn to free it
we learn to let go in some deep full way so there's breathing room for this heart
of ours breathing for the mind so there's space for the good qualities
inside of us to flow part of the paradox is that a lot of the
paradox it's the more
we are attached the less space there is
for the best qualities in us to grow and develop
the more we've let go of attachment the more space there is more breathing room
for the best qualities we have inside have to grow so to liberate
to learn to be truthful to recognize not just what wants to be
healed but a deeper place is to recognize where liberation
is to like recognize where we're stuck
and uh some of this more you know some of the more deeper places some are difficult
things to see because some of the most deep seated attachments we have
are not seen on the surface mind the surface of our life we have to that's one of the functions of meditation is to
really get quiet enough to see the depth of what's happening that's overshadowed by you know a lot of
discursive thoughts and ideas and reactivity
as we learn in ourselves more and more with liberation is
then we can appreciate that other people have that capacity too
and in some ways it'll break your heart even more than more than seeing war
is to see how this wonderful profound capacity of the human
heart gets squashed by war
gets lost in the pain and the fear and they could go on for generations
the effect of war now there can be some healing
but to really for people to discover the best possible form of happiness and
well-being that can only happen when we're free of our attachments
work and really kind of make that hard and difficult to be a witness not only for what's
difficult in the world but to be a witness for the possibility for people to be happy
the possibility that what's beautiful and best in them to come forth to be a witness for the capacity of
people to start becoming free both politically and you know societally
but also free in their hearts i think something in people's hearts
maybe by osmosis or subconsciously resonates when there's people who know something
about liberation and they can be a witness to that possibility capacity in our world
so to liberate what needs to be liberated in a place like ukraine
there's not going to be any deep or very little deep liberation of the heart
without supporting this country to become liberated from the oppression of russia
they're losing their freedom there and so i think that the dedication of
coming out of meditation is to appreciate that yes we have to kind of support these people
to become free and where all the freedom is
you know is it only with the russians but is there other places but to appreciate liberation
and then the fourth part of meditation is to let the best qualities of who we are come forth to grow and cultivate and
and expand it's remarkable what our hearts are capable of
love of all forms what a great world would be if we let all the different flavors 32 flavors of love
grow in us kindness good will
care compassion friendliness
appreciation taking delight in other people respect
you know there's all these words that i associate with love and uh to let those grow and develop
generosity wisdom peace
non-reactivity as we learn this for ourselves
let this grow in ourselves then we become a carrier of that into
the world and we become a you know it's kind of like contagious
and whether you have a mask on or not it's contagious the uh
and so to be able to come into the world oriented around these good qualities
if we don't do that then there's very little hope for the world we need people who are
demonstrating the possibility of meeting even the most horrific things
free of hostility free of
the greed of self-protections i'll just take care of myself and not other people
but to come with this beautiful capacity for love and care and support for others
to appreciate that maybe we live in this world in mutuality
cooperatively the world is a cooperative place earth nature societies
are cooperative enterprises and so how do we live cooperatively
how do we let the whole cooperative function well and completely what do we
contribute how do we support those of us who can the welfare and happiness of others
so this is my attempt to say that maybe it's healthy for to have a sense
of uh appropriate urgency
around doing you if you're meditating already in any way anyway that's what we do
please continue but maybe you can add
a important rich valuable motivation and understanding
that the meditation is you're not just doing it for yourself but that
at the same time as you're doing this deep practice for liberation for yourself maybe
you can also do it for the welfare and happiness of the world to support this world that's also
challenged and there's an urgency to do that
not to put you not not not for you to hurry through your meditation because it's urgency that way but rather
but rather not a hurry but rather to give a kind of wonderful
ballast or wonderful seriousness wonderful weight
to the practice so that you're like i'm going to do this this is important
and so you don't so easily wander off into daydreams or wonder often into
you know doing sudoku problems in your head maybe
but you kind of you're really there with some gravitas some sense of this is important
this is where and to meditate for the world so this way
we can meditate for peace
so we have a wonderful practice i hope that it will serve all of us
to be able to contribute to the welfare of this world that needs
a lot of help let's be the helpers for it all
let's help not hinder hinder what this world needs
so thank you very much and uh
you know the usual format has been to end at the old days 10 45 and
the youtube time ended right around now so 10 30.
so um but if some of you here and i could try to look at the chat if some of you would like to ask any
questions or make any comments you're welcome to do it
it's kind of nice to hear from the community now that we're together and
so you and if you could say your name when you uh
start then we could also get us sense richer sense of ourselves
your voice will go on youtube unless you yeah
um yeah i didn't know it was going to be on youtube but anyway um my question i'm yolanna
and my question is when you witness
the fear or the worry
what happened to the emotions i mean i have a lot of emotions
you just shut them down while witnessing you know the fear you
witness them you make room for them you don't act on them you don't
pick them up and think about them and reinforce them but that's where learning to be a
witness is you want to see at all it's almost like you can step back
and not live in the emotions not live in the thoughts but you almost like step back and see oh this is
these are emotions look at this this is chaotic this is and uh and learn the art of stepping
back so the seeing the witnessing
is not entangled in what we see
so what you're saying is witness the emotions too okay yes
thank you and uh one of the one of one of the ways of understanding it with fear
is to when we witness fear we're helping the fear feel safe
because fear is kind of if we're attacking fear trying to get rid of it and have some idea it shouldn't be there
and i should be better i've been meditating for years i should not supposed to have fear and this is an embarrassment to the buddhist world
then you know the poor fears is going to feel terrible and what we're trying to do is to help
just to witness it oh it's fear in a way that the fear finally feels safe
okay it can just be there it's not it fear doesn't have to be afraid
okay great thank you yes
hi i have a question exactly about witnessing certain
brains i would say certain experiences have created a fear-written brain
a fear dominated brain yes right
and in the witness scene because sometimes a fear-dominated brain
will continue to bring up again and again really fearful
experiences right and in the witnessing of that
i have a fear that the neurology of the fear
and the same would be with anger that ultimately the neurology
of witnessing and experiencing something that's coming up so quick so
frequently that it will amplify yeah
and i you know there i have a certain concern about that but you know there are certain brains that
are so prone to that and i'm just wondering mindfulness in that kind of context so one of the core
principles of the dharma is to be mindful of the effect the consequence
of what we do so if the consequence of being a mindfulness bringing mindfulness or
bringing witnessing to our fear produces continually produces more fear
that that's not that is not helpful and then so that but it's useful to know
that so part of the benefit of mindfulness is see oh this is what happens when i am present for fear i
get more afraid i shut down i this stuff kind of happens so once you see that's happening
that is then you have the information you need which tells you i need to find a
different way and uh and so in meditation some people switch their
meditation practice to do loving kindness or compassion meditation some people find it useful to do a very
uh emphasize a lot of body meditation just rest in their body rather than in the
emotion and to find a neutral place in the body where they can kind of stay with and be
with some people find that uh they need to do something very different sometimes
there's you know there's there's a we have a wealth of uh of uh what's called trauma therapy now
and so which is the working was very issue that uh it's too hard for some people to
just be present for their own fear and a hurt and pain
and so there's all these techniques or ways of working with it indirectly or or not indirectly but
wisely that is not really the place not really the strength of
buddhism buddhism historically helps people a lot of
people work through trauma but more than just maybe
a lot of other things but sometimes we need extra help extra support and so specialists who know
about it and to find out how to work with work through it and all that is uh
and uh and nowadays there's a lot of things to try besides meditation when when when
the repeated contact with fear produces panic or more fear or shutting down
yeah thank you and uh and also but also sometimes one-on-one conversations with a meditation teacher
can sometimes show how mindfulness or how you know what you can do that's
different how to practice mindfulness differently so it can be helpful so
you know so it's all these things are possible but this answer your question
yes i my intention was to bring up this to the light in the in today
in today's talk yeah thank you
hi my name is molly um i have found that uh people are so vocal
uh about their opinions in the media and
so strong-willed that they almost make it sound like it's factual so
sometimes i feel that it's a struggle not to be judgmental
it might help for today to distinguish being judgmental from being
from being evaluative or judge judgmental versus
recognition so it's possible to recognize what someone's doing or suspect what
someone's doing and uh and it might be evaluative where you say well they know i don't think
this is a healthy thing for that person or for all of us and uh and that doesn't have to uh
be a hostile or devalue the person
or or you know push someone away
and so sometimes one of the reasons why the word judgment is so powerful
is that it's it's not a simple evaluation of the situation
it often comes with this hostility itself or this pushing way or shutting down or
creating a strong sense of other they're wrong as a person
so but if you want to if you stop being judgment some people think that if they stop being judgmental they're not
supposed to be evaluative anymore and so that just makes the whole thing
more harder so you might see if you can relax a little bit
and switch the orientation of what you're doing to being evaluative
to recognize and evaluate what's going on and see if that takes the sting out of it
so behind you i'm
hi my name is grace i just want to say that yeah i really appreciate it there's a question louder please because my
hearing turn it back on oh okay my name's grace i just want to say that i really
appreciate how you point out it's all starting with end trying to work on internal healing
and that's how we can relate to things differently so that's really really um eye-opening
and profound for me thank you wonderful thank you i appreciate that
you know one of the motivations i have for being a buddhist teacher is is to contribute to a better world
but i have a strong belief that this practice does that hi
i'm gaurav thanks for the talk and meditation
one of the things that came up in my mind about witnessing was like i have this mistrust of the media
and that's how we how i witness what's going on in the world
so there was a conflict there like how do i witness when
media has an incentive to manipulate my emotions yeah this is a really important question
so how do we become wise consumers of the news
so i think one of them is to ask yourself the news that you are listening to
can you figure out find out what their bias is and recognize sometimes it's very
clear and uh and then when you're when you're reading it you're looking at it you remember that and you say well i should be
careful here to how they're doing it the other is to uh is to look for
sources that maybe don't express as obviously bias there may be more neutral
there's a website called i think it's called all sides maybe allsides.com maybe or outside something
and uh and it's uh they'll have lined up three columns one newspaper that's uh has news from
the the right political right the other one another column on the
other side has political left and then the middle is some news that they value it as more
middle and sometimes it's fascinating to read news from all three
because then you get a sense of the range and it's clear how people are biased if you see that way
another thing that i like to do is i learned this many years ago when i was living at the monastery
in the 1980s that we were deep in the mountains and uh the
newspaper would come in uh maybe once a week or something so then the new uh almost always the news
was old in the newspaper and uh and i learned it was really
eye-opening to see when i was reading news that was two three four days old
that my my body my mind my heart would not
get excited would not get alarmed the way it did when i thought the news
was fresh is and so you might try reading the news late
you know or read in a weekly magazines or monthly magazines that to talk about the same
thing you know you don't have to be right on top current by the day
and uh maybe just read the headlines currently and then but to go deeper maybe you could do it
something is you know what a little bit older just because then you then you also have
you yourself will be able to pick up more not be as reactive to the bias or what goes on
and then a neutral source that i've i've i've enjoyed doing sometimes
is sometimes i go on wikipedia and read about the particular news event in wikipedia
and it's kind of like an encyclopedic entry and i'm sure it's biased there too
but it's it doesn't have the charge and not not written with the the
the kind of the charge of popular news where they're trying to get kept your attention and really kind of keeping you
there with the news and the writing is a different style it's like an encyclopedic okay so okay okay okay it's
kind of a matter of effect and it tends to be broader and simpler and does so i find that sometimes very
helpful for me to go check there so is this give you some ideas
it's it's a really important topic you bring up so it's becoming being wise and how we relate to the news is
important part of this and so one of the things to do in terms
of whitney being a witness is to be a witness of how that how your
reaction is to the news and uh and that's really important
can you not getting can the best of you come out rather than the worse than you when you read the news
okay well thank you and uh very much and uh
may you be a peacemaker within and without