hello excuse me i kept my voice back here good evening
my name is maria stratman i'm really happy to be here it's good to see you all
this evening i want to talk to you
about the general topic of impermanence but recently i've been inspired by a
poem by amanda gorman you may remember her as the poet laureate
for uh who read her poem uh the hill we climb at the inauguration
the brilliant yellow coat that she wore and the verve that she delivered that that poem with
well she's written a book recently and it's called call us what we carry and in
that is this poem and one of the things that intrigues me is i'm just not sure why she chose the
title she did so tonight's topic
in response to the poem considers the intersection of impermanence
intentions and seeing clearly
what is true now and how can we be in the presence of what is true now
in the presence in this time of uncertainty how do we meet uncertainty and what does
it mean to meet uncertainty in the next place i've called my talk the heroism of being
changed so if i forget that as i ramble on please remind me
wave your hand and say wait a minute what were we going to talk about heroism and being changed
so let me start with the poem the poem is called closure closure
to begin again isn't to go backwards but to decide to go
our story is not a circle carved but a spiral shed shaped spinning
shifting inward and outward odd infinitum like a lung
on the bank of speech breathe with us
we disembark both beside and beyond who we were who we are
it is a return and a departure we spiral on pushing up and out
like a growing thing making its form out of earth in a poem there's no end
just a place where the page glows wide and waking waiting
like a lifted hand poised and paused here is our bond unbordered by bone
perhaps love is how it feels to breathe the same air
all we have is time is now time takes us on
how we are moved says everything about what we are to each other
and what are we to each other if not everything
to begin again isn't to go backwards but to decide to go
it's the same as the meditation instruction when we find that our mind is wandered away we say just come back
to the breath and begin breathing again we don't spend a lot of time worrying about how we got there or what was the
the definition of the thoughts and what direction where they were going we just come back and we just
start breathing again we just come back to the breath it's the same instruction it's the same instruction for everything
we just come back and we take the next step
this poem invites us to show up in this moment
show up in this moment in these days in this month and this year
to show up with these conditions just as we are not as
the person we used to be not as the person we would like to be not as our ideal selves but as this
person this person that is weary
or excited this person these conditions
this room show up this way and then take a step
don't worry about how you got here or where you're going to go when you leave here but who is this person right here
our practice is to be aware to be aware of our state of mind to be
aware of this condition this experience this place
we do that in meditation and we do that in our lives this this place
and to notice i'm not the person i was yesterday i'm not the person i was just a few minutes
ago i'm this person to recognize
not so much how we've changed but that this is the person showing up for these conditions this is the person who has to
decide whether to sit here whether to leave whether to breathe whether to not breathe well that's usually not so
voluntary
so we want to apply this mindfulness of just how things are not only
in the meditation but when we get up from meditating and when we take the next step
and to see that what life is what experience is is not so much our changing what we're
going to do next but that we carry this this forward into the next moment
that what we decide in this moment what we do in this moment
what our intentions are in this moment condition the next moment
condition tomorrow condition what happens next
it doesn't determine it
we come here with our intentions some of those intentions are large
intentions some of them are small intentions some of them act like motivators and some of them get in our
way being aware of what our intentions are
occasionally asking ourselves what are my intentions here what is it that i'm doing
why am i doing this what is it that's showing up here in
this moment and keeping in mind how it is that we want to be in the moment not who we want
to be who we want to be this mythical self
is not the person who is here in this moment
you know i've always had as the overriding intention in my life
to be open-hearted this is this is how i want to be
and i realized that that begins with be open-hearted it doesn't say anything
about becoming open-hearted and that the beginning of that is be open
oh you know i always thought of being open-hearted as what the generosity that
i was going to bestow on others but the first thing i have to do is be open
that was an interesting realization that the the way that i am in this world with
you in this moment is what i'm working with
it's wise if i know what that is and how that fits the intentions that i have the
large intentions and the small intentions the everyday intentions
the practice is to show up with our intentions and what those mean
are intentions of kindness of wholesomeness of skillfulness
and to see is it here now am i ready am i ready for just this
oh i'm not ready okay i know i'm not ready well i'm kind of ready well i'm here
this is what i'm working with this is what i have these are the skills i have
what i cultivate come out of my intentions and what arises out of my actions now
that conditions the next moment that's the next set of conditions i have to worry about
so right now having just sat for 45 minutes i'm feeling fairly relaxed
pretty easy you know public speaking doesn't frighten me so that's okay i can just
i can just be here and so i have a certain amount of ease with that right okay
i've been kind of relaxed i've not been worrying
all right that's that's the condition i'm bringing into this but earlier today
uh that was not strict that was not necessarily true
i was out walking this afternoon and um there was a couple i i walk around this
pond in my neighborhood it's about a quarter mile around the pond to give you an idea of the size of it it's not very
large has lots of koi in it and a couple of ducks sometimes geese sometimes an
egret feeding on the fish and this afternoon a couple had their
dog and they were throwing balls out in the middle of the pond so that the dog could run in and chase the balls
now this is a protected pond and nobody's supposed to wade in it or get in it and not disturb the fish or the
ducks and so i'm watching this and i'm thinking i should go up and tell that person this is not acceptable
they can't be doing this they shouldn't be putting letting their dog in much less encouraging their dog and i'm
feeling all of this ill will and agitation building up in me
and i'm walking walking walking and i realized that there was outrage and
a sense of injustice that was getting really strong and i thought well now how can i
approach this person and the thoughts went to what's what's right speech which why speech here
and then i said well first i better check in and see who is this that's trying to decide this wise speech and i
decided part of what was happening was that there was this overwhelming feeling that
i've been carrying around with me for days around the war in ukraine and that the feeling of the injustice of
invasion and all of the experiences of frustration and helplessness that i've been having
had built up in me and i was about to take it out on this guy throwing his the ball into the water
in this pond recognizing that that was there that
that was the condition of how i've been walking around my anxiety and
sense of helplessness about war was really useful to see
so i checked and you know the fish had all moved away from that end of the pond the dog wasn't really aggressive nothing
was being hurt so maybe the appropriate thing for me
was not to think of the best thing to do but to be aware of this container i have
that includes my distress over the war in ukraine
and maybe time better spent thinking about what does that mean for me
how am i reacting to that what is what is that condition leading me to as
opposed to worrying about wise speech
definitely noticing the agitation the distress the lack of satisfaction
how do i meet that taking all that frustration and
releasing it in the direction of somebody else innocent or not innocent
just might not be the answer
at other times i notice the other day i noticed
i woke up after dreams i don't know if you dream i i tend to dream when i'm under stress or
whether or when something is really moving in me and i was having all the classic anxiety
things in my dreams you know like i miss my flight how can i get to japan
who knows why i wanted to go to japan but i needed to get there and and how was i going to do that or or i start you
know my cars i have a flat on my tire or i have to get under and and adjust something you know those kinds of dreams
dreams about helplessness and as i got out of bed i was aware of
that and i thought about ukraine and so i said okay yeah yeah yeah and then i noticed
that the feeling that i had was this closed-in feeling and very tight and
i actually had a feeling of smallness i don't know if you've
it's hard to talk about an attitude of mind like this but it has to do with a sense of space
and i realized i was compressing all of these things
and that what was needed was space i went outside
and allowed all those feelings that i was that just seemed like too much to just
be true where there was more space for them
just be true not chasing them away
just giving them a little more space and in that space it was easy to see
easier to see ah i need to meet this how can i
affect something positive but when it was all compressed it wasn't possible for me
so being aware of the attitude that my mind the mind state
tells me something about this person in these conditions who's trying to
live life doesn't tell me what to do but it gives me information so that i see clearly
i see the campaigner the person who wants to do something
and rather than finding the place where i i have to fix something or i have to
take out the frustration there needs to be space to see ah this
is the person that's showing up now this is the person
this is what it feels like to be the person who is feeling frustration and
helplessness sadness and not start listening all the reasons that's true and all the all the
all the all the dictators in the world or whatever feeds into the story but
noticing this oh this is this is the effect this is this is the agitation that is
here and knowing the agitation that is here
it is it's the energy of just allowing what is true to be true
i don't know if any of you heard gil's talk from this morning but he actually he's talking about the sati patana suta
and this morning he talked about attitude of mind and that that was really his talk uh the the mind state
and and the the learning what the mind state is how
it feels is a practice
it's not automatic you know when i talk about the space seems small
sometimes that must feel strange to you it's only the way that i talk about it
the mind state is not a thing like a brain it's
it's more i i like to think of it as the container
in which my experience is taking place this this is this is the condition
part of the condition is the energy that i bring into the moment whether that energy is low energy
or high energy whether i'm feeling compressed or spacious
when things seem confused okay things seem confused
oh i don't like confusion i have to do something about confusion why am i confused let me get it all
organized i'm going to plan something notice the tendency of the mind to want to plan in the state of confusion
oh that's interesting what would it be like if i didn't do
that what if i didn't plan what if i didn't do that activity what would that what would be true what
would arise am i okay with not knowing what's going
to happen next what does that feel like
we cultivate this kind of mindfulness in meditation
and we think of it as mindfulness and stillness is there any way to get at that
stillness when everything is chaotic when everything feels out of control
how do we get how do we realize that when we come to the space where we say
oh i see there's just a moment of ah
that and it's a moment if we notice of ease there's just a kind of feeling into it
that's oh that's here oh that's here
and just that moment of ease should be registered
oh i noticed i got it i caught it oh great
rather like when we come back from being lost in thoughts on meditation we say i'm back here i am i am still here i'm
here and that i am here sometimes puts a little ease
in the chaos of what's going on and when we recognize it then it becomes
something we know and it becomes a way of
shifting our awareness from whatever it is that we've encountered that we may want to analyze
fix change and say oh this is what it feels like to be confused
and just that much shift in awareness brings us to a place where we're not
rolling around in whatever the the emotion is that we might have recognized
how do we not get caught by the state of mind but catch it
so that if we wake up sad or confused
or angry we can say ah sadness is here
hmm i should be careful about that or confusion is here
oh you're trying so hard or anger is here
oh anger is here wow
i don't have to then list all the reasons i've ever been angry or list the reasons i've been angry with
this person
i can develop a relationship to uncertainty
anger is here i don't know for sure what's going to happen in the next moment confusion is here
i don't know what's going to happen in the next moment
when we have space for things to be just as they are we have a freedom to not be have have to
control what happens next
so we aren't caught by whatever it is we can say oh that is here
we're we're reflected by afflicted by uncertainty at every turn
we have you know i could go down the long list there's covid you know over six million people have
died in the world from covet six million people
we've lost people we've been isolated many of us have decision fatigue is this
safe is this not safe there are over uh 1.7 million refugees
from the ukraine in the last 12 days wow
where are all those people there's inflation and financial and
insecurity there's climate change there's inequality there no
end to things that we might worry about and we as humans try to protect
ourselves against these things we become ever vigilant and we become more vigilant and more
vigilant and pretty soon we are little vigilant machines and we're so busy being vigilant we haven't noticed that
our hearts have turned down that we have locked ourselves up that we're constantly looking with an eye of
suspicion and so something we were counting on
comes up and somebody says well i'm not going to be able to make it and all of a sudden because we're
carrying this suspicion around with us oh what's this about why are you doing
this to me and all of a sudden there's this adversary relationship what is quite possible the other person
just something came up and there's nothing they could do about it we don't know
we don't know
ajahn chah said looking for certainty and that which is not certain you're bound to suffer
looking for certainty in that which is not certain you're bound to suffer how do we free ourselves of that
how do we find a place of safety without spending all our lives trying to be safe and not
letting anything happen and trying to control the outcome of what happens
we look to what our experience has taught us we can trust this we can't trust that this is safe that's not safe
and we'd say that with the idea that it's always going to be the same but it turns out that it's not
the conditions are never the same they're always changed in some way
just as we're changed in some way so no end of planning no amount of
planning is going to assure that everything's going to happen just the way we want it to
better to say oh this is what it's like to be disappointed
oh this is what it's like to be disappointed i feel sad
i feel let down i feel thoughted whatever that experience is like
we can look at that experience and not oh this is your fault we don't have to
have blame for all the bad things that happen in life we can say oh a bad thing has happened
now what's the next step what do i do now what what's what how do i approach this now
where is my intention now one of the ways we do that is by taking
advantage of the space between what arises and naming it our own
one of the best instructions somebody ever gave me was to realize that i could
name something that was going on and not make it mine or me
anger is present but i'm not angry i'm not anger anger is here if anger is
here something needs to be done but it isn't me i don't have to make it mine
and have it be oh this this is an angry person i can notice okay the energy is up in my
body adrenaline is running i want to retort well wait a minute
okay i can't do anything about that adrenaline but knowing that the data adrenaline is rushing gives me a moment
in which i can remember my intention toward kindness and i'll say yeah but i don't feel kind
okay not feeling kind is here i don't like the way that feels it feels really crummy
and that we're not held by it anymore once we see it we can disentangle
ourselves from it we don't have to push it away i have a little problem with the
instructions to just let it go because it feels too much like putting it away
but if i can say okay it's here and my intention for kindness is here and they are struggling with one another
now it's out here there's space i'm not in here fighting it i'm looking at it i'm saying okay okay okay i see both you
guys are here when you're in that space of seeing of discerning the difference
between what has arisen and who i am
then we have more freedom to choose the wise next step
sometimes when the adrenaline is running through our bodies the best thing to do is to turn around and wash our hands
do something that takes care of that energy without responding without jumping into
what's the wise thing to do here but rather take advantage of the fact that i notice
this is happening
noticing the feelings becomes a habit of mind noticing mind state becomes a habit
of mind and it begins to show up when you're not looking for it
and you start realizing oh this is what oh this is happening now oh i see this
and not oh this is my habit and this is always happening
whenever i hear stories about refugees
what comes to mind is a hangover from when i was in grade
school it was the time of the hungarian revolution which gives you a clue of how
long ago that was and two little girls showed up at my school
they did not speak my language they were extremely exotic my god they had their
ears pierced unheard of in 1955 57 58 58 probably in
in billings montana unheard of these were the most exotic people i'd ever seen and i was so eager to get to know
them and find out about them and they i couldn't speak to them and they were terrified and i remember that look of terror and
the two girls they were sisters would huddle together and they'd kind of hide from everybody
and they'd look around with suspicion
and every time i hear about refugees of any kind i remember those two
i have no idea what happened to them they were only there a brief time but they impacted me and they are a
condition of my life they are a condition that this person who's arrived in this
place is always affected by refugees any refugee
anybody who's put out unexpectedly unknowingly
and i can't imagine i don't i don't know what it would be like to
feel like that but the experience for me is a very open
experience it doesn't leave me with fear and dread it leaves me more with
the feeling of compassion of oh my god what can i do about this
and to recognize that in the midst of the uncertainty and despair
is to realize there's this unpleasant thing and there is this pleasant thing
and both are conditions that the very distress we feel about
injustice inequality those feelings of
this is not right this should not be this way are also in the same room with the
feelings of how can i make this better
what can i do about this and the intentions that we have toward
kindness and compassion and wholeness show up in that moment if
we allow them if we allow ourselves to see them and not be dragged away by whatever it
is that that comes up but rather oh this is here and what else is here
words matter what we name things matters uncertainty
is just impermanence fully realized
to not be uncertain not be certain about who we are what is true
but to every moment see it freshly what's true now what's true now
is to look at change and realize that all the conditions that we've been
through have changed us and continue to change us the new
conditions change us and to be willing to see
i'm changed by this i'm changed by this experience i'm changed by this knowledge i'm changed by
recognizing who's shown up in this moment in this body
i'm changed by that and to embrace that change
in the sense of just allowing it to be true just seeing it
this is how it is it's like this it's like this this
what arises in the moments when
the unexpected arises what happens i recently took a week
when i realized i was really busy trying to make everything happen
and said what happened what happens if i don't do all this responsible stuff
and for i decided to work a crossword puzzle and for four days that's all i did i
worked that crossword not a crossword puzzle i mean a thousand piece puzzle a regular puzzle i'm a crossword puzzle
fanatic so that came up but what i did was work this puzzle just to see what happens if i don't do
all these things what happens what arises what do i think
what do i think it this person who is this person here
what is useful is to realize that almost anything could happen
and to know that we don't have to know the outcome we don't things don't have to be the way
they are how we think they should be
we can't go back to a non-existent past
we can only access this moment this person who is here in this moment
we do so with the accumulated wisdom and humility of all the things that we
have thought and been in the past who are not who we are now
as amanda's poem said we are both beside and beyond who we
were who we are
it's always changing we are the heroes of our everyday
we take the next step into the uncertain with the confidence of seeing clearly
and the wisdom of our own intentions so those are my thoughts for tonight
i hope it's useful do you have any questions observations
i'd be happy to hear
let me read the poem to you again
closure to begin again isn't to go backwards
but to decide to go our story story is not a circle carved
but a spiral shed shaped spinning shifting inward and outward odd
infinitum like a lung on the bank of speech
breathe with us we disembark both beside and beyond
who we were who we are it is a return and a departure
we spiral on pushing up and out like a growing thing
making its form out of earth in a poem there is no end
just a place where the page grows wide and waiting like a lifted
hand poised and paused here is our bond
unbordered by bone perhaps love is how it feels to breathe the same air
all we have is time is now time takes us on
how we are moved says everything about what we are to each other
and what are we to each other if not everything
may you know the peace of uncertainty
the possibilities of uncertainty
may your practice lead you to a place where you can see clearly
so that wisdom is with you always thank you