so good morning everyone can you hear me okay is that loud enough
so welcome and uh both your person and online on this
Christmas morning for those of you who celebrate Christmas Merry Christmas
for those of you who don't marry anyway
a day of chair um I've been inspired by Christians who
celebrate who Christians who celebrate Christmas as a day of love
kind of a universal love so um
today a little bit uh following and continuing
kind of a theme that I've been teaching this last week I want to start with a quotation from
the Buddha where he says something like
um if it were not possible it was if it was not possible
to cultivate the wholesome I would not teach you or instruct you to
cultivate the wholesome but it is possible to cultivate the
wholesome therefore I instruct you or teach you to cultivate
the wholesome so uh it's a kind of I think a very kind
of a celebration statement about our potential that we have the potential whether or
not we use it to do things that are wholesome the Pali
word is kusala and um you know if you want to make it really
simple in English we would say do good but that kind of misses some of the
nuances or richness of the term that the word kusala
means both something which is really wholesome or beneficial or helpful it
also refers to something which is skillful which is done well for a particular purpose
and then you have to ask her what's the purpose but when you translate it as wholesome
then the purpose is itself it's to be nourished to be supported to do something that feels like it's hole
making makes you whole or wholehearted or something part part of it
but the kind of the the idea of wholesomeness is uh though that what has
been beneficial for us are beneficial for the world that it's a
non-afflictive it's a absence of causing any kind of harm to oneself and to others
and to be for our welfare so this this with this language of our welfare for
our benefit to help us to develop us to strengthen us all kinds of things we have this
potential now we could just ignore that potential or just kind of take it on
some kind of Faith well I'm good enough I don't have to do anything special you know I just
can't go along with my life and you know I'll stop I'll stop for pedestrians
you know and you know you know live a good life but they um but the word um
so that's fine you know maybe you live a basically good life but uh it's possible to cultivate this
wholesome so that it brings a feeling a sense of inner thriving
a sense of abundance Within and uh this is part of what the
teachings of the Buddha was about was not just to do good for yourself and for the world but to cultivate something
that brings a kind of fullness a wholeness an abundance a phenomenal
sense of thriving from the inside out so our sense of thriving does not depend
on conditions in the world that uh you know that
but rather has to do with the conditions of Our Own Heart their own inner life
and so there's a lot of attention given to this inner inner life that we want to cultivate and develop
and I was kind of maybe because I was giving this talk I was struck when I was meditating with all of you now
that after some minutes there was a clear shift Within Me and the shift was you know I've been
thinking about the things over these last few days and coming down here and
and so I was still kind of a little bit my mind was a little bit in the momentum of my concerns my thoughts my activities
lately and then after sitting here breathing for a while I could feel there was a shift and I I could say oh now I'm here
it took me five minutes or it took me a while but now I'm here and now I was
here I could feel the sense of being here not just in this
room but more kind of physically almost I'm I'm here in this body it's almost
like now I'm connected and I had this sense of expansive space in my body when
I was finally here okay here I am and um and now I could feel that now
that I'm here in the space of my body now there were space for the good for the wholesome for the
beneficial to flow or to grow whereas when I was caught up in my
thoughts uh the space within was kind of tight if I even was paying attention to
the space there was no space it was tight it was contracted I was kind of in my head in a sense
and the head is a very different place for to be the source of the wholesome
than it is to be kind of here in this body grounded in it with space in it for
something to flow and to well up and to be here the difference is that when I'm in a
head I could have the idea and the admonition I'm supposed to be good I'm
supposed to do nice things and and it comes from a conceptual
conceiving world of logic ideas things I've learned from other people how
things should be it's a place because I'm so disconnected to the rest of me it's difficult sometimes to notice the
bias that's operating there it just seems like it's the truth or something and um and there's all kinds of biases
by which you know this thinking mind can live by without even being seen but when I dropped in that moment where
this thing switched and I could feel oh here I am I found that I wasn't as interested in my thoughts anymore
they were okay but they weren't really the name of the game and but I had much more clarity
about it and I had much more choice about what I did next
I had some Choice a brother to stay there or I had some choice to you know I would
had I had some really good thoughts going so you know and uh and so I could go back up in
those thoughts and um you know I had a choice but I could feel that what felt
wholesome what felt really good and nice place to be was settled here in the
present in this open space in my body within that it was a there I could
generate different it was different source for choices I make different choice for what
I want to develop or how I want to be what or different choice about what I want to give energy to
the um you know what do I you focus on is you know gives a kind of energy to things and keeps things spinning and
going sometimes but if you give your your attention here inside
um and there's qualities of generosity or love or
kindness or gentleness calmness wisdom
then to focus on that within makes room for it allows that to grow make space
for it validates it authorizes it to kind of be there it's
okay you're allowed to be there it's good I'm not going to overlook you
one of the interesting things about this switch to kind of really being here it was a little bit easier to see that
these deeper feelings deeper way of being was not so connected to my usual
self-identity my usual kind of self that I'm operating and this is how I need to be and this is what I need to do and
this is what those people did to me um but there's something you know certainly happening within me
but I was less inclined to take it you know to take it personally or to
claim it or appropriate these inner wholesome feelings I could feel that if
I appropriated it it made some smaller space for it so we have this wholesome that Buddhism
Buddha said cultivate the wholesome and then he offered things like meditation practice as a as I think of it as a seed
bed that you prepare sow these seeds of the wholesome can grow
and that's a very different way of thinking about it just saying do it just do it which might come then from the
conceptual mind the head it might come from all kinds of other places than just coming from the seed bed deep inside
that Wells up and flows so one of the things that's needed if we
want to cultivate the wholesome is desire
and without some desire for it why would we do it why would we put any energy
effort into it and I emphasize this emphasis this this uh idea of the need for desire because I
think that generally us Buddhist teachers including myself
um um don't talk about the desire in a good
way that often don't hold it up as being important if anything we talk about you know
attachment and craving and thirst and greed and the issues should let go of and it could easily and you know easily
kind of Desire gets put into that same category just listening to us
but uh without some kind of desire for the
wholesome why would we cultivated why would we focus on it and um
so and the Buddha actually said that he talks about you know have the desire
for practice have the desire to cultivate you know awakened desire for the wholesome
so it can I think you know a little bit thus Buddhist teachers need to spend a
little time reclaiming desire as a good thing as a place for us
the danger for doing that is uh in any kind of uh instructions to
cultivate something develop something is one is also dangers one danger is it puts us in the
self-help camp and a lot there's such a strong momentum among many parts of the culture around
here to be self-help which just becomes another attempt to reinforce and develop
you know there's yours your idea Your Glory as a self
and the danger of that is that it's impossible to maintain that so sooner or later you'll crash and uh you can't live
up to the hype and the you know of kind of building up a good perfect self it's
no such thing the other thing is that some people here I have a few of people occasionally you
see it somewhere in this kind of part of the world there's certain kind of neurotic attitude towards doing
the more the better we have to do more have to be efficient you know you have to get ahead you have to you know work
60 hours a week if you're kind of want to you know but ideally 75
but you have a generous boss so it's only 60. and um you know this emphasis on you
know doing doing doing and then we have so much possibilities for many of us here that
even those of us who don't have to struggle to survive we you know so many things we feel like we should do and
accomplish and manage and keep up and so this idea of doing is kind of
that lends itself to more doing even more I'm so busy already now I have to do this Buddhism thing on top of it
give me a break and um and so and because of the certain
kind of neurotic sense of doing and entertainment and improving oneself
Buddhist teachers in the west have made a lot of emphasis on um not doing on acceptance just letting
shelf be just being which has been very powerful for many westerners because it allows something
to unwind and to settle and then at some point maybe they have that switch that I described earlier today you switch and
oh now I'm here I feel yeah it's okay just to be and then
you can turn on the desire you can turn then you can maybe have the
desire for the wholesome you can switch it on in a Wholesome Way and that's the art of
it how do you have desire which is wholesome how do you have desire which you feel
nourished by you feel inspired by you feel you're delighted to have this
desire wow I'm so lucky I get to have this wonderful desire
it's not a burden it doesn't it doesn't you don't add it to your to-do list like okay desire
wholesome States check that off done that it's uh it's uh it's like wow
just even having a desire feels like wow that's pretty cool is that possible
it is but I think it requires a really being
grounded settled here in the present moment in yourself
if you're racing around in your head spinning around with thoughts ideas racing around your body
and then it's hard to find that seed bed that Source inside where there can be because a welding up
of almost a selfless desire it's almost as if it's not really you
know part of your usual contracted sense of self
and feel the goodness of it oh here is something within me that really cares for me that really
wants the best in me that wants the best even for the world because how can I
support and bring welfare and happiness to others if I don't have it myself
so this desire oh look at that it's almost like kind of wakes you up to
pay attention oh look at that desire desire for the wholesome for the
beneficial the desire to thrive emotionally or
psychologically or you know this inner spiritual way that we talk about in Buddhism
are we allowed to do that there are people who feel they're not allowed to do that
I've known people whose own kind of teachings they got no not Buddhists
growing up was uh you were absolutely not supposed to have a lot of Joy because Joy was kind of almost like
bordered in a carnal sin and so and so kind of held that hold
back I've known people who've held themselves back in meditation because they couldn't get themselves
wouldn't let themselves get concentrated because as we get concentrated there tends to be good feelings that come and
some of those good feelings are very physical and they like I'm not allowed to do that there's something wrong with that
and then there's people who feel that any kind of focus on personal well-being
is somehow selfish and all you're supposed to be altruistic all the time and so the self-focus is a
problem it is a problem sometimes and uh and maybe that's part of the some
of one of the challenges uh in in a practice like we
do where there's a lot of this introvert Focus is to be able to differentiate between narcissism and healthy
inner Focus that's not self enhancing or making and as a teacher I talk to a lot
of people about their practice and every once in a while in a great while I talked to someone who is saying all
the right words about you know focusing inwardly and I kind of think wait a
minute this is somehow something doesn't seem quite right here maybe it's the frequency frequency in
which they use the word I just like this is like it seems like every other word is I
and so so it can be a problem what we're look what we're talking about here but
the important thing is it doesn't have to be there is something really beautiful
that awaits us within that we can cultivate in a beautiful desire to awake
to do it so um the
uh so the kind of the uh there's something called for right efforts which I've talked about this
last week so some of you have heard this already but I think it's worth hearing again if you did
so these four right efforts have to do first two have to do with the unwholesome
the inner thoughts ideas impulses motivations desires
that were within us that are unwholesome unbeneficial they're called in by the Buddha
afflictive they hurt there's an ouch in them and and then there's the uh wholesome
which are beneficial they bring about welfare they bring out a certain kind of healthy kind of pleasure they kind of
they feel good to have them so two two of the right efforts have to bother about the unwholesome and two
have to do with the wholesome the unwholesome the Buddha says uh uh
have the desire to make an effort
to to prevent the arising of unwholesome states
so if every time you go in the shopping channel
you feel miserable from the exhaustion of all the things
you want to buy so that's that desire to want to buy all
those things is unwholesome so have the desire to prevent that from
happening don't go on the shopping channel or limit yourself to a minute
or do something else you know anyway so there are things we can do to just avoid
have the wisdom to know what to avoid because it triggers you in ways that are not healthy
the second right effort is to ER is to bring up the desire
to make the effort so it's not just a desire for something but the desire to work for it to make
the effort for it bring up the effort to abandon
the unwholesome that has that's happening inside of you
and what's this very important part of this language because Buddhism often gets associated
with letting go these Buddhists are all about letting go when the Buddha talks about what we let
go of it's always inner mental states which are unhealthy
I don't think he sadly ever soaks about letting go of things in the world but he is talking about the letting go
of greed and hatred that we have resentment Envy avariciousness all kinds
of things that are inside that are unwholesome so the world is the world but how we
relate to the world is the issue so this abandoning of what is unwholesome
have the desire for it then have the desire for the for evoking
wholesome States so wholesome states are good so what would you do to evoke them more
make sure you get enough sleep if you can make sure you have some down time
be sure you spend time with people who inspire you and bring out the best in you make sure you I don't go in the shopping
shopping channel go if you can if you really have to do open the channel go on some some channel that inspires you if
you feel good and kind of it's delightful for you whatever it is
um you know there's a there's choices to be made here it's not just leaving things to chance
and part of the choices is what we what behaviors we avoid and what if behaviors
we engage in that's what a wise life is involved in that kind of reflection and
thinking and then um
evoke the desire to make the effort
to develop expand Thrive
strengthen increase the wholesome the Buddha uses a whole series of words
here what you do all these you know kind of phenomenal words like the word abundance is in there or increase and
develop strengthen so avoid the wholesome
cultivate the unwholesome so I went through this review for some of you because if a very important
reason having desire to developed to strengthen the wholesome
is important that desire is important
we want to look at the desire study the desire get to know your desire
to ensure that your desire is wholesome
that the desire is not it doesn't have any unwholesomely mixed in it if there's unwholesomeness mixed with
your desire for Spiritual practice chances are you're going to suffer
chances are you'll have stress and not a few people have gotten done
something like meditation or Buddhist practice and they're greedy like or
they're ambitious or they're afraid and they're you know or they feel like there's a duty and
they have to they should do it or they're trying to get rid of something that's they don't like and so they're doing the practice because of their
aversion those are all unwholesome states
and if you those states are mixed into the desire the desire becomes
unwholesome so what is a wholesome desire
wholesome desire has no stress as part of it
and do you have any do you have any inkling of what a stress-free desire is like
you have a lot of desires every day I guarantee it the desire to go pee
desire to open the door a few of those desires have no stress in
them you do them almost mindlessly almost like unself-consciously
study those desires that you have through the day that have no stress in them
and see get a hang of them a feel for it to get a sense of what it's like to have
desires that well up that are stress-free tension free
also there are desires that the wholesome desires have no
um they don't have any sense of burden to them I think it's a burden obligation
I don't know if that's always unwholesome exactly but it's rarely going to produce a wholesome feeling in
the desire I think rarely sometimes
and um and so certainly no sense of burden in the desire
no big I should do this but rather it's more like the feeling
inside maybe translate this for yourself but for me to say it's more like the feeling inside
wow I have the opportunity for this
wow let's do it how often do you have that feeling
you get up in the morning to make your breakfast wow I'm so lucky I get to have
this desire for food for breakfast and desire to make something here as opposed to make breakfast like I have to get
sober as quickly as I can because I have important things to do like it's like to like maybe meditate
and learn to be present and instead of
learning to be present with making breakfast so what I'm trying to point to here is
the idea that we can become the students of Desire of your desire
and to discover how your desire can be wholesome beneficial
something that brings you some sense of nourishment or support or Delight or joy
in the pursuit of other wholesome things
do you have any sense you have any clear idea of what inner movements desires feelings
impulses emotions motivations
mind States heart States that feel for you
nourishing supportive delightful inspiring
and I would suggest that for many people in our society they have very little experience of this
without having the world evoke them for them and so they go looking in the world for
something to do that is going to bring up these good things inside but but to discover how to find it in
oneself and really recognize it in oneself and
then have it kind of be able to have the desire to strengthen it to expand it to
grow it to take that seed bed and water it and
fertilize it and do what it takes to develop it and grow it
so the Buddha said if it were not possible
to develop the wholesome I would not teach you to develop the wholesome
but it is possible to develop the wholesome therefore I tell you develop the
wholesome so I hope by the end of this 30 minutes
okay if the first time I said it was a little bit burdensome for you to hear
oh no more work these Buddhists I'm hoping after the end of this talk that
maybe have some sense that this actually could be a quite inspiring teaching
and um and maybe it's one that will prepare you
to get ready for the new year so thank you very much and we have 15
minutes before we usually end so we can take maybe a few a little bit of that if you want to ask any questions or comments
and before we do over here I'll just last thing I'll say is you can go ahead
and give them the mic is so we're not going to be open next Sunday uh so that'll be the January 1st
we won't meet here and so we'll we'll meet um so I'll be back before
yeah so yeah I won't be here the following someday either we have a guest teacher for that week
foreign hi Gail my name is Rick thanks for the
talk and uh I just wanted to ask you if you would mind elaborating on something
to make it more real for me um I definitely relate to like the joy of
sitting down and making music or sometimes just having my croissant but I wonder you said there's something
very beautiful within that we can cultivate I would love to just hear an
example or two of how that is real for you I think love is one of them kindness
love that does in there a warmth the tenderness there is also sometimes a sense of
generosity that's there that's quite beautiful and strong and full kind of embodied generosity not like just like a
policy in the head there is sometimes feelings of peace
that are quite lovely to fix it Tranquility to feel inside that are considered wholesome
there is joy happiness
is that enough okay contentment is another one
thank you Gil um
the word crucial it comes from a grass called kushala
grass which is very sharp so you find it used throughout the scriptures
it has even though they translate it as skillful it has the connotation of razor
sharp skills like a person walking on a tightrope or somebody operating with missionary where
they can get injured so it refers to the discriminative knowledge and in fact in the bhagavad-gita this is
one of the definitions for yoga yoga is called yoga Karma kaushalam it is it's
fine to keep your mask on I hear you fine yoga is called Skillman action
it's it's called um yoga Karma kaushalam so it's a skill it's the razor sharp
skill in action so I just want to do it okay thank you
I've heard that before and that I said it takes a lot of skill to be able to pick the grass because you'll get cut if
you're not careful how you pick it
I just wanted to say thank you for your teaching all year and all the years great
thank you Gil um regarding desire I'm aware of desires
that I have that create a great deal of tension and that is the desire to be better at something
I happen to be a dentist and I have a desire to be a better dentist and it
creates a lot of tension how do I react to that or how do you
what would you react to that so when we start with the the top kind of the top
end or like bird's eye view looking at this desire of yours yours that brings tension
uh what would be a Wholesome Way of beginning to address it
hard work and step back further because the heart is hard work feel wholesome to you yes
oh so tell me how that works how does hard work feel wholesome that
how do you you feel better after you work hard oh yes I my my highest Highs
are after having accomplished something difficult and having done it well great
lovely so now how would you address how using that way of working hard how would
you now address this tension around wanting to do it better
I am I'm aware of I mean I work because I
want to work and I enjoy it a lot I don't have to work anymore it's different than I was 20 years ago but um
I'm aware of a kind of another conflicting desire like
why would I go to work and do something that's very difficult when I could just sit at home
you know I could sit at home and listen to meditation tapes or music whatever
and it's an interesting quandary that in my own mind I mean I would like to be
comfortable but I want to be um have have the accomplishment I guess
I'm kind of seeking the high of having done something well and that is just hard
work and requires a lot of creates a lot of tension yeah I think I think that the
them in the generic against response to you is for you to spend a
lot of time being mindful of what's really driving you and what's really happening underneath the layers is
happening in your mind because there's probably layers of beliefs and attachments and clinging operating there
you don't even see especially because of all the tension and it has in there and um
so I think to do some kind of a deep investigation of this maybe with the
help of someone else who can you can have me in conversation with and kind of dig into it would be really nice
but you also seem to have something really wonderful about you and that you have this wonderful sense of uh doing
and throwing yourself in to do something really well uh that's it seems like could be a
beautiful thing to free from all the attention to do without any tension but to do it with the light and
wholeheartedness is a wonderful thing and listening to you I wondered whether
doing your Den I don't know where you do it now but if you do your dentistry in a different place then you're doing it
do it for free for people who are low income and I wonder if that would give you a
whole different sense of accomplishment and whole different level of challenge because you say you don't need to
anymore and that that would kind of allow you to explore a whole different side of yourself
that would come and grow then then you can if you do it like in the old what
you've been doing for all these years yeah I do a fair amount of that fantastic that's um does that make a
difference where you do it in terms of you're what you're talking about here not really no it doesn't matter if somebody's paying a lot of money or not
very or no money the the it's the work and the outcome of the work that matters
yeah well I think you have something good going here but uh there's something
for you to discover there that frees you from the tension and it might even allow you to without
the tension you might actually find that you enjoy it even more that there's a you're kind of in the flow of it in a
much more a beautiful way wonderful way thank you thank you
um I had heard the word um Chanda offered once as like a a counterpart to
Taha his wholesome desire and um and then another scholar told me
that it's more like neutral like you want to turn left here to go where you're going which was disappointing
because I had named my dog Chanda by that point um but it brings up a whole new thing of
neutral sort of Desire yeah um but my question as a practitioner is
um a tendency to cross-examine myself is this spiritual materialism am I is it
becoming grasping so I guess like a distinction between a wholesome desire
that's inspirational and and and leading to a good place versus sort of a near
enemy of wanting well for us is already said first about
Chanda so the the poly word c-h-a-n-d-a is um
I don't know if it's exactly neutral but it's um it's um ambidextrous
so it can be the word can be used both for wholesome men on wholesome and
sometimes in context is clear as being as unwholesome in context that's wholesome and um so it kind of can take
different shapes that way so it's still a good very good word in context so in the context of your life it's still a
good good name and um
so then that you're asking about the difference between wholesome desire and grasping
one what oh yeah spiritual gas screen yeah it uh
if um if you have some some intuition that there's spiritual grasping going on
um then see if you can flush out the stress or the dukkha the suffering
that's part of that grasping because sometimes it's just becoming an
expert and recognizing stress or tension or dukkha the Buddhist word suffering
becoming really sensitive more and more sensitive to how it operates even the most subtle ways is a window to be able
to identify what's unwholesome
so suffer better laughs
thank you for a very nice session on the wholesomeness of the desire
uh I think in our first conversation one-on-one with you I have presented to
you that my connection with Buddha was I used to
visit this place um it was actually a hotel where they had a
um a restaurant called Lumbini Lumbini is essentially the birthplace of
Buddha yes um and right next to it they had a bar
called Krishna within the same compound the hotel called Siddharth and Krishna
is essentially a bar in the hotel is called Krishna
Krishna
oh the name of the bar is is called thirst craving
so I I wondered like I mean if that's like a wholesome uh desire like I mean
that's uh like it's why would they would name it that way I mean or they're just
being honest so the word in pal in Pali it's Tana in
Sanskrit I think it's uh and
um it's under I don't know with all the meanings are you know different areas of India in the English of Indian
language but then listen the Buddhist terminology it means it literally means
thirst but it has the connotation of uh craving
and so the so a good place to go for the craving for alcohol is to the bar
so they're just being honest and I I would hope that Buddhists would
see that and say oh that's not my place [Music] so he would rather go to Lumbini than
yeah so so we're fascinating that that will be near the birthplace of the Buddha there's a bar called that no the the
restaurant was Lumbini and the bar was Krishna ah I saved great well
maybe the last one please yeah this might be my name's katita um this might be similar to a question that was asked
but I still wanted to ask it um two wholesome desires that I feel
like I have um they feel like their intention with each other one is like generosity and
wanting to help others and the other is to like be in community and just to be with others
um and yeah I guess my question is
yeah that they almost seem to like work against each other to the point where it feels like I can only really cultivate
one um and I'm just wondering
I guess what do I do about that in the sense of like I have this deep desire to help others and to be better
and to to just um when I say help others and help myself just be the best like we can be
and I work in mental health and just to like you know so everything around me I see in this way in light of how we can
be better and do better for each other and then I see community and I try to be in community
um but it's difficult for me because it's not it's not achieving like the standards I have for myself or wanting
people to be better so I'm like constantly um judging the way we do things the way
we reach out together in just just different things like that and I'm just wondering how to so let me so let me see if I understand
so the desire to be generous to do good for the world is really out there in the
wider world so to live in a community bounds you limits you
for because that takes time to be in community and so that you have less time to do the work the good work out there
so is that the attention yeah and I need community and I want to do it with
another I guess wholesome desires to do it with people right but it's it's kind of hard to work together sometimes
I'm noticing people you know we work differently worked and it's like I don't know there's like a it's almost hard for
me to sit in that yeah Community is uh easy except for the people who are in it yeah
the um so so uh I mean I mean this is a really important topic so I feel like
whatever I say will be just shorthand for okay so please for you know allow me so one is that um
part of your desire to do good for others can be for the people in that community that you're in
and that takes much more work it takes a lot more time you get much more reward
sometimes by doing things out there where you don't have to deal with interpersonal issues but to click to to
work on the interpersonal issues in a community in a Sangha or anywhere is doing uh similarly important inner
work as sitting in meditation by yourself is doing inner work you're purifying yourself you're clarifying
yourself discovering yourself in in really rich ways and there's plenty of Buddhists who have not done
the community part of work have just done a lot of meditation and they're really truncated in terms of their
development because they haven't been challenged by interpersonal issues and if you really want to kind of really uh
discover and work through a lot of the attachments and limitations and and unhealthy ways in which we can be to be
find a community that you feel like the right place to struggle in for you
then then you're pure you're kind of developing yourself and clarifying
yourself purifying yourself and so the work you want to do Beyond there is does two things you're better at it because
you know the interpersonal stuff really well that's been come that's become your clean Channel now
and the other is you've helped create a model for others about how a community
could be together and having more we need more Community models of healthy community
how does that sound it's very inspiring and it makes me want to just keep trying and to find a good community and to find
a community that I can trust and feel safe in and I think I have a few options I just have to realize it's a process
great great so it's not a community that is every you don't go through a community of just people who are all
Angels no no that's no fun I don't enjoy those
communities anyways but rather it's more like oh these are the people I want to be if I'm going to be in conflict with
someone these are the people I want to be in conflict with
thank you so much thank you so thank you all for being here and
being part of this and I wish you well for this end of the year and and the beginning of the next one
and uh Gloria's hosting the potluck and if you didn't bring anything would like
to stay you're very welcome to stay for it and um
wish you well thank you