so so so for the theme for tonight's teaching
um i wanted to talk about um something that
inspired me actually i was reading uh stephen levine's a year to live i love
the book and there was a there was a few lines that that really struck me and
i thought and they inspired me to dedicate tonight's practice
to this theme so so the theme for tonight is um how to have a bad day well
how to have a bad day well you get the joke right you get the point
right because now and then of course we're gonna have bad days days that are difficult days that
difficulty happens maybe we feel really really sick random example
or just challenges arise and how to have a bad day
well you know we can we can add insult to injury we can
blame ourselves we can resist we can really add second arrows to the first
arrow that's already there all these second arrows or we can have a bad day well
we can meet the challenge the difficulty the misfortune the
whatever it might be with with grace with compassion for ourselves for others
with ease instead of resisting and refusing seeing what is needed what is the
appropriate response right now is it kindness is it care is it rest
is it um [Music] wisdom what is it so what what um having
it a bad day well can really save us um
from a lot of misery a lot of dukkha a lot of pain in this
this life because guess what challenges having what we're calling a bad day or
difficult part of life it's not that you've made a mistake or you're to
blame or or um it's your fault it's it's part of
life to have challenges challenges are part of life
and how can we how can we what are the ways
that we can have a bad day well having a bad day with
grace with generosity with kindness so that is the theme
and i will share this paragraph here from um from stephen levine
uh page 126. if later you guys wanted to go check check it out
um it's actually the next paragraph
actually i want to say one more thing before i read the paragraph and that is also
acknowledging or realizing that the times when things are challenging that looking perhaps back at
how much how much wisdom how much kindness how much
um compassion you've already uncovered in your life and how much momentum you
already have because when there is a challenge it seems like it's all lost it's all oh you're back to
square one but actually turning back and realizing that there's so much momentum that you already have that is going to
support you that is going to support you so taking heart taking heart in that momentum
the forward momentum but that you have uncovered with kindness and compassion and wisdom
through your life so here's the paragraph i wanted to read um [Music]
so so yeah the more the more we practice how to have a bad day well
the better a day it will be and it continues when we stop protecting ourselves from
life each moment takes on a new significance
we come to treasure our being even more than our becoming
i want to read this again it's so beautiful so profound okay i'll start from the top when we
stop protecting ourselves from life
each moment takes on a new significance we come to treasure
our being more than our becoming
each moment of remembering is precious the eternal moment
in which there is no other eternal
moment in which there is no other
so i think that is plenty of sending the frame for tonight's practice and of course
we'll have a chance to to explore together in the guided meditation and in the groups
later and just to say i'm excited tonight for the groups because the prompt would be
how what are some of the wise and compassionate choices you make to have a
a bad day well how do you how do you try to have a bad
day well i think that the wisdom of the community wisdom of the small groups could be
quite quite interesting and juicy tonight so so i hope you hang hang around for that
all right so without further ado let's meditate together
so i'm gonna silence myself and take cough breaks throughout
so inviting ourselves inviting ourselves welcoming ourselves
to this moment this just is sitting here
this moment this body
allowing this body to land
to arrive
just as it is doesn't need to be any different
than it is right now
and releasing releasing
releasing thoughts for this moment releasing tightness holding [Music]
contraction
welcoming welcoming this moment
welcoming yourself this being who is you
simply being in this moment
without the need to become anything or anyone
without the need for becoming [Music]
just celebrating being in this moment
however it shows up
allowing the breath to move through this body
releasing easing [Music] every muscle
every tightness every holding just letting be
letting be releasing relaxing letting be living be
letting be
and turning the gaze inward
to notice to welcome [Music] the sensations of the feet
if you're sitting on a chair planted the bottom of the feed planted
on the earth sense of stability
your sit bones your bottom planted firmly gently and firmly
on the cushion of the chair
and a sense of uprightness in your spine sitting upright
upright upright upright sense of integrity
a brightness not moving fidgeting but just a sense of landing in
your body in your posture the heart
feeling open the chest open to heart open to yourself
in this moment in this intimate infinite moment
letting there be a sense of appreciation is the gentle recognition of kindness
i can naturally be here as you open your heart open your spine your chest
often our physicality not often but always our physicality
impacts our mind our state of mind
can this moment be nourishing is sitting this
being breathed can it be not effortful
not effortful but nourishing
can you sitting here be so easeful
no striving letting go just letting go of any striving or
wanting
to just be let your being be completely embraced
acknowledged appreciated
being human is difficult enough let yourself just be in this moment no
projects no ambitions
to become this or that
be humble be an earthworm
relax the heart just be
especially if you're having a difficult day
any moments of challenge which i bet we've all had here and there
as it's part of being human let there be
even more ease more kindness
in this moment more nourishing
let the breath be the medicine
the most potent medicine soothing
calming like a lullaby
not beating yourself up not comparing yourself
to this ideal unreachable self
not kicking yourself for any challenge or difficulty you've had today
i should have i could have if only let those thoughts
let them rest let them take a break let them take a nap
come come pick a nap it's okay
let there be a nourishing feast of just being
breathed no expectations no becoming
soothing just being
just being with each breath
and if the mind wanders the thoughts of the future or the past
it's okay it's all right it's okay be kind be kind to this mind
this wandering restless mind it's okay sweetie it's okay
rest come rest come be nourished
sitting being breathed with kindness
like a healing soothing self
just being
you don't have to figure anything out right now nothing
just be breathed sit be breathed be nourished
by the breath
by the depth and infinity of this moment
just rest
mm-hmm um
just being briefed
not trying to figure it out not struggling against
anything
is an act of kindness to ourselves such kindness to let go
rest feel nourished just be
letting go again and again again and again taking refuge
and if needed if an extra dose of kindness is needed
given the kind of day or body what's been happening the arrows
slangs and arrows of life of life
it's okay to feel with every in-breath
that you're breathing in kindness breathing out kindness even if you don't
know what that means even if it seems abstract it's okay
breathing in kindness in this body breathing out kindness
or if other words work better for you breathing in care
breathing out care
or breathing in mata breathing out menta
not so many concepts trusting your heart
your mind knows how to do this you don't have to figure it out
and if there are thoughts i can't do this complicated i'm failing you know how to
do this in kindness in this moment let go of the
previous moment just this moment breathing in
breathing out
now i have an invitation for you you can either stay with
the breath or you can explore
these invitations you have choice feeling feeling embodied feeling
the breath in your body acknowledging that there is more call
there is more settledness even if it's a tiny bit more
compared to when you started to sit
acknowledging landing [Music]
in that spaciousness in that extra bit of calm
as if you're inhabiting it more fully owning it yes it's here
i see you [Music] i see you calm
settledness relaxing your body into it
and from a place of embodiment
if it feels okay bring something that was challenging today not the biggest
challenge perhaps it's a minor challenge
open your heart invited to this calm spacious
space of kindness just that moment that lived moment not
into your head not to think about it this is different you invite this moment
into your heart as if a hologram held in your heart with kindness
that moment of challenge maybe you beat yourself up or whatever
it was let your heart open and hold it with
kindness
as if you were able to use the momentum of your
practice
you relive this moment
support the karmic knot of that moment of challenge
ah yes i can be kind to myself
maybe you were kind to yourself already recognize you were having a difficult
time [Music] you were kind you were wise
and it's not too late it's not too late now
to bring kindness to bring generosity compassion to yourself
it's okay sweetheart it's okay that was hard
that was a challenging moment
and noticing how holding yourself with kindness
maybe something drops away maybe some weight drops away
or some recognition arises maybe that it's not needed that extra weight to carry around
it'd be just a split second of seeing
differently and letting go
letting go of the whole exercise returning to the body to the breath
just feeling nourished and breathed for another couple minutes
breathing in kindness breathing out kindness
may we all have the wisdom may we trust
in our inner wisdom and compassion
and rely on it more and more
so that we can have our bad days well
lift them well as a gift to ourselves
as a gift to others all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere including ourselves be happy
may they be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone
may we all learn to practice how to have a bad day well
so we have some time for reflections
for questions for reports from the field
you can type them in chat if you're typed to me privately i won't read your name
you'll be private and if they're typed to everyone i will read both your name and reflection and
you can also raise your zoom hand if it's your physical hand i will not see you because there are many of us online
so any reports from the field what might have came come up for you
with this practice of just being just being not becoming
letting go of becoming or any insights came up as you
as you viewed the challenges of your day with more kindness with more compassion
sandy i see your hand please
i teach preschool kids and it strikes me how much all this applies to them
and pursuing this kind of thing i haven't been to your event before but
it's so helpful for me to be even better preschool teacher
to have deep empathy for them and then watching how
instead of oh you shouldn't feel that way you know it calms them down
so i think the deeper i go the better i can be with them
so thank you so much for all of you all that offer this yeah thank you sandy thank you so much
for showing up for coming to happy hour welcome and for for doing this practice both for
your own sake and clearly for the sake of those you teach and support all these
little ones what a beautiful inside of the calmer and the more stable
your heart becomes oh it's more available to empathize to hold with compassion
these little ones as they're forming these patterns for life
yes yes exactly pattern them for life really transformational
yeah thank you thank you thanks andy beautiful
other reflections questions aha moments challenges
wendy please so i'm pretty new this is my second
happy hour um thank you for for you being here and for everybody
being here so i had a really bad day and um just i mean the day was fine my feelings
were really bad and they're not any better now i mean and i think like having a bad day
well is coming to this rather than distracting myself with something else but
no buts i just i still wanna i just wanna cry yeah you know
and um so i guess to just trust that feelings pass they always pass
yes and i made a good choice
yes yes yay just as you said um
you know the the point of this practice meditation practice
in general not just meta and kindness isn't to make
things go away because sometimes we try to use it as a like make it go away make
it better make it and that's actually using the practice
in not in a skillful way because it will trip us up and it may not go away the challenges might still be there but our
relationships might be different it might the heart as you said right now is still heavy like
oh this has been a hard day and yet the wisdom of having the bad day well not
distracting yourself but coming to a place where you can sit in silence feel nourished have some stability
um have more kindness with the support of sangha that oh yeah they're in that there's a
little more space right there and you feel that space
i trust wendy yeah yeah i see your thumbs up yeah no i
do you yeah yeah and and trust and it's
it's both trusting that feelings emotions everything is transient everything is
impermanent everything of course everything is impermanent right we have this delusion of permits like it'll
never go away this will never change so that's part of that part of the
realization of sweetheart it will go away and yet it's
i think what i like to say is is learning to be okay with not being okay
that there's so much stability we can have there's so much spaciousness and trust
we can have really that sense of trust we can have that even if things are challenging
right now that we can be okay in the midst of not being okay there's there's
more to us and and that our vision sometimes when things are
challenging our vision gets very small that's all we see it's like oh this is just a challenge we come
right it's like like a little binocular that just
focused on the challenge whereas open open it up open it up there's so much more to you
there's so much more to your heart to your your being that this challenge is just
yes it's there but there's so much more here as well so these are a few suggestions for
holding the difficulty having a bad day well thank you
thanks wendy so dear ones let's turn
to our small groups the breakout rooms
break out group breakout rooms which i like to call them breakthrough rooms because so many breakthroughs
really happen in the breakout and for tonight as i mentioned there's a particular prompt
and the prompt is what is one way that today
you have been kind to yourself and maybe an example is oh i brought myself i had a
tough day i brought myself to happy hour this is the way i was kind this is the way i i had a bad day well just as wendy
was was sharing and modeling beautifully like one thing that you did oh i was feeling really cranky and i decided i
was tired i took a nap that was my kindness to myself or whatever it might be just a share of
sharing your uh one way that wisdom and kindness showed up
to to meet a difficulty in the day and if today there has been no difficulty for any of
yesterday this past week the past month and of course a new part of human life is to have challenges but just in case
so uh what what way what way do you meet do you meet and that way
it's so beautiful to let ourselves be held witness by others our own care our own wisdom
and both sharing and let ourselves be seen again we're sharing these not to educate or impress
anyone that's not the point the point is let ourselves be seen and witnessed by
others we're speaking for our own sake we're speaking for our own sake these amazing
other two human beings are just holding us witness so each person will share one nugget not
a long monologue but like one thing you've done today and then the next person will say one thing
then the next person will say one thing and then i'll come back to you you can add more at that point and the next
person the next person go around and around make sure everybody has plenty of
time and let's go in the order of first name alphabetical order just to
make it simple and be kind be kind to yourself be kind
to others really hold witness with uh kindness
and also not a good idea to share to to um
should i put it it's um be be judicious
with how you share what you say you want to feel both
comfortable in in your heart and and also take care of others in a way so
we're taking always taking care of ourselves and taking care of each other okay i think i've said plenty to set the
space so so creating the rooms now give me a moment
and please don't hop off it's so um these rooms can break out
rooms can be so um supportive and if you have to go no
judgment no judgment whatsoever so so creating the rooms
here we go and um wow it's right on
seven o'clock i think we had a lot of reflections um so i tell you what i like to respect the
time and and bring the practice for clothes but i'll stay a couple of extra minutes
afterwards for those who are on zoom if there any reflections you like to share any aha moments that came up
from the small groups would love to hear them so let's dedicate the merit
may all beings everywhere be happy be well be free including
ourselves may all of us practice having a bad day well
[Music]
thank you all