so welcome welcome everyone as always sweet to see the uh the chat line
um okay
that reset
just all at once embrace
all the experience that is your life
i trust wherever you are
safe enough not to read all the signals here are all
the alarm bells of threat and opportunity
it's safe enough just to
melt into this moment
now the vigilance and all the armoring
all the bracing
the numbed out disconnection
all that just melts into the moment too
we become very alive
we surrender some of the reference points the referentiality
sandwiching this moment between the past and the future
diligently keeping track of where i end and you begin
keeping tabs on what we like and what we don't like
all of these reference points squander
the intimacy what's here
what's arising and passing
don't fight with yourself at any level my
teacher said
radical permission
for experience to arise and intensify and crest and
fade
we're truly not getting anywhere
not strategizing to get anything
letting experience soften
our heart through the gesture
of non-resistance intimacy
so natural
for us to get called back to our reference points
the story of me my life
what i want what hurts
it's like we try to take up some perch in samsara
and see everything from there
but the perch is really just more experienced
the illusion of
all our reference points
so we tolerate not knowing
tolerate some concern about
not getting
let me let the heart rest
away every experience becomes exchangeable with every other
it's the dance of a nature
and here resting in equanimity
we don't pick any sides
it's good too um good to sit with you
in this uh realm uh benefited from uh
brudasa wishes that um all beings dance eddie is in the breeze
with minds left silent
by laying to rest all things
um duke uh has displaced dukkha
which has displaced other dukkha
and it's hard to keep track of all the things we might worry about
there's so much to to care about so much to love
and sometimes it feels like our our nervous system wasn't really designed to
care all the time i sort of wish it were
but it doesn't feel that it is and of course how much rest we need how
much the heart needs to rest what constitutes rest that changes over the course of a
practice but
a flower isn't meant to be in bloom all the time right
sometimes i guess confession time i really wanna
i don't they're no closed buds but i really want to pry open the the kind
of pedals that are closed
i guess more accurate confession is not that i really want to it's that i do
sometimes i know that's bad it's bad but it's like
uh i have issues whatever you know this is my impulse but
a flower is not meant to be in bloom all the time
you know heart opens and closes
and i was considering the analogy with with sleep sleep you know
sleep this like pervasive disconnection from our
environment we have our dreams but from what's around us pervasively
disconnected and that comes as a serious opportunity cost to just disconnect for
five or eight or ten hours
but that disconnection actually is necessary for our functioning for our learning for our growth
and our heart needs rest too yeah
and maybe maybe equanimity is the kind of
deepest form of rest for our heart our own hearts way of of sleeping
our heart in other words needs
these moments of being unstimulated
we usually try to to rest
through more stimulation you know it's like we're over stimulated by life
by the human condition by our responsibilities and then to soothe that stimulation we
kind of pile on more stimulation and build a kind of
cocoon of unconsciousness and um
we know those moments right of kind of like
usual usually technologically aided unconsciousness you know
all the streams of data full and that's a kind of rest but our heart
is actually highly stimulated and maybe we say equanimity this fourth
brahmavihara is is something like true rest
so ts eliot says teach us to care and not to care and um
sounds harsh can't stop caring right
just not to care we practice caring and we practice
acknowledging that our our wishes do not govern
the first noble truth do not govern samsara this realm
and the the buddha did
worry about nihilism worried that
the teachings this path might be construed in such a way
it's compatible with nihilism and
wanted to guard against that and it's uh
there's some concern you know in in emptiness one one experience is it's
highly interchangeable with others really the raw material of samsara
doesn't matter much at all
that's what i was alluding to in the sit
everything becomes one one taste
so the the play of change of a nietzsche
and sometimes people get the sense from this
that nothing means anything
and when nothing means anything love dissolves goodness is at risk
but then there's the other side living with the sense that everything
means everything every moment has
tons of riding on it every decision each longing this pain this hope
this lifetime this generation
and everything means everything and then you kind of can't stop caring or giving or
worrying or can't even justify a moment's rest
and so we trace out the middle path
the middle path between everything means everything and nothing means anything we trace out the middle path
and for me a lot of this is around the relationship the balance of equanimity
and compassion equanimity and compassion
and so um two two quotes both about uh the death of uh
one's father representing these two sides for me
somehow they capture it beautifully equanimity and compassion
so the first first uh karl over north guard
um now i saw his lifeless state
and that there was no longer any difference between what once had been my
father and the table he was lying on or the floor on which the table stood or
the wall socket beneath the window or the cable running to the lamp beside
him for humans are merely one form among any
which the world produces over and over again not only in everything that lives but
also in everything that does not live drawn in sand stone and water
and death which i have always regarded as the greatest dimension of life dark
compelling was no more than a pipe that springs a
leak a branch that cracks in the wind a jacket that slips off a clothes hanger
and falls to the floor
and catherine schultz from uh lost and found
this is the essential avaricious nature of loss
it encompasses without distinction the trivial and the consequential the abstract and the concrete
the merely misplaced and the permanently gone
we often try to ignore its true scope if we can but for a while after my
father died i could not stop seeing the world as it really is marked everywhere by the
evidence of past losses and the imminence of future ones
this was not because his death was a tragedy my father died peacefully at 74.
tended through his final weeks by those he loved most
it was because his death was not a tragedy what shocked me was that something
so sad could be the normal necessary way of things
in its aftermath each individual life seemed to contain too much heartbreak for its fleeting duration
history which i had always loved even in its silences and mysteries
suddenly seemed like little more than a record of loss on an epic scale
especially where it could offer no record at all the world itself seemed ephemeral
glaciers and species and ecosystems the place
of change as swift as in time lapse as if
those of us alive today had been permitted
to see it from the harrowing perspective of eternity everything felt fragile
everything felt vulnerable the idea of loss pressed in
all around me like a hidden order to existence
that emerged only in the presence of grief
the hanger jacket slipping to the floor
or something so sad the shock of something that's so
sad could be the normal necessary way of things
and so we have equanimity and compassion in relationship
in relationship
equanimity perhaps purifies our compassion
our compassion when purified by equanimity becomes
less compulsive less co-dependent less grandiose the self-righteous
more patient
and then our compassion is strengthened by equanimity actions arising from
equanimity are more potent have greater moral force
than those arising from clinging
and so we we zigzag our way through caring and not
caring finding finding the balance that's right in our
heart for our energy for what we're willing to give right now
and we rest and we serve and we rest and we serve
offer this for consideration
so uh so thank you um
it's been um good to be with you this uh this week and um
yeah i appreciate the uh the opportunity to uh
um yeah to to explore these themes together which feels very much actually in
dialogue even though all we've got is the chat and me talking but uh feels very much like a
relationship and aliveness and um
yeah so so i will um wish you wish you well stay stay on the
chat and um there are any questions might be able to
i've been reading catherine schultz often so that's lost and found
um gill has one more week of retreat i
believe nikki is here next week and then gil will return the following
so um yeah thank you thank you all yeah may you
may be well