so good evening everyone and welcome nice to be with you all nice to sit here
and uh I've been sitting here you know
during this pandemic um sitting here teaching alone
with the camera a lot of the time
and but to have 45 minutes to sit with others in silence something we used to do all the time and I think I took it
for granted but I haven't had that much experience of it over the last period
so it was nice to sit with you this way thank you
and um I debated whether just to take the evening as a time for questions and
responses but um maybe we can still mostly do that
but partly out of that sitting and a little bit I've been thinking about this or being with this topic for the day I
want to share with you and um there is a lot of value
if all you do in meditation is nothing
if you sit up straight or some appropriate medical you know their way
of being with your posture kind of present here
and then notice all the ways you try to do something
some of it is you notice that you know if you've been kind of running around all day you might feel that your body is
still kind of running wants to run around and you feel kind of the urge to vote or to move or to shift or
um and then the eyes don't want to sit still the eyes are doing something they're still darting around maybe
and then slowly just by doing nothing um things settle and quiet down
or you might notice that you're thinking a lot and the thinking is soft into doing a lot of thinking is motivated by
some form of wanting wanting something or not wanting something and there's a kind of activity of doing
wanting reaching trying to understand remembering planning
figuring things out telling stories to yourself it is a kind of a doing
and if the rest of you doesn't do much if you sit quietly with your eyes closed
sooner or later you start noticing all this doing in the mind and you might also notice that the kind
of the mind at some point doesn't want to do it anymore it's like you know it's a lot this is a
tiring or you know isn't there some other way of being maybe it's just you know enough of that already somehow the Mind itself will sometimes
begin to settle partly because if there's a lot of thinking there's tension in the mind or
pressure and so you feel the tension and pressure after a while and that's the that's kind
of represents some of this doing momentum of the Mind and just sit quietly it kind of settles
down and quiets things quieter and quieter and a lot of it comes from not doing
and I say it because some people bring the habit of doing and fixing and making
something happen and trying to attain something trying to get concentrated with them into the meditation practice
and it's not uh wrong to do that in fact sometimes it's helpful and nice to have that sort of intention or direction that
you're practicing but a lot happens just by not doing
keeping it really really really simple and for sometimes as you know as a teacher I
some people who are you know really doing is their specialty
I'll tell them to in meditation that the only thing they should do in meditation
is to avoid doing anything just that's it like I I given I
shouldn't give them any practice like folk follow your breath that's just too much doing for them just just be really attentive to every
movement of the Mind the heart the body to try to do something make something happen fix something
and just don't do it so they just don't do it a school of meditation
and what's remarkable about this it is not a passivity if you're sitting you
can fall asleep if you're laying down or too slouched in the couch or something but it's not passivity
it's the releasing of a healthy kind of energy inside of us there's a different
kind of flow of attention of sensations of aliveness of presence that's
available in the body that it's very different feeling than that of being agitated or over
caffeinated you know like you plug yourself into an electric outlet and like wow
and um you know you feel kind of Jake all Jane gold or something but as we
settle some of the tiredness some of the tensions some of the all kinds of things
begin to settle away and something gets released inside and some people call it a movement
towards Harmony where the energies the sensations the feelings the emotions the in our body
begin to kind of gather together organize themselves settle and there can
be start being a nice feeling of of the there's comfortable to be in the body it's nice
to be here even if there's pain sometimes there's pain in the body even so there might be some other parts of
the body where there's a kind of a nourishing feeling of wholeness nourishing feeling of presence or of um
kind of like you're in a warm bath you know wow this is cool and um and the remarkable thing is
that's the kind of a good feeling really good to be in your body it's like really good to be present and be here
can come believe it or not if I'm not doing anything but you're kind of like a high quality
not doing you know really really sitting up and not just letting be letting be letting
be and then sooner or later and what becomes even more delightful
is uh with this at some point what's kind of not the only thing that left which would become stands out in
highlight is that our minds can know our minds can be aware
and awareness which is not being um recruited to accomplish something to
do something it's not being hijacked to be critical or angry or about something
or to be somehow you know it's not being hijacked by thoughts which are kind of undermining
or those which are somehow mean-spirited in some direction or other
uh there are thoughts that the the awareness becomes more and more left
alone because the doing quiets down and the
and the awareness starts to become a kind of uh Lucid clear vibrant it
becomes its own kind of wonderful thing like just like the body feels like you're in a bath after a while that the
mind the awareness can feel like um and the fog is cleared
it was just like suddenly you know the clouds with fog has to speak clearance completely everything's so clean and clear and it feels so good
foreign talk was a little bit of a
coming out of an appreciation for how much can happen by not doing in meditation
and one of the ways to use mindfulness is to be attentive and very attentive to
how you're starting to do something oh there it is trying to make something happen trying
to get trying to get rid of something and see and experiment with nice and Chase it's really good to see all that
and and back away just okay don't do it just let it be and then see what happens next and see
what happens next and so the mindfulness is used to support this not doing rather
than mindfulness being used um in support of attaining or getting or
fixing or correcting or whatever else it gets caught in
and um so I offer these the words kind of like a little bit in a kind of oh that I feel this evening there's a
whole process of what can happen we can unfold and we sit and meditate that it can feel like super
healthy super good and um
and you didn't accomplish anything imagine that
anyway so that's my words I hope they make some sense I hope they're a little bit inspiring for you too maybe
appreciate the value of not doing in this kind of high quality way in which
we do it in meditation so now if you have any questions comments or protests
hey you're welcome to uh to take the mic and speak
hi good evening thank you so much for the sitting what's your name what's your name um and Rose and oh hi
um the part where you were saying go about like noticing when you are doing
something but but what about like when you're trying to investigate try to investigate you
know that or like anything with like with the those acronyms or the raft I mean isn't that like a good thing yeah
yeah yeah well there's many ways of practicing mindfulness and so there are ways that are more active like this and
um I spend a lot of time in meditation just being with my breathing I choose my breathing I'm there with it so I'm kind
of a doing something there and um and sometimes uh using like the
raft is really helpful the acronym you know practice because if you don't do it it's worse
and um because then you're really caught up in everything but if you go through this kind of Investigation things settle
down you see clearly what's happening and you see what it you see what you can stop doing you see what you can relax
so part of over time what we learn in doing this practice that we learn when it's
wise to be a little bit more actively involved and to do something like this and when we're better off backing off
and doing nothing but both are needed and at different times different things are useful and so
I think the maybe a little bit that talk my words today were motivated by
I meet a lot of meditators who err on the side of the doing part
and they don't understand the not doing part very well both both are good and if
right now you're kind of learning and getting your bearings with the doing part and you're enjoying it and it's
working for you can doing it well it's not so much enjoyment just
being aware that I am doing something that I would I would probably rather not want to be doing so just
but up thank you once you notice you're doing something you're not wanting you don't want to do
you uh the uh you might be halfway there oh wow so don't underestimate how
powerful it is to somebody say oh look at them doing it again I'm doing it I don't want to do this
um congratulate yourself and then let it be just okay I'm gonna watch you for a while
I'm just going to be with you for a while as opposed to getting in there and immediately and do something so see if
you can appreciate what you've done and maybe maybe that's all you need to do now you can just okay I'm gonna keep my
eye on you and and what will happen is it'll probably settle by itself then
thank you so much that was really helpful a lot of the a lot of the difficult things we do in our mind and this is not it's not always true
um don't they can't really be sustained if they're being watched
and so you don't have to do anything but watch
so so someone else
hello I haven't been here for years it's so
nice to come back in person I'm Lika and um
in my family add runs in our jeans and so this idea of not doing is I feel more
difficult it's difficult more difficult yeah on that level because the mind is
constantly distracted externally also
we get paid to be very efficient and do a lot here in Silicon Valley oh
yes good it's so efficient you know efficiency get it done do do do to-do
lists right um so since I'm not retired yet
or independently wealthy How can I sit with nothing and do nothing when
everything around me is always make moving moving moving and like my mind always grabs on like that there's a
secret visualization practice is when you when Silicon Valley is
coming down heavy on you telling you should to be efficient you visualize yourself this is taking your tongue out
at all of the Silicon Valley [Laughter]
that's what you think of that at least when you're meditating it's like leave me alone enough already
um so so um yeah you know we have an episode of
these things become habits or become kind of even addictions at times to doing and making all that so it's really
helpful to have some something like meditation that breaks the momentum of being pulled and caught and on and on
and on it's unhealthy the way that people are caught in the efficiency cycle and doing
and doing and pretty soon they're being efficient in
Recreation play eating sex you know sooner quicker the better right
so because we want to be efficient so so there's coming to Habit so you
want to kind of you know learn break break that cycle if it can but it's hard you know the addictions
are mental addictions habits are hard to break and sometimes meditation is sometimes
it's not strong enough and sometimes exercise is stronger you know other things sometimes you know
work better than sitting meditating if it's really get caught in something and then for uh people have so-called
attention deficit disorder I have friends colleagues I have a friend close friends who are meditation
teachers who have that so it's possible you know to have that kind of mind it's
better not to call it a disorder it's just another way of mind's work and then you have to just learn how to use he
worked that mind and use that use that kind of mind and what my friends have learned to do is one of them especially
he concentrates in short spurts I can he can get very concentrated for a
few seconds and he's just content with that and then he gets around to doing again gets around through it again and so he but he
can't keep the focus but he just does it in small spurts and he's just very happy with that and it's worked to work really well for him
there's some shows other ways of doing it but
I was there someone told me that there's a Buddhist country in Asia where the Buddhist monks have been
prohibited to teach teachings on contentment because if content workers don't work
very hard
hi my name is Nicole and um I'm really glad to be here again after so long not
being here so thank you um I was just listening to what this
young lady was saying and I really agree with that is that we're taught you know especially as women to be efficient and
to do do do and take care of everything but what I found in my practice is that
when I meditate and I take that time just to blank my mind out for some
reason I I can't explain it you maybe can explain it but I'm more efficient
it's like there's a time to be efficient and there's a time not to be and once I learned how to separate and give myself
the permission not to be like let's say here for 45 minutes something happens in
the mind where I'm able to keep track of things better I'm able to be more
efficient I'm able to get more done but it's kind of compartmentalize like there's a time and a place for it but
when I added meditation and blanking out my mind I got more efficient when it was
time to be official yeah yeah yeah exactly I feel the same way there's a way in which the mind that's overly busy
is scattered and not really be able to focus very well and it's also not very intelligent it's not very not very
creative and so a settled mind A Quiet Mind a focused mind sometimes is much more uh
just efficient or creative and just really being present for what needs to be done maybe Alex makes less mistakes
doesn't forget as much things and the mind is more organized and available and
attentive and I've I I do that sometimes if I feel
like I don't have enough time for it all the things my to-do list um I'll meditate
and it seems like the last thing you should do when you have you know waste your time meditating when you could be
doing things but I find that when I finish even 10 minutes of meditation I
have so much more time than I thought before and then I go about doing what I do and I it seems like it all works out
I think it brings about a a better perspective yeah yeah
hi I'm Caroline and this is a ongoing
question that I've had that I ask many people about but always wanting to find
out more tips and tricks I can get to a point where I'm
doing nothing doing in into the into the nothing the white room a little bit
louder I I can get into the white room yeah um but
I usually have this song stuck in my head and the song
changes but there's always a song that's kind of just pops in and just and I don't know
what to do with that yeah because there's you know I'll notice it and I'm
like okay there's that but it's just it's distracting it can be
distracting yeah well if it's not distracting you can sometimes some people have succession
leaving it in the back depending you know in the background and just continue with their meditation
and then no no don't worry about it um some people find it useful to
um try to understand what's going on with the songs going on you said it's
distracting that might be it's very reason to be there maybe it's uh
something I know some people they use the songs in their head to comfort themselves when they're anxious
and so I know one person who had for years in meditation until she saw wow
every time I get a little anxious that's when the songs begin and once you understood that then it
became a whole different world to live in and so to kind of sometimes to let this let the singing go on but then feel kind
of in the cracks of it is there any what's what's the subtle emotions that seems to be behind it
and is there something some discomfort some anxiety some something that seems
to come along with it and if it is then we would bring mindfulness to that not to the songs
and see what happens see if that can be settled um it's it's tough though because
songs are very very often sorry it can be difficult because songs can sometimes
be very easily leading you into memories yeah you know exterior things so it's
it's yeah but it's interesting to say all right just so it might be interesting for you to uh really learn
mindfulness of emotions and it's possible if you develop a much really rich or really
um you know uh skilled understanding of how
to recognize and how to practice how to be with emotions that this would give you a big handle on what's going on for
you and so um I don't know if you ever heard the have heard the intro class but the the third
day of the intro class that I I've taught for years you find it on Audio Dharma his mindfulness of emotions and
there's all kinds of talks on different emotions and mindfulness you know emotions and if you get a handle on the
emotions thing it'd probably go a long way just learn the skill like the raft thing
and um the um you know it's possible that the the
you know being caught being distracted in songs is um a tip of the iceberg or the
the wormberg or something of something some depth inside of you something really deeper that you haven't really
addressed or connected it's just just the beginning of something it's a deeper intimacy deeper connection to something
really important so I would uh you know things well worth looking into
and then if it's just that turns out it was just a habit that you're caught in and then sometimes you can uh I've known
people who who then um went along with the singing
but they changed the song and uh and I know some people who
there's a there's a kind of a loving kindness songs that people do and they sing the love and kindness phrases at a
nice tune and they just do that and then the Mind wants to go into the old songs but it's busy with a living kindness
kind of tune that you're playing and that's healthy and good and that kind of begins changing the the kind of shakes
it up in there a little bit then maybe breaks the habit and then you can start singing slower and slower until you get
quiet those are all very helpful thank you
it's a real bracket here today Jim they're back and forth again
[Laughter]
yeah sorry about that Jim you're getting your workout my name is Anne
uh so I've got a number of Health stuff going on that have got me all kind of
worried and during the day I seem to be able to you know just notice the emotions notice
the worry notice the fear whatever whatever and I've I have ways of processing it or managing it or just
observing it whatever but lately I've been waking up at like
three in the morning and the mind is all wanting to solve all the world's problems that I'm dealing
with and the brain doesn't I don't have access to any of the the
processing you know things okay this is how we can handle now we don't need to deal with this now we'll deal with it tomorrow it doesn't work at three in the
morning and so I end up like losing an hour of sleep and I'm wondering if you've got ideas of
sleep meditation something to deal with the three o'clock in the morning
Baddies  I don't know what the the one thing
that's useful to do is if you get a sense that this is a regular pattern so when you wake up and there it is again the same pattern same way and you you
know you have worries but same patterns the same kind of same same degree of
wakefulness say My Everything feels the same like here I am I've tried the best I can to fall asleep but I've laid on
that side and this side still left counted cheap I've done everything but I know what's going to happen here I'm just going to be awake for the next hour
an hour and a half and maybe I'll fall asleep at some point but but you know this is this I mean this is
what's happening is um is uh get up and meditate
just get out of bed and go find your meditation seat and um and just take the meditation
posture because the quality of attention uh in the meditation posture quality of
beginning to kind of not get caught in the concerns it's much higher in the meditation posture or meditation than
laying in bed and so it might break the the
the reactivity or the Cycles or the pull or kind of let something relax more deeply then you can relax when you're
laying there that's that's brilliant yes I've gotten up and walked into the kitchen and
gotten something to drink and that will sometimes break it but this sounds like a more direct yeah and you might not
even prepare yourself so you have like a right have it all set up all set up so you just have a warm blanket you can
just put around you right away and and just sit there and be in for a while and
it's remarkable that I was really surprised when I started meditating that even when I had a good night's sleep I
would get to meditate in the morning and I was uh be more relaxed and rested after the meditation than I had when I
woke up from meditation so there's something can really qualitative good can happen there so so two things can
happen one is it allows you to relax and let go and settle the other because we're practicing
mindfulness you might discover better than you are in bed what's really going on
maybe there's something that needs to be addressed yeah thank you
and there's also something which happens apparently that um
some of it might just be aging and so it just kind of like as some
people are getting older don't sleep as well and wake up in the middle of the night and rather than taking it being in
some great big psychological problem it said maybe your sleep patterns are
changed and
so you know maybe other things to be shifted so you can wake up in the middle of the night and do something efficient
and then go back to bed go back to you know and sleep in late
you know
foreign I'm Amanda
it's been a while several years perhaps that I've meditated at in this Buddhist
fashion but I have been micro dosing meditation
I realized that the important parts of the day to keep them from
running into each other I could just take
three breaths if I could even remember one two three
it would help me to move quietly from one
activity to the next and I do that quite a lot
during the day whenever I think about it and when I go to sleep
so today when I came here to sit
it was as if I had leg room that I hadn't forgotten
the whole meditation process I had kept it with me in kind of a
little bag and to be able to sit here and just
be at leisure reminded me that I hadn't forgotten fantastic kind of
second nature was in there waiting for you and you kept it alive these three minutes three breath meditations yes
what a great thing you're doing running through the day thank you
yeah I love the expression micro dosing on meditation [Music]
I hear it's good for depression too
hi my name is Jay um so I've been spending I haven't spent too much time on super study but
moderately and you know the sense I get often
is I read it and sometimes I can feel it's just loaded you know more than just what
it's just the words I can feel a sense of compactness in it
and when I encounter there are times when there are like
three refrains you know how they're well this stuff is repeated like this
refrains like it goes like three times yeah so those times I I by the time I get to
the third time I'm sort of checked out and my question is this I feel like
the Buddha doesn't say this is the sense I get that he doesn't say anything non-essential
keeps it you know tight and compact and uh
so when I read this it feels like um that's the right word
it almost goes uh against the grain of all the other but not when he doesn't repeat
versus repeating there's a there's a difference I'm not sure I'm explaining this right
this is in reading the scriptures yeah so I'm wondering why he repeats three
times you know oh is there is there is there a more because the flavor of that feels very
different from all the other when he's not repeating it feels so Compact and essential and like you know he said
everything he wanted to say because you know but here he feels like you sort of so so this ancient this ancient
literature that that was originally composed to be chanted
and uh and when we you know when you enchant the refrain when you sing if you don't don't listen
[Laughter] a song that has a refrain
um most people are quite happy that there's a comfort in that and uh and a
familiarity and a delight to be able to oh there's the refrain and you go back into it there's the Rhythm and everything and it just feels really good
and it goes sinks deeper and deeper I've done years of chanting Buddhist chanting now repeat the same thing over and over
again and it goes in deeper and deeper it's almost like the layers each time you change it goes in deeper because
there's a different avenue of absorption enchanting than in reading that we then
it's very different and so uh this um this ancient chance which we became
translated into English and printed it's kind of deadly to read sometimes I
mean it's the same if you want to go to sleep read some of it
it's um so just answer your question yes and uh when when you guys chanted it was
that in Pali was it in English sometimes in oh sometimes I've done all kinds of things probably English sino-japanese
well any feeling effect even if it is in a different language oh then it's then it's not the words don't mean so much to
me then but then it's the chanting uh the um the Rhythm so this the Rhythm the
tone The Voice the the vibrations in the body the concentration
that's needed sometimes you run a chant in a different language you have to be more con really present and by the time
I finish chanting uh you know I'm not distracted anymore so it's very focusing and that's the
other you know so what you might do if you're like to read these sutas is um memorize some of
it and then uh and then repeat it from memory over and over again see how it
affects you just not you can just do it you can't just be repeated in your mind doesn't that be out loud but uh see in the
ancient world they didn't have books either and you couldn't go to the library and pick up a book or you know like I'll
I'll look at this later you know the only time it was there is well either you had to hear someone speak it or you
have to memorize it and people's ability to memorize was much better back then our ability to memorize has decreased
dramatically in our culture and um and then people would memorize it and then they have their library with them and
then they'd repeat it to themselves to think about it and be with it and um but
memorization also requires much more something deeper inside of us than just
knowledge wow that's great uh just to follow up on that so sometimes I go to the Zen Center
in the city and you know I used to skip the after the 540 sit at the end they would have
the you know the service and lately I've been staying and
sometimes the chant in English and then they turn it and sometimes they chant in Japanese and when I do the Japanese one it feels
awkward like I don't understand anything but from what I'm taking you're saying still do it there's still um there's a
there's something yeah yeah but give yourself over to it
uh and if you find any resistance or any boredom or any
um judgments about it or you know anything that's uh that's all extra
and you look you can learn not to succumb to those kinds of reactions to what's happening and just kind of give
yourself over to it completely as if it's the most important thing in the world and by the time you finish
your mind will be still and quiet if you're struggling with it then angry
and why am I doing this and it's a foreign language I can't understand it this is ridiculous it's a self-fulfilling prophecy
it is if you think it that way but if you don't think that you it can
become something quite meaningful great thank you
yeah the we should say this is chant the heart suture in English I used to center it a lot and there was something very
powerful you know there's these lines no ears no no eyes no ears no nose no tongue nobody to do to do it's like drum
beat and it goes over and over it kind of goes deeper and deeper and it's like this negation that you hear and like
something let go something let's go something lets go each time I mean I didn't even know what was being let go but like look everything goes everything
goes and it's just like you know it was kind of lovely emptying
it's a gym up here
hi my name is Michael um earlier you spoke about the mindfulness or meditation of doing
nothing versus doing something and I was going to ask what would you suggest is probably the best way to segue between
the both um enjoy yourself enjoy it it it took me
back to a time when I was a kid in mass and trying to get through church rather quickly and doing the prayers and the
Hail Marys and our fathers and oh no he's the the clock didn't move and sometimes I'll catch myself in the
middle of mindfulness and am I doing it right am I doing it wrong and I try and segue between doing something doing
nothing yeah I think all those things you have
all those tendencies in your mind the response to all of them is slow down
thank you slow down
so that was nice thank you and maybe you know maybe we have it just we're supposed to have five
more minutes so um could we have the mic go around you say your name I kind of like to kind
of feel the whole group and hear all the voices Caroline
Sterling Janus
Allen Jay Vishnu
Irina Jamie
Sally Lika
Michael
a Jim Mike
Amanda hi everyone Anne Rose
Nicole and
Kurt mark
Hanya Sue
bill Clarissa
Sue Laura
Sage is there a big one wonderful thank you all very much thank
you for coming and uh I appreciate this very much to have this chance to be with you this way
and and I hope that you have a wonderful week and
thank you