so good evening those of you here and
in the west coast and hello to everyone else wherever you are
and happy to be here have a chance to be here in monday evening and
uh you know for a good part of the last 30 years i've come down
to teach these monday evening talks and so they're quite quite um
um close to my heart to be here and so i appreciate this opportunity
and for the
meditation this evening i would like to suggest
an idea that you're welcome to ignore
if it doesn't work for you but the idea is that you would sit
practice mindfulness during this next 30 minutes or so
to do it with courage had any indication that there's fear
sit with courage and you might be surprised by the layers
of fear that we go through as the mind relaxes
it's like going through the layers of the mind layers of the heart and not uncommonly there's places of
fear and certain layers or certain corners and to not see it as a mistake
to not see it as indication that something's wrong with you or wrong with anything
but rather see it's something for this period of time something to sit
with but to sit with courage a courage that maybe also
allows you to do it with the heart curl in french the word courage comes
from heart the kind of courage that
keeps your heart open keeps you so present and aware and
willing to experience what's here for you
so this is not the courage of bracing yourself or stealing yourself through something
but rather the courage to be present for whatever is
but to be present kindly but with a kindness that's strong
to sit with courage so to begin by assuming a meditation
posture that has some qualities characteristics of courage
that evoke some courage for you
if you're sitting maybe sitting a little more upright than confident
adjusting your neck so that your neck also
somehow has space at the back of the neck
for there to be a kind of strength and courage
maybe the chest is a little bit expanded
not proudly not effortless effortfully but just as you sit up straight to allow
the chest to expand in a confident way
in a way that perhaps brings your heart to the forefront
the sensitivity the emotional sensitivity that is there in the your heart
is awakened and then
gently close your eyes and taking some long slow deep breaths
but see if it's possible to do so with a sense of courage or strength
perhaps even to use a dangerous concept maybe even with some sense of power
the power of presence the power of showing up and being
present here and now
and as you exhale to relax without giving out the up the strength
and the courage but relaxing whatever tension is unnecessary
soften relax
and letting your breathing return to normal
and if it's available maybe you'll feel a gentleness
in the breathing some parts of the breathing might feel
the cycle of breathing might feel gentle
soft peaceful
and courage and strength can coexist with this tenderness softness
gentleness of the breathing
gently relaxing on the exhale
relaxing their mind relaxing and quieting your thinking
so there's more room and awareness to show up and be present
here in this body with courage and strength
and with peacefulness and gentleness
breathing in and breathing out
and there's where you come to the end of the sitting
can you tap into a place of quiet courage
strength
the courage not to assert yourself on the world but the courage to show up fully
be present for yourself all of who you are
be present for others for all of who they are
when there's some courage perhaps it's easier also to have respect
for oneself and to have respect for others
may we as we come out of this meditation aspire
to be present for others and for ourselves
with a steady presence with attentiveness and listening and
curiosity
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so hello and
on this pla on this evening of martin luther king's
holiday and i would like to read a quote of his
people fail to get along because they fear each other
they fear each other because they don't know each other they don't know each other because they
have not communicated with each other
so someone read this to me or posted this
just a couple hours ago and i was struck by it and
thinking of martin luther king as a great champion for
non-violent civil disobedience nonviolent protest
i remember that my first real interest in buddhism
was when i was a freshman in college
and i was of the age that could be drafted for the war in vietnam
and so that was a big topic of discussion the other freshmen
and i took the i always had the seemingly the extreme pacifist position
i didn't believe in war and wasn't going to fight in a war
and um so i had this very strong ideal
pacifist ideal but i didn't think of past this kind of
pacifism as being passive as being doing nothing
i felt that it to live up to this ideal i had to be willing to put my life on
the line at a protest or to confront some of the injustices in
society and i recognized that i was afraid
to do so and i didn't feel good about having fear not to live up to
my ideals so i searched around
for how to address this fear and i don't think i had any
strong irrational reasons for this but for some reason
i came upon buddhist practice that this was the way
to find how to work with this fear to work through this fear and it didn't really propel me into the
world of practice that was a still a year or two away but
it was kind of the first kind of
interest that i had so to
hear this wonderful quote from martin luther king today
and that about fear and that um
the people fear each other and i think that uh
he's saying something very important here that sometimes assertion of
power over over others sometimes hate
mistrust can have its root in fear
and there's many things that we fear i think it's a hugely
pervasive pervasive attitude many people have anxiety
and and part of buddhist practice is to
encounter that fear to meet that fear to learn to be present for it
and to not cower from the fear but rather to
show up for it to really find a place within
that has the capacity to be with fear
not succumbing to fear and part of the
wonderful possibility of meditation and mindfulness is to learn how to show up in a strong
way how to be present in a strong way to what is challenging what is difficult
including fear and life is very different
if we are not influenced by our fear now there are certainly things to be
appropriately afraid of and buddhism recognizes that there's
appropriate fear and inappropriate fear skillful fear and unskillful fear
and compromising our ethical integrity
is something to be appropriately afraid of succumbing to hatred
or greed is something to be appropriately afraid of
but succumbing to anxiety and so coming to our imagination
of what we think is dangerous is not appropriate it's not helpful
and to be able to distinguish between the fear that's appropriate and the fear that's inappropriate is part of the
benefit that comes from stopping and taking a good look at fear understanding what it's about
and uh is it uh about the future and if it's about the future how much
does the imagination play that role and how strong is your image imagination
sometimes the imagination is so strong that its tendrils of imagination reach
down into our muscles and activate them with fear sensations
fear contractions and the fear can feel so much more anxiety and so much more real
it doesn't feel like it's imaginary it feels real because the imagination has triggered a real response in the body
and it's not to be dismissive of the power of fear or the challenge or fear
and it's certainly not to be dismissive of fear itself fear maybe should always be seen as a
messenger and it's a messenger that something here needs attention
and sometimes is that what needs attention is what's in the world so as martin luther king said
that if we don't know each other that we can be afraid of each other
and so the fear of others might be a message that we should get to know the other person
i've had many kind of um negative feelings for people
and but by going and talking to them
i'm surprised how quickly they go away and sometimes i've had you know that
could be also with people that we're afraid of and occasionally it's because people we
have occasion reason to be afraid we have the wisdom to know when it's
appropriate but sometimes we go be counterphobic
show up and say you know what's happening here and can you tell me what's you know tell me
what's happening and can i get to know you let me tell you something about myself
and so fear is a multi-faceted complicated
thing one of the things we want to be careful for when we
are mindful is not to see fear as a mistake or that we're bad or that
it's something wrong but rather it's a sign of something that
we want to show up for and sometimes we want to show up for ourselves and there are layers of fear
within ourselves that really could use our attention
and the attention that i've learned that is most helpful for
the layers of fear within us is the is the attention that helps the
fear feel safe that helps the fear uh
not feel like you're being dismissed or seen as wrong or we're trying to escape
from it and run away from it and
so [Music] an awareness an attention a mindfulness
that holds the fear that's present for the fear the image that
has been very very valuable for me is the image of taking my hands and
cupping them together and coming underneath something and just holding it there
and so coming underneath and holding the fear touching the fear
helping the fear rest in the in the palms of awareness
and then breathing with the fear and meditation is a fantastic place to
do this because hopefully when we sit and meditate in that time
there's nothing to fear there's no external dangers that are threatening us and so maybe it's a place where it's
safe enough to offer this kind of attention to fear and see what it opens up to and where to
where it takes us and sometimes it takes us deeper and deeper into ourselves
and sometimes it takes us into the ability the strength and the courage to be able to talk to others get to know
them better and hopefully let them get to know us better
i wonder how often people's despair
[Music] upset um about
what's happening in the world is based on fear that is reasonable enough to have
but the fear is unduly influencing us that somehow we've allowed the fear to
take over as opposed to having the fear accompany us
i learned some years ago that i had fear
and i i just felt i just imagined the fear was sitting on my shoulder
it accompanied me through a situation that was a had some danger involved and
and but i i was not afraid but fear was present for me
and and i kind of came to i just came i didn't think that i would be able to
not be afraid i would not have the fear but i could
i knew how not to have the fear take over so i just imagined was sitting on my left shoulder and it was my companion
as i went through the dangers i was doing going through
so one of the
possibilities with mindfulness practice with mindfulness is to cultivate a new relationship with
fear a new relationship with anxiety one in which
we it's not only it doesn't somehow have an impact on us because we show up
strong enough courageous enough that we're able to be present and breathe with it without believing it necessarily
or identifying with it or taking it on without letting the
the all the muscles kind of contract and react around the fear so the fear gets um accentuated
so what if the gift that we able to give the world
is the gift of fearlessness and what this means in buddhism
is that um it's a gif giving people the gift that they
don't have to be afraid of us and so rather than being so focused on
our own fear one way to let put the fear up on its
place on the left shoulder perhaps is to turn the whole fear thing around
and offer ourselves to the world as someone that others do not have to be afraid of
to offer the gift of fearlessness and
and also there's a gift of fearlessness for ourselves that we do not fear
and when we don't fear others that's a gift to them as well it's not a healthy thing
to have anxiety and fear for others now there are times where it's
appropriate to be afraid of others they are dangerous and um
but there's plenty of times when that the fear we have the social fears we have
maybe are not as appropriate as the emotion believes maybe we don't have to succumb to it
and so to learn how to to give ourselves the gift of fearlessness
either by not having the fear or having a strength and a presence where we
we recognize the fear but we are stronger than the fear
so to sit with fear to practice with fear and to begin discovering that we have
strengths that we didn't know to have courage
to have a heart that can has the strength to stay open and
present and sensitive to this world a heart that can look directly
at what is happening look reality right in the eye and see for what it is
i don't think what i'm saying this evening is easy it's not something it is something that
requires wisdom and care but it's a wisdom that comes from stopping and taking a good look
really studying a situation look if recognizing what's really happening
so that fear is not doesn't evoke the imagination or running away or
cutting ourselves off from what's happening but we use it as a reminder
now is it's a messenger now is the time to pay more careful attention
what's really happening here and if it is a real real world danger
then perhaps we're in a better position to take care of ourselves and find safety and if it's a
comes from social anxieties or imaginary fears of what could and
possibly can happen in the future i wonder if there's not there isn't
another alternative than changing the world running away
but rather to the opportunity to really stop and breathe with fear and take a look at
fear hold the fear and find the strength the power
the courage to be with the fear
in a way that helps the fear be safe helps the fear feel reassured
because it's being held in the strength and courage of your good heart
so those are my thoughts this evening for martin luther king's holiday
i think that i don't know how much fear martin luther king had but
he certainly was a courageous man
who kept showing up in all kinds of situations of great danger
and it took a lot of courage to show up in his non-violent way when others wanted to harm him
i think it's a great lesson and it's a great buddhist lesson
to live the power of non-violence with courage
the dedication to change the world for the better
because if we can change the world even in the smallest kind of ways
we do change it for everyone and to change it
in the direction of fearlessness of safety of getting to know people of
communicating deeply so that in that knowing in that communication in that
recognizing each other the depths of other people are humanity perhaps we teach
we learn ourselves not to fear others but maybe also more importantly
we teach others not to fear us
may we give each other the gift of fearlessness may we all live in safety
thank you