i'm struck by all the greetings and good mornings good days and
one i think is in portuguese and maybe tomorrow when we gather all of you
all of you who do speak uh whatever language you speak whatever
your native language is if you want to offer the greetings in your native language in english
certainly and any other it'd be fun to see all the different
kind of languages of greeting
so i offer you a warm hello from redwood
city here at imc in our second gathering for the new year
and one of the things that we are
discovering in mindfulness practice is
new new a new relationship to our capacity to be
aware we're discovering something new about attention
and attention awareness is something that where that many of us will use
throughout the day unself-consciously without much attention and
and it kind of needs to be that way we get through the day more efficiently if we just don't have to think about being aware so
much but i but in mindfulness practice we're
beginning to discover the nature of something which is very intimate it's kind of always with us
when we're in our conscious moments is to be aware to pay attention
and um and uh mindfulness itself is kind of a i i
think of it as a heightened awareness it's possible to
be rivetedly involved in some kind of absorbed in some conversation with someone
and i might put down my glasses and and forget where i put them like just
now i went look to my right when i just a moment ago i put it down to my left and um
and uh and putting down the glasses not to be so attentive to the fact of putting them
down attentive enough to let it register in some deeper way
and so this idea of heightened awareness maybe could be
expressed in the little saying that when we do mindfulness practice we stop
for awareness we stop to be aware
whatever is happening whatever is going on um uh
in the moment we're bringing if we're if we're attentive we're bringing kind of a we're stopping to be
aware to let things register in a fuller way and uh
and so what we do as we do this meditation now
the mindfulness of breathing the whole and the whole endeavor the
whole adventure of mindfulness practice the journey of mindfulness
in the instructions of the buddha it begins with
a heightened knowing registering
of the experience of breathing and
so when i was driving down here today i needed a certain ongoing attentiveness
to the road to the driving and i couldn't just kind of be casually
you know paying attention to other things i had to be here with the road
when i came down here to imc i looked at these big windows we have here to my left that have these wooden
frames and because i was going to give this talk i asked myself what's it like
to see something new in these windows i've seen them for a
long time i look at them every day but it wasn't so much interested in finding
something new but what's what kind of attention do i use so that i can discover something new
what is that a little more sharper focus a little bit more heightened attention
what is that like and then sure enough i saw something new i said oh cool
that's pretty cool that the wood grain has been the carpenter put it in that way for the wood grain to
flow in like that that must have been unconsciously
so as we do something as simple as breathing
it isn't that we're trying to get deeper and deeper into the breathing exactly
but more clearer clearer in the attention to breathing
the receptive registering and maybe in the process of just like as if you're going to discover something
new in the breath and breathing it isn't so much discovering something new is important but rather the kind of
attention hopefully peaceful relaxedly interested
available without preconceived ideas without
straining to discover to have to acquire something new understanding just kind of a heightened attention
and breathing is the experience the medium through which
we are beginning to cultivate this heightened attentiveness one that
allows us to become absorbed in the present moment and not distracted by our thoughts
so to assume a meditation posture
and to take a little bit of time to
have a posture that allows the chest to be a teeny bit more open
maybe even for the shoulder blades to be allowed to
rest backwards down the spot but down the back
and gently closing your eyes
and it's my experience that every time
i sit down to meditate breathing is a little bit different
than how it's been before
or it's going to be unique for this moments
and being aware of your breathing and aware of
the sensitivity to the experience gently take a few long slow deep
in-breaths
and as you exhale what kind of attention is needed that supports you
to relax your body as you exhale
breathing in breathing out
and then letting your breathing return to normal
breathing in and feeling your body on the inhale
and as you exhale
attentive to the experience of relaxing as you relax different parts of your
body
and then settling into your breathing
and the rhythm and your breathing can be used to
bring attention to awareness itself
attention to breathing
helps us to be aware
of awareness
and if there's any strain or tension in your uh tension
as you exhale relax
the strain
it might help be helpful to have a sense of receiving the inhale
receiving it into awareness
in what way can attention be calm and peaceful
perhaps allowing the thinking mind to become quieter and calmer
as if you're going to discover something new in the experience of breathing
curious interested
it's not that you have to discover something new you might
feel the attention that's used
for that exploration
how would you enter into awareness into attention
so all there is are almost all there is
is breathing and attention to breathing
intention awareness of breathing and breathing
what would what would that awareness be like
and be content to discover that in short moments
coming back again and again to discover
a new way a clearer way
of receiving the experience of breathing
what is the quality of your attention now
and as i bring your attention to awareness
can you take a few moments to sit here with relaxed open awareness
a receptive awareness or
if it's available sensitive to a clarity of attention
and then i'm going to say a few words
concepts see if as i say the words
maybe with associations you have with them see how that changes the quality of your
attention of your awareness
love
hate
generosity
greed
wisdom
delusion
confidence
anxiety
in a sense awareness is the medium through which these
different states operate and they can have a big impact on how
we're aware the nature of attention
but to appreciate that awareness is the medium
and to use that medium for the welfare and happiness of oneself
and others and as we come to the end of the sitting
consider how being aware and attentive is a means
support for love and good will
for generosity and care
and may we stay close to our capacity for attention
so that attention itself is the byway the highway the means the path
the medium for how we
care for this world in being attentive
may we contribute to the happiness of others
the safety of others
the peace of others
and to their freedom may all beings be happy
[Music]
you
um
so here we are the second talk focusing on
the buddha's teachings instructions on mindfulness practice
and it was a surprise many years ago when happily eagerly
i picked up the text i'd read it before but i picked up the text
and i really wanted to discover uh what did the buddha actually have to say about mindfulness
what did he actually say about practicing mindfulness and the word the pali word is sati
s-a-t-i and
and i went to this text and as i went through it i was
surprised actually a little shocked that how little he actually says about
mindfulness the title of the text is the four foundations for mindfulness
and so i thought for sure there would be lots of references to this word sati
mindfulness and then surprisingly there is very little
there's a little bit in the introduction about mindfulness just just a statement about
it one is um one is mindful
clearly aware and ardent so i want you to practice and it's and here mindful
is a adjective it's not a verb in the way it's used
and then as i said yesterday morning there was a section beginning it says going to a forest
root of a tree empty building sitting cross-legged body upright
and establishing mindfulness to the forefront the rest of the long text that we have
the word mindfulness doesn't appear until maybe the very end again a kind of a conclusion
and all the exercises all the instructions of what to do
are do not have the word mindfulness in them so that was a little bit surprised i
thought what does this mean and as i started looking through the text of the of the buddha
there is nothing that in his teachings that would that would be comparable to the english
expression be mindful like you my mother might tell me you
know be mindful gil when i was growing up and
where the mindful is used as a verb an activity that you would do do mindfulness
and so this sati whatever sati is that was translated as mindfulness was not being something that we do
and um but rather something that um we establish
and if it went through the the different teachings of the buddha i saw the sati was associated with the
verbs to abide in to establish to cultivate
so if a farmer cultivates a plant
the farmer's not doing the growing the farmer is creating the conditions
the plant can grow um if we
abide in dwell in something i love the expression abiding
because of me it's just kind of a peaceful way of just kind of yours there and like at home in some place
and it's where you're supposed to be kind of and to abide
in sati and mindfulness is current to rest in it
and um i once uh made us uh used a photograph or a slide of a big
whale floating kind of peacefully in the ocean underwater photograph of this big whale
as abiding in this abiding in satin awareness
and and so so this sati is not associated with an
activity of doing it's more like a state of being aware
so what what so how am i supposed to do it what's the activity so then if you go look at this text that
we're going to study over these next weeks the actual activities the practices that
we do are not practices maybe could be called maybe it could be
called mindfulness practices in the sense that they are there to cultivate to establish
to grow mindfulness so we can abide in it
and and so uh the instructions the verbs of things that we're doing
are the first thing that's talked about is to know uh to know that one is breathing
to no one is breathing long when one who's breathing a long breath short when it's a short breath
and um and then there's a later on there's instructions to
clearly recognize what's happening so it's a little bit higher uh more
order of of mentality mental activity to recognize something and i'll talk more
about that later the text also talks about observing
and then it talks about something that has the word sati in it but it's a compound called pati sati
and this is lucid awareness so i'd like to translate sati as
awareness rather than mindfulness partly because in we have this you know
wave of the mindfulness movement going through the uh the modern world
and um and the the meanings and definitions of what mindfulness is these days is very much
influenced by how it's taught in that movement nothing wrong with how it's taught
but they use the word mindfulness differently than how the buddha uses it
in that for the buddha this word sati is is a
state that we can abide in establish cultivate grow
it's not an activity that we do and but the activity we do
is this knowing and so but knowing you know we don't want to do a meditation practice that
feels like a lot of work and it makes us busy exactly but the knowing is this wonderful
special quality to know something and it doesn't have to be so
you know cognitive or so you know thoughtful a lot of thought involved
if i'm sitting talking with a friend and uh and where i'm engaged fully absorbing
the conversation and my attention is there for sure and then i put my glasses down
and and then i continue talking and then i get up to go to the bathroom and get some tea and come back
and then i said where's my glasses i have no idea even though five minutes before i might have put them down but i
put them down without clearly knowing i was putting them down or or or clearly
present for the experience of of putting them down
and this idea of being present enough to let the experience what we're doing register
enough so that it can stay little bit in our memory and that's a that's uh one of the
meanings they before the buddha the word for sati had associations with memory
and it's the kind of receptivity attention that's required
for us to um to kind of remember something later like i said where my glasses are
it isn't like we're memorizing which is him in a higher order of mental activity but there's a kind of like
i like the expression we stop to know we pause to know
we engage knowingly with what we're doing so we're present for what we're doing so
we maybe do one thing at a time we're really there present for it and in that presence there's a heightened kind of
knowing recognition kind of attentiveness to the experience
as that heightened attention height kind of knowing operates it then supports
the cultivation the growing of awareness awareness follows in the wake
of the practice of knowing and it's meant to be a peaceful practice
so it begins with just knowing the breathing and it's such a powerful practice to uh
mindfulness of breathing it's not suitable for everyone so it's fine to do other things
but it's a wonderful thing to acquire the ability to get focused centered on the breathing
concentrating the breathing to learn to gather the mind together so that when with experience of
breathing we're not scattered and distracted we're just there with that
as if we're present to know it well as if almost as if the kind of attention
we bring to uh if we were going to look at something we've looked at a long
long time we've passed it by we've been with it and they said let me stop and look to discover something new in it that
you've never noticed before and um not straining to to know or discover but
just to relax kind of glancing at it looking at it roaming around the
thing oh look at that i never noticed that before about it um and um
and so it requires a kind of knowing that uh wretched or something deep more
deeply so we could in a sense then remember it
i'm spending a lot of time now with my mother who has kind of advanced dementia
and we can have wonderful exchanges back and forth and very clear
in the moment but her memory lasts probably 30 seconds
and so i'll say something and she'll come back with a wonderful reply and um
and then i could ask you know if 10 seconds later i could ask the same question and and she would come back with the same or
different reply she doesn't remember i said it and so for her nothing sticks
there's a clarity to her but uh the attention something about the attentiveness is not all there
that it kind of has a place to register or stay or stick i don't really understand how dementia
works so well but uh whether i'm accurate exactly with this is not so important it's trying to i'm
trying to convey to you that uh this idea of of um the specialness of knowing
that to attend to so that we know it's something in a
deeper way and uh but without it being uh heavily
cognitive or investigatory or questioning or thought-filled kind of exploration just
very very simple so that as we know the breathing and get kind of more and more centered and
present for just the breathing we know it more and more clearer and clearer but the mind also gets quieter and more
peaceful calmer the difference between a concentration
practice and mindfulness practice is that in concentration practice we're
getting absorbed in the breathing in mindfulness practice by its when just
through concentration in mindfulness practice if we're getting absorbed it becomes
absorbed in the knowing and the clarity of awareness that takes in the experience
and so we're more available in mindfulness to register the details the fullness the richness of an experience
how it changes over time then we are often if we just do concentration practice where
we're just trying to hold the mind still in a certain kind of way or rather than letting the experience become richer in
the knowing mind so sati is awareness and tomorrow i'll
talk a little bit about how these exercises of knowing and recognition and observation
leads to a heightened awareness and this path this journey to heightened
awareness is the is the trajectory is a journey of
satipatana of the foundations for awareness and
in the meantime maybe you'll explore
the nature of your awareness of your attention of your knowing
all these faculties of attentiveness that we have and for today especially notice
the your faculty of knowing to the simplest knowing the kind of
knowing that if you really let it register something you would remember where you put your glasses
before you put your keys just that simple
so um so thank you and i look forward to tomorrow
and tomorrow when you greet if some of those of you who are connected to the chat and
would like to do the good mornings or the greetings i would love to see greetings in your native language
and uh so many of you nate english is your native language but um but to all the different places
in the world let's be not lovely to have kind of a gathering of the globe and through the languages
so thank you