so I'd like to start tonight with us quote from ambika body
some of you may know bikubody is he's one of the key figures in this
tradition he's I think he's from the Bronx or
Brooklyn or something like this he has a little bit of an accent and bikobodi is his ordination name
it was ordained I don't know you know maybe 30 40 50 years ago
and he lived for decades in Sri Lanka as a practitioner as a monk
and I had a very he's kind of you know not kind of he is he's conservative and
he's also the primary translator of the texts that we have today
it's a quite a remarkable person really I have so much respect for him his
translations as well as just his writings I think are fantastic
but you know he said Monk and as part of the rules for monastics and this
tradition is they don't drive they they want to go somewhere somebody
else has to drive them or and they also don't handle money
and they have all these restrictions on their lifestyle to keep their lifestyle
really simple really simple and also to have it that they have this
relationship with the non-monastics so that they the monastics aren't
sequestered off doing their own thing but they rely on a relationship with others
for their to go to the doctors or you know anything like this kind of stuff so
but Biko Bodhi so somebody who probably hasn't driven I you know I don't know how old he is
it's conceivable maybe 50 years 40 years something like this and then he says
the mind is like a drunken driver I don't know why I just kind of get this
uh kick out of this this idea of somebody who doesn't drive but to
recognize that he's pointing to this sometimes drunken drivers or of course I want to
go down the middle of the lane like we all do but when you have this drunkenness you
kind of find yourself swerving and going a little to this side oh maybe hit a car or nearly miss a car hopefully and then
you'll go oh man maybe off the edge of the road and then this way and that way and
so in this way that there's this um he's pointing to
how the mind you know we kind of wish that we would like go the direction we
want it to go that there would be it's kind of in the middle not getting pulled
One Direction or the other but this recognition that often we are
having this craving we're getting pulled towards something over here or maybe we
have some aversion we want to get rid of something over there so we're kind of going this way and this anything but
going down the camera like the center of the lane
and sometimes this um craving or this long anus for
something that was in the past doesn't even exist or maybe we have this craving of
something in the future that doesn't exist either right the only thing that really exists is this moment
so this idea that the mind is kind of careening back and forth
being pushed around even though there's this wish to be going down the middle
so equanimity is this quality that enables the mind
that lets the mind go down the middle of the lane not careening from one side to the next
not leaning from one side to the next and one word that put one poly word for
Equanimity is I like saying that word I don't expect
anybody to know how to spell it or even to be repeat it
but uh if we were to translate it into English literally it means standing in
the middle so this idea of equanimity I've been able to stand in the middle
so it's pointing to this stability or this
deadiness or this sense of balance or
unshakability we're just staying here going this direction not getting pushed
around so as this strong sense of inner balance
that might come from a what we might say like a ballast you know a heavy thing
that's preventing it from preventing the Mind from getting off course
is one way is one poly word that gets translated as Equanimity but there's a
second word that also gets translated as Equanimity into English and this word is upeka
Pekka and this word is more about seeing
clearly or seeing the bigger picture or something about this so this idea of equanimity not only is
there standing in the middle but there's a steadiness or this balance that comes from
like perhaps in the same way you might be on a hill where you have a view
and maybe you can see things that you can't quite see
when you're like in the midst of it from the hill side maybe you can see
things in the distance that are about to about to arrive if you were there you wouldn't be able to see them yet
but if you're on the hill and you see then you're not surprised when they whatever it is that arises when it's
coming in the distance it's like oh yeah of course of course this is here
so this Equanimity is being able to see the bigger picture but
it also has this quality of this even-minded acceptance
of ourselves of others of whatever is arising
not getting pushed around by craving or aversion the way of saying that is a
certain amount of acceptance like yes this is how it is right now
I'm not going to demand or insist that it be otherwise this is how it is
but it's not this resignation like oh okay yeah I'll just wait until this ends
until something better arises instead it's this acceptance that grows out of our respect
a respect for ourselves respect for others a respect for all the kind of
like the conditions that come together that makes whatever is happening right now
happen but things start to happen magically of course not
there's reasons and so this kind of respect that even though we don't know all the reasons
this recognition that there are reasons for why things are happening
right now you're hearing my voice most likely
maybe that's I mean there's so many reasons for this one is that maybe it's
because I have a microphone that required somebody to invent microphones required IMC to decide that
they wanted microphones to purchase them it required svet over
here to push the right buttons to make sure that you know the voice is going out it required me to have this idea
that I wanted to speak and that I had breath in my lungs that I could put through vocal cords and right we could
go on and on and on so Equanimity is part of this respect
this acknowledgment that there's so many things that come together
to make everything happen and so it's
this recognition that there's we don't have to take it so personally
doesn't mean that we're a good person or a bad person or that it's always going to be this way or all these stories that
we like to make of course we do this human beings do this
is this recognition it's just this coming together of all these different conditions supports this equanimity
so part of the reason why I'm talking about Equanimity tonight is because I'm continuing this series on the seven
factors of Awakening these factors of Awakening are these
qualities of the mind and the heart that really create the conditions in which
Awakening can occur and we can think about Awakening in so many different ways you can think about
it one way is just this increase in Freedom this increase in peace increase
in well-being can also thinking about it with the
Buddha talk taught is you know there's these certain attainments
of Awakening when there's this radical letting go that allows a shift a permanent shift in
one's perspective with this
letting go there's much more Equanimity available after this letting go
but Equanimity is the seventh factor of the seven factors of Awakening so it's
the last one It's Quickly I'll list the other six there's mindfulness
and then there's these energizing factors of Investigation energy and joy
and then there's these calming factors of Tranquility concentration and
equanimity and I'll continue in some other talks like how these seven all work together
and how they're sequential and balance each other and all these kinds of things but
today I'd like to continue a little bit more with equanimity [Applause]
so for some of us we hear this word this Equanimity it
certainly was not part of my vocabulary before I found these Buddhist teachings
it's just sounds I don't know it doesn't sound very attractive
it sounds like okay whatever that is it kind of sounds boring and dry and dull
maybe something like this but there might be a way in which it doesn't
sound attractive because Equanimity it might feel like it's a type of disconnection
a way in which we're not present for what's happening
for in our lives or in that in the moment or maybe it feels like it's a
type of coldness or indifference
or maybe it feels like it's a kind of grayness or aloofness it might have some
of these ideas about equanimity but it's not that Granny mini has this
quality of this vitality and this openness and spaciousness and warmth
it's the not having to be removed from life not having to be removed from our
connections with other people not having to be removed from what's
being experienced but having this be able to have some steadiness or
stability no matter what's happening
this radical idea that there might be so many things that
happen that happens that so many things you know in our external
conditions the news what uh others are telling us or not
telling us or maybe there's inner conditions maybe we don't feel well maybe we have a disease an illness
what a beautiful idea that we don't have to be
careening of course or into some territory that we'd know isn't
good for us or supportive for us when these conditions change
but having said all this part of equanimity or practicing with equanimity
is this kind of like slide into indifference I would say that this is
what happens is that some we have sometimes we want to disconnect because
it feels uncomfortable or painful and so sometimes it tips over into
indifference and this is I love this so much about the Buddhist teachings that
well this is how we learn oh yeah this is indifference I feel kind of
closed down I don't have a sense of Vitality I don't
have a sense of contentment instead I feel
maybe sad or tight or something like this so part of
the way that we discover what Equanimity is and how it's available for us and how it can show up
part of that is learning how it isn't
and so it's natural that humans fall into indifference on occasion
maybe it's a lot maybe it's only on occasion but can we recognize that
I recognize that there's an alternative stay connected but still have this stability this
uprightness [Applause] but there's another reason why
Equanimity might sound unattractive and that is it's not uncommon to have
this belief that's maybe you know in the back of the
mind not in the front of the mind but maybe there's somewhere in the back of our minds that we feel like in order to
have some I don't know juiciness in our lives
some something that feels invigorating
we might feel like we have to have a certain amount of drama a certain amount of you know angst or so
I don't know or something like this you know big huge problems that have to get solved or something like this right
so much of the kind of Human Experience is about like solving this problem and solving that problem and all these
different problems and so this idea of having some contentment and uprightness
and this ballast some steadiness in some ways might feel a little
frightening who would I be if I weren't the person that had all these problems that had to
be solved or who would I be if I didn't have these emotional outbursts or difficulties
who would I be would would I just be gray and dull and boring but nobody like
me would I just sit in the corner very
quietly foreign so often you know it sounds a little
silly to say these things and these thoughts certainly aren't in the front of our minds but there might be a little
bit in the back of our minds of well this is what it means to be human to be alive is to be filled with
uh energy maybe that's born from anger or this uh
wish to fix things that things aren't right and or this just wanting things to be
otherwise so Equanimity might sound like that it's
I think that it's uh maybe a little bit frightening a little bit dull this fear that it might
be dull but there's this openness this spaciousness right if you have this
stability then you don't have to protect yourself and things that can arise can just kind
of like just go right on through we feel them we acknowledge them we know
them but we aren't being pushed by them
so this experience of equanimity
I'm talking about it like it's one singular thing but in fact it's really a
spectrum I like this idea of spectrums instead of this binary on off either you got it or
you don't I don't know that just it doesn't uh because most often we feel they go I
don't I don't got it I don't have it but this idea of a spectrum
to really having little stability the slightest thing sends us off kilter to
having a lot of stability right there's this spectrum and then this practice is
just moving One Direction towards greater and greater stability without insisting
that anything less than that is somehow not not enough
so it's not an on off switch it's a spectrum
and we might say that with equanimities over here maybe emotionality
is on the other end of the spectrum but a part of being human is having emotions
I of course it is and it would be awful if somehow this
teaching was about you can never have emotions again or something like that or this thinking that
we should have this stayed demeanor all the time
so we can ask ourselves do we have this do we know both ends of
this spectrum do we know what it's like to have emotions and to be sometimes overwrought
or to be gleeful or and do we also know what it's like to be really steady
and to have this fullness this richness this vitality
that's available with this Rich emotional life and also with steadiness
and do we know how to maybe move back and forth right we don't want to be in
Equanimity if somebody in our family is really injured or hurt or emotionally
her trait we don't just want to be standing in this uh
I don't know this being stable we we want to connect with them we want to
have compassion and maybe it breaks our heart to see their heart breaking
so can we practice in such a way that we are in contact with our emotions not
pretending that they're not there having respect for them
but also recognizing that there's something else that's also available
Equanimity in this life there's emotionality
equanimity can we get to know both ends of this spectrum can we move from one end to the
other when it's appropriate when that's what life is asking of us at that moment
I appreciate this very much because it's not asking us to
be different than we are it's just asking us to maybe stretch or
expand our capacity or our idea of what it means to be
a human or what it means to be a Buddhist practitioner or what does it
mean to be somebody who does mindfulness practice or whatever it might be
so Equanimity part of the
maybe I could say this at functions is it just makes life easier to navigate maybe this goes without saying right if
we recognize these two ends of the spectrum and we can move from one to the other
then we can respond to what's needed at any particular time but not only that
we don't have to hide from difficulties
having Equanimity allows us to have confidence that okay whatever is going
to arise I I can I can be with it I can handle it
and it allows us to not be blown around by these eight
worldly winds maybe some of you are familiar with this maybe I'll unpack this at a later time
in another talk but tonight I'll just mention them
something else I appreciate about the Buddhist teachings is that the Buddha is saying there is nobody who is immune
from these eight worldly winds nobody praise and blame
sometimes we get praise sometimes we get blame Fame and disrepute sometimes we there's
we have a good reputation and sometimes there's something bad that gets said about us whether it's true or not right
sometimes this happens nobody is immune to this
Pleasure and Pain course right we all have this
and then the last one gain and loss course our life cannot just be gained
gain gain without any loss and just this recognition that all eight
of these what's called winds will blow in our lives we don't get to have just
the positive ones and completely avoid the negative ones no matter how much we might wish that
were so of course we can't have that so equanimity
allows us to be able to have some steadiness in these different Winds of Our Lives start
blowing and so another part of the supports for
I'm sorry one of the functions of equanimity is as a support
a support for letting go it's so much easier to let go of
whatever it is we're holding on to if we have a sense of it's okay
I'm not off balance I'm not out of kilter
then we can let go it seems you know but uh
comes to my mind is kind of like water skiing or something like this right when you're off balance
right you're holding on so tightly but there's a way in which sometimes maybe
it's just best to let go and just kind of like go into the water instead of being pulled in a way that's
unhelpful there's this expression that's kind of
like a rope burn right that you're just holding on so tightly and it just hurts because things change and we're holding
on so Equanimity allows us to let go not to
not take rope burn and of course
Awakening Liberation ease comes with letting go
I think we all know this that clinging eventually leads to suffering if not
immediately eventually it always leads to suffering to difficulties so to support to support our not clinging
equanimities helps us to let go
and so how do we practice Equanimity or were there some supports for it to arise I'll
just for Dimension a little bit now and think in the talk that I'll give next
week I'll talk more about this but one thing I wanted to say is that with
Equanimity we start Where We Are we start where we are of course we do
like we can't start anywhere else right so we start Where We Are
And We Begin by bringing Equanimity to little things in life
small things we don't have to do anything completely
radical but maybe uh I know on Retreat practice or there's uh
during Retreats there's it's uh the meals are served at buffet style where there's these big
platters or containers of food and then there's a line maybe Equanimity is
saying oh my goodness this is my favorite maybe there's cookies or something and like well maybe I'll just
wait and see if make sure that everybody else gets one and if there's still some I'll come back and get one maybe
Equanimity is you know something very simple like this letting the car in front of you get into
the lane or something like this and these really small things it's
really small certainly like the difficulties if we think of difficulties on a scale of one
to ten like start with things that are like a one or a two
and just kind of like let go or practice kind of like some steadiness like okay I
don't have to go towards this or get away from that I
can do whatever I can can practice some Equanimity here some
steadiness [Applause] so don't underestimate how powerful this
can be even though I'm saying start with the you know one or a two there's a part of us often thinks like no no no no no I
really want Equanimity so I'm going to start with a nine but
usually it works best if we start where it's easy
start where it's easy and just get used to it just get used to this and that we realize that how much
it see how I don't know how much uh confidence it gives us and it's
a good feeling to not always be going after something
or pushing away but instead to have this steadiness
so to kind of like talk about this I I would like to read this poem
this idea of starting where it's easy with the equanimity poem is by Rosemary traumer and it's
called driving with my son the night before his driver's test
we turn off the music practice left turns onto the highway
park on the bias park on the street we get gas drive backwards use the median
change lanes use the blinker slow down full stop
there's a rule for everything and a comfort and knowing the rules
and you can practice everywhere notes are DMV guidelines so have at it
imagine if we all practiced everywhere if we all signaled before every turn
of heart Turn of Mind turn of plans
imagine if we all agreed no matter where we're going and
no matter where we've been that we are all travelers on the same
side knowing we're on This Road Together
imagine if we agreed to stop in an orderly way no drama no shaming no blame so that
someone else might take their turn to go
imagine getting along with others no matter what they believe
could it be as simple as keeping it steady
looking over your shoulder making eye contact and a Crossing
giving each other some space
imagine if we agreed to stop in an orderly way no drama no shaming no blame
so that someone else might take their turn to go
imagine getting along with others no matter what they believe could be as simple as keeping it steady
looking over your shoulder making eye contact in a Crossing
giving each other some space
poem by Rosemary traumer driving with my son the night before his
driver's test I appreciate this very much her just
kind of pointing to like driving as represents so many things but just this
idea of keeping it steady keeping it in the middle of the lane I speak about he
says in the beginning there so I'd like to stop there and open it up
if there are some questions or comments
foreign
if they want to type in a question they're welcome to do that too okay dead
when you say the spectrum of emotionality and equanimity
um is there not a way that you have some emotion you
know you could have a lot of strong emotion but as long but you don't um
allow it to take over does that make sense yes yes that's kind of what I'm pointing to
you know some sometimes in our lives right it does take over and we just uh
collapse into our emotions but there can be a way in which there's tears and like
okay this is what sadness feels like and there's a lot of sadness but there's a
certain not getting lost in it or but still
really feeling it and yeah yeah of course right I mean humans grieve and we
have some losses when dear ones die or something like this right of course there's going to be
tears and yeah
anybody else have a comment or a question
no requirements but uh if you'd like
um my question is how do we keep this from becoming a really easy way to absolve ourselves of responsibility for
like broader like social responsibilities if that makes sense I can see it being very difficult for
Equanimity to become like a real like a problem very close to home like in our
like families and there's like something happening but I could see it really easily
becoming a way for people just to say like oh well like at 60 000 feet like
impermanence and things will change and yeah yeah so Equanimity is not
indifference it's often you know it's easy to feel like it is but instead it
allows to feel like oh the pain of the social injustice for all these things and to really to feel that
and still be able to have con contact with our greatest wisdom that allows us
okay how can I make a difference what can I do next that comes from a place of
wisdom and care not from a place of fear or or
anger that's you know out of control or something like that is that helpful
thank you yes I I certainly had this idea that it was about indifference too because I was
certainly the only thing that I knew was like you were either disconnected and aloof or you're from my for me before it
was kind of or collapsed into I didn't realize that there's something like a third alternative to be feeling and
knowing what's happening and feel that pain and the sadness or whatever it
might be and still be present and Be steady be
available
maybe uh
so we have a couple of questions here could you please say a little more about how the eight winds are part of
equanimity a part of equanimity the the eight wings of equanimity yeah
part yeah yeah so Equanimity is part of
the way it's defined is that it's the steadiness this ballast this stability
when these eight wins blow so it's like it's uh not being pushed
around by these eight things and part of that is equity is like you know seeing
the bigger picture well part of the bigger picture is to recognize of course
there is gain and loss even though we only want gain but loss is unavoidable
and we of course we only want pleasure we don't want pain but pain is unavoidable
Fame you know these are maybe clunky translations but to have a good
reputation or to have a bad reputation right it's there's always going to be somebody who's you know displeased with
us of course it's impossible to avoid that so that's part of how Equanimity is seeing the bigger picture of that the
negative things are going to happen and not being pushed around when the negative things happen or when the
positive things happen I think when the we have this good reputation or maybe it is fame maybe we get our
Fame 15 minutes of fame or something and not to think like okay I finally made it
and now I don't have to take care of anything else in my life or I don't know whatever this is you know just not to
get out of balance for that and was there another one
uh there's a question about a relationship between tranquility and Equanimity yeah this is such a good
question relationship between tranquility and Equanimity I would say Tranquility is more of a
um like a bodily experience or it's definitely a settledness but Equanimity
as a little as flavor of wisdom like seeing the bigger picture restaurant quality is non-education and
stability and settledness I guess so it is relate I mean they're in the same family
but um equanimia has this quality of wisdom or
yeah I'll use this word wisdom I've seen the bigger picture and having this understanding of conditionality whereas
Tranquility is more just about the settledness this is a good question and
I'll talk about this more in a subsequent talk the relationship between all these uh Awakening factors
so it's okay
okay well or do you have
thank you for your talk Diana um
it triggered a number of things in me I won't say them all but
one of them was I just recently watched the movie um beautiful day in the neighborhood oh
about Mr Rogers yeah yeah I haven't seen it but uh yeah and there's one scene in
which he's comes into a family's home and
the the father of the family is dying of cancer and nobody's really talking about it
nobody's release and he said something like you know death death is part of life
and he said and it's part of Being Human and he said anything
that's part of being human can be talked about and anything that can be talked about
can be managed so that's
what came up when you had been talking about that um you know facing anything yeah I'd love
this Mr Rogers thank you right for watching Mr Mr Rogers won't you be my neighbor yes I
love this thank you Jim for saying that I'll have to see this I meant to see it
when it came out years ago I didn't so I don't know that just makes me smile thinking about Mr Rogers
okay so maybe with that uh as an ending just um thank you for your kind
attention and thank you for your practice and may you have some Equanimity in the
upcoming days thank you