welcome welcome everybody it's
it's such a pleasure to practice with others even if i'm alone in this room just knowing that
you're on the other side of these screens so thank you
so gil max ertstein and i are teaching a course on ethics
i think it's i'm not exactly sure now maybe 10 months long 8 9 10 11 months
around there and it's a lot of fun you know sometimes
this whole topic of ethics just feels like oh really like i don't want to be told a whole bunch of
rules or the sense of morality just feels heavy and
something that's not so interesting but we're approaching it in a way that
i'm finding really delightful and i know some of the students are as well
and the way that we are approaching it is less as a set of rules
because that's you know marginally helpful what's really helpful is
some ways to navigate our lives some ways to
make decisions to help us with decision making and choosing which direction to
go what to do these types of things that's really helpful and useful
so in this ethics class we started with just some foundations this idea of
wholesomeness and this idea of care and compassion
and we're now into the precepts looking at each of the precepts spending
a little bit more time with each one and we recently finished the second
precept to not take that which is not given
it's a little bit stilted way of saying it it's kind of like saying not stealing
but uh the buddhists have a little bit higher or different um conception of it that it's
things have to be offered and then we get into all these questions about ownership and offering
and all kinds of things but that's not what i want to talk about tonight
instead it's just this idea of how we navigate our lives how we make decisions
in so many of the mundane things that we do i know sometimes when we think about the
dharma and the teachings of the buddha we might have these really lofty ideas which is fantastic
and certainly there are plenty of those that can be helpful and supportive
but we might also sometimes feel like some of these little corners of our lives
these mundane corners of our lives we don't really bring the dharma to
so the last few times that i've given a talk on monday nights i talked about some of these mundane things like new
year's resolutions and how we can bring the dharma to them
and i'd like to continue on that vein and share a story that we shared in this
in the ethics course and to talk about some of the ideas but
not the ones that we should talked about in the ethics course i'm going to bring in some other ideas
just highlighting how there are so many different
practices or teachings that we can bring to just ordinary
activities in a way that support us and nourish us
coach us guide us inspire us without feeling like it's this
heavy burdensome thing that we have to do on top
of our ordinary life instead it just it gets uh woven in
integrated with in such a way that it's a support
so there's two stories that we talked about one was as i said with the second
precept and another story we talked about in this ethics class at the beginning when we were talking
about some of the foundations of ethics and they have a common theme
and i'm sure you'll pick up the common theme but this first one that i'm going to
share is in some ways it's kind of silly it's a poem that rhymes that has a particular meter
and it's colorful and but part of the beauty of it is that it's kind of mundane
but there can be some real depths also to it
this story i tried to figure to discover like when it was first published and i couldn't find it i did find some
reference that somebody had said um it first came out in the 90s
but it was originally written in the 80s but i didn't actually see the
publications at that time so i don't really know and honestly i don't even remember where
i heard this first it might have been in a dharma talk something yeah right
that's how all of us drama teachers we just hear um when we're co-teaching or when we just hear other dharma teachers
and we just pass around all the same stories so hopefully you haven't heard this one
too many times okay so
maybe um i won't uh say the name of the poem
and the artist the poet until after the end
so that um just yeah i'll always the end
here we go a woman was waiting at the airport one night with several long hours before her
flight she hunted for a book in the airport shop bought a bag of cookies and found a
place to drop she was engrossed in her book but happened to see that the man beside
her as bold as could be grabbed a cookie or two from the bag
between which she tried to ignore to avoid a scene
she read munched cookies and watched the clock
as the gutsy cookie thief diminished her stalk she was getting more irritated as the
minutes ticked by thinking if i weren't so nice i'd
blacken his eye with each cookie she took
he took one too when only one was left she wondered what
he'd do with a smile on his face and a nervous laugh
he took the last cookie and broke it in half he offered her half and he ate the other
she snatched it from him and thought oh brother this guy has some nerve and he's also so
rude why he didn't even show any gratitude
she had never known when she had been so galled and sighed with relief when her
flight was called she gathered her belongings and headed for the gate
refusing to look at that thieving in great
she boarded the plane and sank in her seat then sought her book almost complete
as she reached in her baggage she gasped with surprise
there were her bag of cookies in front of her eyes
if mine are here she moaned with despair
then the others were his and he tried to share
too late to apologize she realized with grief
that she was the rude one the ingrate the
thief so this kind of uh
amusing poem is called the cookie thief by valerie cox c-o-x is her last name
right so this scene unfolds at the airport
and this woman has this whole entire story created about the
person next to her she's getting angry she even has this uh
saying what is this um if i weren't so nice i'd black in his
eye right getting quite angry right this this
bewilderment and anger is coming up and then right when she gets on the
airplane and discovers that indeed she has her own bag of cookies just in that moment right
just that moment it doesn't take any moment longer everything gets reinterpreted
oh right i'm the thief i'm the in great
i'm the one that was not behaving so nicely
right it just took a flash so there's so many things that we can
learn from this story but one thing that i'd like to look out to right now maybe there's two things
one is as i just mentioned the view the view of this person that was sitting
beside her she had he was a thief he was in great he was rude had this whole
story right by something he was doing and that how it could change in a flash
so this view this idea this opinion they're really
insubstantial they're fleeting
they are not the something that is uh
going to stick around forever and all it took
was her to have one piece of information for her to look in her baggage
and to see her bag of cookies so just this recognition that we have
ideas we have views we have opinions and sometimes we
hold on to them so tightly were willing to threaten somebody to
blacken their eye picking these views
and all it takes is one additional piece of information
for us to realize oh we're completely mistaken
so why are we holding so tightly to our views a they can disappear poof they can be
gone just like that with just one little piece of
information and she had plenty of data we might say
to support her right that he kept on taking the cookies but he even
uh broke it in half and shared with her but that didn't change her opinion
she had already set this view of this poor person sitting behind her sitting beside her
she already had made up her her opinion about how he was
even though he did something that didn't uh suggest that he was a mean ungrateful
person or a thief i don't think a thief would share things
so it's just a reminder to all of us we have views
about ourselves about others we may have data to support it right we there's
reasons why we have views but we don't have to hold on to them so
tightly so much so that we're willing to villainize other people
and willing to make them the bad person right and she says if i weren't so
nice i'd blacken his eye right so she kind of builds herself up
i'm the good one he's the bad one and that's kind of this righteous indignation
that's building and building and building until just one piece of information
so in the story just a reminder for all of us that not to hold on so tightly to our
views and i'll talk a little bit more about that in a moment here
but also this um idea that just having one more piece of
information one more idea is enough to really
completely transform the way that she thought about that the way that she thought about that
whole scene that unfolded while she was waiting for her flight
this is part of what insight is for insight meditation is we start to see things we start and seeing and there's
this understanding and then our our interpretation or the way we move
the world or understand the world starts to shift and change based on that information
based on seeing things differently so these insights
are a way that it's a new way of seeing that also relieves suffering
that's kind of maybe the traditional way that we might think of a insight in this tradition
is it's also tied to the lessening of suffering because this is all going towards freedom greater and greater
freedom so this idea of we might have a new understanding but that it's also linked
to less suffering and we might say that the woman in the story that she had a little bit more
suffering at the moment when she discovered but unfortunately maybe she didn't take the
opportunity to really harvest all the different insights that could have been there
so maybe before i go on and start to talk a little bit more about insights i will say that during this ethics class
we have talked about a number of different things related specifically to the second precept the nature of
stealing what does it mean to steal and if people really know or you're stealing
or the nature of ownership what is it like to own things the importance of
generosity the importance of communication right a few words between this woman and this man might
have made a world of difference they could have discovered a love of the same kind of cookies and chatted and become
friends and who knows if they were both single kind of been their true loves
they were traveling to the same location maybe they were even neighbors and they didn't know it you know like a whole
story right that i'm creating here but my point is if they had spoken to one another right of course it would have
changed but they didn't
and this i she could have not only this woman could have maybe she did right we
don't know what happened after she realized that she was actually the one that was taking his cookies
but this idea of insight is central right to
this path of practice and that buddha points to many times in many
different ways it points to the importance of not clinging to views but
instead there's this alternative to creating views that we really hold on
to or these beliefs of course we're gonna create views
it's it's human nature and we need to in order to navigate our lives navigate the
world friend or foe harmful helpful right we have some of these initial
ideas but the buddhists so the buddha is not pointing to
not doing some of these human things but holding them lightly
not clinging to them and not using them as something for us to build up our own sense of self for us
to kind of bolster any sense of self that we might having but instead just to
say well it seems like there's a misunderstanding here
but in particular because one thing we might learn from this story or this woman might have learned at this
story is something about the nature of experiences
how for example i'm i'm highlighting that the moment that she had this
additional information then how everything just flipped and switched her understanding her
interpretation of everything happened so there was this one story this one view
that arose and then passed away this man is ungrateful he's a thief he's
rude i can't believe he's taking my cookies and then bam that she no longer thinks that of that
person so the buddha pointed to the value for us to notice the arising
and passing away of experiences the rising and passing away
of our holding to a view sometimes we don't recognize how we're holding to a
view until we let it go but the tremendous
power this has in our life to notice oh yeah impermanence
they're rising and passing and if we notice this intentionally bring our mind
to it or when we notice it because it's so obvious
that just to allow the mind and the heart to linger and the noticing of the impermanence
just so that we don't so readily forget it and try to make think concretize and
substantiate and permatize so many of our experiences in our views
because it leads to suffering we know this right clinging to anything
including our views and beliefs leads to suffering
so of course the buddha was pointing to that our experiences are inconstant they're always changing
they're fleeting they arise and they pass away but he also
pointed to some other qualities of our experiences
this triad of gratification danger and escape is
the way that pikaboti translates them so all of our experiences
do have some can be a sense of there's a gratification there like something
is something that's maybe
even if it's really fleetingly can be fulfilling in some kind of way
there's this the they can create the conditions for pleasure and joy but sometimes just
having sense experiences can be satisfying but i have to be careful here right it's
not any lasting happiness it's not any lasting satisfaction right because
they're impermanent and so there is this little bit of gratification and we might say in this
poem this story was she was enjoying the cookies we might say that she was enjoying her
righteous indignation she was enjoying if i weren't so nice i'd blacken his eye
right she's like look what a nice person she is she's not yelling at him or
or blackening his eye or something like this right so
there can be this gratification is the word that sometimes get used for this
but all of these experiences also have kind of the danger maybe danger is too
strong of a word but this idea that our experiences don't last forever so
even if they are bringing pleasure and joy they're going to end
and that's gonna bring the opposite of pleasure and joy
sorrow and grief of some magnitude maybe not to the same magnitude but
there's often sometimes there's this little bit of fear like when is this going to end or a little bit of distress how long is this
going to last that's often you know bubbling
underneath so many of our experiences
this poem we do see her becoming more and more agitated and as i said earlier she had missed an opportunity to maybe
have a connection with somebody who was traveling the same place she was traveling
so the buddha talked about notice they arise and pass away there's gratification there's danger and there's
escape so escape is this
removal of the things wanting to be different this ending of kind of leaning
forward this greediness for them and we see this we have this experience
temporarily when we meditate there can be can be when we sit
a sense of contentment quiet even if it's just for a few moments and
even if that's not our dominant experience but just to know that that can be part
of our experience can be enormously helpful
and then of course the ultimate escape from the dissatisfaction of
or the danger of experiences is awakening where a person is no longer fooled into
wanting to cling or substantiate or concretize
reify our experiences or our views
and it's helpful to create the condition so that we can see the rising and passing
of our experiences and the gratification danger and escape of them and this is a big part of why we
meditate just to allow some settling down if we're always running around rushing
around we'll never really notice the we will notice but it doesn't really
register we don't really take it in and let the ramifications affect us
if that things are inconstant arise and pass away and are changing
so the cookie thief
title right it starts out he is the cookie thief and at the end
she is the cookie thief the stories of cookies and at the
airport there's much more i could say on this poem and maybe you have some of your own
ideas on this but now i'd like to shift gears a little bit and read a second story
that we shared in this ethics class and also has cookies and an airport
and this one is a little bit different this and at the end i'll share the title
of the poem and the poet and this poem is maybe written more in prose
style wandering around the albuquerque airport
terminal after learning my flight had been delayed four hours i heard an announcement
if anyone in the vicinity of gate a4 understands any arabic
please come to the gate immediately well
one pauses these days gay day four was my own gait i went
there an older woman in full traditional palestinian embroidered dress
just like my grandma wore was crumpled on the floor wailing
help said the flight agent talk to her what is her problem we told
her the flight was going to be late and she did this i stooped to put my arm around the woman
and spoke haltingly shudawa
shubidak abbipdi stanishway minfadlik
asking for forgiveness on how terrible i'm probably i'm probably butchering this so my apologies
so she speaks this little bit of arabic the minute she heard any words she knew
however poorly used she stopped crying she thought the flight had been
cancelled entirely she needed to be in el paso for major medical treatment the next day
i said no we're fine you'll get there just later who is picking you up let's call him
we called her son i spoke with him in english i told him i would stay with his mother till we got
on the plane and right next to her she talked to him then we called her other sons just for
the fun of it then we called my dad and he and she spoke for a while in arabic and found
out of course they had 10 shared friends then i thought just for the heck of it
why not call some palestinian poets i know and let them chat with her
this all took up two hours she was laughing a lot by then telling of her life patting my knee
answering questions she had pulled a sack of homemade mamul cookies little powdered sugar crumbly
mounds stuffed with dates and nuts from our bag and was offering them to
all the women at the gate to my amazement not a single woman
declined one it was like a sacrament the traveler from argentina
the mom from california the lovely woman from laredo
we were all covered with the same powdered sugar and smiling there is no better cookie
and then the airline broke out free apple juice from the huge from huge coolers and two little girls from our
flight ran around serving it and they were covered with powdered sugar too
and i noticed my new best friend by now we were holding hands had a potted plant
poking out of her bag some medicinal thing with green furry leaves
such an old country tradition always carry a plant
always stay rooted to somewhere and i looked around that gate of late
and weary ones and i thought this is the world i want to live in
the shared world not a single person in that gate once
the crying of confusion stopped seemed apprehensive about any other person
they took the cookies i wanted to hug all those other women
too this can still happen
anywhere not everything is lost
so this poem or story is called gate a4
by naomi shihab nai naomi shihab nai is a buddhist
practitioner and i believe she's even like practice with the san francisco zen center
and she's i think her as a palestinian father an american mother and grew up in both
palestine i believe and texas
she and says this is the world i want to live in the shared world
not a single person in that gate once the crying of confusion stopped
seemed apprehensive about any other person they took the cookies
i wanted to hug all those other women too this can still
happen anywhere not everything is lost
cookies and airports may all beings be free from suffering
and may they recognize that not everything is lost this can still happen
thank you