hello everyone welcome
and maybe you've had the occasion to
make a effort to listen to some faint sound
maybe there's a bird in the tree and you're trying to understand
what bird is that or where is that
singing saw a bird song coming from or perhaps
i recently was hiking in the mountains nearby here and
and we knew that we were getting close to our destination when we could hear the river
and so i would listen and and for that the faintest little hint of
that sound of the river to know that i was getting close
so this ability to kind of uh and and and for me with this kind of way of listening
the mind becomes quieter things become quiet and still in the mind so that there's no static
to try to hear the very faint sound so in the same way
in meditation there comes a time where it just
not that we're straining to to to pay attention but at some point
uh it's helpful to understand that we're letting the mind become quiet
so that we can hear or perceive or feel something really deep inside of us
something that when there's a lot of static a lot of thinking and concerns and preoccupation
it gets drowned out it gets covered over it's somehow we don't get to see it
and and so one of the things to listen for in meditation
is some of the deeper messages voices or thoughts
attitudes that underlie everything if we go deep enough down
we'll find sometimes some of the foundational
attitudes beliefs that kind of permeate everything else above the foundation
that we don't even know is there and some of those are
not helpful for us as we live our lives when i was a relatively new meditator
i discovered that underneath it all as i meditated
was this belief that if it was happening to me it was it is not the real thing
and so that's about the extent of how logical it was but so no matter what i
was experiencing meditation uh it was not really what you're supposed to be experiencing it wasn't
the right thing and there was something else that was the right thing but i didn't have any contact with it
and so that was a so that kind of attitude went was carried into everything that i did
in meditation and in my life as well and so i couldn't you know was always
then wrong it was always never could be never could do things adequately or never had the right
experience i was always wrong in some way so that was kind of eye-opening to see
that and the seeing of it was the beginning of healing from it and and then maybe being able to listen even
deeper to a voice where or to an attitude a belief
that didn't carry that along and uh
so um so what is uh so to allow yourself to become really quiet at some point during
this meditation to see if you can listen for the thoughts
that are there when there's nothing else
they might be not helpful for you they might be very helpful for you they might be nice thoughts
but uh to see them whether they're helpful or not helpful they have equal value
for the purposes of mindfulness there's nothing wrong with discovering you have unhelpful thoughts
it's actually the doorway to freedom it's it's not you know to celebrate that
you have great thoughts good thoughts that foundation those two are the doorway to freedom
but to listen what's there and um
and sometimes it begins not with a belief or
idea you can present but it's more of an emotion a feeling that's underneath it all
and at this deep level there might be this intimate connection between it being a kind of emotional
and a belief at the same time kind of and so some people the entry way is to listen to the deeper
emotion and then some eventually you can see what's the belief that goes along with
it and sometimes it's the other way you feel the deep belief no it's
recognize it and then you can feel how it carries with it a mood and emotion that maybe is there
kind of as a background influence on your life
so i'll i'll direct this a little bit and
so to begin as usual it's kind of nice i'm hoping it's nice that to have a kind of a ritual
beginning where it's more or less the same what we do each time so the familiarity allows your system and your
in your life kind of to kind of feel like it's entering into familiar
territory and settle more quickly so assume the meditation posture
and then gently close your eyes
with your eyes closed
gently settle on yourself
gently enter into your inner bodily experience from the inside out
and feeling if there's some ways you're going to adjust your posture now
so you're more comfortable more alert
and taking a few longer inhales
and longer exhales in which you relax settle in more
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and on the exhales relaxing the different parts of your body
or if they don't relax to soften them soften around them
and then to begin centering yourself on your breathing
and you might try to it with your breathing not to breathe deeply
but ever so slightly gently lovingly do breathe
in a little bit fuller just a teeny bit more than you would otherwise
a little bit more intentionally exhale as if you're relaxing or
as if you're saying ah on the exhale
the intention of exhale might be a little greater allowing of the exhale
and maybe a little bit more allowing of the inhale
and as you exhale to relax
in the thinking mind
to let the thinking become quieter
maybe a little slower
this
maybe imagining that every time you exhale
the exhale is carrying you a little bit deeper
into yourself
and so that every time you exhale you want to listen or
attend to that
for what is deepening attend and feel and sense
the places deep inside that the exhale is taking you
so
with the exhales letting the thinking mind become quieter
so that you can better listen better sense
what is deep inside of you underneath all your thoughts
usual thoughts your daily thoughts concerns ongoing concerns
and listen feel the beliefs that are there
the attitudes that are there
the feelings that are there maybe deep inside
and don't expect that you'll necessarily hear or listen
what's valuable is letting yourself become quiet
the quieter and and listen to become quieter on the exhale
and sense deeper
if nothing shows itself it's okay it might actually be quite good
to feel the quiet that's there
and if this makes sense to keep doing this continue on the exhale
to let go relax into the deeper places within
as if the exhale is holding your hand carrying you
deeper underneath the usual concerns
maybe a place in your body that's underneath it all
and i'll ask a question and see what responds inside of you to
the question maybe before you think about an answer
whatever responds spontaneously or close to that
it might not be in words it might be just a feeling or body sensation
or a place inside that your attention goes
relaxing with the exhale
letting things be quite quiet near the end of the exhale
for a moment
and that and then that deepest place that you can contact within
the question is if it could speak what would it say
so
and then bring your attention to the inhale
and feel the way that the body expands as you inhale
maybe the body lifts a little bit
and let that inhale carry some of your strength
some of your confidence so that it spreads through your body
having the expanding of the inhib inhale
let it move through and with
any care love good will
compassion that's within you
that you can spread through the body through your heart through your mind
on that inhale letting whatever degree of confidence and
strength and love good will
grow and spread and expand maybe beyond the edges of your body
as if you can reach out and touch the whole world with kindness
just a gentle touch maybe at the top of the inhale
may our attention that spreads out into the world
may that attention carry with it
our care for the welfare and happiness of others
may our attention awareness of others carry with it
a wish for everyone's happiness
may everyone be happy
may everyone be safe
may everyone be peaceful
may everyone be free
[Music]
uh
so this relationship between thinking
and emotions emotions and thinking that we're talking about this week
and thinking has many layers many different within us
and some of the more surface layers are is called
discursive thinking thinking that involves having a conversation or
telling a story or imagining some scenario that
um uh you know sometimes it's almost like there's uh it's watching tv or
something and um this can have a powerful effect on our emotional life
and uh because sometimes you know we're humans are storytellers and stories have
a big impact and we have an ability to imagine stories as if they're real and they you
know feel them in our emotional life so we want to be careful with the stories we tell and the discursive mind
but then thinking can get quieter and it doesn't have to be discursive thinking
a story we tell but there might be some repeated attitude
judgment we carry with us and uh and that judgment might be one that uh undermines us or might point one
that inspires us or buoys us up as the mind gets quieter and quieter
then it doesn't mean that we stop thinking but the thinking becomes more subtle or
more foundational or more underlies everything else and sometimes and that's part of the
advantage of getting calm and subtle the meditation is that we can start hearing or seeing
or recognizing that deeper ways deeper currents of belief of thoughts of attitudes
that are in us that are often overlaid by discursive thinking or
judgmental thinking and and that deeper layer is
valuable to see sometimes it's even sometimes we don't even know that
it's there it's casting its influence and everything else it's kind of like the the root from which everything else kind
of grows or the root which kind of spreads some kind of
food into everything else in the plant but the food might be
you know might not be whatever it takes in from the soil it might not be healthy
or it might be healthy so this deeper attitude to start seeing what it is and is going on
and and to give you some examples of some of the some kind of maybe simple deeper
attitudes beliefs that might be there is um sometimes when people get really quiet
still and meditation is just really tracking the breathing people are really doing breath meditation
uh it's you can see that certain attitudes could appear for some people at a particular
point in the cycle of breathing so there are sometimes people if i see that oh i don't want to exhale
because i don't want to lose something i want to hold on and uh it's not safe to have to be safe
by holding on or the end of the exhale is a common place where some people get afraid
because sometimes there's a feeling the end of ex say and a loss of control there
or we're kind of everything's going away and i might disappear i might
die or something i won't exist the end of the the end of the exhale
or sometimes i've known people who have an attitude as they breathe in they
don't want to breathe in like leave me alone that's too much work it's like the world is imposing itself on me and so
there's a resistance kind of very subtle um and so these are kind of so these are kind
of symbolic it's kind of we discover that in relationship to breathing is a relationship that just plays itself
out in the rest of our life but it's so subtle and so quiet uh we might discover that there are very
quick foundational emotions that are there and those emotions give birth to a
way of thinking or to the discursive thoughts so to get quiet and quiet
so as i said earlier in the meditation one of the
attitudes that i had that in my early years of practice beliefs was that
if something's happening to me it's not the real thing not necessarily logical to have that
belief um but that's kind of i never thought about it i didn't think
it out i didn't even know i had that belief but there it was when i got quiet deep
down inside it was like that wasn't a policy that i had towards everything so
i could never you know do things right or never never felt satisfied or content or or
at home anywhere because it was always the wrong thing so
you might think then you might think then that we have to cultivate the opposite
and that everything i'm experiencing is the right thing is the real thing
and or for example if you've discovered deep inside that you feel that um
you are somehow um you know bad
then you might think that now you have to that's what the thoughts tell you that now you have to cultivate thoughts that you're good
and so there's a trap in recognizing what's deep inside some
belief we have and thinking the solution is to have the opposite belief the
positive version of it so if you're
you know if you have a belief that you're wrong or bad then you have to kind of find a way to
believe that you're right and good and but that's kind of a headache that's
work and how do you do that really and that becomes kind of a strain and a
expectation that we live by in a challenge
now the alternative is to recognize some of the deeper beliefs that we have some of the deeper
emotions we have that are difficult and not set up the idea we now have to
experience the opposite it's enough it's powerful and enough
just to stop thinking i'm wrong just to stop thinking that i'm bad
so rather than thinking you have to become now a good person you just stop believing you're bad
um instead of thinking that you're because you're you're afraid
now you have to develop bravery and courage um
it's a really enough just to learn how to settle and quiet and and uh and let go of the fear perhaps
you don't have to replace it with something else and um because if you replace it with
something else you tend to be in a pendulum that can swing too easily between these success extremes
and also the attempt to go into the positive sometimes it's wonderful to do and nice
to do i don't want to say never do it but it often carries with it
even deeper attitudes a deeper belief around self me myself and mine like i'm the agent
and then only then will people really love me and so
there's a deeper belief about what it takes to be loved for example or concerned for that
and so as we go deeper and deeper in in the practice what we learn is that it's it's powerful
it's wonderful uh simply to stop
the this way of thinking these beliefs that we have and not replace them
and they're in the depths of who we are maybe we'll discover that there's a kind of a peace
a kind of a kind of stillness or kind of spaciousness or a kind of
calm that has no opposite that there's a kind of joy and a
happiness that has no opposite and so then we're not swinging so much back
and forth and it just it can just be there and it comes without a belief
it doesn't have to have a self connected to it it doesn't have to have some idea of who we are and what
we have to accomplish and what we have to do in order to be a good person a successful person
and and we can just be we're allowed just to be at home in
ourselves we don't have to prove ourselves we don't have to defend ourselves we don't have to
ex have any particular experience that's the experience we have to have
that we're allowed just to be ourselves and then
sometimes there's the idea that we when you are yourself the dharma is the dharma
when you just allow yourself in this kind of way to live in that deep place where there
are not living in the opposites that we swing by it's just this deeper place that has no opposite
so um [Music]
so this idea that there is a deeper voice belief attitude mood that
underlies it all you might want to see today to let it be a quieter day and see if there's
something there for you you have to be very careful with this and very tender and compassionate and it
feels like this is too much for you or if the information you learned now is something you need to digest and work
with and get support for by all means do that don't stay don't stay kind of
right up against it all the time but you might also see if this can be a day
where of this deeper quieter listening and you might have a busy day but maybe
other little corners of the day where you can sit quietly and just kind of tap in what's deep inside
and if what's deep inside what does it want to say if he could speak
sometimes that reveals something that won't be get revealed if we're just kind of feeling or tending to it
so maybe you'll discover too
that in the depths of who you are that's where your wisdom resides
so thank you and we'll continue again tomorrow