so hello everyone and welcome to our meditation
and um somewhat following the
demon last few days of mindfulness
of the for
properties elemental properties of earth water fire and air
i'd like to suggest some little variation of what we did yesterday
and today the instructions are to
follow the sensations in the body
follow the trail of sensations that their body
sends up and if you're with a relaxed mind
relax kind of not fixating or focusing on anything particular
let your body take the lead to so that and your awareness follows your
mindfulness follows so if
you're aware of a coolness in your fingers your mind would your awareness would go
to the fingers then aware of a teeny cough you'd be
aware of a little cough aware of warmth in the chest
you would go to the warmth whatever appears in the body
if you keep your attention open and relaxed to your body
what then sensations appear some may persist and last for a while
but if you stay relaxed around it and just kind of aware of it in a soft
kind of way kind of floating floating way
something else or some sooner or later will appear
and then you as it appears you follow that you continue on the trail
along that sensations so in other words you're not directing the attention
to something new or some idea you have what you should be paying attention to except for sensations of the body
but you're following the lead the body takes the lead and you follow maybe it's like a dance
where there's a lead and a follower so you just follow with awareness
and see what happens when you relax into
following along with no other responsibility but to follow along and to feel the
sensations that appear and then at some point
later in the meditation i'll offer some little additional instruction
so to about to begin to settle into your body to relax into
the present moment if it's nice for you you can take a few deeper breaths
a clear kind of ritual recognition of being here in your body
breathing in deeply
and extending the exhale longer than you
your exhale will do that on its own especially on the second half of the
extra exhale extended part of it is there more places in the body the
arms the shoulders that you can relax the belly
just
a ritual connection as you breathe in and the ritual of relaxation as you
exhale
then letting your breathing return to normal
and continue with a few more breaths just ordinary breaths
as you breathe in feel some place in your body where there's tension
and as you exhale relax and soften
breathing in breathing out relaxing into your body
and if you have any concerns thoughts pressure to think
feel that pressure as you breathe in and without expectation without
force as you exhale relax the thinking mind
and letting go of your thoughts and as you do letting go into your body
whenever you need to let go of your thinking let that be the same as letting go into
your body
and then for this meditation let your awareness your mindfulness
follow the trail of sensations that appear in the body
with your mind relaxed
be curious follow the what appears in your body
in whatever way the sensations your body appear disappear
appear persist for a while and then others appear follow the newly arising sensations in
your body letting your awareness follow them in a
relaxed slow way floating
to the next sensation that appears to the next one to the next one
where the trail the lead is set by the sensations
and awareness follows
whatever new sensations arise
let your awareness go there and then when the new another new one
arises let it go there be sensitive to
the new sensations of body that appear
sometimes it might include sounds appearing sensations of the years
if you think about what's happening you will miss the next arising of
sensation in your body see if you can quiet your mind enough
that you can float between the new sensations that arise in your body
in a light relaxed way
where no one sensation is given extra emphasis
or importance it's just a new arising
and now for the end of this sitting
to have felt your body the sensations of your body come and appear and disappear
is evidence that you are alive
this is the animated body
one day this body will be not alive this body will be a corpse
and none of those sensations will be here
and there's nothing no sensations for the body to take in
be aware of no sensations to
react to or to cling to worry about
no sensations
and there's no awareness of sensations no mind
this wonderful powerful gift of nature
to be aware will not be here as well
what is it to sit in the middle of this living body animated with
sensations and awareness without clinging to any of it
feeling the uniqueness the timeliness of this in this time in
this moment now is the only time and place
where all the sensations the awareness exists
the lived moment of the present
aware but not attached just aware
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to know yourself as an animate being alive with sensations alive with the
capacity to feel and sense
to be aware of the emotional life in your life of awareness and thoughts
and memories and futures with a heart that's sensitive to the
comings and goings of life the challenges and joys of life
and like you other people are the same way they too are
animated beings with sensitivities of body and heart and
mind with capacities for their inner life to be happy and free
or suffering and caught up
knowing that others are in some ways like yourself
in their capacity for happiness and suffering
open your heart of compassion and care the heart of love
to all beings
imagining how wonderful would be if they could be happy and free
just as it would be wonderful for you to be free in this precious living
life that we live
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
thank you
so today we move into the last of the
mindfulness exercises for the body with the body
there are six of these exercises and
so it starts with breathing then with mindfulness of postures
mindfulness of activities mindfulness of the parts of the body
mindfulness of the elements properties of the body
and then there's now um the mindfulness of or maybe we call
it the corpse meditation reflection consideration of a corpse
and this one um begins with the words
as if as if we're viewing a corpse
and so here we're calling upon the imagination and now some buddhists will go and spend
time with corpses so they this
mindfulness of death is a time-honored practice in buddhism most years before
covet i take people to anatomy lab to spend time with
the corpse it's fascinating to see it be with the corpse but to be with it in like an anatomy lab where we're
seeing a whole different perspective on life and the body and people
when i was a freshman in college i took a drawing class
and um halfway through the class the teacher took us to the anatomy lab
of the university and um there was uh we would go into the lab
and there would be this there was this person laid out who had died a corpse and um
and it was you know it was the first time i've ever seen a corpse in that kind of detail and way in
and we were supposed to draw it and the first day we were there two days
the first day i went to i drew the person's foot because that to me was the furthest i
can get away from having to deal with this this death
when i went back to next time i realized what i'd done that i'd been avoiding
so i uh then decided to draw the face to really kind of be there with it
the teacher explained that the reason he took his drawing classes to the anatomy lab
is that after the visit everyone's drawings would be stronger i never
asked him what stronger meant but apparently he appreciated somehow the something shifted for people
and um so this time modern way of being reminded of our mortality
of being really kind of knowing that we're going to die
that you know it's easy when you're young to think well you know operate as if no
i'll never die or i know i die but it's irrelevant and but to some point to really kind of
consider and reflect and look death right in the eye and take it in and
consider it for the purposes
of becoming free in this life for the purposes of somehow
connecting to this lived experience of ours so that we can live in the midst of this
lived life freely the contemplation of death is not a glorification of death
but it's meant to be variety do a variety of things for different people there's different benefits from contemplating death
and for some people it really and i think this is it helps them to really
show up and be really present in a cute way for this life like now is the time we have to be aware
to practice let's not put it off in this
there is you know the direction the practice is
going each of these exercises is to be able to very deeply settled
peaceful undistracted to be able to settle back and just
observe things arise and pass away until observing arising and passing away
of phenomena the changing flow of experience something inside let's go the clinging
and the grasping so when the suta introduces this corpse contemplation
we have to understand i think it's good to understand that it's it's for the purposes of this
really getting concentrated and settled and and being able to observe
in a deep way so it's not meant to be disturbing though it might initially be disturbing
it's meant to develop concentration in a peacefulness
it doesn't work for everyone but knowing that that's the purpose then so we oriented ourselves around this
contemplation with that as kind of the north star
so how is it we contemplate the corpse that supports this
well one clue is that uh it is a little bit of a visualization imagination
and it's maybe kind of compelling one rather than going and finding a real corpse to look at
um it may be a little bit uh less disturbing less
you know challenging to imagine one if you could imagine it kind of lightly
or in a way that's not so disturbing just imagine there's a corpse
and and then um and so for beginners i think it's what's
nice is to uh there's nine of these contemplations but to start kind of in the middle
and to contemplate a skeleton so if you come across you know they're
in an anatomy lab or a museum or somewhere
a human skeleton to contemplate it
when i was practicing in thailand with a famous teacher named buddhadasa
he had mostly he was really into practicing outdoors and teaching outdoors and
but because it rains there he had a big yet big
meditation hall dharma hall that had open sides but had a roof to protect people from the rain
it was kind of a big big big building big roofed area
and in a respectful way hanging from the rafters were a couple of skeletons
and one of them was had a sign under it
and under the sign it said miss thailand 1936.
so i imagine that's been up there for all those years for a good reason
for me in the dharma hall and a place where teachings and meditation happens
and i suppose it's to remind people that any preoccupation with beauty
is you know attachment to beauty physical beauty and to identify with
that and hold on to that and be preoccupied with that you know it's only temporary
that underneath that and in the end of that there's the corpse there's a skeleton
in what way is that not gross in what way is it not disturbing in what way can we contemplate that that
skeleton in a way that's beneficial for us that supports us on this path of freedom and
liberation it's easy to be disturbed it's easy to protest
it can be much more difficult to put that aside gently
not rejecting it but just putting aside if we want to benefit from these
exercises we don't benefit if we protest we benefit if we do the inner work like how
is it that this can be helpful for me
so um the uh so these the text begins
as if one is viewing a corpse and then it ends
with um with uh each each of the nine contemplations
it ends with the reflecting
this body too has a nature like this will become like this
will not avoid this so in other words the contemplation of a
corpse is for the purpose to realize this will happen here to me
this too will happen and in what way does this realization this discovery
um or taking this in this you know true thing in what way do we benefit from that
where's the wisdom of that how does that guide us in a good direction how does it wake us up
how does it help us shed the distracted mind the preoccupied mind
the mind that's involved in things that maybe are not really to our benefit how does it create a kind of seriousness
a kind of aliveness a kind of dedication and in the context of this
meditation how does it even create a kind of love
for being present now so that we can get
really settled here really clear that this is the place where the meditation is in here in the
present moment here and now so
i'll describe more this contemplation of the corpse later um
the um but for now i'd like to encourage you to contemplate a corpse i don't know
about where you live but around here this last halloween there were
the population of skeletons increased dramatically never seen so
many halloween skeletons and some are still hanging in different places and
the last one i saw a week or so ago was someone had outfitted the skeleton with um
climbing gear mountain climbing gear with shoes and belts and everything and had headed climbing um
uh underneath the eaves up onto the roof of their house so all these fun things people are doing
but uh maybe contemplate skeletons maybe consider your skeleton uh that now
right now is clothed with tendons and flesh and
but consider that someday your skeleton might be without flesh
or some someday maybe your your skeleton will be all that's left in
in terms of ashes if you get cremated and now and how it does you know you
might consider this and think about it in a way but the exercises to do this is to consider in what way can you do
this it's beneficial so you're not getting depressed or upset or horrified but rather in what way does
this light some kind of
greater present moment awareness some ability to really okay here i am no question about
it when there's a skeleton there's no animated life no awareness no sensations
no nothing we see nothing we hear
and how to rest in that be free in that
so that's the homework if you'd like to do it and then we'll continue this tomorrow
and um and i placed in the
in the underneath if you're on youtube i place underneath the um
the you know this you know the picture of the video in the
description section of youtube underneath it one of the
contemplations you can see the text of the skeleton one and then finally what i'd like to say is
that just give you a heads up since will maybe be here friday
that next monday the 21st of february we won't have we won't have the monday
uh 7 a.m youtube we'll take a break what you might do is
go back and redo re-listen to and follow one of the previous
videos on the satepatanosuta kind of refresh yourself on some part of it maybe a part that was maybe more
impactful but i'm going away i'm going to my father's 91st birthday so i need to i
won't be able to be here that monday but i'll be back on tuesday
so thank you and i look forward to our time tomorrow