so hello everyone nice to see you arriving
let's go ahead and get started together Okay so
settling in for meditation
sensing into the body arriving at your spot
and closing your eyes if it's comfortable for you to do so
maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths
really filling the lungs and then just allowing the breath to naturally
exhale just to really Connect into the feeling
of the body and then just letting the breath be
natural
and as is often helpful at the beginning of a sit inviting some ease throughout the body
sensing into the head area
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
letting go of all the little muscles on the scalp
down through the jaw and the throat
and releasing the shoulders entity holding in the upper back
so that the heart can naturally be forward
just letting the arms float freely
and all down into the belly area releasing the diaphragm
softening the area of the belly so that it can
kind of round out or drop down farther into the abdomen
releasing any holding in the low back so that we're just balanced on the spine
and releasing the hip joints down through the legs
the calves the Achilles and into the feet
just inviting is inviting some connection to the body
and it's okay however it is
bringing attention also to this state of the mind or the heart
first of all noticing what's there how are you right now
and then also inviting some ease in the mind
one way to do that is to find some bit of ease somewhere
and just connect with that kind of emphasize it in attention even
if there are other parts of the mind that are not so much at ease
connecting in with the sensations of the breath
scenting the breath maybe like a warm bath
something gentle
something that envelops the body
imagining that we can steep the body and the breath
just encouraging the body and the mind to be simple
if they're complicated or agitated parts we can put them more on the back burner
and keep the Simplicity of our awareness and breath and Body on the front burner
if you begin to sense some degree of peace or ease
or even wholesome pleasure in the experience of breathing
it's fine to favor that in attention to emphasize
that
this is actually how the instructions for mindfulness of breathing go
mindfulness is not always purely neutral
so go ahead in favor any sense of ease or peace
feeling the simple rhythmic rocking of the breath
and if we're getting to involved in the pleasure and the joy of the breath will
feel that as agitation or if we're resisting
this idea of enjoying the simple experience of the breath I
will feel that his agitation also finding the middle way that's very
simple intends toward ease
for now I will offer a shift
now turning the attention more toward the changing nature of the
breath it's the same experience but we turn
attention more toward the flow in and out Sensations that continually
changing experience of the breath
we see that it's never the same from moment to moment
but there is still some use in just resting with the flow
we can gently open just a bit
the investigation aspect of the Mind
acknowledging that the breath is a multitude of Sensations
that are arising shifting and passing away
in an overlapping kind of way really allowing the Deep acknowledgment
of that in the body in the mind
keeping the Mind soft as we open to the
flutter Kaleidoscope of change
that is the bread
and it will rest in Silence with that for a bit
and in the last few minutes of this meditation
we can reflect that what is experienced
just in the breath is
also paralleled in life daily life
as well as in the Arc of our life and if there's a continual arising
shifting and changing and passing away of things
and the degree to which we can acknowledge and rest in that
we're in touch with how things actually are
relationships change over time
there are new ones and sometimes they end our work has changed
our body and health shift over time
the weather the seasons it's always in flux in some way
and of course we know this at some level
but we also forget it
and often times when we're suffering
our times when we are out of touch with this natural flow
so we can reflect on the way meditation prepares us for Living Well in the world
it's not about knowing a lot about the breath it's about having that experience
and relating to it well that then somehow can come forth as we meet life
so we can hope that in our day today and going forward
we're able to discern these patterns of how things work
in order that we can relate well to people and
live in a way that is inspiring and reminds people in even
just a simple way that it's possible to flow along with life
in a way that doesn't have too much suffering
[Music]
foreign
we've made it to the last item in our list of five Dharma resources for
meeting life well we've talked about confidence SATA
ethical conduct or virtue Sila listening and learning
suta and generosity and letting go chaga
and then the last item can be seen as something distinct but it's also one
that emerges from and sums up the other four and it is discernment panya
that word is also translated as wisdom but we'll lean toward using discernment
for today and there are many things that it's useful to discern on the path to Freedom
the most fundamental is understanding what is unskillful and what is skillful
so Discerning between what leads towards suffering and what leads away from
suffering so this links ponya to Selah virtue or
ethics but it also goes outside the conventional range of Ethics into areas
like choosing how to navigate the Mind during sitting meditation
sometimes people think that there shouldn't be any form of judgment in practice
we just accept everything all the time in a passive way
but this is too broad brush judiciousness is essential for waking up
this is from the Dharma Potter in a chapter called the just
the wise person who as if holding a set of scales selects what's good and avoids
what's evil is for that reason a sage whoever can weigh these two sides of the
world is for that reason called a sage
so I apologize for the word evil that's what the translation said we could just think unskillful or unwholesome
and the same chapter also says one is not just who judges a case hastily a
wise person considers both what is and isn't right
so these quotes affirm that wise judgment is indeed part of practice
but they also imply the way these ones were written having some kind of time to
consider options you know weighing the two sides of the world considering both what is and isn't right
and sometimes we have the space to do that and we should when we can this is part of living a conscious reflective
life um but there's also what happens in the moment so unfortunately there are other
ways that we can train our discernment so that it becomes a reliable resource
even right in the moment when it's combined with mindfulness
so to do this it's best to understand the ways in which we tend to make mistakes in how we
see things and then we can train to see in wiser ways
so um these are various ways that we don't properly discern what's going on you
know when we're making mistakes basically because we gloss over details or we focus on the wrong thing
so the Buddha identified three main mistakes let's say to watch for I think
he called them distortions so one gloss that we make is to see
things that are impermanent as permanent or things that are changing as
unchanging and in many cases this comes down to a matter of careful mindfulness
so you know suppose we're outside and we look across a clearing and we see a
black line across the ground it looks solid but as we get closer we see that it's
actually a line of ants it's lots of ants walking close together in the same
direction you can see this sometimes like on Retreats out in Retreat centers that are
in the jungle or out away from you know from the cities I've seen
several of these ant lines so as we get close this solid line breaks up into
individual ants in motion or maybe you've seen those um fire
sticks that people sometimes wave around on holidays maybe more often in Asia than here but you do it at night and
it's a stick that's burning on one end where these days it might be an LED or something and you it's twirled rapidly
in a circle and it looks like a solid circle of light because we don't see that it's a single light being moved
when it's going fast like that there are many things that are like this you know we look out and we see a tree
but if we get closer and closer and closer like really close eventually you'll be looking at
molecules that are that are all in motion you know how solid is that tree
sitting in meditation we might perceive pain in our shoulder to be a solid wall
it feels like a hardened area almost like a stone but with careful mindfulness if we're
willing to turn toward it sometimes the pain can break up into many little
Sparks of sensation often in quite a small area I mean it might still be there as strong
sensation but we can't quite believe in its solidity anymore
if we look with careful mindfulness so experiences like solidity and
unchangingness are actually products of how we're seeing uh if things are changing slowly or if
mindfulness is not very precise you know we're just catching a moment here and there not every moment then
they can seem relatively permanent it's a very important Dharma insight to
see into the impermanent in constant and changing nature of actually all
experience and this greatly assists in letting go because we discern in sort of at an
intuitive level that there really isn't much to grasp and we can train the mind to discern in
this way we can incline towards seeing in that way and as we do we do that you
know just throughout the day and in meditation that way of seeing will be available to us as a Dharma resource at
moments where it's useful so then a second gloss or misperception
is to see what is ultimately unsatisfying as fully satisfying
so we typically carry the idea that getting something pleasant something
that we want is going to satisfy us maybe it's even going to be the thing
that really does it for us you know if I just get this one thing or if I just get rid of this one thing then then it will
be better for example we might think
ah I'm going to take a hot bath tonight that is really going to do it for me
after a long day of work and if the conditions come together and we do get to do that we enjoy it but
does it really satisfy completely doesn't your mind just go on to the next
thing that will be just perfect so we're talking here about this quality
of dukkha unsatisfactoriness in human life and it helps very much to
understand that duka doesn't have to have this narrow meaning of suffering which is often how it's translated
definitely a nice hot bath is not suffering nor is it wrong to enjoy it
but a hot bath is Duca because it is not able to ultimately satisfy us and if we
don't know that we're actually setting ourselves up for genuine suffering
and if we're honest really all those special Pleasant things that we create in our life are quite temporary and
sometimes not even as good in the moment as we think they're going to be yes the hot water is nice but sitting in a
bathtub I find to be a little hard on my back resting on a hard enamel surface
and after 10 minutes anyway the water's cooling off a little bit so
there's an image given in the sutus for the hindrance of sensual desire which is
dyed water like water that's been tied a certain colors so we don't see very
clearly through it I think it's in sort of an early version of rose-colored lenses
so it's helpful to train our mind to discern when we're looking with
rose-colored lenses and not allow ourselves to think that things are going to be more satisfying than they are
now definitely sometimes people resist this idea of training the mind to understand that a given experience
cannot be ultimately satisfying but I see it as actually very supportive
in fact the very fact that we have a distorted perception that some experience is going to make us fully
happy it actually diminishes the enjoyment of it because it places kind of pressure on it in a sense and when we
actually understand that no experience can inherently make us happy it actually makes it much easier to enjoy things
fully and then to let them go as they're as they're passing so you know it's really just a
protection for the mind don't worry life is still as many good things but we're just not distorted about them
okay and then the third Main gloss let's say or non-discerning way of
seeing things is to mistake or does not solve for an abiding self
and in this case I haven't found very much value in in really thinking about this cognitively it's really much better
just to do as a practice um a great practice that can be done in
daily life as well as on the cushion is found in the instructions that the Buddha gave to Bahia and I think some of
you are likely familiar with them he said in the scene let there just be the scene in The Herd just the herd in
the sensed just the sensed and in the cognized just the cognized
so we practice seeing experience in kind of an unadorned way a simple way
you know for example the sound of a bell just ring a bell I guess I could do that
have one
easier okay listen to this
so it's a simple experience of sound just arising and passing
it doesn't have much to do with our self unless we add one on
but really it's just the sound coming and going so in cases like this
that are simple we get a glimpse of the way fruiting yourself onto something it
would be actually imputed onto experience by the mind if we were to say that's my sound that's a special Bell
just for me you know things like that it's obviously something extra and
that's not to problematize that we do that sometimes it's just to be accurate that you know putting yourself on is
something extra it's additional to their experience see for yourself it takes
careful mindfulness but you can see this for yourself in the words of Joseph Goldstein only
six things ever happen seeing hearing smelling tasting touching and mental
activity so the Buddha concludes his teaching to Bahia by saying this just this is the
end of dukkha so we can see exp when we can see experience in a simple way then
there isn't suffering or stress so essentially when we train not to be
fooled into these non-discerning ways of seeing then we're much more likely to
make good decisions in the moment so non-discernment is to think that things
are in the words of Ruth Kane I love the way she puts this we think that things are permanent perfect and personal
and what we want to train in is to not be fooled by that
so if we see more wisely more discerningly then we
won't be foolishly trying to hold on to or control things that are bound to change we won't be setting ourselves up
for disappointment in duka by tying our happiness to things that change and are limited
and we won't be getting wrapped up and thinking that things are inherently personal inherently ourselves and all
the Duca that goes with that so this is kind of a culmination of all the
things that have we've been practicing up to now the confidence the Seal of
Ethics the learning of the teachings and listening carefully to our experience
and then being willing to let go whether in the form of actually giving something or the releases that happen along the
path you know then we come to have this Discerning view of understanding the
changing nature of things and how to live well in the world
and as a reminder the Buddha said that these five qualities are a form of inner
wealth their form of fortitude of character their Inspirations when we think of how
they can be known in the world we feel happy and people who possess them and
have them well at hand are said to be spiritually mature one that I didn't say up to now is that
these are also said to help us at the time of death and when these are well
established in the heart they assure uneaseful death
so these serve us both on and off the cushion to meet life well in the moment
and we can strengthen any and all of them through training which is very worthwhile to do
and all of them are made potent by mindfulness practice that's the the core
Foundation behind all of them so thank you for being here for this
week I very much hope that something in it landed for you and that it will
support you and all those around you to take it into your practice in life
be well