good evening welcome welcome it's nice to see you all
so today I'd like to continue my exploration of these seven factors of
Awakening and
there's not surprisingly seven of these seven factors of Awakening
and I've gone through all seven and I'm doing a little bit more on this last one equanimity
so there's no requirement to memorize all these lists
maybe they'll become familiar after you um practice for a while so I don't want
it to feel like burden some it's um frankly it's because I'm going
to be teaching a class on these some factors of Awakening it starts in a couple weeks
and I just wanted to teach this series to give me an opportunity to think about it
all these topics and also to share them in the form of a Dharma talk as a as
opposed to a class so what are these seven factors of Awakening
mindfulness investigation energy and Joy are the first four I'll just say
mindfulness is just being aware of what's happening and then there's these
three energizing factors investigation energy and joy kind of
like bring the energy up and then there's three tranquilizing calming factors that bring the energy
down those are Tranquility concentration and
Equanimity and even like if you've never heard any Buddhist teaching whatsoever
you would just recognize oh yeah energy and joy is a little bit more bubbly and
investigation feels like something that you do as opposed to Tranquility concentration
equanimity and so I'd like to kind of like flesh
out a little bit more just talking about equanimity and as I mentioned last week this wasn't
a word that was in my vocabulary until I kind of encountered Buddhist teachers
teachings and teachers and with this kind of beginning equa I
figured it had something to do with equal but uh Equanimity turns out to be a
really rich word and there's so many ways we can think about it look at it understand it
practice with it and for me this is something that I appreciate so much about the Buddhist
teachings is that there's such a depth and a breadth and a richness there
no matter how many times I come back and maybe teach the same thing or study and I do a little bit of translating and
kind of like look at some of these really the early teachings I'm always
finding something new like oh yeah this is related to that
either another teaching or like oh right this is that experience that I've had I
wouldn't have put it in this language but now I understand it differently and so I kind of hope to maybe share with
all of you some of my appreciation of the richness of what's available and
and of course for me and I'm imagining for many of you too this is in contrast
to some dogmatic view like this is the way that it is I am and I have encountered teachers
that you have this kind of fundamentalist dogmatic View and I don't know it just makes me feel uncomfortable
so instead I'd like to encourage like a spirit of inquiry or engagement as
opposed to okay this is just some list I'm supposed to memorize but maybe it's a way you might see that
it makes sense to you and it's helpful for in your life and in
your practice okay so equanimity
kind of a way that I'd like to think about it and practice with it is this recognition that it's a number of
different has a number of different qualities including that it's a steadiness
of the mind and the Heart what is steadiness um
when I was young there was these I maybe watched a little bit too much TV and there was this uh commercial that came
that was still in my mind it's quite something where I tell some of these commercials you know decades later are
still in my mind and there is this toy that was called
Weebles some of you are not in your head right and you know what the little like jingle
was like Weebles wobble but they don't fall down so that's for me a little bit
of equanimity like this idea that we might you know get a little bit off balance but then
we'll the kid come back to Center and maybe we get a little bit way off balance or maybe it's just a little bit
but Weebles wobble but they don't fall down I never had any of these Weebles but you
know I just saw enough of those commercials I understood the premise of them so the steadiness that is there you
know maybe there's a little bit of wobbliness which maybe brings me to another point about Equanimity is that
it's not an on off switch it's not a binary you have it or you don't have it
maybe sometimes you get way off balance maybe the wobble is pretty far before
you come back to a sense of balance or maybe there's just a little bit but
whatever it might be it's pointing to this idea of not falling down
or if you do falling down finding your way back so it has this steadiness with maybe I
might say this in our balance and I'm using this Weebles example but
another way is um I think it's called a keel on the bottom of a sailboat this really long
bit that helps the sailboat not tip over when there's winds
so it's like maybe having some a keel but it's uh not only this kind of like
stability or the steadiness this balance but it Equanimity also has this quality
of seeing the bigger picture and that's part of why it doesn't get
off balance is because it understands like a number
of things what the bigger picture is one of it is like oh of course it's this way of
course I'm late because I left a little bit late and I forgot it was commute hour and I had to stop and
get gas in my car and so instead of this friend of like oh I'm going to be late and what are people going to say and I
just said I wasn't going to be late anymore or whatever it might be instead of recognizing like of course it's this
way because there was all these conditions in place to make it that way
of course I don't feel well because I got some really difficult news and I ate
junk food because I wasn't feeling well and I didn't sleep so well last night so of
course right now I'm feeling a little out of sorts and maybe that's why we were short with our co-worker or our
partner or whatever so being able to have this sense of that
things are the way that they are because there were conditions that they are there to support it
and maybe this goes without saying but maybe it's helpful for me to just make it more explicit that having this
stability this balance makes life easier to navigate
because maybe we have to do less navigating if we have this ability or to not be
thrown off balance so much that we feel like we can't ever come back to some
sorts of some sort of Center and to be clear when I'm saying Center I'm not saying that we're like Rock
Solid right I don't know if anybody's life is like that they're completely Rock Solid
but it's opposed to this you know just going back and forth Within getting blown all over the place
so it makes life easier to navigate because what would it be like if we didn't have
to avoid awkward situations
what if we had the confidence to like okay this is gonna be uncomfortable I
need to set boundaries with this person and tell them it's not okay that they're doing that or I need to apologize for a
mistake that I made or I need to finish that project even
though it's not quite perfect and I really want it to be perfect but I just need to finish it you know what would it
be like if we could do these things recognize the uncomfortableness and do it anyway
like our lives just would unfold better if we didn't feel like we had to avoid all the uncomfortableness is that arise
or if when something wonderful or nice or that something wished for arises
if we didn't feel like oh my gosh I have to hold on as tightly as I can because I might never get this again and I gotta
squeeze every last bit of goodness out of this experience
like wouldn't it be different if we felt like we could just kind of like drink it up and appreciate it of gratitude allow
ourselves to feel nourished by it without this feeling of just holding on
for everything we got or something like this everything we have with all we got
so it just helps life easier to navigate and
as I'm speaking about this it occurs to me that it goes along also with this idea of confidence
so maybe it's not so much the idea that we can do whatever needs to be done
but maybe it's the idea that I can recover from the difficulty or if
it doesn't turn out great somehow that's going to be still be okay or sometimes we have this feeling like
if anything's not okay then we feel like Oh I'm a failure
should always make everything be okay nothing ever is going to turn out right right we have that feeling right
sometimes it just feels overwhelming and we collapse into it so Equanimity is this idea that
we can it makes our life easier to navigate not
only that we can be with uncomfortable situations but we don't have to hold on to
things that are pleasurable and gives us the confidence to try new things or to be in new situations
so I want to speak a little bit just that I appreciate again Diana and her appreciation but and
the Buddhist teachings that the Buddha thousands of years ago I like to think
about this thousands of years ago like how many people have heard these
teachings and they've been touched by and that this is just part of the human condition so much
so that thousands of years ago they were talking about it they were talking about what are the
things that help us make us create the conditions in which we're not
equanimous what are the things that knock us off
balance and probably you wouldn't be surprised
if I said it was a list oh thanks and it's often called it's eight but
it's four pairs and recently I discovered like a new
translation kind of like a new understanding with these four pairs are and I really like this new set
these nudes out of four pairs of uh like that I guess we could call a
new translation because it's a little bit in more kind of modern language language that we might use and every day
parlance and that you can find lots of books of like how to work with these things and probably Untold
talks or something about this so but before I say what these four pairs
are the I just want to emphasize that there is
no human that is exempt from experiencing these
no human like the Buddha right he experience these things
and so I don't know just that alone recognizing that this is part of our
inheritance as humans this is what it means to be human is to have these experiences
and and the reason why they are in pairs is
this idea that you can't have one without the other
as soon as you say well something's on the left hand side then of course there's something that has to be on the
right hand side right as soon as we start defining left then there's right gets defined too
as soon as we start saying oh that one's tall then we have to say that compared to the
other one that's not as tall that's shorter so as soon as we start kind of like
dividing up the world in one way it's conceptually then we're also saying
it's the other way something's good then something else is bad if we're equanimous the opposite of
equanimous is out of balance suffering
these types of things so that's a reason why they come in to come in pairs is
because as soon as you say that you want something then by
definition that means you don't want other things of course right of course
this is how the world works [Applause] so maybe again before I kind of like say
what these pairs are is that it's about Equanimity is not about getting our life
perfect it's not manufacturing creating
engineering to have everything perfect exactly like we want it
and it's not uncommon to have this secret wish like okay well as soon as you know this happens and then that
happens and then that happens okay then everything will be fine
right here we all are if that worked for you you were not to be here on a Monday night listening to our Dharma talk
of course we want everything to be perfect of course we do we want all the Ducks to
be in a row but it doesn't work out that way and
I kind of feel like it's spoiler alert right it's never gonna be that way
so Equanimity is about our relationship to what is it's not about making things
perfect so that we can be happy and feel balanced it's about our relationship like even
though things are not the way that we want can we still feel imbalanced
can we still have some steadiness
I think this is worth repeating it's about our relationship to them sometimes the Buddhist teachings right
there's like we have this Arrow that's things that are unfortunate get stabbed and and then there's the second Arrow
is like this sometimes we talk about how wanting things to be different or you
know this aversion or holding on to it so tightly or whatever it might be
so it's about not having the second Arrow we can't avoid the first arrows
okay so what are these eight things these four pairs
the first success and failure everybody's gonna have success and
failure nobody is immune from this the next status and disgrace
or sometimes we talk about like reputation you know sometimes your reputation is up or down and I think
like in this age of social media I think this is getting really heightened approval and disapproval
this is gonna happen in our lives of course it is maybe we're even doing this
to others like okay well I approve this but I don't approve that right and then the last ease and unease
there's going to be times when we feel comfortable on times when we don't feel comfortable
it's the way it is so how can we
cultivate Equanimity how can we recognize recognizing that these eight
worldly winds as they're often called this recognition that these are winds
that just blow we don't get to control them they just blow One Way One Direction or the other
recognizing that how can we stay balanced how can we do this Equanimity
thing so one thing that I want to point out
is I started by saying Equanimity is that the part of the seven factors of Awakening
and it's the seventh one it's at the end Equanimity is in a number of other
lists also it's in the Brahma vahara it's these heart practices
it's also at the end of that list it's in the power amuse these 10 parames
these qualities that we can cultivate in daily life not always on the cushion a
little bit of overlap but the same factors Awakening Equity is the tenth one it's in the last
one there genas these are like a concentration
States that um for the first four which are the four main ones
Equanimity is the predominant experience or I'll say that experience in the last
one in the fourth one after having gone through the earlier three
progress of insight this development and a little bit later Buddhism of how Awakening occurs before
Awakening is this step equanimity so it's always at the end of all these
lists and one way to understand that is
because all these preceding factors are part of what's cultivating creating
the conditions in which Equanimity might arise because it's tempting of course okay
Equanimity this sounds like a good thing I want some what do I do and we have this idea well can I just
take it out of all of its practices or these Buddhist practices and just do
this Equanimity thing I have to worry about all this other stuff that these Dharma teachers are talking about
and I certainly tried this I have a little story that um
that's going on a long retreat and for those of you who have been among
Retreats you know this that there's this question well how does laundry work
when you're on a long retreat right you know if you're there for months right you don't have months of clean clothes
right so like how does this work and when there were a hundred people in the meditation hall there's a hundred
people's laundry that has to get done so it's a big ordeal
and it's a little bit different now but how they used to do this years ago is
that there would be like the laundry day for half of the people so let's say for
maybe 50 people and you could do laundry for a week's worth 50 people doing a week's worth of
laundry this is a lot of laundry right and it was somebody's job they just had
washing machines and dryers and you know for a whole day you know like this was
they just would run Non-Stop but how to get your own laundry back
right it's one thing to put things in but of course you want your clothes back because Well everybody's wearing gray
sweatpants and white t-shirts right so how do you find yours back so
um laundry tags so they would have some ribbon an indelible marker and you could
write your name on this ribbon and then you would safety pin this piece of ribbon onto every single piece of your
clothing then you'd bring it to the place they'd be laundry and then there'd be this huge pile of laundry and you
would just go through everything and find your pieces not the best system it's as bad as it
sounds so I had this idea after learning this is how it is like okay I'm gonna make my
own personalized little laundry ties I'm going to turn this into a whole little art project for myself
and I wanted to have Equanimity I'd heard about this and I thought okay I'm just gonna do this Equanimity thing on
this long retreat so I made a made it much more complicated than it needed to be but it
was a little art project for myself but I made all these little tugs that said which is the poly word for equanimity
and while I was making all these I was thinking like and I was then when I was on Retreat I'm
safety pinning all these little upaka upeka Pekka and all my clothes thinking like okay this is all I have to do just
say this word over and over again and I'm gonna get equanimity it didn't work
I didn't have equanime I wanted it so badly I thought like okay if I just like
say this word think about it enough or do it over and over again somehow it
would arise but it didn't and it wasn't until later
on another retreat that I discovered something really
important and this gets back to the
Equanimity being the last and all these lists well what's second to last
on all these lists like what's preceding it
so if in the list of the parames loving kindness
is before equanimity the list of the Brahma the horrors these art practices
sympathetic Joy is before equanimity
in the seven factors of Awakening concentration is in the before
Equanimity in the janas happiness is before equanimity
so there's this quality of kind of like this maybe we could say warm-heartedness
or this type of well-being loving kindness
sympathetic Joy that's uh being happy when other people are happy being happy for their uh Good Fortune
or concentration I talked about concentration before also has this quality of well-being
so Equanimity when we think about it makes perfect sense of course it arises
out of a certain amount of well-being when we have a little bit of settledness
or this feeling like we have enough we have enough love we have enough
something inside of us we feel filled up in some kind of way
then of course we're not going to get so knocked off balance
so one of the key ways to develop equanimity
is to develop well-being one of the ways to develop well-being is
some warm-heartedness some loving kindness it's not the only way and next week I'll
talk about other ways but I think sometimes this is neglected when we
think about Equanimity it sounds like a I don't know it can feel a little bit cold-hearted or indifferent but it's
really about this warm-heartedness and this
and seen the big picture with a little bit of care that allows us to maybe
there's a little bit of wobbling but coming back to balance
you might say Okay Diana that sounds nice but how do we cultivate the warm-heartedness for this well-being
well of course there's a list but I'm not going to go through a list
I'm going to just talk about a few things here one is
just inclining the mind towards
warm-heartedness or well-being so there's a number of ways to do this
in daily life on the cushion off the cushion it doesn't matter but one is
notice when it's arising naturally in your experience
just notice when that you get that email that as if
I'm your friend and they say hey do you want to go to lunch and you feel like oh yeah actually I do and that little bit
of uplift that happens or when you get home and your dog is
like wagging his tail so happy to see you and that little kind of like uplift that happens
or when you are with a good friend and you just feel happy to be with them or
whatever it is you're sharing maybe they're having difficulties and you're happy to be able to support them
maybe there's your partner brings you a cup of tea a cup of coffee these lots of
mundane things I'm hoping that these are in your life
it's time it's true that there are times in our life when we feel like they're they're not there I don't want to make it sound like everybody has these all
the time I want to but I want to encourage that when that is there can we just recognize
oh here's that little uplift and if it has some warm-heartedness
I'm using warm-hearted as this really vague word that maybe you can find your way with
some people might say meta or Goodwill or benevolence or something like this so
just notice when it just naturally arises
when you're feeling the opposite of loving kindness maybe just notice you know irritation with somebody maybe just
notice what's what's in the way here why am I feeling cold-hearted here maybe
cold-hearted is too strong at an expression but
and so that's one just to notice when it's naturally there and so when our
minds start to notice it and tune into it notice the pleasantness of it it just
makes it more likely the mind will do that again without our having to try it
to do anything special and then this is something that
um should I say that I appreciate again with uh my Buddhist teachings is that we
don't have to wait until the conditions are just perfect to have this sense of
kindness this sense of Good Will towards others towards ourselves we don't have
to wait for that we can cultivate it and one of the conventional ways is with
loving kindness practice so a few ways we can do that
with a in a meditative setting
maybe perhaps many of you are familiar with this practice it's um
often begins with wherever it's easy whomever it's just easy for you to feel
the some warmth towards to start there
I teach loving kindness on Tuesdays and Thursdays online and Nikki mercifori
teaches it Monday Wednesday Friday so if you're interested five days a week we have loving kindness practice online
and I always say start where it's easy there's no reason not to start where
it's easy and then to feel the connection with this lovable being
and it can be helpful to say phrases may you be safe may you be happy may you be healthy may
you live with ease and I can tell you from doing this
practice over and over again it is transformative and people that have been
coming to this what we call it happy hour number of people are just saying this
has changed my life in such a way I never expected I just keep on showing up at 6 pm and because it was nice it was
pleasant but my life is turning out to be different and so I just want to point out that
it's it's so common that we come to mindfulness practice we
come to Buddhist practice thinking that okay we have to meditate we have to get the Mind quiet we have to learn to sit
still or all these types of things but we might underestimate how powerful it
is to be cultivating loving kindness especially towards ourselves
especially towards ourselves it turns out we're often subtly beating
ourselves up very commonly when we're meditating and we notice that our mind is off the breath or yeah off we've lost
in thought and there's this little like dang it get it together you're supposed to be meditating on this thing that we
would come back and there's this little irritation well we're kind of cultivating a little bit of aversion or
this little like not appreciating ourselves and that cumulative effect you
know it has an impact so loving kindness practices a way that
kind of kind of soften that it's often that
inner critic that can arise when we're doing this practice
so maybe I'll just mention one more things before I open it up to
um some q a that something that we don't do
here very much at IMC we do very little of it but it's a practice that I think
is really great and also can be really powerful and some traditions really
focus on this practice and that is chanting
and chanting the metasuta so there's some of you might be familiar with the the suta that
um it it talks about like good will for others or something and it's very
inspiring and um this can be a practice to chant it
and or memorize it enchant It And I memorized it by listening to it again
and again and again um from the monks by a gear you'll just
mention this they have a whole chant book that's you know MP3 you can download and listen to again and again
so appreciating when it just arises naturally in your life doing some intentional meditation
practices I mentioned one there's some others or doing some chanting there can
be something in which I don't know chanting opens up a different part of us
it's not for everybody but for some people it's really meaningful and helpful
so loving-kindness practice as a support for equanimity
loving kindness is a way to kind of like soften the heart think about it right that when we feel kind of like this
sense of love sense of care
there's a sense of stability that goes with it and there's like this increased capacity to be with whatever is
difficult so next week I'll talk about some other practices that we can do but I would
just like to offer this as well as loving-kindness practices as a support
for equanimity okay so with that I'd like to open it up
to some q a if there are any questions
okay so I guess our friends on YouTube have some questions so yes Sage do you want to use the microphone
um one of our friends from the Internet is asking would you give us the reference to download The Meta suit to chant
so that's a good question I met this Utah
um I recommend going to at buyagiri.org a b h a y a
g-i-r-i if I can write it down on a piece of paper if anybody wants who's here and
wants to come back and let's try it if you're at home I'll say one more time a b h a
y-a-g-i-r-i Abaya giri and they are a monastery that's up near Redding and
this is part of their regular chanting they have a whole chant book and they have it in English and in Poley and that
you can hear them chanting it both in English and poorly and I was and part of the reason why I'm recommending that one
is because um sometimes Retreats at IRC we do chant
that and we chant it in the same style that they do so if you learn it from them then um you'll be able to use it at
IRC and was there another one or nope nope
okay just saying nice things okay well that's nice just uh anybody else have a question or
let's speak there
good evening Diana everyone thank you Diana yeah I had a question regarding
like Equanimity and confidence and I know it's not like oh I know I'm gonna
do this right just just that that whole not grasping the whole thing and how
does one do do that if that makes sense so the relationship
between Equanimity and and faith and not grasping yes yes yes
of course right this is what we all want absolutely loving-kindness practice
this is like something that we can start we can practice with this is something we can do and it does it does make a
difference I am not saying it's always easy and I'm not saying it's fast but this is something that can really
make a difference and then next week I'll talk about some more what we might say wisdom practices but this is I'm
calling it like a heart practice and I cannot emphasize this enough this
idea of doing loving kindness practice where it's easy to really spend time there because what's really often
what's common is for people like we'll do a little bit of loving kindness may
you be happy may you be safe might you be healthy may you live at ease and then they want to do it to the person that
they bothers them the most of course they do and it doesn't work so well
I'll just say here's because you know we can't just switch like this
here's the best way it works is to stay to a living kindness where it's easy
cats dogs babies even imaginary beings and allow oneself to be filled up and
just keep practicing this could be one day one month one year I know some people have done this years
and then what starts to happen is the loving kindness just starts to kind of like overflow naturally
if you practice it instead of it being like a tool that I got to fix this problem instead if you use it as a way
to kind of just roll around in it swim in this loving kindness breathe it it
just starts to you get filled up and then it just automatically flows out and then it automatically just starts to
touch all your relationships including the difficult people and that are making our lives miserable and then that just
starts to kind of shift that relationship is that helpful very much so thank you thank you
foreign
I can just talk um I just I don't have a question but I just wanted to say I love chanting and I
have downloaded the loving kindness meta Sutra on my phone and it's three minutes
long and sometimes I'll use it to fall asleep by and then I also when I go
hiking over at Edgewood Park on the bench I'll play it and sing it at the same time
the Edgewood too so that's fantastic fantastic yeah and you know
um I'll say that uh learning it enchanting
it really helps with concentration I'm kind of like calming and like collecting the heart and the mind too in a way that
this can be really supportive thank you for sharing that it's very nice
we have time for another comment or question
hi thank you so much um you were when you were speaking about the Equanimity and saying
we don't necessarily we can't grasp the larger picture
um I would say that Equanimity is about seeing the bigger picture thank you
seeing the bigger picture um and so
I'm a little confused by that just in the sense of in we don't we don't know
what part this plays in the larger scheme of
things or yeah this is that because you were talking about the things that came
before also and I was confused about like yeah yeah what preceded this
episode seems different than my understanding of like oh we don't see
the whole piece thank you thank you yeah this is a um I didn't really talk about that very
much and so thank you for kind of pointing out that this could be um expanded a little bit so what does it
mean to like see the bigger picture and I talked a little bit about like saying what's preceded it but also another way
to think about it and this might be related a little bit to loving kindness or these types of things is that when
we're having a difficulty or something that we really like then we're completely enamored with
there's a way in which our kind of like awareness or I'll just use that word awareness just
kind of collapses around it and that's all we can see like you know when there's a pain in the knee it just feels
like that's the only thing just the pain in the knee so another way to understand seeing the
bigger picture is to recognize yes maybe there's that pain in the knee but there's also this neutral sensation of
pressure against the body of what I'm sitting on and there's this kind of neutral sensation of sounds or seen
light or so I've seen the bigger picture sometimes it's just seen that there's other things happening at the same time
not in addition to seeing what was preceded at so there's like a number of
different ways we could understand this idea of the bigger picture is that helpful yes
okay okay so uh that's nine o'clock and it's a pleasure to practice with you all
and may you find some balance some steadiness some equanimity
and or a little bit of this loving-kindness thing that I've been pointing to
and the rest of your evening today or tonight and always so thank you