so welcome welcome it's nice to be here practice together
so tonight i'd like to uh i'm going to start with this a little bit of a story that just
recently i had this pain in my arm
and it would bother me when i just did certain movements not other movements
but just particular ones i had no idea how this happened
i don't have any memory of doing anything in particular and it's kind of persistent and
i noticed that of course i just stopped doing certain movements because it was painful right kind of the
and then slowly it got resolved it resolved itself so it's a little bit of
a mystery but what's the interesting part is for me
it's interesting is that i didn't notice immediately when it went away
like often we don't notice but then my uh i did something that and i had
this memory like oh yeah i couldn't do this movement and at that moment when i
remembered oh yeah this used to hurt it doesn't hurt anymore there's this little bit of delight
like ah wow that's great you know kind of recognizing the stories
i had made about like why don't i know what this is and what should i do about it you're like there's all these stories
that accompanied this uh discomfort this little pain that i was
having and i didn't notice when i did when i didn't notice it
it just you know went on and like things were back to normal quote unquote
but when i did notice this sense of uplift this sense of delight
this little bit of happiness and so
it just reminded me that actually this fleeting flickering
sense of uplift or delight is a part of our experience
but we often kind of ignore it or dismiss it because it's
small or it's just maybe it just affirms how we think
things should be or something like this but this can be a support for our
practice this recognition of when something that's been troubling or difficult has
gone away and that little bit of sense of relief when it's gone away
can be a support and the buddha talked about this he uh
there's even a little bit of a a simile about this or a story about this and he
says suppose a person were sick suffering and gravely ill
they'd lose their appetite and get physically weak
i think back then you know thousands of years ago medicine was a lot about just food and you know what you did and
didn't eat you know and whether you were healthy or not is whether you had an appetite or not right
we can imagine right that a couple of thousand years ago their idea of medicine is different than what we have
now so suppose a person were sick suffering
and gravely ill they'd lose their appetite and get physically weak
but after some time they'd recover from that illness and
regain their appetite and their strength and thinking about this
they'd be filled with joy and happiness
so thinking remembering bringing to mind oh yeah
i used to be really sick i'm not so sick right now and just that feeling of
i'm using the word delight but maybe it's gladness or something like this happiness joy
these types of words and so and the buddha talked about this
experience of how it feels when difficulties end and a few colorful stories few colorful
little vignettes i'd like to share a few of them for me i kind of like to hear
it kind of like makes it a little more juicy and come alive to hear these uh
like this being painted a little bit more evocative with some of the language here
so the buddha says suppose a person who has gotten into
debt and then were to apply themselves to work and their efforts proved successful
they would pay off their original loan and have enough left over to support their family
thinking about this they'd be filled with joy and happiness so this feeling of debt and getting out
of debt and even having to be able to support others filled with joy and happiness
suppose a person were imprisoned in a jail
but after some time they were released from jail safe and sound with no loss of wealth
so maybe they didn't get fined so much or maybe people didn't steal everything while they were in jail but
they would become they would be released from jail safe and sound with no loss of wealth and
thinking about this they'd be filled with joy and happiness
suppose a person were a bond servant they belong to someone else or unable to
go where they wished but after some time they'd be freed from
servitude and become their own master an emancipated individual able to go
wherever they wished thinking about this they'd be filled with joy and happiness
are there's are there times in which we feel like we're the slaves to
i don't know just sometimes these social media companies that set it up to you know just click one more thing or
do we feel like we're a slave to fashion or what are these you know all these types of things right
that kind of we get pushed around a little bit but then to notice when we're not pushed
around the ease that's available
suppose that we're a person with wealth and property who was traveling along a desert road
but after some time they crossed over the desert safe and sound with no loss
of wealth thinking about this they'd be filled with joy and happiness
sometimes we might have this idea right that there's a it feels really barren and
a lot of support or things that might be nourishing and we
have to traverse this area on this journey
so the buddha is listing all these occasions or these imaginations or these stories
in which a person is experiencing difficulties
and they all get kind of expressed as you know not being able to
go where you want to go or do what you want to do or kind of this oppression or constriction or
bondage or tightness of some sort and then when that difficulties
resolve they experience joy and happiness
so some of you might have recognized those stories those are the similes
that are used for the hindrances to describe the hindrances
that is these five energies these five habits these five
patterns that are part of human experience
part of everybody's human experience when they arise it is not a failing
it's not something we're doing wrong it's just what it means to be a human is to have some of these five patterns
the first one is sensual desire but like clinging to sensual desire grasping
craving for sensual desire this idea that i'm not going to be happy
until i have that double caramel triple chocolate
ice cream or you know whatever it is
and it's surprising right how often we're kind of pushed around by just wanting the next pleasant experience
of course we are i mean again this is another human thing right we don't want to be uncomfortable but
we live in a time in which advertising is just always trying to promise there's
going to be this next pleasant experience that's going to be so great just the next one's going to be really
great so this often is experienced as kind of like a leaning forward and i want more
give me more that's the first hindrance the second one is ill will or aversion
the flip side of wanting more is not wanting it at all
this turning away i don't want this get this away from me everything would be fine if
only this weren't here you know that kind of a habit or way to meet our experience
and to be sure sometimes this leaning into or averting away from these are natural
human things the and aren't necessarily a hindrance sometimes there can be wise and
appropriate but there's a it's a hindrance when it starts to turn into
well everything would just be fine if only this thing worked here and then i got to figure out how to do this and i
can't do that because of this but maybe if i move this over here then i can do that and then you know this kind of
i don't know in this business the story making that surrounds
the entrances here
so a third one is sloth intorper this kind of this fogginess this lethargy uh dullness
lack of brightness lack of energy lack of a certain vitality
it's also the fourth one restlessness and remorse
idea there's too much energy in this agitation and either in the body this feeling just
can't sit still fidgeting a lot or where the mind can't settle down
it's like maybe going over and over and over something rehearsing or
remembering or just being agitated in general
that's the fourth and the fifth is doubt skeptical doubt the type of doubt
that kind of like you have this feeling like well okay maybe i should do this no well okay no actually i should do
this well maybe i shouldn't do that because i have to do this first so then maybe i'll
do this other thing sometimes shows up in our practices
okay i'm gonna do mindfulness well maybe i should do some loving
kindness practice open up the heart a little bit
well okay yeah maybe mindfulness is better yeah but that person said concentration
is good then i'm gonna do concentration practice so this kind of not really settling down
so tonight i'd like to talk a little bit about this relationship between the
hindrances and joy happiness well-being
delight we could say obviously like okay well
the hindrances are like the opposite of uh happiness but
i'd like us to look at this a little more closely maybe that's not necessarily the case
that it's the opposite so there's of course a sense of well-being arises when we notice
that a hindrance has ended often we don't notice
but it works the other way also that cultivating a sense of well-being
and a really broad definition of that word that expression
can help us even while we're in the midst of hindrances can help us
have the find more ease with the entrances
and this isn't the usual way in which we kind of talk about the hindrances often we talk about okay if the
hindrance is this then you can do this specific thing
if there's sloth interpret tiredness you can open your eyes like is a typical example but i'd like to look at this a
little bit differently than the way that we often do
so as i was saying that something that all these entrances have
in common the sense of restriction
either like you it's there isn't the freedom to
experience or be open to whatever is going to be next and experience instead there's a sense of stuck
and a sense of being mired in our experience
and so in those five little vignettes often not often always there's one vignette
that's tied to a particular hindrance but sometimes i think it's maybe we don't
have to know exactly which one of those vignettes ties to exactly which hindrance
because there it might be just uh all of them might feel like a prison or
all of them might feel like you're going across this desert with no
and you're so thirsty and there's no water for you or something like this
so they all have this quality of this binding this
uncomfortableness and maybe just for final add a little
bit with the commentaries kind of add a little bit extra to the these vignettes and
for example says there is a person who has incurred
a debt but is unable to pay now if they're creditors
when telling the person to pay back the debt speaks roughly and harasses and
beats them the person in debt is unable to retaliate but has to bear it
like how many times have we seen this in the movies where you know somebody does a deal with a loan shark and then
the people come back and beat them up and the person they just have to run away they can't stand up for themselves
or and say no stop it you shouldn't be doing this
so there's a way in which there can feel like
we're being pushed around but the absence of the hindrances have
this quality of release this quality of freedom
and it may be really subtle it doesn't mean it's not there
doesn't mean it's not significant and doesn't mean it can't support our practice
to notice this feeling of release or freedom from the hindrances
and the commentaries add just as one who has freed themselves of
debt no longer feels fear or anxiety
when meeting their former creditors so that's kind of the describing of the
freedom is no longer having anxiety just this uncomfortable feeling
when the creditors show up
so i talked about how the hindrances are part of just the human experience
but maybe even not only that that if we're going to have a meditation practice
it's really a hindrance practice because the hindrances show up unless you're in
the jhanas all the time you're in some absorptive concentration state from the moment you sit down until
the moment you stand up the hindrances are going to be there so
those work together kind of like a meditation practice and working with the hindrances
and we can work with the hindrances by focusing on this part about the well-being the ease the joy and the
happiness so to kind of like demonstrate this i'll
talk a little bit about the first hindrance and i'm using the word first and second
just because there are typically you know a list this might not be the first one that arises of course
so oftentimes this craving for sensual pleasure when it shows up
in the context of our meditation practice and the context of our life
if we don't actually call it as craving for sench pleasure instead we
use this word i need i need this thing now i really need it
and right now these days you just go amazon.com click click click and there
you go right you get you can have like so many things right so there's this way and there's kind of
this reinforcement whatever you feel like you need you can get if you have the means and you're so disposed to
do that this also kind of might fall into i need to take care of myself this way
i deserve it or you know whatever it might be
so what is there a way in which we can work with this sense of i need this and you
know within our relationship with the essential desires one that's not supportive that we
feel it's kind of pushing us around a little bit
one just recognize its present just turn towards like oh
yeah oh my thinking about what i'm gonna fix for dinner
is about sense desire and sometimes that can be really helpful just to name it
and that can take a little bit of the momentum out from behind it
sometimes just seeing it for what it is recognizing it
maybe that can soften it it's not always sufficient though to
make it go away and then next to do some investigation and inquiry
how does it feel like really feel to be having this experience
of wanting this experience of desire
and sometimes it can feel pleasant right in the beginning there's this vitality that shows up like yeah okay i want this
but then if we stick with this idea of feeling and investigating and
feel into it and we see that it's actually not a happy
state it's based on this idea of lack this idea of lack
or insufficiency or inadequacy or uncomfortableness or something like that
and so it actually is uncomfortable
but often we don't stick around or really pay attention to it so that we noticed
uncomfortableness we just go from one desire try to satisfy it then the next one try to satisfy it next one try
to satisfy it and our whole life ends up being this way let alone our meditation
periods so
there might be a it might be a subtle but often there is this contraction or
close closedness or maybe like this feeling of being in
servitude or being in debt like not quite free this kind of maybe oppressed
feeling and then when we feel recognize that
as best we can not to get um have aversion towards that
and this isn't necessarily our first impulse but can we
then turn towards any okayness what's happening
sometimes when there is some difficulty like in the previous instructions to tune into
or turn to the uncomfortableness there's a way in which our
awareness can kind of collapse around that switch uncomfortable
another way to say this is that which is uncomfortable just looms so large and kind of consumes our awareness
but instead can we maybe broaden our awareness
the uncomfortableness is still there but notice is there anything else that's
okay neutral or even pleasant
and this often takes a little bit of energy to kind of like open up
from this collapse kind of way in which we are with the difficulty but to open up
might be some neutral experiences in the body feet on the ground pressure of the cushion against the body
there might be a way in which we could pay attention to the breath and allow the breath to be really
soothing as comfortable as possible
maybe there's a way we could just relax the body notice oh is there any tension in the shoulders
maybe i can look at my posture and tuck my chin just a little bit make some space at the back
of my neck and that often kind of brings a little bit more ease in the posture
so to orient towards something that's neutral or even okay or comfortable
both in the body and in the mind
maybe one or the other might be more evident and so this does a few things one is it
interrupts this momentum of wanting this maybe doesn't make it go away but it
takes some of the momentum away from it
and it also reminds us that there's more than just this
particular experience that we're having there's a multitude of experiences
because this entrance in particular but many of them it can be like a
like in the buddhist tradition we have this uh story of the hungry ghosts that these
beings that are never satisfied right so they have this big belly and really small
throats so that doesn't they just can never get enough
nourishment they could just never get enough so in some ways it can feel like
that but if we are
locked into this idea that some sense experience is really going to be
satisfying it's gonna take care of that discomfort
then what we're actually doing is feeding the hungry ghost
mindset like oh i need to get one more sense experience one more sense experience one
more sense experience and i'm encouraging us is there a way in which
we can look at something else that's not just another sense experience
that brings a little bit of okayness maybe even a little
delight or gladness relaxation in the body
letting the breath be pleasurable the way that we breathe tune into the rhythm of the breath
and then we could ask ourselves what is really
lacking in this moment like really
i'm sure we don't have the double decker chocolate thing but
this moment this this moment not just the past one and not the next one but this moment what's really lacking
and to tune into that that kind of also disrupts this idea of
this hungry ghost that gets created that can't ever be satisfied
but instead there's a little bit of a contentment
and again this might be really subtle it doesn't mean it's not there
for the sense of yeah okay okay i'm still breathing
this moment i'm still here and whatever sense of okayness
neutral is there and so learning to have this kind of a
wholesome kind of nourishment pleasure i'll say
is very powerful this can be transformative
not necessarily easy to train ourselves to look away from which is that is difficult because
right this is what humans do we have uh it's like the difficulties are a magnet and we just attracts our
attention and we can't let go of them and i don't know we just get a little bit
obsessed with them but if we can turn away a little bit
the hindrance the difficulty is still there we don't have to make it go away we don't have to solve it
but just notice what else is there that's neutral
and or even pleasant
and then we become kind of less infatuated with this idea that
something out there is going to make every make everything better
and instead we're cultivating something that is enormously powerful
this idea that's that we can [Music] be with our experiences and be present
in this moment this is allows us to be with something that's more fulfilling
more nourishing there's a more has a depth to it
and to train ourselves to do this takes time it's not something that we will do
immediately of course but it's really worth the time and the effort
because just like how the end of the entrances have some well-being joy and happiness
turning towards well-being helps to end the suffering it goes both ways
but we don't have to wait for the hindrances to go away completely
we can open up to what else is there and you may say
i don't know diana this sounds kind of odd really can we approach the entrances with us
and i'll say that there's uh lots of places in the sutas
where the hindrances are kind of like partnered with the same factors of awakening
the hindrances are what hinders gets in the way of freedom
awakening wisdom not to let alone you know getting
concentrated or seeing clearly or these types of things
so the hindrance is aptly named because they hinder that some factors of awakening are the ones
that support finding more freedom and ease support seeing clearly
support concentration and
one of the seven factors of awakening is joy and there's also concentration in there
so there's this way in which cultivating this joy and happiness
is part of the sem factor's awakening which is an antidote to that five entrances so that's kind of like a
buddhist list technical idea about this idea but or we could use the buddha's own
teachings to support this idea but i would just like to encourage that
to tune into to recognize that when there's a difficulty
and when it ends or subsides most of them do not all of them right
we do have aging this isn't going to end and some of us have illnesses that probably
aren't going to end right but notice that maybe when the severity
lessens or when there's difficulties when they end
there's a little bit of delight and use that as a reminder that we can cultivate delight
happiness well-being to help us with the difficulties and one
way to do that is to open up our experience and maybe loosen up the
the magnet the um i think rick hansen famously says right
so that uh they're like velcro the difficulties are like velcro we kind of get stuck to them
so can we loosen up that velcro a little bit and notice what else is here
so happiness and the hindrances one way that we can
work with these difficulties that arise in our life
so may you find plenty of opportunities to explore happiness and to experience it and allow
it to be a support for you and whatever difficulties are arising for you
and may that support us to also support others
so that we can be part of what makes this world
runs more smoothly or with more care with more warmth
thank you
you