so there's two things i want to talk about today and
two things i want to talk about because i want to talk about the relationship between them
and the first in simple language can be talking about freedom or liberation and that's kind of
many people understand that that's really central to this buddhist practice
but the one that is not mentioned very much is the idea of bow
kind of idea of a commitment and these two go together so
and but val has a very interesting kind of part of the unfolding of practice for
some people when people first come to practice they're interested
and the interest is what engages them and that interest might be driven by a
need so we will hope that somehow this practice will make a difference for the need the suffering that people have
as people practice at some point there becomes something in the family of commitment that happens
that people or decisiveness or clarity this is what i'm going to do i'm going to do
this meditate every day i'm going to give myself over make somebody a priority for my life and
exactly where that priority how strong that priority is how strong that commitment is or how big it is is very
individual but at some point it's like okay this is this is more than just an interest now
and for some people it becomes a life and then but at some point the commitment
changes to something else where it becomes uh something like a vow
and i'll talk more about what that means but the many religions have vows you know people who are ordained how to take
vows people get married have bows a vow is
something that is affirming an aspiration a wish that arises from
within that's not something we take from the outside and put on like a coat
but rather it's a recognition that now something is there's a call from the inside the recognition that now
there's something that is flowing animating us energizing us from the inside out
and the vow is the recognition that this is this is where i'd like to live this is my orientation this is my direction
and so and this points to how with practice that practice changes over time we change
over time with it with a freedom there's also a kind of a
correspondingly i list a three-part step that goes on the first is the beginning
a lot of the practice has to do with relaxing relaxing for some people is not
spiritual enough so we can call it calming maybe that helps
a settling a tranquilizing a calming of all the agitation the busyness of the mind the heart
calming and relaxing has a lot to do with healing healing that which is fragmented or
hurt or wounded inside of us and so um but there's a relaxing that
goes on as the relaxing deepens at some point
there's a letting go so there's a clarity that some things that we've been doing
are not something that we want to do anymore and there's a letting go that happens
and uh and that letting go is a choice at some point there's come to a point okay enough of this this stop doing this
i'll stop doing this and and then
but then with enough letting go there is release
and release is a whole different animal than letting go because release is not something you can
do but rather something we allow for so i want to talk about these two
different things so there's freedom side and this vowel side
so in the freedom side the letting go
sooner or later becomes very important some of the letting go just happens some people are surprised as they meditate
how much of their ordinary life and concern just settle away and recede into the background
and if that's done clearly enough strongly enough there's um people experience themselves being alive
in a very different way than they've ever done before many people or many you know maybe for
some people it's like oh i haven't felt that way since i was four or five
and that's one of the things that happened for me is that as i started sitting meditating more
i started feel having sense of well-being that i hadn't felt since i was a little
kid i said oh i know this i recognize this and um and so it's kind of a was kind of
a little bit of a homecoming it was a little bit like the busyness of life the
challenges of life the all the different preoccupations that i'd slowly acquired and built up and
made a whole you know complicated world for myself and to live
in it wasn't so dramatic it wasn't like i even knew i was doing it
but as i meditated and got and just simply kind of stayed with the breathing let go of my thoughts came to the
breathing set up quietly slowly these things receded
far enough away that i started to experience myself in a radically different way than i had
before and one of the consequences of that
is that when some of the things came back which they almost always did
the usual daily tendencies i had attachments i had the
selfishness i had the conceits i had the stories i had about myself and others
and all that they said to come back some of them just didn't seem to be so
important anymore or valuable or even healthy to have and there became a desire to let go of
them not live by them anymore and some of them i was able to put down
some of them i changed the way i lived so i wouldn't be caught in them as much as i had before because something the
very lifestyle that i was living supported certain attachments so i shifted my lifestyle so those
attachments wouldn't be so easily supported as this practice deepened then for me
then the it became not clear that the letting go
that sometimes happened on its own without me trying to do it was something that i could also
sometimes choose to do and so i learned to let go of certain things and some of the
things were things of the world which were not healthy to do but some of what i learned more and more
was it wasn't about the world and anything in the world it was really letting go of the clinging
the holding in the mind and that was a big revelation to realize
that that's where the real issue is to let go of how it was holding on
and the advantage of seeing that is then you don't have to let go of things in the world unless they're
unhealthy some people who are into this buddhist practice and letting go let go of things
that shouldn't be let go of but what we can do is rather than clinging to them
some things we can keep but we hold them with an open hand and the advantage of holding things with
kind of the equivalent of a open hand is that some things are worth keeping
appropriate to care for and have in our lives and there's no need to let go of them they're valuable
but uh reality sometimes has other ideas and sometimes
they go anyway and then if but if we're not holding on
tight it's a lot easier when things go
and so it wasn't your choice to have them go it wasn't because you wanted them to go maybe the opposite you didn't want them
to go but still with this life that we live sometimes they go
you know people die all kinds of things just happen
we don't know when the san andreas fault is going to blow here in california right
and if it goes there's a lot of changes coming about here in california
and i bet and uh and so things are things will go away
but the the freedom from clinging makes a huge difference how we navigate
that then and how we work with the changes in life so we learn to let go
but we come to a point in this practice that we do buddhist practice
where it's clear that we have to stop
doing the letting go because letting go still can still be
represent having control you're in charge i'm the one who's letting go
and that can only go so far because before we feel that it doesn't make sense to do that anymore it's actually not possible anymore
one of the places kind of like one of the places of holding on
is control and to
let go of control is to stay in control in a paradox so at some point you have
to so the letting go becomes at some point in practice it becomes letting be
allowing and this can feel like a very profound part of practice especially when
practice is quite subtle and strong that there's a there's a form of letting go that involves no letting go at all
but just letting it be it's kind of like stepping back and having a wide spacious perspective of
the situation of ourselves what's going on and learning how not to be troubled
irritated by what's happening even our clinging we let it be we allow it
because to constantly be involved in letting go of our clinging is to somehow be going in the wrong direction which
becomes clear as we go along it's kind of like
sanding rough wood you can you sand it with coarse
sandpaper first but then you have to stop using the coarse sandpaper to use finer and finer finer sandpaper
and at some point if you keep using sandpaper it doesn't work you have to just use a
cloth and so the same thing letting go letting go letting go
it can work for a period of time until it's no longer the right grain of sandpaper the right grain of
activity and at some point letting be allowing
and letting go of control then something
that only then can release happen release is very different than freedom
we can we can talk about uh fighting for our freedom asserting for freedom demanding our
freedom release you can't fight for release
for your own release you can't fight for the release of the heart release of the mind you can't uh lobby for it you can't
assert it it involves an allowing we let go enough
to be and allow for something that's not in our control
and this point where different people in practice come to this place of letting go of control at different points some
people really early they're struggling with this some people it's quite well advanced in
their practice but at some point the idea of the controlling is trying to
control so everything is safe controlling so that you know i get what i want controlling so that i
know certainty and trying to avoid uncertainty many things we're trying to avoid with control
avoid feeling our fear our distress we have to let go
and then that that makes room for something to happen that's not our doing
all we have done is put the conditions in place for it a deeper release
in that the deeper this letting go happens the deeper this release happens
uh it influences the other movement of practice which is i'm
referring to as interest commitment and vow
that as we practice there's interest in the beginning
and then somehow the practice begins to show that it works
something begins shifting and changing in us and for each person that shift and change is a little bit different it's
very personal but at some point we recognize oh i'm different because of this
and uh one way to some people to recognize this if they're if they're able to meditate
every day for some time maybe for a few years or even six months
to make it maybe more of a manageable goal and then stop for a week
stop for a month and then see how life is different because of that and some people say wow you know i
didn't realize how important meditation was because without it i tend to i'm not so
calm or i don't see so clearly i remember i was suggesting it to a long
time practitioner who done a lot of retreats and that he should stop meditating for a month
and he started crying it was so important for him and i think it was important that month
to really see what was going on in a deeper way and it wasn't necessarily seeing something difficult it was seeing
something very profound and important within himself that he hadn't quite understood
and so there's a shift that happens and so with that shift comes a
commitment maybe a commitment to let go of the things which are unhealthy that
we do a commitment to do the things that are healthy for us especially spiritually
healthy but then you know because that's you
know that commitment has more to the world of what we do where we have some control
as important as commitment is it can only take us so far
and at some point when the release is deep enough when the letting go is deep enough and we're in touch with something
very you know very much in touch very connected to what's happening here and
ourselves in the world there's a source for
an aspiration for a wish for a dedication for doing something
that is almost impersonal and that it doesn't belong to that part of the mind or the ego
where we kind of ration think things out or trying to improve the self or doing it
it's not it's not really about self anymore but it arises from some place that's it may be inside
that's not exactly personal it is personal in the sense that it's within us
but not in the usual way that we think about ourselves as there's some people talk about a
calling there's a calling there's i love the word aspiration because uh it's connected to the word
breathing like respiration so it's something deeper that wells up
there's something that begins flowing or rising or some feeling of this is what
is important this is what my life is about this is what i want to do
so for me when i was uh a zen practitioner in the monastery
i spent a year kind of living close to this junction
this place of the vow of this really what was most important for me what was the most meaningful thing i could do
with my life and trying to grapple with it and understand it and
i didn't do it continuously i did it um every five days more or less
because the monastery i had a five day week and the fifth day was the day off and then i would go for a hike in the
mountains most of those days and that's where i was kind of checking in and grappling
with this what i was going to do with my life and what was important for me and
and uh what arose was something that uh
surprised me in that it it it arose within
and it was like oh of course this is what i'll dedicate myself to
but the decision was made before my mind said that the decision happened in the heart
something shifted and changed and the decision was for me was to
dedicate my life a vow to work for the ending of suffering in this world
that's what that's what my system had come to there was nothing else that was more important
and the vow was not something that i took on
knew the vow was simply the expression of what was already happening to me
this movement this dedication and uh
and partly the idea of vow was it was came to me because at this at the zen practice the vows are very
important part of the tradition and uh and there they have something
called the bodhisattva vows which is uh goes something like this there's four of
them and so the vow to um
it says beings are innumerable
i vow to save them all liberate them all desires delusions are inexhaustible i
vow to end them all
dharma gates are boundless i vow to enter them all
buddha's way is unsurpassable i vow to become it
so it's like the impossible dreams or song maybe it's like you know
uh beings are numberless i vow to save them all it's ridiculous right i mean
who's going to do that i mean in some ways that could be seen as phenomenal egotistical
dedication like you know you're going to try to say well being you but you have some kind of
messianic complex that and um
but it's not it's it's uh the way where it was understood was that
in up two different ways one was uh there was a certain way in which the
you're going to keep coming back to a mind that's liberated and so we're freeing all beings in our
minds maybe freeing them from our attachments that was one understanding
the other understanding is that yes it is impossible to do this
but succeeding in this then is not the point what's the point is
this is what we're going to do this is the task
this is dedication this is the life that we're dedicated to without concern that you know we're not
going to get to that many people before we die and so the same thing with delusions our
delusions are inexhaustible it's very humbling to realize that to have this idea that someday you'll
come to the end of all your delusions is maybe a kind of a conceit or kind of
a problem but to always practice always be looking at the ways that we
have delusion and those of us paying attention to our society these days
will appreciate how many delusions we live in that were unconscious unconscious bias
that we live in our society and that you know we're coming beginning to kind of slowly get a handle of and
but maybe there's no end to understanding them and they're endless so but so the dedication yes
i'm going to keep looking keep discovering my delusions keep working and willingness to look at these
difficulties that's the task dharma gates means the dharma practices
dharma experiences dharma openings that we can have are endless
the point is not to come to the final one the point is just keep practicing just that's the dedication
and the buddha's way is unsurpassable i about to become it become the buddha kind of
well it's impossible but that's what my life is about so i don't know if this is satisfying to
hear but this idea that vow it doesn't is not about succeeding at
anything but the vow is that orientation the dedication of a lifetime the what's most
meaningful and some people find something very clear
and it can be wide-ranging you know it's for a buddhist teacher who made it commitment to this buddhist practice the
way i did it can sound like maybe like this is what everyone's supposed to do but no i mean it could be that there's
all kinds of ways of living a life many many ways some that are that
are kind of not so obvious or very subtle or very
personal in different shapes there's a room for all but the point being that as we practice
we might discover more and more what is most meaningful for us
because what is less meaningful or unmeaning not meaningful begins to be shed begins to settle out begins to
recede and when our distracted mind when our preoccupied
mind when our fear and our ambitions and desires get quiet tranquil settled
what is left in there what is left here what is left as being the most
meaningful the most important for us that we want to live by that we want to
that's we want to do i have his faith that this practice we do as much as involves a settling and
letting go a connection showing up here in a very full way
it does not lead people to be couch potatoes that's not the point
uh just to end up just being someone who can now happily peacefully
you know has no desires no wishes and just you know okay i guess sit here on the couch and just
smile and breathe i think that is not possible i think that as we connect and drop in deeper
and deeper and deeper to what's here the heart
is set up the heart has been created for in ways that uh very different than you
probably would have imagined if you're caught up in the social constructs and values that
we inherit from our society and our families and to discover what that is in your
heart what is most meaningful what is the most animating what brings you alive what is
it that gives your life the most meaning that is enduring that really really
makes you helps you sing or help something really come forth
and so that i call that the vow the vow that we can live by to devote
what we're devoted to or dedicated to and for some people it involves making choices between
different things that are good things to do i had to make that choice for myself
because i was dedicated my my youth to go back to graduate school
to work on the issue of soil conservation in this world of ours
i had studied agriculture and soil science and i knew that toward the hue one of the huge challenges of our
world was the amount of soils that were being devastated eroded
and we needed to do something about and not too many people knew about this huge issue
and so that was what direction i was going and that's still a very worthwhile thing
to do so i had to choose between this buddhist path at some point and doing that
and i chose the buddhist one so that wasn't that was part of what i was doing that year reflection what's most
important here and then the advantage of having a vow
or even her commitment and dedication is that
you wake up in the morning and you know what you're doing you know what you're about
you it's a there's a clarity in this world that's very very hard to know what to do sometimes and sometimes it's hard
to know what's meaningful and what's important it's hard to know what to choose to do
when there's a vow it's like oh this is what i'm about this is what i do this is what i'm dedicated to
it's a ballast it's a foundation
it's a teacher when it's difficult to live by the vow then you have to look at it more deeply
it's a it's a protection it's an inspiration it's a
it's a guide for a life
a purpose and uh so to live the vow
and so the question is you know what is that for you what might it be for you
some of you might not be ready for that question in the way that i'm i'm talking about about today
where val has to do you know it really comes at the end of a series of practice
and really developing but at some point you might come to the place it might be
a very natural stage that you come to it's not like you have to rush ahead now because i talked about it
but you'll just feel and sense inside of you that something is moving you something
is becoming so important for you that something is going to shift
some choice decisions can be made some dedication
and that some of that is not a choice some of it is not you controlling the situation
but you're allowing something that maybe is a surprise to you
to surface and call you or speak to you or animate you
and you might have to make something you might if you want to listen to that it might call on you to
make make big choices that decisions
what you let go of what you stop doing and what you change and do differently
and and i think that that becomes for some people an important stage and so you
know what's important to keep in mind is the more deeply we go into this practice
that um it's not just you're doing a practice that helps us to cope
manage more effectively with the life that we're living but really that helps us to question the
life we're living in a deep way and i probably most of you would consider that would be
if it's not useful for you that if you look across the country across the world and how many people live their lives
probably you wish a lot of people would question in some deep way what they're doing and
how they're doing it and why they're doing it you know there's a fair number of things
which are dysfunctional going on around us but it's also probably true for
ourselves in some way that we start questioning and what is the calling what is the new way
of living that really has meaning and purpose and is right here
the um so i think this practice is uh that we
do is not only stress reduction it's also something that sooner or later hopefully will challenge
you in some very deep way and uh and that you're willing to be
challenged by it because you're not being challenged by the something external the challenge really coming from the
inside out it's coming from yourself some better part of you is beginning to
to flower come forth and uh
and at that point maybe it's not a matter of bringing your practice into your life
but rather bring your life into your practice
rather than finding a way to live your life as it is it's a way rather to live your life
from this place that's uh has been freed
released through this practice
so release and vow
so we have a few minutes some of you would like to ask questions clarifications
concerns you have about what i've talked about or how this
what i've said how this sits with you is it difficult to hear is it inspiring or
nice so over here i think
see if that's okay yeah
um so gil um the wow is a wonderful topic in sanskrit
it's called rata it's called in sanskrit
yeah yeah and i'm using actually the word aditana
in pali adishtana may be inside so i'd like to draw an analogy with the
yoga philosophy where the first of the eight limbs in the patanjali's
sutras are the yamas the it's ahimsa satya non-violence truth and
all these things brahmacharya so patanjali calls them the mahavratam
sarva-bhama mahavratam which means irrespective of place time
everything it is universally valid and
there is a fact called shraddha it is faith but faith from a very
deep source which makes people take these walls
and the power of this is enormous in this in mahabharata there is a
character called bhishma he's known as the one who made the terrible wall of
celibacy and the powers he gained are so much that he
could give up his life when he chooses to that is the power of these
mahavratas so i just wanted to bring their vows of power yeah great thank you ganesh
talking about what goes on in these early indian texts i mean it's so common in so many
different religions that people come to a place where they already do something like a vow and it's kind of interesting to reflect
on how this is a common phenomenon religions religious practice at least if we
distinguish religion from the practices and uh so it certainly is
worth reflecting on and considering and understanding a little bit about
what it what it points to in the heart what it points to in our kind of in our nature that
that people go in this direction
yes for me
this path has not involved so much of a
a commitment or a vow but rather a knowing
so i can tell that oh yes you know this buddhist
these teachings are are great and they mean a lot to me
i think they're very beautiful and they've made all the difference in the world in my life
so just knowing that has been yeah a great thing it's a great thing yeah so i would have but yes but
my discipline the what but and yet there's something resistant to turn it up a little louder
please there's something sort of resistant or stubborn in me so that my discipline
when it comes to practice has been poor ah so
maybe i do need a little bit of that vow or commitment
quality that i have been missing so this has been perhaps wonderful yeah
i can imagine that yeah the knowing is one thing and deciding to live accordingly by that
knowing is a different thing and so maybe commitment intention vowing would be important for you to
look at yes it could be and uh and ideally at least
the way i i understand these things is in looking at it
it doesn't become an act of brute force to okay now i'm going to do it for
but rather you recognize that that there's a animating force within
that it's like of course i'll do it now i'm going to write i'm going to ride this wave of intention of commitment of
our thank you thank you
thank you so much girl um you helped me understand something about
futility um with your dharma talk today and and i was just think futility or utility
futility okay but turning it actually into utility and and the image i had
was of the cellist on the titanic actually and your notion of
well you know is it kind of crazy to go and try something that's obviously sort of futile right you know you're a
sinking ship and we often use that as an analogy of well that's something useless right why would you
go you're gonna you're gonna drown but in some sense what else would you do if you were a cellist
you know in the titanic you might as well go play and those last moments are your way of
organizing a little bit of the universe that in every other sense is quite chaotic
and even hostile so i'm no longer going to use that as a as a notion of futility but rather
it is a little bit of a way of organizing your hostile world and so anyway i don't know
if that's useful or not but at least to me that's the it helped me really sort of rethink what
we often think of as just you know futile attempts at
at calming anyway wonderful i think what you're saying is actually quite important
that um the
some of the ways in which we respond to crisis are not such useful actually
it might seem essential to panic it might seem essential to get
angry and and bark at someone and that's like it's not what people do it has to happen this
way but if if it's your last day alive
is that really the best thing you can do with your time is to be afraid or to bark at someone
isn't there a better alternative if you have a few hours left then isn't this the time to really do
something really different in your life than the usual anger and desire and fear and
isn't that a time to kind of play the jello or smile at your neighbor or do do what you
enjoy or you know or put your mind and heart at ease
because now you don't have to you don't have to prove yourself anymore you don't have to accomplish anything and
so you know one of the questions for us practitioners is
what's the best option that's available for us and i think there's a lot of better
options available for us than some of the ones we choose and so choosing to play the cello might be the
best option for that person given the alternatives that were available
and and so what's our best option
and it's exercise of thinking well this my this is at my last afternoon alive
what really is the best option if you then you can reflect well
actually maybe i have a few years maybe that's still the best option
and and so this call this being connected to something deep inside to have released let go in a deep way and
really touch something that's really meaningful is to touch a higher quality of living a
higher quality of mind and heart that then it becomes less and less interesting
to succumb to other forces where we lose something that's so meaningful and so important
so that's i appreciate your your idea that what might seem futile
it sometimes has a lot of utility and it could be very inspiring to see
i've i've been with a lot of people as they're dying and it's
it's strikes me how much how much of an influence it has on the people who are there their their friends
their family who survive how people die and that some people die it's a
beautiful to watch their peace they're letting go and their equanimity
it's like inspiring it's like people go there for darshan people go show up and want to be with them because they haven't experienced so much peace in
someone's and other people die afraid and anxious and all kinds of things
so this ability to this practice to discover the better option the better alternative and really know it for
oneself and then choose choose to live by it
is uh this vowel okay so maybe maybe one more and then
we'll stop and then what we'll do is uh we can continue in uh afterwards in the
in the parking lot we can take off our masks we can make some chairs out there and see if any of you would like to stay and be more informal out there we can
continue yes gail thank you for this i'm sitting thinking about um
the dichotomy between advocating for myself in situations where
i see or experience unfairness or
not being you know i just experienced
a week ago a situation on the medical area where i felt that
i was i had to really push for advocating for what was right for me right
and um but i also recognize where
you know that that was very much about survival a sense of survival or sense of
ego or sense of just wanting to have to survive and
there's a lot of there's a lot of continuum with that there's times where
it's probably egoic to but but how to how to kind of like navigate through
that sense of advocating for what you feels right for you know
versus allowing things to let go yeah it's a good it's a very good
question because some things i said like earlier you shouldn't let go of some things need to happen and so
being an advocate and holding your ground and saying no or insisting or staying present
and it's not it's not a spectrum it's not like they're just a range it's more like these things can co-exist
it's possible that part of our motivation is is a clear wise intention to care for our
well-being so we can care for our family or something and some of it is that
pure egotism both can coexist and uh
and then it's really a pity for us to you know if there's if part of
it is a good intention and part of it is unhealthy to sacrifice
the good intention give it up because there's some bad and bad you know intentions as part of it so we
have to weigh these things and the impact on them and the harm we might cause or the benefit might cause it's a
it's a complicated world what you're bringing up i don't have a simple answer for you except one
and the simple answer is um uh learn how to be really mindful of
yourself so you can track all the different component parts of what's going on for you
and recognize the tension the stress the clinging the
contractions that are unnecessary and generally
the physical tension the stress that builds up in the system
you can bet generally take that as being unnecessary
and whatever is driving you that causes that stress
that probably is not useful to have but if you can be motivated and
activated engaged in a strong way without that tension or that contraction
that brings you suffering go for it if it's the right thing and my hope this practice actually makes
us more courageous more willing to kind of stand up and
fight for a good cause not less but to do so at ease to do so with peace
okay great so thank you all very much for being here so those who would like to stay for
a while and chat more there's folding chairs in the cabinet just outside in the other hall there
and uh grab one and bring it out to the parking lot and we'll sit in a circle there and we can take off our masks
there when we get there and and then
thank you so much