so good evening and what i'd like to talk about
is one of the foundational teachings in our in trouble hearing
you will turn it up a little bit louder so let's see now is that going to be loud enough we also have hearings
hearing assistant devices that might help so good now okay
so um i'd like to talk about one of the foundational
you can call it teachings of our inside tradition
but i want to teach about one of the fundamental
set of qualities that we activate when we do mindfulness practice
there are qualities that get activated in anything we do in our lives they just that
many things get activated but these are kind of universal in some way and so they're useful both for our
practice that we do meditation or mindfulness in life and they're also useful for any activity
that we do to try to figure out a wiser way or a more satisfying way
to do it to engage in them and these are five uh kind of inner
gets activated it comes alive and they come alive in different proportions
different levels of proportions to each other and depending on how they come into
balance and what is strong and what is weak they can affect how we do things or how we engage in what we do in our life
and and how the meditation unfolds so these are five qualities that are
quite useful i think to memorize for yourself learn what they are and then have them as a reference point
so that after what at first it might feel like somewhat artificial to memorize this and think about them
but over time it becomes kind of second nature to do it it's kind of like riding a bicycle if
you first time you ride a bicycle as a kid perhaps it um
it's awkward and you know so many things to take care of you know you have to handle bars in one way and the pedal at
the same time keep your balance and and figure out where the brakes are and
you know it's a lot to figure out but after you do it a few times
at some point maybe it's really second nature to do it and all the little things that
seem so complicated at first to begin working together in harmony and at some point you take your hands
off the handlebar and say hey look you know hands-free pedaling because you have everything lined up
just right in the speed and everything so these five qualities then that we
want to learn and and make them second nature is tracking them is the what's called the five faculties
it's five and they are faith
and there's other english words to use for that engagement the effort we put into the
what we're doing attention or mindfulness itself
concentration the real ability to really focus on what we're aware of
and then uh insight or discernment the ability to be wise about what we see
and what our experience is to be discerning about the experience
so you know i think that if you ride a bicycle for example if you if you know
how to ride a bike and you're going to ride a bicycle from here to monterey
you would without even thinking about it these five faculties would come into play for you
you first you'd you probably wouldn't take that trip that far unless you had some faith that you can do it some
confidence you can do it and that confidence is probably necessary because if you don't have the
confidence the doubting of uh
your ability to get down there is probably going to undermine you and sometimes doubt becomes a
self-fulfilling prophecy i can't do it it's too hard and the very that very mindset
it drains us and interferes with us and it sometimes becomes true almost
because of that mindset but there has to be some confidence
and maybe the confidence is not very strong at first but then after you've gone 20 miles or
so far oh i can do this so you make it up over the santa cruz mountains
down to their side and then you have a lot of confidence then it's like okay now i think i can do it and then it's a
whole different feeling to go biking if you're if you're confident and then you have to engage
and you have to figure out how to engage depending on the slope and the terrain
that you're in you see the hill coming up in front of you and you realize okay i need to kind of
maybe pedal a bit harder now and get some momentum going up the hill or
i need to slow down because i have to kind of catch my breath to really be ready for going up that hill
and you get to the top of the hill and you coast down still downhill then you don't need to apply any effort
anymore and then you naturally know okay now all i have to do is use gravity and not coast down just make
sure i don't go too fast so you kind of are moderating and monitoring your energy levels as you go
and then you got to be mindful when you're biking like this there's a lot of traffic and cars and dangers on the road
and potholes and the dogs come running out and whatever goes on
and you can't really slip up in fact some people are probably have a higher level of
mindfulness spiking a trip like that than they do when they meditate because the consequences are so serious
if you don't pay attention and the feedback is very quick
and like i did when i was 14 and i was biking along and i was just
minding my own business until i ran smack into the back of a parked car with people inside the car
i wasn't paying attention to what i was doing just biking along look i don't know where i was looking at boom
and um so there has to be some mindfulness some attention
and then uh sometimes you're biking you need to stay focused really focused not just mindful but focusedly mindful
sometimes you really need to pay attention carefully to with the terrain the potholes and the
bumps and the rocks and sometimes you have to stay focused on the traffic and what's going on and you have to really kind of zero in
on what you're doing and how you're doing it and it kind of very kind of sometimes detailed focused concentrated
way if there's a lot of traffic that's going on you have to really navigate it carefully
you're probably not going to think about how you you know what was that problem i had on my taxes in april
you know you're probably not going to think about you know what am i going to have for dinner today or so whatever it is that those things fall
away because of the need to stay focused here and then sometimes you get up in a wide
open road where there's no cars and now it feels very relaxed and
and there you might let your mind roam a little bit and then you're not so focused
and then you have to have a lot of discernment when you're by ride the bike you have to kind of know i'll make all kinds of micro decisions
as you go along about exactly where the tires go in the road and
how fast and slow you go and where you fit on the road and when to slow down and when to go to speed up and there's a
lot of little decisions made some of them which are about sustaining your effort for the long trip
using and not exhausting yourself but to going you know figuring out how to go in a slow and steady space
pace so you get to the at the end on a long trip so so this is to suggest that this comes
into play in something as mundane as riding a bicycle you can do the exercise of almost
anything you do if you decide to make bread or cook something at home in the kitchen
those five in some degree come into play they come into play when we meditate
and so to be able to recognize them their presence in us when we meditate
allows us to make to be discerning and to adjust and and
adjust what's happening to create the conditions that are optimal for us to for the mind to be able to stay present
and grounded here and now and not wondering awful lot so confidence there needs to be faith in
what we're doing there confidence in our ability to do it and that's the the faith that paying
attention to the present moment is valuable it's not automatic as many people
discover when they sit down to meditate when they realize their mind has all kinds of other things in mind to do
and there is a certain compulsion to think all kinds of thoughts to be preoccupied with all kinds of
emotions and feelings and the pull into that world is so strong
that sometimes people never knew that that was the case when they just went about their ordinary life it's only when doing something like
meditation we try to try to not be lost in thought and preoccupation we can realize the
strength of it and i think it's probably fair to say that it represents that
something not you consciously but something in your system has a lot of faith
in reviewing the past and planning the future faith and the value of going off into
fantasies of all kinds have a lot of faith in churning resentments and bitterness
a lot of faith in kind of churning and staying kind of connected and kind of feeding anxiety
we wouldn't normally think we have faith in those but if an anthropologist from mars came
and studied human beings and they were able to kind of see what goes on in their minds they say wow these people worship
anxiety you know wow you know there's there's no requirement to be anxious all
the time but they just like love it they must have they just have this wonderful thing about anxiety and it's amazing
there's those people here but there's also those people who have a lot of anger and they must have like
you know and they have this altar you know they have this monitor that's like the altar
for anger they listen to politicians you know that they're
they really believe in its value and what we're doing in buddhist practice is as we do it over time
our value system begins to shift and our value of system tends to shift
to being more ethical more honest more kind more compassionate
and more not because we have to but because we start feeling and recognizing within us
that these things are just feel better these things feel right these feel less
stressful they feel more productive of having a good heart and so it just kind of becomes of a
natural thing over time the meditators tend to become more ethical their values change
but that change of value represents a change of where our faith is faith of where our trust or confidence
is at some point we start getting more and more confident in the value of being
present being attentive to what's happening in the present moment
it's not obvious to a lot of people it wasn't to me when my mother told me repeatedly growing up guilt pay
attention i mean i became a meditation teacher because partly of the karma of not listening to my mother
and you know i didn't hardly knew what she was talking about or was i certainly wasn't interested in her her
instructions to me as i walked mud across the carpet or something
and um so the so to begin valuing
the beauty the wonder the richness
of heightened sense of attentiveness to what's happening here and now
it becomes so marvelous this confidence in attention
that it becomes more wondrous more valuable to feel connected to awareness
than it is to anything that awareness knows
so if i you know if i look at the bell i can get preoccupied with a bell and think about it and all kinds of things
but it's actually quite wondrous that i have the ability to see the bell
to understand this is about to recognize and the very fact of being conscious is
a miracle it's amazing that we should you know end up in a universe where
we're the recipients of this very rich capacity for consciousness and it's important to have to value
staying in this close connected to present moment consciousness because of how rich and wonderful and
what emerges from that world so over time having confidence in the
practice like this is valuable to do so when you sit down to meditate
you're less likely to wander often thought you're less likely to doubt yourself
and your abilities and the value of what you're doing and then meditation does involve
engagement putting an effort of some kind even if the effort is
dedicated ardent effort to stay relaxed
and i say it that way because many people as soon as you talk about effort people
kind of feel discouraged or feel upset or feel like oh no this meditation is a lot of work
but it's a lot of play it's a lot of it should be delightful
and to learn how to engage with our attention with the present moment in a way that does not feel like
work that feels enlivening that feels kind of like this oh this is this is a
good effort to make i feel clearer in the process i feel
more relaxed in the process i feel more
refreshed from it all so what kind of effort what kind of engagement allows us to feel that
one of the ways is to engage with a certain kind of wholeheartedness in the practice
where there is not com no complacency and no resistance
no kind of uh yeah no resistance to it and uh not not easy to do but when the
mind wants to do so many other things besides being present and we come back to the present moment come back to the
breath over and over again there can be discouragement wow this is hard i can't do it
not realizing that it's the very effort to very effort we made to come
back and wake up again and again that begins lighting a spark inside
allow something to grow and develop ten thousand times we have to bring our
mind back and wake up again and then slowly something begins to shift and change
to make an effort which the effort does not feel stressful it doesn't feel punitive
some people when the mind wanders off in thought um pounds back jerk their mind back
some people it's like they're playing a whack-a-mole with their mind you know to come back and there's like it's almost
you know it's really harsh the way people practice that kind of effort is not helpful
it but to make an effort that is uh an effort that like if you're biking all the way to monterey you want to take
your time and create an egg ride the bike in a way that sustains your effort over time
so with meditation how do you engage that's not too hard not too forceful
not too complacent but something that has the spark of clarity in it
a clarity which doesn't feel like it's work but feels like it's almost a natural
expression of our capacity to be present
and then mindfulness is the key of this this is the capacity not just to be
aware and attentive to the present moment but to have heightened clarity
of the present moment so we can recognize in some kind of detail or some greater
clarity what is actually happening here some people meditate doing mindfulness
practice and they're kind of soothing and soothing themselves into kind of a complacent relaxed
calm but dull calm but cloudy state and they might be improved
it might feel good because it's more relaxed than how they are we're in a stressed life
but in the long term that doesn't really sustain the practice and doesn't lead to the
kind of the to the greater benefits of this mindfulness practice we're looking for how to bring some
clarity to the present moment and i love the expression to wake up
we're waking up to experience to be awake to what is happening and why one of the reasons i like the
word awake is that um awake is kind of like opening the
windows of them of attention and then allowing the sights and sounds and smells to come in
being mindful for some people is an interpret that's work where you have to now stare at things and kind of
try to pierce what's going on to be awake is just to be available
with clarity and attention and so to start cultivating a capacity
for attentiveness to the present moment in a way that feels nourishing feel
supportive then there's a
concentration unification of the mind it kind of means that
you're now you're focused on what you're doing in the moment and so for meditation maybe you start organizing
yourself to be really focused on being present for the breath being present with your whole body
and so to really begin zeroing in kind of focusing but not like a laser
but rather as someone who's gathering together everything and bringing it all together
all of who you are incl it's more like this too is included as i be with the
breath this too this too is part of it there's no outside
but everything then is included for the purposes of kind of holding
the breathing whatever you're focusing on so to really stay and then part of concentration is sustaining the
attention continuously through time the continuity of attention just stay here stay here
stay here all these first four qualities
then support our capacity to be discerning to become wise about what's happening
to recognize that when we're how we're practicing is creating too much stress too much
strain that doesn't work to recognize when we're being too complacent and letting our mind drift
off into thought too much and just you know you know just you know just
comforting ourselves with fantasies about food or something uh to be discerning about uh
what we do with our discomforts in the body rather than struggling when we're
sitting not used to sitting in meditation posture parts of your body might start aching
and hurting and what is it useful to do people who know how to do it might find it useful
to bring their mindfulness to the pain as opposed to ignoring it
other people might say given how discomfort i have i think it's better if i mindfully move and change my posture
and not not continue with the pain or some people say i move every time i'm uncomfortable
that's what i do my whole life i think would be wise is to learn what's
going on for me when i'm always moving at every discomfort let me see if i can develop some patience
let me try to understand myself better what's operating when i move and shift
every little discomfort i have might discover you have a lot of aversion or a lot of fear that's
operating and so the discernment part is to understand what's going on to know how
to make adjustments in the meditation so you're more likely to wake be awake
more likely to be present in a useful way it's looking at the other four qualities
and saying do i need to call upon my faith in this practice
do i need to engage a little more wholeheartedly here is more attentiveness needed
is more focus and continuity of attention what's needed here
and and by asking those questions you know and being wise
then with time you become your own teacher just like if you bike from here to
monterey and you do that regularly after a while you become your own coach who's you know what you need to do in
order to sustain the journey the trip so over time you begin becoming wiser
and wiser about what's needed any given time you sit down to meditate
every day you're going to be a little bit different every day your life experiences are going to affect you in different ways
and sometimes you're going to sit down and be agitated sometimes you're going to be sit down and be tired sometimes you're going to be sit down
and be overwhelmed by things all kinds of things will come along in this human life of ours
and as you start having a sense of how to check in with yourself around these five
qualities you can kind of begin understanding how to shift and change
these qualities and adjust them to match the circumstance you're in
if you are really tired you might say i need to put more energy in here the
second quality if you feel overwhelmed maybe the concentration factor is the
most helpful thing because it kind of settles things down to just keep your focus on a simple thing like breathing
it's a classic thing to do when people are anxious is to take deep breaths there's something about
the being massaged by the rhythm of breathing in and out that can be very calming
so when overwhelmed maybe getting calm is what's needed if you're really discouraged maybe
try to remind once yourself of the fate your faith or think about what's inspiring that might inspire your
meditation practice so a life of discernment that we engage in this process ourselves
and then the wonderful result of that is that at some point in meditation you
become your own teacher and that's kind of the goal to get to learn how to be so you can
you can use meditation as a as a support for no matter what happens in your life
and if you engage in this process of meditation now
you'll be ready for a time when there's a crisis to be able to the meditation can help
you in a time of great challenge if you wait until the crisis to meditate
you won't get as much benefit so what i talked about today these five
qualities might seem a lot of work but if you just practice
sincerely your meditation i'm guaranteed that over a year or two
or something this will become second nature without knowing what they are
however knowing what these are these five qualities it's not meant to make you busy now
you know every time you go you go with measuring sticks and seeing how am i doing here but rather it's a little reference point
that's there in the back of your mind and so you kind of from time to time no
more likely to notice how this is working and uh and just kind of let it be a
gentle support a periodic support to find your way
as you go about meditate meditating in a calm relaxed way
you can consider okay i'm a little bit in balance this way and we'll balance this way
let me make a small adjustment here more energy here more calm here more concentration
maybe i should be more discerning maybe i'm sitting here a little bit too passive
not really engaged with what's going on let me see if i can try to understand a little better what i'm feeling and
what's needed here in this situation
so five faculties faith engagement
mindfulness concentration or calm and discernment
sometimes they call it's called wisdom
so those are my thoughts this evening do you have any do you want to ask any questions or clarifications or
about these five
any thoughts about them
your five faculties are all in perfect balance
so i feel like i'm i guess not a very sophisticated meditation
closer um is it green light on yeah it is
usually i'm too loud yeah maybe it's not up what number to say on your mic there's
our number on it number four
so i think now i hear it so i think of myself as a beginning meditator
and i'm happy with that um one of the teachers i listened to
described i don't know if you'd say consciousness or whatever is happening when you're
meditating but as kind of like a puppy you know this on and i like that imagery
so i kind of just watch my puppy
do its thing and just um you know come back to the breath in the
present moment but i feel a little uh i don't know the right words for it a
legit just kind of a a lightness to
uh playfulness to an exploratory attitude towards it like beautiful the
the way i've heard the puppy analogy is uh is you're training the puppy
but you're not punitive to the puppy for not listening you have to be very patient and over and over the repetition
and you do it in a kind way and it may be playful away and and
so you know just take your be very patient do it over and over again and and have a kind of a a yeah and i guess i feel i'm
not trying to train my puppy i'm just watching at this point yeah that's fine and then
the training part comes when you feel that you spend enough time drifting off and maybe maybe there's a way of having
a little bit more ability to stay grounded in the present moment so at some point it's not just
appreciating the play of the puppy but it's also trying to help the puppy not to always
poop in the house [Laughter]
i like i like the analogy of seeing your mind as a puppy
okay well thank you and if you have any if you do have questions you don't ask publicly welcome i'll be here a little
bit and uh wonderful to be here with you and thank you