foreign
[Music]
sorry about the noise so Diana's Gonna Get Us started for our
fifth class and the five hindrances
I wish there were more hindrances so we can just meet longer
laughs no so I'm happy to be back I don't think maybe you know that I was traveling and
then I was Ill but now I'm better and I'm happy to be here so last week you guys talked about sloth
and torbur and Tonya tells me that you didn't talk specifically about the homework but some of the homework if you
read it was about experimenting with the amount of energy that you have or adopting posture sitting up straighter
or doing some walking meditation is some way to maybe work with the effort level
as well as just this recognition that sometimes we can tease apart sloth and
torpers sometimes it's helpful to do that sometimes it doesn't matter but we
might think of sloth as kind of like this bodily feeling of
heaviness tiredness or you're just not enough energy and torpor is maybe like the
mental side this dullness fogginess kind of a
moving through Jello the mind kind of feeling so I just offer that as a really brief
introduction to see if you have any comments or questions about what was covered last week before we jump into
this week
the one thing I noticed is that um becoming aware of either
noticing how I was sitting was really good it just kind of brought me back to like
okay look this is you need to actually spent energy in being present here for
this right and for some reason for me the the how I'm sitting is really important
and I think I mentioned to you also that um one of the things that was shocking was
like not just how I was my spine was but also
the angle of my head that if I'm too far up I'm reaching for something if I'm
down I'm actually going off into sloth and torpor so forcing myself to actually be at sort of an even yeah keeping like
the head like distinction straight yeah looking straight ahead and it's very sensitive and I can really feel it and
it turned out to be really useful it has turned out to be really useful yeah
thank you thank you for sharing that interestingly I'm putting together a
class I'm going to be doing on Equanimity because the same thing is kind of similar with Equanimity if we
feel like we're balanced and poised then it's easier to be more equanimous so it's quite striking to this connection
with just how our posture is yeah and for me I'll say also kind of pushing
the chin back just this tiny little bit somehow opens up here and and I just feel a little bit more
present somehow it's quite something yeah thank you for sharing that
it's you you don't have anything that you want to share or no pressure [Laughter]
I've had um kind of sleepless nights this week and by the third day sorry Richard
I went to yoga last night and I was like almost Delirious I was so tired but I
did notice when I was in yoga it was like the jello mind I was like even the
hearing of a voice like the teacher I was like oh my God I'm so tired and it
feels like walking through like the Muddy Waters but I was present with the yoga and then went home and went to bed
so I noticed it then did it feel like a hindrance or was it just like okay this
is what sleep deprivation feels like or did it feel like not there's something
extra here that's making it yeah it was really hard for me to listen to or like
follow along in the class I almost felt like I wanted to do my own thing but I'm like nope there's a teacher here and he's telling me what to do and I have to
do it so it did feel a little bit more of a hindrance and then I think about at work it was even
harder because I had all these tests that I needed to do and I was like gosh
gosh I am so so beat from sleep deprivation hopefully you got some good
sleep since then I did thank you I'm happy to hear that it makes a difference right sleep makes such a difference
great thank you Tanya
I'm so glad you're feeling better and here with us tonight
so you know we're gonna start and finish with doubt
and I actually you know we've when we've taught this before we taught it first because it's so significant
and um do you even just even as I was thinking about you know it again tonight
I was like you know so many of the characters have a
combination of hindrances from The Wizard of Oz and the doubt is there for all of them
and you know I was thinking of so how do you
decide the primary and secondary you know is there a primary hindrance and the secondary hindrance and
and I was thinking about them all of them and all the characters and I'll speak more specifically and I thought
well if they had confidence if they each had confidence I don't
think they'd have the other significant hindrance the way they do so let's let's explore
this a little bit so the lion right his primary hindrance
was um worry right very cowardly and fearful
and his belief right was that he needed courage so that he wouldn't feel fear
so he had um you know he felt he needed courage he
didn't have the confidence right so he doubted his own ability and he he had a
belief that it wasn't okay to be fearful and we know that that's it's okay to be
fearful right we can be quite courageous and have fear and if we have confidence we know that
if we're afraid it's still okay so so you know maybe his own doubt and his
awareness and his own capacity really created the huge feeding ground
for tremendous amount of worry Maybe and then later you know we know he has
courage because I don't know if you remember but when they go to rescue Dorothy from The Castle because the
wicked witch kidnapped dorothium had her in her castle and was going to kill her
and it was the lion that led the way up as they were climbing the mountain
he was the one leading the pack and he was afraid and he still did it
so the end you know the wizard gives him that fake Medal of Honor
but that's not where his courage came from it existed before right
the Scarecrow his primary entrance was restlessness
right very all over the place and his mind followed right and very very much
followed that and you know his belief was that he didn't have a brain
believing he didn't have a brain he did not think he he could think he had no confidence in his ability to think
and um you know so if he had confidence if he
had doubt in his own capacity would he have been so Restless
I don't know and let's just sort of also think about
the fact that who was it that was the strategizer who was it that came up with the plan to
get the guards and get the costumes and change into them so they look like the monkeys and get in the
it was the Scarecrow he's the one that had this idea and this
has been before the wizard gave him that fake diploma so it was the big diploma that gave him
the confidence to believe and then he shares the
equation what was it I don't know if some sort of the square root of blah blah blah blah blah blah blah blah you
know all of a sudden he you know has this wisdom because of this fake
certificate your wisdom is all about knowing math equations that's right
and then we have the Tin Man right whose primary hindrance appears to be sloth
and torpor right moving slowly Frozen speaking slowly you know sort of and
um interestingly to me it's this connection to his heart right he he
believes that he he doesn't have a heart this is a belief he has right
so he believes he can't be in love and love be loved
and and yet he's sad Longing For Love and longing for love can we be sad about
love and long for Love Without a heart I don't know I don't think so
so his own own belief structure his own idea that he doesn't have a heart
creates tremendous doubt and his ability to do what he most wants to do
for all of them really for all of them to do what they most want to do and so that Foundation this lack of
confidence or belief in oneself and one's capacity creates a beautiful pot for growing
hindrances [Laughter] and I'll just say about the tinman also
just um you know he demonstrated Not only was he
longing for love and really caring about it and but you know he demonstrated a
lot of a lot of caring for Dorothy and the the you know Straw
Men when his um straw got pulled out by the monkeys and you know this is these are acts of love
and so did his caring come from that fake ticking heart that the wizard gave him
no it was there beforehand but yet this heart somehow gave him confidence it was
somehow somebody gave him something that he then could borrow their confidence
and bring it home and connect with his capacity for love more more freely
and then finally with Dorothy so Dorothy had this Chanda this healthy
desire right and and this faith I think she she was she never really questioned
her ability to get home I didn't really feel like she ever said forget it
you know she was willing to go into this scary forest and confront the wicked
witch and just go on this journey by herself in the beginning she was by herself you know traveling and made
these companions so she had this drive this Chanda this desire for Freedom or
home um but she thought it was somebody else
that was going to get her home she believed it was somebody else that
was going to kind of give her the way home
and really you know it was Dorothy getting herself
home there's no place like home clicking her own heels you know you could say home what is home home is awareness home
is being present you know
and you could say uh you know the uh the land of the Oz is
like a dream right we it's this technicolored dream and she chose to wake back up to her
true home which is okay Uncle Henry and Aunt Em on this little farm and it's
shot in black and white you know but she that's that's her home she chose to come
back and be there with our family so
she she needed a lot of you know borrowed confidence too with the Ruby
shoes and the the Glinda the the kind witch or so to so so
she seems anyway um so
there we go Diana it's kind of it's fun to listen to this
Tanya I was thinking like wow what other movies could we do this with you know when these five characters but I think
one of the things that's pointed out is right these are like archetypes for a reason because it's something that
happens to everybody it's just a part of life of course it is right it's part of the
human experience and in this context of Buddhist practice we can work building
on what Tanya said doubt one way it shows up is this doubt in our capacity
to practice and our ability or this it might be like this little niggling
feeling like doing this right I don't think I'm not doing this right
everybody else looks like they're just on the brink of Awakening and I feel
like I'm still just doing my shopping list or you know this kind of a feeling or like uh I'm
not I'm not sure should I do this practice or or I've heard meta practice
is really nice and I had that time when it was a lot of fun and my heart felt expense so I'm gonna do some loving kindness practice and then you do living
kindness practice for a few minutes and like oh but I I don't feel really loving
and that person that's sitting next to me is really irritating me so I'm now gonna go switch and try to do just some
concentration practice and oh it's too hard to do concentration practice so now I'm good right you get this right this
right we do this we do this so this feeling like oh maybe I can't do it it's
kind of like doubt in ourselves or maybe like doubt in the practices like which
practice should I do there's a sense of hesitation or a vacillation or just
spinning around in circles but not a sense of moving forward so maybe in the
same way with the Wizard of Oz there was in the very beginning when we first meet the characters they're kind of stuck
they're not really moving forward but then they kind of find their way and literally and figuratively right
they go down the yellow brick road and live happily ever after and I promise you're going to live
happily ever after [Laughter]
I wish I could promise that but uh I don't think I can though so
so I just want to maybe when we think of this word doubt for me I find it helpful
to think of it's when there's hesitation vacillation a wavering resistance this
is how it like shows up it's often not these clear thoughts I'm not sure if I can do this I'm not sure
about these teachers this teaching I'm not sure about the relevance of the teachings usually those thoughts aren't
so fully formed it's more just maybe a little bit of stuckness or a sense of
not going forward and then I also want to highlight that this is a natural and expected part of
practice absolutely there is not a single practitioner in which this has not happened to it's
part of the human experience is part of when you do learn anything new including meditation
but I also want to say that there's not only is it expected and part of practice but it's I would even say it's an
essential part of practice because how else would we learn about
the way that we behave when we're feeling not so motivated like what we do or what are some of these underlying
beliefs that are fueling our practice or that kind of like sabotaging our practice we wouldn't ever look at them
or examine them unless we were kind of really struck with some doubt so it has a function I would say as well in our
practice but sometimes when we hear this word doubt we may feel like it means that
you're not sure about all the answers and so again that's not what we're pointing to here we're pointing to is
this sometimes we might think of it as stuckness or hesitation or wavering
because doubt is helpful
right we need help we need to like if you receive a completely out of the blue
this uh email from your bank like oh we have a new policy now so please send us
all your personal information so that we can update our files right there's a
little doubt like is this right is this right right and you just know okay I'm
not going to go there so we need doubt in our life and we need
it in our practice to if somebody promises you you're going to live happily ever after right you need to
have a little bit of doubt so it's helpful to kind of distinguish what is helpful and what is not helpful
and so one way to think about it is well is it have a sense of impeding us moving
forward or is it maybe impeding or moving forward and
encouraging a certain disengagement because that's the real
I don't know the sticking point or the S or something that's really important
about doubt is it's so powerful it can have us just fall away from the practice like
I can't do this or they don't know what they're talking about or that's silly
and you know and then we could just walk away from it so of course
so that maybe maybe I'll say so the healthy doubt is a way that we're not
just buying everything Hook Line and Sinker of course there's this Dharma teaching that it's you know to come and
see a hippos ago come and see so there's a real invitation
find out for yourself as opposed to you just believe these things or just do these things and
you'll be fine instead it's what's being pointed to is
I guess I would say that it's Paramount to engage with the practice
discover for yourself allow what's being pointed to by other
teachers allow that to maybe
indicated direction to go but it's your own practice that's going to answer the
questions and um and help guide you with some of the
fine-tuning sometimes there's practitioners or that might think well
okay as soon as I learn everything precisely then it'll be okay memorize all 16
stepsati or all 37 wings of Awakening or you know all these types of things but
it's more about allowing some you to learn kind of the
direction to go and then to go and so what that means is that when you
go quote unquote is that naturally there will be
stumbling blocks there'll be other hindrances they'll be confusion all
these types of things but it's just to stay engaged what do I mean by engaged
one just to continue practicing if you can if you can't then it's an opportunity to do a little
bit of Investigation just to have this sense of
well what is going on is there something here that is that I'm not seeing that I
really don't want to see is there is there a I have this note I'm looking
for myself I had this nice word that I wanted to use but now I don't remember what it was but
the less I can say this instead of like
struggling with the struggle or feeling like oh this is just too complicated or
I or either just resistance I don't want to do it instead one way to engage is maybe just
to settle back open up and maybe ask the question what am I not seeing here or what is
going on that I don't want to be here and I'm trying to pretend it's not there or or is there something here that is
touching into fear or creating the conditions for fear or something like that
then we're back in the practice so I would say the opposite of doubt
is investigation
either investigate in your practice or if you can't get to the cushion just for whatever reason and this happens right
we have seasons in our practice where there's just so much resistance we can't go maybe see if that you can clarify are
there a particular question they talk about not self and yet there's
this rebirth thing and like I don't know that seems too weird to me I'm just not
gonna do it but maybe you could like if I'm just making this up right
we'll do some investigation ask somebody read about it or if that feels like something that is uh hindering you from
engaging with the practice I just offer that as an example
so sometimes it can be that we find ourselves I did this in the beginning
I'm going to do Mentos I'm going to do concentration and then I'm going to do this sometimes if you notice that's
happening it can be really helpful just to say oh this is doubt
doubt feels like this this vesselution is swirling around
so maybe I'd say that's the second so one is to investigate this is one way you can work with doubt
two is it just name it there's something quite powerful by saying oh it's just a
hindrance just like the Tin Man the lion Dorothy the wizard The Wizard might even
have doubt too right he has to overcompensate by having this microphone and this Wizard and or a curtain you
know everybody has some of this doubt right so just to name it kind of might help
normalize it and maybe take some of the authority away from it that might be a
second way to work with it a third way is to work with it is to
just notice if there are any beliefs that you will find the perfect practice
so easy gives immediate results and it's Blissful 100 of the time
or two that you find the perfect teacher that's always available when you need
them they have the perfect answer you know or you know whatever these we um
sometimes without even recognizing it we have these ideas of what we think would be helpful and then when I'm saying it
out loud it sounds silly but there might be like a little pieces of that or vestiges of that like
oh there's got to be something easier or something better so just inquire what kind of beliefs are
is fueling this this Stout this hesitation I can't practice because the
lawnmower is going yes right I can't practice because I don't have the right cushion yeah
you know there's so many ways we can say we can't practice because it's not
right or I can't practice because I only have seven minutes right I could practice for seven minutes right yeah
there's so many different things that we can do so maybe a third thing I'm looking at my
notes Here what time am I supposed to finish it there's no rush okay
I want to um maybe just say for the sense of
completeness that that we can in this tradition take
beautiful teachings that support us that make sense to us and help support a
sense of freedom and ease in our life and leave behind the other ones
just say you put them on the Shelf I don't understand that I don't think it's helpful it seems a little bit too weird
whatever there's no requirement that you believe absolutely
everything or take absolutely everything you don't even have to you know
become a Buddhist quote unquote whatever that means so this is really just offering what's helpful and somehow just
appreciating that kind of allows some of these doubts about some of the things to just like okay you don't have to you
don't have to believe that or do that and then maybe the last thing that I'll
say here is that I talked about how doubts often don't
show up as um clear thoughts than the way that I describe them but
they might kind of show up in some of the thoughts that Tanya was just saying I can't practice because the lawnmower
is going or I can't practice because I don't I left my eyes off of you at my
friend's house or whatever it is it's helpful to recognize
thoughts are just thoughts they're just thoughts
we don't have to believe them they don't have to be authoritative I'm not saying it's not true that the lawnmower is
going it's not true that the zofu is there but it's just a thought that says oh I can't practice now
and we can practice anyway so or we might have you know thoughts
that might get tangled up in philosophizing about things and well this Buddhist tradition says that that
Buddhist tradition says this they clearly don't know what they're talking about or something those are just
thoughts too so there's a way in which we can get tangled up in our thinking
which really can have our practice ground to a halt or something and just
to recognize oh those are just thoughts if you just wait a few moments other thoughts will arise
and you can be with those other thoughts maybe those ones are a little more supportive for practice so
you know what you're saying makes me think too it's like um it's almost it's almost the thought
that's not said yeah right because I can't practice because the lawnmowers
running why there's no why given there's an assumption
right and so it's that's why like I love what you're saying about it's it's the
doubt is very hidden it's not so Direct
I think you're you're absolutely right they're not clearly formed as I can't practice because the lawnmower it's more
irritation at the lawnmower I'll say I can't practice because they'll learn more but if you really keep playing this
sentence out and say I can't practice with the lawnmower because it's too loud and you say okay so it's too loud
and if it's too loud I can't practice well why not if I can I be aware that
it's too loud yeah oh is that practice oh yeah I guess
that is it's sort of like we just kind of end with this kind of almost a declaration
that shows up as resistance or it's kind of like pushing away or something
but maybe underneath that is this doubt I can't practice somebody else might be able to but I
can't and maybe this is something else that's kind of really highlights with doubt there's this constricted sense of
I when there's a doubt it's like I understand I can't do it and this can be subtle
to this feeling of the self is tight and
I don't know constricted not open and spacious and flexible
maybe I'll offer that so
would you what would you um I was would would maybe provide them an
opportunity to talk about this with yourselves right without uh us around it is that what you're thinking Tanya or
yeah well I was going to ask them you guys yeah you guys have been here since the beginning you're both good small group discussing discussers so are you
comfortable just talking to each other great I think I think [Laughter]
so um so I'll give you a few
um questions so and then just because there's two of you can kind of like go back and forth kind of like bouncing
around back and forth with us so one is what is uh how can you tell
and I mentioned this but maybe you have your own experience how can you tell when to skillful and hopeful and when
it's actually a hindrance when is it getting in the way because there's sometimes we might think
oh we don't want doubt we might feel like oh I have to believe everything or something like that so that's one
like when is it really a hindrance when when is it helpful
maybe I should just give them that let them talk for a little bit and then ring the bell and give you another question let's do that
yeah that's easiest okay thank you
the mic up for uh this second question
what does that absence of Doubt feel like
so you know what what is how does it feel in the body as I feel in the mind
and then of course we might say that um and how would it be helpful to know this
like how can it be a support for your practice to have this familiarity with the absence of Doubt feels like
okay
this is a good sign I didn't have to ring the bell you guys are looking at me so
um here's a third question to drop in this idea of Doubt do you feel like you
have more doubt about your capacity or to practice or to do what the
teachings are or about the teachings like is this really going to make my
life the way that I want my life to be or maybe about the teachers it could be me and Tanya or it could be like the
Buddha or just however you want to Define teachers Gail franstal whatever you know
so which do you feel like you have the most doubt that the hindering doubt
about and Maybe and then maybe just throw in what
beliefs might be underlying that or like we talked earlier about sometimes the doubt shows up as not a clearly
articulated belief but might there be a belief underneath that so
okay so maybe finishing up and while you guys were talking Tommy and I just
designed a whole nother course let's do this I'll do that
great great so I think Tonya you're gonna take well just you know
do you mind sharing any insights that are you know anything that got more clear to you as you talked about down
together anything that you would share to the people in YouTube land and listeners
that come come along the way
um for me feeling doubt is kind of an
indicator that I'm in the right place ah you know
uh plastic that said um
I'm not sure about investigation being the opposite of doubt or maybe not how I think about the
opposite of doubt went out arises I can't I'm I can't be
present enough for investigation I mean in in my practice for my mind right my
mind is at all times and I'm meditating trying to get me off right introducing
doubt introducing this introducing that when I feel those it's like okay there
you are let's get back but I can't
I can't get into investigation what does work for me is
um in the end it's it is in fact a sort of
a blind faith which comes from my practice so far yeah and that's the
benefit of just continuing the practice is that eventually you just start to understand that there's benefits that
you couldn't have even described I've had a couple of insights while
meditating which blew me away and they're extraordinarily important
there's no way I would have gotten there without meditating and so at this point I have like this
this just belief that's I'll call it Faith it's belief just keep doing it
just keep doing it and I got to thinking you know there's this there's also the
the business about the sword and just kind of cutting something and just saying I've cut it I can't quote what it
is fully right but in a way one can do that with doubt also
right you can just say no actually I'm just going to bring the sword down and I'm just going to cut that and I'm going
to make what I think that is really is a commitment to like no I'm going to cut that and
not think about that I refuse to let it be a part of my life anymore and so move
ahead which is again I think a matter of
trust it's a matter of nice yeah fantastic this is fantastic so this
comes from practice right having had some practice like okay I've been here before I I know that if I just hang in
there or that this has benefit even if it's not comfortable or those types of things so I mean this also comes more
recently from and having coming back to practice at this point after some years if not because
my going in and out took years the realization was that
[Music] um I mean I've been in therapy for some stuff and the realization was that I can't make
progress by what I can think through right now
and that I need to seek Avenues which come at me from different directions
which I'm not looking for meditation is one of them
there's been a couple things that have come up recently where it's like oh yeah yep that yeah that right
but never they never would have come from just thinking it through right yeah
and I've I made that commitment recently to just like
kind of the sort coming down no just do it and I'm going after a retreat I've
never been motivated to go to a retreat but I'm going to go to a retreat
so anyways I just wanted to bring up this business of the opposite of it and
I mean I think in meditation there's no
there's no way to address that without actually just doing the practice just
meditate just do it for a long enough period of time so that you can really say to yourself I have investigated I've
just given it enough of a enough of a chance
beautiful yes that's very nice it makes me happy to hear this too that you get this ability to like no I'm just not
going to do this making this commitment having some loyalty to yourself to yeah
yeah it's beautiful very nice Richard do you want to share your little
shall I say it I'm just well I have to say it now
just to doubt doubt you doubt doubt yeah
without doubt very nice very nice yeah
it looks like Cassandra you didn't want to say much so shall we move into um doing the raft practice
yeah okay
so feeling your feet again bringing your awareness choosing where you direct your
awareness and bringing it into the body in the present moment the feet bottom hands
maybe lift the shoulders roll them back opening up the chest cavity
where's that chin finding that you know sort of Straight Ahead posture with a
little teeny tuck in the chin just feel
like maybe taking even a posture of confidence this uprightness
and just let yourself feel the impact of setting this posture
is holding this the space for practice
this uprightness that creates a container
for things to come in and flow out and be held
to be seen
from when the time is right for you you can drop in this question when you
feel that solid space a connection with the
confidence and the brightness of being here
drop in the question and be the Observer
what am I insecure about or try where do I lack confidence
or maybe where do I feel like a fraud
and ideally this is in reference to your practice or Your Capacity to practice
and witness what arises
where is their insecurity or do I feel like a fraud
and as you allow yourself to witness what the Mind offers see if you recognize doubt anywhere
see if you can see it clearly
and of these things that arise and if there is some doubt in the practice or
in your ability to practice or in the teacher
can you choose one of these that's not overwhelming that you're able to sit with and
look in the eye without sinking into the abyss of doubt
that you feel you could investigate with curiosity
and if you find that recognize
the r of raft I see you I see you doubt
yeah right there I see you I kind of look it in the eye
and see if you can hold space that's allowing the a of raft
allowing the doubt to be present and witnessed not to consume
you not to chase away
but to recognize look it in the eye and allow it to be there
and then to feel it the follow it into the body
and notice how it manifests
where do you feel it
be patient
what happens when you feel it
and you give it permission to be there
remembering this uprightness this capacity
to hold the space
to observe as you're aware of the experience
and as you're sitting with who may becoming aware of different
components the different pieces that come together
to create the possibility for this doubt to exist
and as they present themselves allowing them to have a seat at the table
the memory of an experience
is connected to the Stout
a belief you have held or were taught
that feeds the Stout
the image of who you think you should be or shouldn't be that may be involved
and supporting this doubt
and the sword that cuts through
the faith that has grown from your practice your experience
allowing all the pieces that unveil themselves
reveal themselves to you to have a seed at the table
while maintaining the container that can hold it all the
space the awareness
almost looking down at the scene
sort of taking it all in
not needing to do anything other than to get to know
all the components that come together few or many
making room for them all
and at some point as things begin to be clear or settled
whenever that happens for you there can be a sitting back
and away a relaxing back
the sense of trust equanimity
the capacity to be with and be at ease
there may even be moments of Joy in the clarity that's offered
just allowing yourself to settle into this space that feels more
confident trusting equanimous
with it all
foreign [Music]
foreign thank you Tanya I've been thinking of it as rafty
because it has the two T's that kind of makes we won't go down there
recognize allow feel in the body tease apart and Trust
and maybe trust is really kind of flip out a little bit about doubt too it's like putting aside the doubt
I hadn't really thought about in that terms before but I think so that's a nice way to think about it
so just opening it up to see if you guys have any comments about that guided meditation and kind of like using this
rafty with uh doubt
doubt about ourselves with the practice and kind of starting that way which I think I was just saying to Tonya
I think probably everybody has some of this
if you are attending or listening to a class on the hindrances that means you're in the practice enough that you
care about working with the hindrances so everybody's like oh how can I work with these difficulties that keep
on showing up for something
I was just laughing because I had doubt about doing a raft practice about doubt
I don't doubt that you doubted oh my God
how am I gonna find something to doubt this isn't going to work that's exactly what happened
I love it I love it you get bonus points for that one Cassandra to laugh well I
was it was quiet in here because I just saw it so clearly I love it and I love
it that's fantastic it doesn't get better I think our work is done here right if
you saw that out nice that's very nice
on the rough part of it I guess it does describe to what happens except for one part when I'm meditating and feeling
doubt when the doubt arises or terrorized in several different ways but recognize for sure
allow I don't fight it actually it's just like okay you're there feel I do try to feel that in my body
and we were talking about this right we we do wind up becoming aware of it in our body I will not tease it apart
I will I will trust that it's okay it's just happening right now
it's not forever but I think if I tried to tease it apart
it would disrupt my meditation for one beautiful because it would get kind of heady
and it's giving it too much weight it's giving it too much voice you know
so I would just raft mistake yeah yeah
I think that's been eye-opening for me too because the teasing apart I doubt the teasing apart because I'm like I
don't know how to tease this apart I don't know where to find this and where it's coming from and then it feels stressful almost so I appreciate
introducing a alternative tea for me yeah which is trusting and it feels like
so much better to just trust what's happening yeah so thank you for bringing that up
yeah and I'll just say that you know again I think my guess is Gus there's a
way you're already teasing it apart so quickly you don't even need to go there
you know it doesn't have to sometimes it's just it's it's like not complicated
oh you're familiar yeah yeah you know like okay I know what happens oh if I go
down there I'm gonna get lost or get caught in the mental you know so
you really are putting your it's a really it's a it's so simple
you know and sometimes uh the allowing happens instantly when you see when you
recognize you know it's like these are these are parts of the process but they don't all have to be huge in and of
themselves it depends on what we're practicing with
it really just depends and so it's good to trust what's heart we should just do tart
fart think of all the
French I don't know we can come up with all the different versions of it yeah
just feel it in the body and then feel it leaving
just allow you might want to have other people leave the room before you do
I think you're right about how much well maybe okay so what happens for me when I'm meditating also my sense of time
disappears and so something May actually have happened but I really
don't have any idea of how long it took I'm always shocked when the bell rings
it's like really seriously and I know that I've been I mean I've not fallen asleep I've never been awake the entire
time right so maybe you're right maybe it's just it happens but I don't
yeah or it's just so subtle it's just I mean it's not there's not a lot you know like
Cassandra a few weeks ago I think you had a lot of pieces that were coming up you know and sometimes it's like that
but sometimes it's you know it's enough to just just say
this is a thought and this is doubt and you've done it right there that's recognized yeah maybe
a little bit of allowing and that's it yeah we don't necessarily need all the
steps
well I think doubt infiltrates the way we think
maybe I would say almost thinking is doubting in some kind of ways instead of
just opening up and experiencing yeah yeah we're trying to we're thinking you know
we're trying to uh somehow put language to an experience
and it's always interpretive
maybe I'll just introduce one idea maybe like an expression that I don't think Tony or I said today and once I say it I
think you guys will recognize it but I sometimes it's helpful to just be explicit that sometimes doubt masquerades as
wisdom we might have this feeling right that oh
right so it's just helpful to notice that like if we have this oh right now I
can't think of what I thought that would be a doubt thought masquerade wisdom maybe you have one to do
I'm not going to do that that's ridiculous I don't know but sometimes we might think that we're being really wise
or smart or yeah I know better yeah something like
that but when it's really just doubt that's fueling these kinds of thoughts
to make us feel better yeah and not to feel because doubt is
uncomfortable too so that's part of what's fueling the thoughts right we like to feel like we can control or that
we know or something like that so it's there's inherent this uncomfortableness
that the self really wants to get away from and we'll do almost anything to
get away from and then I'm trying to think
um is there anything else as we kind of I'm closing things up
maybe I'll just offer this to something that Tonya can uh rolled into the guided
meditation but sometimes if if it feels like it would be helpful not if it feels burdensome and cumbersome
but if it feels like it might be helpful like before a sit to just remind
yourself of some of the things that you are a capable person that there are things that you have skills in or
whatever it might be because just reminding ourselves of that
can just switch the mindset enough that when we sit down we're coming from a
place of some stability or not all consumed with doubt or something like that
so I just offer that sometimes it might feel a little bit awkward though do you do you have you done this Tanya
where you kind of remind yourself before you sit down like okay I am a capable
person I know how to cook some food I've been able to hold down a job or you know
whatever it is I think probably my early my first when
I'm sitting strategy is more to arouse Faith to kind of connect with the Buddha
um or experiences with the practice and then if I'm wobbling in the practice I might
do what you're describing which is you know you've sat through a lot more
it won't kill you whatever I need to say to help sort of um
I know how to cook I say this because Tanya's a fantastic cook
that's an exaggeration but I know
and I think that's good so I have a few um a few fun Wizard of Oz things to
share yeah yeah I definitely have some I'd really like to share
and I'll start with um you know so the wicked witch right when she is in
the castle and she's Dorothy's escaped and they're right there's this
um Dorothy's running this way and all the Witch and all the monkeys are coming out and on this walkway
and um and so Dorothy grabs you know the the
Scarecrow she writes she lights the Scarecrow on fire the witch does
and so Dorothy grabs a bucket of water
this is such a strong metaphor to me of like you know what does water do it cleanses it puts fire out it purifies it
helps us see clearly right so Dorothy throws the water puts out the
fire the fire of whatever it is you know and then it gets on the witch
and as the witch is melting because of the water she says this
what a thought a good little girl like you could destroy my wickedness
[Laughter]
and to that I thought oh my God all right who would have thought something simple
like letting all these pieces sit at a table could have it all like Fall Apart
right it's not some War it's it's just cleansing clearing
allowing right I just love that love that
and then with the wizard you know Diana you brought up like yeah
how much of him is covering his own doubt with his
robustness you know his Illusions you know
and um you know what is behind all the illusions that we create right there's
this part of it is or covering things that we don't want others to see
but another part is what the Mind itself does it's a little like a magic show
so to me some of the what the wizard represents is is how the mind works it
creates these things these these like stories and fills in the details and
predicts the future and there's many movies right so this is kind of he the
wizard kind of represents what what's going on the inner workings that can happen in the mind especially if we're
not wise with what's happening and the way that you know the Oz uses
Illusions and tricks to maintain power and status and control but you know the hindrances
their Illusions and tricks and they the more energy we give them the more power
and control we give them Toto I already talked about but I just
love thinking about Toto as mindfulness itself unhindered right being able to
see through See Clearly pull the curtain back and Dorothy carries Toto everywhere
she goes nice nice so we need to bring mindfulness with us everywhere we go
and I may have said this before too but the the path this yellow brick road and the path right with our path it's not of
practice it's not out there it's within and it's revealed with the
practice with mindfulness
so we want to invite you to pull back the curtains to discover what's being
hindered the teachings say that the true mind is
quite brilliant right and we hope that I think I can say we
that you'll kind of let the lightness of the characters linking arms skipping down the path you
know and that their own ability to like you said it so nicely Diana they were
pretty Frozen with their hindrances but they worked together and through it and
got more free and free together as they dance down the path together so
that's and maybe together is represents both you know
hindrances but people together absolutely same with others like what a difference
it makes it makes such a difference
do you want to please bring yeah yeah please bring this forward I love this
since this is the last time and we might as well just get as much as we can into the analogy right I just said something
about bringing uh Mara into thinking about the wicked witch maybe you can say
more about Mara no please you say more about Mara okay
there's no such thing as the Devil Within Buddhism but there is this concept of Mara as somebody who gets in
the way and um
not pleasant and in this case that's what the witch
embodies just getting in the way
and it's the cleansing water that just gets rid of Mara and
that story right that's really pretty is the Buddha just
touching the ground right and saying tomorrow I see you and
touching the ground and being fully grounded and that just kind of taking care of Mara
and the Buddha also asks the Earth to witness and and to say his He's Worthy
say what I'm sorry he's worthy right he belongs right and we need you know like that that Faith the
confidence you know is it does come from within but it also
it is helpful to have that grounding the witness the community the Sangha
I mean in some respects maybe it is useful to know that this concept of chaos at Mara sort of
encompassing chaos representing chaos right it's true it's real it's
I'm I'm staying away from the devil part of it that's not the point the point of
it more is yeah chaos and the the advantage of thinking about
this way is we don't have to take it personally right it doesn't mean anything that we're a failed meditator
doesn't mean anything like that it just this is what happens when people practice this is a Rises
it happened to the Buddha what happened to the Buddha what happened in a Buddha it happened to everybody in this room
I'm pretty sure so
um I'll just you know say one more thing which is um that next week uh I'll be
starting another intro series with Sandra Sanabria and we're going to include breakout groups as part of the
intro Series so um that's new and different and but it's
been a Hallmark of our Thursday night so and it'll only be in person we will not
be streaming on YouTube so hopefully we'll come together and you know keep practicing and sharing
Thursday yep so may this the benefit of our time
together be a benefit for all beings everywhere
yeah thank you thank you guys this was fun it was one
sorry I weren't here for more days because