now I'm Amplified yeah no yeah
so welcome warm welcome [Music] happy to see you all
I I imagine you're
here because well you all have your own reasons for
being here all of them good
all of them I'm assuming you come to a place like
this for out of goodness
you could say maybe out of love
that you love yourself you ever think of it that way you love
yourself and you think something is going to happen here in your meditation or
right being here maybe I'll say something that will help be helpful
just this be this place it's just so nice to be here it's it's a Sacred Space
so it's nice to be in a Sacred Space where you know we feel Maybe feel uh
held in love in this Sacred Space
this holy place that thousands thousands and thousands of
people have come here too to be healed
who come here out of love for themselves
out of compassion they for themselves
we want to be free I want to be free
and I'm assuming you want to be free
so that's compassion right
like you see a dog that's you know maybe in pain and you feel you want to be free of that pain
or you have a loved one who's trapped in an affliction
you want her to be free
so I don't want to presume too much but I I
want you to be free
and I I'm assuming that you all are here because
in some way you want to be free you have compassion you have some essential
compassion there's something in US this basic
inclination
I had a cookie before I came here tonight
maybe it's made me happy I want to be happy you want to be happy
anybody here not want to be happy raise your hand if you don't want to be happy
you say well I'm a masochist well that makes you happy to be a masochist
it's so uh Beyond uh
psychology in a way it's so essential
it's just we we all day long from when we get up in the morning
I don't I didn't know what I was going to say tonight but here I'm saying something
makes me happy to say what I'm saying I love to talk about love I love yeah
makes me happy to talk about love makes me happy to talk about compassion
so think about how you went through your day-to-day and all the things you did
out of care even making your bed you know brushing
your teeth it's caring for yourself
going to the bathroom you know we always have this love in us
it's in it's all day long I just crossed my legs I'm a little more
comfortable that way you just moved here getting more comfortable it's okay it's
good
you should recognize we have this but maybe sometimes we think we're bad
huh
the Buddha said or somebody
like the Buddha said we have this love we're so strong in us
it's like the way a mother cares for an only child this love is so strong
so Buddhism and uh Buddha
and all the Masters all the Buddhist Masters
and I think all religious all mystical religious
Masters say that we are love
that we are compassion that we are awareness
that we are wisdom
think about who you are in essence Who You Are
we have all these thoughts all these identities that come through our mind
these boxes and we step into those boxes
and for a while that becomes me
as I was sitting here tonight with you
I wasn't trying to think about what I was going to say but different things all these you know
beautiful things came coming to my mind that's a good idea that's a good thought that's a good thought
been out of love I let them go I didn't want to get caught in a box
it was deeper than grabbing onto that box was it was a
more essential in me to let go of that box it was kinder to me a more compassionate
to me to let go of that and to allow
to allow the boxes to come and go
and then their silence can you hear the silence in the room
there's silence all there's always silence
there's space between the boxes
and sometimes the space lasts longer
and we I think we want to be really silent we want to we want that to be our
meditation to be as to exist in silence that's what we want
we strive for that we we meditators really love silence
but that's really grasping silence too
we don't have to grasp at the silence just you know the silence comes naturally in the silence
is between the thoughts and the silence is always here
so if we relax into our own kindness
essential kindness which is always here we can count on this essential kindness
we can count on this essential love
then we don't have to worry so much about the boxes
the boxes don't matter you could say who cares about these
boxes who cares rather than stepping into a box
letting it allowing it allowing every box
to free itself they will free them they do even if we grab hold of them they'll
free themselves eventually what box were you in an hour ago you
don't remember so it does free them it does free itself
it always frees itself we've been creating boxes for I don't remember I am 78 years old I've
been creating boxes for 78 years and they've always freed themselves
amazing
so what's not the Box
what's not the Box in you what isn't it what is it what is it in you that isn't
this little prison that you create that we create for
ourselves what's in you that isn't that
much bigger than that is it the silence
is it the love love is always here
is it the compassion the kindness that allows sounds
Sensations
allows the whole kitten caboodle
to arise
and cease and rise and cease and rise and cease
allowing allowing that flow
we can try to grasp and stop it on a me
that is particularly wonderful particularly praiseworthy
particularly I don't know
laughs
and these are all awareness kindness and love
all exist all exist they're all qualities of being
just being just relaxed
open aware being
we all want to come home we all want to be ourselves
we all want to come home and relax and just
really would not not worry about
all this stuff
but we do worry about all this stuff
we worry about the human value system what I'm talking about is not really
human I mean it's very human
but the human value system is what people think of us
stuff we worry about our reputation
our Glory
I think he's having fun out there he's happy he's having a good time
so who are we hear that and maybe you feel
we see
foreign
we sense
and we're aware of all these things that are going on we're aware of our feelings
we're aware of our thoughts we're aware of our hearing
we're aware of our sides we're aware of yeah
and all those things that I mentioned
are conditions that come and go and come and go and come and
go and come and go
but in this instant of time
there's this awareness this presence
that knows what we hear that knows can you see that in yourself
that knowing there's this knowing there's a wake awake quality
who are you aware are you aware right now
aware of sound
the Buddhism great Masters says we are this is what we are we are awareness
all those other things all those conditions keep all of our
so-called life
come and go come and go come and go Instant by Instant by instant
but awareness doesn't come and go
the Greeks called it neosis g-n-o-s-i-s everybody you know all these great
cultures religions they all know this in their own particular way
that fundamentally we are awareness
other than that we're nothing at all because it all comes and goes
you can't grab it anything you can't grab
that sound
my voice you can't grab what you see I think you think I'm think I'm seeing this but it's
really changing my focus is changing whatever is out there is changing
and I'll leave this place and that won't even I won't see that anymore anyhow
Sensations are changing
but my awareness in this instance isn't changing
the awareness is here The Knowing is here
What If instead of being devoted to
um things that are changing
like praise black reputation
like money like getting something material like a success
like some temporary Glory
and being so afraid of the opposite of criticism of disapproval of
being neglected being not recognized
so afraid of failure so afraid you know we have all these problems of low
self-esteem low self-worth anger at someone who says something we don't like
fear that somebody's going to say something we won't like or we're not going to get what we don't get all these
afflictions what if we weren't so devoted
to those things that come and go
and just were devoted to this
that doesn't come and go
this awareness like I said try it out
don't even don't even make any effort just be
what if we're devoted to that
which includes love because we're allowing it all just
allowing it all to freely flow
and that's freedom when we're not grasping
onto one of those really painful boxes
I heard that these Devils these Devils create Hells for us
Hells of anger Hells of fear
but they become angels those Devils become Angels when we let
go and let be there
ushering in a bigger understanding for us your afflictions those devils
if we allow them they can be angels
do you have any questions or comments about any of this
I don't think there are any questions no
anybody feel like saying anything
well I cut clothes with a story
there was this rabbi whose name was zuzia
and everybody loved this Rabbi it was a very wise Rabbi he was very good really
good Rabbi good person completely renunciate
he gave way people would give him money give him stuff and he'd give it away his family unfortunately well maybe I'm sure
it was fine they lived in kind of a poverty they lived
and he was very wise and and uh
good kind so it came time for him to die
and he was crying he was sobbing
and his his all beat these congregants that loved
him were around his bad zuzia why are you crying
and they they said are you crying because you weren't oh he says I'm I'm crying because I'm
afraid to face God and they say why were you would you if
all people be afraid to face God Zeus yeah
and he said because I don't know so they said are you are
you afraid that you weren't enough like Moses that you weren't wise enough like Moses
and Jesus shook his head no that's not it are you afraid that you weren't
so completely devoted and loving of God like like
Abraham or Isaac or Jacob any of those great prophets that we're doing
and so she said no that's that's not I'm not crying because I wasn't kind enough or I wasn't wise enough I'm not afraid
of God accusing me of that what are you afraid of zuzia
I'm afraid that God will accuse me of not being sousia
so what does it mean to be yourself to really come home
just to be yourself who cares what they think it doesn't
matter doesn't mean to not be caring
but not being so preoccupied with the human value system
whatever you're worried about whatever your problem is and recognize
your your innate goodness a nakedness Buddhism believes
that we are innately good innately pure not innately
laughs bad in so many ways no no we're all
you're all perfect you're all innately good you're all have you have awareness
it's unmistakable you're awake you're alive you're not a rock
and you want to be happy Your Love
and you want your friends and your and really all beings
if we could we would we would love all beings to be happy I think
and we would love all beings to be we want ourselves to be free of afflictions right
compassion we have this compassion
and to know this to know who you are is wisdom
and we have wisdom it's all here it's all available
okay thank you