so we we just still have a couple people coming in here but Richard's been reading us
the chat so it's nice to hear from you out there and YouTube land and glad you're joining us and
nice to hear that um at least for one of you you've been enjoying the course with Donna and I
well thank you and as Richard said in the chat if you have a question specific to what we're teaching
go ahead and put it in the chat and we you know if we have the capacity to respond we will so
all right Don foreign ready
so a warm warm welcome everyone welcome back to those of you who have been with
us for some or all of the preceding weeks and a warm welcome if this is your first
time also so today tonight
my friend and co-teacher Tanya Weiser and myself are doing the fifth of a five-week
introduction to meditation course class and
we've been over these last four weeks gradually learning more and more about
how to be with the intimacy of the direct experience of living
watching with awareness mindfulness and mindfulness being a way of
noticing experience while it's happening in the moment much like a bird watcher
or a naturalist might notice experience what's arising in the birds and the
forest around them and this kind of learning how to pay attention on purpose
is process of beginning to cultivate a capacity for choice
for Choice rather than reaction to what's happening in our minds and what's happening in our lives
so I'm going to give a very quick overview of the last four weeks we covered
mindfulness and breathing mindfulness of the body of emotions
and of thinking and the way Tanya put it a couple of weeks ago these are like
cocentric Rings or ripples with the breath in the center and going outwards
from there the reason that we often start with the breath is that it's always here as long
as we're alive it's changing and dynamic and it can help to build Focus
if the breath doesn't work for you and you know it doesn't the body sensations of the body or attending to
sound are two really good alternatives which brings us to the body
that was the focus for the second week and we talked about how the how the body
has a form of intelligence it has its own form of intelligence and
that listening to our bodies is a skill it's a skill we can develop through
mindfulness practice Sensations are the language the body speaks
and this skill of listening feeling into the sensations of breath
and body have the advantage of anchoring us here now
you may have noticed your body is always here and now the breath is always here and now no matter where our minds go
what they're up to the next week
was mindfulness of emotions which can range from
the uplifting to the downright awful right
emotions are a form of communication often kind of a Gestalt form of
understanding what's happening or at least how we're interpreting what's happening
and that word interpretation is key because emotions can be based on what's actually happening in the present
or they can also be triggered now by something that has happened in the
past I think Tanya used the example of seeing a glass of water on the counter and that
triggers something in the past and there's an emotional reaction or seeing something
a person's shoes and my pathway might have the same effect has nothing to do with the shoes or the water
has everything to do with that combination of past experience
being triggered by present moment emotions
biochemically are only a 60 to 90 second process in our bodies and our brains
if we don't interfere with them they flow through and they can move through
so part of a large part of mindfulness practice is learning how to be with them
and let them just flow through without buying into them without interfering
with them repressing them pushing away or getting on a soapbox about them
and that brings us to thinking and thinking and emotion are very
closely related right symbiotic relationship unseen emotions fuel a lot of our
thinking and thinking feeds a lot of our emotions
both are true so how our minds relate to thinking
has a lot to do with how we relate to reality itself
and we have talked about this a lot over the course of the weeks
how we relate to things is critical so important
to learning mindfulness meditation and to living a life in harmony with what is
actually happening how we relate to it so in beginning to
understand thinking as something Beyond reality itself as just flits
of our minds it's helpful to understand there are different modes visual maybe
word or concept sound it could be like a movie
Tanya talked about this I think it was last week right and then it's also helpful to understand there's
different types of thinking imagining remembering planning fantasizing
all of this is important because the experience of physical and mental pain
increases or decreases depending on how
we think about it how we relate to it
which brings me to the last sort of review point which is just like we suggest you take an outer a
posture in your body that's a combination of grounded relaxed and alert
there's also an inner posture the mood or attitude relationship to
experience that's so core and that attitude it's helpful to have
interest or curiosity kindness and the willingness to start
again over and over so this all brings us to this week's
topic which is bringing it all together we're going to teach a form of meditation called open awareness or
choiceless attention but first we would love to hear from you those of you who have been here
how your practice is going if you have questions from the past weeks
anything you want to ask about the practice right now the floor is open and both of us will respond
maybe that microphone ah yes and please help each other with the microphones
Elena can I put you on the spot to model the ice cream method of the microphone you can see
beautifully Done Right very close
um so it The Sound goes in through the top
was anybody willing to share yeah behind you Elena
thank you and please say your name um hi everyone good evening I'm Divya
um and I guess um
I've been coming to the sessions regularly I've been practicing meditation a little less regularly
um which I'm trying to give myself Grace for sometimes it's a five minute mindful stretching
instead of a 20-minute sitting practice um and
I feel like I don't know if it's Placebo or what it is but I do feel like it's made a big
difference in the like past two months that I've been practicing I've Incorporated some other stuff in my life
to like yoga and other things that could also be helping but um
like right now I'm going through a kind of difficult situation that I feel like a year ago would have put me in a really
bad place and right now I feel like I don't know I'm
like it's hard but I'm okay um and so I feel like that's something
that it's really helped me with is like put things in perspective and try to give myself a break from like spiraling
all the time so yeah wonderful it's really beautiful to hear how even just a
little bit of practice and the learning over the past weeks has contributed to
this greater Equanimity in this greater sense of being able to show up for whatever's difficult in your life
exactly that's great that's great I I love too
that you're um you know and this is tonight the second half I'll be talking about mindfulness
in daily life and it is mindfulness practice to be
mindful of movement so that is practice so yes yes
oh great so this is a question from YouTube which Tanya helpfully handed to me yes I did
I'll read it aloud can you explain the difference between mindful meditation
and Insight Meditation it's a great question so this is the Insight
Meditation Center and here we're teaching mindfulness meditation
and I guess to start with I'm going to try to keep
it short which is not always my strong point mindfulness meditation
is the sort of
one branch one kind of process within a much larger range of forms of Buddhist
Meditation and mindfulness meditation can become
Insight Meditation absolutely certainly but it doesn't necessarily have to be
Buddhist it doesn't have to have any religious connotations to it it's a term that has
been taken outside of Buddhism and used much more broadly to talk about the
kinds of skills that we've been teaching for the past four weeks this being aware of our own capacity to
be aware of the breath the body emotions thinking open awareness
so mindfulness is focused on that capacity
Insight Meditation refers to the poly word vipassana
which is to discern break apart to see clearly
and mindfulness is one key very important component of that but it's not
necessarily the whole thing and other skills and other dimensions of
meditation also come to the fore concentration being one of them and so when we talk about Insight
Meditation we're talking about it from a Buddhist framework and we're talking about it as a larger part of a Buddhist
path that incorporates some of these other factors in mind as well which do
come into play in mindfulness but not necessarily to the same degree do you want to add anything to that
Tanya that was great okay yeah I can we ask you to move over just a
tiny bit to the right thank you perfect okay I was just a
little concerned about the camera behind her head it's no longer behind your head come on
in please welcome hi
welcome again please settle in and we're going to move into the first set
of instructions tonight I'll be talking at you for about another 10 minutes and then we'll go into a 15-minute guided
meditation so
I'd like you to do an experiment with me it's um kind of an exercise
so please close your eyes and I want you to very intentionally
think of a leaf like a leaf on a plant or a tree
and if you're a visualizer you can picture it but to just
think of it and hold it in your mind
and now open your eyes and what do you see here
perfect a leaf not the leaf I was thinking of was it the wreath any of you were
thinking of right so the reason I'm bringing this very
simple example is that the thought of a leaf is not a leaf
the concept of the leaf is not the physical Leaf right
so all of us probably were picturing slightly different or even very different leaves from each other
if I had been told to think of a leaf this would not be the leaf I would have thought of either
so that's an important distinction we're
going to play with tonight is the difference between concept and what actually arises in experience
in this case in your visual experience of seeing this leaf
now um
just notice this Leaf would you say it's big or small medium
medium yeah I think that's fair to say I saw some really small ones I had a good time on a hike today looking finding
this so now how big is it
yeah so this is a really important kind of concept
is the concept conceptual differentiation of comparison
right small large or four medium
so this is the large leaf right we're all agreed okay
is it still the white leaf so again it's the distinction by
comparison so now here's like really important question is one of these leaves better or worse
than the other leaf no silly question right is one of them
bad or wrong for being larger or smaller
not really um so the reason I'm being a little bit silly
about this is our minds do this all the time we draw comparisons between our
experiences and usually we have value judgments associated with those comparisons
this experience is much better than this experience right
or actually I wanted this experience but I've got this one
right so letting go of the value judgment
associated with distinguishing between big little medium large small
wanted not wanted is a really powerful kind of capacity to begin to develop to
just experience the leaf as a weave not the concept in your head not the oh this Leaf this is a bad leaf
it's all twisted it's too curly whatever I'm not able to experience it as itself
if I'm doing that and just like that we're not able to experience our experiences
if we're constantly harshing on them judging them comparing them
to last week's experience or the person next to me's experience
right so
no right or wrong Leaf no right or wrong thought experiment experience for the
purpose of mindfulness meditation they're just
arising and falling happening and going away all in real time right
okay so indulge me here we're going to do one last total thing
why don't you check out the space between the leaves
take a look at it notice how your eyes might shift Focus just a tiny bit
looking at the space between the waves
and maybe maybe notice the space between you and
all of the weaves between where you're sitting
in the space in the room
so this this is a little bit like sometimes in
meditation we can notice the space between sensation thoughts
sounds breath
emotions and that can be a really helpful shift it's not that it's bad to notice the
leaves the objects the experiences that's totally fine and if we're starting to get snarled up
in them sometimes it's really helpful to look for the space in between
right sometimes meditation open awareness meditation can get
spacious that way where we start the mind starts getting more interested in the space in between than the actual
objects of our attention Leaf breath sound sensation whatever
and that can be beautiful but isn't necessarily any better or worse than
noticing Leaf sound object thought
the really it's helpful to notice the difference the really important capacity
we're developing and it's like a workout in the gym it takes time usually can't lift everything right away
we're developing the capacity to be aware on purpose
and so that's the last little part of this silly experiment is
notice that you're knowing these leaves
this instruction this moment notice that you're aware that you're
here that you're present was that hard to do
anybody but knowledge no not hard
so that simple noticing that's mindfulness that's awareness mindful
awareness there's another word for the ancient Buddhist term for mindful awareness
another translation which is to remember what's harder for most of us is to
remember to do it over and over so part of what we're training
is like we remember anything else we want to remember anything else we do it over and over and over again
and it gets easier until it's practically natural
becomes a treat so
for the purpose of the meditation that we're going to do tonight eat Leaf each experience is simply
itself not the concept it's not the comparison right
and it's also really helpful
you know I think you might just stopped my battery just went out
um
I'm now tethered can you hear me okay
how's this a little bit better I'm actually going to hold it a little close because I don't want to change the configuration
from your face so tonight
the kind of meditation we'll be doing as I mentioned is called open awareness or
choiceless attention and it can be really helpful
to give our minds something to do to stay in contact with whatever is
coming up in the present moment so in the earlier weeks we were focused on mostly
paying attention to say breath and letting everything else in the background or emotion and letting
everything else be in the background this week we're going to ask you to
settle into meditation using whatever anchor of attention feels
most comfortable to you given the other weeks you've been doing this
and then the invitation is going to be to open up to whatever arises whatever is most dominant in the present moment
at that point and when it becomes less obvious
to return to the anchor and then eventually just to kind of float and experience for a few minutes and let
things move through sound sensation thought mood whatever
it can be really helpful to use the technique that we introduced a few weeks ago
where you very softly Inside the Mind silently say a single word or a label
like thinking imagining
feeling breathing whatever it is just to name it and that
helps the awareness sharpen just a little
so let's give it a try I'm gonna switch
mics before I give it a try
okay can you all hear me okay great
so settling into a comfortable posture feet flat on the ground
seat grounded in the chair
softening your eyes softening your tongue
and if you're comfortable closing your eyes closing them
perhaps taking two or three intentional breaths
really attuning tuning in to the sensations
of your body breathing maybe feeling the belly rising and
falling
feeling the chest expanding or Contracting a bit
or perhaps feeling the breath coming in at the nose or mouth
gentle Sensations
and allowing your attention to settle in your body
your life's breath
resting on the flow of in and out
steadying the attention
perhaps in part
by making a gentle soft mental label
breathing in breathing out
or Rising falling
inviting inviting the body to soften and relax
The Head and the face
the neck and the shoulders
the arms and the hands
allowing the breath to massage the chest and the belly from the inside
softening and warming the Torso
feeling the grounding the weight of your hips and buttocks on
the chair or cushion
and allowing the tension to drain out of the thighs and calves
shins and ankles down through your feet and outwards
and opening the awareness to the whole body
and to the experiences arising in the moment hearing
thinking feeling
and as it feels right using a soft note
whatever's arising sound tension
warmth relaxation
noticing what arise as an experience
letting it flow through
from time to time
maybe noticing the space between the sound and another sound
or a breath and another breath
or any experience at all as it flows through this moment
noticing are you aware
what's obvious
receiving experience
foreign
as if you're sitting in a simple room a one-room house
the windows and doors all open
and you're in a comfortable chair the only piece of furniture in the house
letting all experience
move across the windows maybe even come in the door and stay awhile and leave
but nothing stays because you are in the one seat
s allowing experience to flow through the
heart the body of the Mind just like that
[Music]
foreign
thank you for your practice
thank you for the meditation
so we have another time for question comment sharing questions
and yeah great you want to grab
okay I'm sorry to hear that it's helpful I'm speaking of hearing if you um you
don't need to do it for that you were just saying you couldn't hear but to use a microphone
um were other people having a hard time hearing song
there's the hearing aids yeah yeah or the assistant yeah
this room also has a weird little dead spots sound wise in it I've discovered
in the past so you happen to have bad luck you might end up in one of those
was anyone able to kind of have that experience of a feeling that you were grounded in a
chair or on a you know sitting somewhere and letting things kind of come and go
were you able to have some degree of that experience in your meditation it's not
necessary not always so easy just wondering if that
um connected for you not for you
if you will not you want to go ahead go ahead did someone else sorry
I'm just gonna say that I think the um labeling that you mentioned like
labeling different thoughts was really helpful for me because sometimes like one thing just kind of waterfalls into a
bunch of other things and before I know it I'm like why am I thinking about this again so it was kind of nice to be like
oh okay I'm like imagining this and I'm wondering about this and I'm planning for this and I'm you know what I mean
and that really helped me like at least realize what I was doing in
that time yeah yeah great so identifying the different kinds of thought or the different
processes it sounds like was really helpful to kind of get a handle on that they were happening
great any other comments I think you you had one yeah yeah please I don't know if I
just did this this is not a very deep comment but just to say that when you when you
talked about um the muscle I think like I haven't sat
for quite a while and I was definitely sort of drifting off and it's just
interesting to observe that you know that that my muscle is a little bit out of practice and
um so yeah I'm feeling quite inspired to get back into it
yeah it's a great observation you're noticing that the conditions are different if we
don't practice for a while the conditions are different the muscles get a little deconditioned
and it's easier to wander and it's different from there's a difference between valuing something and actually
embodying those teachings and well said that's right
that's right very well said Tanya did you have one from YouTube yeah I do have a question from YouTube but I
I'm gonna answer it later because it works well with something I'm gonna address later
oh yes please Corey yeah I help each other with the mics guys if you can
uh I thought it was uh intriguing to focus on the spaces between sounds
because usually when I do practice mindfulness on sounds I'm
focusing on the things that pop in and uh generally they I notice uh
sounds pop me into the present moment but then also
evoke imagery as to what's causing the sound at the same time so and that gets
me spinning too so it's kind of does both things but focusing on the space between sounds
I noticed some sounds like train sounds
were long distances between sound and other sounds were very small apart so I
I thought it was a good I'm gonna try that more it's very nice
so did you find that focusing on the spaces helped you stay a little bit less in the discursive like oh that's a train
yeah I think that's what kind of appealed to me a little bit is that I
don't get caught up in the what's causing it and then get caught up
into it's more just the raw sound not
focused on you know who's walking who's driving or what's
you know yeah that's kind of yeah that's a good way to put it
your great observations
did anybody find it challenging hear about that too
yeah can you hear me uh hi everyone Brian yeah this is challenging for me
um I think so for me it's the breath like focusing on the breath and if I'm not focused on
the breath then my mind just goes everywhere and then I can't before I know it I've spent
five six different thoughts and then I'm like oh that was a thought but it's been too long right so then I
just get lost so then if I when I recognize it and then I come back to the breath
then it's fine but then I was like oh the whole point of this was to like watch the spaces
and then I lose it again so I have like three separate cycles of that
or I just couldn't just be grounded it's like grounded for like a few
seconds and then gone again
um yeah I can respond you can read the question Don and um
I I think all what I want to point to Brian is you know what helps you anchor
your awareness which is the breath and that's a power right there that's a
strength it's a skill it's really um lovely that you know that you can do
that right and um
you know sometimes that is like that no matter how much you're practicing or
whatever the mind is is just a bit of a choo-choo train
um and what I'll kind of be talking about is mindfulness in daily life and there's
this you know the idea of going to the gym gym and building the muscle right and
and it really is a matter of not not just the lovely idea of what meditation
is which helps us even if we're not doing it it can because it can help us
remember but actually when we start to practice regularly
just like we start going to the gym regularly we actually do build up some
capacity a muscle the gym you know the capacity
to be aware and mindfulness and
and then what we can do as well is we don't just have to meditate we don't
just have to practice mindfulness on the cushion so it's not like we can only do grow that capacity on the
cushion but we actually can start to practice it in daily life
that you know we don't need weights we can just watch our thoughts we can notice our emotions we can feel
our body as we're walking and moving um you know I did a practice for a long
time where I used every time I got up at my office and walked anywhere I used it
as a mindfulness practice and it really grew my connection to the
my whole chest my sense of breath and my body and it became something that was it went
with me everywhere so um I think the the encouragement is you
have you've already got some capacity which is to be able to tune into the breath
and keep experimenting and practicing more practice in more ways more times
is that helpful
I'll just briefly add that the experience you described indicated to me that you were actually quite mindful of
going off and coming back and just give yourself credit for that because that is building that muscle in
a really powerful way because life isn't as simple as watching your breath right that's why we call it practice in
some ways it's all simpler when we're just sitting so this is a question from YouTube
when you say notice that you know it almost seems like you're asking me to be
aware of awareness and that seems impossible so could you please clarify
I'm happy to be I'm happy to clarify what I can there
so um as Tanya was just talking about this is a process we don't start off immediately
being able to notice that we're knowing or be aware of awareness itself
and it is the direction the practice goes as it matures
so the invitation in the little instructions I gave and then just for a
moment in the meditation was just to respond to the question
if I ask you right now are you aware it's the answer
is anyone not aware it's kind of impossible not to be once
the question is asked right so the capacity to develop that
reflexive awareness the ability to know that we're knowing builds over time and part
by cultivating mindfulness of the breath mindfulness of the body awareness of the spaces in between
but it's not something we can make happen I have found in my own practice asking
the question every now and then especially if I hook it to a daily life activity like Tanya talks about
like I've gotten in the habit that every time I walk out my front door
the question I ask the question every time I'm walking back in to my apartment I ask the question every time I open my
car door and get in or get out asking the question and over months that built to now the
question doesn't happen anymore the awareness just comes because like
conditioning a muscle we can condition that capacity so it can't happen on demand for most people right away
but it can be developed I so play with it experiment with it some
people even put little um like reminders in their phone that pop
up like are you mindful right now you know comes up during the day a few
times it's a way of kind of hacking the phone to be more about bringing you into the present moment than what it usually does
so that's what I have for that I hope it was helpful great thank you Don
let's um let's go ahead and shift I want to talk about more about this thing
about daily life and mindfulness and daily life um you know
in the very first class one of the things that I talked about was
you know part of the gift of the practice is growing our capacity to
choose reducing our reactivity in life
increasing our ability to respond in life
that this is one of the huge Gifts of this practice and I I kind of think that
um choice is a superpower you know and we grow that as we grow our
mindfulness you know the superpower so
we don't you know we can we we can talk about sitting and practicing every day
and five minutes ten minutes 20 minutes 30 minutes but when you finish a formal meditation
you don't have to stop your commitment to being aware
you can you can keep it with you you can have a sense of
it's kind of good to be aware I like to have a choice I like to not feel like
I'm just reacting to life reacting to my thoughts being driven by my feelings
so one of the ways we can you know kind of develop
um or you know bring our practice into our daily life can be like Donna and I are both saying choosing an activity or
moments in our life so I'm going to invite you if you're willing
to do a little bit of play acting with me
and I'm going to ask you to do this three times three different ways so first is can you bring to mind and
you know something that you do every day for me I'm I'm going to focus on making
my coffee in the morning something that is a routine fairly
simple um but something that you really reliably know you do and
um you know so everybody got something in mind okay
so we're going to be mimes together if
you're willing and so what I want to invite you to do is just first pass we're going to do the
same activity each time okay so I'd like you to imagine so you can
join me at any moment okay I'm pulling out my coffee machine so we're not narrating but I'm just
telling you to get you know and then I'm gonna stop talking and I'm going to show you essentially
what I'm doing right but we're not really going to be looking at each other just know that
because we're all going to be focusing on acting out our little routines so
join me anytime that you feel ready
okay finishing it up
okay so I mean did what you did now this time
as you do it try and be really really aware of
intentionally I'm moving my hand and pouring you so you'll do less
right just be very intentional in your own mind about okay I'm doing this and
feel it notice it just kind of bringing upping
the mindfulness and upping a sense of experiencing your routine okay all right
here we go
okay finish up yeah okay
what did you notice was there a difference yeah
would you anybody you got the mic do you mind saying Alina what the difference was
it slowed down the process it slowed down the process and when you slowed down I was more
it's more mindful more aware more like each step
compared to doing it automatically yeah yeah kind of like mindful beautiful I
like it not so you know not not as automatically that's a great way anybody have another word or
anything that they would say about the difference yes
um yes I was making tea and on the second time I noticed that
like I was feeling how it felt to like open the door handle the cameras Oh it's
like a metal handle and then when I put the mug down it's like a granite
countertop and that kind of makes a sound that I didn't do that the first time and how how often is it we don't
even notice what we're touching or hearing right because we're in automatic
or we're thinking all right so the third pass the third time
we've got the routine we've got increased mindfulness and now what I
want you know this is about remember we're talking about a relationship to
our experience as well we've talked about the word this idea of it our inner posture right
um I like also to think about it just wow we're relating to our experience in a particular way
there's an emotional or relational quality could be curiosity
it could be hatred you know it could be you know
idealizing what you know that we can bring these attitudes um
into even mindfulness right well let's invite in that relationship
that communicates Compassion or caring
like this matters I care
I care and maybe even hey I'm taking care of myself right now
I really I want to make my tea that is so such a sweet gift to myself
I'm gonna make this tea to help me start my day so you ready
all right go for it
and finishing up gently compassionately taking your time don't
have to just drop
did you notice this time did anything change for you
I noticed myself and tasting kind of savoring maybe in a
way that I hadn't been like this idea of like oh yeah I really want to open my senses up
to receive and and you know feel the sense of you know what I'm doing and taking it in
what did others notice
I I notice a sense of gratefulness of like oh and thankful thanks for all to
take care of myself kind of like it's a mundane routine
thing I do but I didn't see it as taking care of myself so I was like oh I'm
thankful for that beautiful do you mind bringing that back
to Chelan thanks
okay so um I was brushing my teeth it's nice because that's what I do before I go to
bed and it's the one thing I can't stand not to do I like to get in bed with
on brushed teeth and um but when we did the third part of the
exercise and I was doing it as a treat to myself and it rather than something
that I had to do yeah I could really get into okay I love I
love the feeling of really clean teeth and this I'm doing for myself you know I
can just enjoy it and so it was made the whole process very different beautiful
so this is this is a great illustration experientially of that the different
kind of relationships we can have with our inner experience
we did the same thing same task but the way we related to the task and
being aware of the task changed the way it impacted us
so this is what we've been trying to point to right is is that inner relationship
to you know how are we being mindful how are we being mindful
yeah yeah just along that line um when you invited us to to
imagine that activity as an act of self-care yeah um I noticed that I also slowed down
yeah and um I also felt more emotion like it felt
like it allowed room for other emotions that I have to be felt like my
father passed away about a month ago and I and I unexpectedly felt
sadness you know like I was allowing myself the space in that act of self-care to just be
present with with myself so beautiful rather than like a fast road kind of thing yeah yeah
so automatic pilot you know shifting out of automatic pilot into mindfulness
right then we do become aware or available
to receive our actual experience and when we're on automatic pilot we
don't really receive it it can't really be processed it can't really be felt
you know and it is in the receiving it and the feeling of it that allows it to
transform even it allows it to kind of move through us in a different kind of way
we end up carrying things around a lot because we don't actually let them be felt
you know or are we ruminate on them in a particular way that kind of keeps them locked in right
so now the question is where do you go from here
this is the end of the five-week series and
you know I want to just invite you to reflect for a moment and
however many times you've been here for this series what are you more aware of
right now
another question for you is what do you want your practice to be
like what do you want it to look like like when you get in a relationship with somebody at some point you talk about
what kind of relationship you would like to have how much time you would like to spend together and what kinds of things
you'd like to talk about you know like to start your day together end your day together right so what do
you want your relationship to be like with this practice
is it something that for you it's good enough to do it on the cushion one time
a day and you know that feels like the gym enough of a gym for you or is it
like oh I actually think I'd like to intersperse it throughout my day or
you know like what what kind of relationship what do you want it to look
like and as you kind of Imagine That
what would help you create that relationship what would support making that happen
so if you're willing it would be nice to hear and to respond to you about you
know what what you would like it to look like or what you think would be supportive or helpful and then I can
tailor some of what I talk about in terms of other things available other
practices um or I can just you know talk about them
but if anybody has any anything in particular they would like to share please find a mic
yeah great
um well I was just up visiting my grandchildren and
I wanted very much to be able to be coming from my center and being with
them in a really calm way and they are not calm
and so I I'm just I you know I what I what I did the few times where I was
just kind of like now what am I going to do what I did was I said what am I grateful
for right now and then I you know and I could just say I'm I'm just so grateful
to be with them and that was kind of letting go of this other fantasy I had
of how we were going to hold you together not quite it wasn't quite there
but but it it helped it helped get me centered because I get out of myself
yeah and and I'm out there instead of yeah here so yeah beautiful and do you
have a sense of what would help you you know it sounds like you did a beautiful thing and what would support you and and
continuing to grow that capacity to come not be out there but to be in here
I I think that in addition to what I do which is
to sit in the morning it would be to give myself maybe
a couple of times during the day where I just took back took myself back and and didn't get so
caught up out there and just just kind of settled back in great and I I you
know it's it's hard yeah so what you said is so lovely and I'm not sure everybody could hear because
I'm sorry but I didn't want to stop you because you were it was coming together for you right okay yeah
but um so you you're thinking that it would be helpful to stop a couple times
during the day to kind of actually literally invite yourself to come back home yes yes yeah beautiful because I I
start off the day and then I'm gone right right at least with my
grandchildren are around and they're seven and five so what a precious thing yeah thank you for sharing anybody else
oh great I see somebody else getting a mic
I didn't realize this was the last of the series is that right tonight is there another series coming up yeah
there'll be um yes so I can we can talk afterwards no no I'm going
to talk about that okay as part of but anybody else want to say anything about kind of yes great and then I'll
come back to your question okay because I also wanted to get tips of during the pandemic I got completely out of
meditation and I just I really have been for the last few weeks making I have to get back into it so I just came I
thought well this will get me going because it's open now and there's people here and I can't do zoom and listening
to things and sitting at home so great yeah I want some more ideas perfect
so I appreciate the question of what do you want it to look like because that invites a decision
um and um I forget what else you asked but one of the things that I was just thinking
or you asked what does it look like or um you know for and for me I'm just very
aware that there's a choice and there's a difference between how I
experience my inner life when I am meditating more regularly and when I'm not
and so something that would be really helpful for me would be to have a
regular Circle that I can come and sit with and you know regular talk that I can come to
at least once a week and I'm just arriving in Palo Alto so
um new to the area and hoping to find that so great
okay so I think I'll um I'm running over my time a little bit
but I'm gonna I need to say a few more things and I think it's important so
so at at IMC we have a number of different things different options I'll
start with just Thursday night because you're all here right and you're available on Thursday nights so next
week the net for the next three weeks um just in person I won't be streaming
on YouTube but um I'll be talking about establishing a practice and and so and
I'll be here I'm kind of really wanting to respond to whatever questions and I have lots of material to share but I
also will make myself very available to what what's going on how it's going questions about the center or things
like that so um and Don and I will both be here next Thursday and so
um so that's one place to continue this conversation right sort of to learn more
um there's also um like Monday nights there's in person with a Dharma talk and a
I think it's a 45-minute meditation and then there's Sunday mornings here
which is a Dharma talk or a like a 35 40 minute meditation and a Dharma talk
afterwards and sometimes on Sundays there's tea social tea and sometimes
there's potlucks sometimes there's occasionally there's like a community meeting so that's
another opportunity um let's see there's also I know not for
you but there's happy hour which is every night during the week at 6 PM it's
a loving kindness practice on Zoom from six to seven which is lovely it's one of
my favorite things and it's a you know combination of a guided loving-kindness
practice and then small group breakouts so you get to talk to people from all over the world who
have been coming really for a long time to this little Sangha of meta loving kindness
and that's a lovely support that's there and then every morning Gill on YouTube
or whoever's covering for him does morning meditation with a
um like a I think it's is it is it a half hour guided meditation and then a
15-minute darmet so just a short little like nugget for you for the day
um and Wednesday is a half day so that's like uh you come and you have a sit and
then you walking meditation and then another sit in a dormant so it's a
wonderful practice and then you can bring we do Sangha cleaning together
then we meet in a circle out in the community hall and then you're invited to bring your lunch and sit down and
connect with each other afterwards
is that yeah but not the cleaning yeah the circle in the lantern
yeah 9 30. yeah starts at 9 30 and I think
officially the outside circles at 12 15. so but then there's lunch afterwards so
those are some of the things that IMC offers um and there's more there's day longs
and in fact this Saturday there's a day long an introduction to
mindfulness meditation day long taught by Bruni Davila and so it's like 9 30 to 4 or 9 to 4 30.
nine to four thirty nine to four Thirty so it's a nice and she'll be giving
instructions on breath mindfulness of breathing mindfulness of body mindful of
emotions mindfulness of thinking and open awareness practice throughout the day
and bring your lunch and then I'll be co-teaching a class
with Diana Clark in uh March thank you on the five hindrances
and the five hindrances are the five things that tend to interfere with our meditation practice
so and we'll be using the Wizard of Oz as a reference point and so it will be
very fun I'm very excited and then in April I'll be doing this class again so so that's
some things that are going to be coming your way can I interject here yeah especially for all of you are most
welcome and especially for those of you who are constrained to YouTube I'll also be offering an introductory series on
loving kindness meditation starting March 11th it's a five-week series it's
much like this except that the focus is on meta kindness and compassion
cultivation so and that'll be on Zoom or YouTube that will be on YouTube and um
actually I know for a fact it'll be on Zoom I think it'll only be on YouTube after the fact
so if you want the interaction with people you can register by looking at the IMC
calendar there'll be a link on a set on Saturday it's on Saturdays starting
March 11th and it's from 9 30 a.m to 11 A.M five Saturdays and then the
following Saturday I'm doing a half day so there's a lot of stuff happening a
lot of stuff going on um so
there was a question on YouTube which is how do we decide which meditation
technique to use and I think the simplest the funnest way
to answer that is to share a story about another teacher in our tradition named Natalie Goldberg and she also is a Zen
practitioner and she was sitting with tick not Han many of you know tignan Han
and she asked him how he kept his practice alive you know for all those years and he he
smiled the rice sweet smile she says and he said to her so you want to know my secret
she nodded eagerly I do whatever works and change when it no longer works
so the idea of what do we how do we decide what kind of practice what to be
doing you know we've taught you a lot this was a smorgasm board of you know
meditation practices and I always like to say start with what's easiest
right you encounter the least resistance you get your momentum going so start
where it's easiest start what calls to you start what feels right and there's a lot of research on change
and it shows that you know smaller commitments smaller bites is much easier
to sustain and feel motivated instead of getting discouraged so
um so with that we'll open up for a few more questions
before we close yep grab the mic and
there's yeah I just wanted to say that I find it
really helpful to tune in to the morning
fit and then the Dharma really short Dharma talk and it starts at seven
o'clock if you want to be on time but it'll it it's on YouTube the rest of the
day and actually if you miss a day you can go back and catch up on that day and so I I think it's it's so available that
it doesn't mean that you have to be up at 7 A.M yeah that's what I wanted to say thank you
get the mic get the mic oh you were scratching your head okay
any other questions requests comments
how this has been for you if you've been coming to the quest anything you want to share about that
it's also welcome even just today yeah even just today yeah
yeah she has a question um
I this is my first time doing this class and I attended the four noble truths
class as well last year um and I feel like I really enjoy the
interactive aspect of it a lot um like something that I think happened a few times in the four noble truths was
actually like small breakout groups when there were enough people um and I feel like that was it was just
so nice to talk to people and share what we were going through and so so we'll be
doing that the next three weeks and the four hindrances class awesome yeah I just really I love five entrances
[Laughter] yes I'm glad to hear that they're really helpful to me I really love offering
that so good hopefully you'll be here definitely great
I just wanted to thank both you Dawn and you Tanya this has been a really good uh
five-week class although we missed last week and we are starting to invoke
more mindfulness in our daily life it just yesterday we were at the airport
and um situation got a little stressful I
remembered that it was a good time to practice
mindfulness and then that was that was very helpful
so I can remember another time I was um I used when I was driving more I had a
practice of being at Red stop lights and using that as a moment to practice mindfulness
because normally you're in a mindset where you have to be
somewhere and this red light is preventing you darn it so yeah
uh yeah so I really you asked the question of where I where I want to take
this practice and for me um as far as it will go and there's
there's so much I'm learning that and so much unknown that I feel like it really
I don't know where it's gonna take me right now so I don't know what it looks
like I can't imagine it right so that's great wonderful yeah living on the edge
of the mystery
is that it more comments and questions
it's great it's been fun to be here with you guys it's really really nice and very fun to
teach with Don yes yeah totally fun this is our first time teaching together yeah
and Sally's our Lifesaver and Richard our amazing recorder
who's also the great you know helper with sitting posture and encouraging you
talk to him afterwards he'll encourage you along just keep going he'll tell you so it's a team we're a team here
glad you're a part of it so um so let's see
I'm just just a reminder that at IMC you know this place exists because of
volunteers it's an all volunteer kind of Sangha the building was bought
by people's donations to the song God it's not you know there's nobody here
that gets paid for anything it's all all the teaching all everything so
um and member there's no membership other than your desire to you know
have a mind that's present in a heart that's available to this world so in ourselves
so to me that's a very inspiring thing and you're here and you can keep coming
as much as you want and if you want to become more involved in the center there's lots of opportunities for
volunteering so that was helpful for me when I came here I liked having a
I don't know it made me comfortable to have a job right and like I felt like a little bit more like I belonged so
so let's um I have one practice of dedication of Merit I think we have time to share with
you all which is the dedication of Merit this idea is that you know everything we're
doing we're doing it for the benefit of ourselves for the benefit others and
both so without exception all beings
and that's a big topic right a big idea of all beings everywhere
so I'd like to invite anyone who's interested to maybe name a group of people that
that are thinking about right now that they have um that they want to invoke us to think
about some people one person um said all the people in in cages
meaning people in prison you know he wanted us to think about them and um so is there any group of people
or any beings that you would like us to bring to mind as we dedicate our Merit
here's the mic right there yeah the rohingya beakapo in Myanmar
thank you women and girls in Afghanistan
beautiful you could pass the mic and just you
don't you people don't need to speak into it just hand it around if anybody wants to say something great
and YouTube you can type in there if you want the name something
um I guess people who this is like a vague term but just
people who dedicate their lives to helping others in a very real way and
maybe not expecting a lot in return to beautiful
beautiful
all these beings that have been named and everyone we didn't name may all beings benefit from our practice
including ourselves right without exception
[Music] thank you
and that's it Don and I will be here and as well as Sally and Richard if you guys have any questions afterwards and hope
to see you back