so hello everyone is it loud enough you to hear yeah
go sometimes um the challenge of meditating before
giving a talk is that there's nothing to talk about
now so I'm thinking of the solstice which
happened a few days ago and that now we're in a sense we're
turning towards the the time of light and there's a saying that goes
something like we are conceived in the
dark and born out of the dark we are born BN into the
light and we grow in the light so there with the
seasons we go into the darkness and that has its own value and
now we go out for those of us in Northern hem hemisphere we go going out into the light when we
meditate in our tradition we tend to close our eyes so it is a rhythm of a
kind of um going into the dark and then we open the eyes and we're
going back out into the light and what is it that's conceived
when we close our eyes to meditate what is it that is born out of
meditation that then is Born Into the Light of our social life or work life or
lived life and not only that but grows in that light in that
life and this rhythm of going into meditation and coming out is actually a very important one where we a retreat
tradition so we put a lot of emphasis on going off on meditation Retreats and um and there's a rhythm
with those as well some people it's it's a yearly Rhythm maybe once a year they go and Retreat and it's important part
of the year is to go in there and and something shifts something changes something is touched into something is
born that then is brought back into the world uh and practice in the world or
explored in the world or applied into the world and then after a while we go back into meditation and then that
Rhythm and that rhythm is something that um uh goes back to the time of the
Buddha when monastics who were the primary practitioners back then who do
lots of practice go retreats uh had a lifestyle where 3 months of the
year they would uh do what's called The reigns Retreat where they'd stay put in
one place in order to practice practice a lot of meditation hear teachings and
things like that and after the rains retreat they would go out into the world
and wander around Northern India and that tradition continued in
variety of Buddhist countries and and I was told that in Korea they have that pattern where monastics would gather for
a monastery for a 3-month period of the rains and the end of those three months they all monks scatter and then they
come back the next time around that rhythm of coming and going when I was at the tasahara Zen
Monastery here in California down in down in the in Los padris National
Forest in the middle of it in Santa Cruz mountain in the Big Sir mountains
um we had that similar Rhythm where we would have the winter time we would just
be alone in this little Valley in the middle of the Wilderness with the river going through it practicing with a small
group of people and a lot of meditation a lot of silence and um and then rather than
scattering at the end of that period uh during the summer from May to Labor Day
in September the um would be what's called guest season
and the rather than going out into the world the world would come in and it was kind of a partly a resort and people
would come to a monastery to Resort and um and uh and as a
practitioner there I felt it was very important that Rhythm that by the end of
the winter um there was something very important about meeting all these guests in the more complicated life of the
guest season and uh all the social intera actions and happen there that
applying what I'd learned uh having attested by what I encountered as we
went through the that monast you know this worldly life of all these
activities and um it allowed something to grow and develop though by September I was ready
for the guests to go and I was ready to drop into the
silence again and and return to some kind of deeper place of being that was
the kind of the place of Genesis the place of something being conceived something being different kind of has a
chance to be born from that really settled place so our tradition is a retreat TR
tradition but regularly I've thought it's rather unfortunate that we call it them
Retreats and um and yesterday I looked up the atmology and the history of this
word retreat and um and it means it comes from French and then from Latin
but in French uh it meant something like uh to pull back to step backwards and it
was originally used U as a military term for the military to retreat when there
was a need for that in the in battle and then uh but then at some point it became
a religious term for in about the in the in the 1700s apparently a religious term
meant uh religious people going off pulling back from something in order to
be in seclusion to do their kind of spiritual life and then a few decades later it was it became apparently for a
while a term used for um um institutions
to house the mentally ill they they get to go and
Retreat and um but still this pulling away so I think
it's kind of unfortunate uh that we call it Retreats pulling back uh pulling away like you're
leaving something behind that my my if I could redo the English language I would
uh call our Retreat centers return centers not because you're returning the
that damaged goods but uh rather that it's a place to
return to yourself and and um because uh what what I found through meditation practice just
sitting here now partly why I didn't have wasn't kind of ready to speak when we
started was um was there's a return to a place of inner psychological Health
there's a return to a sense of Harmony everything when if it goes well in meditation it's a return in a sense to
much closer to who I fully am than how I am if I'm out about uh especially this
season out I went on the roads a few days ago and boy it was like crazy the cars and the people and the lines and
the stores and and uh actually I enjoyed myself because these in the lines because I thought this is just as good a
place to meditate as any I'll just do standing meditation here and if I can't do standing
meditation here then I probably can't do it anywhere you know I should be able to do
it here too and so I actually enjoyed it standing there and I and I kind of looked forward to next door with the
next long line and um but anyway this frazzled
kind of uh life that we can live and I I sometimes feel disconnected to some degree for myself that sometimes I only
realize when I sit down to meditate and then by meditating something begins softening and relaxing
and um and the fragmented quality of my life settles down and the fragments come
into harmony get settled and the way that the mind gets more
peaceful uh also it harmonizes it settles it stabilizes there's a idea of
unification that's part of meditation practice and this unification means everything comes together in a kind of
unity and when everything's in unity then no parts are working against each
other uh partly to make a point you can disagree you will but I want to kind of
religious people make uh hyperbole a lot so I can get away with it sometimes so
in case you don't like what I'm about to say uh but uh but the uh the um whenever
you're carrying around tension in your muscles you're in conflict with
something is that interesting idea might not be 100% true but uh it's a very
interesting idea that many times I think that we're in conflict with something and if we're living with that
tension chronically all day long week after week month after month decade after
decade uh then we're living constantly in some kind of conflict something we don't want something we're protecting
ourselves from something that we're trying to push away something some ambition we're trying to
attain and that and ends up a kind of alienation from ourselves
and to sit down and meditating and let the tension dissolve and relax then that sense of conflict
disappears and we're not we're not in conflict with any part of ourselves and this wonderful possibility
of breathing being alive settled here with nothing no opposition to what's
happening in this psychophysical being is a remarkable experience and I when I when I've
touched into this in clear way ways to me it feels like uh this is
Health this is what being healthy is like I have this issue uh one of my
little delusions that I sometimes comes affects me is if I get
sick um at some point I'm no longer really sick I'm just a little bit
sick I'm getting better and I'm I'm still really tired or achy or something
and and and my delusion is I don't want to believe I'm still sick and I'll have
these thoughts Gil you're probably fooling yourself you're probably not really sick and maybe this not this
you're a lazy or you're something you know and like I'm and then because I
can't quite tell I I can't quite believe it but then the next day oh now I'm
healthy you know this is what health is you know I really know so the same thing
psychologically spiritually we can have a sense oh now this is
health so when we go on these so-called Retreats that's the place where we
return to who we are much more and we pull back from that we
withdraw from that for whatever reason we Retreat from that when we go back into the world all
too easily and uh and so there's a loss of
ourselves and from a meditator point of view um meditation is not an altered
state of mind it's the normal state of mind it's the healthy State of Mind the
alternate State of Mind is how people are walking around in everyday life that's pretty altered full of greed and
hate and fear and anxiety and that's what's the of finding the mind and so this return so you know we
could call these return centers the Insight return
center and um and and someone says you know so you say you're you're going to
tomorrow you're going to start a new return as opposed to a new
Retreat it's a returning a returning and um so this rhythm of this
turn to something deep inside to Harmony wholeness and all that and that the
deeper kind of possibilities uh of meditation that Buddhism offers uh come
uh come from or uh arise out of this kind of return to a healthy way of being
being settled whole no longer living in Conflict no longer living with this
tension that we can often carry in our daily life and um and that's kind of that that
state is not the end end state for Buddhist practice but in that state of
health we can feel that there's a calling there's an onward leading nature
there's a way in which the heart wants to continue with something
profound and that profound thing that wants to be that wants to be born is all
kinds of things and U but what is it that wants to be born is a wonderful
question what wants to be born and and how do we allow it to be
born in us and that's one of the functions of meditation is to create the
room in our hearts in our minds in our body to allow something to be born that
wants to be born in out of the darkness when we go through serious
psychological challenges emotional challenges really depressed
really feel betrayed feel angry really feel like we've lost
something profound relief grief with anger whatever fear all these
difficulties that people struggle with I think there can be less
struggle around it all if we appreciate that in the right conditions in the
heart of them something wants to be born what is that what wants to be
born sometimes we're so reactive so caught up so judgmental so disturbed by
the emotions we have sometimes we even receive messages our society you're not
supposed to be this way and that makes it harder as well the meditation life is a life that
somehow we allow ourselves the possibility to feel the difficult emotions we have
meditation life is a possib time when we we give ourselves a possibility of experiencing the positive
emotions that we capable of having some people those are hard to experience both of them in their heart
there's something in there that wants to be born that's the nature of our inner life there is something seeds that want
to be born and when we in this state of health when really learn to settle and not be
in conflict with things including not be in conflict with the difficult
emotions and create the space to allow something in the darkness
to come forth we don't
know what is being conceived in the darkness if we think we have to know
everything we're maybe sure changing ourselves elves part of the subtleness
of meditation is to allow ourselves not to know to really feel ourselves deeply and
not know because you can't know what's happening in the darkness
within and even if it's like The Dark Night of the Soul kind of time things seem really
challenging something wants to be born what is it that wants to be born if you don't make the if you don't
make space for that possibility it might get might never be
born so to see meditation as a time to really trust being here present there's
a possibility of Inner Health that comes from just letting go and settling and
getting focused arriving and being here in the present moment in a full intimate kind
of kind of you know a committed
way it allows for whole other possibilities that cannot happen if we
stay distracted and so little bit you know to
challenge you it's when you're
distracted that you have withdrawn that you've retreated because You' you think
you've lost the battle Maybe
it's coming back and sitting here returning here that our life can come to a kind of
fulfillment that can't come when we're distracted caught up
intense so we're at this kind of Junction of the year that uh it's gotten become darker
and darker until Thursday when it was the darkest day of the year for the
Northern Hemisphere and
um and who knows what that has been for you maybe it's like the rhythm of
sleeping most people sleep at night and then they awake during the day who knows what was going settling and quieting
down and who knows what was what was happening as the days got darker and
darker for you maybe it was in very important time to slow down important time to do less less to be outdoors and
do a lot of things and now we turn towards the
light and now is a time to be particularly receptive what wants to be born out of
that so with the solstice on Thursday and in a week or so there's the new
year I'd like to propose that we have this wonderful limal
time to be careful with ourselves this next during this
period because at new years's there's a custom of making a
resolution for their year so but most
people I think are not really making the resolutions very well it's wishful
thinking what I propose for you is that you use this next week to ask yourself
what is it that wants to be born in you what is it that wants to sprout what is it that wants to come out
into life if you sit quietly if you go for walks quietly if you if you try not
to be if you avoid being too busy during the season and spend some time being kind of connected to yourself feeling
yourself sensing maybe meditate a little extra and maybe in medit coming on of
meditation maybe you can ask your question what is it that wants to be born in me what is it that this time of
the year as the as the light as light gets longer daylight gets longer and longer and symbolizes this way in which
something gets born into the light and grows in the light what is it that wants
to be born in you if you get no answer it's fantastic
that you spend time with that sensitivity to feel for it or sense it so don't worry don't feel
bad you don't know what's going on you don't know what's being gestating in there so don't worry about that but if
you come with something that what you feel oh that's what wants to be born that's when you
make the resolution resolve for that resolve to feed that and let that grow and and
develop in you care for what what wants to sprout
and um maybe it's something directly related to meditation directly related to a life of
mindfulness and Compassion maybe it's something directly related to a life of
service caring for the people around you because that's what wants to be born
or maybe it's uh so many possibilities maybe it's a life of
honesty maybe it's a life life that's not being driven by fear or driven
by desires or anger Hill
will maybe it's a life that for the
next 10 11 months does the inner
work that would prepare all all of us for the
[Laughter]
elections don't let you be don't don't let yourself be surprised prepare for the best best that
you have the world no matter what happens the world needs the best we have to offer
always let that be grow and develop in the light so what is it that wants to be
born so
th so those are my thoughts and uh now I welcome you if
anyone you have any comments or questions or so in the back Martha in
the
corner hi I just wanted to point out that the uh winter newsletter uh there's a copy when you go out the door has an
article an excellent article by Kim Allen uh in fact on resolutions since it
is the beginning of the year you might find it interesting nice the newsletter has an
article and makes making
resolves
uh how do you think about setbacks in life so often we visualize goals or we set resolutions and you know maybe it's
health related and then you fall ill or you know uh you want to run and then you get injured um how are you using your
practice to I guess respond to these moments uh well I think this Pro
so didn't help okay so
um um I mean one of the two two ways that I want to mention three many so many ways
but one way is that um the healing from these kinds of things works better if there's no
tension if there's profound rest and not just the rest of getting enough sleep but even deeper deeper rest and um so
when I've been sick I just I will rest really I'll go to bed and not just lay
there sometimes I lay there my eyes closed and kind of meditate and relax and just try to get as deep rest as I
can um and uh and support Aid that rest because then things seem to heal
better and um and so and then to let go of tension that we
have to let go of the tensions of it being different as often protests in the mind and anger at how we are I know
people who have had injuries that seemed like horrific injuries really changed their life the rest of their life they
were in you know maybe infid or something and um I I don't want to belittle the challenges of that and how
difficult it is but there are some people who after many years will say it was the best thing that happened to them
because they had to really the more they were challenged the more they were upset the more that they had to give up uh
when you're practicing the more realize that represents something very deep inside deep attachment deep holding on
deep expectations deep sense of identity that we have and so this practice allows us to really go in there and question
where am I still holding on what you know because why am I so disappointed or
discouraged and go in there and find what that is and let go of it and then
uh the whatever the injury has been which maybe was a permanent injury uh is not seen as a as a as a as a problem but
more as an asset because it gave a certain kind of inner Freedom that wouldn't have happened
otherwise and um so that's some of the ways meditation
can help that was that satisfying enough than
yeah may I ask uh why are you asking oh
um Mike um I I ask cuz I think of you know setbacks whether they're injuries
or you know failures in your life as uh you know moments that can shake your
your sense of self and uh you know stray you from your progress or your goals or
you know whatever things in life are that get you out of bed every day and I think in each religious practice it's
important to kind of identify how your faith structure you know helps you
respond to those whether it's you know familial death or you know something like that that just really is
something that's difficult so great thank you that's very nice so maybe if
we understand how we can use these things not as a setback but as some
allow something beneficial to happen then maybe it's a set
forward hi Gail um again I had a um question as you were asking you know
what is waiting to be born um you know meditation at least um has
helped me understand a bit more of my own suffering but I feel it has also
particularly this time of the year also made me a little more attuned uh to the suffering of others in your family um
and and other places but there is sort of this mix of um helplessness that you feel when
people aren't quite being able to help themselves but you you ALS also really only can go so far how do you you know
how do you deal with that sense of wanting to be of service but not quite knowing exactly um what may be able to
help particularly when these are situations of uh of psychological and mental he well the the simple answer
that hopefully respects the complexity and the fullness of your life and all that is that there's probably more than
just wanting to help them the wanting has extra baggage and so if you look at your
desire to to help someone or support someone or companion someone in their difficulties what is that extra that
you're bringing and that's one of the things if
you ask that question and then really get quiet and really look and feel what are all the motivations that are behind
you and the needs and the desires we're and the way to one of the ways to to to um to find answers to these questions
question s that I think can be very helpful and practical is to uh feel your
way literally physically to where the tension and the stresses around this issue and that
sometimes can reveal uh uh once you find the stress levels you can kind of
sometimes then start feeling the emotions behind it and you realize it's not just compassion but there's also
some kind of fear and once you recognize the fear then oh there's more here than just wanting to be
compassionate thanks
Gil hi Gale you the example you gave of when you were still sick but you thought
that it would be time for you to be healed um is that does that have happen
because we um we're not in touch with ourselves or
is it is it because it doesn't match our goals anymore to be
sick um and how can how can we help that how can we see that more
clearly um I think it and it helps to look at what the beliefs you have around
it and and also a little bit maybe it helps to understand your personality your disposition towards things and um
number of things that I affects me so I don't know what goes for you one is um I
I really enjoy doing things
just it's just you know I'm a doer kind of person so I I enjoy it and so I'm
just ready to do something okay I'm ready but you're sick
no yes no can't be true so that's part of it uh sometimes it has
to do with the sense of responsibility responsibility is prob probably my achilles
heal and so I have to do something I have to respond to that email no you're sick no
but something like that and what can help what can help seeing
that that that really helps the most is to see the tricks of the Mind how it
works so you don't uh uh otherwise if you don't see what the mind is doing in
terms of the tricks the beliefs the attitudes the fears then uh uh we we then what we're
trying to do is trying to override it and that is often creates even more
tension hi um thank you for your talk um so I I have a kind of a a deep health
condition or or Challenge and then I have my meditation and in my mind they've
actually never met it it's like never occurred to me at all well how could your meditation
practice address or help so which begs the question then um is there a
particular way that when I meditate do I think of it as addressing the Health Challenge or do I just kind of uh keep
going and not is there some specific thing that I do to make them meet this is a this is a
great question Beverly we appreciate it a lot and um so you know I don't feel
like I know you well enough to answer you specifically so if this misses you or don't take it too
personally um so it's possible that
um you have you have to distinguish between two challenges there's the Health Challenge
which is the literal things you have to actually do do the research talk to the
doctors do the exercises physical whatever it might be the things you should
do and but in in the Dharma those wouldn't be called
challenges those are just things to do in the Dharma we call challenges psychological challenges around them the
frustration the anger the many yeah so so the the how to bring
mindfulness to that is to recognize what those psychological challenges are maybe
get a write them down just really make a list of all that just kind of get a sense of the Ecology of the
psychological things going on when you call it you're challenged the anger the
frustration the impatience the the hopelessness they all just make make the
list and then uh choose one and spend some time
uh uh under looking looking looking at the Ecology of that particular challenge
what are the beliefs what are the emotions what are the Body Sensations body stresses tensions that come along
what are the emotions what are the Mind States what are the stories kind of
begin kind of unraveling all the pieces of that ecological system around that one thing
like impatience and then and then the more you could unravel and see the different
pieces of the ecosystem it might be easier for you to
then sit in the middle of it and breathe and this is where the meditation comes into play in meditation stop
thinking about all this that's what you do other times meditation now you can better identify y it and sit in the
middle of the complex and just breathe with it and see what
happens does that that make some sense uh yes thank
you hello hi Gil um I have a question about
um so sometimes um I need to do something like
I it's let's say this is I work I I must do something um but I'm not sure what is
the right thing to do and by the right thing to do is
usually um like in the moral sense of the word um is what is what Moral Moral Moral
what's the moral thing to do with work oh this is a good this I love it when people have this question uh I don't
love the challenge of knowing how to answer the question so um and some sometimes it's
really hard I I think left and right and back and forth and I'm not sure what's the right thing to do how can this
practice uh help in that sense well one of the things is when we if we can
return into some deep sense of uh feeling connected deeply to ourselves and feel in harmony with ourselves so
that we're not operating on fear or or on anger or confusion or delusions a lot
of kind of spinning stories we get below the story level then in in a in a moral
sense we can be more in touch with the the ethical deep deep ethical Sensi
sensitivity and Sensibility that we're capable of and then you might be easier
to understand what to do may be easy to understand what you have to do even though it's not
popular or understand what you have to do even though it might mean losing your job or you know you know giving up your
job um but if we are too anxious about this uh and even if we know that this a
moral issue but we're so anxious about trying to figure it out they were so we're spinning out in storying spinning
around the mind uh we might not be in the best state of mind to really address
it so one of the things our practice can do is to have this return to some deeper
sensibility who we are that's one the other thing is that this practice
mindfulness a lot to do with understanding what our relationship is to any challenge we
have and so there might be get there also there might be fear in relationship to it or desire in relationship to it or
a lot of selfing in relationship to it what do people think think of me for example and so to clarify that how we're
relating to the challenge uh might simplify our ability to understand what the real issues are that have to be
solved that's something else another thing that practice can do is that uh it
can mindfulness of speaking and mindfulness of listening can uh if we if
we practice it can help us slowly learn maybe uh how to have honest
communication I figure out how to speak honestly without uh challenging other
people but letting other people know that you're challenged you know I have this ethical issue around this and can
we talk about it and and I I feel like I'm left alone to make this ethical decision but it's going to affect the
company we're in is there some place I can go where we can kind of brainstorm or go back and forth and find out and I
can get some clarity around this and and I don't know if where you work there's any possibility of that or if a colleague you can go for
a lunch walk during a lunch break and have this kind of conversation so this idea of using the practice in
conversation so that we can have clear more honest conversations about the very
thing I like to believe that mindfulness that honesty is mindfulness out
loud so that we're learning how to not just keep it to ourselves but learning to process it uh in relationship to
other people as well those are some ideas than so last
one was next to you oh it was saying that was okay
great okay so maybe uh uh given this
very special time of the year turning into the light and we're all kind of doing that together here in person if uh
you would like to turn to a few people next to you and say hello and and um see
what they want to do with this growing light as we get bored into it and uh
introduce yourself and but look around so that you kind of you say hello to two
at least two other people so no one's left alone kind of