so uh a little announcement to begin with is that I uh really
um value your feedback as participants and
um I'd be very interested since we're all in this together
um if you could especially give me suggestions for improvement
so thank you very much for that in advance and I can't read the chat while I'm
teaching but I'll hopefully download it afterwards and and we'll read it then so thank you
very much I appreciate it so
um this week we're exploring how we might
train and emptiness as a way of countering our instinctive
habitual and reactive reoccupation with the self
which is often expressed as you know in discursive thinking
so when we meditate we can allow ourselves to drop down into the flow of
our lived experience rather than reifying it into self-referential
thinking so for these minutes of meditation
the invitation I propose to you is to keep in mind
that we are as Vera bonellio says dropping the burden of the ego
so take your meditation posture
create a feeling of being grounded and settled
and then balancing that with being quietly energetic
especially in the spine
what was in the eyes that's comfortable for you
I'm taking a deep breath and connecting with the flow of breathing
they're being friends with our body and we'll Begin by offering it meta
as we do a brief fluid scan
so we bring kindness and appreciation to this body
from the head down through the neck your shoulders
the arms and hands meta
in the Torso going down into the pelvis
and into the legs and the feet
still in touch with the flow of the breathing and breathing out
we light a little candle of meta in the heart
letting it warm and reassure this body and mind
just as we are
and now dissolving the edges of our hearts and body
we radiate arnetta unconditional friendliness
through all of the participants who are meditating with us here
May everyone in this sun go be well
letting our Metal Flow out to each and every one of the people who are here
today meditating together
when letting go of the words and radiating just the feeling of meta to
everyone
benevolence as we connect with the physical process
of this body breathing
dropping the burden of fabricating thoughts
robbing the burden of the ego
we know that it's enough just to be here
present with his beautiful sound gun breathing
no need to indulge the ego in thinking
and so we offer our presence to each other
and feeling the support knowing that we're all breathing
together
dropping the burden of the ego we can luxuriate
in the wholesome feeling of being present present with the breathing
and present with one another
the body and mind imbued with a sense of meta
benevolence as we stay with our lived experience
breathing together in the warm companionship
of our fellow practitioners
and if the ego pushes its way into our consciousness
by fabricating thoughts we see it and we say no thank you
we know we don't need to invest in thinking now
it's not nearly as beautiful as being here breathing
with this song God
thrilling in the flow of our lived experience
empty of Fabrications empty of proliferations
just the goodness of being here
with our most important Ally
mindfulness awareness
awareness imbued with mitta
experiencing the flow of phenomena
not adding any self-reference
to bring this collaborative meditation through clothes
we each open our hearts and reopen the boundaries
of our son God
to include well-wishing for all beings everywhere
may all beings be safe and protected
being safe may we all be contented
at ease
may all beings abide in peace
and may all beings everywhere be free
I do honor your practice and your sincerity
and I feel a great gratitude for this practice
yesterday uh participant commented that it was a nice moment
when we all bow in unison around the world at the completion of the meditation
so throughout this meditation let's join our hands together
and bow through each other
thank you greetings everyone good to be here with
you
um give again a short announcement that I made at the beginning of the meditation
which is that I really value your feedback
in the chat and uh since we're all in this together
I your suggestions for improvement would be especially welcome
and um we'll have a q a session on Friday
after the talk
so this week we're exploring how we might
train and emptiness as a way of countering our instinctive
habitual and reactive reoccupation with the self
offer expressed as discursive thinking
what is emptiness in the early Buddhist texts
emptiness is not that we don't exist or that we're not important
it only means that living beings do not have
substantial and permanent selves
and especially in meditation when the Mind slows down enough we can see
that everything is in flux
and since we're constantly changing in reality there is nothing that we can
identify as a self
so today I'd like to uh share with you um the teachings of a very important
discourse the shorter discourse on emptiness
121 and
um I'll read to you um parts of it at the beginning from my own
translation and of course I've used all the translations of all the great
um Scholars especially the monastic Scholars um and
I I did this as part of a course in poly that I took this past year
and my interest was to go into each poly word and study the etymology and The
Roots behind where the word came from and to choose uh renderings that best
Express this and also um as a lay practitioner I have a different
point of view than um monastics do especially male dynastics
so it's a beautiful discourse and um
it begins that the scene is set at 70 in
the palace or the Hall of megaro's mother
so this is where it's it's like a building with pillars and this is where the Buddha and his monastic song are
were meditating
then what it was evening the venerable Amanda Rose for meditation
went to the blessed one and after paying homage to him he sat
down at one side and said the blessed one
better will serve on one occasion the blessed one was living in the second country
where there's a town of the stockings named nagaraka
their venerable sir I learned from the Blessed one's own lips
you know he's quoting what the Buddha had said to him at that time
now Ananda I often abide in emptiness
and then Ananda goes on to say did I hear that correctly vulnerable sir
do I learned that correctly attend to that correctly remember that
correctly so you can you can sort of picture Ananda really wondering what the heck is
talking about uh abiding in emptiness
so uh the Buddha replies now Ananda
I often abide in emptiness
and um he said you did certainly
uh you heard that correct they learned that correctly attended to that correctly
remembered that correctly Aranda just as this Hall where we are is
empty of elephants cattle and horses
and there is present only this non-emptiness namely the Oneness of the
sun gun monistics
so here the Buddha is um this is the just the beginning of of
this discourse but the point he's making here is that um
what's in important is to know what uh things are empty of
um to know not just what's present but what's absent so he used the example of
all these monks sitting in this fall meditating in the evening and saying so we we can know that there
aren't elephants and cattle and horses and other animals here
but what we do know is here is the song God and so in that situation
the Sangha is the non-emptiness the presence
and so um in the early text there's uh the use
of the word emptiness as a noun is quite rare um
most of the time it's when the Buddha or someone is talking about
what something is empty of
and um what we're supposed to understand as
practitioners is that whatever is present in our experience is empty of a self
and what belongs to a self empty of what is Everlasting
or unchanging so you may have heard other teachers
talk about the Bahia sutta it's a very famous One
and um in that certain the Buddha instructs
Bahia with a really beautiful kernel of what
we're supposed to do as practitioners and the Buddha says in the scene there
should just be the scene in the herd there should just be the
herd in the sense just what is sensed
and in the cognized just what is cognized
so we stay present with whatever sensory information we're getting from the the
six senses and we know that
and we see um especially if we can slow the Mind down
and take a break from proliferations that everything is in flux and is
changing so fast that uh there really is nothing that we could
pinpoint and say okay now this right here right now is is what the what
this elephants so our job is to
um be able to stay present and emptying ourself of our
proliferations of all that mental chatter
um elsewhere the Buddha instructs
do not think of the past and do not long for the future
in the present moment want you to tend with mindfulness
for the lack of stability of whatever phenomenon there are
the whys awaken in this way
so this is what we were exploring yesterday
is by paying attention to um
the fluidity of our experience and letting the mind
uh quiet down we're able to see things as they really
are and it's there is no way that we can pinpoint anything that would be
substantial or permanent Everlasting
so um
mindfulness is really the uh the most
important tool in our arsenal of tools to walking the path to Freedom
because this is where we this is is by placing our awareness where we place our awareness
is um determines
um which way we evolve if we place our awareness
in Me Myself and mind and
proliferations of self-referential thinking or fantasizing about the past or
recriminating about the future or having pretend to conversations
um we're missing
the wholesome path which is when we we see that
in attending to our experience with an open and quiet mind
we don't need to keep carrying the burden of the ego
we can choose peace
and um the Buddha's instructions
um for mindfulness of breathing he tells us that
the first thing we should do is to go to some place empty
so the value of seclusion is uh temporarily
um taking a break from worldly concerns
and cultivating mental seclusion as well
by emptying the mind of all our concerns and worries
and when we do that we can taste the Pure Clean Water of The Quiet Mind
and this gives us a feeling of ease even a subtle sense of Joy when we
inhabit if only for a short time
a mind empty of proliferations
the joy of being alive or that's the overlay of Me Myself and
mine and it feels so awesome
and it's also such a relief when we drop the burden of the ego
nothing to prove we don't have to be anybody
we don't have to go anywhere
amazing you don't have to prove anything or be anybody what Freedom that is
so please enjoy these moments when you don't have to be anybody at all
and also be patient with your tendency to proliferation
and no that the lovely Taste of emptiness is
indeed possible for each one of us
thank you for your attention thank you for your practice