so I will start with a guided meditation short guided meditation
and
maybe I'll start off giving some instructions and then we'll kind of
go into the silence so hopefully there's a little bit for everyone
so just taking a moment and
getting settled in the
the seated posture
it's always been interesting to me that
some of the most experienced meditators that I know
take really take their time to find their posture
you know maybe we could say that during the whole meditation
we're continually finding our posture we're continually discovering what it
means to be centered
to be balanced
to be upright
I don't think the sitting posture is is some particular place we get to
but is this exploration so just to take a few moments and feel
into this body who what does it mean for this body
be grounded
and alert
what does it mean for this body to be at ease
there
putting the eyes closed if that feels helpful
and perhaps taking a few deep deliberate breaths
and with each out breath
just noticing this letting go
is there some way in each out breath we can
let go of the momentum
of the thinking mind the momentum
conditioned habitual
thoughts and let ourselves be here
remembering that in this practice
our primary intention is simply
to be present for what's happening
In This Moment sounds are coming and going
Sensations the body
are being felt
this moment also includes our mental activity
thoughts passing through
images in the mind
feelings and moods emotions
all part of the fabric of this moment
can we allow ourselves to
receive experience
receiving sounds
receiving any of the sensations of the body
as they manifest
at some point we may notice that this body is breathing
we may notice the rise and fall of the belly
the expansion and contraction the chest
or perhaps the flow of air right at the nostrils
seeing if we can be present for one
complete in breath
one complete out breath
just one breath
there's no need to breathe in some particular way
but rather just observe
and notice this breath
sometimes the breath will be long
sometimes short
times shallow
sometimes deep
with each in-breath
this opening
receiving
welcoming thank you
and with each out breath
wonderful letting go
releasing
giving back
perhaps we can notice
and tune into the Rhythm
of our breathing
rhythm of
welcoming in
and letting go
foreign
thoughts will come
feelings will come
not a problem
whatever we experience
as part of the fabric of this moment
is worth our care
or attention
oh
is it possible to rest here
right in the middle of this flow of experience
thoughts floating by
sensations of breathing sensations of the body
sounds
passing through
in the final few minutes of the meditation
perhaps we can take a moment to
acknowledge whatever may be difficult right now
whatever may be challenging painful
in this heart in this mind
this body
to include this to meet this with
our warmth our care
compassion
foreign
[Music]
good morning and welcome again to IMC I know Hillary has an announcement
good morning it's so wonderful to see so many people here on our pod luck Sunday
so whether or not you brought something totally fine feel free to to join us
after the Dharma talk for our potluck and um there's seating inside and
outside so whatever feels comfortable for you and we'll just um just kind of make a line at the table and we'll ring
a bell and have a blessing before the food and and we also welcome anybody to
help at the end to help with clean up thank you
just uh just a reminder that all the teachings here are freely given there's
never a charge the entire Center runs on donations so if you're inclined to make a donation there's a box near the front
door with the spelling of the teacher's name and a slot for operations there's
also an electronic kiosk near the library door if that's more convenient and our teacher this morning is Max
ernstein good morning Max good morning good morning
well it's it's very nice to see
to see you and to be with you and to see so many people here
it feels like the good old days before that thing happened called covid
and um I feel like maybe I should introduce
myself a little bit because it's been a while since I've been here and
one of the great things about a place like IMC is there's old friends who are who are familiar and
have been coming for for years and I'm always new people who are coming in
and so it's such a great mix um
I first walked in these doors so to speak but it wasn't these doors
in I think in 1999 so
um this group had a
had a few times that it would meet at the Quaker Friends Meeting House in Palo Alto I
don't know if does anyone remember that just was here then yeah so okay yeah laughs
and um I remember I walked in and it was a
I think people were sitting you know was a little bit of like a rectangular room and people were sitting
facing the center and a friend had told me that there was
meditation it sounded interesting and I walked in and everyone was just
sitting there quietly and so I just sat down and was kind of waiting for it to start
waiting waiting waiting you know and then at some point okay
this is it
and that's sort of been my practice for the last 20 years you know
waiting waiting and then it's like oh yeah this is it this is it
cool um
I was just thinking to myself during the meditation how wonderful it feels
um to sit in the sitting posture and I think those of us who
have developed a little bit of a meditation practice over time
it sounds a little cliche but this idea of kind of coming home you know and coming home to ourselves
and coming home to the moment and for me when I sit down and cross my legs
and kind of sit up straight and close my eyes it's like oh yeah right I forgot
about this in my dramas in my problems in my suffering oh yeah this is possible this
is possible to [Music] um to be here
to open to what's going on
um in a simple way and even though it's simple
I think that
the meditation posture whatever that means for you whatever that means for your body but it's that orientation
to our life the meditation posture
brings a great power a great power
um but it's not a power it's it's not a kind of um
I don't think it's a it's a power to do or a power to assert or a power to
fix but it's a it's a power to accept
ourselves and it's a power to accept things as they are
you know so for me I associate the meditation posture with this capacity
to accept things as they are and
a close friend of mine recently lost a parent and she was going
through this process when her father was quite quite sick for
a few years and then you know um
sort of in hospice for a few months and
we talked about this a little bit it's like you know it's like what can we do what can we do in a situation where we
don't have control you know where we're there we want to be
present we want to be helpful we want to be awake we
and my suggestion was find a few moments every day
to sit in this posture just take this posture you know
and I think there's so much strength that can come from that that capacity
to open to our life as it is
you know
so that's one of the teachings that you
know has kind of stuck with me over these years and
I don't have the kind of mind that can really track or remember complicated
lists you know Buddhism has a lot of lists there's the 12 this and the 16 this and
this and you know they're great they're great and
um but to just sit down and let this moment be what it is
and soften the kind of struggle and soften the resistance and soften
the self that's always trying to get what it wants and get away from what it
doesn't want you know that's what stayed with me um
but it's funny how these some images or some teachings will will
land in the mind and a few weeks ago or maybe it was last
week I was here um and we had a one day sitting and it was it was a silent basically a day of of
quiet Day of Silence and I gave a talk at the end of the day
but what I was remembering was this story that I guess I heard early in my
practice and I was after I started sitting here with Gil in Palo Alto
so in those days Gil used to talk a lot about Zen because you know Gil who is the founding
teacher of the center also has a Zen practice and started his practice in Zen in the 70s I guess this was closer to
the 70s it was the 90s and so I heard a lot about Zen from Gil and
I got very interested in Zen Zen Center and send my beginner's mind which is kind of
the famous book that the teacher there Suzuki roshu wrote and so I started sitting in San
Francisco at the Zen Center as well and somehow I heard this story
about how um
you know in a Zen meditation Hall all the students are sitting facing the wall
have you you know have you ever seen that yeah it's a different format so all the students are facing the wall and
then the teachers at the front of the room facing the students and then usually there's another
kind of student who's facing out who's kind of like the meditation home manager
I think they call the Eno in the Japanese so the Eno comes in later and kind of
makes sure everything is okay and you know and so
this is a story that this manager the student told that
all the students were sitting and Suzuki roshi was there facing the hall and the manager walked in and saw one of
the Scrolls on the wall was a little bit Askew it was a little crooked
so being the manager and being in the Zen tradition where if you know Zen
it's a little I don't want to say OCD but everything needs to be lined up needs to
be perfect you bow in a very particular way and you walk into the room with a particular foot
not your left foot I can't remember which one it is but it's one you know it's the left to the right and you and it's a choreographed and it's kind of a
mindfulness thing and it's kind of just the way we do things the thing it's very
beautiful you know that there's a way there's a right way of doing it
so anyway the manager walked in and saw the scroll was crooked and so he straightened the scroll and
then went over and found a seat and found
and then uh Suzuki roshi the teacher got up to walk out of the room
and on his way out
he reached over for the scroll and
messed it up again quick you know could slanted it I walked out
you know in one beautiful graceful gesture and that was the story
you know and
in my early days of Zen practice I'm sure I heard that story and
you know it stayed with me and one of the things I appreciated about it was it was a little bit of a
corrective for especially in Zen there was a sense that there's a right way to do everything
and being a kind of overachieving
want to be perfectionist or something I was kind of trying to do things the right way and I'm sure that everyone was watching
you know and um and there are times that everybody
watches and then because you get your meals in the meditation Hall so they're
servers who come in and serve you and everyone's just there looking at you serve and you there's a certain way you
do it in a certain way you bow and you think and so um
there's that element of it and and usually in a community Zen Community like you know in any Community
there's a person or two who really enjoys correcting you and telling
you that it's not supposed to do that and
so this story for me was a great teaching
and there was something there was something about it that
um for me was a
a pointer that we're not in this practice we're not
trying to endlessly correct endlessly fix endlessly perfect
you know we're not trying to scrub the mind of all of its
bad things and insert all these good things and you
know that's not quite it you know maybe there's a maybe there's some there's a you know some some aspect
there of that but that's not the that's not the point and so for me this idea of
um
kind of changing you know letting letting things be
letting things be as they are that was the teaching that I got from that
and then when we sit down to meditate um
we're opening to the experience of this moment however it happens to be
however it happens to be sometimes
will feel calm sometimes we'll feel agitated usually there's going to be a mix
of a lot of different things going on and thoughts coming through
and feelings and
you know I love the fact that our Center here is
you know is it a neighborhood people are driving and kids are laughing
and there's cars and people talking and you know we're sitting in the middle of
life we're sitting in the middle of our life we're not we're not trying to get to some
absolute silence silent place and
you know I know for myself early in my practice I had the model of I need to be I need
to have complete silence you know so like earplugs or
I mean there's a there's a place for that like when I fly I like to you know I have my
headphones and my eye mask and I'm trying to just you know disappear
um but I think meditation is not about disappearing and it's not about escaping
to some place where nothing can bother us nothing can touch
us um it's more about opening more and more to
our life and our life is not a
um what are those called the the chamber
the flotation tank you know if it's totally want to get to a place where I just it's totally silent
totally peaceful I can't feel anything am I here you know yeah maybe maybe we
have moments like that that could be nice but um if our freedom if our peace only comes
from when everybody else does what we want them to do be quiet
I don't know how how valuable that freedom is
but when we can be free when we can be at ease
when a parent is sick when we're late for work when we're stressed about something when
we're sad about something where we're irritated when we're wanting something
well I think that's a more valuable Freedom that's a
that's that is um
to be awake to be aware to be alive
right in the middle of delusion right in the middle of our life
without attaching to delusion or enlightenment
um so I was saying the other day that
in one of the um places I practiced
there was a scroll on the wall and the translation of this goal was
um don't remove delusion
don't even seek the truth you think well
but isn't the Buddha's teaching removed illusion
seek the truth one day
Etc so why why would there be this teaching right next to the Buddha saying
don't remove delusion don't even seek the truth
and so for me it was this great pointer this great
reminder that um
it's closer what we're looking for what we're seeking the Dharma
is closer than any idea any any division of even delusion and truth
it's here it's this and to let things be to open to to this
moment truth is not in some future moment some better moment
when I'm some better version of me and the world is some better version of itself then I can be happy then I can be
free if it's not here where where could it possibly be if it's
not here um so here's a here's a little story that
maybe is presenting uh some
aspect of this once there was a monk who lived in an
old Temple taking care of his retired teacher and tending the temples rather famous
garden one day visitors were coming from far
away to admire the garden and so he spent the morning meticulously raking
the sand and Gathering up all the Stray leaves after he had gotten everything to look
just right he noticed his old Master Looking Over the Garden Wall at his work
very nice the old man said but there's one thing missing
what's that ask the Monk taking hold of a branch of a tree
that leaned Over the Garden Wall the master gave it a good Shake sending
Autumn Leaves cascading Every Which Way onto the pristinely raked sand
there said the old master now it's perfect
if you've ever gone to Japan or seen these these Zen Gardens
you know and the stones are kind of raked in a certain way and it may be a maple tree in the corner and
and they're beautiful and they're it's a kind of serenity
no it's there's like a Harmony of and
Stillness and you know if there aren't a lot of tourists and all this you know
but you know you kind of kind of It kind of puts you it becomes your mind you know it's it's one image of the Mind
and and so to be in an environment like that and you see oh this one Lone Tree
is relating to the pond
and it's relating to the stones okay and you're kind of there
um but there's also something about it that's very meticulous
that's very controlled that's very deliberate you know and certainly there's a place
for that and it's a certain kind of beauty so then why would the master you know
mess it all up and
um maybe it's not an accident that the master is as you know in the story
anyway is a kind of old guy experience I kind of Imagine
imagine him as someone who's has seen a lot of life has done a lot of practice
has a mind that's that's really wide that's really
inclusive that's really um
welcoming and I kind of Imagine The Young Monk
as someone who has a lot of energy who has a lot of ambition in a way
and wants to do something wants to accomplish something has this energy for practice wants to get it right
and
you know so so maybe in a way we could say these are two different models of of
the Mind of Dharma practice
one is that were continually raking continually cleaning
up continually um
you know taking care in a way it's beautiful I mean I think when we sit down and we notice that
the mind is all over the place and I'm so you know thinking about oh that happened oh I'm kind of stuck and
yesterday or last week or 10 years ago and then to kind of say oh yeah I'm here
you know and to sit up a little straighter to come back to the breath
and apply myself and put some energy and gather the mind
I mean that's important that's you know that's what we're doing and I think this is the side of practice
that's kind of like a training you know um
I don't play piano I wish I did um actually I wish I played guitar but
um I think that learning an instrument
or learning anything is a little bit like this this learning
of mindfulness and breathing you know we first sit down and we talk about okay just follow your breath
like that sounds easy you know there there with a couple of breaths and then we're gone totally gone
you know and if you've ever done this practice of counting the breath you know
if you're familiar with that you know it's great I still do it sometimes and
it's like with each out breath you're just very quietly
say a number you know not random number just like one to ten basically so it's
like [Laughter]
you know so you're breathing in and then
you kind of play with it and then the way I think about it is like the number
it's like a little label that the thinking mind if you give our thinking mind something to do
give it a little activity so we're not thinking just randomly so much so it's like
and so but 90 of the awareness is with the sensations with the feeling of the
breath but then there's little lame of one than breathing in to
three and then once we get to ten we start again at one
so you kind of do these Cycles and so you know
if it's just this wonderful way of sort of helping the mind
stay with the breath and accompany the breath but usually when I when I offer this to
people to groups or something and then we'll talk about it afterwards like who didn't get higher than three in a
few you know because we get to you know one and two and then the mind is just off
then we notice we notice whenever we notice whenever we wake up we just come
back to one so it's this great it's a little bit like
I mean this sounds a little pejorative say like training wheels but I still use training wheels I think
it's great it's like it's like it just helps us
it just aligns us aligns the body and the mind and the breath
um so this is kind of a training and and so maybe in a way we could say this is like
raking the garden cleaning up the garden we're organizing the mind
we're sweeping the mind but that's not all there is to this
practice um and so what is it
to be able to not only accept that
the uncontrollability of Life the uncontrollability of the wind sweeping
up the leaves whipping up the leaves you know
um if any of any of us have a garden and no it's I mean it's like you know it's continuous right you clean up only in
the next moment it's like it's all it's like okay
um so practice is not about once and for all
it's not about I'm going to meditate so one day I can just sit back
and enjoy the Perfection of this clean pristine Garden that has no
mess no squirrels who are eating our ripe
tomatoes no you know no trucks going by and noisy
trucks and I just don't like the trucks and you know whatever it is um
and so maybe the master is saying the point of practice is to see the uncontrollability
is to see the mess as its own kind of perfection
it's like oh yeah when I take this posture
and I open the mind and open the heart and let myself feel
let myself think let myself breathe I can sense that this moment
is just what it is you know um
and it has its own kind of perfection and all of the Dharma all of the truths
of the Dharma of impermanence of interdependence of emptiness
is all here you know it's here in the sounds of the baby right
it's here in [Music] um
the mind that's worrying about something are those worries some
fault of mine is there some problem or is it just another
of the Endless expressions of this moment you know
um so I think when we can open to ourselves and open to our life that way
is such a gift such a gift we give to ourselves this is a gift
we give to others um
so I in my own practice I've become a little bit allergic to the kind of once
and for all thinking of like because the other side of once and for all is
I'm not there yet maybe I'll never get there
what am I doing here why you know what if you're doing all these years and and this is a very very common
you know feeling that meditators have um but I think of practice a little bit
more like sorry for the
prosaic or kind of tidion is that even a thing so example but it's a little bit
more like brushing our teeth you know we don't really think that okay if I
brush my teeth really well maybe I'll never I'll never have to brush my teeth again I'll press them so
well if I get so clean I'm done
you know what a relief you know no it's like
it's like part of our ongoing care for ourselves that we accept that this is part of
being alive right that um I'm not expecting Miracles when I
brush my teeth I'm not brushing my teeth waiting for
um some once and for all Big Bang experience
um you know so ordinary it's it's so woven into the fabric of
our life that we don't even we have to convince myself that it's a good idea yeah you just do
it and maybe there's a way that Dharma
practice can be more like brushing our teeth
that we sit down and we we
um
who it's like we
we metabolize our day
this is one of the reasons I love meditating at night I know I know early morning meditation is a
very virtuous thing if you're a very good person
you get up very early
I remember when I was living in a Zen monastery they would start the cities I think at
tassaharas it's like 3 40 something like that 350. and then you know but they don't just
leave it up to your virtue because if you don't show up at 350
you get a knock on your door
Max
is everything okay [Laughter] there is a person whose job is to round
up all of the stragglers it's kind of great you know
because in the monastery it's a kind of training if you do it
whether you want to do it or not so in a way it's the easiest place to
practice because someone's basically telling you go meditate now okay you're gonna ring
the bell you go ring the bell you stop and um in our own life it's a little you
know it's more nuanced but I love meditating at night because it's like this
it's like metabolizing the day and I just often spend a few minutes and
just doing nothing just sitting there and
just just feeling what's what's going on
um so
it's not that glamorous but I think the day in Day Out
meditation as brushing our teeth is a great practice it is a deep
practice and as I often think about it it's like you know
do you remember phone books I know they're kind of a a bad example
I feel so dated rather you know one page of a phone book
it's like so insubstantial it's nothing right it's this thin thin paper
and so I think a day of practice a day of sitting down
and being with this mind as it is exactly as it is
it's like one page the phone book but you know you do that day after day
after day and something substantial develops you
know and there's a real thing there and so
um
Maybe with that kind of consistency of being
kind to ourselves of of growing our capacity
to be with the full range of who we are the full range of emotions the full range of
experiences that life gives us um
we can see that we can appreciate
when the garden is pristine and we can appreciate when it's full of
leaves when it's a mess when it's when our life is full
of meetings and difficult conversations and
stress and you know and
and to find the beauty in in each thing in each moment and you know I hear this
baby and I have three of them so it's it's heart opening for me
and the thing that stuns me is how fast it goes you know babies are changing
like so quickly we don't perceive how we're changing you
know we're also changing um but it's like it's this great reminder
for me to and just enjoy enjoy each moment and it
goes by so quickly and I think meditation is a way of
reminding us and teaching us um
that each moment is it you know don't save don't save ourselves
for some imagine moment in the future you know so
we're so so often we give up this moment if you think there's something better
has to be something better right but um
it's one of the uh that's one of the memories I have of those stories from early in my zen
practice and as the story went we were
students were on one of these long meditation Retreats and you know and in the Zen tradition you there's pretty
strict and you don't move you can't move and so you have a pain a lot of you know
usually some physical pain in your knees or this if it's burning or [Applause]
so in the middle of one of these week-long sachines teacher
comes in and is going to give a little a little word of encouragement right a little something to open our
hearts and help us and what why not Suzuki where she says
something like doesn't get better later
so and I think it's up to us is that is that depressing
or is that liberating you know
and I think that some of the most present some of
the most awake beings I've had the Good Fortune of being with
maybe it's no coincidence have been either very young children
or people who are
at the very end of their life you know that these two
extremes these two ends of the lifespan where the children don't
the children are just are just in the moment right and they don't know enough to
compare or worry or
um anticipate
you know they're just there they're just delighted by every new thing
and and then the friends who've been at the
end of life it's like they too
are not waiting anymore are not um
someone I know this acquaintance of mine who's kind of a Dharma teacher she's a Dharma teacher I think she she wrote a
book called Death and the subtitle is
the end of self-improvement [Laughter]
you know finally
finally
I had a friend maybe I'll end in a minute but I I had a friend who
was this lovely woman in her 70s
I think when I knew her she was 77 and we knew each other because we were
part of a cohort of the Buddhist chaplaincy program which is part of this you know Gill and
Paul Haller and Jennifer block for many years have taught a chaplaincy
program and this we I did this in 2007 I think so it was a while ago
and and this woman we became friends and we
would kind of meet for lunch and the program ended and she was so wonderful and she
she was a psychotherapist but she had many different lives and many different careers and she just had this great
sense of humor and down to earth wisdom and I just loved being with her
and um she was so healthy and so vibrant and so
full of life that it was a shock to me that a few years later she
was diagnosed with terminal brain cancer and
and it was one of those things where you know
not no good treatments and so she basically said
I want to enjoy as much time as I have left whether it's
five years or five weeks and I when I feel like I'm no longer
myself I want to be able to kind of you know push a button
and and let go and this was before all of this was legal and other anyway she kind of had
some arrangements to do all this and she but what what she found was in
those I think it might have been maybe 10 weeks eight weeks 10 weeks that she had
she became so happy she was so free and she was so happy and
she even met with some of her Buddhist teachers to say is something wrong with me
why am I so happy why do I feel so she's like
she you know it was like a weight was lifted from her shoulders
that she wasn't um you know I don't know exactly what she
felt but it you know I imagine that she could really
be alive and appreciate safer each moment without worrying about the future
without worrying about this or that and she was so happy
and instead of a funeral she when she felt that she was really
getting close she threw a huge party and had her closest friends come and
they drank cocktails and played cards all night
and this was who she this was how she you know wanted to
um celebrate you know and memorialize her herself and
celebrate her life and so I sometimes think about her and I think
about these kind of two extremes of life
and then here we are kind of in the middle right and we do have to think about the future
and we do want to improve and you know and that is the side of
practice where we're tending the garden we're taking care of things we're
developing our skills we're raking the leaves and then there's the side of letting
every single leaf fall exactly where it falls
and seeing the perfection in
in this as well so
maybe I'll what time do we stop 11 or 10. no no oh no okay sorry
I can go on and on um well I wanted to have a I don't know if any we have time for questions or
comments or okay yeah yeah okay
of course yeah yeah well thank you very much and enjoy the potluck yeah thank you
thank you thank you