so hello everyone hello and welcome to uh the happy hour so for today's
practice given given what's happening in the world geopolitically and so much
suffering I thought might be appropriate for us to do some um tonglen practice
specifically tonglen practice it's a compassion practice in in from the
Tibetan tradition and [Music] um it's um maybe I'll say something last
time on Monday um a reflection came in that how how can our practice here be of
benefit how is it I hope it's being of benefit may it be of benefit given that
many challenging things happening in the world and let's consider that as long as
we are not number one adding to the hatred that's already happening in the
world um as long as we're not adding we're not fueling adding fuel to the
fire of hatred um no matter what side we're on what side of the argument Etc
as long as we're not adding hatred um then our practice is of benefit because
we're not making it worse by getting riled up and getting others riled up
and if we can have compassion for the human beings who are suffering the human
beings who are suffering um 360 Degrees
people who are at this time they're running to go into shelters or they
don't have shelters and running and living in lack of safety no matter what
their background their their religion their belief their color their history
doesn't matter they're human beings just like us and they're going through living
through a very very difficult time so that perspective that that with
compassion 360 Degrees that way we can have a healthier stance to actually have
an appropriate response in the world instead of adding more hatred to what's
already there's there plenty of in the world so so and through compassion practice we
can have a again more stable ground more stable ground for
compassionate action for compassionate action for altruistic action for
offering support but first we need to stable stabilize ourselves so the
practice of tongue Len which is breathing breathing in and breathing out with and and I'll describe more I'll
lead you through it is a beautiful practice an appropriate practice at this
time for us to engage in so without further Ado let's um let's begin so
everything you need to know I will share with you uh during the guided meditation
so so let's begin so arriving arriving in your
body arriving in this moment in time
and taking a moment of Refuge first to find your your
stability to
connect connect connect with the center stable calm
grounded nonreactive center for the sake of yourself and for
the sake of all
beings and for this moment putting down putting down the stories the thoughts
the arguments the images
the nose flashes putting it down for a moment and just
connecting connecting with the body breathing the body sitting
and
breathing this body like so many bodies sitting and
breathing letting the breath be received
just in the abdomen let the breath be received in the
abdomen justce in breath justce out
breath
and let the breath be calming
settling a sense of stability
groundedness
with each moment of connecting to the breath receiving the INB breath offering
the out
breath and now like to invite you to imagine that
the breath is moving through your heart center the
center of your chest being
received Center of your chest and as it's receiv received waking up
it's it's bringing [Music] about
disc connection with a sense of a connection with a sense of
care for yourself for others for the world and with this each out breath
you're offering that care to the
world
and now imagine that in your heart center the center of your chest the proverbial Heart Center
often associated with the sense with the center of kind and caring emotions meta
radiating out imagine there is an orb orb of
light orb of light
transformative bright
orb of light representing care kindness
compassion for yourself and for others all
beings and this bright orb of light is shining
bright but each breath in breath and out breath it gets
brighter and this bright orb of
light in the center of your chest it is yours and it's also not yours
it's Universal care and compassion that's being
held by this living being who's you but it's Universal it doesn't belong to
you it's larger than
you
yours is one
instantiation of this Universal
compassion shining brightly
now imagine that suffering challenges pain sorrow
fear anger yours and
others like a fog it's like a
fog or
smoke it's like a fog that when
it's Breathe Into the Heart Center it gets
transformed into a bright light of comfort sucer and care and gets breathed
out and shared it doesn't affect
you because this orb
of universal compassion and care and your heart
center is not exactly yours much bigger than yours you're just holding it for
now in this lifetime while you're
alive you're extending
compassion like an Olympic torch you're carrying it for limited time
and as the suffering as the pain enters is breathed in into this orb
gets transformed into care compassion and then it's breathed out
you can imagine it is breathed out as a bright
light of care a comfort goodness bringing
AIDS Comfort feelings of
safety to those it
touches so that with each breath you're spreading Compassion Care
with each mind moment with each
breath you're reducing transforming
pain hatred anger in the world into care and
goodness it's being
transformed your heart too is being transformed in your
mind find your own way with this
practice if you find you're struggling then let your own struggle be
breathed in as this
fog be transformed into ease and breathed out over your whole body as
comfort and ease
care your heart is strong
enough Grand shining with
compassion stronger and more courageous than you
realize
suffering being breathed in to the Heart Center in this
orb this transformative space of compassion
transformed into love into care and breathe
out your own suffering or other people's suffering
and if it helps to add phrasing could do that too as you breathe
out May you have ease in the midst of this challenge midst of this pain
suffering and you be free from this sorrow this suffering this
pain or I care for you and
wait
may all beings All
Humans especially those who are suffering right
now in war zones where there's lack of safety
there's fear
danger anger heartbreak so much
suffering all fellow human beings be free from
suffering may all beings be free from sorrow and pain and
suffering
may we all grow as a race to love to love each other to love our
neighbors
ding [Music] ding
ding thank you all for your practice I don't have my bell with
me so so I want to share this teaching from the
dapada and many of you might have heard it
before and it goes like this this is a this is
one version of the translation hatred never ceases through
hatred by Love Alone does it end
this is an ancient and eternal
law hatred never ends through
hatred through love alone does it see this is an ancient and eternal
love when I came across this teaching decades ago now this is before
I had practiced any Buddhist Meditation or was familiar with any other Buddhist
teaching and I saw this actually in Japan it was on a
plaque and it
um I forget the exact details but basically was a plaque a small town in
Japan and told the story of how after World War
II there are many it was um it was a meeting of the United
Nations and and the victors wanted to they were quite angry and wanted to um
to exert punitive damages on those who had lost the war including
Japan and I forget who but the prime minister of another country a Buddhist country
got up and shared this quote that hatred never ceases through
hatred and it is said that it completely shifted the energy of the the meeting
and the victors decided not to exert punitive damages and in fact support
um I believe it was Japan so that it could restore and it could rebuild
itself I was so touched by the wisdom of this teaching hatred never ceases
through hatred we know this from our own lives not just from Nations but from our
own lives if we keep ha ha hating and hating it never ends it's only
through love love through care and Gandhi and Dr Marth Luther King knew
this too well and taught this especially the teaching of Martin Dr Martin Luther
King [Music] so with this I'd like to invite us all
if you would to engage with reflecting out loud for your own sake
but in small groups about how this practice was for you this evening or
this teaching how it impacts you and again you're speaking in the group for
your own benefit you're not trying to educate edify impress you're not
speaking for anybody's benefit you're only exploring for your own as if you're
journaling but out loud and the other two people are only holding you witness
and if you're holding someone witness and you didn't even understand what they said don't ask them a question just let
it be just holding kind presence for them to explore their own understanding
okay it's a very different way of being in community in small groups it's and
it's not a support group it's not vexing or Etc it's a it's a
special way it's really a reflective way of exploring and teaching out loud while
being held withness it's rare and it's it's powerful so please do take
advantage of it so offer one reflection exploration the next person will do the
same the next person will do the same and your turn will come and you can also say pass no problem you can definitely
say pass and don't make it a long monologue so that everybody has the chance to speak and in small groups
please turn on your camera um if at all possible to respect one another okay and
be kind to yourself be kind to one another and let's go with um order of
birth who um Whoever has a birth date closer closer to January
1st I don't mean age I just mean birth birth date right so whoever is closest
to January 1 will go first so that means at the beginning you just say your names and you kind of figure out what the
order is okay so please be kind be take
care of yourselves take care of each other we're here to cultivate compassion
and care for ourselves and for others okay all right be kind take care here we
go opening all rooms okay having trouble here on muting and hi
everyone the rooms are closed everybody's back and we have uh a few
minutes or any practice reports if you like to share how the u meditation was
for you or what you might have discovered in the exploration and if you haven't shared um a while in the large
group I'll invite you to raise your hand and if you have spoken recently you're welcome to share in chat I just changed
the setting so that you can um type uh your Reflections in chat directly Mima
please yeah Nikki I just want to say thank you for bringing this into the room tonight I feel since um the
beginning of everything that's tragedies that's going on right now um I needed a
place to be able to find some refuge and be able to express what was waiting on
my heart and I feel that tonight um yeah I think it was really helpful
for me to be able to share that in the rooms and the feedback that I got was also very constructive so thank
you thank you so much Mara yeah thank you appreciate you yeah saying this
verbalizing yeah yeah thank you for your practice and thanks for coming and and
in the way way um yeah it's it's really each of us
coming together in this way creating the space of Refuge for one another in in
such a challenging time of tro
Neil I got tense and stiff and panicky right at the word tonglen I hadn't even
start it and I'm like Oh my gosh I'm overwhelmed and I remembered and I will
share right sort of like what got me out of it was I remembered maybe a year ago we were
talking about Quan in a breakout room and someone said you know the typical
story is that Quan's job is to go around with a magical vase of soothing water
and pour it on the suffering of the world but some people say she has two
jobs one is to pour the soothing water on the world and the other one is to
keep the vase filled with soothing water and that just so struck me this
must be a year ago um and you know when I panicked I'm like I need to fill the
vase not pour right
now it was a lovely prce thank you lovely thank you Neil beautiful need
to F of us yeah and it's so interesting that um I so appreciate you sharing all
of that and of course it it it takes I just want to acknowledge that it does take courage to say you said that word
and I was panicking so thank you also for the courage to and model that yeah
we can stay we can stay with what seems difficult or challenging or or we want
to just bold um so thanks for modeling that that that courage and and stability
that actually compassion can support and and um and also couple of a couple of
things here one is the um beautiful
image of keeping refilling refilling because it's it's both it's not just
pouring out it's not just giving and that aspect of tongland I there many things about tongland that could could
be um uh scary perhaps as as a practice
um but but this uh thought of I need to give I need to give I need to give and
I'm going to be diminished I'm going to be left empty whereas actually the practice of Tongan is this resourcing
practice it resources us while we're practicing it and in fact we whenever I
prac practiced tonglin I feel good I feel um calm I feel it I remember the
first time actually I practiced it there was just the sense of joy and delight and the feeling that came over me was
wow I'm breathing in a way that every breath matters every breath is is bringing
sucker to this turmoil to this world of turmoil wow my breath breathing has
never felt so precious anymore important so that's feeling of resourcing so thank
you for sharing these both as these both aspects that then supported to have a
beautiful lovely practice and also maybe the next time I introduce it I said we're going to do a practice together
maybe I won't mention tonglin because tonglin unfortunately gets a bad rap with practitioners as this
challenging practice which isn't anyway thank
you
Jerry says I struggled with how religions are often the cause of much suffering in the world like Buddhism in
Southeast Asia so I found it soothing to focus on compassion for everyone yes we're all confused human beings
trying to find our way causing harm
ah yeah thank you
Jerry I see Claire's
hand very quickly M Nikki I just wanted to share because of what you just said
about we're all confused and I may have told you this before but I went to a very very very famous therapist who
founded the school of cognitive therapy and he used to sit in with his groups
and when people brought up problems he often would say and he was world famous
he would often say yes we're all up Val human beings and he meant he was
referring to himself as and he truly meant it he was just as screwy as the
rest of us you know and uh it was delightful it was just
wonderful thanks what you said reminds me of um this line
I forget whose poem it is maybe one of you will will pull it in chat if you know it's um love your love your crooked
neighbor with your crooked heart love your crooked neighbor with your crooked
heart so I just love that yeah thanks Claire and I
see I thought I saw one more hand or maybe not maybe that's
it I see Diana I was saying in my group um you
know this is not when I heard the word tongland it seems
unfamiliar but it isn't because I think just through this practice in this metag
group at least for myself a lot of us have it already halfway there just just
in our compassion practice we do here in our other loving kindness practice and
so it's to me I was I was happy tonight to do more and I felt oh that's not so
it it can seem like it's come some sort of scary exotic thing it really is not
wasn't all that exotic it just flowed and I felt um warmth afterwards and so
um with that I I really wish that we
could maybe do it once a month maybe you would spring it on us or
someone once so we don't have to you know know and advance
and and then we do it so we just get a little bit more used
to it's not that different it's just apprciate yeah
yeah thank you iate yeah yeah thank you Diana so so so
couple things one is that um it and as you were saying that it
didn't seem so unfamiliar it was it was pretty uh you know it was familiar to me
you were saying and and yes exactly because here in this group we have done
a lot of I usually bring in the breath and I have done a lot of practicing of
meta connecting in with the breath breathing in kindness breathing out kindness breathing out love breathing
so we've done that a lot yes it's that's um the part that sometimes feels
challenging for some people's breathing in suffering because some people think oh I'm taking it on whereas you're not
taking it on it's just this sense of compassion compassion in in in your
heart center that's just transforming it so that's the part that sometimes people have trouble with so so I need to set
that up as I did tonight like it's not yours this is universal compassion it's just doing its own thing so so I've been
bringing it in Diana yeah yeah just one small point but we're also used to all
the imagery that's used so when the imagery of the taking in whatever it was
put as a fog or that or whatever it was put as it we're used to imagery in
meditation and and we work with that and it's helpful so never that was just an
add additional thought so thank you thank you Diana thank you so
much so and yes thank you Neil uh the quote from the poem is by wh Ain says
Neil our great resource finder thank you you shall love your crooked neighbor
with your crooked heart you shall love your crooked neighbor with your crooked
heart and um and H I did see your uh question you sent to me directly but
since it has to do with AI and and Transcendence and all of that and yes I
do know it seems outside a perview of the conversation we're having so I'm
going to um not take that question right now so so thank you all thank you
for your practice thank you for your cultiv cultivating your
hearts may all beings everywhere be free from
suffering may all beings everywhere including ourselves learn to love
well may we all be free thank you all take good care ding ding ding I don't
have my bell here but that's it for the dedication of marage okay