hello and welcome to this meditation session and as an introduction to the
meditation I want to mention that occasionally in the world that uh I
travel in the concept of
power is often seen negatively and and partly because PO is
used in interpersonal relationships in society in ways that are quite power quite painful and
harmful and uh if you go back and look at the meditation teachings of the
Buddha he has a lot of references to power that are power within
oneself some of the faculties we have for doing meditation
practice as meditation develops develop in develops into Powers there's a of
power strength that carries them with which they carry us they
support us there's the power of
confidence the power of effort the power of
mindfulness the power of Mi and the power of
wisdom and none of these are being referred to in relationship to power
over anyone else and maybe not even power over
oneself but they are strengths that develop and that from the Buddhist
perspective we we don't need to be afraid of they're here to support what's
really best in US power of wisdom is clearly related to uh
the power to recognize and act on what is beneficial
for us and to avoid what is harmful for us as we
meditate so this can get very quickly a complicated idea
discussion but for this meditation I would like to see if we can
I can support you to meditate where there's some underlying
sense of power in this body and mind
strength that is an aid keeping us grounded keeping us
centered here and now keeping us gently
but firmly rooted here in this practice in this time and place
place not with strain not with striving not with
expectation but almost like a
delightful appreciated sense of being
rooted in the practice so assuming a meditation
posture that is right for you
a posture that maybe is
adjusted maybe small adjustments so
that it expresses a
confidence a kind of power that we
have almost almost like Gathering ourselves together preparing
ourselves maybe for like a
physical activity we have to do that requires all the strength that we can
muster we might take a deep breath we might take a good
stance we might Focus kind of bring together our whole
body so a posture a meditation posture that
gathers together and gently closing your
eyes and
to find a place within that you associate whether it's
present now or not you associate with a location
for Gathering Power
strength a definitive feeling of being yes
here no question about it Gathering it together to be
rooted here for an important
activity is there a place where you gather where you
Center and from that place to take some long slow deep
breaths as if your breathing begins there and spreads from there as you
breathe in and returning there as you
exhale relaxing as you
exhale almost as if you are relaxing around an inner sense of
strength so any complications around the edges of it fall
away
and then to let your breathing return to normal and continue to breathe out of or
with some sense of inner strength
power and with a gentle breathing
relax on the
exhale maybe so there's a sense of calm or
peace around that sense of strength however small it might
be
a sense of personal strength or power in
meditation is closely connected to confidence a simple
confidence in the value of being present here and
now a confidence in not staying involved with thoughts and
attitudes which undermine
you
confidence and simpath awareness so that awareness
too is rooted in an inner
strength Gathering Together of
oneself a joining of
mindfulness with a peaceful strength power definitiveness
here now and if you find your mind wandering
off to the best of your ability reenter
yourself and whatever sense of inner strength or
power that's available to you however
small so with confidence and Clarity and definitiveness
you return to being aw aware now now
here
for
e
to connect mindfulness with an inner source of
strength power that is not
assertive but rather is closely associated
with
Vitality the sense of being
alive in a clear definitive
way
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting do once again
settle in yourself maybe on the
exhale maybe settling in a grounded rooted place where there's a feeling of being
strong in being
rooted a strength of
presence the advantage of which you're not going to be pushed
around collapse give up but stay
present able to look kindly calm calmly onto whatever
challenges you're aware
of and from this way to be able to gaze upon the world
kindly generously with care
compassion without fear interfering with a
care without feeling
inadequate in the face of what's happening in the
world and to wish well to look kindly upon
others to wish them the best to wish them to be free of their greed
hate and delusion to wish them to be free of
Oppression hunger
illness may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
free and may the way that I'm present for
people support
that [Music]
thank
you
so so welcome to this third talk about the Buddha's teachings on disputes
quarrels and we know that disputes and quarrels can be verbally violent they
can be assertive there can be a lot of power and strength that is evoked in
disputes and sometimes uh some people's
uh sense of personal power gets awakened and channeled through
anger sometimes through conceit and part of the
some people who don't have much sense of connection to their personal
power will really value being angry because how it makes them feel powerful
and strong but when um when our personal
power is channeled into disputes and quarrels it makes the whole disputes and quarrels much more complicated and it's
not so easy to for us to find ourselves in that there's a losing of ourselves in
it and it can come along with uh all kinds of unfortunate things that go
on one of the things that is um that Buddha talks about is uh what gives
strength to any expression of greed hatred and delusion is
people's uh love of power some the sense that uh identifying with power say I am
powerful I want power and that kind of power Social
Power is a power that's uh that uh has to do with power in the
relationship we want control over others we want to um not just be right in the
arguments we have but we want to have a sense of that we're powerful we can get our way in a
situation sometimes because there's a w only we only believe there's a win lose option
it's either that person wins or I win and um and so we want to win we want to
be safe we want to not be losing doesn't feel good and to feel
powerful is a way of kind of winning in a sense or being right or having a sense
of control or a sense of pleasure even in a sense of power power over
people and um and because power is so often used um for people to get their
way or politicians to get their way or rulers to get their way uh and sometimes
and it's expressed in all kinds of horrible ways um uh Power is often seen as being
evil or wrong or people then become afraid to express their power sometimes
because if they express it someone else will come along and knock it down someone will Express even more power and
say that you're wrong or conceited or something but uh the Buddha put a lot of
discussion about power personal power but it was never power over anybody else
it was all in relationship to power over oneself though occasionally talked about
having the power uh to enter into relationships in such a way that uh to
create healthy relationships and I'll talk about that so some of the forms of
power that Buddha uh talked about developing is the the power of cons of uh having a
conscience so the power of being having conscience and care and just and to not
cause harm he talked up the power of confidence the power of power of
confidence over knowing what is uh healthy and unhealthy beneficial and not
beneficial he talked about the power of effort the effort of doing what's wholesome and avoiding what's
wholesome the power of mindfulness and part of the purpose of mindfulness to really be present is not to be calm but
be able to find our way to recognize what is healthy and unhealthy what is wholesome and UNH
wholesome the power of samadi the power of being grounded here in the present
moment and the power of wisdom and one of the ways that Buddha defines wisdom
is in fact the wisdom of being able to recog recognize what is beneficial and
what is not beneficial what is wholesome and what is not wholesome and um so over and over again
we see the Buddha is wanting people to have power over themselves over the
choices their mind makes their heart makes their their body makes and their activity to be able to choose
well and one of the ways of choosing well is to choose the the kind of a
strength of mindfulness of being present without Asser assertion and without
giving up without um um running away or
collapsing without assenting to things we don't agree to but to be able to hold
our own calmly in a relaxed way to stay there and be present uh rather than
turning away from conflict uh I think the Buddhist approach is to stand up
tall metaphorically uh to hold keep our seat and um and be
able to look at reality directly and calmly without
flinching and uh without collapsing without getting confused or a agitated
or and this is not an easy thing to do but uh by emphasizing that this is a
kind of P there's a kind of internal power that's meant to be awoken and and
support us in this Buddhist practice uh when this practice is uh uh
only associated with being being calm being peaceful sometimes we we're short
changing ourselves of what's possible here yes being calm being peaceful is part of the practice but it's a partner
with having strength a partner with a certain kind of inner personal power
that uh so that in the peaceful state We're Not Fragile we're not vulnerable
we're not so so sensitive that that we feel like it's everything is too
much so a couple of things that Buddha emphasizes that um in one place he he talks about four
powers and um and the first is the power of wisdom which he clearly defines as um
the power to know what's beneficial and what's not beneficial to know what's wholesome and not wholesome
the power of um energy again like I said before to be able to act on that wisdom
to act on what's beneficial to avoid what's not beneficial and then the power of
blamelessness this I love this one the power of not living in the world where
you people have reason to blame you sometimes he calls that the joy of
blamelessness but he also the power of being being that way a certain kind of strength that comes to be able to walk
through the world um not not being uh feeling that no one has anything
anything to blame a real they might blame us but there's no cause for it and
then um and then the power of sustaining favorable
relationships the power of sustaining favorable Community bringing people together and
this also he Des describes in four different ways four kind of sub powers
in a sense uh the power of giving as opposed to the power of taking
taking power for example from other people controlling them the the power of giving giving
people the benefit of the doubt being generous to them the power of giving them the their opinion okay we can agree
to disagree and you're welcome to your opinion it the power of um kind speech
or loving speech so often the in disputes and quarrels the speech is not kind and
sometimes is actually downright mean and so the power of knowing how to speak in kind ways
and and then um the power of beneficial conduct so not just knowing what's
beneficial and but really knowing how to act and giving is one of those kind speech
is another one and um and but what you know to really stay conduct oneself in
beneficial ways not succumbing to harmful ways of being and then the the uh fourth one is
um uh The Power of Equality the power of a certain kind of
impartiality where we treat everyone equal and this is the one that our
society needs tremendously there's so many different ways that we have bias
Prejudice uh towards people of all kinds of differences from ourselves and um and
the power of treating everyone equally uh that that a kind of a power of
respect so I offer this teachings today in the context of disputes and
quarrels to uh in disputes and difficulties and challenges you have
with people uh to uh call upon a
personal power but don't engage in disputes and arguments uh asserting
power over over other people uh but have it over yourself so
that you know how to stay present and even just the power of presence uh of keeping your seat keeping
your place without succumbing without giving up without um um um agreeing just
because the other person's more powerful seemingly to you or is arguing more strongly than you or you're afraid of
them but to be able to breathe and stay rooted here and it's a sense of inner
power that might be in the long term in all our complexity of our life may be
more important than trying to hold on to being calm and peace ful but the more
that we can have the power of attention of being present of being rooted I think
the more our calm and peace can accompany us and support
us so um so I hope that all of us can
grow into becoming powerful people but
powerful over ourselves with ourselves so that we can do good in the world
World powerful enough that we can avoid the habitual Tendencies to be mean to be
argumentative to complain to um uh just be upset about all kinds of things with
other people in ways that uh undermine and maybe create uh make the
world a worse place for other people uh to have the power to hold our
tongue when what we're going to say is going to make things worse so uh this practice of ours is
meant to support the development of powerful strong people um and uh who can do good in the
world and good for themselves not to assert ourselves over anyone so thank you and uh may this
support you in disputes and quarrels that uh um
you're being pulled into U or or or
you're tempted to get involved in and maybe it'll teach you how to be present
for discussions when there's disagreements without it being a dispute or quarrel thank
you