good morning welcome
so and welcome to this 7 A.M Community the YouTube meditation community and
I feel it's delightful to come together this way and the repetition of doing this for us
such a long time makes it feel like kind of a homecoming to sit down here and to be with you all so thank you
and um so one of the metaphors that is used
sometimes for meditation is listening
and in fact listening is sometimes considered to be a profound spiritual
practice especially if we listen to
what is not a sound we listen to our hearts listen to what's inside
listen to The Silence that's here many years ago someone told me that I
think it's the the Catholic order of the benedictines they're kind of a description of their way of
life begins with a Latin word esculta meaning listen
and the Disciples of the Buddha
were called the direct disciples who listened to him were called the
listeners savakas and um
but to sit in meditation and think of that we're listening the reason why it's such a useful metaphor or idea is that
with listening we have to listen well we have to suspend our judgment suspend our
commentary suspend our projections onto a situation
we have something has to become quiet to listen well
and if mindfulness is a kind of listening to the moment
and close your eyes it's often listening to ourselves in some deep way
why do we have to suspend to listen well what are the commentaries what's the
noise of the Mind that we quiet and willingly quiet
wisely quiet because we are interested in
we put Great Value in what gets revealed when we are not having commentary not
preoccupied in thoughts and stories past and future and to have this stance of listening
also we don't interfere with the sounds that come our way
I mean I guess you could go and turn up or down the volume on this broadcast if you'd like but there's something about
sounds that come that in and of themselves they come without
blocking the sound or attacking the sound there's something
about the receptivity of listening that is um
profound aspect of mindfulness practice
so to assume a meditation posture to assume a listening posture
I think sometimes if we go into the forest and someone points out mentions oh there's a special birds singing in
the trees it's kind of faint can you hear it and I think the the posture that we take the sometimes
for that is lifting the neck a little bit out of the shoulders
lifting the head up a teeny bit almost like we're becoming a better antenna to hear
pulling away from the static in the mind to be quiet
gently closing the eyes and adjusting your hands so
the position of the hands is the best position for the
shoulders so the shoulders have some room to relax
and gently maybe lovingly take some deeper breaths than usual
but not so deep that it's a challenge full our breaths
as you breathe in feeling the Torso expand
as you exhale feeling what releases and relaxes in the
rib cage the chest and the diaphragm
and to then let your breathing return to normal
and continuing to feel the gentle or not so gentle expansion as you
breathe in and relaxing the chest as you breathe out
as you breathe in feel the global experience of being in a body
so you can recognize where there's some tension
than when you exhale soften the tension in your body
feeling any tension or pressure agitation in the thinking mind
as you exhale Relax The Thinking mind
as you exhale her gentle gentle calming
of the Mind
and then centering yourself on your breathing
maybe the metaphor of listening to your breathing
can bring an interest and a non-interference to breathing
receptivity and a non-judgmental however you're
breathing as if it's something to Simply listen to
maybe listening from deep inside the body
as you exhale letting the thinking mind become a bit quieter
so there's a higher sensitivity in the body to listen or feel
the experience of breathing
listening to the deep in the body where breathing begins
or being sensitive and quiet to hear or
feel the quiet and
soft ground or basis
through which breathing occurs
a quiet place underneath or behind your breathing in
listen feel sense
deep inside
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider what a good skill listening is
and many people what they most want is to be listened to to be heard
in their challenges and their difficulties to be heard to be seen to be known
and may it be that this practice that we do learning to be attentive and mindful
can help us become better listeners to the world
better listeners to our friends and family and colleagues and Neighbors
this practice that we do leads us to be interested in others
so that we can know them better and that this is one way
that we extend the benefits of this practice out into the world
May our ability to listen to others bring them happiness
bring them safety bring them peace
bring them freedom
in this simple practical way may we bring the benefits of this
practice into the world for the welfare and happiness of all
by becoming better listeners
thank you
so continuing on the theme of Attunement
living in a tune to the suffering of the world suffering of the people we encounter
to be attuned to our own suffering means not to Simply experience it
in the usual way your experience in ways that are challenging for us
but to engage in a process where being attentive to suffering is for our
betterment and leads the betterment of the world and one of those ways is to be attuned
to suffering being in harmony with it to find a balance with it
so we're using these uh This Acronym acronym touch which seems very nice for for compassion
that um to be to be compassionate means to be touched by the suffering
and this idea of being touched in some deep way it's kind of tender it's kind of loving it's kind of like
we get touched by the things that are important for us that we value that that move us
and then in return to touch others
in uh not literally maybe but to touch others with our kindness with our support
and sometimes it can be literally sometimes a gentle touch on the shoulder or the arm
can be so meaningful for someone who feels lost broken hurt isolated
to be to touch others is to know that they're not alone so to think about the suffering we
encounter to find a healthy way of thinking about it to be open to it
to be upright in the presence of it and today the eight the sea is to stands
for to communicate to take time to communicate with the people that were involved in that we who
are suffering who are challenged um and one of the reasons why this is important is that it's very easy to
encounter someone who's suffering and to um assume that they're suffering the way we
would in a similar circumstance and we project our own experiences our own
history our own fears onto the other people and then we
might miss them we might not understand what's happening there what's what's really going on
so to communicate is to find out a little bit more what's happening or what's this experience like
people are suffering don't necessarily appreciate at someone appreciate probing
questions that people are really trying to you know to do probe deep into what's
going on but simple questions very open questions or statements like oh that you
know just simply they say No this must be hard is an acknowledgment and recognition of
what's Happening that sometimes open doors for people to feel seen and
recognized that they're willing to share themselves more than they volunteer how
it's how it's hard the simple question like uh you know what's
the hardest part of this what's the most difficult thing for you in this circumstance
uh it can be eye-opening to find out someone might have maybe broken their
leg and um is now kind of has to stay home and rest their leg and
I don't know could be immobilized for a while and they're suffering and it's difficult
and and you ask them what's the what's the most difficult thing what is it what's so hard for you or what and they
say oh the most difficult thing is that I was really accounting on going to a graduation of a dear friend of mine this
was a culmination of so much of their life and such an important thing and I wanted to celebrate with them and now I
can't do it and you had no idea that that was the biggest thing that they that's causing
them some distress maybe for you the idea of being
independent is so important that you assume that what's difficult is now they can't denote on freedom and movement and
they have to depend on others so to find out what is going on for people and hang out with them and talk
about what's happening and learn more deeply as don't assume we know what's
going on it's a nice question sometimes to ask is
how might I support you with this or what are some ways that you can be
supported don't even promise you're going to do it yourself but what are some of the ways you find support in this kind of
challenge and some people find it helpful to be reminded with a question like that then
they think oh yes I forgot meditation is important for Me Maybe
This is a time to meditate or friends are important for me and um or you know whatever it might be
and um asking very simple questions or acknowledging what's happening with
someone is a active expression of compassion of caring for someone
and some people that's what they mostly need they don't necessarily need someone to fix them or do things with them but
just kind of sit with them and recognize oh that's what's happening I've been with people and I've been
challenged by something who were really quick to want to do things and like let's go and do this and
that and that'll be make it all better and I just simply wanted to be quiet and be present and be with what's going on
and I would have valued having a friend who sat and just be we gently quietly talked about it and I could just ex you
know in the voice and my feelings and thoughts that I have so this ability to listen deeply
and listen in such a way and communicate in such a way that we're not trying to
fix people we're not trying to be the helper first and foremost we're trying
to be the person who uh understands to sees gets to know the
suffering we have in the world and um and the more we can be directly with
people to find out the deeper we understand what the suffering is if we read about suffering in the news
that's far away the other side of the world we can certainly have compassion for that we can certainly feel the pain of
that in some ways but the chances are that we're projecting a tremendous amount of our
own assumptions onto that situation so our imagination has come alive and some of the imagination might be
true enough but it's very different that we're on the ground being with people and seeing exactly the details of what's
Happening and um so this is enough communicating and seeing and learning more so when the
suffering is Far Away really take the time to read study look more deeply into
the situation get it so deeply that you have sometimes um a sense of what it's like for
individuals in that circumstance and because now with the with all kinds of
social media with news with the videos that's happening so easily often you can
see people being interviewed or people who are talking and saying how it is so that there's a deeper connection to
people to what's actually happening for them so finding ways to communicate finding
ways to listen finding a ways to speak speak that are open-ended that are caring that are that
are not and in rush to fix and to help and also be very careful learning
how to communicate that in our communication you know talking with people who are suffering we're not first
and foremost taking care of ourselves or or moving the attention of the
conversation to ourselves and you know a classic way of doing that it's a is to say something like oh I
know exactly what you're feeling I went through the same thing and then we start telling the story of what we went
through and maybe it's not the same thing we don't know actually what's going on with others
and it's a way of disconnecting an extreme version and disconnecting and
now the conversation is more about oneself and about the person we're with so when people the more people are
suffering you want to be very careful how much you talk about yourself and uh and sometimes talking about
myself is a way of caring for ourselves or trying to kind of assuage or calm down our our own
discomfort we have what's going on sometimes talking fast talking a lot
asking a lot of questions rushing to Solutions is more about taking care of
our own discomfort than is really taking care of the other person that we haven't learned to get to get to know yet
so communication is such an important and profound phenomena
that sometimes I think of the word sacred communication
that somehow the um when we when we communicate from the place of practice
from the depths of Who We Are then the communication goes better
and this is why something like meditation where we've learned to listen deeply to
ourselves can show us a place inside from which we
can listen to others with some depth and maybe even for some people in our
listening in our communication there our depths can touch their depths
and so that it's really something profound that goes on between two people
I've been in situations of being challenged some suffering in my life
and had conversations with other practitioners that turned out to not really be about particular suffering
where have I was having but somehow we dropped into some deeper place of where
we find the most value and importance in the practice and that being reminded being touching
into that that was like the best medicine for me in this situation that I
had and from that I had the resources and the ability to be open to be upright
to be present for the challenges I had foreign so communicate
um so think about be open
be upright communicate and then tomorrow I'll talk about help
the last uh part of the acronym touch
and um so what's important here is that the
helping comes after the first four so that rather than thinking we have to
help first and foremost first and foremost we want to prepare ourselves to be ready to help
and and thinking openness uprightness and
communication prepares the ground for effective ways of being support of
serving other people so that's for tomorrow thank you