good evening everyone welcome
uh my name is Jim Podolski Diana is away this week and so she asked
me if I would fill in for her so I'm sort of a substitute teacher
so he can expect the same that you might from a substitute teacher
most of the alternate teachers actually started a three-week retreat yesterday
so um
so I'm going to share with you some of my
thoughts on understanding about Buddhist practice
Diana didn't give me a particular subject to talk about
um a couple weeks ago I went to visit a friend of mine who this year was put in a Memory Care
Facility and he's still pretty high functioning
and he was quite displeased with how things were going
and so the head of the um this place uh called about 10 of his
friends together to talk to him about what his dissatisfaction was and how we
might help in a in a skillful way in a way that
um would both benefit him and also not lead to him being harmed
one of the things that he talked about a lot were issues of freedom and autonomy
and choice and
it really struck me you know like we hear about Freedom so much
particularly on a day like today 9 11. um and it took me back to the late 90s when
Gil franstall gave a talk on freedom he said that oftentimes the type of
Freedom that we talk about in day to day um environments
is what he calls freedom 2. so it's freedom to do certain things
freedom to say certain things freedom to think certain things
and sometimes that's goes along with some
recognition of responsibility and consequences
and non-harming sometimes it doesn't you know sometimes
it's Freedom too is some expression of wanting to just follow one's impulses in
a in a way that may or may not be wise or beneficial
what Gil said and stuck with me all of these years was that the practices that the Buddha taught
were me really maybe better characterized as freedom from
so freedom from mind States and actions that might harm
oneself or others
and it then made me think a little bit about
how what brought the
Prince scotama the Buddha to be to
um go out and discover what he discovered
so you may have heard this story I'll give a a very short version of it
um but Prince Kodama was living in a palace
his father was a king and so he was in an environment where he had you know the
best food the best clothes the best entertainment um
you know as much pleasant as could be put together and as little unpleasant
and that that was kept from him as much as possible
and that sort of worked until he got into his second later part of his 20s
and he got curious about what was going on outside the palace walls
so he made an arrangement with one of his attendants to sneak out of the palace
I suppose probably got some sort of Disguise and walk out you know in the village and
see what what was it like outside of the palace
one of the things that he came across one of the first things he came across was a person who was sick
now believe it or not as he was growing up they were able to keep from his view
anybody that was sick so he had no idea what sickness was like what disease was
like and it shocked him you know he didn't realize that that was part of
human life and they continued on and then
they came across somebody that was old I imagine somebody that was probably
sort of bent over maybe had a cane of some kind um
living in that realm myself right now I know most of many of my friends have trouble hearing or seeing uh and I'm
sure back then there was there weren't cataract surgeries or hearing aids so he saw somebody that was um
old I suppose probably wrinkly skin and he again was you know just was
astounded that this was uh that this occurred and his attendant
you know told him oh yeah that this is what happens to human beings
and then the Third thing that caught his attention was he
saw a dead person he saw I assume somebody that was maybe you
know a funeral procession or being prepared for uh
cremation and he wanted to know what what is this why why is that person not moving
and so his attendant told him well this is death and um
it's inevitable you know everyone is going to die
and then the fourth person that caught his attention was a monastic somebody in
robes walking I think it was across a field in a very
Serene and peaceful manner and so we went back to the to the palace
and this this really shocked him this really you know had an incredible effect
on him so much so that he decided he was
struck with this question of is there any way out of this is there
any way out of sickness old age and death he had to know he he didn't want to
believe that that was true and of course associated with sickness old age and
death were suffering and pain and grief
and so he made a decision to
to leave the palace to leave his wife his newborn son
his parents I mean his father I think his mother had passed away before then
and um you know leave the security and luxury
of the palace to to go and really seek answers to is there freedom from
sickness old age and death and
I suspect because he saw the the monastic that he decided to go in that
tradition you know put on robes and um
seek teachers he apparently mastered many forms of meditation
um he thought maybe the problem was the body itself and so he
ate like one grain of rice a day until his body was emaciated thinking
okay well maybe just um
maybe that's a way to get free of the of the um
suffering of having a body and at some point he decided no that's
you know he wasn't getting any closer to the freedom that he was looking for
and so he started eating again and then he had
based on his seven years of practice he was able to have deep insights that led
him to be one evening to become totally um
awake totally you free from
uh these concerns that he had you know kind of saw that there was
that the that there was some clinging that um
led to the suffering so
to me that was quite inspiring somebody well they would just drop everything you know I suppose in
in this day and age it would be like quitting a good job
you know giving all your money to charity um and just
you know wandering around looking for teachers looking for
Spiritual teachers
um on Saturday there was a monk here tan
Jeff who gave a talk about the four noble truths and one of the things he
said towards the end of the day was that one should cultivate desire for the
path cultivate desire for the goal and so
I wondered how how does one cultivate desire to be free
to the degree that the Buddha did and so I asked Han Jeff how did you cultivate
the desire that led you from going from being potentially a college
professor to a monk and he gave a very very brief answer he
didn't he didn't go into his life story but you know it was basically from
suffering you know it he had had a roommate in college who had
taken his own life and um had some
intense psychological experience that made him decide to become a monk
um so that's something that I ask myself about like how
do I develop a sense of desire for
walking the path I don't think that it's just through
willpower through the ego
it's helpful to have friends that are on the path Sangha places like
this um call the animita groups
the other thing that I've learned over the years at least from from Gill
was that you don't you don't have to imagine that
the fruits of this practice are something that's going to happen a long time from now
you know like it took the Buddha seven years of just you know practicing non-stop doing nothing else
um it might take that to to get the full realization that the Buddha had I don't
know I'm I'm not there but there's also some Freedom that you
can experience moment to moment you don't have to be fully enlightened
to have some benefit from this practice some
freedom and
that leads me to um you know sort of the question of well
what what is it that you want to be free of
are free from and so one of the lists of of things
that it's I'll say it's considered valuable to be
free of but I think it in practice I've found that it's it's valuable to be free of are what's known as the hindrances
and there's a book that I just happen to have here called unhindered by Gil franstal
that um explains in Greater detail what these are and how to work with them
um so I'm going to give a maybe sort of a synopsis of this
the hindrances are mental activities that tend to cover
over what's going on so
uh sometimes sometimes I think of the hindrances as
um my unskillful helpers you know they want to protect me from
seeing something that I don't want to see uh uh maybe that's useful in the short term
but in the long term uh that isn't helpful
so the first of the hindrances is sensual desire
you know desire to have certain sense experiences
now there's nothing wrong with having sense experiences the problem comes when
they take over when we when we lose
um awareness and become
uh I'll say in a certain way captivated by them
so I suppose a simple sensual desire is
I know that I have a box of chocolate covered ice cream bars at home
and when this talk is over I'll go home and I'll have one and it'll be enjoyable I'm sure
um if I were to go home and eat the whole
box that may not be so skillful um
the analogy that that's often used for sensual desire is like a pond that has
die in it so you can imagine like a swimming pool at somebody poor
dye in that it would be hard to see accurately what's in there
that the colors wouldn't be correct and it might be kind of dark
so
I suspect you've all had some experience of being captivated by sensual desire at some
point you know whether it's for ice cream or food or
um thrill rides um
and so how do we get when we're caught by something like sense desire how how
can we get free of it how can we become free from it
and the suggestion again in this book
is to First be mindful of it so mindfulness
is a really important tool for freedom in that
although we we often cultivate mindfulness on something simple like the breath or the walking
it's helpful to be mindful of what's going on in our mind so paying attention to
is there sensual desire that's acting right now in my mind
and um and then to bring some examination to it
what happened that this arose what what were the conditions that came together
um is there something underneath it are
there some some emotions or some thoughts did something just happen
that that we might not want to see
um and so examining it and that doesn't mean
just thinking about it over and over again but really feeling
what that's like in the body um
allowing it in a certain way not taking a not making it the enemy not making it
something that um we have to fight against
but really kind of getting to know it
and in that recognizing of it with mindfulness in that examining of it
we may find that over time it lessens it might just lessen on its own like at
some point you might just find that it's
you know you just like well what was that um
you may also want to do something about it so there there are some antidotes for
these mind States uh
one of them for a sense desire is often
seeing the downside of it like one of the practices that the
Buddha taught for when you become obsessed with
a body either yours or someone else's you can do this practice where you
imagine the body being taken apart and so like all of the different organs
and pieces are like laid out on the floor in front of you it's called the 32 parts of the body
and you can look at them and you think are any of these desirable you know you know and that's kind of an
extreme practice well it's certainly a practice that I've been
aware of for some time and it is practice on Retreat some
um but there's other practices that one can do to consciously lessen that sense
desire [Music] um somebody told me that when they
practiced in Thailand they were in a monastery and there was a skeleton hanging
in the back of the hall and there was a sign on it that said this is the skeleton of Miss Thailand
1932. so when you look at that skeleton you
know there isn't you know any kind of attraction to it that
I'm Gonna Miss Thailand in 1932 might have evoked
so um so there's being aware of the hindrance
examining it uh lessening it
um and then at some point um letting it go it may let go on its own or you may just
decide to substitute some other thoughts or practices
and then finally appreciating the absence of that hindrance
like noticing when that hindrance isn't operating it's like oh yeah you know
right now I'm pretty content pretty happy
and so by appreciating the absence of it it may make it easier the next time it
arises to see that it isn't something that you really want to um
Foster
so that was the first of the five hindrances is sensual desire
the next one is ill will and the
image for that I think the metaphor for it is uh like a a boiling water
so when water is boiling you know if you try to look into it and all you see are the bubbles you can't really see
um clearly or accurately
and again with ill will recogn you know
first of all developing what I call a certain vigilance for when
ill will is operating in the mind this one
I think what I've noticed these days is that in
well ill will seems to sell newspapers right you know getting people angry
getting people upset um
so there's a so it takes a little bit more active
practice I think to just notice how often triggers for um
ill will or aversion arise and
you can then do the same processes for sensual desire you can first of all
recognize it see what it you know kind of feel it in the body
um notice what it's like
uh examine it you know what what were their triggers for it or their thoughts were
their emotions where their activities um
that triggered it um is there a way to lessen it
um one of the things for ill will like one
thing that can lessen ill will is doing an active practice Like Loving kindness practice
um I do that as sort of a
like taking my medicine before I get out of bed in the morning I always do a
period of loving kindness before getting out of bed just as an antidote for probably what's
What will what I will encounter that day
um letting go of it
you know that's I think if you really feel what anger is
like you may find well this is this actually isn't very pleasant this is not a place that I want to hang out in
and then appreciating its absence so noticing like throughout the day just
asking yourself well is there ill will operating do I
you know
there's many many forms of this you know all the way from just raging violence to
just mild annoyance so it isn't like it's just one uh
one size fits all
um the next hindrance is actually described as a pair of hindrance it's a sloth and
torpor now those are kind of old-timey words that we don't use in
or I don't use in my day-to-day interactions with people but they point
to sort of low energy one of them is low energy in the body and one is low energy
in the mind and this the this pair that's often
described as a single hindrance I think that's one of the ones that's that's the hardest for me
um it's hard to be mindful when you don't have much energy you know you just if you don't have much energy
you don't have much curiosity and much incentive
so it takes some getting some
desire to get curious about it and investigate
sloth and torper those are often described as like an
algae filled pond um
again so allowing it really recognizing that it's there then doing some
examination and then lessening it
so from for me one of the skillful ways of lessening sloth and torpers
to get up from sitting in front my computer and going for a walk
you know or just doing something you know getting some movement going
um another way which is probably just sort of so-so is um
iced tea and and dark chocolate those those those tend to bring a certain
energy to the body that uh
in the monastic tradition I forgot about that yeah in the monastic tradition they don't eat food after the midday meal
but chocolate is considered medicine so they can have that at any time so on Saturday
at the end of the day I gave tan Jeff two bars of dark chocolate because I knew he I knew that that was something
he could accept after the midday meal and I happen to know that he likes it
um
and then Letting Go letting go of that you know sometimes I find by just
starting to do something the energy will return and um
and it's kind of like I get get out of that being stuck
and then appreciating the time when sloth and torper aren't I act aren't
operating you know just I tend to be a night person so this time
of the day I don't feel any sloth interpreter when I wake up in the morning it's a
different uh case but you know appreciating like oh
yeah you know it's actually enjoyable
to be um appropriately energized
another pair uh another hindrance that's often given as
a pair is restlessness and worry so just like sloth and torpor are low
energy in the body in the mind restlessness and worry are sort of
agitated energy in the body and in the mind
and again you can do the same thing recognize when those are present examine
uh what thoughts what emotions what
actions preceded that um what does it feel like
I suspect it's mostly unpleasant but you may actually find agitation Pleasant
uh lessening that uh
sometimes when I'm feeling restless it's because there's so many things that I'm trying to do simultaneously and so
sometimes just starting doing one thing will bring a little bit more focus and
reduce the the restlessness and agitation
and then appreciating when those restlessness and agitation aren't
operating and then the final hindrance is doubt
and that's sometimes described as a mud filled pond
and doubt is also one of I think it's considered one of the hardest
hindrances to work with because it's one of the descriptions of it is like
you just don't know what to do you know like you're unsure of what you should do next or is this practice going to really
work or should I be doing some other practice you know maybe I should be doing Sufi dancing instead of
this mindfulness so
examining doubt can be um challenging you know it's like you
look at it and you go well is this doubter isn't it what should I you know is there a way for me to lessen it
um this has been something that that has
been a part of my experience all my life um
when I was in graduate school I got married and I was married for about 10 years and one of the things that I liked
about my wife is she never had any doubt she was always absolutely sure of
herself I didn't always think that she was right
and uh there were times when it was annoying but whenever I was in a place of
uncertainty outside I could look to her for certain you know like well what should we do and she had very refined tastes and and
tell me what's tacky and what's not tacky um
but that that strategy really didn't work you know if you if you try to rely on another person
to get you out of uncertainty uh
it develops it doesn't work at least in my experience so
sometimes I think you just have to make a decision and just you know decide okay
I'm going to do this and then stick with it for a while and see what happens
and then when doubt isn't present appreciating it you know again that sense of like oh yeah I
I know exactly what I'm going to do after this talk I'm going to go home and have my
truck ice cream bar there's no doubt about that
so those are that's one of the lists of
things that one can I I believe you can develop some freedom
from here and now you know it doesn't take seven years of aesthetic practice or
something to reach some final and um
irreversible freedom that that there is there is freedom
available in this practice moment to moment that you can access by
by paying attention you know by bringing some curiosity some
investigation to um
checking it out feeling what's it what's it like you know what's it like both when that hindrance is operating and
when it's not and so in the short term there's freedom
and then in the longer term you may find that the hindrances don't
arise as much I don't know of anyone whose claims that
the hindrance has never arise for them anymore
but I think how you relate to them can change over
time as you do this practice
yeah so um
so freedom from I think is something that that's
um something that we can aspire to and practice day-to-day
so um and again I'll get one one more uh
plug for Gill's book on unhindered if you look at it you can see that it's
I obviously haven't read it multiple times but I have read enough of it to um
remind me of what I've learned from Dharma talks and other
sources over the years so
thank you all and we do have some time for questions if anyone wants to ask Sally will give
you the microphone
now Michael
thank you I get two things usually I'm pretty hard on myself when I'm meditating and then I heard a dog
barking a little while ago and if anyone else heard it but I was thinking oh that's funny and silly and I kind of enjoyed it oh the kindfulness and loving
kindness is working and then when you're talking about doubt I was thinking that it struck kind of a tone with me I think
maybe today's generation or just today's society we're sort of bombarded by choices kind of a paralysis by analysis
should I do this type of meditation or that type of medicine which one of the ten and sometimes it's just hard to pick
one or the other and whatnot but thanks for the talk oh you're welcome yeah there we really do have a lot of
choices and I um
for me part of it is consciously not making choices you know like somebody
says well you know A or B A or B and I go well I'll get back to you
you know at least some some choices you
I decide judiciously which choices to to me but
thank you for your comment
thank you for your talk tonight uh sorry I was late um and just like listening to the
hindrances on the one on um it's out also I just kept thinking it's kind of
another form of unwillingness in some ways first it could be
um I mean making a decision or not
um I think like I can think about like what I'm not willing to do and usually it's
because of there's something underlying and for me sometimes it's fear or
it might be um I know it better or I'm doubting someone
telling me something you know those are the things that they're so familiar that
I can catch myself and then just go for it because you can ask your question like you could ask yourself what's the
worst thing that would happen you know if I did make a decision you know it just um it I think sometimes I think
like making decisions eliminates all those other possibilities but you just
have to take a leap and yeah I think out of everything you've talked about I
started really thinking about doubt yeah and how it is for me but yeah
good yeah that's as I said it's it's considered one of the hardest
hindrances to work with I find that I often
well I shouldn't say often some of the time I feign confusion to
get out of doing something so so I don't know if that's even
fold out or something but yeah it's
yes thank you for the talk so one very
light-hearted question can you have like coffee instead of iced tea for low energy
yes you know it's interesting um when I first started going on meditation
Retreats they would purposely not offer coffee you know they would not make you
could bring your own and you could have those little pour overs and that but they wouldn't um
offer it I guess because it if you drink
more than a certain amount it kind of causes agitation in the mind
more recently I found it at the inside Retreat Center they make coffee every
morning there's enough people that wanted it so it's kind of it's uh
it's it's uh kind of changed I personally for me
T doesn't make me as jittery as coffee so that's kind of a personal
experience but uh yeah
is that something that you like doing drinking coffee yeah I think like
if I go on a retreat and don't have coffee then I just like sleep off during the meditation
I think like there is some sweet spot like you said in moderation then I'm
able to like be one pointed but if I drink like too much then anxiety
yeah so thank you so much thank you
any other questions
okay well we're just just about at nine o'clock so thank you all for um
yeah