okay hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be with you and and uh hear
your hellos see your faces so for tonight's practice um I wanted to
bring in this framing um something that I learned um
uh recently so
so um and it has to do with Natural Sciences it has to do with the way that
our minds work our minds work our brains work our body works
so uh the visual system as as an example of how we process information in the past
scientists thought and and you know when we do naive reasoning we think that okay
there's an object in the world and the visual processing you know the the road
the cones and rods and you know we process the shapes and colors and lines and it's all sent to the brain for
processing and we go aha it's a cat right that's the way naive uh biology
but it actually turns out that scientists have discovered that there
are more um uh uh uh what is it called uh
um uh not neurons but these long um there's more information sent from
the brain to the eyes instead of from the eyes to the brain there are more Pathways that's the word I'm looking for
there are many many more uh Pathways from the brain sending down information
to the eyes instead of eyes to the brain like okay so scientists first realize
this it's an interesting quandary like why is that like that's surprising And yet when you think of it it makes sense
because if if our information processing is humans we have to process all pieces
of information fresh and fresh and fresh it would be so inefficient and nature is
very efficient so guess what the brain actually is sending down
expectation for what it expects to see what it expects to see to the eyes and
the eyes are just seeing the difference it's it's actually very similar to many computer algorithms for image processing
that you don't always process if you're processing say video you just process the differential you know if there's a
movement like oh you only process that or you're uh you don't have to process every frame over and over so it's just
your expectation so basically with the implication that this has for us as
human beings is that we construct our reality we know this and yet this is
such an interesting example where our brain is constructing our reality
through its expectations we expect to see maybe a cat because we just perhaps
process the cat or this is the you know this is the animal we expect to see when
we open the door and and that's and and not only with our visual system in in
the world the brain sends us to our processing systems what it expects to see and then our processing system oh
gleans the information to kind of to support the the suggested delusion that
our brain has so so this example of the visual system is is so interesting and radical and yet
it's the same it's the same with how we process information otherwise in the
world so if we are looking at the world the sense of okay this person is mean to
me and the world is a mean place an unfriendly place an unkind Place well guess what we're going to see guess what
we're going to pick up and yet if we expect kindness oh yes the
world is a kind place this person is kind I am kind I see my own goodness
gets guess what we see guess what we perceive so our perception is based on
our expectation is the in the most fundamental way in many ways of
processing I just bring up the visual system as an example so we create our
own reality and um and not only physicists and and
natural scientists um this is the new way of thinking but also
of course philosophers and and and um contemplatives we create our own
reality so let's create a reality that is kind let's set up these expectations that are
kind that are generous that are onward leading let's set these expectations for
kindness for goodness for Goodwill so that is the part of our training
um in this practice at happy hour we we train ourselves our our habitual
patterns our expectations our set point however way you want to relate to it to
be one of Goodwill kindness so that that's how we act that's what we perceive that's
how the world becomes through our perceptions through our set point so
enough of a framework tonight so let's let's uh
let's set the conditions for Good Will and kindness that's actually tonight I
think I want to do gratitude and appreciation seeing the good in the world so let's do that so
so so let's practice let's settle let's arrive in our bodies
foreign
settling it's always first with the breath
with the body arriving arriving
receiving the breath with appreciation all the sensations of sitting
feet touching the Earth hands touching our lap said bones
on the chair and let's be silent and just settle
relax the body connect with the breath appreciatively
foreign
thank you not now giving my heart to this practice right now
just letting the breath be received in the abdomen
how lovely to be able to sit in and breathe
Sublime
and receive each breath in this body with appreciation
as if a new beginning
foreign
receive the sensations appreciatively
throughout the body
this feeling of being alive
through these Sensations we know you're alive foreign
foreign exhale letting go
a little bit into relaxation
foreign
how can we turn expanding expanding the sense of
presence as if her breath was a little
wider not just through our body but a little wider
the breath is breathing us
we're sitting in this
space spacious being calm soothed
through the reverberations of our breath
Beyond
our skin
thank you
and now as we said
feelings Sensations spaciously being breathed
a spacious container
opening our heart
inviting something that we appreciate to Walt's end
not going out and searching for it but just opening the door
letting it
gently saunter it
be something close near just maybe your breath
with the sense of being able to sit upright
something we usually take for granted or let this goodness
whatever it is as Waltz whilst in let it fill your heart
relish with each breath keep connected to the breath
relishing appreciating
foreign
with the breath and Sensations foreign
container relax the body with ease inviting is something else
it wants it to your heart
foreign
so there's not too much switching here and there it can
imbalance the Mind settle stay with something for a little while
and in your own time [Music] in hide another guest
come in and be appreciated another gift into your heart
foreign
something about ourselves to appreciate
appreciate we often focus on we don't appreciate we judge ourselves but turn invite
something we appreciate about ourselves what we're doing we're not doing
or being and not being foreign
foreign
[Music]
this person owes me doing their best
and thus appreciating this effort
and now turning opening up to perhaps aspects that
are somewhat challenging or have been challenged
be not the most challenging items but
some things
challenging and seeing the gift seeing the good
in between
at night I feel grateful for this too can I is it possible and if the answer
comes back no it's okay don't push it move on to something else
and ask the question can I not possible
imagine the situation that
it may not be the easiest for you right now
for someone else in a completely different situation this would be an absolute blessing
for example if your work is very heavy very demanding
you're tired someone else doesn't have a job would
love to be in your shoes
can you appreciate the good
not to condone the challenges but the good
and as we bring this meditation session to close
and we appreciate ourselves this opportunity
offered the community through technology all the amazing
causes and conditions that have to be
appreciate all of this and are showing up we open our hearts wide and appreciate
all of that giving it a big appreciative hug
and sharing our blessings our goodness for gladness with all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
foreign
I think there was still problem with the audio did you hear the Bell no no okay
let's try that again yes
lovely thank you all for your practice
so let's let's move things around a little bit I'm going to uh open the chat but
what I'd like to invite us to do actually instead of sharing Reflections inviting your Reflections now
let's move into the small groups now and we'll save space at the end for Reflections just trying something a
little different so the invitation for the small groups
is um is we'll do a round robin going around and around and actually this
practice can be so joyous yes thank you Neil also for posting the survey
information again uh in case you lost the previous link
um so that there um invitation for the small groups is
um what what are you grateful for you can share one thing what are you grateful
for it can be anything what are you grateful for the next person will share something and then the next person I'll
come to you and just go around and around and this practice can be so happy making so such a sense of yeah abundance
such a sense of abundance both holding one's abundance and and uh and
witnessing others supporting others and of course you can say pass just the hell
hold space just offer offering from your own experience not asking not querying
not directing but just offering something from your own experience if you wish and
[Music] um and let's do reverse alphabetical order
just for the fun of it and um
yeah so going to create the rooms and take care
of yourselves take care of each other okay all right check the rooms up we switch
something around hold on a sec can I recreate them it's all done
okay let's try that give me a moment
uh okay here we go
okay rooms are closed everybody's back so
um so the first question that I have for you was did that feel like enough time
or not if you if you feel like it was enough time raise your hand and I'll go through yes feels like enough till I see
a few hands okay if okay if it feels like it that was not enough time raise
your hand how many hands do I see not enough time
okay all right I see half and half okay we've got all right
okay great ah great so um do we have time for uh
for Reflections now a few minutes either about um
the uh meditation well if any aha moments
surprises questions or about doing this practice in in the group this gratitude
practice around about what you might have noticed red and Barbara
red or Barbara or both well I'm the one who raised my hands jumping unless you
want to say something too but um I was just feeling how well this this practice goes with the loving
kindness it feels like a very natural fit and the three of us who were together
um I think we all really enjoyed just bringing to mind things we are grateful for and it's like a little a little
Thumbtack note on the wall of Consciousness here that oh yeah there's so much to remember
um and and it has to you have to actually do it uh you have to do it consciously
you have to to Remember to Remember and then there is so very much to be
thankful for in every day um and it seems like it it builds on itself it seems like you you uh you
erect the kind of pyramid of of of conscious thankfulness about the day and that makes it a better day
so thank you yeah thank you Fred and I appreciate the many officer relations you made one being this this sense of
pyramid this is what I like to also call The Virtuous cycle because when you start to pre-con condition yourself to
see the good then you start to see the good and then you see more good and then it just it becomes a virtual cycle
um yeah and when you said that um one practice I usually do in the
evening when I lie in bed I before I sleep I think of a few things uh I'm
grateful for it for today I can't go through the day from the morning maybe to the evening or this happened and this
happened or that Oh that's oh that was lovely that was oh wow so it really brings a lot of Joy uh to my heart
before I fall asleep so I share that if you may want to try it on for size
any other reflections and you can also type them in chat as
you know if you type them to me privately I'll only read the reflection not your name so
it'll be private and if you can if you like to type it to everyone you're welcome to any other
observations about this practice shaping our own reality through
through appreciation and gratitude
okay Barbara
um what I wanted to add to what Fred said was that
he and and another person in the breakout session said that they had done
the Gratitude email to someone else in the group that you get pitched as an
assignment two years ago and they're continuing to do it
and that was something that they were grateful for and so this virtuous cycle you you've
got yourself to thank for that just saying [Laughter]
love it love it love it thank you thanks for bringing that in part I just that
makes me so happy just to no end thanks for sharing that oh my goodness
yay Fred and whoever else they're doing this for all this time yay and thanks
for bringing that in made made Inspire other people to to start doing that in
in the in the community in the north Sangha that is so awesome love it love it thank you so much Barbara that's so
great that's so great hmm Diana
I was just happy and astonished to hear about the visual system
and about the brain um with many many more Pathways than the
eyes it goes a long way to explaining why especially in the recent past I've
been looking for something looking for something an important document I think and I can't see it and it is absolutely
right in front of me in an envelope with its name on it and the next morning it's there there's
no been nobody around there's something else happening in the brain attention wise whatever we're looking
for or not and it's happened several times recently seeing uh
not seeing what's right there um with distraction whatever else is coming
in the brain those important scientific discoveries so yeah yeah it's it's thank
you you're so welcome it's so remarkable really just the way that we actually
shape our reality the way we perceive is not it's not what we think it is and has
so many implications um maybe actually what I'll share and and there's so much more in this book
The the book where I learned this um there's so much in this book it just
it's been it's been blowing my mind maybe I'll just share the name um it's called helgoland uh
h-e-l-g-o-l-a-n-d um and I trust Neil will send it to the
group by Carlo Carla ravelli called car I think it's called the ravelli
um and um it's it's actually the book is about
he's a physicist and the book is about [Music] um
um the um not String Theory but the um uh anyway without getting into too much
detail it's it's it's maybe I'll bring some other uh details uh about the book
in in the next few sessions but it's it's it's it's pretty awesome pretty wide let's see if I'm trying to find yes
it's Carlo robelli r-o-v-e-l-l-i anyway
um so let's see I think I saw another hand I think that's it I saw oh yes it's
seven o'clock um yeah um oh yes it's about Quantum Theory
that's what I wanted to say the book is about Quantum Theory and it's it's very accessible and it's it's pretty awesome
and pretty wild really pretty wild so so thank you all thank you for your
practice I am grateful for happier I am grateful for you all and that's one of
the things that was coming up for me as I was doing this practice tonight among the many things I'm grateful for I am
grateful for happier so grateful for you thank you thank you for your practice
thank you for being part of this amazing beautiful community may all of you may
all of us may all beings be wealth may all beings be free
thanks everyone take good care be well