greetings everyone I'm going to begin with an announcement
that yesterday we discovered that the 7 A.M teachings for this week were double
booked on YouTube so starting today IMC will stream them both
and I'll teach from seven o'clock to 7 45 and Matthew brinsilver will teach at
this same YouTube link one hour later from 8 to 8 45 Pacific time
so the theme for this week is opening the Dharma heart
and we are exploring five wholesome qualities that the Buddha used to determine if
someone was ready to have the Deep Insight that leads to enlightenment
so as you know in meditation we're training the mind and it's really up to us to become our
own teacher little by little we learn how to let go
of unwholesome qualities and to cultivate beautiful qualities
of the heart and mind so to begin again we'll start
by exploring our intention what motivates you to meditate
the Buddha encouraged his followers to practice both for their own benefit and
for the benefit of others so if your intention includes altruism
as well as improving things for yourself it will be all the more powerful
so take a moment now to articulate your deepest wish
and assuming your meditation posture see if you can lengthen the spine
gently stretching the base of the spine down towards the Earth
and carefully balancing the head on top of the spine so that energy can flow from you
through your body from Heaven to Earth and back
letting the eyes close gently
and now doing a quick scan from the head down through the Torso
relaxing the shoulders arms hands
relaxing the belly hips legs
and feet and softening the muscles of the face
in the forehead around the eyes
the lips and softening the contact of the jaw
take a long slow deep breath letting go of tensions wherever you can
because even minor bodily tensions can create blockages in the mind
inhibiting our freedom so it's worthwhile to get to take time
to get to know these areas of tension and find ways to release them sometimes
it might take years to release a particular knot foreign
to really relax something that's very tight maybe it's possible to soften around the
edges
so here we are the miracle of being here in this spot
and breathing together with a supportive Sangha from all over
the world letting your breath nourish you
and everyone here
now as we did yesterday bring to mind a benefactor
someone who instantly brings you gladness when you're in their presence
it could be another human it could be a pet that you know they care about your
well-being just as you care for theirs
looking into each other's eyes you both smile in your own way
enjoying the warmth that you share together
so wishing for your benefactor may you be safe
and protected may be happy
peaceful and free
and as you offer your wishes to them you can feel that they fervently wish the
same for you so you can light a little candle of
friendliness in each other's hearts
in the company of your benefactor you know that you're in a safe space
and now we resolve to leave all your preoccupations
worries concerns outside the door for the remainder of this meditation to
the best you can and if you wish you can pick them up on the way out
or the rest of this meditation we will endeavor to stay here
in the present moment with a warm heart
ready for whatever arises
bringing our attention to the breath as our friendly anchor
and exploring the whole cycle of the breath
letting it light up with the attention of our mindfulness which is operating in a context of warm
friendliness
receiving the breath with a mind that's soft and open
and letting each in-breath and out breath reveal itself to you
is there anything Pleasant in the felt sensations of breathing
if so feel free to relax into them and enjoy even a small feeling of goodness
it's really quite incredible to actually be sitting here reading together
I love the idea of kindfulness which is a word coined by ajan Abram
so it's mindfulness that is imbued with
benevolence
breathing in radiating kindfulness
breathing out radiating mindfulness
foreign
thank you
only in birth radiating kindfulness inside
on the out breath radiating kindfulness to all beings
everywhere
if the mind is wandering somewhere in the past or the future
first of all bringing the smile okay
this is what Minds tend to do but for this meditation practice
I'm going to come back to being here in this body carefully
kindfully attending to the cycle of the breath
staying close and soft with the felt sensations of the breath
foreign
foreign foreign foreign
we might want to or have to appreciate
the gift that is breathing
and perhaps enjoying carefully unwrapping this gift
in order to be with our breathing
breathing in radiating kindfulness inside
breathing out radiating kindfulness to all beings
the gift of breathing becomes even more of a gift
if it is imbued with kindfulness
question
foreign
of this sitting through the goodness of this practice
may we from our Center of softness
and guidefulness now gently radiate
our heartfelt wish that all beings everywhere be safe
may all beings be happy
peaceful and free
foreign
[Music]
I'm happy to be here with you all and I'll repeat the announcement I made
at the beginning of the sit um for those of you who are just arriving
that yesterday uh at IMC we discovered that the morning teachings for this week
had been double booked and uh so starting today IMC
um we'll be streaming both of them I'll continue teaching at this time
and if you're looking for Matthew Brent silver you'll find him on the same link an hour later so
uh he'll be there uh teaching uh
his meditation at eight o'clock and his little darmet at 8 30 Pacific time
so the theme for this week is opening the Dharma heart
and to be honest I have never seen the expression Dharma heart anywhere in the
Pali Canon but these texts do often speak of opening the Dharma eye
and the Dharma eye is opened when one has the Deep insights
that then give rise to Awakening
so in the in the early texts there are a number of Stories of the Buddha teaching
and the person listening becomes enlightened right then and there
but this doesn't work for just anyone well it has to be ready
and the text of the Brahma yusu which I talked about yesterday gives five
qualities of mind that are necessary for awakening
in Pali these qualities are called Kala mudu
varana and pasana
and Paulie is a highly polycemic language
polysemic means um a word that often has a number of quite different meanings
which is uh great for poets but it's difficult for translators because if
you're translating you have to discern uh which meaning is meant uh in that
context and in this particular group of the five
wholesome qualities of mind they're more like variations on a theme
rather than five clearly distinct elements foreign
Ty we talked about yesterday was receptivity getting ready and available
to wake up and that includes having the mental Fitness necessary to accomplish the goal
you're not going to run a marathon and start your training uh two days before
it's you know it requires preparation
and foreign Ty also includes the Nuance of a mind
that is pliant and that brings us to the second quality which we'll take up today
and the poly word for this is mudu which is often translated as soft mind
a mind that is malleable the root mood
actually means both soft and happy
and the softness of Moodle also includes being receptive just like what we saw
yesterday being flexible and pliable the commentary explains uh mudu as being
free of the defilements of fixed views and conceit
when I was 15 my father said to me if it weren't for you we'd have a happy family
foreign not only physical abuse but
psychological abuse as well and the model from my father was being
quick to anger quick to criticism and I learned to be judgmental
and the reason I share this with you is that it took me decades to learn to become a bit less judgmental
and for me if I wanted to cultivate a beautiful mind that was soft and
malleable this tendency to pass judgment all the time was one of the first things I
needed to let go of
and I learned that being judgmental has a lot to do with being opinionated and
having fixed views as well
yesterday I talked about walking this path as a process of emptying
uh that which is unwholesome and I've seen in myself that
what's sometimes underlies conceit is trying to overcompensate for a deep
feeling of not being Worthy
so I might look like a lion trying to reject an image of strength but really
I'm just a little tiny Mouse pushing around a big cardboard lion
to try to fool everybody that I'm strong
and probably what you know is most uh
arduous is emptying the mind of conceit and as you may know in the Buddhist
texts conceit is not just thinking you're Superior to others but it's any way that you compare yourself with
others so all that comparing I'm better than I'm worse than not as good as or
just as good as and you get to a point where you realize that this is taking me nowhere
so emptying the mind of thinking that somehow we have to measure up
and this um Fetter of conceit is one of the ten
Vetters that we need to completely uproot on the path to Awakening
emptying the mind of needing to be somebody ordering to exist
so from my experience cultivating a soft malleable mind
seeing the futility the unskillfulness of clinging to my opinions and comparing
myself with others and this Begins the gradual training of
seeing these beautiful Tendencies start to arise these I mean these unskillful Tendencies
excuse me you see that something like this uh being judgmental or uh some kind of
comparison is starting to arise and you can nip it in the bud
but um and you can say ah I see you needing to
be somebody no thank you not going there or
um oh dear boy this sounds so judgmental and then let's not go there
so if we really want to cultivate a soft
mind it's up to each of us to find out where our sharp edges are
and once we recognized and learned where we tend to be sharp rather than soft
we need strong mindfulness practice so that we can nip these unskillful
tendencies in the bud before we do any harm
and um I'm thinking that a fertile field in
which we might cultivate a soft and malleable mind is by practicing right speech
that before I say anything at all it has to satisfy the following criteria
it has to be true it has to be useful or helpful
it has to be kind and the tone must be soft and gentle
and it must be at the right time for the person receiving it
and if any one of those criteria is not fulfilled then it's better to keep silence
so that right there is a is a very strong uh
uh it's a it's a practice that can evolve over a
long long time we first of all have to learn to be less
impulsive and to not speak as as soon as we want to say something and to catch
ourselves before the reactivity is already sent the words out
so the federal of conceit
and not needing to prove oneself
has been a big one for me and also when I see the tendency to be judgmental
uh of myself and judgmental of others
you know for a long time I saw how unskillful that was I and but yet it
kept happening you know so at some point um
we need to really see that this is this is not
something that we want to keep doing and and this is where uh mindfulness is our very best friend
so the more that we can cultivate mindfulness in every moment of the day
not just in meditation the better chance we'll have of avoiding
unskillful Behavior which keeps us trapped
foreign
like a little homework practice for the next 24 hours you might try investigating where your
sharp edges your prickly is prickliness is
and also what would be in the most skillful ways for you to soften them
and if you have a Dharma buddy or a good friend that you feel that you can
confide in it might be interesting to to share what you learn about yourself
in terms of where those hard edges are and your ideas about how you might
soften them so
yesterday we cultivated receptivity a day we're cultivating softness
and malleability in the mind thank you for your attention