hello everyone I'm Maria strotman I am sitting in for
Guild this week who is I hope enjoying the retreat he's leading at tasahara
so [Music] um over the course of this week what we've been talking about
is how one comes to grips with the feelings of self-criticism self-blame
and we've taken the approach of considering at the con the cultivation of blamelessness
rather than trying to get rid of something what would we like to cultivate in our lives and we began by
talking about impermanence that we're not the same people that we were yesterday or will be
tomorrow or in the next moment for that matter and then we talked about judgment
and how judgment leads to suffering and then we talked about doubt
and today we're going to talk about forgiveness
because forgiveness has as its Central feature letting go of blame
letting go of blame not forgiving or not not pardoning or
condoning but letting go of blame so
we've used as our Talisman through the week the opening
discussion in in the dhamapada and it starts with
all experience is preceded by mind led by mind made by mind
speaker act with the corrupted mind and suffering follows like the wheels of the cart behind the
hose of the ox all experience is preceded by mind led by mind made by mind
speaker act with a peaceful mind and happiness follows like a never departing
shadow but that continues and that's the subject of today's talk
he abused me attacked me defeated me robbed me for those carrying on like
this hatred does not end she abused me attacked me defeated me
robbed me for those not carrying on like this hatred ends
hatred never ends through hatred by non-hate alone does it end
this is an ancient truth many do not realize that we here Must
Die for those who realize this quarrels and
hatred never ends through hatred by non-hate alone does it end this is an ancient truth
this is the spirit in which we approach the idea of forgiveness
forgiveness really is for you forgiveness is letting go of the blame
the hatred the ill will the resentment particularly the resentment from past
events forgiveness is realizing that whatever
the source of this pain is whatever this this uh insult to you this this uh
behavior that you find offensive all of that happened in the past
but what's present now is the pain of your remembering it of your recalling it
of your re-energizing it by telling yourself the story about how of course we justify
this you justify this anger and this resentment
yeah but that anger and resentment is actually no longer linked to what the
cause was it's all here it's all in US
and the task of forgiveness doesn't even require the other person or
the other place or are agreeing with ourselves
what it requires is laying down the determination to be resentful over
whatever that insult was being hurt is the normal consequence of
living we all have experienced hurt from ourselves from others
it happens stuff happens deliberate or non-deliberate stuff
happens and we get hurt
but the refusal to let go of the resentment toward ourselves or others
is just pounding the nail over the head after it's already in the board
it's done it's in the past now there's a famous phrase that that
forgiveness is giving up all hope of the better past all hope of a better past
it's over that has happened so now what
so now what it's a very human thing to want to blame
somebody for something that's happened it's all part of that
if I'm feeling threatened I have to protect myself from being from harm and so there's a natural reaction that I
should understand what happens so I can protect myself against it and we tell ourselves the story over and over again
and we say oh well that was your fault well if it wasn't your fault if if I
want you to love me and so I can't really make you into a bad person then I make me into a bad person I blame me
but blame does not have to be the response to something that is unjust
unfair unwanted it does not have to be the response and
if we understand that that's the part about holding on to the corrupted heart the part where we're holding on to that
resentment and we're stroking that resentment and making it part of
everyday living we are reproducing the harm in ourselves we are the source of
the suffering we are the source of this suffering it is not to say that whatever happened
is okay it isn't okay we're not condoning we're not pardoning
the act of forgiving is giving up blame
not easy not easy but if you think about it and you
realize it's really coming from here it's coming from here
you know for years I love Thanksgiving I love everything about it it's a
wonderful family day it's got lots of wonderful food and for years
I had terrible thanksgivings because the family would all come in and they would
expect me to take care of them and I had envisioned something totally different we'd all get together and we'd all cook
together and we'd have a good time together and other people didn't have the same vision
of Thanksgiving as I did and I suffered every year until I gave up my idea of
Thanksgiving my idea
and for the last few years it's been absolutely delightful because I don't require everybody to
meet my view of what it looks like that was a great lesson for me the first
time somebody told me you know it's your fault you're suffering I was Furious what do you mean they're the ones that
are just laying around no it all had to do with my wanting
things to be a certain way now that's easier to do than
some harm that's been done to you some harm that's been done to you to let
go of holding on to the resentment of that is the task at hand
to let go of the resentment of that but remember the forgiveness is for you
it's not for the other person
you have to give up expecting things from your life or other people that they
do not choose to give you
you have to give up expecting things from your life or from
other people that they don't choose to give you the fact that they don't give it to you
is you're wanting things to be a certain way
and that's where forgiveness comes in it's the letting go of I need to be right about this
one of the things that we can do when we find ourselves telling that
story to ourselves over and over again when I find myself putting energy into oh what that's just not right
I recall that that all of that energy of that is
not right is being created right here I'm burning up that energy instead of
burning up the resentment and I'm reinforcing it
and what's required is to say how can I let this go how can I forgive
there is a practice a forgiveness practice where similar to something like meta or Equanimity practice you could
say certain phrases to remind yourself of what you're trying to do and they're they're very simple and
probably most of you have heard them before if you've been on Retreats at Spirit walk for example
so what we say is if I have hurt you
by word thought or deed deliberately or undeliberately
may I be forgiven if you have hurt me by thought were to
deed deliberately or inadvertently I forgive you
if I hurt myself by thought word or deed deliberately or
undeliberately I forgive me
now these phrases are just phrases but if you can say them and repeat them
to yourself and keep them in front of you with the idea of intention the intention to
soften your heart to have peace in your heart
it's amazing what it can do
but the first thing you have to do is want to get rid of the pain in your
heart you have to want to let go
some things have become so ingrained in us that they feel like part of us this is who I am I'm the person who who is
the victim of this I'm the person that is fighting against this thing I'm a I'm
a person fighting this bias and all of that reinforcing of me as the
person who is fighting against this is all Happening Here in our own minds
and it's up to us to decide whether we want to let go of that pain or not do I
want to continue holding on to that live wire
my my stepmother is in hospice right now and
earlier in the year I she's 97. so she's she's lived a long
time and I thought I should go see her because there were some things between
us that were not right and I determined I needed to go and talk to her and just get the air cleared to
make my heart at ease and I went to see her and she's she's uh she was even then
somewhat demented and she mostly remembered things 50 years from now that's mostly what she talked about
earlier 50 years earlier and my husband kept saying uh you you
haven't you haven't talked to your mother yet you haven't talked to your mother about that yet you haven't went and I said you know it turns out I don't
need to talk to her it's all in me this this discomfort this unease
I no longer need to say anything to her it serves no use useful purpose
totally unneeded not because it was too late but because
I finally let go of my own holding on to the discomfort
I finally just said oh it's all in my mind it's all in my heart
it's miraculous
it's going to read another Jane hirschfield poem this book is just wonderful
so the name of this poem is the bowl if meat is put into the bowl
meat is eaten if rice is put into the bowl it may be cooked
If a shoe is put in the bowl the leather is chewed and chewed over a sentence
that cannot be taken in or forgiven a day if a day could feel must feel like
a bowl Wars loves trucks betrayals kindness it eats them
then the next day comes spotless and hungry the bowl cannot be thrown away it cannot
be broken it is calm unequipsable rindless and big though it seems fits
exactly into human hands hands with ten fingers 54 bones capacity
strange to us almost past measure scented as the curve of the bowl is with
cardamom staranus long pepper cinnamon hyssa the bowl is just the bowl it's what we
put into the bowl that we eat
so I hope this has some meaning for you and understand that it is the laying
down of the flame that leads to blamelessness thank you
hey thank you Maria so if anyone on Zoom or YouTube has any questions can raise
your hand Zoom or you can put your questions into chat on zoom and YouTube and we'll
read the chat messages to Maria as they come in
um I I had a quick question about the Thanksgiving dinner actually so um you know I think it sounds like you
had a change of mindset or change of how you looked at things
um and our expectations it sounds like and so was there any
I've experienced this myself where I've kind of changed the way I've seen or drawn boundaries sometimes and like did
you communicate your change of expectations to your guests or was it just kind of like well I've changed my
expectations and they'll have to just deal with my shift in mindset
well of course the shift to mindset was really positive for them because I stopped grumping around
so it wasn't necessary for me to say you know I've changed my mind and now I'm going to think this about it what what
what I did was uh I first of all began asking people for something rather than
expecting them to offer it to me you know what that's like well you know if you loved me you would just do this
right I wouldn't have to tell you so I would say you know you have special special need requests would you mind
bringing one thing that that you I used to make three separate meals at
Thanksgiving to meet everybody's uh particular dietary requirements you
know and so I would just so I would ask people for something and I would give up
my idea of what it had to look like and so I gave up wanting the food to be
a certain way and and let let go of of uh I I heard that people treated a
holiday as a day I can let go and so my gift to them became letting go for them
allowing them to let go and not resenting them for letting go and laying around that's what they
wanted to do with their holiday so it involved looking outward and not so much
emphasis on what was inward I didn't have to say anything I just
became a more pleasant person not by Design but by effect
so yeah yeah the communication sounds like it was also a good kind of lubricator as well too yeah cool it's
great sometimes you have to tell people what your expectations are expect them to
know yes exactly yeah uh so we've got uh Lucinda if you want
to unmute yourself and thank you hi hi I really enjoyed this
week very much thank you um two questions one is on which uh book
for the Jane hirschfield uh did you read from okay okay thank you
um and then I recently discovered it turns out I had another copy on my shelf already
I relate um my my question uh is around forgiveness I've been um uh recently
struggling with a family member and um came to around a pretty huge conflict
and uh through basically through this practice
um have come to a place of true forgiveness and um the but what's come up for me is um I
am uh scheduled to go on a family trip with this family member
somebody I deeply love um and who's and my ability to get hurt
by this person is uh monumental and I don't know what to
do with it other than not to do anything about it I mean I just I don't have any idea it's it's not until December but
it's a big trip and um I'm just letting it be I don't know what
else to do I mean I feel like I have this thing that wants to have a conversation with this person but
he he's not a very he's not open to that often uh any any insight
or suggestions so uh it's a little unclear to me well
um what the what the fear is it sounds like the you don't want to be in conflict
with this person but you want more than that you want also to to have a feeling of affection between one another yeah so
so um
all conditions are different so but all families are are different but similar
and uh I have been in conflict with various members of my family and want
them to be uh and want that not to be true and so the approach I've taken is
to avoid those places where I think where we are in conflict and recall call
to mind in me what it is
that I would be the attitude that I would like to have so what I mean by that is I want people to be friendly to
me I begin by being friendly and not by putting my Awareness on how we differ
um so I I work inside myself to to be what
I want to be and not become someone who knows how to deal with this does that help at all that's so helpful
that is so helpful thank you thank you
okay and from YouTube uh Kane is asking how do you let go of judgment and blame
from close family especially when you know your intentions are correct and you are doing the right thing it feels like
I I have to emotionally close off to them to protect myself
no no we're actually going to talk about that tomorrow
that is my topic for tomorrow it has to do with uh Equanimity establishing
Equanimity and um and it it has primarily to do with the
realization that what others choose to do
is not my they choose to do I don't get to I don't
get to determine what they do just as they don't determine what I do and so it
comes from a place of my suffering arises from my own
intentions and actions not what others may wish for me despite what I may wish for others
things are as they are there's a certain amount of letting go
of the need for it to be different that is essential but I'm really going to spend a lot of
time talking about a lot of time we only have 15 minutes but I'm going to talk about that tomorrow so I want to delay
that that particular theme what I can say is that uh
the act of judgment the the deliberate you are wrong about this
is building up in one's heart the resistance the blame the anger the ill
will that will lead to suffering and understand that in doing that you are
doing that to yourself I am doing it to myself if I am get if I
arrive loaded for bear you know you need to
we all need to see that not everybody is coming from the same place
and whatever they choose to do is their choice we can we can
be as generous as possible with what we think will help them but we
can't make them do anything they will do what they will do
and some of the pain arises from the frustration of not being able to fix it
so to recognize one's own need to fix something is adding to the suffering of watching
their suffering is useful so Cain without any uh
specifics about the issue the the only thing I can say is that anger resentment judgment lies
in US and then way to let go of them is to see
when they arise to not be enchanted by them
and they fall away to not be enchanted by the unrightness of this to not be overcome with
righteousness but just to I see
you're suffering my suffering arises from our own intentions and actions not
what others wish for us so we we will talk about that more
tomorrow thank you hey Susie uh you've got your hand ray so
you can go ahead and unmute
you're muted Susie okay
you're there
Susie we can't hear you now you're muted
sorry about that can you hear me now yes I have I have four Bluetooth devices I
can't I'm trying to always connect because a computer says perhaps out good morning Maria
um I was I was sort of fixated on use the word refute one's refusal
to um which is I haven't heard you use that word before and and it reminds me of a
past lover would say that I say to me that I choose suffering and I would respond you know if if I could it's not
it's not something I would actually voluntarily choose I just don't know how to do it differently so the refusal was
a little new for me in your vocabulary and and I was thinking also that when
you responded to a woman about uh the Thanksgiving dinner how you
Focus you you choose you give your attention to what what you I forgot
already what you said what you like what you have in common with your with the family members rather than areas of
difference so when that resentment anger judgment hurt victimhood arises and the nature
The Habit energy is that Groove is so deep where can you know before we fall in
besides noticing the Rival which is arising which is already not being
intoxicated you know what where where can we go you just said some a place to
give our attention but it's not so familiar it's not familiar um place for me you talked about
intentions and actions and is there something more um a lay person
friendly um yeah and and once again I am going to
talk about this tomorrow so uh the um
I discovered for example that I got into uh
group behavior that a group behaves different than an individual and so to
deal with my family what I did was call everybody up or text them and say I want
to meet with you just you they appreciated the attention and then we didn't have the family dynamics that
altered it if you know this is just an example of something that is
that is just a shift away from how things always are so that I set up in
advance a little bit of protection around habits right so so I no longer go
to big parties with my family I see them individually and I've learned so much more about them I like them so much more
and I assume they feel the same because it's just us and it's simpler
now if it's a one-on-one with someone and I uh
I can um feel myself saying oh you always do that
as soon as I hear you always do that in my head I remind myself they don't always do
that and this is this is me putting the emphasis on you always do that it's me
placing blame and if I can just stop placing blame and hear whatever it is
they're saying Just Hear It actually hear it
I'm less likely to be reactive it's when I think it sounds just like then I'm I
drag myself into that pattern so I listen for my own triggers
and that you always do that that statement just right away catches my attention
you always do that oh and I always react this way and did you really do that and
what are you really saying it's a pulling back into now and letting
go of all the things that happened before you know that little string that we
carry along behind us of you know the continuity of life it is just
get back into the now as fast as you can just oh wait a minute what's happening
right now what did you just say what what and hear it without the baggage of
the habit it just takes practice Susie
and sometimes I fail boy there's a wonderful animal out here
making clicking sounds and I don't know what it is but I am not going to be distracted by it other questions
Theresa you can go ahead and unmute hi Theresa hi Maria
um maybe this will all be resolved by the time tomorrow when you give your
other talk but um I'm having a lot of trouble with a sister of mine who's a year younger
than me and the last year we've just had these terrible art conflicts and arguments that don't go anywhere like we
get so angry that I just get lost and I think I'm coming
to the fact that it's very possible we just can't relate to each other
and I'm I'm having trouble letting go of her like it it's almost like I'm anxious
about it and um I mean I hear everything you're saying and a lot of is about I want this
reality to be a certain way I want this to be a close sister relationship and
for years there's been something wrong so let me let me remind you that the the
the vision of it being a close sister relationship has is a specific vision
and for you a close relationship looks like X and I'm not going to presume what
it is yeah whatever it is that's the expectation that's not being met not the
closeness the intimacy intimacy between people is very tricky
because we have an idea of what it looks like what it should look like yep
that is the place that view is the place they're not matching my view
so there's somebody very close to me that I was in conflict with because for
political reasons it would be a huge gigantic political Gap
and I kept and and all of us would say
how can he believe that how can he believe that he must not be who I thought he was and I kept reminding
myself he's exactly who I thought he was he's living his life this way despite
what he professes and he is a good man
so I shifted my attention to knowing what I know about him and not the
argument that we're having between us and I never let go of
he's a good man and and the subject of her which
we fought hasn't come up in about a year and a half
and he is a good man
and and it was a it was a serious breach
but what got me through
was just recalling this is a good man
it's where you put your attention it's it's the meat you put in the bowl is what you eat
the shoe you put in the bowl is what you shoot you chew on
so yeah it's an expectation of a family that is hard to it's dying
it hard yes yes yeah
I'm just hoping it it does pass because it it just eats at me and keeps
me awake but yes I just need to continue it's in you yeah you have more control
over it than you think it's just that we don't have control so all we do is just repeat here's my
intention but it doesn't have to look the way I see it this is really important it doesn't have to look the
way I see it I got my happy family Thanksgiving it didn't look the way I thought it
would look that's what I had to let go of okay okay
and uh so I also want to say that you know the the Saturday group had a couple of
people drop out of it those of you who know about that and so there are a couple of open spots on the Saturday
practice Discussion Group so uh next Kevin
hey Wendy you can go ahead and unmute
Wendy oh hi
um so I was um thinking about the forgiveness
and I have a family member that
caused me some childhood trauma and
I had actually kind of you know let go of that and kind of
forgiven him but then I started to feel like I wasn't
honoring myself and that that was hurtful and that maybe
I should you know I don't know what I would do with that
but maybe I shouldn't let him off the hook
so easily I I don't know I'm not really sure you know what I I don't know if
this is I do so once again forgiveness is for
you not for him forgiveness is for you
it is it is so you hold in your heart peacefulness
so so there's a place to start from and and then I remind you that it does not mean that
you condone or pardon the behavior you're not pardoning the person you're
not telling them it's okay it is still not okay
but the fact that it's coming back says that there's still some part of you that's that is holding on to a piece of
of uh pain and resentment over it
I can tell you I went through forgiveness practice with my father who had
caused some pain in my life and I finally got to the place where I had
forgiven him and I said okay he did it the best that he could do and after I
heard that in my head several times I said what if he didn't do the best he could do
and I realized that my forgiveness was conditional I had made an excuse for him
and I had to go begin all over again to let go of
I can only let go of this if I make an excuse for you
so I did more forgiveness practice and more forgiveness practice until I realized that all the pain I was
creating when I felt you know it's one thing to intellectually say you're creating your own Pain by recalling this
and and holding on to resentment and it's quite another to feel it coming and
going quite another
the determination to live with a peaceful heart
allows you to notice those moments when there is peace in your heart and to say ah into those moments
and then you don't choose to suffer you say ah
that was then and today I'm at peace and that peace grows
I hope that helps Wendy yeah yeah I just have to
make the decision I guess not to find myself going back to
the memories of those events from my childhood
things about my father that I really loved only the people who you love can really
hurt you interesting yeah
I guess so yeah so I just wish there was a way to turn that
off in my head it feels like I just keep going back there over and over again I know
so I I had I had some uh an offense that that came up that I worked with a lot
that uh the forgiveness was kind of global and um
that is it didn't have a single person that I needed to let go of and over time
I became to the realization that this had become a kind of metaphor for
for unhappiness in my life that is I began to see that when that story came
up in my thoughts it meant I there was something I needed to pay attention to that that was not actually the proximal
cause of my unease it's just that in my mind I went back to that
so whenever I hear a particular story that has to do with something in my life
when that story starts running in my head I think oh oh there's some similarity here
something is going on in my life that I'm not paying attention to what is it I saw it now it's become a kind of uh
not a touch tone but a warning light that story so you might consider that also that
that it comes up because there is some need in your life that needs to be seen
yeah okay thank you
Maria we had a question about the Saturday group and how someone would
find out about that uh so if you get the The Weekly Newsletter it's always in
there there's a section that says you can talk with teachers either through the the group practice discussions or
individual practice discussions and also on the website um
I always it changes so on the website there's a section I'd
have to look it up Maureen do you happen to know can can you help us here where where to find
that exactly Cindy actually just posted the link on um oh that would be wonderful thank you
that's great if someone posted the link so it's a Sign Up Genius thing
okay Cindy posted it um and I just reposted it in Zoom so
okay great thank you um Cindy actually had a question
in chat is it okay to stay away from the person that has caused trauma in your
life I can forgive but I'm not interested in being with the person because it's upsetting
well why would you put yourself through that yeah stay away from them
you know you're you're not required to seek out suffering there's plenty of it to go around
so uh until I can feel
and you know the the thing is not to make it into a thing I'm never going to be around this person but to to avoid
being in a place that that stimulates the memory and the pain in this and the
suffering there's no need there's no need to make yourself feel unsafe but you can test it every once in a while
and see how sensitive you are to that and see if the sensitivity changes
yeah Cindy well other other people in my family you know like try to put guilt on me you know
that I won't participate there's seven kids in my family Irish Catholic anyway so
um it's one person out of seven so I guess that's not bad but but
um yeah it's just the pressure I get you know because I don't want to go to
family reunions I don't want to be involved in um they say what's your you know they
just put pressure on me it's hard to let go of we're going to talk about that tomorrow okay great
specifically thank you hey Maria well I think that's uh that's
all we've got today and um I think you've provided uh a good enough wedding of the appetite for tomorrow's talk so
it sounds like everyone's looking forward to that so no pressure right thank you everyone
may you know peace in your hearts thank you everyone and as you sign off feel free to come
off of mute if you want to say goodbye or give me greetings thank you Maria thank you bye thank you
bye-bye thanks everybody thank you Maria
good to see you all thank you thank you till tomorrow