great so hello and welcome everyone just happy having heard your voices and your
hellos from different parts of the world just ah happy making this sense of connection
um but we have knowing that there are other practitioners in the world joining
us we're all practicing together so so
let's just start and I'll start the guided meditation and the theme will
reveal itself to all of us during the the meditation so let's begin
Landing arriving in our bodies in this moment
Landing with with out breath letting go
of whatever has come before foreign
this moment the experience of this moment is all we truly know
can we befriend this moment foreign
s in the body the breath
your heart mind
collecting and Gathering ourselves peacefully with the breath
make a lullaby especially if we need calming and soothing nourishing
as if we're being rocked back and forth
in the arms of the breath gently rocked back and forth with the breath
aching Refuge
foreign
letting go of wanting things to be any other way than
they actually are right now tell us for a moment you can always go
back later to wanting it to be different and right now what if we
relax often
foreign
thoughts that will come Reflections contemplations memories
some of them helpful some of them not what if we just turn away
take refuge in the Simplicity of just being
here being braved and say not now thank you even if they're helpful thoughts
Reflections later
just enjoying being not doing not planning not becoming not
all of that just being
as if you were throwing out cold here in your cup
emptying your cup of stale teeth
letting the breath cleanse you calm you stabilize you
an act of love to let yourself be soothed this heart to be held
and the simplicity of not doing one thing being it's an act
of Love of care to release
loving and accepting this being who is you
just as they show up in this moment
tired cranky sad excited
relax soften
let yourself be held lovingly the breath
foreign
love with the silence
silence the rhythm of the breath
silent ends within can we fall in love with it
enjoy it not seeing something else
entertainment planning destruction just be content
with the amazing gift of the breath
foreign
or whom you have Meta Care kindness
with whom you have an uncomplicated relationship ideally
children or pets are fine bring them to your mind's eye your heart
as if they were in front of you and for this practice we're invited
to see their goodness their good qualities of course everyone's a mixed bag and
areas to grow all of that yes of course but
see their goodness see their strength see their goodness
tune into that
stay with the breath stay embodied and with each breath
let your heart love your head let your heart see feel into the goodness of this being
with appreciation
let it serve as a source of joy
that this being with these qualities is in your life
foreign
ties let yourself really relish them
maybe they're really a good cook appreciating
and they've cooked for you just the Delight of their goodness your skills their generosity
let yourself relish their light
the light of their being
foreign
but in nature their goodness relishing that basking in their light
their strength and their capacities or good heart
it feels so good to recollect the Buddha nature the
goodness of another bask in it with delight
with vicarious Joy
now as if you're removing yourself so that you're not seeing this being how
how they benefit you per se but just the way they are
Shifting the lens slightly still seeing their goodness
um or objectively
foreign worker they work hard
either dedicated to their friends and their family
see their goodness more generally foreign
making space
foreign
as a beloved other see yourself just as you are seeing this
dear being see yourself as a third person see your own goodness
strengths capacities as if you're saying your own Buddha
nature by asking in the goodness
same way
foreign
tuning in to your own goodness maybe see yourself from the perspective of this
dear being
foreign love you I admire you
foreign
in your own goodness your own Buddha nature divine nature
divinity
foreign
period together let your heart be filled asking
enjoy take delighted the fastness of this being who's you
you barely know
of this earth and the Earthling and so much Beyond
so much Beyond in ways you don't know and understand not reducing yourself
to a two-dimensional version foreign
letting the goodness of our practice whatever Roser did not arise
dedicating with generosity this goodness together
to each other to ourselves to all things everywhere may all beings everywhere
know their own goodness okay all things everywhere be afraid
including ourselves
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
[Music] joyous to see here
faces on the screen your light shining all of you with your
own Beauty goodness capacities light each of
us in our own unique way shining our light
so so as I
set up the small groups if there are any quick Reflections you're welcome to share them there will be more time at
the end but now I like to invite you all to uh to see you know this is an engagement of
the rubber meeting the road as we engage in small groups together
and uh the sense of letting letting your goodness letting your good not focusing
on your challenges your difficulties what's going wrong what's but actually
letting your light shine and speaking about this person knows you as if you're
representative like oh yes this person who's me actually they they love to practice or they they they
are dedicated to honesty or they're dedicated to their friends or or they
they like to be generous or they're good cook they're loved to cook for their friends just something about the
goodness of you as if you're sitting on your own shoulder you're being your own representative okay let me tell you about this person they're great in this
I'm just sharing that and if you feel too shy it's not you it's your representative that's sharing something
but it's it's nice to actually say something about that like oh yes this this person who's me like likes to be
generous like it's true and don't shy away like oh I don't want to own it what
if you actually showed up with your goodness we show up with all our problems and difficulties in the world
but what if you actually let your goodness shine again not from a place of ego but if I'm a place of goodness it's
very different and see if you can navigate and see that difference if you're speaking from a place of egos
okay say pass I'm gonna just pass and stood with this and maybe the next time it comes my maybe I'll say something or
you can just say pass if it's like a little uncomfortable it's totally fine so past I'm just gonna hold silent and
I'm not quite ready to talk yet perfectly fine hold other people's Beauties and goodness with with with
modita with vicarious Joy but it's lovely to celebrate that with each other
unusual we usually don't celebrate goodness we get together and complain about what's not going well celebrate
goodness just try try something a little different why not let's experiment
so so let's go in alphabetical order and
again you can say pass it's perfectly fine but something you share one one thing but you're realized about this
being in this person is a hard worker they work really hard um
Etc and uh just say one nugget one thing share one thing the next person the next person comes back to you maybe one other
thing or not just uh but make sure everybody gets the chance to to share
something and to be celebrated celebrate each other yay how fun how fun so
I'm gonna open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other up
let me recreate the rooms hold on here we go okay creating rooms all right take
care of yourselves take care of each other here we go okay the rooms are back the rooms are
closed everybody's back welcome back everyone and uh we have time for a few
Reflections you're welcome to type them in chat either to me privately or to
everyone or you can also raise your Zoom hand if it's your physical hand I may not see you how was this practice seeing
someone else's goodness and then seniors celebrating your own goodness and and also in the group Kim please
I just have to apologize because I was put into a room and then I was trying to
press the enlarge and I was pretty pressing the X and so I was kicked out and then I was invited to another room
same thing went for a large if they acts but I was successful in the third in the
third room so my apologies to those of you I came in and jumped out
ah but that's sweet you visited lots of different rooms came you you spread your your light
and and the other any other anything else besides an apology or or
you know sharing what happened with the group any observations you want to share again while you have before
you don't have to switch on the spot um it was a good meditation it was uh
I enjoyed it I was able to um fall through with it and I would at
one point you know I was visualizing my lovable being and it kind of came
into me and then you said uh give yourself some space moved them back out
and then I was able to um yeah see myself from their point of
view and then also think of some memories of me of when I
was showing some good qualities sweet thank you thanks for sharing that
Kim lovely beautiful yeah Ellie please
hello yeah I was uh very interesting because I'm just so uh close to the inner critic
for so long I mean it was just hard stretch for me to do it and then I said why not
and in the first one that came on was a little hard but then it kept rolling and it just like I started enjoying it kind
of like befriending myself for the first time because the other part I know so well but this is very very new
so thank you very much Nikki oh thank you Ellie thank you so much wonderful
and I'm so happy to hear delighted to hear that you stuck with it even though it just seemed a little unfamiliar and
difficult not usually don't quite go here but I'm just gonna try it out and then oh wow it gets easier yes of course
it does beautiful so appreciate you sharing that for the benefit of everyone all ever who might also be in the same
uh spaces you shared thank you Ali lovely thank you
Fred please thanks Nikki um Kim we were happy to see you come in
for a second sorry to see you disappear another time um
um I would have found this impossible to do if I were speaking from the first person and uh if I was doing it
correctly referring to myself in the third person uh made it possible and uh
still not easy uh but but feasible in a way that you know using the eye would just would
have been out of the question nice thank you Fred so appreciate
um you sharing that actually having the third person perspective made it easier
it just created a little bit of space and beautiful thanks for sharing that
that Insight it just makes it a little easier beautiful yeah
um Neil says we use the term damn weird
funny [Laughter] uh and Chloe thank you for sharing that
you've been uh recovering from mysterious bike accident and and wonderful that you're able to join us
now wonderful hope you feel better soon yeah on the other maybe I'll just make a
pause for one given that this is such a quote-unquote damn weird factors but
just you know it is possible it's possible to see the goodness of this person yeah they are good in these ways
how wonderful to celebrate that
well I'm glad that you were able to celebrate some of your own goodness and goodness of each other in this practice
this in this moment and uh yeah thank you thank you for showing up for
cultivating your own goodness letting your light shine you have so much goodness every single one of you oh my
Heavens so much so thank you for sharing that take good care may you all be well
may we all be well may we all be free
[Music] hey take care everyone
I'll see you on Monday we have a guest