so uh so welcome folks um
yeah nice to see her your names over there in the chat um
uh question about recordings those will be posted in a
couple couple days of volunteers working to uh edit those get those
posted to Audio Dharma but they're of course always available on YouTube
okay um very sweet all right let's uh
that's it
maybe we could summarize the Dharma saying
something like
we're becoming more and more sensitive to goodness
the goodness within oneself
goodness of others
goodness of Peace Love
wisdom
goodness of the path
sensitive to goodness
and the goodness that runs through US surrounds us becomes
both very ordinary and very touching
and becomes the foundation of our practice
kind of Bedrock from which our efforts emerge
to which our efforts return
how we live and we die
so sensing as we begin no way goodness runs right through you
if we get tight contracted
let's touch back in with any uh
reminder goodness
ensuring we're not alienated from from it
poison that goodness we let the breath come to us
foreign
noticing the relief that comes
when oxygen hunger builds and we breathe in
saturating our body with exactly what it needs
no pleasure of breathing out
when we've been nourished by the in-breath
the relief of exhaling what's been
let's nourish their body
these cycles of giving receiving constitutes a life
we can be clear precise result higher resolution
in perceiving breath as it comes and goes
we're gonna be clear precise resolved
that uh tension
kind of devotion that is uh unhurried
it's uh so natural to hedge our our bets on this moment
to uh try and tie up all the the Loose Ends of
Being Human so we allocate
some of our love to the Future to worry to the Past
but maybe
suspended in some some sense of goodness of care
we relax our vigilance feel safe enough
to [Music] devote ourselves to what's here
to your body breathing
you don't need to manufacture the sacred
foreign
that's good to uh good to sit with you
um so yesterday we started um with uh
with faith faith first of the the five faculties
and uh today uh um energy energetic Vigor very uh
so I I uh just a few days ago finished
um teaching a retreat at IRC with Inez Inez Friedman and um
the theme was was doing and non-doing and we would
sort of alternate Dharma talks and she represented the effortful side the
doing and I represented the dimensions of the path where we mostly get out of
the way and it really um
it really is a dialectic between the doing and the non-doing
but the effortful side is no joke you
know it's this is not this path is not something for nothing
the uh and and guter and Nakaya the Buddha said that uh that he is careful
never to rest on contented with his skillful qualities
says relentlessly I exerted myself gladly would I let the flesh and blood
in my body dry up leaving just the skin tendons and bones but if I had not attained what can be
reached through human firmness human persistence human striving there will be no relaxing
my persistence yeah and uh
you hear that and you can see how it lands in your mind and
I think historically I've been quite inspired by kind of images of
warrior-like effort and uh
yeah they've held a certain place in my heart and mind but we want to interrogate where do we
Source our effort from
sometimes it's okay to strive most long
term practitioners have periods of striving there's some striving there's
some clinging and just so you know it it's not like we
um spontaneously combust if we strive
but but all the the kind of willfulness can
actually reinforce a sense of self a sense of me striving to make practice
make practice work you know kind of
and that um that striving
yes solidifies the the kind of wrong view maybe we say
I I described a a very kind of willful mode of practice
to a teacher and uh with Incredible really just
Exquisite kindness the teacher said to me something like
Matthew you're running a Dharma race from stupid
to stupid
moments you don't you don't forget that it actually filled me with delight you
know just to like feel in that moment released
yeah released from this willful mode of the area of effort because for me
somewhere early in my practice Viria and
sakya Didi got yolked together this effort and self-view the
contraction and tension of self got yoked together
and the sense of of who I was and my place
on the spiritual path and progress and my problems my defilements
they're all kind of congealed in this sense of um yeah in a way beginning with
wrong View and there's this real um tangle of of dhamma Chanda and
conceit of damachanda longing long by heart longing for the Dharma
and the kind of sincerity and and beauty of
that longing was mixed in with a whole raft
of self-view and in that in that cell view in that
conceit uh there is self-harseness is born idealism
and unbalanced striving is born comparing mind competitiveness is born
a whole kind of um
blood of of pain and so
we we make effort we really do make effort
but we must all witness the the limits
of our willfulness to witness the limits of our work to
actually vividly encounter the willfulness failing us
to encounter the ways that that sourcing our effort from that Wells Spring
uh leads to some tension and so the the question like what what
does effort for you look like on the other side of
your willfulness that's a kind of koan
is it possible for us to uh to rest amidst effort
I I would love when uh teacher teacher Dal Qigong we would do
Chi young in the morning before Rich you know Retreat sitting started and uh
and the language he would use it like under do it under do it
we're still doing it it was still 6 a.m and we're doing we're
awake and moving but under do it
a sad adaptation here says right effort is effort with wisdom wisdom
because where there is wisdom there's interest the desire to know something is wisdom at work being mindful is not
difficult but it's difficult to be continuously aware for that you need right effort
but it doesn't require a great deal of energy it's a relaxed perseverance and reminding yourself to be aware
when you're aware wisdom unfolds naturally and they're still more interest the mind's relaxed the Mind
knows something about itself the meaning of effort is to continue try
to be patient try to be relaxed
effort is um it's a major major theme in
the the suit does my I'm not a scholar but my understanding is it's like uh you
kind of numerical count you know effort is is uh is up there in terms of uh
frequently mentioned uh themes and
it is in part A major theme in the suit does because
Neurosis is often the path of least resistance
I talked about the the pervasiveness of goodness the sensitivity to goodness that's that's
all true too but Neurosis is often
the path of least resistance meaning like my bad habits require
precisely zero effort
the Glide path to Donuts is frictionless
yeah whatever yeah nothing wrong with donuts
um William James says uh uh were mere
bundles of habit we are imitators and uh copiers of our past selves
that kind of psychological karmic neural momentum
imitators and copiers of our past cells and
not all of our habits are conducive to our happiness
and so deep growth deep growth is not always comfortable sometimes it feels
like water running down a hill but often takes energy it takes energy to
it takes energy to [Music] listen to our own best advice
when we know what needs to be done we often have some access to
wisdom but it's hard hard to listen to that
Shanti Davis says we hate suffering I love its causes
as a remarkable distillation of so much hate suffering but love its causes
one way of of reading that is that um clinging has partially worked
it's been reinforced it's been conserved over time certainly over evolutionary
time but over the time of our own life clinging's been reinforced
and the craving clinging acquisition maybe momentary relief
and then disappointment and then
a new back to that that disappointment the on
quenchability of Cl of craving that gives rise to a new cycle
another round we tried again and
Dharma looks at the the ways that suffering has been reinforced
the partial satisfaction of clinging anger with its honey tip and poisoned
root the mudassan that's just one example
but to to put down the poison we have to renounce the honey
and that takes effort energy
I hate suffering but the love its causes energy is often about
loving the causes of suffering thus
and we do what we can to source that
effort from from Wise view from Wise View
from relaxation from sensitivity sensitivity to goodness
offer this for your consideration oh wow
that's lovely to uh think of you out there somewhere all of us out there
somewhere and uh
we'll uh we'll keep going so I wish you all a good day May uh may
you not be alienated from uh from goodness