all right so I'm gonna take a breath then I invite you to do the same
kind of find your your groundedness in your body
feel yourself resting into the chair the cushion
giving your weight to the support it's here for you
and just check in with your system your nervous system your sense of ease and
maybe Orient to your location IMC
right feel free to peek if you need to look around and help your mind kind of come
into this moment this space right here help it kind of bring this
energy this location here here now
I'm taking some yeah deeper breaths so let's lift the shoulders if you wish
toward the ears and then roll them back and even bring the elbows toward each other so we want to have the curve and
the spine and then push the elbows down toward the hips
and this helps us engage the diaphragm and breathing opens the chest so we can
more naturally take a fuller deeper breath
it's at the start of the meditation I often do these things including these
intentional deeper breaths to help my body
my nervous system shift into a space of more ease well-being
so I'll just allow a little bit of Silence here and then I'll begin the guided practice
foreign
a guided visualization but I want you to know that you can translate the visual
into any way that your mind imagines
connects also invite you to shift and change any
of the scenery or the words so that it resonates with your being
and feel free to tune me out as well
so we're preparing to go for a journey
and we have ourselves ready and we're at the edge of a nature
preserve a forest
and we have companions with us
and as you look around at these companions
you recognize softness
gentleness patience
attentiveness
when you think to yourself these are people I would like to have around me
and as you look up and out toward the path where you'll be walking
you notice that there is a richness a lushness
to the forest
and you all begin to walk together
there's plenty of room walking at a pace that feels comfortable
and you start to notice this feeling of
inner what is it bubbling Joy or
peace a sense of a heart lifting
the sense that we're going somewhere important
as we're walking and it just gets more and more beautiful
and the path is opening up ahead you can see more light more space
in a Gateway sort of a large arch of flowers and Vines
they're pink and purple
and every color you love the most
and as you approach the Gateway you see there's some words
and you see that the space and the words on the garden
say that they're dedicated the space is dedicated to the well-being and happiness of all
and as you walk in you can feel this clear
the way it's arranged the places to sit or rest
the shade and the Sun
and as you look around you understand that everyone here
is kin we are all connected
we all belong in this space
and we are all included
there's a feeling that this these wishes of well-being are rating radiating out
into the space into ourselves each other
her attention is warm and clear like the sun and water for all the
plants here and we notice the feeling
and we dwell in it
we feel it's spreading
feeling safe
feeling happy healthy
and at ease
abiding here
and in the distance you hear a child
it was laughing and then it starts to cry
foreign as you hear the child cry you feel your heart
open caring
you can feel that you are
experiencing empathy for this child care
and you can see that her loving caregivers
are attending to her gently kindly
and it's soothing to you too to see this care offered
it soothes the heart
and you remember yourself as a child
moments of crying or difficulty and you see this little being and you
think to yourself oh I see you're suffering
I remember suffering that way too
just like you I suffer and just like me you suffer
may your pain and sorrow be eased dear one
and you rest knowing she's being cared for at ease
resting back the softness of the grass or the chair
you're in
taking in the smells the sounds of nature
you feel the warmth of the Sun
it's shining bright
right now
and then you hear the child and others giggling
happy and at play
and you just open your heart to This Joy rejoicing in their happiness
grateful for their happiness
it's like the sun is Illuminating and
brightening and supporting the joy
and you think to yourself and to this happiness I'm happy that you are happy
radiant Sunbeam of happiness
and Joy shared
and it's time to move on to another part of this beautiful
Forest and you prepare to stand and walk again
with your friends enjoying the scenery as you walk
marveling at the sounds and the smells
you're feeling serene a sense of balance and ease
calm
and there's a clearing my head
looking out over a beautiful Valley with a
a mountain lake that's incredibly clear and bright
the scene is so calm so peaceful
breathing in I notice my body is calm
breathing out I notice my mind is calm
thank you I find a spot at the side of the lake
overlooking it just a bit
I find a comfortable posture
I feel like a mountain a bright
still steady strong committed to being here
and I sit
day turns to night night turns today it rains it Suns
and I sit unchanged still
foreign
all right it's really delightful to be here with
you and to see many faces and to know people are wearing masks that feel
comfortable wearing masks thank you for being here
so I want to talk about the Brahma baharas
and um you know I think the most important things that I wanna
I'm hoping to highlight as I make my way through this talk
are that the Brahma baharas are natural States they're natural States they arise
from within they don't need to be fabricated
they they are accessible and there are things that get in the way
and there are things that help connect with them
natural States things that get in the way are also gateways
to them and there are things that we can do to
support ourselves in accessing the states of loving kindness compassion sympathetic joy and
Equanimity these are the four Brahma baharas Heavenly abodes
so if you're not familiar with the role and the place of the brahmaharas in this
practice I'll share a little bit about that but they're um
I'll say first for myself that accessing loving-kindness compassion
sympathetic joy and equanimity it's sort of like a compass for me like
I'm no I notice in myself when I'm engaging or doing something a sort of
where's the heart how's the heart is there a sense of uplift and ease and
openness maybe Joy doesn't have to be Joy but just this sense of
there's space here the heart is free and that's sort of
feedback for me about how what I'm thinking about doing or how I'm engaging so tuning in to this
inner compass that helps us recognize when we're sort of engaging in this
territory and by eating in this territory
and and when I notice that the thoughts that I'm having the
feelings that I'm having the physical states that I'm having are quite the opposite
then recollecting these practices like one of my most favorite recent practices if I'm
noticing this just the mind is just filled with aversion or
difficulty or anxiety I just start to watch it like it's a
stream this flow of content
and I just imagine all this loving kindness and compassion filling up the
waters so all these thoughts and things that are coming up are being held in this
field and so I'm not you know trying to make myself feel better or trying to change
the thoughts or the content I'm just oh may you two be at ease
may you be safe just the thoughts the images the worries
so they're they're really important for me and important in the practice
very kind of transformative they can help us dissolve
self-centeredness and support us feeling connected which
is huge huge
so in the tradition you know they they're talked about as
and these practices related to them are talked about cultivating virtuous
qualities for overcoming self-centeredness
for deepening meditation practice they're actually used as concentration practices
and they help the Mind settle they help the mind come into Unity into
at rest and ease and they are purification practices they
sort of purify by supporting wholesome States and thoughts to arise
and they help us integrate wisdom and insight so if we're the mountain
and we're able to sit with the changing nature of life and experience of the
nights and days and rain and snow and people coming and going and things
changing if we can embody that spaciousness the solidness the
groundedness of the mountain we can be with the ever-changing
experience of life in a way that's balanced right we can see suffering and
not collapse into it
so um Aya kemma was a a nun she was from
Germany and um she described the Rama baharas as
feelings and she also said there are the only emotions worth having
and um and so I'm a therapist right and so I'm
going to contextualize a little bit of the neuropsychological aspects of
understanding emotional states and how they're connected to the Brahma baharas or how we can connect with them
thinking about ourselves as like you know living beings with the nervous
system that shifts changes and is impacted by both inner and outer stimuli
thoughts experiences there's a physiology to the Brahma baharas
our physiology changes when we connect with these States
and so we can use the body to support the mind and support the arising of
these states so some of the very simple Little Things Are um
you know a lot of people will do meditations and they'll say put a smile on your face
have you ever heard that yeah I I I've never been able to have that
help me yeah but recently I was playing with it and
so I invite you to just like non-smile
oh it's not going to work right now but to play with not it's not a smile but
the subtlest lift of the outer lip just the subtle I mean like a micro movement
so that instead of the more downward slant there's just even the flat or just not a smile just a slight slight upturn
just imagining it so not trying to force some sense of smile that feels
manufactured to me I like that word manufactured it's not helpful but if we
actually the there's a lot of research about why smiling is supposed to be helpful it actually activates all this
you know the nerves that are connected to emotional states in your face changes your mood States but maybe a
manufactured smile doesn't work so I played with that and I found this subtlest little bit helped
some other things that we can kind of play with are our tone of voice in both
inner and outer so really noticing how are we talking to ourselves not just the words but the
quality the tonal quality and sometimes that's you know hard to imagine so
forgive me if you've had me do this with you before but it works usually so
um right now just imagine hearing your own name several times just hearing the name
and as you do just kind of pay attention to what you notice in your body
okay now I want you to imagine
somebody who just absolutely adores you saying your name
be an animal anything at all but somebody who really
really likes you they get you I want you to imagine hearing them that
voice that tone hear your name just say your name in your mind a few times with
this voice this affect this tone and notice what happens in your body
Can You Feel the difference
hopefully you can if not there are ways keep trying good
now just for comparison because we're going to be talking about different
neurophysiological states very briefly
I want you to imagine you're in trouble and you hear somebody calling your name
who knows you're in trouble just once or twice just notice how that feels
okay let it go did you feel the difference
yeah okay some of you I see yeses some of you heads are not moving but I'll Trust
enough of you could connect or know and remember that it feels different
and you know um these are we're shifting our
nervous system States as we are imagining and connecting with different ways
of hearing our own voice um and that in it's my belief that there
are certain neurophysiological states that I'll talk about that are actually
the foundation for the way that we feel when we connect with the Brahma baharas
now there are some people talking about this but there's no like literal proof at this point but I think there will be
they'll be doing studies and there probably are some already
but when we um there's something called the vagus nerve in our body which a very
big nerve that goes all the way down into our gut and when the ventral vagus nerve is is
activated it leads to calmness a sense of connection emotional well-being and this this is
associated with physiological changes in the body including our heart rate breathing patterns and a feeling of
safeness
so our blood pressure reduces our digestion improves when the ventral
vagal nerve is stimulated and we have reduced inflammation
our emotional states are more regulated
so there's something called State dependent
traits have you heard that term so states are like emotional states
right or and they are dependent on
in this case the nervous system and where our nervous system is functioning
so if we're in a fierce base right our nervous system is in either
sympathetic arousal or dorsal vagal Activation so there's very clear shifts
in our nervous system this is the most important point there's like a inner gear shift
and we can learn how to shift into different gears with our nervous system
with practice and diligence and and Attunement
it also requires courage and determination because as I said before
um when difficulties arise when things are difficult and we aren't accessing these
states those difficulties can actually be gateways to the Brahma vihars
if we can turn toward our suffering our difficulty and be with it with wisdom and care
and then we activate these practices they can actually help us access
a very different state
so the Buddha when he was teaching about the Brahma baharas
and he was talking about these these states he said he described the Buddha
describes a farmer who works hard to plant and water a crop but cannot command the plants to grow
instead with the seasons have changed there comes a time when the crops grow mature and bear grain
so this comes back to this idea of cultivation activation versus fabrication right not
needing just like the farmer can't make the plant grow
by yelling at it and telling it it the farmer creates conditions
supportive conditions for the FL the the plants to grow themselves
so like you know like the blossoming of a flower we don't need to do much but we
need to let it have sun shine and water and you know pull the weeds out from
around it and it'll do what it does in the same way you know we can be the
Gardeners of our own inner life and we can cultivate and support the
arising of these qualities
I have a lot of notes I have so much to know so many notes I have to scroll through you know kind of skipping around
my notes to uh find what I want to share
so the role of the gardener
it's the role of the gardener right for our inner state so you know taking where the caretakers of
our minds our hearts and our bodies so you know just like it's so important to
have sun and water and good soil we need sleep right we need to eat we need
social connection engagement it's you know kind of simple but easy
things for us to ignore too right but very very important
and um you know as the farmer does we we need to observe
what's happening on the farm you know noticing the conditions
and devoting time to practicing caregiving caretaking
and we need to learn right we need to have wisdom and be learning about how to care for our garden right
so that's in this in the field of the Dharma that's studying the Dharma and practicing the Dharma
and spending time with spiritual friends
and knowing what we want to grow and what we don't want to grow
and being really clear about that being clear about the dangers of growing
greed growing hatred and growing delusion
they will overtake the garden
so everything I like this point that everything is an opportunity for practice and it can be a
gateway to Freedom
things can be weeds or seeds and the weeds can even be turned into
seeds right to fertilize her at least
so for example if I'm thinking about
[Music] um a situation and a life that might be fairly common
I might think about um
a time when someone's mind is you know filled with ill will
a lot of hatred or fear and anxiety which is also a form of
ill will and
when one finds themself in that space because it can happen to all of us right
if we recognize it if we name it and see it clearly
and we can turn toward it in a way that isn't engaging in it
we see the suffering right there right there
and if there's a sense of natural loving kindness present we can go right to
compassion but sometimes the foundation is the loving kindness
so the sense of deep connection with knowing like all beings
we want to feel safe we want to feel happy we want to feel healthy and at ease
so if for example this the cause of this hostility is somebody else and what
they're doing it might not be possible to say just like you I suffer just like me you
suffer right we might not be quite there but we can connect with the fact that we
want to feel safe happy healthy and at ease and we don't right now
so we can start to connect with that wish the loving kindness wish for ourselves
right and we can start to kind of just not try and make ourselves feel that way but
recognize that is truly what we want we don't want to feel miserable
right we want to feel well and when we when that wisdom and that
Clarity comes in that the loving kindness can become accessible
and sometimes when we start to feel it enough for ourselves it's just automatically there
for the other person and then compassion is much more accessible
and the compassion is really seeing that somebody else suffers just like we do and they just want to be
happy just like we want to they want to have well-being and ease and so whatever it is that's happening
you know whatever's motivating it we can recognize inside this sense of oh well
this is what they want and I want this too and I care
so if we can you know just recognize these states that are filled with greed
right wanting something that somebody else has for example
I want that chair I want that job I want that
scooter whatever it is that car whatever it is that shirt
that smile when we see that sense of I want that I
don't have it you know I wish I could have it ah there's greed and the opportunity
right there to have sympathetic Joy if we can shift again Foundation is metha so if the meta
is not there maybe we need to cultivate it a little bit and recognize our suffering right we
oh may I be it safe and at ease and then oh oh yeah
I'm happy you're happy I'm happy for you that you have this job or this chair
the smile I'm happy that you know this is bringing you Joy
oh and yeah actually I as I sit back and take in your happiness I feel some
happiness too and so we can work it's just a reminder we've just walked down the wrong path in
the garden and we just need to help ourselves reorient the same spot maybe
facing a different direction
Maybe you know where we're lost in thought and we're
trying to imagine exactly how we're going to do this and then that and then that and what if this happens and then
that happens and we're exhausted trying to figure out you
know how we're going to cope with this and make this better and do this and do that so we're just filled with
building these Futures and plans and it's like a mix of greed and aversion and lots of delusion
lots and lots of delusion and we can see if we step back and we
see oh look this is so much activity so much effort it's no longer useful no
longer helpful and we can go oh
wow yeah things come and go we can like things change and this I'm in the middle
of change or change is about to happen loss or you know whatever it is and we're trying
to prepare for it or adapt to it or prevent it right uh okay
I'm trying to control something that is not within my control we can cultivate then what Equanimity right by
recognizing what's happening the delusion the effort
and just say you know things come and go they do it's the nature of life
and there's Equanimity phrases that I really like that I find really helpful and they just start with breathing in I
calm my body breathing out I calm my mind there's a long time in my practice that's as far
as I could go when I came back when a mini practice I just kept having to just breathe in I
calm my body breathe out I caught my mind
and then you know at some point we can move on to this sense of oh yeah may I learn to see that things
come and go things change and may I learned to do this with some balance with some ease
or some sense of stability
you know sort of connected more with the sense of groundedness
that mountain and sometimes when I find that um I'm
having trouble even when I'm kind of know what's going on and I can't find equanimity
it's probably for me because I have some attachment usually it's an attachment to somebody
else and how I want them to be how I want them to feel
what I want them to be doing and so you know I need to recognize that
I'm having some attachments
and so there's these other phrases that go with the loving kindness practice that I just find so helpful
so you call to mind this dear being or this annoying being or whoever it is
and you connect with those you know the wishes of loving kindness you know may you be safe may you feel safe I like
feel not be because there's no sense of permanence and safety right there's
things are changing so may you feel safe may you feel happy you feel at ease and
well-being and I think about this person
and sort of yeah you know went in my best states I know I want all beings to
feel this way all beings and if I'm particularly
this is somebody I love dearly and I just see that they're having a hard time and I can't really do anything
it's really helpful for me to say okay dear one
your happiness and your suffering I wish these things I wish you to be well I wish you to be safe and happy and at
ease and and I see I know
your happiness and your suffering are a result of your actions not my wishes for
you my wishes don't create those States for you
and something in me let's go and I I lean into
how much more useful it is to trust that these states are possible
for everyone and that we all need to find our way to cultivating them
and so if I can look at this person with eyes that believe that trust in their innate capacity
natural States natural ways of being that they can find them if I believe
that and I see them with those eyes is probably the best gift I can give
them and myself
I'm just feeling that myself
as a a parent um
it's been such a journey to start by really literally taking care of
doing everything creating the smiles and the laughter right and
signing them up for this and that and doing all these things painting the room the right color to sort of really
support the well-being of my children and then they get older they get older and you
see you know you try you're still trying to make everything just right you're you know beyond the point that
you should you're still trying and then it starts to bug your kid and
they get mad at you and irritated and you know or they just get you know
they just Rebel and they won't put on their coat when they go outside and you just have to like let go right
you have to trust the natural consequences will if some something they've got to
entangle with they've got to meet it they've got to have mistakes they need to to learn
there's so many ways along the way as a parent that I would get caught my mind would get caught oh my God they'll never
ever ever ever ever sleep through the night oh my God they'll never ever ever ever whatever
so much suffering and that's so so much delusion in that right
now over time if you if you're willing to turn toward these moments of suffering you start to collect a library
of resources to reference that remind you you know oh jealousy
oh you know you know like wanting to control somebody else oh these things no
suffering suffering suffering okay what do I do and then we have the Brahma baharas
this place to turn toward this sort of even though we don't feel it maybe
it's just knowing that these states exist and knowing they are our Birthright
our absolute Birthright it is something that we just it's here
it's here and it's accessible and sometimes it's harder to access
but maybe just trusting that it's possible even touching the tip tip of the states
even just remembering these States can be enough to help
so the last little bit that I want to talk about are kind of um
maybe some of the the daily life practices that we can do
the things that we can do that just build into our life that can support our orientation toward these sort of
um more regulated expansive heart opening States
so you know loving kindness meditation nice thing to start your meditation
practice with right just orienting toward these wishes
can be a nice way to just start
centered breathing you can do driving in the car you know just sort of breathing into the
heart and out from the heart letting the breath move in and out
and imagining feeling your heart with feelings of love and kindness and compassion and ease
you can also do like counted breathing practices
there's something called soothing breathing rhythm you breathe in to about the count of
five and out to the count of five you keep this very regular pattern to breathing
and these things can sort of actually help shift the nervous system
back into a more neutral space when we're activated gratitude practice
journaling or having a text Trend that you share things that you're grateful with
four
with social engagement some of us have social anxiety right some of it's awkward to be in big settings other
people are extroverted and it's no problem but um one thing that can be really helpful is
to connect with the fact how you want other people to feel around you
instead of focusing on you know what you're feeling focus more on how you want other people to feel around you and
what would you do to cultivate them feeling at ease
and that can help kind of get us out of the selfing that keeps us stuck
and make other people feel good which is nice
taking little breaks throughout your day when you need them and when you don't
consciously saying you know like I want to be compassionate to myself my mind my heart my body
you know Finding ways to stretch or do things that you know maybe feel like a
hassle but you know or what what are good for you
for people who have um you know a sense of comfort with
imagination we all think you've probably noticed that what you
think affects how your body feels yeah if you haven't Notice start practicing
tracking the way we're thinking what we're thinking about we'll have a direct impact on how your body is feeling
so practicing thinking or imagining things that are cultivated in goodness and
well-being and wholesome States help yourself help your mind sort of
move from that place
and then engaging in compassionate actions toward ourselves and others
it's another way that we activate the ventral vagal complex
another little simple thing that I want to mention some people have this idea that in Buddhism we're
not supposed to like get really you know attached or or enjoy pleasure
that's my view is not that at all that you know we need to notice the beautiful we need to receive the Beautiful
and so there's something called hedonic pleasure which you know is pleasure
that's generated by external things nice ice cream sunny day
and actually I see that as sort of like the clutch for Shifting the gear
so when these natural things happen in our lives if we don't get stuck on just wanting the next good thing we can use
the positive feelings that arise naturally to kind of put in the clutch and then move into cultivating you you
demonic happiness which is actually connected to meaning and purpose and
turning toward that which is difficult with determination right this willingness and we cultivate this sense
of like just by turning towards something in this way it does create the
sense of inner well-being that's more sustainable it's it's uh less dependent on things outside of ourselves and
doesn't keep us on what they call the hedonic treadmill chasing after the next good thing so
you know little gifts that you get little nice Pleasures little great enjoy
them fill them take them in and let them support moving into like more
sustainable States instead of getting caught and just chasing
so no mud no Lotus right
the difficulties the suffering in our life can be gateways to the to you know
freedom and um that was nice how sweet thank you
um he's just going like this so this big smile it's like yes I love it
um yeah so what do you think thoughts questions responses
there we go Martha foreign
yeah I really appreciate the talk thank you so much it's very wise and very
helpful and deep it's really profound you know leaning
into the suffering like you're talking about where we can really just Embrace and have this incredible loving kindness
and compassion for even defilements and hint of five hindrances and with that
incredible loving kindness and compassion for these things they don't stand a chance they just disappear
that's right it's so beautiful so I just I just was coming up in the mind when
you were speaking and it just really felt alive so I just wanted to say that I appreciate the talk thank you thank
you very much anyone else have a question challenge
comment other idea about how you work with what
I'm talking about Gene I've got it
and then Abraham after Gene oh thank you so much
um well the vagus nerve uh is very interesting and um I haven't heard this
corroborated but I think that's why acupuncturists always put the the needle in your ear and one way to activate it
is humming so taking a breath and then humming out nice and do that for a bit and it will
change at least for me beautiful yeah yeah yeah there's some great things Kristen Neff has a lot of suggestions
like warm water and touching your lips yeah so there's some great things we can
do yeah thank you Gene Abraham do you want to walk over there and get the mic oh
yeah there we go
thanks um just in terms of exploring the body
mind connection yeah a little while ago I was going through a
period where I was quite irate at my son and it was jealousy I was really jealous
of just how mature this guy was so much more mature than I I felt myself to be
and someone suggested to me that I could send him
um sympathetic Joy to get my mind off of the craviness and
I could actually feel in my body the craving of the jealousy like give me
some of that maturity and on the other hand he's been very
successful at his business he's got a wonderful marriage and just this real Joy at
his successes and just feel that move out of my body toward him in much more
spacious so this one the first impulse was to really become constricted and
tight and the other one was incredibly expansive and of course freeing of this
toxic jealousy that I was having so beautiful Abraham beautiful
anyone else have a practice experience great
uh Tanya you were talking about uh making other people feel at ease around
you yes so yeah I have a practice for that
um oh nice something I learned a long time ago um um uh I noticed I would be leaning forwards
into social situations like if I wanted them to work out well
I don't want him wanting yeah so you're waiting for it you're you're off balance
yeah and the other person isn't so comfortable and you know you're not so happy so I'm so I'm been reminding
myself to to stay in uh vertical kind of a mental maybe physical Mountain pose
and uh works so much better nice thank you beautiful
a sea of richness here
great
um I appreciate it uh the explanation of starting with meta as a foundation for
Brahma vihara practice um I noticed that
I tend to start with compassion and Equanimity um
you know there's a lot of suffering and I want to get rid of it so I practice to get rid of it
but there's um there's it's kind of feel the practice field by aversion right and so
um yeah just hearing I don't think I've ever heard about starting with meta so
the intention of Happiness safety and peace supporting the whole Brahma vihara
practice rather than you know getting stable and getting rid of the suffering
so so that I can get rid of the suffering yeah yeah yeah you know watch your intention when we're trying to get
rid of something wrong practice I'm going to take you the wrong way but yes it's a foundation it's sort of like
the gateway to all of them you know they kind of unfold and support each other right and sometimes you know
um you can move right through you know but but we really have to be and maybe it's
connected to this idea of the physiological state right where we're in the ventral vagal
kind of activation a sense of openness ease you know this is a foundational
practice the loving kindness to help us access that state if we're wanting to
get rid of something more in the threat state we're in the sympathetic arousal right
which is not not going to be conducive to connecting to states that are more
open hearted yeah so yeah start there
and you know don't try don't try and manufacture it you have to be patient
and just kind of try and connect with the the sense that this is my wish
may not be what I'm feeling but it is my wish yeah great I think one more right what
time to wait the last one okay I'm a chiropractor and
um so I work with the vagus nerve a lot it's at the base of the skull and it controls all our organs and basically
every part of the body it's one of these Gateway nerves and so I found it fascinating
um you know I've been meditating for many years but I find it fascinating this is the first time I've ever heard anybody correlate the vagus nerve to our
mental States as far as meditation meta and so forth it makes a
lot of sense so that that was really fun nice hear your hear your connection with that nice
beautiful well I really appreciate your sharing your attention and I wish you
lots of meta compassion sympathetic joy and Equanimity so