okay hello and welcome everyone to happy hour
lovely to be with you and see you in in cyberspace on Zoom seeing your smiling
faces and um your two-dimensional presences
wonderful warms my heart warms my heart
so so for our practice um this evening what I wanted to do is
actually um uh try something a little different which is not say so much about what I'm
going to do sometimes I frame it sometimes I give a little darmet ahead of time and sometimes I do the guided
meditation and say something about it afterwards so tonight what we're going
to do which is different which is what I do but but not as frequently is let's just sit together
let's just sit together and and explore with a sense of curiosity these
invitations for for settling in the body with the heart with
[Music] um yeah with meta with kindness Good Will with sense of presence and and see what
what unfolds with a sense of curiosity let that let that lead us so
so without further Ado Let's uh let's sit together
her sitting in a chair there be a sense of Integrity to our
body maybe sitting a little more upright be rolling our shoulders back
bending our chest making sure feet
flat on the Earth if you're sitting on a chair
a sense of integrity of course you could be lying down
if that's what the body needs right now make sure maybe your arm is at 90 degrees or
maybe eyes are a little open to stay awake maybe you're doing standing meditation which is perfectly fine
foreign you're sitting
feeling your sit Bones on the cushion or the chair
and Landing Landing
Landing in this body
the felt sense of this body Gathering Gathering collecting
foreign
and relaxing
go with alert and relaxed at the same time
inviting beforehead to relax
noticing if there is any tension
the face
the eyes
the upper part of the face
moving down to our cheeks
the jaw
let the tongue be solved
resting
relaxing the face some more muscles
noticing any tension to be released
thank you
noticing if there is tension the neck
shoulders arms
elbows hands
release
let their way to drop
chest releasing the test the area
surrounding the proverbial Heart Center the middle of the chest
the upper back
the lower back
upper abdomen lower abdomen
and as we bring awareness to these areas
releasing tension letting go
ah notice that they may feel
more expensive
releasing the said bones
relaxing
the upper legs
so for the out breath you're unhooking unbinding
[Music] and intention tightness
grasping and binding letting go
it's okay just as it is nothing needs to happen
if there's tightness and pain
hanging around that's okay it's all right offered a lot of space
continuing the awareness of the body moving down to the
legs
upper legs knees lower legs feet
the bottom of the feet release onto the Earth
feeling the breath moving being received invited into the
lower abdomen
the whole body if you like
it's not so much that we are intentionally breathing making it into a
project rolling to breath no let the breath happen just as it has
been all these years
there is any doing it's just bringing gentle gentle knowing
it was already happening this breath
already moving on its own
your awareness just hangs around hangs out with this good friend the breath
breath knows how to breathe you no meddling needed
let the attention awareness just hang out with this good friend
spending time spending Loving Care
but the sensations of the breath in the body
your thoughts balloons of thoughts want to pick you
away here and there past future [Music]
and gently lovingly release them for now thank you not now
later later
I'm giving my heart this practice right now
soothing healing nourishing just to be
just to be receiving
sensations of the breath in a relaxed as much as possibly relaxed
body
an expression of care of kindness
for ourselves
if there is a cacophony of thoughts wanting your attention
clamoring for your tensions okay okay let them be you don't have to get entangled
ah it's enough to just be here with the
breath and the body
it's a courageous Act of Shifting turning
habitual patterns not to get entangled but to just be
present kind
it's courageous it seems simple but it's profound
we not didn't get in the ring
stay here receiving the breath in this body with
kindness with patience
it's a Sublime training
clamoring gets loud say thank you please come back later
you can be kind yourself to the thoughts to everything
that passes through this fear of awareness
just this breath this relaxed body here
thank you
Can You Feel The expression of good will
for yourself ever so subtly present
the fact that you are sitting
you're practicing there is movement towards care Goodwill
for yourself and others and you see how that is
informing imbuing this entire Act
of sitting here and take Heart Take heart
and the goodness of this good will
there's goodness in coming together with others
that too
right in your heart
thank you goodness of you and fellow practitioners
multiplied we just meet this moment in this body
this mind in this heart with patience with kindness
spaciousness
such a radical Act in our society
just this breath this moment
planting the seed of goodness for so many moments to come
here here
foreign
thank you
radical kindness to just be present
with our reactivity for ourselves as much as possible
getting support the body from the breath
Sensations that ground us
profound training and care and non-reactivity right here
thank you
foreign
appreciating there is goodness and beauty within
so much beauty within
not turning always towards the challenges but also the beauty the goodness that's here
beauty of her kindness there's others ourselves
and as we turn towards bringing this sitting period to a close
celebrating even one moment of
cultivating goodness presence
patience expansiveness it's a moment of living beautifully it's
a moment of a beautiful life lived beautifully
beauty within
I can be so much Beauty
with patience care awareness presence
living a beautiful life
internally and sharing that goodness that beauty of our heart
even if their challenges internally externally everywhere sharing that beauty
that goodness with all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
for sharing for cultivating moments of beauty
beautiful life eternal life be shared to be brought out
into the world
or others for ourselves
so today's practice was subtle I admit
but that was the intention not so much the words of
meta but but the subtleness of Goodwill that can be very subtle really imbued in
the fact that we're showing up for ourselves with others there's so much good will so much meta
and The Meta of of non-entanglement in what arises subtle
but profound cherries as well what a nourishing practice
thank you for their reflection Jerry I'm glad it it felt it was nourishing for
you that was the intention that was the intention not too many words
Pat also says on YouTube basic simplicity so nice thank you Nikki
you're welcome back Sandy says wow hope posted to Audio
Dharma as want to re-listen multiple times yes I will surely
hosted tonight to Audio Dharma you are welcome sridevi
you like my sweet and soft voice you're welcome it's not me not mine I was born
with it so I can't claim any credit right it's just it's impersonal
uh I welcome Reflections what did you
discover if you want to share or you can post and try it and if you send them to
me alone it'll be considered a private reflection I would just read the reflection not your name
and if you want to raise your hand that's grade two you can speak your Reflections
if you want um questions comments
it's all welcome
and also nothing that has to be said it's it's all okay
it was nourishing right it wasn't maybe there was one
nourishing moment yay celebrating that beauty that
that goodness yeah maybe I'll say one more thing if there
are no reflections and that is this this idea this concept of
living a beautiful life and it's not an external concept it's an
internal it's not you know there's so many different concepts of beauty it's not about things
it's not about ease in in the external setting of our world but it's there's a
sense of internal beauty internal wholesomeness internal goodness living a
beautiful life internally there could be plenty of challenges plenty of pain in the body challenges in our lives
difficult emotions it's all part of it but moments of Grace Beauty touching
into this this dimensionality of of of life that is both ours and and Beyond
Beyond ours big bigger than and me there's a sense of perhaps interdependence that arises maybe it's
through all maybe it's through love through loving kindness through just the
sense of ethical Integrity there's a sense of beauty living a beautiful life
and can feel very simple it's not complicated somewhat like the invitations tonight
very simple but profound
[Music] so how about we turn
now to uh sit together in small groups
[Music] um in maybe group sizes roughly size of
three we'll see how it turns out and the invitation is
[Music] um is to maybe share if you if something
arises you don't have to talk you can just hold silence High silent presence
with others um it's a gift to yourself as a gift to others and the prompt is I'll give you a
prompt actually um feeling into an internal internal sense of beauty an
internal sense of beauty internal sense of beauty when I invite
you to conjure up or feel into a sense of beauty
um internal beauty living a beautiful life in a way or however those words
might work for you sense of beauty sense of Grace sense of presence sense of
service love whatever that however that beauty expresses for you maybe you say a
few words if you wish about that or maybe not maybe sense of beauty internal
beauty is expressed for you by holding silent presence for others like oh yeah
this is how I offer my internal beauty tonight it's perfectly fine if you do share intend to say something say
something brief make space for another person maybe they say pass
or maybe they say something and then the next person and then they'll come to you so you can go around and round if you
wish or you can pass every time but then be patient no sense of inner beauty
sense of Beauty in her life Beauty what is the sense of beauty that yeah maybe
you have an inkling towards maybe there's a sense of oh yeah I feel sense of beauty when I'm I'm aligned with my
ethic with my ethics when I don't just open my mouth and just say whatever
comes like actually you know there is a sense of beauty there's a sense of goodness maybe that's when the sense of
um Beauty shows up or maybe when I'm really serving or loving or or whatever
it might be so so with that I'm going to open the rooms
take care of yourselves take care of each other and let's go with alphabetical order okay be kind here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back and we have a few minutes actually
for uh for Reflections that might have come up from
this uh inquiry about beauty inner beauty living
in the Beautiful Life internal Beautiful Life how you connect with that so I'd love to ask if if anybody would like to
share Reflections about that specifically what came up
can type them in chat you can raise your hand Fred please
thanks Nikki uh yeah we we had a lot of there are a lot of things that we talked
about that uh that were beautiful that I won't go back into but I
um I think we were all feeling this that it was beautiful that we've been able to do this for some time
um and the three of us who were together uh though we've never been in the same physical place we um we
feel an affinity and and friendship for each other and it's only has been possible for
for us because we've been meeting here and and uh because it's something that
you facilitated and make it happen and and that we keep coming and uh you know
it's mutually reinforcing and all quite a beautiful thing then thank you
thank you so much red hmm thank you for sharing that
that um sense of co-created Beauty but that we co-create
together and we have co-created together for a while so deeply appreciate your reflection yeah thank you warms my heart
yay happy hour is a beautiful thing yeah thank you
thank you Fred Diana please
I I just shared individually on something
um that when it was all over uh through um
the various ideas there I just felt with the Simplicity of this meditation a very
strong sense of presence I just felt kind of like more together and presence
than I normally do uh I wasn't off doing things that I I just was kind of
um together and simple and there beautiful and so
beautiful I appreciate that thank you beautiful thank you Diana just glad it's
my heart as you describe the sense of um being together the sense of alignment
the sense of together the sense of yeah Beauty inside it's an eternal Beauty when there is oh yeah sense of presence
how lovely that is thank care Catherine says simple and Powerful
practice I'd love to practice this way again yay okay I hear you
yeah sounds great okay dear ones it's um 7 P.M in
California and um the time has come to dedicate the Merit of our practice together may all
beings everywhere be safe happy healthy have ease may all
beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone thanks for your practice see you on Wednesday