hello from Insight Meditation Center
welcome to the meditation and one of the
important Tendencies to become
conscious about is how much of our Behavior our words and our thoughts
our attitudes are in fact unconscious or
operating on habit energy we don't think about it we're not aware that
you know we're not choosing it they're just kind of moving along and unthinkingly kind of thinking doing
saying whatever kind of comes up
and the opportunity is that with mindfulness is to be aware
of what's operating within us what are the habits of attitudes habits
of beliefs habits of ways in which we relate to ourselves and
to others and habits are kind of how we speak to ourselves or speak in our mind
and uh to uh to see it clearly enough to see that we have a choice or notice
where we have the choice and so that
we can choose to think to relate to ourselves to
speak to ourselves in our mind in a way that is kind a way that is
supportive a way that is nourishing a way that is produces or brings about some of the
best qualities of our hearts and to speak to us ourselves or have an
attitude towards ourselves that heals that that helps create friendship within
ourselves and a caring attitude of all of Who We Are
where we're not in conflict with ourselves or not saying things are
being in ways with ourselves that or with others that if we really step back
and listen or hear or feel the impact of what our mind is doing
we would feel sorry we would have compassion we would have maybe even some
sorrow over wow this hurts this is difficult let's see how we could do it a different
way and the choice point in meditation has to do with how we then
bring our mindfulness how we bring our attention to what's here can we find a way to when we have a
choice to be consciously aware to shift some of the inner Dynamics so
there is a kind of a friendly holding of our experience
some kind of way of being with experiences kind of like being with a difficult person who all we have to do
is listen and be present and make room for them to speak that they begin to relax they stop being defensive or
assertive and and they can feel or that we're not going to harm them
so to listen and shift our attention to ourselves that way and to come from that
place of meditative care meditative friendliness or kindness
um not to override what's happening but to begin shifting how we relate the
place of choice in our relationship so in this meditation
to settle in and start becoming aware and
noticing what we're doing with our mind that is not connecting to this warmth not
connecting to a meaningful supportive connecting way of being with ourselves
that we begin holding all of who we are in a attitude of
kindness friendliness support and um
and so one of the next axioms or maxims for this is to
be still and gaze upon everything kindly
so assuming a meditative posture
and you might think of the posture as not something that is stiff or forceful
but something that the posture itself promotes
both alertness and a friendly attitude
and a warm-heartedness
and then to gently lower the Gaze or close the eyes
and gently in a way that feels caring and just right for you
take some little deeper breaths just enough to adapt their breath that
you really start feeling connected to your body
when you have breathed in deeply you might take a moment or half a moment
to hold your breath before exhaling just long enough so that
your attention Gathers around
the top of the inhale
and then breathing out exhaling relaxing and letting the exhale be longer than
usual just a little bit so it feels doesn't feel challenging
and they're also for a moment a quarter of a moment just
very briefly holding the breath before breathing in holding that end of the exhale
just so that there's a beginning of a gathering a little bit more Focus
on the experience of breathing
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale look around your body for places that
you can relax softening the body on the exhale
and you might take a moment or so to pause at the end of the exhale
and in that pause to relax the body more let go release the holding
and then settling into
be attuned to your breathing
and seeing if you have any choice whether that Attunement that attention
to breathing can be done with a attitude of good will
attitude of kindness or care friendliness
and as you continue with your breathing from time to time notice
in the deeper and deeper layers of the Mind
is there any habits formation of
unkindness unfriendliness
criticalness or even animosity
and it might not be possible to stop that
but with your conscious mind seeing that
to hold it all in kindness
in Good Will and care
Let The Habit be habit and let you
be that place where you choose
a caring attention to what is here
to what degree are you operating on habit energy or
habit of thinking and that in that habit the attitude
maybe is not the one that is
nourishing for you and nourishing for how you'd like to be in the world
and to the degree to which you have choice
can you choose without forcing you
an attitude of friendliness or good will
okay and as we come to the end of this meditation
to consider that Buddhist Meditation is moving towards a
radical transformation of how we relate to ourselves
so that we relate to ourselves without any animosity without any
greed or delusion that we relate to ourselves with Good
Will and care
and as we learn to do that meditation we realize that this is good to do in
all directions not just for oneself
and so to express that or be reminded of that we end the meditation with the
dedication of Merit dedication of the benefits
may it be that the benefits that have come from this meditation today
may it serve for the welfare and happiness of this world
in whatever way that they can spread out
mayor care extend out to the other other people and other beings
wishing them well may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be free
and may we find ways
to live with this attitude the attitude of care and love for all
beings
[Music]
thank you [Music]
so hello welcome to this third talk on wise
speech and um
and calling it wise speech it includes the idea of kind speech
or speech which supports healthy relatedness healthy
relationships with others and then bring that to the Forefront
that we want to establish healthy relationships that are beneficial that
are mutually supportive that are caring that express love and respect
and it's all too easy for our words to not do that our words to carry with them
sometimes hostility sometimes our frustration sometimes are
criticalness of others and in that the Habit formation and then of saying things which are mean or harsh
saying things in which the relationship doesn't come together into some kind of
connectivity or or um you know real real healthy relatedness
but actually the opposite we're pushing people away we're creating bigger
divisions between people bigger Rifts between people by what we say and if
we're in extreme versions relationships might take a lot of work to repair or maybe some times when we
use our our harsh voice
we do it to strangers and we never have a chance to repair anything if it's clearly created a kind of we push people
away and maybe that's what we want to do yelling at someone who's driving we
don't like and um and we'll never see them again and
um but it contributed to the society a society of angry people frustrated
people of people who somehow feel now defensive or feel more likely to be
triggered and stressed by everything and um
so uh wise speech supportive speech speech that connects
people it creates Unity unifies people not divides people and these are
teachings clearance instructions from the Buddha he talked about the importance of speech which unifies and
rather than divides and um the um
uh he talked about abandoning malicious speech which divides people
but speaking in supportive ways and kind ways that unifies people brings them
together so one of the ways that in terms of these five areas five ways
of why speech the Buddha talked about speaking with a
um a hey okay sometimes it's translated as a
gentle gently gentle speech Pleasant speech
soothing speech these are all translations of the Pali word and and I think of it as speech which oh
it's speech with the Buddha says go straight to the heart so in a good way
a speech which is pleasing to the ear and so here we're still looking at the
question is how does our speech connect us to other people how does it unify us how does it create good Bridges
between us and other people and for and what in addition to that in
what way can we speak that brings out the best in people that touches them in
a good way and how we speak is really really important so uh to speak with a tone of
voice that is not harsh some of the voice a speed of voice a loudness a
voice which doesn't come across as harsh doesn't come across as unpleasant doesn't make people cringe or pull back
or shut down but to speak in a way in a pacing a tone a a loudness a choice of
words which uh is nice to listen to pleasing
to listen to it goes right to the heart it doesn't shut the heart it opens it it
warms it it it helps the kind of support a warm-heartedness
and um so this is much more than so one of the
aspects of this is to be conscious be mindful enough of how we speak when
we're speaking on the Habit energy habit speech where we're not really conscious
of what motivates us to speak and we're speaking impulsively and often when we do that we're
asserting ourselves on other people we're asserting our wishes our attitudes our feelings onto others and in order to
get our way and uh sometimes within reason that's
okay we need to do something like that but to assert ourselves in such a way
that it's unpleasant for the other person is that really necessary is there another way and I would like to suggest
more often than not there is another way there is another way of caring for
ourselves and and taking care of ourselves in this situation but doing it in a voice that is
is not perpetuating the divisions not perpetuating the harshness the
unkindness that can exist and and sometimes it's by saying things
like um wow that was difficult to hear but to say that in a kind voice to say
that in a gentle voice wow that was difficult to hear or wow that was quite something and can we pause a
little bit or can you can you you know did I hear right what was that about and um as opposed to immediately coming
back with something harsh and critical make space and something like that oh
that was hard to hear or I don't think I heard that properly to say that in that
kind voice highlights for the other person what they just said so they can become more
conscious some people then will give it a second thought some people become aware of
their impact that they've had that maybe this wasn't the best thing to say rather than meeting a harshness with
harshness is you meet it with some other way that of what you can do
and um the and I think of this kind of gentle
Pleasant speech is one where we maybe are caring for ourselves and trying to find out trying to get what we want but
we're not asserting ourselves and others we're not pushing on others we're not
diminishing the value of others it's done with respect for others and in respect that they can feel in how we're
speaking is this too much work is this too much
of a burden to pay attention to how we speak and speak in a nice way
it is if that's uh that's the only thing we're doing but uh hopefully for people who meditate
um we're doing it on a foundation of being settled on ourselves maybe even
feeling at home and connected to ourselves when we don't feel settled on ourselves
we don't feel connected to ourselves then for mindfulness practitioners it's
a high priority to find a way to do that because if we're not settled if we're
not at home if we're not comfortable in ourselves or really present for ourselves some modicum of calm
that that's when we're more likely to do things that we later regret
and so we want to uh and so on that Foundation of well-being
then speaking kindly pleasantly caringly for others it goes right to the heart is
not uh we're not forcing ourselves or doing a should where it's welding up
from within in a way that seems natural of course we want to do this way
and so so not just to take these as admonitions speak kindly but take it as
a as a encouragement instructions that speak kindly yes but do the inner work
so that you have a foundation of well-wishing of well-being yourself
that from which speaking kindly seems like a natural thing that speaking harshly feels like you're
doing violence to yourself why would you do that
and uh and speaking kindly speaking gently speaking pleasantly becomes something which nourishes
ourself something that is supportive for ourselves we feel the benefits it goes
right to our hearts it comes from our heart rather than closing it or
or irritating it or you know
harming ourselves in the process so uh to spend time care
to speak gently kindly respectfully
politely maybe I don't know what the best word is for here in a tone of voice that's not harsh
and um and that's Pleasant to hear that's Pleasant to speak
and if you can't do that maybe there's it's time to take a pause and really
kind of do a check do a and sometimes these kind of checking in with yourself
doesn't have to take long there's what I call the three minute three breath
Journey just take pause for three breaths and you really connect to yourself
and those three breaths doesn't take long but that might be enough where it just feels more easy and natural to
avoid harsh speech and um so I want to end with um
a I think a very
inspiring at least for me but also instructive and and challenging uh
quote from Mahatma Gandhi is this is from his autobiography
my hesitancy to speech which was once an annoyance is now a
pleasure its greatest benefit has been that it has taught me the economy of words
I have naturally formed the habit of restraining my thoughts and I can now give myself the
certificate that a thoughtless word hardly ever escapes my tongue or my pen
I do not recollect ever having to regret anything in my speech or writing
I have been spared many a mishap and a waste of time experience has taught me that silence is
part of the spiritual discipline of the Seeker of Truth proneness to exaggerate to suppress or
modify the truth wittingly or unwittingly is a natural weakness of
people and silence is necessary in order to surmount it
a few a person of few words will rarely be thoughtless in his or her speech
he or she will measure every word so I'll end with the idea
that um
if silence is the better option don't speak
it doesn't mean don't speak at all don't prefer silence but when silence is the better option
maybe don't speak if you're going to make the situation worse through your speech
maybe you should not speak or at least pause and be silent and see what you can find
so as you go about this day if you're interested you might try
um first look to establish yourself in some
little modicum of well-being or subtleness or connected to yourself maybe do lots of times through the day
the three breath Journey just be quiet and just attend to three breaths
and then go about what you have to do or say and and see if you can experiment with
speaking words that go straight to the heart that come from the heart then go to the heart that are Pleasant to hear
Pleasant to speak and um and uh just experiment with that
and see what it's like see how you benefit from that and see how it might benefit the relationships you're in that
people you're with the connection you have with them so um
so thank you and um I look forward to continuing tomorrow