warm greetings from IMC inight meditation center and Redwood
City and I'm delighted to be here with you all many years ago good number of years
ago I met um a woman who uh had a career as being a
psychologist and she when she was younger she had done research on um
early childhood development and her research involved uh for for a couple of years
involved once a week or so going to visit a new
mother and um who was kind of at home taking care of this new child baby and
toddler and so forth and uh for two years the the
researcher went and just sat in the Liv living room quietly didn't have any conversations with the mom and uh and
just watched and took notes on the child and mother interactions and what
happened and as part of her study so after two years of doing this uh it was
time to for the researcher to stop that part of the the study and and uh and you
know announced that she was leaving or something and uh the researcher was stunned to hear what the mother had to
say uh she hadn't said anything they had they had not having conversations and I
guess the researcher was meant to been kind of um a a non-interfering Observer
of it all and the mother said that uh the few hours that the researcher spends with
them were the most important hours of the week for her and uh she felt so much
peace she felt so much sense of well-being just having someone in her presence
watching and uh I don't have much more to story to say the context of why might
have been so profound for the mother certainly mothers sometimes feel isolated in the challenging of raising a
child and um but uh the power of presence the power of observing the
power of listening to people is quite profound um I think there's almost like
a very deep need to uh for especially for people who are for children and
maybe for everyone to really be recognized be known um and so meditation is that for
ourselves and what would meditation be like if the observation the listening
the presence that we bring to ourselves as we meditate is medicine
is a a a form of love a form of caring a
form of respecting and valuing ourselves that we're important enough to really
tune into and be with and I think it's not always easy
for us to have that relationship to ourselves we might have that with others but uh too easy it's possible to
Discount oneself too easy to uh focus on other things rather than
ourselves sometimes it's easy to be critical of ourselves it's easy to get caught up in Loops of of uh habitual
preoccupations which in some ways uh maybe even take us away from ourselves
oddly enough that uh to be caught up in stories and thoughts about ourselves is
to be kind of living in abstractions and uh uh but to really be
the Observer to sit in the living room of our hearts and minds and really be
there not to interfere but to really see and hear and witness in some
profound way what this inner life is like our hearts might need
this so to assume a meditation
posture that allows us to be comfortable in the living room of our hearts and
Minds so that we can be
here to be a witness to see with love with
care what is here for us gently closing the
eyes
and beginning directly with just with the eyes closed and feeling and sensing
the body being a witness being an
observer of what we find here in our body our hearts and our
minds
without judgment and without needing to change anything just the power of
observation here
now maybe allowing your attention to roam around your body your heart your
mind just check in and recognizing what all is here for
us then gently as if it's a
tender quiet gentle
Act of care or love take a few
slower deeper breaths and
longer exhales than
usual almost as if the expansion of the chest and the belly as you breathe
in is a greater touching all of how you
are and the exhale is a settling and a relaxing into the middle of it
all not to let go of anything but find ourselves
seated in their living room chair at the middle of it all to be an
observer
Witness
and then letting your breathing return to normal and if you do use your breathing
as the that Center place to Center yourself in the middle of it
all if it's easy enough imagine that the
body's experience of breathing the sensations of breathing in the
body it's almost like it has eyes and ears in the body
itself and from the coming and goings of
breathing to observe
ve the movements of life as they occur in the present
moment to listen hear in a deep way sense in a deep
way through the Dental movements of breathing in your
body without judgment about anything just
witnessing from The Refuge of
breathing
for
e
whatever is happening to you now in the present moment consider it something that should
be witnessed seen and
heard not analyzed or figured out or
judged just [Music] seen from the quietest place
within
for
e
e perhaps your awareness can rest
within as if sitting in an easy chair in a living room
observing all things in the present moment as they
unfold observing with
love as if being aware is
love
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting there is a way in which we can be seen
and heard by others that I can feel as if the seeing and observing is a
form of love it can have the same [Music]
warm inspiring impact on
us and to imagine that your ability to with witness the world to hear the world
be present for this life around you to imagine that it can be a form of
love an expression of Love A manifestation of
love to bring an intentional caring
attention to the entire
world near and
far a Love or
friendliness that's carried in these words may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be
free and just maybe you'll contribute to
this in the quality of attention that you are offer the
world your attention is that important attention is a vehicle and
means by which love appreciation friendliness and
respect travel out through our
communities
thank
you
this is the fifth talk and final talk on wise listening that's borrowing from the
Buddhist criteria for wise speaking
to and um and the fifth one is to
speak uh with friendliness to speak with speak with mea with loving kindness or
Good Will and so if we're listening to listen
with love with Good Will with friendliness and it might be
easier to listen with Good Will friendliness
generosity then it is to speak that way sometimes speaking we don't know what
words to say sometimes speaking um maybe can feel a little bit
like we're offering ourselves too much to someone else and um maybe the impact we're
unsure of if if you walk up to a stranger or you sit down with a stranger on the bus and you say I love you who
knows what's going to happen but if you sit there with a stranger on a bus and uh listen to them attentively
with care and with love in the listening it it could get complicated of
course but uh it's probably much safer to just listen with respect attentively
as if the person is valuable and important as if the person worthy of being known being heard being
seen and um I I sus I suspect that there's
a kind of a crisis in our society of people not being seen and heard and
respected enough and um and we can do it with our
capacity to listen and it is listening is intentional it's different than just
hearing and uh sometimes in meditation it's wonderful to kind of just rest in hearing and be so simple and
quiet but in our social lives um things get enriched by our
intentionality by doing things on purpose and to to listen to someone on
purpose as opposed to not really making any effort to listen and just hear them
as if you would hear the traffic outside or the birds outside or something uh
there's not much depth in that that way of hearing others but to really turn to
someone and hear them out to listen to them on purpose with
intentionality to engageing an intentionality can be multifaceted part of the intentionality
is to listen to them with appreciation with a sense that it's worthy worth listening to them that what
they have to say is worthwhile to hear and worthwhile to be a witness to this
person's life and um and so to
listen with with Good Will and to call Meta Goodwill maybe is an
easier approach than say listen with love love it gets complicated sometimes
with what that means and how high it's kind of like a high bar for people to always love their everyone but even
people that we have trouble with challenged by or even don't like sometimes it might be possible to find
Good Will wishing them well uh wishing them the opportunity to be heard we
hoping that being being that they in being heard and respected and appreciated that maybe it touches
something deep inside of them that maybe is beneficial and helpful and maybe the
person as a result won't be as challenging and um so to listen with Good
Will and um uh good listening is a form of love
is a form of Goodwill is a form of respect and care for others and so how do we do this what
what are the means for this um I think it's helpful to think that listening
with love listening to Goodwill is not only just having an attitude of good
willll but it it's it's what more we bring into the
listening the listening can be active we could ask questions as if the person's
you want to know more as if the person's valuable enough to find out more what they think what their experience is like
um and um but you know caring questions and so just asking
questions sometimes um appreciating what they've said and some people it's very
rare they get appreciated for what they said and sometimes in group meetings and group situations there's plenty of
people who are not appreciated when when they speak some people kind of are recognized
as uh easily by others they have a lot bigger presence or have a status in
society that maybe gets them in people focus on them and other people don't
have that and people sometimes will Overlook them sometimes people will even someone will say something no one will
acknowledge it and then a little bit later someone else say the same thing and they're acknowledged but to pay attention are
people being appreciated are people being listened to in meetings in different situations who's not being
listened to who's being overlooked um over you know overheard
not uh can you listen can you fill in uh the places and meetings and social
situations and fill in for the lack of attention or deep listening that some people all too often
experience so this is an active purposeful yes let's listen let's pay attention here the um um the other went
away to this active kind of loving uh listening is um uh don't rehearse what
you're going to say instead consider what the what the person is saying
consider consider it and listen to what's not being said listen to the feelings the emotions behind what they
say uh listen to what they might be asking for without it being a question
listen what what what's the purpose for which they're saying something and so to be actively involved in listening means
to be considering what people are saying more than considering what you're going to
say to listen with love is not to interrupt people
to let them speak finished of course sometimes it's appropriate to interrupt sometimes the very game the playfulness
of conversations involves kind of a back and forth and interrupting and but that's in context it's it's appropriate
and people you're familiar with but uh you know at times love is not
interrupt so uh uh purposeful listening
and then we consider what is the purpose for which we're listening for and going and
doing and um the um so some of the
purposes of these five criteria is it to listen in a timely way
listen when it's really important to listen um uh know when to listen in a
conversation rather than to keep speaking and saying your opinions U maybe you don't speak all all
you can say every time you have something to say some people are kind of have a strong habit of feeling to get
things off their chest and get their opinions out there and to be right so to speak in a timely way means to give
other people a chance to speak and to hear to listen to what's really true to
purposefully look for the truth and that has a lot to do with reviewing ourselves that we're not overlaying judgments and
biases on top of what we hear to be able to be clean
listener uh to listen in a way that is um uh touches the heart it's kind of
related to this idea of listening with love but listen in a way that uh that
helps people feel safe or comfortable or or or comfortable around
you and to listen for what's beneficial listening beneficial way listen for a
way that supports you and others and then again this last last one maybe is related to that and that is to
listen with Good Will so these are all purposes that we choose to live by and there are times
when uh when this Buddhist practice of ours calls upon us to live an
intentional life a purposeful life and listening is one of those interesting places for that when we appreciate the
difference between listening and hearing we can hear without any sense of purpose
at all we enrich ourselves if we listen with purpose provided it's for the right
purpose provided for a purpose that feels like it comes from the depth of us
and supports something that's beautiful and wonderful inside of us to flow and
come um kind of on its own uh so we're not straining and stressing
to for the purpose it's a purpose that allows something to flower and one of
the most beautiful flowerings we can have is uh is
love and to live a purposeful life where love is at the center what a great gift
it is for our world so
listening listening is one of the expressions of
love if let love has a language um listening
is maybe the grammar for that language or something so um thank you and
um so uh this uh Sunday I begin uh teaching a three-week retreat at our
Retreat Center inite retreat center and so I won't be here for next three weeks
and um a number of the people who normally would come here to teach are not
available uh next couple of weeks so at least for the next week and maybe maybe
for the next two weeks the um uh we're going to do a a replay on 7 a.m. we'll
still have the 7 am. period for but it'll we'll play some of the series that
I've did did I think about you know almost three years ago now or in 2020 so
it's been a while and maybe it's uh nice to have it repeated and um so it'll
it'll it'll appear as if it's a live broadcast and um but you know it so you
can participate in chat and all that but it's um it's not um I'll be here live in
spirit in heart not not in person and um and then um in in so the
third week that Mo way Nikki mapori will speak wonderful teacher here at IMC and
and um very happy that she's going to share herself with you for that those
days so thank you all very much and I look forward to seeing you in about three
weeks