great let's do this uh nice to be with you
since we we are quite literally all around the world good
morning good evening and good night let's um
let's pick up where we left off with the study of the apartments the Perfections uh my name's kodo
very very happy to be here with you we'll be doing a very simple meditation
this morning um say more about this in a bit but the two
parties the two Perfections that we will focus on today are energy Viria
and Conti patience energy and patience and we'll look at how they work together
what I'd like to do during the meditation is something very very simple
uh which is which is a after we after we settle
to pay attention to how the in-breath brings just a little bit
of energy into the system and how the exhale brings just a little
bit of relaxation into the system
so we'll look at these two look at these two qualities energy and patience
and um see during the meditation how we can sense into them
how we can get a feel for them how they're accessible right here a little bit of energy with the inhale a little bit of relaxation
with the exhale so let's find our way to our
preferred meditation posture
let's take our time let's take our time arriving
not hurrying to be here
mentally setting aside whatever
can be set aside
any unnecessary thoughts or preoccupations you can come back to them
after
just here
we find our way here through sensing
feeling maybe the seat
maybe the flow of breath that now
it's because of temperature on the skin
and feeling our stealing our way into alignment
long spine relaxed ribs and torso
yes it's helpful
as we did yesterday we could do a quick scan through each of the scent stores
it's relaxing each in turn and letting that relief register
your eyes years
nose tongue in the mouth
body and the thinking muscle
in each adjustment all the more here
any attention right here
and then our simple practice for this morning foreign
to observe how the breath turns the energy
on the inhale and how does that register for you
a little bit of energy coming into the body
oxygen into the blood give you a little bit of this
maybe a brightening in the Moon could be anything
foreign
now to get familiar with of the exhale turns the energy
in the body even in the mind
maybe it's subtle Sensations that you notice
a little bit of relaxation or Slack
a little slowing down
rounding
foreign
for the rest of our sitting freely exploring these two
energy coming in with the inhale
relaxation settledness with the XM
however seems fit I'm going to be launching them
way back and forth or favoring one or the other
as is appropriate for you now
thank you
you know something in your mind is a little dumb
perhaps living in charge of emphasis to the
in-breath the energizing breath
and if the mind is a little Restless
after noticing the nature of restlessness
living in terms of emphasis to the exam
the grounding breath
all in the service of Being Human
who seem clearly
and for this last minute of our sitting
the invitation is to relax any effort
and fully rest
letting any of the benefits or goodness of our practice
register and nourish
foreign
[Music]
again
after our meditation together now turning to the Perfections of energy and
patience
so so far we've been practicing these armies the Perfection step by step
uh first first we we had a discussion about Donna giving
and uh one who practices Donna learns a a
one kind of letting go that initiates this path of the Perfections
and then once Sila The Virtue their ethical conduct matures and we grow in
this sort of ethical sensitivity sensitive to the ouch and the ah of our
actions and then we practice wise renunciation
seeing more and more clearly those States and actions and cravings and
clingings that no longer serve us and then desire
compulsive desire let's go and then one grows wise about
distinctions and perspectives that support liberation
and in doing so we learn where to direct the effort of our practice our energy
and this brings us to urea so these last two days we focused a lot
on some of the basic principles of part of me practice and we've reflected on this approach of reflecting on the
benefits of of quality of a part of me and reflecting on the drawbacks of the
opposites I think this has a basis in the dhamapada one of these well-known
teachings doing no evil engaging in what's skillful
and purifying one's mind this is the teaching of the Buddhas
so today I plan to highlight a little bit um something a little bit different
which is how power and these work together and I want to share this from the
perspective both of our meditation practice and daily life
appropriately the very next line in the dhamapata after this is the teaching of the Buddhas is patient endurance is the
Supreme austerity so immediately patience and energy are named
so I mostly want to talk about how Viria energy and patients work together and then why is that
what I've what I've noticed over over the years of this kind of wild monastic
semi-monastic and lay Dharma life is that for a practice to be nourished
and balanced long term this relationship of energy in patients points to some of
the central concerns in his essay the joy of effort
um Begins the discussion of energy this way he says
when explaining meditation the Buddha often driven allergies with the skills of artists Carpenters musicians archers
and Cooks finding the right level of efforts he
said is like a musician tuning a loot
reading the mind's needs in the moment to be gladdened to be studied or inspired
is like a palace Cook's ability to read and please the taste of a prince
so we may think of energy as something we have something we hold
on to and something we give over like it's a discrete quantity
or that it's something we have to muster when there is none when we're depleted
but what is it what does it do to reframe the idea of energy as something we tune and we attune both
to the appropriate level and to the knees of the moment
so in masutas and the anguta and ikaya there's this there's this very well-known uh well-known story that's an
Israel gecko is referring to here called Sona the Sona
Sona is an Ardent energetic practitioner who is uh pouring himself into his
sitting and walking practice as a monastic and he is discouraged
he's been practicing diligently but he's not free he's not free and he is
considering giving up giving up the training so the Buddha goes to question him
oh
so the Buddha goes to question him and he says Sona when you were a householder were
you skilled in playing the loot yes yes spontaneous I was
if you tuned the strings too tightly did the loot tune and play
didn't and how about if you turn the strings too Loosely with the loot tune in play
oh no no no it wouldn't and then the Buddha asks him so when you
tune the strings neither too tightly nor too Loosely then the loot did the loot
tune and play and the Buddha concludes in the same way Sona
over aroused persistence leads to restlessness overly slack persistent leads to
laziness thus you should determine the right pitch for your persistence
and attune the pitch of the other faculties to pick up your theme
something I'd like to highlight this morning is what's the opposite of energy
what's the opposite of energy and I'd like to say it's not rest
I believe that sometimes the most appropriate Attunement of energy is to rest
um maybe to overstate this I could say that the Pyrenees of energy and and patience
could be considered the power of these of our times and we can think about this in terms of
the maybe incessant demands on on our
energy maybe this comes in the form of compulsive activity or overwork
rest is necessary for the path to develop long term
I think here the the cycles of um a fruit tree over the seasons
when a season turns cooler and the days get shorter and the tree
draws its energy back into the trunk and into the roots in a sense to hibernate
before the sap and all of the all the biological processes sort of initiating
the energy back outward and then leasing flowering
one one Dharma teacher described the intention of a sabbatical as to live fallow
they want to add to restore and rejuvenate and replenish so rest is really necessary in
supporting our Dharma practice long term this is the part of me of patience in
the form of time and non-exertion
so this is another way that energy and patients seem to work together and we played with this some during our
during our meditation with the inhale the energy coming up the exhale the energy uh settling back down and this is
another natural cycle of the parmes energy and patients
in meditative terms as the Buddha put it the over application of energy can a
client us to restlessness and agitation and then attuned energy
and be can be a a condition for the arising of Joy
and Rapture and leaning onward to happiness and concentration
and Beyond so sort of skillful tuning of the the energy that I'm emphasizing a lot this
morning something that Suzuki Brushy called adjusting the flame adjusting the flame of our energy
that's uh adjusting the level of effort just to suit the moment just to suit this mind in this activity
the question I hear a lot how much effort should I apply it's almost never a question of
uh one prescription it's a matter of discernment what's appropriate
when discussing Viria dhamapala um tends toward the heroic
you can imagine him talking about uninterrupted effort for four eons with
the compassion for all beings and this can be kind of this can be inspiring if we're um receptive to it or
in the right frame of mind or something but it can also be discouraging like venerable Sona that may come across as
impossible or not realistic one of these ways that um energy or
aspiration can can lose its balance is if our aspirations become demands on the
universe uh practicing the parmesan order however
sort of hedges hedges this problem where our Donna are giving our ethics
our pronunciation and our wisdom support us in knowing how to attune our effort
this practice is a marathon not a Sprint
so we tune our inspiration so in everyday practice
I think it's all the uh I think it's very important to have Energy's partner
patience one of the most interesting teachings from dhamapala on this is that the
proximate cause of patients isn't what I expected I imagined it to be like on
Force endurance it was seeing things as they are
the proximate cause of patients is seeing things as they are
and in many of the Buddhist teachings seeing things as they are is it's an insight that comes through sustained practice
sustained observation we see something in a new way three of
our misperceptions wisdom is a cause for patients rather than Force
so among other modes of wisdom one of them is noticing that we are not in control of reality
doesn't that doesn't that influence our sense of patience or impatience
but we're not in control of this reality this body ages
Pleasant sound Fades a desire of mind doesn't Manifest this person next to me
in traffic you can fill in the blank we're not in control of reality
instead our role as practitioners you hear this again and again is to contribute conditions
we contribute conditions to a complex system of reality and experience
um in one of the most um maybe maybe the most clear examples that
comes to mind for me now is the Buddha taught how the when and the where of karmic
fruition how our actions have effects in the future the win and the wear of how that will happen it's nearly unknowable
by anyone but the Buddha but he strongly emphasized that we be
circumspect in our action so we can't we can't know how the effect will necessarily Ripple out for the future
but take great care with your action nonetheless so our role is short of omniscience and
total control but we contribute we contribute conditions of our intentions our actions our skillful means our
compassion and that sort of perspective uh supports the Perfection of patients
namapala also characterized patients in a way that was much more powerful than I was used to thinking so he
describes it as a strength a supreme source of constancy
a sure bounding the great ocean of hatred
um an unimpeded instrument in the development of noble qualities
and also we we know how patience affects the way people see us we respond to them
with patients that that affects the interaction in this way damapala calls
patience an adornment the basis of a good reputation
and has the function of quelling hatred
one part that he teaches that I think is well worth our consideration is that patience has the function
it has a realm it's an appropriate response to other people's anger
so um based on Doma Paula's emphasis in this and our current social scene I
think this is another way that patience and energy could be considered the power needs of our times
his counsel is to have a number of wise Reflections available to you to use on the spot when
facing others anger and they tend to fall into the categories of making uh making it impersonal
Maybe by reflecting on the fact that the sense faculties will necessarily experience Pleasant and unpleasant so uh
we can expect to encounter unpleasant and one of my favorites reframing our
perspective of the other person then I think of the the I think of the wisdom of parents in this
regard because the reflection is to see all beings as my own children
and I think of all of the all of the wise restraints and patients that are
that a parent sometimes cultivates
so in practicing patients with their energy we reclaim some of the power that's lost to impatience
we have agency because of a patient perspective and can then employ a
skillful attuned response in the moment patience allows us the wise direction of
our effort so I think for for today as we're coming
to the end of our time you can take and take into your practice for Wednesday
uh where is energy showing up where's effort and persistence showing up and
where's its opposite showing up maybe sloth torp slackness and then where's patience showing up
where's endurance forbearance uh steadiness that adornment of patience and where's its opposites showing them
and then particularly for today how do these two support each other
how do energy and patients support each other in your own life
thank you for sharing some time in the practice this morning may all beings benefit
and we'll pick up the thread tomorrow with the next two Perfections thank you