readings fellow practitioners good to be here with you
um I asked the tech team to put up in the chat that I do offer
um practice discussions and if you're interested you can contact
me about that and I also wanted to thank you for your
comments which have been very helpful so
today we will gently lean into
the factor of neroda which is usually
translated as cessation
when we're about to become an aura hunt near Rhoda means that we have completely
stopped read hate and delusion
but as I've been trying to uh demonstrate this week it's really
possible to even to take on these uh very
Advanced uh practices as beginners
because there's a whole um spectrum of
ways in which we can do it
um so yesterday we explored
gently letting unwholesome tendencies
fade away that was firaga
and then Tuesday we explored protecting our minds
by a cozy seclusion from distractions while meditating
so today we'll experiment with stopping
I think it's important to remember that we're not glued
to our unwholesome horses
and it's really good to know that
as long as I'm mindful I'm gonna be okay
because then we can you know present with full awareness in the moment and we
see when something unwholesome starts to arise
and we could say no it's done enough
so the um work for the meditation this morning
is not work it should be more like tasting
um we'll try to savor those moments whether they're just very
brief glimpses or they last for a few seconds
or maybe it should really Advanced a few minutes when the mind is quiet and undispracted
steady and we're just here with our lived experience
In This Moment so with that as a as an introduction
the invitation is to assume you're meditation posture
and since we're on the theme of stopping today uh
I'm going to make a suggestion but you don't at all have to follow it
but if you'd like to it can be difficult for some people but
see if you can get through this whole half hour of meditation
without moving once you've decided on the posture that you want to meditate in
so it's fine now to take a few moments to know see which way is up
and see which way is down and in the way that's down get in touch
with the center of the Earth which is holding on to us really nicely
and then as the meditation evolves will do our best
to let go of thinking
stopping thinking and when we managed to do that for just
an instant we can celebrate it's fine if you feel
joyful if you have a moment of peace
so closing the eyes and
visualizing your posture
so that the main centers of the body are in good
alignment lahara or otherwise known as The Dan Tien the
belly as the foundational Center
and then the heart chakra resting
vertically above that and in balance
with the belly and the Heart Center the head Center
I take a long deep inhale followed by a long
peaceful exhale noticing the transition spaces
and again with it's always nice
for me anyway in my meditations I like to begin with at least a brief minute of meta meditation
to sort of create an atmosphere which has the flavor of kindness
because I know how important it is to be kind to myself to not be judgmental
like thinking I'm not a good meditator or even worse that I don't even have the
right to attempt anything like Awakening
so give yourself a moment to
see if you can be aware of the whole body altogether breathing
and at the same time shower
this precious body and mind which is all we've got right now
with love and kindness and acceptance
we don't have to be any different than Who We Are to be on this path
May the heart be open and may we have the wisdom
we greet each moment with friendliness
not needing to turn away from anything
or judge anything [Music] knowing that it really is okay to be Who
We Are with all our foibles
because we're human
so with our best friend subtle
mindfulness awareness as our protector
we make sure the sheet is right in front of us
meaning that she is our highest priority
I kind of like that in Bali satya's feminine
she's a great Ally so do your very very best for the rest
of this meditation period to keep her
established within you
mindfulness of the body
this body
mindful of breathing
connecting with the whole cycle
of the breath
mindful of vedana
the feeling tone of our present moment experience
whether it's pleasant experience or an unpleasant
or we're not sure which it is
and when we've connected the feeling tone of our lived experience
we invite Raza which is the Bali and Sanskrit word for
taste we taste those feeling tones
we taste our lived experience
and with our awareness of tasting
we have some insight into our state of mind
now we invite Sati
are awareness
to be aware of our mind state
both the mind In This Moment just knowing it
we don't have to change it or fix it but it is very helpful
to be aware of it
mindfulness of the Mind
and now that we have put in place the first three of the City by diamonds
awareness of the body
awareness of feelings
awareness of Mind state
we can now invite our awareness
to include gammas
and it's that was our like mental
objects for example the five hindrances
if that's meaningful for you you like do a little checklist
see if any of those are present or the seven factors of Awakening
Etc
one way of evoking 30 patana of
mind objects that we could do this week
is to consider
invector seclusion from distractions
what's that going
we could investigate the Mind object of viraga
dispassion fading away
how are we doing with iraga letting unwholesome qualities just
fade away
and then Mirada cessation
stopping our tendencies
who want to be anywhere else except In This Moment
keep practicing like this
and if these instructions sound like Greek to you
don't bother with them just do your practice the way you usually do it that's fine
and if the Mind should have jumped onto a train or a pleasure boat or a
unpleasant Adventure
this is the time to say time out
just take a pause from those distracting thoughts
the Beauty and the fullness of the breath
the gratitude for being alive that's plenty
and in the last few minutes of this meditation
let's take our
State of Mind our loving heart any kind of Peace we may have
garnered from not indulging
thoughts and offering
that Peace by radiating it out
so just imagine yourself as a candle
and you're able to radiate in all directions
in front the right to the back
to the left above and below
the sphere of peacefulness Rippling outwards from your heart
into the universe
now at the end of our practice
let's share the benefits
of this beautiful path with all beings everywhere
may all beings be safe from harm
may all beings be easy and contented
may all beings be peaceful
[Music] and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice
greetings everyone I'm delighted to be here with you
to share the Dharma with you and to
feel uh The Vibes that are coming my way
from your practice
um I asked the the tech team to put an announcement up in the chat that
uh if you're interested I do offer practice
discussions and you can contact me about that if you like
and I'd like to begin by um
correcting something that I said yesterday in the Q a
in response to a beautiful question about
how does one recover from trauma
and I I spoke about my own experience from the trauma of being
physically and psychologically violently abused
when I was a child and
the the path that I went on included lots and lots of psychotherapy
and help including uh analyzing my dreams and
uh a lot of professional help
and then there was a lot of support
especially from Suzuki roshi and the community of practitioners that
is in Monastery in tasahara where I
cried every singles Us in period I didn't make any noise but the tears were
just streaming and this was a kind of you know a purification that I had to go through
and everyone was very sweet and accommodating and compassionate towards
me that was really of
and so and then also in my case since it was having to do with my parents
um forgiveness became a big deal in letting
go of trauma so
um I think when I identified as a trauma victim I was
um still bitter
and when I moved to being a a trauma Survivor
um through the practice of forgiveness and understanding that the sort of ancestral
dimension of what we inherit uh I was able to deeply forgive my
parents knowing that they did the best they could and
and then um in a practice discussion one skill helped me by suggesting that I just drop
any identification with PTSD with being a survivor
that it was not necessary for my identity
that was really um helpful at that point in my breakfast
uh and then um I mentioned that not all trauma comes
from family history as it was in my case but I have a dear beloved Dharma buddy
named Francisco who has become a marvelous teacher who has shared a lot with me about
the drama that he went through in a devastating car accident where he was just smashed to smithereens
and um and in the Q a I kind of tried to guess
what his process might have been like but I regret having said that because he
didn't I didn't hear it from his own lips so um
I'd rather let him tell you if if you're interested then you know
inventing what I think he might have been through so forgive me for that
and then by request in the chat yesterday for the list of the Bali words
for you know what we're exploring this week um
I'll I'll talk about that today and I need to give you a disclaimer that
this is not a canonical list from the early Buddhist texts it's one I put
together for the purpose of teaching this week
and in addition I add some of my own efforts at translating the terms
into English so
Monday was Raza and
Raza in uh both poly and
Sanskrit the root means doesn't mean taste so it literally means to taste
and then more figuratively it's the flavor of our experience or the Savor
and then a really interesting sort of development in where we can go with
tasting is the second meaning of Raza which is essence you know like in perfumes it's
sometimes the essence of such and such uh
but it that essence also means essential function
so in a way we're um we're tasting our essential function as
humans our experience our ability to be sentient beings
how does that taste so that was Monday
and Tuesday was viveka uh which literally means separated
um it's usually translated as seclusion but I think a preferable translation would
be Independence it also can means solitude
detachment disengagement
and interestingly another meaning in Ali
goes farther than that and takes the vecca to also mean
discrimination understanding true knowledge
so the Sanskrit root is very interesting also the the poly root literally means
um uh separated but the Sanskrit means to
sift sort of like we're we're sifting um grain or something
um so the idea is having a clear sense of separation
from the unwholesome and according to the commentaries it
often applies seclusion from the hindrances so a lot of times you may you may see
you know once you know once um a monastic was secluded from the
hindrances at that point they could go deeper in meditation
um but I've taken the liberty of broadening that idea of seclusion to in
the context of our meditation to seclusion from distractions
how do we you know just the the it's it's really very powerful
to be able to leave our distractions on the shoe rack outside the door
and to stay present
and then yesterday we evoked viraga
which and probably literally means Away From Desire
um The Fading of Desire or something or dispassion towards something or
detachment or indifference
um but the word Raga in Pali also means
color phew or a dialogue for dying cloth
and it might evoke the image of a a blood stain
on a pure white cloth
that Fades Away by washing it and hanging it up
in the sunlight so we can take the the stain to be a
metaphor for the impurities of our mind and the white cloth
to be a metaphor for the Purity the innate purity
of our mind which we all have but which we may not be experts at
accessing it's the treasure inside of us that all
this work of meditation and mindfulness practice aims to reveal
so it's it's a beautiful image I think especially since the varaga fading away
uh happens naturally you know wash it and let it dry in the
Sun healing through sunlight
um
so in Pali it also goes farther than uh dispassion to also mean
um uh leaving aside infatuation or lust or
passion uh like like I said there's there's often a whole spectrum of meanings for
these uh dhammas these poly um
mind objects
um and then today and I see that the clock is ticking
um the theme is niroda which literally means without
obstruction and it's usually translated as cessation
uh the ending or termination finishing off
ah and both the poly and the Sanskrit roots are the same it comes from root
uh meaning obstruction so um
the commentary says it also means release from imprisonment uh or confinement being locked up
and in the Chinese agamas translating the polytexts into Chinese
the character given to represent uh niroda is stop and see the two
characters stop and see together um so that's the value of stopping if we
can stop long enough we can see what our
foils we can see what our Temptations are and with that
we have the freedom to make a choice whether we want to go that way
or maybe we want to just be peaceful
so um yeah we stopped long enough
to be able to see what's happening with the clarity of an open
quiet and steady mind
so tomorrow we will look at vasaga meaning relinquishment
and the homework for today if you're so inclined
is to stop from time to time to observe the mind
and to see if there are any obstructions you need to remove from your path of practice
so that you can continue on your wholesome journey to end suffering
thank you and a last announcement is that I learned
um just today that A revolution is happening in the terravada forest
tradition um used to be called the Thai Forest tradition
but now there's a kind of official uh
new um breakthrough which uh is the I remember when I when I
first moved back to um California after living 40 years in
France uh it was a full moon night and the first thing I did was drive up to buy a Gary
to meditate with the monks all night long in the Moonlight and at one point I
the next day I had an opportunity to ask John Posner a question and I asked him
what's the problem with bikuni or ordination why why don't you you monks
here support that I was kind of an indelicate on my part which that's kind
of who I am you know stepping in the bottles
um but he he he really got it and he really replied beautifully saying that
you know the the hierarchy of the lineage in Thailand
is old guys and they're unlikely to
change and so it will require you know gradually they'll die and they'll be
replaced by more moderate um officials in the in the Thai Forest
tradition uh so what's happening is that uh Audrey
and pasino has um sort of been able to put in motion
um this revolution as specifically what that means is that there's going to be a
monastery in the Seattle area um gathering around uh John's nisabo and
corvilo and yes including bikunis
and on the body santusika and chitananda so I'm just I'm getting Goosebumps
telling you about it there's I have so much more data and uh in the chat There's the link so
excuse me for going over time and if you're interested in joining
the Q a and you're uh watching from YouTube you're welcome to transition
over to the zoom thank you so much
okay thank you Mega so if anyone has any questions or comments you can either put
them in chat or you can raise your hand uh and zoom
and while we're kind of waiting for people to collect their thoughts
um there was a question on YouTube yesterday um
and it asked the person asked uh if you could touch on how to be in a
contemplative mind skillfully without leaning into a ruminating inclination
so I don't know if you want to touch on that Meg
um I I tried to touch on that at the end of our discussion yesterday in the Q a
I think and and I think it's recorded I mean it's it's up there
okay great but anyway if not I'll do it tomorrow
okay I'm gonna switch to Gallery wait okay
oh these beautiful faces
oh
hey Marilyn you can go ahead and unmute yourself okay good morning from Charlottesville
Virginia and uh I'm I'm so happy about
what you just said um so I just want to thank you for sharing that um and bringing in all that
other stuff I guess I don't know what to call it um but uh
yeah um uh my other comment was just to sort of
say like I I did really appreciate your sharing about how we transform our suffering and how
much like that you know I just kind of had an Insight yesterday when you were
talking about um how how like
um I guess the compassion for your parents comes in and how how like I have
a similar experience um that you know and I've never understood it
before like I used to feel so much pain but now when I sort of think about that
suffering like I'm overwhelmed by like compassion for the people who hurt me
and stuff yeah and it's yeah like I've never understood it I've I've like like I'll be trying to
explain it to people and I'm like I don't know what's happening to me now
um thank you so much for sharing that Marilyn I'm crying I actually was on a
retreat with Gil in May at IRC my first uh residential retreat in three and a half
years and boy was oh wonderful to have that
seclusion and um and that sort of came to my mind
because it at one point Gill asked us to he was doing a a guided meditation and
he asked us to go into the place
in our body where we identify as the self where we reside
and for me it was just right away the heart center and I started crying
and
it's amazing because etasahara I was you know when I was 21.
I was crying out of pain just raw pain and that's a purification process that I
had to go through and this time at IRC
I was crying with compassion for my four parents who must have had an
even more difficult childhood than I did and so that transition from raw pain to
compassion I know exactly what you're talking about because I just went through it myself
it's it's really amazing when it happens and I think you know that's also part of
the purification process it's kind of like growing up into
compassion from being angry
yeah okay well that again just um I'm so moved and I will be I mean
just be metabolizing this week so thank you again sure thank you for sharing
yeah uh
I guess we can also take this opportunity to thank our uh wonderful kind of like editor team that we've got
uh they've kind of been stepping in this week um uh there's uh Dimitra
job Julie and uh Kevin H um they've been helping out this week
like Julie's been helping to post some of the announcements in in chat chats and everyone else has been kind of
pitching in to help out with the audio editing for our guest teachers and then
the video editing for the YouTube videos so thank you um you guys are really a crack team
you're you're not just amateurs you're you're you know you're pretty Savvy about all this stuff and I'm very
grateful to you for what you've taught me about teaching on Zoom so thank you
thank you
while we're waiting for to see if anyone has a house has any other comments um it's kind of I don't know if this
will help anybody but I actually like now that you kind of mentioned Francisco actually had the chance to talk to him
once when when we were doing a zoom um live stream and we were talking about
back pain um and uh he was saying that I asked him well how did you get over yours it
sounds like a hundred times worse than what I go through and just kind of simply said oh I just meditated so that
was really cool to hear sure it sounds simple yeah that that's sort of what I read
into you know um so it but like what I guess yesterday was probably accurate but still I I
didn't want to just leave it at that yeah yeah he just went deep deep deep
into his meditation like you know like I think that's pretty safe to say
okay hey Bill you uh you got the floor thank you
um once once in my entire Buddhist career
um my mind got so still burn extended period of time what six
and a half hours that my back pain completely disappeared not a trace of it some yeah only once
but now I know what's possible at least uh but what I really raised my hand to say is um hearing hearing people talk
about um they're um imperfect upbringings and their
imperfect parents it's such a common story yeah uh
certainly you know true for me you know so I had a little bit too overcome
um like 20 years of depression um very common I hear it from other people
all the time not all the time but but often enough um and um my reaction to that is just to
look around me as I go through the world and um if I
see people unhappy realize what a common thing this is and and um
just kind of feel compassion for it makes it easier understanding this makes it easier for me to feel
compassion for other people who may be acting up
um are are not doing well in one way or another
and for their parents and their parents and then you know so
the whole society it's in in a way
um being happy and and relating well to other people
it seems so simple yeah just let go demand just let go
uh I've been in practice that does seem to be hard doesn't it so anyway I just
wanted to mention this way of relating to the world a little bit better because of
understanding of what people have gone through thank you so much for sharing that
deerville uh and I remember you know I I started
practicing with a wonderful zen master at the age of 21. well I'm 76. uh that
looks like 55 years of practice but uh you know I'm I'm just kind of you
know starting out in a way um
and it's true and and you know I can remember over the years thinking you
know if almost every Retreat I would go on I would be so frustrated with myself because I know that I
don't want to go down the you know the river on that uh pleasure boat of
thinking or planning or whatever and
and yet uh it keeps coming back and I just I just think Meg you know
anyway uh for some of us it takes a really long time
well I've only been doing this 21 22 years so that's
uh 48 or nine um really late starts so um so there's
this so there's hope for me huh the Buddha you know he said there was
vote for everybody I mean he he gave uh unguly Mala or the nation you know so
yeah yes we was for those of you who are not familiar he was the this mass murderer
at the time of the Buddha who wore a necklace of uh not 199 fingers because
he his goal which was imposed upon him by his own spiritual teacher was to kill
a thousand people in order to become enlightened and he only had one person to go and it
was going to be the Buddha anyway and instead of him being able to kill the Buddha the way he was able to
overpower everybody else whoever came across
um it would have got the best of him and then showered him with compassion and
ordained him as his own disciple if anguli Mala can do it so and he did
become an our hunt in his lifetime so we finally Molly can do it being that evil
uh we haven't killed 999 people so there's a there's hope for all of us
thank you Leila you got your Andrews
hi I um I'm curious about because in the vadenas
I find neutral to be such a powerful
State and I just wonder is there is it similar to no Road high it's like
a secession I'm just curious but I and I think it's under supported or under rated neutral
and what's the rest of your mind like when you're in a neutral feeling tone
well the whole state feels like ah you know like a kind of relief in this
it reminds me of tignat Han's celebration of I don't have it too fake
nice but it's just it seems like I don't know I celebrate neutral and I I
think that's a great uh contribution to our discussion because
um you I I may be wrong um but I don't remember reading anything
like this in the canonical texts that neutral vedana
uh was a was a good thing it's usually in the commentarial tradition it's usually
strongly associated with delusion and uh it's but I think that you're
absolutely right if if in your case you know it feels like a relief and you're
not just um escaping from
uh going after pleasure or going away from pain
uh and you just don't know which one
I think that's um a very positive way an instructive way
that you've found yourself to
appreciate when you have neither pleasure nor pain and um
congratulations that's like becoming your own teacher you know well and I know because I I work with
trauma with myself and with people and the trauma is really big and sometimes
resourcing to access anything that might feel like pleasure just feels unaccessible but to move from
yeah an overwhelmed trauma state to neutral is a doable movement yeah
that actually offers something other than yeah the vortex it's a door opener
for you and it's a valid door opener for you and so this is something that we we
need to take from uh the Buddha's example also
is that it wasn't one teaching for everybody it was a different teaching for each
disciple and for each situation with that disciple and
um and in fact at some point
it's really up to each of us to have the the wisdom the discernment
to be able to wisely know that this is a good thing this is this is wholesome and that's
kind of what we were talking about um yesterday with uh viraga
you know letting are on wholesome Tendencies just kind of quietly fade
away and you know it sounds like you're uh
feeling tones of um desire and aversion just sort of faded
away and you were left with a nice Open Door
it's almost a gateway to Equanimity exactly exactly
perfect well thank you thank you for asking that thank you for
bringing that to the discussion
okay I think we don't have anyone uh we don't have anything any other comments or questions in chat or uh
um so thank you for teaching today Meg and
um as we kind of sign off today if anyone wants to
um come off mute and say goodbye or
well wishes please feel free to do so thank you Meg and thank you thank you and all the the
tech folks yeah really really indebted to you yeah yes thank you
thank you see you tomorrow
yeah my pleasure yes thank you for that opportunity to
converse yeah nice I appreciate it too
bye y'all