good morning good morning YouTube I am Sia Sanga happy to see you
it's a rainy day rainy morning here in Redwood City California
and I'm enjoying seeing the weather report um even here in Redwood City power back on
sunny in Tucson snow
nice to see your friendly greetings
oh please please [Music] um enjoy I'm reading the chat and just
enjoying it enjoy the warm greetings of your fellow Sangha
mates
and um
little observations from different places please help each other out with technology if you can
and um drinking
drink in the goodness the friendliness
coming from all over the world through this little screen
and when you're ready and you're ready maybe taking one or two deeper breaths
one last cup of tea simple team
and settle in settle in into your chair
your cushion your map whatever it is that you are
currently sitting around or whatever kind of
surface is supporting you softening the eyes
maybe closing them if you're comfortable closing them
I'm tuning in turning into your surroundings
maybe one or two more intentional deep slow breaths
where you let any excess tension anything else out on the out breath
allowing the tongue to stay soft the face
to stay soft
noticing your immediate surroundings
maybe a different distant train whistle soft rain
Hawk cries or Birdsong whatever ambient
sound is around you
and noticing too
the way your body is situated and immersed in the moment
feelings of warmth or cool
pressure or lightness
perhaps vibration or tingling from the inside of your body
and the Comfort to sense of
support support of the chair maybe the support of the map of the
ground beneath your feet
feeling health held by the Earth
having the attention rest
ing on the breath
on the sensations or sound flowing through this moment
settling
if distraction arises you know the Mind continues in the world
of thinking that it's so common just noticing that with kindness
beginning again
returning to the moment
rededicating yourself to awareness
this breath this sound
from time to time rededicating yourself
to non-preoccupation
the Simplicity of Silence the spaces in between
spaces in between but sound
simply being
in the last few moments of this meditation
the invitation is if you haven't already
let go of any primary anchor of attention
and dressed allow all sounds Sensations
[Music] mental phenomena emotion anything just
to flow through noticing the knowing allowing
foreign
is the formal meditation practice begins to draw to a close
taking a moment to appreciate gather up soak in Savor any moments of
peace quiet
patience Goodwill mindfulness anything
no matter how small gather it up and savor it appreciate it
your heart and body
and in casting your internal gaze outwards
generating the wish That Others May experience
goodness kindness patience Goodwill
awareness reflect on how it feels to wish them
well perhaps setting the intention
to be one of the causes and conditions for that goodness in your life
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign [Music]
foreign
[Music]
oh dear son go we are now in the fifth of five
books explorations on inner and outer Harmony
we've drawn from the Buddha's teachings on the saranya dhamma
principles of cordiality so just a quick overview if you've just
joined us today welcome and um
the previous days Monday was mindfulness and wisdom of benefit for ourselves
others self and other and everyone
Tuesday was the benefits of kindness and
Goodwill internally and externally personally and relationally
Ben was a sharing or generosity and yesterday was the power of ethical
consistency or persistence in today's topic
which the Buddha held is the most important by far amongst these
principles or qualities is noble and freeing wise View
wise View area so it's
um awakened wise View and this is a huge topic it could easily be its own series
and today I'm going to most of you explore why have you compared to the alternative
which is fixed speculative views opinions buying into our opinions about reality
other people ourselves wise view instead isn't an opinion
it is a perspective an understanding about the way things unfold through
conditionality how disparate conditions
come together and form this moment everything that came
to now formed now all these little interactions
so the simplest and most famous formulation
of wise view conditionality is a kind of a diagnostic process I think of the
Buddha as a doctor and that is the Four Noble Truths
first is acknowledging suffering exists second is seeing the arising of dukkah
suffering disease in any given moment third is the ceasing the ending of true
God or suffering and the last fourth Noble Truth is the
path to the ending of suffering now I'm not going to go into detail
about this this morning it amply covered by other teachers including a series of girls talks for
this from 7 A.M online Sun got back in 2020 which you can find on
audiodarma.org if you want a lot more information excellent teachings
instead I'm going to talk about how process perspective including the
diagnostic process perspective of the Four Noble Truths provides an alternative to being Swept
Away by distorted by our internal obsessive thinking imagination speculation
and these obsessions are what the Buddha focused on in his more relational
teachings about group compatibility friendliness getting
along cordiality because they're quite damaging when
bought into and often lead to quarreling
so in so many Adama the principles of cordiality the Buddha teaches that wise
view is being aware of versus obsessed by unhelpful Tendencies
of mine and this is incredibly powerful he specifically mentions being aware rather
than obsessed by the five hindrances of lust for sensual experiences ill will
sloth torpor and rigidity restlessness and remorse and doubt
now that too is a list that can be amply covered in series
but just to notice rather than even trying to remember all the words I just
said in that list notice when we're hooked and when we're not hooked
more than anything as I mentioned the Buddha highlights
the freedom from being obsessed by adhered to speculation
especially speculation that leads to quarreling disputing or as he put it
stabbing each other with verbal daggers right
instead the Buddha speaks of an alternate way of
being a non-ranking a lack of need to win arguments or be
better than rather than being better than or worse than there's this deep internal respect
for differences relationality among each living person
each living being this kind of non-comparison is a radical
kind of humility it's an understanding that vast web of
conditions actions possibilities pasteurizings that we emerge from in any
given moment it's well known in Buddhist cultures and it's known in other cultures too
including indigenous cultures my dear colleague Kyra Duolingo
introduced me to Enrique Salmon's idea of kin-centric ecology
this is an understanding that he articulates as that life in any
environment I'm quoting here is viable only when we humans view the life
surrounding us as can as kid
can we see those we disagree with as kin to
rather than winners or losers or some kind of flavor of other or wrong or bad
it doesn't mean condoning Behavior or attitudes or opinions of those we
disagree with we're still allowed to have differences
and discern what behaviors our attitudes might be harmful or hopeful
that too is wisdom instead it means seeing the humanity
the other conditions or just knowing that they're there the conditions that
derive Behavior underpin attitudes and understanding that
those two come from this interplay of all different kinds of
life forces that we may or may not have shared with
these others this takes a deep insight
a radical kind of perceptual humility an absence of need
to have my own opinion or my own speculation be right
and the Buddha kind of illustrates this there's a story from the ancient um
Buddha's teachings this comes from the imagine the middle
length discourses and um it's a story of the Buddha who's sitting
calmly calmly in the forest meditating I think perhaps receiving
visitors I don't know when Along Comes this young man big stick like a walking stick right
and his name in the soutas in the discourse is literally dandapani which
means stick in hand now to really understand the resident
said this you have to understand that the term stick and handle often implies violence
it's kind of a phrase used to talk about violence or
quarreling right so don dapani apparently the
commentaries explained he's kind of just puffed up debater type amongst many in that era
and he is going out for exercise or walking comes upon the food is like ah
someone I can argue with and begins to provoke the Buddha asking him what what
he teaches and what his doctrines are right
well the Buddha answers him this self-important philosophical debater he
answers him I offer teachings that quarrel with no one in the morning
I do not quarrel with anyone in the world
and apparently he did so with such peace
such equanimity and such evenness that dandapani was just completely put off and they
described him making a very funny face his eyebrows shoot up his tongue Wags and he sort of shakes his head and walks
away so some of the Buddhist followers I can't remember if they were around or if
he just relayed the story afterwards but um they asked well what did you mean by
that and a senior teacher
and the Buddha both explained explained that the Buddha instead of adhering two
opinions views sees the world in terms of dependent
arising conditions arising and can see the perceptual distortions
as such rather than being booked by them now I
am definitely paraphrasing and condensing here it's quite a deep teaching but the Buddha is resting in oriented to
the process of understanding subjective experience
as it is which is kind of orthogonal to any kind
of particular opinion so basically
he teaches over and over if we take our perceptions distorted by obsessive
thinking to be reality that causes
or helps to cause conflict argument and suffering the alternative
internally and externally is to focus on the conditions that
lessen suffering and increased peace
the grounding of how we move through the world here now in this moment
versus what might happen there and then right always asking noticing
where's the suffering right now reuse the piece right now
it's a great alternative to stunning wife stories
so noticing being versus being caught by
the mind's tendency is towards concoction speculation
and taking those Tendencies with a sense of humor
I just think of the current Dalai Lama's infectious laugh he's asked basically
are you fully awakened I mean it just laughs and says my mind tried sneaky stuff on me all the time but he notices
it of compassion and humor being aware versus being obsessed
is the key because anything anything we clearly see
with awareness is fuel for wisdom food for awakening
this is where the other qualities of Mind we've gone through this week are really supportive mindfulness of what's
beneficial to ourselves what's beneficial to others our attitude is their kindness and good
will sense of sharing or generosity
and the consistency and Persistence of always beginning again with kindness
all of these things support us in being able to respond to alleviate suffering
rather than perpetuate it in our own minds Hearts lives
and in the ways we relate to each other
so in the days between now and Monday if you wish to you might consider noticing
what lessened suffering and what increases peace
in your own practice in your life and your relationships
so thank you thank you dear Sandra very much for your kind attention
it's been a joy to be with you