I made it welcome welcome everybody had a little wrestling with a
zoom this morning but uh here I am nice to see you all if somebody could
give me a thumbs up that they can hear me that would be
great want a sound test Zach ask yes I made it
were you guys getting a little worried oh no it's getting close to 7 a.m. yeah usually we TR I try to uh
thank you Jamie give me the heads up that you can hear me
yeah Zoom decided it needed absolutely had to be updated and I tried to
circumvented and just made it take longer but I'm here now I'm happy to be
here oh a slight Echo yeah I'm afraid that that I'm not sure what I can do
about that I think that's probably just the space where I am
sorry
I'll wait another minute or so just because logging on a little bit late
allow everybody to get on board and to say good morning or say hello right that's part of the best thing about the
7 AM is checking in in the
morning
morning good [Music] afternoon good evening good day wherever
you are and whatever time it is sending some warm wishes your
way welcome welcome it's a pleasure to be here with you all on these 7 a.s though I have to
say right you know the pressure is high there's such beautiful wonderful teachers who do this 7 am teaching so
uh I'm just happy to be part of the team here supporting
everybody and today or this week um I thought I might title
the week like five fun faculties for fearlessness forever five fun friendly faculties for
friendless for for fearlessness forever you know just go a little crazy with the alliteration but um I'll just limit
myself to faculties for fearlessness and I want to talk about something that
we're all familiar with the five faculty but I want to look at them in a different way through a different lens
emphasizing different aspects that perhaps we haven't considered so instead
of introducing something new I'm sure many of you are familiar with the five faculties I want to introduce them in a
way that uh perhaps you hadn't considered that you already know and
that they can be a support for working with fear so that is a short introduction
let's do a guided meditation
so taking alert
posture settling
in once you've settled in is there a way that you could be just a tiny bit more
comfortable able bring a little bit
more Ease Into The Experience we're still maintaining the
meditative posture but there's no reason why it can't
have ease as well as
alertness and to begin we open your senses even though your
eyes are closed to open the
senses maybe there's Shadows or
shapes with the eyes even though the eyes are
closed feeling the sensation of touch or pressure
as the body rests on the surface that supports
it maybe that touch of air on your skin feeling of clothing blankets
against the
skin maybe there's just a general sense of heaviness or light in the
body opening the ears so to speak the sound of my
voice other sounds in the room or in the
environment allowing the sounds to just be received
not having to go out and get them but receiving
them is there a sense of smell or
taste toothpaste perhaps
having some ease with the senses open
relaxed and checking to see if there's a quality of
wellbeing that you can tune into this moment might not be that dominant
experience might just be a sliver of your experience but can you tune into
any sense of
wellbeing that sense of well-being to get as big as it would like the key word
here is [Music]
allowing there isn't a sense of well-being can you bring to
mind a memory of a an occasion a
locasion perhaps in nature petting a cat or a
dog being with a loved one can you bring that experience to
mind and how does that
feel
opening to this experience of well-being
is maybe there's a feeling of
spaciousness in the
body maybe there's a sense of
softening relaxing
opening
just know that you can always come back to this experience
tune in to this type of an experience during this guided
meditation maybe sometime during your
day
and we'll do a slight body
scan as I name a body part you can simply notice what you
feel that body part no judgment no need for it to be a certain
way just welcoming whatever experience there
is the
jaw the area around the
eyes these are Cal many areas we hold
tension maybe there can be some more ease maybe not
too
shoulders
noticing the experience of the
shoulders let them be away from the
ears the
chest
the
belly maybe you don't feel anything in particular or just
numbness that's okay maybe you feel a sense of
softening relaxing that's
okay maybe you feel a sense of aliveness
buzzing tingling energetic feeling that's
okay the
back
pressure of the contact whatever the body body is contacting against the
body the Bic might be the back
legs
our feet Le with they are touching
contacting as well as the experience of having
feet
the
arms
hands
and then resting our attention on the sensations of
breathing feeling the movement of the body as it
breathes
breath doesn't have to be any particular particular way we're just
noticing the movement maybe in the chest or in the
belly for some of you might be feeling the air going in and out of the
nose
and if the mind wanders that's okay that's what happens
when we meditate and just very simply gently Begin
Again
it doesn't matter how many times we begin
again it's just the activity of coming
back giving oursel over to the sensations of breathing
e
[Music]
is
welcome welcome this um first day it's a Monday
on a 7 a.m. here what a pleasure it is to be here to join you all it's funny
that we just call these the 7 a I don't know internally at IMC we call them the 7 A.M but for many of you it's not 7:00
a.m. but nevertheless so this week I wanted to
explore working with fear and specifically to use tools and
I'm going to use this word tools that we're already familiar with but maybe emphasize different aspects of these
tools or different uh views or perspectives on these views tools and
maybe combine them in a way that's maybe not novel or new way or a different way
and when I was thinking about this this week I was thinking like oh it's not very exciting or interesting but I hope
it's practical because sometimes what we need are just things to help us with some of
these rough spots or some of the difficulties right our lives have difficulties so the tools I want to
introduce are the five faculties I'm not going to go through the list of them right now because I'll introduce them
each day I will say that they are conventionally they're taught in a particular order but
I'm going to teach them in a different order and maybe talk about them in a
different way so that it supports specifically about working with
fear this recognition that when we have fear that we don't really have access to
our practice or our wisdom it doesn't matter how many teachings we've had sometimes we just don't have access to
them so my aim is to simplify or to bring things in in a
way that become really practical and as I said at the beginning of the before I started the guided meditation I did play
around with uh just maybe being silly and playful of ways to think about this and so many different alliterations I
came up with and now uh while I was meditating just kind of bubbled up now I forget the exact words but it was
something like you know five fun fabulous faculty for fearlessness for freedom
forever okay so in all seriousness and to say a little bit
about fear we all know what fear is but we may not really recognize what a large
role it has in our life this fear of not being understood or fear of being embarrassed or fear of failing you know
I I certainly have these fears and it's uh striking to to think about like what
a impact it's had on my life maybe things that I you know haven't done or tried because of these
fears and then say also maybe technically there's a difference between fear and
anxiety but for the purposes of here I'm going to kind of lump them together we could say that fear is a response to a
very specific imminent threat danger whereas anxiety may be a little
bit more unfocused and may not be a specific danger or threat that's
clear it's more like just going to the dentist and having some little bit of
anxiety before having to go to the dentist or but I'm going to treat these the same
essentially so the first faculty I'd like to introduce is
Sati conventionally or commonly translated as mindfulness and I want to introduce this
first because whatever we are experiencing it's even if it's mightily
uncomfortable and exactly what we don't want to be experiencing or maybe we're not even sure it turns out it's always
better to be present for our experience no matter what that experience is and no matter how
uncomfortable it is and even if it's the last thing we want to do and somehow to trust that to be aware
of what's happening is always helpful even if we can't really be
present for the experience itself maybe we can be present in a different way and
I like to talk about that a little bit here but first before I do that I'd like to just offer some questions to
consider what would happen if you got curious about your fear and worked with
it would it be uncomfortable would it build your self-confidence or what parts of your
life would it impact if you got curious about your fear and worked with it and
how might that set you free how might that bring more freedom
to your life so this mindfulness one thing I want to start
with it's maybe like the most course or the most obvious recognize what's
available in the present moment environment so that is like very
specifically right now I have this desk in front of me see a computer computer
monitor I have a light there's some books I have this dongle on my computer
very mundane things and this might feel like di this
is not very spiritual to notice this but it turns out it's incredibly helpful to
just be aware of our environment and if we're for particularly if we're feeling
particularly anxious it can be really helpful to notice particularly mundane things specifically
Corners where the ceiling meets the wall the corner of the doorway in the
lower left the corner of where the flooring meets the wall the corner of
the baseboard the corner of the desk here the corner of this dongle
thing so there's a way in which bringing our attention just to the
environment can really bring some grounding and some resources to our
experience and sometimes that's all we have access to when there's some fear or
anxiety maybe we don't have access to all these teachings and wisdoms that we've heard so the first is maybe to
bring to our attention to the environment and then to the bodily
experience turns out as humans and contemporary humans we we've developed this incredible capacity to be
disembodied and what happens is the mind right is going um its own way with
thoughts and there's this fear and fear and anxiety which can build on itself and there can be this tremendous
momentum or maybe it's just this unending chattering bringing awareness to the
environment and then to our bodily experience interrupts that
momentum so what are some neutral maybe more readily accessible bodily
experiences such as feeling the feet on the ground feeling the pressure of whatever
is on is contacting the body feel that experience it can be pressure of what
you're sitting on standing on could be maybe the feeling of the clothing against the body again some other more
readily accessible neutral experience es to bring mindfulness attention
recognition awareness noticing using all these syn synonyms that we might use for
Sati to just our experience in an uncomplicated
way you also might notice the breath and slightly just slightly extend
the exhale a little bit is this something else that can bring some more calmness to our
experience and interrupt this momentum of this fear or anxiety and certainly we know that the
Buddha did this right he brought awareness to his bodily experience when he was experiencing fear before he was
awakened he talks about like maintaining the same posture just knowing how his body was and just staying with
it now the second thing is the bodily experience first the environment second
the bodily experience we're coming closer and closer and then here's something that could be enormously
powerful recognize the strong sense of no I don't want
this no the sense of resistance like the sense of go
away and we tune into that and how does that show up for us
let me bring some curiosity what how does this no notice that I'm not talking about fear yet I'm just talking about
the no I don't want this go away and so how do you generally act
when fear arises do you believe it automatically do you recoil from it and shut down do
you avoid everything that makes you feel afraid do you attack do you get angry do
you become crit critical or blame do you feel bad about yourself
this idea well if I were a different kind of person I wouldn't be afraid if I was more of this less of
that so just tune into maybe noticing how you're reacting no need to judge it
and if you are critical of the way you're reacting can you notice the
criticalness how does that no I don't want this feel at that
moment maybe that's a sense of more energy coming up maybe it's a sense of energy going
away maybe it's a particular sensation in the body a tightness in the throat
or some something in the belly or in the chest can you be with that no
experience Again part of that is to tease apart Their Fear we're not looking at the fear yet we're just looking at
this big sense of no I don't want this nobody wants to feel
fear and then maybe even getting into maybe even a little bit more
subtle is what is it that feels threatened and this might be something that we'll do a little bit later when
we're not in the midst of the fear we could just stay with the sensation of no
and we'll notice that as we are with the sense of no then the sense of fear starts to obey we don't have to be with
the fear we can if that's available to you you can be with that bodily experience but it can just be with the
no and you'll notice how as we work with that strong sense of resistance the fear itself starts to Abate and
soften but also we can look at we feel fear when we're something which we're
trying to protect feels threatened so what are you trying to
protect what feels [Music] threatened maybe it's a inner story
about aging or health or how you should
be maybe it's a belief that it's dangerous to speak up it's dangerous to
Hope or ask for things or maybe it's a sense of wanting
things to be a particular way relationships security
health maybe it's a fear of dying these are all Perfectly Natural
legitimate fears but if there's a way that we could bring some specificity to the fears like
what is it that feels threatened and this can be a
doorway to have greater freedom not only Freedom From Fear but just freedom in
general so bringing some mindfulness some curiosity to what is it that's
feeling threatened and to do this from a sense of
care in the guide meditation I pointed to some well-being if there's possible
to maybe have this inquiry not over in the midst of here maybe it's possible but maybe from a sense of well-being
when the fear Isn't So Paramount is there a way that we can bring some
curiosity what is it that brings some specificity I'm sorry that feels fear
what is it that's feeling threatened and can we bring some specificity to
that and maybe that comes to just dropping in the question what is it that feels
[Music] threatened and just allowing whatever
the answer might be to Bubble Up we don't have to do an archaeological dig to find it
but being present and honoring and respecting what comes
up so in this way STI mindfulness one of the five
faculties can be a tremendous support for fear anxiety and I talked about
going from the most obvious the external environment this is a common technique
for psychologist those people who work with trauma to help people to just start with what's in the room the plant the
picture on the wall the computer the desk like these are completely normal things and not to be dismissive of them
but to just like notice bring your attention to them and then maybe some neutral Corners
if that's helpful that will help the whole nervous system to calm down and then to our bodily experience
at that moment and in particular like where we feel contact some grounding
maybe this sensation of fear you don't have to because accompanying that fear
is the sense of no I don't want it tune into that sense of
no how does that feel and then to just have some Curious what is it that feels
threatened bring some mindfulness to that so here's the first faculty for
fearlessness for freedom forever and maybe you guys can come up with some other alliterations but wishing you all
a wonderful day today and maybe you'll have an opportunity to bring some mindfulness whenever you notice some
fear or some anxiety and thank you I look forward to
our journey of exploring these this week wishing you all a wonderful rest of the day thank
you