so hello and welcome everyone to happy hour so for today I want to um share a
little teaching that um I was inspired to to learn from my dear beloved friend
and teacher Sylvia bin um and
um this teaching is about um making your
minds and hearts safe for yourself and others the same way that it's it's as if
it were Mr Rogers Neighborhood Mr Rogers neighborhood so um anyone not familiar
with Mr Rogers Neighborhood raise your hand I'm looking at my other iPad I'm not seeing any oh yeah one person oh
great okay so there's one person who's not familiar okay great I'll tell you I'll tell you about Mr Rogers so um it's
um and and I became actually familiar with Mr Rogers after I moved to the US um as well when I was 16 years
old later than that but anyway so so Mr Rogers was uh or Fred Rogers was a
pastor who was um responsible who who actually did uh children's programming
and and he was such a kind kind beautiful being uh through and through
it wasn't just a performance he was a beautiful kind being he he taught meta
and compassion to children of all ages um and actually his programming was
really Progressive for his time in so many ways there's so many Beautiful Stories so if if uh anyone does not know
about uh him I do highly recommend you look up Mr Rogers later and and read a
little bit about him so one thing that he would always say begin his
show with was it's a beautiful day in the neighborhood it's a beautiful day in
the neighborhood um and and um and then what
we he say won't you be my won't you be my won't you be my neighbor so and then
I think he would begin and end the show that way so so was Mr Rogers Neighborhood there a lot of cets a lot
of characters and really basically he taught meta compassion wisdom by any
name just um so so Sylvia um using this as a
metaphor in her teaching to make our hearts and Minds like Mr Roger's
Neighborhood safe safe for everyone for all these characters for all these
beings for all these little puppets that that show up in our minds and hearts can
we make it a safe neighborhood both for ourselves and for others so
so um yeah and there's Al so much more to say about Mr rogers's neighborhood
which I think I'll just leave it at that I think most of you are already familiar much better than I am with Mr Roger's
neighborhood so much more so I'll just leave it up to you to to feel into your
own associations affiliations with with u yeah what that means what that means
for you um and if you're new to it again and think of a a loving a a a batva
teacher who's just who a Buddha likee n teacher who's made the safe neighborhood
with lots of teachings on kindness compassion internally and externally so
so with that let's sit together let's sit
together arriving arriving in our bodies
with awareness with
kindness and how can we offer kindness to [Music]
ourselves can we make this neighborhood that is our heart and mind safe for [Music]
ourselves and we make it even a little safer than it already
is a little less self judgment a little
less [Music]
criticism a little more friendliness with each
breath
and what if this body this mind this
heart was feeling [Music] held in safety and Care friendliness as
if held in the friendliness of Mr Roger's
neighborhood for those who have an association
with Mr Rogers and his kindness and his compassion and
his his guests the various characters
puppets and we imagine characters in our mind as these
these puppets we get to offer safety and
kindness
to we get to be friend we get to befriend all aspects of
ourselves treat them with dignity with kindness with respect
ECT and know that in some ways they are made up they are puppets and yet and
yet it's how we cultivate our Goodwill and kindness It's how we train
ourselves in
goodwi maybe even you softly hear as a
metagen it's a beautiful day the neighborhood a beautiful day in the
neighborhood asking all aspects these puppets these aspects of
yourself won't you be your
neighbor we don't have to get rid of them
squash them get to know them with friendliness
kindness you're here for a
reason
and now what if we made ourselves safe for
others made our hearts our minds and our bodies Our physical
actions words thoughts say for
others expanding your good will
to others offering Mr rogers's neighborhood
to others to everyone we interact
with won't you be won't you be won't you be my
neighbor
radiating the kindness of Mr
Rogers
SP making ourself safe through kindness and
Goodwill
then see what is needed whether more internal offering of safety is needed
more external or maybe both internal external no
separation offering ourselves and others safety and
friendliness all the characters all the little madeup
puppets internally and all the characters
externally all this impermanent arising and passing away
everyone worthy of friendliness and
kindness
as we turn to bring this meditation to a close
remember remember to be kind as everyone we
meet whether or not we see we know we appreciate everyone we meet is
fighting a difficult battle with challenges this life is challenging for
every single one of us in different ways so be kind be kind to yourself be kind
to Others May all beings
everywhere make themselves safe for themselves and for each
other may we all make ourselves safe for one another May there be peace in the
world thank you all thank you so much for your
practice I was having a fun time with Mr Rogers so tonight I would like to not
offer um small groups because I'm a bit under the
weather and I just wanted to offer a uh um an opportunity maybe for just a
couple of Reflections um that we can take either
um through your voice or or you can type them in chat either to me privately or
to everyone CH changing the settings now and uh maybe we'll end there so that I
will be kind to myself and offer myself some time to rest
so so any Reflections you like to share or questions about
this Mr Rogers Neighborhood practice
and if anyone by the way hasn't seen the movie um that came out a few years ago
um it's I forget what the name of it is I'm sure somebody will type it in chat it's a really a it's a a great depiction
of of this amazing character this amazing being so any
Reflections what this practice was like for you if something opened up for
you
Claire um thank you m uh n i I wanted to say first of all that I'm sorry you're
not feeling well um I hope it doesn't spoil the the weekend for you um but I
was immediately reminded I I had the wonderful opportunity of going to a very
very famous therapist he start he founded the school of cognitive therapy
and he was aging when I went to him but he would sit in with groups and you know
people were talking about things that were bothering them and every so often
somebody would sort of beat themselves up for you know not doing things better and his his response almost invariably
was yes we're all up Val human beings but it he put himself in our is a
total equal to us you know there was nothing special about him he loved us
just as much as we loved him um and it and it showed you know he really cared
about everybody in the group and so your description of I always you know I'm a
great admirer of Mr Rogers but the person the approach to life very
similar great thank you thank you field thanks for braying this in
appreciate it yeah beautiful and we have Reflections in chat one of you sent
privately to me Mr Rogers and meta makes a perfect pairing yeah I agree it does
doesn't it uh and thank you Neil as always for finding resources the name of the movie
that came out in 2019 is a beautiful day in the
neighborhood and um and Tom Hanks did a did a really amazing
job I think um yeah depicting
depicting him and also Don says Mr Rogers Neighborhood I guess yeah you can
find various um uh YouTube um
Renditions thanks for your good wishes read yeah and Diana last
reflection I just really welcomed this uh it was so
refreshing and um I liked the idea of
humming along and singing which I did during the meditation it was very um I
I'm reminded of chance and things but the engagement of that part of the system and it was all very warm and U
very sweet and I started to think about everyone in the neighborhood it's very simple and uh not complicated and it was lovely
so thank you beautiful thank you so much Diana that aspect of you know the chant
the the resonance we can have with uh with sounds and um I also in my head was
hearing the you know it's a beautiful day in the neighborhood like a little chant and it just warmed my heart it
warmed my heart more and more and and I also um one last thing I would say is I
I also remember there's a scene in the movie that shows him that um while he was swimming in the pool um he was a
swimmer Mr Rogers and he would pray for everyone he would think of the names of
everyone and just wish them well wish them well wish them well and it's just
such a beautiful practice of meta um wish others well so anyway so with that
and thank you for all the good will wishes coming my way the chat I
appreciate it let's let's close let's close our evening together May our practice be a cause and
condition for our hearts to be a safe place for ourselves and for Others May
there be goodness kindness compassion in the world for everyone may all beings be
well may all being be free including
ourselves thanks everyone I'm going to stop the recording
stop