hello again and welcome to happy hour everyone wherever in the world you are
joining whatever this time zone might be
so so for today's theme um I wanted to invite us to practice
with with self-kindness self
yeah self um appreciation in a way not in a selfish
way but in a way of you know we're often looking outside forsaking ourselves for
for others perhaps and sometimes the perhaps in romantic relationships we're looking
for the other for the other to to make us happy um not everyone but but romantic love
tends to be um idealized quite a bit as the answer to
all the suffering and all the issues and problems and sadnesses in in our culture
and many cultures so um there is a beautiful poem that a
friend of mine shared with me yesterday and it took my breath away it's such a beautiful poem so I wanted to to share
the poem with you and uh yeah maybe I'll show it at the beginning
and then also share it when we're meditating together so the poem is by a
celebrated author and poet whose name is Maggie Smith and the name of the poem is
is bride bride b-r-i-d-e and you are welcome to either
make it gender neutral for yourself or or con get in touch with your femininity
you know yin yang we all have aspects of uh the both both feminine masculine in
us so so see how we can work for you but really the the idea of the poem is
embracing embracing love and care for ourselves so here we
go how long how long have I been wed
to myself calling myself darling dressing
for my own pleasure each morning choosing perfume to turn me on
how long have I been alone in this house but not alone
married less to the man than to the woman
silvering in the mirror I know the kind of wife I need and I
become her the one who will leave this earth at the
same instant I do I am my own bride
lifting the veil to see my face darling I say
I have waited for you all my life darling I say
I have waited for you all my life
so with that let's let's collect ourselves in meditation
survive let's settle in our posture
perhaps calling ourselves darling darling here you are darling
here you are sitting darling I have waited for you all my life
here you are
this being this person who is silvering in the mirror
this beloved silvering in the mirror
connecting connecting with the breath the body of this beloved
just as it is in this moment
foreign
letting the breath move freely through the rooms of this house
this dear breath this friend is companion through throughout our life
this breath is not a stranger
we forsake sometimes this breath
or the for thoughts of another past present future
can we be here
learning with care appreciation
receiving this gift not taking it for granted
there will be a day that there will be no more
and however the body is and however the body is feeling receiving
this wrath tired tigered anxious energetic
heavy light however it is greeting greeting this
body this house this heart
oh darling darling
as if we lift the veil to meet ourselves In This Moment
foreign
[Music] beloved other foreign
this being this darling who is silvering who is silvering in the
mirror
foreign
be the caring companion
to ourselves we seek
I'll read the poem one more time
see what phrases resonate for you
how long how long have I been wed to
myself how long have I been wet to myself
calling myself darling
dressing for my own pleasure
each morning choosing perfume too turn me on
how long have I been alone in this house
but not alone
married last to the man than to the woman silvering in the
mirror silvering with the mirror
I know the kind of wife I need and I become her
laughs the one who will leave this earth at the
same instant I do I am my own bride
lifting the veil to see my face darling I say
I have waited for you all my life
foreign
the one who will leave this earth at the same same instant I do
lifting the Veil to see my face
thank you
how long have I been wed to myself
calling myself darling
darling I say I have waited for you all my life
and we have that sense for this dear being
who is ourselves
can we have meta Goodwill love acceptance friendliness
relax into our lives into our bodies
with kindness
foreign
and as we turn towards the closing of this practice period
and we appreciate that each being each person
around us people we know people we don't know people who are dear to us
people with whom we have challenges they too are their own dear being
their lives are precious to them may they have kindness for themselves
may they meet themselves as its yearly beloved
just as we wish to meet ourselves as it dearly beloved caring for ourselves
cherishing like a mother
I could beloved and trusting that as we
plant seeds of care of meta friendliness for
ourselves for this person who is me filling our own cup with kindness with
care we can be more available to fill others cups
to care for them not in a needy way so that they care they take care of us
but with no strings attached with generosity with freedom with kindness
abundant kindness so trusting that this act
of kindness for ourselves meta for ourselves is a radical Act of generosity
towards others and may all beings everywhere
be happy be healthy have ease
may all beings know their own goodness may they be afraid including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so different ways to relate to
to cultivating kindness friendliness appreciation acceptance for ourselves
now we have time to turn to Community Practice and the invitation is
in small groups too perhaps share if you like
or something about this practice or the way we related to it today using this
poem through this poem something that lit up for you is there
something that connected for you or maybe something that was challenging for you but frequently fine or or you can
just offer your silence and say pass
perfectly fine and you can show up in the breakout
group just with silence just with care just say pass hold space and the next
person will offer something the next person will offer something perfectly it's
and if you do choose to speak please just share from your own experience not
asking questions not directing the conversations just show up with your own
heart with your own practice and uh and share with with others
so so I'm going to make the
breakout rooms now and we're going to go alphabetical order
is the invitation and um Again The Prompt is what what came up
for you what what connected for you what what
what what came up for you what connected with this practice with those way of
relating to the practice and what um did not connect for you perhaps or
was challenging either you can talk about either or and
um and yeah again just speaking from your own experience not directing so
I've made the rooms and take care of yourselves take care of each other here
we go hey welcome back welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed everybody's back and we have time for uh for reflections
um questions comments practice reports especially if you
haven't spoken in the group for a while it would be lovely to hear from you how was it for you what did you discover in
the group what did you discover in the practice and also I'm going to post the
link to the um uh poem which showed up in the new New
Yorker magazine so that everyone can have a link to it and I'm sure I trust
that uh it'll be sent later by uh um but I but by our dear Neil to the
Google Groups so so Reba Reba I see your hand is up
yes hi it's nice to see you again I've
studied with you on Retreat before and um I really appreciated
um you're offering the opportunity to uh change the gender of the of the poem
and I um and I just wanted to offer just a further um expansion and an awareness that
um that I was adding to my own practice to help myself be more present just to say like you know not the partner in the
other room but you know myself um to to move it out of the idea of um
to acknowledge not only the gender issue but also this very particular kind of heteronormative relationship model that
doesn't reflect all of our realities in words like my reality so just another place to just help my body and my spirit
be more present beautiful thank you for sharing that I'm I'm delighted to hear how you worked with it to make it work
for you and the creativity yay it's invited especially with the practice of meta for us to accept all parts of us
all of us in different ways and and and a particular poem in a particular way
may not work or might even be like yeah that's not my reality so yay thank you for doing that and also thanks for
bringing that into the space appreciate it Reba you're so welcome okay let's see Sarah I see your hand
please hi there Sangha um
I usually can't make happy hour but I listen to the recordings on Audio Dharma
frequently and so I'm delighted to be here tonight um and it's the perfect theme for me as
well because my partner is Moroccan and he just went back home for a month and
so I'm here in the U.S without a partner for a month and it's a great poem to
carry through this next month and just the concept of like dating myself you
know I spend a lot of time with him when he's here and I'm gonna have a lot of time on my
hands to spend with myself so I'm I'm just that this felt very
um serendipitous thank you beautiful thank you Sarah thank you for sharing
that that's it I I so appreciate the timeliness um of this poem for what's what's
arising for you right now that's that's lovely great um and there are a few Reflections I see
in chat um oh did I sense change the chat oh I
haven't changed the chat settings you're also welcome to to share your Reflections uh publicly if you wanted to
but uh let's see one reflection just to me so I contemplate a lot about I me
versus soul and body which I are we
trying to practice today great great that's that's a great
um that's so interesting so so the question really has to do with
the teachings on the relative and the absolute uh or actually some people
don't call it the absolute the ultimate or or the universal um so the relative and the universal or
or ultimate so they're the teachings really also in Buddhism that exist about
uh self you know there is a self you exist do you you have an address you
have feelings if you get hurt you grow you die so there is a self and then
there are the teachings about about not self impersonality it's not personal
it's it's what everything that's happening the body also even the body is
not personal it's it's nature etc etc so so the way I invite relating
to the practice of Meta Meta doesn't quite work if you're wishing well for
these impersonal atoms that are arising and passing away and very quickly or or
the four elements that are arising and passing away so metal works better in
the relative um with relative concerns but in the relative realm but actually the practice
of meta leads to insights um in the in the ultimate it leads to to
sense of compassion and care and love that's Universal with no strings attached for all beings everywhere
so um so that's how I invite you to to relate to that the person who who
shared that question one more reflection send
love the poems PT with tears ah it's beautiful PT
meaning Joy join Paulie with tears that's lovely thank you so much for sharing that
and yeah and let's see
um is that long node let's see if I can read it quickly what should I do if
thoughts that I am a bad person with examples from past keep coming up I say
I know and I'm different now and getting better and becoming peaceful I also send
loving kindness to people whom I have heard if they show up in my thoughts that highlight I am bad can you please
share your thoughts thank you for sharing that question yeah it's um the need for forgiveness that that
the thoughts that arise with you know with the stories that you are bad and
believing those stories and and being stuck there so what I recommend whether
I suggest sometimes it might be helpful to switch to
the practice of um uh forgiveness actually self-forgiveness
as much as possible may I forgive myself as much as possible in this moment it may not be completely accessible but
tuning into that sense of uh self-forgiveness for yourself or asking
for forgiveness in your heart from others and maybe making amends later but
that's the practice that's needed because sometimes the what what this questioner asked it can feel like too
hard to to get through that so the appropriate practice would be self-com it would be
um both forgiveness as well as here's another thing to turn toward with towards
oneself towards oneself with self-compassion for the pain because in that moment you're the one who's really
hurting you're taking a dagger of memory and just stabbing yourself with it you're bad you're bad ouch so turning to
that pain and letting there be compassion um for that pain because it's not
helping anyone that that pain we think that it's leading to remorse but
actually it's getting us stuck it's forgiveness that leads us to to remorse
and taking uh responsibility so that's a short dormant there you are
welcome the person who asked the question you're very welcome another person said thank you for the poem
perfect for me great I'm delighted to hear that there are many people
um who connected with the poem and those who who uh chose to to work with it to
to make it work for them so beautiful so yeah a full full day of practice thank
you all thank you so much for your cultivation thank you for your practice may we all
see your own goodness may we all befriend ourselves may we all befriend ourselves
and befriend Others May all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves
thanks everyone be well [Music]