hello from Redwood City and welcome
and it's a wonderful thing to be with you all and it's a wonderful thing to
come here and sit in this seat that I have meditated in for so many years and
to assume my position uh my meditation position which
um I want to emphasize for you for this coming
meditation one of the pervasive emotions in many people's
lives sometimes quite evidently and sometimes in the background is fear
anxiety and sometimes the opposite of fear is um courage
but I would like to uh offer another uh kind of antidote or alternative to fear
a healthy one and that is to offer our full presence to what is
happening so we might not know what to do we might not know what to say but uh we
don't maybe we don't even courageously deal with the fear or face
the fear overcome the fear but we offer whatever the situation is our our
attention clear present attention we don't we
don't NE necessarily have courage but we don't cow we don't necessarily distract
ourselves um but we uh attract ourselves to the present
moment we stand here We Stand we sit we're present with a certain
intentionality that uh that maybe is an alternative to fear
especially fear that's an attitude chronic fear that's a almost like a
that's been conditioned into us by life circumstances that's not really necessary to have all the time so the
attitude of fear we somehow will transform it into an
attitude of mindful presence and for that it helps to assume
a posture that offers some stability strength and
Clarity that we are here really here and present kind of like you know standing
our ground or taking our place so if you're meditating lying down
uh one way the posture might help this if the body allows for this is with your
feet you know on the bed or on the floor the soles of the feet bring your knees
up towards your chest having your elbows to your side on
the surface on the bed or the floor and have your your your hands pointed at 90
your arms at 90° angle so your hands uh fingers are pointing directly to the
ceiling parallel to each other so that uh there's intentionality and Clarity
here I am with the feet with the hands that kind of oh this is here I'm really
here I'm present and there's an intentionality in both those that uh is
comparable to the intentionality if you're sitting cross-legged is to sit uh
well balanced on the floor on your cushion and sit upright uh but there's an uprightness
and a little bit of openness of the chest if you're sitting in a chair or a
couch to see if you can adjust yourself so that um there is a
greater presence you offering being present in your
posture just like if you sit up straight and come forward on the
couch or something you're going really going to listen to someone and really show that you're that you're really attentive to what
they're doing you sit up and maybe you come forward so to assume a posture of
presence of attention more than you normally would in meditation if the focus on meditation
is relaxing so taking some
care one way to do this also for if you are kind of leaning back into
a chair or the couch uh if you if your hands aren't already this way is to put
your hands uh on your thighs either with
Palms down or Palms up whichever one of those gives you this greatest sense of
kind of strength and presence and here I
am and then lower your
gaze and if it's comfortable gently close your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths emphasizing the inhale more than the
exhale where the inhale we're taking our place here we're
filling the immediate space of our body and with our breath with our attention
with with this kind physical feeling
of clarity around here I am here I am in this body in this
place on the exhale relaxing into
here but emphasizing the the strength the clarity the um
fullness of filling your lungs with oxygen
and a little bit greater sense of substantiality or fullness of the body
in breathing out in breathing
in
and then letting your breathing return to normal and take a few moments to
feel whatever stability or strength or Clarity of
presence that you can feel through your
body
and with that as a support becoming aware
of how the body experiences
breathing
on the exhale relaxing the thinking
mind
softening the energy of
thinking
not living in your thoughts by feeling
recognizing what is beyond the edges of your thoughts certainly your thoughts
don't fill the universe beyond the the edges of the
thinking the sensations and feelings of the body being
here
usually we do some body relaxation at the beginning of a
sitting instead feel your body as it is tension at
all without being troubled by
it letting all the sensations of the
body kind of coales or support a Clarity that here you
are here you take your
place fully
unapologetically
for
and if there is fear maybe find a place
within maybe a small little point of stability where there is no
fear
and allow the fear to be in the background in the foreground the
stability of
presence
e
for
on the exhale relaxing your thinking thinking mind
mind on the
inhale assuming your place here
fully with some strength with some clarity with
some sense of really belonging to this place at this time and you're allowed to
with your your full body to inhabit this
location as you breathe in filling yourself with attention and
presence
for
e
with the
gentleness enter into this moment more fully through your
body with the posture maybe a little more straight and upright
or the hands in a little bit more of a intentional
position
or with the
inhale feeling more rooted here in this place this
body
steadying yourself in the body here and
now as an alternative to being afraid
anxious apprehensive
iive in such a way that fear recedes to the edges of our
being still there but it doesn't interfere it
doesn't color this place of stability and
presence
e
gently but clearly offer a real presence to this
moment this time here in this
body a presence that a little bit like
a snake that's growing bigger and it sloughs off its
skin a presence which is strong and firm and
gentle which something grows so that something else falls
off or receed EDS maybe fear recedes and falls
off
for
and as we come to the end of this sitting to take a few moments to imagine
visual realiz what would it be like for you to be in a place
situation that normally involves a bit of
anxiety but rather than giving into the
anxiety you establish yourself stand
sit with presence stability
kind of really showing up at least for yourself here and now in the
middle of an anxious
situation and perhaps when we're
not in our anxiety but rather in our presence our
attention it's easier to have good will to wish well for
others and so we end this sitting with a well wishing for all all
the people we might encounter
today may they be happy safe peaceful and
free may they Thrive May good things happen to
them may may may they be safe enough that their fear
abates and when we with them may we be a safe person for
them maybe through our presence may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free of
[Music]
suffering thank
you
h hello and welcome to this talk second talk on the topic of
attitudes and as I'm bending this week on this topic I'm pairing up uh an
attitude which is not very helpful for us with an
attitude which is and by attitude here uh I'm more
focused on not so much attitude of the moment particular circumstance sense where we might have an attitude we don't
like it or we're impatient or we feel frustrated with something and we it's kind of an attitude than we have while
we're present for that particular activity but rather something that's more pervasive in our life and today the
topic is fear and one of the advantages and maybe sometimes the
challenges of doing mindfulness practice meditation especially going on Retreat
where we practice bringing attention all day and because we're there all day kind
of really being mindful we start seeing how often we get caught and uh and then
we see the patterns of what our mind is thinking or our emotions are feeling and
not a few people discover that uh there's a pervasive level of fear or
anxiety through their life much more than they realized and it's kind of in
the background or underneath all the other kind of concerns we have and
sometimes in being pervasive it casts its influence on the way we think the
way we behave the way we even physically look at the world um we can be looking
the World Through The Eyes of of anxiety or fear
apprehension and um and so there's a lot uh of wisdom and
a lot of uh uh for bringing attention and
Care uh maybe even love to our fear and one of the things I like to teach is
that the one of the roles of mindfulness really being present for anxiety is to
help our anxiety feel safe so we don't spin out even more by We Touch into our
fear but we allow our fear to be there so that we uh it can kind of begin to
relax I think of fear as always a secondary unless there's uh something
imminent danger like a uh in the moment I think of a lot of chronic anxiety to
be secondary to something that more deeply that needs needs us needs
attention and the avenue to it in classically in mindfulness meditation is
to learn how to be present for fear anxiety so that it can begin to relax
and you can reveal what's deeper for today I would like to suggest an another
alternative to uh an attitude of anxiety attitude of apprehension or fear that we
might be carrying with us pervasively through much of a day or all the time and that is um uh a clear sense of
being present and to do that in a embodied way physical way even if we
don't feel uh confident or feel uh you
know that that's kind of we don't feel strong or don't feel stability and presence we can
assume with our take take it take on but a physical posture a posture that here I
am I'm present and um and that doesn't mean that we have to go towards the thing
we're afraid of we don't have to resolve it we can even do this you know we take
a few steps back or if there's a a social situation where we feel anxious
uh we don't have to be in the middle of it we could maybe be you know standing you know on the edges of the group or
something but not to give into the fear not to continue to let appr apprehension
condition us have an influence on us but rather uh recognize that it's
there and then offer our presence to the situation offer a clear like we we we
are taking our place here and now if we're standing we're standing our ground
if we're sitting we're taking our place like this is almost like our Throne or something like this is where I belong to
sit here upright and dignified and we're not resolving the fear we're not but we're not acting from
the fear we're not addressing the things we're afraid of directly we're just uh
not cowering or shrinking or being preoccupied by the fear we offer we're
here we're present and uh in one version of this is something that I had to learn I don't if
I had to learn it but I uh was motivated to learn it uh when I noticed how much
fear I had was to be counterphobic and I couldn't do that initially but at some
point I had the confidence the ability to turn towards the things I was afraid
of and take a step towards them sometimes literally so and that made a
world of difference for me and and uh to not uh uh allow the fear or the
apprehension to dictate how I my posture my voice my behavior um but to somehow
break through it and this idea of taking our place maybe standing upright and
strong or sitting upright and kind of really present um as a way of not not
denying that there's apprehension and fear but not letting it unduly influence
us and affect us and affect the choices we make about our posture what we say
what how we look what we what we look at or um we don't you know look down and
avoid or kind of excessively shy or something but to really take our place
here and offer our presence and uh I'm offering this suggestion also not as a way of
resolving the issue or if there's some kind of present moment re reason to be
anxious um you know coming into Thanksgiving for many of us in the United States there might be social
situations that Thanksgiving Gatherings that brings us anxiety and um and not to resolve those
but not to but and but not to uh cower either not to go forward not to go
backwards but take our place here I'm here definitively I don't know what to do but
I do know how to be present I don't know what to say but I do know how to be quiet in a way where I feel
like I'm I'm really taking my place I'm here I count I have value I'm here other
people might not treat you differently because of it but it might make a world of difference to have that as a practice
um than you know the the implicit
or unintentional practice ice of practicing fear practicing
anxiety and um and when fear anxiety has become an attitude uh it means that we
are we've spent too much time thinking about it too much time being conditioned
by The Chronic way of thinking about this there's danger there's fear there's problems and there certainly are in this
world of ours and I don't want to deny the the the realness of some of the
things we're anxious about but it's not necessary to always be anxious when the
danger is not imminent because if we do then it's conditioning us and adding and
strengthening this pervasive attitude and there's a loop between feeling you
know an attitude of fear that creates influen us to have
thoughts about fear about what we're afraid of and concern and that creates more of the fear and it's a kind of a
loop and sometimes you you know it spirals out to a panic attack but to uh
to somehow break that maybe gently that Loop that looping by not always giving
into the fear but taking our place standing up being really
present and um and this is different than just being mindful of situations
because sometimes when when we are relying only on mindfulness uh we don't see how much our
mindfulness our attention is somehow unintentionally maybe even
subconsciously being shaped or influenced by the the fear itself and so to kind of break the
cycles of fear or break kind of the mold of it that we're kind of stuck in by sitting up clear strong present and
having a sense of steadiness and stability that maybe is not very strong
but is there as an alternative to only letting the attitude of fear have the
upper hand or be have too much influence on us and I'm not suggesting that this is
easy in many circumstances but there might be some circumstances where uh you can practice
this and um to switch the attitude from Fear to being present to being present
in an embodied way and um and uh and then see what
happens what happens next maybe it's easier for you maybe you do feel like
you're breaking out of a certain kind of for some people even a kind of prison or kind of uh to be always in the you know
you know surrounded or caught up in apprehension fear anxiety and I'm not offering this as a
solution as the final you know this is going to make everything go better or easier but uh it is a different attitude
that we can step into that can begin to make a difference and can also change
our relationship to fear uh so that uh when we do bring
mindfulness to fear that respects fear that holds it gently that uh we have a
greater capacity to do that because we bring that sense of stable presence to
the fear and when we're fully present for it then uh we don't get uh pulled
into it or unduly influenced by it so
um so if you find yourself with fear
especially minor fears or minor anxieties for this exercise uh and we want to be careful
when there's strong fears and you know strong tendencies towards anxiety that this what I'm saying might not be
appropriate but to practice with the small ones and see what difference it makes and see uh what happens to the
anxiety and fear when uh you offer this alternative embodied
presence um being really here present so um thank you very much and
um and I'm hoping that this focus on attitude today will be a
particularly interesting um topic of mindfulness on this holiday weekend
where our life is a little bit different than how it usually is and maybe has
different kinds of challenges than our ordinary life so thank you very
much