Hello friends greetings sa happy to be with you in this moment
in time and uh practicing together so today we continue to
explore the five Aggregates the constituents of our experience as human
beings and today we uh turn our attention to the fourth
aggregate um the Saras often translated as mental
formations or volitional formations um and they include both the aspect of
physical Behavior physical speech including internal speech as well as
thoughts uh mental behavior and um they include both what is um intentional in
the way of per purposive aspects of our mind as well as a reactive aspect of
Mind including um especially with psychological Behavior our thoughts the
proliferation of thoughts um as well as cultivating thoughts of um compassion
kindness uh Clarity mindfulness so there it it it um this bucket of experience
is um the it leads with volition with this this even if the volition seems to
be mild in the moment but as a a part of
pattern of behavior that has built up internally and again in our practice
this this morning the guided meditation I'll guide us to to turn attention to
um to noticing the the movement of the mind or
the movement of the Body for example if you want to if there intention there is intention to to move to pay attention to
that volitional formation for that movement or or if you you uh notice that the mind
has been distracted and uh and there's volitional formation to pull the mind
back to bring it back or yank it back or hopefully not yanky but if if that is
the case to notice all these volitional uh formations in the mind and
in the body as well as internal speech that that that pool that pattern that
pulls us into particular patterns of of uh experience anyway that is the frame
for today's uh practice so so let us arrive let us arrive
letting go of these words these explanations and
just arriving arriving in your experience in this
moment making a moment to fully arrive
and
settle with the body making sure the body is sitting
comfortably shoulders are rolled back
perhaps the spine is straight with a sense of integrity
and the body is relaxed the body is
soft bringing awareness to the Poise of the
body what is the Poise of the
body
what is the Poise of the Mind mind heart chipa translated as mind
heart hyphenated what's the Poise of our heart mind in this
moment I'm
aware and is it possible to
release to soften to calm these poises of the body and mind
and
heart with gentle intention setting Our intention at the outset of this practice
setting wholehearted intention to be
present fully present to be
kind being
undistracted not following
any distraction or sound
or or alluring thought that arises sending an
intention for gentle persistence gentle
with kindness and ease with each
breath
as we feel relaxed in the body and mind bringing
awareness all the volitional [Music]
formations our sphere of
experience if you're turning your awareness to know the
breath there is volitional formation there in this intention this
volition to be
aware if you find the mind is lost in thought there is some thinking that's
happening
it is relational even if it may be reactive based on patterns of thinking
in this way for years notice
notice
it is helpful to have a relaxed posture in the mind and the
body and let this stream of experience of the stream of volitional
formations be
known as if you're watching a movie of your
mind
relational or mental formations
other recall and this moment is the storm of mental volutional
formations become aware of the landscape and recognize this constituent
of Human Experience
clearly it's like this being
human
if you notice there is some discomfort perhaps in the body and there is
the desire the intention the volitional formation to move pay
attention pay attention to that get to know
it
and if and when you move notice the volitional formation in this
behavior of movement how it shows up with this bodily
action slow it down slow it
down
don't let it be reactive stud
it
are there familiar patterns of [Music] sounds internally thought thoughts
really internally arising the Saras this familiar pattern
set into
motion noticing its energy movement or maybe it's calling
the volitional formations are calm
notice
notice if the Mind picks up a pattern
as if picking up a
stick as if it's used to doing that there's leftover
energy volition from doing it before and it just does that automatically
seemingly now this pattern of thinking
engaging get to know this and can it be released if it's not helpful or healthy
skillful
as we turn to bring this sitting to a close
together can we give rise can we cultivate
appreciation thoughts volitional formations mental formations of
appreciation gratitude Goodwill and
kindness for ourselves for others who practice with
us and all beings everywhere Wishing Well sharing the goodness of our
cultivation regardless of of how we may judge it to be today distracted
sleepy doesn't matter you showed up there's goodness
here trust it sharing this goodness with all beings
everywhere may my practice may my cultivation be of benefit to all
beings may all beings be free may all
beings be happy including
myself spray your practice everyone and take a moment to transition
the recordings
hello and good day so today we
continue exploring the five condas the five heaps
um translated as heaps um often these
five constituents of our experience also Aggregates which is this funky word five
Aggregates um the constituents of our
experience and and today we come to the fourth one which is the
Saras uh translated as formations as volitional formations or
as mental formations uh or sometimes as as
volition because volition is the leading one volition is the leading one in this
formations in in this bunch of them um and sometimes in this category we
perhaps simplify it and think of it as as with mental formations we just think
of thoughts just this tangle of thinking that often we
experience in our experience of being human so um more generally it's helpful
to think of the the Saras as both um as I mentioned both as
not just reactive but also the purposeful the purposive aspect
of the mind that both include intention as well as Behavior so both of those
aspects and intention is an important aspect of it even though I'll put an asterisk here sometimes you might say
well I'm not intending to have all these thoughts they're just coming so there's no volition or intention here so is this
still quote unquote volitional um formations yes it is it it
also has to do with with the patterns that have been in place the volitions
the way we've been thinking or doing it it also has to do with Karma so I'll
talk about that it's a big asterisk I'll get to in a moment but in terms of definitions as we
set set it up so so also so examples of this both
reactive and purposive aspects of the mind that both include intention as well
as Behavior Uh it includes both physical Behavior
any activity any intention to move for example it it
includes um intention for verbal behavior for any speech uh gentle or not
gentle wise or unwise as well as this third category which is our our thoughts
our um the psychological Behavior the psychological
behavior and includes the pro PL PL
proliferation of thoughts for example or again cultivation of of thoughts of uh
of mental behaviors of kindness Goodwill compassion Clarity stability release
calm all of that so so with with
Saras um it both includes again this is really important and we can get to see
this in our own practice and experience it both includes this volitional this
intentional movement of the mind for example you sit and you turn you there is this movement of the mind of the
mental behavior that you're turning to say calm to um if you're practicing meta
thoughts of good willll kindness uh etc etc either during your
practice or in daily life you can see these uh volitional the the way these
formations there's volition there's a tiny bit of volition in there or maybe a lot of volition for example if you're in
the middle of um say Mind Storm thinking thinking thinking and it's very
unpleasant and and wisdom comes and it says no no stop thinking about that this
is not helpful or stop doing this stop just stop that there's can be very
strong volitional formations uh in the mind at that point so you can notice the
the strength of these these Saras these volitional formations either in in our mind States
or or or trying to shift our be turn um uh to to um form our Behavior physical
Behavior as well as speech uh our behaviors in terms of speech I can
there's always volition there's always these Saras there's always Saras volition uh before we speak um forming
our speech or stopping our our our speaking sometimes it's it's of course wiser and Kinder not to say anything um
and you might think that oh sometimes I open my mouth and just say something which I regret later and or there is no
volition there yet there is volitional formation Cara there having to do with
the patterns in which we have done things in the past so so um so we have
to talk a little bit about uh Karma you cannot talk about Saras without talking
about Karma they're just they're so connected to one another so again karma is this big huge topic
and yet the what I want to bring in as a cliff notes of our ex as as our of our
understanding it is not skillful to think of karma as oh what I've done in
the you know in the past life and it's not affecting me or whoever this person was in my past life and it's my karma
it's my bad karma my good karma that is not helpful way to understand this
teaching the helpful way to understand the teaching of karma especially as relates to Sankara is habit pattern and
and also think of the teaching of karma as an empowering teaching which is
whatever you engage with right now in this
moment it sets into [Music] motion the tendency to do the same thing
to continue in the same way in the next moment and in the next moment and we can see that in short moments right if you
are uh feeding say thoughts of anger and you're really juicy and you're just
thinking angry thoughts okay this mind moment then the the next moment was
likely going to be an angry moment so you're seating it's it's it's you're cultivating this pattern the Saras the
volitional formations you see how they're connecting Karma and Saras volutional formations you're
you're you're creating you're putting you're solidifying these volitional formations in the next moment the next
moment and next moment so that maybe a day from now a week from now a month
from now oh yes when you think you know the stimulus comes to mind this perception you know perception of this
particular person say or thought comes to mind remember yesterday Sonia perception um then oh these volitional
formations with think like oh I don't want to think uh Angry thoughts about this person but you but we've spent a
lot of volition intention you engaging and and and planting these seeds on
wholesome seeds so so these seemingly this this um mental formations it seems
like there's little volition but there's still left over energy it's left over
energy left over karma from when we really engage so think of karma in this
way it's it's really our we're air to our own actions and decisions not from a
past life just not don't don't make it too magical but really taking responsibility I'm responsible I am
responsible I take responsibility for my own um the way I think and I behave and
I act whether with kindness or or in skillful ways or unskillful ways so
these thoughts are just coming so karma is actually very um skill is is is an
empowering it's an empowering teaching um and the Buddha and the dhap has said
and I love this line whatever you Ponder and reflect upon
frequently that becomes the inclination of your mind so what we ever P whatever
we Ponder upon what whatever we Ponder and think about frequently that becomes
the inclination of our mind that's who we become this is so powerful this is
the teach in of karma in in this empowering way because yeah we can it's
like yes it's it's it's actually good news yes you can change the inclination of your mind you know this been showing
up to these teachings 7 A.M Pacific Time teachings for a while you know that the inclination of your mind throughout the
day starts to shift and change you can shift this inclination of your mind these Saras these volitional formations
this fourth aggregate that we're talking about today
so so so and and also know that in the present moment we are shaping forming
these volitional formations of our mental formations mental thoughts our
speech our patterns of speech the way we speak the way we act whether it's
mindful whether for example a discomfort arises in our body in the middle of say meditation and we just jerk like oh yeah
you slow it down sweetheart slow it down yeah discomfort oh yes intention to move
okay slow it down just notice just notice this our meditation can be a
Sandbox for us to see our volitional formations in the making which is it's a
um a Sandbox for when say you're in in a um interactive in a social situation and
somebody says something and you just open your mouth and oh it comes out it these are related if you slow it down if
you slow down and really observe your volitional
formations when you're alone when you're meditating when there's not the pressure
and the interaction of the social interactions then you can get to see oh
yeah this is this is how it's happening these volitional formation they get stronger and stronger and they get out
of hand and and you shape and form your
Karma your volition for your your um this this your the patterns of your own
action you get to craft it you get to to um to lovingly
lovingly um set the Motion Set set into motion these these beautiful actions and
results in in in in a in a um a helpful
way um ah that's all the time we have that's
the end of my sentence there's always more but you know I think that's enough so I'd love to invite you today to um to
notice to notice the volitional formations the mental formations that
are either the result of or the karma of the the result of the Habit patterns of
the past oh yes here it is or notice how the mind is setting with its own
volitional formations with its own subtle volitions is setting making new
ones being bring become aware of it how is this happening am i solidifying h
habit patterns um and of course in in the new arot um of our modern Minds the the
neurons that wire together that fire together wire together so notice notice
how we're setting we're we're create co-creating ourselves together of course it's not just all on our shoulders but
but with the causes and conditions in our environment and our Zeitgeist and our experience and it's pretty
fascinating this being human anyway thank you all for your practive become aware of the the sarus
today know them know them and looking forward to continuing together tomorrow all
right be well