all right so let's go ahead and get started with our meditation together
just allowing yourself to arrive physically of course but also internally
for meditation
settling in to your posture whether you're sitting or lying down or maybe
you're even standing that's fine too
just having a sense of your body in the meditation posture
perhaps feeling the contact points here seed against the chair or the cushion
or whatever you're lying on your legs or feet against the floor
and just letting yourself feel that support
letting yourself be supported
and then sensing the straightness of the body sometimes really letting go into the
support gives kind of a counterbalancing upward release to the spine
letting the spine and the head just naturally Elevate upward
so that the body is both straight and relaxed
and seeing if you can tune into any sense of ease in the body
some part or area that feels comfortable right now
and maybe tying that sense of ease to the breath
so as you breathe in breathing into the ease in the body
and as you breathe out maybe letting it spread through the body
and if there are various thoughts happening in the mind that's fine they can just be more in the
background can bring into the foreground the sense
of the body and the breath
I'm tuning into any feelings of Stillness in the body
the body is a dynamic entity and there's always some emotion especially from the
breath there may also be a sense of Stillness at least overall the body is not moving
much
maybe feeling how the ease is related to the Stillness
so we may sense how the body provides
kind of a stable container for the breath
and also for various emotions or thoughts
the body can be the reference point the anchor and these
other things move around the natural seatedness and strength of the sitting
body
sometimes sitting is likened to being like a mountain
just there
while the wind and the Sun and leaves blow around the mountain just
sits there calmly
and then they sit you are invited
to remain with the body in this
Mountain state if you will
so that means not shifting around
not holding ourselves rigid but if there is some kind of discomfort in
the knee or the back or the hip or the shoulder
the first inclination would be to just let that be
like a little disturbance on the mountain
and just sit perhaps breathing through it
meditation teaches us not to unthinkingly react
and that includes automatically adjusting the body
so with complete ease smiling at the body just sitting if there's
some discomfort or an itch and how does the line deal with that
maybe there won't be anything so we need to create it
but feeling the deep rest of just sitting
still
it's always possible to turn the mind again toward the ease in the body
breathing into there and spreading that
and of course if there's a actual physical injury or a real sense
that there would be harm and of course it's okay to move
but we would do so slowly mindfully so I'm noticing the intention to move
and then gently moving and as we do so feeling how the whatever
pressure we were feeling slowly dissipates
it's also quite useful just to sit with things as they are
that is the practice to be with things as they are feeling your ears and the rest and the
beauty of chilling still
foreign
and if there is coming to be any sense of
inner Joy or happiness or
contentment it's fine to breathe into that and allow
it to spread into the body
acknowledging that sometimes happiness is part of things as
they are
feeling into any sense of peace
foreign combination of softness and strength
that emerge from just being with things as they are
if there's any hardness there will be Duke of there needs to be strength
so what is it like to have softness and strength
as we come to the end of this sit
perhaps taking a moment to reflect
how valuable it is for both you and for others to
have the sense of a mountain-like presence and posture
just being able to be there
sometimes what we encounter is Duke Eye and others
suffering in some way and in order to be helpful we have to be
able to be present sometimes their suffering is coming out in the form of
words or actions to us that are unwelcome
and again it's very helpful if we have some ease with being that
this kind of presence in the world keeps suffering from perpetuating
farther and it can even bring it to an end
and it's very well cultivated through our meditation practice
so it may be a day of softness and strength
in order that the beauty of the dorm room can be felt
[Music]
okay so we're continuing with our series on The Art of Letting Go
seven practices that lead to letting go and yesterday we had the pair of using
and avoiding and today we have another pair that sounds like a big contrast like that
we have Letting Go by enduring and letting go by removing
so is there some active removal of things or is there a more passive
endurance of them and again we have some discernment about
that when do we hang in there and tough it out and when do we eliminate something that
is unwholesome or harmful so starting with what to endure
the teachings say what taints should be abandoned by
enduring here a person reflecting wisely Bears
cold and heat hunger and thirst in contact with gadflies mosquitoes wind
the Sun and creeping things and it also goes on to say various kinds
of pain we have so this one starts with various kinds of
discomfort after all we don't always have a choice in life about
what we have to endure and particularly with our body right these are about our body have you noticed how much of your
attention and energy go toward making things comfortable for the body
that's not inherently bad of course but it's also not so reliable and is it you
know that we're always going to be able to make it the right temperature and avoid
under and thirst and contact with things we don't want to touch
when I lived at Insight Retreat Center about 10 years ago
at that time there wasn't much control over the temperature in the building and
I really suffered when it was too cold and I tend to run a little cold and
um you know there were various mental machinations I could apply to that I
don't know if they really helped things like I'm supposed to be a good Buddhist and I'm supposed to just be mindful
um and then you know then the mind would just answer with no wait I need to care about myself and have compassion and it
should be like this and it should be like that um so I was enduring in a sense but there
was a little bit extra added by my mind let's say and eventually
I realized you know a very undramatic way that I was fine
actually I could handle the temperature variations and it really wasn't that big of a deal
so you know enduring and seeing the way the Mind tries to endure
but with a little bit of greed or aversion added onto it and then finally just settles down into
actual Equanimity um gives the confidence that this practice
of just being with something does actually work you know if if one actually uses mindfulness
it will eventually engender genuine Equanimity and not the false Equanimity
of putting up with something and obviously it's not just grating your teeth and burying it that's
not what this is referring to it says enduring I don't know what other word we could use but it means actually enduring
in a way such that there's letting go and there is peace in the mind and body
just come to peace with how it is so these are practices that lead to release
and it's important as we go through the enduring process that we see how the
mind doesn't want to endure doesn't want to actually just have Equanimity and then it will eventually
settle down because there's duga in that extra that's added this is like the second Arrow teaching there is the first
Arrow of how it's not always easy for the body and
then there's the other ones we add on about I don't like it it shouldn't be
like this how can I stop it who's in who's responsible and how can I talk with them you know these kinds of things
um so life is definitely going to give you opportunities for this um
but we can practice with it deliberately also I remember one time
Gill coming back from a vacation he had been on where I think he was camping in
the mountains somewhere and uh by a mountain lake you know and those Lakes are often snow melt and you know I think
it was in the spring maybe and I said it wasn't it you know you didn't really go in the lake did you and he said mildly
it was cold for 22 seconds so clearly he had timed it
um so we can practice with this deliberately also at times in order to challenge our system
so um you know when we endure we get the chance to make the all-important distinction between unpleasant feeling
and wanted to go away those are different
and we contact also I said I'm looking at her mind we contact our relationship
to powerlessness you know how do you relate to having no control over something
that's actually a big one to work with so then you know one fruit of this is
that we gain the confidence that we can handle certain things which is important how is it going to be in the end when
you die you know when you get very ill and your body is not able to move or function properly
there may be very unusual feelings of that being able to endure them is good I
don't know it might be painful or it might not but it will certainly be very bizarre out of your normal Zone the
feelings that come dying so being able to endure that can allow a more
clear-minded death and then the the sutas also ask us to
endure besides the gadflies and the cold and the heat is uh it says ill-spoken
unwelcome words and those I know can be very hard to endure it's another area where we don't
have a lot of control though people say what they do even if we live our life
trying to be kind we can't guarantee that we're not going to receive ill-spoken unwelcome words
and you know how do we can we endure those or do we react and defend
immediately I know that's not easy the texts say that one of the best resources
for handling unskillful speech coming at us is mindfulness of the body
it helps I've found to literally put attention in the feet and stay grounded
if you can remember and another good way to do it is to expand awareness to
include the whole body and even the space beyond the body um
I remember venerable analio among saying that he was once in a conversation with
another Monk who was very angry that inalio had done some scholarly work
defending women having the opportunity for full ordination there is some
conservatism among monks that say that that shouldn't that shouldn't be allowed and and this one came and was very angry
with him and analio said he just sat there while the other monk attacked him in his work and he just focused on the
space between them and around them and eventually you know he didn't react and
eventually the other monk finished his tirade and left what else was there to do and so he he just stayed present with
it so it is important there are times when we will need to endure
so then there's also though the text also says that we can sometimes let go of things by removing and you know what
is it that we are supposed to let go of by removing generally they are unwholesome line
States so mind States agreed hatred and delusion we don't remove them
immediately though generally we would do it once we have investigated them enough
um there's a reason that this method comes fairly late in sequence I think we want to go with removing only when we're
very clear on what we're doing and how and why so basically we have to be careful not to mix a removal with
aversion which means it can be kind of an advanced practice it might be that we
have to endure for a little while and so that we have Equanimity and care when we
do remove um and also we'll see actually that removing can have a very gentle flavor
as well as a stronger one so we can maybe look at some examples
sometimes we do need to remove actively when the mind is in a really bad State like we would get a snake out of our
house but of course we'd do that carefully right um so if we can see and we're seeing was
the first method if we can see that the mind is repeatedly getting caught in harmful thought patterns you know maybe
we would try just having mindfulness at first and see if that works you know just noting anger or irritation but if
that doesn't work then there are other things we can try we can try redirecting our attention or we can try reflecting
on the difficulties that come when we have a wholesome line state
um or we could just kind of withdraw our attention from it that's kind of like the avoiding just waiting for the energy
to dissipate by being careful not to feed it it's a little bit like what an Alia was doing
and if all of that doesn't work then we have set ourselves up well to be able to
firmly say to our mind know more of this no more of this and if we do that if we
do it too soon I think there can be a version but when it rises up out of genuine strength then it's compassionate
another teacher has said that we remove unskillful thoughts this way by saying
in our mind you will not get one more minute of my life
I mean do you have thoughts where they've had too many minutes of your life your life is valuable
why wasted thinking these terrible thoughts that are only harming you so it's like setting a boundary
you will not get one more minute of my life and there are other times you know when
removing can be so gentle we might get free of something by just applying
wisdom quite directly such that it dissolves there's a suta that
distinguishes it distinguishes using mindfulness to let something go and using wisdom
it actually sets up a series of conditions so first it says that maybe a
person just tolerates various unskillable mind States hardly even knowing that they're unskillful and it
says that that person is completely fettered I think about maybe how my mind was before I even knew the Dharma all
kinds of stuff ran through my mind and I never thought about whether it was skillful or unskillful or it was harming
me you're going to harm others I mean maybe I did sometimes but not a lot
so there's a lot of fettering there and then um there can also be the case where we
see with mindfulness and we see what's going on and we gradually are able to release through our practice of daily
life mindfulness that person is said to be on the path you know still fettered
like many of us but moving toward Awakening because there's mindfulness of
what's going on in the mind and then according to this suta there is a person who divests oneself from
unwholesomeness it's like it arises and it's just immediately quenched or maybe it's you know eventually even
doesn't arise so you know we're not always in such a clear wise state but it is good to know
that abandoning by removing can be just straightforward and gentle it doesn't
have to be some kind of a battle that's the the message I want to impart so
so we have Letting Go by enduring and letting go by removing and again there's
a matter of seeing which one is going to be effective we have to know something about what it means for something to let
go what does that feel like and then we can be then we can know whether a given method has worked and if if so great and
if not we might know have a sense of which one to try next maybe for those really sticky knots
we're going to need more than one actually probably we will so
we continue exploring this Art of Letting Go
and we'll continue with that tomorrow have a beautiful day or evening