say hello everyone and warm greetings from Redwood City
from the inside Meditation Center I've been away for a week and it's nice
to be back and nice to be back here in this early morning somewhat early
morning way of starting the day
so um thank you for being here
so um when I first came to Buddhism I studied
Zen when I was instructed to sit in meditation
one of the peculiar instructions that I didn't understand at that time
was to put myself in the meditation posture and
and be with the breathing and to put my attention in my hands
the hands were together in a kind of mudra kind of one hand Atop The Other in front of my belly
and instead of putting my my attention or my mind in my hands
and sometimes in Zen had told me to put my mind in my belly in the Hara in
Japanese the spot about two inches below the belly button maybe about an inch in
from the skin so kind of in a similar place the hands were kind of right in front of that
place and this idea of putting my mind there it was a little bit different than
putting the attention there maybe and uh but over the years I've learned
that we have many capacities for perception awareness sensing knowing
and that uh it's a little bit of choice of the mind
not necessarily your choice if you're not conscious of it of where the where
where we identify as the locus the center of our attention where is attention you
know up in the head and are we looking down on the breathing or the attention in the breath is it par
is awareness part and parcel of the experience of breathing not separate from it
is the awareness um somehow disembodied kind of above and
behind us watching the whole experience is it in our hands is it in our belly
is it in the Torso and in fact it's a little bit optional
where we feel the locus the center of gravity of where of awareness of
attention where where we um
we identify in a sense the center of attention and that itself is sometimes what we
follow along with where we identify ourselves Me Myself and I so it's a little bit optional we can
move around and kind of let different things be the center because it's a
little bit of a choice of the mind to to kind of prioritize rest in that
particular part of the body for where awareness is aware
so I don't know if this makes sense to you it didn't make sense to me when I first started sitting but I think it's a
very helpful idea and and we'll talk about more more about this later
so for now to assume a meditation posture
and gently close your eyes
and spend the first minute or so of your meditation relaxing your body as much as you can
while letting the body be have a certain quality of alertness
being alert
relaxing in the shoulders
bring your attention to your arms and your elbows and your hands
can you move or reposition them so they're more relaxed
so the elbows are not pressed in towards the body but are hanging loosely
and to relax in the belly
a soft belly
and when you're and then to kind of sit quietly for a few moments
with the rhythm of breathing
as you exhale to relax a thinking mind
quiet you're thinking
and then for a few minutes
heighten your awareness of the body's experience or breathing
really let your awareness
kind of like it dials in
tunes into the breathing more fully
and as you're aware of your breathing where's the place from which you are
aware
is it in the head if it is in the head where
around the eyes behind the forehead
between the ears is it the upper hip half of the head or
the lower half of the head
and if we locate a place just a minute here so to where else
might it be might it be somewhere in the neck in the voice box
right the place from which you know and are aware is in the chest maybe in the heart
the solar plexus area
is the location for awareness of breathing
in the breathing itself
there's no sense of knowing or being aware in some other place than the breathing
is the place of awareness might it be in the belly
in whatever place if there is a place where is the place from which you're aware
what does that place feel like were the sensations
that are present there
may be a Sensations associated with being aware
being aware of the place from which you're aware
maybe breathing with that place
breathing through it having the experience of breathing
be received into the location
from which where you're aware
wherever your location is from which you're aware
imagine that it's an easy chair that you can relax back into
settling back into that soft receptive chair
so that your awareness
relaxes softens
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to switch the location from which where you're aware
to your heart as if there's a chair an easy chair in
your heart and you can settle into that chair
that the heart is a place to relax it's home
safe
and to imagine that you look out upon the world from the heart
you look out upon the world from a place of safety in
nothing's required of you not for the time being nothing is
challenging you or dangerous for you the heart is at ease
looking out upon the world
with eyes of kindness and care
and if it
you if you find that there is some kindness some care some love compassion
in your heart that you can spread across the globe
spread wide and far
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and they the way in which we look upon others and on the world
may they may that gaze that look be soft kind and compassionate
may we spread our kindness in the way in which we gaze upon the
world
[Music]
yeah so warm greetings on this Monday morning
as we begin another week of this 7 A.M
Community practicing together and a new week of teachings
in my mind in my heart the teachings for today are going to
um kind of continue from two weeks ago when I talked about compassion
the different elements of compassion and I want to have I have more and I
want to teach about compassion but there's an interlude for this week because the medium
for compassion is our awareness our attention to be
aware of the suffering of others Beware of the suffering of oneself is the medium is the the means by which
compassion can arise and so I want to spend this these five
days looking at different ways to be aware
because if we have a greater repertoire of how to be aware then when we're present with suffering
our own Suffering The Suffering of others we have different options about
how to be aware of it how to connect to it how to know it if we only have one option of how to be
aware and we never thought about those different ways of being aware
then it's very easy to sink into suffering to somehow be entangled with
it or it's easy to be impacted impacted and
impacted by it in ways that are even detrimental they're not helpful
for this kind of sweetness and Clarity of compassion itself
so to learn that there are different ways of using awareness and that we can shift modes of awareness
at different times is very helpful so if one mode of being with suffering
is not really working for you you find yourself sinking into it or
excess will be impacted by it someone else's suffering becomes your own suffering in a way that actually is
quite painful to feel and look overwhelming then you might want to question the the
way in which you're aware of that suffering and see if you if you have a repertoire of different ways of being
aware you can switch it to another way and um
and so what I like to do for this week is to maybe discuss five different ways
of being aware and a lot of this has to do with locations from which we're aware
um and um so we know we'll go find our way through it this week
and but this first this principle that I just said that when any situation is
difficult for us I've been trying to find our way with the situation
one of the variables that we can consider is the way in which you're
aware of this challenge and often that's not questioned often we
the challenges are we absorb the challenge and absorbed in the difficulty and we're kind of kind of absorbed kind
of entangled or caught in it or concerned with it so strongly that we
don't step back and say well is the way that I'm concerned the way that I'm attending to it is that the best choice
is there other ways of attending to it that might be more useful at this time
just that question itself changes the ecosystem it's like having
an ecosystem and you introduce a new element to it then the whole thing morphs and changes accordingly
so to introduce this question is there another way of being aware of this challenge
is Beginnings it's the beginning of creating a new ecosystem and one that's probably is
much more going to be much more useful and healthy and for one half for because when you
ask the question is there a different way now to be aware of this just that is beginning to loosen the
attachments the clinging that grasping that pushing the tightening contraction around the challenge you know no I got
to take care of this and that gives space then to be able to kind of see it more clearly and relax a
little bit around it so um
one of the ways um that uh some you know and and this is
very different for different people how they're aware where they're aware from the first mode of of how they're present
with awareness so um so as you hear these teachings this week
um just be aware that uh uh it's not like um
your way is wrong but rather to discover what your way is
and then to have that learn the capacity to fluidly relaxedly change that mode
when it's useful to do so so
um so for today I just want to talk about being aware from the head
there are some people who live from the neck up and everything is taking you
know the center of locus the center of gravity the center of everything is in
their head and um and usually that means that they
spend a lot of time thinking there's a lot of thoughts and ideas and that the way that they're aware is
or the place that they're where from is the thinking itself
so maybe it doesn't have exactly a location that thoughts or maybe they do but uh it's so strong the thinking that
that's that's where awareness is kind of that's what you know that's where we think awareness is that's who we think
we are I think therefore I am and identification with thoughts are so
strong that for many of us we are our thoughts
and so to be aware through the lens of thinking from the lens of of um of thought or the
place in which thinking happens is almost like saying I am that place
where thinking is happening that's the locus the center the the Nexus of who I
am and um and so to be aware that oh mostly my awareness is in my head
and might not be through thinking for some people it's through the medium of their eyes and we're not the eyes
literally but the mind's eye but somehow they kind of live close to their physical eyes the very I I focused uh
people and so not necessarily thinking Focus but I focused so even with the
eyes closed their physical eyes are engaged like their look almost like they're looking at the breathing with
her eyes and that looking that the eye Century kind of way of being a attention that's
the place in which we're aware and um and um
and some people where they're aware from is um is maybe related to thinking is the
place where the voice is projected or the speaker system where
the speaker is for the voice of the mouth is for The Voice or where the projector is for the images
that we're seeing maybe almost like a screen in front of us or we're aware through through those
images on the screen and that's part and parcel of experiencing being aware is having
images that kind of come up and somehow inform us what's happening or relate to
what's happening or something and so the awareness is partly rooted in
these images in The Voice in the seeing
sometimes there's tension in the head someplace and and that tension is uh the
place where we kind of would identify with that's who where I am that's the locus of me or that's the locus from
which I'm aware it's not wrong to be aware from the head
often in our Buddhist circles it's like somehow they're not supposed to do that or something not wrong it's one mode of
being aware one place from which to be aware and all these places have a time and
season there's no one way which is the wrong way one but if one way is the only way we
have then we're quite Limited so first we want to become aware of you
know how are we aware and if you're aware if your center of awareness the
place you're aware from if um is in your head then
see if you can find ways to soften that place like imagine that you feel the
place where you're aware from it might be the place where you're thinking from or you're seeing from
and see if you can kind of like settle back into it like it's in a nice relaxed
easy chair and then you might be able to benefit more from that way of being aware than
if you're you know tense in that kind of spot if being aware from the head is not what
you do try it anyway see if you can
and partly partly what's been a can be beneficial being aware from the head is
that sometimes it does remove us from our experience it kind of pulls us
away like say there's a emotional pain in the sometimes in the Torso by being
aware in the head there's a kind of distance from it and some people will automatically
assume distance is wrong but distance actually is one of the modes of being aware which has its benefits and I'll
talk more about that tomorrow but uh for now I just want to see see if
you can a little bit uh get to know uh your mode of awareness where you're
aware from and if there is no place is it in your little toe
is it in your heel is it near Pinky
are you mostly aware you know as it turns out if you ask those questions it actually begins coming in closer it's
yes it's in the whole torso and then is it if it's a whole torso is
it uh in your back is it uh by your tailbone or is it in
the back of your neck some people when you ask those questions say oh no it's mostly in the front of the Torso
people who very quickly will say how much there's no place location for me to be aware
if they start coming from the from the most wide out and starts working their way in they
kind of uh by a process of elimination find that the oh I'm mostly aware in the
chest in the middle of the chest or mostly your way here this is a location
and when you find that location or close to it relax the attention wherever it might be
so um so this will be a beginning and um I'm
very aware that this might be seem a little esoteric for some of you so if
that's the case this this week of awareness and where it's located I ask
your patients with it and um and uh and I don't think it'll be harmful and
and hopefully they'll you'll benefit a little bit from it that when we turn our
attention to compassion again that you'll see the Richer options of how to
be compassionate so thank you and I look forward to being
here tomorrow