welcome welcome nice to see you all
how is the volume it feels a tiny bit loud for me does it seem loud to you guys that is this okay I have to talk
non-stop for an order for this to can I get a thumbs up yes okay thanks
so sometimes it's helpful to think about or reflect
and what is our hearts deepest longing
recognize it right that we have limited time on to be alive and limited resources and
limited energy is it are we spending it in a way that's
meaningful for us that's going to help to go in the direction that we would like
what are our deepest aspirations
maybe we'll just take a moment just to think about them
it's useful to reflect on this taking some time and what are you most inspired by
what makes your heart sing
when you think about it or maybe it isn't clear right now that's
perfectly fine but when we kind of like align with an
aspiration or we remind ourselves or touch into what's really important for
us there can be a feeling of lightness or
some ears or maybe some openness or relief
in contrast to this feeling like oh I should do this that's kind of like the
opposite of this openness the sense of should kind of has this sense of contraction or restriction or limitation
something like this but this kind of reflection it's good to
do regularly otherwise right or life just passes Us by
while we're taking care of all the things that need taken care of
sometimes it's easy to get disconnected from what's most important
and maybe to feel motivated like how can we even if our so much of our time and
energy has to go in one particular direction maybe there's a way we can weave into our life something that
supports our aspirations
with regard to our spiritual life we might think like aspiration that sounds too much like goal and I
don't think I want to have any goals with my spiritual life I just want to just have a spiritual life I don't have
any goals there might be some people who have that idea but
then we might be able to say well maybe you have a goal to
be mindful and practice mindfulness regularly or have a meditation practice regularly or maybe you have a goal to
listen to drama talks or read Derma books or something like this
or to practice with the Eightfold Path or with the precepts or so we might consider those kind of goals and then we
might ask well are there some goals that are okay to have but not other goals
or do we dare to Aspire for more and more freedom
do we dare to Aspire for more and more peace and ease
or do we somehow feel like that's not available for us
maybe you have this wish in your heart for some happiness
maybe you have a wish for happiness not only for yourself but for others
maybe you have an aspiration of service supporting others
in whatever way makes sense for you and in whatever way you're
life supports that
there's no right answer of course not it doesn't have to be one particular way
in all of us I'm sure have our own versions of this or maybe own flavors of it
so it's this and even if we have a similar aspiration the way it gets expressed will be different with
everybody I mean to say something like service is such a big General word but that should be for
different for everybody or greater Freedom you know maybe that looks different for everybody
so the Buddha recognized that uh there's aspirations
of course he's promoting the aspiration to lebana is teaching suffering and the end of
suffering so he's highlighting the ending of suffering but he give gave some talks on what how
to support our aspirations that include something in the list right are you
surprised is a list that are maybe not the usual list of things that we hear some of them are the
same but there are some things that are a little bit different and I appreciate in thisupta
the Buddhist starts by saying that just in the same way that a child of a
monarch has this aspiration to be the monarch
in the same way a practitioner has aspiration to find Freedom
kind of like this because when we think of the children of monarchs everybody's just assuming that they're gonna next
gonna take the throne I was just kind of think assume well that's of course what's going to happen and this is
the direction their life is going to go and maybe their whole life has been
around preparing for that to take the throne wear the crown whatever
it might be so I kind of like the idea is like as a similes that just in the same way
practitioners will not find Freedom like maybe their whole life is going this
direction or getting prepared for that or there's this way we can just assume yeah that's the direction we're going
in the same way that the children of the monarchs assume that they're gonna take the
monarchy at some time so what are these qualities that the Buddha less
the one is confidence confidence that the aspiration is even
possible I'm a little bit inspired to find out
Buddha's story of his story of um becoming a weekend
some of you may know this story and part of it is that he had some meditation teachers and with those
teachers he had some significant meditative attainments that today we would kind of call these meditative
attainments and he became just as Adept as his teachers
and his teachers were you know the most senior in their tradition
where you know they were their own tradition they were like the equivalent of the Buddha but uh
um you know they were the leaders of their own religious tradition let me say that and the Buddha he had the same
proficiency that they did and yet he felt like oh there's something more even
though there wasn't anybody else who was saying there was something more he had this sense he had this confidence that
oh yeah there's something more there's more freedom available so after the first teacher he went to a
second teacher had even higher meditative attainments and yet he still had this idea there's still Freedom
available there's a little bit of suffering here I can feel it I I believe there's an ending of
suffering so maybe we don't have that same kind of confidence that the Buddha did but just
pointing to tuning into or becoming aligned with the
sense that we feel like oh yeah there's there can be more freedom can't be more happiness more peace more ease whatever
word you want to use whatever inspires you whatever your aspiration is
Okay so in the classic teachings they will say kind of like confidence in The Awakening
of the Buddha or confidence that the Buddha is awakened you know that this is possible that people do get enlightened
but it's not only confidence that Enlightenment exists or whatever your aspiration might be
it's also so important that we have confidence that we can do it right otherwise that
just seems will be dismissive and not really apply ourselves if we have this idea yeah that'd be nice but that's for
other people it's not for me yeah that'd be great but I can't do it
that's a different uh feeling right of this confidence that the Buddha hand
and so I'm just going to say a few words here about this inner critic I kind of I
bring this up often just with uh and practice discussions with people I I
know it comes up and it certainly has come up a lot for me in my life this idea this maybe this constellation
of emotions or thoughts inside of us that it's kind of like belittling us or
making us think that we're inadequate in some way or making us feel like we just
aren't capable or a way that it's blaming ourselves for everything or
maybe just this voice of negativity or often it has this quality of harshness
or maybe it's just a quiet soft you'll never make it that kind of
feeling right so when this is kind of this
constellation of thoughts and emotions and when it's up and running there's this feeling that of this kind of should
like I should do this I should have done that
I should stop doing this you know this a bunch of this this should
so when there's a sense of should there's kind of this also is like really heavy and I'm maybe gonna have this
oppressive feeling which is the opposite of aligning with our aspirations which has this
this uh brightness and openness and ease
[Applause] so there's this way in which having this set of should is maybe the suppression
or maybe I could use the word pressure that has this lot of effects on us but
one of his one of it is that it not only does it squeeze the Joy or
happiness or ease out of practice but it also blocks our capacity to ask deep
questions when we have this inner critic that's really loud and authoritative then
there's a way in which we don't even dare to ask what our higher aspirations are
maybe for fear that we won't get achieve it or maybe for this feeling like well
who am I to even Aspire for something beautiful for my life
who am I to even think that I can do that
so this this ability to us these questions in some ways we might even say kind of get strangled
with the pressure of this inner critic senior critic isn't true but we believe
it's true it's it's very persuasive very like authoritative
but what are some ways that we might work with this
maybe I'll say that um for quite some time I taught about the
inner critic in the context of what a happy hour was which I did for a number of years on Tuesdays and Thursdays so in
the rather than giving a whole talk on this on the inner critical point to just a
few things but there is a playlist on Audio Dharma about working with
it so what's the one thing we can do with the standard critic
practice with kindness kindness wherever it's easiest
because sometimes when their inner critic is up and running it's like that's a really tall order to say oh I'm
gonna have you know love myself or you know something like that that's you know I'm not really work so well
but instead to do some loving kindness practice wherever it's easiest wherever it's
easiest puppies kittens babies somebody that's in your life that's just
really your heart melts and when you think about them or maybe somebody who
was in your life a coach or a mentor somebody a teacher who really helped you
and supported you in your life maybe they're still in your life
and to bring them to mind and allow that to soften your heart and maybe do some regular loving
kindness practice there's just this softening of the heart that kind of like removes some of the
harshness of this inner critic and kind of like shift the mood of our heart I'll
say maybe is one one way to work with it another way is
allowing it to be there but maybe not buying into it so giving it some space
like oh yeah there you are I recognize you okay come along I'm not gonna listen to
you but you might as well come along but you can you know just keep on talking but while you're talking I'm gonna go do
this you know so we're honoring and respecting that part of our experience
but we're taking away its Authority taking away its ability to boss us
around or maybe we can start to learn how to
question this inner critic like maybe do some dialogue with it something like really is that so that
I'll never do it well there was a time that I thought I couldn't do X but I actually did it
doesn't mean that we haven't had failures but it also our whole life has not been one constant failure there are
some things that we have done we've gone to school
we've got dressed in the morning some mornings we don't get dressed
that's okay but we don't want to sit a really high bar just notice that uh
we're not complete failures right
so this is the first thing is to have confidence and is helpful for aspirations and I wanted to address a
little bit about that about the inner critic because sometimes we don't even dare to have dreams we don't even dare
to Aspire they're kind of getting undermined by this inner critic
but a second quality I change the order of these you know and the Buddhism
there's all these lists and they're usually in a particular order I change the order of these but so what I'm calling is the second isn't
the second in the order it doesn't really matter so much being honest and open
the word sometimes gets translated as sincere so this is not the usual that don't tell
a lie but instead it's to be open
with others and yourself and in particular it talks about with
wise friends that you have so to have you know somebody
or some yeah maybe somebody or some group
in which you can share a little bit about your what's happening with you or maybe even
some uh about your practice for those of you who have participated
in girls or mine year-long courses Gail's just finished up deepening
meditation program I'm just finishing up seven factors seven shining jewels
we have people in breakout groups and we have them talk and part of it is just
that to get that opportunity to share you don't have to tell your deepest darkest Secrets but there's something
about sharing a little bit about how practices with others that kind of like normalizes what's happening and there's
wisdom in other people you might learn like oh I never thought of it that way or oh that's a great idea I'm gonna try
that so there's a way we can borrow the wisdom from other people and not feel so
isolated sometimes having a meditation practice is not the usual things that
people do and it can be really great to connect with other people
so to have this openness with others and in the in the classic teachings it talks
about with the teacher and other spiritual companions
especially in these days when we have social media and there's a lot of you know we have
curated uh I don't know like existences online I
don't know if everybody does this but right you know it gets posted on social media is like the best version so often
so there's this kind of pressure even if it weren't social media but to only share what's the absolute picture
perfect but what's being pointed to here is to
step away from that I'm like here's what actually happens in my practice
and to recognize that all of us have the hindrances nobody is exempt from that
all of us have struggles all of us have difficulties in with getting to the
cushion or whatever it might be and it can be really great to be able to connect so whether you have good
spiritual friends or you come here on some Sundays there's
discussions after on Sundays on Wednesdays on here there's informal
lunch people can talk and then these courses that get taught these year-long courses always have every meeting and
aspect of just people getting together on Thursday nights uh Tanya Weiser her
teachings also have people get together talk to each other so just this recognition that it's a really nice to
have somebody to talk with being honest and open
but there's another element to this idea of being honest and open
I have to be honest with ourselves and we might even say that this what
this that is what this practice is all about is really just
seeing what's really happening with ourselves and sometimes we don't know we're disconnected from ourselves we're
busy we have lots of things to do or we're distracted or maybe it's painful
and we're trying not to be with our experience
I am not saying jump into the most painful experience by no means am I
saying that but this practice so much is about the truth of what's really
happening with us and we might even say that without a commitment to truth there isn't really a
path of practice because this practice is so much about just being with what's actually
happening not our ideas or not what we wish were
happening or what did happen but to actually see the truth of the moment the
reality of the moment and you might even go as so far as to
say that the Dharma is all about truth
and so this being honest and open is one way to have this way in which we can
express the Dharma and practice with the Dharma [Applause] and so it's not only that it's just
enormously helpful to learn what are our patterns what are our habits what are
our sensitive points where we get triggered or derailed or get confused or were we
shut down just to learn that about ourselves so we can work with it skillfully
instead we just end up spending our lives trying to avoid those areas and then our life gets smaller and smaller
we want our lives to be big and rich and full of whenever we want it to be full of
so with also with this getting to know ourselves and our habits and patterns
then maybe we can have a sense of how to move towards our aspiration
maybe we're the type of person who just wants to feel into where is their more
spaciousness and ease and I'm going to follow that or maybe it's a person you feel like you
know what I like to follow rules and I'm going to learn like what are the
Buddhist teachings and I'm really going to stick to that and use that to inspire me or me or maybe you're somebody who's
like well you know what I I'm gonna sketch a plan whatever it might be just learning what
motivates us and what derails US is enormously helpful I'm not telling you
anything you don't already know but I I like to think that the Buddha
recognized that that each of us need to learn for ourselves how we can apply
these teachings to so that we can reach our aspirations so that our life can unfold in the way that we want it to
unfold so a third item on this list is having
like applying energy applying effort
makes sense it's one thing to think and dream it's one thing to get to know oneself and
certainly that is part of the path of practice but this recognition that effort will be required
for these aspirations and so we might say something like
perseverance or forbearance or steadfastness I don't know when I hear those words I
feel like uh you know it just feels like you know so much hard work
but it I mean it is effort right the Buddha wasn't able to just go Shazam everybody's awake
right he's was pointed the way but he couldn't like help everybody to become
awakened not to deny that apparently there were some people that heard the Buddha's
teachings and became a weekend the rest of us we have to apply some
energy some effort and part of the practice is to learn well where should I apply my
energy and not only that how much energy should I apply
and I like this assembly of a Goldsmith I've said this a number of times but um
I'll just I'd like to share it here because sometimes when we hear this like
we have to play energy it feels like it has to be full on effort pressure all
the time but this simile of the Goldsmith points
out that's actually not the case it goes like this
suppose a Goldsmith would prepare a hot furnace heat up a receptacle
take some gold and using tongs put it into the receptacle
and then the receptacle would go into the furnace and then from time to time the Goldsmith would blow on the gold
hotter from time to time the Goldsmith would sprinkle water on it cool it down
and from time to time the Goldsmith would just look on as the gold was Heating
if the Goldsmith were to only blow on it the gold would just burn up if we just only sprinkle water on it and
it would just get cooler and not be malleable and if the Goldsmith were just to look on then the gold would not reach
the right consistency but if the gold smith if the Goldsmith
would would from time to time blow on it sprinkle on it and just look on then the
gold would become purified bright unblemished rid of imperfection
malleable wieldy steady and attained to
imperturbability all those qualities is how the Buddha
described his mind right before Awakening so I appreciate sometimes a little more
effort and sometimes a little bit less effort and sometimes just looking on
the fourth quality is this something that we off also don't see so often is
this recognition about the importance of Health like our physical health
and the suit is it's stated as being seldom ill so you don't have to have
perfect health of course but I'd like to open this up to
seldom ill rather to just being able to work with whatever our health is
like old age and sickness is going to happen to all of us and it doesn't mean
that we can't practice and the Buddha knew this so it doesn't have to be perfect health but maybe I'd like to
kind of expand this to have balance in our life between some of these things
that maybe are you already know do we have are we so busy that we don't
make time for our spiritual life for meditation or whatever it might be
do we have work and play do we have play in our lives
do we have time with others and time alone
and of course do we have exercise and rest just some of these things like we need
to have a balance in our life in order for us to reach our aspirations to have the best life that we can
so I appreciate that the Buddha is pointing to health and I'm imagining that life you know thousands of years
ago was very different than how it is now and I imagine living Closer To Nature as
they did and you know their life of course changed with the seasons that
maybe they had a little more balance than we do here where we're living in buildings and we
can be completely removed from what's the seasons and what's happening outside we have all
these nice lights right it doesn't matter that it's dark outside and then the last quality to help
support aspirations is having wisdom about impermanence
and I'm interpreting this two ways one is having wisdom about impermanence
reminds us that you know we're going to die just like
everything else does you know there's things end things that have the nature to be born have the
nature to die so sometimes we might think like oh I'll get to this aspiration stuff tomorrow
I'm going to do it later as soon as something or rather is done
Perfectly Natural we we do this so often
there's an encouragement to maybe is there a way that you can do
something that moves your life in the direction that you want it to go maybe towards some Big Dreams that you have
also this idea of impermanence if we start to see that well not only us of
course but everything is impermanent there's nothing that is permanent nothing that we can really hold on to to
be a source of lasting happiness nothing is always gonna consistently be a source
of Happiness forever that just doesn't exist we keep on looking for it
and we keep on holding on to what is bringing some pleasure or what is
bringing a certain amount of happiness but there will be a time in which it doesn't
bring the amount of happiness that we wish of course we all know this even though
the advertising companies want us to forget it and we do forget it
there's nothing I don't want to beat us up for forgetting it but this insight into impermanence when we really see it
in a deep way then we stop asking all our experiences
to be sources of lasting happiness and instead there's this kind of flooding go there's a opening a
softening and we're letting our experiences to just be our experiences
instead of demanding that they satisfy us in some particular way and it turns out that that is enormously
satisfying just to let experiences be experiences
rather than saying this is mine it's only happening to me or getting clinging around it in so many
different ways or assigning meaning to it or there because I had this experience it means this about me you're
letting all that go instead just it experiencing it that means allows some letting go
and that is the ending of suffering which supports all aspirations no matter
what your aspiration is and in suffering allows that one to
happen well that was anything to happen so these five qualities to help us with
a our aspirations in the same way that the children of monarchs aspire to become
the monarch and there's these five qualities of confidence
being honest and open having enough energy or applying effort I'll say
um having some health and well-being I'm expanding that to say balance in our
life and seen in permanence having some wisdom impermanence can motivate us as
well as maybe help us to not cling which helps us to have less and less suffering
and more and more freedom so maybe with that I'll open it up and
see if there's any questions or comments
there doesn't have to be I don't want anybody feel pressured but yeah so I have a question here
um I get a little confused between the aspirations and the experience because
sometimes my aspirations are for experience so
I don't know where the where the line is drawn what
what is an aspiration you know what oh I see you know
okay I think I'm defining experience a little bit different than you are I think I'm saying experience like right
now I'm experiencing that there's pressure against my backside while I'm sitting here I'm saying like that's an
experience so absolute mundane just what the body
is experiencing through its senses what it sees what it hears that what it feels
what it tastes what it smells that's kind of all I'm saying is an experience okay just
you know whatever just daily being alive things as opposed to some
the Disney Experience or you know something like that right okay does that
help that's helpful yes thank you thank you for the question that was good that was I love getting questions that help
me clarify things so thank you for asking that somebody else have a question Norman
yes it made me feel
I like the part from the suta that you talked about the Goldsmith
um both uh watching
the gold and blowing on it and sprinkling water
and the picture I got from the way you told it was that
um although skill was needed and and no doubt it took some effort
for the Goldsmith to develop that skill once he had the skill
um doing those things was just kind of methodical
and maybe didn't
seem like effort he needed the discipline he needed to put the time in
need to do the things but but uh it wasn't so hard
I see which makes I guess if you can just get your frame of mind about oh you know figuring out
what what the meditative process is and practicing enough to where he
develop the skill Maybe it doesn't seem hard I see
I was interpreting it a little bit different please tell yeah just that the
sensitivity to like okay how is the gold now what is needed now now is a little
bit more effort now is less effort and or backing off or and maybe or like
cooling down like if you feel agitated or something like that and sometimes it's just to do nothing just to abide
that's how I was interpreting it and then it's what you were saying a little
bit different than that I think yeah I was thinking about how you can get to a comfort level
with whatever you're doing in this case I think we're talking about meditation I see
so that no matter how much effort is required there's something at the same
time easy about it I see just like every joyful and joyful maybe
yeah just like everything we do it gets easier but I don't think we ever stop
having to feel into is a little bit more effort needed here it's a little bit
less here or should I can I just hang out here in this experience I think
we're always having to do that I would say that's part of the art of meditation is knowing this
it's like when do I need to apply a little bit more mindfulness or effort and when can I just
because no two meditations are exactly the same exactly
thank you thank you Bill any other questions or comments
okay okay so thank you for your kind attention and
I'm wishing you all a wonderful rest of your evening thank you