so for those of you who don't know I'm Diana Clark as Martha said there at the beginning and it's a delight to be here
with you all some of you may know that I teach on Monday nights so here I am on a Sunday
morning instead of a Monday night but today I'd like to share a little bit
about asuta my story specifically that's in a suit uh
maybe I'll start by saying Gil and I taught to study course for ended up
being almost two years it just ended and a theme that we kept on pointing
back to in so many different ways the theme was the importance of direct experience like what is happening right
now this moment as opposed to our ideas about it as
opposed to some philosophy as opposed to some mystical or metaphysical ideas just
this you know encouragement to come back what's actually happening In This Moment
and it was quite something to see just how this showed up in the sutas in so
many different ways and I would say that a big part of practice is learning to make this
distinction you might think well that's obvious I know what I'm thinking and I know when
I'm sensing but it turns out this can be even more and more subtle the way that
our Concepts our Notions our ideas our beliefs our views our little bit
different than what's actually happening in this moment
and of course we do this of course humans do this they have ideas and Views
and opinions of course they do we need them but there's so much a way in which we
are often living in our heads instead of being embodied
there's a way in that we are looking for the answers we're looking for ease we're
looking for Comfort we're looking for happiness with something that's out there and out there being something that's
going to happen in the future or in another setting or anywhere but here
right and out there of course only exists in our minds doesn't happen right here in the moment
if we're not looking for a happiness and well-being or end of suffering with
something out there then maybe it shows up as we're trying to figure something
out like everything is going to be okay as soon as I solve this problem or maybe there's that problem right have
you noticed it never ends right and of course we do this many of us in
our professional lives or in certain education we've been rewarded for this type of thinking and just solve the
problem the next problem the next problem the next problem and everything will be fine and it's such a radical idea in some
ways that this teaching is pointing to can we just be with actually with the
experience is here and then Phil I'm going to ask you can you put that volume just a little bit
higher I feel like I'm straining a little bit with my voice to make it just be a little bit louder
thank you so many of you will be familiar with
this suta that I'll be talking about it's the Bahia suta
and I'm going to kind of tell this story and then drop in some commentary as we go along
so The Suitor begins thus have I heard many of you know this is the common
beginning and maybe we could say once upon a time something like this
have I heard at one time the Buddha was staying near sovereignty in Jedis Grove and at the pindicus park I'll say that
so many sutas start this like where the Buddha is kind of giving a setting
now at that time Bahia at the bark cloth was residing by superica on the ocean
floor so Bahia he's in another place the Buddha's over here but he is over there
but he was honored respected revered venerated and esteemed and he received
robes alms food lodging and medicine and supplies for the sick so they're kind of giving but he is
credentials you know who is this person he was a spiritual leader a lot of people followed him thought that he was
a good leader and these list robes alms Foods lodgings and Medicine those are
the usual like the list of four things that spiritual leaders need and in
particular Buddhist leaders need they would say they need those four things and only those four things but that's
another story to talk about that but maybe we'll also say that Bahia is
not a Buddhist practitioner and partly we know this because he's wearing bark cloth
so just in the same way that we can tell the difference between who's a lay person who's a tariff automanastic who's
a Zen practitioner who's a Tibetan monastic by what they're wearing in the same way back at the time of the
Buddha we could also but he's so he's not a Buddhist
practitioner but he's this esteemed spiritual leader
and then coming back to the sutta when Bahia was alone in seclusion we can
understand this as when he was meditating when he was alone in seclusion this line
of thinking appeared to his awareness now of those who in this world are
awakened or have entered the path of Awakening
am I one he's wondering about his practice he's
wondering I think I'm awake and everybody else thinks I'm awakened but am I really
so I appreciate this very much right but yeah he's not complacent just because
everybody thinks oh yeah okay this guy is uh a leader he's a spiritual leader
of course he has it all figured out of course he's not trying to solve problems or not in the present moment or whatever
it might be like all these things are kind of get projected onto spiritual leaders but he
wasn't buying all of it and this question am I really awakened
and importantly he allowed this doubt about his practice to be there he didn't
immediately push it away he didn't immediately start thinking of other things you know distract himself
or he was had this willingness to stay present
to that experience of having this doubt which you can imagine was an uncomfortable experience
to say well everybody thinks I am but am I really
maybe this is different than having some
ideas of this imposter syndrome that sometimes or maybe it is the same as an
imposter syndrome that sometimes happens when people feel like well if people really knew me they wouldn't think what
they think about me maybe but he is doing this of course I don't really know
but his willingness to stay present and to stay open not to just collapse
and close down when there's this doubt about his practice shows up this willingness allows
another voice to enter so a continuation of the sutta
then a Deva who had once been a relative of bahia's compassionate and Desiring but he is
welfare and knowing with her own awareness the line of thinking that had Arisen and bahia's awareness so this
David knows what's going on in bahia's mind
but here that David went by here and on arrival said to him
you Bahia are neither awakened nor have you even
entered the path to Awakening you don't even have the practice whereby you would
become awakened or enter in the path of Awakening
you can imagine if he has like as well okay
so here we go we have a Deva meeting uh
that be here in this suta I don't know exactly what Divas are
yes there's uh different ways we might understand them some of them have this disembodied entities
one thing that I do know that in all the suit does teachings the Devas are just
like humans in this sense that they are not awakened either they're not completely they're not you know uh like
they're not like other Buddhas or something like this but something I appreciate very much and
this is by Douglas Phillips who's another Dharma teacher who teaches both in this tradition and in the Zen
tradition and the one way that he considers this Deva is by the
role that she plays rather than what exactly David is what's the function in the story of having a
Deva come and meet Bahia and Douglas Phillips has this idea that
the Deva is the embodiment of feminine wisdom of course I kind of like this being a
woman myself I like this but there's a way in which we can imagine sometimes uh there's this
masculine side of us that's trying to go get things make it happen
and then there's this we might say right this is a gross generalization of course right gross generalization and not
accurate but it's a way we might think about what the role of Davis is that
then there's also kind of this feminine wisdom that's like wait is that the only
thing that there is is this going and getting things and she like challenges but here with
this brutal honesty right this is kind of painful like she's just cuts to the chase nope you're not awakened and
you're not even gonna get awakened so telling Bahia that despite his years
of practice and despite he has all these admiring students he's not even a beginner on the path
another way we might think of this idea of the feminine wisdom is that there's
sometimes making this distinction between masculine or feminine no matter which gender we are that there sometimes
are aspects of ourselves that we're cutting off a little bit that we're ignoring not paying attention to
we can just drop this idea of feminine or masculine there's just often parts of us that we are
trying to avoid that we're trying to you know pretend
aren't there and maybe even secretly wish that they'll go away so this is when Douglas Phillips is one
way that he's interpreting this Deva but no matter how we think about it we might
notice that maybe doubt has it risen in your
practice too maybe you've had some ideas like am I
doing this right everybody else seems like they're awakened or on the brink of awakenment
and I'm here struggling with uh being lost in thoughts or whatever it is that
we might be struggling with at the moment
so we might have doubt about our capacities we might have doubts about the teachings
what's this idea of Divas might have doubt about the teacher do they really know what they're talking
about does she really know what she's talking about
or maybe we've had expectations about you know the results of this practice we
had this idea okay I'm just going to learn this meditation practice is everything is going to be easier my life
is going to be better and maybe it hasn't turned out exactly the way that you were hoping or wanted it to
be so maybe in some ways we're kind of like Bahia
but there's something here that what do we do when we have these doubts for our
practice or we have some indicators that we still have some work to do
there's two ways that we could do this that we could approach this when this doubt arises one is to go down
the path of resignation self-judgment despair
bitterness blaming disdain like there's
all kinds of words I could use here and sometimes we might travel some distance down this path before we
realize this actually is leading to more suffering not to less suffering this
isn't making things better to have this blaming or
collapsing or resignation
that's one way to go chances are all of us do some version of that and I know I
certainly did certainly earlier in my practice I didn't I would just get angry at the
teachers these poor teachers they didn't know what I was projecting onto them like I just thought I don't know I just
thought it was their fault somehow that this was so hard and I didn't know how to do it or I was getting lost or having
difficulties I thought if they would only be better teachers
now I'm one of those teachers right I can tell you we don't have all the answers for
everybody right we have to find our own way of course we do of course we do
and that's the second path or that's the second response we could have when we have all this response when we discover
that there's some difficulties we could rather than the path of blaming
or self-judgment we could go down the path of practice
that is we could bring attention to our experience at that moment
this is what doubt feels like this is what
blaming feels like this is what despair feels like
this is what feeling confused and angry and not even sure I want to do this
practice anymore feels like it feels like this and it's uncomfortable
so there's a way in which we can just bring our practice to our experience which to be sure might be the precise
thing we don't want to do but this is what's been asked of us not
to be somebody different not to have different experiences but to be with what's arising
as best we can as best we can with whatever's arising
so if we do have some doubts about our not only our experience or about the teachings or the teachers what can we do
we can be with our experience but bring it with a sense of curiosity do some
investigation talk to a teacher read Dharma books listen to Dharma talks talk to other
people there's so many ways in which we can maybe share our experience in a way
that feels comfortable for us that is a part of the practice
I would say for me I certainly would not have stayed with this practice if it weren't for some friends that I had
along this dormant path to share kind of the difficulties and
after Derma talks to talk about things like what I didn't get it did you get it you know this kind of thing or to just
like share ideas
and maybe the last thing I'll say about this that's this when we're having difficulties to engage with the practice
and to bring some curiosity about it maybe some of you will recognize this as investigation
many of you will know that investigation is a factor of Awakening like it's an
integral part of this path towards Awakening so it's not like something that we do on the side until we could
get back to the real practice it is the practice to bring some curiosity some
some just being present like what what's going on here to what's actually happening
okay to get back to the suta Bahia so the David just told him okay you're
not awakened and you're not even going to be awakened and I give but he a lot of credit
because here's what happens next without hesitation Bahia asked the Deva
but who in this world is awakened or has entered the path to Awakening
and she said Bahia in the northern city of saviti lives the
blessed one the Buddha a rightly self-awakened one he is truly
awakened and he teaches the Dharma that leads to Awakening
then but he had deeply chastened by the Deva left saparaka and traveled all the
way to where the Buddha was traveling with where the Buddha was staying put this in context this is thousands of
years ago and the distance between where Bahia was and where the Buddha was it's over a thousand miles
right he had to walk right maybe he had a chariot part of the way or some of the way I don't know but
a thousand miles is a long time right before there's roads or Pavements not even it doesn't exist yet you know this
is but here he undergoes this he has this commitment and he's willing to travel this distance
in my mind this this uh in adding this little detail into the story is pointing
to the the amount of commitment that Bahia has like he really wants to get
awakened so
I uh so but he doesn't defend or rationalize uh his but everybody else
thinks I'm awakened are you sure instead he says well if I don't have it where can I find it and then he goes to see if
he can find it so he travels to where the Buddha is and
getting back to the suta there but he have found a number of monks doing walking meditation outside
he went directly up to them and asked where venerable sirs is the Buddha stain
I must see him immediately he has this you know urgency
and then he was told that that Buddha had gone into the city for Ohm's round right of course the monastics every day
are getting alms so the Buddha wasn't there the place
where other monastics were he was in the town so but he had hurried immediately to the
city where he found the Buddha on alms round the Buddha was moving with great calm
his mind at peace tranquil and poised
this is how Buddhas are but he approached the Buddha threw
himself to the ground before him and with his head at the Buddha's feet he said teach me the Dharma blessed one
teach me the Dharma a holy one so that it will be for my long-term welfare and
happiness the Buddha replies this is not the time
by here we have entered the town for alms
so in an irreverent way in my mind he's saying if I'm on my lunch break I got
back later
I'm sure the Buddha would be a little bit different but you know that's kind of what happened right and recognizing
right that this time the Buddha only ate one time a day right so he needs to eat he needs to have a meal every day
but but he have pleaded with the Buddha a second time but holy one it is hard to
know for sure what dangers there may be for the Buddha's life or what dangers
there may be for my life please teach me the Derma o blessed one
so that I may be happy and free so be a Bahia say no no teach me now
because you know we don't know what's going to happen in the next moment
again the boo that but Buddha tried to put off Bahia and he's saying that it wasn't the right
time to teach because this is the arms around so but he is persistent
he has a certain amount of diligence but he also recognizes you know
impermanence this recognition that you know we're not guaranteed a next moment
none of us are not even Buddhas
even though we might be thinking okay I'll be doing this later later everything will be fine later I'll figure that out later I'll practice
later I'll be with my present moment experience but here has enough wisdom to recognize no
we don't actually know what's going to happen the next moment
so he's but he is respectful but tenacious
so the suit continues but he had pleaded his case a third time
and this is a common theme that we see in the suit does it's very interesting and I don't know the origins or the
story around this but common that if you ask a Buddha three times after the third time he will
relent just keep that in your back pocket the next time you meet a Buddha you can ask
them three times for something
Bahia pleaded his case a third time and this time the Buddha relented and said
well then Bahia you should train like this
in the scene will be merely the scene in the scene in
The Herd will be merely The Herd
in the sensed will be merely the sensed
in the cognized will be merely the cognized
so that Buddha is pointing to just being with the present moment experience
cognized we could have that stand for all whatever mental events are happening
in the mind sensed we could say there's a shorthand for any senses
in in addition to seeing and hearing
so when seeing or hearing is happening just to be only searing or hearing or
sensing or having mental events
we might say that uh a big part of practice is discovering
all the extra quote unquote things that we do besides just being with our
experience sometimes the experience is uncomfortable
and then as we spoke about earlier there might be this but I don't want it to be
here and then there's a whole story making that happens many of you might be familiar with this
idea of papancha right this mental proliferation that often starts with something's really Pleasant or
unpleasant then there's a way in which the Mind wants more and it starts to make a story about how it wants more I
want this or I don't want that or this reminds me of the time that you
know XYZ or this means something about me this often happens right and then
we're no longer with the present moment instead we're with what's off lost in
our stories so the Buddhas pointing to the
importance of just staying with the present moment experience
so then The Suitor continues it's more than just being with the present moment experience
the Buddha says and when you have trained in that way and the scene will be merely this scene and the herd will
be merely the herd and this sensed will be merely the sensed in the cognized
will be merely the cognized then be here there is no you
in connection with that and when there is no you in connection
with that there is no you there and when there is no you there there is
no you here nor Yonder nor in between
and just this is the end of suffering
upon hearing this brief explanation from the Buddha but he is mind was immediately freed from the defilements
from grasping and he became an arhand so you might wait and wonder like wait
what what happened there what the Buddha is pointing to is that
imputing a sense of self or having this self-concept
is extra and it's associated with suffering
so we might consider like the Buddha's description of when the scene is just
the scene or the hearing is just the hearing might be a description of what it means when there isn't this
self-concept that's getting overlaid on top of our experience
this idea of that there is a there's a
pattern of experience but there's no entanglement with it there's no papancha
that's happening after it as an example
you might have noticed that sometimes during meditation
sessions the most peaceful
the most delightful part of the whole meditation session
is when the bell rings at the end because at that moment like there's a
little huh and there's any doing that had was being done like there's a
meditator here that's trying to meditate or I'm meditating for that moment when
the bell rings that sense of oh I I quote unquote have to meditate gets put
down there's this kind of this relaxation this little bit of a just an opening
like oh okay now what's next I finished that but before there's the I finished
that that moment there's this this can be this peacefulness at the next meditation session notice what happens
at the moment when the bell rings there often is this opening this relaxation
this ease because at that time there's like the
mind isn't like doing anything you're not trying to meditate you're not trying to be a meditator nothing needs to
happen right at that moment and it might just be a flash or a flicker but just notice how at that time there's
this peacefulness or this delightfulness
but not only is there no longer this sense of somebody who's doing this
meditation but at that moment also the reactivity
and the measuring has been quieted or dropped
there's often such a subtle way in fact it might be subtle and so constant and
familiar we might not even recognize it but there's a way when often when we're
meditate or we're trying to meditate there's this subtle way in which there's
a I like this more than that
oh it was better yesterday what am I going to do tomorrow so I can
have this experience again or I don't like this as much as that right
there's this subtle measuring or comparing or a sense of me trying to
make things happen that gets tangled up with our experience
and what the Buddha is pointing to is that's extra we don't actually have to do that
that doesn't need to happen in fact that can get quieter and quieter and quieter
and usually this is how it happens is it's uh this x during the extra is on a
spectrum sometimes it's so obvious like I don't like this please make it go away I hate this when is that tank Bell gonna
ring and there can be a really strong sense of I want something in particular to
happen or there it could be a really quiet
just every now and then there's a thought that floats up like oh yeah this is nice I hope it stays like this wow
look at me I'm meditating there can be something like this it can be really really strong or really really
subtle it's not a binary on or off when this uh this extra is added
so this reactivity this measuring this entanglement
is caused we might say by the self-concept that there's this
idea of a self that because the self it wants things to be a particular way
wants things to be pleasant and comfortable
and it's this way of trying to bolster and protect this notion of this core or
this notion of an essence that underlies suffering
and whether that's suffering is just stress or uncomfortableness or just flat
out awfulness it's this self-concept at the beginning
at the this at the sense of this being at the core that is the source that's
fueling the reactivity it's fueling the suffering
so whatever is happening
and whatever moment and each moment whatever is happening
this can be the entry point of practice
learning to live fully in the life that we have
not in some imagined future or remembered past but living to just be
here oh yeah this is sensing feels like this
seeing seeing is like this hearing
hearing is like this whether you're in a meditative stage
whether you're in a meditation poster whether you're just washing the dishes or driving or whatever it might be whatever
your experiences this can be a doorway to practice
and just to be with the seeing or the hearing or
whatever mental experience is happening and freedom is possible Right There at
that moment we don't have to wait for some imagined
you know perfect conditions whatever is happening right there we can be with the
experience and maybe it's just a moment a flicker of a little bit more ease
but this is exactly how the practice unfolds is with a tasting or a
recognition of oh yeah there's a little bit more ease this direction when I'm just with the experience there's less
ease this direction when I'm adding on all the thoughts and ideas of how I
should be or how this experience should be
so being with our experience and the life we actually have
can be the doorway to Greater freedom thank you