so hello everyone and welcome to this uh
last talk on the aspirations connected to Compassion or the meditation connected to it
and um and uh more deeply than a
love and appreciation and Devotion to the value of compassion
is a love dedication Devotion to something that's deeper that I like to
believe that is the source of compassion within us and one maybe a simplistic way of saying
it is um because it can be so easily misunderstood or so easily
seen in a simplistic kind of surface way is that the source of
genuine healthy maybe even healing compassion
is being ourselves fully and and but in some deep way and another
way of saying this is um to maybe appreciate maybe the
profundity of that statement is that it's really uh uh letting go completely
of our normal senses of self and letting something deeper within us
move us something deeper within us um
the Dharma work through us and what is it that is so deep within us
that we can trust and allow it to unfold whatever is there let in the unfolding
and I one way of saying it in a maybe a less dharmic way is that um life knows
how to bring life forth life knows how to Let's the the fullness of it of life
flow forth in any kind of situation if we can let life flow in a healthy
harmonious a way so for ourselves
to trust that there's some deep movement towards Health not always physical
health because we're all die at some point but um but some deep uh
heart health some deep spiritual health some deep psychological health
that where um something wants to be born something
wants to be healed something wants to come to homeostasis something doesn't want to be
um stressed or in pain or in suffering and it's a movement to freedom from
suffering for sure and to trust this deeper thing that that doesn't require us even to
generate compassion to live within a sense of obligated you have to live a compassionate life
but rather there's this deeper Source that's what we want to live and from that comes compassion at the in
the situations that it's appropriate for so I offer that in the beginning of this meditation
that one of the values of lessening quieting discursive thoughts
being attuned to ourselves in a deeper way than discursive thinking
that there there can be um so there's there's something very
significant the Dharma our heart life that's kind of wants to come out in
a full harmonious balanced way and we might be far from that because of
all the challenges of our lives and and complexities of our psychology and all
kinds of things but it's waiting for us and so to drop below the discursive mind
and begin attuning yourselves or sensing something deeper is one of the possibilities of meditation
so with that beginning we'll begin with meditation
so to assume a a meditation posture
where there's respect for that posture a care it's a posture that we take
to allow ourselves to be better attuned better aware better more space for
something really to show itself from within
and a posture that focuses too much on relaxation
where we kind of give up kind of a certain degree of
Vitality of sitting upright or being clear or engaged or intentful
might not allow the full unfolding the opening of this deeper dimension
it's almost as if we want to be have the body have some degree of alertness
so that the very places that the body is alert and engaged is a place where
something can begin to flow and move and develop
and then to gently close your eyes
and take a few long slow deep breaths
and the fact that your body has been breathing for a lifetime now
mostly without your directing it to do so
means the breathing is connected to this deeper
care and health of movement of life within us
letting your breathing return to normal
and attuning yourself to the body breathing
relaxing into the body breathing
and if the focus on breathing means you immediately get engaged and work at it
or get tense or something
imagine that you're stepping back away from your breathing almost like you're observing the breathing
in your back rib cage or if you're observing your breathing from
behind so there's not interfering with
breathing but discovering how breathing breathe itself as itself
relaxing around the body breathing
relaxing around your breathing in wider circles so more and more of your body
is softening relaxing
into the breathing
allowing your thinking mind also to soften and relax
in the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and maybe seeing if you can switch an orientation
away from being interested or involved in discursive thought
it's an orientation towards a quieter deeper place within
a quieter attention a softer awareness breathing body of
what's here
there's a way of attention being soft and
attentive present to our body
to the quieter places within
that's making room for whatever is here
making room for whatever wants to unfold whatever wants to show itself
whatever wants to be born
and whatever is occurring
is okay if
the awareness is soft enough broad enough wide enough
to allow it to be there without picking it up participating
reacting to it
fighting it or holding on to it
without expectations or wants just allowing what's there to be itself
on a path to in a deep way allowing you to be
yourself
where life where our wholeness knows how to bring itself forth
and our role is the quiet non-discursive awareness
maybe with which we know and make space and to feel
a deeper Attunement
to the life flowing through us
can you find some Corners some place of awareness
of attention of mindfulness
that's quiet maybe quiet of
the discursive thinking mind peaceful
peaceful and not being for or against anything
open or spacious
making room for whatever is here
but not getting involved in it just knowing just aware
quiet peaceful spacious
is there a place is there some small
corner of your life where
you can sit breathing aware
in a way that allows makes room for trusts
life as it moves through us in whatever way it is
foreign
okay
and perhaps as we bring this meditation to a close
attuning yourself to your capacity
to be peaceful and may be that peacefulness is found
in the effort to be attuned
a peaceful Attunement a peaceful awareness
and maybe attuning yourself to it is partly helped by memory of
how some point in the past you've been peaceful
a deep State and maybe of calm or feeling of safety
ease peace
maybe a time when self-concerned self-preoccupation
self assertion self-doubt
was absent and is there some way that that
absence of some quality of stressful self self-concern
can you attune yourself to that as we sit here
quality of peacefulness
and can you imagine or can you feel
a capacity for care for love for compassion
that flows from that peace
that it's not something that we are choosing or generating or
doing but something that's part of
the flow of life that flows from being peaceful
and perhaps if you can imagine that maybe remember sometime when your life
with maybe you're close to that imagine that these following words
are part of that flow deep Attunement to peace and to
ourselves being ourselves in some deep peaceful way
May the people that I see and know and
hear about may they too be happy
may they too be peaceful
may they too be safe
may they too be free
may they too being happy and safe and free and peaceful
may they discover the gifts really being themselves where
the hearts movement free of discursive thought free of self-attachment
free of greed and hatred have a chance to
Revitalize enliven
heal and
give a profound meaning and belonging to their
to their life may all beings
know that peace
where there's an absence of self-attachment
[Music]
thank you
so for this Fifth and last talk on
aspirations that are support or an aspect of compassion
a manifestation of compassion that I want to emphasize
the possibility that aspiration can arise out of a peacefulness
out of peace and that peace is a wonderful reference point
for the motivations that are connected to being compassionate
it's not a few people for whom who confuse compassion with distress
compassion with their own discomfort around being in the presence of
suffering and they confuse the motivation to be compassionate to act compassionately
with the motivations that flow from that discomfort and that distress
and some of that has to do a lot with our attachments to self at all kinds of
attachments we might have and so even even some of the
most important kind of ways and things we can do to be compassionate and caring for others
we carry with us a something which is not peaceful something which is
stressful something which there's attachment and clinging as part of it of force and assertiveness a
tension and um and and it's possible to do have
the aspiration to desire the motivation to be compassionate to uh be peaceful useful to arise kind
of in an easy light way and where there's not a lot of
self-attachment self-concern that's entangled with that
where it's coming from not from any sense of being distressed or being
challenged or being somehow uncomfortable with being uncomfortable
but rather it comes from our capacity to be attuned to be open to be appreciative
to be aware in a broad open way
and those three aware attuned and appreciative are three of
the important aspects of compassion that we've talked about already in this series
and so all those lead to the possibility that of a certain degree of Peace
certain degree of ease and um of non-clinging
and to have compassion arise out of non-clinging has it looked very different
than maybe conventionally what people think compassion is supposed to look like
sometimes people feel like if there's some injustice in the world we're supposed to be angry we're supposed to
be upset and if we're not upset enough we don't show that we care
but that upsetness that anger uh it may
very well be a symptom of something that we're attached to something we're clinging to
some assertion of self that's not really necessary as part of it
and the alternative to being distressed and angry is not passivity is not
avoiding but it allows for maybe an equally or maybe even more powerful
motivation to rise within us to to to to change the Injustice to fight it in a
sense to but it comes out of it's part of the world of inner world of non-clinging and
in peace and the dharmic the Dharma kind of orientation around this is that
is that there's a we want to we want to trust the Dharma within us we want to
trust those natural processes of healing of freedom of of of love and
compassion that can flow and move through us
um without this kind of clinging and self-assertion as being part of it
and so I've in a in a category way I call this peace to trust peace and to
use peace as a reference point to understand the motivations we have to be compassionate
is the motivation to be compassionate is the actions of compassion coming from a
peaceful place a subtle Place coming from a place of calm or quiet someplace that's kind of not is below
the level of discursive thinking where we're spinning stories and fears and
Fantasies and projections and memories and all kinds of things that this swirling around that are driving
a certain kind of attached attitude towards it all that supports
fear supports anger supports the stress but if we can listen to that place below
the discursive thought the place that's more peaceful than most discursive thinking is reactive thinking then we
have access to something quite different we can have this this uh the flow of
life uh you know life knows
what to bring forth life knows what movement towards homeostasis the harmony
to peace for everyone concerned and it's not a passivity it's very
important to understand this but it's to make room for this deeper motivation that sometimes
can lead to tremendous courage that doesn't look like courage perhaps because it's not forceful but it can be
give birth to a lifetime of dedication to live a life for the benefit of the
world to benefit of trying to find a way to uh
alleviate more suffering in this world but if we can do it from this place of
peace then it's sustainable and then it doesn't give birth to
at least maybe it's an ancient phenomena but it has in only in modern times does
it have a name and that is sometimes called compassion fatigue or compassion overwhelm
and and it's kind of unfortunate these two are connected fatigue and compassion
but it's when our our so-called compassionate actions in the world uh go
come along with um these complications of attachments of
clinging of self-assertion self-definition self-victimization that goes on when we
act and we don't know how to come from this peaceful place but we come more from you know some other place where
that we're much more vulnerable to be impacted in negative ways and be
exhausted but to um so to use as a reference point
as we study is we're mindful of our aspirations and realize that all the different aspects of aspiration that
that make it richer the world of aspiration you know Wonderful to have a reference point of peace is it
peaceful is it free of clinging this aspiration and one of the reasons why these are
important questions is that one of the directions orientations for where to be
compassionate is in fact to ourselves of course many of us will be attached
and clinging many of us will have our inner challenges many of us will be will have fatigue and distress
it's not a crime to be this way it's very important not to add layers of criticism of ourselves or
shame even on top of that but this peaceful place to be aware
uh and and using that as a reference point can help show us oh I'm not
peaceful and the compassion also can be directed here to myself to what's happening
within me can I hold this with a kind of peaceful presence that
maybe a friend would offer you sitting on a bench in a park just being present and listening to you talking
about your difficulties and it's so meaningful that someone just is there in a non-reactive way in an
attentive way peaceful way you know not asserting themselves not fixing you not
treating you as someone you they need to help but treating you with respect and and serving you in a sense with their
presence and their attention and their attentive care um to be able to do that to oneself
in a deep way so uh so these different aspects of
aspiration that I've talked about today this last one is maybe maybe it's the
most difficult because it you know this is what comes maybe with a deep
spiritual growth maybe the Deep growth in the Dharma is we become more and more attuned to a place a possibility of
Peace of calm of ease that it can't always be that way or be
fully that way but it becomes a reference point for
um for seeing more clearly what is here and that peace and that kind of peaceful
way of being aware can be seen to be a 360 degree awareness
that includes ourselves includes the whole world and uh and for aspiration to be that way
or the possibility of aspiration to be that way is one of the reasons why I feel that as this deep aspiration this
deep intentionality this deep motivation to live for the welfare and happiness of
the world is one of the most beautiful things that we can have even if it's partial even if it's you
know haltingly it's just that this capacity is something we have and that we can live from that
I think it's a beautiful beautiful thing so
um aspiration so um
so we're going through these different aspects of compassion and then the five that we that you know
before we've done now so far is awareness appreciation awareness Attunement appreciation and to
and this aspiration and the next time I'm here at the 7A at this YouTube teaching
um I'll do five days on action the fifth part of compassion and which is very important as well but
for have the action arise when these other four are have been kind of in the
picture have been included and considered then the action becomes much more important or valuable for everyone
concerned including oneself so I'll do that so I'm I won't be here
now again for three weeks I'm going down to uh tasahara The Zed Monastery in in
the mountains here south of here uh in order to teach um seven three week Retreat a kind of a
Zen retreat but kind of a Zen vipassana hybrid of sorts with my friend uh then teacher Paul
Heller and um and uh
and then I'll be back uh up here at the IMC or you know part of teaching
on a Saturday July 29th and I'm teaching a day-long
retreat that's titled freedom and mindfulness of emotions through uh IRC
the Insight Retreat Center and I'll try to put the notice of it in the what's new at the imc's website
under Reflections from Gill but some of you might want to come to that online day-long Retreat I think it's from 9 to
4 30 in California time and we have some wonderful teachers
coming in the next couple of weeks and I think right now we don't have a teacher for the third We Come Away
um but uh we're still looking for someone and hopefully that's easy enough
and and we don't have to be creative what we do that third week
and um and um
so thank you and uh I'm certainly appreciating this chance to explore compassion this way with all
of you these weeks that I'm here and I look forward to continuing when I come back on I guess I'm back on the
there there I'm not sure if it's the first day of August or the last day of July that
Monday so thank you very much