Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour
and if you can hear me okay please give me a thumbs up it's audio okay fantastic
great hi I'm Nikki I'm in Mountain View California and sit at all only land
welcoming you to happy hour and uh as always we start by saying hello
welcoming each other welcoming ourselves so who wants to say hi who wants to warm
up the space with hellos take it away
and hello one wheeler on YouTube from Tarzana California and kitten from
Thailand and uh who else wants to say hi on Zoom
lots of folks joining us on YouTube Leslie from Santa Cruz hi Leslie
hi it's Claudia I'm in San Mateo today hi Claudia and San Mateo today
meal in New Hampshire hi Neil good evening to you
it's Barbara and Alameda hi Barbara and and we also have folks on YouTube we
have uh hello Nikki Sleepless in Scotland UK yes it's pretty late there hello Clarion
that and oh we also have us from folks joining us from Australia we're quite
International in this moment who else wants to say hi maybe I'll take one more a couple more hellos
hi Amy who says Aloha in Oahu
and hi Nina zooming in from East Elmhurst New York City
live spending lots of time zones Durham North Carolina High cantons so okay
let's get started the Sangha has assembled
we uh yes we are here from lots of different places in the world so
so thank you Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google Groups if you are new to happy hour
um you are warmly invited to join we have a Google group for keeping in touch with
one another with uh to to receive information and at this time I change the settings
so I accidentally I'm muting won't happen the space will stay quiet and I
send I change the chat settings to be um only coming to hosts but I ask you to
keep that channel quiet because it can be quite distracting to receive uh chats
while I'm teaching I'll open it later for reflections and last but not least
I'm going to turn on recording on Audio Dharma
here we go great so hello and welcome to happy hour
friends wherever in the world you are joining from it's lovely to be with you
lovely to sit together so
so some of you might know that this week I'm subbing for kale and
um for the 7 A.M and the uh theme for this week I'm exploring
is compassion it is compassion the theme that we've explored of course a lot in
happy arts and I wanted to to explore and invite us to to practice with very
subtle very gentle uh quiet compassion uh this evening with the breath just
very subtle very um yeah let it be in the background in the
foreground background in a way uh suffusing our breath suffusing this
moment and and we'll have a pretty quiet that's my
intention at least we'll see what arrives um guided meditation tonight to really
settle into the space with Silence with kindness with warmth and holding whatever challenges there might be
um with uh with compassion with kindness so so that's the plan and let's uh let's
practice together so arriving
arriving in this moment in time
in our bodies and on the cushion or the chair relaxing
softening the body
and however the body is in this moment inviting
the body to soften to relax not pushing away any discomfort
but softening around it softening around it softening into it
and letting the breath be supportive in this softening
and lending awareness enact and greet each breath in the body
the entirety of the breath the entirety of the out breath
really support us to land especially if we're feeling restless or distracted
connecting with the entirety of the breath not as assured
not as a grim duty but
but with care with kindness towards ourselves
and we allow can we invite kindness to be breathed in with each
breath breathed in and breathe out breathing in kindness breathing out
kindness breathing in kindness towards this body
breathing out kindness good will friendliness around this body
not so much as an effortful breathing in but letting it be breathed
imagining that the air around you is infused with kindness so there is no
other way there's no other way than to breathe in
Good Will kindness friendliness into this heart into this
body to these lungs nourishing ourselves with good will
letting good will find its way to every cell of this body it's already
available [Music] it's no work it's already here
it's also breathed out it's so natural As Natural as the breath itself
as breathing itself automatic
Maybe you experiment with greetings kindness that's being breathed in with a smile
or maybe a smile shows up because it's quite lovely to be breathing in kindness and Goodwill into
the body and feeling nourished by it there's a natural gladness that arises
foreign
and realizing that the conditions are like this right now whatever the conditions are in the body
in your mind in your heart that it is like this right now
and if there are any challenges present right now in the physical space or
or emotional space letting this kindness that you breathe
in that's being breathed in the good will friendliness
meat meat really hold Great Space around
whatever challenge there might be
and difficulty is met with kindness with good will this is compassion
meeting difficulty pain physical pain emotional challenges pain
with kindness with gentleness good wealth
is compassion for ourselves
so let kindness be breathed in again good will continue to be breathing
breathe out and meeting whatever is necessary in
this moment
and don't make breathing in and out kindness into a
hyperventilation or too much work let it be natural
it's just in the air around you it's very subtle very subtle
you're sitting in it
it's infusing your body your heart it's kindness holding whatever might be
challenging
maybe you find that your body feels more relaxed or safer
more at ease maybe something releases some holy
releases in the heart or in the body
as you sit in this air imbued with Good Will kindness
gentleness as it's breathed in
and out naturally
nowhere to go nothing to do it's not a doing
this invitation not a doing
it's a non-doing it's a natural way of being let in Let It Be As Natural
as the breath happening on its own
infusion of Good Will kindness meeting whatever is arising
with meta and if it's a challenge it becomes compassion
as we turn to bring this meditation to a close
letting there be kindness
gentle appreciation or having showed up
as best as you were able to In This Moment
no need for judgment comparison and if any arise
let them be held in this air in the space of kindness
trusting we are planting seeds goodness kindness
to support ourselves support our loved ones all beings whose lives We Touch directly
and indirectly may all beings everywhere
be well be free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you friends thank you for your practice
ah
I love this gentle practice it's it's like sitting in a warm bath
breathing in air of kindness just the whole body can relax into it there's not
so much doing and I certainly feel happier and more
gentle and also more awake more alert [Music]
um so what we did was basically I invited
you to to work with kindness not as so much a doing but as natural as as breathing
breathing that kindness being breathed in kind of spring breathed out towards the body towards
others internally externally though our Focus really was ourselves
and then I asked you if there's there any challenges in the body or in the
mind let this kindness good will meet meet the difficulty the pain
and as many of you might already know when kindness when meta meets and holds
suffering and pain that is the expression of compassion compassion is
meta plus suffering so that it becomes
um that gets expressed as karuna as compassion so we're playing around with
that in this session in a very gentle um non-doing way just letting it be
letting the body rest in it and letting kindness good will
Infuse the body so so
as always as we after we practice on the cushion on our own with our eyes closed
we have an opportunity to bring the practice into a relational field into a
relational field can we now enter a space of kindness towards ourselves and
towards a couple of other practitioners with this gentle air of kindness as if
there is kindness in the zoom room um in in the bits and bytes in the
electronic in the as we breathe together and showing up with this kindness for
ourselves in this relational field then the invitation is if you want to share
anything about how this practice was for you if there were any aha moments or challenges
you are welcome too and you could also just
say pass and hold [Music] um compassionate kind presence for yourself
and others also the three of you in the room can
sit together in Silence the whole time or until somebody wants to share something
and let it Let Yourself speak from the heart let it be a counsel where you
speak from the heart you don't ask questions just share and you speak from your own heart and the next person if
they want they do that and then the next person will come back to you and they'll go around and round
um and um take care of yourselves take care of each other no directing just showing
up either with Silence with kindness or with words whatever you like to share
so I'm going to create the breakout rooms and it's quite a gift to be able
to to share the practice with with light-hearted I don't not just
like-minded but light-hearted um practitioners it's it's such a gift
so create the rooms and if you do say something let it be brief so other
people have a chance to to to join you okay take care of yourselves take care
of each other your rooms are open here we go
their rooms will close in about 10 seconds so we'll wait until everybody is
back
okay the rooms are closed everyone is back and we have some time for questions
Reflections um
and um I'm gonna change the chat settings you
can also type your Reflections in chat if you like
Malaya am I saying your name right
yeah I want to say thank you so much um I feel like this meditation really
helps me because I've been experiencing some physical health problems lately where I have a lot of discomfort and
pain and then when I was meditating like I thought of like a flower and then I was
like oh I am also a flower and it looks like this is strange I was like I am
also flower and then I was like well I'm a flower because I have my own Beauty
and I'm growling because flowers grow and they blossom and they have their own
Seasons because I feel like I've been judging myself comparing to myself how I was before I started experiencing these
health problems so thank you oh wow
thank you so much Malaya for bringing that in I see the hearts in this in Zoom
thank you so much for sharing so beautiful oh thank you for bringing that
in and and both being witnessed for your own sake and also for for everyone's
um supporting everyone with our with our insights how beautiful to have this
inside yes I'm I'm part of nature just like a flower I have my seasons and
they're different seasons and I continue to grow uh through through this challenge
and um yeah so beautiful and the sense of
kindness and also yes and what you said this beauty acknowledging your own
Beauty your own goodness this flowering yay it's so beautiful thank you so much
for sharing that how lovely yeah
Claire please
and your little pity because my computer's not working right but what I
really wanted to talk about was the difference between compassion and self-pity or the relationship uh because
I've I've had an extremely difficult life I really truly have but I spent a lot of it going into fits of self-pity
and not accomplishing very much because I felt so sorry for Claire little by
slowly I've been introduced to situations where the people around me had more
difficulties by far than I did I'm not going to tell all their stories but anyway I'm now working for an
organization that Fosters Independence for the disabled and it's a marvelous experience because
it's forcing me to stop looking at all my woes and look at the people whose lives are much more difficult than mine
and I am able to feel compassion for them but this practice tonight was perfect because it's exactly what I want
to keep working on um it's it's really it bring can bring so much joy when when you're trying to
do provide service for people who really needs it uh and not get wrapped up in
self yeah exactly it's a way of serving and also it's us right not them versus
us or their suffering is it's I could be suffering any more things can shift and
change it any moment and and we all have our seasons of Malaya beautifully
brought in we all have our Seasons we all go through challenging periods and none of us
every single human being will go through changes transitions challenges so it's
really us so thanks Claire thanks for bringing that sense of service and humility and and gladness and yeah thank
you and one question I'll I'll address is uh
one person has asked that um in as uh uh what how to handle when
in small groups uh people ask questions of one another especially not following
instructions and and um uh
um and um you know how to handle it so so it's perfectly okay to to ever so
kindly and gently and lovingly remind each other you know not not in a
policing way but like oh yeah we're not supposed to ask each other questions we're not supposed to give advice to one
another and we're not supposed to do that we're just supposed to share from our own experience so so feel free to to
to to um take your seat of compassionate
awareness and serve the community in this way oh yeah we're not supposed to that was part of the instructions it
could be you know very gentle or perhaps in a light or even humorous way but but
it is okay to do that it really is okay to do that because we are giving I am
inviting you to create the sense of safety for one another and not ask questions and not give advice right so I
hope that is helpful to everyone and especially for the person who asked this question in chat
Serena Serena thank you so much for giving me an
opportunity to share uh I haven't shared for a long while now
so um I have a question because well what happened in my
meditation is I had this overwhelming feeling of Joy like that I kind of
brought in from where I was earlier so I hardly kind of
I hardly kind of was able to kind of tune into your
instructions because this overwhelming feeling of Joy was like you know in my
being so the best I was able to do was to just be with it and and be with the thoughts
that were associated with it so I'm just kind of wondering in terms of practice
whether that was skillful or not yeah yeah thank you for for bringing that in
and asking that and um you know what I'm hearing is that
there was a sense of overwhelming joy and and what you were doing is to be
with it is to to with to be with it to witness it to hold it and I also heard
that there are maybe a lot of thinking was coming up if I heard you correctly to be with this not to not to get all
um and maybe the way to be with it is not to get taken away and and and go on
a journey of thinking and and not that but stay with the joy stay with the joy
but not with the thinking so what I would suggest is drop the story drop the story of the joy and the happiness and
this and that which might be looking forward to something or reminiscing about something drop all that and stay
with the physicality the sense of joy in your heart how does it feel in the body
in the mind um and be kind you know kindly as long
as you're being kind to whatever arises during PR during your meditation you're
doing it right so if Joy arises be with it with kindness if something painful
arises be with it with kindness if just the breath arises be with it with
kindness so that's what I would suggest that's uh the way to be with Eterna does
that help thank you so much yeah you are very welcome thank you
so thank you all thank you for your practice for your wholeheartedness for
your cultivation um this is such beautiful beautiful
cultivation we're doing together for the sake of ourselves and all beings everywhere so thank you thank you may
you be well may you be happy may you have joy may you have ease and realize every single
one of you one of us is a flower appreciating what Malaya brought in
every single one of us is a beautiful flower and we have our own unique
fragrance that we we share with the world we spread in the world and we also
have our Seasons we all have our Seasons to appreciate that
it's all the season so be well they take good care may all beings be well may all
beings be happy thanks everyone
thank you