so uh so welcome folks welcome
um yeah happy to uh happy to be with you
I'm uh Matthew and um as you know
um Gill is uh away traveling and uh and teaching teaching Retreat right now and
happens to be in the north of uh New Zealand which uh was received a cyclone
and I was in touch with him last night and he's he's fine and the song goes fine and they're uh hunkered down and
practicing and doing uh doing well um and uh
yeah but happy to be with you this week so uh let's uh that's it that's it
foreign
so if you have any routine ways of relaxing or directing attention
that helps you establish
sense of embodiment mindfulness please uh please do that
and if there's anything that needs awareness is blessing
in order for you to put it down
and give that blessing
something that's recently happened something you're anticipating big
existential questions and issues
it's not that blessing with awareness resolves it ties up the Loose Ends of
Being Human but it's that we make enough peace with
it that the attention
is no longer compulsively pulled there
we can become available or our life
In This Moment
body in the posture mind in the body
relaxation in the mind
to the present bird is to momentarily give up
hope for clinging
some part of our mind as these utopian fantasies
about what clinging might be able to get us
the Buddha says
not so much
and sometimes we have to mourn the truth
that are clinging cannot work out the way we hope
but in our relaxation in our
letting go
the settledness of equanimity
we received the Dharma
those blessings
and all the anxiety and agitation bound up with the sense of needing
to steer and control our life Moment by moment
starts to Fall Away
our heart becomes more and more are available
and uh poignancy of our life
dawned
our hopes and fears become
Maybe less entangling
but still poignant
in a sense of self becomes less entangling
but poignant
rather than reaching out to control the moment
we're willing to receive it be changed by it
and says something in the heart rests
[Music]
foreign
so it's good to uh good to see with you um
so last uh last time I was here uh just a few weeks ago I did
uh the um series on the five five spiritual
faculties of faith and energy mindfulness samadi concentration wisdom
and when deciding what to uh what to teach just generally like I kind of
float this balloon in my mind little trial balloon
and then imagine the Sangha imagine speaking to
that theme and um and try to feel into that and
this time like all my balloons all the trial balloons immediately kind of
deflated and fell to the ground I didn't know what to teach so I um I
made up a list not official by any stretch
[Music] um kind of factors that don't show up in uh
in the list but from what I can see lead us deeper into uh
into the direct path and so today is uh
awe and wonder it's the researcher
um Decker Keltner uh oah is the feeling of Wonder and
amazement of being in the presence of something that something vast that transcends one's current understanding
as part of a family of states that includes elevation appreciation and
admiration the majority of all experiences occur in response to Nature other people who
display virtuosity or Magnum magnanimity art and music religious experiences and
ideas similar to other pro-social emotions like gratitude compassion
are reliably predicts increased sharing assistance and generosity
so awe on this path we
we develop I would say a kind of awe for the Dharma
I I remember early early in practice maybe I don't know a year into practice
or something I was at a weekend retreat with Galen
Ferguson and the Tibetan tradition and
Galen is uh I think a professor and was a professor
he is a full-time Dharma person very beautiful teacher quite buttoned up you know kind of and
um the weekend was on the unity of of shamata and insight the unity of the the
tranquilizing and the Insight side of the path and it touched me quite deeply and
afterwards I kind of approached him crying and sort of rambling and just
trying to express something something what he had done to my heart and
uh I was trying trying unsuccessfully to say something like
I'm falling in love with the Dharma you're helping
I wasn't able to say that and just kind of
sat there a little messy in his uh kind presence and he said something like oh
yeah um gazing out over the vastness of the
Dharma ocean you know that can be a lot
and in a Dharma life we we
develop a sense of awe for the path awe for awareness itself
the the sense of how um how close the distance
from suffering to peace can be in a given moment
it feels so far and yet we come to know it as being so close
and the potency of of awareness becomes
a kind of object of of all
this life this life this life we are somehow given
I remember again early in practice I think from the Tibetan tradition the
image of being born human is like a turtle swimming in the great ocean that
breaches the surface of the water once every century
and happening to poke its head through a small ring floating in the vastness of
the ocean the chance of that is like the
preciousness of being born human with this possibility to wake up
and so yeah there is wonder wonder for having been born Wonder for
the possibilities of Being Human
and wonder or the question of like how might I live
how might I live we're so so hemmed in so constrained by
prevailing narratives and cultural assumptions and the the seeming
foundations of a human life but in Buddhism uh
the the foundation of all things is empty
and so what if what if everything I consider
natural and customary the right way everything I consider to be self-evident
to be common sense is empty empty
the the kind of usually translated as attachment to rights and rituals
um and has said said to be shed at stream entry the kind of first uh real
taste of enlightenment see the Bata paramasa
kind of endowing all the conventions of our life with um more
and in a way our entire culture is silabata paramasa
and when we recognize the the groundlessness of all convention
there's a lot of wonder how might I live
unconstrained by this attachment to Convention how might
I live wonder wonder is uh is an especially
clean engine for our motivation and Dharma effort
clinging of course is the Buddha says is at the heart of
suffering but how do we avoid trying to cling our way to peace
so many of the moves that we can make on our experience the Dharma moves we make
in one way or another express some clinging
and wonder wonder this deep abiding interest
this is a very powerful place to practice from and I I feel you know in my capacity as
a teacher when people become interested in their minds my job is kind of done relegated
uh primarily to just being a cheerleader and I like that role
but it's um there's something that happens when we like are interested
interested in our minds there's no real agenda and interest in
wonder and this uh is a powerful
condition for the arising of wisdom and love
ah is associated with the the sense of self becoming smaller sense of self
becoming smaller sometimes this is seen you know in the
classically gazing up at the stars or something and um
it says an astronomer she writes um our galaxies located at one end of the
local group a small cluster of galaxies with the Andromeda galaxy at the other
end the local group is near the outskirts of the local supercluster
which has a diameter of a hundred million light years the biggest supercluster is the Perseus
Pegasus filament which stretches for roughly a billion light years a number
of other super clusters and voids are known but astronomers have only mapped
the large-scale structure of a small part of the universe there may even be larger scale
structures to really you know just to really 100
billion light years whatever to really take that in it's um
it's tough tougher to get too lost in the details
of a particular life but um
but here's the thing the self-becoming smaller means the world gets much much
bigger much much bigger the less the less clinging
the more life
and so we discuss we we wake up to awe in the face of the vastness there
awe in the face of the vastness of of suffering
it just brings you to your knees
and awe in the face of love to know how vast our love might become even though
it does not resolve samsara does not tie up the
Loose Ends of Being Human
but to be kind of humbled how vast our love might become
measure this it said measureless in the sense that we're stepping out of
measuring and also that there is nothing on the other side of it
so oh and what under on this path
offer that for your consideration today and um
yeah I wish you um I wish you all well and we'll uh we'll
keep going tomorrow so uh yeah thank you uh thanks so much and uh
yeah have a good uh have a good day