so I wanted to talk a little bit about fear and I talked about that uh last
week when I was here and those of you who listen to the 7 AMS know that I'm doing a week on fear
there and part of the reason there's a number of reasons because there's
fear we have fear and uh you know it shows up in our
lives and maybe much more than we realize there's like this fear is
underlining so many of the things that we do the decisions we
make sometimes like fear of boredom like oh I can't be bored I got to make sure I
have my phone with me I guess we have phones for other reasons but you know just
this you know afraid that we we'll be alone with ourselves or maybe there's a
fear of sometimes our shadow side sometimes we're afraid of what might arise if we're quiet and
really touch into the anger or the sadness or the shame some of these
things so we don't go there CU you know we're afraid of what's going to happen
or maybe have this fear of failure we don't try new
things we don't kind of like stretch ourselves put ourselves in unfamiliar
settings try for different jobs or make changes or something like this because we have fear of
failure fear of endings maybe we're awkward around when something ends and
it's time to say goodbye and just leave or or we hold on too tightly or don't
want to even just deal with it when coworker leaves or somebody moves away
or whatever this is there's like this uncomfortableness this fear of endings or this fear
of I want to say not being in control but we're really not in control as much
as we think we are but kind maybe fear of like just the
feeling of not being in control of course we want things to go
the way that we want them to go and this fear of maybe feeling
Unworthy of course everybody's worthy being unworthy doesn't actually exist
but doesn't mean people don't feel that way feel like okay in order to be worthy
I have to succeed or serve or you know I have to do
something it's really if we kind of like want to look at it in this way we'll see that there fear is like so prevalent is
really having a big role in our lives this is part of the reason why you
know fear is something to look at and become familiar with and learn to work
with last week I talked about the f a practice the fair practice F is for
friend kind of say like bef friend the fear e is for explore the fear a is for
allow the fear and R is release maybe was not so much that we're
actively doing the releasing but releasing of fear happens when we are exploring and allowing and being
friendly with it and soly the BRD he gave some teachings on fear I'm not going to go
into all of them today but wouldn't it be easier if there
just weren't fear if there just wasn't it just fear we
just didn't have fear if that just didn't arise it'd be so much easier just think like how much Freedom it would
have the the things that we could do if there weren't fear the how many people we could
benefit and support ourselves and so many others if we didn't have
fear so the Buddha he talked about this road
to fearlessness I stumbled upon this um this verse that's kind of like tucked
away in the samut Naya it's maybe not uh so
common but I thought I'd play around a little bit and explore kind of like these instructions to
fearlessness instead of just learning how to be with fear how to just not have
fear so kind of like this uh it's written in
verse it's very that's common there's a lot of things that are written in verse
but maybe I'll just say in a little aside that to translate poly verse into
English depends on your point of view is either really difficult or really
easy because it doesn't follow the usual grammar rules and it uses
uh word forms that are really unusual and it uses maybe some archaic
vocabulary like archaic even for poly so in modern times you kind of there's a
lot of interpretation that has to be done and
um so there's a way in which it's not you know like the verse is um pointing
toward something and then there's a way in which we can have to see it make sense of it and I thought maybe I'd
share with you kind of some of my thinking it's not you don't have to agree with me but I'll offer kind of
like my interpretation but part of the reason why I want to offer this is to encourage you to find your way
too with some of what's been said here and so maybe on the big p so not
only I'll say not only does it use verse but it's also using a metaphor and the
metaphor is this idea of a chariot you know that was like the fastest thing that was the only probably
vehicle at the time right was a chariot so this I way this to get to
fearlessness apparently according to this you just have to get on the right Chariot going the right
direction but what does that mean okay so here's the verse and then um I'll
unpack it and I'll share with you some things here and there's some things that are I think a little bit surprising at
least I felt surprised and then when I thought about it I felt kind of actually uh happy it made me happy to think about
this so the verse goes like this the path is called the straight way
and fearless is its destination The Chariot is called
unswerving fitted with wheels of Dharma conscience is its leaning board
mindfulness its upholstery I say the teachings is the charioteer
with Right View running out in front one who has such a vehicle whether
a woman or a man by means of this vehicle is in the presence of
nibana so there's this way that the destination is fearlessness and it's also going towards
nibana this recognition that uh Freedom includes like Freedom From Fear but also
this movement towards greater and greater Freedom right there's a shedding of a lot of the fears and a lot of that
has to do because so many of these fears that I described at the beginning were
fears about our sense of self like how will we look to others or will we be
safe and have security and as we find our way towards greater and greater Peace and Freedom
the sense of self is not as hungry for attention or needing to be uh
fed or protected or that's not as strong it's uh not driving the ship quite as
often I'll talk about that a little bit more when we get there but maybe I'll start here with the first
stanza the path is called the straight way and fearless is its
destination The Chariot is called unswerving fitted with wheels of Dharma so this
idea of the path is called the straight way some of you may know that about the
eight-fold path it's kind of like a foundational teaching in this tradition is a one of the way to um
Awakening and it's there's other places in the sutas where it's called the straight way I just want to say a little
bit about this eight-fold path as you might imagine it has eight parts to it I'm not going to
Define them but I'll just say very quickly we um before we use this word write
s I'm using the word write I learned it this way but often it's um also you
could translate as wise or correct or appropriate So Right View right
intention right speech right action right livelihood right energy right
mindfulness right concentration my only reason why I'm saying all these
eight is to point out that actually sometimes it gets summarized Sila Samar
PA ethics ethical Behavior mental development wisdom so
these three buckets these three types of practices is the eight-fold path and
we'll see in this verse here that there's Al three of these get mentioned
manip ethics mental development and
wisdom it says Fearless is its destination and as I was saying that um
as we have more freedom there's a sense of self doesn't need to be propped up as
much but somebody who is completely awakened it no longer has this idea that there's a
central core or Essence to their experience it's not
like they have something a central core to which other things happen instead it's like there's just a bunch of things
happening this isn't something that you have to believe or you have to adopt a view about but uh this can be part of
one's experience so to be
Fearless doesn't is what uh means to no longer have fear because
there isn't this core that has to be protected instead they are with whatever
is rising and whatever is rising without building a story around
it saying like oh that was awkward what I just said or what that other person
said and then they don't have to make a story like oh my gosh I'm so embarrassed that I tripped or whatever there isn't
anything extra that gets added on to it it's just like oh that's an experience and it felt like
this and one thing that's interesting is like as there's more and more freedom there's also more and more connection so
it's not like an aloofness it's not like a separateness it's instead of uh trying
to protect the core it's like wanting to connect and support other people so
fearlessness you could see where if you didn't had fear it's easier to so to
show up when others are having difficulties it's easier to say the
things that you know would really help somebody but it's hard to say or it's
easier to support people when they're waiting for test results back from the
doctors or something like this so this verse continues and it says
The Chariot is called unswerving this idea of
unswerving this goes along with the idea that it's the path is the straight way so maybe the Chariot doesn't need to be
swerving but I also would like to think about this is unswerving as it doesn't
go to other destinations if we follow this eight-fold path Mani PA it's not
like that we're going to end up someplace terrible where we don't want to go it's going to bring us to fearlessness
and greater freedom and peace but here's something that I think is
really evocative when I think about when do I swerve when I'm in my own version
of a charot that has a four-cylinder engine and you know however many gears you know this kind of thing we swerve
often to avoid something for our safety but um you know
just to avoid things what if this path means we don't have to
avoid anything everything becomes part of
practice everything gets folded in we don't have to try to disown parts
of ourselves we don't have to try to avoid certain situations instead our
capacity to be with difficulty grows our capacity to hold what's
uncomfortable grows so we start becoming more and more comfortable with being uncomfortable
it's like okay uncomfortableness feels like this pain feels like
this but our confidence even to be with the difficult things right we're all
going to get sick in our lives we're all going to have illness in our lives we're all going to have people pets family
members who die right it's unavoidable so I like this idea like the
path is going straight whatever arises next it's able to
meet and this is the practice it turns
out the path is meeting whatever arises that's we might think like oh
this um this often sometimes we talk about like the hindrances like this
restlessness like okay I'll be able to practice or I'll be able to meditate as soon as this restlessness settles down
or the opposite soon as this sleepiness goes away it turns out that restlessness is
the practice like to be with restlessness feel it in the body explore
it learn how to hold it and there's all kinds of things we can do discover like
what causes restless to increase or what are the things that cause it to arise in
the first place all these things I'm just using restlessness as an example but this idea of the Chariot
this something that's going to lead us to fearlessness is meeting whatever is in
the way and we can use as supports the these
factors of the eight-fold path right action is about ethical
Behavior showing up in a way in which we're not causing harm not causing harm to others and not causing harm to
ourselves there's a way in which being mindful just being present for what's
happening even if it is exactly what we don't want because let's face it sometimes we
get exactly what we don't want but sometimes there's a way in
which being mindful bringing some attention to to it helps to maybe uh unpack it away from
the dreaded whatever it might [Music] be the ending of a relationship maybe we
desperately didn't want that to happen or was afraid it was going to happen and then it looks like it is
happening it doesn't help to pretend it isn't instead it helps us like to turn
towards and to okay what's needed here what can be sensitive to what
needed so this Chariot is unswerving and then the next line is fitted with wheels
of Dharma I like this expression wheels of
Dharma and uh one way that I'm thinking about this is maybe this contemporary uh
expression is where the rubber meets the road so that kind of like the Gera right
the Dharma is not yes we use it for the D um the Buddha's teachings but really
it's not like some just philosophical ideas that just exist in our minds not
just Concepts or Notions but the Dharma is really how we show up in the
world it's the way in which because these teachings that the Buddha offered
shared are they're really pragmatic it's not like here just believe this
stuff it's more like show up in this way CU he's really concerned about what
leads to suffering and the ending of suffering and things that you can see
and discover for yourself a real encouragement not to just believe the teachings he was not interested in
metaphysics or speculative views or when somebody asked him well what's the
nature of the cosmos he didn't answer and he said he
didn't answer because it that kind of thinking those types of concerns doesn't lead to the end of
suffering so when this Chariot has that D fitted with wheels of
Dharma it's like there's so many different ways we can think about this but one is our
practice is that what what do we know about ways to be in the world what can
what parts of the a-al path can we bring maybe we can bring mindfulness maybe we can bring right action of not harming
right intention bringing compassion right effort is looking at
okay what's uh helpful what's not helpful what's wholesome what's not
wholesome so fitted with wheels of Dharma and then the second stanza
or maybe I'll um yeah I I'll I'll leave that there the second stanza is
conscience is its leaning board mindfulness its
upholstery I say the teachings is the charioteer with Right View running out
in front let's unpack this a little bit conscience is its leaning
board so I tried to look this up like what is a leaning board in a chariot but it turns out it's not so common I guess
I couldn't really find this so this is my understanding is in this is in
Diana's mind right when I uh think of uh chariots is um there's like somebody
who's standing and it's like What's um like protecting them in front so that
they don't fall forward onto the horses or something like this so so conscience is its leaning board so
it's this maybe that goes around like this and we could say it helps them from
not falling out so conscience so conscience some of
you might know this PO word HEI some and I'm translating it as
conscience here and hiri is um that
Buddha called it like the one of the Guardians of the world because it's this
um it's this sense of recognizing how uncomfortable it is when we've done
something UNH wholesome when we've done something that we knew wasn't the best
thing to do but we did it anyway and this he is this you know this um wish to not
cause harm and it's based on a respect and a
care for ourselves and for others so it's not like this external like you
should not do this it's more of like oh it feels awful when I cause
harm and I care and respect others so I want to take care I don't want to cause
harm this feels for me like a nice way to think about how to be in the world you know it requires that we're
sensitive to what's going on with ourselves what feels uncomfortable but it builds on on this
wish to support others and to support ourselves not like we have to choose
oursel or others but both so this idea of conscience as the
Leaning board is something that's here that helping us F so that we don't fall out of the Chariot of um that's carrying
us towards fearlessness and in this poem in this verse and with this metaphor The
Chariot is we could also say is the practice
what's taking us to uh fearlessness and then there's this very
curious expression mindfulness is its upholstery like
what I did I poked around in the poly here to say like okay par varum is the
poly so it could also mean something like covering or drapery
but um I was thinking well maybe you know this is speculation on my part that
uh maybe like this Chariot has a covering that protects them
from whatever they need to be protected from the Sun this is India right it's
hot and the you know the rain but we can think of mindfulness as something that
protects us from whatever it is we need protected from there's I spoke about this earlier
there's a way in which if we can bring mindfulness if we can bring attention to what's
happening there is a way in which it protects us because it enables us to
bring our best wisdom we're not necessar less we're least less likely to be
caught off guard but instead we can be noticing what's actually happening
it's so common that when something's uncomfortable we start blaming or we or we collapse and then
we're no longer kind of connected to what's actually happening we're too busy
like yelling at the other person or yelling at ourselves or just shutting
down but there's a way in which mindfulness if we can stay present with what's
happening allows us to be sensitive to what's happening and not having to be
like the blaming and the shutting and kind of like blunt our
awareness and as best we can right some of some things in our lives are really
difficult and it's difficult to be with but to have the aspiration to know that
to know to pay attention to is better in
the long run even though it might be uncomfortable than just trying to avoid or pretend it's not there so mindfulness
it's upholstery I'm going to maybe say and I thought about this when I was uh driving here this evening like
upholstery I looked at some other translators they had the word
accessory but the poly doesn't really support that that this was a in little
little too far from the poly and then the second second stanza goes with
I say the teachings is the charioteer so actually this word is Dharma
again so the charioteer the person who is doing the driving is the
practice or it's our practice or maybe it is the teachings Dharma has so many
different ways we can interpret this word but I like this idea that it's guid
the journey like where the Chariot goes but not only
where like how fast like maybe things need to move
slowly maybe we need to stop and pick up some other passengers or let off some
other passengers or something like this those people that were sharing the Chariot with or whomever we were CH
saring it with but the Chariot teers maybe there's a way if it's the Dharma
it's also um wanting to go towards where there's less suffering so it's in my
mind right this this somebody that has their on their Reigns and is doing
what's best wanting what's best for us and then this idea that with Right
View running out front so the chair teer is following
Right View Right View is out in front so right view this is the first
element in the eight-fold path some of you might know and I'm using this word right not because the opposite is wrong
right means uh like the most appropriate or the most helpful or in the same way
that like um the right tool like we don't bring a hammer if we're trying to undo a screw the right tool is a
screwdriver so I'm using right in that way not as moralistically
right so rate view is a perspective or it's a frame of reference that and it
provides a simple straightforward understanding of how to bring suffering
to an end is this some of you might know that
part of right to view is the Four Noble Truths
the for so it's this recognition of this is suffering this is the arising of
suffering or this is the origin of suffering this is the cessation of suffering and this is the way to the
ending of suffering so what's out in front what the charioteer is following what the
Dharma or the teachings charer is following is this perspective or view of
the sway to suffering and this way to the ending of suffering this is the way right to Creer
Freedom this is the way to nabana this is the way to fearlessness because there's this way in
which our views our orientations our perspectives our beliefs the ways in
which we understand ourselves and the world these are like the basis on which
we make so many decisions in our lives are views and for the most part they're
unseen we don't even know we have them in fact there seem like such a inherent
part of ourselves it just seems like they're the truth or it's the Natural Way of the
world but our core views are just seem like embedded and
habitual but they might not be accurate they may not be true and they might not
lead us as clearly to the end of suffering such as views as the world is
an unsafe place I'm only worthy if I serve
others it's important to always be comfortable at all
costs it's important to never be vulnerable there's so many of these
views that we have that we might not even recognize that we have that don't
always support us so right view is this orientation to
be sensitive towards suffering what is leading towards suffering and what isn't leading towards
suffering so then the third stanza of this uh verse
goes one who has such a vehicle whether a woman or a man by means of this
vehicle is in the presence of nibana so these two lines one who has
such a vehicle whether a woman or a man they're just trying to be inclusive maybe today we would say no
matter the gender but notice that they're not
saying you have to be a monastic or that you have to come from a
certain background or there's nothing like this they're just saying whether you're on
this vehicle the vehicle is this Chariot on the straightway you with the
aold path it's this it's it's about what you do it's
kind of like the wheels of the Dharma it's kind of like where the rubber meets the road the Dharma is not as I said not
some esoteric teachings but it's how we show up in the world it's the way that where we find
more freedom and then this then the lines that this poem ends by means of this
vehicle has drawn close to nibana maybe I'll read that whole lastanza one who
has such a vehicle whether a woman or a man by means of this vehicle has drawn
close to nibana Nana being
Awakening I was thinking about this has drawn close to nibana is near nibana
they don't say that you get to nibana but you're like really
close maybe it's and I I don't have a excellent answer why this is but I was
think well maybe they don't want to give the impression that nabana is a location that it's you know someplace
over there that you'll get to later CU like nabana is found
here it's so common we have this idea we have to seek and go and find and certainly something like this uh it
suggest that to this idea that there's a path and that there's a chariot there's a little bit of a paradox here that it's
not actually over there some other time and there's this another ology that
I heard years ago and um it's really stayed with me I think it's really
powerful this idea that if you want to
get to nibana and it feels like nabana is over there we'll call that point B and you're
at Point a you're at Point a here whatever here is and you want to get to where there's complete
Freedom it turns out the way to get to point B is to be completely at Point
a right here with whatever it is so a little bit of a paradox here and
this is you know verse allows us to do this but maybe I'll end here with this idea
that you know what's being pointed to with this verse is that the way to
fearlessness is the way to niana Freedom peace and
ease and the way to nabana Freedom peace and ease includes ethical behavior and
includes views as part of wisdom you know seear ethics mental development and uh
wisdom so sometimes we feel like oh just to not to be less Fearless we just have
to have courage we just have to learn how to have courage or something like this but it might be an interesting
exploration in our own lives what is the relationship between our ethical
behavior and fear what happens if we clean up any
little areas of unethical Behavior white lies or whatever it might
be and this idea that our views what views do we have that might
be promoting some fear what would it be like to view our
experience through this idea of you know to simplify it this is leading to suffering and this is leading to less
suffering no suffering and it's interesting to maybe even use this language of leading to
because to be sure sometimes I mean we are suffering and if
you think your whole life is just to get out of suffering then you're just pursuing pleasure
and if that worked you wouldn't be here right we you were just out pursuing
pleasure nonstop right we all have tried it of course we did and it didn't work
so we found ourselves here so I don't want to give the sense
that right view is just about you know Finding you know just being suffering or not suffering but this idea of you know
feeling into our wisdom is this going the direction I want it to go or
not I'm being sensitive to that and the relationship to view and
fear so this poem that's verse maybe I'll read it I'll close with uh reading
it this one last
time the path is called the straight way and fearless as its
destination The Chariot is called unswerving fitted with wheels of
Dharma conscience is its leaning board mindfulness its upholstery I say the
teachings is the charioteer with Right View running out in
front one who has such a vehicle whether a woman or a man by means of this
vehicle is in the presence of nibana and then maybe I'll open it up
and see if there's some questions or comments this idea OFA
Samar ethical Behavior mental development which includes mindfulness
and concentration and wisdom have a role with fear support us
for find in less fear more
fearlessness hey thanks de really appreciate it quick question on the you
mentioned the you know Sila samadi PA how could you define the difference between concentration and
mindfulness yeah there there's a number of different ways we can um say this so
sometimes I like to uh say the difference this way concentration is so so often when we're
doing uh mind I'm sorry mindfulness when we start we're doing like maybe with the breath and then as we often teach it
here at IMC if there's uh something that's compelling we turn our attention
to that let's say there's a really loud sound and we'll just like say oh there's
dog barking and we kind like just rest maybe with the dog barking and notice
that and when it's no longer compelling come back to the breath with the knee hurts go to the knee come back to the
breath so in this way with mindfulness practice this whole notion of
distractions doesn't exist instead we whatever seems like to be troubling we
just turn towards and fold it into our practice we bring our attention to it and we bring our mindfulness to it so
mindfulness is inclusive whatever is arising we're paying attention to
concentration it's a little bit more exclusive we have like okay I'm going to be on the breath I'm going to be on the
breath I'm going to be on the breath I'm bring on the breath dog sparking breath breath Just Breath like we don't bring
our attention to anything else we're just stay here and a breath and we bring a sense of um
wholeness and a sense of collectedness and a sense of a centeredness around the
breath does that make sense yeah
pH so hearing all this tonight I'm really aware that it's about fearlessness not courage and in my mind
there's definitely a difference like courage is what I have to do when I'm not fearless and I got to do the thing
anyway was there that concept when this verse was written of Courage of Courage
as different from fearlessness yes and Viria which is one of the fact
uh faculties is sometimes translated as courage can be translated courage and it talks about it so very sometimes uh also
translated as energy or something like this so yeah there's that idea of Courage
also thank you for your uh talking today
about fearlessness which we all need yes
uh um [Music] I uh reflected on
one or two stories which are related to Buddha where Buddha says ahinsa
paroda um we have talked about uh you know even some like musicals and songs
from Gregory peek of India but um there is
uh I feel there are two parts to the
fearlessness for everyone around the world being
Fearless One is uh I'll quote one story can you hold the microphone just a little bit closer so I can hear uh the
story is uh about anguli Mal mhm which I
have quoted the before also so there is uh it's uh so one self
dealing with uh fear or like uh what is out there is one part of it which is
essentially courage um but the second part is also I think
equally important in which case when
angulimal thinks that okay you know I'm just using an analogy he used to chop
fingers off people and make a Garland out of it um or killing people people or you
know gouging people I mean I'm using strong language here so I hope people are able to bear with me but just to
establish a point here um it's also it was like seemed
like Buddha took this upon himself like his duty to educate anguli Mal
hey uh he called out hey stop
um because he was preparing to do this whatever he was preparing to
do and Buddha it was like a transformational thing he
said um I have stopped but when will you stop so it was transformational for
him that he was educated he learned that it is a bad thing to gouge people's eyes
or chop people's heads or fingers or whatever or like
eat you know uh meat or whatever I'm just causing I'm saying violence is a
bad thing I mean there is a book I have quoted before the dance of
Shiva where the I mean the author Anand Kumar Swami he goes on to say violence
even in thoughts is equivalent to violence that is also Buddha is
saying um in there are 14 essays over there um on all philosophies all
religions so the point is it's it's actually it's a it's a
two-fold uh matter one is upon oneself the fear myself I um let's say I a
chariot here I am I can be Fearless uh uh but then there is also
like the passengers that I'm carrying it's my duty to kind of educate them
that I see the yeah but I'll say one thing though about the story about angula for those of you who don't know
angul Mala is like this mass murderer and he's going to kill the Buddha and he's like running towards the Buddha and
the Buddha seems to be just casually walking but and Gully Mala can't catch up to him and Gully Mala says hey stop
and that Buddha says I have stopped you stop but so angula kind of saw that the
Buddha a was not afraid of him and B um couldn't be caught and then kind of
unfold like the Buddhas had stopped doing things that were unethical or had
stopped you know all kinds of other things and that's why anguli Mala couldn't uh catch him and and also there
was like some Supernatural thing happening there maybe I don't know and so it was when
anguli MOA saw something that was really different saw that there was a really different way that he then became a
eventually became a follower of the Buddha and became awakened eventually so
this story it's a very famous story so yeah there's different ways in
which fear shows up yes there's this definitely thank you for say get rid of it also you know I guess I mean if there
are people like you know I I don't know if we should be sending PE monks around
the world to talk about these stories and people to be
awakened thank you thank you thank you so thank you all for your time and I
wish you all the lovely rest of the evening thank
you