great so hello and welcome everyone lovely to see you lovely to be with you
In This Moment In Time whatever time zone whether you're in Thailand it's 8
A.M um or you're in Hawaii
um or west coast East Coast it's lovely I just love the hellos that we have at
the beginning just warms my heart when the song assembles and we all say hello so
so with that the sense of being together or being here being here in this moment
in time being here in this moment in time so what I'd like to invite us to
practice with today uh thanks Amy Amy says it's 3 P.M yes your
time baby in uh um in Hawaii so whatever the time zone
is and being here in this moment in time In This Moment In Time the sense of
presence to to practice with
the joy of being here being here and now and tuning into the joy of being here
and now exactly as it is as one of the Brahma viharas the the
four heavenly abodes the four practices of the heart meta loving kindness being the first one
compassion the second one vicarious Joy or sympathetic Joy being the third one
Equanimity the fourth one the practice of Joy sympathetic Joy this
delight Joy taking Delight in our own Good Fortune taking joy in other
people's Good Fortune it's just such a generous way to go through life this
sense of joy for what is good here what's good elsewhere so
this activating cultivating this this to Joy
or ourselves being right here right now and
and I mentioned I think a couple of nights ago this term for us to cultivate
Jomo the joy of missing out instead of the fear of missing out fomo fomo is so
common in in our culture this fear of missing out and this this sense of Envy
like I want what other people have whereas in this practice we cultivate
the joy of being right here right now loving the sense of presence
and the gift of presence calms as much as it might be
available but just the gift of presence and being in this body with all its gifts and challenges
exploring the joy of this and and a way of gently letting go of
whatever else might be happening because at any time in the world so many things are happening of course and we can't be
everywhere um all the time and yet if we are right
here and taking delight and joy in the sense of presence right here it can be
so delicious we don't have to be in the past in the future anywhere else this is
the most delicious most joyous most nourishing place to be
right here in our hearts so so that's what I would like to invite us to to
contemplate and cultivate Jomo the joy of being here just here the joy of
missing out on everything else may all beings be well happy may they have joy
in whatever they're doing in in the midst of their presence in their moments
of being aliveness so so it's really a Counter Culture Act of cultivating Jomo
instead of follow so we're counter-cultural here in a way cultivating peace ease and joy Delight
in what is right here so so that's my little darmet and I'll
share some invitations as we practice so let's begin
ah let's begin and arise let's begin and Rising our bodies
arrive in this moment in time
land land in this moment in time
opening our hearts relaxing the body
breeding This Moment In Time
nowhere to go nothing else to do but to just be here here
aware conscious amazing Let the Body be relaxed
if you find that the mind is wandering the past the future the little puppy running around
be kind to the puppy it's okay you're right
and celebrate the moment of realizing that you are here I am here you know on
these Maps where there is a pointer and a big star you are here
I am here you are here this body in this moment in time on this planet
you are here nowhere else none of the past or future you are here
are here
and opening our hearts and celebrating I am here
I am here and even if it does not feel like a
celebration maybe it feels boring oh I'm here
it's amazing that you're here that I'm here
the fact that so many cause and conditions have come together
for me to be created at all
Stardust I am Stardust to be here
I am Stardust I'm here
conscious aware knowing how amazing
it's simple a simple joy in life
of just being here relaxing softening the body the heart the mind
exhaling ah I'm here
last year with the breath sensations of the breath sensations of
this body
let there be a quiet soft
quiet Delight
being with the breath in this body
a quiet simple Grace
easier than you think
there be ease in the body exhaling um
pleasure the Delight of just being here
the moment expands into Infinity
here here
the joy of presence
the joy of being undistracted here even for a moment
the longer we stay here here now it deepens it opens up to other
dimensions
and nourishing indented Joy
Joy of being here just here simply here
but if you meet this moment this being here
with a smile try it on wear a smile on your face a
meeting this moment Delight this moment right here with a smile
bake it till you become it the joy of being here
not wanting to be anywhere else
this moment deeply present here the joy of it
is there even has there been a moment second of
contentment just one is enough
here simply sitting being breathed
In This Moment can be one of contentment just dipping our toes
it's okay it's all okay not only okay
but enough maliciously enough
the joy and gentlement
of here now
and as we turn to end our sit together
letting go of whatever happened or did not happen
for any judgment you showed up as best as you were able
to hurray the joy of showing up as best as we're able to
and we are planting seeds trust that you're planting seeds
they ripen they mature in their own time not our time
us this may I
may I nourish The Joy the Delight of presence
just simply present
amazing Grace of being present
yeah I wake up
the depth and breath of possibilities may all beings
everywhere may they awaken may they be free
including myself
[Music]
everyone thanks for your practice ah
well I certainly feel more present more joyous
the joy of of presence of just being here not being scattered wishing you
were elsewhere here there past present future Joy of just
this such a deep nourishing Joy
wish I could we could share this with the whole world especially young people
nowadays on social media they keep wishing they were here and there and actually are
being right here there's so much nourishment and contentment I was seeing surgeon general's warning
about the state of mental health of of the young people especially due to
social media use which really brings up a sense of formal fear of missing out
being here there is really the opposite of that is the joy of being just here so
much contentment so much peace you know this we know this
so thank you for cultivating this deep deep wisdom knowledge Joy as a community
and give it away give your joy away give your smiles away give your calm away to
those who need it spread it okay
so we have some time um now for
for the joy of just being here present in community in small groups
and you can say a few words about your practice if you want you can just be
silent silently present with one another that's perfectly fine
just compassionately kindly joyous and just appreciating the miracle of being
here and the Miracle of other human beings being here too these amazing
um conscious beings so as always please only speak from your
own experience um I statements not directing not
leading others um asking questions to show up maybe with a nugget about
yeah the joy of just being here how do you experience that you can say something maybe a little nugget
or say pass make space for others somebody else to say something somebody
else to say something in go in and out of Silence together just really feeling
into the presence not your head talking blah blah blah you're speaking for your
own benefit not for anybody else's so don't feel like you have to educate or impress or or
give them information no you're just sharing oh yeah this is how the joy of this present moment shows up for me ah
my heart feels relaxed more at peace there is no
pushing and pulling or however it shows up for you so so with that and let's Go reverse
alphabetical order just to make it easy uh the decision making and I'm gonna
create the rooms and um yeah take care of each other take
care of yourselves take take care take care so important to take care
be kind all right I'm gonna open the rooms and here we go
okay all the rooms are closed everybody is back welcome back everyone and we
have some time for Reflections you can type them in chat if you type them to me
privately I will read only a reflection not your name so it'll be private you can type it to everyone you can also
raise your hand especially if you haven't spoken for a while and happy I would love to hear from you your
Reflections why did you discover in this practice was is there something that opened up for you or maybe something was
challenging and one of you sent in chat when I become the change I want to see
in the world the world smiles back at me happy to see me coming I love that of
course yeah the world smiles back at me happy to see me coming
the joy of being here the joy of this present moment the joy of missing out
and just being here in one place oh kill says not much conversation in
our group everyone was too calm and relaxed
that makes me smile and laugh it's just that's the contentment right not not
much needs to be said like oh yeah we're just happy to be here together we're holding we're being in community
together so that's sweet and of course if your group was more talkative and sharing that's perfectly fine too it's
all good it's all good so any Reflections you like to share especially
if you tend to pull back and not speak much what's happy hour you're invited if
you like
what did you discover in this practice the joy of just being here or the joy of missing out is quite counter-cultural
Reflections complaints what the heck do you mean by Joy of
missing out I hope I already explained it but anyway uh oh you're sweet Don
says Nikki you're awesome thank you Don you're awesome thank you for your practice
fossil please hi thank you I um
I just every moment just being here and
you know following the instructions to see the joy and being here just brought it a sense of gratitude for
every moment as A Moment Like an opportunity to to learn how to deal with the next
moment in the next moment the next that was nice thank you Father ah I'm feeling into the
the space of gratitude that you took us in to with in into which with with your
reflection because you are speaking from that space of gratitude at this moment and then this moment and this moment
thank you this was lovely swazil
Jean please I just found that to be really Blissful
and um I and I I think it was helped by my heating pad and the sun coming in my
window and um I was just so happy to cultivate that with your guidance but I I found
myself wondering what if my neighbor's music was cranked up or I was feeling chronic pain and I
know there's various different instructions yeah included about how to sit with pain Etc but in this in
particular this Jomo um how do we take it to those times when
things aren't optimal absolutely thank you for this question Gene and somebody
else also sent this just uh now in chat so I'm going to combine the question you
asked with theirs let me read it out loud could you remind us of the joy of being with difficult moments I have
experienced it briefly as impermanence of those moments but could use a refresher beautiful yeah thank you for
both of those questions both Gene and the anonymous questions so
so um when we are with not just the pleasant
moments or or the neutral moments the joy of of those are more apparent to us
but when something difficult is happening something difficult in the
body or some difficult emotion there is a
a dignity there is a dick it feels dignified there is it there is a joy and
I'm going to call it the joy there's a sense of dignity to be with what is difficult instead of pushing it away
instead of being antagonistic with it and instead of fighting with it or
hating it or pushing it away to make space for what is difficult and being
with what is here that the body relaxes the heart relaxes
um to open up to what is here and
um having having worked with a lot of physical pain myself in my practice
there and and even now as I'm speaking with you yeah the body is tired and achy
and quiet actually yeah achy right now and then there is there is this Joy of opening up to it ah the heart relaxes my
heart is relaxing as I'm opening up to yeah this body is really hurting right
now and it's okay there's just if I was hating it and I wish it didn't hurt and
it was would be terrible ouch ouch ouch is the double it's all the second and third and fourth arrows
but where I'm actually opened up to a there's a joy there's a delight there's
a dignity there's a uh a brightness of being present with what is difficult so
the joy can actually be present with the difficulty and this blows our mind away
I remember when I discovered this at first from myself the Opposites being
present at the same time it doesn't have to be just pain or just Joy both of them can be present at the same time and
there's so many invitations in Buddhism to ex to experience the Opposites at the
same time it's it's it's blown my mind away to be able to do that
um and that the mind is able to hold both of these dichotomies you can feel
for example uh feel heaviness and lightness you know it's like either oh either heaviness of the body or the
lightness but no actually the mind can open up to to both at the same time and
it blows your mind when you see that's possible or joy and sorrow joy and and
pain at the same time Your Capacity expands so
foreign so that's what I would like to share and uh that is that is that helpful Gene
you're well yes okay good okay good enough okay great um and also the person who sent it in in
uh chat you're welcome to save that that's that hopefully opens something up for you
Peggy please
um you actually just spoke to everything I was experiencing uh thank you although mine wasn't quite
as um trifling enthusiastic as you sound um just a lot
of resistance and but there was a dignity about coming back coming back and it is not what I
wanted to do I wanted to leave the beginning many times but um so it was
interesting and and there were moments of joy and that sense of dignity and also that
that muscle can grow by by being here when I don't want to you well part of me
doesn't want to in those opposites that you mentioned so I really appreciate that night a lot of
those things came to mind from all the previous happy hours I've been to and just to try to have
some kindness towards all those dimensions of self non-self
beautiful thank you Peggy thank you so much for your practice report I I I'm loving you
reporting the the push and pull that I don't want to be here I want to leave I'm just going to leave happy now stay
stay dear I'll stay come back with this difficulty stay and then there is just
as you said there is a sense of um dignity there is a sense of dignity
and oh yeah I'm here and then there's the sense of expansion of the heart that
oh I stayed and then there are the there are moments of Joy just as you've said they're moments of joy of staying of
knowing oh actually there is a sense of trust that grows oh yes it is possible
it is possible for me to stay with and make space for make
space for what is challenging and it loses its power what it's challenging it
loses its power a little bit it softens it a little bit it's still here but it doesn't have the megaphone to scream all
right it just it can be present along with other things yeah yay and you're here you may you you
yeah you showed up and you continued to show up for yourself this is a celebration
so much making this space thank you Peggy so much Beauty and
dignity in that thank you for your practice and and your practice report sharing with others
yeah and Claire it's the last one before we close
thank you I was going to share something actually very similar it's funny you would bring this up it happened on
Friday I'm in a new job and something went terribly wrong that was the result of my not doing something yeah it was
not a good thing um and you know I offered to help and didn't get any takers
and I went back to my desk and I was perfectly okay in the past I would have fallen apart I
would have just been this big Heap on the desk and said I calm down and I knew
it would work out and you know it wasn't all my fault and it but it was like
being two people and I was I was sitting there and I couldn't figure out what was going on because I'd never felt like
this before in a catastrophe and I was just sitting there this is so strange I
feel perfectly fine and I'm sure it was exactly what you're talking about that was a beautiful
experience actually Claire this is lovely I felt responsible but I didn't feel
like I was gonna die you know oh my God that and would detail I see people who
are who are just share you know hearts are coming on the zoom space
um bill says Claire I've experienced that at work too it's great yes as you said so you still feel responsible of
course you feel responsible but as you said you don't feel like you're gonna die it's not you know it's not a sense
of panic and sense of oh this is awful and all the like yeah something is wrong
but there's a sense of equanimity and because actually especially when there is equanimity we can take more
responsibility instead of beating ourselves up because we can really help out when we're
completely devastated and we're in fight or flight or freeze but when we have
this calmness and it feels strange at first oh beautiful
yay thanks so much for sharing that this just makes me so happy thank you well
this is so great this is so lovely thank you thanks Claire and then um well it says such a good reminder
that change is possible and this practice creates change over time yes
yes yes the meditation practice actually changes our brains indeed and a couple
of Reflections from our YouTube Friends thank you for the practice a question came up for me oh I think this is maybe
this was an earlier one I didn't see if we experience pain and suffering in the present moment how can we practice bringing joy to it oh yeah I already
answered that one thank you uh uh yeah someone else is being and then
the same person thank you so much dear Nikki that was very helpful good so I'm glad the explanation was helpful and another person says being here makes me
feel so blessed this partic this practice makes my heart swell ah that is
such a lovely note to end on this practice makes my heart swell too with
you as as this beautiful Community online on zoom on YouTube on Audio
Dharma thank you all thank you for your practice for your cultivation may you cultivate the joy of the present moment
whatever the conditions are whatever the conditions are may you all be may we all
be may all beings be happy safe and free
thanks everyone take good care