okay good morning welcome welcome
good afternoon good evening wherever you are whatever time it is
even future your future self maybe even listening to this welcome welcome
so today I'm going to continue on this theme of The Poetry of practice be introducing some poems
one I'll introduce during the guided meditation and I'll just drop in and then I'll
repeat it during the dermit and we'll talk about a little bit and provide some other poems that are on a similar theme
but all about you know this idea of practice and there's something about poetry that
allows for this we might say this compactness of expression like there's a
lot into just a few words or a few lines and there's this way that to have this
competence requires some directness or some simplicity
and then maybe in the same way that there are we have a with meditation and
non-distracted mind so this kind of Simplicity and this pointedness that we
find with poetry might be in some ways similar to a
meditation practice and we might even imagine that the poet
has a still mind in order to really hone in on some of the right words or the
Expressions as well as the one who's reading the poem
they might be someone who like reading the poem requires like a dropping of way of all the extraneous spurious thoughts
and instead it's kind of like brought to this directness of what's being pointed
to so in some ways poetry and meditation are just a natural
companions so I'll say that as an introduction
and I'll um let's just uh begin the guided meditation now
so taking a moment to settle in
and feeling the sensations of sitting
I like to begin with this feeling connected and grounded too
this location and this moment
so feeling the pressure against the body
maybe their the feet are touching the ground feeling the groundedness of the feet
whatever they're touching
maybe the back of legs are touching
chair the cushion feeling the connection
the buttocks sitting on the chair
cushion the bench couch bed whatever it might be
most of us spend a good portion of our days sitting I pray in a chair or some other
way it's a way that we can imbue this experience of feeling the pressure
against the body with some awareness
sitting feels like this
and maybe the back is resting against the back of the chair or couch whatever it might be
and we feel that connection also
and if the back isn't being supported can you feel that sense of uprightness
this internal support the spine
holding up the body
and can we inhabit this body with aliveness with presence
it's like a life to the body and the way it feels right now
you might notice there's some areas of tension some tightness
maybe the shoulders or up a little bit
can we let the shoulder blades slide down the back
and maybe took the chin just a tiny bit
such a small movement that maybe no one would notice that you
didn't but we took the chin and then moving the
chin back straight back
it's up to the back of the neck
and a review small subtle but impactful way
sometimes tension is held around the jaw or around the eyes
checking in with the Sensations on the face
you don't have to make them be different but it might be that bringing some
awareness allows for some softening
or just being with this experience of you might say bodily life
right now opening to it allowing it
as best we can
and is it possible to set the sense of direction
the attitude that we're using or is present
as one of kindness
there'll be some warmth some softness
just for this meditation period
can there be some care openness
and then allowing that attention to rest on the anchor
for most of us the anchor will be the sensations of breathing
for some it might be sounds or the body
but tuning into the experience of breathing
the body breathes we don't have to
make it breathe we don't have to change the breathing
we're just noticing the sensations of breathing
what would it be like to give yourself over to the sensations of breathing
feeling the complete inhale
and the complete exhale
and the transitions between inhales and exhales
foreign
than when the mind wanders as it's apt to do
within this attitude this field of kindness and warmth
just very gently simply Begin Again
with the sensations of breathing
foreign all right
so I'm going to drop in a poem
you don't need to do anything with this poem
just allow it to land
touch you or not it's okay it's okay
whatever Horizons
and the poem goes like this
when everyone else was meditating [Music] I'd be outside
circling the whole finally I went to confess
I'm hopeless I said
the Elder none smiled just keep going
she said nothing stays in orbit forever
if this circling is all you have why not make this circling your home
I did as she told me and went on circling the whole
if you find yourself partly in and partly out
if you find yourself drawn to this path and also drawing a way
I can assure you you're in good company
just keep going sometimes the most direct path
isn't a straight line
if you find yourself partly in and partly out
if you find yourself drawn to this path and also drawing away
I can assure you you're in good company just keep going
sometimes the most direct path isn't a straight line
foreign foreign
foreign
[Music]
okay so welcome everybody
so in the guided meditation I dropped in a poem
that's where I'm continuing this series on the Poetry of practice
and um it's a poem that's written by Maddie winegast
his last name is w-e-i-n-g-a-s-t and it's from the book
The First free women and Maddie looked at the poems of the
terrygata that is the first Awakening poems I should say The Awakening poems
of nuns that are preserved in this Buddhist tradition
and Maddie was inspired by those poems and leffert wrote his own poems that are
based on those but to include some Modern thinkings and some Modern twists
and so they're not translations necessarily but just uh use
them as inspiration and I think these poems are just wonderful because Maddie
is pointing to something that we recognize in practice but maybe we haven't you know articulated so well or
maybe even understood so well so the poem that I dropped in during the
meditation maybe I'll say it's pointing to you that we get to be exactly who we
are with this practice it's not asking us to be somebody different it's not
asking us to completely transform ourselves into something or somebody
that we're not I love this this is like so important I feel like it's asking us to move
towards authenticity and to cultivate the skillful the
wholesome The Helpful parts of ourselves but not to pretend like there isn't
other parts of ourself instead we just fold in everything into our practice and
this is the way forward so sometimes this uh poem is pointing to
that sometimes we feel stuck sometimes we feel like we just can't get anywhere
we think we should be different than how we are but we can't stop being how we are and therefore we kind of like feel
stuck like oh I shouldn't be doing this way or you should be doing that and not
be doing this and just kind of find ourselves going around around in circles
not really having this way forward and this poem also points to oh it can
be helpful to practice with others especially some when we're feeling stuck
others whether it's a teacher or somebody else that's on the path or maybe they're not even on the path but
they're a good listener and they're sensitive to for them to recognize maybe what's going on with us the stuckness
that we feel and maybe it takes somebody else
to point out something that we haven't seen to help us get unstuck
but I'll say a little bit more about this after the poem but uh here's the poem again
when everyone else was meditating I'd be outside circling the hall
finally I went to confess I'm a hopeless I said
the Elder not smiled just keep going she said nothing stays
in orbit forever if this circling is all you have what
why not make this circling your home I did as she told me and went on Sir
clean the hall if you find yourself partly in and
partly out if you find yourself drawn to this path and also drawing away
I can assure you you're in good company just keep going
sometimes the most direct path isn't a straight line
so I like that the poet is using this word circling and and this uh poem and
we can't imagine it might be literal circling like walking around and around the whole you know never quite you know
coming into the meditation session or maybe there's this way we like sign up for Retreats but never quite go or might
be a way in which we put on our calendar yeah I'm gonna get up and early and listen to those talks or I'm going to
stay blade and attend those Derma talks whatever your time zone might be or whatever the offering might be there
might be a way in which we feel like okay I'm going to do this but yet we
just find ourselves kind of circling around this of course is not uncommon
that especially you know this path as you know it's not the usual way in which
we do things so it might take some circling around before we can maybe
settle in so this might be one way we might understand this word circling that the
poet is using here but maybe circling also means the sense of being stuck
like not getting anywhere I'm just maybe moving a little bit but it just feels like it's a circle like there's no sense
of um forward Direction This Center movement
and then something that we might think about or consider that this feeling of
stuckness of not getting anywhere of just circling most likely
is related to holding to views
holding on to beliefs having these particular Notions that we
are maybe on uh intentionally or maybe at the top of
mind and maybe even unknowingly these ideas that we're holding on to
because views have a sense of embeddedness
a sense of inertia this like resistance to change that's
partly what makes them views is that they're there and we may not even recognize them and they're not shifting
maybe I'll say the only things in our experience ever
that don't shift or change our views
everything else is changing our experience is changing things we see hear taste touch
they're changing all of our experiences are changing only views like Notions we have are
things that don't change so if we have this feeling of stuckness there's a view
that we're holding on to that we're not quite noticing
so in this poem practitioner she has this view I'm hopeless she has this idea
right I'm hopeless and implicit in this idea is like I can't do this everybody else can but I
can't do this and we might recognize well okay that's just the hindrance of doubt
this is a part of practice doubt I can say it feels like this it feels
like this hopelessness it feels like wanting to give up it feels like that I
somehow and separate from everybody else I can't do this but everybody else can
something deficient or insufficient in me
and so what can we do when we feel doubt there's a few things one is I would say
is to investigate is there a way there's two things that
we can notice what what does this doubt feel like this sense of hopelessness maybe it feels
like this heaviness in the shoulders or this way in which there's a sense of
I don't know giving up it's kind of deflation it's one way we can investigate the
actual experience another way we can investigate we have
this sense of Doubt is to maybe uh see
if there's a question that we can formulate
is there is there something like we can hold maybe like boil down to this doubt
instead of I'm hopeless is there something like why
or maybe the question could be something like everybody else having this difficulty
is this part of the path is to recognize how out of control our minds are
is it the case that in the beginning practice is difficult or some days are
easier than others I just offer these as suggestions so that could be a second way to work with
doubt so this feeling is stuck this feeling of just circling is certainly not getting
in anywhere most likely related to holding on to views
one view can be in this poem the person has a sense of I'm hopeless
to this view which we might understand is doubt doubt about one's capability
and there's doubt you can investigate this is a perfect antidote for doubt I'm
not going to ask oh just believe that's not what this practice is about practice is investigating what what is doubt feel
like and what specifically do you have doubt about there's another view that's getting held
on to in this poem that's supporting this stuckness and that is the idea that things can't
change I'm hopeless it will always be like this it can never
be different like implicit in this idea of I'm hopeless means there will be no change
now this idea that well this is permanent and of course there's a part of us that
knows oh Everything Changes it's not true that yet anybody is
hopeless that's absolutely not true but it feels like that sometimes
but can we notice that this is a view that things are not going to change that
is what's being held on to so when we feel stuck with practice when we feel like oh we're
just circling and circling we can ask ourselves is there a view here that's not being seen
and it's chances are it's a view that's just under the surface
and so it might be something that we could drop in during our meditation practice what view is not being seen
here and we can just tune in to the
experience that we're having and that's just right into the practice just what's actually happening right now
maybe one last thing that I'll say about this uh poem this idea of circling is that if there
are seasons of practice there are and a season May last one day
one week one month one decade different for everybody but there might be seasons of practice in which there's
a lot of learning and there's excitement and we're consuming all kinds of information listening to lots of Derma
talks this enthusiasm and wanting to understand
there might be a season of practice in which we just really want to sit and explore the Mind explore this experience
maybe listen to a lot of guided meditations there might be a season of practice in which we just want to sit
without guided meditations and there might be a season of practice
in which we feel like Community is more important than being alone with our
sitting in meditation or reading Dharma books or listening to Dharma talks so is there a way that we can respect
that there are seasons of practice a lot of a retreat practice no retreat practice
it doesn't always look the same so whenever we feel stuck maybe there's
a way to just notice that there's different ways in which practice shows up
so maybe I'll just read this poem for this uh one last time
when everyone else was meditating I'd be outside circling the hall
finally I want to confess I'm hopeless said
the Elder nun smiled just keep going she said nothing stays
in orbit forever if this circling is all you have why not
make this circling your home I did as she told me and went on
circling the hall if you find yourself partly in and
partly out if you find yourself drawn to this path and also drawing away
I can assure you you're in good company just keep going
sometimes the most direct path isn't a straight line
thank you and I'll see you tomorrow for some more
poems thank you for your practice