greetings greetings everyone greetings friends my name is Nikki mergafori and I joined
this virtual space from Mountain View California on seated olonieland and uh
I'm delighted to be supporting um the Sangha for this week while I mean
everyone greetings friends all right let's try it and I joined we have some problems hold
on space from Mountain View California on seatedland and uh there okay sorry
about that I also have an iPad going and it was not silenced yay there we go
technical problems um so hello again hello again uh
as I was saying um happy to be supporting the Sangha sitting together this week as as Gill
travels and uh hope you're all well hope you are well and this week
um I'm delighted I'm looking forward to sharing teachings on
um one of the path factors and um
the path Factor that's very important and we engage with every day even if we
don't get the chance to formally sit and meditate but we always engage with
speech so why speech or write speech I'll say much more about it in the
dormant but that is the theme for uh career this week and uh very important
theme so let's let's just begin let's just begin and meditate together
ah arriving arriving and Landing Landing in our bodies
In This Moment In Time arriving together
now letting go letting go of whatever has come before
maybe dreams or getting ready for sitting or if you're in a different time zone whatever has happened
letting go also of the future of the plans for the day
you can pick them up later tell them you will pick them up later thank you
but not now giving our hearts fully completely
to this practice in this moment
noticing if there is tension anywhere in the body
and if there is kindly gently
caressingly
let it be released softened relaxed
really taking the time to befriend this body In This Moment In Time
hello dear buddy how are you where are you tight my dear
an inviting inviting these areas to release to relax
really taking time not rushing to the next thing but really
taking our time lovingly lovingly with the body
letting the breath be received in the abdomen and the whole body and
all the areas where there might be tightness or
holding let the breath be life-giving relaxing soothing
and if there's any internal noting or conversation or
or speech really in general notice the tone notice the
quality of it is it kind
it's a gentle or harsh this internal speech
Let There Be kindness towards yourself with your inner speech with your
breath every breath
calming soothing settling Awakening
cultivating
and if thinking arises just notice its tone notice its tone
not unmesh with the content
notice the quality of the tone release release the thought
release the body that might have become tense and begin again
notice what quality is present in the mind and art
call Restless
bored
happy sad
how does it show up in the body
and we make space for everything whatever is present
relax release make space for everything to arise
stay for a while pass it's all okay all okay
such is the nature of Being Human
In This Moment including it all
your full catastrophe with heart with expansiveness
patience and wisdom
and as we approach the end of the sitting
noticing what's present
and celebrating anymore goodness that's present
gratitude calm spaciousness
kindness wisdom the beautiful qualities of the heart
if their challenges challenging emotions
present
in the mind and the Heart it's okay bringing some kindness to them
bringing some kindness to them
holding them with kindness with compassion
and letting go of any judgment or expectation before what this period should have been must
have been didn't happen let all that go not necessary you showed up
yay that's all that matters appreciating yourself
and the whole Sangha
further support
and together offering our goodness
to all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere
you see happy healthy and happy East
may all beings including ourselves be free
thanks everyone for your practice
so for the
Reflections today as I mentioned for today and for this week I'd like to
uh share teachings on wise speech
which is a very important part of the Eightfold Path
and as I briefly mentioned even if we don't get the chance to to uh perhaps
sit in a particular day have a formal setting formal meditation
practice we pretty much every day engage with speech either externally
with others or internally the way we talk to ourselves the way we treat
ourselves so speech is always happening internally
um at least if not externally and
speech forms are
our personality forms our mind forms the person
who we are who we become and sometimes actually our speech may not correspond
to uh who we think we are and
um and through actually through cultivating wise speech we can
um as a formal practice taking it on as a formal practice
not as a yeah yeah yeah I'm truthful enough but no actually taking it as a
formal practice we can really engage in shape and and support our development
it's it's it's a beautiful and I don't want to make it tight serious but it's
it's it's a profound practice why speech is a profound practice
really profound in shaping who we are what we are so
there are various there's definitions for what wise speech for uh what why
speech is and the Buddha also teaches about um or ways to questions to ask ourselves
and this week I will go through them all um and through multiple lists the Buddha
has different lists and if you combine those different lists what one list has four definitions and one has five and if
you combine them we end up with actually six guidelines six questions to ask
ourselves um and I'll combine given that we have five days in the week I'll come one day
I'll cover two of them so that we can cover all five all six
so um actually first I want to say one more thing about uh speech um so in the
Eightfold Path uh why speech shows up pretty much right
after wise perspective or wise View and wise
intention so of course the root of everything is our perspective how we see
something how how what our view of the world is our wise view wise perspective
and then Our intention coming having make forming an intention for action and
then the third one is why speech so it's really right after the the first two
basic fundamental Holdings you know what everything what what holds the whole
practice up is really our view our perspective our perception and
um and Our intention our Compass have what we said our compass compass to be
so with why speech
in order to practice it I would say two general um uh directions that will apply to
every question that we'll we'll cover this week first is to actually make a commitment
make a commitment to engaging with why speeches making a commitment so that
commitment is the the second path Factor wise intention intending this is what
I'm going to do I'm going to engage to speak skillfully appropriately
not gossip not lie not be unkind
etc etc and we'll go through them so first is really the intention we make
at the outset and then later in real time as we're actually speaking you
pause we feel into our bodies if we are um about to shape the truth or let's
tell a white lie or or gossip feeling into our bodies what's going on am I
stressed do I feel threatened am I trying to self-aggrandize
feeling into the body of sweetheart yeah interesting that's what's going on okay
and can we reconnect with Our intention can we reconnect with Our intention
so these are the basic ways to engage
and then one more thing to say about the tri um in Pali in the Eightfold Path
um appropriate speech or why speech is Sama vacha Sama vacha and the word Sama is
sometimes translated as a right right speech uh why speech appropriate speech and
early in my practice when I heard right it's it sounded so Puritan right speaking wrong speak whereas actually
the word summer really means appropriate as in using the appropriate tool so for
example the appropriate tool for hitting the Bell is is the you know the Bell Striker uh it's not a pen or a mug it's
the appropriate tool so what's the appropriate speech what is the right appropriate
um or wise uh Speech in a given situation
foreign [Music]
right so okay so
today I like to cover the first um in the time remaining there's so much
I want to say but um the for the first guideline really is
um is it truthful is it true and factual
and truthfulness is the only
[Music] um um moral commitment really is the the
commitment to truthfulness it is said that in the progression of a
bodhisattva uh from going through many many many many lifetimes uh to become a
full Buddha the bodhisattva uh truthfulness the commitment to the truth
is so important that that's the only moral precept that a bodhisattva cannot
and does not uh break so so this not only symbolically but um but
this the sense that our commitment to the truth really is the foundation of the whole path it's a really Foundation
of our Awakening um in in our Humanity through many many
lifetimes if we have a funny relationship to the truth yeah that's is
our commitment to Awakening is a little not quite straightforward so so so the
commitment to truthfulness to truthfulness and the Buddha talked about how
dangerous it is actually how lying is dangerous because it it has leads to a
slippery slope of more um lying more complicated behaviors you
have to tell more lies to cover the first one and and more moral corruptitude and actually there is
um there is research that supports that and what before I tell you about the research which is actually fascinating
um also I wanted to mention that as we know when we tell a lie
um it it really um uh betrays trust it betrays trust in
relationship and others have trouble trusting us later as Nietzsche said I'm
not upset that you lied to me I'm upset that from now on I can't believe you
very powerful words so
so I want to tell you about a um daddy that's fascinating so in the study
um and I'll tell a very brief version here basically um the researchers wanted to study lying
and how uh can progress how it can impact the the brain Etc so they made up
they created a setup a a situation uh where the subjects were tempted to
lie or tempted to lie just a little bit to get some um uh Financial reward which was again
tiny so at first the participants lied a little
bit they exaggerated a tiny bit they had to estimate the number of pennies in a
jar etc etc won't get into the complicated setup um so at first they they upped it just a
little bit a tiny bit and when they opted a little bit their
amygdala the amygdala part of the brain that really is is is
um it is said to be the alarm uh uh part of the alarm network of the brain you
know fear and and and also this so so there was a sense of oh a discomfort like ah the amygdala would engage when
when people lied a little bit like okay this is I don't want to lie but I did like uncomfortable there's a sense of
discomfort in the body yeah as the experiment progressed
well people when people have had lied their light their lies became bigger bigger and bigger and so that by the end
of the experiment they were just widely overestimating the number of the pennies by more than if you know 50 or so just
it's snowballed really lying snowballed but what's amazing actually is that
they're amygdala became less reactive
that's profound so their body didn't feel as comfortable they didn't
feel as uncomfortable lying anymore they had trained their bodies they had
trained their heart they had trained their minds they had trained themselves to feel more comfortable with lying
and they had changed through their behavior
they had changed their Compass because our bodies are in many ways our moral compass have you
decide have you figured that you know with mindfulness of the body we feel into what's happening in the body and
really it's our Arts are it's our tuning fork it's our tuning fork but through
our actions we can shape and form our bodies to become either less or more
sensitive to our moral conduct to our Awakening towards us we can become more and less
sensitive to our Humanity to our goodness wow that
is astounding and and not surprising right we know that
um so so commitment to truthfulness really is is is is Paramount really the
first and foremost of these of why speech invitation and I
also want to um mention that um in samsutas it's not just is it true
the question to ask ourselves um what I'm about to say is it true is it true what I'm about to say it's actually is
it true and factual so that Nuance of is it factual is
actually is a very important Nuance so so the truth is not relative it's not my
truth it's your truth because yes we all have our perceptions and perspectives but the Buddha suggests that we actually
um examine is is it supportable is is this what what I consider to be the truth is
this supportable by facts oh this person is mean they they meant to hurt me
wait a minute are we attributing or is it really supported by facts is it just
our perceptions our feelings yes it is true we were hurt yes we can say that
but can we attribute uh intentionality or is it that okay well they said this I
said that this is so it's like a third person conversation essentially you know they're in in actually um
there's one book that I love and highly recommend is difficult conversations and
in whenever you're about what you need to have and we need to have difficult conversations in our lives a lot
of course not they may not necessarily be difficult but but you know impactful
conversation and for example in this book really which to me is a beautiful Dharma book talks about how uh we
separate our the impact that something has had in us from the intentionality so
one part of the conversation is okay why do we perceive something to be and then we can put ourselves in the other
person's shoes what we perceive things to happen from their perspective and then there is a third person
conversation which is the objective just just objectively what happened they said
that I said this they did that just very simple without any interpretation
without any attribution of intentionality just it's it's objective objective so so this um
uh edition of is it true and factual is [Music]
um uh is it is a very important Nuance that that the Buddha the brilliant Buddha uh
ads okay a lot more to say um happy to be practicing together and
sharing the Dharma take good care have a wonderful day and looking forward to
continuing tomorrow be well