good morning good morning Global IMC Sangha
how are you today as always it's just lovely to see all
the names and morning good morning global imc's excuse the feedback
as always it's just lovely to see all the names
[Music] use the feedback
as always it's just that we need to see all the means
[Music]
I just love seeing all the greetings
sorry about the echo there it is an imperfect process using
technology to connect with the rest of the world but gosh it has some beautiful beautiful qualities to it doesn't it
so I'm just waiting to hear if the sound is okay so when you get a chance please
um give me a sound check to make sure it's no longer looping or distorted on your end
foreign
thank you wonderful
so
great wonderful so the invitation is to
um I don't know how it feels to be helpful giving feedback with this found
and notice how it feels to be in Connection in connection with this
far-flung virtual Sangha that this community is built
over these past years
and then drinking that in Gathering it up
and when you're ready bringing it into your heart and softening your eyes
perhaps closing them
doing whatever works for you to settle in settle into meditation
perhaps one or two slightly longer slower breaths
allowing your belly to relax
really allowing the exhale to release let go
any excess tension
anything extra took to get here
maybe like me you had to play with the technology to get it to work right
just relaxing noticing noticing your surroundings
perhaps distant sounds outside your window
or the soft hum within your home
or room
noticing the immersion the immersion of your body
your heart your mind in the moment
contact of your feet against whatever they're resting on
grounding if you're setting the contact of your
hip points and buttocks in the chair or cushion
the contact of your skin on call
air perhaps your hands or some other part of you is touching
noticing how that feels on the outside of your skin
and then noticing how it feels to be present inside
all the ways we know we're alive
foreign
and perhaps noticing the Integrity of your skin
and the strength of your spine and your bones
they hold this body upright
allowing your muscles to relax around the bones
allowing your belly and your chest to soften
in your life's breath to move unimpeded
in and out
that we settle in noticing too
quality the inner posture the mind the heart
and setting the intention of kind
generous awareness to be kind generous discerning
with whatever arises even if your thoughts are a bit of an
echo chamber this morning
are you okay it's okay
to step back and rest
rest in present moment experience of breathing
body or sound
even resting in the present moment flow of awareness
you notice your mind has wandered seeing how kindly and generously
can greet the re-emergents of awareness the integrity
of mindfulness
in the last moments of this meditation
the invitation is
gather up notice any little moment
or a long stretching
pleasure or positive quality any little glimmer thrust
peace mindfulness concentration
kindness generosity many other gather it up
and soak in it be nourished by it
appreciating this practice we've done together
and then casting your internal gaze gaze of your heart outwards in your life
Wherever You Are whoever you encounter
and if it feels right generating the aspiration that they too
May benefit from the fruits of your practice
be others in our lives be happy safe peaceful and free
and may our practice our actions in some small way help support that
thank you [Laughter]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice [Music]
oh good morning good morning Sangha light to be with you
and a special welcome to those who tiptoed in a little bit late into the
live stream room today I'm going to continue the theme of
this week which is qualities of mind and heart conducive to inner and outer
Harmony we've covered so far this week
mindfulness and um wisdom kind of applied to benefiting
ourselves others ourselves and others in the broader
world we covered that on Monday and then on Tuesday we covered
how the cultivation Retreat of kind kindness good will
can be a huge support for our progress in maturation of
meditation and spiritual practice and in our relationships
and then yesterday we covered the quality of sharing or generosity
and how that too is a profound support in the path and in daily life in our
relationships in today's topic is the value of consistently showing up
consistently showing up with persistence ethically with ourselves internally and with
others externally it's walking our talk and again this is one of a number of
principles qualities the Buddha taught in the Sarah Nia dhamma often translated
as the principles of cordiality like so many things the Buddha taught
cultivation Inward and cultivation outward
both are beneficial
this principle in particular this way of being consistency of showing up
is something that the Buddha says creates love and respect showing up ethically creates love and
respect both internally and externally and there are a wide range of the
ethical virtues that the Buddha talks about in the ancient teachings far too wide to cover in one little
15-minute talk many of you are familiar with the basics for those of us who are not boarding
gymnastics the five precepts they were covered in detail a few weeks ago in the
7 A.M talks in brief just to recap they include not
killing not stealing abstaining from sexual misconduct
and not lying or engaging in harsh or divisive speech
and finally not engaging in heedless Behavior due to intoxication
so we could list many many more including this week's
practicing with wisdom keeping our own benefit and the benefit of others in mind kindness
sharing and generosity so my invitation is for you to call to
mind reflect in your heart on what you consider virtuous is there anything you'd like to add
list just reflect on it firmly
hmm regardless regardless of how we Define
them expressing virtue consistently with persistence is key it builds beneficial
habits internally and externally and it builds a momentum a momentum in relationship and a
momentum in practice so that quality of persistence consistency itself is a kind of virtue
or can be if wisely applied showing up over and over is the
fundamental prerequisite for gaining skill in anything really
including meditative and spiritual progress right it's just like going to the gym and
working out if I go lift weights or if I go running once a year
I'm not going to be a very big difference but every other day three times a week
every morning something begins to shift to change
even within a meditative session as Matthew pointed out last week beginning
again starting over returning consistently
that's a profoundly helpful action
another way that this kind of quality is really helpful
and this is a completely classic practice is to internally silently reflect on and value
your own good qualities your own virtues any and all of them
it's considered to be kind of a preparatory practice especially for practicing meta or Good Will meditation
and virtuous behavior in general is associated with progress on the path
in fact it's one of the key factors associated with Readiness for awakening as well as expression of Awakening
this comes from a discourse entitled the practice for a trainee
the Buddha is quoted as saying and I'm paraphrasing here for Simplicity
just as a hen has eggs she covered incubated rightly
even though she might not wish or intend for her chicks to break out through the eggshells
still it's likely that the eggs will hatch in the same way when a practitioner is
consonant consistent in virtue and develops meditative skill and
concentration they too they will break through to Freedom
to Awakening
one of the ways this works is by building confidence and Trust in the
practice and in our own hearts and Minds
and it's also true and this again this is probably obvious
but it's worth saying out loud consistently and persistently showing up
with others ethically also increases our own confidence and that of others even more
Robert Anton Wilson writes the conduct of Our Lives is the only proof of the sincerity of
our hearts the conduct of Our Lives is the only proof of the sincerity of
so this persistent kindness aren't you generosity is specially under pressure
it's a repeated theme throughout the Buddhist teachings and the teaching Stories the myths the fables that
evolved later so it's not just when things are easy
but rather when things are tough times are tough that's when our strength shows
when things aren't going well showing up with consistency virtue
kindness it can really build an unshakable confidence with others
if others also value Integrity ethical Behavior it can also build a really deep
appreciation and reciprocation deep bonds I've seen this in my own work
when one of us experiences a really difficult time in the hospital
the way we show up and the way others show up with us help cement these
beautiful beautiful bonds of trust
the Buddha is um quoted in the numerical discourses saying I think it's a verse in poly but
in English the rhyming doesn't come through generosity kind words
beneficial help and consistency in the face of events in line with what's appropriate in each
case in each case these bonds of Fellowship function in
the world like the linchpin of a moving cart
the linchpad a linchpin that holds our friendships
our bonds our communities together
I recently heard a psychologist a research psychologist I believe Dr Marissa Franco say when we are around
other people they're kind of like an advertisement for ways we can show up in
the world and it's true perhaps even more to the point for
practitioners or spiritual aspirants is this
that when we are around other people we are a kind of advertisement
Exemplar for ways others can show up in the world
people notice our Behavior more than we think and pick up on it
just like emotions are contagious virtue is contagious too
or to put it another way we teach other people how to be with us and how to Simply Be
in the way we act in our attitudes our frame of mind
so to bring together these internal and external benefits
to Harmony of showing up with ethical consistency just a brief anecdote and this is from
ancient Buddhist Legend kind of an introduction to the Legends
called the jatica tales and the myth says that the Buddha to be
the Buddha that we always talk about shakyamuni Buddha many Millennia ago
encountered the Buddha of that time and he was so inspired that he decided
that he was going to practice not just to Awakening but to full buddhahood
the ancient Buddha saw this in him and gave him one piece of advice
to hold to Virtue to hold the truthfulness and move consistently through the world
it said the way that the star of Venus moves through the sky
to move through the world the way the star of Venus moves through the sky
I really like this little anecdote it points to the combination of aspiration
persistence consistency of a kind of dieting constellation as a way of moving through
life moving through our worlds
and as a Venus has a connotation for us the underpinning of that at some level
It's a Kind of Love so tomorrow if you wish to
take any homework with you you might just notice how do or how
might the qualities of consistency persistence and whatever
virtues kind of behaviors that you feel drawn to
how do they benefit you how do they benefit your practice how do they impact the others around you
and your relationships so thank you dear Sanga for returning
attention it's a delight to be with you and um we'll just dedicate them very
briefly here may all beings everywhere
benefit from our practice here together may all beings be safe
happy peaceful and free
[Laughter]
[Music]
foreign