hey Kim hello everyone my name is Ines and I'm
from Houston hi Nez welcome good to see you
and this is San Mateo hi Susan
um hello I'm Holly from New York hi Holly welcome
and also bill says hello from Dallas and fazo says hi from Chicagoland Amy Says
Aloha from Oahu and Deb is sending warm greetings from New England Hugh hi
Violet from Portland Violet you're still in Portland um hi kittycon who's joining us from
Thailand it's 8 A.M there good morning kittycon joining us from YouTube and hello to all the YouTube friends for
joining us right now as well as uh Zoom friends and hi Peggy from Southern Utah
very cool I think the space has been warmed up so I say let's begin let's begin and this
formal beginning is the cue for Neil to post information in
um the chat about happy hour Google Groups if you are new to happy hour you
are warmly welcomed to join the slow traffic mailing list
um quotes or shared references are shared um it's a way to keep up with the the
Sangha I like to say it's low in traffic and high in heart so
so the other changes as we transition to the formal part after we say hello is I change the
settings so accidental unmuting won't be possible I also change the chat settings
um so that chats will only come to host who's me but I ask you to keep the um
that channel quiet the chat Channel quiet I will open it afterwards it can
be quite distracting when I'm teaching um to receive a chat but I will open it afterwards and the last of the
preliminaries is I turn on the recording for Audio Dharma the audio recording
here we go great so hello and welcome everyone it's it's
a delight to see you whether you are new to happy hour welcome a warm welcome
lovely to have you joining and uh if you're an old-timer welcome lovely that
you're joining again from wherever in the world you are joining and yes more hellos are coming
through from Sydney I think it's the afternoon that time John is joining in
Barbara anyway so um yeah it just always glad into my
heart the the hello part of our coming together when people talk about
different time zones and this feeling that we are practicing together even
though it seems like we're practicing alone and showing up on Zoom or YouTube we really are supporting one another we
really are supporting one another and this community um
is a lovely beautiful Community who's been meeting more or less for about
three and a half years online so it just makes me so happy that we continue to
practice together so so for today's practice
[Music] um what I'd like to do is to um not
introduce a theme ahead of time but actually introduce the theme ever so
gently drop it into the meditation it'll be light there won't be too many
um there won't be too much but that that's that's the way we're going to do it
today so so let's uh let's settle in let's settle in and if you're sitting in a chair see
what your body needs to sit comfortably
and if you need to shift or move to lie down that's perfectly fine or stand up
I'm gonna assume that you're sitting
so sitting listening with sense of ease in the body
relaxing inviting the body to relax when the body relaxes the mind can relax
so first we invite the body to relax often
let go of the weight of your torso unto
the chair or the cushion
let it support you let go of the weight of your legs your
feet onto the Earth
let go of the weight of your arms your hands onto your lap
no resistance
let awareness be kind be gentle and spacious
there is not so much doing but receiving receiving
the body relaxed the sensations of the body
receiving the breath in the abdomen
and let awareness greed the breath in the abdomen the entirety
of the in-breath as if greeting a dear friend
the entirety of the breath pause the entirety of the out breath the
pause
let it be useful joyful there is no should
it's a gift this breath is a gift
can we receive it gladly needed in this moment gladly
as the awareness greets the breath in the body and the abdomen
the senbra this out breath
with friendliness
with newness this breath is new it's never been here
before like this In This Moment
laughs and as the awareness greets the breath
with kindness with friendliness as if a good friend hello friend hi welcome
glad you're here dear breath
then it's as if the breath also is greeting you greeting your body
with Good Will with kindness filling your lungs your body
with oxygen with energy
with goodness let yourself relax and receive the
goodness
and if you notice awareness is wandering with all past
future this and that it's okay be kind be kind you have a choice
to either berate yourself for having wandered and gotten distracted
or take delight at the moment when you
become aware In This Moment 50 50. you have a choice
choose kindness choose Goodwill celebration Delight
thoughts
come up that are challenging
you're not doing this right this is boring
what am I doing or any other type of challenging thought
make space make space with kindness if you push it away
if you fight it you give it more energy
take a breath relax smile smile at the thought
and maybe a very friendly way very friendly humorous way
as if you're joking with a dear friend is that so is that so
this question is meant to bring some curiosity interest gentle
kind humor so that we're not stuck in our habitual
patterns of the Mind is that so dear is this so is that so
and if the space of the heart is quiet
let the breath be nourishing
that the knowing of the breath be an act of kindness to yourself
Good Will friendliness very simple very simple
relaxing and receiving each breath
with friendliness
thank you
may I meet this moment with kindness
may I meet this moment as a friend
may I meet myself
with kindness
may I be a good friend to myself
thank you
foreign
if there's any tension and the body relax the body
maybe taking a deep breath and relaxing the body softening
connecting reconnecting with the breath
in a meeting meeting this breath as a friend
's moment as a friend yourself as a friend
what if you stepped outside of yourself for a moment
and saw yourself this being who is you
doing their best the challenges
are the gifts they're given see yourself as a dear friend would
appreciating you having love for you
maybe even as you see yourself through the perspective of a dear friend
you are moved to offer a hug or support or care
a supportive hand
maybe a smile a word of encouragement
maybe something like you're doing your best sweetie it's okay
or I care for you thank you
I care for you thank you I love you
or whatever version a friendly kind
sentiment feels appropriate
seeing yourself with friendly eyes
and whenever it feels appropriate sticking stepping back into your cell
connecting with the breath at this moment with yourself with this
body with friendliness and kindness
thank you
and in your mind's eye inviting a good friend
or a relative someone who's easy for you to feel care for bring them to your
mind's eye into your heart's face
and sharing this friendliness the sense of Goodwill for them
wishing them well in these
may you be happy and well
the other one
and trusting that this being is not so different from you they just
want to be happy they don't want to suffer they're doing the best they're able to
in this life with all they have been given
gifts and challenges alike
wishing both of you well may both of us
be well have ease meet ourselves
with friendliness
and as we turn to bring this meditation session to a close opening
the Circle opening it wide
all beings All Humans everywhere all beings they
just want to be happy they don't want to suffer
We're Not So Different in our Humanity
just as I want to be happy just as I want to be well
as I wish myself well I wish others well
may all beings everywhere
be well
may they meet themselves and each other
with Good Will and friendliness
trusting trusting that we have planted seeds of Good Will kindness towards
ourselves towards others the seeds will ripen
will come to fruition in their own time not our time
so letting go of whatever happened or did not happen
during the sit being kind to yourself in this moment appreciating that you showed
up you showed up you did your best all that matters
and sharing our goodness the co-created goodness from our showing
up with all beings may all beings everywhere have ease friendliness
happiness may all beings everywhere be free including
myself [Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so our practice today was
revolved around kindness for ourselves meeting ourselves
will be started actually we started with with relaxing softening the body
with meeting the breath with kindness meeting this moment with kindness like a
friend and when you receive the breath as a gift then the mind starts to shift starts to
shift and this moment starts to shift into a gift
and then we shifted to to meeting
ourselves as a friend stepping out of ourselves seeing ourselves with friendly
eyes um with goodness with friendliness
stepping back and then towards the end we brought in a dear friend we shared
our Goodwill our meta with them then at the very end we expanded to all beings
everywhere and whatever happened or did not happen
as long as we met it with kindness with Good Will with friendliness whether
there was distraction present or pain present difficulty present
it's okay we're planting seeds of kindness we're not trying to do this right that's
not the idea here we're planting seeds of kindness so whatever is arising as
long as you meet it with kindness and let's say for the 30 minutes you didn't mean anything with kindness but in this
moment you meet yourself with kindness just now it's okay sweetheart you showed
up it's okay darling you you're doing your best you did your best ah just one
moment of kindness acceptance for yourself for challenges maybe there's
pain in the body pain in the heart this moment of kindness is infinitely more abundant
than zero moments of kindness so
so at this time I'd like to invite us
to uh to show up with friendliness to show up with friendliness
with kindness for ourselves and for one another so
it's happy hour we have small groups and in the small groups roughly the size of
three the invitation is be present with yourself be present with your body and
in the space of kindness It's really where the rubber meets the road we can be signed you know we're doing silent
meditation our eyes are closed but now we get to be kind in public but it's
like a Sandbox it's a Sandbox it's not the world where we're working
Etc but it's a sandbox with people who've just practiced meditator around
kindness so it's it's a gentle reintegration into being kind to ourselves kind with
others and the prompt is you and you can share or not share you can just offer
silence just show up with silence and if you do choose to share know that
you're sharing for your own sake you're speaking just to be held witness the other people in the room are just there
to hold you witness and support you in in being kind to yourself and you can
say tonight's practice I was sleepy I was distracted but I Met
Myself with kindness maybe that's your report or maybe something else happened
um whatever you say there's no right or wrong [Music]
if judgment arises be kind to the Judgment so just be kind be kind really
that those are the seeds we're planting which is quite Counter Culture and when
we're kind to ourselves we can actually take more responsibility
both for our actions be kinder to others etc etc so
so I'm going to create the breakout rooms and again the invitation is to
stay in your body be kind I suggest the order to be um
alphabetical order according to first name tonight and
[Music] um and again you offer just a nugget and then make space for the next person to
offer a nugget the next person then it'll come back to you so you'll go around a few times and when other people
speak maybe something you remember something or you get inspired to say
something and no asking questions from one another no not directing you just
show up and share something if you like from your experience
um so creating a safe Brave space for one
another to interact in a container of kindness okay all right I'm going to
open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind be kind
be kind okay here we go
foreign
thank you
okay the rooms are closed everybody is back welcome back everyone and
um we have uh some time now for any Reflections or any questions questions
complaints reports it's all welcome and you can either raise your Zoom hand
if you haven't spoken in the group for a while or if you're new if you like to you're welcome to we can also type in
chat your questions Reflections and if you type them just to me it'll be private I'll just read your uh
reflection privately and if you want to type it to everyone then it's public I'll read it publicly so what did you
discover what what was it like either the groups or the practice
um
and I did some Smiles did see some smiles when you came back from the group so
I wonder how that was
bill says not able to focus this time
um frustrated and found the frustration feeding on itself it's is was it
possible Bill to just have a moment of of kindness to this self this being who
is frustrated yes says Bill yay so that's a moment of kindness that can
support the the um you know the perpetuating the feeding of itself it can actually pause
and and end that cycle break that cycle
Jerry said it was great to have permission to just feel the kindness of being here ah thank you Jerry yeah yay
Terrence please thank you so very much Nikki
um I was very soothed as typical by just being in group and being in the field of
your voice and allowing myself to you know just uh
almost I could say float with it see um soothed by it by your voice
and then came through this thing of meet yourself and oh my God it just like boom
it really got my attention and pulled me into a different space you know which
woke me up in a sense um
yeah it Harkens back to other meditative Retreat experiences I've had when meeting myself
with kindness and you know how and seeing how I wasn't caring for myself very well
really and it's kind of heartbreaking but so important to see
thank you so very much for that oh thank you so much Terence for sharing
that oh thank you so much and I'm bullied and delighted that that the
practice today for you it did support oh meet yourself meet yourself with kindness and yes there is sadness there
of the times we have not made ourselves with kindness and and yet there is this moment of Awakening oh yes
it is possible I can awaken to to meet myself with kindness instead of perpetuating this this pattern so thank
you thanks for sharing that turds oh thank you so much one reflection it's just wonderful to
talk and communicate with like-minded folks wonderful Community thank you Deb says so wonderful to have the
opportunity to Simply Smile and feel the tenderness here ah thank you and that's
hearted by someone else Jim says the kindness towards myself is easier in silence once I start talking fight and
flight Sensations Vie for my attention uh thank you for sharing that Jim it
takes a lot of courage to to actually bring that into and say that out loud
write that out loud in the community because that is um that is the case when we it's very
very common so that's why we keep practicing in silence and then in these
um small sandboxes of you know two or three other people we try to meet
ourselves with kindness and and notice that oh yeah flight from flight flight freeze is showing up and
can we be kind to that pattern can we be kind to that and the more we do it so so my recommendation is Jim
um don't let that be a reason for you and others who have the similar observation to say oh I'm just not going
to show up to the small groups because it's just too hard to be kind to myself but actually keep showing up keep
showing up and keep observing the fight flight and freeze and keep being kind to it it's okay sweetie you're doing your
best it's okay this is hard it's okay and then that is really the training ground
um the the um you know it's the scaffold it's the training wheels for us meeting ourselves
in kind with kindness in social situations in the world which are professional or this or that and a
higher high station we can still be kind to ourselves so thank you so much for bringing that
up so important so important so
so I don't see any other hands or any other Reflections so
Let's uh bring this practice to a closure together thank you all thank you
all for showing up for planting seeds of kindness towards yourself towards
um the world because really when we fill our own cup with kindness when we do
that when our cup is full then we can fill other people's cups and we don't go
around the world saying love me love me love me in a subconscious way so so it's so important to to fill our own cups
with care uh meeting ourselves as parents and meeting ourselves meeting us
ourselves with care because hey who else would if we don't so so thank you all for your practice
may you be well may you be happy may you meet yourselves with kindness
and they ring the bell here we go [Music]
take good care be well and see