so welcome welcome to everybody it's nice to be here with you
all today I'm going to continue on this theme of poetry of
practice and today I'm going to use a poem that chances are you've heard it I
think that I've heard it a number of times in Dharma talks but there's something about this poem and I would
say in all poems that have a I don't know the poems
that tend to touch us share something with the sutas you know like the early
Buddhist literature and what they share is this um depth or maybe we could say
width that is even though with we might read them or hear them again we find
something different we hear something different and I know certainly in the
sutas this is true for me many of you know that um Gil and I have like T thought suas for a number of years now
we're not currently teaching a course right now but uh and we often are saying
this like wow we've taught this uh already once before but when we look at it again we're finding something new and
and the same thing with poems that even though they might be similar that we find something new when
we look at them and I only I only might they be similar might they be the exact same poem but maybe we're not the same
and um this poem that I will drop in during our
guided meditation this morning something that's very simple it doesn't have a lot
of uh complicated uh imagery but it has some real distinct imagery or doesn't
have a lot of comp complicated Concepts but maybe part of the power is in its
simplicity part of the power is part of the imagery that's been used that I
think all of us can find a part of our Lives find something that uh is relevant
or to this particular poem and I will give the name of the
poem and the name of the poet after I ring the bell because I would just you
know allow yourself to just experience it without already having some preconceived ideas of whether you know
the poem or not or what it's about or sometimes when we're on our computers there's a Temptation like oh just Google
it or you know something because but um just encouragement just to allow the
poem to be received and experienced and then um we can explore
it together afterwards
okay just uh taking our meditation
posture I find myself doing this long exhale as a part of a way to like shift
gears like to orient towards oh now now is a time for
meditation if that's helpful for you you could take some
big exhales and as that's happening allowing
the body to adjust in any small or maybe even large
ways so that you can feel balanced
upright alert and with ease
can be helpful for some people to make a very small movement where they move
their chin like back like back towards
um backwards so not up or down but back a little maybe slight sense of
tucking this opens up the spine there in our
neck can allow for a little more balance of the head over the
shoulders
doing a light body scan checking
in with the
face humans are expressive of course we are and our
face is often a place where we can hold tension around the eyes or the jaw or
mouth resting Awareness on those
areas with an invitation to soften relax
open resting attention on the
shoulders letting them also have some ease the shoulder blades sliding down
the
back the chest the belly
and feeling the pressure against the body the chair the cushion couch bed
whatever it is that we're sitting on literally or
figuratively upper legs
lower
legs
f
arms just resting our attention nothing needs to be done so to speak we're just
moving the awareness scanning the
body tuning into the sensations in the
hands are the hands
touching is it smooth or
rough it warm or
cool and tuning into the experience of having
hands vibrancy this embodiment of hands there might be a
tingling sense of Vitality sense of
energy
and expanding that attention into the
vibrant experience of being embodied expanding that to the whole
body in a relaxed easy way
maybe there's a way in which in a
sense this embodiment just gets as big as it would
like this sense of
aliveness
we're here now
experiencing
this and then resting attention on the sensations of
breathing the movement of the body as it
breathes
and can we do this being present with the experience of
[Music] breathing with a sense of warmth and
care we're not trying to force ourselves we're not beating ourselves
up and we find the mind is
squirly maybe some more like curiosity or like
petting a
cat of course petting a dog
too and when the mind wanders we just very
simply gently begin
again making a story chastising ourselves that's
extra it's not needed just allow that to be in the
background
tuning into the experience of inhale and
exhales the embodied
experience not about thinking or concepts but a different type of
knowing
for
I'm going to drop in a
poem just allow this poem to be
received let that needs to happen that you need to do with this
poem let the words wash over
you the palem goes like this chapter
1 I walk down the street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I Fall in
I'm lost I'm helpless it isn't my fault it takes me forever to find a way
out chapter 2 I walk down the same
stream there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I pretend I don't see it I fall
in again I can't believe I'm in the same place but it isn't my fault it's still
takes a long time to get out chapter
3 I walk down the same street there's a deep hole in the
sidewalk I see it is there I still fall in it's a
habit My Eyes Are Open I know where I am
it is my fault I get out immediately
chapter 4 I walk down the same street there's a
deep hole in the sidewalk I walk around
it chapter five I walk down another
Street
I'll read the poem
again chapter 1 I walk down the
street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I fall in I'm lost I'm helpless
it isn't my fault it takes me forever to find a way
out chapter 2 I walk down the same street there's a
deep hole in the sidewalk I pretend I don't see it
I fall in again I can't believe I'm in the same place but it isn't my fault it still
takes a long time to get
out chapter 3 I walk down the same
street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I see it is there I still fall
it's a habit My Eyes Are Open I know where I am
it is my fault I get out
immediately chapter 4 I walk down the same street there's a
deep hole in the sidewalk I walk around
it chapter five I walk down another
Street
for
chapter five I walk down another
[Music]
Street
so this poem is by Porsha Nelson it's called autobiography in five short
chapters again that's Porsche Nelson autobiography in five short
chapters I think I just love this uh title it's pretty you know
descriptive I'm just going to stop the recording and then do a new one
here
okay so here we are talking about uh yet another
poem that uh we explored during the guided meditation and I'll read it again
here chapter or maybe I'll just say that the excuse me the title of the poem is
autobiography and five short chapters by Porsha
Nelson I think maybe if I had to said the title at the beginning maybe there'd be a little bit different understanding
of the poem but um if I said the at the beginning of the guided meditation but
here we are so chapter one I walk down the
street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I fall in I am lost I'm
helpless it isn't my fault it takes me forever to find a way
out chapter 2 I walk down the same street there's a deep hole in the
sidewalk I pretend I don't see it I fall in again I can't believe I'm in the same
place but it isn't my fault it still takes a long time to get
out chapter 3 I walk down the same street there's a deep hole in the
sidewalk I see it is there I still fall in it's a
habit My Eyes Are Open I know where I am it is my fault I get out
immediately I walk down the same street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I
walk around it chapter 5 I walk down another
street right I can't I find myself smiling when I'm saying this partly because uh you know this poem it's so
simple right it's not complicated you know that we have to like figure it out but maybe that's part
of its beauty and part of its power is its Simplicity one thing that I appreciate
very much is of course this uh poem it has a pattern right you know the
different chapters uh kind of like all start the same and maybe in the same way for those
of you who are familiar with sutas know that many of the sutas have the same thing where there's this repetition this
repetition except like one little bit is changed this is a real common
theme and let's be honest it's a common theme in our lives that we have patterns
and some of them are more helpful than others but just this recognition that patterns is such a part of our life the
way that we behave and the grooves that we can get stuck in as well as the
grooves that can really support us regular meditation Practice coming to 7
AM regularly and connecting with others on in the chats or having a SAA in some
kind of way so just this recognition of the power of patterns and both those way that they
show up in our lives but also in the way that uh we learn things like we learn like oh yeah this
is similar but this little bit is different and sometimes what's different is what gets
highlighted because in the same way even though this poem of course has this pattern that's getting repeated and
repeated there's also this clear sense of progression there's a sense of movement
like literally the speaker is walking down the sidewalk but also
figuratively you can sense that there's more and more freedom until it at the end you know just this oh I'm going to
walk down a different street so this
movement and I'll maybe I'll just say that when I read this poem and I hear this walking down the street what comes
to my mind it might not come to other people's minds but when we take refuge
in the Buddha Dharma and sa many of you have done this this is a tradition that we do the beginning of
Retreats and we chant
buam literally means like I I go for refuge in the Buddha Dr
and S but this idea I go for Refuge is sometimes good Chi can be translated as
like I walk towards so so there's a way in which we can this sense of movement
is such an integral part of our life and maybe there's a way in which we can
influence where we're walking the direction we're
going because something that I else that I really appreciate appreciate about this poem that might I didn't understand
or didn't appreciate the first time I heard this or maybe even the second time I heard this poem but this time was
looking at this is that there's this sense of resilience there's a sense of
resolve the speaker continues walking down the street they didn't sit down and
refuse okay I'm give up I'm not going to walk anymore or anything like this and
one way we might understand this is that the the speaker has a growth mindset a
belief that the person's capacity can be
improved in contrast with a sorry a fixed mindset this a limiting belief
that oh we can't it's all we can't change nothing's going to be different it's always going to be like
this and it turns out more and more that having this growth
mindset turns out to be incredibly impactful just this General belief that
things things can change that they can be different yes there are patterns but they're not always 100% the
same when we find ourselves in these patterns something different that's
happening maybe we're different occasion is different and um of course in this poem part of
the difference and part of the progression of this poem is the amount of awareness the speaker
has chapter one the speaker says I am lost I am helpless know just this kind
of recrimination kind of beating oneself up with then the second one's maybe a
little bit more awareness like oh okay I see it but I pretend that I don't and
this is human nature we often like okay I'm see it but maybe if I ignore it it'll go away if I look the other way
you know maybe maybe it won't be there and then the third chapter I still
Fallen it's a habit My Eyes Are Open I know where I am so this recognition of
oh yeah this is a something that uh recurs in my life this is a pattern I
have and then things begin to shift in the later chapters after there's this
recognition I know where I am they're not saying that they like it
they're not saying it's fun it's not saying it's their preferences is they're just saying oh I know where I am and
then things really begin to shift they start walking around the hole and then they start walking down another
street so part of this uh progression and practice in our lives maybe we can
even use this word uh maturity is not only about awareness but it's also about
our relationship to what's happening that starts to shift
like we don't get to choose what life brings us what kind of holes there are in our sidewalks we don't get to choose
that but what can be shifted is our relationship to what
happens to our lives in one way is the amount of blaming do we have the sense like okay
it's it's a problem for things that are out there they have to be changed this person has to behave
differently this institution has to beh differently you know everything out there the problem is out there without
looking at in here and to be sure I am not saying that uh people are victims
and that uh things out there are perfect of course not right that's not helpful
and nor is it accurate but is there a way in which we
are focusing on what the speaker here in this poem says in chapter 1
it's not my fault so instead there's kind of like this stubbornness like I don't have to
do anything everything out there has to be different and they say this the speaker
says this again in the second chapter so until we get to the third chapter and we say it is my fault and then they
immediately get out of the hole there's a connection
here between whether we spend energy blaming
maybe it's blaming what's out there but maybe we even are blaming ourselves and when we like put down the
blaming this is when things are shifting can be different and to be sure like
part of this practice is developing our character and developing wisdom this
patient uh training and repeated cultivation right this is a part of
practice working with the patterns of our minds and hearts and gradually
shaping the direction of Our Lives because something else that's also
implicit in this poem that we don't see is this restraining from acting on
impulses that cause harm we don't see the speaker in this
poem intentionally harming thrashing out hurting others hurting themselves but
maybe systematically like kind of like bringing their attention back to being
present perhaps rather than lost in thought or and you might say even cultivating
mindfulness and many of you know this but some of the parames these um
qualities that really support finding more freedom that we do in our daily
life these qualities the parames and often translated as the perfection
include patience resolve loving
kindness to doing this with warmth and the factors of Awakening which also
support this movement towards greater and greater freedom in cour includes tranquility and
equinity so these qualities kind like implicit in this
poem we might say that through cultivating just showing up for our
lives The Good the Bad and the Ugly right our lives are a mixture of
things part of it is to just keep showing up and then maybe allowing these
beautiful qualities these positive qualities that are already in our hearts
and Minds allowing them to Blossom allowing the wisdom
to shine through maybe some Faith some confidence
that okay I'm GNA keep on walking down this street until we realize oh there's
something completely different there's another Street maybe one last thing that I'll
say here is you notice that the the speaker of this poem is not
emphas izing that we have to be completely different because the
patterns and we might even use this word archetypes that make up our individuality they're beautiful it's not
something that we have to completely change this practice this poem is not asking us to be somebody we are
not it's just allowing some transformation to change to arise change
to arise so that we all can find Freedom we can walk down the streets
that allows us to have our best life our best wisdom to show up and maybe some of these other streets
are a way that we can help other people that our learning like oh watch
out there's a hole in that sidewalk is something we can share with others it's not to stop walking and it's
not to become a different person but it's allowed the wisdom to
Blossom inside of all of
us autobiography in five short chapters by Porsha
Nelson thank you