so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be together in this
moment in times and for our practice together I
want to invite us to uh to continue to engage with the practice of
compassion there can't be enough compassion in the world for ourselves
for others because there's so much suffering in the world bod hurt Hearts
hurt there is unfortunately the continuation of of geopolitical
situation so much pain and suffering as the Buddha said greed
hatred and confusion not knowing any better not knowing that harming each other hating each other doesn't end
hatred so let let's continue with the practice of compassion wherever it's
called for um couple of days ago we started inside and internally and went
outside and maybe we'll do the same today so
so with that invite you to find a position where your body is comfortable
enough in this moment in time and if there is discomfort presence
that's okay to can we welcome
that can we relax soften with whatever is present in
this
moment inviting our hearts our minds our bodies to relax as much as possible
relaxing into around what is with no
agenda
and if thoughts are arising In This
Moment not a problem and yet can we relax them
too invite them safety ease can they
rest as we invite this body to rest and collect
itself
letting the body relax the heart the mind and just
receive the breath in the belly calming
soothing s settling settling our minds our hearts can be so
agitated especially when there's pain and
sorrow and settling is not the way to deny pain and sorrow
is a way to establish more stability so we can be with pain and sorrow
skillfully with compassion instead of agitation and
reactivity so settling settling with each breath No Agenda just to
settle
Soo in breath and out breath two
companions new friends
and as we relax our hearts our bodies Our
Minds we Rel relax our our
embrace our hearts Embrace with a very very light
touch to relax around and ever so lightly Embrace what is
challenging maybe in the body right now in the mind in the
heart not looking for it if there's nothing challenging it's
okay let yourself just stay with
this this gentle open Embrace of
care arms
Open Hands turned up ever so gently
breathing
and notice if as you fully relax and soften your
body with each
breath through this complete relaxation and
settling the body can feel
lighter softer a little fluffy [Music]
perhaps again don't try so hard it's not about trying but Letting
Go softening relaxing more and more of your
muscles of your [Music]
thinking into nature of What's called the air
element embracing the air [Music]
element of your body light
moving feeling the breath being
breathed and as if you this body of your is the breath itself is the air
itself
expansive as if this body is
gas and with
the container of the skin
released this body spreading these molecules air
itself spreading the air of
compassion traveling far and
wide becoming a breath of
compassion
when traveling to perhaps a loved one or an area of the
world as this air the air element air
spreading and as you surround each being
with your
presence as this air of compassion is being breathed in and
out blessing each and every person
with Comfort
Care being compassion being care bringing
sucker and
ease wherever the air element of your body
shows up and
spreads compassion as the air we breathe
becoming being
compassion in your heart's
desire if we could bring sucker calm and
care if we had a magic wand and we could
shape shift our form become gas become
air bless every [Music] cell of another being's
body to be free from sorrow and suffering wouldn't
you this practice is an exp exploration of this
wish offering yourself
up to the altar of
humanity one breath at a
time
and as we bring this meditation to a
close offering our practice offering ourselves our
goodness all beings everywhere as if we could spread our
goodness molecules of goodness all around this planet this
world may everyone ways I can't imagine
benefit from my good will my friendliness my
care may all beings be free from suffering and
sorrow may all beings be well
all beings be free including
[Music]
myself so your practice everyone so the way we explored the
practice of compassion this evening this in this
session is unlike any time in the past we've explored it it's it's a new way
diff different way and
um and as I was leading the meditation the different images different teachings
came to mind and one of them was
how in the jica tales which are the tales of the stories of of how um in
many many lifetimes their children's tales of the lifetimes of the Buddha
before he became the Buddha many many rebirths that he
had um just how he developed these various
qualities and each time he would be reborn perhaps as an animal
and in one of these Tales I forget what animal he was
but again my memory is a little uh unclear but basically there's
this story of of him considering or actually offering himself
as for food offering his body as food for for
uh a uh I think uh lion and lion cubs who were starving so the sense of
offering your body like offering your body out of compassion so so in this
practice maybe coming up from my own pain in my body the sense of lightess
that was coming and feeling light and and Airy what if we we could offer our
bodies our our bodies is air that others breathed and brought them comfort and
care so this transformation of our wish to bring comfort and sucker as our us
transforming ourselves into this agent that goes around you know this air that
hugs people and engulfs them and penetrates their cells through the oxygen they breathe
and brings comfort and ease and and
um sucker so again like any practice this might have
worked for some of you might have been an aha moment and for some of you may
not have and it's all okay not a problem it worked for you great add it to your
Arsenal and if it didn't let it go no worry so many different ways into the
temple so I like to invite us to uh explore how this practice was for us in
small groups and please take care of yourselves take care of each other stay with the content of your practice
compassion practice and the cultivation of your heart um
and and um maybe I'll just ask Neil again to bring actually it's I think
it's already in the chat the the HH etiquette if you're not familiar with it
please familiarize yourself how to um actually wait I need to open chat if if
uh Neil can in fact tell you what I think I can post it to here it is oh
there it is thank you Nia right than you um so that you offer safety and care to
one another you know the drill so so
um let's go alphabetical order according to first
name just keeping it simple tonight and I'm going
to excuse me create their rooms and uh take care of each other
take care of yourselves be kind and I'm going to open the rooms
now and here we
go [Music] welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed and uh given that I'm not feeling well I'm only going to take one or two
Reflections tonight so feel free to write them in
chat or raise your
hand Mary
okay mute so um it's can you hear me okay so
u i just to speak to what you just said uh I felt that to realize you seldom
talk about yourself but it was quite a human moment to experience of course it
uh it made me feel sad that you were in discomfort but it also at the same time
uh I felt uh a connection to you uh and the group in a different in a different
way that we all have our challenges and uh even the Buddha or the teacher so
thank you thank you thank you Jerry
appreciate appreciate you appreciate your reflection
yeah I see Reflections in chat Janette says I feel so much
gratitude to you for meeting with us and giving us the gift of the beautiful guided meditation even though you have
pain tonight H thank you Janette thank you
others and Fred says thank you for being here tonight Nikki thank you Fred fosil
says I hope you feel better Pon thank you me too and
Hugh last [Music] word h thank you thank you Nikki what I
was struck by a phrase that you said tonight about how we should uh offer the
best of ourselves up on the altar of humanity you know and it reminded me of
the phrase Namaste which to me has always meant um Namaste the The Very
Best in Me salutes the best in you you know and u
i and now tonight I'm thinking oh yeah just offering up a plate of food like a
tasty Mor so here take me nothing but wholesome and nourishing
intentions for towards you have a oh thank you you thank you so much
this is so beautiful I I love it yeah so yeah this invocation of of Namaste the
very best of me sees the very best of you and giving up this very best of us
ourselves for the sake of all beings for the sake of ourselves and all beings
yeah beautiful thank you H Amy says I was reflecting on the
wind a wind being like the air of compassion blowing through and it
reminded me of the song my dad sang to me at bedtime called the
Windy Maria I don't know that song now I have to go look it
up yeah thank you beautiful thank you for the Goodwill get well soon wishes
they coming fast and beautifully thank you so much thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for your
cultivation of kindness good will your good heart your compassion for the sake
of yourself and for the sake of all beings everywhere may all beings be well
free from sorrow may all beings be free including
[Music]
ourselves thanks everyone oh Claire says they called The Wind Maria is the song
title okay I they they called The Wind Maria okay I have to go look it up good
now I have a good reference thank you all take good care I'm going to uh stop
the recording