hello everyone and welcome back happy to be here
and um
one of the profound opportunities or possibilities with military meditation
is to be aware as we sit in meditation be aware of
ourselves be aware of sounds the situation we're in from some place within
that is not filtered by our discursive thinking
and to be aware from there but also to be aware of their
to be aware of what's going on deeper than discursive thinking in US discursive thinking can often color our
perceptions our experience of the world uh this whatever kind of story idea
judgments commentary we're making sometimes can be
undermining us if it's uh depressing story we're telling then the
telling of the story repeatedly conditions more depression if it's anger
it conditions more anger if it's some attitude that uh I'm incapable or
unworthy it kind of conditions us to kind of feel that and be that more
it's almost like discursive thinking is fuel for
to support any kind of negative thinking that we
might have about ourselves or the world and it might be a sum of thinking is accurate enough but for it to be the
condition that the conditioning that shapes us can be often quite unfortunate
so if we can somehow listen to us listen deeper listen from a place that's not or
perceive or to know or to feel ourselves a meditation to feel to be
embodied in our breathing to be embodied in our experience of our emotions to be
embodied in our moods or what's happening to sense and feel almost from the heart
or from the Torso or the belly then through the medium of wherever we're
thinking stories and ideas and if we can do that then
um we're not going to be so conditioned by the thinking
and discursive thinking and they'll still be thinking but to that think thinking which is not a story
tends to be wiser it tends to also not have the same
kind of impact that an ongoing story or commentary might have
also it's very respectful I think the deepest way to respect
what's happening within us is to not see it understand it through the lens of an
ongoing commentary ongoing judgments ongoing stories and predictions and
Fantasies but to really to be present for what's deeper inside with
a quiet mind with a quiet heart and then mindfulness has kind of a Midas
Touch everything turns to Gold Everything has a chance to transform into something good it's remarkable even
if something is you know deep down feels kind of negative it's remarkable when
that's a tend to two respectfully from the quiet place within below that
discursive level something different begins to shift and
change and open up it's kind of like if we're in some kind of level of distress
and a friend sits down to us and just listens to us doesn't fix us doesn't even try to help us just listens and
it's present it tends to kind of shift what's going on within our relationship to it
so to offer that to ourselves so to assume a meditation posture
and this idea of taking an upright posture either actually or
metaphorically I like to think of it as a posture of that we begin the uh
the attitude of respect for ourselves
for all that we are and so an attitude that demonstrates
that or allows for that and then to gently close the eyes
and take a few moments to be as quiet as you can
Don't Force It and just listen feel sense
yourself in a full way in a deep way
As You Are Here and Now as if you have permission to be this way
and you're just going to be present for it
almost like a discovery or or a reacquaintance
or like you're your own friend sitting with yourself just here to listen to be present for
her and if you are quietly present for yourself Here and Now
without spinning off into the discursive thought or without living in it it might still go on
but to live in a deeper place the quiet place that can listen and be present
and then gently not too much take if a bit deeper
inhales and a little longer exhales
almost as if you're massaging or opening settling
this deeper place within
relaxing your face and shoulders and belly
relaxing the thinking mind
and if there is a lot of discursive thinking it's okay
see if you can listen or be present from a quiet place a deeper place within
so you become your own friend sitting at a bench listening feeling sensing allowing something
deeper to show itself underneath the discursive thinking
and they're settling into your breathing normal breathing pattern
and if you can offer this deeper quiet attention to breathing
just that is profound
and as different things occur Within
let it be known from whatever place that's available for you
that's underneath or deeper than discursive thinking there might be simple thoughts involved
in knowing it but those thoughts will probably be more peaceful
or simple than or maybe even wiser than what's available through discursive
thinking
and rather than fixing anything or making anything go away
let it be known respectfully by this quiet presence
through this quiet presence let it be known by a simple mindfulness
awareness
that is an act of respect everything is respected
in a sense nothing to fix because
we don't see anything as being broken
it's just something to hold in our awareness breathing with it
letting the breathing the rhythm of breathing support awareness from the quiet place within
relaxing as you exhale and in the relaxing
can you settle into quietest place within
where you can be present for yourself where you can know or sense or feel
that's underneath or deeper than story making mind
the commentary mind foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider what it's like to offer a presence to others
that's from a quieter place without our need without projection or judgment or
commentary but to be present quietly for the
humanity of others as they are with respect and care
and then consider the ways in which good will might flow from this quiet place
a simple Goodwill well-wishing
care for the happiness and well-being of others
into wish as we bring this to meditation to an end
to for the well-being of everyone so that we begin
reminding ourselves or can begin familiarizing ourselves
with how this meditation practice
is something we do not just for ourselves but for the world around us
to prepare us to come into the world with friendliness and good will
so we contribute we can contribute to the possibility
that all beings may be happy
all beings may be safe all beings
may be peaceful and all beings may be free
may it be so
[Music] thank you
thank you
so continuing on this theme of aspiration one of the really beautiful parts of
compassion is this desire for the alleviation of suffering for suffering
to come to an end and we're so fortunate we live in a world where people do have this
aspiration have this wish and um and because it's such a beautiful and
important desire or wish it's important to consider the different facets of it
or how to how to do it well and if we do it kind of just on it you
know kind of automatic pilot but you know what we think it's supposed to be like we might do it simplistically or
ways it actually might not even be helpful I'm involved with training people to do
chaplaincy Buddhist chaplaincy and there were chaplaincy is kind of uh
in the public sphere one of the few maybe professions where it's much more
explicit almost like a job description is to bring Compassionate Care
to patients in hospitals to be inmates in prison to all kinds of
different situations to hospice excuse me schools colleges many places
where they have chaplains and one of the kind of core ideas of chaplaincy world
is um that the Compassionate Care should be
done in the service of others as opposed to fixing them or helping
them there was a famous article by Rachel uh Raymond
who wrote about this distinction between fixing and helping and serving
and not not representing her so accurately but speaking for myself that
fixing uh implies that someone is broken
and if we're going to go fix them then we're fixing their Brokenness and it doesn't really feel good to be
approached as if you're a broken person and um and it kind of well the
compassion might be there it comes along with a message that that can reinforce
all kinds of societal ideas and personal ideas that there's something wrong with
us the other idea is to help that seems
like it's innocent enough this idea of help and helping and it's it's often a beautiful thing to do
but it provided that we're not seeing other people as being helpless
and if we see other people that helps helpless we're also kind of conditioning people or viewing people in a very
limited way and so if we go in there to alleviate suffering for people
and we're trying to get rid of the suffering as fast as we can we might actually be limiting people dramatically
serving is the third option and the idea of serving is that there's deep respect
for others and for their agency and for their capacity and for their potential
and that we're there to support that to grow so yesterday I talked about going deeper
below this uh to the causes of suffering and today I want to emphasize that we
also want to go deeper and look at people's potential how they can develop and how they can
grow and um and it's more than just removing the the causes of suffering it's really
growing up and developing ourselves in such a way that we have the strength the Inner Strength the inner capacity to uh
people everyone had helping to develop the inner capacity to be with the
difficulties of life and the adversities of life that challenges of life is often where people
grow where people develop and get stronger and wiser and and working
through some of the complexes complex kind of attachments and and conditioning
we have that gets in the way and so to Simply go there and alleviate suffering too quickly
kind of can deny people the opportunity to grow into it and develop themselves
and so to see people as being not broken but see them as capable see them as as
whole beings moving towards wholeness see not as helpless but see that yes
they have the potential the capacity to help themselves and so then we serve those capacities we
serve their ability we serve their wholeness their movement towards wholeness and so we're available we're
there we're not the Savior we're not coming in there in our you know with you
know as uh you know you know Savior and shining armor to be the one who helps them
and uh it's a delicate thing because people some people sometimes want to be
saved they're looking for others to take responsibility they're looking for others to do it for them and and we come
along and offer them help and we even fix them in some ways temporarily perhaps and they're so grateful and so
rewarding as a compassionate caregiver to feel the Gratitude and the wonderfulness of people that we've saved
and we feel like we've done the right thing but uh Maybe not maybe we've done a fine
thing maybe it's maybe it doesn't cause harm but maybe it's uh shortchanged
people and what really what needs to happen is people need to grow up they need to grow or even if there are grown
up there's all this continued capacity for emotional growth spiritual growth
relational growth that people are capable of and and so if there is
emotional psychological challenges that um maybe there's we should be a little
bit tender and careful not to interfere with people's ability
to struggle and people's ability to find their way with what's difficult
and as serving them where they're with them we're accompanying people we're available we say I'm here for you let me
know what I can do what can I how I can support you or I'm here with you and I
see that yours your challenge you're struggling and I want to support you in
that struggle to find a way through it um and then you know we kind of are there
as a companion as a support as a sounding board as a maybe we offer ideas
maybe we offer questions that helps people understand but it's important not to take away
people's agency to take away people's ability to to move to wholeness because
that movement towards wholeness that movement to health is a a health health
and wholeness in and of itself so um to allow people to develop
so people who suffer where do they need to develop what needs to grow and be
cultivated and so for example I mean I'm because
we're I'm in the meditation tradition someone who's suffering a lot maybe you
support them to go to a Meditation Retreat and then they're really sitting really
present for themselves and for what's going on and it's remarkable the deeper connection the deeper process of working
through things and growing and developing in capacity that can happen on a Meditation Retreat
so being coming to help people you know you're helping them to help themselves
and you offer them the possibility of do a retreat there's many other things they could do but the idea is to support people to do
it and find a way themselves and um so development and service
and to be careful with the fixing mode and the helping mode so these are two aspects of aspiration
to look and see how to support the people's development
and to look and discover how within ourselves we can be of service
and one of the supports for this for ourselves to be able to have Compassionate Care this way
is to learn how to be present for ourselves and for others from someplace
deeper than the realm of our discursive thinking discursive thinking even when it wants
to help people can come along with so much bias and Prejudice and simplistic
ideas and stories and memories and associations it's remarkable that discursive thinking
is not so innocent it's sometimes heavily conditioned by so much
background luggage that we carry along with us and so to be able to
feel or know or connect to a thinking that's deeper than discursive thinking
um is one of the great skills that can come from meditation practice where we learn to quiet the discursive mind
so that we can listen and feel and know and be wise from some place that's below
that level and as I said in the meditation part of the problem with discursive
thinking discursive constructions of stories and ideas and commentary is that
if any of that is negative in nature at the stories we say about others stories we say about ourselves the
ongoing nature of discursive thinking means that that's being reinforced and it's like creating an atmosphere and a
mood and once we start creating atmospheres and moods within us it feels
like it is us it gives it a kind of sense of Truth or this is how it really is there's kind of an authority sometimes
in the moods and attitudes and emotional states that we end up in
but when those are reinforced by discursive thinking it's probably best not to give them a
lot of credence so to um so to have the ability to drop deeper
and as I said in the meditation as well one of the ways of using our capacity to
to know and feel and sense from a quiet or deeper place is that we can turn that to our
discursive mind itself kind of like we're being with a friend who is troubled
and we're not fixing them we're not saving them we're not helping them except what we're doing we're being
present and listening and accompanying them showing them they're not alone
listening to them deeply maybe asking simple questions to help kind of bring
forth what's really happening and uh and so the same way we can do
with ourselves that deeper presence the deeper awareness towards our discursive mind
and all its constructs and ideas that's spinning in there's always going to be
something deeper underneath it that's oh that's always a surface expression of something that's really more important
than needs to be heard and felt and known and so as we learn this aspiration for
aspirational aspects of compassion we're learning also how to connect and be with
ourselves and with others from this deeper capacity we have that we are developing
the capacity to be present from a place of wisdom of Love of care
that is not skewed by some of the spinning discursive
thoughts that are so easy to live in our minds so um
so thank you and um and I hope that these words are useful
for you and if they're not then please feel free to discard them and then we'll
continue with this word aspiration tomorrow thank you