good evening welcome welcome nice to see you all
hmm you're welcome to move chairs or to
sit um a place that's come for those of you that are on the floor you're welcome to stay where you are but you're also
welcome to move chairs so you don't have to sit behind something
so I'd like to give a talk that builds on a talk that I wait maybe before I go
there I'm going to say happy first day of spring I feel kind of happy about this the
Spring Equinox even though I spent a few days I just
got back from New Mexico where it was snowing and it's hard for me like oh it
is spring I felt like it's actually winter but here is spring I guess it's spring there too
but okay so I wanted to build on a talk that
I gave last week and I was talking about this idea that there's a difference between like direct
experience like what were experiencing in the moment
an example would be like stabbing throbbing
spacious attracted tight notice how these are just like
adjectives there there's not like a sentence it's just an adjective that's
the whatever the experience is and then as humans we put a label on
them and then we often have a relationship with the label not so much with the experience for example there
might be stabbing in the knee throbbing maybe Heat
as soon as we label it pain then we have a relationship with the
word pain and then you know I don't know about you guys but I don't like pain
right and there's fear that comes up and all this kind of stuff right so but
something like this stabbing or throbbing that feels a little bit more manageable
like okay this is just this experience right now and might even bring a little bit of curiosity in
and so much of our practice is about getting clear about this distinction about what's actually happening
and then the label we put on it and of course we need labels I'm not saying we're not going to do that
but often the label can be a springboard for all kinds of story making and
thinking and sometimes we use this a Brutus word that there's a fun word papancha I think
it kind of has this feeling of popcorn or something
you know everything that's going afterwards so in the example that I gave
about with the pain is that we might the human mind has like
this tendency to like elaborate and kind of like spread out on pain oh my knees
bothering me from that bike accident that all those years ago and I can't
believe that person did that and caused me to have that bike accident and that reminds me I need to do this or that you
know then you know like just off we go based on just having this throbbing
sensation or stabbing sensation and so papancha this idea of this
proliferation or this effusion of this mental commentary this story making that
happens or maybe like this thinking run amok as opposed to just thinking of what's
needed in the moment to solve a problem or to plan or communicate
right of course we all need thinking for that but papancha is just that proliferation
yeah and I'm noticing that you're looking at the light to the slickering light is this annoying
[Laughter] can we turn off that light and leave other lights on is that is that possible
and then there's a light yeah there's a thirds maybe we can
maybe that's
yeah okay so we'll be a little bit more cozy that's better than the flickering light I think yeah yeah
thank you Jim thank you Bill
[Laughter] those who didn't hear Jim said he thought maybe it was the metasuta in
Morse code short short long long short kudos to you if you can do some Morse
code so
I'm gonna part of the way that I want to explore this is uh with a suit up passage which is a story on Kevin I want
to like give this story and kind of like annotate or maybe my own version of
papancha with this story some of you will know this story it's uh
well known but I want to maybe emphasize certain parts that uh
aren't necessarily emphasized usually
and I'm not going to tell you the title yet you'll figure it out because then you'll like slap a label on
oh I've heard this before and it's all about this but when we can just be with the experience of what's unfolding here
so this starts like this thus have I heard for those of you who don't know most who does start this way thus have I
heard at one time the Buddha was staying near saviti in jetta's Grove and at the pindicus park
now at that time Bahia of the bark cloth was residing by suparaka on the ocean
shore so just to put this into perspective the Buddha is in sovere tea is one location
Bahia of the bark cloth somebody who wore a clothing made out of bark is near
the ocean about 1200 miles away this is a long time distance right at the time
when there's no pavement there's no roads you know that's a long distance
to walk without established roads or
okay so Bahia was residing by suparakan the ocean shore where he was honored
respected revered venerated and esteemed and he received robes alms Foods
lodgings and medicines and supplies for the sick so a few things we can say about this
he's of the bark cloth so that means that he's not a Buddhist practitioner
that just like today we could tell the difference from a Tibetan monastic from
a turban monastic from a Zen priest by the clothes that they wear just in the same way we can tell by this that he's
uh not of the Buddhist and he's a we could say he's esteemed
and well-respected spiritual leader enough so that people are venerating him
and supporting him in the same way that they might support some Buddhist petitioners
and then the suta continues when Bahia was practicing in seclusion
this line of thinking appeared to his awareness hmm
of those who in this world are arhads somebody who's fully awakened or our
Huts or have entered the path of our hardship am I one
so here's a little bit of doubt he has the oldest attention of other
practitioners they venerating him supporting him but he's wondering hmm am
I really awakened what my experience do I think that I'm
really awakened I appreciate this that he wasn't just complacent thinking that okay because people treat me a certain
way I must be that way but instead he's like trying to like he's open to the
idea that there's more to learn more for him to do
but not only that that he allowed this doubt in his mind to remain there for a
little bit you'll see why in a moment what happens next so he doesn't like immediately bat it away so like oh
that's silly I must be awakened everybody treats me as if I'm awakened but he and he doesn't get into Pancha
about it he's just this thought arises am I awakened hmm
so he doesn't ignore it or pushing away but this willingness to stay present
with this openness maybe this kind of like doubt this question about his
practice then allows what happens next
then a Deva this is a
disembodied Spirit we might say a diva who had once been a relative of
bahia's and who was compassionate and Desiring but he is welfare and knowing
with her own awareness the line of thinking that was in bahia's Awareness went to Bahia and said to him
you but here are neither in our heart nor have you entered the path of our hot
ship you don't even have the practice whereby you would become an R hunt
so this is quite something right that David just says to him straight out
you're you're not awakened nor will you be you're doing something completely
different they never say what this practice is but uh just straight up you're not maybe as
awakened as you thought you were not as awakened as everybody else thinks that you are
and so some Douglas Phillips who is a zen teacher
and sometimes teaches a little bit of the teravada also he likes to interpret this Deva that that's visiting Bahia is
saying as some feminine wisdom that maybe but he was completely disconnected
from but it's when he opens up this question am I awakened and is able to
just stay with that inquiry and then allows maybe something else to rise maybe
something in his mind to arise so that's one way we could interpret this idea that the Deva comes
and so she's like challenging him kind of her directness is well maybe we might
even say brutal or maybe it's just fantastic the way that she's not
beating around the bush right she's just saying nope you're not awakened and you're not even on the path to Awakening
so despite his many years of practice and all of the practitioners that support him
and so maybe we are not visited by David that says hey we are not awakened but it's
not unusual for us to sometimes have doubt about our practice
in so many different ways maybe we find ourselves yelling at a loved one and we realize really after
all these years of practice I'm still upset or I still get triggered by things
I'm still really reactive or or maybe we find ourselves thinking like
hostility towards people who are doing something that we feel like is really
against our values harming others harming the planet or just causing harm
in the world and we find ourselves our hearts getting constricted and not
being generous in our thoughts towards them maybe we have doubts like is this
practice really working I've been doing all this meditation listening to Dharma talks reading Dharma
books whatever it might be so maybe there's some way in which we also have had doubts
there's so many different ways that Stouts can show up it can be about ourselves maybe I don't have the
capacity we might have this idea or we might think well those teachers
they I'm not sure they really know what they're talking about they're not they don't seem to be perfect
or are they teachings might not seem compelling like maybe there's something
oats that's more it's easier or faster or whatever it is
that we're looking for maybe we had this you know expectations about the practice that just aren't
being met and doubt arises so when doubt arises there's a few things
we can do one is kind of go down the path of some maybe bitterness or resentment like I
can't believe I spent all the time practicing and it's I'm still the same or
this kind of Road of thinking maybe some self-judgment comes in or maybe even
some despair I thought this was going to help and if this nothing if this doesn't help maybe nothing can
that's one way to go when we feel like our expectations aren't being met
it's a legitimate way and for many of us we might have to go
down that road for a while before we start to realize that's really not leading towards more
freedom instead it just kind of really restricts our freedom limits so as we start to kind of like
collapse and feel disempowered but an alternative way is to just fold
it into practice feel like okay I I feel unsure about
myself and these teachings what can I do one if you could be mindful this is what
it feels like to feel unsure or to have doubt
or we can investigate we could talk to a teacher we could talk to other people we
can read Derma books listen to Derma talks there's we don't have to just kind
of say well this didn't work maybe different teacher maybe a different style a different tradition within
Buddhism or maybe not even Buddhism at all but to not just like give up and
collapse around it but instead to take it as a
an indication or an opportunity to explore and investigate
so then we'll get back to this after hearing from this Deva that he's not awakened and he's not only that he's
not on the path towards Awakening the suta continues without hesitation Bahia asked the Deva
but who in this world is actually an our hunt
and has entered that path that David knows she says Bahia in the
northern city of saviti lives the blessed one the Buddha a rightly self-awakened our heart he is
truly in our Hut and teaches the dhamma that leads to our hardship
then Bahia deeply chastened by the Deva left separaka and traveled all the way
to where the Buddha was staying like you just okay that's if that's what
it takes this is what I'm gonna do Pax his bags or I don't even know if he had bags right so we might have just been a
monastic 1200 miles walks halfway across the continent or
subcontinent quite something because right this could
have been an opportunity for a lot of papancha a lot of how dare you talk to
me what do you know or you know there's so many different ways we can uh respond
to this but instead he's like oh okay I'm not awakened well what can I do to
get awakened who can teach me at this time right there's not books or
anything else to inform a person except another person so this is why he's
asking who is that's the way of saying where can I find the teachings
so he doesn't defend and rationalize deny blame he just wants to go to find
where he can find the teachings that can make him awakened
so then we'll continue with the suta so Bahia walks all the way over to where
the Buddha is and when he's there he finds a number of Buddhist monks that are doing walk-in
meditation and he asks venerable sirs is where is
the blessed one stain where is the Buddha I must see him immediately
he was told that the Buddha and then the monastics told Bahia that the Buddha had
gone into town for alms he's like he's on his lunch break kind of like I don't bother him
but here he immediately turned to the city where the Buddha was the Buddha had
gone into the town for alms rounds and Bahia went in there and then but he had found the Buddha on
alms round then Buddha was moving with great calm his mind at peace tranquil
and poised with the restrained senses of a great one so but he had notices right away
that the Buddha is different there's something about him he has this calm and
tranquility and Poise that even before Bahia has spoken to the Buddha can tell
something's different about him he approached the Buddha threw himself
to the ground before him with his head to the Buddha's feet and said this is a sign of extreme respect to put your head
at the feet of somebody else in Ancient India this is a real sign of respect
and he says to the Buddha teach me the Dharma o blessed one teach me the Dharma O Holy One so that it will be for my
long-term welfare and happiness
he traveled all this way he wants to hear the teachings the Buddha said to him this is not the
time but he uh I have entered the I'm on the alms round
and but he had pleaded with the Buddha a second time Holy One it is hard to know for sure
what dangers they may be for the Buddhist life or what dangers there may
be for mine please teach me the Dharma o blessed one so that I may be free and happy
so but he is saying we don't know when we're going to die I might die before
you finish alms around or you might die the Buddha before you finish alms around
and again the the Buddha said by here this is not the time for me to give a
talking I'm on Ohm's
so but here he's persistent he has this uh idea that he wants to have they
receive these teachings but not only that he has a certain amount of wisdom about impermanence that
recognizing that none of us are guaranteed the next moment none of us are guaranteed that
after our next meal where everything's going to be fine
so he has some wisdom that you know things are inconstant
impermanent we don't get to there's no guarantees
so getting back to this pleaded his case a third time to the
Buddha and this time the Buddha relented and said well but here
you should train like this in the scene
will be merely the scene so scene like uh what is seen like what is visually
known like what is seen and the herd will be merely the hurt
like what sounds are heard I'm saying this because somebody told me
a few years ago that they thought it was like seen like a pastoral scene with Rolling Hills and
s-c-e-n-e so and it is kind of like that but then they heard they thought well maybe it's
like a herd of cows or deer you know they had this whole like pastoral scene
so uh that's why I'm kind of like spending a little time to say it's the like Visual and hearing
and the scene will be merely the scene and the herd will be merely the herd and
the sensed will be merely the sensed and the cognized will be merely the cognized
saying simple Poncha nothing extra
just for each experience be with that experience including the experiences of
a thought cognized there you the word here is like what arises in the Consciousness or
something like this and then the Buddha continues
he says when for you there will be only the scene in reference to this scene only
the heard and reference to the herd only the sensed in reference to the sense to only the cognized and reference to the
cognized then there is no you
in connection with that and when there is no you in connection
with that there is no you there and when there is no you there you're neither
here nor Yonder nor between the two and just this is the end of suffering
and upon hearing this brief explanation from the Buddha but he is mind was
immediately freed from the defilements and he became awakened
so what's an interesting thing here is like that's added at the end so not only to
keep it simple and not not to do with Poncha or just you know allow our thinking to run
amok after each sense of experience but the Buddha is also pointing to this
is how we create our sense of self for this is how the sense get sense of self
gets created for example
we'll get back to like stabbing sensation in the knee something might be like
I don't like it perfectly reasonable
but there's all of a sudden this eye that has a problem that has to get rid
of it as opposed to something like and this is awkward we wouldn't normally do
this but for illustration purposes I'll say instead of saying
um the sensations of stabbing have it risen or stabbing is known
something like this that's different than I am experiencing pain or I'm
experiencing stabbing I admit that this language is awkward
and clunky but there's a way in which there can be experiences without having
to say there's an experiencer because as soon as we start to say
there's an experience sir then all kinds of extra stuff comes along
things we like and we don't like and we have to like protect
and bolster and make sure everybody else sees us the way we want to be seen and
that we see ourselves the way we want to be seen there's all kinds of extra stuff
that comes up soon as we create this self
or maybe like and we're not doing this intentionally so maybe I should say as soon as his self is created
a sense of our self that with our stories as opposed to
there's this experience that's happening right now
it's unpleasant there's a wish for this experience to go away
these are all true but it's uh there's a Glenn there's a
cleanness about it because this sense that
I am experiencing this stabbing and I don't like it and I want it to go away there's a certain amount of getting
tangled up with it a certain way in which we're clinging onto it or grabbing onto it or
this self is so way in which we're not just allowing the experiences to rise
and pass away but instead to
create the conditions in which we are I'm trying to see if there's a better
way to to describe this often
when we I can describe maybe this sense of self as when there's a sense of me
against the world or us against them then there's a real strong sense of oh
there's an entity me here and everything else is out there and we
have to make sure that everybody look thinks the right things about us whatever we want them to think that
we're smart or capable or attractive or whatever it is that we might want others
to think then we have feel like we have to show up a particular way
but it turns out that's extra we don't have to do that and there's so
much Freedom that's available if we're able to put that down and even if we
can't put it down to just soften it to not get
[Music] um filled with um
anxiety about trying to bolster the sensor self or trying to
make it be different than how it is trying to change our experience the
reason why we want to change our experiences because it doesn't match a sense of self that we might be creating
or something like this so we might consider that these
instructions that the Buddha gave is what it's like when the self
disappears and the scene is just the scene and the
hearing is just the hearing and the sensed is just the sensed and in
the cognizance is just the cognized so there's still perfectly fine able to
move through the world without this extra without this extra self
which is the fuel for the papancha the proliferation of thinking that that we
like to do so
what this teaching is also pointing to is that whatever is happening in our in
this present moment whatever it might be impatience
sleepiness confusion annoyance
pain in the knee whatever it is we can turn towards that and experience
that directly and just that turning towards and experiencing it directly like stopping
any contention with reality we might be having but just like Yep this is the experience
that's the doorway to Freedom whatever is happening if you're annoyed
if you're happy if you're tired if you feel Restless
just to be with the experience in a clean way
as best we can and if you feel like I don't even really know what she's talking about this seems kind of weird
or maybe you're like yep I know exactly what they're talking about just the sense of
is there a way that we can hold our experience without
trying to make it different without trying to add on to it
without I'm going like this with my hands open so to hold this way as opposed to this way but to hold it this
way without being in contention with it or trying to
manipulate or manufacture or engineer The Experience so that it's different in
some kind of way so this is the good news sometimes we
might think like okay they'll be more freedom as soon as the neighbor's dog starts stops barking
so I can meditate or as soon as I get a chance to do a lot of retreat practice or as soon as I find the right teacher
or teachings we might have this idea that in the future the conditions are
going to be okay or better and then we'll be able to find some more freedom but this is pointing to
this precise moment this moment this moment
whatever you're experiencing we don't have to wait for the conditions to get better
let's let's just will be more seen hearing sensing and cognizing that's the
only thing that we will be doing ever so why not now
why not this moment
then maybe I'll just close with this learning to live in this
way live fully being with our experience
as opposed to thinking like okay well sometime in the future that'll be better then and then I will
be with my experience but instead to live this experience this is a way in which
opening the door to more freedom now as opposed to in the imagined future
some other time to live our life fully
okay so with that I'll open it up to some questions or comments
thank you so much for that I was just wondering in this story what does what is cognized refer to is that that we
added interpretation to the experience or just that we thought about it in some way or what
does that mean yeah this is such a great question it's kind of a clunky translation I would say what we thought
I would say we would just say thought I think that's probably a better word to say so just recognizing that thoughts
arise and then just to be with the thought without saying like oh I shouldn't think this I can't believe I
thought that or do anything like that or just say that thank you for asking that question it's a good question
back here
thank you um thanks for that talk I I guess I have
a question of at the end when you say you can still move through the world after having these realizations
how does that work necessarily if you know you're really only experiencing your senses really deeply not having
thoughts about them how do you continue having like motivation to do things day to day or to go about the world like like you
described just kind of would be interested to hear your thoughts on that yeah yeah do you want to say a little bit more
about uh your concerns about this or you're saying like how do we do it
without motivation that we'll turn into couch potatoes yeah I guess from the description of it of someone who hearing
is only hearing yeah seeing is only seeing it sounds to me like kind of a passive Observer of everything that's
happening and I just I don't know what it feels like to be in that state but it seems like someone who
is um you know I just can't imagine someone in that state
getting up and eating breakfast and you know going to work et cetera so I'm just curious how it
fits into day-to-day actions when you've reached that point of just what you're describing yeah thank you thank you
that's a legitimate question so eating breakfast happens
getting out of bed happens getting dressed happens
planning happens work happens everything happens but there isn't so much of a
sense of like I have to make it happen there isn't this sense of I have to
engineer manufacture create and do everything to make it happen instead
there's a a more allowing it's it's quite something actually that we aren't
as we're not as in control as we think that we are and we're not creating
things as much as we think we are but when we step back still everything that needs to happen
happens and there isn't this extra um
thinking you know what are people going to think about me oh I better do that or take care of this there's so much more
energy and Clarity that uh actually a person can have more impact
in the world and can be doing a lot more just because they're freed up from so
much of the things that we are that tie us up in knots I don't know is that an okay answer yeah
I wish I could say precisely something that uh but that is kind of like
breakfast eating happens [Laughter] what was that bill
oh okay anybody else have a have a comment
yeah yeah right here the person who's uh spoke
earlier we're just using so everybody can hear no right right here Jim
another question that I had was what do you think is the
instructive element of the story in the part where he's asking for the
Insight while the teachers on their lunch break and in
sort of repeatedly asking and being told no and then
he concedes and does give that you know share that Insight while on the lunch
break like what what is that part about do you think so a few things that this
is a kind of a shows up in the tradition a number of times to be asked three times it's a
it's a cultural thing I think from ancient India to ask three times it still exists sometimes in some Buddhist
Traditions you have to ask three times for a teacher or for certain things
but I'm interpreting it that uh the bahio is persistent and these are and
maybe some version of this did happen
I'm not going to say this is a true story because I don't know but we can
imagine that maybe there was a time when something like this did happen say well you know actually this is not the time
and then there's the tradition of Eskin three times so that's my interpretation
of it
yes right so I didn't finish the the whole suit done no I just said that the final piece is
he dies so maybe that was why we can't know we
can't know where there's a real story but the parable right is that he dies and so
um that urgency was very relevant in this context that recognition of impermanence yes yep
yep he's telling the Buddha well you may die I may die we don't know I don't know
and then I come to find out Bahia dies soon right thereafter I don't know if he knew he was afraid he was going to die
right yeah yeah thank you for that
maybe I'll just add a little bit of how he dies this is very this is like part of
um a cow he gets killed by a cow so like that's
not really explained but uh the interpretations he got between a newborn
calf and its mother or something like this and got trampled by a cow this is a curious part of the story
but he is not the only one in the suit does there's other people who get killed by cows too
I don't know what to make of that
but he became awake and he was awakened thank you and between the teaching and the glory
and that's absolutely right
it's interesting that um you know the David tells him
that he's not on the path you know he's in his current practices not leading to Enlightenment and yet he
laid he clearly laid the foundation you know clearly he'd been cultivating parmies
um and been cultivating samadhi and so that then when he received the
teaching um he was he was well prepared for insight
so it's he wasn't on the path and yet
he was cultivating his mind in ways that made him very
receptive yeah so that his attainment was rapid yeah
great great thank you thank you for pointing that out and we know like then the earlier in the
suta these pointed out that you know he was venerated by others and stuff so we knew he had it was a spiritual leader of
some sort but uh much on this particular path but
it makes heart and Minds were being cultivated so that he was receptive
okay oh yes one more question okay here we go this will be the last one
okay I struggle a little bit with or a lot um I mean so human beings are
pretty naturally sense making creatures right and and so this kind of teaching
is inviting us to lay that down completely and just it
sounds to me I'll frame it as a question um it feels like to me that it's
inviting us to experience what we're sensing just as what we're sensing to experience our
thoughts just as thoughts that or maybe that's that's the place where we can have thoughts which are probably meaning
making but we don't get attached to those specific stories and cognizances or you know
maybe that's where the trick is or the the skill is of yeah
that it's okay to make have to be to have thoughts that are making meaning but to observe those and not become
attached to the particular narration yeah I I would say and and not get this
proliferation of thoughts right not just going off on uh tangent or you know something like this
but of course I don't think it's possible for us to not make meaning yeah yeah of course we'd do that
thank you okay okay so thank you for your
attention and wishing you a wonderful evening thank you
questions