be mark
are you all comfortable with my taking my mask off while I'm teaching and done
as well great [Applause]
welcome yeah thank you thank you for being here
we're making the journey really lovely to be with you in person and thank you for folks out on YouTube for
joining us as well so this is the third of five week series on
introduction to mindfulness meditation myself Tanya Weiser and my friend and
co-teacher Don Neal she doesn't have her mic on so I'll
speak for her yeah and um so the way that this thought this class
is taught is consistently taught no matter who you come learn it by and this
kind of concentric Circle way the first week of the class is focused on breath
the second week is body and the third week which is this week is emotions
and it's sort of like you know the breath is this kind of core experience
sort of more focused and we expand to include all of the body the second week
and now we're going to expand further to incorporate emotions mindfulness of
emotions and then each week we invite you to
preference the theme of the week and your meditations
preference being aware this week of emotions to practice learning like a study you're
studying them more when do they come up how do they come up how do they impact you that kind of thing
not that we expect you won't keep breathing or having a body right and we
haven't talked yet about thinking and it's not that we're expecting your thoughts to have gone away so
um so just as a refresher in week one with the breathing
we talked about establishing an anchor or a tether for our awareness a
reference point or something to help ground us and stay aware of the present moment
experience and breath is often a chosen anchor for people it's um Dynamic meaning it's kind
of constantly moving shifting it can be felt in a lot of different places in our body
for many people it's a very neutral thing to pay attention to if it's not a
neutral if it's triggering for you in some ways then shift to mindfulness of body or or sound those are the two
easiest other objects and so that's just a basic summary of
week one week two was mindfulness of the body and some of the things that we talked
about were kind of that the you know the body has Intelligence in it
there's more and more science neuroscience and other science to talk about like the gut brain literally some
intelligence in the brain that communicates directly with the the brain brain things like butterflies in your stomach
are part of that communication pattern there's a ventral vagus nerve that
travels wanders around the body but all the way into the gut up to the brain it goes kind of
zigzaggy heart you know chest
um and that this is a pathway of communication between the body and the organs and the Brain
and so if there's intelligence in this body and it's trying to communicate with us
and it's not using words I like to say the sensations are the way
the body is talking to us it's communicating through sensation
that's the language of the body and and receiving those Sensations receiving
those feelings recognizing them is how we listen to the body how the
body feels listened to
we have the lights the way they are sorry they're a little dark because there's some flickering happening so but
please feel free to sit closer or back wherever you want but you're happy you know we're happy to have you here
um so what else about the body um
another beautiful thing about the body which is true for the breath too but the body-based experiences
are always in the present moment we have Sensations here right now so I like to
think about it as a Gateway a way for us to access connection to the present
moment so not in the mental ideas and stories
the imagining we do but the direct connection with the present moment experience
so it's a very helpful very helpful and important part of mindfulness practice and I think there's a quote from the
Buddha that goes something like that like if if you want if you want to reach
liberation develop mindfulness of the body it's incredibly important
so another part of kind of Shifting and that we worked on last week was how to
experience these Sensations how to experience the body without a commentary without a like evaluation comments like
you know bad good
um you know like judging right good and bad are judgments it's more like this
neutral kind of just recognizing the pure more pure sensation like oh it's
not a good or bad sensation it's a strong sensation it's a pulsing sensation it's cold or it's warm right
so as much as possible that's a very supportive part of practice is to kind of be moving out away from that
judgmental or evaluating mind into more of a pure kind of simple way of directly
knowing and naming in a real simple way or experience
Dawn also talked last week about pain and how to work with pain and one of the
things that she mentioned was it's a dynamic and changing experience and so
if we can start to pay attention to how it's changing and bringing that more neutral kind of way of recognizing the
sensations instead of kind of maybe we it's almost like um
uh or amplifying the pain in the way that we
talk to ourselves about the pain
and then finally we were kind of we've been doing this each week but kind of
Don brought in this idea of the inner posture so there's the physical posture
in your body but there's also an inner posture and this this is referencing our relationship to our experience
how are we relating to our inner world this week
will expand to talk about emotions and I would love to hear a few words
from you all what do you think about how what words
come to mind when I bring up the word emotions what
are emotions how are they meaningful to you are they problematic to you
would anybody willing to say a few words there's two mics on the floor maybe you guys could just pick them up
um turn them on those are close to them how long you mind yeah thank you guys
for helping each other and um so just this very simple word or
two nothing no like just just a few little words like what do you think
about what comes up when you think about emotions
unified unified okay great
I see them as interpretations of the current circumstances
interpretations great stories stories
anybody else
reactions
feeling I think you said feeling feeling great
so the we all have kind of complex relationships with our emotions right
some emotions maybe we really like some emotions we don't like
um emotions can be both Sublime and extra excruciating yeah there's this whole
range I I like to think about them as a way of
I like these words interpreting or responding reacting kind of like our
it's the way our minds and bodies have synthesized
and created associations to what's happening emotion is about our response
our reaction to what's going on sometimes actually it's not about what's going on now but something that reminds
us of what has happened in the past so they're not so present-centered based they're just triggered
which makes them tricky right and sometimes if we you know have a
reaction to something um that has grown our response our
associated experience to something even as simple as the way a piece of you know glass of
water is put on a counter something like that can generate very strong emotions
or fear of flying or speaking is something that we start to grow this intense more and more intensity
that has very little to do feel free to come in yeah
so one other thing I'll say about um emotions is that another thing I like to
think about is that um they're a communication system they're
trying to motivate us to get us to do something like there's if you think about emotions
like sadness they tend to inspire or result in a body that is heavier leaning
forward more quiet not moving right whereas anger would have the opposite
with a lot of energy a lot of uprightness perhaps you know
running or attacking energy right um so in a way it's like if we're tuning
in really carefully and we notice early on we don't have to go maybe as far with
the emotion in terms of the intensity of it if we notice it sooner so
that's a little mini intro do emotions and we'll be talking about it more and
um so we want to open up now to see if you have some questions about your practice
this last week any stories that you'd be willing to share about things that you're noticing
ways your practices is changing um or you know anything that I brought up
that you want more clarification around so again if you don't mind picking up
the mic if it's by you and just turning it on and being ready to help get it to anyone who
might be interested in Sharing or asking a question
if you could please give your name for the benefit of the whole group as you ask your question that would be
wonderful okay so where's my hand last week you mentioned about
listening to the sounds while meditating and I'm very sensitive to sounds so like
for years I've suffered from all these noises around me and my residence has
this Square end up path of airplane so that has been really bothering me but after we we talked
about just paying attention to sounds and maybe embrace it and letting go
that helped me kind of oh good so you felt yeah go ahead Don I'd like to hear
your voice so I tried to sleep with that earplugs for last few days and just kind
of embrace the sound and not concentrate on the airplane noise but other noises like a car or just little noises around
it and that helped me go to sleep without the earplugs
that's wonderful wonderful to share that thank you so did I hear you correctly that you
also said it didn't bother you as much when you were just focused on the sounds
right before just focusing on airplane noise oh so you opened up the your um
hearing kind of sentences to all sounds not just the one that was annoying you
right so I was just concentrating on the car noise maybe my neighbor you know making noise
or just anything and sound of the wind the rain and just other things and they
were all kind of pleasing sound all together wonderful was a little more peaceful more peaceful
that's great it's a great observation interested to hear how it progresses as
time goes on I would say one thing Grace um about
what you're sharing is an example of how when odd something starts to become
automatically preferenced in our awareness like there's a been a
preference in your mind because of the aversion to hearing the airplane sounds and now you're actually choosing
and preferencing to open up to other sounds that's like you are choosing where
you're giving your awareness that is amazing yeah yeah your World opened up a little bit
that's wonderful world the sound beautiful world of sound
and to say that the same exact way of opening up your attention does wonders
and working with pain too this is a similarity this preference thing that
Tanya is talking about if it's aversive preferencing it can
really lock us into a feedback loop whether it's with the annoying sound or with the annoying sensation or whatnot
and this really powerful move you did of opening attention more broadly
can work in any of the senses oh okay I didn't think about it that way but I
sure could use it wonderful anybody else
yes please
it's on yeah it's about the first can you turn the mic this way toward
yeah and somebody will eat it yes yes
except you don't really have to the you talked about the first week
about breath the second week about body
so when we talk about the body
um and you talked about experiencing it
um there is dancing like for example that
in like what comes to mind is not like the body pain or whatever but the
mathematics of it like or the science where that is people involved in that is
part of the you know the beat and the even the
uh the physiology of the various muscles that are moving like 14 000
limbs you know there is a um in
the there is a book which is Turtle dance of Shiva where he talks about
Unison earlier I used the word Unified where the dance
is referred to as something which is unifying the entire universe
um by that experience of of for the body
and there is mathematics and there is science I mean like for example in classical dancing there is
we can make a circle in four steps or a diagonal or you know the
um so that rhythm with the exercise that the body is able to get by
virtue of this you know the scientific methods is what I wanted to say how we
experience how we can experience body yeah so in our our scene here in
the terravata scene the mindfulness meditation
we try and um kind of keep our experience
our attention focused on our direct experience not the concepts but the direct experience so one thing
you're pointing to is there's you know like the muscles so sometimes in our practice like we might tune in to a
muscle in the body but we might also tune into the whole body but again it's like how do we just experience it not so
much how we think about it but how do we experience the heartbeat
in the body or these other things that you're referencing so direct connection direct experiencing
thank you yeah go ahead I have a quick question I
I have experienced that when I meditate my my dream world is more relaxed like
if I skip one day I don't meditate um I have more like a vivid or kind of
like anxious dreams like a little bit into the nightmare but it doesn't happen when
I meditate it just has any relationship or it's just a
is my observation great great I think it's a great observation very
good noticing of cause and effect potentially or at least some kind of correlation
I would encourage you to stay curious stay interested in the effects both on
your dream world but also on your Waking Life on the days you meditate versus the
days you don't many people do report sleeping better the days they meditate it seems there's
something that processes through mentally and physically
um that makes sleep a little bit easier but I'd be hesitant to draw a one-to-one
this is always going to be this way it's going to change constantly perhaps
or maybe for you it doesn't but to just stay interested stay curious Tanya do you want to add anything to
that I love what you're noticing I really do you know and
I think it is good to be really curious about it the I think what Dawn is also pointing
to is to remember we like to figure things out
you know we like to kind of X Plus y equals this
but then we start to relate to experience as a rule
does that make sense it's this is that but experience is so much more Dynamic
and there's so many things that are influencing what happens you know it's it's and we're changing
all the time so what we want to be careful of is making like these fixed
ideas about you know this is going to lead to that well it probably will but we always need
to stay connected to and open to what's really happening or
we start to relate to experience from our expectations instead of what what's actually happening
Monique did you have something
so I read in this science book that um when a stimulus comes and it generates
an emotion then you know whatever chemical process arises in the
body if you just observe it and allow it to
pass through it should flush in I think there is a finite amount of seconds 90
seconds you're actually taking an anecdote right from the top I'm about to go no that's great I will stop then
great so yes good good anecdote that that'll lead me right in then
the scientists that I'm familiar with you may have read a different citation is a woman named Jill bolte Taylor she
is a neuroscientist at Harvard and she talks about how emotions from an
embodied perspective we're not reducing emotions just to this but from an embodied perspective they're kind of a
chemical hormonal physical process and if left alone as Monique said
they tend to flush through our body in about a minute and a half 90 seconds
now most of us don't just let them move through most of
the time right we have extra layers of reaction another
emotion about the emotion are based on an assumption about the emotion or there's a thought that comes in
so all of those extra layers perpetuate the loop of the emotion
in in the Buddhist framework the Buddhist
framework this is called adding a second Arrow piercing ourselves with a second Arrow
the Buddha tells this story of just an unnamed man
who is hit by an Archer one Arrow let's just say in the arm it's not a mortal wound but it's very painful
that's the first Arrow that's what life throws at us right
or it's a mistake or whatnot the second arrow and the third and the
tenth and the 15th those are what we add on top
so if I'm walking through my house and I stubbed
my toe out that's the first Arrow if I then start to have a lot of
self-recrimination ah stupid clumsy what were you thinking second Arrow
what am I doing teaching mindfulness I wasn't mindful at all whack hit my toe
people are going to discover I'm a klutz and not a teacher oh no third Arrow
fourth arrow and it can build from there and there and there and just get bigger and more complicated and more convoluted
even with this silly little example right so
mindfulness helps us not to get over involved
and not to believe the second Arrow third Arrow tenth arrow and eventually
not even to pick it up or not so that the arrow doesn't have as much pointiness as much pain associated with
it so
there's a kind of a beautiful quality of mindful awareness when it comes to
emotions and into thinking but especially to emotions
and that is if mindfulness is able to really hold
an emotion the afflictive the difficult emotions those tend to wane and wither over time
through this careful mindful attention
The Beneficial emotions those that come from a kind of deeper Wellspring in US
altruistic love peace calm
generosity those when seen with mindfulness and
this kind of discernment those tend to grow
so there's a real power in stepping back and being open
and allowing our emotion space to respect them
this is an opportunity on the cushion and many of us aren't necessarily used to feeling the full range of our
emotions because we live in society and we're in relationships and we have jobs
or commitments or whatnot and it's not always wise or even safe to express
every emotion happening so the habit can be to kind of shut out the ones that aren't convenient
right mindfulness is a kind of pause of presence a sacred pause that allows all
of the emotions to flow through and happen and get metabolized
get metabolized so
it can be a really powerful experience to allow this to happen it's
not always an easy one but the key is to let an emotion Express
and not get over involved not pushing away
not repress it not deny it and not fuel it not add fuel to the fire
right so let's just try a little three breath
Journey here it's really simple
taking a breath and settling into your body settling into your heart
and allow whatever prominent emotion
opening right now just to emerge into your heart your body your mind
breathing second breaths feeling the sensations
of the emotion emotions happen in the body
does it feel like and then with the third breath
notice your relationship to the emotion
whatever that is like dislike board
whatever
so just that little three breath Journey gives a sense of how emotions
kind of live in the body and are also inextricably
interwoven with the mind and the Heart Right
in the Buddhist framework of how the mind works
emotions and thoughts are two different species of mental activity in this big
overall ecosystem and we'll talk more about thinking and
thoughts next week but now for now just to acknowledge as Tanya said it's not
like just because we're teaching emotions you can't think your minds are going to think
but to just notice it and for this week this session to privilege the emotions and the Body
Sensations related to them
and notice notice how mindfulness might just help
emotions come and go flow through without as many complications of
judgment or aversion or resistance or stories or
preferences and if those things come up
to just notice those don't need to do anything to them and you certainly don't need to start adding
another arrow because this natural process comes up
that too Withers over time in most circumstances through this process of
mindful awareness
the alternative that mindful awareness cultivates is a kind of letting be
kind of letting be not even the self-recrimination about
adding the arrows right even letting that be if necessary
so to notice the looping the amplification
that this neuroscientist Joe Bolton Taylor talks about to notice it
when it happens and for now we're going to provide you with some Alternatives I'll provide you with some in this
guided meditation and Tanya will teach a great technique for investigation later
on which is another alternative to kind of get in there and and fillet
things apart but meanwhile it's really helpful to
notice whatever emotion is happening while it's happening in the body
if you see the second arrows tenth arrows extra layers just internally notice them as such and
for now return to the body return to the breath let them be in the background
like Tanya said our bodies they're always here they're always here now right
they're not there and then and most emotions not necessarily that first
arising the 90 seconds but the loop is often about it there and then
or a set of assumptions
it's really helpful to notice Sensations and posture
extra reactions can include neural tension muscular tension even physical
pain so just notice that if it happens
and most of all to notice that internal inner posture
inner relationship too okay
so we'll do a longer guided meditation now um
I'm starting us off here some of you are already meditating but
if you aren't just take a moment to notice how your
body is and notice how the feelings are just having heard all
that all this talking neat ideas the great comments the great questions
and take a moment to relax and soften
maybe taking a slightly more relaxed longer breath or two at the beginning
into your belly your diaphragm
and now sleeping your attention scanning through
your body noticing the places that might be
inclined to relax
start with some of the places that are most helpful
to tune into the details of the meditation posture
noticing the balance of your head over your
shoulders softening the eyes
if they're not closed and it feels okay to do so closing them
training from staring forward into the future
perhaps allowing the eyes to be Softly downcast behind the closed lids
or even slightly looking back towards the body and the Heart
allowing your face and neck to soften
inviting the shoulders to soften and maybe roll back a little bit
giving just a little more space in the rib cage for the breath
noticing the shifting changing position of your
ribs and your chest as the breath Moves In and Out
noticing how the breath might soften your back
middle back lower back upper back
and allowing your belly to hang Softly
gently
softening the buttocks and the thighs
allowing any excess tension
to drain out of your calves and ankles and feet
as well as out of your forearms upper arms hands
just inviting may this body relax
allowing the attention to be in your whole body
noticing the movement of breath
noticing any Sensations in your chest around your heart
and inviting allowing
any emotion that might be present
can be helpful perhaps to softly name it inside with a label
gratitude or sadness or
calm whatever it is
noticing any Sensations in your body
your heart your belly
with the naming the acknowledging
that starts to shift and change noticing that
and if no emotion is obvious it's okay just to rest
your attention on the breath and the body
from noticing then what replaces that emotion what comes
next
letting be with
allowing
and as you explore this noticing too any extra
layers second arrows of reaction
judgment story
oh okay the reaction
bye-bye
charging or allowing
whatever it is
noticing the relationship between any commentary
and the feelings emotions emerging
if you find yourself pulled into an emotion or a story about an emotion
returning to the body returning to the breath
your anchor of attention homebabes here
and when the mind the attention has studied a little bit
perhaps with part of the attention on the breath noticing again if any emotions
are arising
returning again to this moment
noticing as gently and kindly as possible what's present
what's the inner relationship the inner posture
to what's happening right now
and in the last moment or two of this meditation
returning the full attention
this body and the breath feeling the effects
of these moments of mindfulness on any tension or relaxation
sensation
noticing acknowledging whatever emotions or moods are present
noticing too the internal response all the way
through the bell ringing
[Music]
foreign
thank you for your practice you're going along on that little trip
and I both of us would love to hear any
comments or questions how that was for you anything you want to share
there's no wrong comment or wrong question
and if there's a microphone within your reach if you could grab it and turn it on and just have it ready there's one
there and one right there do mine just helping um move them around as needed
hi um thank you for the meditation in the session
um I guess I had a question um because I feel like I'm having a hard
time with noticing emotion um I feel like the past two sessions like
noticing your breath noticing like Sensations in your body your pain and things like that feel very tangible and
like doable for me uh and I guess in this session I noticed
that um I start with thinking to notice emotion
like I'm like because when you were like oh like notice what emotions are present for you and then I'm like okay let me
think of all the stuff in the back of my head and then I start to label like okay these are the emotions I'm feeling
and then I guess my brain doesn't know what to do so it goes back to thinking and it's like okay let's think about everything related to these emotions and
how I'm gonna fix it what I'm gonna do um so yeah I just feel like I don't know
how to like find the space or I don't know if I know what it means to notice emotion and I feel like I
get caught between like I can do the breath and body part
and maybe that feels like I'm not focusing on the emotion when I'm
doing that or I'm not feeling the emotion but then to feel the emotion I end up going straight to thinking so
um yeah that was my question there's Ancient Ancient Habit in all
humans tangling those two things together so good noticing very good noticing of
that that you're getting pulled in it's sticky as what we call it in our scene sticky right there's like a
gravitational pull into the thought world so um
one thing that's really helpful is to slow it down and to when you do feel an emotion maybe
instead of I hear the natural sort of ticking off you know there's all these because there's all this stuff in the
back of the head if it's possible to slow it down and pick one and then like really
feel in your body if you feel anything associated with it or not
and kind of take it one bird at a time so to speak right
one one at a time so that's one thought Tanya do you have
anything you'd like to add to that yeah what happens if I ask you right now
how are you feeling I think it's the same thing like I go
straight to like oh I I guess I'm feeling all these things because of
all the thinking that's happened in the back of my head so if you were gonna answer me with a feeling word how are
you feeling a little anxious
it's okay right there just stay with a little anxious
where do I feel at my body how do I know I feel anxious or a little
anxious and the next practice we'll do will help you also with essentially a lot of what
you're asking but um you know I think Donna's right that in
your right you know emotions get very the relationship between emotions and
thoughts right like it's a big one big one so it does take some refinement
but it's so powerful when you can start to pull them apart so incredibly helpful that's what starts
to get us out of that reciprocal kind of reigniting an emotion over and over
again is once we stop the the thinking process and we turn more to the raw
Direct oh okay all right we'll set on I know I feel lots of things anxious so how do I
know I feel anxious right now what what's happening in my body that tells me there's anxiety
where do what does that feel like so it's a lot of focusing on those
tangible things related to the emotion yes okay that's helpful thank you
hi Tanya hi Don good evening thank you um this this session I I felt uh was
released and because of the lights at first I was like wow this is new but I I
don't know maybe this it being so subdued contributed to I think for the
first time in my sitting I was just kind of aware of my breath and the noises
from the outside so that was nice and um the attempts at wanting to clear my
mind there was no attempt it was just
there and it was nice and then I kind of noticed when Don had
said let's I'm gonna ring the bell and notice how that feels
but then I was also noticing well when's the second one coming
um but then I'm like it's just I'm noticing things more rather than attaching
things to it which is really nice so this the meditations from this from last
Thursday to now I've been able to just note oh okay right now I'm feeling blank
and just being with that so it's just it's just very it's just very
helpful I don't think I'm trying so much as I'm just doing it without the trying I don't know how to
explain it sometimes it just sometimes it happens and no as Tanya said no two sittings are the same so
thank you okay
thank you great report
anybody else please
you have a question about emotion
yeah yeah I meanwhile please
how come can you write it down in Jared and bring it over because we gotta
one comment you made earlier about the arrow and the second Arrow the third
Arrow um while reflecting it's like
if we want to feel the pain it's like one way another way is
like um let's say it's a there is a curved mirror
and the ray comes at an angle versus like right in
the center of the you know the um mirror
so when we have the if it is coming at an angle then
it will never hurt it's it will be grazing um
if we that is how we feel that feel those arrows versus if we
really say that okay this is really coming right in the middle then that's like the
um I don't know if I'm so I'm just interpreting your comments
so how we alleviate pain or how we let go of that pain even despite that you
know it's one two three several arrows still but they are all
okay you didn't know am I so I'm not sure I'm understanding everything you're
saying but it sounds like you're saying there's something Less Direct about the
second third fourth tenth arrows is that right we we are aware
we are aware that those arrows are there but
um even if like the first one has made us alert and aware but
even if there are several of them but they just keep grazing
now it is up to us how we interpret um so whether
it is like a soft um
tenderness or whatever we would I don't know what we will call it but it's
it is um arousing the tenderness but it is
not um significant enough that it is
causing any harm it is it is just making us aware
one by one I mean or even if there is just one Arrow that's that's fine too
I'm just making trying to interpret those comments about the
um when you um talk about arrows and you know the being
aware or being pres I don't know if you I can say being present with respect to
pain or whatever so what I hear you saying is that the
interpretation of what happens next is very important and there's a lot of wisdom to that
and it's helpful to notice the interpretations our minds are
making that are increasing pain and the interpretations are increasing the tenderness you're talking about that
make them less that make subsequent judgments because we were the the analogy here to the
second and third and fourth arrow is in our own minds right our own interpretations there's a beautiful
story of the Buddha's Awakening where the forces of delusion are sending
arrows at him and he turns them into flowers so a very
um attuned mind can take anything a wake mind can take anything as information in
order to increase wisdom understanding even Awakening so
thank you for your comment great
so let me introduce another part another way to work with emotions a little more
structured it's based on an acronym that essentially spells the word raft
but with two T's and before I describe the raft in terms
of what the acronym is I want to just say what the place of the simile of a raft is in the
Buddhist teaching which is essentially the Buddha taught a story about how the
tools that you learn the practices that we're learning will act like a raft that can help you
cross a river to the shore of Freedom away from the
shore of suffering suffering and that we use those tools
we have to actually actively paddle with our arms and legs on that raft
to get from one side to the other and once we get to that side we don't
need to keep using the raft right we can leave the raft on the shore
but it's a very this idea of a tool or a way or a practice that can help us stay
afloat in the current of life the flow of thoughts and emotions and
experiences and arrows so this simile of a raft is a very
profound one in the teachings um
the other thing I'll say about the simile is that it is essentially
a way to relate a guide for relationship to our experience
a step-by-step process to help us find our way
with emotions in particular
and you know we're really trying to emphasize awareness and attention so
being aware of and what we're attending to and then the relationship
we're having with our experience so what is our you know inner
relationship with tenderness or harshness right
or many other adjectives you can choose and
you know or in our ordinary life when we're not practicing mindfulness
you could say that our minds act like a boat or a raft
that's adrift in the currents we're not paddling we're just getting tossed about we're
going to and fro based on whatever is thrown our way internally or externally does that make sense
so you could describe the ordinary mind or the unmindful Mind as a mind that is
unrelated unconnected ungrounded disconnected right to a process to being
aware to we're not really relating to it we're reacting or going
in this flow and that when we're when we get carried
away by it like that we lose perspective we can't see the
shore right so we can't Orient we don't have a um kind of anyone we can
turn to there's no relationship there there's no reference point
so as we grow our awareness as we grow our mindfulness our self-awareness
right we start to grow a self-relationship a
meditation relationship
and a lot of um awareness itself that just knowing
is this actual simple ability very pure simple knowing
very very simple and pure knowing kind of almost even a neutral attention
but it takes some time to get there to that neutral space so we use
kind of our capacity to grow our ability to relate to ourselves with
this more open more fluid more responsive way of being
there's a quote from Victor Frankl and man search for meaning and it's
between the stimulus let's see between a stimulus and a
response is the place for potential Freedom that
pause between something happening and are reacting to it the pause
is where our freedom is found and the more pause the more freedom more choice we have
so that creating the capacity for that pause requires a neutrality
if we are immediately reactive to what's coming at up it feeds the intensity right the more
likely we are to react quickly to something
so this you know kind of attention this awareness it is possible to become aware
of being aware we can start to notice that oh I'm aware and there's a way that
when we see that oh I I look I'm not I'm aware oh now I'm aware I'm anxious
there's a little bit of a sitting back that can happen into that oh just pure
knowing so that'll happen from time to time you'll move in and out of it but when
you notice it try and when you feel like oh yeah I'm aware that I'm aware ah feel
into that space that that's there's something there that can be very supportive and helpful
so now we'll come back to the acronym raft I'll tell you what each letter stands
for and then I'll move into a guided practice for you
so R is a simple recognition like oh hi Corey I see you you're
sitting here like just this oh hello right I see you you know so the naming
is part of that like the wrecking you know naming is a way that we get into
Clarity with something right like that's where the naming of an emotion becomes
helpful because we get oh now I know what I'm focusing on okay there's a lot going on in here but
oh let me name that emotion and if it's hard to name you could
choose to say describe it in a simple word like painful or Intense or hot you know so
don't worry about getting the exact right name but something that feels like
enough right um so recognize
The Next Step the a is to have a relationship with what
you're recognizing that allows it to be there allows it space
a lot of times we don't want what we're feeling or we want more of what we're feeling
and either way we're not really allowing space for that emotion
for what's going on so recognize then allow see if I can't
kind of accept as another optional word but sometimes people have a hard time I
can't accept that I'm feeling this way or that this is going on but can you
allow that it is already happening that's the thing it's already here
so allowing that reality to be acknowledged the F and the raft is to feel it to find
and fill it in the body so that's when we start to really turn into it in more intimate way like okay
I named this as anxiety this is such a good one so common what does that feel like where
do I fill up my solar plexus oh no it's more in my stomach kind of spreads up or
oh it's like in my chest I can't breathe feels like pressure
you know um it feels like you know squeezing it feels like
pounding so whatever words work but to describe the sense sensation of it the
feeling and part of what we're doing is disconnecting from the thinking Story right which allows us to stop that kind
of circular pattern of reigniting the emotion and sometimes it's so simple and
fast it's almost like oh I named it and it disappears literally it can really
move just instantly through us other times emotions are longer lasting even
if we're we think we're trying to shift toward the sensation because there's something stronger in the mind some
image or idea that that kind of permeates
the next part in the raft is to tease it apart like to literally help yourself oh
here's the memory of that back then that's not happening here and now but
this memory is part of it oh here's the story I'm telling myself about having this feeling like aren't I done with
this yet aren't I better yet that's my story so I like to imagine a
big round table with a lot of chairs and a lot of space
and so as I tease apart what's happening in the in the emotion if I get this far
because it may have dissolved already I'd like to give each little part that I
become aware of a seat at this table I don't have to do anything else but
name them and give it a little space sometimes they need recliners
you know you can play with your mind and what helps you let it sit what you what
helps it allow it to be there and kind of let it it's like pulling apart something so you can see it better you
got a better view oh my God look at this I'm anxious right now partly because of
what happened to me in kindergarten oh oh and and there's the friend that I had
at that time sitting over here too and I don't even know who she is anymore right so it starts to help us kind of
disentangle the the big tangle inside our minds
the last T and the Double T is to end with a sense of trust
can we trust the nature of Life can we trust that these emotions
come and go what can you trust because what does trust do when we feel into trust what happens
Ah that's not letting go we're relaxing
and that's really important because we've just done a lot of work trying to figure these things out and now we just
don't need to do anything else we can trust what we know we can trust that there's a process just like the body
knows how to digest food when you eat it your body knows how to synthesize an
emotion if we feel it we don't have to like tell it step by
step what to do it knows how the system knows how
so if we can get out of the way if we can stop at shooting the arrows
can we trust the system can we trust nature can we trust awareness
can we trust that things change come and go and that this is going to change on
its own in some point some way all right
so now let's practice so first of all I want you to orient
we're going to do this fairly quickly but anytime we're going to practice it's
always good Orient okay where am I right now what day is this what time is this how is my body what is my posture
take a minute to yep Rock back and forth sit up okay I want to bring an upright
attention to my practice I want to be awake I want to see
I want to connect and then finding you know the body
finding yourself settling into the body
set your attention to be aware I want to work on being aware and
mindful and present for my experience Here and Now
as directly as I can be not the story the experience
and then let's take three deep breaths just three longer breaths
with the exhale inviting and letting go to relax into an upright posture but
letting the muscles soften
okay and then just like if we're
coming into contact with another human you might ask
what are you feeling what am I feeling right now
and you might feel many things so just just choosing and naming
one emotion one feeling
kind of like oh I'm I'm mostly relaxed but I can feel a
little Edge a little anxiety little sadness
a little frustration whatever it is just okay let me tune into this
I see you
so choose one part of your emotional experience that you're willing to relate
to right now in this moment
and then notice with the a am I able to allow this emotion this
feeling to be acknowledged right now
allowing it to be known
there can be a feeling of rightness that happens in this moment a feeling of
okay yes
and when you feel that sense of okay I can allow this
move to the F the find and fill it if you can't find that feeling of allowing
what you can then name is resistance not wanting and an emotion in that
that might be what you end up then recognizing oh yeah I can allow myself to recognize
I'm resisting I'm not wanting I don't like okay
and then we move to the f can you find it and feel it in your sensation body
key places to check are the belly and the chest
the shoulders and neck
the jaw eyebrow Temple area
eyes but even the hands you might notice or
the feet and legs can be bracing
seeing if you can't gently recognize the sensations and where you feel them in
your body just that acknowledging awareness just as it is
and rather than resisting it or succumbing to it
kind of standing with it in Witness
if you find any of the feelings or sensation become overwhelming
it's okay to back up shift your focus or just tune into one part that feels
manageable we don't need to try and do too much or
work with something that doesn't feel like we can be with it
when you're ready if there's something there that still would be worked with
we move to the teasing apart this is that idea of the table
the chairs where we might acknowledge
oh here's the story I tell myself about this feeling and give it a seat
oh here's an image of myself give it a seat
oh here's liking or not liking this feeling and give it a seat
so there's ideas about things there's stories beliefs
memories images
preferences these are all parts that could be teased
apart maybe if you can figure out two pieces of it and just set it at the table
that's enough
and as you allow this some space you might just drop in the question
hmm what's hard for me about being with us
or where do I feel stuck
what what do I want to get rid of
in what way do I not want this experience
and then moving to the last t because you just because we're
practicing quickly with this right now you can always come back
if you were going to shift to the last T what can I trust about what I'm seeing about my
experience about mindfulness
like emotions won't kill me for example might be something you can
trust maybe breathing helps me
can you trust that
maybe it's helpful to know it's impermanent and that it will change can
you trust that
and giving yourself another 20 seconds to find what you trust
something simple inviting that trust to come more fully
into your being
[Music]
so we have time for one or two questions or comments
um how was that for you how was the raft process for you
great grab the mic
I think this one was kind of intense only because I was recognizing that I oh
all the stressors that I've allowed in my life and and how it's just been I've allowed myself to be dominated by the
stresses of work and I'm like oh I have more to cultivate outside of that and
then then I was allowing myself to uh allowing myself with that kind of
recognition that my life is not my job and then feeling I
was feeling all the the things and focusing but then I was also just recollecting
all the things that happened today at work and but then I noticed that it was all positive stuff and so I think
towards the end I've I just was trying to trust myself in
that I can I can just be like put the practice and just whatever happens it's
okay I can just know what I'm
at least be more aware of what I'm thinking what happened and Rose when you
got to that point what did you notice uh
it was a bit free a bit frame just a little bit a little bit is a lot
I but there was also the part though that you had mentioned about
the space between the thought yes and I just I don't know if is it because I don't
have the emotional maturity yet to to not respond you know or just
I'm like I want to have that emotional intelligence to not react in a way where
I I will regret what I'm doing or saying I just can I can I say something
about that emotional intelligence piece is that
um it is wisdom we grow
but it's it's wisdom that's like a muscle not like IQ
it's a muscle that grows the wisdom that grows from direct experience direct knowing
directly having that little moment of a little bit of freedom
every time we have that experience with awareness we're growing and strengthening that
wisdom so it's a combination of a a muscle that
we grow the capacity but also the taking in of the wisdom
does that make sense so it's a process it takes practice
we don't go from no Gap to a huge gap
usually so thank you thank you
and that was wonderful illustration and I'll be here after we need to shift to
closing so if anyone has other comments or questions afterwards please don't
hesitate to approach Don or I yeah we'll both stay after meanwhile I just want to
offer on behalf of both of us are deeply sincere appreciation for all of you and
for coming here and for cultivating this in your practice and
to invite you to um consider some homework assignment to
Mission should you choose to accept it there's four components this this week
and they're all on the handout but I'm just going to briefly mention them now
the first is to up your meditation time to 25 minutes a day if you're not
already practicing that much when you can with all the caveats that we know
that life happens so whether it's five times a week or seven times a week or three times a week
to do the best you can the second is to really at some point in
the week you can do it more than once if you want notice an emotion coming up
and just ride it out just dried it out rather than
Building stories about it or getting into commentary about it see how
what best you can ride it out and use the tools the raft tools that Tanya just
gave they are also on the handout so you don't have to remember everything she said
the third thing is to really take time to notice and Savor any feelings of
Happiness contentment Joy anything in the positive beneficial Realm
and the last is um notice which feelings which emotions
pull you into preoccupation
many of us have sort of a Greatest Hits list right and to just start to notice
what your pattern is we've all got them so those are all written down
should you choose to accept it that's what we're asking you to do and
also just to mention that there are other resources here at IMC there is a book of Gil franstal our
guiding teacher one of our guiding teachers essays called the issue at hand and I believe that stack of books is in
the front on the little counter the Donna box as you exit and there's also on that same area a
newsletter so both of those contain resources of different kinds essays or
entries about other classes other groups that kind of thing
so thank you again so much for your practice for being here together in
community and with us and if you all have other questions or
comments please feel free to come up and chat with us thank you guys we're going to dedicate
the Merit very briefly sorry may all beings everywhere
including and especially ourselves and those Our Lives touch benefit from this practice
[Music]
thank you all