so welcome welcome everybody so before I start I have two
announcements but it sounds like that volume is a little bit
high thank you Jim if we can turn it down there we go thank
you otherwise I yeah end up doing something weird with my voice if I I
feel like the volume is a little bit off two announcements um there will not be a
gathering on December 25th Monday night December 25th we will not have something
here and the next week January 1 I'm going to change the time a little bit
I'm going to have a start 15 minutes earlier so at 7:15 and end at
8:30 so the meditation will be 30 minutes It'll be longer I'm sorry
shorter and so that uh and then the Dharma talk will be the same 7:15 to
8:30 just so the night ends a little bit
earlier so those are my kind of like two announcements I guess we have a few more
Mondays with the regular schedule and then January 1 will be the new schedule I'll try to remember to make
sure that that's the calendar will be changed I'll try to remember to make sure that the website gets changed too
I mean that there's a notice but if you end up showing up at 8 7:30 that'll be okay
too okay so today I wanted to talk a little bit about what are some of the supports for
practice or what are like some of the fuel for practice or what are some of the nourishments for practice we might
say no matter what however we Define practice whether it's uh meditation
mindfulness practice or loving kindness practice or concentration practice or
practicing with ethical Behavior or practicing generosity and
compassion you know whatever whatever we have as a practice or whatever we Define
our practice as the truth is it's not like we always every day all the time
feel motivated to do this right of course not we're not machines we're humans but what
are some of the things that can be a support for us I know sometimes like out
there in the greater World they talk about well remember your why like you know why you're doing something okay so
that can help but maybe there's a little bit more uh detail or something more
that we can add here and so in the suas there are a a number of things that are a support for
practice and it's not formalized as a list instead I kind of like pulled
things out of some other lists and some um other teachings and kind of like I'm
gathering them here today just to something that might be a resource or something to think about like what is
the most meaningful for you like maybe there's something I'm going to talk about that really will be a support for
your practice you know maybe not all of them will be maybe you'll feel inspired or motivated and maybe you won't but the
objective is I just wanted to offer something to
consider so one thing that's kind of interesting to this like some of these supports to practice are often related
to what brought us to the practice to begin with in some ways this is kind of like
you know remembering your why like why are you doing this
but there's something um the reasons that bring us to the path are very often
kind of like smaller they're like a they're not as uh vibrant they're not as
compelling they're not as provocative as what supports us or as what propels us
on the path and I'd like to talk about that a little bit more but because part of what
uh really supports practice is connected to maybe some like some deep um deep
longings or deep questions that we have that we might not even know that we have
until after some practice maybe there's a way in which we start to maybe see
some benefits or we notice that as the mind starts to settle down it touches
into some other things that uh we didn't even know were there or
there's a way that uh that something that's maybe deep or really inside of us
can be your support for practice and um maybe there's this way
also of kind of practice is uh this o o opening up of what's
possible maybe we used to think like okay yeah I'm going to start meditation because I'm a person who has a lot of
anxiety I'm just going to bring this up but then as we start to practice we start to realize oh yes I have anxiety
but yes I have care for other people and yes uh I also have some warmth and I'm
able to develop that or so our ideas about our s
grows and also our ideas about what the practice can offer
grows so with that as an introduction I'll introduce uh one of these first uh
qualities the poly word is svea and it's often translated as a sense of urgency
like a sense of yeah this is something I really want to do and I'm going to get with it I'm going to do
this and some of you might know maybe all of you know about this story of the
Buddha when he the Buddha to be before he was the Buddha when he was just like
us that he was uh he encountered after having this opulent
lifestyle filled with you know every Pleasures known at that time he
encountered sickness old age and death which because uh just the circumstances
of his life that they had been pretty much sheltered from maybe in some of the
ways in which we often are sheltered from this sickness and death death right
often that we don't have encountering dead people or dying people unless there
are immediate family or something like this right it's not something that's really part of a popular
culture so the Buddha to be that we would call him a Buddha SATA at this
time before he's a Buddha he encounters old age sickness and death it's like wow
this is awful is there a way that we can get around this
I don't want this and of course isn't it's one of the
truths about uh The Human Experience and so this is what spurred
him on to practice some of you might know that he left his life as the palace
he lived in and became an aesthetic he went from one extreme to the other and
practiced for many years before becoming awakened but whether for us it might be
some something like sickness old age and death but maybe there's something that
there's a tragedy in our life or a loss in our life could be with health or a
loss of a loved one or of a relationship or whatever it might be some sense of
real deep uh grief and sense of loss and maybe we start to feel disoriented and
losing the meaning that we had of our life or what we thought what a good life should have or how am I going to make my
life work now that there's been this tragedy or loss so there's a sense of like okay
well I think uh a spiritual practice might you know be a support for
this or maybe even the loss isn't something about health or relationship
maybe it's something about an existential crisis something about what
is life about is this all there is is is is there anything more I thought
it was going to be better here I am at this age and what you know it's still so
much work or I I don't know there's so many different ways that we might think about this what comes to my mind right
there's a reason why people in the middle of their life buy sports cars or you know do
something different is because they're thinking like yeah I I was kind of hoping there'd be something
more so maybe sense of urgency is maybe that's not a good
translation but this sense of this wish for more and and a maybe a belief that
there can be more it's got to be something richer or Fuller or more
satisfying some Vega and so ton taniku he uh has this
definition for s Vega that he says it's this sense of
dismay or a sense of alienation that comes with realizing like is this really what life is about
and then coupled with that is this maybe a sense of
uh complacency or foolishness like oh I've been following this path I've been
organizing this my life in a way that um my community Society supports but it
didn't lead to where I thought it was I followed all the rules I you know did
what Society expected of me and yet my life isn't turning out the way that I thought so some Vega sometimes this
sense of urgency Chanda this this another poly
word often gets translated as enthusiasm or Zeal I like this word zeal enthusiasm
a good word too but um it comes from that's one off not this
isn't the only place it gets described but uh in one of the sutas it it's described as
um uh the Buddha is instructing like okay how can you find a way to freedom
to nibana to Awakening and he gives this long
detailed list of steps you can do and it starts with um finding what you think somebody who
you think think could be a teacher and evaluating them do they have
qualities or do they behave in such a way that seems to like promote a sense
of greed hatred and delusion if so they're not a good teacher but do they
seem to not be promoting greed hatred and delusion then they could be a good
teacher so this real thing you know don't believe everybody but to evaluate
them and to and gives particular criteria and you're welcome to do that with me do I have greed hatred and
delusion I'm not perfect right I'm not a completely awakened person
but so then they said that okay so if you find that there's somebody that is
not promoting greet hatred and delusion then um go to listen to their teachings
and reflect on their meaning and only accept them after consideration so not
only just believe everything the teacher says but to reflect on them and uh
accept them after consideration and then they says here
that's just natural that some enthusiasm or some Zeal Springs up that like this like okay I hear somebody who's talking
about something that makes sense to me I think there's a um a willingness to
engage with the teachings willingness to um um put them into practice to try them
out right easo was like this key teaching come and see and so part of
this the teacher is like well come and see here's uh what the teachings are and so this enthusias I'm like okay I don't
have to just believe it and you know just do what's being told to me but there's a way um I want to try this out
I do want to see for myself what's being described so maybe there's a way that
something just make makes sense to us by what the teacher is saying like oh yeah
and I'll say for me personally when I first heard the four noble truths which
was very surprisingly was during a yoga class I didn't wasn't seeking some
Dharma teachings they were in at my view at the time they were uh what's the word like
they were like forced on me they were push put on me I thought I was going to be taken yoga class they were this
little Dharma talk got put in there but wow when they talked about the formable
truth like there is suffering there is a cause of suffering and there's the ending of suffering and
a way to the end of suffering it meant a lot to me it meant like oh yeah this is
something I really want to pursue to look at and explore and for me that was
uh I had some real enthusiasm and Zeal from what I had heard I didn't really know that teacher didn't have an
opportunity really to examine or investigate them but uh that just that's
hearing something that made sense to me kind of had this Zeal show up so maybe
that's something also that can be a support maybe there is a um a way
that you can keep in like what what brought you to the practice and maybe even like some of the deeper
aspects of it can be a support for practice to touch into that here's a a third thing that can be
a support for practice the poly word is do this means a like Vision or seeing I
guess literally would be seeing sometimes translated as Vision but more
specifically this Vision or scene of what's
possible it's Not Unusual for people to maybe when they were younger or maybe
even just recently they had a sense of what is possible sometimes this is they
have an extreme experience tragedy or um like near
drowning or you know something like this heard of this or some uh real
severe uh accidents or psychedelics let's be honest some
people do psychedelics and this practice was started you know it's not an
accident that the the founder people who brought this back from Asia I think the
reason why they went to Asia back in the 60s is because they had their own psychedelic
experiences so there's people who have this touch into this view or this idea
like oh there's more to this world there's something else and they want to do a meditation practice as a way to
touch into or see or experience that again or maybe
sometimes there's people who have meditative experiences that they try to you know
touch into before I I this is very very common
people like oh yeah there was that time that it was so Blissful and happy okay I
got to do it again and I was let's see what shirt was I wearing when I did that and what breakfast did I have and you
know we'll do everything we can and I have certainly done my share that too trying to like recreate some
fabulous experiences which by the way never works just but you won't know that until
you try it so it doesn't matter that I said this because what happens right as soon as we enter this we do this like oh
I want this again just that wanting is prevents it from happening
so just a heads up about that not to be disappointed if uh you don't immediately
have those experiences again in fact I think uh I heard this as a dermat talk um I
can see the name of the Dharma teacher his name now just right left
my um Steve Armstrong I heard him say this one time he said uh during a
Meditation Retreat he said there's nothing that ruins your whole day more
than a really good sit first thing in the morning because then you're does you
know try to have it again or something like this so but dos this vision of
what's possible and wanting to maybe like oh yeah even knowing that there's a
different way of viewing or experiencing the world or
just having a really Pleasant peaceful expansive spacious experience where the suffering is um
drifted away and and it is true there are Bliss states too and so maybe you've
had something like that I've had like just tears of happiness this usually
arises more on the longer Retreats when you have time to really sink in but
that's was quite something to just feeling like yeah just just tears just
lots and just so beautiful nothing but tears so daana is another thing that
might be a support for
practice and so another one is this poly word niida and this often gets translated as
disenchantment and sometimes when uh people hear some Buddhist teacher talking about
disenchantment then what they kind of hear is like discouragement but it's not about
discouragement at all in fact it um it follows it's in this liberative
dependent arising in this uh stepwise um list of Freedom it
follows um Sam which is a kind of like a collectedness of the mind and a
settledness of the Mind that after Sam is seeing things as they
are yatana and then uh then there's this
niida this disenchantment so seeing things as they are that leads to this
disenchantment so this is what's um being pointed to is that we see things
that don't bring us the happiness that we thought they were going to bring that uh seeing things
that as soon everything will be I'll be happy as soon as I get this as soon as I graduate as soon
as I get promoted as soon as I get that better job have the perfect relationship as soon as my partner stops doing this
soon as my partner starts doing this you know these types of things
right and then we real well then maybe maybe some of those things actually do happen maybe we do graduate get a job
our partner changes we change lose weight whatever it is maybe those things
happen and then we realize oh I'm not as happy as I thought I was
going to be right this is very this isn't an uncommon thing we
have uh very powerful Industries to
enchant us right advertising right Madison Avenue right is all about
telling us you'll be happy buy this look like that do
this or now we have uh you know these little electronic computers that we carry in our pockets like who who cares
if you're not happy here distract yourself this will be your you know something that'll make you happy happy
enough or something like this so a disenchantment is this no longer
believing oh yeah this really isn't going to be a lasting source of Happiness like I thought it
was so it's like no longer being Under This Spell you're no longer Enchanted by no
longer Under This Spell of believing that something else is is going to solve
all your problems something in the future cuz that sets up this seeking
mind everything everything's going to be better
later so something's going to be different later and then there's a way in which we
can just create our life is all about seeking whereas this practice is
pointing to no it's about kind of like finding here in this moment this
experience so disenchantment is maybe also kind of like the way that we not no
not only are we um no longer Under This Spell but maybe there's a way in which we kind of like
outgrow some ideas to in the same way that a snake that
grows its skin sheds its skin as it's growing maybe we like shed some
enchantments as uh our practice grows and
matures maybe no longer thinking that just pursuing pleasure just you know a
measure of our life is how many pleasurable experiences we can have or
chasing status or more and more money and it's often the case
that we it's not until we have a little bit of something um maybe we do get a
little bit more money compared to earlier in life or maybe you know we have a little bit more status or
whatever it is a little bit more pleasure it's often not until until we've achieved or attained some of these
things that we actually realize oh that didn't make me as happy it wasn't as
satisfying as I thought it was going to be or maybe even this idea of the kind
of like the other side of maybe there's just realizing that
worrying something doesn't actually help
and it uh makes us feel kind of awful this you know this little bit of anxiety
so no longer Under This Spell of thinking that worrying or
um yeah nagging ourselves or nagging others or something like
that so niida disenchantment something that this can
be a support for practice is realizing you know what all these other things
aren't what I thought they were going to be maybe there's this practice is something that can really support this
greater sense of well-being and freedom and another one is
compassion poly can be karuna and or
anukampa so compassion is this we this wish that we want to do something for
the world we see all this suffering and we want to do something
to end the suffering whether it's in ourselves or others one way to that compassion gets
described as it's this uh warm heart this loving heart this
uh loving kindness this respect warmth care that uh kind of like radiates
out and when it's radiating out it it encounters people who are having
difficulties of course it does CU there's a lot of people having difficulties including
ourselves and so this kind of like this kindness this
warm-heartedness when it meets difficulties it turns into compassion so
it's this uh born out of uh warmth and it's a wish for suffering to
end it's so that's compassion coruna and un PPA it's also kind of related to this
idea of this urge to maybe understand suffering is
stronger than this urge to just always avoid it maybe he's like what what's going on
here that's underneath the suffering so that I can really help
alleviate it for others and for
ourselves for some people this can be a real you know driver for
practice you know this is scene like it doesn't right it's it's uh we see it all
the time it's not like it's hidden on the difficulties of the world right
there's a whole another industry that's Mak sure that we can see all the suffering that everybody's having right the media industry is all about this
too highlighting everything that's awful maybe I should be a little more
kind in my ass test but sometimes it feels like
this so here's a um a short verse that kind of like um talks about also this is
the Buddha before he was awakened there's a verse that describes something
like what happened when um he was encountering some
suffering so this is written um in the first person so again this is the Buddha before he was awake
when he was at buddhis SATA just look at people and their
quarrels I will speak of my dismay and the way that I was shaken seeing people
thrashing about like fish and little water seeing them in conflict with each
other I became afraid I felt discontent at seeing only
conflict to the very end then I saw an Arrow here hard to see
embedded in the heart pierced by this Arrow people Dash
about in all directions but when the arrows pulled
out they don't run and they don't sink so he was seeing difficulties out
there like conflict everybody was had and he was shaking feeling
uncomfortable and this kind of and he said I felt discontent then I saw an arrow here in
the heart kind like noticing okay there's what in his heart is is what he
has is what other people have and was kind of like underline this this content
this conflict this suffering so in some ways this is kind of like about compassion too like
feeling seeing the difficulties and this wish to the difficulties to end and part
of that way that difficulties end is that we see how we are contributing like
how does what how we are help us understand how humans are in
general and maybe there's something if we can show up in a different way then
other people can be touched by that they are touched by that we all know this when we've been
around somebody who has some calm or ease or
warm-heartedness when there's a lot of difficulties it makes a difference it
does make a difference even in small ways and maybe I'll just share there was
a time earli in my practice when I was a chaplain at uh San Francisco General
Hospital those of you who don't know like San Francisco General is like a county hospital there's like this is where there's a lot of suffering there
I'll just say that there's a lot of suffering and um it was quite something for me to you know show up in hospital
rooms um you know wanting to just you know really kind of my role as a chapen was
just to provide an ear for people who wanted to talk it's hard when you're in
the hospital and uh I was in part of my training to be CH and I uh appreciated
so much what one person said said sometimes your job is to just get thrown
out of the room because they can't throw anybody out these poor people right they're
getting woken up in the middle of the night here let's take your temperature let's take some blood or you know all these things they don't get any control
out of this but at least the chaplain they they can throw out the room and
they can feel like they have some agency and St so I I kind of liked that too look like not like I had to provide
anything in particular necessarily but just this idea of you know wanting to alleviate suffering for
others and maybe there's all kinds of different ways that it's supports practice but for me when I wasn't thrown
out of the room you know it was a practice to be able to uh stay steady
and balanced with uh encountering
really the type of suffering that I hadn't seen in my kind of life you know
some of these people didn't have homes they you know had uh
addictions and they had uh mental illness and was you know just a lot of
suffering and so for me that really supported me like okay I wanted to be
able to show up with warmth and openness and spaciousness that required that I
like I had meditation practice to touch into some of the Stillness and touch
into some equinity so here are some of these
things I just wanted to offer kind of like this list of things as support for practice this isn't like a usual list
but maybe there was something here that can support you like as a nourishment for
practice so the this list let's say I started with a some Vaga this sense of
of urgency then Chanda enthusiasm or Zeal
often after hearing teachings and the sense of urgency is um
often when there's a tragedy or loss a vision of what's possible do
having touched into or seen or sensed I remember um in some practice discussion
I was saying to the teacher when I was on a retreat yeah I can like smell that there's more
freedom available like I just had this sense dos is a literally seen but
there's a way like we can feel like yeah I can see how this direction of the Mind
settling down and the heart and mind opening can continue even though I don't
quite maybe haven't experienced it I have this sense that it's available so I could be
do and then Nia this uh disenchantment maybe it's like well all
the things that I thought was going to make me happy or was going to work didn't so maybe this is something I'm going to
do here and this um I should say this
disenchantment um is comes right after that is a Vaga which is um
like no longer saying through colored lenses or a way of um sometimes it gets
translated as a yeah actually I'm not going to go down that route I'll just say
disenchantment no longer being under the spell of
things and then compassion on compa or karuna you know this wish to each each
suffering again suffering of others or ourselves those are some of the things
that can be a nourishment for practice that can help support our
practice and you'll notice that the things that I described here that are things that are often just arise
naturally through our life experiences and sometimes we might be
dismissive of them but just noticing some of these things that arise and
maybe we can bring mind as a support for practice so I'll end there and open it
up and see if there are any some questions or comments about what I shared
tonight could you please read the arrow poem
again yeah I'll just say for
um this is my own translation so you'll find if you look at it you'll find something a little bit different this is
just suan Napata 4:15 just look at people and their
quarels I will speak of my dismay and the way that I was shaking shaken seeing
people thrashing about like fish in little water seeing them in conflict with each
other I became a afraid I felt discontent at seeing only conflict to
the very end then I saw an arrow here hard to see
embedded in the heart pierced by this Arrow people Dash
about in all directions when the arrow is pulled out they don't run and they don't
sink I've kind of like this idea of people dashed about in all all directions right this is what we do like
fish in little water right we when there's difficulties we kind of flail
around and dash about you know maybe it's not the most smooth or elegant that
we can be from
act yeah theas yes but this was before he was the Buddha but it's in the suas
it's suata 415 yeah but before he was
awakened anybody else have a comment or
question um the poem really strikes a chord for
me right now um it's it's actually kind of uh crazy what a synchronicity this is
because um I uh got involved in labor organizing a few years ago and was kind
of processing my experience with a friend recently and said like you know it was like an arrow went through my
heart when I started engaging in organizing um and you know it's it's
been a big experience and a big chapter of my life but um got myself into some
uh novice trouble with I think anybody who's engaged in organizing probably
knows how complicated and and difficult and at times um you know I would even
say traumatizing organizational change can can be um but since I've started
coming to IMC and and practicing and going to therapy and doing these things for for personal growth it is kind of
like I can just rest in solidarity with others and and bring that kind of like
warm expansiveness into spaces like that that that you were describing so
um yeah I'm grateful to IMC and thank you for sharing the poem fantastic
fantastic thank you for sharing that that's really great I love to hear that thank you thank
you um since in the quote he does
mention that he saw the arrow and when the arrows moved you know people don't think he
says the so is it fair to assess that the Buddha already had some level of
attainment when he said this because he was not enlightened but he was still saying something pretty insightful right so is it is that
coming from such a place it doesn't feel like a na is saying it right so but he was saying it before he was enlightened and it still strikes a chord as powerful
as something that he would say after you know the point I'm making so it feels like so is he have some level
of attainment is he yeah it feels like because he's not enlightened but it really strikes a chord for me still like all the other sutas I'm like boom it's
like a bomb okay I get it here he's not enlightened and still really powerful so that difference is kind of jarring for
me yeah yeah yeah you know um the context of this poem is never said in
the sutas it's it's part of a collection of poems that none of the poems have
their context stated wait so yeah that's right
so I don't know I can't answer that question but I think uh all of us can relate to this though right that where
we do see this arrows in our heart I I gave a dermat talk on this uh um on this
um poem maybe I'll kind of dig that up and uh kind of Flesh it out and do
something again yeah feels feels Noddy in his head yeah cuz I love this one too
it's it's really it's a really powerful one just as you said yeah yeah yeah for some reason uh when you said that the
image of uh a crosswalk in New York showed up you know in crosswalk where
people are running heless culture in New York like a New York mindset yeah and everybody struggles with it but the
image of that sort of came up you know
yeah okay are there any more comments yes can
put evening so I want to Circle back to the
poem again I guess we never left it so no need to Circle back but so the fish in little water I'm sort of picturing
like a a fish that's been flung into the bottom of the boat or something it's like it's flailing around trying to get
find bigger water somewhere I don't know where that leads
but when you say the he sees the arrow here and you point to your chest and
that's not the image that came to me at all I just thought like oh there's an image on the there's an arrow on the ground or didn't seem like it was
necessarily so the line is then I saw an arrow here hard to see embedded in the
heart H okay so that's that's why I was getting this embedded in the
heart okay is that helpful and well when
people have the Arrow removed they neither sink nor what is it rise
or pierced by this Arrow people Dash about in all directions when their
arrows pulled out they don't run and they don't sink so Dash about in all
directions when they have it but when they don't have it they don't run and they don't sink yeah so sink for me this
brings like you know you uh cross over to yeah maybe I'm getting
um you know there's this idea that uh you're on the near shore where there's all the difficulties and then there's
the farshore where there's no difficulties and then there's water in between and so you don't sink means that
you can get across to the other Shore yes
okay but do you want to say more about the fish thrashing about you were thinking that it was in a boat so like
somebody well that or it's maybe the Maybe um the flood waters have receded
and now it's where it's trapped it's yeah it's
doomed ultimately whatever and they flop around they try to yeah go into search
mode they're looking for anything to escape yeah maybe there's a certain chaos too
right it's not like they're organized flopping like okay I'm going to go there right they're just uh it's random Walk
So Random walk nice nice
okay oh one last com changing the hours in January January will start 15 minutes
earlier and end at 8:30 so 7:15 to
8:30 how long meditation 30 minute meditation instead of
45 thank you no don't for 45 you can come earlier
I was thinking to myself if it were up to me or it is up to me actually but I was think that I think about it right
tell you i' like to do like an hour sit but I don't think anybody will come to that I was thinking like oh maybe I'll
come early you know at 7 and start sitting at 7 so I could still have 45 minutes so I don't know can we go back
to it in the spring having a longer sit yeah that's a good idea
I can't promise anything but uh I I think yeah yes back to
yes could you get the mic oh yeah yeah can we have the the
mic um so when when you recite
it one is that we running around with the arrows and then the thrashing fish so
they can of like headless chicken to me um can you hear me
now she was just talking about uh fish thrashing about people when they have
the arrow or dashing about kind of like chickens without their heads kind of
this similar yeah and it's very interesting that you you pointed to the
distance between um a very active turbulent Place versus one that is not
but I think I kept wondering how does one get the arrow out it's like a torn right you take the torn out and there's
relief yeah and I was curious about that so like how one gets the yeah and I
would say that's what practice is about so our meditation practice Ling kindness practice generosity ethical behavior all
this kind of stuff takes the thorn out then our whole mind might just starts to
settle down thank you you're welcome
okay so that's to end this evening so I wish you all a safe travels home and a
lovely rest of the evening thank you and if you'd like you're welcome to
come up here and ask some questions or say something more