Hello friends hello greetings from Mountain View California where I am
unseated all known all lonely land and uh good morning good afternoon good day
to all of you wherever in the world you are delighted to be with you this week and
um supporting Gail and all of us readings oh great
there technical glitch
um um yes feeling into gratitude feeling into my
gratitude for for this moment in time for us being together in this way
dispersed in space perhaps in time for some uh who will watch this later but
coming together with our heartfulness to to practice together
um brings me a lot of joy to feel your presence all around the country and the
world um and I actually invite you to take to take Delight I see so many
um hellos and greetings uh from different places from different time
zones and just to start with that um
sense of appreciation gratitude or or Sangha for Community or
or the teachings and uh with the possibility of waking up
so so having expressed my appreciation for
our practice and time together I'd like to invite us to um practice together to meditate together
and I will introduce the theme for this
week through the uh guided meditation ever so slightly and
more so I'll speak about it uh during the uh the offering the dharmet so
so let us begin let us begin
thank you I'll let us arrive let us arrive in this moment in time
let us arrive in our bodies
let us land and the body
feeling the connection of our feet to the Earth
our legs if we're sitting on the cushion our sit bones
relax let go of your weight
to the Earth feeling supported
breathing this breath and the body ideally in the lower body in the abdomen
greeting this breath the sensations of the breath
as if spring as if new in each moment
and not as if actually they are new and fresh in every moment
arriving like they have never arrived before
a sense of possibility openness
open-heartedness
and now can we bring an attitude of play an attitude of
curiosity of Interest
and the Curiosity and interest are not so heavy
or not letting
they don't have gravity but they have a lightness a playfulness to them
about this moment in time the experiences that arise
and pass all the possibilities arising in every moment
I'd invite you to try this on for size not in your head but in your body
breathing this reflection
feeling it in your body and the reflection is
what if this moment of awareness this moment of being alive
this moment of being mindful
is not so tight so serious
but giving it more space of this character who is you
this character in it the play or a game
is playing an infinite game an infinite game without winners and losers
it came with curiosity with interest
like children the way they play games endlessly curious created
with Wonder and awe
what if we receive this moment This Moment's experience
the breath Sensations thoughts emotions all of it
the whole catastrophe what if we receive it receive all
as if we're a child engaging in this Adventure this curiosity this
interesting game
learning growing
delighting
these are the invitations for the practice can we practice
with this perspective this attitude
with childlike curiosity interest be light
freshness levity
oh
you know this we've all been children or witness them
your body knows how to do this receive each moment
with this perspective
maybe from this perspective of lightness
judgments
distracting thoughts ongoing Etc things that otherwise would
feel heavy and tight maybe through this perspective they feel lighter
the heart doesn't cling around them so much they feel much
lighter they come and go
and this lightness of being lightness of being
lightness of being
maybe through lightness of being perspective
the heart is lighter the mind is lighter
the body is lighter there are more possibilities In This Moment
more space more ease more freedom
and we treat moments of life
not with lots of shoulds
make a grim Duty but imbue it with lightness
lightness of being lightness of heart possibilities
as if we're playing this infinite game
with the light of a child
rekindling delay
and poly Delight
and as we bring this into a close
depreciating any sense of
Delight a shift in perspective
to receive this moment with interest
lightness curiosity the slightness of heart
where there are lots of possibilities appreciating
if there was just one moment or just a little bit of softening
into the freshness of this perspective and trusting that we're planting seeds
wholesome seeds individually and together
seeds of goodness and
offering all of these seeds and in the ways they were flowered
their goodness to all beings everywhere
may my practice make my life my cultivation be of service
the well-being Freedom not just myself definitely myself others and all beings
everywhere may all beings be well
may all beings be free including myself
thank you for your practice as we take a moment's pause
between the meditation and the dark Dharma talk darmet
you're welcome if you wish to type a Word in chat maybe just one word
or a short phrase to what is it Rising for you right now
something to capture this feeling of this set
hello again and greetings everyone
it's lovely to be with you in this moment in time and just having finished
our meditation together I asked if you would put some words to capture
what's arising In This Moment and so many beautiful words are in the
container I'd love to just read them a few of them they're so beautiful just make my heart so happy
this morning gratitude calm lightness songbirds grateful
ease softness spaciousness peaceful light a smile
who would I serve today Joy increase the lightness these calm presents planting seeds
appreciation enlivened so many beautiful yeah
um presence the whole catastrophe karuna
smile buoyancy curiosity the Delight of beginner's mind appreciation expansion
calm secure the tickle of childlike curiosity happiness gratitude calm
friendship love and acceptance so many beautiful ones and they keep coming they keep coming thank you all thank you
they're so beautiful the last one I see right now wonder it's possible surrender
relief ah my day just feels more open and and
light so beautiful so beautiful thank you all thank you infinite possibilities of
delight seeing God as infinite possibilities of delight beautiful
thank you all I feel in this space of practice with you really
engaged so engaged
no so in many ways I think the theme for it
this week has been introduced through this guided
meditation and and the way that um all of you have engaged with it they're
just so beautiful just to feel the engagement uh in any way that was accessible and
possible so so the theme for this week
[Music] um let me introduce it in this way so
Delight Delight Bliss gladness happiness
so many um gifts so many gifts that the practice
gives us but also when we support these beautiful
qualities in our life in our practice the practice deepens our life
finds other dimensions of beauty service goodness so
as the opposite of this Grim Duty I should should you know I have to sit I
have to practice I have to become awakened I have to serve all of these
are so heavy and in fact they get in the way this this tightness gets in the way
whereas when we have curiosity interest all Delight this
interest this zest this is zest is childlike zest
which we've all had at some point of course we've all had it every child has
it we know this we know this curiosity interests lightness
zest and and that is the theme of this week
this week in ways of bringing this this sense of play the sense of play the
sense of freshness the sense of practice and life um as
as a Divine play as a divine game that we're engaged with
and and this week for for the uh for the teachings for
[Music] um what I'm finding inspiration in is
actually you know as it said sometimes art imitates life or Artistic Endeavors
support life and vice versa is the artistic Endeavor of of improv
improv so improv for those of you who may not
familiar with this term it's um some people consider it a comedy
performance but it's not so much a performance actually in turn well it is a performance from externally that's how
it's viewed but internally there's quite an art of the way of being an improviser
an improviser in the art of improv comedy
which actually tie in so beautifully into practice Thai beautiful into
practice and in fact we're all improvisers if if
I just said the word improv and you froze up uh improv I can't do improv guess what you've been improvising your
whole life we're all improvisers we don't know the
next thing that's going to come out of our mouths or the the next thing we're going to do necessarily your
interactions or life life is an improvisation life is an
improvisation we all of us are improvisers we don't
have a script things happen and then we improvise responses we improvise our
thoughts our our everything is improvised so can we actually
um take the art be be a little more skilled
in the art of improvising our lives and improvising in the moments of our
practice with more lightness with more interest curiosity so
and also for some of you might know I I've uh studied and and performed improv
for many years and actually have taught uh workshops on improv and mindfulness
and how the two can support each other actually well how improv can support mindfulness really
um as as an art as a way of being lighter in in the world and deepening
our practice and it can actually be very very deep um insightful it can bring so many deep
insights this way of approaching so I'd like to introduce some of these Concepts this week
um to support to support our practice and bring some lightness bring some
ah Delight some freshness some interest curiosity childlike curiosity so that is
the frame for this week so
so the perspective so the the whole frame is a frame of
of as I mentioned during the guided meditation a frame of what's called an
infinite game versus a finite game hmm so a finite game is a game where
there are winners and losers and there are rules that are set ahead of time so
for example chess backgammon um or any sports they're finite games
infinite game dancing is an infinite game one one so
in infinite games are games are are are played for the for the Delight of the
game itself not there no winners and losers and and the rules keep shifting and changing and
and they're made during the game so dancing when it's done for its own sake
for the Delight of dancing that's an in it's an infinite game there are no winners and losers
improv is an infinite game it's just for the delight and the rules get shifted
and changed and in fact the um the ultimate
game the ultimate uh infinite game is said to be life
there are no winners and losers per se we all are born we all die
um and and it's so important to have the sense the freshness of
this life or the sake of itself for the sake of its its um
the you know it's not a winning that we do but the sense of awe curiosity
exploring which actually this brings emptiness and it's it's a marriage of
emptiness and fullness because in in the dharmic sense
emptiness nothing exists independent of anything else there is
inherent emptiness everything to everything that is so so
that emptiness brings so many possibilities so it's things are not
fixed in a in a particular way and then in that
emptiness there is the fullness of possibility because things are not fixed
in a particular way so so life as an infinite game life as an
infinite game really is an expression of emptiness of acknowledging emptiness of
all things and fullness this marriage of emptiness and fullness
so just try to set a bit of the frame this
week there's a lot more that I'll bring in this week but just something also to
leave us with is um I often think and have thought of of
improv as kindergarten for adults there's a way of playing through this
bringing this sense of curiosity play freshness possibility to each moment of life
and similarly what if we saw our lives our lives as this kindergarten we're
here we're here to learn we're here to explore we're here to to ex express our
fullness in the midst of this The Emptiness and possibilities this
freshness as if says spring sunrise
so thank you all for your practice for exploring
this bringing more Delight curiosity interest this
to engage in this infinite game from this perspective of emptiness and fullness with delight
I'm excited to uh to practice with you to share these uh
these insights these teachings with you in this week thank you so much
be well and be light today oh yeah I forgot that
actually um maybe I'll say one more thing um the invitation for the rest of the
day if you can still have this attitude of lightness childlike curiosity
through your life perhaps the things that are even routine can you
approach them with new curiosity with new freshness make a different choice
shift things a little bit just bring this freshness um
of this infinite game infinite play the interplay of emptiness and fullness
with delight all right thank you so much take good care see you tomorrow