hello everyone and welcome
in the The Jump Right In
there is a significant very important teaching
that the Buddha gave to a monk named katyana gota
and um and in this uh I'm going to paraphrase
or or exemplify the teachings rather than to say them
in relationship to to support this meditation today
so the inhale when we breathe in
when it begins we cannot say that the inhale doesn't exist
but when the inhale finishes and we begin exhaling we cannot say that the inhale exists
anymore and so and certainly we can say that it
exists continuously non-stop because that's it it's a solid static phenomena
rather it's something that comes and goes it exists as a process
it exists as a as a
in terms of breathing it exists in terms of a few moments the inhale
and if we see the inhale as something we cannot say so in a sense we
can't say that it neither exists nor doesn't exist in a static ongoing
non-stop kind of process it exists as a process
that's temporary it exists as it's going through its motions
and uh and the reason why this kind of teaching is emphasizing in this teaching
to katyana gota had said kind of more universally more generally
but that if we see that the breathing comes and go the inhale comes and goes
it doesn't make any sense to grab a hold of it to to to get attached to it
because if we grab it get attached to it soon enough it disappears
but if we get upset about it disappearing it only reappears a few moments later
and so in relationship to breathing we learn to trust the process we learn not
to be attached to it not to hold on to it we also learn not to resist it
and uh in as meditation deepens there becomes a deeper and deeper trust in the
process the natural process of the body just breathing by itself
breathing breathes itself so the same thing is true of the exhale
when it begins we can't say it doesn't exist when it passes when it ends we can't say
it now it exists
uh it exists as a phenomena that appears and disappears comes and goes
so by emphasizing this with breathing maybe you can appreciate
one of the many reasons why mindfulness of breathing is useful here it's because as we get centered and
focus on breathing it's possible to kind of I'd like maybe it's not the best
word but savor or have an intimacy
with that aspect of each inhale and exhale which is
how it begins it appears and it disappears
and in that appearing and disappearing There's an opportunity for a
spaciousness for an allowing for a non-clinging
for a trusting of letting it appear and letting it disappear
and one way to trusted is to not then get caught in thoughts about it
ideas and wishes and hopes around breathing because those thoughts
also have the nature of appearing and disappearing
and uh thoughts are kind of fickle that way even though some of them might
predominate and as we Center ourselves into breathing
and seeing the coming and going of it we might then also with time also begin
appreciating how a lot of things come and go and things that we thought were kind of this is the way things are
that turns out to be related to thoughts that think that
but those thoughts themselves come and go
so assuming a meditation posture
and
gently closing your eyes and with your eyes closed
to appreciate your body
your mind your heart appreciate that you are taking this time
for an intimacy
for a caring and protection and support
that's provided with meditation
and then to bring forth something that maybe doesn't exist yet but it will
appear for a little while and disappear
to have appear a few deep inhales and long exhales
deep enough just enough not too much not too little
but just the right amount for a greater connection
to the present moment to your body
and to relaxing in your body
that in your breathing return to normal
in some things don't come and go quickly
but some things they're passing we can watch and see and support
so tension in the body there might be some of it
that you can relax a bit support the passing
of tension maybe as you exhale to relax the face
maybe as you exhale to relax the shoulders
there might be a feeling small feeling of relaxing that begins
and then after the relaxing it kind of Fades away
relaxing the belly
relaxing the arms and hands
maybe the thighs and legs
and relaxing the thinking mind
maybe with a feeling that as the Mind relaxes
they just it expands
or spreads out quietly
in the kind of way that waves in the ocean might settle and spread out
to create a flat surface
and then than breathing normally
follow the exhale to the end of the exhale and when it's time to breathe in
allow the inhale to occur
let there be as receptive as you can to the body
beginning to breathe in
receptive to the full inhale and recognizing it when it stops when
they inhale ends no longer there
inhale appears and disappears
even if you're controlling it it still appears and disappears
in some ways exists and then it doesn't exist
when the inhale has ended allow the exhale
allow it to begin
let go as you end the exhale to allow it to finish
staying aware this way of inhales and exhales
keeps you connected to the fullness of breathing
The Full Experience of the body breathing
Sensations appearing and disappearing
all connected to breathing
foreign
as we continue
can you bring forth to trust
the trusting of this process that allows breathing to come and go
inhales come they go exhales come and go
thoughts appear and eventually disappear
there's a deep Trust in this process of coming and going
the process of unfolding that happens best when we allow things
to follow their own course of coming and
going
trusting the awareness
that makes room for all things to come and go
thank you in Awareness which is intimate with breathing
trusting they're coming and going inhales and exhales
in that awareness in that way of being
can you recognize
freedom from clinging freedom from resistance
a kind of freedom of letting it all unfold on its own getting out of the way
is there any even hints small sense of that freedom
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
might there be something
within you that has a little bit more taste
feel for freedom
of freedom from being a little less preoccupied caught attached
and if there is something that
gives you some sense of Freedom that
take a few moments to breathe with it breathe through it
make space for it to grow
and then to allow that whatever sense of Freedom there is
to grow and expand maybe only with your imagination
imagining bringing this freedom
to your whole life
maybe with a sense of ease or peace
and that you can bring this with you to your contact with other people
imagine that that is so
and imagine that in this freedom and peace or ease
through space for your good will for your kindness
for your well-wishing and care
for this world
may this practice that we do be for the welfare and happiness
of others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
thank you
foreign
so as an introduction for the last talk on what is the Dharma
I want to say that um there's a long history of Buddhists down through the centuries
and different countries having a celebratory attitude towards
the Dharma uh sometimes when you spend a lot of time with the Buddhist monistics you
don't get a quite the sense of Celebration because they're kind of required to have a decorum of being calm
quiet and not so expressive and uh but uh in fact many Buddhists
will celebrate and sing and and chant and uh have a quite historically quite a
wonderful Rich celebratory feeling about the Dharma feels they feel so fortunate so lucky it's so wonderful
that the word Dharma represents something huge for them
the the Buddhist teacher a very famous kind
of uh on somewhat naturalistic a teacher in Thai in Thailand uh John
buradasa a great intellectual he kind of reformed much of
Thai Buddhism from much of its superstitious background in them earlier
times times and um he um
he was involved in a lot of inter-religious dialogue or some of some of it and uh he was quite content to equate
the Christian and and the Muslim idea of God with Dharma
so exactly what he meant by that and how it worked but it kind of has the same place that this word Dharma this concept
this this uh this reality of Dharma uh has this huge place in the life of
Buddhists that they celebrate and they're you know they're delighted for and inspired for and they go to it for
protection it's something that protects them and and that keeps them safe
so it's a powerful and wonderful topic and uh and I think that
as a Dharma practice Buddhist practice deepens and fills out and becomes grows
that there can be a wonderful sense of that there is this kind of support
protection uh there is this kind of inspiration this growth this tremendous
value that comes from the Dharma that almost treats it as something that
is um has has its own existence however the Dharma that we're talking
about is inseparable for the people who practice the Dharma it's the Dharma is something which kind
of exists within us as a natural process so something natural and com that's available
if we make room for it if we allow for it if we practice and it's a little bit like
someone who lives a very stressful life very busy always running and doing and
all that and their health suffers dramatically and the doctors say you
have to you know you're not going to live much longer unless you change and the person sure enough changes radically
maybe they retire they they go on a long vacation they slow down they meditate
they go in retreats and and mostly they stop doing
and in that not doing there's a whole settling and opening and healing process
that can unfold that is mostly not because they did the healing but that's a natural process
by which uh you know so much of the distressing brings brings with it allows
the way there's just a movement towards Health that the body can to some degree in some ways allow for
and even if it's not physical health there are people for whom there's been
um who have who feel like they were healed while they were dying
uh which some people that sound that's counter-intuitive or kind of goes doesn't quite work they weren't cured
but there was a deep psychological spiritual healing that happened in the process of dying
that also didn't necessarily seem to be their own doing but it was available here in this letting go this opening up
this allowing something to unfold and flower and come to fruit
so the last meeting meeting that I want to talk about this week about Dharma
is that um well go back to in the first day I said that there were three primary
meetings of Dharma the first is uh the and all of them are
kind of verbs kind of important to understand them is it's an involvement in engagement that is involved when we
talk about the Dharma it's not something abstract removed though it's easy to kind of see well the Dharma is the
teachings of the Buddha I'll get a book out to read about it um but the real dharmas comes from
engagement and so the first one is the Dharma which
is the process of learning learning those teachings and not just learning the memorizing
them but engaging them and arguing with them and and exploring them and and
discovering how they work for ourselves the second is uh meaning of Dharma is
the practice that we do the Dharma practice and in some ways that probably is the
most important I put a tremendous value in the practice love it and
and the third is um attainment the higher
arrival higher coming into a new way of being
sometimes it's called when there's this threefold definition of the Dharma this last one sometimes is called
penetration so to to penetrate for oneself to know
foreign oneself that the heart of the Dharma but not by just the knowing of it
but the transformation of it so this uh uh the the last of the three
kind of definitions for Dharma is to um is the attainments that transform us so
we can maybe call that Dharma is transformation uh in the realm of freedom in the realm
of of all the good that the Dharma represents including
compassion and care and love and freedom and wisdom and joy and happiness and
honesty and a lot of things that come and so this attainment this last uh
what Dharma is that itself is sometimes divided into three categories
and that is that it's um it's called this wonderful terms uh
the first two path and fruit
there is the path of that we practice and it puts us on a path the dharma's onward leading there's a
road there's a conveyor belt there's a stream that we enter into this entering into the stream entering
into this path is a phenomenal a wonderful thing it usually doesn't happen in an instant but usually people
who practice after some point it Dawns on them wait a minute there's something happening growing developing unfolding
here that's supporting me I'm really in the Stream I'm in this current I'm on
the conveyor belt there's not really any getting off it anymore this is a powerful momentum
uh for health and and freedom
so that's the path and uh when we kind of enter into it and then there's the path comes to fruition
uh it has a it's called fruit and this is also a beautiful kind of organic metaphor that of something which
naturally grows and ripens at first uh in the tree there's not even
the leaves in the after the winter and first the leaves grow and then the the
flowers appear and then the flowers get pollinated and that the the fruit begins
to grow slowly and and then by the end of the season the fruit is ripe and uh a
wonderful example of fruit here fruition of practice is that if you leave the fruit alone like an apple alone on the
tree at some point the connection of the stem of the of the Apple to the branch
um falls apart and the Apple Falls and so the same way that at some point
in this practice we ripen and then most natural process of it all
is that when the ripening is full which we can't know when exactly it is
that something releases something lets go in a deep full complete way and you
don't put the apple back up on the tree put tape on and try to get it to be attached to the tree again
it's uh it's a kind of irreversible that process once it falls off
so fruition is something that's irreversible change transformation
and that the third is nirvana nibana and this is the experience the knowing
of the absence of clinging it's the release and knowing
that release knowing that freedom of um of no longer
clinging resisting craving wanting holding on tight to ideas to anything to
and uh and that idea of a path fruit and release freedom
is available in hints and small ways from the very beginning of persons practice
it's at some point as we practice it's really helpful to get a feel or a sense
intuition for the momentum for what's opening up
that oh something's opening here as feel a sense of
of it comes to a fruition it comes to there's a the fullness there's a
possibility of really being free here and then there is a feeling the sense
that of what that freedom that release is like and these These are can be found just
right there in mindfulness or breathing to really trust the coming and going the
arising and passing of the inhales of the exhales as I pointed to in the meditate meditation just now
that there can be little hints that oh this is what it's about here is the here
it is it's unfolding from the beginning to the end of the meditation something unfolded I was in
the Stream I was in this onward leading nature I'm more settled more open
a little more sense of being of being released and not caught take these into account know these
appreciate these so they can grow and when it doesn't go in some nice
linear fashion that way sometimes I'm with practice that conveyor belt or
practice brings us to places in our lives that we have to have difficulty we have to where
we encounter the unresolved issues of our life and then we can maybe appreciate that oh
I don't want to look at this I don't want to deal with this this is painful but the Dharma knows best the Dharma
knows it's time for me to be able to practice with this too so it's going to be a little bit more
difficult or quite a bit more difficult now for a while but this is good
that in the context of doing this practice this has arose and now I get to
face this and work with us and so this gives a uh adds to the
freedom that we can live with the freedom of
being willing to be with the difficulties of our life
to practice with those as well and if our freedom we're finding this practice doesn't include a certain kind
of freedom and a willingness to practice also with our difficulties
then I think this Dharma doesn't have a chance to grow into his fullness then it's not really a real thing that has to
do with our life so Dharma
Dharma is a foundation for and this under hopefully this understanding that we offer I offered
this week uh will offer a foundation for what we'll do in the in the upcoming
months here and on this uh morning teachings there
so thank you very much and um
next week Monday and Tuesday I'll be at the retreat center
and so I'll be broadcasting from there and so you'll see a little bit different
or quite a different location and and probably I'll I'll sit where with uh
patachara the the statue of the nun patachar that we used to have for a
while here early in the pandemic but now it's down at IRC so thank you and I look forward to
Monday