hello everyone and
welcome and as an introduction to this meditation I would like to
evoke the emotion the attitude of
love as a part of meditation in integral part of
it and I'll use a metaphor now that it's getting cold sometimes
the windshield on my car is frosted over and there have been times uh when
it was so frosted over it took some time to be able to clear the ice to drive
away and um so there's different options of how to bring back the clarity in the
windshield one one is to Simply wait for the sun to come up and the sun will
slowly warm it up another way is to turn
on the car and the defroster and let the coils that are in the windshield slowly
warm up or let the heater in the car slowly blow warm air on the
glass and then uh with time the glass will be warm enough that the ice
melts the other option is to go out and get a ice
scraper and to uh scrape away the ice
and sometimes that's easy if it's just a little light frost and sometimes it takes a lot of work to get a thick layer
of crusty ice off the windshield and uh especially when it's
really cold then it kind of frosts up right away as even even as I scrape it
away so when we sit to meditate The Liberation that we're
looking for is could be understood to be Clarity to be clear of the obstructions
to our seeing to be clear of the frost that
covers our perception so that's uh our
our fears all of them which agitate all of them which OB obstruct in some
way and we could try to let go we can try to scrape it away and if it's a light
frost maybe that works fine but or we could let the
warmth melt it all and that could be the inner warmth
that we the defroster in our ourselves that we bring along so that when we are
mindful of our experience we are mindful of it with some modum of Love
warmth care Good Will
appreciation respect valuing that awareness is not
neutral but awareness is infused with
love or we can use the sun something outside of
ourselves that might also help something warm up something which is frozen or
caught or stuck inside of us so it begins to thaw and it could
be the love that we feel from other people it could be a sense of universal
love that it just exists in the fabric of the universe it could be being in nature and
feeling somehow some warmth some nurturing that
comes from the natural world and so to sit and
meditate and to call upon our capacity for
love and to do so you
are kind of speeding up a natural process that as we deepen our meditation
and relax and open up we will slowly
defrost we slowly develop the clarity that allows the heart's
tenderness and care and warmth to flow from
us so whether we call upon that warmth to whatever degree we
have or we clear the window so the clarity is there to see
and feel that warmth it's all part of the meditative
process so to assume
a meditation posture
and what posture would you take if it is a posture that
expresses alertness
relaxation and love
warmth some people are very fond of putting their hands on their hearts as a way of kind
of more directly feeling the warmth the tenderness
the The Good Will of a warm
heart and if you find no warmth inside of you that you can
call upon to support this meditation maybe you
can call upon what's outside of you and for this
meditation I will spend my time meditating with
um uh actively having Goodwill meta for all
of you you some 400 people here all of you I will just sit here and wish you
well so then gently closing your
eyes and to whatever degree feels loving for you let yourself take
some deeper breaths gently
lovingly as if you're caring for your body and taking in the
oxygen and relaxing as you exhale where relaxation also is a
expression of self-care
for
and letting your breathing return to
normal and gently feeling whatever
tenderness or warmth there might be
within maybe in the area of your heart maybe somewhere
else some people can feel something like that in their
hands for some people it's in the
face for some it might be in the
belly and putting aside
any expectations or Ambitions or older ideas you have about what it
means to be mindful see if you can become aware of
your breathing with an awareness with an
attention with attention that is
loving carries with it warmth and
tenderness maybe a
gentleness for different people different manifestations of
Love are most available kindness
Good Will
compassion deep
appreciation a deep sense of
care
sympathy where every moment of knowing
awareness touches with love
with warmth no matter how difficult the experience
is touching it with a warmth warm
awareness as if the warmth is going to melt it not fix
it
for
there are parts of ourselves
which benefit immensely from being
seen seeing In Love sometimes are
synonymous and there are parts of ourselves that really need to be benefit from being
[Music] heard at times being heard
well is just almost the same as
love to perceive to be aware of yourself as you sit
meditating as an act of Love Of
Care compassion with each
breath
for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to imagine or let it
be that your capacity to be
aware comes along with a warmth a
tenderness a love
and then as you gaze upon the world around you that that warmth and
tenderness spreads through your body like a little radiator that fills a
room with warmth and that it spreads beyond your
body out into the world
with the imagination or the hope that your love your
warmth care can radiate out across the
globe beyond the building you're in the county Province you're
in out across the
lenss and imagining that there's a kind of a Midas
touch that whatever your awareness lands on touches it with
love may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we be the recipient of the kindness and Good Will
of others and if we don't feel it from
others then they're definitely those people are definitely in
need of warmth to melt the frost on their
windshield let us melt each other's Frost so we see each other with
Clarity and in that Clarity we care for each
[Music]
other
thank [Music]
you
e
so hello and as I begin this fourth talk about my
own story my own life story with Buddhism with Buddhist practice
and so when I was about 22
then is that right no I was
24 I came to live um first near the San Francisco Zen
Center and then um after some months I moved to the green g a farm to live in
Zen Center and and
um and it might be interesting for some of you to hear my experience of the first uh 7-Day silent Retreat I signed
up for it was when I was still uh at the University of of
Davis uh studying and between my Junior and
Senior year I signed up for a 7-Day sashen at the Zen
Center and um a week or two before the
the retreat was supposed to start I called up the S Center and explained to
them that something important that come up and I wouldn't be able to attend the retreat and they said okay and that was
it what I didn't tell them that the important thing that had come up Was Fear so
I chickened out of going to my first silent Retreat so some of you maybe have
had been nervous coming to your first Retreat some of you haven't been on a retreat and feel nervous about doing it
if that's the case you're in good company and that uh I did not only was
nervous going I didn't go but then I did sit uh in a um a 7-Day
retreat at um green Gulch in the spring of
89 and that's when I decided to go live at the the green Gulch
Farm I was still thinking about uh going to graduate school and in fact I had been accepted to a soil science program
at UC Berkeley after studying Agronomy I was aware of the tremendous um challenge
of soil erosion around the world and I wanted to be someone who addressed those
issues and um but then as I was um getting time to go to green to UC
Berkeley in the fall of ' 89 um somehow in the middle of August I
realized it dawned on me that school was starting in a couple of weeks and I better figure out what to do where to
live to make arrangements and um and I went to the
new enchanting of the heart Sutra they do at uh at uh at
greenl and um it was a a noon that mostly people didn't go so I was just
there with a few people and it was optional and and we were chanting this this chant that had chant
many times by then and that wasn't particularly thinking about anything uh but the chant and suddenly there was
this inner explosion inside and I knew that um instead of going to graduate
school I should go to tasahara the Zen Center Monastery so I called up or maybe
I wrote a letter to UC Berkeley and said something has come up something important has come up and could I I
postpone my um uh beginning of graduate school for the for one year so then in
January of um 1990 I went to the middle of the winter
I went to this cold place in this um in the Santa Cruz in that in the Big Sur
mountains and uh called tahara it's down it's deep in the canyon uh about 14
miles on a dirt road deep in the natur National wilderness in a small private property small maybe maybe it's 100
acres 140 acres and um and so I started my monastic life
there and um I loved it for the most part and I was really happy that
lifestyle sometimes I thought this was a perfect lifestyle I just loved the whole
the whole thing about it except for um the times off about every five days we
had a day off and then I would often go hiking in the mountains there and that's
when I started thinking about my life what do I want to do with my life and should I go back to graduate school and
address the soil erosion problems of this world and um and uh I wanted to be of help to the
world but I had a deep suspicion of or mistrust of the desire to help I I kind
of had the suspicion that that can be more often than not uh self-serving and selfish to do that and so I had this
doubt about myself and what I should do and and um I spent a and that made me
kind of miserable during those days off thinking about that there was no solution and and then next day I was get
into the monastic routine and that was great meditating a lot and I continued
like this for probably um quite a while and
um and then um at some point I was walking in the mountains and I said this
is ridiculous uh I'm living in a world of imagination imaginary Futures imaginary
things I could do imaginary possibilities things that I can't really imagine properly and know anything about
and um and uh it's not really taking me anywhere I feel stuck and so I kind of
spontaneously made a decision uh to start my life over again and just take the next step whatever the
next step was I was going to that was going to build my life from there and and start over in a certain kind of
way and it might seem even to me that was somewhat naive to do that or maybe
simplistic but in fact that's was a decision I made and uh I felt now in retrospect I'm
so lucky that I decided to do that at a Buddhist Monastery because the next step
meant they rang a bell and it was time to go meditate they rang a bell it was time to go do the monastic work and go
to a Dharma talk and so I had all this wholesome kind of Dharma practice that
was the next step and um but it allowed me to kind of just settle in and then I decided not to
go back to graduate school but just stayed there keep practicing at the
monastery and um and at some point um I
uh I began wondering about you know what I should do with my life again or what's
next I wasn't thinking about it too much but I started to recognize that um I I
stared to be changed by the years of doing Zen practice and it was a very slow change and one of the primary
changes that happened was that I didn't get the enlightened but I became
compassion that I was sitting for those years with a lot of suffering inner suffering of myself and um but in Zen
practice I wasn't given any tools any mindfulness practices to do with with it the only practice we had was to sit
upright and accept the moment as it is and turned out that worked out really
well for me and so I would just sit there and have this accepting practice
of my suffering and slowly slowly that was that practice tenderized me it
softened me and uh I started kind of um I had a great need for compassion and I
started seeing and feeling was compassionate all around me and I was clearly projecting on my need onto the
world but uh I think it was very effective to receive from externally the
kind of warmth and love compassion that my suffering needed so sorely and slowly uh something began to
uh soften and dissolve and as it did so uh there awakened a sense of
compassion and uh that com sense of compassion became very important for me
simultaneous to that was also a softening of conceit a softening of any
kind of strong sense of a boundary between myself and others and I felt like uh in some I think healthy way that
I was continuous with the people around me and the people of the world that in some ways their suffering was my
suffering but as I continue this process I was not oppressed by the suffering of
others I wasn't uh uh dismayed by it but rather it was met with more and more of
this kind of warmth this compassion and um and I started to feel
that uh uh kind in some ways that as my strong sense of self dissolved more and
more that there was something inside of me that was responding to the world that
was not exactly the classic or conventional idea of Me Myself and mine
that there was a um that uh uh I was becoming
responsive can't even sa me I was becoming there was started to be a response a compassionate response to the
circumstance I was in and living in that response just felt so right so
appropriate and um and so uh you know it was very it wasn't like a sudden
realization understanding this is what was happening it was a slow process of of something dissolving and warming
up and then one day the uh the Abbot who was seldom at the monastery uh we could
seldom have a chance to meet with him came and um for a few days and I had a
chance to have a one-on-one meeting with him and so I went and sat by the the creek that's there the tasahara river
and just overlooking at the creek kind of reflecting what should I talk to him about and what should I do and what
should I do with my life and all that and and I think I was doing it in a very uh relaxed way and maybe there was a
certain kind of creativity or receptivity or openness to this and a
little bit like it had been in that chanting the heart Sutro at Green Gulch suddenly there was a I just something
just shifted inside of me and I knew exactly what I should do and there was
no question about it and that was I should be ordained as a Zen
Monk and um and because I'm a rational person I thought well I have to have a reason for that so then I I spent some
time thinking why do why do I want to do that and in some sense it was maybe a little bit it was the reasons I came
with were honest enough but they didn't really represent the fact that there was this it actually there was there kind of
was no reason it was just a knowing I had that this is what I should do but the reason I came up with was
that um I really wanted to respond to the suffering of the world and I wanted to
respond to it from the deepest place of of freedom from suffering that I had I
knew about and if I'd gone and done soil erosion work it would have been very
important work but it would have I would have always been felt a little dissatisfied because it's one thing to
help farmers and communities um but their suffering their depth of their suffering are still going to be there
it's very important to do solar work I don't um but I want I didn't feel like I
I was always going to have that dissatisfaction that I wasn't really addressing suffering at its roots and
that being ordained as a Zen priest was how I was going to or how I was going to do that at the roots of
um of uh of it and I I didn't think I would be effective or I didn't have high
ambition of what I could do my image of myself as a Zen monk or priest was to um
um have like a storefront meditation uh Center that was just
really open room in a storefront small place in the city and I had the key and
I would keep the place clean and I would open and close it for people to come and meditate with me we meditate together I
had no thought about being a teacher or or um you know I was just the the caretaker of a place for people to come
to meditate so that was my and uh and the route to becoming a Buddhist teacher
back at Zen Center in those days was a very slow route I think I because there
were so many other priests there at that time and the training was very slow through each of them that I I kind of
thought well I have to be here 25 years before I even begin uh entering into a
teaching role and I was fine with that I wasn't thinking about becoming a teacher and so I asked the Abbott to be
ordained and he said yes and within nine months I was ordained and um and I was
surprised uh how much that ordination ceremony changed me i' hadn't I didn't
have much feeling or appreciation for rituals but there was something very
deep that changed in me and in different ways but I'll say now to end that
um uh I became a public figure I had a shaved head I had robes and uh I stood
out now and people would strangers would come and talk to me in the ways before when I was more or less like a hippie
and scrawny and maybe dirty and um and people would you know more likely avoid
me than to approach me and so being a public figure this way as a representative of the Dharma um my own
foibles my own shortcomings became much more obvious and uh and at the same time as
my own shortcomings became more clear to me uh it was more okay to have them
because now I'd become a child of the Buddha and it's a kind of metaphor for what was what happened to me and this
combination of being able to see my shortcomings better and feel more okay
about having them because I was somehow sitting in the lap of the Buddha um I thought it was a a wonderful
and significant combination I could this is a wonderful balance
so those years of Zen practice uh compassion me and a warmth and a
tenderness and a gentleness uh with which then I would sit my zen meditation and which then
motivated my life and that then set the course for the rest of my life that
somehow my dedication then was to um alleviate or help alleviate the
suffering of the world and that was the response of this life it wasn't even
personal or something but it became the center of the life that was coming out of this body was that's what it was
going about and and that's what it's been ever since I feel like this that's the center and um my practice is
important and but the one expression of it is uh wanting to meet suffering and
and help uh bring about the end of
suffering so um and then at some point uh in the Zen practice um I encountered
vasana inside meditation and um maybe to leave you with a cliffhanger uh that'll be the
story for tomorrow thank you