good evening so
oh I'm not sure I got all my pieces together here hold on a moment
somebody had larger ears than I did okay I think we're there
so uh my name is Maria stratman I forgot to
say that last week so I'll say that now and I'm here for Diana who is on retreat but she should be back next week
so um tonight what I'd like to talk to you
about is experiencing ease
so when I say experiencing ease I do not mean that everything is going
to be easy or that you're going to be happy or that everything will suddenly stop
being a problem for you in fact it turns out that ease is
somewhat difficult to talk about and mostly what I'm going to talk about
is the what it is not what ease is not and then how we might be able to go
about that so last week I sort of introduced the topic by putting an emphasis on mindfulness and the need for
being aware of things just as they are to be able to see just this Justice
and the importance of perseverance that is that you just keep coming back
you just keep coming back and you just keep showing up
and you don't stop you just keep being mindful you keep
reminding yourself recalling this is what I'm doing
and another important idea we talked about is that the whole thing all of the experience is a process it's not a thing
it's a process I'm having trouble with my glasses tonight sorry about that
so the mindfulness is a process it's not a place it's not uh we think of it as a
technique but what we're really doing is paying attention to this is what's going on now this is what's here this this this and
this and this experience as we know it is transitory
comes and goes our thoughts come and go the feelings of our body come and go sounds come and go tastes come and go
everything is transitory it's conditional
that is we don't get to determine what it is it's based on all of the things that
have happened before we came here the environment that we're in the attitude that we have when we get up in the
morning whatever our experience is is conditioned by all the things around us
and within us and before us and what we're thinking it's all conditioned by
that and we don't control those conditions
and it's uncertain we don't know what happens next
despite the fact that the brain that we operate with believes
that we know what's coming next we actually don't know what's coming next because an experience doesn't
happen until it happens we can't make it happen we can't control
what happens it's in process
as are we the person that we call Self is also in
process we're not the same as we were
this afternoon I was reading a poem by The Poets in borska maybe I get that
right who had written a poem about herself as a teenager
and she said I I look at that girl and I say who was that
she can't identify with who she was as a teenager at all it's very clear I'm a different person
even though she knows that person very well both of those persons
they're not the same and that's true of each of us we're not the same as we once were
not the same as we were a moment ago what we experience is very momentary
and we experience it through the this body through all the feelings and sounds and
tastes and thoughts of this body but to think that this body isn't
changing and that there is a me that isn't changing is not paying attention
it's not being aware of the really transitory conditional nature of Who We
Are Who We Are and that this is controlled by the
memory okay so memory being the continued processing of information
and offer information retention over time the thing that that the neural circuits that are
created in the brain that the brain uses to tell us what to do about these conditions so on the way
here I left with plenty of time and I turned on to Sand Hill Road which
is kind of the main artery out of Palo Alto going to 280 which was the route that I take
getting here and so I turned on to this the street and was shocked to find a
line of traffic at seven at night it just is unusual five o'clock yeah I get it but boom to
stop and then the light changed and we didn't move and I thought what's happening and
I could feel that prison of fear around oh I'm going to be late
and all the associated thoughts around that well I should check this and I should have checked that and what if I
did this and maybe and then and what I did instead was say and how is my body
doing what's happening am I leaning forward which is what I tend to do when I'm rushing
of lean forward you know grab the grab the steering wheel no I wasn't doing any of those things I
was quietly my hands were quietly just barely grasping and I said oh
despite this prison of fear about how I have to rush I'm not yet rushing I don't have to rush
so even the bright though the brain was giving me signals all this this is this is potentially bad you should prepare
for things that being what you expected I didn't have to react to that
and it was so um happy making to realize I wasn't
reacting to that even though I felt I felt the prison of fear if that was
there but I didn't have to rush
and then I felt contentment and then I said but I have to drive
it's constantly changing it's going all the time but I did not have to get into
a mode based on what the brain told me was true
the other thing is that the the mind the the yeah the Mind tends to create a concept around our experiences it likes
to turn things into nouns you know so what I called a person of fear was
really a feeling in my body that I translated interpreted as a frisen of
fear a small excitement but it was really just a small
excitement and it was only when the Mind named it fear and set up all those conditions
around well here's how you react to this that I had to worry about it
what we're interested in the way to experiencing ease
is to find oneself in the alternative ways to to notice there are
alternative ways of interpreting what the signals of our bodies and minds are sending us
there are alternatives to the reactive way that is common whatever that
reactive way is we de-personalize the sensation we take
it out of the realm where we're saying this is who I am and I will do I take care of the things this way here's what
I do in this Sati batana suta which is the
suta that talks about mindfulness discourse on the establishment of mindfulness it kind of it makes a
statement that is really about ease although it doesn't say that
the statement is one abides independent not clinging to anything in this world
now on the surface you look at that and you say okay this is another message about not clinging not holding on
but the real word that I want to put your attention on is the word independent
independent and it the independence here is um not about
well it is about Freedom actually but it is about being Unshackled un impelled
I'm I'm not forced to do this I don't have to do this the independence is
about not succumbing to reactivity
and we can only do that by being mindful of what's Happening by seeing what's
happening by being clear seeing clearly oh this is what's going on this is
what's going on the mind is continually engaged in the
process of wanting or not wanting I like this I don't like this this is Pleasant this is unpleasant
all of that that string of of uh arising that comes from the sensation the
feeling it's Pleasant or unpleasant I like I don't like I want I don't want that all happens very quickly
and the mind is constantly setting this up I want I don't want
we form patterns of reactivity around that and then we translate those patterns of
reactivity into who I am so shortly before I came I picked up I
foolishly looked at my email and there was a last minute of the day message
that somebody had sent out do you know about this form call me if
you have any questions and I thought oh my goodness this person is totally misinterpreting this form I filled this
form out long ago and it wasn't for them it was for me and my mind immediately wanted to solve
a problem without actually knowing what the problem was except that it was unexpected that he wanted me to call him
with my questions and uh immediately the mind went into I have to
have a solution for this I have to handle this it has to be done now and I kind of laughed at how quickly
that happened now I have to do this now
and what is it I have to do now it's already done
but somehow there was this impetus I have to do this
and I kind of laughed at that person that had to do this and I spent a few minutes sort of well
let's see what are the consequences a brief analysis of you know what is the problem here
and then I say okay it is how it is there is confusion
this is contractual confusion between two different organizations by the way so it's not just somebody
misinterpreting me it has to do with a lot of other things and so I thought well
okay it's done
we're not assigning them this right and so now all I have to do is manage it was
a sort of it was not so much a simplification as a stepping back from the idea that it's a problem
there may be something to be solved but the truth is it doesn't require
establishing fault blame anything that has to do with why this is
happening just this is happening so now what do I do okay so so it's stepping back from all
the defensive things and all of the um creating a problem part of it and just
saying oh now this is how things are now this is how things are
practice of finding oneself at ease
is not the result of a deliberate action it's not like I can give you a practice and say well practice this and you will
be at ease you don't get to make an agreement with the universe if I do these five things then I get ease right
because ease is something that arises out of the conditions
in which we're practicing it has a lot to do with the attitude
that we're carrying around what do I think about how I am in the world
how do I feel about how things are in the world
am I attached to whether things are desirable or undesirable or can I be
independent of that decision can I be independent of the reactivity
on whether this is desirable or undesirable [Music] if that is a function of needing things
to be other than they are do I need things to be other than they are which is what gives rise to
suffering needing things to be other than they are
the way to ease is to find oneself in a place where you
just let things be what they are this is not to say complacent it just
means that you say oh that's how it is now what
oh that's how it is you don't rush to blame responsibility
criticism resentment all of those things are extra things
mindfulness from the Satya batana Sutra says one is aware as it actually is
this is suffering this is the arising of suffering
this is the cessation of suffering this is the way leading to the cessation
of suffering this is the practice to see things just
as they are and to see oh this is causing suffering
oh suffering is less when this happens oh if I do this
I notice the suffering decreases
there's an another kind of uh system within Buddhism that talks about
how we think about obstructions or how we think about how
wanting things to be other than they are and that is a a system whereby we look
at the gratification that comes from having things as they are we see the danger in that gratification
and we let go of it which is called Escape Escape so it's
gratification danger escape so if I Can See Clearly doing this
creates this potential Danger so wanting something so much that it
makes my life miserable wanting so much that this has to be this way
does indeed make my life miserable and I can see that that wanting is very dangerous
that wanting that wanting is so strong that it's tying me up in knots
that's a danger and how do I escape from that Danger
by lessening by lessening the need to want so if we think of
any affliction wanting or not wanting as a form of enchantment
you know I really I just want this can't I just want this come on
it's not hurting anything
if we see how entangled we are through that wanting if we see that entanglement
then we are no longer deluded that everything about it is wonderful
we see ah we become disenchanted
we're not enthralled by that way of being and when we are disenchanted we become
dispassionate the energy flows out of it
and we say oh I guess not
I guess no I I have to see that I have to see
what's actually happening now that I see it I can't unsee it
what we're talking about is becoming unattached to what we want
unattached it doesn't mean we stop wanting things it just means we don't have to have them
we don't adopt that that feeling of I must have and we see when that arises
and we say ooh sticky sticky
and we don't necessarily do anything about it it's not a call to action
the principle is when we see it the tendency to hold on to it is
automatically lessened so I can give you an example of that
let's say uh let's say I have I have something that I'm very resentful about
okay somebody has done something that is just Unforgivable
now I can spend a lot of effort trying to forgive them for the Unforgivable but it's more useful for me to see
I am resentful that there is resentment here I can see the resentment
and when I see that resentment I can say that hurts I hate that resentment
yeah but it's not fair it's not fair and my need for it to be fair when after
all it's already happened I can't affect the outcome of something that has
already happened I can see the futility of that I can see there's there's no hope for
that okay so I I'm gonna give up wanting it
to be better oh I can see that the resentment has
nothing to do with the person or group that's caused this thing
but everything to do with my desire for what has already happened to be different than it was
the resentment is all mine the suffering of resentment is all mine
it's not caused by you or your action
it's tied up in my reactivity to wanting things to be different
and it's already happened it can't be different you 've already happened
and you could argue yeah but if I just let that pass nobody said anything about letting it pass
it's different what we're talking about is very subtle
what we're talking about is the need to have it that way the need for it to be
different you can feel it in your body you feel it kind of leaning into it in a kind of
there's there's a tight energy when you feel that tight energy you say
oh alarm alarm I should see what's happening here what's really happening
here
the art of just being present for what is true
is it kind of uh uninvolvement it's not it's not really uninvolved so much as
it's unattached it's unattached you have to be completely in it you have to know what's happening to see clearly but you
don't have to hold on to it and and and make it mine it doesn't have to be about
you it could just be this is a risen this thing has arisen
so if we think about ease what we're talking about is what people
like to call equanimity and I kind of stay away from Equanimity
just because everybody thinks it means I'm comfortable with and everything is
balanced and and what I really mean to talk about is that ease is
this the attitude that allows you to say I see you whether it's Pleasant or
unpleasant it isn't about it being good or you
being good or anything being better or worse than it was it's seeing clearly this is how it is
resentment is here I see the resentment but I don't have to say I am resentful
I can just see the resentment and if I don't try to justify it to myself thereby re-energizing it by
telling the story it kind of loses its oomph
it's really actually hard to hold on to it there are
there are people in my life there's I'm thinking of somebody yeah so so Mary was a
is no longer with us but when I first met her the two of us were pretty uncomfortable
with one another we were both pretty strong women with with uh lots of opinions and she wanted to go this way
and I wanted to go that way pretty much we had the same thing in mind but we just wanted to do it
differently so we ended up being on a committee together I think we were trying to we
were trying to get an increase in property tax assessments to take care of
our roads so this was not an easy project to go around and convince people they should raise their taxes but
we were on a committee together to do this and so we decided we needed to get to know each other because we were both
aware of this discomfort we had with one another so I told her uh that I was that I had
worked for a company that built cyclotron so if you don't know what that is it's a very large physics machine
that producers radioactive isotopes or radiation beams for a variety of uses
our applications were medical so I was telling her that you know I used to
build cyclotrans and all of a sudden everything changed
and I assumed you know it had to do with Will okay so she knows I'm not an idiot
and you know I know this is a bright woman and so maybe we can be more comfortable it was only after she died
that I learned that her father was EO Lawrence who invented the cyclotron
she never told me but the openness
to just not requiring her to explain to me what was different and her
willingness and my willingness to just be open to each other over things we
didn't know about each other led to actually a very warm friendship
unfortunately she died less than a year later
but it is it is that openness about I don't know what's going to happen I
don't know about you you may make me uncomfortable but I actually don't know
you and so what I'm uncomfortable about has to do with something I wish was true
that doesn't have any meaning doesn't have any reality it's not part of the experience it's what I'm creating
out of the reactivity for I want things to be this way I want things to be this way
the poly word for Equanimity is upeka and the components of that word break
down into a looking over looking over something looking
broadly about something that the idea is you're looking at what is
unfolding and you just allow it to be the mind is responding to what's arising
but we don't have to go into the place of reactivity we can go into neutral
open okay it could be this but what if it's not
what if I'm just available for how it changes for what arises next
you can literally feel the energy in your body change from a kind of
stretching like a rubber band that relaxes
just just thinking what if I'm wrong as long as it doesn't go all the way the
other way to oh my goodness I could be wrong and we developed a fear in the other direction but just that neutral
place of I don't know what's going to happen fear is present uncertainty is present
anxiety is present but I don't have to take it in make tea
for it turn it into my life story I can just let it be
I don't even have to let go of it but I'm letting go of is the need for it
to be different than it is
so I I'm walking around at night I stub my toe
it hurts fortunately I don't break my toe
it's your fault for leaving that there it's my fault for being so clumsy it's the fault of the chair for sticking out
so far I should have gotten rid of that a long time ago all of those thoughts are extra creating more stress
it just happened and the pain is enough we don't have to create more pain
by castigating ourselves or someone else by creating fault the toe is already stubbed
okay despite all efforts I keep getting older
now older is older than right
but I'm not really old
if I get tied to I don't want to get older sort of missing the whole point
the point is I am still here I am still this way no I'm no longer
that way nor am I what I fear in the future I'm just this
rather than holding on or pushing away I'm just here for this
I'm not Enchanted by how I wish things could be I just see clearly
doesn't mean that we disengage with life or that we don't have things that we
fight for or that we believe in or goals that we set for ourselves
that's all part of fully living this life
but there's an attitude of mind that can be open to any experience around what my
intentions are without condemning those experience experiences without elevating those
experiences by just seeing the experiences just as they are
it's actually not dispassion in the sense that we want to be passionately
alive but to be passionately In This Moment it's when we passionately want things to
be other than they are that we get into trouble and it's the need to change them to
affect it to manipulate the present the need to manipulate what we see that
gives rise to suffering and it's distinguished from
determination that I'm going to make these changes or these improvements or I'm going to
stand up for these rights those are all good things
what is also true is it's not saying that if I don't make this happen
I can't be happy I can never be I can never be satisfied unless this is true
we can work towards something without it having to be true in order to not suffer
what we pay attention to is where am I struggling if we're struggling suffering
is present we can join a struggle without struggling I don't know if that makes
any sense to you we are not free of conditions in the
world we are not free of intentions but we can be free of the stubborn holding
on to our way we can be free of that
for years I had miserable thanksgivings because I had an idea about what
Thanksgiving should be that my family never met and when I gave up that idea I started
enjoying Thanksgiving again it took me so long to figure out I was
the one making me unhappy because they weren't behaving the way I wanted them to behave
but what I let go of wanting them to be a certain way lo and behold
all of that tension washed out
and I could just enjoy the family I had to give up the idea that it had to
look a certain way and if not everything hit the table at the same time the food didn't hit the table at the same time
and the turkey wasn't cooked exactly this way and the tofu ferky was
different and I used to make five meals for Thanksgiving it was ridiculous
all trying to have it look a certain way
the need to make things as we want them is the thing that gives rise to
suffering
there's another set of three that's important in Buddhism that's part of this
suffering Continuum it has to do with the determination of Sila samadhi and
tana so that is integrity or virtue
stability samadhi being meditation meditation comes in between
a virtuous life and wisdom Panna is wisdom
in order to experience ease one must be comfortable with these three legs of how
we practice forget about
the over emphasis on technique it's not that if I sit most effectively
in meditation then all of this is automatically going to happen because that's not the case
in order to be able to look at things as they are I actually have to know that I am
leading a well-intentioned life
the confidence that comes from I am living my best intentions
can't be overlooked it doesn't mean we don't mistakes we don't make mistakes that we don't uh behave in ways that we
don't like we can say oh there you are doing that thing again but we don't add condemnation on it
we say oh look what's working
we develop The Virtuous life we develop the ability to be stable
to follow through on our intentions that's what we do in in meditation when
we find a place of Stillness so when I describe to you the the uh
getting in line on Sandhill and saying where is my body I felt a Stillness in me
that told me I wasn't reacting that there was still time to just be
still you have to become familiar with that place of Stillness in order to reach it
in order to recognize that it's there I'm not talking about deep jonic States
here just the stability of I am here I am here I am here
I am in this moment this person just as she is is in this moment and to feel
that settling that comes from that thought the Stillness and stability of
I'm still here and the wisdom that comes from seeing
the habits of mind that are operating to see uh prison of fear but I don't have to
these these three areas Sila samadi Pana
are really about the Eightfold Path the ways to the cessation of suffering
that's integral to it so what I'm saying
is the way to ease is to adopt a life that allows you to feel it
that that increases the likelihood that it can arise in your life
and that involves each of these three factors it involves being Mindful and seeing
things as clearly as possible so that we are not Enchanted but become
disenchanted and therefore not delusional if we can say oh I see this is what's
operating it may not be comfortable
it may be wonderfully comfortable but I don't know what's going to happen
next being present for that is what it really means to be alive
so I'm going to give you a little quote here from um earthlyn Emmanuel manual who wrote a
book called The Way of tenderness and the subtext to that is Awakening
through race sexuality and gender so she is a Zen priest black woman
uh let's see and here's here's the quote
I speak simply of just being still of finding that place where our only Act
is breathing in this state of Stillness we do not seek answers for our active Minds but
allow one breath to be the total experience of life
a moment is not now a moment is simply a state of being itself
we too can be in a state of being ourselves and not worry about now
we can be holy ourselves as ourselves while engaging the breath
as a result of this breath as a result of the meditation that arises from it
our motivations become purified of our wounds our expectations our stories and
our distorted perceptions of others as a result of this breath
as a result of the meditation that arises from it our motivations become purified of our wounds our expectations
our stories and our distorted perceptions of others
it is the Simplicity of awareness this is how it is
the Simplicity of awareness nobody said it was easy
just simple the fullness of attention on just this
allows us to see clearly we have breathing room we're not
we're not constricted by all the ideas we have by what we think about what's going on we just let what we think about
is going on just let it lie there just let it be there
just know it's like this or I don't have to explain it to myself
I don't have to Nuance it I don't have to know all the details of why I think it's like this
just it's like this and I remain steady in my purpose
I don't get distracted by trying to explain it to myself
it's like this from this we develop the confidence of
just thisness just being here just just this
and we can say ease
and ask yourself what is ease what would what would Place me at ease
right now not a solution of the problem
so here's practice ask yourself
what might you let go of so you can be more yourself
so I have a little thing I want to read you from
David White this is a poem called a tillicoa lake
in this high place it is as simple as this leave everything you know behind
step toward the cold surface say the old prayer of rough love and open both arms
those who come with empty hands will stare into the lake astonished
there in the cold light reflecting pure snow is the true shape of your own face
leave everything you know behind step toward the cold surface say the old
prayer of love and open both arms those who come with empty hands will
stare into the lake astonished there in the cold light reflecting pure
snow the true shape of your own face
I wish you the true shape of your own face thank you
we have only a brief minute if anyone has a comment yes
we have it would you speak into the microphone because they're recording this
hello um I could not stop thinking about the whole time you were talking abusive
relationships um I was in a very long one where at first I didn't want to get out because I
didn't know there was a way out yeah and then once I knew there was a way out I didn't want to get out because I was
like well what will I do who will I be you know like I just this is I'm I'm attached to this house so I'm attached
to this life and so I I can't want something different or better for myself once I
began to want different and better and safer and you know that was the
beginning of a self-love journey and I notice my friends around me are in relationships that are very
unhealthy and they're telling themselves they don't want to leave and that there is no better for them so that's I was
hoping you could kind of touch on the Nuance of that that it is
so um so I know what this is like
and uh you know there's a place where the devil you know is safer than
what's out there if this is so scary out there could be even worse because you
begin to get the idea there are several ideas that come up one is well I don't deserve any more than this one is uh it
could be worse than this now that I know this is bad even worse could wait for me out there
there are all kinds of variations on that and what is needed is to say where
is suffering this is suffering I do not need to suffer now when when
you're really when when your sense of safety is tied up with this
the the real delusion is thinking that you're safe in that situation so what is
needed is a a reassurance it it it actually amounts to compassion toward
oneself and to achieve compassion towards oneself you have to say
you have to be able to get yourself into the place where you feel
I'm doing the best I can I'm really trying hard
and I love me because ultimately it comes down to a
decision on whether you'd love yourself how you can move forward
it it really has to be something that that settles on your own
sense of worth in order to reach that
you have to look at how am I living in the world am I not harming
am I not lying am I not stealing am I not abusing sexuality am I not
abusing intoxicants no I'm not doing any of those things
then life is good you are you are doing your part to be free of afflictions
and so you deserve you deserve
To Love Yourself to get to the place where your worth is
not dependent on other people where you can just see here I am
and there's a there's a seeing of all the other stuff that you're attached to
it it's in that place of um uh gratification
and escape to escape gratification danger escape so how you how you see
the momentariness of the gratification and the danger that exists outside of
that gratification so the gratification is I'm safe here but then it turns out you're not safe there
then when you see that when you see that really clearly I'm not safe
then you you can't unsee it and you don't need to cooperate with
being unsafe but that's that's a very personal journey and it's not one you can do for
someone in the end you can only do it for yourself
and you can urge other people and support other people but you actually can't do it for
other people and you can't judge
that the conditions that someone else chooses are necessarily
unskillful you know I watched
some very negative behavior in my family and
have encouraged people to do otherwise and they're still my family
and they didn't do otherwise
okay those are the chase choices being made
and so as a friend you're in a position of supporting that person not
necessarily what they're doing but that someone makes a choice it's it has to be
their choice in the end it's their choice and to to disabuse oneself of the idea that I can
fix things that that's delusion you can't fix because you can't control the conditions
so you can only make individual decisions I really appreciate that response that
was beautiful thank you so much it is more of a focus on the love I have for these
people less on what I want yes exactly
exactly thank you
good night everyone