so hello everyone welcome and uh
hope that those of you who are local and not local are
safe in the weather here in Redwood City
we didn't have much much rain or storm or wind in the last 24 hours as expected but we
did lose electricity big parts of the town and um
at home where I did no electricity and then just a couple blocks away from IMC
it's still no none but here we're we're good for now
so
it probably can um never been to be over said oversaid
overspoken that the emphasis on this meditation of mindfulness
and meditation of the Buddha puts a great value
on what we can see no experience
Here and Now in this own field
of direct perception I was going to say here in our own body
but um but it's the whole way in which through the senses of the body we
experience directly whatever it is might be and so learning to come into the
fullness of our direct perception direct experience unmediated
by theories and doctrines and speculations and
views about the nature of life or even the nature of self
it's a radical phenomenal pointing the Buddha does to the
Simplicity of here and the metaphor I'd like to use for this and for this meditation
is that of opening a present there's a gift
someone who cares a lot about you loves you and wants the best of you has
given you a gift and that gift is wrapped it's in a
wrapped in maybe beautiful wrap wrapping and
maybe maybe in wrapping paper the person has made themselves
I've gone through all the trouble of of uh paper making
so it's beautiful and then within that there's a box
and so you take off the paper and because it's your friend's beautiful paper you don't want to just tear it up
you can take it unwrap it very carefully and as you open it you smooth it smooth
it out so it's flat and as little creased as possible so the beauty of this handmade piece of paper kind of
stands out and it's a beautiful box maybe the box is made from some also
maybe your friend has made and it's made from local
wood that the person has been able to maybe create that fell and person build
the wood and cut the wood put it together into a beautiful box
and so again you want to be careful and loving and appreciative of the box as much as what's going to be inside the
Box the paper and the Box itself is part of the gift
and then now you do open the box to see what's inside and there's a something again that this person has made maybe
it's a beautiful Exquisite clay Bowl that clearly is very thin very fine
clearly very fragile could easily shatter if it dropped just a little bit
and um but is exquisitely made and and you can see the care and the love that
went into it and so you don't just pick it up with one hand and kind of like you know flip
it around if you want to because it's so special and delicate than a gift you pick it up carefully lovingly and hold
it maybe in both hands and kind of hold it gently
so the same way we enter into our own direct experience
maybe thinking of it as a presence and there are these three layers
and the way that we can unwrap it is to relax deeply
and first we relax the body and that's the the handcrafted
wrapping paper for it all and so we were and relaxing is how we
unwind how we unfold it how we open it up and take it off relax deeply in the body
and then we relax the mind the thinking mind and the mind the pressure the
tightness that pre the the contraction the hardness
the resistance the fear that's kind of embedded in the thinking mind itself
and that's and that's uh you know opening up carefully it's beautiful
handmade box our friend has made beautiful it's not quite handmade but
beautiful mind that we have care or love
and then and then finally we get to open it up
and pick up what's there and in the in the middle of the of this box there's our heart
and now we hold the heart carefully coming around with mindfulness a soft
soft Palms of her of our hand holding our heart our emotional heart or
depth of our kind of inner life where it's the deepest place of
and we hold it gently lovingly so it also can relax
and the present is not the present the present is what's left when we're fully
relaxed so in this way coming into our direct
experience for this purpose say taking a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and begin to feel into your body
feel where it feels tight maybe where it aches
where it feels loose comfortable
and if there's easy ways of relaxing your body soften relax
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
and the long exhale in which to relax further
relaxing and then letting your breathing return
to normal and again taking some time to
feel your body as you inhale feel where there's still some holding
and on the exhale to soften the body release
the body
and then on the inhale sensing feeling
the thinking mind the thinking muscle
wherever in your body there's the energy the impulse to be thinking
whether in images or words or another way
and you feel if there might be any pressure or tension
contraction hardness
agitation
a feeling of activation
as you exhale
let the Mind relax soften
release
as you relax the mind
do it letting the Mind open up
spread out as if you're opening a beautiful box
to see all the spaciousness and openness in the mind
that's just beyond the edges of your thoughts your concerns
I think your thoughts buy it
almost as if they're melting into the space spaciousness around them
and then to now on the inhale feel your heart
or the center of gravity for your deepest emotional
life
and maybe as the you inhale it's like a hand two cup tens
they come gently from underneath to hold
to support
the inner emotional life that we have whatever it might be
the heart center the emotional Center or the
very well maybe even the very center of
or lived life
and see if you can relax the emotional Center and relax the
emotions let them relax so that they are
settle more deeply into the palms of awareness
as if the palms of awareness offer safety
support
so that it's safe to relax the Heart Center soften
and when you relax steep as you can
letting go as deeply as you can
with no concerns and preoccupations take you away from here and now
just here
what is left for you in the Simplicity of breathing in and
breathing out
below all the wrapping paper all the tension
what is the gift of freedom
unbounded freedom
experienced with every inhale and every exhale
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to relax now let go
now that we're coming to the end there's something about the effort or
the bracing yourself or undoing the practice
and you can let go of
and let go more deeply into yourself taking off all the wrapping paper
and settle to the deepest place of rest
so subtleness Within
from whatever degree of rest within that you can have
from that rest gaze outward into the world
thinking about the people in your life the people in your communities neighborhoods
on the streets in the in the news
wherever there are people that you're aware of in your life
The Gaze upon them from their settled place
and perhaps Let There Be kindness
her friendliness
good will a simple good will it
is not demanding or a high standard that you have to live up
to just resting in Good Will
in that letting that good be a well wishing for others
what a wonderful thing it would be if more people could be happy and safe
and peaceful and free may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
male beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
um warm greetings for our fourth talk
on what is the Dharma and um so one of the meanings of Dharma
is the teachings of the Buddha what he taught and it's interesting then to look at
because there's the volumes and volumes of of texts that uh report to be his
recorded teachings I find these many of these quite
inspiring and then really delight and swimming in the
those those ancient teachings but the um
but what specifically is the Dharma and the analogy I'd like to use maybe a poor
analogy is that say there's a modern teacher that um
that has wonderful Buddhist teachings and the person used often talks about
um some as a metaphor assembly for their traffic lights driving down the road and
and when this teacher talks about traffic lights mentions that green means
go and red means stop so then over the centuries
people recognize that this is in the teachings of this teacher and so sure enough maybe at some
point society change decides are the better colors for go and stop but that teacher said you know it kept
he's referring to you know the colors that we have in the modern world for go and stop
and so the people who are into that person's teachings will say wait no no
we believe that green means go and red means stop and that's the way it is and
that's our religion and that's our faith and we have to believe that because that's what our teacher said
and now that's a misunderstanding of what the teachings were really about that that was just a metaphor an example
just because using something in the modern world is and it wasn't necessarily that the
teacher kind of held absolutely this is the truth that has to be this way
so in the same way the Buddha taught a lot and and is all of it really what you
know he was about really his teachings how much of it was just using and folding in uh teachings of his times and
ideas of his times and concepts of his times and we find people coming to the Buddha
to ask questions in a particular Paradigm particular framework
and uh and then the Buddha just accommodates that framework but he twists it or transforms it into his own
teachings what he wants to teach but he uses that person's framework and um is that framework you know the
Dharma or is it a little bit different it's kind of it's a vehicle for the
Dharma but maybe it's not exactly the his core teachings what's really essential to
Carry On from generation to generation so what we can do to find kind of answer
this question what is the teachings of the Buddha is to go back and look specifically at the places where it said
these are the teachings this is the Dharma and where it's that specific that's
exact what's it being said and what we find is a remarkable thing
that over and over again predominantly the message is has to do with some
direct contact experience with the present moment uh something right here that we can do
um and um and very much what's pointing to is not only direct experience but
more than important than experience the actions that lead somewhere so we've been
talking about Dharma means actions or and then that these actions can have
consequences so we want to kind of choose the actions that have the beneficial consequences
so for example the Buddha says in one place a very famous simile the simile of the raft
um that the Buddha says so I have shown to
you how the dhamma the Dharma is similar to a raft
being for the purpose of crossing over a river not for the purpose of grasping
so he says that the simile is that you come the person comes to edge of a river
and there's no way of getting across big big river except by making a small raft
getting getting wood and Reeds and different things and constructing a raft
and then paddling the raft across the other side when they get to the other side the
purpose of the rest is not the gra of the raft is not then to carry on your back into the forest and down wherever
you go next it served its purpose so don't grasp it leave it behind
so one of the teachings here is a Dharma something provisional it's something contextual that is useful for a
particular purpose and beyond that we don't look for it to understand what color traffic light
should be the um and um and it has to do with not
grasping and um so then it goes up we're going to go on
to say when you know that dhamma is similar to a raft you should abandon even the teachings
how much more the teachings are things that are contrary to the teachings
so there's tremendous importance on not grasping don't even grasp these the
Dharma the teachings of the Buddha let alone other teachings don't grasp on you
know ideas about traffic lights don't grasp to anything so this idea the centrality of not
grasping in this little passage represents what I'm trying to say today that these teachings are so
about the immediacy of now the imminence of now how we live now
um something that we can experienced just as well 2500 years ago as we can
experience today these are very modern teachings except we don't build rafts but
but the um so much but um them so I'm grasping here
so the dust the Dharma has something to do the heart of it about not not grasping
um and here's a fascinating uh description of the purpose of the Dharma
that Dharma is for the elimination of all standpoints
all uh obsessions
all adherences all underlying tendencies
all decisiveness around teachings this is a true teaching
for the stealing of all reactivity for the relinquishment of all
attachments for the ending of all craving for a cessation for Nirvana
so uh this so whatever the Dharma is it's for this purpose and this purpose it's
kind of a lofty purpose it's not exactly you know something you experience in the moment but it is something that's part
of the moment part of our direct experience there's nothing here about future lives nothing here but you know
fantastic ultimate communion with a cosmos or some deeper
insight into the true nature of reality uh it's mostly about releasing and
freeing and in particular around teachings earlier said don't even grasp the teachings the Buddha says here all kinds
of opinions viewpoints standpoints uh that we hold on to and
this is how it should be he teaches so we don't do that
somewhere else he teaches very eloquently
um that what he's teaching is not a view is not an a philosophy is not a Doctrine
uh what he's teaching is the uh is the letting go of all that
and something deeper something more valuable and it's a distilling of all
reactivity so the relaxation we did in the last meditation could be called rather than
relaxation could be called distilling of all reactivity bodily mentally and emotionally
that when we relaxed it's always relaxing our reactivity that somehow is
built up within us a monk once came to the Buddha and said
can you are you teach me the Dharma in brief so I can remember it and go into
the forest and have practice on my own and so um this is you know that's kind
of an important you know he's going to give you you know now that Buddha is going to give the pithy a
short version of this is what the Dharma is and in this case he said
um uh you should let go of Desire
to anything which is impermanent anything which is inconstant
let go of clinging to it that's all he says that's the heart that's what one of the
very simple key ways he wants to say it we can protest we can have our doubts
about it what about wait a minute but some here is pointing to something very deep and the important thing I want
to say here is that it's uh it's an action the action of
letting go um it's a letting go for uh for a
particular Consequence the consequence of becoming free and this is kind of the domain the area
what Dharma is about and earlier I talked about not grasping here at talk about not having desire for
anything impermanence anything's gonna if you hold on to anything which is going to change you'll suffer
what's the alternative way to be with it and um
and we find a good number of times the suit that someone comes to the Buddha and says teach me the Dharma in brief
and repeatedly it's about it's something very immediate something a very
practical almost modern terms and be psychological that doesn't have any recourse to
metaphysics to Supernatural to anything beyond what's possible to experience in
our direct experience um so the last thing I want to read when he
says when you know the Dharma for yourself that's the point he's talking about something you can know for yourself not a teaching that you have to
take on faith but a teaching that you can experience and you know this is why we're
practicing this mindfulness to really be able to have some deep experience of this for ourselves and here is a another
pithy way where he says how you know that what the Dharma is for yourself
when you know there is greed hatred and delusion
within you and when you know there is no greed
hatred and delusion within you then you know the Dharma is visible Here
and Now immediate inviting to be seen for oneself onward leading and to be
personally realized by the wise so here you again
maybe it diminishes in some people's minds to call this psychological
but I use that as an alternative to Supernatural or metaphysical or or
something kind of beyond the kind of what our everyday experience is like
that that to know green head and delusion of
all its different forms and to know that it's its absence
then you know the Dharma the Dharma is about seeing that what's happening uh
knowing suffering knowing the causes of suffering and knowing the end of it
and that end of great hate and delusion or it can be temporary but the Buddha says here even if it's
temporary you have a qualitative experience of really free of great hate and delusion maybe
accidentally on a very good day he had good sleep appreciate that there's something about that that you're experiencing you're
knowing the Dharma directly oh this is what it's about this is a Dharma this is
possible this is what I have a relationship to
this is what the actions can be about how I live my lives in accord with or supportive for this movement towards
this kind of freedom and um so the Dharma as a teaching
is what supports or points to or highlights what I've been teaching the
first three days of this week about what the Dharma is it's the relatedness that
we can live in it's the actions that have an effect on that relatedness
and it's uh the actions that transform
that relatedness to one of freedom of Goodwill of care of compassion
this is this is the Dharma and um so
so if you'd like to do some homework there on this
do this relaxation thing relax open up the present
see what's here and see if you can have some taste some experience of non-grasping of
non-clinging of non-reactivity that gives you a feel for oh the Dharma
this is valuable maybe you have a small experience but then if you extrapolate if this
became complete became full oh this is good Dharma
so thank you and um look forward to the last talk on this
topic