and warm greetings from IMC from the Redwood City
and I'm aware that some of you logging on to this YouTube through
in the calendar at IMC or it does this seems to be not working some of these links that we have
so you're here so you found a way to do it and but we'll try to repair some of
these links that we have so um
so classically in certain kind of reputation for Buddhism it said that
there are two Wings to Buddhism compassion and wisdom and compassion
is you know usually considered to be some an attitude and motivation
that we have in relationship to other people who are suffering and wisdom has many meanings but one of
them is that we become wise about how to monitor ourselves
how to become free of our own greed hate and delusion how to get free of our
attachments that interfere with compassion that interfere with our freedom
and these two work together they're said to be the two wings of the bird and uh and uh so in meditate into
meditations functional meditation is very much and through this wisdom side
and part of the wisdom is to practice with a focus on oneself
so that one can have a healthy and beneficial focus on the world on other
people so it's not meant to be selfish you know self-centered to be have an inner focus
on oneself it's a means towards caring for others or caring for the
world around us and one way that this works is that we learn how by this inner focus of
meditation we learn to find and recognize and support some of the uh uh some of
the healthy ways or Precious Ways or
peaceful ways that are waiting for us inside we learned to put a rest some of them
forces of distraction forces of preoccupation forces of anxiety and and
aversion and greed desires forces of
kind of attachment to self-concerns and
so paradoxically there's a kind of inner focus on oneself that is meant to free us from a
unhealthy focus on ourselves free us from the ways in which we create
strong divisions between Me Myself and mine and the world around us and others
as well but I say this in preparation for this meditation that there is a very valuable
way of taking the time to pause from all unusual activities of the
Mind that take us away from ourselves take us away from
you know caring for ourselves in a deep way and to care maybe compassionately for
ourselves is to find the place where we can sit quietly
with peace with a sense of ease with a sense of warmth and and maybe
appreciation or of ourselves or not in conflict with ourselves and
non-conflictive State resting in our own Hearts resting in our
own inner life not spitting out and this is not necessarily difficult
um but uh it's uh
this is not necessarily easy not but it's a well worth Journey
and to know that that's part of the journey is this inner Journey and with time as it is inner Journey
to really rest in ourselves and be at ease with ourselves in a deep way we find
ourselves in certain way turned inside out ready to be present for the world
ready to be a compassionate and caring for the world ready for a kind of
selfless service for the world uh that is a healthy because the
selflessness comes with a real uh establishment of a healthy inner life
so to assume your meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes
whom
just sit here quietly without doing anything else
and notice how you are right now
with the idea that you're going to allow yourself to be as you are
but being your own good friend who's there for you there for yourself
to sit with you to be present to be a deep listener
not to fix not to give advice but a friend who sits with you allows
you to be yourself and accompanies you as you are
and then to
now in the midst of listening for yourself being with yourself
from the Navy from whatever depths within that you can
let a deeper inhale arise comfortable Fuller
maybe a satisfying deep in-breath
and a relaxing exhale
breathing in and breathing out relaxing
and on the exhale relaxing into
yourself deep inside
and then letting the breathing return to normal
and maybe for the next three or four exhales continue to relax and settle
on yourself into yourself
breathing in and breathing out
and then again checking in with yourself
maybe in the depths of your heart depths of your being
depths of your breathing body
and offer a kind of Compassionate Care
a compassionate caring listening feeling sensing
what is inside in such a way that whatever you find
inside feels reassured
feels a matter to recognize known in such a way it can
ease up or relax through space around how we are
with each breath a reassurance
to your inner life that it's okay to settle and relax and
Center yourself Here and Now within your body
feeling and sensing your way
to a place of well-being
even a modest sense of being at ease being in harmony
being free from conflict just here
present for yourself as you breathe in and breathe out
no need for the mind to wander off
into the past future or other places
it's profound to be able to be present here
for yourself breathing
taking the time to feel how you are deep inside as deep as as easy to feel and
know how are you
and is there a way to recognize and know how you are
that your inside feels cared for
that how you are feels like there's a friendly presence friendly attention
a loving attention that how you are is allowed to be
and so relaxes Settles
moves into a place of deeper
at homeness Here and Now as it is
foreign
so then as we come to the end of this sitting
to check in with yourself again how are you
on the inside
how would you characterize the quality of your inner life interstate
and is there a way of relating to your inner way of being how
you are with compassion and care
with friendliness so no matter how you are deep inside
it feels that is if you are
there to support yourself to Aid whatever is there to let something settle and relax
deep inside
and as you feel a greater care compassion well-being
Within may that be a foundation
for a dedication to support the well-being and happiness of others
may this practice that we do serve for the happiness of Others May all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be healthy and may all beings everywhere
be free [Music]
[Music] thank you
so hello on this Tuesday second day for our
series on compassionate action and um before I start I want to mention
that uh I also noticed that the link to this YouTube channel and some of the
places on IMC is um inaccurate and I'll see what we can do
to to fix it today and um but if you go to the home page
for imc's YouTube channel there's a a
square there for what's being broadcast live so that's one one-on-one way to get
to it and um I'll play by tomorrow the links that are will be repaired
so here on the issue of compassionate action yesterday's talk was about
um it was focusing on compassionate action for the sake of others
and that is commonly how compassion is understood that we're caring for others
but uh equally important is that our compassion for others
should also include a care for ourselves
to have action to help and support others for my own sake as well
that as much as Buddhism might talk about not self and not living from
selfishness self-centeredness there is an emphasis on really being
responsible or caring monitoring carefully this this inner life of Our Own
and to care for that this too is important to have compassion for this too is important to uh bring care and
friendliness to and in terms of uh compassionate action
in the world being kind of having compassion for others and acting on that compassion
um we should all so the focus might be on doing things for others but as we do
it we should also do it for our own sake and that means two things
one thing it means is don't abandon yourself as you do it don't give yourself away
don't sacrifice don't easily sacrifice your own
well-being and Welfare for the sake of supporting and helping other people
it's not necessary there are sometimes we become uncomfortable sometimes our comfort level of sacrifice for the
well-being of others sometimes we do sacrifice certain things for for others
but but don't sacrifice don't abandon yourself don't give up on uh staying
connected to the practice for yourself monitoring yourself knowing uh when you get attached and when you
are getting stressed when you get contracted when you get afraid when you
get overly anxious in what you're doing and override The Compassion by despair or
dis or dismay or a sense of obligation and and
fear of consequences if you don't do the action so the principle that to have
compassionate action in the world in a way that also is for your own sake
so that you benefit from it so that it's a way of caring for yourself simultaneously
as it is caring for others this caring for others and caring for oneself does not need to be two separate
things and many times the idea of compassion is considered to be almost synonymous with
being altruistic um and uh and and that's often
synonymous with it kind of giving up from what's up abandoning oneself and sometimes Buddhist teachers will
even say that as I said yesterday that one of the ways of one of the purposes
of being compassionate is for your own happiness and well-being by giving up on your selfishness or
self-centeredness but that does not mean that you give up on yourself in some deeper way it means that you
don't get attached to self you don't cling to yourself you don't try to lock on to some definition of who we are or
who we aren't but or to do the compassion action only
for ourselves in order to make ourselves feel better we don't really care so much about other
people but but rather we care about others we try to act in ways that support them
and we're doing it in a way that we're not compromising ourselves not adding
stress we're not abandoning ourselves we're not um uh allowing ourselves to lose touch with
our own inner well-being our own Beauty our our inner practice our place of
Peace calm and the reason one of the reasons not to lose touch with that and stay connected
and do it for your own sake is so the compassionate actions that we do in the world are not stressful for us
so there's not we don't succumb to compassion fatigue or overwhelm so that
we don't um wound ourselves or hurt ourselves
by giving ourselves over to others in a way where we're open and receptive to feel the suffering of the world but
we're not available we don't know how to experience that suffering in a way that cares for ourselves as well
and so the suffering of the world kind of can you know very difficult for a heart that can break our hearts it can
shatter it can wound Us in certain ways but if we know how to maintain a place
of openness and non-clinging openness and receptivity that things are received
but they pass right through we don't hold on to anything or resist
anything then the Compassionate Care and contact of suffering and others doesn't have to
be challenging for us uh in fact so then we can be
compassionate for a long time if we don't get fatigued we don't get overwhelmed by it
and more important than that is that the quality of compassion the quality of our
relationship to other people is much higher if people feel that we're
at ease feel that we're a peaceful feel that we are
comfortable in our own being if we're this uncomfortable and anxious
and dismayed angry or upset in some way and that's the filter through which
compassionate action operates in the world people we're caring for will feel that
maybe uh maybe maybe it's not exactly conscious on their part but they can
feel that something's off it's kind of like by osmosis or the medium is the
message so if compassion is offered in the medium of anxiety if compassion is
offered in the media in the medium of upset if it's offered through the medium of
uh of a kind of selfish self-concerned or you know all kinds then um that's
some that that medium and which is done that actually uh skews and and
um shapes the kind of action we do and the impact that action has on others
it's very different if people feel us care with spaciousness with kindness
that's open with non-anxiety non-upset non-dismay
uh that they feel now I'm with a person who has the ability to be equanimous and
present in a full way and I don't feel like I have to take care of them or I
don't feel like I have to now be nourished be fed by anxiety be fed by
upset be fed by self-preoccupation or whatever it might be
so the quality of the compassion I think is much more significant more valuable when we act
compassionately for our own sake as well and we have a sense that for our own
sake there's something really here to care for there's something valuable here within ourselves
some valuable Center valuable way of being valuable sense of of
inner beauty or inner peace or inner wisdom inner goodness
and um and how do we discover that one of those ways is in many ways but one of
the ways is to meditate and and have this inner Focus we really
start tracking and monitoring and working with and discovering finding uh
deeply what's inside and settled the conflict inner conflict settle the inner
resentments and hurts and fears to really kind of drop down and discover
something marvelous Within so that when we from this kind of
wonderful place of ease and peace we can come forward forward into the world
so meditation is one way the other way is through compassionate action for the sake of others
that if we do that in a healthy way that reinforces this side this healthy side
of ourselves that mirrors it that's that kind of helps us to tap into it if we're
monitoring ourselves and and know that we're coming from this place
and then ultimately there's this wonderful cycle of mutuality cycle of of
um of how caring for others we care for ourselves and in this way of caring for ourselves
we end up caring for others as well and self and others in this way are not
separate it's not like it should be one or the other they are mutually
supportive until at such a point that the
Compassionate Care uh you know we feel this marvelous way that
there's no difference between self and other for the purposes of our care some some kind of barrier some kind of
division that many people live in begins to soften and not that we merge with
other people but that we become kind of
um there's a kind of a vast sense of openness that within which
caring for others and caring for the self there's no difference
just caring for whatever our perceptions our attention lands
so caring for oneself so compassion action for one's own sake
as the as the next kind of characteristics of compassionate action
yesterday the compassionate action for the sake of others and not not that
always is there for compassionate action and now including as we do care for others we
also want to care for ourselves not abandon ourselves not give ourselves away
so that there's more here in ourselves to be able to offer others
abandon oneself there's actually less that we can give
so thank you and um if you're interested in experimenting
with this you might see the situations where you are doing something nice for
others and seeing how you can um
do it in a way that feels satisfying for yourself that feels like it's this is a
good thing to do a good way to be in the world and maybe you do that in small small ways maybe that's where the best place
to experiment and um and um
and uh and then learn from there through the more difficult places
so thank you very much