so there was once a cave meditator
who wanted to practice you know by himself up in seclusion in some
mountains and he finally got together the conditions to be able to do that he had
some benefactors who were supporting him by having food and other supplies dropped
off at some place nearby that he could get to so he didn't have to go the several days to get back to the village
that was nearby so he had support and in his little cave he had a nice
altar set up you know with a Buddha image and some
other sacred items and he would make you know he would light incense and make
offerings every day and he practiced very diligently
in the in the cave and he did that for some years
and found it deeply beneficial it was often
grateful to the manufacturers supporting him and then one day he heard that they were
going to come visit him in his cave and his response at first was to
Spruce everything up and you know sweep it out really well and clean off the
Altar and make it so beautiful so that for them when they came
and then this thought came into his mind what am I doing and you know I've been meditating to let
go of the ego and the self and all of this and here I am putting on a show
and so he picked up a handful of dirt and he threw it on the altar and
later he um he said he was recalling that time and
he said that that was the finest offering he made on the whole retreat
so the topic for today is reverence and
irreverence and it may be that one or the other of
those is very meaningful to you and you've practiced it or you consider it
part of your life or maybe they're not so clear maybe that's not don't feel as
relevant to you but the suggestion for today is that
both are important ingredients in our practice and on our path and it's worth
getting to know both reverence and irreverence
so we may see ourselves as definitely having one of those and not the other
that that gets a sort of a common pattern but um reverence and irreverence are
actually just both practices that we can do and as such each one can be done
skillfully or unskillfully each one of those can read unskillfully or unskillfully and we'll probably
sometimes need each of them in their skillful form along our path
and if this idea of reverence and irreverence isn't
something that you think about very much or maybe something that you kind of avoid thinking about then this talk
might be even especially relevant for you so
we can start by asking you know what is reverence what are we
talking about and I would say it's a a range or a spectrum
and on a on a basic level it means taking something seriously
early in my practice I was talking with someone who had practiced much longer
than me and he was a person who often spoke very
directly I was a little bit his character and he said to me
Kim you know you don't take yourself very seriously
and he meant that in a particular way he meant that
I wasn't um taking so seriously my spiritual longing
or my interest in the Dharma my path my deepest aspirations you know early in my
practice I didn't quite know how to relate to that I didn't feel up to that
I didn't I felt I don't know what I felt but from my background I didn't have
maybe the qualities to be able to take that seriously and bring that forth in
myself that came later and so um I felt maybe a little
uncomfortable about acknowledging how much I cared about the practice how much I cared about the Dharma
and how I might even have Awakening as an aim I wasn't really ready to say that and he
picked that right out I'm grateful for that and when I reflect back on this older
friend I realized that he was he's one of the
most reverent and the most irreverent people that I know he has both of those very well developed
and it's admirable it's admirable
so the spectrum of reverence starts with taking something seriously
and it extends out to even feeling awe or wonder
being willing to devote one's heart or one's life to something that feels
valuable meaningful so there's a real strength you know
there can be a real strength to this quality of reverence
but at times maybe even often
our reverence can get a little bit misdirected there is
as I said before they're skillful and unskillful reverence and irreverence so
there's four combinations and I want to talk about all four of them so we get
kind of a map of this space and they're not merely opposites
so it is there are four distinct things to talk about so these four quadrants and we'll start
with the quadrant of unskillful reverence actually
cases where our reverence is somewhat misdirected if we even have it
so what is it that we're taking seriously in our life
what is that are there things in our life or our mind or our heart
that we are in some way paying homage to that maybe don't deserve that level of
devotion I want to read a a couple of lines from
a verse and then I'll we'll talk through what it means
this is from the 37 practices of the bodhisattva
locked up in the prison of their own patterning whom can ordinary Gods
protect so it's a little bit poetic it's talking about the ordinary things in life that
we place our trust in so pleasure you know the things that we
like and enjoy maybe wealth maybe power
maybe health and fitness you know our body is feeling good right now
our relationships learning
physical safety ethical purity even meditative Bliss or meditative
enjoyment now many of these things are good that's where it gets entangled confusing
these are good things that are worth having in human life all of them actually but they become
problematic when they rise to the level of being revered don't they
yeah so that is when things become Gods they're ordinary Gods they're just
ordinary things but we can make them into gods in some way and if we do that what we're doing is
buying into the world view or the psychological pattern that they uphold and we're trying to use that to protect
us you know if I just had enough money then
I would be safe that's a world view
it's not that we shouldn't have any money but that world view is dangerous to buy into
or you know my physical health is who I am very dangerous to buy into
so we've done this maybe in some ways and the problem is that all of these
things are are transient they're not true protection and they're not really totally in our control are they
so there's always a little bit of stress if we've made these into gods
so these are the ordinary gods that most of the world reveres at some level
so ordinary Gods can also be more subtle they can be psychological patterns in
our in our mind or our mental habits you know for example we also get stuck
in various views and opinions and ways of perceiving things we may be very
attached to our political perspective or some
ways of seeing the world and sometimes we're not even aware that that's it
that's that's what we've done but meditation will eventually if you do mindfulness meditation you'll eventually
see some of these patterns in the mind we can also get stuck in stories about
our life stories about how we got to hear stories about who we are stories
about what we're doing and again those are things where we wouldn't want to have none of that we have some sense of
who we are and in our life and so forth but again these things are so easy to
get hooked into and they shouldn't really be taken so
seriously that they're made the foundation of our well-being it can be humbling when we realize what
we have allowed our heart to get entangled with and there are many people who come to
meditation practice and to Buddhism because there has been some kind of a shocking event in their
life that revealed that these gods were only ordinary and
were not protecting them loss of a job death of a loved one a change in our health
maybe some of these things resonate for some of you in this room of as to why practice became meaningful to you
it's not always like that but they can jolt us into seeing our misplaced reverence so they have a way of bringing
into Focus what's really important for us
so let's shift then toward the quadrants that are associated
with irreverence so they're not just quite opposite
um each quadrant is distinct not just the negation of the others so you know if we decide that we're not going to
Revere bodily health and financial success and those kinds of things
learning education that's one for me that I find valuable
it's not that we would turn around and reject these things say all right none of this matters it's not about nihilism
or that kind of cynicism so we've looked at unskillful reverence
let's turn to what skillful irreverence is a little bit the opposite so
Dharma practice and especially mindfulness practice helps us to see through things that that
we might have been stuck with if we if we continue with the practice we have to see more and more it's just how it works
the the mind gets drawn to seeing because that's what we're practicing we're practicing paying attention in the
moment to what's going on in the ma in the body in the mind in the heart in the emotions and eventually if we continue
to take data in that way if you will moment to moment a moment we watch what's going on the mind is going to
start to see patterns in that and mindfulness has a way of breaking things
open or differentiating experience so that we see different aspects of it
different parts of it not be fooled by the solid seeming nature of it that we
saw at the beginning so one term that's used for this in the
practice is disenchantment nibida and Pali but it's not a it's not
a bad kind of disenchantment a negative kind like that word sometimes has that
implication in English but it actually means that we're no longer Charmed or Enchanted as if a
spell had been cast on us we it's a it's a minor form of waking up to see through
things and realize oh wow I was really caught up in that
so it's a positive term
and once we have some experience with seeing through things like just as an example it's fairly
common for people to come on retreat spend a few days like a meditating so a
little bit more immersive than usually at home and realize in that time
that they view everything through a certain lens like maybe the lens of fear
it's fairly common for people to say I had no idea that this was underlying so
much of my life and that you know that's like a it's a seeing
through it's a moment of no longer being in the spell caught under the spell of the fear but you wake up to it you see
it doesn't mean it's over but seeing it is so important that moment
and once we have some experience with seeing through in certain ways then we gain the ability to be
skillfully irreverent of some of the mind's tricks some of the mind's
patterns and also some of the cultural patterns that are out there in the world
Jack cornfield says that he was going through a period of seeing a lot of
patterns in his mind and he started naming the different ones that he would
that he that he found like you know he had a certain voice in his mind that was critical of everything he did you know
oh you're probably going to mess that one up too and you know he couldn't necessarily stop that voice from coming
we don't necessarily get a choice about that but when it would come he would say he
would like bow to it he had a name for it and he would say thank you for your opinion opinion and move on you know so
there's um there was a way that he could lighten up a little bit be a little bit irreverent toward that voice because it
wasn't helping him so um I also think about Sylvia vorstein has a a nice little set
of phrases that she says that are useful words that are useful for how to practice she says we should practice
with gentleness precision and humor
and I think that the order is important but also but the humor part you know she
says you have to just sometimes laugh at what the Mind comes up with wow
where did that come from you know where did that thought come from where did that idea come from
so it's very freeing to be able to smile a little bit at the antics of the mind
at least sometimes I know we can't do it all the time we're still practicing we're still getting caught up
but when we have those moments to be able to be skillfully irreverent
of some of some of what the Mind comes up with just based on habit
and then this um this can extend even into some of the conventional Norms
out in society we see that they're just conventions and again it's not that we wouldn't
have ways of doing things in society but it's nice if we can see through those a
little bit um there's a fellow who drives around Santa Cruz in a sort
of a custom camper kind of thing very large actually and it had it's painted in his you know
clearly his own work artwork it says you know Peace and Freedom in big letters on
it and it has streamers and decorations you almost you can't miss this thing when it's driving
around and you know it's all done in in kind of a humorous and and yet serious
way of poking a little bit of fun at um people just going about their
conventional lives you know he has this way that wakes people up a little bit
it is tricked out camper let's say
it can even extend into the spiritual or religious realm you know I think about how the Dalai Lama
laughs at the pomp associated with his position I mean he takes his position seriously he he you know he acts as the
bodhisattva of compassion for our world but you know the price of that in a
sense is that when he comes places there's gold brocade and these fancy things and people are always attending
to him and he has a way of very gently showing that he sees through that you
know he's going to go and sit on the throne but I remember watching a a video of him where he they had some very high
seat for him to sit on to give a teaching and it was very beautiful and you know he came and he did his vows and
he got up on the seat and he noticed that it was it had been padded it was very soft for him and he's he realized
it was a little bit bouncy and he paused and he and he bounced on and you know
just for a moment and then you know and then he went back but you could see him like oh look at that bouncing I bounced
when I was five years old on a chair but you know so he he takes his position lightly in a skillful way this is
skillful irreverence of seeing through things certain lightness lightness of being
there's a prayer in vadriana practice where one asks give me energy to see through life's
illusions wouldn't that be nice if we could always see through life's Illusions beforehand
yeah so
here in the United States I would say that we have a culture of celebrating certain types of irreverence
it's a little bit in our nature that we um
have that quality somehow but we can pay a price for that and
sometimes sliding in let's say to the quadrant that we could call unskillful
irreverence okay so we talked about skillfully irreverence but we can go too far
often we can be cynical we can have sarcasm
about our approach to life
my father says that um perhaps when he was in his
twenties um he was once told around that time by an
older Mentor that he was not quite mature yet because he still sometimes
used sarcasm and he never forgot that um to be told by you know this older guy
that he wasn't quite mature yet he was thinking he was Hot Stuff being a 20-something guy
and but he and he he realized over time yeah sarcasm doesn't always serve
other aspects of unskillfully irreverence
include that we don't often take some elements of spirituality seriously so
devotion prayer um here in the west the Western version of
Buddhism those were actually deliberately stripped out when they were brought here
because the teachers thought that westerners wouldn't like that sort of thing might be true but if you go to Asia
people are so devoted many times at least in the places that
I've been and seen there there's a lot of devotion there is even the acceptance of using prayer
and it's there's a lot of heartfulness and you can feel it in the energy of the
temples there um and there can be a way that we don't honor that
quite in our version here sometimes we also feel
too irreverent to be willing to surrender in our practice
this practice ultimately asks us to give up quite a lot
and you know renouncing aspects of our
attachment to self renouncing some of what we thought was
so important earlier in life those ordinary gods if we have too much irreverence too much
there's even some ego sometimes in your reverence we may not be willing to give up what this practice asks us to let go
of to be truly free so
we might be irreverent toward things that are really quite beautiful
if we were willing to open to them and that can leave a hole in the heart
it doesn't allow our heart to be completely filled by our practice something would be lacking in our
spirituality some juice not quite there if we're not willing to touch Into the
Heart Dimension the Letting Go the giving up the surrender
there are times every few years I don't know if we've done it for a while but every few years
here we have a refuge ceremony probably it didn't happen during the
pandemic but it was it's a time when um people who want to you know who are
interested to do so can come and formally take refuge in Buddha Dharma
and Sangha and there's a little ceremony that Gil does with that and
I was not too keen on this idea I did the ceremony I think in
2008 something like that and I wasn't too keen on it but I was getting more
involved in IMC and felt like I was I had joined the board at that time and I
felt like um somehow it felt right and so there's a little class you take a few
sessions and then there's a ceremony at the end and I kind of thought in my mind
well okay I'll do this thing you know the thing to do here at the center and
I I don't think I was you know disrespectfully irreverent but
nonetheless I was taken by complete surprise that I was deeply moved by the
simple act when it was made formal and the lights were dark and we lit candles
and offered flowers and then sat in meditation and took the refuges and
precepts officially that I just my my body just felt light
it was flooded with this spiritual quality called PT Joy and it was
probably better I think that I had no clue that I was capable of that kind of feeling
um because it took me by surprise and it was so delightful
um it opened something in me yeah probably better that it was a surprise
[Applause] so the remedy if you will for unskillful
irreverence where we've gotten a little bit into that sarcasm ego I'm not gonna
let go is the is to open to healthy skillful
reverence some people move toward this kicking and screaming and others Discover It others
have it naturally which is nice but that's the last of our four quadrants so we're now moving to
skillful reverence so we had skillful and unskillful reverence and irreverence
so let's get to skillful reverence so one basic form is Refuge as I as I
talked about with the ceremony so refuge in the triple gem Buddha Dharma
and Sangha and when we started back four quadrants ago in the quadrant of
unskillful reverence I read two lines from a verse about the
ordinary gods and I want to read you the whole four-line stanza now the whole four line
verse locked up in the prison of their own
patterning whom can ordinary Gods protect who can you count on for Refuge
go for refuge in the three jewels this is the practice of a bodhisattva or
we could say this is the practice of a sincere practitioner so we can start out doing this at you
know kind of a surface level but then we'll find that on unfolds over time you know we have to unfold it more
and more maybe we just say the words at first like if you go to a retreat for example often on the first evening
everybody is invited to take refuge in Buddha Dharma and Sangha and say the
five precepts as a creation of the the container of the community container there and if you've never done that and
it's a little bit of a surprise when it's happening you might just say the words and move on
but then eventually there's a way that they can start to work on us
you know recalling my experience with the ceremony I had said the refuges before that but
suddenly it came alive when I did it at the ceremony so they woke me up to looking more
carefully at Refuge so skillful reverence includes taking
seriously the beauty of Our Own Heart everybody's heart has Beauty in it
even just for wanting to do the practice or for starting to practice mindfulness
there's Beauty right there but there's also so many ways in which we are living ethically ways in which
we're offering meta or gratitude or care to and to people to the world to animals
everybody has something perhaps we have something deeper perhaps
we have a spiritual longing that's bringing us to practice in some way
there's a word for this in Pali samvega sense of spiritual longing
Gil tells a story of a man who came to a temple and he was
not too sure about practice but somehow he was drawn to coming to the temple and
he saw a statue um outside the doors maybe and he
sat and looked at it for a while and he was sort of debating you know should
I really open to practice I don't know
and this this was a statue that had some magical qualities
through the power of this Temple and it said to him why not
and he was very shocked and um and the stat and the statue just said
again why not and the man was so scared he ran away
have we done that why not why not so you know don't dismiss don't
dismiss those deeper feelings in your heart you don't have to speak them you
don't have to share them but at least for yourself please open to them at some
level don't brush them under the rug
there's a suta where that's about a it's actually about a dream that somebody has
but it's a very mythological and allegorical dream if you will and in the
dream he has a series of choices you know like he he's digging and he finds
things along the way and he you know he's digging and he finds a fork and
um the advice that he's given is throw out the fork and keep digging so he throws
out the fork and he keeps digging and he finds he finds all these things I don't remember all of them one of them's like
a chopping block with a piece of meat on it it says throw out the chopping block and keep digging with the knife and so
he keeps digging and eventually after eight or nine things he um he finds a
Naga serpent which is a powerful mythical beast in Buddhism generally
benign um meant to represent great power
that can come from practice or even big things in general are just called nagas
like elephants are called nagas and sometimes arahans awakened beings they're called nagas so he finds a Naga
Serpent and then the advice is pop stop digging honor the Naga serpent
and the sense is that we keep digging and digging in our heart in our life in
our practice in our path and we keep finding things where we have choices and we let go of the things that
are not useful the fork is doubt don't need that The Chopping Block sensual pleasure we don't need that we don't
need to pursue that make it a god eventually we find something very beautiful an August serpent in the heart
don't throw that one out I'll enter that one
there's also a suta about the monastic Sangha but we could just think of it as
a spiritual community where there's a new monk who is you know they have so many
rules for monks to follow you know like over 200 little rules that
they have to some of them are big some of them are little that they have to follow as they go through their day
their life and there's a new monk who is continually making mistakes on the rules
and you know you're supposed to in some way admonish among who is not fulfilling
the rules so that he can benefit from them but there's a
asuta where the other monks sense that this Monk who keeps having trouble with
the rules is actually just proceeding from very deep love and faith of the
Buddha and that that's that's filled his heart and that's why he ordained and
that's all he cares about and he can't get the details but he has this love and this faith and when they see that they
decide not to admonish him right away because they worry that that will dampen
his faith actually and it would be it would be more un beneficial for him to
to to have that happen than to you know keep going and and so and eventually he
sort of grows into being able to manage the rules but it's so compassionate right that they saw his love and his
faith and they you know let him find his way so we might consider that for
ourselves also as we move along with this practice skillful reverence for
our effort our best effort that we're bringing
so in light of all this we could say I think it's fair to say
that spiritual maturity includes skillful healthy reverence of some type
do you dare so we have to discover I think for ourselves what this is we can't borrow
it from someone else or imitated um
I would say that it even matters in secular ways also you know out in society
there's a way in which we've lost touch with being reverential
and daring to acknowledge what is worthy of reverence out in the regular conventional world
and that may have something to do with the challenges we're seeing in our society
and in our world we may not take seriously things that are worth taking seriously
even the Buddha felt moved to express reverence he's the Buddha right but there's a suta
um a discourse where the uh it's I think soon after the Buddha's Awakening and he
says this is what the line is he says it is painful to dwell without reverence
and deference the Buddha says this and
um the word translated as reverence is which is probably most closely resembles
our idea of respect so the Buddha was looking around for
something to respect he had just woken up and he um
he couldn't find any being in the world who was his Superior in terms of Ethics in terms of meditation in terms of
wisdom in terms of liberation and yet he still wanted to offer something
you know those waking up didn't take away that wish in his heart
and so what he decided to do was he he said that he could still feel reverence and deference to the Dharma
isn't that sweet and you know this was before he had done a lot of teaching so I don't think he's referring to all of
the stuff he said because he hadn't said it yet I think what he was referring to
is Dharma as nature you know Dharma as the way things work
the order the way things unfold which he awoke to completely and waking up he saw
how it all works and that he could offer reverence to
the beauty of the universe I find it quite touching that the Buddha
still wanted to dwell in reverence and deference so I would think it's really it's
appropriate for us also so I look for this in people as they
practice you know does it seem that they've found something that's worth
taking seriously or feeling awe for I look for that as people practice over
time have they discovered something worthy of reference reverence
what have you found just reflect for a moment what have you found that might be worthy
of that
so there's an important change in people when they shift from wondering how the Dharma can fit into
their life to wondering how their life can fit into the Dharma
it's a shift spiritual maturity might also include
healthy ear reference a certain lightness of being
bouncing on the seat like the Dalai Lama you know so we don't want to take ourselves too
seriously in all of that there should be a little
irreverence toward the silliness of the this predicament we're in laughing at
our foibles laughing at our eccentricities being willing to be wrong
yeah willingness to let go
so to end a few practical tips you know how might we act on some of what's been
said today a very simple way is to invoke an
attitude of sincerity at the beginning of your sit so maybe just acknowledging as you sit
down on the cushion acknowledging that what you're doing matters why are you doing this why are you
sitting still on a cushion or a chair for half an hour or 45 minutes or 60 minutes
so feel the sense that you care about your inner life in some way or you have
a spiritual longing or you you just know it's beneficial even if you can't articulate anything that's fine
so feeling your sincerity that it makes a difference to sit
and maybe sometimes that simple sincerity or respect will
open into a bigger perspective having a sense of the
the lineage that brought this teaching to us and that we're participating in at that
very moment of sitting you know we don't take ourselves so seriously sometimes we think oh yeah you
know Buddhism and these ancient wisdom texts and the Insight Meditation Center
and all that but I'm just I'm just a person who sits a little bit sometimes
no you're participating in something big something that's been going on for 2600
years and um you know the dharma's vast and profound
and it's amazing that we found it think of all the people who didn't find it or think of all the other things you could
have found some of which are great some of which might be just as good who knows but you found this and it's quite
good so there can be a sense of being part of something larger
so we can practice skillful reverence we can practice skillful irreverence
maybe we'd even get to the point of being willing to throw dirt on our altar
if we wrote that we were getting attached to it in some way But first you have to have the altar
and be revering it then you'll learn
how to lighten up on that so reverence and irreverence
which one might need more work which ones have are skillful which are unskillful there's some some ground to
play with there and I hope all of you might find a something something amid all of that
that connects were you
these are my thoughts for today and may they be of benefits and if any of it
wasn't you can just leave it here I'm not attached
so I think we're right at time so we'll end but if anyone has any questions I'll stay here for a few minutes thank you