you so welcome my name is Maria strotman
sounds so strange to say that I haven't given my name in so long
I'm going to read a quote for you and unfortunately
I have forgotten where I got it so you'll just have to trust me that it's a great source
there is a dimension of life of awareness that you can discover
tune into rest in that is silent deep
embracing of all an imperfect balance with it a kind of
wisdom that says yes these are the inevitable changes on the
surface and here's the Stillness of awareness Underneath It All
there is a dimension of Life of awareness that you can discover tune into rest in that is silent deep
embracing of all and imperfect balance with it a kind of wisdom that says these are the
invis inevitable changes on the surface and here's the Stillness of awareness
Underneath It All so I I've read this and I thought about
it a bit and I thought you know this is really this is really reassuring what a
wonderful idea that there's a Stillness Underneath It All
and it's a kind of wisdom and I can just be with this in this
space this embracing this space and I thought about
the idea that this was gladdening to the heart and so I have been thinking about
gladdening the heart for some some days a week or so
and tonight we're going to speak about gladdening the heart gladdening the heart having a little
heartbeat light light not happiness but a gladdening of the
heart a quickening of the heart an uplift of the heart so we're going to begin
I'm going to invite you excuse me I'm going to invite you to eat some
blackberries with me now I would love to be able to pass out blackberries but I don't have any with
me and anybody listening who's not in this room wouldn't have access anyway that just would not be fair
so you're going to have to use your imagination to conjure up these blackberries that we're going to eat
and use your use your visual memory your sense of smell your taste feel the
juiciness and we're going to go Blackberry eating with Galway canal
I love to go out in late September among the fat over ripe icy black blackberries
to eat blackberries for breakfast the stocks very prickly a penalty they
earn for knowing the black art of blackberry making and as I stand among them lifting the
stalks to my mouth the ripest berries fall almost unbidden to my tongue
as words sometimes do certain peculiar words like strengths or
quenched or firmed many lettered one-syllable lumps which I
squeeze squinch open and Splurge well into the silent startled
icy black language of blackberry eating in late September
did you taste any blackberries did you see any blackberries
just the intensity of being with blackberries
I squeeze squinch open Splurge well in the silent startled icy
black language of blackberry eating in late September
the feel of being in those blackberries and really experiencing those
blackberries there's they don't have any meaning they don't have any fundamental
relationships to what it means in the world they don't have anything to do with
suffering they have a little bit to do with pleasure here but it's just the tasting and the seeing
and and the being with those blackberries that I want to call to mind here it's the joy the Delight of just
being with it being in the process of eating those blackberries
unlike the joy of getting my iPad to stay awake
so when I speak of gladdening I'm talking about that uh introducing to
our practice or recalling in our practice the Delight that comes from
practice it's not uncommon to hear someone say I am so grateful for my practice I never
could have gotten through this without my practice the practice has been so important to me and it's beginning to
feel like a terrible burden to have this practice
and so I want to remind us that the practice is to be held lightly
that the practice is really a gift and not a burden
too often our practice has something to do with how we do it and when we do it and how
often we do it and am I doing it right and how far along am I in my practice
and what's going to happen next but the gladdening of the heart
is really about the Delight that just happens just happens it's not like we do
something to make a gladdened heart it's a gift to just kind of come as it's
like Grace you know sprinkles on you when you least expect it
we're not managing suffering when we talk about gladdening the heart
we're not trying to write a sense of ill will
we can be in the presence of ill will and still glad in the heart I heard something Gill said a couple of
weeks ago where he said okay so if you can't bring yourself to push away ill will
at least be grateful that you want to at least be grateful that you want to
that's a gladdening of the heart that's in not taking everything that's happening to you and condensing it down
into some black hole of seriousness and an inevitable pulling
but really being with the process of just living being alive
I want to recall the joy that arises in practice
for this to be enough in practice
to not think of our practice as something that is of a lace a suitcase
that we carry around full of all our tricks but that the suitcase contains us
so that we can experience the smoothness or the roughness of what we are experiencing
the intensity of it or the boredom of it
whatever the experience is we want to be totally present for it
because in being totally present for it it is just itself
it isn't something that we have to make into a story of Our Lives
another piece of this that I've been thinking about is that we we have us the story of our life
and okay we accept the fact that we're changing all the time but there's this little thread that we
carry around with us that's that's Maria Here Comes Maria and Maria was here and now she's there and she's going to go
over there pose you could meet every moment and you
don't have to be Maria or Audrey
or anybody else you don't have to be someone you don't have to be the person you think you are
you don't have to be the person someone else thinks you are you don't have to be meet any expectations you can just take
the next step in this experience just the next step you don't have to be anything in
particular how does that feel
not to have to be who you think you are who you have been
so um those of you in this room probably remember that the Reigns of New Year's
Eve when there was a lot of flooding and the the storm was significant
and early in the morning I was out on my back deck I live on the third floor of this Condo
building and I was it was dark so I couldn't actually see anything but I could hear
the storm and what I heard was water the water was
dripping through the trees the water was hitting the roof the water was running in the gutter the water was
rushing down below which is I have to tell you not common it's usually dry down below and here it was rushing
through the area around our building and all I could do was hear
all he could do was hear so I was just listening to water
I was listening to water and all of a sudden I had this feeling
of total Delight just wow water
I thought how magnificent it was because all I was doing was just hearing
I wasn't thinking about what the water was doing or where it was going or why is it here or how much is there
I was just listening and in being totally in the moment
there was Delight it's not like I was going after Delight
I was just listening and that to me is what it means to
Gladden the heart to be available for the heart to be gladdened
to be totally totally present for whatever is happening
without without an opinion about what's happening you know just just here
today I read a story about uh two people who are friends so
uh there was an article it was in the New York Times and it was about too unlikely to be friends people
one of them was a well-known Christian conservative who speaks out against gay marriage and abortion
she's a former civil rights lawyer who spent most of her career fighting to desegregate schools and protect
transgender kids from bullying these are two pretty different people and they were both assigned to the same
committee called let's see it's called the U.S Commission on International religious
freedom one was was assigned to the committee by a
Republican and one was assigned to the committee by a Democrat I'm going to let you guess which one was
which and the two of them went in he is uh
he's a white man older Conservative Christian from Louisiana
she is a Hindu from South Chicago
really different people but it turns out they had much more in common than they had separate from one another
and the two of them began testing what checking with one another when they were
trying to get they were looking at at religious freedom outside the United
States we won't go into why they were looking outside the United States but that's
what the commission was formed to do and they would support people who were being
penalized by their government or by other people because of their religion and the two of them were often fighting
on the same side and the consequence of that was that they began they actually became
friends and they kept in touch after their commission assignments expired
to their great surprise and the the the man said you know what I
realized I realized we were friends when I when I realized she was in my prayers
and it made me really careful of that how I referred to anything because I didn't want to offend her
and so I became much more careful in my speech and as I was listening to that
I teared up and I realized that that tear was not about sadness and
it wasn't about happiness it was a tear that arose from the hope
that polarization doesn't have to be the sad thing that it is
that people can talk to one another that people don't have to be on opposite
sides of things and just the presence of that I found so hopeful it brought tears
to my eyes that is a gladdening of the heart
that that appearance of Hope that reassurance of hope that
possibility lightens the heart and you say ah it's
possible and you can see it's possible this is what I mean by gladdening the
heart but it's possible not to notice it we could just go through life not noticing
it that would be pretty easy actually if I am determined to be upset about
something I'm not going to not be upset about it
if I'm overwhelmed with a sense of Injustice or righteousness I am not going to be able to see a way
out of it I'm just going to be bemoaning it
in the same way last week I found myself
talk uh I was very discouraged I'd been working
on a project for about a year and a half and it looked like it was just over it just was not going to happen
and in that moment I thought you know I'm going to be okay with this I'm a
good Buddhist if it was meant to be if it was going to happen it was going to happen if it hasn't happened I can just
be fine and Meanwhile my heart's just going oh oh how can this how can this be true
this particular project is not something that personally benefited me but something I really believed in
and it looked like it just wasn't going to happen and so like somebody encouraged me to go look at this other
place go check these people out and I thought I've checked so many people out I did had a meeting with them
they were terrific they had great plan that it was much less expensive than the
other proposal that had made to me I was so excited about it and as I was reporting it I found myself saying
I see the approach of a Pollyanna complex I so much want this to be true
that I'm just going to believe anything and in that moment I realized it wasn't
it was a fear that I couldn't be Pollyanna that it was a fear that I couldn't be optimistic
I'd been so discouraged before
and to suspend the opinion about whether I was being
overly optimistic and just said well let's just see what happens let's just see what happens and of course I still
don't know what's going to happen because it's a process
but in the moment that I let go of either denying optimism or totally
embracing optimism and left myself in the place of just I wonder what's going
to happen everything's lighter
I didn't have to have an opinion about whether I was being optimistic or not it
just didn't matter it was let's see what happens and that let's see what happens part
is is the place of a gladdened heart
it leaves hope and possibility and a sense of
freedom a sense of freedom
think of how much courage it takes to be really present
it implies a great deal of trust you have to trust
that the people you're talking to the position you're in is is somehow going to not hurt you
we get kind of in the in the habit of vigilance
I have to be careful about this I have to be careful about that I have to watch my sense of that I have to be careful of
free speech I have to be careful of wise speech I have to be careful and we find ourselves being vigilant about
everything and the energy of that vigilance
sets up a barrier to experiencing something just as the
raw experience because now we're measuring it against all of our little safety tags
how does it how does it measure against that how does it measure against that how does it measure against that
not only does it take a lot of energy but it distorts what we see and how we
experience just being alive I am not advocating that one gives up
all diligence or vigilance only that we see when vigilance is
operating that we notice it that we notice how careful we're being
one of the really great things about retreat is that you can just sit
in a fairly safe place you don't actually have to talk to anybody you don't have to explain yourself to
anybody you'd kind of have to explain yourself to yourself
but it's a relatively safe place you can just you can allow whatever feelings you have
to come out to allow whatever things you have been suppressing in your
life to just kind of happen in a safe place well suppose we could do that more often
suppose we could do that without having to be on retreat
suppose suppose we could just show up for this moment and not worry about anything
for just this moment just this one not all of them just this
one it's safe in this room right now
right now it's safe and as soon as I said that I felt myself
take a deep breath wow
in the last days of the Buddha the the suta Maha paranab niba nabana
suta the last days of the of the Buddha there is uh there were a whole process
procession of people who were coming to see the Buddha at the end and each of them that came there's a you
know how suits are there'll be a phrase that keeps getting repeated this happened and then the next people come and the same this happened and and the
phrase that was that that kept happening was this one and the blessed one spent
much of the night instructing them in the Dharma rousing edifying and
gladdening them rousing edifying and gladdening them
this is what the Buddha chose to do in his last hours and days
rousing edifying and gladdening the rousing is about energy the edifying
is teaching the truth of the dhamma and the gladdening is the appreciation
for the fact that if if we have a heavy heart if we are loaded down and burdened
we can't take anything on and the gladdening the loosening of the
strictures around how we experience something is key to being able to move
forward in practice
gladdening is one of the first steps in uh the string that's called the uh the
gladdening Pinhead the string that leads to samadhi you
know there are five things there's Gladden Joy
Tranquility happiness and samadhi
it isn't like you you do something to get to those steps what you do is step
into the flow when each one leads to the other and a gladdened heart leads to Joy
how wonderful it it moves when you're in the flow when
you're just allowing something to happen when you're just allowing the experience to be
and when you're in meditation the SE can inevitably lead to samadhi and deep
concentration in a place where you can see things clearly
that I maintain that we're more likely to be able to see things clearly just as we're walking
around in the world off the cushion if we can do it with an unguarded heart
with a gladdened heart and so I seek that not as the thing
but as an opportunity the opportunity for just thisness
okay there we go
so the other thing about gladness that I wanted to to talk about is that gladness arises out of out of practice
and supports it you know it's not like
uh now let me put it another way if I recognize Delight in sitting and
meditating I'm much more likely to meditate and if I'm meditating more I'm much more
likely to give up the strictures around my limits on how I will experience
something I'm much more likely to have a light heart I'm much more likely to be involved in
the mindfulness of this moment I will grow more familiar with what mindfulness
means I will become a person who knows what's
happening in this moment not ahead of time or behind
but experiences this moment and says oh I know I'm sitting here
I know I'm speaking
where we treat the experiences actually happening and not just part of the story
so that mindfulness just becomes habit
that leads to a gladdening of the heart and the gladdening of the heart in turn
leads to Joy leads to increased attention to our practice
it is a both an evolution of practice and something that supports the practice
it becomes something that's not a task that's something that we can be aware of
so it kind of works like this the the uh excuse me
I'm going to take a drink here hold on
okay so uh tomorrow I'm leaving on a road trip at 7 30 in the morning and tonight I was coming here to talk
and I've got this project where I've got vendors yelling at me why are you not answering my bid and the reason I'm
going on the road trip is that my mother's in hospice and I want to go see her while I can
and you can imagine there's a lot all kinds of family Dynamics around this I have lots of siblings where I'm going
so that's been on my mind and why are you doing this and why aren't you doing that and I'm you know I'm doing laundry
and I'm packing and and my husband decides he wants to rebalance our investments again today
and so late this afternoon I found myself in the midst of great chaos
mental chaos a lot of mental chaos
and I had my sister on the phone who wanted to tell a story that which wasn't relevant to the time
and a text from the person who's going to take care of my plants what what are you are you ready to tell me about that
and I I looked at my hands and I realized they were moving like this moving moving
moving and I said well I could just let the hands move I don't have to move
and as I dissociated myself from the the train of I have to get all these things
done I was able to say well what will I choose to get done in this
moment I'll end the conversation with my sister talk to you tomorrow
and just okay some things are going to fall down the realization that the chaos
was really just trying to do everything at once which wasn't going to happen
so I could become filled with anxiety and stress
and lose my sense of presence
by getting lost in the story of all the things I had to do or I could just say oh things are
falling on the floor look
you can actually do that that's what I did I said well some things are going to fall on the floor
and just the act of saying that even if I didn't quite believe it
I didn't quite let go of everything I breathed easier
more easily
see it can't be about all the things I want even my good
intentions if I'm too wed too well as a good Buddhist I'm going to be
totally equanimous In This Moment I'm going to deny that things are
falling on the floor because then I have to be you know there for the fact that things are falling on
the floor things are not getting done things are things that people are unhappy
why didn't you call me and in that moment of realizing
things don't have to be better to be at ease with them
the at ease part is not everything's smooth and I don't have to
worry about it but rather I'm okay with everything's not smooth
everything's not smooth
and to not make it a a piece of responsibility or judgment it doesn't
have anything to do with me it's just how things are right now
you know I could tell myself stories about how I should have organized my day better but what's the point of that the
day is already over so that's not useful
I am here and this is what's happening I am here and this is what's happening
oh knowing this is what's happening is a lot easier than writing down the list of
things that could be true
to to be in the presence of stress and say how do I know I'm stressed well
there's this tight feeling of this pulling okay so so just let it have all the room
in the world and watch it spread itself out
and notice does it have colors my stress tends to be Gray but sometimes it's red
I have a sense of red and Heat and sometimes it's just boring old
pulling and to be right there with that feeling
frees you from having to think about all the reasons that you might be stressed you're just dealing with you're just
feeling stress so just feel it just be there with it just notice it
give it a name hi Fred
there doesn't have to be a story attached to everything that we experience can just be itself
just as we can just be the person that has shown up for this moment we don't have to be something
just this and the Heart gets lighter
we don't do it to make the heart lighter we just lighten the load
stop carrying around the burden
if we were to cultivate gladness of heart what would we do
what would you do how would you do it what would you what would you do how would you be
the most important thing is to just be present just be
here really here and not in this story
the story of your life
and to be here with a sense
of ease you know if you're here
you're not there you don't have to compare yourself to
anything you just hear you you just experiencing
this and just this is actually easy
it's oh just this
one one of the practices that I took on a few years ago that I still practice diligently as the
practice of of equanimity practice and it's the the moment when I say
my suffering is dependent on my intentions and actions not what other people want
despite what I may want things are as they are may I see things just as they are
the act of saying that over and over and over and over again to myself
frees me from the requirement to explain all of my experiences
I see things just as they are that's how I want them to be or only
looking this way at them yes even the practice of meta can be distorted you
know if we do meta purposely to get rid of ill will
and be a better person and get along with our neighbors more these are all very good reasons for
doing meta however now we've set out an agenda
where these are my intentions and if my intentions don't come through then I'm there's something wrong here or the
practice is wrong or I'm doing it wrong or I'm wrong whereas if you do meta with the idea of
really wishing yourself well really wishing someone else well just just that
no further than that just wishing all beings well
there is a softening of the heart an opening of the heart
and ill will does not coexist with that we don't do it to get rid of ill will
we do it so that that's the condition that we're introducing into as our contribution In
This Moment of just an open gladdened heart
and we cultivate the Eightfold Path it turns out that it's really hard to
have a gladdened heart if you're cheating
cheating at anything if you're taking the shortcut that is
harming someone else if we're not living up to the ethics of
the of the uh precepts if we're not if we're taking what's not freely given
well it ordered this this little bit won't hurt this isn't hurting anybody
it turns out that that squeezing of Our intention of the
squeezing of our the way we are in the world shuts down the heart and burdens
it so that we can't have a gladdened heart
and we say oh I I guess I I just maybe I don't I guess I won't do that anymore
and the Very Act was saying I don't want to do that anymore opens up a space
the other day I had this ridiculous uh well not
ridiculous I had this strong experience of Shame
strong experience of Shame and it was triggered by something I watched on television it wasn't something I had done
but I recognized the feeling of Shame
you know that kind of cringing feeling and you want to go high then or you
come up with something more like bravado where you think about injustices or
why do I feel this way and all of those thoughts came and went in my mind and I
thought okay so shame has been triggered because the
people in this program were so shameful but the shame is mine
there's something that there's something that I'm not able to recall
that has been triggered by what I saw so I don't have to own the shame or
figure it out or decide what it means I can just feel that shame and let it
just be
and watch as it fades away
it was quite odd not to ask what's this about
but just let to be just let it be
and then turn the direction turn your awareness in a different direction I
also didn't have to grab the shame and roll around on the floor in it either I get to say huh
that feels really icky and I know I didn't do anything so it
isn't that I have something I have to stop doing
and so I look at something else and say there is some Delight in this world
and there is some virtue and some things that I do in this world
and I'm going to think about them I'm going to think about the other people that I know I'm going to think about
kindness and the heart is gladdened
I'm not shoving anything under the rug with that movement I'm just allowing
something else in the view the way one would if you were
you were on you were trying to meditate and you can't you can't quite settle
just can't quite settle and so you decide to think of someone
who does settle and you just sit and picture that someone
and you're inspired by that
and you settle inspired by the possibility of that
taking refuge in the possibility
I'm hoping I'm going to put my hand right on this
this is a poem by uh David bud Bill winter tonight sunset
tonight at Sunset walking on the Snowy Road my shoes crunching on the Frozen
gravel first through the woods then out into the Open Fields pass a couple of
trailers and some pickup trucks I stop and look at this guy suddenly orange red
pink blue green purple yellow gray all at once and everywhere
I Praise In This Moment at the beginning of my old age and I say a prayer of
gratitude forgetting to this evening a prayer for being here today now alive
in this life in this evening under the sky
I offer gratitude to you for being here on this evening
in this room under this guy
for your practice for your willingness to show up and be present and I wish you gladdened hearts
and the joy that follows thank you
so time is up but if anybody has any comment or question I'd be happy
to entertain it
go enjoy thank you