hello everyone welcome
and
so a few words about meditation before we start
that it can go without saying maybe that
didn't context of community that practices mindfulness
that mindfulness is important but I think it's probably often the case
that for all of us we don't appreciate how important it is
that our capacity to be aware to be attentive
is uh is not is not what we pay attention to
is important it is but how we pay attention how we are
aware that's the real key and the goal of Buddhism is found more
in the freedom of awareness where awareness is not hijacked for our
desires and our versions that awareness is not drowned out by our
self-preoccupations that our connection are in La the way
that awareness can enliven us is not lost by the focus on what we're
aware of and so to pay attention to how we're
aware and see if we can find some degree
of freedom in the how we're aware some degree of nourishment some degree
of peace some degree of of a kind of coming home
where it feels really right
to abide in Awareness to simply be aware and not be tricked into thinking that
what we're aware of is important what we're thinking about it these things are important but that
what we're thinking about what we're aware of is the solution is where the you know we
have to fix these things or have a better relationship to them or better mindfulness of them and then we can
we need to be mindful of things but how we're aware of them how we're mindful
so to assume the meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes
and to begin the meditation to do is just as simple as possible
check in with yourself how are you
you know it could be as simple as from scale 1 to 10 where 10 is really good and one is pretty
feeling pretty lousy where are you on that scale
and as you recognize how you are
are you reactive to how you are are you judging how you are
do you do you somehow are you somehow
entangled or concerned about how you are
or is there a way of just knowing how you are and let the knowing be so really simple
almost as if the part of you that can know
maybe it doesn't feel the way you are knowing just as peaceful and quiet
open and maybe not that's okay
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal normal enough
and continue as you exhale to soften and relax into your body
settling here
and as you exhale to relax the thinking mind
softening in the mind
and then becoming aware if it's there
where in your body
might your reactivity still remain
who where in the body are you emotionally activated
either in ways that are Pleasant or unpleasant challenging or comforting
and gently let that part of your body soften as you
exhale
not to make it go away
but let it allow to be there in a soft way
it's okay
taking a few moments to feel
your Global body the way your whole body
feels as a whole as your attention roams around inside
the body
and then as if it's in the center of your body
become aware of your breathing
centering yourself on the breathing so that as the inhale expands
feel like it the whole torso core breathing fills your body
feeling the global body as you breathe in letting it all return
to the center within as you exhale
as if breathing is a gentle hand
that's accompanying you with however you are without being reactive or
without being for or against anything just there
breathing with breathing through
and then notice how you're aware
is there some adjustments you can make to how you're aware so awareness is more peaceful
you might have desires but awareness doesn't you might have aversions but awareness
doesn't
you might be in all kinds of ways but awareness is like the space
within which all things occur
letting your awareness be like space or letting your awareness be peaceful
awareness knows but it doesn't react
thank you foreign
thank you
and as we come to the end of this sitting to check in with yourself again like at
the beginning and how are you
how are you on a scale of one to ten and keep it that simple
the simplest recognition of how you are
and to see how you can recognize
yourself without reactivity without judgment
that holding on or wanting a different just aware
but also becoming aware of how things have shifted for you
from the beginning of the meditation to now
is how you are changed
is there a way to know yourself here as you meditate
visit that is an act of care or respect or even love
just to know allowing yourself to be as you are but
to know it
knowing that's not impatient knowing that's not
filled with wanting just knowing
and then to turn that attention out into the world
into open awareness to this complicated world we live in
but let the knowing be simple the knowing the
knowing know itself as peaceful as calm
is open and spacious just aware
of all things the ten thousand Sorrows the ten
thousand joys
and finding a home in awareness
find your good fortune in awareness
and to extend that awareness out into the world so it can be a channel
for your good will your well-wishing
you don't have to love others to wish them well
but understand that meditation
is here to help us benefit ourselves and benefit the world
and may it be that whatever we've learned in our meditation for how to be present how to be attentive
may it be the channel for our Goodwill
may we be part of our hearts Joy
to wish people well to see them
to appreciate them
in their inherent value in their preciousness
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe male beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this fourth talk on wise listening
and uh so the fourth topic is to listen
so that it's beneficial to listen for what's
the most helpful for others the in the ancient language in terms of
speech the fourth criteria is to speak what is beneficial but the the word for this being given
for beneficial is which means also the goal and the goal is freedom the goal is to
be free of suffering classically in Buddhism and so we apply this to listening is to
listen from a place of freedom the best that we have
from a place of listening from a place where the benefits we receive through
meditation may be the best benefits we received becomes a reference point to how to listen to others
and um so like for example for me there's a few times maybe I'm having to
go someplace a little bit late but someone wants to talk to me and I can feel inside I'm impatient
and I've learned to recognize that my impatient is my own
and not in any kind of way project that onto the others like other people
and somehow think poorly of them or think the problem is with them
but rather I've learned that my impatience harms me my impatience is
unfortunate that I should lose a subtle place so I make it my practice then to return
to a place of subtleness or openness or Freedom where I'm not caught in the impatience
the byproduct of that is then I'm can listen with with out that impatience
which is a much better way to listen and so I'm listening with the highest
benefits for myself as a reference point and as I practice with that then I you
know with a little bit of luck can be available without that hindrance and
just be there listening to others so that pattern of checking in with
myself what the hindrances I have and freeing them myself of it means that I'm not trying to be
impatient act impatient well really what's happening is I'm impatient
uh really what's happening is I'm caught up in my desires or really what's happening is I'm trying to not I'm not
listening I'm caught up in needing to prove myself or defend myself or do
something and uh that gets in the way of really being listening to someone but rather
than insisting that I should listen the practice is Gil take a good look
here become free of these hindrances or at least free enough
so that it becomes I can come into the listening without it and then I'm a better listener
as a byproduct of doing this inner work I might be motivated originally to be a
better listener but I know that I should check in and work on myself so that I can be a better
listener so to listen in a way that's beneficial
to listen in a way where we're tapping into the deepest benefits that we know that's available maybe from practice or
from our spirituality or from our life this is uh part of healthy listening
Dharma dharmic listening and then to list it in such a way that
we have other people's welfare in mind as well so to listen and in a way to
so that you know we hear people out I mean for people to be heard out to receive the
gift of listening to receive someone who holds it all spaciously even if they
have a tendency to over speak and are dominating there's some wonderful Aikido
a wonderful kind of movement that just instead of being reactive to that step towards it and
open up and listen even better the very thing maybe that I sometimes don't want to do because now I'm
reinforcing their over speaking but sometimes to step forward oh and get
involved active listening and get interested and sometimes people who speak too much haven't had that
experience of people really interested them and perhaps something deeper in them
needs to be fed or needs to be met then just the words they're speaking
so the idea of what you know offering the highest benefit to others through
our listening um and now it is a wonderful reference
point for being a listener it doesn't have to be this way all the time it maybe shouldn't be this way all the time
because there's none naive and overlooking the context but this is one of the gifts that can come around this
practice is uh really becoming not only a good listener but listening in such a
way that we're attuning ourselves or or connecting ourselves to some deeper
potential of Freedom that's possible in the other person one way one formula takes is to listen
uh appreciating the other person appreciating something about them maybe
that they can't even appreciate them in themselves um appreciating their capacity for love
they're appreciating here is a tender person here's a person with life experiences that's been difficult and
they're doing the best they can given their challenges
so yesterday I read this poem the song of the open road by Walt Whitman
and he has a wonderful line I think the second line of the poem that goes something like
um I ask not for Good Fortune I am good fortune
so rather than asserting out in the world provide me with Benefits provide me with good fortune
he says I'm I am good fortune and this is the possibility of this
practice is that we're not looking outside of ourselves to be happy or to be peaceful we become
our inner peace we become an inner happiness we find it in ourselves
and it takes some responsibility for finding it here so is listening
in a way that's beneficial that has the highest welfare in mind
um can transform an individual s that we be we just feel like yes all
kinds of misconventional misfortunes can have with us it could happen to us but we are the good fortune we are the
free heart we we are the open mind
um and and that's so beneficial that why would we
allow ourselves to get carried away by impatience as I said talked about earlier or Carried Away by
reactivity or fear when we have a practice
to help us go back and find that place of Good Fortune find that place of
freedom find that place of openness and then from there listen to others
from there take care of what needs to be taken care of in the world take care of
our challenges and our difficulties but they carry our Good Fortune with us
so to listen from the place that's most beneficial in
us to have some sense of that then that's one of the
values of this meditation practice is to find some reference point
of well-being that can help us listen to that and with
that be in the world be present in the world connected to that open to it what's the
highest benefit here for me and certainly I asked this for myself
and um and and frequently enough I've been caught up in
something that seems important and and it's not the highest benefit
um I went I had my car serviced yesterday and um and you know I was a little bit
concerned about the price and the concerns with with some little bit would I be overcharged and different things
but uh I could see that why would I come with that tension and tightness to
uh and cause myself this kind of tension with those kinds of concerns
so certainly I had those thoughts in the back of my mind but I relaxed and just kind of stayed there and and appreciated
the service person that I was with and and uh and uh and just uh it was in very
nice conversation and I delighted in him and I think he's kind of started smiling and was happy as well and
and at some point he asked me um
um you know something like how are you and I said honestly I said oh I'm quite
happy because I was sitting there quite happy I'd done my work to be in that kind of place
and then I said yeah I'm quite happy um except for the you know you know I'm
not so happy about the high price of the service you know I wasn't asking for anything but that was just true you know
there's a little bit you seemed kind of high expensive and uh and he said okay I'll I'll take
100 off and um I don't know if it was I don't know how
much you want to make from that little story but uh the important point was here was
a situation where I was going to be present I was going to take care of myself in
this situation and not sacrifice my own well-being because of my fears because of my
concerns in this small situation like this I was going to take care of the
situation the best I could but I was going to care for this place of freedom and not get caught by
something that compromised it did myself so I kind of became my own good fortune
in a way that Walt Whitman talks about so to listen be present to others
from our freedom from and do the inner work that stays as close to that that's really great that's a fantastic
thing to do so um thank you
and uh so we have one more talk tomorrow and
wise listening