okay so we'll go ahead and get started I know some folks are still continuing
to join but let's go ahead since it's the top of the hour
uh this week the theme is I'm going to
call it flavors of the Dharma and I'll say a bit more about that term flavor
after the sit when we when we get started but just as a little Preamble
um Dharma teachings and Dharma practice can have
distinct flavors or emotional tones at different times like the way a poem or a
scene in a movie could have a flavor you know like it could be dark or joyous or
suspenseful but of course the difference for the Dharma is that there tend to be flavors
that support practice in particular ways and maybe part of the art of practice is
to know what tone to take when relating to experience
so each day this week we're going to take up one flavor and there will be a
couple aspects to exploring it we'll look at some sutus where the tone of the
teaching conveys that flavor because the Buddha had a variety of teaching styles to fit the circumstances
and then secondly we'll consider when in our practice it might be appropriate to
bring forth that flavor or that emotional tone and today's flavor will be very
foundational we're going to look at love or compassion it's a flavor
um but first let's meditate together let's get started on that
so settling in for to your meditation posture
and if it's comfortable to do so gently closing your eyes so that the attention
comes inward and the meditations for this week
will touch into what are called the elements in Buddhist understanding and these are
not literal substances materials but they're really actually more experiences
that we can find in the body and and even in the mind
to some degree so we'll highlight one element each day
and they might have a connection to the flavor or emotional tone that we'll be
exploring each day we could maybe imagine a connection
so again touching into the sitting posture
that you've taken perhaps feeling the contact points
where you're sitting so your seat against the chair or the cushion or if
you're lying down you're against what you're lying on maybe your legs or feet
are against the floor and so you have a sense of the contact
with where you're sitting and allowing yourself to feel into the
stability of that the groundedness
perhaps even softening into those touch points
so that you feel yourself giving over your weight to what you're sitting on
and ultimately to the Earth
it's useful at the beginning of a sip to take just a moment to
really get balanced where you're sitting so you can even shift from side to side
or forward and back just to really align
and then we can notice the way the body kind of Rises up from the stable base
as if it's buoyed upward or maybe like a sea plant off the sea floor
allowing ourselves to be drawn upward or if you're lying down you can sense the
natural straightness of the spine when you've tuned yourself into a meditative
mind I'm just softening various areas that we
may hold habitual tension softening the eyes and the eye sockets
softening the face
the jaw
softening the shoulders letting them drop maybe Imagining the
shoulder blades sliding down the back
allowing the arms and hands to relax
and down into the chest area
letting that be soft open
or if you feel tension just being okay with that
releasing what can be released in the belly in the low back
letting both of those perhaps soften on the out breath
and down into the hip joints
the groin muscles the thighs
that place that's supporting you if you're sitting up just letting that open
a bit more down into the lower legs and all the way
into the feet just inviting
some ease through this body
and now as you as you look through the body if you will
with mindfulness notice any places that feel
warm like often the core area may feel warm
the hands are warm and others not
generally areas that feel warm and also you may notice in cooler places
contrast and this quality of heat
or coolness is called the fire element
it's an experience in the body that's often there there's often a
temperature associated with parts of the body
so that just notes the presence of fire element
one of the constituents of form the material world
so you can then bring attention particularly to the heart area
maybe imagining breathing in and out of the
heart area not the literal physical heart but notice that area
energetic area of the body
and if it's a little weird to imagine breathing in and out of the front of the
chest you can imagine how the air coming into the lungs flows around the
heart area naturally lungs lungs around the heart
and scenting into whatever quality of fire element is present in the heart
maybe it's a lot maybe it's a little after seeing if you can detect that
no continuing with a little bit of imaginative practice
just imagining gently spreading the heat around the
body the fire element from the heart area using the breath
so as you breathe in perhaps feeling a gathering of the energy and on the out breath
and biting it to spread throughout the system
perhaps it's more natural on the in-breath to spread the Heat
throughout all the little tissues of the body just the natural heat we have we're
not engineering anything but just allowing it to spread through
the body as it wishes to
maybe as you feel warmth or heat touching a certain area
like if it's spreading into your legs or feet allowing it to
there to be relaxation as the heat spreads in
keep working along with that a sense of care for yourself
Just As You Are no sense that anything needs to change about how you are right now
they might call it a very basic sense of positive regard
or this being right now
we'll we'll let go of that imaginative and more directive part of the
meditation and just settle into feeling the breath in the
body relaxing my mind and opening to
receptive mindfulness
but maintaining perhaps that gentle sense of positive regard that sense of
caring through the heart area
and now just letting the breath energy spread through the body
and being receptive to experience as it comes and goes just simple mindfulness
practice
staying with the flow of experience
in the present moment
if the mind has wandered away into thought
just gently returning to the breath perhaps touching into the heart area or
the sense of warmth in the body letting the fire element be a reminder
of the present moment and softening into that
sense of warmth
foreign
foreign foreign
and in the last few minutes of this meditation
again inviting in our imagination to sense
the fire element in the body as a direct experience actually it
doesn't need imagination [Music] sensing the direct experience and then
imagining kind of spreading it throughout the body inviting it to
touching to all aspects of our being
and what would it be like to carry this sense of warmth and Flow
and a connection to our heart area out into our lives today
what would it be like to let whatever degree of warmth is there
spread out to meet other beings to meet the Earth the environment
it's not about how much there is but really how we use it
using it well
bringing some sense of warmth the softness of care
into the world
not with an agenda or a course
but simply because that's the way we are today
to the degree possible and see the result of that see how just that natural degree of heat
to whatever it is can have an impact
in a very simple way so that's an invitation to
to try out today if it's of Interest
okay so the first question is were you able
to hear the Bell I've been having some trouble sometimes with the Bell not transmitting on over
the Electronic Connection so if you didn't hear it the Bell did ring
and please let me know in the chat so that I will know what to do tomorrow
and in the meantime we'll go ahead with the talk
so this week is called flavors of the Dharma as I mentioned
novel okay thank you we'll fix that tomorrow
um this week is called flavors of the Dharma and I mentioned just briefly before the
sitting but in case you weren't here we'll be exploring how certain teachings
have a distinct emotional tone or flavor that is meant to support practice
um and the the reason I've chosen this particular lens or way of seeing it is
that there is a a precedent for it from the aesthetic culture of ancient India
um the Buddha was teaching in a cultural context that included a highly developed
aesthetic sense so he was in this environment and of course spiritual
teachings are distinct from art like poetry but still there was this context
surrounding the presentation of spiritual teachings if you will which also have an emotional tone of course
and there was a word for this it's called rasa r-a-s-a which means nectar
or Essence or taste and it it's the emotional experience that's evoked in
the listener and there was a standard set of Rosas that were evoked in art this was kind of
understood and people in the sort of high up in Indian society would have
known about these Rosas and we see them some of them reflected in the sutas
so today we have the rasa of Love or Compassion or more generally care and
all of these in a spiritual sense of course in the regular Arts they would include romantic love or other things
like that but within the sutas we do see a flavor of care in a spiritual sense in
a way that would support or practice or path toward Liberation
and so um you know with each of these flavors we'll look at sutas that are examples of it and we'll consider when
and how that flavor is useful in our practice so I hope that will be of of Interest this week
so this Flavor of Love or care it really underlies and supports Dharma practice
at a base level there's a suta about the king of kosova
whose name was King vicinity and he was a follower of the Buddha a devoted
follower but not a great meditator very sincere nonetheless
and in this teaching he is talking to his Queen whose name was Queen Malika
and he says to her my dear Queen is there anyone more dear
to you than yourself and apparently he was hoping that she
would say why yes you are more dear to me than myself
but that's not what she says actually what she says is there's no one great
king more dear to me than myself kind of straightforward and then she
asks him the same thing and says well well King is there anyone more dear to you than yourself
and given how the conversation has go gone up to that point he has to reply
and kind well no actually there is no one more dear to me than myself
and he's a little um taken by this conversation and so he
goes to the Buddha and he says everything that happened in that conversation and the Buddha excuses it
as an opportunity to offer an ethical message of care you know so the Buddha
approves of what the queen said and he says having traversed all quarters with
the mind one finds none anywhere dearer than oneself
likewise each person holds himself most dear or herself most dear hence one who
loves herself should not harm others so we see that this sense of you know
being dear to ourself is actually in this suit up pointed to as the basis for
caring for others so at a base level we are generally dear to
ourselves we care about ourselves in some way and this is normal and is in
fact the basis for wholesome conduct so the Buddha is praising this the
Queen's assertion of self-love um
in another suta with this same King vicinity the king notes that people who engage in
unwholesome actions treat themselves as a foe even if they say they are holding
themselves dear and also people who engage in wholesome
actions treat themselves as dear even if they say they regard themselves as a foe
and the Buddha again agrees with him so
so our actions you know if we are
behaving poorly out in the world we're lying or we're manipulating people or
we're being unkind in some way even if we say we're doing it because we care about ourselves we're standing up for
ourselves we're I don't take care of myself who will we're treating ourselves as a foe
because we're engaging in these harmful actions that actually have an impact on us even if we think we're helping
ourselves and people who attempt to live ethically who try to be kind who don't lie or
steal or manipulate um sometimes people like that will say
that they're unhappy with themselves and um you know that they don't love
themselves so much but these very actions of trying to care wanting to care are good for us they help us at
some level so we could get in better alignment actually by also loving ourselves also being kind to ourselves
so we see that the Buddha is quite clear that ethics and positive self-regard overlap
ethical conduct is the basis of bateful path and so is care for ourselves and
others there's another suta that says this in a
nice way there's a story of a newly ordained Monk who keeps having
difficulty following the monastic rules because there's so many of them right but the other monks so he's always kind
of making mistakes and looking awkward the other monks are you know he didn't
do that right but they sense that he is proceeding from deep love and faith in
the Buddha you know he's ordained out of really deep faith and so you know when
they think about it they decide not to discipline him very much because it might dampen his faith and love and they
don't that would be more harmful for him so they're they're kind to him and
eventually he grows into being able to manage the monastic life and and live up
to all the rules that there are so we have this sense again that deep
love and faith as a basis for practice really help things to unfold well
if we look across the suit as [Music] probably the case that the Buddha rarely
displayed what we would conventionally consider to be love here in the west
many of his teachings were a little analytical or a
little tough sometimes to wake people up a little bit but many of his teachings
you know really were profoundly caring he met people right where they were
using language that they could understand that in and of itself is an
act of care and love and compassion you know for example there's a story of
I think many of you know the story of Kisa gotami who was a a woman who whose
child had died and you know she she wasn't really a practitioner at that
time but and she was so distraught that her son had died that she was actually carrying him around while he was dead
and trying to get somebody to to help her and people were turning away and she finally
found the Buddha a little bit when she was a little bit crazed and he said to her okay okay
um I can help you so she's oh thank goodness and he says go to a
house uh find a mustard seed from some household where no one has died and
bring me that Mustard Seed and so she sets off to do this task right
and you know Mustard Seed is hardly worth anything everybody would be willing to give her one but she goes
from house to house and of course there isn't any household where no one has died so she learns in that way
that her situation although difficult is just real it's normal that's how it is
and that that was so much more profound of a way of learning it than anything
else you know that could have been offered it could have been told to her or explained to her or
um anything like that so this is a way where the Buddha was being profoundly carrying although you know somewhat uh
strong tough and she comes back and understands and is willing to bury her
son and she becomes a nun and becomes awakened as these stories go
so there are many many examples of love and compassion and Care in the Buddhist
teachings it's threaded all throughout and it also comes forth explicitly in some of the cases like the ones that
we've explored today so you know when is it appropriate to use this flavor or Savor maybe we could
say rasa is sometimes called Savor also Savor of Love or Compassion or care
I mean there are so many right but we could just name a few which is you know we need to give ourselves
we need to give ourselves time so we need to just do the practice
without seeking results or achievements you know it's it can sometimes seem
a little distant you know why am I sitting here trying to be with the breath I really need to think about this
problem that I have I have to work on this relationship that's what keeps
coming to mind but if we just stay with the breath stay with the body stay with the
mindfulness practice that we're doing uh it has a way of affecting us more
profoundly than we realize you know like going to house from house to house asking about a mustard seed
that was so much more effective than say grief counseling if you will
um you know when that instruction was given by the Buddha and she was willing to do it so you know there's this this doing of
the practice just to give ourselves time to unfold to let it let it do its work
that is profoundly loving and of course at moment when there's a
lot of duka we can bring self-compassion directly to our situation
um sometimes that might look like self-care in some way or or maybe just seeing clearly that what is what is
happening is the most loving thing that we can do we may not need to bring in ideas about
our story and other things but to see directly and feel feel how it is yeah
it's really hard right now without a story it's just this is it deeply compassionate
and also you know love and care is the indirect basis for so much of cushion
practice there are so many cases where um in kind of in a standard sequence of
sitting down to get ready to meditate some of the sutures will say that the
practitioner sits down has an upright posture establishes compassion for all
beings and then brings mindfulness to the fore and begins to meditate so we
can do this also is have a sense that we're meditating out of compassion for ourselves and all others
so I really see this as a foundation for so much of what we do it helps so much unfold when we have a basis of love or
care and I'm careful to use those General words so that we can find our own way of meeting that
today in the United States it's a holiday it's Juneteenth which celebrates
or commemorates the emancipation of African-American slaves in 1865.
and so maybe it's appropriate that we talk today about ethics and love and
compassion and care as a basis for ourselves our
life our relationships and indeed our whole society
so tomorrow we'll be on to a different flavor a different rasa five of them
this week and I hope you'll enjoy this tour of some of our some of the emotional tones
that we see in the in the Buddhist teachings will be well