so warm greetings on this Monday morning
and welcome and
to introduce the
meditation if uh there were Anthropologist from Mars who came to
this earth of ours to study the people here and the question was what are they
committed to what is it they really like to do and there are times that and places
where they would say people are committed to
anger hostility they really like to be hostile and some of them are hostile
towards others some some of them are hostile to
themselves but then they would find that there are some people who are committed
to being not hostile
nonharming and that there's a remarkable difference between the
two one seems to be always tense the other seems to be calm
the others first doesn't seem to be oriented towards helping
others except for those maybe who are closest to them and the other seems to be oriented
towards helping others when they meditate the one
dedicated towards hostility uh finds that sometimes even
the meditation strengthens the hostility
the one dedicated to nonhostility to non-harming seems to be able to be
resilient to be to manage to be calm in the midst of the storms of
life so in Dharma practice Dharma in meditation and
Buddhism the reliable commitment that uh or
love that uh the basis of doing medit ation practice maybe the basis of Buddhism in
general is non-harming nonhostility and this is considered to be universally
applicable if you want to have a commitment that's deeper than just a commitment to mindfulness deeper than
commitment to meditation it's a commitment to non-harming to nonhostility
and um and so to meditate with that kind of commitment to have that be the
foundation for meditation the foundation that's maybe
more provides much more benefit to us than having mindfulness or awareness be
the foundation unless the two are considered
Inseparable and um so in this meditation that we do
today if you would like see if you can have it be a
commitment to nonhostility to non-harming and some of that will be
towards anybody you think about where you meditate and some of it will be towards
yourself to What's Happening Here you might still have impulses to hostility
to anger to criticism to
irritation to aversion to what's happening those things might still
happen but don't be committed to them don't believe in their value during the
for the purpose of meditation instead believe in the value of meeting it with awareness that's
non-hostile meeting it with non-harming it doesn't condone it it's
not an acceptance of it it's a peaceful nonparticipation in it letting it be
letting it the Flames of anger the Flames of hostility um blow themselves out because
they're not being fed so a constant coming back to
nonhostility non-harming and uh maybe with every
breath so to assume a meditation
posture and perhaps if it's possible a posture
that manifests a degree of confidence kind of a confident
presence lowering the Gaze if it's comfortable to to close
your
eyes and as if you're holding a little wounded bird
that you don't want to harm in any kind of way very gently holding it CED in your
hands kind of a gentleness than which you would maybe hold the
baby gently take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe 2/3
full and gently relax on the
exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal and continue with a very light
touch nonassertive touch as you
exhale relax different parts of your
body
the attitude of nonhostility non-harming has no
weight has no force in it it's gentle
light but like the air it pervades can pervade
everything
each Act of relaxing in the body is a
fusion of
nonharming
and then settling into the experience of the body
breathing
with every breath
remembering the possibility of nonharming non
aversion towards whatever
arises a non aversion which is a nonp
participation with whatever is harmful or hostile or
aversive
for
e
whatever is [Music] known through
mindfulness let it be known
peacefully let it be known with an attitude of non-harming
anything with the care and the gentleness with which you
might hold a newborn baby softly
lightly everything that you know let it be known with non
aversion
for
e
to meditate with an attitude of nonharming
non aversion means that whatever we
know whatever is known Here and Now is
safe safe from our hostility our
aversion
and perhaps whatever is known in feeling
safe it can
relax
e
for
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to consider whether this emphasis on
non-harming touched anything important inside of
you is there a value in you
within a feeling a knowing a
wisdom regarding
non-harming and to now to imagine that that wisdom that
knowing that attitude can radiate from you spread
from you out into the world as a
gentle suffusion of Peace of
kindness of nonharming so that others might get a
taste of the power of non aversion
nonviolence of
Peace may all beings live without experiencing
hostility may all beings be free of
harm may all beings live in
peace may all beings be freed from all
forces of harm and suffering may they be
free
and may our commitment to this peace help support peace wide far and
[Music]
wide
thank
you
so good day on this Monday and the topic for this week is to
continue with um what's usually called the 10 protectors the 10 supports
supporting things that the 10 helps helping help 10
helpers and um today's uh protector is love of the Dharma Dharma
love and um but then uh Dharma what does that
mean here and I'd like to propose that the essential meaning of Dharma more
than the teachings of the Buddha more than anything else is
nonharming and so a love of non-harming that's the
protector and um and it seems uh
wonderful coincidence that uh to emphasize this on
the day that the United States we celebrated it as indigenous people day and uh people who have suffered
hundreds of years of harm by the European colonialists who came and
settlers who came and uh sometimes uh committed tremendous genocide even right
here in California and um the uh and also uh the
Monday after this weekend were the horrendous violence in um Palestine and
Israel and the Gaza Strip the and
um and we have so much experience as human beings with the endless cycles of
violence and the endless cycles of hate when two people hate each
other uh then the only solution is to kill each
other the cycles of hate just escalate and then it just continues on
and on the cycles of this going on and I think the 60 years of more now 70 years
800 years of violence in Palestine uh has shown the cycles that
violence doesn't provide a solution and the horrendous damage here
in the to the Native Americans in United States and
Canada much of uh Latin America um has also showed how much harm
can be done that gets Contin for Generations after the big harm has been
caused there has to be another way and the way that the Buddha taught
is non-harming a radical commitment to non-harming so the love of the Dharma is
not a love of the teachings that that's possible it's not a love of the practice
but love of the very Foundation of what the teachings and the practice is about
and that is a life of non-harming and um the four noble truths
are all about not harming uh where the word for harm is Dua or usually
translated into English as suffering and in the for Noble Truth it usually applied to
oneself that uh we're looking at suffering within ourselves the causes of
suffering that we have within ourselves and the ending of that we could say the harm we experience from
ourselves and the ending of causing that harm and um U but also the four noble
truths can be equally there's no pronouns in the way the four noble truths are taught so they apply equally
to the world around us uh to uh understand the suffering the causes and
to meet it with an attitude a way a way of life which is non-harm a life of
non-harming that's you know primarily represented by living the eighth full path and
non-harming is embedded in the whole eful path uh
Enterprise and so the love of the Dharma and a k dama Kama and uh in the
description of it it's talks about um one of the protectors is loving the
Dharma um having um uh uh having affect
affectionate conversations I love this idea affectionate conversations with others
right after loving loving the Dharma and being inspired by the practice and the way of
life here the word for practice is Abid uh dma Dharma and the and the um
way of life is via which for the monastics is the life of
restraint but for the non- monastics the life of restraining from uh
harming and so this um and if we want to have a
love uh which is um reliable Universal
profound the love of non-harming it doesn't mean naive
nonviolence it means that uh that it doesn't mean that we are being hostile to our own
Tendencies to hostility and hate but we're not we're not committing ourselves to the impulses of hate and hostility
we're not imp committing ourselves to the impulse of violence but rather um we allow those to
surface we see them clearly and we see them with non-harming we see them with
non particip ation we see them uh without believing them or without
believing we have to act on them it's a hard belief to come by because uh
sometimes um uh you know it seems like we have to harm others in order to protect
ourselves the Buddha said something similar for monastics he said that a
monastic um is allowed to strike out against an attacker for the purposes of
escaping provided that the monastic has um has Good Will has
meta so it's not just only have you know just just sit there quietly and have
non-harming uh there is a time and place to act but how that act is done is
mostly not to harm other people but for the for the purposes of avoiding getting
hurt exactly how that applies in all kinds of situations in life is as you
know that's the the um the huge question but um uh non-harming is not naive it's
not just allowing other people to roll over us but uh it's profound to uh to
live a life of non-harming there are many people in this world who have never experience
safety and to feel that someone is really safe for them and this part of the value of monastic life is that it's
a public life that kind of gives the impression to people who see monastics that this is someone who's not going to
harm and um is not going to live with aggression and anger and hostility and
so there's tends to be a relaxing around monastics uh that uh they can walk in
all kinds of circumstances in life and people receive them because uh they
clearly represent a very radically different way of living than many people have
experienced but uh um but what I want to emphasize today is the love part that uh
there can be a delight and inspiration an affection for uh the
Dharma for practice that um that uh um can be a
great love the um it can be for some people who like to an morphies these
things can be our beloved can be something that we really take up and one of the interesting ideas
about uh the Beloved the the loving the Dharma some people will love the Dharma
more than anyone else and uh and then our partners might get upset like what I'm second best to
the Dharma the um the then you might explain to them it works this way that uh with a
with having the Dharma at the center there's uh love of the
Dharma um our ability to love others increases so yes they're kind of second
maybe to uh to your commitment to the Dharma to practice to
non-harming but um but if you didn't have the Dharma your love for them would not be as clear or Pure or open or rich
or forgiving or something and uh so they get more
love if you they allow you to love the Dharma even more and so everyone
benefits and uh in the end I don't think that it makes that you know there's no
conflict and um but this ability to have this heartfelt warmth and and uh and
affection uh for something that's really profound and have it be the most
reliable form of love and affection because it's as I keep saying
maybe it's a universal nonharming that's the essence that's what the Dharma is and everything
else about the Dharma the the all the different teachings are attempts to kind of expand on that basic premise or to
find uh to really study how this applies or how this is supported in all kinds of
different ways not hard harming ourselves not not harming others and to
be a liberated person to be an enlightened person means uh it's an
ethical transformation it means becoming a person who is incapable of intentionally
wanting to harm anybody else a someone who's fully awakened is incapable of
killing incapable of stealing and so
the incapable of wanting to cause harm so if you're committed to feel like you
need to be committed to the possibility of harming others then maybe the Dharma
is not going to be so good for you because if you really take it all the way um you're going to be incapable of
doing that but on the way there there is a love of the Dharma the love of
non-harming and even if um it's even if you decide that it's necessary to engage
in in something that's harmful and violence as a form of self- protection
or something um uh don't let that um
diminish the possibility of really loving non-harming and in this teaching uh the
love of the Dharma is a protector so it protects you from the
forces of harm from within yourself and from others living a life of Peace
living a peaceful life of not harming people tend and the operating word is tend tend to relate to us very
differently than if we walk around angry and I've known people who are very
aversive who just feel that everyone else is just mean all the time without
them realizing that people are kind of challenged and maybe aversive to them
because of the aversive way in which they show up and so it's a self fulfilling uh kind of prediction people
are mean so I show up being mean and then of course they're mean back if we show up non-harming loving
caring attentive to others um they respond in a different way to
us so um so to uh love the our um as a way of
being safe making ourselves safe and as a way of protecting others
from ourselves and as a way of protecting our
Dharma practice it's difficult to remember to practice it's difficult to be in to stay
inspired in the Dharma and this way of life but to to keep coming back to that
inspiration maybe from these affectionate conversations we can have about the Dharma this is a way of
keeping the momentum the inspiration the motivation here to really uh
refine uh the tremendous value
and wisdom of living a life a sophisticated life of non-harming not a naive
life nonharming loving that so
um so it makes me very happy
to to consider this wonderful idea of loving the Dharma of living a life of
love and a love that I hope is contagious and that spreads uh peaceful
away throughout this world that needs it desperately because
violence I hope the violence soon enough is going to be seen as a
completely counterproductive to the welfare and happiness of
everyone thank you