greetings everyone greetings good morning good afternoon good evening
to all of you from all the places in the world that you're joining from this
beautiful Sangha my name is Nikki mergafori I'm joining you from Mountain View California on
seated olonieland and delighted to be with you this week supporting Gil as uh
as he's away this week traveling so
[Music] um so so for the theme for this week
um I'd like to continue with the theme of compassion I know that uh Gail spoke
about the seven factors of compassion last weekend there was so much to to explore we're not done in one week or
one month or even one year exploring this practice of compassion I continue to to to learn and explore it it's a
lifetime or maybe multiple lifetimes practice so we'll explore it
um this week in in different ways from different dimensions or different ways to to look at it and and um
and perhaps slice the pie or Cut the Cake from different layers looking at
that compassion for ourselves for others what what supports it what blocks it
um in a practical way in a very practical um useful way
um news you can use and of course all of Dharma is is applicable to our daily
lives anyway without without further Ado let's let's
sit together let's practice together I'd like to invite you to come to your
seat come to your body ah and if it's comfortable for you
Maybe take a couple of deep diaphragmatic breaths into the
belly or rather let the belly breathe in the air
hold for a few seconds and release with a sound if you like ah
the way to arrive become centered
maybe a couple more in your own time
only for a few seconds letting go high
and now letting the breath be natural however it is
shallower deep
in a few deep breaths can help us physiologically
to reorient as a bridge from activity
and perhaps a sense of hyper drive more sense of calm
returning reorienting
the mind is particularly busy right now
enacting with the entirety of the breath
the pause and the out breath
and let us turn
through the breath to the sensations of the breath within
the body within the framework of the body
not breath as a concept but a felt sense
Within this body that senses feels aches
earning our awareness or knowing
intertwined with kindness
towards this body
not so much in the way of whipping it to shade to sit and concentrate on this practice
but making kindness compassion the object of our
practice towards this body the parts of this body
softening relaxing
if there is any discomfort
or a challenge in the body areas of tightness
achiness
earning turning to these areas holding this area of the body
with our awareness with our spacious knowing intertwined with kindness
the same way that
a loving mother holds a newborn tenderly
especially if the newborn is crying
in some discomfort
patiently patiently holding
loving
rocking this and tender precious life
same attitude
can we hold this body especially if they're areas of
challenge discomfort
unease
and we tune into compassion for this body
In This Moment In Time in general
this body that aches sometimes get sick agents
if there's any challenge right now
coning into the patience and compassion and the Delight
there is Delight a quiet Joy
in being patiently loving
there is a source of strength and uprightness
courage
in turning towards what hurts
with love
practicing to patiently hold
lovingly hold physical discomfort
is training for being able to hold
and be kind with mental emotional challenges
it's the same process
the same relaxed
spacious body there is any emotional challenge
disappointment judgment
pain in this moment in time can we too
breathe with it
patiently be with it with the same stance of loving mother holding a tender
newborn
same gesture of the heart
not trying to rush through it but patient
loving stable
it's okay sweetheart it's okay
taking time to hold disappointments challenges not to ruminate let go of the
story let go of the story not helpful at all
but simply holding kindness
and patience
the tenderness whether physical or emotional
and notice the wholesomeness the goodness
of turning towards instead of pushing away um
breathing with
it's okay sweetheart it's okay
following yourself kindly
may I have ease with this disappointment sorrow pain
may I have ease and Peace and Freedom
of heart
with this challenge
may I meet this difficulty with kindness
as much as possible
as we begin to close this meditation
can we note the sense of uprightness and goodness
wholesomeness
there is in meeting what's difficult with kindness turning
towards with patience kindness instead of pushing it away or
judging it or berating ourselves or ruminating
there is a wholesomeness and just meaning
it's difficult with kindness
and that brightness a quiet strength
as we bring this meditation to our clothes
appreciating that we showed up if there are any judgments arising for
how it was or wasn't can we meet that Dagger of self-judgment
with kindness
appreciating ourselves
and our beautiful Sangha for showing up and planting seeds of
kindness compassion towards ourselves
and the world compassion starts with ourselves
may we be of service
maybe serve compassionately
may we be kind to this being who's us to all those whose Lies We Touch
directly and indirectly may all beings everywhere
be free have ease
with their challenges with their suffering
may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you friends thank you for your practice
and if you like if you feel moved you are welcome to put a word
but what is coming up for you in this moment so I take a moment to transition the recordings
greetings everyone lovely to be with you
this week practicing together around the theme of compassion continuing the theme
and as we just did a meditation together and I asked
you to if you wanted to put a word or a phrase in chat about
what's coming up for you and the theme of our practice of course was compassion for the body for our own Hearts starting
with the self a few words tears beautiful and helpful
gratitude peace compassion for my form uh for myself to myself for restlessness
yes is tranquil appreciation courageous
vulnerability just reading a few words thank you for bringing those
into the space I needed that compassion this morning yeah
um steadfast kindness beautiful so many beautiful nuggets we're bringing back in
to support each other
some compassion for this tired body yeah
I missed a disappointment beautiful thank you all thank you for being in
there and really engaging with this practice just so beautiful I am so
touched by this beautiful International Sangha ah engaging and supporting each
other in this way in this way
so hmm I feel nourished In This Moment by
both our practice as I'm in there leading you
um from these states myself and it is nourishing it's really a beautiful
um strength of the heart to be with to be
with challenges instead of rushing through them and it takes time it takes patience
no compassion so much we can say about this and so much we can explore so what
I like to turn into today is um
is compassion for self -compassion self-compassion as the basis
for compassion to others compassion to to the world etc etc
and maybe I'd like to take a step back first and uh
[Music] um offer a definition maybe a couple of
definitions of compassion just so that we're on the same page we we have a
sense of what compassion is and many of you have been practicing practicing for a long time and yet it helps to
reconnect with with okay what are we talking about so it's not a fuzzy fuzzy
you know compassion which is you know panty about this word
so so in the taravada tradition
kindness or meta is the primaries the first practice of
the heart kindness loving kindness Good Will and basically what kindness or
Goodwill is is um just the kindness of the heart say when you are walking around and you
smile to a neighbor or or just a very simple sense of good will just sensible
kindness It's not complicated we all have it readily access it many many times a day
when you see someone you care about oh there's just a sense of simple care so
good will foreign t a or translate as kindness loving
kindness love Good Will so many nuances
it's basically kindness of the heart that meets a being who is in a neutral
State neither suffering nor happy just kind of like kindness of the heart okay
now if you take the same kind and the same meta and it meets
suffering it meets the suffering either your own suffering or suffering of someone else some other being that meta
when it meets suffering it holds suffering becomes compassion
so compassion is love meta plus suffering
in other words it's also been said that compassion is the love child
of love and suffering so there needs to be a challenge so a
some kind of pain suffering difficulty and it's met and it is met with kindness
okay so that is one way to consider meta
to consider compassion in Pali karuna and of course just to just to
[Music] um um give you the if you have not heard this before if
the same kindness meta meets joy in the world someone who's very happy or your
own Joy then it gets expressed as as mudita vicarious joy joy for the joy of
others or also if it's for ourselves it gets expressed as gratitude which is the third Brahma vihara the third practice
of the heart mitta being the first one meta karuna being the second
[Music] um being the third and the fourth one being
equanimity Brahma vihara is being the practices of the heart the the Heavenly abodes
practices and many of you in in the have practiced this already and if you've
been coming to the happy hour in the evening uh you you've practiced with
various dimensions of these practices so so compassion is needing needing
suffering needing suffering with with uh with kindness
foreign s that are required for compassion we
need to have an awareness of suffering we need to know we need to turn know
that this is hard this is painful and really that first cognitive knowing that
suffering is happening is the most important aspect because
often we don't rock that oh
this is suffering this is pain this is Disappointment this hurts that first
ouch that ouch is the most important is really the most
important step first how many times have you been yourself suffering having a challenge
and and just bulldozing through it I know for me
um many of you know that I've had a chronic illness for many years and and at the beginning when I was just trying to get
my head around it I would be tired and and aching and I wouldn't rock it I wouldn't crack that actually I'm not
feeling well I'd be like okay come on let's get going you've got work to do you've got emails like come on it's
going like there would be judgmenting it took a while to realize oh sweetheart wow you are tired you are in pain this
is hard ouch this is hard so that first recognition allowed and a wise response
which was kindness patience the appropriate response to come in but without that acknowledgment also with
towards others too like ah they're just being fussy or they're just being this or relabel it with very sometimes unkind
we we miss that oh this person is struggling this person is having a hard time
um so that that cognitive is taking a pause uh to to have that cognitive awareness
is very important and and often if we are rushing through life if we feel
stressed ourselves if we if we are internally stressed externally stressed
and not taking a moment to pause and and realize and that pause as you've been
practicing you realize that that pause becomes more and more available the
longer we practice and yet it is important to have this in the background of our minds
to take a pause or what is happening how am I perceiving this situation is it
really what it is or am I perceiving it through a through my eyes of rushing rushing
um about and compassion for self kindness for
self really is the basis for kindness and compassion for others it's really
the starting point is the starting point we can't fill other people's cups if we
haven't failed Our Own Cup first we have to fill our own cup and self-compassion
is not selfish it's not [Music] um
self-aggrandizing it's not enabling and in fact there are there are research
studies that suggest that when we are self-compassionate we are um
we take more responsibility for our actions not less we don't become
oh enabling like oh whatever but actually we take more responsibility maybe I'll just take one minute to share
one of these studies with you and um many studies but one of them is the work
of Mark Leary and colleagues that and they found that when a participants were
instructed to be self-compassionate when thinking about a past mistake
humiliation or failure they were more likely to accept personal responsibility
for what happened instead of blaming outside things outside or events outside
and that makes sense right you know when we have a sense of kindness for ourselves we can accept our own failings
like oh sweetheart yes that was unskillful yeah you screwed up it's okay I still love you it's okay we'll do
better next time you see it's more available whereas if we don't have that if we have self-judgment like then then
we don't have the capacity to it to acknowledge that we screwed up it's like oh no it wasn't me no no it was their
fault we we point finger everywhere because there's no capacity because if we we ex we acknowledge that we screwed
up ooh ouch they're going to be so many daggers we're gonna and they're gonna be so many daggers so so self-compassion
allows us to actually take more responsibility for our actions
in the world and it's the basis for or compassion towards others so so
um in this brief time we talked about some definition a perhaps a one
definition of compassion there is more we talked about the importance of knowing of that ouch of acknowledging of
awareness of of of of suffering with this physical emotional internal
external and self-compassion really being the basis uh before compassion for
others there is there's a lot more to explore and I'm delighted that we have the rest of this week to to practice
together so thank you so much dear ones may you be compassionate to yourself the
rest of the day May you take time pause if there is an ouch physical emotional
disappointments to just to just acknowledge maybe just with a hand on your heart or just saying ouch to to
practice with this for the rest of the day thank you so much be well and looking
forward to being with you tomorrow