so hi everyone hello and welcome to happy hour lovely to see you to be with you in this
moment in time whatever your time zone might be so for the theme for today I'd like to
invite us to explore um befriending our mind befriending our mind and
and when I say our mind it's a mind Dash heart
it's um you know befriending ourselves befriending our mind befriending our
mind heart the word chitta from Pali we often translate it just to mind but it's
really mind heart to befriend ourselves this practice of befriending ourselves
and in some ways we can think of
this practice as training ourselves in befriending and
befriending our minds befriending ourselves befriending others it's a practice of befriending and especially
when we bring the practice of insight or vipassana which is mindfulness
is a way of seeing seeing our thoughts seeing or what's arising in our mind in
our body in our heart and befriending befriending
so the whole of this practice perhaps could be summarized as befriending our
minds befriending our hearts befriending ourselves and others um
and in order to befriend in order to notice what's happening there needs to
be at first some stability in our attention in our awareness there
needs to be some stability to even know to even notice what is
going on to notice if there are thoughts that are
not helpful to notice if there are thoughts that are
downright judgmental and berating
and don't believe them instead of just believing them and going with them
so there's some stability in our awareness that is needed in order
to befriend in order to have enough wisdom enough
know how but oh yeah this is happening this is not really helpful
so with that the invitation for tonight's prac today's practice whatever
your time zone is is to start with um building with start with stabilizing
with the breath in the body the breath in the framework
of the body and then turning opening to this process
of befriending befriending ourselves befriending what it rises so that's what
we'll be doing so with that let's uh
let's begin let's arriving if you need to move or
shift so that you are comfortable
arriving in this moment in time arriving
arriving in this party
not letting there be sensitive presence stability with the breath
awareness connecting with just this in-breath
intending to be with this in-breath the entirety of Libra
and then intending to know to feel feel the entirety of
this out breath then reconnecting again with the renewed
intention through this ingra feel the whole thing
connect with the intention to fear the entire out breath
retraining retraining our minds to pay attention
it doesn't take so much effort
we will notice if we gently reconnect with this intention
for just this in-breath it's a light reconnection steady but
light
steady but light reconnection with intention
okay
reconnecting gently With Our intention to feel the entire in-breath the entire
out breath at the beginning of each
not heavy doesn't have to last very long this intention
it's gentle a persistent
foreign
if we notice that the mind is resting on a thought or a memory it's okay
let there be no judgment no berating but gladness
for the moment of awareness celebrating delighting the moment of
reconnecting with intention you have a choice you can berate yourself you've been gone where you can
delight at your path equal choose what's helpful
just the same breath Justice our breath
foreign
calming nourishing knowing it
as if it's a friend a breath as a friend
foreign
our awareness or attention
with knowing the breath the feeling of the breath in the body
feeling this in-breath feeling this out breath the entirety of it
let this fear of awareness become a little wider including the body
including sounds not the sensations of the breath still
be the anchor
but let the sphere of awareness be wider more spacious
including thoughts thoughts can arise and pass not to be entangled in them
but to recognize them and can we be friendly can we be friendly
towards sounds towards Sensations in the body
towards thoughts befriending our mind and heart and befriending being friendly doesn't
mean that we entertain them indulge in them but it means that if
they are not supportive and entanglement and thinking while
meditating is not supportive we release
we don't believe them if there are doubts you can do this
you're confused or you're bad or whatever judgment it might be
thoughts of the past and future thank you thoughts you're trying to be
supportive and helpful to protect me it can release you can let go it's okay
it's really okay dear thought the way you would relate to a friend
befriending our thoughts befriending our mind befriending our body our heart
so again let the breath in the body be the anger
it's fear of friendly awareness be wider
thank you
sitting studying the awareness
with the breath
the wide sphere of friendliness with whatever arises
thank you
our heart relax get our heart relax
into friendliness for ourselves
Good Will kindness and compassion if needed
if it's hard right now to soften
solve it into friendliness care
thank you
foreign
what needs to be held what needs to be held with friendliness with kindness
with compassion in this sphere of awareness right now
maybe just an acknowledgment that this is hard
befriending our mind befriending ourselves
and as we bring this sit to a close together
consider what was one way that you explored befriending your mind
in this practice
maybe it was not believing judgmental thought not getting entangled maybe having more
kindness compassion for yourself maybe trying to steady
your awareness with the breath or something else
acknowledging appreciating your own goodness your own wholeheartedness in
this practice in this exploration
together sharing this goodness the planting of these seeds
not just to ourselves for our own Awakening for our own well-being but to
all beings everywhere may my goodness may my
cultivation and friendliness stability may you serve
be of service in ways I can't fathom all beings everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings be free including myself
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so the theme we explored together was the theme of befriending befriending
our minds befriending our minds our hearts ourselves
and first we established some stability of the mind
of attention with the breath in the body and I invited you to try to
connect with your intention at the beginning of each in-breath beginning of
each out breath because that can be very helpful helpful approach to steady the attention steady
the awareness especially if you find your minds going every which way that to reconnection with intention can be
helpful and then we opened the sphere of
awareness to kindness Goodwill friendliness relaxing into it
wherever it was needed the thought space heart space body space
so as we turn the invitation as we turn to practicing
in small groups and exploring the Dharma together the invitation is at the end I asked you
what was one way what was one way that you [Music] um
explored what was one way where you befriended was helpful today
to befriend your mind one way so
if you'd like when we come into into small groups together again showing up
the first thing is really showing up with befriending befriending yourself befriending befriending each other
befriending yourself befriending each other the space of friendliness space of
kindness maybe you don't say anything maybe you just show up with silence but sense of friendliness
foreign [Music] comes to speak if you want to say
something about your practice what you discovered today about one way to
befriend your mind one way to befriend your mind you're welcome to share that one nugget and then the next person and
then the next person and please feel free to share from your own experience but not asking questions not
directing the conversation just just show up either with silence or what you
want to share just a nugget make sure everybody has the chance to speak it will come to you again if you share one
nugget so you'll go around and round a few times and let's go in alphabetical order
according to first name and again be kind befriending your mind and if your
mind in the middle of talking says you're talking too much okay thank you
um be kind to yourself in real time and be kind to each other in real time
so with that I'm going to uh create the
breakout rooms it'll take me a quick moment okay and
um again be kind to yourself be kind to one another
and here we go
okay the rooms are all closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
we have some time for Reflections what did you discover from the practice
um your reflection at the end of the guided meditation from discussing with one
another if you haven't spoken in the group you're welcome to raise your hand please uh your Zoom hand if you're
you're physical hand I may not see there are many of you um but um and and you're also welcome to
type in chat either to everyone or just to me and if it's just to me private privately your reflection I will read
the reflection but not your name if that's what you prefer so
why did you discover befriending your mind so many tools
bill says when my mind wandered my response was to be amused rather than
annoyed yay oh that is so much more skillful that is so great Bill humor is
so it's terrific I see the hearts showing up in Zoom this is so great so
happy for you build it this is a transformation really this is a huge transformation not to be annoyed but to
be amused okay here here goes this mind and not giving it so much power the
um that not getting not giving being annoyed this aversion being you know it
is a type of evolution not giving it power and the mindset okay being amused
it's much easier to actually steady it so much easier to study when we don't
get annoyed we get amused delighted for your practice build this is exciting great I see Fred and Barbara
hi Nikki thank you hi um I just found your suggestion to
focus on the positive to to note that it's that I'm happy to return to the
breath I found that really helpful and and as I was saying in our smaller group
maybe it's just because I eliminated by half or more all the
well by 100 I guess if I just focused on glad to be here
um all of that muted not quite articulated articulated
negative impulse around oh I've drifted off again you know and I mean how many
times can that negative pulse be there in the course of 30 minutes just uh so
much and to to then experience the positive um was really booing and I was able to
more happily be present in in the very simple breath
so thank you thank you Fred I am dancing with joy as you're sharing your Insight
um I'm truly dancing with joy um this is a significant Insight what
you just discovered in your own practice and and
um it's it's it's easy to lean into it's it's not it's natural it's natural
unfortunately right as as humans for us to lean into ah I wondered again oh mine
wandered again oh you know that ah that ouch instead of well we have a choice we can lean into that or we can we can lean
into yay wow I'm aware I I'm awake I'm gonna learn this moment you know it's
it's 50 50 just as you pointed out right it's 50 50 so and when we lean into the
then it just kind of sags the energy and I can't do this but when we lean into the celebration it it completely shifts
our practice it just completely shifts so so I'm both dancing with joy for you
and for you having articulated it so powerfully for the community
um that that yes when we lean into that so thank you Fred that's just lovely yay
thanks
so and send me a note assume you know that your suggestion is practiced by
therapists we use a form of therapy called cognitive emotional therapy I'm
not surprised Claire there are so many practices from the cognitive emotional
therapy which are taken from Buddhism and you know this is all we're interweaving intermission I didn't know
this was used there but hey I'm a Buddhist so I'm just claiming uh but who
knows maybe maybe the this has been infused in into the Dharma teachers
lingo from cognitive emotional therapy I don't know it's all good it's all wisdom
it's all wisdom that that works Christine please
thank Nikki thank you I enjoyed this tonight I uh I was at the beach today
and you know when we were practicing that ebb and flow that came in and out
today and it was a beautiful day there and you know I have some family uh system a few sisters that are having
some issues health issues and you know my mind was trying not to ruminate on
everything that could be going on there and just walking on the beach today it was just like you know it Ebbs and it
flows and I'm still here they're still here and I always got to song about 10 minutes
before it started today as I got back from that from the shore and it was just
it's a great day today and having this as the end of my day it was just a real blessing so yeah so thank you
beautiful thank you so much for bringing that into the space this ebb and flow
Christine this sense of equanimity ebb and flow
ebb and flow with gratitude with with Equanimity and and it's a way of
befriending it's a way of befriending it all befriending the ebb and the flow beautifully said thank you so much
yeah um Amy shares this practice today was
really supportive for me I feel the meta reverberating through me Mahalo ah thank
you Amy that makes me so happy that this was supportive and The Meta is
reverberating through you very sweet Mahalo and John on YouTube says happy
that annoyance becomes briefer and briefer with practice thanks so much you
are so welcome John yay it does become braver this is just lovely yeah it this
practice works it works we just hang in there with patience with patience
it's not overnight and it does transform us so
so thank you all thank you for your practice your patience your perseverance
your befriending yourselves your minds your hearts and everyone around may we
all be well may we all be free and may the seeds be planned to serve all beings
everywhere
[Music] thanks everyone and now I stop the recording I stop