so good morning and welcome
and I appreciate the chance to be here today and
more poignant even more the appreciation that the theme of the week is appreciation
so for this meditation I'd like to suggest that one of the
purposes of meditation mindfulness meditation is for us to understand ourselves better
and if there's too much emphasis on relaxation or having particular
experience of concentration or
even to emphasis is on somehow diminishing the
amount of suffering we have all those are fine but if they're done at the cost of
not really understanding oneself well and deeply then
they some of the ways in which our mind our hearts behave or act or function
will continue to operate subconsciously or in ways we don't understand because
we don't understand ourselves and we won't necessarily understand what our needs are very well or what our
challenges are that we have to somehow would be nice to
live a preventive life preventing or suffering rather than responding to our
suffering or trying to reduce it once it's there
so this task of understanding and what is it that you don't understand
about yourself that's sitting quietly can make known
not to analyze or think about this question and now to analyze and think about
whatever understanding that comes but even just the attitude that what
we're doing here is making ourselves available to understand ourselves in a deep way
uh and um so
part of what's helpful for that is not to not to come with a lot of
preconceived ideas not to come with preconceived attitudes about ourselves about what we're doing
any preconceived Tendencies to judge in any kind of negative but also positive
ways but to really be able to quiet and be still and just with a kind of a
open available mind what is it to be understood here
how could I understand myself better so to assume a meditation posture
and to close your eyes and perhaps with this theme today to
begin right away if you're quiet just with your eyes closed
and take a deep look at yourself as you are right now
what is there to understand about yourself
what is it to understand that's maybe particular to this moment the
thicker their time
as if you're a friend to yourself a friend who really listens
what is there to understand right now
so then to take a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal until we still relax your body as you
exhale relaxing is also
a releasing or giving in to the pull of gravity
and as you exhale
to also soften the thinking mind
a calming of the thinking mind
like calming the waves on an ocean
thank you
and then to settle in here with your breathing
maybe letting go of thoughts as you do
and what do you have to understand or acknowledge about yourself
so that that understanding might allow you
to settle further into this moment breathing
if you understand any ways that you're unsettled
maybe that can and create space or
room for a calming attitude
towards whatever is unsettled in you
thank you
in order for your heart your mind to be Freer
well it'd be useful to understand about yourself
what stands in the way of deep ease and peace
that in knowing that
moves you in the direction of peace and ease freedom
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
what might you understand about yourself Here and Now
that might open you prepare you
to look out upon the world with kind eyes
with eyes of appreciation appreciating others
eyes of good will wishing others well
into it and the sitting
with gazing upon the world kindly and wishing it well
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
may all beings be happy in being well understood
may all beings be saved
cause they're well understood
may all beings become peaceful having been understood by others
may all beings be free because others have helped them
understand themselves
may we live for the welfare and happiness of the world
and may understanding be a vehicle for that
[Music]
thank you [Music]
so good morning and um
welcome announcement before giving a talk
and um that is that I thought that this Friday we could have a community meeting
for those of you those of us in this YouTube Sangha
and so after this is over at about 7 45 on Friday
I'll open a zoom room and and then we
could meet there and you know I could have some discussion and maybe have some
breakout groups you could meet each other a bit and I kind of want to do it partly
because I'll be gone the month of June I'm going to go and do a self retreat
up in the Sierras and I'll be completely disconnected from
the electronic world and um and so I thought with my absence
before going off we'd love to say hello and chat little bit and and talk a little bit and so I'll post
the zoom Link in the calendar for the Friday event also on
the IMC what's new page and also I'll put it in the chat here
for on YouTube so you'll find the different places I'll repeat these ideas on Thursday
and um and those of you who don't want to go on Zoom we'll keep the YouTube
continuing but there might not be in much exchange and I might be looking at
the screen for the people on on Zoom
so um look forward to meeting those of you who stay for that
so one of the ways of appreciating people one of the ways of showing
appreciation is to show them that they are understood understood
humans have a big need for to be understood I've been in many situations where
there's been conflict and people disagreeing vehemently about
something and or some people quite hurt by some behavior and they're trying to work it
out and the whole situation changes when uh
one of the parties or both parties understands the other shows that they understand how what's going on for the
other person they haven't necessarily agreed with the other party's uh
point of view but they have understood the point of view and made that clear understood
maybe the background for that point of view or background of what happened and their experience of something
and there's kind of like a magic magic that happens in communities and in between people when someone it feels
like they've been understood something can relax oftentimes some even if yeah there can be a greater
feeling of safety or or being respected and so
um when we run into people situations where they're suffering and a situation
which maybe evokes our compassion to quickly respond compassionately
before we really assess the situation well can lead to inappropriate action
inappropriate intervention or intervention or connection or support
for someone else that maybe isn't as rich or as valuable as it could be
so one of the ways of appreciating people one of the elements of compassion
is to take the time to understand them better and um
and part of understanding them an important part of that would be to understand oneself better
because without understanding oneself we want to understand the bias we have or
the the orientations we use to understand the situation
different people can encounter the same person who's suffering and see the suffering in very different ways some
people primarily might see it as something emotional and respond as to their emotional situation
some people might understand it as as physical and let's make sure that we get
people some water and food some people might see it as being something societal or something about a
larger situation we have to fix and so they're fixing the situation to help them feel better but we're not really
taking time to know them and so we Orient ourselves sometimes
very quickly in times of suffering because we think it's a crisis or we're we're alarmed
but if it's possible to slow down and take time to understand the other person
and even if we can't support them or help them with their particular suffering it can make a huge difference
for people that they are understood and now that they feel understood or
their situation is really taken into account and so to
um uh and I've known people I've been to with people for example in the hospital where people were caring for them in the
hospital but the people did not feel really understood in their suffering and their challenges they were having
and for someone to come and and not try to fix their medical situation or not
try to I know make a nice picture of it all you'll be okay but to really
acknowledge oh I understand that this is difficult for you um something relaxes in the person
so take time to understand the other person and maybe simple questions maybe
how is it for you and and oh this must be difficult for you you might say and
and then the person that's a prompt for a person sometimes to want to explain more and say more
because they know you're interested you seem to be attuned to them and um or you ask you you know that this
is this sounds this seems really difficult what's happening uh what part do you find the most difficult
because uh you sometimes we can be quite surprised but what we think the
difficulty if we're someone else is very different it might be you're focusing on
them and their challenge they have but they're actually focusing on how their challenge is limiting their ability to
take care of a relative or a neighbor or something and so in helping them you might be
missing what's really important for them so um to ask you know to understand
others is a form of appreciation and allows us
also to find out what we can appreciate by people when people think that we really want to
understand them or we're beginning to understand them some people will open up more some people will relax and we see
them more fully and there's more to appreciate the more we appreciate the
you know the the uh the more it's beginning to be a compassionate action
compassionate action can begins with appreciation begins with understanding that is compassion in in action
the other part of this understanding is how important it is to understand ourselves
the we have so many biases so many so much
so much conditioning about how we encounter suffering and do we understand
that what we're doing is really wanting to support the other person or are we taking care of ourselves some people
said you have compassion is to address suffering so that they don't have to
feel bad um it's more taking care of ourselves to
fixing others to take care of ourselves to make ourselves more comfortable or it could be that we have a certain
opinions about what does uh deserve compassion and what doesn't or what
counts for suffering and what doesn't or what elements of the life need to be
addressed when they're suffering and so all these kind of to understand that we have
preconceived ideas often that we carry with us to understand the situation
and this is where mindfulness is invaluable because when we have trained ourselves
to be mindful we can we'll start becoming more sensitive to the beginning point of an
opinion we have the beginning point of an orientation of you a selective
process of a way of thinking and we can see it Arise at the beginning then we
can question it put a question mark is this really so if we see we're focusing on people's
emotional life is it really so that that's what's needed do I always look for reading people's
emotions or there's what comes up is idea something needs to be fixed here and I'm
responsible to fix it one of my achilles heels is the sense of
responsibility for things but you're not necessarily my responsibility it's up to me
so I've had to learn to notice that in myself that how quickly that gets activated that oh it's you know I have
to take care of the situation where it's not mine take care of but it is mine to
connect to someone help people feel understood to appreciate people to
empathize to sympathize and so forth
uh also to understand that um you know what are we trying to do when
we are being compassionate or when we're trying to be with suffering um what are we trying to are we trying
to you know how much self is involved there are we trying to look good are we
trying to um look good in the eyes of people who are not even here that we're supposed to
be a certain way are there a lot of shoulds that we're operating under or or opinions that um
that uh you know are we scared so to understand ourselves better so
both these movements take a little bit of time and
maybe in some situations we have the time and so to not be a rushed into
compassionate action but to take time to appreciate the other person to find what there is to
appreciate to appreciate something about maybe that's deeper than their surface
Behavior or what they're saying and and then to uh try to understand
them a little bit more deeper what's behind their surface Behavior what's behind what they're saying
what uh what what do they need what do they think they need what is their uh
what does this difficulty mean for them or what is it how did they understand it for themselves but because there's so
many facets which of them it might be that facet that's important for you that
you think is important is not important for them
so to and then to turn the attention to yourself
and to ask the question you know what is there to understand about myself in relationship to the suffering that
I'm encountering am I afraid am I over eager to fix do I feel
responsible do I am I judging the person in some way or other what they're doing
so um so to
um so one element of appreciation is
understanding in fact maybe we can't really appreciate others without some deeper level of understanding about them
so an important element of compassion is
appreciation and an important element of appreciation is understanding
so um you might see how this works today when
you're with people maybe they don't have to know that you're you're making an effort to understand them better
but you might see if you can you can kind of in their conversations with others
ask yourself you know what is it what is it to under can I take time to understand this person more
uh can I understand myself more if I understand myself maybe I'll understand them better
and in that deeper understanding is there a deeper appreciation
and is there a deeper understanding of what are the issues that need to be
addressed so um thank you very much
and um we'll continue this um
discussion about different aspects of appreciation tomorrow thank you