okay hello again seems like we got this I got disconnected from the
internet hmm so I'm going to give a moment for
hopefully the uh you see yes seems like
folks are coming back okay hmm well conditions are like this
right now challenges this is this is a great
lesson to practice uh this is a great opportunity to practice compassion for
the difficulties here I was happily guiding a meditation on my own
and here you were struggling and oh we're disconnected what happened so oh
yes instead of coming up with with
in our minds cases to to have compassion 360 degrees here is an example there's
so many different ways our minds can react so many different ways our minds can react
and of course compassion is available oh this is
difficult this is difficult to be cut off in the middle of this meditation in
the middle of our community time and
um and compassion for the challenges and keeping our our Equanimity keeping our
stability so so let's let's begin again let's begin
again uh let's begin again every moment A New Beginning every
moment A New Beginning every moment A New Beginning so
so I think I have a sense that the connection was lost
pretty early on so we're exploring today we're
practicing compassion 360 degrees for all beings
everywhere including ourselves so let's uh let's begin again each
moment a new arrival age moment in New Beginning so let's
let's arrive in our bodies
let's settle
feeling our breath
and feeling this body settling feeling this body settling
with kindness with kindness towards kindness towards itself
and kindness towards others kindness towards circumstances compassion towards
oneself other circumstances things are challenging
in this human life surprises change
things don't always work as we expect them to can we have a sense of stability and
feeling our feet on the Earth our sit Bones on the cushion
and breathing breathing
and having kindness compassion for for this being who is me this body who
is me if it felt confused or uncertain or frustrated or or if there
are any challenges in the body pain and
your other emotions connecting with
extend the stability of kindness stability of
care
perhaps imagining that there is this bright
light bright orb of light in your chest in your body
that shines this golden yellow light of care
this golden yellow light of soothing kindness compassion
and whatever whomever this light comes in contact with
it brings peace it brings ease
notice that this light in your chest first and foremost shines
through your body
touching your whole body all the areas of your body but this soothing compassionate light
and then it shines out
if there were a
perhaps imagining a curtain around you
the curtain was opened curtain 360 degrees for this practice
this way of exploring it the curtain was opened
in front of you and
you acknowledge the compassionate bite
streaming streaming of all the beings
to the front of you
and it's not so much a an effortful shining but this light shines on its own
the ends of the Earth and Beyond
letting your light shine
as if the curtain now around you is opened up further and the area to your right
all the beings to your right hand side all humans
all animals too legged
Birds swings all fish insects
all sentient beings
may they all be well may they be free oh
from challenges suffering may they have resources they
need they made difficulties
and now putting the curtain to the back feeling oh feeling this
light energy of Good Will kindness permeating behind you
all the beings
baby free from sorrow behind me all the beings behind me
spreading good well compassion not just
in front of you but behind you and now to the left side imagine the
curtain up any further disappearing
all the beings to your left
all the beings to my left may they be well
may they be free from sorrow may they have all the resources
they need be well and happy
and feeling also this light shining above
all the beings above me and all the birds
all being seen and unseen
all the beings below me through the Earth all the insects
on the other side and Beyond
all the beings All Around Me 360 degrees
this light of compassion shining out and it's not a forced Shining
you relax into it just relax and let your light shine
acknowledging witnessing this light of compassion is shining
touching your own body first fetching this body of yours
as it shines out of your heart
a passion for yourself first and then equally
shining out to all beings everywhere
imagining that this light when it touches any being any person any animal
planet Earth brings ease it brings goodness
healing
your care your compassion flowing with ease
when doing this practice it's okay to imagine or to see with your heart
your mind's eye
different beings different categories of beings
all babies may they be free from challenges
from suffering may they be well
me all older adults
at ease be free from sorrow and suffering
may all people they all adults in the middle meal
have ease freedom from stress may they have everything they need
to live happily
may all birds
all birds everywhere maybe have ease may they be freeing from
sorrow challenges pain
in your four-legged animals
that bees
and that freedom from pain
and continue as you wish your own categories slowly
gently not to get overwhelmed
may all beings everywhere be free from suffering be free from sorrow
have ease in the midst of their challenges
acknowledging that all the beings
we've been practicing with the during this past week
not just yourself is included in all beings too
bring to mind your dear friend or benefactor
as well as the neutral person as well as the person
you're having challenges with
may all of them all of us all of us beings
not this planet and beyond all of us
of peace and ease the midst of our challenges be free from
sorrow suffering
may all of us be happy and heavies
and may the goodness of my practice our co-created goodness need because
the condition for freedom of all beings everywhere including
myself
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
though as we transition the recordings if you like to put a word about what's arising
For You In This Moment from this practice of cultivating compassion for all beings everywhere
you are welcome to
greetings everyone and we just uh practice together
cultivating compassion 360 degrees for all beings and I ask you and on YouTube
to put the word in if you like about it's a rising for you and there are lots
of beautiful um Reflections and I'll
share a few of them uplifted to joy happiness gratitude hope and gratitude
radiating light of Midtown 360 degrees in all Dimensions spring seeds
Humanity
thank you so much for these Reflections it's it's very common actually this um
for this practice of compassion 360 Degrees compassion for
all beings everywhere to have a sense of expansiveness
um to have a sense of lightness to have a sense of ease to have a sense of
um just joy for it to bring a sense of joy and uplift and an expansiveness so
if any day you're particularly feeling particularly heavy
um this is a great practice to do to just expand the heart and in its care
feeling expansive and also you can do this practice in daily life as you're
going for a walk it's so happy making if you're going for
a walk or if you're going for a drive every being you you pass by you you
share your kindness you share your good will you share your compassion and imagining you like just like you them
too just like me just like me they suffer just like me they have challenges
just like me and may they have ease may they have all the resources they need
just to expands the heart otherwise we that the mode we tend to operate in all
of us human beings is if again evolutionarily this is what
we have uh it's our bequest is what we've gotten is a sense kind of being in our own mind
in our own world thinking about our own problems and our own me me me it's it's
just the way that evolutionary we run so if we do this practice for all things
everywhere it we tend to become less um centered in some good ways not to be
for our perspective not to be so narrowed all the time of course we have to to consider our lives and our
problems and our issues and yes yes of course we are our own primary concern
and it is it's absolutely appropriate for this being who is me to be of primary concern for me and yet sometimes
our our lens becomes far too tight just focusing on me me sometimes it's
poor me why me oh again me oh and instead we can we can expand we can
really expand over here all beings on this planet all this all beings yeah
we're in on this planet together and and um and with with Earth Day actually and
and the timing of the earth day today doing this practice together also has for me had this sense of oh yes all of
us together on this Earth together may we have ease from the suffering
[Music] um from the pain suffering of of climate change
that impacts all of us so
so different few things I want to share with you today
one of them is to come back to the word boundaries as we talked about yesterday and I do want to expand that a little
bit and um and before we go there there's one
other thing I wanted to say about this this last category this category of all
beings so so just a review that we have been practicing in concentric circles
starting with ourselves then the benefactor dear friend the
neutral being the person we had entanglements with challenges with which was yesterday and then all being so so
with the all beings category of course all of these categories are included in
all beings all the um as I brought in towards the end and it is helpful to to
acknowledge that and there are different ways that this practice is done today we explored uh
two ways very briefly and given that we had a YouTube glitch earlier it became
even briefer one way is directionality so
traditionally it's to the north and south and east and west and and Northeast and Northwest and all these
directions and and up and down is expanding so it could be the eight
Dimensions or or um sorry six uh six dimensions or it could be eight
dimensions around you or or in front of you behind
you so there are different ways to do this and also you can do this with
categories and you can go through categories in your mind all babies all adults all
adolescence or two-legged animals all four it just so many different
categories all birds all ducks all fish Etc or even finer categories
so there are many different ways to do this practice in order for the mind to
not numb out to not numb out and say oh yeah all beings wow that's I don't even know how how to get there but you you
you play around with it oh yeah all um all crickets may they be well see I
know whatever categories you can be playful with it too however be careful not to get overwhelmed
because it can be overwhelming like wow so many categories
um and the mind can become a little too full so if that happens then it's best to just lean into The Shining of this
light of Goodwill just resting with the light and just letting it Shine Shine
The Shining of of the Good Will and again
as review but just to keep this in mind that the practice of compassion is where
kindness meets suffering so if we're practicing compassion there needs to be
an acknowledgment of challenges but without falling into it without it
becoming empathic distress
and talking about empathic distress as a near enemy um on the second day I believe of this
week so but it but the if we're practicing
compassion there is an acknowledgment of suffering of of a being and holding that with care and love
instead of just um just meta which is Goodwill which is
lovely Imagining the being in a neutral state but but here we do touch into the
suffering and again with climate change it could be quite easy to imagine yeah this being is impacted in way scene and
unseen um or or any other way so but be careful not to fall into grief and fall into
empathic distress because that is not helpful that is a near enemy and it's
also not pity which is unless that
um so let me turn and actually this last day is a perfect day to talk about boundaries so I mentioned this earlier
but the culmination of this practice the practice of the promise that let's talk
about compassion specifically as we're we're cultivating in this week together so as I mentioned the one of the tests
mentioned in visudi Maga the path of purification manual which is a thousand
page practice manual somewhere behind me there um in in
um in this manual one of the the quote quote-unquote tests that is or
the test for this practice is as I mentioned um is if you imagine in the olden times
if you're in a carriage and in the carriage you are uh taken you know the
bandits come thieves come and stop the carriage and in the carriage there's you
and there's your benefactor or dear being and there is your neutral person
and there is the person you've had challenges with four of you are present and the question
is which of you are you going to give up you have to in your heart think about
which you're going to give up and if you've practiced this to its culmination to its fruition if you've practiced
um The Compassion to fruition when you consider when you um think about you know who am I going
to give up myself well my life is dear how about the person have challenges with actually no now they're they're
like me I love them as much as I do again not condoning actions but there's
a sense of common Humanity so this is called
dissolving of the boundaries this practice this test because then there is
no there is no boundary there is no boundary so there's dissolving of the
boundaries there's the the the yeah the boundaries essentially dissolve that's
the culmination of this practice so now coming back to this work in
Western um a psychological Canon boundaries you have to have healthy boundaries Etc I
can I can see the idea that that can be helpful and yet maybe there's another
word that in our for me I'll just sharing for me can is more helpful and
for me when I think of the word boundary there's a sense of oh yes there is a wall and I have I'm I'm kind of weak and
I'm like oh okay because you know there's like a um tall wall I'm defending myself like
don't don't don't come here is my boundary whereas the way that I've seen the practice of meta and compassion for
me have really shifted and changed this idea of actually having healthy space
healthy space and relationships that may not be helpful uh or or supportive is
this sense of as I was describing to you today or or inviting you to feel into it
this the strength of the The Compassion the strength of of this light of this
this strength this power this uprightness there's there is a fierceness that cares about oneself and
it cares about the other being so it's like a force field it's like a force field of compassion it's like yes I care
about myself so much that that uh yes you can be around you can it's not that
I'm creating a wall between you and me but yes you uh but
um out of compassion not out of hatred not out of fear I'm not putting up a
wall but there's a sense of you cannot hurt me there's this force field of compassion I care of self-compassion I
care about myself so much and I care about you so much that it's not that
that this force field is invisible it's not this boundary that you're putting up so so for me this works better and also
so it's aligned with with the culmination of this practice which is dissolving of the boundaries so I can't
put up boundaries and to solve boundaries at the same time for me as practice it doesn't make sense but this
uprightness of fierce compassion from me and and the other person
um that we've been entangled with um it it it's out of love it's it's
giving us space giving each other space out of love not out of hatred not out of
fear it's a different way the the impact maybe the effect maybe in some ways is
similar but actually feels very differently it feels very differently it's not avoidant it's not pushing away
it's more upright and it's very loving it's very full I've explored both of these before
and this feels just so much more nourishing so I invite you to explore this and see if it works for you this
this is something that works for me and I've discovered in my own practice
so dear practitioners it's been delightful it's been a joy to to
practice with you this whole week thank you so much for your practice for your cultivation for your dedication for this
beautiful Community thank you may you cultivate compassion for yourself for
for all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone and maybe see you at
happy hour come to happy yards at 6 PM California time every weekday see you
then take care bye