oh testing testing one two three okay great
okay how is this for volume does this work
a little loud
sting I am continuing to test uh whether this is an appropriate volume or not
is this an appropriate volume for speaking this is more of me speaking I
can't tell whether this is the appropriate volume or not if I was to chant it would be louder than this
test oh okay
is that too loud and too soft okay one more try all right
foreign
[Music] so write volume okay great
[Applause]
and this is
just testing testing it's okay okay
foreign
welcome to everyone who's joining us for
an open house from hosted by imc's Asian Dharma Circle
and so I'm aware that there may be people who are seeing this on YouTube as
well a warm well welcome there as well and so we are going to start with just
about 10 minutes of meditation and to allow ourselves to ground and
settle and before we open to our event today so I want to sit quietly
and I will ring bell when we end
foreign
welcome for everyone who's here attending this
imc's Asian Dharma Circle hosted open house event
and those who are online joining through YouTube as well as those who are in
person and so happy to see some faces that I've been weeping Lilo and I've been seeing
on the zoom and now we get to see you all here in person that's nice
I want to say a few words about today's open house open house event
um so we don't have a long history but we did start this last year
where Our intention was to allow the Asian
Sangha in IMC to meet with the broader IMC community in some way that may be
meaningful and supportive of the overall community and the last year I waited this and now
we also had our guest guest teacher and speaker and
joining us at Chen Xing Han who shared a bit about her book
and um being The Refuge and we had a good
time discussing the book and its relevance in our broader community
and she's here today those who are online and you will see her hopefully in
the course of this event and then today we're so fortunate to be able to have
Trent Walker here with us um Who Will Be Our Guest teacher and
guest speaker who I share a deep
practice and history in the Asian Dharma
scene and today and Toronto will be sharing his new book as well as the
leading um some chanting that is rich in the Asian Buddhist history
and so we'll be doing some chanting together and learning about the book
and the formal part of our gathering together will include
some of this introductions and chanting together as well as some chance to have
interaction interactive discussions for those who are here in person
and some question and answer time
um and kind of we are exploring this together as a community
and we will end the session around 2 30 Pacific time
and after that the uh the formal part of our session
will end close and those who are here you're welcome to join us for an
optional Gathering out in um
the parking parking lot of IMC well
we'll have time for some tea and some snacks and and so just kind of informal
connecting and so that will be happening out in the
parking lot and so with that I'm gonna pass it on to lilu
thank you Ying it's just such a pleasure to be here in person
um there's kind of an energy in coming together that I'm really
um appreciating right now and for those joining online I'm just loving that this
is happening here but also happening in Prada broader scale across across the
world wide web um I'll say a little bit now about our group The IMC Asian Dharma Circle
um I think it's been it's been two years maybe a little bit more than three
three and a half years that we've been going for and um the the uh the group kind of
just sort of happened to come together in a way I think I had come to a point
in my own Dharma practice where I almost accidentally started sitting with people of color sanghas
and noticing how in those environments something
dropped away that I wasn't I didn't know was there something relaxed that I hadn't been
aware of that was a holding and there was a wish that the benefits
that I was receiving could could continue for others and for myself and
so I wanted to see if MC could have something like this could offer
something like this for practitioners and fortunately Ying was also happy to
join and Lead it and so we sort of started this and we've been going since
the pandemic and it's just been such um such a gift actually for my own
practice and for all those who I've met who seem to have benefited a lot from
this group as well um we meet twice a month on the second and fourth Sundays at this time about
one to three one to two thirty actually and um it's a usually pretty intimate
but kind of casual group we have some regular people we have some people who come
um and they're new and we offer a guided meditation and a short Dharma talk and I
think what's really rich is because it's a smaller group there is a lot of time to ask questions and interact and kind
of share of each other and connect in a way that's really rich that I think has
been very helpful for our own practices so that's a little bit about Asian
Dharma Circle at IMC and we have this tradition this is our second time of Hosting this open house once a year and
um it's a way to acknowledge that the boundaries of what is constituted as
Asian if they're not you know firm and hard and that many of us have family members friends
um the practice of what is constituted as Asian Buddhism is also kind of porous
um and to just explore and appreciate this together so today we have Trent and I'm so happy
to have him coming to share a little bit more about chanting practice in our
group there has been a lot of interest in kind of chanting as a practice and
I don't know if it's coming out of kind of growing up hearing chanting or just
being in cultures that are more amenable to this practice but wanting to share it and bring it to the whole community
and I'll say a little bit to formally introduce Trent so Trent researches and teaches about
Southeast Asian Buddhism literature and music he is currently a postdoc fellow at the
host Center for Buddhist studies and lecture in religious studies at Stanford University
and Trent received a ba in religious studies from Stanford and a PhD in
Buddhist studies from UC Berkeley where his dissertation focused on
Cambodian chanting manuscripts and you can visit his website where
there's lovely audio recordings of him chanting many of the pieces from his
book it's trentwalker.org and I just feel like
it's such a treat to be able to be here in person and hear you share about this
work and just be able to be part of this this like auditory experience so thank
you so much for joining us today
thank you so much Ying thank you so much Lulu for inviting me here it's such a
pleasure to be here on this special day for the Asian Karma circle on this
sounds like second annual open house and to see both new and and familiar faces
so um thank you for for making this this possible
I just wanted to say a few things about chanting about the book that some of the
translations I've put together in this packet are coming from and how I came to
this particular mode of practice and and study but mostly what I'd like to do in the
time we have together is make time for us to chant and that's what the the
packet here is for it's just to allow us to
sample and experience a couple of different types of chanting together and
many of you I'm sure have experienced a whole wide range of of chanting Styles whether in your own practice or things
that you grew up hearing or things that you've encountered in Buddhist practice or other kinds of practices in your life
and for that I'm also grateful that ying and Lilo will facilitate some reflection
and discussion both about sort of what we've experienced today and then also
tying that into your lives and your practice more broadly
and thank you to everyone joining online as well it's a real pleasure to be here
I'd like to begin just by passing around a few things if that's okay I don't have
a PowerPoint but I just want to give you a few images if I may and maybe we could pass them in different directions
so this one here that I'll pass around this is one of my main teachers of Chan
I just wanted you to be able to see a picture of her when I when I speak of
her and this next one is of my other main
teacher I just just so you can see a picture of him
and I'll just pass this around as well because you can see in this book
um some Cambodian Banner Banner paintings of scenes from the Buddhist
life that are connected to some of the chants so just so you have a sense of what might be happening visually in
context with some of the chats so I'll just just pass those around foreign
maybe I'll keep passing things around is that okay can I pass these around too these are just two examples of chanting
books in the Cambodian language or Khmer or Kumai and I just
especially so you could see the cover the covers show a scene of some of the
ways this chanting one of the particular styles of chanting that I'll talk about more is used
my interest in Buddhism and Buddhist practice and music really grew up
together when I was in high school I started to practice at a couple of different
Buddhist centers in San Francisco at Gold Mountain Monastery in Chinatown and also at the San Francisco Sun Center
and in both of those contexts I was drawn to silent meditation but also to Ritual
and chanting practices in particular I had also grown up
here on the peninsula studying music trumpet and voice these kinds of things so I was really curious about this
interaction this intersection between the Dharma between the teachings of the
Buddha between the practices that we engage in and sound what what might be
happening at this this intersection and that Drew me after finishing high
school to go before going to college to work for a year in Cambodia with an
organization called Cambodian Living Arts and doing research for them on this intersection between Buddhism and music
and through through that organization I became connected to the two teachers
whose images I've I've passed around so you can see
who became my root teachers in the Cambodian harma song or thought tradition which is this particularly
melodic style of chant that we'll get to explore together
and that that experience and then also studying chant in a monastic setting I
spent about half a year ordained temporarily as an office in Cambodia
um made me really curious both in my own practice and in my academic
life to continue thinking about and trying to understand what's what's
happening in this relationship between a particular Buddhist teachings and ideas
and the way they're lifted into music or Sound or a chant
if it's okay I thought I might mix up the portion in which I'll I'll say a
little bit more about the Cambodian harmasan tradition but I would like for us to chant together a little bit first
then we can get a feel of some chanting in our bodies
and I'd like to begin with a chant that actually isn't in your packet but just something very very very very simple
and this is coming out of the Cambodian tradition in which certain forms of meditation
practice involve concentrating on syllables these may be repeated silently
sometimes repeated aloud and that's somewhere in between might think of chanting as a practice that takes place
out loud and meditation is a practice that takes place silently in the Cambodian Buddhist context and this is
similar in Thailand Laos other places as well this word this poly word bhavana
that we might think of as meaning mental cultivation or meditation
in many cases really refers to chant I often chant done silently in this way
here I would like to take these three syllables
these are syllables that in the Cambodian tradition can stand in for the Buddha the Dharma and the Sangha they're
syllables that can stand in for the virtues of our mothers our fathers our
teachers and other kinds of symbolic meanings within the esoteric theravada
context but for now I just like for us to explore them as as sounds
so the the syllables again are MO
ah and uh and so
let's chant just uh we'll begin with MO
and I invite you I will start on a particular note don't feel you have to do that note you
can pick any uh one sound that feels comfortable to for
you and your vocal register and then we'll just do that for one
breath then we'll move on to ah and then we'll move on to ooh so I'll
start each of those and then you can join in just hold it for one breath and we'll
pause take another breath in go on to the next syllable and ending with u make
sense okay
more
foreign
[Music]
[Laughter]
now let's do the same thing but for each syllable whenever you come to the end of your
breath just take a breath again and rejoin everyone else so we'll continue on more until I ring
the bell then we'll pause to all thermopods and then do ooh make sense
[Music] more
more
[Music]
[Music] oh
oh
[Music]
[Music] oh foreign
[Laughter]
[Music]
now I'd like for us to continue that same
approach to sound but extend it to this first chant here
on the top of page one as
you might be aware the Pali language is pronounced in many
different ways depending on the particular linguistic or cultural context in which
it's used so there is a so-called indic or
International pronunciation of poly it's similar to not exactly the same as the
Sri Lankan pronunciation and for this first chant it would be something like
and then there are also depending on the phonetics of local
languages all kinds of other ways Bali might be pronounced so for instance in the Cambodian context that same phrase
is pronounced yeah
so let's try this chant one thing that I wanted to highlight
here is in Gray those are the syllables that are longer
and the ones that aren't in Gray those are the syllables that are shorter
um in many styles of chanting that distinction between short and long
syllables when chanting in Pali determines the rhythm of the chant this isn't true in all styles but in many
styles particularly in Cambodia Thailand Laos to less extent in Sri Lanka and
Burma but particularly in those three contexts that distinction between short and long syllables determines the Rhythm
and the long syllables are exactly twice the length of time as the short ones
so it leads to this rhythm of
gluten so slow down yeah
so let's try that we'll try it in this International pronunciation of first
and then like before just breathe when you feel
comfortable and you don't have to breathe at the end of the phrase so in some styles of chant
one might recite yeah [Music]
but here let's just continue without a breath there but take a breath
whenever you would like to because we're chanting in a group and then join back in wherever the group is so for instance
if I'm if I was chanting by myself in this way I might go
foreign [Music]
[Music]
[Music] make sense
so let's try that all together this simple phrase just means
um foreign
[Music]
alone
let's continue with that same style but we'll add the my pronunciation just so
you can feel what it's like to chant in a different pronunciation of poly so instead of
here yet so let's just repeat each syllable first
nah mole yeah
more but here yeah
great so we'll do the same thing and feel free to experiment with what
pitch you're chanting on it doesn't in the in Cambodian styles of
chanting that sounds monotone sounds like each individual chanter is usually on one pitch
generally speaking in a group people take on many different pitches whatever is comfortable for them and it creates
this interesting layered kind of sound so feel free to experiment
foreign
[Music]
no more [Music]
can I get a time check on how much
okay wonderful thanks so much so let's do maybe just one more uh chant
in this simple Style of uh just chanting on one pitch and
then I'll transition and we'll explore some of these this more melodic style of Cambodian chant
of course yeah
just a curiosity really in the top line where it has the Khmer script poly which
I can't read nonetheless it says that there are only two long syllables
compared to the three below is can you say about that sure sure so if you look
at that second long syllable you'll see that the second part of it
looks a little complicated so there are actually two syllables in there in other words the the ha is
written kind of below the so it's like namo yeah
and many scripts that are used to write Pali have similar kinds of principles
so that's why it happens to look like that sure
so let's look at this second chant here that many of you might be familiar with
this one that in the international style of pronunciation would be this
or in this Kamai style pronunciation
maybe we'll do it just in this International style but just want you to just invite you to be aware of these
other kinds of pronunciations and often when this is chanted the
individual words might be separated with a pause on my chance of thing like
that would be one style but let's try this other style where there's no break between words
and the only thing determining the rhythm is this difference between the long and short syllables here the long
ones again are highlighted in Gray so we get this pattern of
[Music] um
[Music] so let's just do that once I
altogether three times again without a pause at the end so all
together three times
[Music]
[Music] thank you
so we can if you'd like and we if we have time we can explore more about
different uh other chants in this often than this monotone style if you turn to
the second page now I just wanted to offer some other uh
approaches to chant so this distinction between long and short syllables and The rhythms behind
that are part one part of the aesthetic joy and beauty of chanting in Pali so
for instance this one at the top which is often used to recite prior to
reciting Buddhist texts to invite local spirits on Earth and in the Heavens to
come listen to a recitation of Buddhist chanting the uh the the pattern of these
syllables repeats each line and that's how poetry in Bali works there's these
patterns of short and long syllables that repeat each line so this is a slightly more complicated pattern but
when in recitation we can hear the pattern very clearly of sage
um foreign
having this same kind of rhythmic pattern but sometimes in a Cambodian context it
might be recited in that way like
um
[Applause]
or sometimes a Melody would be applied to it it's these Melodies that I was
really drawn to in encountering this Cambodian Dharma song tradition so I'll
just give you one example of a melody of this and then we'll turn to some of the other texts in this tradition via
English translation so one Melody that could be used here I'll just give you an excerpt of it
would be some games
[Laughter]
[Applause]
oh man anything
and when I first encountered this tradition through I was really curious about
what's this relationship between the sound of the chance and the texts what
what's happening in this relationship and kauran in particular really emphasized
that some texts and The Melodies that go with them are designed to bring about
this experience of Samuel some Vega being this Bollywood that means this
experience of shaking or being stirred particularly being stirred by the
encounter with impermanence so when Buddhists texts narrate the life of the Buddha and describe him leaving the
palace and encountering the four sites of an old person a sick person a dead
person and a renunciate this is the feeling or the experience that's described and some Vega in this
Cambodian tradition as in elsewhere in taravada Buddhist context is sometimes paired with this experience of basada
Assad that literally means this sinking down or this just as a glass of Muddy Water if it's
allowed to sit the mud will sink to the bottom and the top part becomes clear and bright so it has this sense of clear
bright faith and Clarity in the mind that can be paired with some Vegas so
some other kinds of chants in their Melodies and in their texts might be crafted to bring about this kind of
experience so if you turn to page four on your
handout this this this is a very simple melodic
style chant if it was that here would be trans
chanted in Cambodian and Kumai in the language of Cambodia
um would sound something like this
[Music]
[Music] and because our time is short
let's just try chanting we'll just take one stanza of this and and learn it in
English together and let's learn the fourth one the one that says here no joy
equals that of peace nothing else can end suffering here in this world and Beyond peace is the cause
of true Joy and I've made this little space in between the lines here so that each line
is divided into a group of four syllables then a group of three syllables and in Cambodian chanting in
not in poly but in Kumai often are almost invariably The Melodies
are structured based on a certain number of syllables for one part of the melody
a certain number of syllables for another part of Melody you know very analogous to when we're singing a song
that has multiple verses usually there's approximately the same number of syllables in each verse so that we can
put the same words to that same Melody so the same practice is happening here
so let's just try this one this one is one that's associated with this experience or this feeling tone of
basada of of clarity or bright faith
so I'll I'll recite a short bit and if you could repeat after me that would be
then we can experience this one together
[Music] oh
no joy equals
[Music] that of peace
that of peace [Music]
nothing else can
nothing else can and
suffering suffering
here in this world
hear me in this world [Music]
and behind [Music]
and be yond
[Music] peace is the call
s peace is the calm
s of true Joy
[Music] true Joy [Music]
let's try that one more time but we'll just do it all together I will chant along with you don't worry if you can't
remember what the melody was just listen to those around you and we'll we'll make
our way through it no joy equals
[Music] that of peace
nothing else can
and suffering [Music]
here in this world foreign
[Music]
[Music] let's just do one last one here
let's just do the one in the next page
and uh I think we'll have time just to do this
in column response and let's let's say let's skip to the
third stanza this is one that's associated with some Vega and the story here is this is
recreating this moment after the Buddha has been born and his mother is in these
texts described as dying seven days after his birth and this is Maya Queen mahamaya
offering her guidance to mahapajat to be called me who as the Buddhist Aunt takes
care of the Buddha after Amaya's death so this is Maya's guidance then to go to
me so if we just take the third stanza here in Kamai this sounds something like
[Music] um
and so we'll apply a version of that same Melody for this line what can I do when we are born only to be destroyed
Etc what
can I do
what can and I do
[Music] when we are
going on me too
born only two
[Music] The Stride
be the strong
all humans and [Music]
all humans
[Music]
by Nature [Music]
by Nature thank you
so I think we're going to transition now to have a chance to discuss and reflect
uh you're welcome to um
take a look at any of the other chants that we didn't get to the other ones on like Pages five six seven eight those
are just examples of other ones in this Karma song style they have Melodies of their own that might be recited for
when someone is passing away sometimes for a funeral sometimes for the consecration of a Buddha image sometimes
just for a ceremony in gratitude for parents so many different occasions
and the book that they're coming from until Nirvana's time the this book just
has more translations and essays that try to um
for me try to fulfill what my my teachers promote and gauran wanted to do
which was to share this particular Cambodian tradition uh with the world
um first to Cambodian American communities those particularly younger Cambodian Americans who are maybe more
familiar with English than Kumai so that they can access this part of their Heritage and their tradition but also
for people who are not Cambodian but want to appreciate a this particular
window on the Dharma that's offered through the Cambodian dimersang tradition so thanks for your attention
and I'll turn it back over to the two of you
thank you well thank you so much Trent I feel like I could sit here and listen for a while
and feel this hmm we have a chance and to um
for those who are here in person to get into a small group of three or four
uh to share a little bit about what this experience is
chanting listening to the sound of the chanting and maybe
um um what might have evoked in your heart
in your mind in your bodies and I would invite
folks to mingle a bit so maybe go to the people you may not know much at all and
we can spread out in the hall and maybe even outside on the deck if you like we
have about 10 minutes or so um and once you settle into a group
um um maybe just take a moment and uh
to kind of collectively recognize that you're in a group and um
find a way you know whoever might to wanted to start first and then go around
the circle and to say one thing at a time so as we
get together I kind of also are learning from each other and uh this is not a chance to
um comment about other people's experience but really allow this to be
something that we're sharing together collectively sharing together
and receiving the gift of sharing
and so um maybe we can just
um uh stand up and form the groups and for those who don't find the group so maybe
you can come to the center of the hall and we'll find you a group
thank you
some somehow it wasn't test test
oops test test test test
there
so welcome back I hope you all had a good small group experience
um we'd like to just take a few moments now to share with the larger group
um if there's anything from your small group that um you know
that felt important for you or kind of resonated for you that you would like to share now with the rest of us I think
Ying Trent and I had a little group of ourselves and it was just wonderful to
hear each of our experiences and to share that I think the richness of this
chanting really comes forth in the individual experiences so we'd like to hear from you
together
it was a very rich and moving sharing I'll just say one thing that really um
came clear was how much depth and richness and dimension as a Buddhist
practice this has mindfulness concentration
heart heart practices all of it so that's just one small piece
thank you for that I think in our group um there is just so much attention that
could be paid paid to all the experiences within our bodies and in the
group interacting individually and with the group and um
yeah for me it was where the chanting was coming from like in my belly and
noticing that this wasn't something I could do half-heartedly that that it really called for a full engagement
especially in a group Live felt very
used used some Vega and Posada and I I think I felt qualities of that in in the
in the experience of chanting together we also remarked this about the space how it felt to be doing it in this space
um it's very special
any other comments anyone want to share anything else
I'm just accustomed to hearing the monotonic uh
chanting which I think I think we talked about in our group is it seems very it's
kind of um conducive to a meditative state right it's a very
kind of calming um whereas the melodic is so evocative of
of emotion and devotion which I really love
and I was really curious about the different sounds or the different
quality of The Melodies I mean early on I'm in the chanting trying to sound it
to me I I mean not that I'm very well versed in any kind of world music but it
sounds a little uh like Pacific Islander like even Hawaiian and then I heard then
later on it almost sounded like a gory enchants and I was just so curious about
um yeah we're all that and they're so different I was just interested in learning more
about that
thank you so the melodic chants within the Cambodian
context are often following the
musical Theory and practices of broader my secular music as well
and so the the scales that is the musical notes that are being used are
ones that we might see in other kinds of Cambodian and musical context as well
and those you know like any kind of musical tradition in the world it's always in conversation with other
musical Traditions so and then there's also just all kinds of parallels whether
it's the particular notes that are used or the focal technique that we might see between
vocal Traditions that are geographically quite separate from one another
so just to give a specific example for your question the second chat we did this one the
second melodic one we did Maya's guidance for go to me on page five I put
this is not meaningful for everyone but for those who for whom this Western
musical Theory context is Meaningful I just put the imagining c as the
fundamental pitch and putting out the other notes in the scale
in relation to that pitch and the particular scale that ends up being used
is something like uh
and this this scale is quite there are other musical Traditions that use that
scale but it's one that's very particular to Cambodian music as well
um and sometimes when people are chanting in a Cambodian Temple say here
in the United States people are chanting together they have different natural vocal ranges sometimes people will end
up settling on particular notes of that scale just in the monotone chanting because it fits within music that people
might be familiar with and so that someone with a lower voice might settle
on a note like oh and someone might tell them they're like
something like that um this not consciously but just as an
expression of this connection between musical Traditions outside of a particular Buddhist tradition and within
that Maybe
maybe we have time for one more question or comment did you
okay Amy
yeah thank you so much for being here and offering this um the session um I was attending online I just got
here that I basically was listening and participating um yeah I've um I've had the opportunity to
actually stay in different kinds of Buddhist monasteries including technohans and monasteries and the style
of chanting there is very melodious like this I've also stayed in Sri Lankan monasteries and Thai Forest monasteries
and something that I really miss um when I kind of you know started practicing more in this tradition the
Insight Meditation tradition was that there isn't really much chanting and I was wondering why like you guys don't
have to answer but it's kind of like a question for IMC leadership and IMC teachers like why is chanting kind of
almost intentionally left out that's what it feels like because I actually feel kind of sad about it I feel quite sad about it because I feel there's so
much um uh there's so many functions and purposes to chanting like first of all
as someone mentioned it evokes this quality of devotion for me um especially as I go along the practice
and also it's a way to memorize the teachings the matasuto the mangalasuta has a lot of important teachings and in
the monasteries when we chanted it on the full moon and New Moon nights I mean it's a way to kind of reaffirm Community
too a sense of um building community and strengthening the bonds within the
community so that's my question it's not you don't have to answer but like why is it left out
could I ask a question back to you I don't I don't have an answer to this
this question but I'm curious since you because of all your experience and encounting encountering and
participating enchanting in different settings are there certain kinds of settings say at IMC or
other centers you may participate in where you you would like to see more chanting and if so what what kind I'm
just trying to imagine what might be most meaningful or important to you
people would be like you know at certain dates that are very significant in the Buddhist calendar like for example vsoc
you know or something like that but also just like you know um Sunday mornings
are the most attended events just including something simple like um like what was that the
Reflections on universal well-being that's in the Thai Forest tradition or you know it's something that people can't even take home with them and
practice on their own and anyway just just ideas I mean there's no you know events of significance but also just
something like a regular you know something regularly done maybe once a week
once a month even I don't know thank you thank you so much
I think um how about now
okay well um I'm glad you brought this up Amy and I'm hoping that this event
today can kind of stimulate that for us and maybe allow us to begin reflecting
And discussing whether this is something we'd like to and can offer here I I myself also feel that I would benefit
from some sort of regular chanting practice done at IMC so we can we'll
look into it and I'm glad this event actually is stimulating these kinds of conversations as IMC is reopening and
we're having more and more in-person events the other thing I really appreciate about chanting is that it's
in the moment in person is so rich in those qualities
so um we're almost at the end of our formal time together and I want to again thank
Trent Walker for all that you bring and are sharing and from this lineage and
what you've spent time studying and really refining so that you can keep this tradition alive
and I also want to recognize tension Khan here who has a new book one long
listening so if any of you want to check that out conversations in chaplaincy and
I don't think I got the subtitle quite right but um and I'd like to invite her to come up here and Trent attention are
going to help us close with a dedication of Merit
so if you could turn to page two in your handout and then there's this
dedication of Merit chant this is just a translation of a vernacular command
language chant um that chant goes something like
et cetera and uh we'll do a similar melody in English
something like let's try to find a pitch that's good for for you maybe you could start us off
[Music]
and cross to reach [Music]
so this isn't it as an example and we'll do it all together now so that with that
same rhythm of essentially short short long short short short long for each of
the there's seven short lines per stanza and so we'll do it from the beginning to
the end uh again don't feel you need to be wedded to the notes that we're starting
on and you can find what feels
most resonant and true to your particular embodiment at this moment
so um may we
dedicate this Merit of of being here together of practicing chant together to for all
beings and then also for exactly how it's expressed here in the chat we'll do
together thank you [Music]
may your life done with care and craft
both words
[Music]
be soon
and gone and to come may my foreign
[Music]
thank you thank you
thank you everyone and this concludes our formal session of the program
and thank you for those who joined us online and we hope you join us soon in
some other ways and so those of you who are here in
person would like to hang out afterwards please we have some snacks on the
counter and their tea and feel free to um grab something if you would like to
get a chair to sit out feel free we will open the cabinet for those who don't
know to get the chair and we'll go to the back door go through the back door and we'll be out in the parking lot
and those who have a burning questions are Trent and changing feel free to
ask questions around in the parking lot as well yeah
yeah okay thank you everyone for coming
foreign