warm greetings today from the inside meditation center
and here in Redwood City and
I have the Good Fortune of being able to go between these two wonderful meditation centers
and this is the kind of the Home Center happy to be back and happy to be with you here
and um so
people associate Buddhism with truth often What's called the Four Noble Truths
and sometimes put those at the center of Buddhist Buddhist teachings
and that's fine but uh in terms of practice what is repeated over and over again in
the teachings of the Buddha much more often than any reference to truth
uh which uh is um knowing and seeing
and perhaps knowing and seeing are meant to be a alternative way of talking about
knowing and seeing truth because you want we want to be able to see and know what's happening in our
direct experience and one of the things to distinguish is between
what's directly known directly seen
that we can really verify through our direct experience and what is our
interpretation what is the value you we put on something what's the meaning we assign
to it and how do we what do we what uh meaning
do we assign it to ourselves or what do we what do we make up about ourselves in
relationship to experience and the interpretation the meaning the
purpose the value um they certainly have a place in this
world and practice it's important but we want to really see the difference
between the direct experience and the added layers we put on
and then we sit down to do meditation mindfulness meditation we want to
emphasize the directness what we can know what we can know directly
and it's possible to know directly that we are adding meaning we are adding
layers of interpretation we are adding values
judgments commentary projections into the future
associations of what we have in the past and there's layers and complexity of all
the stuff that we add that's extra and and even if it's has some value and
important to do so it's still not the same thing as direct experience
so when we sit we want to kind of become sensitive to this so that we can prioritize direct
experience when we're meditating after meditation there might be a time
for a deep contemplation deep reflection about meaning and purpose and and um
contextualizing what what's happened but for meditation we want to try to
keep it really simple as if the what we could know and see directly
that's the door forward uh in the Dharma that's where we can begin freeing
ourselves from the layers of reactivity free yourselves from the layer of of
uh cloudiness the filters through which we see uh it's the way in which we could see
more clearly what's happening and in doing so become wiser
so in this meditation you might um you know
do the basic meditation mindfulness of breathing being here in the present moment
but keep an eye out from the difference between the Simplicity of the direct experience
and what we add to it meaning interpretation even something as simple as
you know are we at the end yet or boy this is
taking a long time or um or Gill is talking a lot
all that is commentary and there's nothing wrong but necessarily but uh oh there's the
commentary this is not the direct experience the immediacy of it is just like Gail
talking just a voice talking and um and the sound happening
uh the breathing as you breathe and if your mind wanders off a lot
the idea that I'm a poor meditator that's an interpretation that's a
made-up layer on top of it it might have and and um
the immediacy what we can see directly this is so simple and sometimes and this
is the relief that can come from it is so simple that we're freed
from the weight of these interpretations so the mind wanders off a lot in thought
then we see oh the mind is wandering off it's that simple
and uh even the idea that it's doing it a lot
means that we it's higher level of interpretation based on history based on
what we remember the repetition of it all at the moment what we can see and know
the mind is involved in thinking let's bring it back
that simple can be a relief so to become sensitive to
how you leave direct experience
and then return to what can be known and seen known and perceived directly Here
and Now so assuming a meditation posture
and
the beginning of knowing and seeing directly in our own experience
is to do so in our physical posture maybe moving around a little bit
twisting rocking a little bit to really feel and sense ourselves into
an aligned balance good posture
slowly closing the eyes
and as already now just sitting here like this are you telling yourself
stories interpretation about what's happening how it is for you and how you are and
are you judging or you're evaluating are you interpreting
even if it's accurate it is not the same thing as direct experience
if we're seeing through the lens of those interpretations
if we see interpretation as interpretation then we're back to the world of direct
knowing
and then gently taking some long slow deep breaths
relaxing on the exhale
letting the breathing return to normal and continue to relax on the exhale
anywhere in the body where you feel holding
and then centering yourself on your breathing
the direct experience of an inhale knowing how it's felt and known
through the body
knowing and seeing knowing perceiving the exhale
as it's known in the body
and now their thoughts or feelings that interpret react
assign meaning or
a sign of future
and if so recognize it as such
and come back taking refuge in the direct experience
foreign
when you are more involved in thinking than with breathing
chances are as you're involved in the story making mind the interpretive mind
the planning mind you're involved
you've lost the touch with the breathing the direct experience perception
and then with whatever with whatever energy or capacity you have to think
direct it instead to knowing and perceiving breathing
if you're telling stories or interpretations or
thinking about something perhaps it's something deep inside that
needs to be reassured it's okay
for now and then to find a refuge
a place of safety for a few minutes in the Simplicity of direct experience
here breathing your body
just knowing what is actually happening here
without story interpretation
and then as we come to the end of the meditation
how simply can you now
open your heart to The Wider world
open your thoughts to simply know
or sends or have a general idea of the people of your life
people you know the people you don't know people you'll learn about today or meet
and to perhaps aspire
to the best of your ability to know them directly
without the lens of our interpretations and stories and
judgments values meaning
Futures and pasts just to be with a person in their basic
simple way Humanity of the moment
and to have good will
to wish them well the kind of Wellness
simple safety stability contentment
we're being happy being well
brings out the best in people
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may it be that the way that we are together with others
makes it more likely for them to feel some happiness and safety
some peace some freedom
may we be a refuge for others
[Music]
thank you
hello everyone and here we have the third talk on the
Dharma of challenges and
maybe in some ways life is one continuous challenge with little interludes between them
and so learning to be with challenges learning to be wise about them and find
our way through them in an effective way is a very important part of Dharma practice
so Dharma has different meanings in today's
meaning that the third meaning that I've listed before is Dharma as truth
and what we mean by truth is very important to consider and and one of the simplest ones that I
like a lot is um mindfulness is a practice of
truth-telling that the truth means that we're honest and um
that uh honesty is basically truth out loud
or truth that we discover is to be honest
with ourselves and whether we should be verbally honest and truthful about everything we
experience is questionable since sometimes truth can hurt people
but we always want to be truthful towards ourselves we're really honest to
learn how to be honest and um we are honest with ourselves
and so how do we learn to do that how do we learn to stop and take a
moment or take time to really recognize how we are and what's happening for us
the truth of how we feel and one of the important really
important things to learn this quest for truth and to honesty is to be able to distinguish between our
direct experience and the interpret interpretations we add to it the layers of meaning making
judgments commentary value that we add on top of things
the time that we add on top of things for example if this continues this will
end up some terrible way this means that you know terrible things will happen or passed this is just like what
happened before and uh and therefore I know what this is about
so some of that layers of meaning making and thoughts and interpretations that we
have are appropriate and wise to do but it's also a place where we get into
tremendous trouble and when we have challenges in our life the chances are fairly high that the
interpretive story making mind predictive mind value mind judgment mind
um uh is operating more strongly than usual
it kind of makes sense we have a challenge we're difficult and so what does this mean for me you know how do I
find my way out and what's wrong here I have to understand what's happening so it makes sense that we get into that
mode but the interpretive meaning making story making mode
is a fair amount of time is inaccurate it doesn't have the full picture it generalizes it it uh it uh
settles in a particular interpretation a particular aspect of what's Happening sometimes it has blinders on it doesn't
see the Fuller picture sometimes we don't really depending on
what the challenge is we don't see ourselves fully and one of the ways to learn to
distinguish between really see or this is an interpretation this is an added
layer maybe it has some accuracy some truth to it maybe it's something that we
have to principle or an idea that I need to somehow take into account and act on
but it is an interpretation is a story it's an added thing and so to take the time to see that then
we have more ability to have choice and clarity about what we're doing
so that if we have a challenge with another person if we can say
you know something what happened what you said yesterday was very difficult
for me and part of the reason it was so difficult is I understood it to be or
interpreted to be uh you were angry with me as soon as you say I understand it or I
interpret it I add you know that's how I understood it there's a little bit more room for it not to be dogmatic you were
angry but rather to let the other person participate than explain well I was
irritated but I was also really scared and then you get a bigger picture of what's going on
so to be able to know to hold and see something a little bit more
provisionally when we know it's an interpretation or
story or as opposed to what's happening to us directly
also when we are challenged with other people or with ourselves even to
perceive the direct experience as a direct experience gives us a a much
very important reference point for how to go forward or what needs care needs to be made so if someone was angry with you
yesterday and the direct experience is because of that you feel hurt
and you have a tendency to maybe when you're hurt to be angry back
and be in the attack mode and so but if you what was the direct
experience what happened to me oh yes uh I was hurt
and and now I'm in the attack mode or yes I was hurt and now I'm trying to
run away or I'm afraid or I'm sad
and um and then also when you know that information then you can begin looking
at well given that I'm hurt or afraid or sad or angry what what do I practice
with that how do I be with it how do I be with it so I don't act reactively
how do I be with it so that I'm caring for myself because sometimes when we react to
challenges um then we often lose ourselves in that process
so in so to take time to find out what's true here what's a direct experience
what's what's the direct experience and what's the interpretation or the story that I'm telling
and but stories are important and so one of the interesting things to do is uh when
there's challenges is to tell the story but uh maybe to a neutral party
can I tell you how I understood this what happened tell you the story and what happened
and some of the story will be accurate and sometimes here and you said you say it in a neutral way and and having it
kind of the taking the pressure off the the bottled upness of the story and the
feelings by telling the story gives us more clarity of what's going on
and um and one of the ways to tell the story is to tell it to yourself some people Journal about it
and then it's interesting to journal because it's a there's a record now of what you what you're thinking what
you're interpreting and illness it's possible then to go back and reread it and much better understand where the
interpretation is where the story is where the story making is the values the
all the things we add to the the basic raw story The Raw Story versus how we
are interpreting it and um and also uh the way we think
and the way that we write or the way that we speak sometimes pools are a different part of the Mind
and one interesting way of doing seeing this maybe is that maybe when you're dry sometime
when you're alone um uh speak out loud to yourself to speak about what's happening around the
challenge out loud and uh and maybe in speaking about it out loud rather than it ruminating in
the mind uh you'll find a different relationship to it maybe you're speaking from a
different place you understand more your reactivity or you understand more your place of wisdom you're more likely to
come and maybe in speaking out loud you can it's clear it's clarified much more
what's happening for you and maybe you'll find your way with it
so all this is a way of being honest about being truthful the truth of what's
directly happening and to know that what that means direct immediate seeing and
knowing uh and the truth of oh this is one of the story I'm telling myself about it
this is how I'm interpreting it this is how uh the values I put on it the
meaning I put on it the predictions of the future I put on it the this is what
I I dredge up from the past to include as part of this what's happening
and um and the truth of seeing what you're doing in the mind with all this is invaluable
this means that hopefully the challenges we have they're not crises of the moment
but if there's you know it's ongoing in some enough way that we can take time out
uh ask reality if we're a little time out to go meditate to go journal to go
for a walk to spend some time with a neutral friend and just really kind of
begin discovering what is really the truth here versus what is the interpretation
what is really the direct experience interpretation does have a role
but if we know its interpretation then as I said earlier we can
say that when we're in conversation with people and then there's much more space to maneuver and find a way
and um truth is uh makes us uncomfortable you
know it's much much more comfortable sometimes to oddly enough to be caught up in our
interpretations our meaning making our anger our blame our fear than it is to stop and really feel it to know it and
be present for our direct experience but that's what we're trying to do in this Dharma practice this kind of
truthfulness about what's actually happening here and um
and uh and then also to put ourselves in situations
where we're more likely to kind of pop the bubble of our interpretations and
our stories and what I mean by this is sometimes I've I've had difficulties with other people like I'm angry with
them or something and I've learned that my mind thinks
about the other person I don't think so accurately about the person when I'm
angry towards them and so I've learned that it's really important to go find the person and be
in conversation with them because that pops the bubble of the projections the meaning the interpretations that my mind
is making up around the anger and um it's much safer for me much safer
for the other person if we can meet and have this uh you know
direct experience of each other rather than being involved in this a whole other
world of of uh meaning making story making interpretations
so um so today if you want to kind of explore
these ideas in your daily life is ask reality for a timeout
and it could be a minute it could be five minutes it could be depending what's going on and might be a need
longer in order to go for a walk meditate Journal do something that you
begin asking what's true here what's true in the direct experience and what is interpretation
oh oh that's an interpretation that statement that's an interpretation
is a statement of Truth oh it's true that that's an interpretation that's a judgment that's a meaning making that's
oh that's what my mind is doing that's how I'm relating to all this and maybe it's really important to see
it clearly that's what you're doing maybe you'll see that it's false maybe you'll see that you have to take
this into account and act accordingly but to know clearly oh this is what's
happening this is what's happening is one of the really important ways to work with challenges
in the in the long term to get a skill of doing this makes all challenges a lot
easier so um thank you very much and we'll continue on this
theme tomorrow