foreign
how's the volume is that okay Sage can you hear me okay all right
everybody okay with my mask off okay
mask here Gil Gil said just this last week Indiana community meeting
did you stay for that um and he expressed that he's just he's not comfortable teaching when in a room
with everybody with their masks off so we'll be keeping our masks on yep
because without Gill we ain't got nothing
that's not exactly true but [Laughter]
he has he has made a marker in the world hi Stephen welcome
good thank you
thanks for joining us tonight Susan
and Sage doesn't have a name tag on but everybody this is Sage over here
so would you guys be okay we'll just sit for five minutes just take a few five
minutes of breathing and just centering together you got me streaming so people on
YouTube can hear me if they're there so people out there in YouTube land
maybe you can just even let yourself slow down and and sit
silently with us for five minutes
[Music]
welcome hi Julie I'm Tanya
so this is week three in a five-week series on the hindrances
are you familiar with the hindrances Julie great and Susan I think you are too you're familiar with the hindrances
okay Sage you are yeah
yeah so the first week um The Twist of this class is
I'm talking about it kind of through at least partly the lens of The Wizard of
Oz so if you've seen the movie great if you haven't
maybe I'll give enough of information to be able to have a little taste of it
so the first week we just spent talking about what the five hindrances are and also I kind of laid the groundwork for
how the characters and the story fit into a Dharma context
last week we talked about um sensual desire or greed and aversion
and ill will and tonight we'll talk about restlessness and worry
so the next two hint you know weeks will be next week will be sloth and torpor
and the week after will be doubt that'll be the final and there are some things that Diana and
I who's not here tonight but we'll be back next week really want to kind of invoke invite
kind of bring to this exploration is some lightness some Joy
some humor to a topic that can be a little heavy
and that we can kind of have a oh no I'm having a hindrance you know response to
and they're really you know this is part of the human condition as far as we know it these were named by the Buddha
over 2500 years ago and really we see pretty much the same
you know issues today interfering with meditation nobody's come up with a new
list of hindrances you know it's these work well enough which is pretty remarkable
the other thing that we are kind of inviting you to think about is that there actually can be thought of as
Energies so and the energies impact the physical
body and so in some ways you can start to tune into the body and if you
recognize one is a leaning toward a leaning in which you'll often find when
you have some sensual desire getting kicked in it doesn't have to be greed you know but if you want something you
tend to lean toward it you like what somebody's saying you know or there's just this natural movement
and in contrast the ill will the aversion is either a
pushing away of something or pulling back of oneself so there's really you
know if you just right now this posture That's a classic
example of ill will in somebody's body um
so energy that wants energy that doesn't want doesn't like right and then we have
um restlessness and worry which are essentially too much energy
too much energy restlessness in the body so there's an inability to be still oh
yeah you know when you sit down to meditate sometimes you just can't find a Still Point and the body is just
restless and agitated oh sometimes that's so uncomfortable right
and and then the energy in the mind is what is worry and worry is essentially
worrying we're worrying you know this the spinning energy the going around and
round there's a simile that talks about water ponds and for each hindrance there is a
simile for the water for restlessness and worry it said it's like really intense wind going across
the surface of the water so there's impossible to see into the
pond the wind whips it all up there's no Stillness
so the absence of hindrance would be a clear Bond easily transparent you can
see everything going on in there it's said that greed is like adding
um like die to the water maybe a red colored dye so that the the water takes
on a kind of a it makes everything look different right the way that wanting
something sort of like the idea of rose-colored glasses right everything looks a little prettier somehow
and aversion or ill will is like water boiling bubbling you know boiling
broiling steam it's you can't look in it's hot it's dangerous you know there's
no Stillness so these are similes from the sutas from the Buddha that describe
also that kind of this energetic quality and the other kind of invitation we've
had is to see hindrances as something that is like a veil that you know if you pull the veil you
can't quite see through right so this is again this idea that it's covering
something it's hindering something so this is why in some ways actually
working with the hindrance is if you can recognize that it's there it's like
pulling the veil back it's like and and you know sort of
unhindering in a moment in a way it can be a direct path to clear seeing
so um last week we invited you guys to before
each meditation session to kind of reflect on the things that you came up with in your discussion group so there
was a discussion group which we'll have again tonight and they talked about like the things that helped them with working
with greed or Central desire and ill will and they they talked about
gratitude generosity Joy loving kindness doing going to see Arts sitting in the
park right so we invited you to just to reflect on those things and come on in
come sit with us come on in Jay um we invited people to you maybe didn't
even remember or didn't even process oh you did okay so um as a way to sort of help yourself
kind of Orient your mind in a useful kind of supportive Direction before meditating and what happened did you how
did it go Cassandra what did you notice do you mind sharing and we've got the
mic because we're if no before meditating this week to
reflect on these these things that you came up with last week did you did you reflect be every time you sat down to
meditate beforehand did you reflect in this way sort of great well it was raining like all week so I didn't really
so there was a lot of visualization going on that redirected me in my meditation
um in regards to all that okay and then I noted I did notice a lot of more hindrances the last week ah so
that's good I guess that is good that's great thank you Cassandra Gus do you want to say anything
I didn't quite do that and generally when I said uh when I start it's gonna
be kind of a surprise yeah I mean I just said as calm as I possibly can be and
start and we'll see right kind of like observing
Arts we'll see yeah we'll see we'll see well I'll just say
um that it's a way to Incline the mind in a
particular you know Orient toward a particular state so
not that you're trying to it's like meta may I be happy may you be happy we're making a wish we're invoking inviting a
connection with a state or way of being so it can be a something to play with at
some point which is when you sit down to meditate to drop to kind of drop in
Reflections that have to do with either the um Brahma vaharas or the the
um ten paramis right the Perfections patience gratitude Joy all of those
things so it's just an invitation yeah did you
yeah yeah I wanted to add something so um I do choose to meditate
where I can see a picture of the Buddha oh yeah exactly always turn myself so
that I'm actually pointing towards the Buddha I can't sit Twisted it has to be pointing towards
the Buddha and that that seems to actually quite be quite helpful yeah and that is very much of the same idea yeah
you know that's one of the things you can do which is to reflect on the Buddha before you meditate it can really be
profoundly uplifting for the heart in my experience yeah
all right so um does anybody you know have any questions
or want any clarification at this point before I move into Restless system worry more specifically
so I'm going to talk a little bit about The Wizard of Oz and how we might recognize the presence
of restlessness and worry in that context and I'm going to start by referencing
Dorothy while she was in Kansas so the way that the movie starts is it's
all around Dorothy and Toto her dog and um
there's this neighbor who's very angry because Toto goes and chases her cat the
neighbor's cat in the garden and so this neighbor um
gets is very angry and maybe mean and yeah I mean
um and so Dorothy's very preoccupied because she's afraid that this woman because she threatens to come take Toto
away in fact she does she comes and takes Toto away and so Dorothy goes back to the farm
um where her she lives with her Aunt Em and Uncle Henry and then the farm help
who all end up being characters in the movie and she's trying to get Aunt Em and
Uncle Henry to listen to her about her concerns that this neighbor is going to come take Toto away
but they are tending to some baby chicks and the the um and so they're
preoccupied with their worry about the baby chicks because the the warmer isn't
working and so they don't really stop to listen to Dorothy they dismiss her concerns
so their concerned and worried about the chicks and preoccupied Dorothy's worried about
Toto right and she feels like nobody's really listening to her and
um she doesn't you know it's like sort of this sense of I don't really belong here people aren't really listening to
me that grows in her and um and then the The Neighbor comes and
takes Toto away so she's going to take him I don't know just some
some place and so Dorothy gets very distraught Toto
escapes from the back of the basket of the bike of a neighbor and so Dorothy
actually runs away with Toto when Toto gets back so there's a lot of you know worry and
restlessness in all of this right and then when we get into The Wizard of
Oz into the Land of Oz the first
companion that Dorothy makes is the straw man and so the straw man if you it's really
interesting because you you wouldn't so much well you see him and he moved he's first
tied up so he can't move but he gets down and he's kind of like dancing and falling and all over the place like he
can't find a sense of stability in his body and
so there's a lot of physical restlessness and another interesting thing if you look at him is his emotional affect his
affect changes a lot he'll go from sort of like oh
like this you know there's just this too much energy like a huge swings of energy
so then they come you know strong man joins Dorothy they continue on the next
character that they meet is the Tin Man but after that they meet the lion
and the lion um you know he he pretends to be a bully
he jumps out from the forest we'll talk more about well actually we won't so he
he's he's um hiding he hears them come along and he
like does this massive like jump out like you know this big lion and he's like
what are you doing here and he starts to bully the Tin Man and the straw man and
sort of try tries to start a fight and says come on hit me hit me you know and
he's doing all this stuff and but then you know they're like
cowering the Tin Man and the straw man and then Toto jumps out from behind a
tree Dorothy's kind of hiding the back of the tree with a dog the Toto jumps out and Barks and so then the line goes
after the Toto oh guess who confronts the lion Dorothy does right she's going
to come out and protect her little puppy so and she gets you know quite Fierce
and she kind of slaps a little and like hits his nose you know it's not exactly
a slap in the face but it's he should definitely hit his nose and
he crumbles the lion absolutely crumbles he starts to cry why would you do that
to me you know he's just and and then he grabs his tail and he's like right like
do you remember this like he's just becomes a melty sad mush and talks about he has no courage so he's hidden behind
bravado his fear his worry right so this is another way that we see you know
restlessness and worry and one thing I like about that is it's very often that people who are worried and uncomfortable
do present sort of overcompensate or try and you know project something other
than what they're really feeling or they swing because it's really none of it's
stable when we're overdoing anything so so that's some ways that we see
restlessness somewhere in the in The Wizard of Oz but anybody else have another example that they want to share
the thoughts about that
great so I want to read you a little poem before I sort of talk from a dharmic
perspective about restlessness and worry from the thinking about these characters
right Dorothy is going to the Oz to get home she wants to find a way home
the straw man is going because he doesn't think he has a brain the Tin Man is going because he doesn't
think he has a heart and the lion is going because he doesn't have courage
so everyone is off to see the wizard to get something to be fixed because
they're not whole right okay
so for me this little moderate size poem talks about this
it's called the Grand predicament by Nick askew a fear of not belonging drives much of
what we do and how we are unknowingly it can Define the experience
of a life most of us live with an underlying sense that we are not yet enough
and assume that until we are we cannot truly belong
we assume that we must become a better version of ourselves
but we're never quite enough in this resent Relentless pursuit of belonging
we are lost to a never-ending self-improvement might we have been looking out there
when all along it had been within might we already be the version we'd
been seeking beyond the endless game of fixing what is seemingly broken
there exists a profound experience of knowing that there is no one to fix it
that we are enough as we are and that we belong without condition
yet we cannot seek and hope to find this it is nature it's as its nature is
defined us and to consume us I love us with no doubt
right it consumes Us by the lack or the absence of doubt
no one can teach us this we cannot learn this in a moment of surrender in a moment of
not seeking The Experience can be renowned nothing changes but everything
is somehow different and then everything begins its transformation Liberation peace and all that follows is the work
of interview so the way we see ourselves right
as lacking or enough so and I think that lacking drives a lot
of restlessness and worry
so in the Dharma and the teachings from the Buddha I already talked about the
simile of the pond is one way he talks about and
so it's helpful to think about what are the conditions that contribute to restlessness and worry
and what are the things that lead to the stilling of it so you know one thing that can be
helpful also is to go back to the sense of the obvious and subtle manifestations
so the obvious right or the sense of agitation the restlessness the scatteredness
you know hard to settle Focus losing distracting dropping our keys you know
and a more subtle is the Mind slipping into thought you know which is kind of drifting off right and getting lost in
thought conditions for restlessness are really
unwise attention to the thinking not recognizing drifting off right not
staying mindful of the thoughts kind of letting them lead us instead of
are being aware as we're thinking
sometimes we actually a lot of times I think this you know there's a belief
that thinking itself will lead to wisdom if I just think about this of enough if
I just figure it out but this is not the kind of the wisdom the Buddha was teaching us about this is
not what he was encouraging this analytical sort of philosophical or you
know um kind of uh conceptual thinking is not
the wisdom the Buddha is pointing us toward the wisdom that Buddha is pointing us to
is about seeing causes the conditions or the conditioned nature and how ill will
energy leads to causing harm to soften others right and what way we are with
our experience will lead to more experience
another thing is like a lot of provocative talk you know a lot of excessive discussion
and rumination with others can be dwelling on past unskillful
actions actually so just thinking over and over and over again about what what we did and what we didn't do and how
embarrassing it was or you know that is going to stir up the Waters of the Mind
Right like that pond
so when we work with restlessness it's actually one of those qualities
where on a wide birth
if you think about when you feel Restless if you think about trying to tighten in and make yourself sit still
my experience in my body is that energy gets more pronounced it's like you know
like it's like a pressure cooker so in the mind you know and with
yourself it's sort of like broadening opening up around it letting the ball
have a huge room to bounce in right does that make sense it's a real small it's
got quick things to bounce against bigger space it's going to slow down right there's more more room
um you know and again this idea of non-identification right it's it's an
experience it's an energy it's not who I am it doesn't Define me it's an experience that comes and goes so it's
really helpful to watch yourself and how you're relating to it
um and
let's see um another significant thing is striving
when we're we're trying too hard we're trying too hard to have a certain
experience or putting too much energy into our meditation practice right it
can build up or or we're not doing enough walking
meditation to balance out our sitting meditation if we're you know doing more
prolonged practice you know pent up feelings like desire
and aversion actually can lead to a feeling of restless and worry
so kind of paying attention you know in some ways I feel like so
much of our practices is about keeping ourselves in balance
you know it and there's a teacher ajan cha from and he used to kind of say to
you know students like okay they're all walking down the road and he goes to
this guy go left go left go left right and so then the person on the right starts oh I
better go no no no you go right you go right and you're right you're right it's like
we we need to be attending to our own self our own practice and what somebody
else needs to be doing at one moment is not necessarily what we need to be doing at my moment there's not always the same
answer so even if we've been told to be go left at one point actually maybe this time we
really need to go right so we have to attend to the energies in the body the
mind the heart are we you know getting enough exercise right for example did we have too much
caffeine right these can also contribute right as well as the kind of conversations in the way that we're
mindful or not
another thing that can trigger restlessness is pain and worry so it's important to kind of
know how to work wisely with physical discomfort in meditation and
um kind of you know if you're in pain and you start to get really restless it
can be really important to just kind of re um reset your posture get an extra pillow
do what you need to do you know or stand up you can stand up to meditate if that
is easier for you if that the energy is just too much so
how was that any questions too much not enough
so then here's a question normally right now what I would do is to
go into a guided meditation practice but I actually just had the thought maybe it'd be better to put you in two small
groups and let you talk a little bit first great I see heads nodding so if we could
you know it's usually kind of good to have three or four so maybe two groups um
so if you want to just turn your chairs and connect to introduce yourselves
maybe say if you've been to IMC before or been coming a long time or whatever you want to say
and then I'll give you more instructions in about a minute or two
okay you ready for the question all right so um
The Firm well I have two questions we'll start with one we'll see how it goes
um what I'd like you to do is give each person like a minute to a minute and a
half to answer the question so one person is speaking three three or
two people are listening while the person just gets to kind of talk about
the role that restlessness and worry have in their life
just how how does it show up for you how does it affect things for you and how
does it operate for you right so that's the start so
um you guys should probably take more like a good full two minutes each because they have a group of four you
guys and I'll be tuning in so if you need extra time we'll just either not do the second question or we'll figure it
out okay so maybe the person is there anybody in
your group that wants to start first raise your hand if somebody knows they great do you guys have gr oh Sage you've
got to start they pointed at you so
are you okay starting okay so great so Julie will start and Sage will start and
then just go the next person to your left would follow you all right please begin
thank you just want to check in and see if you made it all the way around does it feel like a good point to shift
to the next question great so the second question is
you know and maybe just stop and pause I'll give you a minute to reflect on this one
what beliefs do you have that support your worry
what beliefs do you have that support your worry yeah
okay so just breathe and let your mind offer whatever it wants to offer and
I'll ring the bell again in about 20 seconds and and you can begin
and just for the recording purpose I will repeat the question
what beliefs do you have that support your worry
what beliefs opinions views stories
are supporting your worry
so I've one final little invitation
to as a group pick two or more things that you want to share
when we come back together from the Reflections in your group just as a group you can all pick one or you can
come up with two together whatever you want to do but just give some thought to what was useful about this what came up
you know um and and then be hopefully somebody will
be willing to share for the rest of us so just take up a minute or two to to
brainstorm if there's anything you could do that to share
um
[Music]
oh right now
because I I used to think about things and then I one day I said
either get up and do something about it or go back to just couldn't get out again
[Music]
yeah it really is helpful because
yeah restlessness
right
organizations
that's about this yeah so you mentioned you if you look here
and sometimes but lately I haven't been checking in
with myself
I think probably just caring and having them
foreign
[Music] you feel ready okay
maybe think thank each other you can finish your sentence sage no no rush you
just thank each other and just appreciate the energy the sharing
uh oh yeah yeah thank you
[Laughter]
that's right that's right so um we'll give these guys another minute
but uh I just have to say it's so delightful to hear you all connecting
and sharing and key you know you're really engaging with the Dharma right and you're discovering I can feel the
you know the sort of oh sometimes I would occasionally adhere like a thought
or something about core beliefs or something that was you actually I think it just these great kind of insights
coming forward so there's people that will listen to this recording there's people that are watching on YouTube and
then there's each other the people that were in the other group and so I invite I invite a few shares about
sort of your takeaways what stood out for you and it doesn't have to be that
your group agreed for it with it it just was a way to get you to think and share so
if anybody's willing to pick up a mic
is it on Susan
I feel very light thank you sweetheart so I think
what we came we talked about um
antidotes to worry nice do you want to share some of those
antidotes can I share yours so if like I and Julie
talk about you know what and what should I should be an Entertainer
and then I'll know how to use this um like not being able to sleep and what to
do when you wake up in the middle of the night and other than take CBD which is
one thing um putting paper and pencil next year
bed so you can write it down and one of the things that I used to do when I worked um
if I would wake up in the middle of the night I would be thinking I'm worrying about this problem
and finally I got to the point where I decided that if I could do something
about it I would get up and do it and if not I would write it down and go back to
sleep nice beautiful and we all kind of talked a
little bit about that kind of thing beautiful Susan beautiful your group want to offer one
Solutions you know but you got to use a mic
Sage you had something you wanted to share
the one thing that really stuck out to me as part of our discussion is like we all talked about a kind of like
pervasive sense of uh worry and restlessness going throughout the life
um but I think all three of us also talked about moments of like Refuge
um and being able to like take stock of like what's actually going on and I think the takeaway for me there
is like external conditions don't matter so much as the ability to like draw on like Buddha nature or like whatever you
want to call it right so that the the pausing in the middle of the storm can
help you find the eye of the storm the the calm in the middle of it is that
right yes great Jane do you want to add a slight uh
foreign for the most part A lot of my
restlessness worries caught up with things that I think are practical
worries which on what level are true I have genuine you know really difficult situations going on
but I've had glimpses be it in Retreats or just Sunday sets or whatever where
I've Glimpse to the other side I've gotten to a place of equanimity no restlessness
and I've had raging problems I was still there yeah but have this calm like wait
that doesn't make any sense I need to be worrying I am not right so I've had glimpses of
unhooking you know the condition from the state right usually I think oh yeah I should be worrying because I'm plenty
to worry about yes you know it feels Justified and right when it's going on
but you know I've seen you know not that many but many glimpses were
regardless what's the outer state is you know I've been in a relatively uh peaceful State
thank you foreign
I was just saying that um
generally worrying seems to be kind of like a head thing right and for me I don't necessarily have a default
worrying state but stuff will have to start to happen in my body like I start to get a touch somewhere or it gets
really tense over here and that becomes my indicator to start to
become aware of there's something somewhere beautiful that is getting your
attention it hasn't gotten into your conscious brain yet but maybe you want to help it kind of arise
so that you can look at it right and um I connect that also to my practice when
I'm when I'm meditating I actually am because I put attention on the parts of
my body that are currently trying to tell me something and just try
to calm them down a little bit but generally it's
I think one can't forget the role of the body yeah in this
because generally the worrying part tends to have to be happening mostly up here yeah
yeah thank you so much yeah
so just just give yourself a quiet minute and see if anything else pops up that wants to be named or shared
just uh there's something that can be reinforcing about insights or
Reflections if you speak them so just uh you know there's something
there that's valuable to you that wants to be spoken even if you've already spoken feel free to pick up the mic
um I think one thing I'm reflecting on is uh kind of like uh
worry and restlessness around um
like work and and not really or just a typical day I think is a theme
that we all talked about in our group of um contributing on a typical day
and not knowing if we're doing good enough
yeah that's that's so important there's like um what do you believe about yourself or what you're supposed to be
doing that contributes to restlessness worry like I heard the word Perfection or being good enough
all right that it's not okay to make mistakes or you know that it's it's not
productive to be quiet and still and not do anything for periods of time you know these are all beliefs that can
impact the experience also what you're doing for work
you know sometimes what you have to be doing is is busy Restless worry work in
a way and so by doing that work you start to condition that energy in your body
does that make sense Stephen and is that speaking to what you're talking about
I also heard you say um you know it's okay for me to say this that you know we need to be productive
right did you say something about that also like it's good too I found the
whole conversation very uh I feel very harmonious after having the
conversation because I feel like yes there is that urge are we are we
doing that but then um while I was sitting and talking with them I just was thinking about
um it's just human nature yeah and it didn't feel like that big of a deal oh I
love it so I feel like I have some insight around uh
you know I mean even if you're unemployed or or
going through it it just yeah I yeah
it's beautiful thank you so shall we do a guided raft meditation
great so to start
I'll walk you through the raft process which is our recognize a allow
f feel it T tease it apart and and the less Double
T is Trust so I'll guide you through that but that's the step by step it's sort of
it's just walking through a you know mindfulness really a way to help yourself with it and
at any point in the process you may be done whatever you identify it may resolve and
you just don't have a lot more to think about and that's fine so don't feel like you have to make
things up or or figure things out right so
um so the the way we'll start
is I'm going to drop in a question or invite you to drop in a question into
your being and just open up to see what what
happens what what kind of a response do you get and the practice the invitation is to
connect with something connected to restlessness and worry in your experience but you know you don't have to if
something else comes up it's okay to work with that too
but please make sure whatever you choose to practice with is not something that will
be overwhelming it's kind of too big
for you to do in this setting or at this time and
so look for something that's you know okay okay to be with and and if you think it's going to be
okay and it turns out not to be it's okay to stop it's okay to stand up it's
okay to restart right so giving yourself permission to not be
trapped in some practice and pushing yourself through something but keep tuning in to what's happening
for you okay so here's your here's the little question to drop in
it's kind of a funny question in a way what what should I be worried about
right now what should I be worried about right now
so just let let some things Bubble Up and like notice what's there
and see if there's something that that again feels right size
that you might be able to recognize and allow and feel right
I'll just give you about a minute of Silence to kind of settle
and bring to mind whatever this thing is that you you quote unquote should be worrying about
right now
so the first part of the practice is this recognition
and I imagine this is a little bit like um
being able to stop and acknowledge something or a person or a situation
like being able to turn toward it and name it in some way like
okay I recognize this
situation this feeling this fear
sort of in a way that it knows it's being seen it's the Turning toward
so much of you know the difficulties in life we leave even some of the joys kind
of shove off to the side right and so what is it to turn right
toward it and as you name it and recognize it
and you can sense it feels seen we move to a which is the invitation to
see if we can allow it to be in our presence
I'm just noticing if there is permission an ability to allow it to exist it's
already here can we give it some space
not for it not against it just kind of allowing
and if that feels impossible and there's a lot of resistance
recognize the resistance say oh okay the resistance is more
dominant right now not wanting this so name the resistance and then shift and
focus on the resistance and allowing it to be there
and maybe you can't be completely allowing but is there enough allowance
to move and follow whatever this is into the body
to sort of say okay this is the idea this is the experience this is the thing I'm recognizing now can I follow the
vibrations into the body and feel where
this situation lives in my body
how it affects my body
and you may be a very uh sensory somatic person so you're very
strong sense of the sensations the pressure the spaciousness or the
vibratory and you also might be more of a visual person so it might be more like
oh it feels big it's black it has a color it has a shape
in whatever way you can find it and feel it and describe it and be with it so
find and feel in the body in whatever way your mind
can find and feel it but it's connected to your direct experience
it's not a conceptual thing in the body it's a felt thing
being curious noticing how does it respond to being
felt
and how am I feeling it you know there's this energy of
firmness or forcefulness and then there's an energy of receptivity
so if we're too forceful it's like a string that's too tight on a harp and it
doesn't really sing and if we're overly slack it doesn't
really even vibrate depending that right way
of feeling tuning in and being with
at some point whenever you're ready
will move to the teasing apart and there's no rush here you take your
time or you move on whatever you're ready for
for me when we move to teasing apart find it very useful to imagine
a very large round table
but your table could be small too if you want it to be small with as many chairs as are needed
as space as big as it needs to be
and we want to invite each thing connected to this whatever we're recognizing
the thing itself what we've named to have a seat
and then if we had resistance we could let that have a seat at this
table too
if we connected with sadness or other emotions we can invite the emotions to have their
own seat at the table
and the chairs can be relative to the weight or size or need of each piece
our experience is a composite many things coming together
memories expectations fears hopes
beliefs so without digging
more like just softening and allowing whatever pieces are clear
to you to have a seat
notice if you need more space in your room allowing a bigger perspective more
distance sort of looking over all of this
and as you see it what stands out to you
what are you noticing
one practitioner recently said to me I realized
the things that had the biggest seed at the table were really from her past her
memories her history and the thing that she named that was going on was really quite small and
insignificant in relationship to the history that all that past energy and Karma was
getting transferred onto What's Happening Here and Now
and you could continue or if you're ready the next part of the practice
is to connect with a feeling of trust
what does trust feel like for me there's a sense of letting go
there's nothing to protect
I feel like I can trust mindfulness wisdom
sometimes if it's a difficult thing I trust that it will change
so what about the situation or your practice can help you find a
sense of trust in relationship to what's going on for you
there's something quite nourishing about resting in this way
so if you can connect with a little more ease
a little bit more sense of letting go a little more understanding that wow
this is really not me this is doesn't Define me
this is about much more than just me it's a history it's a story
it's imagination
and like like you would lay back on a cozy raft in a warm body of water on a
calm day with a warm sun let's see if you can allow yourself to
be nourished
so we start with recognizing and then we invite ourselves to allow
the experience to be there it's already here
we feel it in our body we move out of conceptual into the direct experience
we could return to sort of the whole thing and try and imagine letting each part have its own
place teasing it apart and if it's accessible
moving into a space of trusting trusting awareness trusting the practice trusting
whatever insights have been revealed
this is you know this raft practice is a way to be with restlessness and worry
without trying to fix it right just to be with it see it for what it is
for anything really the raft works
there's a lot of Stillness here so I hesitate to keep talking you know
but um if someone wants to share or ask a
question this is a good time to do it if not you can stay kind of Stillness
and I'll just say a few more things as we come to a close
but if there's any area you're confused about with the practice or
anything that like stood out to you about how it was a practice in this way
be happy to hear from you
great thank you Gus I was just thinking that for me
it's not going to happen sequentially very quickly it happens over time and just
it's the how long does it take till you get to recognize the recognize this for a while
and so on and so forth right it's beautiful yeah yeah so there's no time crunch here yeah
thank you and it doesn't have to go you know it might just be enough just
recognizing sometimes is all we can do or all that's needed
um I'd say that I've been meditating off and on for I don't know 15 years I've never gotten
intentionally gotten past allow maybe maybe I have gone through
all of these but not with intention um I've I've always been trained or I
believe that you're supposed to recognize it and like you were just saying Let It Go um
so I've been skipping steps this is like mind-blowing to me so I
just really appreciate this thank you yeah so you know there is a
lot of emphasis on just kind of allowing but if something is stuck
if something keeps coming up there's it's asking to be understood to be seen
there's a message there's something there so there's a real delicate balance
between kind of meeting seeing and meeting what's happening allowing its space
and really in a way can we do this that its own unfolding happens I just had
this image of you know the the tea that you put in the water that's like a flower you know you don't pull the
leaves apart the petals apart you gotta let it open like the story of somebody trying to help the butterfly out of a
cocoon so there is this process of whole sustaining attention long enough
and allowing something to unfold and and to not get re-immeshed with it
and also to like see it with Wonder like oh wow there's all these components and
they're maybe they're shy maybe some of the pieces don't stand out right away
maybe it takes a while for them to be willing maybe you just know there's something else but you don't know what it is so you just have a chair for it
right so there is a balance with this overdoing
and under doing thank you so much
anybody else wanna okay so I'll just um
share just a couple little quickie things
it can be helpful to reflect on your purpose for practice Inspire and support continuing to
practice what's the purpose of recognizing the hindrances for you
you know not just to get rid of them but to learn to see
notice when restlessness and worry is not
present is not present notice when it's not there too
and that's something to be equally curious about what are the conditions that supported
your being at ease and I said this in the meditation but
with the trust part right calm and Tranquility can be so nourishing
so deeply nourishing and it's very easy
to dismiss them because there's something more important I need to worry about or do
so be curious about the moments and and spaces where there is calm Tranquility
ease trust faith and let it let it too and like on you
know open up its blossoms be nourished by it
so homework invitations the the handouts aren't numbered in the order we're using
them but you know it's all there and they're also on Audio Dharma they're
they're posted there as well this week kind of the invitation is to
experiment with the ways you can live your life that lessen
restlessness and worry from arising you know what helps lessen it
might be how you're talking to yourself it might be you know how much
Doom scrolling you do and look at things like exercise sleep
caffeine nutrition right and living an ethical life
that's huge but what what can you find what can you
discover about what leads to more ease less restlessness and less worry
thank you for your practice maybe be a benefit for many beings everywhere
have a good night thank you