great so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
and um delighted to feel your presence whatever your time zone it's the present
moment yay we're sharing this present moment
this illusion of time in together how
how great is that so so for the theme
um of this evening I want to talk about
um or invite us to practice with kindness kindness towards ourselves compassion
towards ourselves with impermanence befriending impermanence
sometimes impermanence is on our side when
say the short term there's something that's troubles us maybe something that you
know you had a meeting that didn't go well or something it just you know you've got a parking ticket again the
short term the short terms like ah there's an out but if you take the
long-term view the longer term Horizon with impermanence to changing all the
time the nature of of Our Lives changing all the time in
the big picture this thing that perhaps happened today or last week or the past
month isn't the big pictures it shifts and changes it's not we can have a
larger perspective so even though of course holding this with compassion but but it is impermanent
um so there's some Reflections having to do with that so bringing impermanence long long term View and
kindness compassion and Equanimity so well we'll practice together and see
what arises sounds like a lot a tall order but you know we'll just take our time together and explore
explore our hearts and and see what what is um supportive so
so okay with that let's uh let's begin together let's begin
let's settle into our seat if you need to shift and move
into a comfortable position
and arriving in this body In This Moment In Time
letting the breath be received in the abdomen take the breath be breathed
breath the entirety of being breath the pause
the entirety of the Opera and the pause
taking some time to befriend the in-breath pauses and the out breath in your own time
letting them extend a little bit slowing down
of your thoughts are arising still thinking about what happened before
planning for the next thing it's okay it's all right
oh sweet dear heart let's put down let's put it all down and
just be here and give our heart fully to this just to
this right here this breath
this breath let it be felt received in its fullness like a
cherry blossom in the spring
fresh
full
impermanently grow glorious
this breath
and now as we continue to be embodied to feel the breath in the
body in the abdomen receiving the breath in breath the out
breath it's impermanent glorious breath
like a cherry blossom in the spring
let's turn let us open our hearts to appreciating
appreciating ourselves
we're doing our best doing our best
showing up and every moment is in this life as best as we're able to
we appreciate that we are doing our best given all the causes and conditions
many most of them most of them out of our control
so a little Within our sphere of influence
doing our best Within that's fear
doing our best within the causes and conditions
then again be not trying to pick fights with ourselves or
judging ourselves self-judgment
staying that if things could have been different or could be different they would have been given everything that
came before so many
factors and forces
and resting with this not thinking about it but resting with it
letting ourselves breathe with it
now if you like if there is something that perhaps there is a little bit of an
ouch from something recent today yesterday this past week
not the biggest ouch not the biggest thing but something that's more manageable to practice with right
now
and acknowledging the ouch with kindness towards yourself
maybe it didn't turn out as well as hoped but you did your best
can you have kindness appreciation you tried
and letting go of thinking about it and just feeling into
kindness Goodwill for yourself for this ouch with this ouch
and appreciating your own goodness your own wholeheartedness
your values your efforts
and within this sphere of kindness acknowledging that
yeah didn't go
this was challenging it goes well as hoped or possible and it's okay
it's okay Elisha's like this it's okay
and we have stability equanimity equipoise
and whole things just as they are just as they've been with kindness
and if we could imagine impermanentness
as a friend as as an angel as of impermanence
ate a visit and said oh dear one things change
I'm the angel of impermanence things shift always it's just the way things are
you can put this down you can let go and forgive yourself
you can forgive the causes and conditions
perhaps learn there's something to be learned
without self-judgment there's need to make amends do that
maybe not maybe it's just acknowledging
care learning and letting go
releasing releasing releasing
angel of impermanence kindly invites you to release
let go
knowledgeing with kindness compassion letting go
but the support of the angel of impermanence that permeates our lives our human lives
may be kind accepting loving towards this person who
is me
knowing their best
who has limitations like anyone else
it's okay part of Being Human
foreign
and can we extend this Goodwill others maybe others we've interacted
with or been entangled with they too are doing their best
and we offered them kindness good will appreciation they too have so many
causes and conditions
or how they act or
show up in the world wishing them well
generosity of heart
bearing this generosity of spirit
is Goodwill with others
expanding the circle
people we have interacted with directly and indirectly impacted
many circles have shame
so many beings who directly and directly impact us we
impact them wishing them well
We're Not So Different we're all doing our best
with what we have the causes and conditions of this poorly
existence and offering our goodness
the goodness of our practice the Merit
the wholesomeness of our practice to all beings everywhere May our practice be a cause and
condition or our own waking up freedom from sorrow suffering cultivation of
kindness compassion wisdom may we be free and may all beings
everywhere too be free
thanks everyone thank you so much for your practice
ah so we explore it we practiced with first
coming embodied with our body and breath being within higher brain but outbreak
connecting settling and then we open to
appreciating ourselves sense of appreciation
kindness Goodwill for ourselves for um having done our best and maybe
with something that that there might be a little bit of ouch with so when we when goodness when
kindness meets the outfit becomes compassion so practicing compassion for
maybe a tiny ouch that has happened recently and acknowledging that we've done our
best um letting there be forgiveness letting there be an appreciation of goodness and
then extending your kindness forgiveness not just to ourselves but to someone else maybe renter interacted with them
entangled with them and then spreading out to everyone and oh yes and there was the uh there
was an invitation to imagine impermanence as an angel angel of impermanence
Letting Go inviting us to let go well that was a new element tonight we explored we experimented with
letting go it's all impermanent we learn the lessons we make amends if needed and
then we don't we don't hold on we don't hang on we let go we open our hands our
fist so with that I'd like to invite us to to
engage in a small group together and an
Explorer you're welcome to offer one nugget about your practice how this
practice was for you um how it went or you can be silent to
offer your silent compassionate presence if you like
and we only share from our own experience we
offer a little bit a little nugget perhaps where again silence we don't ask questions to try to give advice and
someone asked last time if you notice somebody else's is offering advice or asking questions it's okay to say hey
we're not supposed to do that we're supposed to just speak from Owen exp own experiment experience just eye
statements please offering safety to one another as much as possible
and um let's go alphabetical order and um
foreign Let The Prompt be something like
um yeah with this practice you know how maybe specifically with the angel of
impermanence if you lean into that what does it feel does it support you to to
lean into letting go to letting to letting be not attaching to see
impermanences oh yes as as as a support as as an angel as an advisor as an
advisor of impermanence so maybe exploring that aspect or any
other aspect you wish I'm creating the breakout rooms and
again take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind and
let's go in alphabetical order and here we go opening the rooms now
take care okay all the rooms are closed
everybody's back I do see some Smiles they make me happy oh let me turn to
turn on the recording there we go great and welcome back everyone so we have uh
some time for any questions Reflections if you haven't spoken in the um large
group for a while I would like to invite you to pull forward if you've spoken
recently pull back a little bit so you can also type in chat if there are any
Reflections aha moments questions comments what was this like for you love
to hear from you
Ali please hi Nikki thank you uh for the practice
I've always I mean I came to the practice because of the wisdom aspect of it you know those two wings of the bird
no I'm still heavy on that so that's why I came you know to the loving kindness
happy hour because I know that is the ultimate wisdom just to have that one and uh so having said that as a
background when you were talking about the throwing the impermanence and I said it's like a glad you know I said that
right something I can just you know chew on and just like just turn it around in the wine and stuff but I was able to see
that as it's like let that go you know I mean that's not why uh even I mean but I
was glad they threw that in there uh put that in there uh but how
still am and this will be okay this is okay too I mean loving the wisdom part I mean that's like
uh but uh yeah that's that's where I am and
that's what came up for me it was interesting that I saw all right she's talking about that uh that's it thank you yeah yeah yeah
thank you Ellie I appreciate what you brought in and and actually before you mute yourself years uh
um well you can unmute if you want um so so so what I heard you say was was given
that you're uh and many people you know lean into the wisdom aspect a lot more
but as you said yeah wisdom and compassion are the two wings of the birds if you have mostly wisdom and you
don't have compassion the bird is Not Gonna Fly it's going to go go around and around in circles so uh so the
compassion aspect the the practice of the heart are so important and wisdom
arises actually I have seen wisdom arise just doing the hard practices wisdom
arises and and ultimately at some point uh if you're just doing wisdom
compassion might arise at the very end when you see emptiness but anyway but the whole path could be pretty bumpy
without without kindness and we're just doing wisdom but uh and and I also heard you say when I brought in impermanence
like oh yes and yet and yet you know maybe the way I heard it was the sense
of wanting to think about it impermanence but it's actually not a
something to think about and you know that it's really something to relate to in our hearts it is part of the it's
it's a um you know to to relate to the wisdom of
impermanence in a hard-based way because usually we grieve impermanence that's the the the the twist I wanted to bring
in tonight we usually grieve impermanence like oh it's impermanent and I want it to stay it's not like but
I was kind of playing a little you know Aikido like shifting like oh here's the
angel of impermanence is telling us to let go it's okay to forgive it's okay to
be kind it's okay to let it put it down so that's how I was reframing it
um so just putting a little more explanation around that yeah
yeah thank you Ellie and anything else or does it feel complete give me an okay if he feels complete yeah it feels
complete great thank you yep yep and I saw Erica please
hi Nikki how are you I'm well thank you good so I have a question because I
personally have said this in in groups before impermanence is one of my North Stars I really appreciate knowing that
everything changes and I guess so the funky stuff it's gonna get better and the good stuff you don't grasp because
it's just gonna do the back and forth but when you start talking about the angel of impermanence and sort of put
this body to it I'm a little confused so can you can you talk about what that is
to you and what an angel of impermanence means yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah thank you thanks for that and I
appreciate also what you brought in about the way you've been practicing with it which is oh yeah it's it's
impermanence you know when when things are challenging It's Gonna Change it's like the saying about the weather in
London if you don't like the weather wait five minutes because it's Gonna Change um and if it's something good enjoy it
shaded but don't hang on to it because things are impermanent of course love it I really enjoy it it's not like oh don't
push it away so and then you're well curious or confused like what's this
embodiment that you're bringing as as an angel so so it's it's to bring um the idea the invitation is is to
bring some Grace to it because I love their attitude you have to uh impermanence Erica which already has a
sense of Grace but one I want to invite us to feel some Grace about empowerment it's not just about how I'm like oh yeah
impermanence one of the three marks of existence yeah these Buddhists talk about everything being impermanent yeah
whatever like no it's actually it's the grace of impermanence oh wow this is the
way things are and it's there's a Grace to us that's what I'm inviting when I bring the word Angels kind of bringing
some Grace or to shift our relationship to impermanence that's what I'm trying
to do does that make sense yeah thank you I love the word Grace so that's that's lovely yeah great thank you
thanks for that question it helps me give a little more Nuance to to what I
was trying to invite us to to explore yeah thank you any other Reflections now
if you have spoken recently you are invited to speak since we've had a round Marianne
I just want to say to you uh you're so skillful of a facilitator and bringing
people to the front that I just have to help by by doing that it's I'm so admire
how you do it um and thank you
um for me the an angel is also a symbol of protection
and so that makes impermanence easier to
uh come to accept or confront or yeah
except maybe yeah those are one it was a wonderful pairing for me a beautiful
thank you Marion thank you so much for your kind kind words and and yay I love
this this pairing that you just shared in this Angel has a sense of protection as a sense of safety a sense goodness
it's and to bring that together and exploring it in that that dimensionality
that that door that can open in that way with with impermanence oh
that's deep that's very interesting yeah I'm gonna sit more with that thank
you Marion thanks so much for bringing that in that's lovely yeah
beautiful anything else to feel complete
the air fellow Travelers practitioners and the chat is open as well yes it is
Malaya I really liked the um when you were
seeing Angel of impermanence because it also made me think of with all the
change happening that there's a caring presence
um yeah yeah beautiful
oh yeah it's the intertwining of of loving kind so then permanence what you
named the sense of care yeah that's not just dropped but yeah
that's beautiful thank you for for saying that the lights light something up in me beautiful
thank you Malaya wow thank you all for your practice this
is so hard heartwarming and just wow it's the first time we're relating to
bring permanent springing permanence into Happy Hour in this particular way and I I have trust they will open more
more possibilities and more ways to explore it for each of us individually
and collectively so thank you so much for your practice dear ones thank you friends may you be well may you be happy
may we all be free [Music]
thank