I as you have a moment
maybe um so I know you guys have been here a few times Corey you've had more practice in the past have you been to IMC this is
your first time have you done any meditation um before of different of any kind
of great perfect glad you're here and your name is Kevin right okay
and um I'm just really bad with names I know you're fake Michael Michael's been here hi Roseanne
good to see you welcome if you feel like you want to
join the circle feel free you can also stay right where you are yeah so
maybe since we're a small group we can just start with names um
Tanya has already introduced herself a little bit my name is Dawn Dawn Neil
and maybe just go around Nathan
Michael Michael Evan Kevin
hi Debbie welcome all of you yeah and we have Sally managing thank you Sally and
Richard recording yeah and for those of you who haven't been
here before there are two bathrooms three bathrooms in the back over there so please feel free to get up if you
need to unveil yourself there's also water over
there and so is it um is our custom to take off
our masks when teaching it makes it a little bit easier for people but first before I do that I want to
make sure there's nobody that has concerns about being in a space with somebody unmasked we do have fans going
but we have filters blue air filter is going
is anybody uncomfortable that one isn't working but um all of the
others in the room are we have several standalones and then we
also have a HEPA filtration system that is going that has sterilization in it
that is running right now right
so if we do unmask it will just be the teacher's unmasked everyone else in the group will stay masked that's how we
keep it safe so could we get an opt-in if people are
okay with the two of us being unmasked
so welcome I'll get us started um and I also want to welcome people on
YouTube I have some friends watching right now glad you're there
and I know there's some other people who would you know communicated with IMC about attending YouTube so
um Richard will be checking the chat for questions at specific times and writing
the questions down and we'll try and answer them as we can for those folks on YouTube
um so I think one thing that is really
important for me to acknowledge about the space is that um Insight Meditation
Center and everything that's offered here is I'm all part of a result of
generosity and that this space um is exists because of generosity
the teachings exist because of generosity the maintenance of the place exists because
of volunteers it's all volunteer and there's no such thing as you know
membership application you're a member if you want to be and
it's really it's really your choice to engage in the center as much as you wish
so we're all the caretakers of the space it belongs to all of us
another thing that feels important to say for people um often hi come on in
is that um the series that Don and I are are teaching it's a series that's taught in
a particular way in a particular order that's um
kind of tradition for the Western vipassana Insight Meditation community
and um we it is you know meditation comes from
Buddhism and other kinds of you know I mean there's a lot of traditions that
have meditation in some form or prayer or another
um but we'll talk some about Buddhism but not a lot you don't have to be Buddhist
to be here or to practice meditation so I say that because some people find
it very helpful to know you don't need to leave any of your beliefs or practices outside of the space you can
bring them keep them and utilize the meditation practice in a way that works
for you
medic meditation can be engaged with without Buddhism but Buddhism can't be
engaged with without meditation and kind of a simple
simple way to talk about what meditation is one one I'll give you a few things but
just one simple thing to start is it's about having intimacy
with our experience with our lives it's about kind of being connected to
and aware of rather than sort of the the analytical thinking about our lives
it's a much more of a direct experience meditation and the practice
it's about coming into intimacy direct connection with our present moment
experience which is most easily found through our senses
touch smell sight Sensations in the body hearing sound
you know sort of helping us just right now even as I say that
orienting toward these experiences of feeling hearing sensing
breathing seeing can you notice anything shifting in
yourself as you bring more awareness into those
experiences
for me I do and it does feel something a little bit simpler and more
intimate with myself and even with you right now
another word that I like um to use to talk about
mindfulness practice meditation um it's about Choice having choice
helping us be aware in a way that
um maybe less of an automatic pilot way of being in the world
more choiceful as a result also it's maybe another way is to think
about the difference between responding to something
versus reacting in this practice
we're learning how to be with and respond to life instead of react
and by reaction I don't just mean externally
I mean even reacting to our internal experiences
the dialogue the judgments the thoughts the images the memories
all the things that happen in our mind
when we're reactive to them we can get carried away carried Downstream carried into a movie
in our movie starring guess who
and um it's just creates this constant intensity of reaction
having rehearsal conversations reaction conversations all of this stuff
that tends to make our lives a little bit more
I don't know difficult actually I think it's complicated
one other thing I'll say um is that there's a in Buddhism and in
this practice there's an invitation toward non-harming and this is also connected to this idea
of non-reactivity that are you know one of the aspirations of the the Buddha in this practice is to
not harm ourselves not harm others and not harm both
so never we never leave out the other and we never leave out ourselves it's always
you know our goal is not to harm not to harm
and so that's just sort of like to help you Orient toward why why we're doing this
practice you know what we're hoping to help you experience Don is
going to talk about how to take care of our body and postures and things for
sitting meditation thank you Tanya
yes so non-harming begins at home and this is home
so I'm going to go through three of the four major postures the four postures
associated with meditation classically in the Buddha's teachings are sitting
standing walking and lying down we're going to cover walking meditation
in a lot more detail in a few weeks I'm going to go through the other three because those are one of those three or
possibly more than one are going to be how you will spend your time meditating
so I'll start with a few basic principles whether you're sitting
standing or lying down there's a principle of balance
we're always looking for a balance between relaxation and alertness
so comfort and energy relaxation and alertness the second principle is that you should
be able to breathe easily so that means having a posture that
allows your chest and your lungs to be open regardless of anything else about it
and the third is a sense of softness
so you can soften your eyes soften your tongue
soften your belly all of those things promote a parasympathetic relaxation response
through the whole body and that's very helpful to meditation
and then there's a few details with sort of your
eyes that I'll show you probably in profile as well as up front
first is when you soften your eyes what I mean by that is to let the world come
to you so right now all of you most of you are looking at me
if you were to relax your gaze and can allow the whole room to be in your gaze
without any Central Point in it that's a soft gaze
so the peripheral is as important as the center you're not hard focused on anything
you might be able to feel it a little bit in your face or behind your eyes the difference it makes just to do that
so many of us spend all day glaring at a screen right
right so I'm going to show you in a chair first you can kind of see me now I'll just
show a little bit here a base that's really important so no matter how you're sitting having your
feet connected to the Earth or the cushion in some way so that's more helpful than this or this
or the you know if you can manage it so that can require props these chairs
don't work for all sizes of people we have a lot of cushions I'll show you where they are in a few minutes
the second principle is to have your spine aligned
so I'm going to show you from the front first one way to kind of start to get your spine aligned and this is an old
zen trick is to rock back and forth a little bit left to right on your hip points
and then find Center like the weight evenly distributed between your two
buttocks and then forward and back just a little bit like your a pendulum
and again you'll find Center and then the ears roughly aligned over
the shoulders and you can imagine a string coming from the top of your head upward to the sky
ever such a slight chin tilt and I'll show you from the side as well
so I'm not going to use the cushions for the moment but the idea here is that you want your
hips a little bit higher than your knees and that may take some cushion adjustment
and for those of us with short legs it's going to be different than those of us with long legs Etc you don't want too
much pressure here I actually fainted once from that so you know be careful
and you can use as many cushions as you need to behind your lower back or under
your feet to kind of adjust but the basic principle is to have a
natural curve in your lumbar spine here and in your cervical spine
so um meditating like this we're like this it's going to give you
neck problems and headaches okay I'm exaggerating of course but again the
thread up from the top of the skull crown of the head chin tuck just a
little eye is soft down at a 45 degree angle
and then closing the eyes your hands can be natural on your lap
you can put them on a cushion as I have them now you can put them on each other but to choose a way that feels restful
many of us and chairs find it's helpful to have a cushion or two behind the lumbar spine especially if you've got
back problems but it's often helpful to have the upper spine separate from the chair
and can see there might be ever such a slight lift in the chest too not to
torque your upper back but just to allow he can feel like an absence of slump if
you take a deep breath you can feel that your lungs can fill easily and that's super helpful
last note here is that the mouth you it's hard and masks sorry if you open
your eyes I open your jaws as if you're gonna yawn a little bit
and float your lips together
your teeth can either be just barely touching or not even touching and then
the tip of the tongue can rest behind the teeth the top of the mouth the
palate and relax the rest of the tongue
and that will provoke a relaxation response as well when your eyes are closed you can either
leave them at that 45 degree angle or slightly almost like you're looking back
at yourself I think it was almost looking down at my own heart just a little don't strain anything
but that relaxes the eyes and the optical nerve the whole nervous system
so those are the basics I'm going to show you on a cushion and a bench now
so hopefully we can adjust the camera so that it's
easy for the people on YouTube to see so I don't sit on a bench very often
I'll just be very honest about that so you're not going to see the best bench sitting
but the idea here again is that the hips are higher than the
knees you're stable right and you can take a cushion in either one
of these or one of these little ones if your hands don't rest comfortably
like this and this for many people is a very stable posture and it's helpful for a
lot of people with back problems actually my preferred version
is what is called in Zen circles Cesar so you take yours off Foo that's this
little round cushion between your legs and you sit on it
and this just works better for my body you can stack other cushions underneath
it if it's not tall enough for you and that'll work fine
so there and then
the last one I'm going to show frontally
if I can keep my microphone on my ear excuse me
so the last style of sitting that is accessible to most of us is called
either Taylor style or Burmese style and it is sitting one leg in front of
the other like this if your knees do not touch the ground you can use those little back support
cushions to support them if your knees really don't touch the
ground I suggest using more than one zafu underneath and getting higher or
you can put it on its end like this and sit
but again the principle is that your hips should be higher than your knees
and this helps prevent all kinds of hip issues hip strain knee strain
there are tricks to getting in and out
placing you want to avoid torquing your knees in this process
so that's the basics there are also Lotus and half Lotus position
my body doesn't do them anymore so I'm not going to demonstrate them but there are plenty of examples online
particularly in yoga there it is yoga poses
so those are the basics of posture
and if any of you recognized during that that you need extra support you can dash
out and get yourself a support cushion right around on the other side of the skull thank you Don
it's a lot to take in right [Music] um and very very nicely shared thank you
so I'm going to take a little bit of time to talk about the first sort of we teach mindfulness
meditation in a progressive order and so the first week we teach about
mindfulness of breathing next week we'll teach about mindfulness of body the third week mindfulness of
emotions the fourth week mindfulness of thinking and then the fifth week will be
mindfulness and daily life and open awareness practice and so
you know does that mean I'm asking you to sit here tonight and not have
emotions thoughts um or have Body Sensations no it not at
all you're going to have all these things what I want to invite you to do tonight
and for this week because it it builds it's like you know building connection
with your breath this week like befriending your breath this week like bringing it with you everywhere you go
like really getting to know breathing and and then next week we'll do that
with the body and sort of kind of taking time like going to tea with somebody and getting
to know them better right sort of just spending time with being aware of your
breathing and so it's more of a preferencing your
awareness toward the breathing this practice this
week right this part and the thing about the breathing and
the reason we start with breathing there's a few reasons one is that um
it's very helpful to pay attention to something that's changing that has a rhythm
and everything is changing but the breath changes you know there's this kind of constant flow of in and out
and it can be felt a lot in many ways in the body right
and we want kind of you know this idea of non-reactivity that we're trying to grow
in meditation it's it's helpful to stay oriented
right it's easy to get lost in our experience and our thinking and so we talk about sort of having a an
anchor in our meditation or a tether for a meditation
and and we're we're what we're gonna do this week is practice using breath in
that way if it's accessible to you sort of like
you know the idea of an anchor is it kind of helps you not drift out to sea right
um the idea of a tether like sort of something that holds you you know holds
you in close so you stay oriented right
um so we use these weird words like object of attention or your primary ink or
object of attention is really just sort of what are you paying attention to what
is what is primary in your awareness anchor is referencing this idea of
something that helps you stay connected to the present moment as I was mentioning earlier the sensations right
seeing hearing sounding touching you know feeling these things are happening
here and and are experienceable easily you know and so
the breath is one of those things that can help us stay more connected to the present moment
so we start with a breath
if you have difficulty being aware of breathing
um you know it's not a problem if you can't really be aware of your breathing very
well so just know that and you can probably the easiest thing
is just the alternate for right now would just be to be aware of your hand or Your Body Sensations use use use
something in your physical experience instead if somehow the breathing is hard
for you but ideally we practice with the breath this week and then next week we shift to
the body and we grow and expand again this is not to say you won't have everything else happening
I just want to invite you now also to just answer silently in your own mind
why do you want to learn how to meditate why are you here
let's see what answer comes up for you
and whatever reason it is you know it's wonderful reason you're here we're glad
you're here and
see if you can hold it close but loosely
sometimes if we get too attached to what we think is going to happen for us
we we get focused on trying to make something happen instead of experiencing
what's happening
so bringing a sense of curiosity and remembering this idea of
non-reactivity like how can I just become like you know how naturalist you
know what a naturalist is somebody like who's a scientist and they
go into nature usually nature could be you know and
they sit down and they try not to interfere with what's happening
they try and just observe just to learn to take it in to to become
more aware and so can we become naturalists be curious about our own experience our own
meditation our own breath our own trouble having awareness of breathing even can we be
curious and just sort of like we don't need to judge it
we don't need to change it we want to learn we want to be open and curious and
staying connected to what are we seeing what is happening
you know it's said in the Buddhist teaching in the major manikaya is one of the canons of the Buddha's stories and
discourses and it says the purpose of meditation in which we consciously develop
mindfulness and discernment is to master and understand the skillful
use of the Mind so we're learning about our minds
we're learning how to be with our mind how to direct our attention
so Don said something incredibly important when she started talking about
um this you know learning how to take care of ourselves
at home and a home is in the body right so when we meditate we are coming home
or bringing our awareness to our home and so our body is really we're served
well if our body is comfortable now if we're too comfortable we'll
probably fall asleep so that's why we work on this kind of
combination of alert but relaxed so it's finding the right balance and
sometimes sometimes we have to be more relaxed
because we're emotionally so tense so our mind is so busy so you know your
posture might change bit from time to time right you might need to
sit on the floor sometimes sit on the chair another time you know
but coming into this space into inhabiting your body
that's how we start and our bodies know how to breathe
we don't have to make ourselves breathe we get to just watch
what happens and so we're going to move into a guided
meditation here as I kind of am talking we're I'm already sort of starting in
that way so feeling your bodies finding that
posture remembering maybe some of these things that Don taught us so beautifully
like oh the softening you know oh letting the eyes oh just
sort of ah receive right and then drop down
in a 45 degree angle and if you're comfortable closing your eyes
and feeling that lift from the top of the head
feeling that there's a little bit of a curve in the small of the back and behind your neck
letting your hands rest comfortably
and this idea of opening the chest so for me I actually literally like to lift
my shoulders up and roll my elbows back toward each other when I sit down just actually kind
of a counter stretch to what we typically are doing in our lives with phones and computers and
driving and then just press the elbows down to your side and
kind of rest your hands again
and here we are we get to witness a breath
all we need to do is it's very simple but maybe not always easy
and just to be here in this room in this moment
in this body with a breath just one breath at a time
don't worry about how many breaths you know or how long just ah right here
[Applause]
and I find it helpful to be kind of clear with myself
to be clear with the mind okay this is a period of meditation
may my mind and body align with my awareness
and come here into this moment and help me be aware of breathing
can I give myself permission to not need to do anything else right now
maybe to tell myself that it's okay if thoughts or things come up
to bow to them and say yes I'll come back to you
if it's possible for right now can I be with breathing
giving ourselves permission to be
to receive our experience not having to make anything happen you don't need to have any particular
experience just be intimate with your experience as
it unfolds here and allow the breath to sort of be in
the center of it all
and during this meditation period I'm going to point you to pay attention
to different aspects of breathing just to orient you just to help you
it's not that you have to do all of these things it's just to help you connect more fully
so you might start by noticing the feeling of the breath on the nostrils
and what is there to feel here with the nostrils can you notice the feeling of
the breath kind of touching the inside of the nose
noticing the difference between the feeling of the inhale and the exhale
you might notice it's a little bit more less less clear with the masks on but
you you can still feel the difference in the temperature of the breath on the inhale
and the exhale
Can You Feel the breath on the area just below the nose on the upper lip
maybe in the throat in the back of the throat
let's bring our awareness into our bellies
and if you'd like you might even place your hands over your belly your belly button area
and just give your self permission to let your belly relax let it hang out
you can feel your belly expand with your inhale
you might need to give yourself a little permission or a little help to bring your breath into your belly
a lot of us don't do belly breathing we breathe higher in our chest so maybe
just imagine with the inhale your belly button pressing your hand out
as your belly expands and with the exhale the hand pressing
into the belly as your belly button reaches towards your spine
so this conscious breathing for a moment just to help open up the diaphragm the belly
just taking a few and more intentional deeper breaths to help us
feel that flow in the belly give ourselves permission
for the belly to breathe in and expand
and then just allowing the breathing to return to its own Natural State however
that is I'm just noticing again the belly now
and see if it's a little easier to feel the breath in the belly
and maybe noticing also your chest
Can You Feel the chest and the shoulders maybe even the ribs
expanding with the breath and how
how does this part of your body feel when it's being breathed
so we've been spending time kind of knowing different parts
of where the body and the breath are impacted by each other
now it might be interesting to sort of hold it all a little bit broader
sort of allowing yourself to feel the whole sense of flowing
the breath coming in and going out
just seeing whatever Sensations come into your awareness
more of a receptive experience than trying to focus in
giving or awareness to the sensations associated with breathing and just
knowing that you're aware of it that's all very simple very light
soft and when the mind gets distracted and you recognize it
great no problem
you can't meditate you know have a wrong experience just being aware
aware of what's Happening
and letting the breath help you
know it's possible to just sort of almost breathe through your thinking or
breathe through a sensation or emotion so if other things are coming up that's
okay just see if you can't just sort of let them be there and let the breath flow right through
one breath two breaths three breaths in a row
[Music]
so we have a few minutes now for questions and for Reflections
we'd be we would love to hear how that was for you what did you notice
anybody willing and we have mics in the room there's two on the floor
maybe you Sally and um you could pick them up and turn them on
and um Anne Rose is that your hand up no no okay yeah great that would be great
got us going is it on
good evening thank you Tanya done um I noticed that whenever
I my attention had deviated from the breath I just had just gave myself
gentle reminders beyond that I just I'm trying to focus more on
awareness without forcing it and that's been kind of
challenging but knowing that I have been doing that has also been helpful so just
trying to start 2023 with like okay let me just breathe then
rather than forcing everything to be calm so yes thank you
is there any anything that question or any comment that you want
um this question is for Dawn regarding the the like you said the tongue position
wise where behind the teeth because I had never heard of that before so I
threw a lot at you guys um so you don't need to worry too much
about it but there's um if you roll your tongue along the inside of your top
teeth you'll feel some gum that sort of shelves off and then starts to go up
into your palate if you touch your tongue on that little shelf right behind your teeth or
wherever it's comfortable for you but the idea is that that very gently
touching it there tends to relax the rest of the tongue the tongue is actually quite a long muscle
and it is one of the um muscles we can relax that gives the rest of our body a
hint to relax so experiment and find the right spot for you some people actually like to have it on
the back of their teeth but I tend to bite my tongue if I do that so you might want it a little further back
thank you thank you for the question foreign
thank you so much I was interesting tonight because I started nodding off
um that doesn't happen that often I guess maybe it's tonight but it really took me out of the practice for sure
when I you know I like kind of lose balance or so yeah just any tips on that or maybe
you should just this time maybe just keep my eyes open or because I was really starting to fall
asleep I I think you said something wonderful
though just open your eyes right and um and and okay so tonight the naturalist
observed sleepiness right so
um was it okay was it okay to be sleepy
I think oh yeah I don't I think I judged it as not okay yeah it's like okay I
need to get some fruitfulness out of this you know I mean yeah it can't be falling
asleep yeah so interesting yeah and you know I mean obviously if we drift off to
a nap and La La Land it's not really practicing but there's a lot to be to
observe about being sleepy you know there's there's stuff to learn there like a naturalist would want to
know about what happens with sleep all all of it
and the trick is finding that interest and enough awareness so you don't just
drift into the foggy land right um but yeah it doesn't have to be bad or you
know a failure it's like oh yeah this is a big part of our life it's sleep
yeah does that feel helpful yeah I'll keep my eyes open tonight yeah
yeah standing up you know taking your coat off
it's a little for me it's a little warm in here tonight so you know that that that makes it harder for me
um the stay alert yeah
great from
Margie how can we deal with tension in the face during meditation that is hard to
release and very distracting
sure I can start with that one um thanks for the question Margie
the um the first thing you may try is before meditating giving yourself a
little face massage actually I'm going to turn off my mic for a second and just demonstrate
that comes from the Tai Chi and Qigong lineage to do that kind of thing just
for a moment or two before clicking in and sitting down the next is to um
let yourself maybe yawn or do another relaxation response in
your face and then just allowing
the best you can to soften around the tension the tension itself might not
want to relax but if you find the edges of the tension in the face and relax around it
that can sometimes start to soften the whole thing
and finally if it's it's becoming distracting it can also be helpful to
intentionally notice whatever response emotional response is happening
to the tension and just acknowledge that and then consciously bring the attention
to the whole body to the breath and just allow it to be there noticing
how it is so I hope that was helpful
great thank you hi thank you um I know it went through a lot but I
tend to to have the same issue that like I've started to fall asleep like I
didn't this time but I started to be like in Dreamland like images and even
though I was not asleep body wise but the brain was kind of like like dreaming
um you mentioned about a standing position for meditation I never heard of
that and I think it would be good at least you know for me
to avoid the sleepiness so I didn't have time to do standing or
lying down during the posture segment but the principle is to stand
roughly keeping the feet hip width apart just sort of like not your outer hip but
sort of under your hip points and you your anyone is welcome to try it now knee is a little bit soft that's the
main key if you lock your knees like this you will eventually fall over
so just a little bit soft as Tanya is so beautifully described at
the beginning of that meditation allowing your belly to be soft let the belly hang out
and then again the whole principle of alignment eyes it's helpful to have them at a
roughly a 45 degree angle not down not looking in particular at anything
most people find it easier to do with their eyes open you are welcome to try it with your eyes closed
for some people that's easy other people find they lose their balance
and then you can just have your hands hanging at your sides if you want to have them clasp in front or behind you
you can do that
and your head aligned over your shoulders all the rest of it's the same
and it's a great posture to go to if you're sleepy or if you've got back pain some people
find standing actually a more helpful posture and if anyone needs to see lying down
tonight I'm happy to show you after class and then we'll model it next week
it's the hardest posture it's the hardest posture by far but some people don't have a choice
you're welcome thanks
foreign
I'm going to take a few minutes to talk about establishing a practice at home
I'm going to cover a couple of things the first is the sort of overall approach and the second is what you
actually do which Tanya covered it beautifully in some detail but I'm going to reinforce sort of at a high level
some high points so first of all it's like establishing any other new
habit or new routine right so it's helpful to give yourself some structure
and do a little bit of planning it's nice to pick or create a designated
spot in your space that's just for meditation or primarily for meditation
and ideally it's away from the comings and goings of the household
away from a lot of distracting things like televisions or computers or Etc not
a good idea to keep your smartphone right there you know some basic elements
you can set it up in a comfortable way as you experiment with finding the meditation postures that work for you
and like get yourself a timer that kind of thing and then
um I would say like just even the corner of a room is fine
but just to have a spot you know you're going to go to and you experiment around and find it and it's okay to be creative
so for example a friend of mine had a horrible commute to work he was a dedicated meditator and he got up really
early so he flipped it he met he drove to work first and then he meditated in the server room
at his job because he knew no one was going to walk in there before work hours and disturb him
another friend who didn't have any time off work would go into the bathroom and meditate for 10 minutes because no one's
going to bother you in there so home is ideal but there are other
options right most people find a consistent time of
day is helpful so now just make it a routine and make it part of your routine you know like
get up brush my teeth go sit something like that and for many of us as I just alluded to
first thing in the morning is really helpful I would even say for most people
so maybe it's after the morning cup of tea but definitely before the news the
email the social media all that kind of stuff and that is helpful because our minds
aren't quite as busy then and cluttered so you can experiment for yourself that
is not a time that works for everyone so find what works for you
a really helpful piece of advice I got early on was to commit to a flyby to my
meditation spot every day my one teacher of mine called it get your butt on the cushion even if it's
just for one or two minutes often it will turn into more than one or
two minutes and you know you can commit to the 10 or 15 or 20 or 30.
while you're considering what you're able to commit to
also it's a good time to start proactively identifying any potential challenges that might come up for you
if you know what they are like one student of mine had a puppy
so one of her challenges was meditating with the puppy and
she learned that puppy walking happened before meditation otherwise meditation didn't happen so you know just to kind
of plan in the things you know might derail you
there's also creating a contingency plan so for example
maybe you want to meditate in the morning and for some reason it doesn't work that morning it might be nice to
have set aside the same amount of time in the evening as a backup plan
to do that sit and then if you to the morning practice you either have the
option of doing a second practice or you get an extra 20 minutes great right
so to know what your own potential challenges are and to sort of
troubleshoot them in advance a little bit maybe even enroll a friend or bring it up here in class
it's always okay to begin again if you miss a day
always okay missing a day start the next
next and always start over start over in general not letting the perfect be
the enemy of the good right do what you can
so and then it's about establishing kind of intentional meditation sessions or
what we often call in this scene formal meditation sessions
pick your posture whatever it's going to be and then it's helpful to start off with
a conscious reflection perhaps as Tanya brought up earlier why you're meditating
while you're there and then I find it really helpful to set
an intention or a resolve can't remember the language Tanya used but to be clear that this is a time for
meditation to kind of tell my mind that so it doesn't go off and have a thinking party
for 20 minutes right but to set that intention to be present
for moment to moment experience just the best you can
it's also supportive to very intentionally then go through the more
detailed setup of the meditation posture whatever it is like we did tonight
you know soften the eyes the tongue aligning your body maybe doing this it's
like you set up a little routine for yourself and after not very long that routine
starts to tell your body oh it's time to meditate and you'll be amazed your mind
just starts to kind of go into that it's again setting up that little habit
can be almost like a little ritual right and then at the end of each formal
meditation session to end with a conscious reflection maybe reflecting back on how that was
how good it felt how appreciative you are that it happened
and then something I neglected to say at the beginning is um
when you do set up your initial posture when you do sit down one of the most helpful things to
keep in mind is an allowing kind attitude I think of it as the
internal posture the internal stance soft
appreciative allowing we learn a lot better that way
just like if you're trying to teach a puppy to come and you whack it on the nose it's not going to keep coming
if you give it a kind word we give our minds a kind word when they come back
they like to come back more often
and then I'll just say finally um it's a real gift
not to have big expectations at first the first year I started meditating I
didn't realize what a gift it was at the time that I had no expectations at all
for what was supposed to happen on the cushion other than that I was supposed to show up there and more or less follow
my breath and the reason I started meditating was to
deal with the physical issue the physical issue did not get better but I kept meditating because I noticed
the difference in the rest of my day and that was enough
so now and then to stop and reflect back on oh how am I the days I meditate
versus the days I don't not to get too fussy about it or do it
too often but to just check in
the Dalai Lama has a quote about checking in on meditative progress said we should do it regularly
at least every five to seven years oh
to not be too hard on ourselves if we're not noticing changes right away
so those are some thoughts about establishing the practice at home
and with that we're going to go into another short guided meditation
so um finding yourself a comfortable
posture be balanced aligned
a balance between relaxation and alertness
and setting the intention to be present for your moment to moment
experience
hmm softening the eyes the tongue the body
and noticing the sensations in this body
throughout the whole body at first warmed for cool pressure
contraction or relaxation
and then especially attuning tuning in to the sensations of your body breathing
wherever it's most obvious and comfortable for you
breathing is the home base or anchor
the object of attention
another tether to the moment that can be helpful
is to very softly in the mind use a single word or a short phrase
acknowledging breathing in when breathing in and breathing out
when breathing out
if you're noticing the breath at the belly or the chest
it could be rising on the in-breath
falling on the out breath
or simply in on the in-breath and out
on the out breath
keeping most of the attention on the sensations
the lived experience of this breath
a very light touch to the note
these notes are one kind of intentional thinking
thinking that is supportive to staying in the present moment
you may notice other thinking swirling around in there
that's okay mind think
the invitation is to allow all other thoughts of then and there
future and past Fade Into the periphery the background
and allow awareness of breathing awareness of this moment
to be in the Forefront of attention the foreground
and try it silently for a few minutes together then I'll chime in again near the end
if you find your attention is wondered
appreciate the return of awareness
and gently kind I
return your attention to this moment
this breath
foreign
foreign so we have another little while for questions comments
we'd love to hear what you noticed if you have any questions about what's come up so far in the class
questions about establishing a practice at home yes please
uh this was perfect so I'm happy to yeah I didn't feel like falling asleep
this time so that was good that's it to the comment great
finding the right sitting gear can go a long way
hi I did this standing meditation for my for the first time my time and what I notice is I'm way more aware
of the breathing and my body and my body starts gently rocking like when I was in
hell in or excelling and it was and I didn't go into the dream world or anything it was just
breathing and and body awareness I really like it I think I'm gonna do it
I'm Gonna Keep It wonderful
it's great you both experimented you know and you know no two meditations are
exactly alike so you know keep keep noticing and adapting as you need to you
know try different things and so that it's fairly comfortable giving yourself permission to
kind of even checking in before you're going to meditate uh what kind of a state am I in how's my body how's my
back today you know am I tired you know and yeah just just tuning in
tuning in and adjusting very good
hi thank you um I was just gonna say that I could
definitely feel a difference after these two small meditation sessions and the
past week my anxiety has been pretty bad which usually affects like my appetite like I don't get hungry
um and this past one I was like worried about my stomach growling which I was like that's good I guess because maybe
it relieved just a little bit of the anxiety enough to revive my appetite I don't know
um but I did have a question as well um especially when it comes to meditating at home which I've been
trying to do more often definitely not every day yet but I struggle a lot with
having it be as effective as coming here in person and hearing someone talk to me
and kind of refocus my mind um
and there's some things I do like I try to listen to some of the recorded
sessions on YouTube uh other sessions that are more guided so that I can
incorporate that but I just it still doesn't feel like I'm able to relax and
let go and focus as much as I am in person here so I was just curious if there's any advice or steps towards
getting there at home
welcome to the club foreign
so what Tanya's alluding to is that many of us find it easier to meditate in a
group even if there's not someone giving the guidance there's just something about
the group field we call it the being together with a lot of people who are
doing the same thing you may have something more to add I'll
just briefly say that it they are different experiences and there's value
to both so to keep doing both um learning from meditation teachers and
hearing the guidance begins to build your own internal voice and your own internal process for dropping into
meditation and it's kind of like training wheels like you don't always want to have the
training wheels on sometimes you want to ride the bike without the wheels even though you're maybe a little wobblier
because it does build a capacity Tanya do you have anything to add to
that maybe sometimes it's good to have the training wheels you know just to say
that too that you know if you find yourself highly anxious or obsessed
about something or angry those are really good times to choose the guidance right even if you've been riding solo
for a while so just just to say yes absolutely Don what you said is
beautiful and I agree we need both experiences you know we learn and we
integrate and and again this adjusting you know sort
of checking in what do I need right now you know what I'm kind of calm maybe I can do it on my own tonight you know
or looking at how long you're doing it for as well so giving yourself a sense
of like I can do five minutes I'm I really feel confident I can do five
minutes and and having some experiences being confident you know maybe it's hard but maybe you cry maybe whatever but you
can get through five minutes you know you can get through five minutes you know and do that for a while and then
maybe it it's like okay I can probably do seven or ten you know just sort of
working with yourself um and giving yourself some experience of confidence you know it doesn't have
to be amazing just okay I can do it I can do it
yeah and Rose
would you demonstrate that I'm going to take the mic off completely
to name that this comes from a different meditation lineage that I started before I was a Buddhist meditator which is I
was a Tai Chi practitioner for many years so this isn't in the Buddha's instructions it comes from that lineage
showing yes as I said you don't have to do it in that order that's a series of
things you can do and you can also invent for yourself like a lot of people have tension right
at your jaw this can feel really good
I guess the general principle is just to kind of take care of yourself for a minute or two as you're settling into
meditation like it might not need to be face massage for you some of us need to just like massage our shoulders for a
second we're like Tanya was saying a couple of shoulder rolls can feel
really good if you've been at the computer desk all day so to just honor your body before you go
into complete Stillness that's kind of why I tend to do this rocking thing and like a little bit of a wiggle first
I actually really like to walk before I meditate I really really helps me a lot to just
to do a 20-minute walk come back down and just sit and I just it's like there's so much
aliveness in my body it really helps me be present
don't overeat before you sit down [Laughter] what's that
right you fall asleep right you just your system just shuts down yeah
some people find stretching right before sitting to be really helpful I did that for many years before I sat
went do the walk and then stretch and then sit then your body just feels so good it makes it a lot easier to focus
on the body on the body's feeling pretty good
yeah your own little routine I no no hands up right now I just want
to highlight something that Don said I just it's worth repeating the inner sort
of what was the inner posture she liked to use the word the inner posture
how are we tuning in to ourselves this is so important this is that idea of the
naturalist how would a naturalist respond if I got sleepy you can always ask yourself you know what how am I
relating to my own experience this is incredible important support for your
meditation if you are being a harsh inner critic you are going to just get more and more
tense and stressed and feel like you're doing it all wrong
so maybe in that beginning when you're sitting down kind of invite
invite yourself to connect with a mindset a voice a person a figure some
way of being that you know kind of will help you be present wise and
compassionate right like non-reactive non-judgmental
accepting but you know not codependent and indulging either right that creating
that kind of inner environment is incredibly important
I'll just lift up Tanya has used the metaphor of naturalist really beautifully a few times
that playful experimentation experimentation exploration you can't
get it wrong just get interested get interested
that's that's an another really helpful internal posture or internal stance to
take is um it's always okay to start over and
reboot the experiment shift the posture change the location
reset the attitude
foreign wrap up or does anyone have anything
else they want to share or reflect or ask
do you want to do the kind of no pointing to them just noticed my name is
on the closing this is the handout for our first week it was on the little
table as you walked in where the masks were those of you watching on YouTube you can go to audiodarma.org and a PDF
of this handout is in the intro to mindfulness meditation series that will
be posted shortly after this session is over so um
it has some really useful information and then it has some instruction on mindfulness
and breathing I like to read that and as I'm sitting and then just sort of close my eyes and
sit and kind of let the words percolate and then on the back I'm sorry the instructions on the back
the top of the back is also the homework yes there's homework in this class
should you choose to accept it and that is to do a 20-minute session of
meditation each day okay and um
the second bit of homework is to remain mindful during some kind of routine
activity washing your hands washing the dishes brushing your teeth
taking a walk like a simple walk maybe to the bus or wherever right but to just
be in a simple way present and aware and then the third thing is
for one half hour period sometime during the week pay careful attention to your
posture as you go through your activities and without straining
take a posture that's alert and upright relaxed just like we were talking about
with the meditation postures and just notice what happens
to your mood to your thought your feelings what happens to your internal world as you bring more attention to
your posture so that's your mission should you choose to
accept it the recordings are available on YouTube
and on audiodarma.org if you want to refresh yourself on any of this stuff
so thank you very much for coming tonight for being with us live or online and
it's a real Delight to have you and your presence and your questions and your interests
appreciate that you're interested in learning about this
so there's a Buddhist tradition