good evening everyone welcome how is the sound is it
okay okay yeah my name is Jim pulski I'm um
filling in for Diana this week while she's
away I'm exactly one year ago I gave a talk here the the the Monday after
Thanksgiving and so here I am again A year later uh also here to talk about
Thanksgiving last year I spent about a week reflecting on what what things I
I'm thankful for what things I'm grateful for and I came up with um lists first
and foremost my parents who brought me into being who raised me
fed me educated me loved me um the rest of my family my sisters
and my brother and my aunt and grandparents
um uncles and aunts uh my community you know our
neighbors um people we went to church with um my friends people I went to
school with my
schoolmates um my Educators my
teachers I started school when I was three in preschool and I ended when I finished
graduate school at age 29 so I spent a lot of time in formal education ation
settings and had a lot of teachers um some I absolutely loved you
know some were kind of like so so but they all
um all of them I felt had my best interest at heart and um inspired me to keep going
to learn about science and math and um many other
things uh who else well
um I know people I knew from school fellow students and then uh I came to IMC in
the late 90s I guess in January it'll be 26 years since I've started coming
here um and so the teachers that I had here Gil and many other
teachers um who just
um offered the Dharma open-handed for so many years for
me um and the and the friends that I made
here um how often people that I consider are
my Dharma brothers and Dharma sisters or I guess not days Dharma
siblings um who I spent time with in cantam camita
groups discussing the Dharma or um just on one-on-one
discussions uh having meals going on
Retreats it's been very rich it's been it's been a very rich Community for me
to be part of um so that were those were some of the
people that I'm thankful for I probably didn't remember all of them um and then also being thankful for
my health um both my physical health and my mental
health um I've mostly been pretty healthy and when I haven't I've had good
medical
care um and I think it's
important certainly for me but I think for everyone to do some
conscious reflection on who the who and what they're grateful for the mind has a
tendency towards it's sometimes said the mind has is like velcro for the negative and like
Teflon for the positive so for things like gratitude it may take some actual
um conscious effort to bring that forth to
um to keep that in your
awareness when I started thinking about what I was going to talk about tonight I
thought well I could I could cover that same ground I'm sure there's other people
that I'm haven't uh acknowledged or things that I haven't
acknowledged uh institutions i' I've worked now for
NASA now for over well I guess it's been like 42
years so my gratitude to NASA uh the universities I've been
in um so about a week ago I was laying in bed
doing um uh mindfulness meditation we call it
lying meditation which means that I'm in a prone position not that I'm lying to myself about whether I'm doing
meditation and I thought well I wonder what'll come up and actually I was laying there and I
was paying attention to my breath and I thought you know I don't know that I've
ever felt gratitude for the breath you know it's there all the time
it's there all the time it's one of the main things that supports this this body
being alive I've certainly been aware of it
um in Buddhism and in other in many other uh maybe Traditions or or
practices the breath is one of the central elements things that we pay
attention to it can be used for mindfulness
developing an ability to really pay attention to what's happening in the present
moment um it can be used for soothing the mind and the body you
know particularly long slow out breaths can bring some sense of relaxation and
ease it can energize the body that's one of the things that I do in the morning is
use the breath to start kind of waking up my mind and waking up my
body getting it ready to um uh launch out into the
day you can use the breath for uh
concentration or for unification of the mind you know just just staying with the
breath continuously not going off to other uh phenomenon like you might in
mindfulness uh I know there's yogic practices of
using the breath for if I I don't I'm not an expert on this at all but I know
if that if you breathe in in one of the nostrils it tends to warm the body and
if you breathe in in the other nostril it tends to cool the body I don't understand all of that but people have
been using the breath for years for for
um cultivating states that are
helpful and yet I think there's something that I was missing out by looking at the breath simply as a tool
you know simply as this phenomenon
um it's not really a thing right I mean it's it's not like you can point at the
breath as something different than this body it's it's a process of the
body and so over the last week or so I've been you know reflecting on
how how can I treat the breath as something other than just a tool
something other than sort of like some impersonal
phenomenon
um yeah and so I've I've you know I I start reminding
myself the breath is what keeps me alive that's pretty important you know I
mean that's that's a prettyy important function
and although it's not the only way to bring gratitude to it it's like realizing that that may not always be
the case you know there's people that have respiratory issues where the breath is
difficult people that use um these CPAP machines to help them get enough air
when they sleep at night so that um so that the body can function
properly you know people who have had um either illnesses or damage to their
lungs um my uh ex-grand or my late ex-grand
father um used to work in a mining town and he
specifically made the decision not to work in the mine he was a a blacksmith
so he could repair equipment and he didn't make as much as he would have if he had gone into the mine but he also
knew that working in the mine you would get mineral dust in your lungs that
basically would lead to an early death so
um you know so being thankful for our
breath while it's still pretty easy and we actually most of the time just ignore
it um is one of the most accessible things that we can cultivate
this gratitude for the other
um so there's the process of breathing breathing and
then oh that's right and then yeah so excuse me for a
little uh discontinuity in my thoughts yeah so there's people that use
these cpat machines for for breathing um I know people that rely on
having machines that either enhance the amount of oxygen that they breathe or actually breathe pure oxygen
uh at the beginning of the pandemic you he heard a lot about um ventilators that people would use to help them machines
that would help them breathe and even in the the middle of
the 20th century there were these machines called iron lungs that people would be in that would help them breathe
that they couldn't breathe on their own so
um I think appreciating it and learning to enjoy it while you
can you know
uh and then in addition to thinking about the body breathing I think of what is it that we breathe you know the air
that we breathe here in the Bay Area our air quality is quite
good I just looked at a website called Purple air before I came here
and there's a little bit of particulate in the atmosphere right now from
probably from uh fireplaces this time of the year um but
mostly it's pretty good now of course if you were here in some Summers while the wire wildfires are going You' see well
yeah you know that the air quality really decreased there was a lot of particulates a lot of
so uh you're advised to wear in 95 D
masks uh and maybe stay indoors uh fortunately that here that
wasn't the case for very long for too many days but it did make
me appreciate more those days when the air is clear and safe to to
breathe I've also worked in parts of the world where that's definitely not the case
I've worked in South Korea I've worked in Houston you know I've
um worked in other places where uh air quality is is definitely an issue
so so I'm thankful for the air
um where my Reflections went from there is
in Ancient India at the time of the Buddha everything was thought of as
being made up of four elements there was the air element the water
element the Earth element and the fire
element so I started to think hm what about those other three so then
I start Ed to think about the water element now we don't as a physical
chemist we don't usually scientifically described the
world anymore with those four elements but I think they're worth looking at they're they're they they their
qualities of matter um but it gave me a framework to think
about what I could be grateful for what I could be thankful for so in addition to a the breath and air said you know
water that's that's pretty prominent as a human being I looked it up on the web
today um the average human being is about 60%
water some for some people it's as low as 45 and some it's as high as 75 but
probably most of us are you know somewhere around 60%
water so we're intricately tied to the hydrological cycle you know intricately
tied to taking in water hopefully every day in sufficient
quantity to um to make the body work you know to Aid
digestion to get rid of um metabolic um
waste materials um to keep our eyes clear clear of uh
dust and and other things um sweating to help keep our body at at
the right temperature and of course every breath
we take that we exhale there's water going out you know
we're continually breathing out water uh you you'd see that most
noticeably if you've ever lived in a uh cold environment you know where you
breathe out on a cold winter day and you can just see this big cloud of condensed
water so um so that's an important
um so we're a flowing processor this body is a flowing processor of
water
um so seeing that acknowledging it appreciating
it uh being grateful for it um are all
possible and just like air uh water is we we
it's here in the Peninsula we can just take it for granted right you turn on the tap and there's water that's not
true in a lot of parts of the world you know that
um fresh drinking water uh in some ways is a a gift it's a gift
to our to us from all of the people that work to to make that
possible you know over the last five years we've had like I think maybe three years in a row of drought and so that
you know that was kind of a time when I think people's awareness of water increased you know they started to say
oh yeah well yeah it's starting to get scarce
it's it's starting to get um we may not be able to do everything
that we're used to with water we may not be able to water our Lawns and wash our
cars maybe even wash our bodies as much as we're used to I know some
restaurants took it as far as not giving you water with your meal unless you
asked for it you know that was just a uh you know sort of a wakeup
call we had a wet winter last winter and I it's expected that we'll have a El
Nino winter so um it's amazing just as Waters become more
plentiful how that awareness of water is is kind
of um diminished for me you know it's like okay well now now
it's over now they we're back to there being plenty but um that may not always
be the case so I think now is the time to be
grateful now is the time to be aware now is the
time to be um
appreciative and then the next um it's all moving on from water uh the next
element is Earth the Earth element and
that's what supports us now you know the Earth is supporting
us it's also holding us here I mean one of the things
that's that we don't escape for a millisecond is the gravitational field
of the earth it's holding us in place it's holding all these chairs in place you
know we set things on tables and desks and everything else and just assume
they'll stay there but um the Earth supplies gravity so um again
gravity we take for granted we quite honestly if there was
no gravity there'd be no atmosphere all the air would just float
off into space so
um one of the aspects of the earth is it lets us know which way is up right the
gravitational field it also um feeds us right
plants use the minerals from the earth um to
grow um they hold it in place the W the Earth holds the
water if you're if you eat a plantbased diet you know the Earth supplies
everything directly if you're an omnivore or a carnivore you you know at least some of
the animals that you eat are fed by plants that grow on the
earth and then the the final Earth the the final element um that I'll talk
about tonight is um what's called the fire element and that might be I don't know
for it's right to say personified by but exemplified by the Sun that which produces light and
heat I know when I wake up in the morning I I look forward to sitting at my my work area because I have a
southern facing window and the sun coming in really does something for my
mood it certainly helps heat up the house
um you know the circadian rhythms of the
body get tied to the to that and almost all of the energy that
we use has is either currently or in the past has come from the Sun you know
either you know the solar energy that we might be using or wind energy that's
coming from the the sun driving the the winds or from fossil
fuels that took sunlight and stored them for millions of years
so
um so being grateful for the sun being grateful for
heat if you've ever been really cold and I grew up in Wisconsin and I've worked
in Alaska and uh Northern Sweden in the
winter I know what it's like to be cold and uh it's very easy to be
grateful for heat when you walk inside a building and uh feel
that so that's just
some a a brief uh listing of the reflections that
I had on those four elements and uh being grateful for
them when I think about well so I'm not a historian and
I'm not a mythologist but I have read history and mythology that cultures
current and past have
recognized the importance of these things of of air of
water of the earth and of the
Sun and have had a sense of reverence for them you know
reverence reverence for the air re reverence for the the water reverence
for the Earth reverence for the
sun um you know recognizing that our lives
depend on all of those those four things you know that's we may not want
to think about it we we may think that our water comes out of the
tap uh you know our food comes from Whole Foods or Safeway uh you know our
heat comes from pg& and all of those are partly true
right but
um but I think it's also there's there's some level of of um
seeing clearly or honestly if we really see how tied we are to those four
elements how they're they're integral to us being alive and that we're not
separate from them
um in some ways breathing is a communal
activity you know I'm breathing the same air as you are and As You Are
and as you are um there isn't some
boundaries that it's something that we share with each other and so having
[Music] some you know having some reverence for
the air and the water and the Earth and treating them
well so that we can continue living um the kind of lives we're living
now I wouldn't I I'm I'm not suggesting that we worship those as though there
are some uh deity but having reverence for them having
respect for them
um doing what we can
to to um support them you know what how can we
change what we're doing to um it leads to better quality air better
quality water better quality
soil Earth and this is a little bit more
far-fetched but what do we do
to um altering the sunlight that comes and
hits the Earth you know we we've actually now reached the point where
human activity can affect how much of the Sun how much of the energy of the sun
gets um trapped in the radiative balance of the earth so how do we recognize that
and and um work with it in a way that will be beneficial for
all so those are some of my thoughts about uh thank Thanksgiving this year of
you know thanking thanking the natural world um not that just supports us but
that we are part of you know that we are not separate from the natural world and
how do we respect it and um care for
it so I leave you with those questions to reflect on thank you
and if there's any questions or comments um Martha has a
microphone it's more more of a comment is that on
yeah um that when you were talking about air water fire and the earth I thought
thought of what you brought up later which is that feeling of connection that
there's something and also the other thing you know people you were thankful for that I
I thought of feeling connected to everyone and and the elements and what a
um what a warm feeling that is and and respect for for all those
things also being a warm feeling so that's all oh
thank you thank you yeah they they they all do connect
us right breathing you know the water the
Earth Sun thank
you I'm grateful for for emotions Joy and sorrow the the whole
gamut of human emotions yeah thank you your talk is
wonderful thank
you okay well um if there's no other questions uh thank you for coming
tonight uh I'll stay up here afterwards if you want to talk
individually and uh and I and I hope
uh things go well for you thank you