so there's an expression in English of
fighting fire with fire little strange topics for today given it's raining
but fighting fire with a fire and my understanding of history of the origins of this expression it had to do with
farmers in the early 1800s in the Prairies of central prairies United States when there were prayer prayer a
prayer Prairie fires
excuse me they learn to um set smaller fires in the
you know in front of the approaching large prairie fire in order to protect
themselves and maybe unfortunately the expression eventually became also understood to
fight violence with violence that whatever whatever someone brings you you bring the same
there is a I think a marvelous story perhaps a myth a fable
uh you have the very first months of the Buddha's teaching of him fighting fire with fire so I'm
going to tell you the story he was wandering around in Northern India
and he needed a place to stay for the night and he came Upon A large group it
says 500 people who ascetics or spiritual practitioners reductions who
were living on the edge of a river who were fire worshipers
and they had a firehouse kind of maybe like a place where they did the fire
ceremonies and you know did their religious life and uh
so he came upon them and he said to the leader of them that would be possible
for me to spend the night in your Firehouse he needed a place to stay
and uh the man said oh yes it would be very happy for you to stay there however
there's a ferocious um
the large powerful serpent fire serpent living in the house
and it won't be danger it would be dangerous for you to go and spend the night there
and then we're like oh no I can I'll be fine could I please stay there
and because it was so dangerous that man thought it was so dangerous for Buddha to do it the Buddha had to ask three
times and in India ancient India if you asked three times you usually don't say no the third time so I said okay you
so the Buddha went and spent mentally explains that he went in and sat down and made himself a seat inside the
firehouse sat down cross-legged and established himself in an upright sitting posture
and brought forth mindfulness so he was going to often the Buddha would sit and meditate through the night
that was his idea of a good night's sleep maybe and um so
sure enough this Dragon came out the serpent came out and was I guess upset
that someone was in the his house and so he approached the Buddha and
started shooting smoke at the Buddha
and then Buddha thought that was interesting and he said well what if I uh match the
smoke with smoke and that infuriated in the the serpent
so then he started with um you know projecting Flames ferocious Flames at the Buddha
and the Buddha thought well what if I match the fire with fire
without hurting without harming the serpent and that's the magic thing without
harming the serpent and then he says and then with filled with Good Will filled with
loving kindness care for the serpent the Buddha matched fire for fire
so he wasn't trying to harm the harm the the serpent and but he was provide he was matching
fire with fire and this uh and so people outside could
see the flames and the smokes billowing out of this Firehouse oh no the ascetic gotama the Buddha certainly
he's going to succumb this would be his end but in the morning the Buddha came out
with um another big terrible serpent in his
begging Bowl curled up and he handed it to the fire worshiper and said here
and the Buddha was no less you know worse off than before he went
in so one of the things the images of this that stands out for me
is the Buddha sat in meditation first so he was sitting for the Buddha in a
strong posture an erect upright present posture posture where you can be really present for something for life
for yourself whatever's going on without leading in and without pulling back
without getting activated and without crumbling down collapsing
this danger came at him and he kept his strong position his
balance position this in a sense a kind of neutral position
but also in a sense a very strong position posture of strength
but a stroke a posture of strength which is unassertive
a power of strength which is not asserting power over anyone not being aggressive just their present
and when the serpent came and attacked him the Buddha responded somehow in kind
but was it really with smoke was it really in Flames there's um
another teaching somewhere else where the Buddha was talking to a person who's a
wood gather as a profession Gathering Woods for fire and uh the Buddha in the course of their
conversation says says to them I have given up the burning
of wood I burned the blaze of wisdom Within
so he's lit in the fight he like he doesn't like the fire of wood he lights the Fire Within and so the inner fire
light or but they say idea of flame of inner fire is also a little bit of a of
a representation of some kind of strength and power but it's inner
and so the serpent comes towards the Buddha and the Buddha keeps sitting there and doesn't move
but I imagine that he looks the serpent right in the eye and flinchingly
and that's you know maybe this is a myth but that's a powerful idea that danger comes and you neither turn
away you don't turn the other cheek but you also don't attack
it's not eye for an eye kind of thing for the Buddha it's the fire I would
suggest the fire of loving kindness his loving kindness a match to
the anger of this terrible serpent
apparently the Buddha thought it was can loving kindness something by
kindness be powerful and strong or how do we how do we let our love have
a strength and power to it that can meet the challenges of our life that's kind of the question
is it possible and I think that often enough in our kind of Buddha scene where we emphasize
a tremendous amount of you know compassion and loving kindness and these things
sometimes it goes along with a kind of meekness a kind of not you know not you
know just kind of accommodating or accepting others and not trying very careful that you have not harming
sometimes it's interpreted um make sure no one feels hurt
and that's a big difference between harming and people feeling hurt sometimes harm and hurt are two
different things if you tell me that you know that I'm pretty lousy teacher because I'm wearing
I guess a red shirt I don't think your Harmony you're you're harming me to say that but I might feel
hurt if my identity is tied up with my shirt
so if that if so I have to kind of go along and help me with this to stay or you know this distinction I'm making
between a hurt and harm there is a distinction that does anything important here
so we have a tremendous emphasis on not harming but even with that we can't be
responsible that some people we feel hurt when there's no assertion no no nothing
you know we're not trying to do anything and sometimes simply being present in a
strong way some people feel intimidated by that sometimes holding our ground is taken as
being assertive sometimes not giving in and accepting of
people saying is seem as taken as an offense
and maybe all these things are true sometimes but uh I think as I think there's a some
kind of an under a shadow side of our Buddhist tradition that I've seen over the decades I've been in it of people
being a little bit kind of ready to lower them so weaken themselves or or
diminish themselves and uh in order to make other people comfortable
there's a time for that for sure but the shadow side is that sometimes done too
often and so the flip side of that is often not learned in our tradition I think and
I could be wrong and you can correct me but what's not really emphasized that often is idea become a strong person
maybe even become a powerful person but in what way
strong and powerful in yourself
for yourself in a certain kind of way over yourself
so I'll give you some examples or at least one of uh something that was very small
at the time I haven't thought about it for decades but recently I've been thinking about it I said wow that was this represents a real turning
point for me in my Buddhist practice that I did this
and uh and how did I come across this idea to do this through this practice
and I kind of thought back at my early years my first year when I was kind of a
full-time Zen student so um
I was living at the San Francisco Zen Center which is a and they have a farm in Marin
County called the green Gulch Farm so I was working as a farm hand there and doing a lot of farm work
and one day with another person I had to carry some very heavy equipment
from one side of the farm to the other Just the Two of Us
and it was kind of a long walk and it was really painful for my hands to hold this it wasn't I don't remember what I
was like my arms but really really dug into my hands and I said okay well my attitude oh this
is interesting let me see if I can manage this without having any reactivity in my mind
can my mind stay at ease well my hands were feeling this pain
and so I don't know how well I did I can't proudly say that I succeeded
somehow but what I succeeded to do was to to maintain the practice of doing this looking at it looking at my
reactivity letting it go trying to decouple the pain in my hand from the
state of my mind and this decoupling that I was trying to
do there then represented a kind of a continued way in which I practiced where
I tried to find a receive my reactivity in my mind and see where I had choice not to give
into it not to pick it up to leave it alone and this I think is so where did I learn
that and I think I learned it by sitting in meditation that as I sat in meditation
there was first a physical Stillness that was hard to learn to do
but I had to not give in to the impulse to move move to itch myself or to avoid
discomfort and that was a tough thing to learn to not have the physical reactivity to
it but I learned to do that for okay but then the next stage was to you know
what you're left with then is kind of like the mind and I discovered how much my mind reacted
I discovered that the reactivity of the Mind often made other pain much worse
physical pain emotional pain much worse so I learned to watch my mind closely
and see okay let go don't do that don't go along with that go back to the breath go back to here
and I was going back to some peaceful place and so over so that so I think that's
where I started to learn this what was going on in my mind tracking my mind so when I was carrying this heavy equipment
across the farm it had become now a reference point for it not just
meditation but in daily life as well to track my mind to see what my mind was doing and to exercise some choice
about what goes on in my mind some Choice by what I pursue how I practice
with it what I'm involved in and in some sense uh I was cultivating a
kind of self-control a certain kind of agency uh strength
over my reactivity to not give into it my reactivity was strong in itself
maybe that was a serpent and I learned to not have the serpent
have the upper hand and so then you know
I don't know if that was the first time I really started doing this in daily life with this heavy equipment but it was you know represented a kind of
direction that my practice went then that the related track was going on my mind
a next phase that happened and after a few more years of Zen practice was that I discovered that as I had this
little more control over my mind which meant that not so much that I could then use it
assertively or you know you know make something happen in the world
that was a power over leaving the Mind alone with not infusing the mind or
having the Mind caught up in reactivity that's where the control was
and as I I became less and like reactive in my mind
I just what became important was love love Compassion Care tenderness that's
what kind of there was space now for these other ways of being to a being to
well up Wellspring within of a lot of goodness
that hadn't had space before because it was crowded out by my
reactivity it was crowded out by all the thoughts and stories and ideas and
proliferations of imaginations that I had
and as those quieted down there was space to feel and sense something deeper
Within and it became a very special time at
some point or a choice I made at some point where I realized that um that the
compassion love kindness was partly a choice
not to do it so much but a choice to lose it
the choice to lose touch with it was a kind of a subconscious unconscious
choice that my mind would make if I gave in to my reactivity
if I got caught up in this in the swirling thoughts and ideas and fantasies of my mind that closed that
part of me out and so at some point I kind of made a commitment
to love to compassion not because I was going to like work hard now to be compassionate
that never was interesting for me but rather I was going to work hard at
not covering it over not making not having it have be
available for myself for to be flowing through and so over then to over time I learned
this wonderful thing that so many different sides and flavors and qualities
that are really beautiful to have but it could also be
be very strong love can be powerful or maybe say differently
love can be matched or be supported by or come along with
a kind of inner strength that we learn to carry with us
an inner strength that is comparable in daily life to the Buddha statue here the
Buddha sitting in meditation practice and sitting upright strong neither assertive
nor pulling back neither
you know attacking nor afraid neither giving up
nor requiring anyone else to give up but very present
looking people looking at everyone he has a very soft gaze usually the statues
of the Buddha in meditation usually they always have him with his eyes half open
and one of the theological bootological theories for that is that Buddha is always connected
to the world but with soft eyes a soft gaze
can the strength of and presence of meeting challenges angry people
can we have such strength that we can be with soft eyes can we meet anger not with anger
but with love so when the Widow fought fire with fire
I would suggests that there was two different kinds of Fire
maybe the serpent was a fire of anger for the Buddha it was a fire of love
and the Buddha said that hatred and anger is never overcome by hatred
it's always overcome by love
so can that be something strong and I would emphatically say yes
but it's not a strength of reactivity it's not a strength that is so much a
doing except it's a strength of getting out of the way so a natural presence
our ability to really be present and state for what's happening has a chance to kind of flower here for
us and be really present in a strong full way
I had a neighbor once who was really angry at some noise
workers were making and were in the property
and came over and yelled at me
just came over and yelled at me was very angry Furious it was completely I think unreasonable the whole thing because
but anyway was it I don't know exactly why and so I stood there just looking at him
I felt kind of uncomfortable a little bit um a little bit afraid
so it wasn't like I was just kind of fearless and uh but I still stood there
just I didn't back away I didn't attack I just stood there and looked at him and
I did wonder how long can someone have a monologue like this
and then when he finally stopped I just looked at him in calmly and I said
you know when you're talking about talking this way I feel afraid
I don't think I was expressing fear but I just it was kind of true but it wasn't like a
I just looked at this that's what's happening and in a sense that was my my meeting
fire with fire I just said this is what's happening and um
he immediately calmed down he immediately kind of apologized and
left and that's the last time that neighbor has yelled at me
and we're kind of friends now again but um you know so I think I wouldn't have been
able to do that unless I'd learned to track my reactivity to track my fear and
how I relate to fear and how fear sometimes gets the upper hand and I believe it and I you know
the usual kind of hindrances around fear might have come up it might have been the fear of you know when hindrance is
is anger you know to blame him anymore attack and others is shut down another
is to get all Restless enough know what to do it's all kinds of things can happen there the reactivity part
but uh you know by knowing and tracking my ability how I'm reactive I was able
to have how I was be much more the realm of my choice
stay here and be here with it I'm not going to give in to these habits
and then I was able to make a wiser choice the one wiser Choice was just stay watch
this was I was pretty confident this was not a person who was going to be violent even though the voice was strong
but also strength
some of you know that Martin Luther King has a wonderful writing on in the book
called the strength to love how often do you associate love with
strength how often do you um
bring forth something in the family of love all the different qualities that we call a family of love
how how often do you bring it forth in a way so it's present in a strong way
not strong because it's infused with what we want desire which is often makes
love complicated and which often gives love a lot of strength this like you know
because we want something but what is it love that is not entangled with desire
that is offered to the world without assertion
without need without wanting something without leaning forward without pulling
back but allows us to be very present upright alert
available for the world and available for wisdom and Care flowing up within us
so that the wisest part of us can then decide to choose what to do
So lately I've been thinking of this as being a kind of strength
but also I'm thinking maybe to start using the expression self-control which
is kind of taboo in our Buddhist scene first because of the word self
and second because there's a lot of teachings that don't try to control your experience don't try to control your
experience and both these caveats I think are important
but sometimes there is very important part of Buddhist practice is in fact being able to control
yourself not controlling what happens but controlling the reactivity with
which you respond to what's happening including your reactivity to your
reactivity some reactivity you can't it can't help at doing but then at some point we have some
choice some Choice some point we take some control over the situation
even if all it is which is not a small thing is I'm going to be mindful of this
I'm going to not shoot a second Arrow
that's that's taking control that's taking agency that's taking
um engaging in the practice
and the self part you know is self-control it's a non-philosophical
non-metaphysical self you know it's like
if you say I'm gonna I'm gonna go pee that I is not the metaphysical problem
there's no I in Buddhism you can't use that well you could do it
for me then you know so it's just kind of that kind of simple way
who else is going to care for you take care of all the
waste products in your mind don't expect that other people do it for
you so um
so this wonderful little tale of the Buddha fighting fire with fire
which I interpret to be that he fought the fire of hatred
with the fire of love and what does it take for you
to have that as a strength so you can match whatever comes your way
with something that's comparablely powerful something that's effective something that matches what comes your
way the Buddha and his teachings put a very high value on the this capacity to do
this very high value to do this no matter how
difficult the challenges you we have and some of the stories are in the
middle teachings of how to do this are kind of outrageous that you know the challenges that he describes that you
should always have loving kindness and and maybe it's religious
hyperbole you know that he's talking these examples but it puts an emphasis
like wow it is possible to develop oneself it is possible to
grow something so that we don't become victims
of what life brings but we become you know the
the I don't know
the first responder that's ready to meet any fire that comes our way
with something that can put it out
so I hope that uh gave you something to think about and uh
and reflect on and maybe it's a wonderful this idea of this Buddha and
the firehouse house is kind of a symbolic kind of tail
that maybe um
can be interpreted in other ways or well as well or can it be applied or elaborated if you think about it
so maybe you'll do that so um
I thought that rather than taking questions today maybe I'd like to suggest those of you
who are willing to stay that you form little groups of maybe three
and and have a little discussion about what this talk has evoked for you
and we have about 15 minutes or 10 minutes you know that we so we'll probably take maybe six seven minutes
for that and then we'll come back as a big group and then we can take some questions and hear a little bit more
and then we'll take a break and then at 11 o'clock we'll have the community meeting so if you don't mind turn to someone
near you and three or so people and introduce yourself and and
um and if you're not interested in staying then you thank you for being here okay