good day everyone it's wonderful to see all your greetings on
chat so our week of Brahma vihara practices is coming to its completion
today with the fourth and very indispensable Divine Abode
equinity equinity is an unshakable balance of mind and it
develops through these other Brahma viharas and also from insight and from
mindfulness practice looking at the world around us
and how life goes we really get to see how difficult it is to attain and
maintain balance of mind we can see life has its ups and
downs and swings between extremes sometimes pleasure and and pain success
and failure loss and gain praise and
blame we are naturally affected
emotionally we respond with happiness and sorrow Delight despair
disappointment satisfaction hope fear we find ourselves experiencing
waves of emotion taking us on the these ups
and downs and no sooner do we think we've come to more
stability then you know we're going along just fine and then we find ourselves caught again so equinity is
the wholesome state of mind that will help to stabilize Us in the face of all
of these experiences this this balance of mind
can help us be with any difficulty that comes our way and give us the resolve to
keep coming back to mindfulness again and again rather than being pushed
around and pulled around by The Human Condition Equanimity can nourish an
inner strength that offers strength to others in the face of all of the events that
give rise to each of our dissatisfaction stress and suffering both in our lives
individually and also as a planet and equinity can help us live
valiantly despite the inevitability of loss
sickness aging and death so this
morning I'll offer an Equanimity
practice uh if that fits for you today if it doesn't fit for you feel free to
let my voice Fade Into the background and continue with whatever practice is
most helpful to you for those who'd like to practice
Equanimity you can offer it to yourself if you're going through times that have
you up and down or you're experiencing some
difficulty or you can offer it to another person you know that you know is having a hard time
coping with difficulties um and this doesn't have to be the most difficult person in your
life it's better if it's not you can pick someone whose
difficulties um aren't affecting you in such a way that it would create
emotional reactivity in you so as we begin the
meditation receiving and recognizing how you are in this
moment perhaps scanning the body head to toe and allowing the in
breath to bring calm energy to each area of the
body and the out breath to release any stress or
tension taking deeper breaths if that that's
helpful gently aware of any area that cannot be
softened being present with it just as it is
and then when you're ready bringing to mind your own difficulty that has you
off balance or someone else in your life
whose difficulties are leaving them in a
struggle
it could be that the person you're offering the meditation to is challenging for you because you're
close sometimes we know someone's struggle very well but if we offer help they may seem
to rebuff that help
or this could be someone a family member friend you see during the holidays whose
political opinions vary greatly from yours and with whom a calm
discussion seems
impossible perhaps this is someone whose response
to challenges in their life is so very different from
yours that you have a hard time understanding
them whether it's you or someone else allowing yourself time to
remember this person's fundamental good
intentions seeing that they are doing their best to make their life work
well and Al also witnessing the ways that they are
struggling
and I'll offer some phrases that you might simply take in
allow yourself to hear them and see which ones fit for you
and if you find some that do fit for you you can silently whisper them in your
mind feel them in your heart whatever works best for
you I care for you but I cannot control your happiness or
unhappiness
things are just as they are right
now
whether I understand it or not things are
unfolding according to the way they naturally
unfold or according to the laws of
nature
remembering that inclining the mind in this way is not a demand for the other
person to change nor an expectation nor an agenda
and with equinity phrases you can be inclining the phrases
towards the person or towards your difficulty with
their being off balance or to
both joy and sorrow arise and pass
away this is a natural part of life's
journey no matter how I might wish things to be otherwise things are as they
are
I wish you happiness but cannot make your choices for
you
it is what it is right
now repeating these phrases or others that work well for
you
I care for you but I cannot control your happiness or [Music]
unhappiness things are just as they are right
now whether I understand it or not things
are unfolding according to the laws of
nature no matter how I might wish things to be otherwise things are as they
are
e
that
[Music]
so as Goodwill and en counters strong emotions in ourselves and
others it may become compassion when it sees suffering sympathetic Joy when it sees
happiness and equinity helps balance any suffering by including warmth and
care really important to know that Equanimity is not
indifferent or apathetic in the face of emotions or in the face of
suffering when we meet all experience with
mindfulness uh we can develop a perspective or an overview that knows
the strong emotions without being caught up in the in the stories around them and
in the things that get us caught we can cultivate this Jewel of
equinity which is an even- minded caring for anyone who is struggling an even-
minded happiness for anyone who's experiencing Good
Fortune it it doesn't look down on emotions or struggles as if
unaffected same way as I mentioned with compassion practice the proper practice of the
Brahma viharas includes this knowledge that if we had exactly the same set of
conditions as the person to whom we're sending our wishes we too would be
having the same experience as they um so we radiate or offer wishes of
goodwi compassion sympathetic Joy or
equinity uh from that standpoint of knowing that this too could be something
we could be going through when equinity is
available we can see events with understanding and we can
investigate the kinds of emotional events that lead to reactivity we can see
it of course this takes time and plenty of practice seeing mindfully seeing
clearly again and again to begin to understand the way that
clinging resists istance and delusion distort the mind in the presence of
anger fear sorrow and the whole gamut of human
emotions so to see the way we get caught in emotions it takes time to see
UNH wholesome behavior and wholesome Behavior as a separate matter from the
person or yourself equinity balances Goodwill that wishes
for everyone uh to come to the end of suffering it balances that with the
realization that we don't have control over how others behave over the
timetable for coming to the end of suffering the eonity balances that and
hand inand with compassion it can help us decide when to take
action so we can cultivate an ability to be open and present with anything that's
happening and discern when something is harmful and it's time to step in and
take action to stop it sometimes when people hear the word
equinity they believe they have to be devoid of emotion but those of us living the
householder so-called householder life can feel emotion and without dropping
down into being mired with them or stuck in them the heart and the mind can be
moved can care a great deal and still ret retain this level of objectivity and
balance that's offered with equinity with mindfulness and with uh
plenty of practice of the Brahma viharas or with a lot of mindfulness practice The Head and the Heart come
together and the wishes that we send or inclin towards well-being towards safety
happiness freedom freedom from suffering and the continued happiness of
others these These Things become heartfelt instead of just words and we're better able to access
equinity as well as the heartfelt quality of all of this so as we see the benefit of these
wholesome inclinations of mind the heart gradually opens it takes time for the heart to
know it in the process it grows the capacity to be with suffering in a
caring way instead of avoiding it or pitying it or keeping it at arms
length and this balance of mind this equinity makes a really important
contribution we learn not to suffer about suffering when there's
Equanimity the presence of it does not mean by the way that we agree with or
are passive about harm that's happening in the world it means we see that harm
is happening we know that causes and conditions have led to suffering and we
have enough confidence in the practice of mindfulness to face things as they
have come to be the poly word UPA is the word that's
translated as equinity and as one of the Brahma viharas it actually acts as a check or a
balance on the other three um you know it's functioning well when it stays
connected to meta or Goodwill to karuna or compassion and to mudita sympathetic
Joy instead of being indifferent um indifference is called
the near enemy of equinity because it could seem like it but it's not the same
at all um it prevents actually goodwi or meta from fear from veering into its
near enemy which is attachment and it prevents compassion
from lapsing into its near enemy which is
pity equinity prevents additional suffering from arising when we see suffering when we
feel it and see what's going on it balances happiness that Wells up in the
presence of other people's happiness and it prevents the near enemy of Joy which
is becoming overly excited which is kind of getting hooked
into other people's happiness or your own happiness to a degree that's not no
longer balanced equinity remains caring through
the development of the other Brahma viharas instead of hardening into
indifference the mind and the Heart know enough about how causes and conditions
result in painful experience and equinity can maintain a
neutrality an emotional balance with a gentle heart and a wise mind that
develop as we practice mindfulness and as we practice the
Brahma viharas no matter how much we cultivate
Limitless loving kindness and Goodwill there will be people there will be those
whose actions are harmful and those who cannot change will
not change as I mentioned in the meditation when we offer these
wishes these are not agendas for other people to change they're not magical thinking that because I wish it someone
else is going to change we can see clearly what the
options are what the um prospects are or the potential and we can even work
towards change but we are still balanced and even mind minded with
equinity it this is a quality that clearly sees comma and comma or
karma in this case means only that actions lead to
consequences that causes and conditions unfold in certain ways so no matter how
desperately we might wish for things not to be the way they are the mature heart
and mind that have matured by witnessing the way things come to be again and again witnessing consequences actions
and consequences the mature heart and mind come to some ability to see the
reality the truth of things in a balanced way by seeing with
awareness the arising and passing of myriad human
experiences we come to know that our conditioned life is marked by the three
characteristics of conditioned existence inconstancy um which is sometimes called
impermanence um the unsatisfactoriness of things that we cannot rely on them
partly because they change and they're impermanent and then that of what's
sometimes called no self which means that said neither we nor anyone else nor
anything has a fixed character that's always going to be the
same there are different facets of knowing that things change whether in the short term or the
long term so equinity allows us to be effective with what we cannot
change for example if someone close to you is dying of a terminal illness being
upset protesting none of that is going to help them or you but you can let equinity
this balance of Mind help you relinquish or give up your desire that it not be
true give up the fighting against it give up the wish this can't be happening
and instead focus on where you can be of support so this is the ultimate in in
responsiveness instead of reactivity I'd like to end with a
reading um by Khalil Jabron that's kind of interesting with
respect to this week then said a rich man speak to us of
giving and he answered you give but little when you give of your possessions
it is when you give of yourself that you truly give for what are your possessions but
things you keep and guard for fear you may need them tomorrow and tomorrow what
shall tomorrow bring to the over prudent dog burying bones in the trackless sand
as he follows the pilgrims to the holy city and what is fear of need but need
itself is not dread of thirst when your well is full thirst that is
unquenchable there are those who give little of the much which they have and
they give it for recognition and their hidden desire makes their gifts UNH
wholesome and there are those who have little and give it
all these are the Believers in life and the Bounty of life and their Coffer is
never empty there are those who give with joy and that Joy is their reward and there
are those who give with pain pain and that pain is their baptism and there are those who give and
know not pain in giving nor do they seek Joy nor give with mindfulness of virtue
they give as in Yonder Valley the Myrtle breathes its fragrance into
space through the hands of such as these God speaks and from behind their eyes he
smiles upon the Earth It is Well to give when asked but it is better to give when
unasked though understanding excuse me through understanding and to the open-handed the
search for one who shall receive is Joy greater than giving and is there ought
you would withhold all you have shall someday be
given therefore give now that the season of giving may be yours and not your
inheritors you often say I would give but only to the deserving The Orchards
in the trees in your Orchards say not so nor the flocks in your pasture they
give that they may live for to withhold is to perish surely he who is worthy to
receive his days and nights is worthy of all else from you and he who has
deserved to drink from the ocean of Life deserves to fill his cup from your little stream
and what desert greater shall there be than that which lies in the courage and
confidence nay the charity of receiving and who are you that
men should Rend their bosom and unveil their pride that you may see their worth
naked and their pride unabashed see first that you yourself
deserve to be a giver the instrument of giving for in truth it is life that
gives unto life while you who deem yourself a giver are but a witness and
you receivers and you are all receivers assume no weight of gratitude lest you
lay a yoke upon yourself and upon whom who gives rather rise together with the
giver on his gifts as on wings for to be over mindful of your debt is to doubt
his generosity who has the freeheart Earth for mother and God for
father so I love this encouragement to give which is at the basis of our
sending wishes to others for Good Will and to ourselves for Good Will
compassion sympathetic joy and equinity wishing you all uh the benefits
of the Brahma viharas hope to see any of you who would like to come to happy hour on week Nights from 6:00 to 7: to
continue to cultivate these and thank you so much for your practice this
week wishing you all continued beautiful practice bye