so good morning everyone and um I'm very happy to be here with you all
and some of that happiness is being with all of you but some of it is um caring with me from my last three weeks thought
that I was at the tasahara's and Mountain Center
and uh it's uh probably the oldest Buddhist Monastery in the country
and when it started in 1967 it was kind of revolutionary because it was co-ed
which was a very very unusual to have men and women practicing together more or less as equals I think that
equality improved over there decades
and um the um
and I trained there I began my training there and spent
about three years there and I started 43 years ago
in 1980 and um so I went back and really went back the
first time to be a zen teacher there more or less I've been back as a visitor
over these years but to go back into my original kind of Zen training Monastery
where I have some I was really formed in bit many ways in Buddhism in my training
at that monastery and to be back there not only to be back in the place and but to be back there
practicing and it was a it was a practice event for three weeks a practice period
and to be practicing there where you know these memories would come back well I was standing there when that happened
and that happened over here and and in the meditation Halls knowing these different spots that were so
significant for me when Ron visited them and bowed to them because oh yeah this is where I sat when this happened or
this and that was quite uh and um but I think one of the uh very
interesting at least for me occurrences of being there was to
realize how long I've been doing this Buddhist practice I've been involved now for 50 years
and um and that's long enough to have an overview of what happens to a
person doing Buddhist practice for 50 years not just what happens on one Retreat or
one meditation session but what happens over the decades in that decade in that decade and and it
felt kind of natural it's kind of spontaneous being there to kind of kind of have an overview of
this life that I've had in Buddhist practice and it might be interesting for to hear
a little bit of it not so much because me but because to appreciate the way in which Buddhist
practice works on people because they're and the Highlight for me was not so much was about this is that
it works in ways that you don't see at the time that there's a way in which things
change gradually over years and then in retrospect you look
back and say oh yeah look at that I didn't I had no idea I thought I was doing X
but really the universe was doing why for me you know the Dharma the practice
was and why is wet flower not X I was distracted by my
what I thought was important in the moment what my plans were with my expectation what the agendas I have to
notice that something different was happening and I would say some of the profound ways that I've Been Changed by
the Dharma I didn't foresee I didn't see him coming
I didn't see them happening as they were happening they happen gradually and in retrospect
oh that's what happened so I wanted to that might be nice to me
to talk to you about this and I said part of this introduction also is to say that
um that the Dharma practice this Buddhist practice mindfulness practice
Works in three time frames it works in the immediate present
it works in the short term and it works in the long term it has ways in which it
unfolds and it's important to appreciate all three because if you only think it happens
over the long term you might mess up the long term because you're straining and
trying to working for some change that's going to happen in the Mythic future and you're missing the present
and if you're only seeing the benefits of the present you might not really allow yourself to
give yourself over fully to the practice so that the long-term benefits can
flower and develop over time to have some sense of the possibility of what this where we're going is also
important and so this combination of the cherishing and loving the practice in
the moment and valuing what happens and also evaluing what happens over time
the um and in the moment you know just as we're practicing it even sitting here
meditating with you it could feel sometimes at the moment of mindfulness it doesn't have to be more
than a moment is that when mindfulness is clear there's a kind of a lightening
up a kind of opening up a kind of calming or spaciousness I like to call
the breathing room certainly is a breathing room for this what's happening now
some people will talk a lot about mindfulness being kind of a pause and if
that's the case I like to think of it as a sacred pause and uh it's a pause that just long
enough to check in and feel no experience what's he what's the present moment
experience is like and uh and that that movement of
attention to the present moment that has some higher quality than ordinary distracted attention
is very different than most people live their lives we are many people are mostly distracted mostly running around
and um and uh my wife just told me she read a
newspaper article I think I said this morning or yesterday about why attendance and churches are
going down and uh and one reason many reasons I suppose but one is that among young
people is they're just so busy and uh so Sunday morning you're not
going to go to church on Sunday morning when you want to spend time finally with your friends because you've been working and overworking and doing all kinds of
things and so so this idea of of uh you know of taking taking time and I'm not to feel and
sense to stop to have a higher quality attention to what's happening in this moment
and they're discovering lo and behold it feels really good lo and behold it feels better than some
of the Alternatives and one of the Alternatives is to brush off and do things half-heartedly or distractedly or
one of the great things that's part of I think Modern Life is to do things efficiently
and uh and even better not only efficiently but do things multiple things at the same time efficiently
and just you know so you can do more and more and more things and one of the really big
disappointments I have for you about mindfulness practice and Buddhist practice is that it is not efficient
and um so if that's what you're into upswept you this is probably not for you
and you know if it was efficient you would come to MC and say why are we sitting 35 minutes I can nail that
meditation in 10 minutes and then you go off and do the important
things and um so but they're really big and
appreciating something really precious and how in some ways the the
precious and wonderful experience of being alive even with the great
challenges of life even the tragedies of life there's something about really knowing how to be present for it in a
full way even present for a broken heart uh even present as we cried that there
is something that is invaluable and and kind of to be cherished or valued
and one of the ways to evaluate is to um is to realize
for yourself that just about all the alternatives to being really Mindful and present for
it go through life um it is not not a it's not
a better alternative than mindfulness if you know of a better alternative than
being mindful then probably to go ahead and do it did I say that with some confidence
because with time you realize this is the best alternative to really be here and present in a good
way and that the rewards of that can be instantaneous just right here it feels good and that's my hope for all of you
is that you will learn enough about mindfulness to feel the instantaneous
rewards the benefits of this is good I'm glad I had that moment to be present I
don't regret it as opposed to if I could have been on Amazon
and um so it so this practice works in the moment it also works in the short term
and some of you might have experienced this just in this meditation session we had that maybe you're a bit because you
sat there long enough maybe something settled in you maybe you're a little bit calmer maybe your mind slow down
maybe it took a while for the business of the mind to stop and quite I don't know so you can feel connected here and
feel like you're showing up here it could be that you carried a lot of attention with you that you didn't even
know stress of the week or the day and this was long enough to let that be
dissipate partly because not because necessarily you were brilliant at being mindful
uh but he just stopped you stopped running around stop checking your
devices stop kind of you know and just being still for a while there is a kind of progression of
Letting Go and relaxing that is invaluable for people and if you add to that recipe
mindfulness attention concentration compassion kindness there's all kinds of wonderful things
that can happen in in a period of meditation or it can happen in over a week of regular practice or going on our
meditation Retreats that's remarkable that most people who go on a week-long
retreat will see it as a journey this is it unfolds over time and not a few people want to leave after
the first day if we advertised what the which we was about based on what happens the first
day no one would come and uh the uh but it's a little bit like
you know when I when I had a running practice that I started up at the monastery and it was um the the police
who ride run was up this Five Mile Road eventually I got it to the top but we
just slowly over the long time kind of get better and better but I remember
I would start up the road and probably the first 300 yards it felt
like every cell in my body was screaming at me stop I hated it it was horrible
and um and then I um something kicked in and they got into the flow and after a
while it felt like you know after I did for a while trained for a while it just felt like it was just that light to run
and and kind of like the body ran itself and until I you know got winded or something but it was really nice so a
little bit like that happens on Retreats too that there's a transition acclimating getting attuned letting go
of the tensions of our life having to resolve some of being surprised by all the unresolved issues in our life that
suddenly appear that you've been overlooking or distracted from and having to work through them so the
transitions at first aid is really invaluable and important thing to go through
um and um and uh but it's often challenging for people and then things
settle down sometimes and
I don't want to make any promises and they settle down and usually by at
some point people feel so happy to be present and
alive and calm and there's a Clarity of vision people start to go outside we're
lovely to watch people go outside of the retreat center to be outdoors in the in the property after about day four and
they're just like marveling at the trees and the flowers and I'm just kind of just sitting having
a tea as if the cup of tea is there long lost friend they're so happy to see and
be with and they're they're just really there for that cup it sounds maybe a little silly to live
that way but it's just such a you know to have that level of calmness and that
level of presence and that level of undistractedness and that level of non-compulsion that we often live with
is phenomenal so this trend you know it takes some days and the sometimes the
longer the retreat the deeper the process goes the Fuller this transformation can happen
so there's there's this change that happens over time and on Retreats for example in a daily
meditation practice you might do there is a kind of change that happens in over
a day or over a particular session over a week or something but often some of the most obvious
benefits from that disappear once you get to work once you start up once you
get back to your usual life and sometimes it disappears in a few minutes sometimes in a few days but it and but
there's also the changes that happen there enduring but that those are tend to be incremental over time
and often they're so incremental we don't see them and the analogy that I've used
sometimes is that uh when I lived in Hawaii for two years when I first got there uh it'd be a nice
sunny day like no clouds in the sky and you know you wear t-shirts and shorts you know and and you certainly don't go
around with an umbrella there because it's sunny warm hot and then they would suddenly out of
nowhere there'd be this torrential downpour and so I did what
everywhere else I lived in the world you do is you Run for Cover
and I very quickly learned you don't have to do that in Hawaii you just let yourself get drenched
and then five minutes later you're all dried out again
Sons come out again and and um and so the drenching doesn't last very long
where I was born in Norway and the town is called Bergen it's surrounded by mountains on three
sides in the ocean on the fourth and the saying there this it rains 360 days of
the year and the other five days it's cloudy it isn't quite as bad as that but the
the local newspaper used to have on the front page a tally of how many sunny
days there's been every year every day of the year so you you're adding up over the course of the year started zero on
January 1st and so anyway so there there was a lot
of all kinds of rain but there was often a Misty Rain that you know light Mr rain
and I would walk through the town and and I wouldn't it was so light that you
didn't really feel you're getting wet at first but if you're walking far enough uh got totally soaked and drenched and
because it was cold it would be really cold so it snuck up on you so a little bit just to stretch you know
a little bit if you're generous to the analogies um the uh going on a week-long retreat
is like getting drenched and then um and then you know it dries out kind
of quickly but if you meditate every day or if you go on Retreats often or if you
live in a monastery and you're practicing kind of all the time it's a little bit like being in the fog or in
the mist and you're slowly getting wet and um and uh but you don't get cold and
you get your heart just warms more and more as you get this kind of Dharma Dharma Mist coming soaking it soaking up
and um and slowly something begins happening but you don't see it happening
and um and so over years over decades that I can speak now it's kind of
remarkable I can speak about decades it's kind of snuck up on me
and that I can see there there have been phases and changes that happen over you
know big chunks of time and um and it speaks to a little bit the
natural process of change that you put together the right conditions that there's something that begins happening
within that's kind of natural because I wasn't trying to do this or attempting to do these kinds of changes somehow the
psychophysical system that we are has capacities for changing in beneficial
ways growing in certain ways that sometimes we don't realize our society hasn't taught us that this
is a possibility perhaps so I want to share with you uh three
phases over this time that were very significant for me and the first phase was when I first
came to Zen practice kind of the Zen practice phase and that was new to practice then and as
is true for many people I came to the practice because I suffered and um
and I thought that's you know but I tried different things and I didn't know anything else to do for my suffering but
to try to you know I'd been introduced to Zen practice a little bit and I said okay this this is kind of what I thought
would maybe make a difference for me and in fact when I sat meditated and did
Retreats at the Zen Center that's one of the things that came to the Forefront was my suffering and some of the deeper
uh ways in which my mind my heart worked that accentuated or was the cause the
operating principles for my suffering so for example I had a lot of
self-criticism I had a lot of guilt I mean not just necessarily had done anything wrong I just be guilt I would
literally was I felt guilty how I walked across the meditation hall floor I was probably walking across the floor
the wrong way you know just so anything you know as I was doing it the wrong way and I was somehow inherently
wrong it was kind of a big burden and the fear of rejection and all my fears that I had
and so I would sit and meditate and these would part of the benefit and the horror of practice is you get to see
your mind well wow like look at that this is bad you know I had no idea
and uh but it's really good to see it because then we can take an honest assessment we can take an we can see it
clearly enough that we don't give into it we learn to find Alternatives we learn to heal it
and um so for me I I said so I because in Zen practice they get very little
instruction except sit sit still and be still and don't move
and just be with whatever's happening so that and so there was no they didn't tell me what to do about the suffering
except I I what I understood just be with it so I did add a little extra instructions to myself and that was to
unconditionally accept whatever was happening so I was practicing unconditional acceptance not of the suffering but of
being present for it just just being within being with it and that was a tenderizing process kind of like
tenderizing meat something began to soften in me and soften than me and I didn't see it happening I didn't
recognize it as happening but and some of it when it began happening I was
projecting what my needs were into the world and the need I have in the contact with
my suffering this tenderizing of what's Happening was compassion and and I started first being very
strongly drawn to images of compassion and one and some of them was the images
of the the Mahayana the Japanese images of the great bodhisattva the archetype
of compassion abulakateshvara and um and I started collecting
photographs and pictures of Kuan yin and putting it on my wall I started drawing
copies of them and I just thought it was a nice thing to do to have these I didn't think about what I was doing I
didn't think of wow you're really connecting collecting all these pictures of compassion and then I would Project Compassion onto
people that I saw and sometimes I would say well that person is so compassionate
and people would look at me you got to be kidding
but uh but for me they were it was you know and I know some of it was projection because at the Zen Center
they had a statue that for many years I didn't know what
that what the name this title of the statue was the artwork it was about five feet tall and you'd see it when you came
up in the meditation in the basement it would be you come up the steps and be directly in front of me back then
directly on top of the steps right in front of you you have to walk towards it and um it was kind of so I said are we
and it looked a little bit like a very a very abstract kind of person by the size
of a person and maybe kind of the narrowness of a person going up and and it was very very sin that's sensuous
but very flowing beautiful flowing almost like it had robes that were flowing and I thought that it was uh this this
archetype of compassion condom and I just would come up from meditation
it'd be so moved to see her standing there receiving me
many years later I found out that the artist thought he was carving a flame
and as a title The Flame fire and uh
and uh so you know I guess it was a projection that I had and so and also I
would feel that the wind is sometimes blowing against my cheek I was being stroked by compassion
probably was a projection you know so I was looking for needing to receive
compassion in all kinds of ways and I did I did encounter compassionate people at the Zen Center who in times of my
distress it was so impressed me and uh I mean so there's such a big difference on me to feel and be with
them and So eventually looking back over my time at Zen Center I saw that
I didn't become enlightened I became compassioned
and uh and my sense of my capacity for compassion grew and grew steadily until
near the end of my time at Zen Center I made a commitment about I was part of
the being ordained as a priest there's a monk there that I was going to dedicate my life to
the compassionate service to the world to the suffering of the world I wanted to somehow I'd met my own suffering and
now I wanted to meet and support others the world to not suffer so the compassion became like the
operating principle for how I was going to organize my life and live my life and that's kind of what brought me here you
know to IMC to you today that that momentum of that choice to live from
compassion and you know that was huge so after my phase at the San Francisco
Zen Center I found myself somewhat by coincidence by
bye not exactly by plan
in them in a monastery that taught to be passana inside meditation in Thailand
and that opened the door for me to continue with that this practice that we do here
and um and I was pretty happy doing the practice and I did the practice in Asia
first and then I came back to do here and I
did it at the Insight Meditation Society in in Massachusetts kind of the earliest
big Center in our tradition and I did a three-month Retreat there
and I was kind of shocked or stunned when I got there to practice the first
time with with the Western sightings with just Western teachers because and it's part of my surprise
because I came from Zen which is serious and just direct pointing to emptiness
the truth and you know and being kind of disciplined and stoic and you're like you know
you know you're supposed to go and in fact when I practice said I I had
an up up I would sit there I have this this classic I wasn't trying to do it but maybe because the attitude that that
comes along this upside down smile
so then I came to to you know this this what this the personality inside
teachers in Massachusetts and they did a surprising thing they did a guided meditation on loving
kindness oh my God I mean for a Zen student like at least
for this one it was like that's artificial that's too saccharine and you know this
can't be real and so so I did the reasonable thing I thought I just tuned
the teachers out when they were doing this guy's meditation and that worked pretty well for me
until because three months is a long time about halfway through the retreat I
was just minding my own business meditating and lo and behold this very strange odd
feeling arose inside of me this I don't know about this
and it wasn't you know this is what they're talking about when they do this guided meditations this is love this is
loving kindness this is this beautiful feeling of Goodwill that is very different than the feeling
of compassion and oh that's what it is so then when
they did a guided meditation oh this is great and now I think it's fantastic to do it
and um and so I wasn't looking for loving kindness I didn't even want it I was maybe holding it at a distance
and it found me and why was that what is it about to be
part for a long time I thought it was because of a personal practice is somehow different but I think I now lately I think it's
because I'd gone through my phase of working with my suffering when I needed compassion
by the time I came to the opossum I was ready for a new phase in the phase for
me was a phase of a lot of well-being I had a lot of joy and well-being and
happiness peace in doing vipassana and not initially but as I went deeper and
deeper into it in a way that I never had in Zen I had degrees of it in times of
it but with vipassanide was extended periods of great feelings of joy and
delight and and uh you know and um and so one of the
byproducts of spending a lot of time feeling really happy and delighted in this practice
is um I think is delighting into people feeling kind of happy in people and
seeing the beauty of people or seeing the pressuredness of others and and in that kind of so not not viewing
people through the lens of through the lens of suffering and they're suffering but viewing people through the lens of
their of how wonderful people are and and how and feeling friendly and feeling
appreciative and feeling grateful and feeling a tremendous Goodwill for others
and so at that phase so so so then there was a whole phase where that was kind of
a character of kind of of kind of what motivated him and where
I found myself when I just love this idea of Goodwill and loved people and delighted in them and and felt you know
felt all this French friendliness or something that grew and developed and
and some of that is because of having this community here at IMC for the last 30 years or so that the opportunity to
get to know people here and know them in a in a nice way I just had this was so
many opportunities to just be so appreciative and grateful and and kind of see the beauty of people that I kept
kind of feeding this kind of Goodwill feeling that was growing in me and I wasn't trying to do it but it slowly
grew and grew and grew it was kind of wonderful to see it grow and develop
well let me look back and see how it developed so that was nice and then something different happened
and this is kind of the phase maybe that I'm in now or maybe I'm due to have this one end
and something new will happen I don't know the the spans of great spans of time
and that was that I started feeling something different and I still called it compassion
but it had a very different feeling than before and it started to have this enlighteness
and a sense of ease there's just in fact a sense of ease and lightness and and
peacefulness around this feeling of compassion um it could cause some problems for me
because I thought compassion was supposed to be a kind of empathic pain
with the suffering of others and uh and I felt like well I didn't
feel that I felt I I felt people's pain I was cared for it I was concerned for
it but I found myself feeling kind of at ease in the presence of it
and am I allowed to feel this at ease when people are suffering people come and tell me tragedies and I feel ease is
that okay am I shouldn't I be kind of distressed
and uh and then with the social justice movements that have kind of the occurred
the last 20 years or so the trends in that movement uh there was
kind of an expectation of uh there's you should be angry or and the climate change you should be
distressed you should be upset and and I certainly cared about all these things but I just couldn't find
myself getting angry or being distressed about all this
um because of this place of kind of this lightness was kind of it wasn't like a
choice it was like why would I give it up why would I be in a good state
that feels healthy and whatever why would I give it up for something that
feels kind of a little bit like having a wound wounding myself or yeah wanting myself to do it
even though there may be there was an expectation or I had some idea that was supposed to be different
and so it was actually it wasn't so conscious that I was struggling with this but in retrospect I saw that I was
constantly kind of up against this and working this and and kind of trying to navigate this Territory between this
ease and lightness and peacefulness that I found inside and how that was supposed
to be in the interactions with the people and suffering and the Injustice
that we find around us in our society and um and then what kind of finally
clarified for me what I was doing was I was reading the teachings ancient teachings of the Buddha and I discovered
there that that um there's discussion about karuna which is
compassion but there's a whole other kind of emotion or attitude or motivation that has gotten very little
press in the West that is actually more important for the Buddha's way in which he cared for the
world taught the world and that is the term Anu kampa and an accompa in some ways is a more
humble or simpler or more basic ordinary
caregiving instinct to caregiving attitude that clearly in the ancient
texts is like how parents care for their kids so
teachers care for their students uh
people who care for children have this under comfort for the their kids in
their care so anacampa was the ordinary just offering care to people caring for
people but this was the common way that Buddha operated in the world was through this under kampa
and it's defined as a wanting working for the welfare and happiness of others
not not working to and alleviate suffering for others but the welfare and happiness I understand that that's that
compassion is a subset of that when they're suffering we want to bring
that suffering to an end but a wider scope of care includes also for people
who aren't suffering want them to be well and happy but more important what I saw when I
started reading about this that this was a common way in which people had
beginning letting go of her clinging letting go of their attachments operating the world in the ancient texts
they operated from this anukampa this care and it was an expression of their
non-clinging and I said oh I'm no longer centered on
compassion I thought it was but now I have this other thing called care
anacampa because now I'm I'm constantly being informed by or Guided by the
experience of non-clinging the experience of non-attachment this is such an important reference point for me
and it's so clear that I'm better off not clinging better off not being attached
than I am being attached and why would I give up the non-attachment when attachment is a
wound is a form of harm to myself and maybe sometimes a harm to the world
so so I've come to really appreciate this kind of new phase of how to be in
the world and care for the world to care for the world with care with this you know character you know
supported by this non-clinging aspect and that also kind of uh you know
evolved slowly over time I didn't see it coming I didn't plan it it wasn't what I was expecting at all
so first I was compassioned then I was loving kinded
and now I've been cared so that was a you know so you know
there's all kinds of other things you could say I can I can report about these many years of change but those kind of
Stand Out stood out to me at the Sahara as I was kind of thinking about and
reviewing my life and how all in these 40 50 years in which I've been involved
in Buddhism and the practice so I hope that this gives you some
encouragement that how this practice can work for you
and one of the more some of the profound ways you don't measure the results by the moment or the week or
the month you don't feel like a kid in the back of the car says are we there yet
rather just just do the practice and in what we what I learned in Zen if you do
the practice then at some point the practice does you
and you and then you need to be available for the practice to do you the practice to practice you it isn't just
you doing it because it was only you doing it that wouldn't be enough you have to also get out of the way
and be available for something deeper in your heart in your inner life to kind of
begin working on you so I hope that was encouraging and that
for me it was been a spectacularly wonderful way of of living a life I'm very grateful for
the opportunity and I'm grateful to be here with you and to share it thank you
and be lovely to see all of you or some of you at the park
that's about probably about seven minutes away from here by car and um
the red Morton Park and there's a there's a small parking lot and a big parking lot at the park
and um and that big one I think is on Roosevelt
Rosa off Roosevelt which and so um you probably want to park
there so um thank you all