it's been such a pleasure to practice with you all this week and today is day five of five and we're
continuing on this theme The Poetry of
practice and there's a way in which poetry can highlight or emphasize or
maybe even like shine a light on maybe some of those dark and hidden crevices
of our hearts and Minds those parts that we don't necessarily look at maybe we're
not even intending to not look at them for they just for whatever reason don't
get seen and this is part of uh the power of poetry is that they help us to see them
and maybe even bring some light-heartedness or bring some new perspective or maybe even some
spaciousness like oh yeah I had seen that and with that recognition of
something new there can be some Delight or some openness or like wow okay I
hadn't seen that before so that's part of the power of poetry is to help us see what hasn't
been seen But coupled with this sense of recognition like oh yeah that is there I
just was not paying attention to it before
more so as I've been doing in the preceding days as part of this series I'll drop in a poem during the guided
meditation but let's start with a guided meditation so taking a meditation
posture maybe starting by taking a few few long slow deep
breaths as a way to connect to the breath to the body to
this
moment there's a way in which the physiology of the body responds to
deeper breaths particularly longer
exhales activates the nervous system in a way that promotes
relaxation so just a few longer breaths to
support relaxation or some letting go of [Music] tension but also so to support our
connection to the bodily
experience tuning into the experience of
sitting in this posture whatever posture you're
in what is it like to be in this posture
today at this
moment
maybe doing a light General body skin and noticing if there are areas of
tightness or tension or places where there might be some more
opening softness ease
available not because we have to get rid of any tension or
tightness just because this recognition that openness and
ease is the direction that our practice
goes and part of how we go that [Music]
direction is being sensitive tuned into what's
happening with an attitude of
allowing as best we can as best we
can
sometimes tension is very subtle around the eyes or the jaw
mouth
sometimes the shoulders are raised up just a little
bit
tuning into the sensations of
breathing and a relaxed warm
[Music] manner with some care
respect for this body that's
breathing
is it possible to set the direction the
attitude of this meditation session as one of care and
warmth
openness
part of the way this warmth and
Care can can be expressed is when we notice that the
mind is no longer on the sensations of
breathing can there be an attitude of oh look at
that okay let's just begin again with the sensations of
breathing
I'm going to drop in a
poem you don't need to do anything with this
poem just allow it to enter into the
space you don't have to figure it out you don't have to have a
commentary I'll talk a little bit more about it after the guided
meditation
but during the guided meditation just
listen I like rexs I like ex junkies I like flunks and ex
flunkies I like the way the career lless career I like flat beer I like people
who tell half stories and forget the rest I like people who make Doodles in
important written tests I like being late I like fate I
like the way teeth great I like laceless shoes cordless Blues I like the one bar
Blues I like buttonless coats and leaky boats I like rubbish tips and bitten
lips I like yesterday's toast I like cold tea I like reality
I like ashtrays I write and like crap plays I like curtains that don't quite
shut I like bread knives that don't quite cut I like rips and blue jeans I
like people who can't say what they mean I like spiders with no legs pencils
with no lead ants with no heads worms that are half
dead I like holes I like coffee cold I like creases in neat
folds I like signs that just don't know where they're going I like Angry poems I
like the way you can't pin down the sea
see I like the way you can't pin down the seat e
see
for
[Music]
all
so hello again welcome welcome
everybody and the short little few words that I
said before the beginning of the guided meditation I mentioned that poetry
sometimes helps us to see things in a little bit different way or maybe to see
things that we wouldn't otherwise see poking into the crevices of our hearts
and minds and Shining a light and hopefully in a way that maybe has a sense of recognition like oh yeah I had
noticed that so that's a little bit about what this poem is like maybe I'll read the
poem or maybe I'll make a few comments before I read the poem so I would say just in general like
this really broad brush about practice Buddhist practice this has a few
movements you might say uh directionality towards greater
understanding of both ourself and others but as well as this movement towards
greater ease and well-being and this movement towards the
diminishment and elimination of suffering so these all these are
happening together this uh with practice and make another really big uh
generalization I would say that there's these two primary types of practices
like subsets of practicing and one is this cultivation developing building
strengthening and the other is Letting Go it's releasing shedding
renouncing so we have both of these types of practices that help support these three
different movements this movement towards greater understanding greater ease and less
suffering so this poem I think that uh helps us
maybe with uh all of this there's a way in which and I'll talk a little bit more about this but it helps with this uh
cultivation and with letting go so the
poem is by Lem CE the last name is spelled s i SS a y it's called something
I like by LM CE I like Rex I like X junkies I like
flunks and ex flunkies I like the way the career lless career I like flat beer
I like people who tell half stories and forget the rest I like people who make
Doodles in important written tests I like being late I like fate I like the
way teeth grade I like laceless shoes cordless Blues I
like the one bar Blues I like buttonless coats and leaky boats I like rubbish
tips and bitten lips I like yesterday's toast I like a cold tea I like
reality I like ashtrays I write and like crap
plays I like curtains that don't quite shut I like bread knives that don't
quite cut I like rips and blue jeans I like people who can't say what they mean
I like spiders with no legs pencils with no lead ants with no heads worms that
are half dead I like holes I like coffee cold I like creases in neat folds I like
signs that just don't know where they're going I like Angry poems I like the way
you can't pin down the C
see there's just for me I just feel so much delight with this poem and maybe I'll clarify that the
very last word c is H the verb like to see
visualize so I like the way you can't pin down the C and that's like the body of water the ocean and then the next
line is just C so feel like this is like an imperative
the poet is asking us to just see and what is it that we're
seeing well maybe we're seeing all the ways in which we don't have
unconditional regard for our fellow beings maybe we're seeing all the ways
that our preferences like push us around the things that we like and the
things that we don't like are we're always trying to avoid void what we don't like and move towards what we do
and wow how much of life's energy gets put towards or used up just
to move away from the things that we don't like or just even mildly
irritating and I have to say this poem is I just kept find myself reading it over and over because I kept on finding
all these little delightful things in it that I hadn't seen before
and I feel like this poet LM ceis has this uh not only the content of the poem
but the way there's this musicality there's this Rhythm to it that just uh
feels like it kind of feels like it builds up and there's maybe a crescendo somewhere in there and of
course that's part of the way that I'm reading it out loud to you all but there's a way in which it's
written too and where the line breaks are it has this uh I don't know maybe some playfulness
too maybe this uh Whimsy that we can allows us maybe to
chuckle at ourselves as opposed to maybe be filled with shame or something to
this recognition like oh yeah yeah these are some of the things I actually don't like and uh here's this
poet just maybe highlighting that for us by saying these are the things that I like
so maybe I will say that this in with regards to Buddhist practice feel like
this poem is pointing to both cultivation and letting go maybe this cultivating the generosity of spirit
this generosity of heart and mind that is more
unconditional that isn't setting limits on what our heart can hold it
isn't setting limits on what the mind can be open
to instead maybe the poet is pointing out to all the ways in which we have set
limits conditions yeah I only like this but not like that but I feel like this poem is
pointing to the possibility of unconditional
warmth care kindness and maybe that's why the poem
like speaks to us I'll say it speaks to me partly for this reason just it points
to the potential for this unconditionality this Limitless care warmth
respect and I would say this poem is also in the same way maybe pointing to the same thing but using different
language it's pointing to the possibility of let letting go of our
preferences I like this I don't like that and this quiet expectation that we
have that experiences things people please us or at least don't annoy
us and then this openness this acceptance really only happens when
there's not a strong sense of self and we've relaxed or abandoned or let go
or softened this strong sense of me against the world US versus
them I versus you and that has been let go of and softened then
everything something that we can like take Delight in or
notice see as the poet's using the the end see just to
notice so I would say part of the power of the poem is this
unexpectedness and maybe the sense of that it creates a sense of space in the
when you hear the poem or read the poem like oh yeah I don't have to say that I
don't like this or I don't like that so here it is I I'll read it one
more time I like Rex I like X junkies I like
flunks and X flunkies I like the way the career lless career I like flat beer I
like people who tell half stories and forget the rest I like people who make Doodles in important written tests I
like being late I like fate I like the way teeth great I like laceless shoes
cordless Blues I like the one bar Blues I like buttonless coats and leaky boats
I like rubbish tips and bitten lips I like yesterday's toast I like cold tea I
like reality I like ash trays I write and like crap plays I like curtains that
don't quite shut I like bread knives that don't quite cut I like rips and
blue jeans I like people who can't say what they mean I like spiders with no
legs pencils with no lead ants with no heads worms that are half dead I like
holes I like coffee cold I like creases and neat folds I like signs that just
don't know where they're going I like Angry poems I like the way you can't pin
down the sea see
I don't know I'm just I have a just a feeling of delight and I'd like to share this delight with
you and then maybe I will end our time together these five days of practice the
Poetry of practice with a another poem that I'd like to leave you with this is
a poem that also has some playfulness in it some Whimsy and but maybe some
encourag to help us practice with this unconditional noticing this
unconditional care this unconditional warmth to fellow beings fellow
situations to whatever life brings
us so this poem is called on International kindness
Day by Rosemary traumer
again I'll say it's called on International kindness Day by Rosemary
traumer and it goes like
this kindness went out and got itself a new engine a twin turbo premium unleaded
V6 cylinder engine something with real oomph something that provides a bit of
giddy up when the going gets tough turns out kindness likes
horsepower a lot of horsepower plus it's sprung for direct
fuel injection to maximize its power output everyone thinks kindness prefers
things quiet and calm but kindness is ready for action ready to Take On The
World ready to travel every back road every Highway every Main Street and get
this ever loving show on the road there's a whole lot of work to do
I love this kind of this idea right of kindness going out and getting a new engine and maybe that's what practice is
about maybe practice is about getting a new engine for
kindness kindness for ourselves and kindness for
others with some of this unconditionality sprinkled in
there maybe I'll read this poem one last a second time it's on International
kindness Day by Rosemary trummer kindness went out and got itself
a new engine a twin turbo premium unledded V6 cylinder engine something
with real oomph something that provides a bit of giddy up when the going gets
tough turns out kindness likes horsepower a lot of hor power plus it
sprung for direct fuel injection to maximize its power output everyone thinks kindness prefers
things quiet and calm but kindness is ready for action ready to Take On The
World ready to travel every back road every Highway every Main Street and get
this everloving show on the road there's a whole lot of work to
do and with that I'll end our time together thank you thank you for your
practice and for allowing me to join this sa for these days thank
you