so hello everyone Welcome to our meditation session
and the
one of the very important principles in Buddhist
practice in Buddhism one of the
principles that when we live by it or when we observe it in the world
can be a source of tremendous inspiration and and happiness
one of the it's a profound principle for human life it's a profound aspect of
Love itself and that is the dedication to non-harming
and non-harming is maybe not often associated with love
because sometimes love is expected to be much more active
actively having a positive regard actively having feelings of Good Will
and compassion and and appreciation and all kinds of things
that come with with love but in fact a profound way of loving
others and loving oneself is to really
see the value of non-harming because in non-harming
let's just keep it for meditation for now if we are dedicated to not harming with
our thoughts not harming with our actions with our attitudes and our speech
that it's uh though the harm is not
interfering with our natural capacity
to mature to grow to evolve spiritually dharmically humanly
human beings are built to change
over time and certainly if you get older we recognize the house change
but part of the change that's built into US is that of maturation
a growth and wisdom a growth and freedom a growth in love
and this phenomenal growth that's possible has a is a natural thing
that has uh one of the most important qualities is to get out of the way for
it to not interfere with it in a life dedicated to non-harming
is a life dedicated to not putting up the obstacles to this
natural growth natural Evolution that's possible within us
so a heightened sensitivity to how our thoughts undermine us harm us
by negative thinking critical thinking um
and sometimes those thoughts come with authority like this is true
but no thought that undermines us no thought which
doesn't look upon us with kindness basic kindness
no thought that um somehow hurts
in some deep way it's possible to recognize that we have
behavior and thoughts and feelings which are not so healthy
but that doesn't have to give birth to hurtful harmful thoughts
seeing seeing our shortcomings clearly
without adding harm moves us towards health
so
so to not harm and then make space for the practice to
evolve so assuming a meditation posture
that maybe allows you to have some nice
balance between being alert and being calm
and the alertness is partly to be alert
to the thoughts the attitudes the impulses
which undermine us deplete us shut us down or tighten us up
that bring tension and reactivity
and the calm is partly to so we can better appreciate the alternative
the calmer the mind the hearts are
the less it wants to harm
so to take a few long slow deep breaths
and to relax the body
to take some long slow deep breaths
and relax deep inside
and then letting the breathing return to normal
and as you exhale see if you can have a wave a calming
wave through your body
exhale and settle in the body calm in the body
on the exhale allow there be a calming of the Mind
a quieting of the thinking mind
and then to settle down into the breathing
and one way to approach a thorough going
attitude not not harming
to assume that in meditation you can do no wrong
nothing is wrong with you
however the practice is to keep waking up
to keep being mindful of what is
to clearly see and know what's happening
where that clarity of being awake being mindful
is leaving everything alone not being involved not picking up
not staying staying involved with thoughts
getting out of the way
it's enough just to be clearly aware
of what's Happening Here and Now
using breathing as the stabilizing force in the present moment
the calming focusing Force
supporting us and not being entangled or involved with
anything that goes on just to see just to know
just to feel how it is
dedicated to non-harming
is there any way that your thoughts or your attitudes right now
are harmful undermining
don't think that that's wrong or a mistake
or criticize yourself for it that's more harm
rather know it clearly
recognize it for what it is
and let it be
don't granted more attention don't feed it with more involvement
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to live a life of non-harming is to live with a certain kind of
reassurance certain kind of inner safety
and a heightened capacity to gaze upon everyone
with an open heart with kindness and good will
knowing that we're dedicated to not harming them
there's nothing that in our hearts that is closed or
regretful or dangerous for others
and even the intention to live without harm
is a beautiful intention it's the beginning of a new Direction
may it be that on this day as we come out of meditation
that we have a heightened interest
intention to not cause harm
and at that dedication is an expression of good will
of kindness of love
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
[Music] thank you
so hello and welcome to the fourth talk on
love when it's hard to love in times of challenges
and today I'll introduce this topic of non-harming which is one of the I think
one of the most marvelous inspiring at least for me qualities a human being can have and is
Central to the whole Buddhist Enterprise and to really appreciate it that's a
kind of a unifying principle or core principle of the Dharma puts everything
else into a kind of a into a very important context a very
important kind of fits everything else together and one of the kind of understandings of
what a religion is is its religion provides values principles orientations
for how to live one's whole life kind of ultimate teachings ultimate purposes
ultimate understandings that apply to all over one's life
and so this is one of those that makes Buddhism a religion that it's a religion of non-harming
um and not to harm
and uh and the core uh one of the core
teachings of the Four Noble Truths is an expression of that it's a formulation of that where the word for harm is
presented as by the word dukka or suffering and um
so I've met people who
they're very being they're very disposition and personality way of being in the world
was clear that they were a harmless person that they were dedicated to not
harming sometimes such people are dedicated to being honest
and I've met people who are it seems like they're incapable of lying
and um and incapable of harming others and uh
this dedication to not harm not harm when I was about 20 or 21
. um I made a mistake and someone wanted to challenge me to a fist fight
and they've all happened very very uh suddenly and um and so there was no premeditated
thought on my part but what I immediately did was I dropped
to one knee and spread out my my hands wide and as if you know I'm now I'm
vulnerable and I'm not defending myself and and I said I can't fight
and um the um and uh so rather than than being you
know defensively being beaten up on the person uh spun around and marched off
and discussed but this idea of not being able to fight not being able to
um harm anyone whether that should be practiced all the
time in the way that I just described for myself that's a personal question and I I'm not for me to say in all the
circumstances of Life what we would do but to have as a in the Forefront of our
hearts and Minds this care to not want
to harm um and to really make that the first consideration the first kind of cons way
of thinking about a situation you're like that's not harm here
and um and I'm teaching about this for this week about love because it's a form of
love to not harm and rather than always expect love to
have a very high bar what love is that it means having um you know just filled with warmth and
appreciation and joy and kind of a Radiance of positive regard for anyone
and everyone and everywhere that love can also not be so
dramatic it doesn't have to be that we always have a warm heart an open heart a
generous kind of sense of kind of gushing um
joy and appreciation and compassion for others sometimes love is quieter it's more
basic and one of the forms of Love is um
is not harming we love others through not harming them
we love others by not setting up obstacles for their growth and their evolution and their development of their
life we love others by giving them room to be who they are
we give love to others by
giving them safety so many people in this world are not safe don't feel safe
grow go have grown up not feeling safe and and don't automatically feel that
other people they encounter are safe for them but to really kind of get a sense that
someone is harmless dedicated to being harmless that they're not going to harm is a gift
that we give to other people and it's a gift of love of care love
being a respect for others maybe we don't have gushing warmth for someone
but we have an appreciation for their autonomy their possibility their
Humanity that we don't want to mess with it
a dedication to non-harming is also indirected towards oneself
that one doesn't want to harm oneself in any way and this is also a form of love
and again same thing as before that we measure sometimes the idea of Love or
meta towards oneself compassion for oneself it was some idea that it's maybe more
than it has to be it has to be some a little bit you know you know warmth and
gushing and delight and and kind of lots of smiles and
but sometimes you know even towards ourselves it's profound it's a profound
form of love that's quieter that's not a big gushing kind of feeling of warmth
but rather just simply caring enough for oneself that one doesn't want to cause harm to oneself
as we practice mindfulness a very important thing begins happening that
Mythos brings a heightened sensitivity to the impact of our Behavior the impact
of our thoughts our attitudes our impulses we have our and what we start discovering is that
when we intentionally want to harm someone else get revenge or you know somehow
cynically poke them in some way or whatever it might be
we are simultaneously harming ourselves in fact for the in the teachings of the
Buddha uh he actually says that when we intentionally harm others
we actually harm ourselves much much more than we harm the other
and uh and kind of mythically they talk about you know rebirth that even if you
do something like kill someone else that's pretty bad for that person who died and that only diminished the horror
of that but for the person who kills they're going to get Reborn
endless times many many many times where they're going to be killed violently and
be tortured and in these kind of burning Hills so those that's kind of Mythic teachings
of Buddha Buddhism but it kind of points this idea how much we harm ourselves more
than we harm others if we want to intentionally harm them and so we can feel that when we have the
heightened deep and sensitivity of mindfulness and um and it's a game changer to feel
that and see that how much we harm ourselves and um
and so that we also then see how we harm ourselves um by our negative attitudes towards
ourselves and uh and to not want to harm ourselves
anymore even if the negative attitudes have some truth to them
they're not needed we don't need to send arrows into our own hearts
we don't need to set up obstacles that interfere with the natural growth into
goodness into honesty into non-harming that exists in every heart
in your heart and our hearts and so not to add restrictions on
ourselves not to add things that undermine us or or discourage us or
depress us you know one of the leading causes for depression they say is negative
self-talk and the negative self-talk can come with such Authority it can seem like it's
true when it has to happen but you know in that it's it's
repetitive over and over and over again it's not useful so to recognize it as a kind of
self-harm might begin to make put a crack into
this strong impulse we have to have negative self-talk
to realize it's not necessary there's another way
there's a way of not harming and it's not easy to make a shift
but it isn't so much that we have to actively do something else like love
other people it's mostly an avoidance and even if all it takes is to bite your
tongue to avoid saying the harmful thing this is beneficial
sometimes we have to really restrain ourselves physically so that we don't punch someone out
and um the um I had the occasion to do that to
avoid punching someone out in a meditation Hall once when I was in Asia
where we were all monks practicing together and but this monk who was sitting next to me must have hated me
and I kind of prejudice and and was constantly poking me and and
saying kind of not nice things to me and during meditation that in Buddhist
monastery and so I just sat there and and you know
I never replied in meditation but there was one day I remember I just was felt
like I just want to turn around and punch the guy in the face and um but I I didn't
and uh I kept my hands to myself and that took a fair amount of restraints
so sometimes it works that way that we have to just restrain and that's the beginning of an alternative
and but also to begin to learn how not to participate with the thoughts and
impulses without having to do a lot of work do not pick it up
do not give in to it maybe even not believe in it
all these efforts all this approach to trying to live with unharming
is a significant way of loving so the question where is the love how
can I love in this when there's a challenging situation here's an you know an easy answer but
not always easy to implement that love is found in the dedication to
non-harming and and I'd like to propose
is that this is such an important and Central value that it's more important to adhere to
that than somehow solve the challenges we're in
and it'll end with a story that Dalai Lama tells
of some point in India he met with a monk
who had been in the Chinese prison camp for 20 25 years before being released
and then he was able to come to India and so the Buddha met with him and the Buddha the Dalai Lama then asked the
monk were you ever in danger in the prison camp you know a violence of starving or
something and the monks answer surprised Dalai Lama
and the monk said yes I was in danger I was in danger of losing my compassion
for the prison guards
the greatest well the greatest Health the greatest thing that the monk had maybe was his compassion His Kind regard
his not wanting to harm anyone and that was that's what he identified
as being the most precious most important part of who he is and um and so more than anything else
perhaps non-harming represents our greatest
wealth our greatest Beauty our greatest home our greatest
kind of one most wonderful place that life can radiate from
and no matter what the challenge that we're in
for a Buddhist the love that doesn't want to harm
should always be close by him may we love the world
through a dedication to non-harming so thank you
very much and priority being back here tomorrow