so um well maybe I I tend to underestimate
how much joy I'm going to feel when when I see uh all of these good
mornings all the good mornings and the reports
from all these locations um I'm streaming I'm streaming to you
from a different place and before now I'm nestled in
this foggy Valley uh just north of Santa Cruz at
IRC Insight Retreat Center very happy to be here doing this
and um I'm unsure about the connection so
we'll see if the bandwidth holds up if it drops off we'll just get to
meditate h a very happy to be with you as I as I heard uh Rhonda McGee put it
good moment not good morning good afternoon good night she just said good morning uh good
moment so the way I think about our our purpose in coming
together for these these sittings and dmets is uh together as a Sana together
as a community and to practice together and have some time to
prioritize the Buddhist teachings um feeding them into our lives
reflecting on them working with them together as a community so we we can we
can learn for ourselves how we want to live well how we want to live peacefully and
dharmically so the theme I I've um chosen for the
week is the Buddhist teachings on compassion and why is
that uh one of my one of my zen teachers uh frequently encourages me to give the
talk you need to hear and when I asked myself I thought
oh what would be nourishing this week and buddh teachings on
compassion I hope you find it nourishing too so let's start with a
sitting we will we'll start with a sort of sitting
that that I hope will will um care for these hearts of
ours that M I think for many of us that that um
really want to wish well for this ailing
world and as much as we would like to give and give endlessly sometimes the heart needs some
rest so our Focus for this morning will be rest we'll do some uh grounding and
balancing at the beginning of this meditation and then we'll move into the breathing
and then scan the body so that bit by bit we can relax bit by
bit so let's find our way into the meditation
posture reclining or
sitting turning back to this felt
body right PRI izing that aware connection with the
body maybe taking a few deep breaths
and feeling the steadying influence of the
breathing or maybe starting with the
ears letting the sounds call us back
here
as we prioritize and tune in to this body this one precious
body inclining the mind to notice its
groundedness maybe the ways that it's
solid
supported
supported firm
steady
if this isn't the experience of your body body in this
moment maybe there's some small place in the
body maybe the soles of the feet maybe the sitting
base or some of the
bones that are just resting with gravity
balanced
grounded
staying connected to the body in this
way the next invitation is
to bring some bit of focus to the
breathing especially the
exhale letting the the inhale come in naturally on its own time
and then you can experiment with the exhale just being slightly
longer than natural just
enough to cue the body to
relax a little bit of EMP empasis on the exhale relaxing this
body
grounding the body inviting relaxation with the
exhale if just this is for you this
morning afternoon evening if it's nourishing please
continue and if you would like to follow along with the next invitation you're
welcome to do
that and this will be to bring attention
so the body section by
section to notice if there's any tension that's easy to
release and giving permission in a
way for this tension to
rest you can do this in your in your own way at your own
pace it may be the whole head and neck attending to
this any obvious tension
release one shoulder and the whole [Music]
arm and
release
the other shoulder and
arm and
release
the whole torso and
back
release
one leg from the hip to the
toes
relaxing and the other
leg
release and you're invited to continue in your own way
giving this body permission to
rest
and in the last minutes of this sitting
feeling free to let go of any effort in these activities we're
doing to sense and appreciate any relaxation that's
come any feeling of rest
and if the sense of rest hasn't come just now may the seeds of rest be
planted for the
future may all beings everywhere know the deep
rest of clear knowing and
release May all beings be well
good moment hello during our meditations the rain
started how wonderful oh I'm getting a note that the Bell was
a little loud I'll adjust that for tomorrow
so welcome again as I mentioned the focus for the
week is the Buddhist teachings on
compassion like to start with a story um
to illustrate this theme the inspiration the theme for the talk today
is how do we have compassion without sinking how do we have compassion
without sinking and the story comes from the very first teaching in the one of the
books of the Buddhist discourses the connected discourses and someone comes to the
Buddha and asks how does one cross the flood
how does one cross the flood and the Buddha and his care and
compassion for this being responds it's by not halting and not
struggling that I was able to cross the
flood the person ask further oh how did you do that fair question and the Buddha said
when I halted when I halted I
sank and when I struggled I got swept
away so how do we how do we have compassion without sinking how do we
practice compassion without sinking I um I asked a very similar
question to venerable an Alo recently I asked him how do we relate
how do we relate to the suffering of this world without being overtaken in a way how do we cross the
flood or how do we have compassion without sinking and the background for this
question I think maybe doesn't need
stating um but the word compassion fatigue comes
to my mind and I hear it from hear it from Friends often of course in
the academic sense it means something quite specific but I think in our
popular popular sense it it invokes something or expresses a kind of um
maybe weariness a challenge a challenge in these uh challenging
times uh maybe conditioned by the fact that um
we have we have in the practice something something that I might call a Dharma imperative to
sensitivity we're training in being sensitive and we're training to
care so again this question how with a with a sensitive heart do we swim without
sinking or care without being depleted um but in a positive
sense how do we love in a way that's
sustainable so the Buddha offered offered his teachings out of compassion it said out of
care and I think we're still we're still benefiting from that so well like I like
I mentioned we'll we will look into some of these some of these Buddhist teachings on compassion this week so
venerable analo in respon in to my question how do we how do we love sustainably how do we have compassion
and not sink he I want to say uh he was speaking
from the perspective of meditative cultivation of compassion so the the
practice of compassion has a broad scope uh for us as practitioners and um
in the Buddhist teaching we have the sort of meditative scope we have the what I'll call the daily life scope
and he was really talking about meditation and he pointed me in this
direction and this is what I wanted to share with you that the the first step in his
answer was to recognize a distinction to practice recognizing a
distinction that allows us to love sustainably now this was given to given
to me at the end of a a retreat so I'd had all this time to rest i' had all this time to really care for
myself and then I heard this distinction so in the in the early Buddhist sense there's a distinction
between uh keeping the heart open to
suffering and refraining from taking it on taking on the suffering of others
like putting it on our back so the distinction here is
important and they're related to one another other so we have keeping an open sensitive
Heart part of the path and that makes possible the wish for
well-being um and these two are they're closely related but they're distinct so
it takes some practice to start to recognize them the example venerable analo gave me
of the difference between keeping an open heart and taking on the suffering of another he used the
image of a doctor more or less saying imagine imagine a doctor meeting
patients and one comes the first one comes in and the doctor takes on takes
on the difficulty of the the person and that's what they focus on how many
people do you think they could see 2 three four five before they were
depleted so the doctor keep keeps their keeps their senses and their heart their
eyes their heart open doesn't Focus only on the ailment
but also focuses on the possibility of Health this is the prognosis this is the
way forward this these are some things we can do we can try the doctor sees the whole scope and
doesn't stop with just the ailment to just stop with the ailment would be in the Buddhist sense
contemplation of Dua which has a slight distinction from the cultivation of
compassion contemplation of duka makes compassion possible but it's not the it's not the
whole practice of compassion of course the Buddha is
sometimes talked about as the the great physician we know this and it's uh it's
understood that maybe maybe he borrowed a medical framework when formulating the
Four Noble Truths that the U the first Noble Truth of Dua suffering of
unsatisfactoriness is like uh the doctor seeing the ailment the second Noble Truth is assessing the causes and
conditions that uh craving that leads to clinging third Noble Truth is like the
prognosis there is an end of suffering that's possible the cessation of
craving and then the fourth Noble Truth is the the treatment so to speak the noble Eightfold
so in this um in this metaphor of the doctor the the doctor sees the whole
scope here doesn't doesn't limit and dwell uh their awareness and their heart
only on the suffering but also sees these other parts what are the causes and conditions what's the possibility of
health and then how do we get there so was venerable andal I's
encouragement was to to get get into this distinction get familiar with this distinction between contemplation of
Dua and the cultivation of compassion both both parts in the
service of loving sustainably in the service of not
sinking so I was considering how to how to practice getting to know the this
distinction between the contemplation of Dua and wishing well for
others as I was looking into the teachings of on compassion one of the things that we
notice is that there's not there's not a um very clear definition in the
teachings about what compassion is and I was a bit surprised by this but
I spec I started to speculate uh that the Buddha was a very thoughtful person
and I started to speculate that this was actually in the service of
our Humanity instead of definitions the Buddha conveys the teachings through
images and stories um that touch on and and sort of
light up in our in our modern language like light up our social system our
social nervous system that connects with other beings so uh I didn't see the Buddha
respond to the question uh dear dear the Buddha what is
compassion oh compassion is X instead he conveyed it through story and image so
that we connect with other beings I think I think that's
basic because the the key the key function of the practice of compassion as we know is the wishing
well the wishing that another being have freedom from suffering
it's that close it's that immediate um it's right here wishing
wishing that another being be free from suffering or wishing that we are free from suffering this is the nature of
compassion in some of the some of the earlier groundbreaking research about compassion and
burnout um they found the key difference between those that those that were able
to sustain and those that weren't was simply um this wish for the well-being
of others so the the everyone in the study was exposed
to uh from what I understand a great great amount of uh pain and suffering in
terms of images and stories and those that those that were able to not sink to love sustainably the
the one ingredient was is wishing wishing others well wishing they be free from
suffering so I think there's a way in our meditation that we can we can get more and more sensitive
to this distinction and I I I feel like it may be important in in practicing
compassion to come into the meditative space and recognize suffering as
suffering as it's present recognize suffering and suffering and also sense as we incline
the Mind may this being be free from suffering and be very sensitive to what
that does there's a close monitoring that's being asked for here between the the
mind that sort of draws to draws to the suffering only kind of like a
magnet and the mind that can be with suffering with an open sensitive heart
and also in in line the to the toward the wish for well-being May these beings be free from
suffering so this question how to love
sustainably how to practice compassion without
sinking this morning and and across these five mornings I'll be speaking about this
topic of compassion doing it in maybe a general sense I think it's important to say that
it's it's for each of us to discern what's the what is the right
healthy amount of exertion and effort and what's the right amount of rest
Discerning our wise relationship and I hope that that sharing some of these these uh teachings from the Buddha on
compassion can be part of your Reflections this week your practice this
week so the practice of compassion may we make every necessary
effort and when it's time to rest may we rest
completely thank you for your practice this morning today
evening may all beings everywhere be
sensitive just enough and wish others well it's
possible may all beings be free from suffering take
care