good morning good morning today we'll continue this idea
of the faculties for fearlessness and there's so many fun alliterations we
could do with five fabulous fun faculties for fearlessness for freedom
forever I'm sure there's many fine we somehow slip in that word fine in there
somewhere but for the titles I'm just saying faculties for fearlessness
and today we're not so much in the guided meditation but in the little talk
that I'll give afterwards we're going to talk about a second faculty and it's I'm
as you may have noticed I'm not going in the usual order of the faculties instead I'm going in an
order I think that a way that we can work with them to be with our fear and today's or well maybe I'll save
what it's going to be um during the when I do the little dermit because when I
say the word we bring a lot of um ideas to it and I want to introduce maybe a
little different idea so I'll wait to say it until then but until
then let's settle into a guided
meditation so taking a moment to settle
in feeling yourself
sitting like what does it feel like to be in this particular
configuration of body and mind feeling the sensations of sitting
the sensation of the touch pressure with the
floor or the cushion chair couch
bed wherever you
are feeling the pressure of the contact
whatever it is the body is contacting at this
moment and using this contact as a foundation for our settledness or
arriving feeling the sense of stability that comes with this Con
contact and Foundation we're here
here chances are the contact is with your
buttocks maybe the backsides of your
legs your
feet and maybe your back leaning against a chair lying
down feel the contact with the
back
then the front of the body isn't necessarily
contacting anything but bringing attention to the
belly can it be
soft relaxed
can we bring an aliveness of attention of
presence the belly to the
chest the experience of having a chest maybe there's a way in which it
just opens just a tiny bit by moving the shoulders back just maybe nobody if they
were to look at you would notice but just a small
movement bringing this aliveness this presence to the
neck resting attention on the
face noticing any tension in the
jaw maybe it's okay tension is there but maybe by bringing it into awareness
there's some softening and around the
eyes
we're here
now this moment there's nowhere else to
be and nothing else to
do allowing the attention to gather into the bodily
experience
and setting the direction of our practice to be one of kindness and
warmth and Care bringing an attitude of openness in
warmth and care to our
practice and letting the attention rest on the sensations as associated
with
breathing feeling the stretch and the release of the stretch
in the chest maybe feeling the
movement in and out of the belly Maybe
or feeling the different temperatures of air as it goes in and out of the
nodes just choosing one of those areas and resting attention
there
and when the Mind wonders as it's apt to do just very
simply gently begin again with the sensations of
breathing doesn't have to be complicated we don't have to make a story about it
we just give ourselves over to the sensations of breathing
again
what would it be like to abide
but the sensations of breathing being at the
center we're not grasping not pushing or just
abiding being present with the sensations of
breathing
[Music]
good morning welcome welcome good day good
afternoon lovely to practice
together so today I'd like to continue on this idea of that faculties for
fearlessness and while we were meditating I had this idea like oh yeah there's another meaning to this word
faculties so maybe it's a bunch of teachers and Professor professors we want
fearlessness I don't I'm just uh sharing with you the things that the Mind does
sometimes right so I want to talk a little bit about fear I'll start there Fear Can manifest
itself in so many different ways shows up maybe just as restless nights or
feeling moody or not expressing our emotions or thoughts you know really
holding back and maybe feeling isolated or you know not wanting
to connect with others we could even say like the list
of the ways that fear shows up in our lives is endless and some it depends on the
person and the situation but there's so many different ways and it's kind of unique to all of
us but regardless of how fear shows up in your life it is a natural part of The
Human Experience like humans are vulnerable of course we are we don't
like it and we try to pretend that we're not but we are vul vable not only to physical harm but to like emotional harm
or some mental harm or something like this but today I really like to
emphasize that it's we have fear perfectly normal and we have the
resistance to fear like we don't like to feel fear it's
uncomfortable and not only is it uncomfortable but we might have this idea like oh I'm doing something wrong
because I'm feeling the fear here or if I were a different kind of person I wouldn't be afraid or you know
especially like social media often like likes to portray you know only the best
signs of people and not everybody watches social media of course but there's a way in which there can be a
valorization of this fearlessness and then we start to think like oh if I have fear somehow I'm a
failure so we're often conflating this experience of fear and the resistance to
that fear and I think for the most part they go together when we have fear often
there's a resistance to fear but it can be incredibly powerful and helpful to
tease these apart the fear and the resistance to
fear like they feel a little bit different in the body maybe sometimes fears like a lump
in the throat but the resistance the strong sense of no I don't want to might show
up as a some tightness in the chest or some hardness in the belly for example
or maybe there's a sense of like the tension in the shoulders with resistance whereas maybe the fear is a knot in the
belly we don't all experience these things the same but in order to like tease them apart it
can be enormously helpful to be aware of how they show up in the body there's the
fear It's Perfectly Natural normal thing to have about so many different things
and then there's this strong sense of no I don't want it how does that no show
up so I want to now like kind of introduce one of the faculties that can
help us with this and as I said at the beginning of the guided meditation I'm not doing the
faculties in order and I want to emphasize particular aspects of the
faculties so before saying the exact name of the faculty I want to introduce this idea of
centeredness like this idea of being centered being collected like not
distracted because there's so many different things that we can bring our attention to right it's probably and
endless and not only the way that we can bring the objects we can bring our
attention to but like the manner in which we do it there can be a way in which there's this striving I have to
focus I have to be connected to this and and anytime we notice any wavering there
can be this you know trying to pounce back onto the object of the
focus but there's also a way in which we can just be centered collected
gathered bringing some wholeheartedness to whatever it is we
wanting to bring the attention to some of you might recognize this as the faculty of
Samar it often gets translated as concentration but I'd really like to
emphasize this sense of gathered collectedness um and some
wholeheartedness because if we just think of it as concentration then for
many of us and I know it was for me for many years this idea it was kind of like that dist strain it was kind of like
this taxing striving associated with just having the attention be only in one
place as opposed to the sense of maybe like just abiding with the what we're bringing
bringing the attention to maybe resting in or bringing attention to standing in
the middle of connecting with I want to bring a little bit
different flavor of uh than what we often bring when we hear this word
concentration instead I want to highlight this Gathering and
collectedness and in particular with working with
fear I'd like to offer that we gather the attention around the
resistance to the fear not the fear itself but the
resistance that strong sense of no I don't want
it no make it go away so it's related to aversion but
it's a little bit different because sometimes the resistance is so strong or so we don't even like know that we are
um resisting it can show up as a voidance as opposed to aversion is often
like this turning away this avoidance this can be kind of like a bouncing off
maybe there's a little hint of fear there's a pulling back closing down that
might happen it turns out that working with
the resistance to fear is a really effective way to be with
fear because to be with fear itself is overwhelming not always but it can be
and it comes along with so much of U these stories about fear what we're
afraid of we shouldn't be afraid of or why is this happening all these types of things so why not just focus on the
resistance this can help us so much in our life not only to be with the
fear but resistance shows up in so many different ways in our life every time we
feel uncomfortable there's a feeling of no I don't want to be uncomfortable that
sense of resistance and there's a sense of
longing like we don't like to long for things that's uncomfortable
too so one way to work with fearlessness is to bring this sense of collectedness
this sense of gathering this sense of abiding in standing in the middle of the
resistance to fear because I would say that
samade this Gathering collectedness centering requires that
wholeheartedness this might be one way that we could even think about Sam as a wholehearted
ESS and so often when we come to fear we're not recognizing the resistance to
fear they're getting conflated and then there's this resistance to the resistance to the fear
and it tends it ends up being a big gnarly mess
sometimes but what would it be like to be
wholehearted so often we can't be wholehearted with the fear because there's the resistance so there's a
peace that's maybe collected around the fear but we're ignoring the the whole resistance so instead let's be collected
around the resistance let the fear take care of
itself and we'll be bring our attention around the resistance to the
fear and this wholeheartedness requires a certain amount of Letting Go we're letting go of the
distractions we're letting go of thinking of the idea that we shouldn't have resistance we're letting go of
fragmentation that might happen if we're not noticing the resistance then there's this fragment of us that's resisting but
if we just bring our wholeheartedness and letting go of the
distractions letting go of the fragmentation letting go of anything
that's not a sense of wholeness and there then the Letting Go opens up
new possibilities this whole heartedness opens up a new way to be with our
experience because what I'm pointing to is to meet the
resistance with
nonresistance and it turns out that the resistance is supporting the fear the
are leaning against one [Music] another if we are bring some
nonresistance to the resistance that resistance kind of Falls away turns out
the fear Falls away too so
Som with the resistance to fear I mean to bring somebody to fear
itself would be great if we could do it but most of us can't do it it's part of our I don't know if is hardwired but it
feels hardwired to resist fear so can you be centered and
wholehearted on the resistance to fear for you what does this no look
like can you bring a not no to the no
can you not resist the
resistance so one of the five faculties for fearlessness for freedom forever is
Sam which I'm highlighting this idea of gathered collectedness
wholeness for somebody so today if resistance to
anything happened to show up in your life maybe you can practice even if it's not with fear just practicing with the
resistance and I'll see you tomorrow thank you