warm greetings everyone welcome and today's topic is
action it'll be action in relationship to com act compassion compassionate
action but for the beginning of this meditation I want to emphasize that the
action is a very important part of the Buddha teachings sometimes uh he was called
a a kada a uh that is he was uh a teacher of
action um
a and he has this wonderful statement that uh beings
are uh owners of their own Karma of the owners of their
action they are inheritors of their action
they the uh actions are their Source they or they originate in their
actions actions are are are they
relatives and actions are our refuge so they say that actions are our
refuge actions are our relatives it's like part of our family it's that intimate it's
close that actions are the source from which our life flows and
develops actions we inherit our actions uh we inherit the consequence of our
actions and uh we have to we own our actions where the consequences the
they're really our own to work with it's a powerful statement and uh and can be a
little bit frightening to think that we are the owners of our actions and we inherit the consequence of our actions
because we know are we careful with what we do but that actions can be our
relatives our cherished Family action can be our refuge and our
protection and um and meditation in the there a long history in Buddhism of
meditation being considered a form of action since often meditation is
associated with sitting still laying still being still and there's a kind of sometimes a paiv in the instructions or
how people do it where we just sit and be available and open and present and
nonreactive just be rather than do um sometimes it lends itself to
reinforce an idea that we are the consumers of spirituality rather than
the producers of it that we are the victims of our life not the Agents of
our life and the teachings in the Buddha is that we are the agents we are the
initiators we are in our actions our life begins each time each day we wake up
each moment that we walk into um it's kind of a fresh beginning and then how
do we meet it what actions what activity do we contribute to it and so meditation
is an action where life begins to only see meditation as a place
to recover from the past recover and respond and deal with and with the past
if that's all we do we're missing an opportunity of kind of stepping into
this moment um with a particular kind of action
of care respect of an action of aware awareness
of Attunement of appreciation of aspiration that we step into it with a
certain fullness like that we count that we're important this is valuable what we're
doing here and so when we sit down to have a posture of
meditation whatever a posture that is sitting lying down standing walking
whatever works to adjust the posture in such a way that it's a posture of agency
a posture of kind of a certain kind of action and not a posture of only
relaxing not a posture of there isn't some kind of some kind of Engagement and
it could be a simple as um you know where we put our hands to put the hands
and maybe so they're together or so the hands
themselves are in a posture that expresses some
intentionality some here I am I'm going to do
this and to then gently close the
eyes and
to there's a way of stepping into this moment this time
here with a certain degree of agency certain degree of taking our place in
this world taking our place here and now showing up
that what we do and how we are is important to take a few long slow deep
breaths to assume your place here and
now and as you exhale to relax relaxing is a
doing and the balance between
the engagement of breathing in and the relaxing of breathing
out hopefully begins to blend
together so that the
breathing in and breathing out is an activity within which we
rest an activity in which there's a peacefulness and a
ease and letting your breathing return to
normal
and gently maybe
lovingly enter into the world of
breathing so the attention the action of in
aention is something we're producing not consuming we're offering
attention the action of attention in which we look for our
ease look for a way to do so peacefully gently
lovingly
remembering our
agency without any
urgency
calmly offering to yourself the action the
activity of being present and aware here and
now to breathing the body your feelings your
thoughts and discovering how to do so so that awareness is a
refuge that the action of [Music] awareness is like a loving family
member that you
enjoy showing up here and
now
for
e
meditation is an action in which we
learn to let go of all unnecessary
actions all the extra things that we're involved involved with
in the
mind thoughts
feelings tensions in the
body the
activity of letting go of unnecessary
activity
for
e
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn our attention outwards into the
world and engage in the action the mental action the heart
action of caring loving valuing respecting
this world that we share with other beings other
people the beings and life and people for whom our life would be not
possible without their
efforts their lives
and to engage in the action of thinking how wonderful it would be if all beings
could be happy and peaceful if all beings could be free of
Affliction hatred and anger and greed delusion
anxiety and and we can be the Agents of
change to expect that other people will change the
world is to give away our individual
capacity for making this world a better
place and rather than giving that away instead give the world your generosity
your care beginning with
your intention your wish for all people to be
well may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all
beings be free and may I may each of
us find ways to contribute to this
possibility may we act for the welfare and happiness of all beings
including our
own [Music]
[Music] thank
you
so hello and welcome to this fifth talk on the joy of
compassion and today is the fifth aspect element that we contribute to
create a healthy beneficial compassion for this for ourselves and the world and
that that is action and usually compassion is very closely associated
with action the action of care the action of doing something to alleviate the difficulties the challenges the
suffering of others or ourselves but to have the joy of it to
enjoy the activity of compassion is so it's sometimes in short
supply sometimes um uh we don't consider that that activity of compassion this
whether it's a simple activity of being a listener for someone or
offering well-wishing for someone or whether it's a big thing that we do and
maybe it takes a long time to really care and tend to someone who's sick or
something that we don't often think about looking at looking at the activity that we're doing is a source of joy as
something that will generate a sense of wellbeing or a likeness or that somehow we feel kind of more at ease in doing
it sometimes the reason for that is that the the need for compassion that what
stimulates it Catalyst for it is so the suffering is so great it's so
challenging that it's so there's so much Injustice there's so much um oppression
there's so much poverty there's so much suffering there's so much unfairness that we're trying to care for and
support people who are experiencing these things and we could feel our own despair
our own anger our own sense of urgency our own sense of of overwhelm all kinds of things come along and so they get
swept those feelings kind of uh uh influence the way in which we do
the action the action these those feelings come along with the action but to trust the action like
think of it almost stepping into a new uh phase a new dimension almost
where yes we can have these feelings for sure but the action we step into is like
stepping into a um new activity a new room a new world in doing the action not
to deny what we're feeling but to not be held in check by it not be unduly caught
in it and and feel like okay now that I'm prepared to offer my care my
Compassionate Care for some situation this is what's important this
is what's valuable I've prepared myself well I've been I've I've brought a lot
of awareness to myself into the situation studied it got to know it I've become attuned to it I'm in harmony with
it I'm not stressed around it or not uh aversive to it or
not um you know indifferent to it or not really connected to it I'm connected and
I'm at ease I'm in Harmony in a certain kind of way with this I'm attuned to what's happening I understand the others
really well enough it's not just my projection and my my um my
preoccupations which are driving me and um there's an
appreciation of the people I'm going to support it's not only the horror or the
distress that I feel around how terrible it is that's taken the time to really
respect these people and what is respect what is appreciation here uh what is
valuing this people whatever being that there at least we're equal we're we're
I'm not there to help or to fix I'm there to serve their welfare to
support and then there is an aspiration which is a beautiful part of a human being so those are the foundations and
then when we get ready to act to enter into the action as if the quality the
the way in which we Act is part of the message that uh we act in such a way way
that people appreciate the activity the ease the calm the generosity the love
the well-being uh when they don't we don't they don't feel our actions as being
like we're it's a heavy burden we're carrying or we're stressed we're pushing
or but they feel something very different and people can be nourished by
the ease the well-being by which we do things and they can be troubled when
we're troubled so to engage in the action not to look for the joy in the
action whereas you can look for the joy and awareness or Attunement or appreciation or an aspiration but with
action not to look for it but rather to generate it to step into the action and
try to find a way you do it with Grace with ease with peace with a nice way of
doing it don't don't have a sense of urgency unless there's a uh you know
sometimes we have to act quickly but we don't have to hurry
there's a difference between quickness and hurrying I think of hurrying we're losing ourselves to do things fast we
don't have to lose ourselves we can stay present to uh do do it in a way that uh
it's a enjoyable way of doing it we enjoy doing this we like it and uh and
uh is it okay to do this do we have permission to do it the proposal is that
it actually makes the compassion richer more valuable for the world and for ourselves it helps make the compassion
sustainable over time it helps us to appreciate it's really good to be
compassionate I enjoy it I want to do it there's more value in it than just how
what we're how we're helping people it's also value for me I feel better I feel lighter from doing it and so when we act
compassionately to as I said not just just to be the um don't look for the
joy act in a way that brings Joy or brings enjoyment brings lightness brings
ease and um and then as I've said it's sustainable over time and so much better
more comes out of it one of the things that comes out of it is that the if
you're doing something that in contact with someone so you're in touch with them uh I think that the relationship
becomes Richer there there's a spark there's a love there's a joy there's a
sense of Rapport between you know that's really nice some sometimes done I've
done compassionate actions for something and I was so dutiful in how I did it and
a matter of fact that did it that I didn't actually take the time to have a
rapport with the person I was doing with and I've done at times where I done things in a different way not out of
Duty not out of an urgency but took my time to do it in a respectful kind
enjoyable way and I could feel that the report then uh grew or developed or uh
became more wonderful with the people that I was
supporting so to to um so
to um care for those that we love care for those who suffer in a way
that they don't feel that we're doing working so hard that they're not
obligated to repay us or that they feel kind of um indebted because it was so
hard for us and heavy and difficult to offer ourselves with ease and fre
freedom and joy and to offer ourselves in that kind of way even with our love
for people who are going through some of the most difficult times this world is a challenging place
to live human beings are challenged life is difficult and one of the things that can
support it is that we care for each other care for each other to with respect with kindness with ability to
listen with with um appreciation um it's a beautiful thing
it's important thing to do and may this practice that we do be a support for
us to um bring our compassion and our care
into the world I think it's a natural outgrowth of mindfulness
practice because as we let go of all the re all the blocks all the the barriers
all the defensiveness all the preoccupations we're left with a
sensitive Caring Heart and what else would we do but care for this
world so thank you very much and um so
probably now completed this series on compassion and I'll start a new series
next week so um I'm think thinking of doing
uh a series on speech wise speech mindful speaking and
um so thank you
all