good morning good morning everyone you know I hope that I clicked all the
right buttons this morning if I could get like a something like a thumbs up or
some other indication that you guys can see me and hear me that'd be great
okay excellent got some thumbs up okay thank you thank you it's a interesting thing to be here and
I uh talking to the camera and I'm assuming there's other people on the other side
so welcome welcome everybody we'll wait a few minutes before we begin
good morning good morning everybody well I'm saying good morning it's morning from me but of course it's not working
for everybody who's listening here so wherever you are whatever time it might
be welcome welcome
for those of you who are just signing on again I'll say welcome we'll begin here maybe
less than a minute or so
okay I think we'll begin now again welcome it's nice to be practicing
with you all here on this side of the camera for those of you who don't know me I'm
Diana Clark I teach at the Insight Meditation Center usually I'm teaching there on Monday nights
so often I'm teaching in the evenings rather than
here in the mornings and as you can see from the title of the
video that I turned out this morning this week I want to do the Poetry of practice
and as the days go on this week I'll unpack that like what are the different ways we might understand that
but I'll begin by saying there's a way in which we can engage with practice
that is concerned with technique make sure the should we be mindful of the breath here right on the upper lip or
should we be mindful of the chest or the belly or there's some way like we're really concerned with the technique or
maybe there's a way where practice that we're concerned with the Buddhist lists like wow okay now what was the 17th step
of uh or I know there's ten parmies but what are all the ten or
something there's might be this way in which we have this real concern with am
I doing it right what are the whole lists and do I have everything all the information that I need
and that is a valuable way to practice and that certainly has its place and it's been a real support for me
in my practice but it's not the only way
and it can be a trap if we think like it is the only way that we just have to learn all the lists and know all of the
techniques and try to get their exact right list for the exact right technique so I'd like to point to this other way
today there's other ways that invites an
another type of knowing that maybe a type of knowing that
encourages an opening of the heart or maybe a tip of coming home
that type of practicing that recognizes something true and pure
inside of us something that feels like really maybe clean and beautiful
inside of us and that allows us to like soften this continually
grasping or evaluating or looking for the next moment that sense of am I doing this
right and then of course is practicing with verse or poetry
that in language touch us in a different way
I don't want to devalue the lists and the techniques I just want to add or maybe broaden our understanding our
appreciation the ways that practice can show up and so rather than just consuming
information and trying to adapt to the information that we learn instead
allowing ourselves to be nourished by the words
to be touched and fed by what we hear
and many of you will know there is plenty of verse in the poly Canon so this is something that practitioners for
the throughout these Millennia have been practicing with first and we'll be doing some of that
and today during the guided sit I'll drop in a verse
a short poem and then in the short talk afterwards um
talk about it and maybe provide some other poems okay so with that as an introduction
Let's uh take a meditation posture
and taking a moment to really settle in
like to sit and know you're sitting
bringing an aliveness of attention to the experience of sinning
breathing the sensations of touch with the floor so the feet
touching the floor or if you're sitting on the floor the legs
the buttocks sitting on the chair or the cushion
bench couch maybe even the bed however
you are this moment whatever posture you're in at this moment
maybe your back is supported feeling the pressure the touch with the back
to the back of the chair
bringing this aliveness of attention this mindfulness
into the body into that bodily experience
inhabiting the body with aliveness with presence
and then setting the sense of direction uh movement we're going
the rest of this meditation period can you set their intention as one of
kindness is it possible to have a sense of this
moment holding yourself in care
within yourself with a kind attitude in warmth
putting aside any Notions of this being a self-improvement project
and through this meditation period return into this orientation
kindness
and then connecting with the anchor whether that's our breath for many of us
it will be the breath and feeling the sensations of breathing
in a relaxed easy way
but not a Cavalier way a way that has some
intention or commitment to being the sensations of the breath
or whatever your anchor is
and when the mind wanders that might be a time to remind ourselves
of this orientation towards kindness and just very simply gently
Begin Again no need to make stories
doesn't mean anything about us as meditators it just means the Mind
wandered and then we just come back
really feeling the sensations of breathing
the beginning middle and end of an exhale
in the beginning middle and end of an inhale
and the transitions between inhales and exhales
foreign
nowhere else to be nothing else to do
we're just here with the experience of breathing
in a simple and complicated way
foreign
I'm going to drop in a short poem
you don't need to do anything with this poem
just allow it to be heard
maybe it touches something maybe it doesn't
the poem goes like this
while walking along the river after a long day meditating
on vulture Peak I watched an elephant
splashing its way out of the water and up the bank
hello my friend a person waiting there said scratching
the elephant behind its ear did you have a good bath
the elephant stretched out its leg the person climbed up
and the two wrote off like that together
seeing what had once been so wild now a friend and companion to this good
person I took a seat under the nearest tree
and reached out a gentle hand to my own mind
truly I thought this is why I came to the woods
seen what had once been so wild now a friend and companion to this good
person I took a seat under the nearest tree and
reached out a gentle hand to my own mind
truly I thought this is why I came to the woods
thank you
foreign
[Music]
hello again
so this poem that I read during the guided meditation
maybe it's written by a poet who was inspired by the poems of the terrygata
some of you might know the Terracotta are the poems of Awakening poems of women
from the time of the Buddha and this poet was inspired by them and like
reinterpreted them and I wrote new poems which I think are lovely which I think are really lovely
and maybe I'll just quickly repeat the poem here
while walking along the river after a long day meditating on vulture
Peak I watched an elephant splashing its way out of the water and up the bank
hello my friend a person writing there said scratching the elephant behind its ear did you have
a good bath the elephant stretched out its leg the
person climbed up and the two rode off like that together
seen what had once been so wild now a friend and companion to this good person
I took a seat under the nearest tree and reached out a gentle hand
to my own mind truly I thought this is why I came to
the woods so sometimes meditation practice is not
befriending our mind but instead there's a certain type of beating ourselves up or berating ourselves or speaking
disparagingly about ourselves about our practice and so what would it mean for us to make
friends with our minds what would it mean to soften this inner critic that sometimes
shows up with the meditation practice and so this inner critic we might think
of it as something like this sub personality inside of us a certain dynamic or constellation of experiences
that puts us down belittles us as this judging blaming nagging
and it has this quality of harshness and it kind of creates this inner
climate or this inner environment of harshness and when this inner critic is
up and running there's this pervasive sense of inadequacy of being enough
whatever I'm doing is not quite right or somehow insufficient
and so when there's the inner criticus
really allowed us authoritative or really present
there's a sense of that we just don't accept things like it's not good enough
it's not okay I don't accept it you know whatever whatever our experience is this
shouldn't be happening and the four noble truths of course
recognize that the first truth is there is suffering
and then the second Noble Truth is there's something that's underlying that's suffering
and so instead of asking a question like what is underlying this what is supporting this and the inner critic is
really up and running we often ask by doing it right
we might have this feeling that we're not doing it right so can we as one way of making friends with
the mind can we change the question
instead of am I doing this right I'm sure I'm not doing this right
can we change the question to one of how am I
how am I right now and this question is very different it
has this question of kindness rather than meeting demands it's a
question of care so when we notice that the inner critic is really up and running can we make
friends with the mind and one way to do this is to just ask
how am I how am I in this moment
and so there's another poem that points to this
points to this orientation of kindness and friendship with oneself and with
one's mind with what's happening at that moment this is by the same poet whom I'll say at the end but right now I'll
just read the poem the poem goes like this
after 20 25 years on the path
I had experienced almost everything except peace
when I was young my mother told me that I would find true happiness only in
marriage and remembering her words all those years later something in me began to
tremble I gave myself to the trembling
and it showed me all the pain this little heart had ever known how countless lives of searching
had brought me at last to the present moment
which I happily married and can you imagine
we've been living together ever since without a single argument
I love this poem right it kind of has this little twist in there that we're not expecting
and the poem starts with it seems as if this practitioner had a difficulty with practice practitioner writes after 25
years on the path I'd experienced almost everything except peace
sometimes this is a way in which the inner critic shows up it's like 25 years you know however long 25 minutes
20 weeks or whatever however long we're been practicing sometimes we have this
feeling like I should get it by now I should be having different experiences
I've been having an experienced everything all this terribleness except
peace there might be some way in which the inner critic shows up telling us that we should have different
experiences than what we're having and then in this poem The practitioner
allowed herself to tremble but some of you might know that
trembling it's kind of like a compassion sometimes described as quivering of the
heart so what if this trembling that that practitioner here this poet is pointing
to is this quivering of the heart this compassion
and showing the pain that she'd had like all these years being met with
compassion and then she marries the present moment
and then she said can you imagine let's see what was we've been living together
ever since without a single argument and I kind of like this idea of that uh
like marrying the present moment because there's a way right in which there's a commitment there's a loyalty
but with no guarantees it's always going to be fun and easy like we know this we
know this in our relationships with everybody you know whether friends
family members spouses Partners kids right we know this with all of our relationships that sometimes there's
some ease and sometimes there's some difficulties but we can have this commitment this loyalty to staying
and here she's staying with the present moment so what would it mean to stay with the
present moment even though it's not always easy not always Pleasant
and then maybe I'll bring in a third poem written by the
same poet and it goes like this
I had said you know of course the same theme I was forever getting lost
until one day the Buddha told me to walk this path you will need seven
friends mindfulness curiosity courage Joy
calm Stillness and perspective
for many years these friends and I have traveled together sometimes wandering in
circles sometimes taking the long way around there were days when I thought I
couldn't go on there were days when I thought I was finally beaten it's scary
to give all of yourself to just one thing what if you don't make it
oh my heart you don't have to go It Alone
train yourself to train just a little more gently
train yourself to train just a little more
some of you might recognize that the list of the seven friends at the beginning of this poem are the seven
factors of Awakening here this poet is uh interpreting them
as mindfulness curiosity courage Joy calm Stillness and perspective
it's fantastic can you imagine if we have these as friends as companions on our path and then the poet is adding a
few more things to this list this confidence or maybe some conviction or
some Trust let me have some antidotes to doubt this
idea the poet writes it's scary to give all of yourself to just one thing what
if you don't make it imagine this is certain way the inner critic shows up it's like what if you
don't make it I better like hedge my bets and maybe I'll do a little bit of this a little bit of that or I'll be
present only sometimes when it's Pleasant or not other times or something like this but instead is
pointing to this gentle persistence at the end with this emphasis on gentle
making these seven factors making some confidence or conviction part of the
companions on this path rather than something we're supposed to
do other than something that we're supposed to do to make ourselves better
or somehow fix something what would it be like to just have these companions on our
path in the same way that we make friends with the mind
friends with the present moment what would it be like to be friendly
with the seven sectors of Awakening to invite them in as companions
so these three poems some of you might have heard of them some of you not perhaps
um or by Matty winegast last name is spelled
w-e-i-n-g-a-s-t Matty wine ghost and these are poems that are collected
in this book that's called the first free women poems of the early Buddhist
nuns and these are Maddie's interpretation of
some Awakening poems of some women and they're really beautiful I love them
they bring in a certain amount of Whimsy they bring in something that seems so relevant in the way of describing
practice in a I don't know coming from a different angle instead of this is what we should
do or something heavy or but instead kind of fussy for me it just makes my
heart sing in some kind of way and I feels like there's some openness and ease a real invitation to bring this
singing this openness this ease to our practice
so this week we'll be exploring different poems but like maybe point to practice but in
a different way in a way that hopefully is a way that maybe nourishes
and warms the heart and then allows kind of like an invitation to all aspects of
ourselves including the inner critic they're invited to
and bring this full-heartedness to our practice
so thank you and I'll see you tomorrow foreign