warm greetings from Insight Meditation Center here in Redwood City California
and and I prefer to introduce myself that way but just
saying that I'm here on this Earth with all of you all
of us together it's widespread so thank you for being
here this week we I'm discussing attitude attitudes and
these are the background moods background filters through which we how we see how we speak how we um act in the
world that uh are often not brought into Consciousness kind of an underlying
attitude that pervades everything and one of those can be um
the attitude that we know that uh
that our thinking the way we understand things is accurate and so if we know something
which is not a hard fact but an opinion which
is a judgment or an evaluation uh and we treat it as fact
then we can get into trouble and uh sometimes these are
opinions we have about ourselves that uh sometimes there's delusions of grandeur sometimes there's
a delusion of of uh the opposite of that uh uh sometimes it has to do with
delusions about uh the world around us that we know something we think we know
somebody we know their motivations their intentions we know uh you know just a lot of knowing
and in meditation as well there can be this attitude like that I know what's supposed to happen I know what is
happening and one of the useful attitudes is the attitude um not
knowing not so that you're ignorant not so that you are are
um um somehow allow something to P persist
that is harmful for you but rather that you don't harm yourself we don't harm
ourselves with the so called knowledge we have the opinions we have the
understandings we have so that we have room to see more
clearly more widely so we don't see through the filters of what we are preconceived
ideas we don't see through the filter of our opinions we don't feel we don't see
through the um the filter of the ways that we're hurt or angry or we want
something and through those filters think think that we actually know what we're
seeing um and to not know is to have the
mind be open the heart be open is to be fresh it's to be curious and interested
what is what's here let's take another look and in fact I love some of you know
I've said this often enough that I'm very fond of the word respect
ECT as a kind of a synonym for mindfulness practice because uh the spe of respect
is like spectac spectac spectacles uh to see comes to the the
Latin word to see and so to respect is to see again take a second look
mindfulness is always to take a second look and a third look what is it with a mind that doesn't
know doesn't impose or overlay our knowing on
top of a situation so to assume a meditation
posture that's right for
you and there spent some time maybe twisting around or wiggling around and
kind of moving the shoulders rocking back and forth
uh forward and backwards to find a posture that you feel the most
aligned your body aligned with
itself and to lower your gaze and let your gaze be
relaxed not looking at anything in particular
almost as if you're not looking or looking through
the peripheral
vision looking just to without seeing
anything knowing without knowing what you
see and then gently closing your eyes
and feeling the glow the hum the
tensions sensations of your body in some Global
Way not knowing not imposing your preconceived ideas
and but as if it's a brand new world to enter the world of your
body allowing the body to show itself to
you and let the different Sensations be
simple without entangling them with knowing
attitudes beliefs
predictions even memories as if you're knowing these
Sensations for the first
time and in a way that is enjoyable for you take take a little deeper
breaths and then a longer exhale relaxing your
body simple very simple enjoyment or pleasure in breathing a little bit more
consciously
fully
relaxing and letting the breathing return to
normal and once again seeing if there's a little bit of pleasure or enjoyment to
be found somewhere in the cycle of breathing in and breathing
out and as you
exhale to relax different parts of your
body
for
relaxing the thinking mind the thinking
muscle
when we're too involved in understanding or believing having
opinions it can be felt as a tension in the
mind a pressure in the forehead or on the eyes
the Jaws shoulders even down
that extra layer of believing and knowing and
reacting let it all relax and for this
meditation allow yourself not to
know being present attentive
without interpretation story meaning
predictions experiencing closely what is
here not knowing what it is
for
e
[Music]
[Music] for
for
if there's anything uncomfortable or difficult as you
meditate notice whether you have an opinion about that
or you believe something about it that's an extra
layer an alternative point of view that allows for something unknown to be
there is that whatever is challenging whatever that's going on
which is not what you know it should
be that something new is being born something new is
occurring provided you get out of the way
let your thinking relax and
quiet and with a not knowing mind feel and sense more
deeply What's Happening Here in the body with
emotions allowing things to be without
imposing
knowing
e
for
[Music]
and then as we come to the end of this [Applause]
sitting to suspend our preconceived ideas about
this moment what's happening and
instead be curious as if you don't know
not knowing can
be an expression of
respect where we put aside preconceived ideas so that we can be open to discover
a new what is here right
now
and to gaze out upon the world out upon all the people we know
and will be seeing these next few
days and to offer them their
respect seeing them fresh thinking of them a new so you can better
know how they are as if every day someone is different every
hour and in the changing ways in which people unfold
and evolve they do have the capacity to be
happy they do have the capacity to be feel at home in themselves and be
peaceful and may we wish that for
everyone May the people in our lives and may all people be
happy may they be healthy May may they be
safe may they be peaceful may they be
free may they too rest in the
joy of not always
knowing and may we support
others in their capacity to grow and to change and to
become better people by not imposing our preconceived
ideas may all beings be
happy [Music]
so thank you very
much
so hello everyone and Welcome to our third talk on
attitudes and specifically more specifically the to to move
from unskillful attitudes to skillful ones and the unskillful one that is very
common in this world is uh ill will or
aversion takes many forms right now I'm thinking about resentment as a form form of
it and um the um living with resentment with kind of a
hurt anger and hostile
hurt uh but uh to be critical complaining is a form of
aversion or hostility to be complaining about people about things too much all too it all too
easily carries with it some kind of ill will and um and it isn't that there to
deny that there are things that are hurtful that happen in the world or things that we need to take into account
that they're not helpful or skillful to what people are doing but to see but to
have aversion or ill will be uh an attitude
and um the um a pervasive way in which we see the world we go into a new space
in a new room with no you know people we maybe we don't know we've known them before but it's we're steing into a new
situation and we carry with us a a mood or an attitude of resentment or aversion
or ill will or criticalness you know where we we have the idea something is
wrong even as we step into the room and we have to figure out what that is and we have to figure out what to fix or
what to avoid and um who are the people who are the bad people the wrong people
and who are the people who are not there's kind of built-in kind of mood of
a verion that can be there and most people don't think that they have that
but um there was a time in my life you know many years ago almost 50 years ago where
um um my friend friends would say Gil you you seem to always be angry and um I
didn't think I was angry at all but somehow there was a mood underlying mood of and it was probably something like
resentment that things were difficult or challenging and I was upset about it and uh it took me a while to kind of
see that that was the case and some of it I was able to see only by doing starting to meditate regularly and then
slowly I started to see that under underneath my ordinary kind of way of
being in the world thinking about the world in fact there was a kind of anger or aversion that was operating there and
uh slowly that began to relax and hopefully now there's very little of it
left and um the um so to uh part of the
function of meditation practice is in fact to discover these kinds of things and if we're too enamored
with uh becoming calm having pleasure in meditation we might not notice if we're
too uh caught up in trying to avoid tension and stress when we meditate we
might not stop to take a good look respectful look at the tension we have
the stress the strains we have in order to identify what is really going on here for us and uh so we can see the
underlying mood that might be operating attitude and then once we see something
it's like then there's opportunity then there's a almost like space has cre create been created that now something
can begin to unfold or relax or evolve or change in a healthy way but without
knowing uh things can often be kind of locked in but knowing begins the process of
changing so knowing is quite important and not knowing is important
so to recognize something and then not know what's supposed to happen not not
know a judgment and not know an opinion that we overlay on top of it and um uh
kind of to make room for something that we can't predict to allow it to happen
many times in my life I've been surprised that things evolve differently than way I thought they were supposed to
evolve sometimes I thought they turn were going in the wrong direction sometimes I thought they were going in a
good direction and um then they would go opposite of what I thought
but what I've discovered is that if I show up to be present for the situation
it tends to move things in a good direction certainly tends to move me in a good direction this this simple
presence and that simple presence can be characterized by not
knowing um uh the respect of being present without bringing our
preconceived ideas our memories our expectations of what is we're going to see or be with so I would like to offer
an alternative to aversion to ill will if we have this simmering background
kind of ill will or aversion or complaining or criticalness that's going on and um or we have resentment towards
some even anger towards someone that we know and it's very clear it's not like a
attitude it's just like when we see that person that's what comes up is um the um uh an alternative is be
curious when you feel aversion when you feel hostility
criticalness shift over to a curious State a curious attitude what's
happening here what's going on here I think this is a time to understand better this is a time to have a kind of
beginner's mind I don't really know but let me study let me pay attention what's happening to this person what's
happening to this situation so that we're kind of stepping forward interested as opposed to
stepping forward critical and uh so even if if we're
angry with someone maybe there's good reason for it if it's safe enough for you to do it um is to step forward and
say and find out what's happening with you what's going on or how are you or uh
just be show your interest and curiosity um
and this is a way of coming forward with some modum of a not knowing mind
genuinely curious what's going on here but also when we step forward with the
Curiosity with interest we're actually creating space for the other person to
change um but if we could step forward with them with our criticalness with our preconceived ideas uh people feel that
and they feel boxed in they feel like they have to defend themselves or react or take a stand or something but if we
come forward kind of with the equivalent in our attitude with open
arms uh tell me more i' like to know more how are you what's going on uh it
can uh disarm people which is a powerful powerful metaphor that uh we use that
sometimes um that we can uh catch people off guard they uh most people are uh
relaxed if we show genuine interest in them and maybe we begin discovering something deeper about the situation the
person than we would if we stayed in our critical stance uh stayed in our anger only and
I'm not saying it's easy to put aside anger there might still be there but see
if you canot let it be the attitude by which you operate instead have an
attitude of curiosity step forward what's happening here what's going on on here and that
could be a gift in a sense many people um uh don't get enough experience of
people who are interested in really knowing what's happening with them what's going on some people don't want
you to probe but um but to you know to come with a beginner with a not knowing
mind and oh hi what's happening with you how are you today and how have you been and and
um and uh making space and then perhaps some of the things that some of the
reasons why we're critical of someone maybe that person begins to relax and
some of those reasons won't be the present in the moment maybe the past issues are still there but in the moment
maybe that they begin operating in the way that's difficult for you and certainly I think it's much better for
us as practitioners to come forward with curiosity and interest than it is to
come forward with aversion and resentment and anger and uh and maybe the person who
becomes disarmed is ourselves and um and maybe in some kind
of way uh it's healthier for us it's safer for us it's uh it's um has greater
benefits for us to be that way than it is for others maybe that's what you can also
discover how you are what happens to you curious
when you come forward curious about others so if you have occasion to be
about around uh other people these next few days and especially for Thanksgiving
where there might be a number of people family members who are challenging perhaps friends who are challenging um
um see what it's like to come forward with interest in
curiosity so thank you very much and and uh I'll be here tomorrow morning which
in the United States is um Thanksgiving morning and um and then I'll go home and
and help with the preparations there so thank you very much for being here and
if there are some people here in the peninsula who would like to come to IMC tomorrow that uh uh Gloria is hosting a
a potluck Thanksgiving meal here I think maybe around noon it's on the we IMCA
website and what's new so if you're local you're welcome to come thank
you