foreign
Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if you can hear me okay give me a
thumbs up audio's alright fantastic welcome so uh let's begin by uh
saying hello welcoming ourselves welcoming each other and I start by saying hi I'm Nicky in
Mountain View California on seated Ohlone land who is here and wants to uh
um say hello take it away I'm Lisa from Redwood City hi Lisa
I'm Peter I'm from San mate Peter I'm from San Mateo hi Peter
Vicky from Oakland hi Vicky
hello Ali salaam shalom Susan from San Mateo hi Susan and hello
Jamie from from coast me walk on Marin County Murray Christine and Bodie from
Down Under good afternoon to you guys hey
um and Aloha says Amy from Oahu anybody else and Bill in Dallas
hi Jesse read in the shadows here in Oakland but
in the shadows I heard who else did I hear the couple of other people who said I heard Santa Rosa I heard Susan was
there someone else too yes Claudia from Carlsbad in San Diego there's Claudia hi anybody else
Jerry from Toronto hi Jerry great is great and hi Adelia from Brooklyn and
you're from San Diego Charlie from Washington came from British Columbia Gita from Vancouver hello dear Canadian
contingent they're coming in one after another I love it celebrating one year since my retreat
with you and Diana hi good to see you
so let's uh let's begin I think this face is warmed up the space is warmed up
so Let's uh uh transition thank you Neil
for posting information about happy hour Google Groups if you are new to happier
you're warmly invited to join um to get uh quotes and references and
uh as I like to say it's low in traffic but high in heartfulness so uh if you are
unmuted please mute yourself now and we're going to transition to the meditation part to dharmint and
meditation and I change the settings so that accidental unmuting won't be
possible we'll keep all the channels quiet especially the chat for this duration please don't send personal
chats to me while I'm teaching can be quite distracting so wait until the end
thank you last but not least I'm going to turn on recording for Audio Dharma here we go
there so so hello and welcome to happy hour
so um or or today's uh practice I wanted to see
something into seed this couple of things actually one is this sense of um
this invitation for um but considering that Our intention
really everything that we Lead With Our intention with everything in in our
lives in the world with Our intention and and
um and intending inviting ourselves for this
cultivation um is is really the very first step so I
want to share a poem that's
um that's written by someone a a practitioner who um
um I'd love to share with you it's inspiring it's beautiful the poem is called a prayer for awakening so the
sense of intention this this prayer for awakening so so here we go and I'll
share it when we're practicing but just to drop it in May my mind be expansive enough
to hold whatever comes to visit may my heart be brave enough to face all
that is before me may my eyes be sharp enough to see whatever is there
may my ears be Keen enough to hear all that is said and may my arms may my arms
be long enough to embrace all that needs comforting hmm
this invocation this invocation of may I may I cultivate may I cultivate my
heart myself in these beautiful ways so I might you to consider may I you know
what invocation do you have the invocation you have for um
your heart your life as a practitioner and
um another thing I wanted to see is um besides this idea of in touch
actually connecting it with intention is that tomorrow in the west especially in
the US it's considered the same to Valentine's Day and and that actually can bring some
sadness for many people oh I don't have a valentine a
partner and um there's so many beautiful ways to
construe to perceive this idea of of love so let's celebrate
Saint Valentine's Day tonight being the eve of it tomorrow the day of it as a way as a way to celebrate self-love as a
day to celebrate this beloved that is ourselves this this being that we
usually forsake for another we just forget like there's this wonderful being
that that needs and appreciates love the first and foremost and also to celebrate
it as a day for Universal love doesn't have to just be this one person
and it's tit for Tad and I like you and if you do this for me if you love them like no can we just be kind can we be
loving to whoever shows up on our path could be the grocery store clerk can we share our
good well meta as good will a sense of interconnection we have with
every human being instead of just thinking this in this
limited way of just one in a particular way Etc so really expanding expanding
this this idea so happy Saint meta day that's
what I like to Saint Valentine's Saint Meadows really Saint met today it's
meta by any way shape or form sorry
is that plenty so let's uh let's practice together so
invite you to land to land in your bodies to arrive
to arrive with your invocation with your intention
whatever it is in this moment may be inspired are the pillow on my red
from a fellow practitioner
Maybe their invitation their invocation
is a seed for yours may my mind be expensive
expensive enough to hold whatever comes who is it
foreign
resting ah breathing with that yes
may my eyes my inner eyes be sharp enough open enough internally to see
whatever is there whatever is arises
whatever is here
clear seeing
may my Years be Keen enough to hear all that is said all that is communicated
internally externally deep listening deep listening to myself
to the universe to others
and may my arms thy proverbial arms be long enough to
embrace all that needs comforting
which might start with my own heart myself I
may need comforting in this moment this body This Heart
as well as others
nothing connecting with the body with Our intention
for the breath
may my heart be Limitless
knowing it's exalt and boundless capacity for care
and love for all beings for myself for others
kindness Good Will everywhere
may I accept and love myself just as I am
connecting with the breath with the body with intentions with good will
your thoughts are arising entangled if you find yourself entangled in Fall
it's okay
and we gently let them go and reconnect with Our intention our
presence our kindness
and good will starting with this being here and now
breathing
alive just this breath
may I love and accept myself just as I am
I love and accept this body
especially if it's having challenges right now just as it is
with each breath relaxing into opening two
whatever is arising In This Moment may I meet this moment with kindness
may I meet this moment this body this heart this mind
may I meet all that arises with kindness
may I Meet myself as my valentine
a beloved other may open my heart to myself fully loving
accepting cherishing
is complex human being that is me who's doing their best
who in the words of Suzuki roshi are perfect this being with me is perfect
just as they are just as I am
and there's always room for improvement
can I open my heart this being here fully In This Moment
just for a moment risking it for just a moment
and always step back let's step in for just a second to see what it feels like
love heals love heals can you offer yourself some healing love
see the good see the good
now expanding our hearts they are expandable
what if we meet someone
we know or maybe don't even know
as a valentine as this seeing their goodness seeing their
Humanity it is said that the Dalai Lama
whenever he meets someone that person feels like they're the most important
person in the world
it gives them his attention care
kind gaze honoring each person each being
their uniqueness or goodness
what if you did that tomorrow on Saint met today Saint Valentine's Day
with say the Paris style makes your coffee see their Humanity
see give them your mother
and the whole world is full of Valentines full of this beautiful
expressions of humanity Why not start tonight
the beings who are practicing with you
it feels overwhelming or back see yourself as in Valentine's beloved
others beautiful human being as perfect as they are and there's
always room for improvement all of us are mixed packs and all of us
are worthy of care of love of acceptance
may I see the goodness in everyone I meet may I see their friendliness
may I receive with friendliness all that arises in my heart and my mind internally
externally in my life may I meet this moment
kindness
as we turn to end this meditation sit together
feeling into your intention again and recognizing the goodness of this
intention why am I here
letting the goodness of this wholesome desire a shine in your
heart in the word outwards
together letting our lights shine and offering our light our goodness not
just to ourselves but to all beings everywhere and all beings everywhere
know their own goodness feel their own love and care their own
goodness may I feel my own goodness my care for myself
may all beings everywhere are you safe
happy healthy navies
may all beings be free including myself [Music]
thanks for your practice everyone [Music] foreign
like to invite us consider your intentions why are we here
why are we here why are we practicing why are we here why are we here tonight
why are we practicing why are we showing up why is that
I'm feeling to that why and what can be the beautiful expression
the beautiful way of saying that as I shared with the poem prayer for awakening what is your prayer
for awakening what is your prayer for awakening may I may I meet the moment of kindness
may I be awake may I be kinder to myself and others may I whatever it is what is
your prayer for awakening so it's powerful to know to see our Our
intention our prayer for awakening it actually makes gives it more
more prominence when it's seen and it's even more prominent prominent
and not only when it's seen by us but it's when it's seen by others when it's held Witness by friendly eyes recognize
shared by friendly eyes and we're going to do that for ourselves now
in the small group so the invitation is we wanted to share something about your
intention let it be honored let yourself honor your intention let yourself be held witness be accountable
may I wake up in this very life may I be kind I know there are a lot of
challenges and maybe I lose my temper in these ways may I may I have more ease in
the midst of that or whatever it might be there's no right or wrong it's just beautiful to to see our intentions and
if you like to speak to it as much as you like or as little as you like
honoring each other and also if you want to show up with silence that's fine so
in small groups one person the first first person will share
something about their intention uh just a short maybe 30 seconds
um or at most amended and then the next person and then the next person will come back to you so we'll go around and
around make sure everybody has time to share only speak from your experience
not guiding not directing asking questions from others just show up as
you are and if you want to say pass or hold space silent space that's perfectly
fine um but such a beautiful opportunity for
perceiving support giving support recognizing acknowledging just very
um take advantage take advantage of this so so I'm going to create the breakout
rooms and take care of yourselves with kindness take care of each other with
kindness Okay so here we go
the rooms were a little closing about 20 seconds we'll wait until everybody's back
but in the meanwhile if you like to start uh sharing your Reflections you're welcome
to do that in chat either type to everyone um
in which case it'll be public or just send to me in which case I'll be private
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back and welcome back
and if you'd like to share any Reflections you can raise your Zoom ad or type them in chat either
about the guided meditation or small groups what did you notice what what a
rose especially if you haven't spoken in this group ever or for a while you're
welcome to uh share your Reflections to step forward
I'll take one or two reflections
Ellie please hi thanks Nikki for doing this and
creating this space for us so uh it's it's interesting because uh with
the inner critic and all that that I love to participate oh that I have
organically you know I do mindfulness and then the loving kindness arises out of that I don't repeat the pattern I
mean the sayings that much but then added a blue for some reason I started
uh kissing my own hand like this I have no idea where it came from or
what it came through but I I I like it but when I remember you
know to be kind to myself I I don't know where that gesture came from I don't know maybe I cooked for myself so much
that's why oh I started kiss you know kissing my own like this but that's a nice gesture I've never had it
before and then the other uh inside they came that I just immediately
went to find out where that came from and all that that's not really important at this point I mean I'm just enjoying
it well I remember to do it that's sweet that is so sweet thank you for sharing
that Ellie that just gladens my heart so much it's you know these these physical
gestures sometimes you know giving ourselves a hug or just appreciating putting your hand on our hearts there's
and and oh this is oh I just tried it it's so lovely just so sweetheart thank
you for doing all these things for me dear Han it's also thanking your hand like oh my God I just feel this appreciation for this hand that types
and cleans and cooks and just does try it everyone it's it's pretty wild it's
the sense of appreciation it's very sweet come on what do you have to lose kissing your own it's very sweet thank
you Ellie thanks for sharing that just such a beautiful gesture of appreciating this person who serves you takes care of
you yeah that's very sweet thank you there's a lot of cooking especially in the pandemic time yeah
yeah thank you Ali and Jesse says thanks Nikki for an
amazing practice I am so excited for Saint meta day oh that's great I love that thank you for that Jesse yeah maybe
we'll make space for one last reflection if anybody wants to share or ask a question
are we close and for those who haven't been to happier for a while I'm experimenting
with a you know 50 minute five zero minute format instead of one hour just to see what it feels like in so far it
felt a little lighter and felt when so the other quick Reflections questions
what was it like for you to have your your intention witnessed
or shared by others
was it empowering supportive scary
I know you have thoughts red please
thank you Nikki yeah I find it um powerful and important actually
say I I want to live with a more open heart
to to have an aspiration that's really unrelated to any that I might have had
as a younger person that has nothing to do with um you know acquiring or you know building
a career or anything like that and and that there's a kind of seriousness about the intention
that um is increased by by stating it and by
you know stating it in public that yes this is actually what I want to do with my life now
um there's sort of a boldness about that and and I like that
thank you yeah yeah beautiful thank you Fred there is a
boldness about that yeah yes may may we all be bold I see a
couple more hands and so let's just honor those and and then close but I'll
ask um see clear and even before that I think people are in chat are telling me that Jeannie is waving her physical hand but
Genie I don't see everyone so can you possibly oh here I see you there okay
you can unmute there you go yes I don't know how to do this hand
raising I've got this little iPad so um well I was just my experience was that
um my partner was a very gracious listened to me it was really nice to share my kind of a new understanding of
thought I had and then I was going listen wanting to listen to him and um
but we ran out of time and so I did you know I so I'm not
used to the time thing I haven't regulated it well to so that you know we
kind of know internally how much time we have and how to you know when to
change off or switch yeah yeah I hear that I hear you appreciate that they
listen to you with care and and there's a regret I still wanted to listen and like oh I wish I had regulated my time
or I still haven't got that done I think what helps Genie for you and also for everyone else
um is what we're doing here in in the group is is to um to
um turn to um before we used to do monologues like
one person would talk for a while but now we've changed that so so it's more a spiral so each person as I mentioned
shares just 30 seconds or at most a minute just a tiny little nugget yeah
yeah and then the next person person shares and then the next person so that everybody has time
but I I do appreciate your your wish to have honored them so I'm glad that you
said that so I could uh bring that out
sure okay you get the last word Claire and welcome Stuart for the first time
here live rather than a recording yay how wonderful welcome this is great
yay live is good all right Claire
uh just to follow up on your discussion of the way that groups work we were a
three-person group and in fact we did sort of stick to the 32nd principle but
what was really nice was that each person seemed to build on the person preceding them it really was sort of an
upward spiral it was really very lovely beautiful we all felt that we were
giving each other something to each other yeah great you couldn't have said it
better the the idea of this the beauty of the Spiral is is the uplift that
happens especially when you talk about your intentions so beautiful like it just it's it's a virtuous
cycle it just keeps going around and we give each other gifts so that's exactly the idea thank you Claire for sharing
how beautifully that that worked lovely so so thank you all thank you all for
your practice and thank you Jerry happy Metta all year round exactly all year
round everyone thank you all for your practice thank you for your cultivation may you be well
may you be happy may all beings be well and free including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone take good care be well
see you on Wednesday I'll try