okay how is the volume vent okay
good
sorry about that I thought I turned it off so welcome to the fourth in a five week
series on introduction to mindfulness meditation in the past three weeks we covered
breath body and emotions in kind of co-centric rings the breath being in the
center as Tanya mentioned last week kind of the most focused object
opening the attention up a little bit to everything that's happening in the body especially Sensations
and then to emotions last week and I'm just going to give a very quick
overview of what we covered so far to kind of ground us before we start this
week's instructions so the first week we covered what is
mindfulness meditation which is being with our direct experience rather than
thinking about it being with experience as it's unfolding
intimacy with our lives it's watching
and observing with awareness like a naturalist might observe the environment
all the interconnections between it as Tanya mentioned that first week this
cultivates the capacity for choice rather than reaction
another really important theme we've been returning to time and time again is
this idea of relationship with what is arising
how are we relating to what is arising what is the internal posture inner
posture or attitude towards experience and recognizing this
is greatly facilitated by anchoring our attention in what is here
and now the breath the body those are always here they're always now
so the first two weeks then we did focus on breath and body the breath being the
often preferred object of attention or anchor tether
and that it helps to build Focus because it's changing it's Dynamic and for most
people it's pretty neutral right for some people the breath doesn't work
and that's okay the two simplest alternatives if you're finding that's true for you is
to notice what's happening overall in your body Sensations or to notice hearing sounds
and that brings us to body our bodies have a kind of intelligence
our systems have a kind of intelligence and it can be helpful to think of it as
three centers of intelligence there's the head which in this culture we often
associate with intelligence but there's also the heart and the gut
and Neuroscience Bears this out there are actual neuron cells basal ganglia
around our hearts in the center of our chest and in our bellies so we really are getting
information that's moving both directions
the vagus nerve is kind of the pathway and it's worth noting that the
intelligence of the body the intelligence of the heart they operate kind of on a different timeline
and it's really helpful to begin to tune in and listen and that listening is a skill
Sensations are the language that the body and heart communicate feelings for the language of
the hard emotions right so
the experience of Sensations or emotions
can increase or decrease based on the ways we relate to it
resisting or being angry or reactive to pain for example can make it much worse
being kind and compassionate towards sadness can help to transform it
so the principle applies like how we relate to the experience is key
last week we covered emotions and they can range from
the absolutely Sublime to the downright awful
right emotions are ways that our minds our
hearts interpret or encode our experience they're kind of their own
form of communication and while they're happening in the present they can either be based on what
happens in the present or they can be triggered by reacting to
something very innocent in the present that is actually
um carrying an overlay of the past so emotions can be
as Tanya said earlier in this course tricky to work with because they feel very authoritative
but they're not always responding to what's happening in the moment accurately
so it can be as simple someone can say something perfectly innocent to me but if it sounds like something the bully in
seventh grade said I'm off right I might not recognize
that this is that deeper part of me my Windex system might not recognize that
this is now and that was then it's still in a reactive mode
seen early Emotions Don't Have to escalate as we talked about last week they're
kind of have like a 90-second half-life process as long as we don't interfere or
interact with them emotions fuel thinking and thinking
fuels emotions so last week's topic and this week's topic thinking are very
closely related they're like symbiotic species in the
same Forest they just they're constantly an interaction
so the topic of thinking is very close to the topic of emotions
and how we relate to our thinking how we relate to it is very close to how
we relate to reality itself and mindfulness mindful awareness can
can help us transform this relationship to a relationship of choice awareness
and wisdom and Tanya will talk more about this relationship and how we begin to shift
it in a few minutes first though we're going to take questions from the past week or anything
earlier that we've covered and before we start I'll just give a very quick tutorial on um using the
microphone
so these mics they kind of they pick up sound at the top so it's really helpful
to hold them like this the classic construction is like you're going to eat an ice cream cone so very
close to your mask if you need to turn it on there's this black on black button here you just
press it for a couple of seconds and the light will turn green and then it'll be ready and we ask that you pass it softly if
you can if you want to turn it off between people you can but it's not necessary
so anybody have questions
oh yes and yeah since we're a fairly small group tonight if the mic is far
away it would be great to help pass it to someone or help them get to it if you're closer to it than they are
so since we've got one there I'm going to put one over here
we would love to hear any questions you have comments you've had things you've been exploring in your meditation
floor is open
even questions about what I just said
okay and if you could please when you're about to speak give your name hello good
evening Anne Rose um well you just have really resonated with
me in terms of the emotions and how our actions can be
driven by them but that through this practice I can be more mindful of them but then I
found myself especially today getting caught up in something and
it was then I realized it was because I was afraid and triggered by a previous
incident and just trying to prevent anything from escalating
and then I and then I wasn't mindful of my actions and how I
spoke to other people and that was like the whole purpose of like my meditation
Journey just mindful of how my interactions and just how I talk
to myself and others and it's just so easy to get to go back I mean the other day I was
just like oh this is really working and then today got caught up I've had you
know I I was unanchored or whatever and
got swept away again and I just having that compassion talking to myself
like talking myself through it without feeling like it's a hokey thing like it's okay and Rose but without I
don't want it to be kind of like a cop-out to like oh you messed up but it's okay no I want them like well
you can do do it differently next time and I just there's a balance at least for me and my
internal dialogue and thank you for listening what a beautiful sharing I really I love
what you just said and how even in the triggering it sounds
like there was still mindfulness present right the way you're describing it I'm
like oh I need to be mindful about how I'm speaking because these emotions have come up
yeah I guess I was trying to and in that because I I was mindful of the fact that
it was angry I I was angry about that and I
sometimes in the effort of not trying
it's just that I just don't I'm just trying to figure out that balance
but I if that makes sense knowing and acknowledging
whatever it is that I'm doing and if it's not how it's not the best response
it's just but yeah and Rose I think um one thing
that's important is but uh it sounds really important to
acknowledge your own anger and not to try and make your anger just go away that there's a reason you're angry right
yes yes and so um we don't want to kind of bypass
stuffing by stuffing or denying and so sometimes if I'm feeling angry
and I know it's I need to be with it I just I actually try not to say or do
anything I try and wait because if in the moment when I'm
feeling that if I'm trying to act like something's different there's a disconnect or something
and maybe I need more time to process what I'm feeling what I'm angry about
what is it I need you know I need to talk through it and sometimes we don't have the luxury it's like we just have
to respond right then and then we can just sometimes I'll just say I'm I'm just angry I just need to name
that I'm triggered I'm angry right now and I'm trying to be reasonable but um you know these feelings are up
I'm not mad at you or it's you know I'm not trying to blame you or whatever it is that's honest and real
I just wow I'm having a lot of feelings
thank you
uh hi I'm Varun I have a question about what you just said Tanya so sure I've
been trying to like you know stay with my emotions more like anger sadness
to process them but sometimes I wonder okay like when is the when have I
processed it enough and I'm just staying in a bad mood for no reasons how do you
know kind of that's a great question yeah last week we taught a practice called
raft so you might want to listen to that because I won't be able to um you know tell you all about it but it
helps you walk through when you're feeling and break apart things a little bit like recognize how you're feeling
what's going on except that that's what happened is happening because it's like well you
know we may not want to be sick but we're sick so we need to accept that we're sick so we can make decisions
right so same thing with emotions and then the next part of the practice
is to feel it in the body because here you know there's this dynamic between
our thinking And the emotions the thinking we trigger
the feelings and so this this part of the practice we're really directing just toward the
true felt sense hot pressing
pounding sinking whatever it is kind of in that way and try and be with that a little
bit and then the the there's two T's in my raft and the first T is kind of like
um tees apart all the different parts oh this is the feeling this is this
situation this is my memory of another situation this is my value that's being violated this is their value this is
um the circum this the culture I'm living in or working in or the job
expectations there's all these different parts that are coming together and
fueling what's happening for me emotionally so I try and we tease that apart and then we can start to look at
each piece individually because as a cluster it has a lot it's a lot harder to work with it
and then in this practice the next part would be kind of to find a some a spot to rest in like trust what can I trust
about what's happening here myself my capacity breathing time will help trying
to help yourself kind of let go of the busyness of the practice
is that feel like giving you something that you could think about doing with your emotions in a different way yeah
yeah great so last week in the class which is you can find you know and
listen to it and and see that Mark and go through a guided practice on it yeah yeah
so the you know there is this real kind of idea that we need to sit with our feelings but very often we're
refueling them or actually making them worse the way that we're talking to
ourself about the story and and you know sort of
what we're saying to ourselves about ourselves or others would just end up kind of making it worse and worse if we
just stay in the thinking mind so um and you know what's true about like
an anger is that underneath it it's usually coming from something that we're afraid of or that we're been hurt by so
often emotions are you know there's there's stacking on top of each other there's the first emotion and then
there's a reaction to the emotion or you know so sometimes we also need to say well what's underneath this you know
um and sometimes we just need to kind of chill out and just let it you know distract ourselves
and and kind of let it relax and then it's like have you ever had that happen where you like and then you come back
later and you're like what was I was so UPS I don't really
even remember why I don't know why I got so upset right it was maybe just you know an
accumulation of stress and situations that just you got overwhelmed by
so yeah thanks for the question
uh my name is Brian I have a good question how do you sit
with the sit with it any longer you feel like
you're going to go into like I don't know uh is the green light on
it is now yes great hi everyone uh name is Brian yeah I was just asking how
like is there any technique that I could use if like my feeling is so intense that I
feel like if I sit with it any longer I'm just gonna freak out
I'm happy to start and I would also love to hear what you have say about that so when I first came to
this practice I had a lot of anxiety so I can really relate to your question thank you for asking it
honestly something Tanya mentioned a few minutes ago is really helpful which is if it starts to get overwhelming
distraction is a completely valid way of relating to it so if you're
trying for example through the raft process if if you're trying to you know recognize and tease apart and everything
in between and it's just mounting that's a good time to if you're
meditating and you can keep meditating shift to a different object go to sound
go to the body go to the breath isn't always helpful if the panic attack is coming
feet and hands open your eyes and also it's okay to shift entirely
right so when you're sitting with it
is it describe how you're being with it when the anxiety starts to build
it smells like um like a fight
you know like one layer and then another layer and another layer and it's like oh man it's
getting to be a little too much and then I'm just like it's the whole like thinking right and I
think okay this is not good and then that just makes it worse yes good recognizing very good recognizing you're
recognizing that feedback loop that cycle right so what we've resist persists right
we're adding fuel to the fire by resisting it so one thing that really helps for me is
to take a step back and notice the Judgment this is not good okay
okay and be with that like you can always take another step back and be with
but the emotion itself might not be the best place to be and this area of your
body tends to be where our emotions live and that's not the most helpful place if
you're going into a fear spiral an anxiety attack so I find looking at the attitude the
contention that inner fight itself is something to notice and be gentle and
kind with Tanya I'm sure you have something wise to add here
I'm truthfully trying to figure out how I'm gonna adjust my time so it's a little
bit hard for me to access a response right now just like
um but I think the my main thing that I want to want to say to you Brian is to honor what you feel like
is your capacity if you feel like it's too much
then say okay right now this feels like too much so
I'm gonna do something different it's okay that's part of me listening to what
what I can take you know and um especially when we find our minds are in
these really active kind of they're just not you can move that chair
yeah yeah please um you know when the mind is so kind of
intense and demanding and has that kind of momentum it's better just to not try
and argue with it and just go do the dishes
you know like go do something different but do it mindfully
you know and um and it's like it's not a problem you're just gonna honor the conditions it's like you want to go
outside and for a walk but it's pouring down rain so you know either it's a good idea or
it's not a good idea or you have a the rain jacket or you don't and you you make your choice depending on the
conditions right if you're sick and it's raining maybe it's not a good idea to go for a walk
does that make sense
okay so I do want to tell you about thinking
shall we shift is it okay all right so I want to do something
um for you know to introduce this topic I want to invite you if you want to this
is an invitation to kind of close your eyes and do an imaginary I'm going to do
an imagination thing with you and if you don't want your eyes closed just gaze or do whatever you want if you don't like
what I'm saying don't pay attention okay it's okay so I'd like you to imagine that you're
you know oh let's say you're three years old
and um somebody maybe even your teacher is
reading a book and the name of this book is you are not
your thoughts what
and you get to look at this picture book and it says thoughts come and go
they never last long one minute they're here the next they're gone
when you look up at the clouds and the skies of blue try to see the whole sky
as the clouds pass through the clouds are like thoughts
the sky is like you
now fast forward to your eight years old
and you're on the playground or you're in a class and something
happens and you have a thought like
I'm stupid or nobody likes me
and you remember oh first you react and then you remember
you know I'm Not My Thoughts I'm not stupid because I'm having this
thought I'm not unlikable because I'm having
this thought this is just a thought and it will come and go like the clouds in the sky
and imagine this in another situation where you had a thought
and you realize oh it's just a thought
imagine you've been able to practice this your whole life
and what would it be like to be here now how would you have a different relationship with thinking
if you'd been read this story many times
and when you're ready you can just open your eyes
and do you think it might have made a difference for you if you'd been taught
you are not your thoughts
no yes maybe yeah okay
so thoughts are one part one part but we tend to really
give a lot of weight to our thinking it's a we identify so much with our
thoughts so it's a it's a sticky place
it's a very sticky place for us to start to work on being mindful mindful
of thinking so
this idea this remembering when we're having meditations and we're thinking it
can be very helpful to remind ourselves I didn't ask my mind to have that
thought right I have thoughts that I feel good
about and I have thoughts I don't feel good about they can be about the same thing and be very different clearly I'm not my
thought right thoughts are part of our narrative they're part of how we make sense of
life and often they're also conditioned by
what we've been taught different values or beliefs or things that we've been told our
thoughts also come from what other people tell us they're not necessarily even you know something we would choose
to have be our our thinking process over time that changes
so this idea of kind of being a little less attached to them like letting them
be those clouds that come through the sky right that as you're meditating
working on sitting back and opening up and just okay there's a thought I don't
have to change it I don't have to agree with it I don't have to disagree with it but literally to create some space
between the thinking and the awareness does that make sense
another way to put this is that as you're meditating thinking is going to be happening right we don't get to have
that on off switch thinking not thinking right so when you're meditating
you can let thoughts be in the background instead of in the foreground
so choosing to keep your attention more closely focused on the breathing or
Sensations or sound and letting the thoughts be kind of what
we give you know we just know they're there kind of more like we know the Train sound is there but
we're not giving our most of our attention to it kind of like that
foreign
to help yourself if you're having really sticky thinking
is to ask yourself what am I feeling in my body right now
sort of helping you kind of get out of the
dream or mini movie of the thinking and helping you connect your your self to
the direct experience in the moment
our mind works to kind of weave together all the things that are happening at
once to create a cohesive experience for us so that means the emotions the thoughts
the sensations in the body The Sounds the plans the what people are doing there's a lot that gets kind of
kind of woven together in our mind so part of what we're doing tonight you
know is unraveling the thinking from the rest of the experience right now trying
to let thoughts be something that we pay attention to in a different way
remembering they come and go remembering they're not Who We Are and um
let's see
another what we'll do in our meditation this first meditation is to notice the
different kinds of thinking so thoughts
um maybe that's right now just close your eyes and just sit and just notice what
can you notice about what what's happening in your mind about thinking how are you thinking
are you hearing a dialogue are you seeing words
are you seeing images are the images moving are the images like a movie
what can you notice about how your mind thinks
how did your mind think about hearing a train
how do you know you're hearing a train
and can anyone say anything about how their mind thinks
let's just move right into the meditation you guys are all nicely settled so
just being aware yep adjust your posture that's right take a moment
get your feet grounded upright
maybe lift the shoulders roll them back
and feel into your breathing just take three a three breath Journey
kind of really letting yourself become intimate with the experience of breathing
so we use this term an anchor
and is the breath and anchor for you does it help you come into the present moment is it useful for you
if it's not is it hearing or Sensations
oh whatever your anchor is if it's not the breath taking the equivalent of a three breath
Journey without anchor
next we want to kind of tune into that inner
attitude or the relationship or the posture inner posture right now
sort of invite a sense of trust trust in being aware
and our capacity to have mindfulness
inviting a sense of caring and kindness
with ourselves and with whatever experience arises
inviting the mind to attend to experience
and as this is a meditation time to practice with thinking
just remind yourself that at any time if you get caught up in the story of the thinking it's okay to bring yourself
back to your anchor it's okay to RECenter
that we're going to get lost in thinking it's gonna happen it's normal
and as soon as you become aware that you're lost in thought you're already back
and we can just Savor that backness that awareness
rest into that there's no need to get angry at ourselves or critical
so over and over again we can re-center re reconnect with the breath or
sound and help ourselves feel our body feel embodied
feel like oh I'm here
I'm right here just hear this now
this breath this sound
and when you feel some stability
you can ask what AM how am I thinking right now our
thinking is thinking happening if so can I be aware of it
like for me a lot of it is just this narrator this inner coach or narrator
kind of telling me what to do and then as I get caught in the thought
it starts to become like more planning and thinking
seeing images seeing what you can witness while
feeling your feet or your hands placed together or your breath
and what am I aware of now
are there images in the mind is there talking in the mind
is there's this concept this thought that I should be having a
particular experience
just seeing if you can't focus more on the process the way you're thinking
rather than the content or the story or the material
sort of preferencing noticing how the thinking is happening
sometimes the Mind needs a lot of
um I don't know maybe a more strong intervention like thinking just naming
thinking or naming planning or seeing and just sort of the mind is seeing for
thinking we might need to say a full sentence sometimes
it's just the lightest little thing it's like oh there's a thought and just it's like so soft
so subtle so experimenting a little bit with your
own mind right now and seeing how it responds
to just a very light touch and then a more kind of
more wordy response more specific response
being careful not to think about thinking you know in your meditation
we're trying to get to know our own minds the way our minds work and notice
they need different things at different times
sometimes the Mind needs a lot of help bringing the awareness back to the
present moment sometimes we can just sort of sit back
and we're like it's like laying on the grassy field and
looking up at the sky and just letting the clouds move
try being really generous with your thoughts just allowing them space
one way to do this is to actually imagine space around the thinking
like small tight room can be what you know
we're in this thought small and tight and then imagine the room gets really big
and there's all this space around the thought other things can be there too
thinking's nature is natural no problem
we need to think you just don't need to be ruled by our
thinking
and if you happen to have one of those moments where
you realize oh I was lost in a thought
see if you can kind of notice what knew that
wow I'm unstuck
I'm aware I was thinking I'm free
in the last two minutes of the meditation I just want to invite you to try a
little less hard right now
just relax a little bit
see if you can't connect with some sense of ease
isn't it amazing that we can think and see our thoughts
and not be them sometimes
[Music]
so what did you learn about your thinking tonight and how your mind is
thinking what did you notice
great
I learned that I'm afraid of negative thoughts um wow what a powerful thing to
to recognize how did you how did you notice that how did you learn that
I I think
like when you said create a space for for thoughts I think then it was like
I didn't immediately go back to my breath and I let some thoughts so then I recognize oh there's
some fear and then at the end when you said try less hard it was also like it was kind of a signal to allow more
thoughts and then you could you noticed you that there was a fear of having negative
thoughts yeah exactly yeah yeah so this the space
like sort of trying to invite this maybe a little bit more awareness of the
thinking gave you the capacity to see oh I'm reacting to the to negative thoughts is that right yeah that's right
that's a good thing to know yeah yeah yeah thank you
anybody else willing to share what their experience of thinking was in this 15
minutes
thank you um well I noticed
I think I found that in the time that I have been meditating
the awareness has grown but in a like
like I know that I'm thinking when I'm thinking it's just
like I would tell myself oh this is the other arrow that I'm adding
but then I still do it and it's that's what's for us or you know I I still go
back to that tendency and it's just
you know I thought I I was kind of conceited in the I I
thought I'm like oh I'm I'm getting this this is good like I'm finally so aware that if I'm ever gonna be upset
I'm gonna be Beyond angry and that was not the case today and
I'm like what is this I'm like I thought I could maintain calm
but emotions or emotions and my emotions
I can be rather emotional so I but I I do like how I'm trying to
practice more or that I am practicing more um loving kindness and compassion with
the the talking to myself and the thinking just sometimes I think too much
right so thank you for listening thank you Tanya thank you
thank you Anne Rose I appreciate your being willing to share
and uh you want to respond on
it sounds like you're really exploring this and learning a lot even the Oh I thought I was beyond anger
or emotion and then observing the effect of emotion right
so um I guess my main encouragement would be
to trust the awareness that you're developing that this is a
slow process for almost all of us and that the awareness the mindful awareness has the capacity
to strengthen all of it over time and this is part of the learning process it's not a mistake
it's not a personal feeling it's not a backsiding it's seeing more and more and
more and and to really trust that
and you know really it's just the thought that you had that you would be able to not get angry that
was just a thought [Laughter]
you know and oh without someone said you know it was very seductive that was it you know oh yeah I like that thought I
want you know that's what happens we have thoughts that we like and then we're like oh yeah I'm and you know
we're duped because you know this because our conditions are always changing
you know it's always changing
yeah yeah
hmm yeah have great grace do you mind um
since I've been practicing meditation um I did become a little more present
with my daily life like I enjoy looking at Clouds more or just listening to the
sounds as they are more um so as I go my day
um you know I feel like a minimal presence I'm really happy about that but in the evening when I'm trying to go
to sleep I just thought this thoughts come back
when I just thought I had a great day and then so I bought I'm going to sleep sometimes
I have bad dreams and
I kind of know where they're coming from [Music] I've had some therapy
and I may have to be in therapy more but I guess my question is
you know I'm trying to deal with this kindness and you know toward me and others
but how do you forgive people who have no abused you hmm
you know emotionally and physically yeah I'm sorry the family yeah I'm sorry
Grace yeah yeah
I uh the first thing I would say is forgiveness is a process
it's a long process I feel like I have to do this like the rest of my life
yeah and that's okay and maybe having them as part of family is a
constant reminder and yeah I have you know um
but just um
you know they don't think it's so really they're about to anything so I know I
can't change their thinking I can only change myself right okay
for um I have found uh Jack cornfield
do you know who he is no he's a Dharma teacher and also a psychologist and he has a lot of YouTube
videos Jack cornfield okay forgiveness those those
k-o-r-n-f-i-e-l-t so um he has some wonderful YouTube videos
and he also has a book a little small little book that's like loving kindness
um forgiveness I don't know there's three words the art of love and kindness forgiveness and peace yeah it's a great
really great lovely little book okay I can look it up yeah each time I
do something you know to help I feel like oh I think as I only got hold of it I got it
and then you know it just comes back this was frustrating
well um Don I'll let Don you want to add anything
um only that um to recognize even that the wish to
forgive is a really beautiful wish to be having to really
that itself is the first step of forgiveness
and it's not totally clear from the way you're talking but of course to keep
yourself safe right forgiving in the midst of ongoing harm oh I mean appropriate right
I don't feel unsafe right now it just happened before when I was wow
this child right so to even hold that child and help that child feel safe in
your own heart second to what Tanya said some of Jack
kornfield's work is really beautiful on this and um
it's on your timeline as is good for your heart
and you know when it's right you can experiment Grace with this technique
that we did with your own thoughts about your history your memories their thoughts too
you know you don't like they can can you give space and let them kind of move
through the sky and just sort of shift your awareness you don't have to get rid of them you can play around with some of
this and try different ways of kind of responding to those thoughts
when they come up and one of them might be just like yes I remember I see you I
bow to you yeah I'm so sorry oh I'm so sorry you know just like that kind of
like yeah trying to fight it just to come to it yeah and just like you know about like
yeah and I'm right here right now
I'm right here right now and it's really safe and I'm now however old I am and
it's you know I survived
okay thank you yeah
so we're going into a second little talk about working with thinking
working with thoughts and
Tanya was just talking about even when working with really challenging material
there's such a benefit to finding a little bit of space so there's a visualization I think Gil
franstal is the first person I've heard give this but I've heard other teachers give it so I'm not sure where it came from
but it's um kind of like imagining yourself on a riverbank
this is a big river like maybe the Mississippi River or another large river
and there are different kinds of boats going down the river
Showboat that's one kind of thinking right like a maybe a casino boat where there's always
a party going on or The Love Boat or there's love
Romance and each of these signifies a different whole realm of thought
right so the way mindful awareness works is it keeps us on the bank of the river
able to have healthy distance from whatever those thoughts are as they go down the river
and the way our minds work we can be transported like that
onto one of these boats maybe without having even realized it so maybe you're just
sitting on the bank meditating minding your own business and
a warship goes by anger resentment battle
next thing you know you've been on that boat for who knows how long
the minute you wake up you're back on the bank and the boat goes on
right there's all different kinds of little realities
that seem huge when we're on them and mindful awareness can pop us back
off the shore off to the shore
so that's the Observer perspective The Knowing perspective
to be able to look at these different boats going by
some of them can be I mean speaking from earlier in my own practice there's the poor me vote
right which is like this decrepit awful Little Canoe thing next thing I know I'm
like half a mile down the river in that thing right poof mindful awareness back on the shore
so to recognize the process that these just keep going and they are substance substantial and immersive
as we sort of allow them to be we get
sucked into them and they kind of become reality for a little while but then poof back out on the shore
they're just another boat moving along on the horizon just another cloud in the sky
that's all they need to be so learning to
stand in the place of the kind of Observer perspective the awareness perspective the knowing
that's a skill any of us can develop and it takes time it takes time to kind
of build the muscle build the habit of popping out of these
very kind of authoritative kinds of movies sometimes in our minds right
all kinds of things as we've been talking about kind of fuel our thinking
emotions past or present physical Sensations
the interest in the thought itself the really big one the identification
with the thought itself or I'm like this or this means I am blah blah blah that's
a big hook very sticky it can be quite a feedback loop right
the stickiness psychologist and Dharma teacher Rick Hansen talks about that
stickiness of thoughts being like velcro our minds just gets kind of stuck
to a thought I'm sorry no yeah I like velcro but then
as mindfulness gets stronger and stronger and becomes more like
a bead of water going along a leaf or along Teflon
it can just flow through just Flow by this is powerful
right just to notice the difference notice the difference and trust that
that will build over time this capacity thoughts are kind of insubstantial right
they're flipped they weigh less than nothing
so Tanya talked about different kinds and modalities of thoughts earlier like
visual or that narrator we've all got a narrator
movies some people even have sort of a certain kind of
thinking that appears as a feeling of movement or expression in their bodies
can aesthetic thinking Concepts words
and then there's the different processes planning remembering fantasizing
those those can be helpful to name and then the Buddha made one other
distinction that I found really helpful I have found really helpful in my practice I still find it helpful
who just simply noticed when one of those showboats is increasing Affliction or suffering
or if it's decreasing it right how is this thought making the
body feel what's the effect of this thought on the emotions I'm having that are arising
right now but to notice that impact
it can get to the point where even just experiencing
an afflictive kind of feeling is a clue that there is
a thought that's not so helpful happening you can follow it like a breadcrumb trail
so to notice what increases suffering and what helps suffering decrease in
thinking the very simple heuristic very simple toggle
we don't have to do anything it takes time and often our systems need to be exposed
to the different kinds of thinking and the different effects of thinking but for most people most of the time
this learning process if it's done with mindful awareness with that inner
posture of kindness allowing it will the system will heal itself it
will write itself over time to be patient with it
by noticing what's helpful what's not thinking arising sometimes that's just
huge when I first started practicing I realized that my entire life I had been
living as if through a television screen or kind of like a virtual reality engine
of my thoughts and I remember sitting I used to sit in
front of a window I started indents and my eyes were open and there's this filmy
kind of curtain that was between me and the outside and one day I realized that those thoughts were like that foamy
curtain they were kind of partially obscuring reality every minute
so notice when the curtain's there and when the curtain's not it's like Tanya said there's space in
between the thoughts for most of us we can make it sometimes it's just there
so are you guys ready to meditate again and settle in
settle your posture
finding a sense of balance in your posture
maybe weaving back and forth up and down a little bit until you feel a sense of
of balance in the body
and noticing to the inner poster
what's the relationship right now in your mind and heart
I'm just acknowledging that whatever it is whatever attitude is there
settling in on whatever anchor of attention
works best for you coming home to the body the breath sound
and resting
inviting privileging perhaps the experience
of any thoughts that arise
just noticing I was just noticing that they're there
returning to the sensations of breathing body
this moment
and then turning in perhaps to what kind of thinking
is arising commentary
planning remembering
whatever it is perhaps giving a soft gentle label
and if it subsides stepping back to the riverbank
returning to the body and breath the observing
faculty
resting in the body breathing
if the mind is pulled into a boat of thinking
noticing appreciating the arising
of awareness mindfulness
savoring returning here
your thinking arises
noticing is this a new thought or a repeat
returning to body breath this moment this sound
stepping back and allowing space
between the observing in the process of thinking
flowing down the river
thank you
and has this short meditation begins to draw to a close
taking the moment to notice the relationship
how is the attitude of the heart and mind
what's been observed
just notice fall okay
[Music]
foreign
comments
we'd love to hear how how you're kind of taking all this in what you're noticing
please thank you don't I have a question regarding you mentioned the film in front and that
it can be pulled away or at least I would like to be able to pull it away it's just sometimes I find that the
reassurance that I seek is outward so I'd like to be able to do that for myself
in inward do you have any tips as to what I can say because I I have found
myself you know stopping myself from okay don't you don't have to share you don't have
to tell you don't call your sister right now to tell her what's going on he could figure it out
and then I still do and then I anything would help
thank you for the question so I I want to understand more about the
relationship between the film and the reaching outward for Assurance can you say just a couple more words
about that I I noticed that when I think or
whenever a problem arises that I allow myself to be consumed by it
and and then I'll try to distract myself and
get busy with work or whatever and then it still persists in the back of my mind
and then for a time I'll forget it but I'll but it's there and I I just know it's
there and I so that's the film yeah and in a sense and I just
I would like to be a better companion for myself I heard someone say that
but I I often just call you know seek it from someone else
and I would like to be there there for them without always having you know I
just I don't always have to do that to my sister so yeah
it's a really you're asking a powerful question really powerful question
so um I don't know if it's exactly a tip
but this process of turning towards your own experience that you're talking about
is building that muscle that capacity and
um for myself the process of recognizing the film
of whatever sort of subconscious half distracted story or or thoughts or
anxiety is going on was a really key part of the process of
like turning towards that with loving attention and just sitting with it
for a while offering that care in that way mindful awareness is a lot like love
it's undivided attention right divided attention
sometimes it can be helpful to just kind of rest your hand on your heart and on your belly
one of my teachers used to model just like doing this self-talk of oh it's okay it's all right
I'm here for you and that too is a way of beginning to cultivate that compassionate
companioning you're talking about how does that sound so far to what
you're what you're asking am I I try to to do that like may I be
you know happy safe at peace be Spirit whatever that stuff but
um I suppose I could do that on the on the daily I do find myself saying you
know it's okay don't worry about it just like Let It Go but then I I still dwell on it that's my
problem I do like to ruminate a lot and that's a that's a sticky that's a
sticky thought that I wish turned to Teflon but I think I I'm recognizing him now more so than I have in the past so
uh just continuing yeah I think the way that you talk to
yourself is really important and I saw Tanya turn on the mic so I
think you have something to add here so have you ever tried to do an uh writing
exercise where you do an inner dialogue like
yeah so for example because it sounds like um you're getting upset about
something and you you're telling yourself it's okay it's okay but it's kind of like
telling a little kid that is upset about something that it's okay it's okay and
the little kid just feels a little bit like brushed to the side does that resonate
so um it's a little bit hard sometimes to get this feeling of how to relate to
ourselves so one way can be to like have it like
you know oh for me it's like oh the part of me um that feels hurt
my hurt part says this and I write out what the hurt part would
say I let it say in the sentence or paragraph whatever it wants to say this
is not fair kids are really mean whatever it is okay and then
there's another part in me like a compassionate self or a wise self
or uh you know a good friend what I would be if I was talking to my other
friend this is what I would say to her so let me say this back to myself
and then let the hurt part hear that and then respond
and then let the you know good friend part hear and respond
so to help you practice how to have this and create this inner exchange right
I think it's hard to start to tease apart our parts
and so doing it on paper can be helpful because then it's like oh
you know oh yeah I'm I'm actually really hurt and frustrated oh look I'm
resentful oh I I'd stomp my feet right now if I could you know and sort of there's a way of letting that be named
and seen and say okay okay well what what do I need what does that part of me need right now
what would be helpful like yeah that was rude you know or you know well maybe
we're overreacting right now you know whatever it is that we need to say to ourselves so
but mostly it's like helping tease apart the parts
thank you I think it's time for us to close huh yeah it is so but you know if
anybody has any comments or questions after we we'll just try and formally close on time and then you feel free to
come up but um I'll start by with two announcements um you've got your handouts which have
your homework outlined on them okay but um this Saturday is coming Saturday in a
couple of days Dawn and another teacher are offering a day-long retreat called
the seven factors of Awakening so it's a really nice opportunity to come and
practice back-to-back meditation with instructions and support and a community
and then next Saturday the 4th Bruni Davila who's another teacher here is
doing an introduction to mindfulness Meditation day-long Retreat from 9 to 4 30. so two opportunities
which you know we don't have that many day longs these days we're trying to have more of them but really great
opportunities you can come for half the day if you you know don't have the whole time you can bring your lunch meet
people like I don't know what you're going to do sometimes the teachers will you can talk outside it's kind of one of
one of the things we've been doing with covid is to let people talk outside during the lunch otherwise it used to be
that would be silent all day but because we don't get much chance to interact that might be possible so anyways I just
I want to encourage if you have any interest at all and you're free um to try try it's really supportive and
it can take your practice to another level so I'll let you read your handouts for
your homework just keep practicing that's really the most important thing
every day even if it's for five minutes it makes a big difference
you know it really really helps to take the time
so may this class May our time together maybe what you may what you each shared
be fruitful and beneficial not just for yourselves but for anybody who listens
to the class who was watching with us on YouTube and
and for yourself and each other when you go out into the world may this be of benefit for all beings
everywhere without exception thank you for your practice
foreign [Music]