good morning or good day and Welcome to our meditation
time and as I usually do I like to do a little introduction and then uh as a as
a background or a introduction to the meditation
so one of the central concepts for Buddhist
practice the practice we do meditation we do the way we engage in the
Dharma is to distinguish between what is helpful and not
helpful what serves us and what doesn't serve us and that begs a question
helpful for what reason or serves us and for what purpose and uh there's many many ways to
answer that and from a Buddhist point of view but one way is that it leads us away
from suffering and towards happiness and with the ultimate H
happiness is Liberation Liberation from the causes of all
suffering and a profound leads us away from agitation moves us towards peace
where peace is the the highest pieace is again the freedom from suffering freedom from all the agitation that produces
suffering and so uh and then uh to love the
Dharma is to love the practice and uh and to love the practice
of of making this distinction and delighting in the opportunity to uh to
move in the direction of what serves us what is helpful and part of the Delight is to know that it's not just for our
own sake but um it we do it for the sake of others as well that uh whether we
intend to or not moving in this direction towards peace towards the
absence of suffering to the presence of Happiness the absence of greed ha and delusion to the Pres presence of um
generosity and love and wisdom that uh of course it's going to benefit the
people around us so to make this distinction and then one way of
meditating which is the proposal for today is to imagine
yourself um as being a someone who sorts uh uh food sorts
fruit uh and I've done this little bit before and but imagine that you're on a there's a conveyor belt that brings uh
and a gentle relaxed flow brings you maybe
apples and um that have recently been harvested and some of them are clearly
defective and can't be used for selling as fresh produce or selling as for
applesauce or anything and um and some are useful and will serve many people in
in feeding them and so you stand the end of this conveyor belt and the apples come and the ones that don't serve are
not helpful for human consumption are used for other purposes they are composted to
and the ones that are going to be sered serve us are are picked up and put in a box on maybe on your right and the love
loving job of just Cho picking them out this goes for the compost this goes for
for others without any judgment without any uh hostility or aversion towards
anything without any greed that in sense one is better than other it's really good to to uh to create compost and it
supports the the soil and some people love making compost it Delights them and
some people you know love uh you know uh
picking the fruits that are going to serve many people and imagining who it's going to serve so in this way sitting and
meditating today maybe there's a way of sitting quietly and uh focusing on the breath
focusing on being present that appreciates present moment attention like just being here here and being
present in a kind way in a wise way in a generous way and uh distinguishing
between what arises in the mind what's happening to us emotionally um and distinguishing in
ways that we relate to what's happening that's the Apple not what's happening but how we
relate to it and some ways we relate we have aversion we have fear we have criticism
we have uh conceit we have greed we uh
and some uh you know are really just good for the compost and just put that aside and some ways I
relate are the the fruit of practice that have great fruit and benefit and um
and that that's useful to keep for for for for later for now and so if we can
meet whatever is happening with kindness with uh openness with um nonhostility
with a clear mindfulness clear open receptive
attention um transparent attention where things just go right through without being stuck on us uh if we can meet
things with wisdom um relate to what's happening in a wise way one wise way is to see it as
just phenomena that's rolling through it's the stream the flow flow of Life coming through and now it's this and now
it's this and there's no need to get reactive to it or get greedy to it or
make any conclusions from it oh this means that I am you know
X not taking it personally making it into something personal just phenomena
happening um and uh so um so to imagine sitting
here present but attentive
to what goes in the compost and what we
keep so to gently close your eyes
and taking some care and maybe some love
for a suitable posture for meditation a posture that serves
you a posture that's
helpful and taking some long deep breaths relaxing on the
exhale
and letting the breathing return to
normal and continue to relax the body the mind the
heart maybe for the next dozen or so exhales relaxing
settling
softening
e
and then as we continue is there anything about how you
are right now that would be good to acknowledge to
recognize clearly so that it doesn't have
a an undue influence on how you're
present how you practice the mindfulness how are
you and how are you relating to how you
are What attitude do you have to what you find how you find
yourself and is the attitude the relationship you have does it serve you
or doesn't serve you is it helpful or not
helpful can you change if it's not helpful can you let
that go into the compost and find a little more helpful
way of being present for how you
are and even simple mindfulness is
helpful just aware non-judgmentally not taking it person
L and settling into your breathing again
maybe imagining breathing is the conveyor
belt and whatever it
brings meet it with a useful attitude with the relate to it in a helpful
way and if how you relate to anything that's happening
doesn't serve it's not helpful put it aside for
compost and find evoke arouse a helpful
attitude a helpful way of relating the simplest
being non-judgmental receptive
awareness
e
for
as we come to the end of this sitting to
appreciate that we have a
choice when we have the choice between speaking or not
speaking do we or not doing
something thinking or not thinking something the choice between having one
attitude or another attitude
between having an attitude which is unhelpful
and do we avoid acting on it in any
way the ability to make choices what we do and what we don't
do what we act on and what we don't act
on can give us the choice to act on love
on generosity on kindness to not act on ill will and
greed and
conceit and to make this Choice calmly openly
relaxedly so that how we are in the world doesn't contribute to more Strife
doesn't cont contribute to more people being
challenged may we instead learn how to monitor ourselves to make the
choice to avoid harming and when it's
appropriate to live from from generosity and love and care and
respect in a way that brings peace into the
world bring safety for others may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you
e
I have to go uh push a button somewhere else to make it work right
back
e
so warm greetings from IMC and and uh to this series on the 10
protectors and yesterday that the protector what protects us is uh a love
of the Dharma and that of course can have different meanings depending what you mean by Dharma and different people
do have different reference points for this wonderful word and the and what I
offered was that uh uh the core aspect of Dharma is
non-harming and um and then the that's pretty powerful in itself but
the companion to that is to do what's beneficial to to do that which is the
opposite of harm and uh this protects us and this protects the world around us now with
this idea with operating idea of love I think is fantastic um so to do this with
love to have love for this so that the way we approach it the way we meet the world is something healthy and and
nourishing for us and for others so now we come to the next protector which is uh sometimes and when
I first first many years I was introduced to this uh it just seemed too Technical and it seemed a little bit too
uh technique for focused or some felt very different than for me than just U
having open mindfulness and presence for whatever is here um and uh it seemed a
little bit judgmental it seemed a little bit more difficult but I've come to really appreciate that uh this what's
coming next here is really again also very fundamental to the Dharma and the
the traditional way of of translating into English is to um to abandon what is
UN wholesome and arouse to awake awaken what is
wholesome and uh sometimes it's said to be abandon what's unskillful and awaken
Rouse what is skillful and um and uh this I like to
think of this as to let go of what is unhelpful and uh pick up what is helpful
do what is helpful and uh sometimes like to say put down what is unhealthy that we our mind
and speech and body can be doing and and pick up what is healthy that we where we
can pick it up and so this distinction uh makes a huge difference if we don't see this
choice we have uh in any kind of situation in our life between what is unhelpful and and what is helpful uh why
would we kind of stop doing the unhelpful if um if if you uh have a
thorn in your foot and you don't see that it's you know that it's helpful or
serves you to take the thorn out and you just keep walking on the thorn uh then
um then you know you eventually you can get infected and might cause lasting damage so the idea is to um you know we
we constantly make this distinction in our life we sit in the chair and we feel
what it's a nice way of sitting that helps us to relax and what maybe is not like nice maybe there's a kind of some
painful pressure against part of our body in a certain way of sitting in the chair so we make an adjustment so this
constant adjustment that we make is pretty much human nature and but when we apply it uh in
Dharma practice is we're learning how we relate to our our experience and the things
that we do that come out of us is uh so as opposed to looking about the world and changing the world
Dharma practice has a very Central thing of taking responsibility for what comes out of us
and if what comes out of us is a um not helpful for the world or not helpful to
us then there's the Art of Letting Go of it if it is helpful or if we awaken what
is helpful then please continue doing that with
enthusiasm and so making this choice so and one of the things that for mindfulness practitioners is it's always
helpful always wholesome to be mindful if the mindfulness is clean if the
mindfulness is not does not come along with um unhelpful attitudes of judgment
or criticism or or greed or expectation the simple
mindfulness and so to um uh to track this for ourselves is a way of being our
own person protector uh because the the deepest harm that we can do to our deepest harm
that we can experience as adults is harm that we do to ourselves even if there's horrendous
things that happen to us outside in our in our deepest heart it's how we relate
to that that really counts in the end and um really has lasting language a
lasting effect on us so if we react with uh uh resistance aversion deep in the
heart if we react with hostility and hate if we react with greed and
desire in some deep way that that you the the greed has a kind of tension and
suffering in it and of itself then we can create lasting harm but if we can
the deepest places within if we can meet with love with care with um
generosity with uh nonc conceit with non shutting down um then there can be a
lasting benefit to us and this is of course very difficult to appreciate when
when the horrible things happen to us but uh the Dharma practice when we really get into it really understand it
well is we understand that we are becoming the custodians of our own hearts and that whatever happens around
us we begin developing the strength to really stay close to that heart of ours
and keep it um uh free keep it clean
keep it non-reactive in such a way that we're actually compounding the the
challenges by adding second arrows to ourselves and uh and so um this ability
this Choice seeing where we don't add the second arrows and and stay close to
that is a way of protect protecting ourselves so um so then uh what I love
and what I find fascinating and just delightful is that in this uh you know
stand standing there and just choosing between what goes into the compost what we don't want don't need is
unhelpful by calling it compost we don't have to think of it as abandoning it as just kind of another form of a
aversion everything has a use some things are just useful for compost
and so when when I have if I have anger if I have greed if I have these things that I don't think they're
useful if I kind of let go of them and and drop into my body feel it all in my
body the body has a way of composting it I don't have to reject it exactly or um
take it have an attitude that's that it's awful or bad or wrong it has a use
that's somehow if I I can let go of it in such a way by letting go of it into the body where it gets kind of
transmuted or settled or supportive for something beautiful to
happen and then picking Awakening what's beautiful breaking what's helpful so the way to do this to
abandon to let go of and to awaken and maintain is that is done uh skillfully
that that's done in a helpful way that's done in a way that's nourishing and supportive that feels
wholesome so rather than making this distinction and navigating this distinction one more difficult
exhausting thing to do it's the attitude the approach the way we relate to that
is supported by the love of the Dharma that we just love doing this practice we
love doing something that um avoids further harm and creates more benefit
how lucky we are that we can do this if we don't have the some kind of healthy
attitude for how we make these distinctions and navigate this kind of natural distinction between what's
healthy and not healthy then it's hard to sustain it uh
it can be exhausting it can be debilitating it can be um feel like a
burden and uh but if we can find a healthy way to do this distinction to
navigate this it can be a delight a joy kind of like the joy of maybe paddling
down the current of a river and just kind of enjoying just staying in the current as we go and um and just that
little choice we make stay in that healthy current stay here be here this is
delightful so um so I love it I love it that the um uh this idea of uh abandon
abing the UNH wholesome Awakening the wholesome follows in this
list uh love of the Dharma and maybe that's a guide for how to do this very
fundamental practice of usually called in Buddhism right effort and um it's one
of the pieces of the e-fold path so it's pretty Central to it all and in doing
this uh we become our own protector and that is one of the I think really uh
significant uh stepping stones in Dharma practice is learning how we can be our
own protector we protect ourselves from ourselves as we do this we also will
become a protector for others and we're protecting them from us we become a safe person and maybe
this seems uh a trifling thing in a world that's full of horrendous
suffering and challenges as we as we're kind of very sensitive to many of us right now what's happening in the
world but um someone has to be this kind of person someone has to be able to
enter into the world so that we're safe for others and who is better than this
than ourselves if it doesn't start with us can we does it make sense to continue
to uh only expect it from others that other people will make the world a better
place um but if we can do it if we can be a safe person for the world if we can
um uh then maybe we have a a uh a u a
stance upon which to stand that can begin encouraging other people to do it
and and speak up about let's let's let's meet with let's meet each other
peacefully kindly and let's try to stand in um um um actively stand
in not in opposition exactly but stand
uh convincing people that violence doesn't work that hate doesn't work
greed doesn't work let's speak up about that but only if we can be know how to
be uh a safe for all people including the people we disagree with
so um and then we'll continue on these 10
protectors tomorrow thank
you