welcome welcome everybody it's lovely to be here very
lovely to be here going to be continuing on our exploration of these faculties for
fearlessness vectors of faculties for fearlessness for
freedom I don't know it's just getting a kick out of this
alliteration we'll start with a just a simple um guided meditation
so settling
in just bringing our attention and our
body to meditation whatever posture feels
comfortable and is available to you right now
and is there a way that the posture could be just a little bit more
comfortable for me it's bringing a little bit more uprightness to the spine
so that the limbs can just hang from the spine letting the shoulders just
relax and tucking the chin backwards just this
tiny tiny bit it allows the neck to be a
little bit more aligned with the
spine for you some other tiny adjustments might be
needed
and then let's open the senses bring awareness to
the senses if your eyes are closed just
notice if there's any Shadows or
patterns behind the eyelids nothing in particular needs to
be happening we're just
noticing and the ears noticing the sounds
the sound of my voice other sounds you might
[Music] hear just allowing them to be
received we don't have to go out and get the sounds just opening to
them they're welcome
too there might be scents or
tastes sometimes it's more difficult when we're sitting in meditation but it
might be coffee
toothpaste
tea
and then the sense of touch noticing where the body is
contacting whatever it is contacting whichever
surface whether it's the cushion or chair couch
bed feeling the pressure against the body
feeling the contact we're
here and this contact is the Foundation of our
posture feeling connected
grounded
and then noticing any obvious areas of tension in the
body resting awareness
there it might be that bringing awareness to the
tension allows a little bit of softening but it might not be also can
we be okay with
that maybe tension around the eyes or the jaw
neck
shoulders opening the chest just a tiny
bit the belly
softening back
legs again feeling the
contact
feet
arms
hands maybe sensing a sense of aliveness or presence
tingling vitality in the
hands can we be okay as best we can with however the
body is at this
moment and then resting the attention on the sensations of breathing
the movements the body does as it
breathes might feel it primarily in the chest stretching and the release of the
stretch and the belly moving out and
in or maybe the nose feeling the cool air go in and the
warmer air coming out just choosing one of those three
areas and resting the attention
there
e
and when the mind wanders as it's apt to do we don't have to make it be a problem
and just very simply gently begin again with the sensations
of breathing
and we do this movement back to the sensations of breathing with kindness
with warmth with [Music]
care
it doesn't matter how many times we have to return to the sensations of
breathing the practice is about returning
beginning
again don't worry about how many
times just Begin
Again
[Music]
morning good day good evening wherever you are whatever time it is welcome
welcome so today I'd like to continue with
this sense of the faculties for
fearlessness just want to recognize that you know fear I think we all know what fear Fe is but it shows up in our lives
in so many different ways maybe in some ways in which we're not really connecting with
fear and one of them is perfectionism this always like finding
flaws that need to be fixed before we can share something or show something
you know always trying to fix everything or maybe there's a sense of
like well I have to wait for when like I can't do something right now because
there has to be a time when things are more comfortable so maybe we're like holding
back something we want to do with our life or say to somebody or whatever it
might be start that more healthy Behavior or something like this or maybe
there's a way in which fear shows up in which we're trying to like avoid uncertainty we're trying to have
everything planned out beforehand or understand it and have it uh I don't
know being known in some kind of way this fear of the unknown so we're trying to make sure there aren't any unknowns
but you of course of course we can't be certain about
everything these are just some of the ways in which fear shows up it turns out to be such a big part of our
lives and then I'd like to offer these five days these five faculties many of
you will know this this is a very conventional list that we talk about in early Buddhism however I'm going to talk
about him a little bit differently that I'm not going to do it in the usual order and I'm going to highlight
particular aspects of each faculty that I think can be a real support for us to
bring to fear and just as a little brief summary I started with Sati and I'm uh highlighting this
quality of noticing for Santi that is we first like notice maybe the
environment the desk the chair the computer this way we get
oriented then notice our present moment bodily experience the feeling of contact
with the whatever it is we're whatever surface we're in contact with maybe the
breath as I kind of lead us in these guided meditations I'm often doing this
movement but then also Santi to notice the sense of no I
don't want this fear or no I don't want to do this and maybe the fear is making
us wanting to do it the sense of resistance noticing that too often
they're conflated and confused and not even recognized but is there a way that
we can tease apart and know there's fear and resistance to
fear and then to go even more internal or
inside to notice what is it that's feeling
threatened do we have a self-concept a sense of what we think of
what it means to be a good person or what it means to be a good practitioner or a sense of how we think the world
should be and is that feeling threatened and to just notice that notice what's
feeling threatened so Sati is noticing from the more external to the more
internal some of you may know that sa is conventionally translated as
mindfulness and then the second that I did yesterday was about samadi and that was about bringing the sense of
collectedness centeredness this wholeheartedness like kind of like a a
gathering of our attention but in particular when we're
working with fear to bring this gness this abiding in to the resistance to the
fear not the fear itself often that's too overwhelming it's too much and
that's like so much we don't want to do this but the sense of no and we might have resistance to the
resistance that's okay bring uh this collectedness this gness about against
the resistance to the resistance or maybe we have resistance to the resistance to the resistance it's okay
whatever you know iteration that we have it to bring this collectedness this
scaredness around this sense of no I don't want it and no whatever way that shows up and
it shows up in a countless Myriad ways and then today I'd like to
introduce a third faculty and that is sadada German teachers often pronounce
it as Sada in paully it would be Sada but it's kind of like Dharma teacher paully it's a
Sada and that is that having practiced with Sati mindfulness and Som this
Gathering Together there can be this recognition that oh this uh noticing and
this gathering together is helpful the consequences of this it turns out to be
a little bit beneficial and we gain confidence in the practice we gain some
confidence in the approach that we're taking gain confidence with this sense
of having this presence of showing up for the fear and the resistance to the
fear and this confidence I'm going to say as sad
Sada and this confidence gives us strength to engage in this
practice to meet the fear to meet the resistance with the fear with the Sati
and Sam with the noticing and the collecting so this confidence in the practice that
there's some benefits to it noticing that there's some benefits and having this willingness to engage with the
practice but we also need not only confidence in the practice but confidence in
ourselves that we can do this and sometimes maybe this is a big
part of practice is to gain this confidence but which implies that we don't always have it I know that
certainly was true certainly beginning of my practice I just didn't think I couldn't do it it seemed like everybody
else could do it and they look like they had it all together and clearly they were enlightened or on the brink of
Enlightenment if they weren't already because they were sitting so still and here I was so Wiggly with my mind going
all over the place so if we don't have confidence in
ourselves we can borrow it borrow it from
others and this is part of the power of practicing with others practicing in sa
just like we do here at 7 amm these people that are leaving
comments right you're greeting one another but you're also kind of giving us confidence that like okay yeah you're
showing up again and again and again we can do it and by this warm-heartedness
that we see in the context in the comments we can see that oh okay the people that
are doing this are kindhearted well-wishing caring they have what we want the world
to be like we have they have what we want to be with
ourselves so if you feel like you don't have some confidence can you borrow the
confidence either from those here at the 7 a.m. maybe you have a meditation
center where you practice maybe you have a small group of friends that you practice with whomever maybe you have
teachers maybe you don't have like personal relationships where you know people but it's just you know of
people that's okay it's borrow the confidence wherever
you need to be inspired by other people but this coming back again and
again be inspired by the confidence they have in themselves or in you there's this way which this confidence and the
practice and the confidence that we can do this is contagious so allow yourself
to catch the confidence in some kind of way other people can believe in you and
believe in the practice even when you're feeling like you don't quite have it you're not
sure and here's part of the beauty about this idea of confidence is we only need
just enough confidence just enough just enough for
to be present for the next breath just enough to show up for the
next 7 a.m. or just enough confidence to not click
away just enough confidence to be curious about what's going to rise next
or curious about what's being pointed to when other people or the
teacher we do not need heroic confidence we do not need confidence that's
unshakable and we have it 100% of the time we just need enough for the next
moment s Sada is
confidence in the practice and in ourselves but I'd also like to introduce
a second aspect of Sada Sada and that is trust you could see how
these are related confidence and trust but there's this progression of
practice as we can like learn to be present and be carefully attentive and
maybe relax into what's happening we discover that there is more going on
within us and that there's this if we allow it there's this
movement towards healing towards
wholeness towards goodness we start to trust oh yeah if we
can create the conditions in which this can unfold there's this natural inner
process towards holess and freedom and it turns out we don't have
to make everything happen we don't have to insist or engineer manufacturer
create all the goodness the healing the freedom big part of practice is
trusting and this trust is part of what creates the condition for this wholeness
and healing to happen trust that Dharma practice enables and allows and makes room for
this natural process to happen maybe in the same way that when we have a cut or an injury right we have
to take care of it we have to clean the cut and put a Band-Aid on it or take
antibiotic if it's infected or do what the doctor suggests Physical Therapy whatever it is for whatever injury so we
definitely have to apply ourselves but there's also a way in
which right we don't actually do the healing it's a natural process that's
already happening we just have to help make it happen and so much about
practice turns out to be this this at some point what is needed
from us is just to get out of the way so I don't want to suggest that no effort is Ever Needed there is certainly effort
that is needed but it's not always this you know
really striving straining there's an effort to create
the conditions in which we can allow in which we can trust the depth of what is
possible within us the trust that this inner process
that's not only inside us that's inside others too we don't have to fix them we
don't have to try to heal them even though we want to of course we do but
they have this inner process too even though they may not know it but
is there a way that we can give space Not only to ourselves but to
others s Sada as confidence and trust is a way
that can help with the fear so even though it sometimes is
uncomfortable it requires a certain amount of letting go of a sense of control and part of the art of practice
is knowing when does there need to be some effort some real you know showing up
even though it's uncomfortable and when does there need to be some letting go some trusting and there's always a
combination maybe there's a little bit more effort and a little bit more letting go and trusting at other
times and this is that part of practice that as we more we practice the more we
start to rec recognize but maybe even hearing this word s
Sada confidence and Trust helps us to be sensitive of when that's already
unfolding in our own lives so the third faculty often
translated as Faith or confidence is s confidence trust in your process you
don't have to make it all happen thank you thank you
and wishing you all a wonderful rest of the
day