so hello everyone on this Solstice winter
day and I'm recalling how my son in when he was
in third grade there was a teacher who gave all the students in the class each of them
their own poem to memorize in the course of the year uh once a week each student would
uh recite their poem for the whole class and my son was uh happiest with his poem
because it was so short and uh and uh it went something
like this is this short that nothing is born without
Darkness nothing grows without light so you certainly you can question
if that's universally true but uh I was inspired by that my son doesn't remember
having having that poem but I do that um that that a tremendous
value of what is what gets born out of the
darkness that uh whether it's a seed buried in the ground in so-called
dark in um human being Who develops in the so-called darkness
of the womb and comes comes into the
light what it does for me is to appreciate everything has its season
everything has a potential and The Darkest Days of Our Lives when things are very difficult are
maybe the seeds within it there contained the seeds for something new to be
born and what wants to be born out of the darkness what wants to
be born out of our difficulties and challeng challenges and I found that this
mindfulness practice has been invaluable in making
space for this deeper kind of an organic natural
process to unfold in the midst of our challenges rather than think thinking we have to
fix all our challenges and solve them we create the
conditions within ourselves that makes room for something profound something right
to be born out of the challenges out of the whatever is
happening so now in the darkest day of the year here in the northern
hemisphere that maybe we can think of that this is
um uh you know a time for birth something new is coming for all of us
so part of that condition is to be simple to be simple enough we
not crowding the space of awareness with distracting
thoughts crowding it with commentary and judgments and planning and Analysis and
reviewing and trying to figure things
out and um and
so the
um so one of the tasks of meditation is not to be lost in thought not to be cut
up in it not to be claustrophobic or not to fill the space of the Mind the heart
with ruminating thoughts discursive thoughts and one of the ways to do this
is to um uh
think thoughts that calm the thinking to have thoughts which calm our
thinking down and for that we first have to have them very clear and I want to emphasize
very very clear recognition
acknowledgment of what's Happening we are thinking we are maybe out of control
thinking sometimes this is discursive thinking this is rumination this is fantasy
whatever it is to um you have to begin by acknowledging it
and when the acknowledgement is really clear really like definitive oh this is
the distracted mind at that moment we're we're stepped away from it part of of us
is not identified with it we're identifying it but not identified with
it and um and then one
possibility is to have that recognition be done with a
voice or a manner that is
calming that conveys a sense of care and goodness and
safety like meeting someone's agitated and talking to them in a calm
way and then to use the simplest kinds of
thoughts that you can to continue with a
calm assured
settled mind thoughts to recognize what's
happening with this so it's used a mental note a note is a kind of
thought so we're using a thought to stay present and not to drift
away and the manner in which we say the note is
calming maybe even soothing if that's what's needed is grounding is
centering and to make the this mental note more
meaningful is to make the mental note say have the mental note to recog note of
recognition come from a profound place within not in the surface mind but in
the Deep Mind maybe in the heart or in the belly some Place
deeper it doesn't have to be a labeled word that you
say it could be from a preverbal cognition
recognition which is kind of a thought but without
words but have that be clear make time for the recognition the
act of noting and do it in a way that's calming
that part of your mind which is agitated calming the one that's wanting to
daydream or think this is thoughts which calm
thinking so assuming an upright meditation or assuming a meditation
posture that's right for
you and gently closing your eyes
and just notice straight off how are you how are you in your body mind
heart starting by acknowledging where you are the the starting
point of this
meditation and then allowing your
diaphragm your body to extend the
inhale and giving more time for the body to
Exhale as you allow the body a little longer time to
inhale use the expansion of the
Torso to feel and sense the
Torso
and the exhale to
relax letting the breathing return to normal
normal and then spend a few time few moments as you breathe to feel your body different
parts of your body on the inhale and then to relax that part of
your body on the
exhale
for
and then breathing in and out feeling the thinking
mind and relaxing the thinking
mind as the Torso expands on the inhale maybe imagining that the Mind
expands on the inhale and relax on the
exhale
for
and then Center yourself on the
calmest or quietest or most stable place deep
inside of
you
like a d Rock dropping into a lake settles in the lake
Bottom let awareness drop into your body until it finds a place to
settle awareness at rest deep in the
body
and from the deepest place available to you the calmest place
within allow yourself to
have certain thoughts engage in certain
thoughts recognizing your present moment
experience maybe verbally or
nonverbally calmly peacefully ful
recognizing with a single
word what is happening what you know and
feel Here and
Now
and if your mind is thinking a lot distracted
thoughts from that deep place within
clearly definitively name that that's the
case saying thinking or distractions
or rumination whatever it might
be but acknowledge it with a word with a thought that is calming and
peaceful where you have all the time in the word world for each label each
note
maybe the note recognizing what's
happening is made on the exhale
calm quiet
definitive thought arising from the
depths and whenever there's thinking in the mind
let that be an occasion to use a calm
note to recognize to
disidentify and to calm the thinking
mind
for
for if you find yourself
thinking lost in thought swept in thought or thinking
habitually there is an alternative and that is to find a place
deep within from which to have simple calm
cing thoughts of recognition recognize that you're
thinking recognize that you're breathing recognizing your hearing
or whatever is happening to take
refuge in a calm knowing
calm thought of
recognition
for
e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting have some quiet calming spacious thoughts think
about how your meditation has unfolded from the beginning till
now what might you have [Music] learned about different ways of
thinking and about how to think in a way that is
calming
what have you [Music] learned about thinking
deliberately so that how you
think is calming
peacing [Music]
deactivating so think about these questions in a way that is calming
now and then and turning your attention outward into the world of the people you
know you don't know and experiment with repeating the
words that I say but repeat them in a calm
way so that there's the calming influence on yourself and maybe on the world itself
self may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all be be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free
thank
you
so welcome to our fourth talk on wise
thinking
and when uh thinking is an automatic pilot it's
way too easy for thinking to be stress ful or even harmful to
ourselves it's very easy to spin out in all kinds of thoughts and worries and
judgments and biases and we don't have to be the
victim of our thoughts sometime some people are really major victims of their thoughts they don't realize it because
they think they are their thoughts they are their thinking and and
if I'm thinking something it must be true because it's who I am but thoughts are not who we
are thoughts are a product of the mind but that doesn't mean that that
that they're they Define who you are any more than the your growing fingernail defines
who you are it's just what the Mind does it's a product of the mind that is a consequence of many
causes and conditions in the inner landscape but we don't have to be identified with
it andc and especially we don't have to be lost in it and have to live at its
whims going along with it or just coping and managing with how it is it's possible to think
deliberately and in doing so to have a beneficial influence on the mind the
heart the body itself on the world itself self we don't want to think deliberately
all the time there's a time for giving the Mind freedom to think whatever it
wants to think I do that when I exercise and I find that very helpful
and nice to give that kind of freedom to my mind but I don't give that kind of freedom to my mind when I'm
thinking um I don't get swept along with with my
distracted thoughts I Marshall a deliberate
attention a deliberateness of thinking to see and know that I'm
thinking to step away and disidentify with thinking so that I can
call upon something a way of being a way of thinking a way of of
thating which uh has a more beneficial influence on me than the way that my
automatic pilot thoughts might be having and um so in vasna we have a
technique called mental noting and that just an emphatic way of
recognizing what's happening while it's happening and sometimes being more emphatic in The Knowing is what frees us
from being caught up in it and mental notes is a form of thought
very simple meant to be simple rudimentary non-judgmental thoughts just
recognizing what's happening and to think of it not as work
not as something coarse that we do but to have the mental note that recognition
come from a place that's very peaceful or calm settled within if the distinction between the
Surface mind and the Deep Mind is relevant for you have that thought well up from the deep mind so from this deep
vantage point this calm Vantage Point recognize that if there's distracted
thought now there are distracted thoughts these are distracted
thoughts and so if you recognize distracted thought by the very same kind
of thinking that's distracted we can stir oursel up even more but if we recognize from this deep
quiet place that has all the time in the world is not in a hurry for anything
just calmly recognizes um then it can be settling for that surface mind it be calming for
it and so to um use thinking to calm
Thinking by using this deep thinking that we're capable of it's the source of creativity source
of of um intimacy source of feeling uh
of wisdom to really kind of drop into this deeper place that is uh wiser than
the surface mind because it's holistic it takes in all the information from all the
different uh faculties that we have and so it is much wiser than the
distracted mind which is very limited in in how it's integrated into the rest of
us and so to have take a certain kind of
relaxed deliberateness not forcing it not overriding your
thinking but in a sense underwriting it coming from underneath it just recognizing it so so that uh like come
sit down relax it's okay sit down and so the idea of deliberately
thinking in a beneficial way in a calm way not exactly controlling the
situation but little bit taking charge uh of yourself by choosing how
you're going to know and see and be present for your
experience now this mental not noting can be done verbally it can be done in images people
have a lot of use images a lot visualize their when they think it could also be
done nonverbally because we often know things before we have the words for them
there's a nonverbal kind of precursor to the words
that we say so there can be a sense or feeling of knowing that doesn't seem to come along with words but it's still a
knowing it's still a kind of a thinking process and it's possible maybe to adjust that so that it's calm it's
peaceful and um to do this in meditation is kind of like going uh to a gym and
working out we're we're working out in strengthening and developing or or or
bringing forth more and more a different way of relating to our
experience we're not just calming ourselves in meditation to just calm ourselves and let that be all we do sets
us up for just getting agitated again but we're calming ourselves by by we're
we're by calling upon a way of relating a way of being a way of
thinking that is an alternative to thinking as usually happens for us and
over time that can become more of a resource for us more of a even a a
little bit second nature a little bit more of the Refuge for ourselves there are ways of thinking
that become a refuge it's important not to overemphasize thinking even coming from
this thinking from this deep place within uh uh the task of thinking is
almost like task the task of thinking is to um unglue us to unstick us to let go
of desires aversions doubts regrets
agitations to experience ourself ourselves more and more free and deep deeper and
quieter and um and so um so that we can enter the
world relating it from the Deep Mind the Deep heart that does have desires but
there's no stickiness in them that does want to engage in the
world and want to speak with our friends but has no
stickiness with it that comes from this place of freedom of calmness of
Peace So if this what I'm talking about today makes sense to you experiment with
this through the day maybe even put a timer on your device that reminds you
that maybe times when you're alone take a time out to assess how your
thinking is going what kind of thinking are you doing and is it possible
to change gears and think from
a deep down inside to think from a calm way peaceful
way and this deepest and the simplest way of thinking that is
calming is to think thoughts of
recognition all we do is recognize what's happening
there's a time and place for other forms of thinking and creativity even from this deep
mind but uh for this practice of mindfulness the how it really supports
us to do a house cleaning and settling and connects us something deeper is to
have the simplest most peaceful calm thoughts of
recognition usually with just one word Maybe to and let it be that
simple so that Simplicity is part of the message is
part of the influence on your whole system it's like stepping into a calm
after being in a very noisy Place stepping into a calm room
ah the simple recognition is that calm room ah this is what's
happening and so what I hope this will this will do is teach you that there are
different ways of thinking you don't have to merily go along only with the way you usually
habitually think as if that's the way it has to
be somehow the causes and conditions of your life has led you to think a
particular way there are other
ways and if your thinking is not good for you by all
means experiment with this alternative I'm offering today find whatever place you can that's
calmer than your surface mind and know and recognize what's
happening calmly to bring a calm
reassuring presence to all that is agitated and
unsettled within
you may you be may you be your own best friend may you be your own
Refuge by how you think about
yourself thank you very much