okay welcome uh welcome folks lovely to uh see all the
names um
uh yeah so um so let's uh let's sit
together
just uh maybe touching into uh the goodness in
in that chat this uh Global
sa circle of of um
Goodwill
it's extremely fortunate that one might ever know
Dharma love
extremely
just uh breathe and land in your
body think whatever thoughts or feel whatever feeling things need to be
thought or felt in order for you to
become available to the Majesty of this
moment
directing uh attention to the feeling circuits of your
body kind of building BL blocks of uh mood and
emotion state of a affective
arousal often along the uh front axis of your body face throat
chest belly but um an affective feeling State
might cover the entire of your
body may be relatively stable or flowing maybe Pleasant or
unpleasant maybe subtle or
intense but feeling encodes a certain kind of
[Music] motivation intentionality moving towards
way and one of the the capacities we
cultivate in meditation
practice is to let feeling be
feeling and to uh renounce
the ways we narrate feeling find an
object for
feeling the ways are longing finds an object the
ways our aversion finds an
object the ways that our body experience kind of blossoms
into a feeling thought Loop
and so here we
practice
feeling without the consolation of
narrative
narrating or feeling
life staying oriented
to threat an
opportunity a very natural thing to
do Keeps Us feeling more
secure so to gently renounce The
Narrative the attempt to to read the Tea Leaves of our feeling
body feels uh vulnerable
exposed
and so it's natural for us to continually act out our
hypervigilance
what is this feeling what does it mean what do I want what must I
avoid
but uh
maybe feels okay to experiment with uh
defenselessness
knowing feeling is
feeling
to uh to feel feeling to be mindful of feeling is to
feel
feeling to do
this begins
to soften the
compulsive energies that usually come along
with uh the feeling
narrative cluster the ways that that
feeling when met unconsciously creates a kind of
imperative a
command
now we're not trying to listen for the command but just
feel in this way we begin to uh soften
something
begin to open to the
possibility that nothing needs to
happen right now
that we'd be okay if nothing
whatsoever
happened
this way we uh learn to distill
out the wisdom our
body from its compulsivity
this uh helps us live
well
okay um what's good to practice with
you uh so yesterday was
um confidence and uh humility these kind of uh pairs the pairs around kind of
more assertive qualities of mind more receptive qualities of Mind how they
work together so yesterday confidence humility um and uh
today uh effort and
effortlessness so I was alluding to to kind of effort effort we we make in the
the SI right to to actually um to feel our feelings to feel
feeling life with and and in a sense renounce the need to understand
everything Moment by moment to narrate it to know its Origins its trajectory
all of this take some effort
and evolutionary pressures have have exerted very potent effects we're
animals it's so easy to forget cuz I wear v-neck but it's like I'm an animal
I'm an animal you know and we're not far
from you know from chimps and um we love predictable things and pleasure and
security and um nibana was not at the top of
Evolutions to-do list right peace happiness that's just one lever that
Evolution pulls and effort effort is um is a major
theme in the sutas because for Animals such as ourselves
you know um greed hate and delusion is often the path of least resistance right
like I I joke that my my habits my bad habits require
precisely zero effort
zero deep growth uh in other words is not always comfortable it takes energy
and we're renouncing uh less satisfying forms of
of pleasure for deeper forms of well-being and that gesture of
renunciation takes takes effort uh especially in the kind of
training period you know which maybe is our entire life but but it there may be
a trend towards more effortlessness but especially as we're establishing a
practice it's like a lot of effort the Buddha described anger for
example like that this beautiful phrase with its honey tip and poison
root and to we know the honey we know the poison
to forgo the honey takes effort our problematic
habits always have some honey even the most painful mind States there's some
honey there's some Solace you know even in our guilt
Even in our self-hatred there's often like a kind of soothing underbelly to it
the honey but this path is against the
stream and uh we're using we're leveraging our effort
to to renounce now uh one way that
teaching teaching functions is that uh the teacher says what they need to hear
I I don't think my Dharma talks are like purely Matthew directed pep talks
but it'd be good if I listened you know um friend of
mine Dharma teacher was like listening to one of his own talks you know and uh
his response in listening to it was like whoa that guy really sounds like he
knows what he's talking about right and um to actually take our own best
advice involves energy involves energy we we uh
um yeah need to need to kind of draw down on a finite pool of our energy in
order to listen listen to ourselves right and
uh um and
uh so effort yeah effort is very clear
um but we can't just be told to to Bear down yeah if
um if if that's all we ever do if all we if
what we think of as practice is just bearing down the effort side of this
dialectic uh one of the effects is only only ever bearing down leads us to
overvalue willfulness and somewhere early early in
my practice maybe I don't know maybe just right as it began Veria and sakya diti got
tangled together varia energetic Vigor the effort side
sakya uh selfie uh my my effort my effort the
very sense that kind of like inner sanctum the the imagined headquarters of
my effort got yolked to the sense of me
some kind of like deficient being that needed to fiercely
exert his will and my my kind of effort and
striving was was this like total tangle of of dhanda longing for the
Dharma and then conceit the melodrama of
self and so part of why we we have to experiment with this other side of the
dialectic of effortlessness is that uh we must
all uh witness the limits of our
willfulness and so the inquiry what what does effort look like on the other side
of your willfulness what does effort look like on the other side of your
willfulness so part of the emphasis on
effortlessness is to actually perceive the selfing in our
effting but part of effortlessness is is just we
we can't always be told to make more effort remember to be mindful to pay
attention to be present to let go of Cravings to let renounce the honey to
keep choosing the wholesome it's too much tired I want a nap right too
much that's why I always kind of shudder when I hear the some some of the sort of
mindfulness instructions like that feel like always so effortful and I just know
that it's not sustainable it's not sustainable and it's like okay I want to
be close to the Dharma right now I really do but the only way I can be
close is if uh what I can do is something close
to effortless you know the only way I can be close is if
if it doesn't ask a ton of the kind of effort
system and many of the actual fruits as we
train as we train um many of the fruits of the practice actually don't require effort
to to keep up we develop Dharma habits traits and traits are about
effortlessness just like the traits of you know greed hate and delusion take
no no uh no effort uh we develop good
habits good habits and we begin to entrust our Dharma practice to those good
habits it's famous piece from uh William James says so far as we are mere bundles
of habit we are imitators and copiers of our past selves it follows first of all
the teacher's Prime concern shall be to ingrain into the pupil that assortment
of habits that shall be most useful to them throughout life education is for
behavior and habits are the stuff of which behavior consists goes on to say the great thing
in all education is to make our nervous system our Ally instead of our
enemy it's very very beautiful to make our nervous system our our Ally instead
of our enemy right
to uh we maybe say like Dharma Dharma it's about effort but it's also
about making our nervous system our Ally and here we don't
go um we don't go against the stream we enter enter the stream enter the stream
it's kind of strange uh um two sides of the way stream is
used we are we're propelled uh propelled by the
momentum of of goodness the effortlessness of awareness
not not marshalling the attention that excuse me that takes effort to
Marshall the attention even if it's just subtle that that takes
effort but there is a quality um of the the kind of an
effortless quality of over awareness that we have more access to effortless
access it it it doesn't we don't have to burn attentional caloric
calories you know the the kind of like we we there's no attentional burn in
awareness and that's not something we control but we gain more and more access
to that the the kind of deep nourishment of
it and we talk a lot about choice and making choices uh in Dharma and
mindfulness giving us room to choose these things but the truth is that
making choices is tiring um and in my practice I I don't really
notice that I exactly make better choices it's much more like the menu
options are better that takes less
effort the nervous system uh is an ally when wholesomeness
wholesomeness becomes more pleasurable than un
wholesomeness not wholesomeness is like some idea some should some ought any of that no
wholesomeness wholesomeness actually becomes more
pleasurable right and the Dharma Dharma practice is a kind of Behavioral
modification where usually we're motivated by honey but we actually
condition ourselves train ourselves train the animal of our body to learn
from the poison we get very clear on the poison we do not blunt the experience of
the pain of acting out in this way or that way with
unconsciousness and that that that begins to to the Dharma functions as a
behavioral modification program it begins to create its own natural
incentive structure right we the the the pain of being
unaligned becomes more poignant and then Letting Go Letting Go
feels like less effort than holding on When Love um increasingly becomes the
kind of default position of the mind it's hatred rather than love that takes
effort nervous system becomes our Ally than our
enemy offer this for your uh consideration and um look forward to
being with you tomorrow okay folks thank
you