welcome welcome and happy New Year again
hard to believe right here we go one more year
and it's not uncommon of course at the beginning of a new year or new season or
new something to reflect back on the preceding
era time and to look forward
to what we would like to do or how we would like the next year or whatever to
be different
so maybe one way in which we do this is to think about what would we like to prioritize in our life the next year
chances are if you're here that maybe meditation has a role there if you made
it here on a rainy I think it's a holiday for some people today so if you if you made your way
here maybe uh meditation it's part not necessarily though but
and then so I kind of want to wrap this in with a the theme I want to continue
from the last time I spoke about kind of like effort and energy like applying effort and having energy
and how can we do that in a way that's helpful and supportive and honors and
respects the amount of energy we have without demanding that we have a different amount
necessarily and working with it to make our lives shape
Our Lives have our lives head in the direction we would like because it's not a secret that if we
want our lives to unfold a little bit differently than effort has to be part
of that part of that equation because no matter what we would like to
prioritize in our lives a sense of maybe a little activity or effort or energy is
what's needed to take it out of the theoretical into something that's actually gets done to take it out of
this idea or a wish into something that actually happens
I'm really good at just coming up with these great ideas so I'm going to do this I'm going to do that I'm going to
do this yeah that's as far as it goes sometimes right
just having these ideas so to help us kind of bridge this gap
between aspiring to doing something and actually like losing it
but what is this effort towards like what like maybe we can unpack this
a little bit and part of it is to do something other than just follow our
preferences and follow our habits right if we don't to play an effort that's the direction Our Lives will go maybe that's
okay but if we want it to broaden or to add
some different elements or shift the direction a little bit so we have to do something other than just follow our
habits and preferences and this takes energy
because right there are habits they are from uh this kind of like
stream that we might say of um activity the body the Mind create habits as a way
to conserve energy right things just kind of go on autopilot so energy is required if we want things to be
different if we want to do something different than we usually
do when I was thinking about this I noticed this is like a minor thing that but in
my own life something that I realized yeah this is going to take a little bit of effort I have this habit of
sitting at my computer and not putting my computer classes on so I'm spending
all this time you know going like this bad posture squinching right it's terrible it's just like this habit I
have of I can't quite see with my regular glasses I just I don't put my computer glasses on and the end of the
day I have this tension in my neck and shoulders this is a minor thing but right every day
day after day week after week month after month right this adds up so it will take a little bit of effort
for me to notice when I'm just have this habit of doing this so we have these habits of things that
we do but we also have these habits that are part of like with our relationships
or maybe there's habits that get supported by the social structure
that we're in there's a I had a friend who would
I really enjoyed reading blogs that were really polemic that were really about
you know we are right and everybody else is wrong and this was years and years ago but it
was quite something if this person my friend had just finished reading one of
these kind of like articles and then I happened to have a conversation with them it was quite something to feel like
all this righteous indignation and we've got to do something and like not seeing
quite clearly like not taking in the bigger picture just stuck in a small
picture about something but if it's our habit it's to you know look at our
phones in the morning and our phones are filled with this kind of this polemic
whether it's a podcast or a something that we read or substag
whatever it might be you know that's going to have an impact on us too
so if we want to do something different G
so I'm going to Define effort as Applied Energy and we might think of
energy as like this maybe this sense of Vitality we have maybe it has a little
bit of a like a buzzing maybe a little bit of
vibration to it I don't even know if that's the right word exactly but
it can also just be a sense of like feeling good like having having energy
is like feeling present I know in the Buddhist world energy and
effort have different poly words but sometimes those poly words have the same
definition so sometimes we talk about effort when we're and energy and kind of
just mix them up together but for what I'm doing tonight I'm going to Define effort as Applied Energy
and some of you might know that in the Eightfold Path which is this path
towards Awakening and not surprising as eight aspects to it
that one of them is what we call like wise effort
like how how to apply effort and something that I'll
highlight here that is as part of the Eightfold Path it's really pointing to
the direction of effort like what are we going to spend our life energy on what
direction are we going to go and what direction are we not going to go
so we could say kind of in a really broad brush that
the wise effort sometimes called right effort right in terms of not moralistic
right versus wrong but right as in terms of the best tool for the job
if we have to put a nail in we don't grab a screwdriver the right tool is a
hammer that kind of a thing so wise effort is this idea that if we
want to diminish what leads to suffering for ourselves and others
and we want to increase what leads to our well-being and others well-being
it's kind of right effort in a nutshell has more elements to it but you know
diminishing suffering and increasing well-being I don't think anybody will protest with
this I think probably all spiritual practices have this direction also
but I like um Gregory Kramer he has this sub definition he says uh right effort
is the energy of swimming towards the wholesome and away from the unwholesome I like
this idea of swimming because like we're moving through water there's a little bit of pressure again says it does take
a little bit of effort but also we can float on the top too right it sometimes
can just be a really restful effort but sometimes there can be this sense of
reading to swim and he he just uh summarizes right
effort as out with the bad and in with the good again I don't think anybody will uh
disagree with this but those um
so here what's the bad or you know those things that cause harm but it's also we might say not only
actions that cause harm but mental qualities what are we doing with our
minds is it helpful or is it unhelpful
this word helpful it's often sometimes a translation for this word kusala
the same word gets translated as wholesome skillful helpful
so not only are actions which maybe that's a little bit more obvious to be aware of that but really what are we
doing with our minds also and so there's a classic core of
teachings of what is abandoned you know like the unwholesome so many dermatocs are about these I'm
just going to list some of them don't worry I'm not going to go through all of these but this what are what are some of these
things that are the unhelpful five hindrances things that hinder that
get in the way of the mind being settled and having some
collectedness there's the three unwholesome Roots it's
this idea that at the base as the foundation of everything
that's unhelpful there's only just three things great hatred or we might sometimes call
it aversion and delusion sometimes called ignorance and sometimes it's helpful just to
simplify things greed really wanting more aversion or hatred you know to kind of
pushing away and delusion just not paying attention at all or being completely unaware
I know sometimes in my practice that can be helpful because maybe I don't really
have the exact word but there's maybe just this more this feeling of maybe
leaning more or wanting more sometimes we might use uh pooling like
wanting something or leaning forward
also as part of this classic core of what is abandoned or the taints
these are said to what's abandoned when a person is awakened
and we can understand these tits as the intoxication with sense Pleasures this
idea that just pursuing endless sense Pleasures is the way to
Everlasting happiness sometimes we're happy if we have some
pleasure but it's not reliable and it certainly isn't Everlasting right we're always chasing
the next one so the taints intoxication with sense Pleasures intoxication with self-making
that is setting up the I'm the person who does X
and I don't do y I'm the person who is kind and I am not
unkind and so we have to ignore all those times when we don't let that
person in front of us in traffic or we're ignoring the person who's talking too loud or whatever it might be
but this sense of having to adopt a
belief about ourselves and not only do we have to adopt this
belief but we have to kind of make sure that everybody else believes it too and this takes a tremendous amount of
propping up and energy and time and effort and shows up in so many different ways
it turns out that having this belief is extra
we don't need it but this is something that kind of unfolds with practice it's not helpful
for me to just say this it's something that really you need to have this
experience but maybe I'll point to you briefly
there's times when like this righteous indignation when we hear something that really angers us that we feel like oh
how dare they and there can be a strong sense of they shouldn't do that there's a strong sense
of self then it might be helpful and appropriate but if you contrast that
with when you're doing your favorite hobby there's not such a sense of self when
you're knitting or doing gardening or something like this you're not thinking about
yourself you're thinking about whatever it is that you're doing so to have this really strong sense of
self I'm over here and all everybody else is over there just takes extra
energy it's not necessary and then one of the taints is ignorance
so these three taints these are said that's what's uh let go of with
Awakening this understanding that sense Pleasures
is not what's going to lead to Awakening we don't need to be make creating this
self and there's no longer ignorance instead there's a clear seeing of the
way things are and then maybe the last thing that I'll mention here is this classic core part
of because it's at the beginning of the year I thought I would say some of these things
is uh clinging it's amazing right how many things we
can cling to even the things that we don't want we cling to them and some
kind of convoluted way so these are some of the classic core of what is abandoned
with right effort and then what is cultivated are seven
factors of Awakening I just completed a series I talked about the seven factors and I'm teaching a
course on the seven factors online just as the name sounds like these are
things that really support Awakening some of these seven I won't list all of them but some of them are like Joy
and some of them it's uh Equanimity you know having some balance some
concentration having some collectedness and energy is also one of them right we
need to have some energy or effort the five faculties something else that's
cultivated this um overlap some with the seven factors
mindfulness energy oh sorry I'll do this in order Faith
energy mindfulness um
concentration and wisdom there's so many different ways we
cultivate those we cultivate the Brahma of ahuras
these are for practices of the heart loving kindness compassion sympathetic joy and
equanimity and the ten pyromes and I'll go through this long list of the poemies
so there's this you know the Buddhist love lists right so and I'm one of those people that like the lists
things to abandon things to cultivate so right effort is really pointing us
towards that but I would make a distinction between this right effort and balanced effort
so balanced effort isn't the difference or the balance between making effort and
not making effort said it's the balance or that's the
recognizing what is the right amount of effort to apply to the task at hand
and what's the right amount of effort to apply given the type of energy we have at the time
sometimes we have lots of energy sometimes we don't or maybe we have an illness and we rarely have lots of
energy we're not being asked to be different than who we are we're just
it's being pointed to to be wise about how we use the energy that we have
and to not use too much and not too little
so the Buddha I appreciate very much this
uh little simile about having the right amount of energy for whatever it is we're going to do
and he uh has this simile suppose a person was to hold a quail you
know these little birds right we have California quills they're so adorable with their little things on their heads
suppose a person were to hold a quail too tightly in their hands
it would die right there oh it's just awful to think about right
suppose a person were to hold a quail too loosely it would fly out of their hands
so this idea of not too tight and not too loose it's about you know how to apply the
right amount of energy so sometimes when we hear about right efforts or applying effort we might
think that this is some type of intense Focus or some has some intensity to it
but um quoting Gregory Kramer again I appreciate very much that he says that
that have balanced effort is like the strenuous effort required to turn
the soil and plant our Gardens get in there with the right tools
trowel or whatever might be needed shovels and other times the effort is like the
steady application of the sun's Heat we need all of these things to make
things grow so sometimes we're in there really exerting energy and sometimes there's
more just like this gentle Heat
and so part of the art of practice is Discerning well what what is needed here
when are we giving too much and when is it too little
part of recognizing if it's too little it's not uncommon when there's too little effort there often is a feeling
of discouragement which then can lead to doubt because there's like we don't quite see anything
happening we're applying a little bit of effort and we're getting a little bit of
results and it's true right this practice sometimes we don't see results in a
short time frame sometimes it's not until we look back over months that we
start to see oh yeah I am showing up in the world a little bit differently I do have a
little bit different inner voice sometimes that shows up that allows me to be more kind towards myself or kind
towards others or more patient or something like this
but I also want to acknowledge that I feel like um these days like these days being like
after the pandemic and as we're still trying to find our way with the new
normal that many of us feel depleted there's a
way in which there's maybe this is not as much energy for what used to
be meaningful for us or maybe it's a lack of enthusiasm I don't know exactly what it is
but maybe it's like this um coach and Paley Ellison he's a zen
teacher he describes it as like the oxygen has left our life somehow
and this recognition that we might feel flat or a little bit disengaged or not
quite attuned to what's happening with our life that there's maybe a little bit
of just going through the motions and we feel like we're living a little bit
like from a distance from what's really happening not quite engaged with it and
then all our energy is going to just doing the next thing that needs to be done just to get through the day just to
get through the to-do list or you know finish the tasks so there isn't this energy to if we want
to make different priorities for our life if we want our life to turn to be differently if we want to be cultivating
the skillful wholesome helpful and abandoning the unskillful and wholesome
how are we going to do that or are we feeling like maybe overwhelmed what we just don't have the energy for it
well often when German teachers talk about effort and energy myself included
often we're talking well some teachers I tend to not do this because
maybe I'll tell this little story that at the beginning of a long retreat there was a one of the very first Talks Of The
Retreat right where we all are kind of showing up and kind of eager to do this whole retreat thing
and this one teacher talked about a retreat he had done in Asia
it was so hard and they could only sleep for four hours and we had to be sit you
know up you are not allowed to move for hours at a time and this person described how they lost like so much
weight because there wasn't enough food and like and it was months of this and
all of us I well I should say me my eyes are getting big like oh my gosh okay I
guess that's what's required oh my gosh that was so horrible Retreat it was so hard and I ended up getting
myself really it happened and tight not striving with my you know shoulders up near my ears and it was completely
unhelpful but sometimes teachers Like Straw Strife
you know you gotta do this or I don't know if they say that sometimes that's what we hear right
because maybe you know this doing that type of work really helped us maybe in our academic setting or in our
professional life but something different is needed here so I'd like to offer a little something
different here and that is this poem by a practitioner her name is Sylvia
ostertuck and this poem is called tiredness
and it's about have to practice with tiredness and
maybe how it actually can be really helpful so the poem goes like this
tiredness is no obstacle to sitting in silence
but to think tiredness is an obstacle
that is an obstacle when you stop thinking this you can sit
in silence very well with tiredness however tired you are
then at last you are too tired to get stressed and want to achieve anything
too tired to bully your breath and keep griping about yourself
perhaps even too tired to think
that the only thing to do is to abandon yourself
gently for this brief moment into the silence
now I appreciate this this idea of you know
tiredness is maybe there's a way in that just supports a certain letting go
and earlier I had talked about that selfing is something that we're moving
away from with this practice and I appreciate she's perhaps even too tired
to think and the only thing to do is to abandon
yourself gently so when we talk about energy and effort
we often are thinking about how much we have to apply but I also want to introduce this idea that we can practice
with whatever is amount of energy we have and maybe there's even sometimes
advantages to having a little bit of energy maybe there's times when we feel
depleted or uninspired
can we sit anyway without this idea of
we have to achieve anything what does she say here at last you are too tired to get
stressed and want to achieve anything there's some sweetness to this I think
it's really tender instead of you know trying to prop
ourselves up in some kind of way but I mean there are times in which we
have this exhaustion and it may be due to not enough sleep
maybe due to illness maybe just simply because we're working too much
maybe you're spread thin with lots of responsibilities
but sometimes this exhaustion is not because of something external like that
sometimes it's about what's um happening internally
so can we pay attention when we start to feel exhausted and have this idea is it
about you know am I just simply too overextended or not getting enough sleep
or is it should I like have this uh investigation what is draining the
energy what is it that straining energy and
maybe it's something like trying to please everyone that's exhausting
right it doesn't work or maybe we're doing too much because
we're trying to feel indispensable or trying to feel important or something
like this that's also exhausting or maybe
we're not able to ask for help or to delegate
in our professional life or family life or you know we find it difficult to ask
others to do something so we end up doing everything ourselves
and feeling exhausted maybe even feel a little bit resentful and that adds to the sense of exhaustion
or maybe it's just we're not taking care of ourselves we're not eating well and exercising we all know we should do this
right and sometimes it shows up with our just being tired
when we don't uh take the or spend the energy or effort to take care of our
physical bodies but I I also want to address one more
thing that might fuel exhaustion and sometimes at the beginning of the new year we might
have some ambitious ideas about what we're going to do okay this
is the year that I'm going to do whatever it is not everybody does this but if we're
going to do it sometimes it's tempting to do it this time of year to make these like big changes
but in these times when we believe that anything is possible we have like these
peaks of energy yes I'm gonna do it this is the time finally
no matter what I'm gonna make this happen and sometimes that works fantastic and it does happen
but sometimes these peaks of energy are followed by valleys of energy to
and part of that not all of it but part of it is if we have this idea that we're
going to make a big change even if it's something that we want it can elicit like a fear response
there's something in us that's not so comfortable with making big changes
and that of course this fear response shows up as like putting on the brakes and kind of like sucking out all the
energy of what it is we want to do so just a recognition that that also could
be something that has a role if we're feeling like oh we just don't have the energy
for to do this right effort to this
Orient Our Lives towards cultivating what's helpful and wholesome and abandoning what's not helpful and
wholesome so maybe it's helpful to just focus on little things that we can do
to improve situations Maybe not maybe it's great to do grand gestures and big
plans but maybe it's helpful to just think about hmm is there something a little something
that I might do differently the next time I'm doing this is there something I can learn about
this instead of this turning things into a big Grand project
so that we Can it can be a little bit more sustainable in this movement that
we would like our Direction our life to go
so maybe I'll stop there with uh talking about energy and effort
and this idea that there's sometimes Dharma teachers talk about right effort
and balanced effort and they kind of put them together but sometimes it's helpful to tease them apart right effort is
about like the direction we want to go and balanced effort is you know are we
gonna squeeze this poor little Quail or are we going to let it make it fly away
or so that it uh doesn't we don't have any energy of what
we're doing so and maybe with that I'll open it up and see if there's some questions or
comments
foreign happy New Year Diana thank you so much I
really liked um your Dharma talk especially in regards to just the effort and the sense
of self and whether or not I'm applying I think I'm just grateful that through
meditation I'm more aware of that the sense of self I'm just
now with the new year upon us I just want to make sure that whatever it is that I'm clinging to with
my sense of self that I can approach it every day with like do you have any
questions like oh and Rose I noticed that I'm trying to
be X or Y or be perceived a certain way or you know it's I don't think to help
point out or to help you realize when that's a sense of self is strong yes so
that way I can just go about life without having to strive for or be
whatever it is that I just I just want to be there be just be here yeah
so I think you're talking about there's a number of things I think that you're saying one is when is there a strong
sense of self and when especially when it's tied up with striving like trying to make things different is that is that
right or yes yeah so one thing I'll say a hint or a clue about when there's a
strong sense of self is when there's a strong sense of other like oh those people over there
whenever that's happening there's a strong sense of self too so that's impossible for that not to happen so
just to notice and it takes sometimes it can be energizing like I'm
in the right and they are wrong and then you have this sense of energy and it maybe it feels nice but it's taxing it's
really right this really doesn't lead to a good life right of doing this then
this sense of striving I even had some notes in here I was going to talk about it if we had a
little bit more time but one thing that um
can be helpful to think about is often there's uh what's fueling or underneath
striving is some fear like this fear right of uh missing out
or fear of having regret or fear of
um turning into a slug or something right
like there's uh there can there can be something like that that's fueling this driving so it can be a strong sense of
self and fears often tied up with that but that might just be something to
have some curiosity about is there is there a sense of something I'm trying to
avoid or I'm afraid of or something like that and that fear or
yeah can be fueling striving okay is that helpful very much thank you so much
yeah you're welcome you're welcome [Music]
oh thank you for a nice talk about uh
um energy and effort of effort and energy and
um I um and also three
um points you talked about were the greed hatred and delusion
I don't know if you agree with me whether they it falls under
one um point which is ego I mean greedy is a
form of ego delusion is a form of ego or um
and hatred is a form of ego some kind
um so how that ego can be lowered or like or be
dispelled is important the second thing is
um is when we are when you talk about the energy and you know the effort and being
tired um personally for example I have been
interested in uh finding you know more like-minded people let's say
and for with whom I can talk about let's say Dharma talk and you know these
things they were not necessarily here it's like 45 minutes and we are done
but so I I wonder if you have any comments on that so we can multiply that
energy and you know that so that is one question I have yeah yeah
so the first one about is ego greed hatred and delusion so in this tradition
um we we would say and you had asked like is there a way to like diminish the ego or something this tradition points
to you don't have to diminish the ego it just recognize that it's actually not
there instead in the way that because when we
would use maybe like the sense of self as with the ego and so
yes it's like 50 50. it's like the 50 percent part like the I I I know about
let's say my ego like this introspection but I do not know about
like my environment's ego or like people I am interacting with yeah
and how I mean one is of course you know I would want to
be in a like-minded environment so people who are I see am I answering I see I I
misunderstood your question so it's easier to not be have greed
hatred and delusion when you're surrounded by people that have similar ideas yeah like we were like during
um Glenn uh his talk we were talking about you know we talk about Gregory
Peck and the Gregory Peck of Indian Cinema and whatnot so if you are like
you know thinking good things you know yeah on top of a mountain and you know like that and
so it's that ego is down and that's
um yeah so a few things like what I said to Anne Rose about the self right is the
same about how to like can we would use the the language the self for ego we ego
is like a contemporary idea about psychology but um this idea about with like-minded
people I agree it's easier but we can't always do that of course and is your
question like how can we or where can you or like just very pragmatic like where where and how can we hear because
it's like a I mean for me I've been looking for like-minded yeah yeah for
like a year more or more and there I I don't want to really call it tiredness
um putting effort but it's like you know it's like at some point you want to
find an answer to the question yes so here at IMC like on Sundays after
the Dharma talk there's discussions and on Wednesdays here there are discussions
too so it's an opportunity to kind of explore and meet other people and
and yeah and investigate and see if it's a place that supports you bringing your
best self forward so to speak thank you yeah thank you
is there a time there's another short question or
um I really liked your analogy about the quail and trying to find the right
amount of energy and effort um what I find in my own life and a lot
of my friends is the world today seems to like have too many demands like I'm at an age where we
have young children and we still want to have careers and there's um the dream I think is to go about the
day you know gently at a gentle Pace but I don't think that it to me it I don't
find that possible because there's too much to do in a day and so I don't know
if you have any advice about how to live in a situation
um where it just seems like there's too much to do and they feel like most people's reaction is to like go really
fast and then get exhausted and then oversleep you know like doing too much and then too little and then you get
into this cycle it would be great to just go at a steady pace and feel like you have enough time in a day to tend to
everything like a gentle Gardener but that's that's not you know I to me
that's not realistic right now so if we sort of can't have that what's like the next best yeah yeah no this is a
legitimate question right so is there there is a way and this is
not easy but it's absolutely possible I promise you to have to be uh doing lots of things
without tension to be doing one thing after the other
but without tension and this is what your point is like it's the dream right it is possible but part of it is to
learn what does it feel like when tension is there to feel when there's this like oh my gosh I have to do this
and sometimes it's I'll get back to saying this idea this a strong sense of self gets created what's going to happen
if I turn this in late I'm going to be the person who turned it in late or something like this but can there be
this recognition without a contraction and a
tension the shoulders going up type of thing and I would say one is to recognize when
there is tension and to imitation practice actually does help because it kind of
um not only is an opportunity to settle but it allows the mind to get used to or
recognize when there is some more spaciousness and Once the mind
recognizes and sometimes the body that oh there is an alternative to the usual
way of doing things it becomes easier to make a change but if you don't have any experience of
doing things in a without tension maybe quickly and a lot of things but no
tension then it's hard to do so meditation practice can help I I wish I had an easy answer right you
know but at least you have an answer thank you you're welcome you're welcome
okay so we're at the top of the hour so thank you will and again Happy New Year