foreign
welcome welcome everybody nice to see you all
and we'll sit for 45 minutes
maybe I'll do a little bit of guided here
just an encouragement to feel the experience of breathing
in a relaxed way trusting that the body knows how to breathe
and it can be helpful to put our hands on our belly
and just feel the movement we're not forcing the breath we're not
manipulating the breath we're just feeling the body
breathes
in a very simple way
trusting that the body knows how to breathe and we're just noticing
no need to change the breath
to allow it to be natural
and when the mind wanders we just very simply
gently Begin Again with the sensations of breathing
feeling the movement the stretching
and the release of the stretch
foreign
thank you
foreign [Music]
so tonight I'd like to build on this theme that I did
um last week on Friday I ended with a theme on kindness
and I like to kind of uh maybe build on that this idea of kindness
and I'm influenced by Sharon salzberg she has a book
if I remember correctly it's called the force of kindness so many of you may know that she's well
known for loving kindness practice she's one of the main people that brought it to the west and popularized it here in
the West a Sharon points out that we may think
that kindness rates pretty low on these
characteristics that we think people should have I mean it's we all think that maybe like
an intellect or a sharp wit or beauty or invulnerability or power or authority or
you know all these other things but certainly must be more important than kindness
and if you look at you know our media what we see and all kinds of media right
we get this message that kindness that's not really valued
but it is right in our lives it's valued but in so many ways we get this message
that it's somehow maybe it seems wimpy like kindness is
something that you do if you can't have a sharp intellect or uh wit or a beauty
or power or something like this like okay well at least this person is kind at least I can be kind
kind of the message that we see showing up in so many different ways I know that sometimes I've felt that what you know
the movies or TV shows you know sometimes like the uh
the sidekick of the really powerful person in media is kind but you know the
the protagonist the main person is powerful or something like this
so maybe there's a way in which we might delegate kindness It's like oh
that's a nice old-fashioned virtue and maybe it's something that uh
maybe I'll say this if we think about the people in our lives who I've really touched our lives
and whom we respect we'll see that they were kind these are
the types of people who actually make a difference in our lives
and I know that when I was trying to figure out exactly how old I was I don't know maybe 9 10 11 somewhere in that
range I had a swim coach who one time asked me you know what did I want to be
when I grow up you know one of those types of questions to ask a kid and at that time I said oh I want to be
a stewardess right and that was the word that we used back then right to be a flight attendant
and this coach said are you sure Diana do you are you sure that you want to
just uh do something that you that you really
not he was trying to encourage me to be think big I don't want to put down
anything about flight attendants or stories this is fantastic and somebody in my family is a one of those but he
wanted me oh now I'm remembering it was because there was this cute commercial that was on TV and that was why I wanted
to be a stewardess because commercial and he was really encouraged me to like
why not think bigger and somehow that stayed with me
I can't say that's exactly why I have a PhD in Biochemistry but it's you know maybe it's part of the reason why I did
think that you know maybe there's something more than just what I thought was cute on a TV
commercial but I remember the kindness that he
showed me that he asked and listened to what I had to say and
encouraged me to think big and I think that was something that uh you know all
these years later I remember so maybe all of us have somebody that touched our lives and it was done with
some kindness so even though like we often get the message that okay kindness it's nice to
have and maybe it's if you can't have these other qualities you can be kind but actually it turns out to be quite
powerful and meaningful and impactful
so but not only that what if it turns out that kindness
is the daring bold powerful thing to do
what if kindness is actually what turns out to require a lot of strength
requires maybe some autonomy and some knowing like what's important
what if kindness actually turns out to be really bold
because we all know it's so easy right when somebody else is putting a third
person down like oh yeah they annoy me too and then blah blah blah blah and you're down we go or maybe there's a
social media right we just know it's like practically designed for people to be unkind
it's just ripe with all of that and what if it's you know to be
stand up for that person and say well you know I think maybe forgive them the benefit of the doubt and in this context
what if they really meant that and they didn't mean what's being interpreted to
be harmful or whatever it might be
so what if rather than jumping into blaming when
things don't go well which is easy to do we blame ourselves
we blame others the all the news I keep on going on about the media I'll stop after this but I do
notice that this sometimes our news agencies are designed just about finding who's to blame that's kind of there
a reason for existence in some ways but rather than jumping into blaming
what would it be like to have some kindness and to have some openness and
some warmth and maybe if we can't have openness and warmth maybe to not have disdain
to not have this quiet aggression or quiet hostility that's often shows up
when things aren't going the way that we want it to go or people aren't behaving the way we want it to behave
we want to sometimes you like shake them don't you understand ah
what if we just like notice maybe that thought arise in the mind and then just let it go
so what would it be like to have a commitment to kindness as part of our
practice or maybe that is our practice this commitment to kindness
which means of course kindness to ourselves so often there's this inner
critic that's berating us making us feel inadequate and that just spills out
to others they're inadequate and insufficient and not doing it right
and there's this flavor of a bit of aggression or hostility there whether it
gets acted out but the point is that it's kind of there's a
way in which there's this closing this contraction I know what's better and you are doing
it right me versus the world US versus them I
know it's right and you don't it's not a comfortable place to be
for a moment there's this thrill of self-righteousness but then we always
have to prop it up and oh my gosh this is not a good life this is a life filled with trying to
make sure everybody sees us exactly the way that we want them to this is a life of never maybe extending
ourselves or Taking Chances because we want to make sure they're always looking good so maybe we might not look good if
we try something new so what if we have this commitment to
being kind to not harm
when I was uh studying Buddhism I remember this so clearly
that being in a class where I was the only person that practiced this lineage
this tradition of Buddhism everybody else they were Buddhists but in all other Traditions probably every other
tradition you can imagine and then Professor asked us so if you
had to sum up one word
for Buddhist practice what would it be it was surprising that everybody from a
different tradition had something different to say but for me at that moment I felt like non-harming
so much about practice is about non-harming and this non-harming is kind of like
there's a lot of Letting Go that has to happen and the way that we view ourselves and view others there's all
these things that are part of non-harming I'm not sure I would say the same thing today but at that time I
thought it was it's such an important part of practice well these subtle ways
in which we are not kind to ourselves sometimes the most
and to not others even if it's not something that we're doing with our overtly with our Behavior maybe it's
something with our mind that we're doing and you know as I said kind of we get stuck
with I know it's better but we might hear this something like a
commitment to kindness and we might hear like oh okay I guess I have to be overly
nice this way in which we might have this
saccharine sweetness like oh yeah everything's fine you can do whatever
you want yeah that's fine it's all okay but there's this overly niceness that
actually is not what's being pointed to here an overly niceness is a way we might
understand is this spiritual bypassing it's this way in which we don't want to
be with the difficulties we don't want to acknowledge what's really happening
there's a way that we kind of like get a little bit disembodied and we're just like on this surface oh yeah it's fine
not recognizing maybe when boundaries have been crossed maybe somebody's taking too much of our time or they're
taking too much of energy from us or taking what's not
like just crossing boundaries in a way maybe it's not even clear to us
but because we want to be overly nice we'll just say oh yeah it's fine oh yeah sure I'll take your dog to the vet and
drop you off at the airport and water your lawn and you like all these things and we don't hardly even know them maybe they're not even friends of ours or
I'm just making these up but these stories but so I want to make clear that when I'm
saying this commitment to kindness I am not saying being overly nice and in fact if we do find ourselves
being overly nice then we can just maybe gently ask ourselves
is there something that I'm avoiding is there something that I don't want to see
and it might be that we might be something that's uncomfortable that comes up and maybe we could just
acknowledge it with like okay that's there I'm not saying that we have to jump into the most difficult the most
uncomfortable there can be some skillfulness in not being with it
there's a way in which we might need to behave so that we're not always like holding grudges or that
we're not always being filled with bitterness so can we conduct Our Lives
in a way that we can have kindness and take care of ourselves
and it turns out this is not so easy it turns out this takes real skill and
practice and is a whole practice on itself
and maybe it starts with being kind to ourselves recognizing oh yeah this is
hard I don't know how to set boundaries I don't know how to say no to whomever I
I don't know how to be anything except trying to please everybody all the time or and just maybe
feel that that's why the kindness starts this is a recognition of the difficulty
of maybe not being overly nice
but there's a way and also that this commitment to kindness as a way of practice
can be a clear like it can be a North star it can be a clear intention of a way
that's that can be a thread throughout our life like when we feel confused or we don't
know what to do or it's lots of difficulties or whatever is happening in our life
this idea of okay if kindness what's the kind thing to do
for myself and for others without indulging and without being overly nice
this is a practice itself how to be kind without just indulging
yeah I'm not going to do that thing that's difficult because I want to be kind to myself and
not acknowledging maybe the fear that's there or the
maybe it's fear about all kinds of things what might happen or what if we fail or what if it
gets really awkward and uncomfortable so this to have this generosity of heart
towards ourselves and towards others this can be a real like direction for
our life and our practice because maybe there will be seasons of our life in which we don't have a meditation
practice for whatever reason we don't have time we
don't feel like it fits in our life so maybe our spiritual practice shows up
this way as using kindness as a Direction and there's a way in which that can
provide some stability in our life too sometimes we might feel like I feel so confused I don't even know what to do
but kindness can be like okay this can be like a touchstone if I wanted to be kind
what would I do authentically kind
embodied kind this kindness that comes from a embodied Place Not Just Thoughts
but to place that feels like maybe a mature is a little bit more settled way
and there's a way in that if we were to take kindness a commitment to kindness as a
direction of our life it's a way in which I
there's a way I'm trying to remember if I have this quote exactly right and I might not but
this idea is like being the change you wish to see in the world both of us
don't want it meanness
fear-mongering we don't nobody really wants that
so even if we take this kindness on as a practice this is a way in which we can
be the change we want to see in the world if we're waiting for you know all the
decision makers in the world to be the ones like okay we're going to be kind in fact there is an international
kindness day I'm not sure if people are more kind on that day but you know there have been authorities that got together
and say okay kindness is important let's make a day where everybody's going to be kind
why can't it start with us why can't we be the ones
that show up with some kindness maybe to demonstrate what it looks like to be kind to ourselves to not always be
berating ourselves sometimes people get together and they that's kind of what they talk about is they're berating
themselves in some kind of way oh I didn't do this I should have and something like that there's nothing
wrong with sharing the difficulties in your life but is there a way that
folded into that can be this quality of care
quality of warmth and so this commitment shows up in the
of course how we Act on the things that we say
and the things that we think body speech and mind
and so of course the things that we think think about others think about ourselves
I think maybe it's obvious things that we act we don't do unkind things
even when we're driving there have been times that when I've been driving and you know somebody is uh
like drifting into my lane and I don't have anywhere else to go and I just can feel like you know what I feel like oh I
just you know I hit the horn but I I just feel like this Rush of uh fear maybe I don't know what it is but
I'm not feeling kind I'm feeling maybe afraid at that moment but
if we recognize okay this is what humans do humans make mistakes humans aren't
perfect maybe if we make this commitment to kindness doesn't mean that we will always be kind
it's something about in the same way with our meditation practices we set the intention to be with the sensations of
breathing and that really highlights what the Mind does we notice oh yeah the Mind likes to
do anything except be with the breath we should come back to the breath be elsewhere come back to the breath in the
same way this commitment to kindness kind of highlights everything that isn't kind
in our lives kind of shows up the way that we might think about ourselves and think about
others and of course the right speech-wise
speech includes this idea of you know we say things that are truthful a beneficial timely and kind
and sometimes to be kind and timely goes together sometimes we don't say things right then
because we know the person is really sensitive or they're in a place of trying to work things out and they just
aren't in a place where they could hear something new or hear something different
but I'd like to share a poem that was inspired by kindness
and this poem it's written by Naomi shihab Nai who's a fabulous poet and she grew up in
Texas and Jerusalem and Palestine three really different places
you know with a lot of different cultural influences and
she went on her honeymoon she went down to South America and she she and her bus her she and her
husband were on a bus taking a bus ride down there and the bus was attacked and
robbed everybody was robbed and one of the passengers died in the with this robbery so they're on
their honeymoon and this terrible event happens
so afterwards a kind stranger helped them
and her husband hitched hiked back to a nearby City to get Travelers checks
because they didn't have anything and it's Naomi she had knives she was waiting for her husband to come back she
wrote this poem so she's a poet and I guess this is what poets do when they're in distress but
maybe you've been touched by some kindness so this poem is called kindness
and it goes like this before you know what kindness really is
you must lose things feel the future dissolve in a moment
like salt in a weakened broth what you hold in your hand what you
counted and carefully saved all this must go
so you know how desolate the landscape can be between the regions of kindness
how you ride and ride thinking the bus will never stop the passengers eating Maize and chicken will stare out the
windows forever before you learn the tender gravity of
kindness you must travel where the person in a white Poncho lies dead by
the side of the road you must see how this could be you
how they too were someone who journeyed through the night with plans and the
simple bread that kept them alive before you know kindness as the deepest
thing inside you must know sorrow as the other
deepest thing you must wake up with sorrow you must
speak it to it till your voice catches the threat of all sorrows
and you see the size of the cloth then it is only kindness that makes
sense anymore only kindness that ties your shoes and sends you out into the day to mail
letters and purchase bread only kindness that raises it its head
from the crowd of the world to say it is I you have been looking for
and then goes with you everywhere like a shadow or a friend
this poem is I love it it's powerful in some ways and it has like some ordinary
things like oh yeah before you tie your shoes and male letters and purchase bread or
just you're on the bus thinking you're just like everybody else going to wherever you're going
and then she says so you know how desolate the landscape can be between
the regions of kindness sometimes it's when they're in our
greatest difficulties and the greatest distress is that throws in to highlight some of
the kindnesses that we've had in our lives sometimes we
maybe are taking some of them for granted or not even noticing them
so she starts with saying before you know what kindness really is you must
lose things this idea that the kindness of people to maybe restore
what you thought you had lost and what you really need what's important to you
and she's talking about literally you know money
but there's a way also in which sometimes maybe we felt like we've
feel despair or we can't see how we could solve a particular problem we just
can't find our way forward with it maybe kindness is a way of maybe helping
somebody to see a little bit bigger or to see something that they hadn't seen before
that's maybe a little bit smaller a detail
so this idea before you know what kindness is you must lose things
maybe there's a way in which having a commitment to kindness we have to lose
some of our beliefs our belief systems are thinking that kindness is wimpy or
maybe we have to think lose this idea that only certain people deserve
kindness or maybe we have to lose the idea that I
don't really deserve kindness or maybe we have to lose the idea that
other people won't be kind to us maybe we're expecting the absolute worst
of everybody so we have a chip on our shoulder and people are maybe even frightened of us or don't even want to
talk to us so this commitment to kindness maybe we have to lose
some of the beliefs or ideas or Notions that we have maybe we have to like accept
that's life has good things and bad things it has awful things and beautiful things
and can we accept the reality of the moment
it's like this right now not what I want not what I wished for but it's like this
and there's a way of kindness to ourselves maybe in an abstract way could even say
kindness to reality to stop denying it to stop turning away like actually it's
like this right now I feel awful
sometimes we might even like turn towards experiences maybe we don't feel awful maybe there's just something
that's you know a little bit annoying a sound that's a little bit annoying
when we're trying to meditate don't they no this is my time to meditate why are there those sounds
maybe there's a little bit of a hostility or some disappointment or
aggression or something like this maybe a commitment to kindness is
having this acceptance or this allowance like yeah okay there's even things that
we don't prefer things that show up the way they show up uninvited
or maybe some of this acceptance is part of
due to discouragement when we can't help somebody else in a way that we think
that would be the most helpful or in a way that feels comfortable for us and we feel discouraged
maybe it's a family member somebody really important to us
we can come back to remembering that we can be kind
to ourselves and to them to them and to ourselves and maybe the kindness is just listening
maybe the kindness is not leaving
and having a commitment to kindness requires finding out if can we be strong
and be kind can we be powerful and be kind
is there a way that we can be smart and know actually what's the answers and be
kind I have a
a friend who knows a lot about the computers I I'm I know enough about computers too
but this my friend is really kind except when it comes to computers
this person is like no it's like this and then do that and then click and then oh my gosh don't you know so there's is
there a way in which you can recognize that okay you have a body of knowledge that maybe somebody else doesn't know
but can you share it with kindness instead of impatience or insistence like
why don't you know this gee or something like this so this commitment to kindness can we be
kind to ourselves at the same time being kind to others not having to choose
one or the other but to take the time and maybe the I'm
going like this with my hands because it requires some spaciousness to to lean into and figure out what is kind to both
me and them sometimes we feel like we have to choose
okay well to be kind to them I have to sacrifice what I want or sacrifice ideas
I have my preferences which is true right sometimes we do compromise that's
entirely appropriate but is there a way in which we can feel what's kind for everybody here
and having this commitment to kindness as I mentioned makes you know just recognizing that we won't do it
perfectly of course we want humans make mistakes humans can be
unkind to others we can be unkind to ourselves we don't always know the right thing to do
and we can be impatient and we don't always remember the lessons that we
learned yesterday some of these lessons we have to learn over and over again
and sometimes you know we do have reactions and we just get caught up in them and kindness just isn't available
so having this commitment to kindness means that when we realize that we haven't fulfilled that commitment that
we are kind ourselves when we don't have me maybe meet expectations we've
had for ourselves so can we just recommit
okay yep that wasn't kind okay I'm gonna try this again or I'm
going to keep going I'm not going to abandon this whole idea of having kindness as a North star or a direction
to go and then maybe I'll end with this poem
and the title is on International kindness day so that's how I know there's an international kindness day
that's the title of this poem the poet is Rosemary traumer
and it goes like this kindness went out and got itself a new
engine a twin turbo premium unleaded V6 cylinder engine something with real
oomph something that provides a bit of giddy up when the going gets tough
turns out kindness likes horsepower a lot of horsepower
plus it sprung for a direct fuel injection to maximize its power output
everyone thinks kindness prefers things quiet and calm but kindness is ready for
action ready to Take On The World ready to travel every back road every Highway
every Main Street and get this ever loving show on the road there's a whole
lot of work to do so I kind of like just the playfulness
of this right or sometimes we do I started saying well sometimes we think it's wimpy or sometimes we think it
always has to be calm and quiet but maybe there's a way that you know this power or strength to kindness
so maybe I'll end with that and if you I'll open it up if there's
some questions or comments if anybody has something they'd like to say
and Dan there's a comment in the chat
it's just a quote and it doesn't say where it's from it I assume it's the Buddha it says monks
these two people are hard to find in the world which too the one who is first to do a kindness
and the one who is grateful for a kindness done and feels obligated to
repay it can you say can you read it again
yes monks these two people are hard to find in the world
which two the one who was first to do a kindness and the one who is grateful for a
kindness done and feels obligated to repay it hmm interesting
yeah I'm not familiar with this quote and I'm not sure that would be in the poly Canon but maybe it is I'm not even
sure the word kindness in poly yeah I'm not sure that I know but thank you for the quote
those of you don't know Rich there's people on the other side of that camera that are on YouTube
is anybody have a comment you don't have to of course
okay okay oh you you yes you
when you're talking about the influences when you're young this summer I've been watching many many
Cary Grant movies at the Stanford theater I love it and they're mostly
romantic comedies but as I think about it one of the
qualities that his character is almost all the time have is a certain kindness
and a very strong kindness you know he isn't sort of a milk toast
character by any means in any of the movies but you know he never
um it's sort of mean just for the point of being mean you know so
I think he's been one of my early mentors in kindness from watching all
those movies but that's a fantastic Cary Grant I love this thank you thank you Tim for who is
there any quote that you want to bring from a movie or just in general or just this has approaches kindness yeah in
general I don't want to put you on the spot but I I can't remember one right now
it's great I feel like I want to watch a Cary Grant movie I haven't seen one in ages that's very nice
thank you all and I wish you a good rest of the evening and safe travels home
and if you like you're welcome to come up here and talk to me too thank you