so also welcome welcome folks
um yeah nice to uh nice to see I'm familiar
with a lot of those names very sweet to see you uh in the chat
and um
yeah happy to be with you this week so Let's uh let's do a thing we do
and uh
kind of just take the posture and um trust that the dharma's there waiting
for us
maybe we've sat enough times
contemplated and Dharma
or enough months or years
just taking the posture reminds us of everything
the poignancy of our life
the endlessness suffering in this this realm
strength and fragility of goodness
the miracle and blessing
of this path
and I wasn't feeling all of that five minutes ago
but in seeing your names
taking the posture it's all right here now
let your breathing
remind you of the Dharma
their practice of course is about opening opening to the intensity of this
realm but it's also about
Refuge protecting ourselves from
the intensity
we use these simple ways of
directing attention
the rhythm of our breathing
as a way of taking a kind of uh shelter for the heart momentarily
is a way of putting down the riddle of our life
temporarily
in the world it's a small and as big
as our breath
whenever our mind
goes uh tending
to what we imagine our life is
we just fold that into the breathing
just fold it all back into the breathing it's like we feed it
we feed our thoughts ruminations
anticipation and memory we just feed it all
to our breath
our breath can absorb the body blows of Hope and fear
can subtly
soothe in the unrest of fear anticipation
can settle the leaning forward
excitement agitation of Hope
we put all our hope into this moment
this breath
foreign
language of uh entering entering
dhamma fields
it seems like we're just pointing the uh attentional Spotlight to the sensations
of breathing but more generally we're entering
a field dhamma Dharma field
entering a realm where everything
including our so-called mistakes our Dharma
where everything
reminds us
foreign
okay so uh it's good to uh good to practice
with you uh I sort of realize I kind of assume like
you we all already know how to meditate because I was I don't know what that was
but it's good to know how to meditate and then see what instructions like that
do to the heart so um
everything uh everything is teaching us uh says right famously
everything is teaching us we want to learn from life and
maybe we say implicit in that is that we we neither want to
over learn or under learn from experiences
so over learn when we over learn we make an experience mean too much
this or that experience disproportionately
um shapes our model of the world or model of ourselves
right we know those experiences that have such a deep kind of emotional
resonance a deep impact that we make it means so much
Maybe an experience of fear for example
we can over learn from that we can generalize in ways that are not
justified we make it mean too much about
the rest of our life that experience means too much
there's so much feeling and so much affect so many thoughts
that we endow it with this enormous significance
we can overlearn but we can also under learn under learn
and by under learn what I'm pointing to is the ways we can fail to appreciate
that this experience has implications for everything else
and in our Dharma practice we're sort of weaving and bobbing between over
learning and under learning we're trying to learn
and this this week
um I'll be uh exploring the theme of of mortality
and the ways we can learn from it the ways in where you
can be softened or hardened by it and this is a Zone where
we can over learn or we can under learn
we can endow it with too many meanings or too few
we can on the one hand just appreciate
mortality death is not such a big deal
and uh and we can also appreciate the the depth
of poignancy this life birth death
and so I'm I'm thinking about this um
really because I I sort of always am but uh also I had a death in the family one
month ago and and I've just been watching my heart watching my heart
and um trying to appreciate that the
ordinariness of death you know like at the the funeral
the people the gravediggers who were like very respectful
but they're there having a very different day than everyone else they're planning their day they're coordinating
they're eating their lunch very very ordinary
and and we ought not
make that seem too ordinary or we must not miss its significance we cannot we
ought not under learn the letter um Kafka wrote the meaning of life is
that it stops and
we can interpret that in a kind of very Bleak way that that death blots out all
meaning meaning of life is that it stops
or that
finitude is what makes anything meaningful
immortality obliterates meaning life is Meaningful
because it ends
and so this week he has about death supporting life
informing life teaching us about them the ways that um mortality informs our
practice and I
um you know consider this sacred ground
sacred ground uh I I remember I was 29 years old and I
was doing the the year to live practice Stephen Levine's practice of
you know following a book with a group and living as if it's the last year of
one's life and I was 29 and healthy and I remember telling my neighbor who was
uh uh lived right across right across the hall and she was Holocaust Survivor
entire family was was killed and um and very you know
that was an ever-present reality in our life and I remember she asked me about
the program like what are you doing and that I remember her indignation you
know and when I explained this this practice you know and I remember Sarah saying like
uh you know you weren't there you weren't in the
camps you you don't know you don't play games don't play games
with this question you know and uh
yeah I don't know and I'm trying to understand and uh
ask your understanding we all have our own relationship to this question
and um this is sacred ground
numb old enough now where uh uh
Kaiser is is actively searching for uh for my death
and testing my body each year and this year negative next year
don't know this not negative forever
my um maternal uh paternal grandmother
um paternal grandmother died when my dad was 12 just before his apartment
actually and um and my paternal grandfather
had mental illness and uh often thought he was dying even when
he wasn't and um maybe not an accident that both of their
children studied medicine my dad and uncle
study medicine trying to navigate Master the realm of uh
of illness and birth and death and so
somehow I've always kind of yeah I just felt felt the presence of
death the meaning of it trying not to uh
under learn or over learn from it
and so how can um how can our Dharma practice be informed
by this how can our our wisdom and love be informed
by mortality and I I sometimes
um sometimes say something like uh a good death
Starts Now good death Starts Now
I get that but um I was struck with I I said that
some retreat and this Yogi uh in one of our practice
meetings very thoughtfully kind of pushed back you know
I was so struck by what she said she said like what do you mean by a good dad
and she said that uh very
great mystery you know really equivalent to The Mystery of Life
and uh I took what she said to heart yeah don't know
and so we we respect uh we respect that respect the
the mystery of it all and um
I don't uh I don't know that Dharma or
anything is uh is a kind of perfect perfect consolation
for death for the changingness of of all things that may be the perfect
consolation but uh it's pretty good
pretty good so that's uh that's our theme
for this week uh how uh death can uh
inform our practice and form our samadhi our
Sila sense of self inform our love how death can inform our love
so I'm happy to uh to be with you and uh
exploring this so may uh yeah may we have a good day
and see you um see you tomorrow yeah