foreign welcome
and uh welcome to the start of a new week and a new series
and uh this week's uh topic will be compassion Following last week's topic
on love and in preparation for talking about that
this guided meditation I would like to make the point that
the best forms of compassion arise out of being
well settled in awareness well settled in being mindful
that it's important not to have compassion in the lead
but rather compassion is
awareness is their lead or awareness is the boat that compassion rides
and if we if compassion is in the lead by swimming
it's a lot of work to keep swimming there's not much ability to do much else
but if compassion is supported by awareness then compassion can come to a kind of
fullness so awareness first and then compassion
and so we're here we are to meditate before this topic of compassion so we have
mindfulness first awareness first and perhaps to maybe interest you in
your meditation your awareness for this meditation so you're curious like what is this and
maybe even a little bit of awe of this capacity you have to be aware
the question is how it how is awareness
what is it about the nature of awareness what's the quality the properties of
awareness what are the benefits of awareness that makes it a good support for
compassion think about this so much but enter into the world of mindfulness
the world of awareness really stay close to it and in the process of it you might
discover some of the answers to this maybe you'll Discover it after the meditation
so assuming a meditative posture
and as I like to say lately is that it's a posture that is unobstructed
that nothing within us is
crunched up or blocked or held in check or
that's a posture that allows a feeling of openness in the body and it's a posture that allows
for a deep relaxation and the combination of unobstructed flow
of life within us and a deep relaxation go hand in hand
that which flows unobstructedly the way they were animated
is what brings wakefulness alertness
relaxation keeps everything calm
non-reactive quiet
and together they make a wonderful partner partnership
gently closing your eyes and feeling sensing
this posture of yours this body of yours
as if all you need to do is to discover how it is right now
no need to judge it or be disappointed or
try to fix it just become aware of this body
and awareness at all his borders aren't being permissive just allowing it to be there and you
discovering
and then to
take some gentle deep breaths
maybe three quarters as deep as you can breathe
and exhaling longer than you normally would
Maybe a quarter longer than usual
and as you exhale the longer exhale let there be a quieting of the thinking
mind
especially as you get to the end of the exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and to continue relaxing the body
maybe with each exhale
and then letting yourself breathe normally
settling yourself into breathing
almost as if your whole body can settle into the sensations of your
body breathing them the movements of the body the expansions and contractions
maybe even settling into the belly soft belly
where the softness of the belly varies as you breathe in and breathe out
and then sitting here quietly aware of your present moment experience
oh where in a kind of Silent Way
without discursive thought without conversations in your head or
story images with your eyes
where you're aware of it all including the thinking
awareness that's independent
of everything
it knows it's mindful
without being for or against
without being identified or defined
by what it's aware of
foreign
mindful not thoughtful
after meditating these minutes still quiet with the eyes closed
what has happened to you in the course of the meditation
are you a little calmer
do you feel more aware or sensitive to
your experience Here and Now
might you be a bit softer predisposed to be kinder
might you be more aware than usual of
how involved you are in thinking and reacting to things
whatever way you are it's okay
but is there a way that how you are now
can be a support for compassion
compassion for yourself compassion for others
is there any way that you can build
on how you are at the end of The Meditation
to have more compassion for yourself for the world
how does meditation support compassion
both on its own in some way that we
consciously use the meditative experience
to support compassion
and then coming to the end of the sitting
to open your hearts your minds to the world around you
and to consider how you can live this day
with greater kindness and greater compassion
greater care for others
may it be that this meditation we've done today serves for the welfare and happiness of
others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
male beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so with this talk I begin a five part series on compassion
and compassion is one of the wonderful capacities that human beings have
and probably it's a capacity which is underutilized maybe even underappreciated
and um they can make the central or be the central organizing principle for a human
life what gives a life purpose meaning Direction
um support inspiration and that's certainly been true for me
and I think for a good part of my adult life that compassion was a central organizing
principle that I set my direction of my life based on compassion for the
suffering of the world and whether that's still the case
um is maybe a matter of kind of subtlety
that I don't know if it's still Compassion or something that's kind of almost the same as compassions
things change and morph over time and and now maybe the central principle is
why what I call care but the that somehow is I don't know a little
different than compassion but compassion and um the simplest definition of
compassion is um being um sensitive
to the suffering of usually others sensitive to the suffering of others in
such a way that we have the aspiration the wish
the desire to alleviate that suffering
so those two things sensitive they're suffering and the
desire to alleviate it and those when it's when it's compassion
the Buddhists can put focus on compassion it's not an obligation it's not
something we should be doing we might want to do it but it's but it's
meant to be something that Wells up within we talk about being compassionate but
when some people hear the idea that we should be compassionate uh they interpret the B part as do we
should do compassion and and it's very profound this idea
that we be compassion rather than we do compassion because with the idea of being
compassionate that's something that Wells up that something just kind of oozes out of us or kind of there for us
it's not something that we have to make happen or act in a certain way
so the but this way of being is a is a profound possibility
that has different characteristics and qualities and the uh and uh so in this week I'm
going to talk about five different characteristics or aspects of compassion only the fifth which is action
meaning that for this being compassionate there's a whole slew of
ways of being in ourselves that sets a stage for compassionate action
and without those prep that preparation without that Foundation then a compassionate action might not be
compassionate it might be actively involved with alleviating suffering but
it could be done with anger it could be done with distress to get done with a
sense of strain and stress and tension and it can be done in a way that that it
can be exhausting or stressful or worse for people
but how is it that compassion can be enacted and acted on without it being
exhausting without it diminishing us so that the compassion is
sweet there's a there's a beauty and a kind of profound beautiful pleasure
that comes along in Us in the compassionate action
um so for that to happen four other things uh kind of would be good to
gather together and have as part of it so the four the five things I'll be
talking about today all start with a so maybe that's helpful for remembering
and uh so today I want to talk about awareness tomorrow Attunement
a little different than it may be empathy but Attunement to others
and then appreciation and then aspiration
and then action so awareness Attunement
appreciation aspiration and action
so those first four then support the action and so to be grounded in those or have
those developed in us and or practice in us then the compassionate action is well
supported as kind of has a chance to be a beautiful thing a profound thing that
we're just glad to have it to feel it there's not necessarily any distress
with it so uh it begins with awareness
mindfulness attention and
and here there's a kind of very important point I want to make about awareness practice or having a strong
presence of attention awareness mindfulness and that is that uh we're not leaning
into things we're not sinking into things but there's a kind of autonomy maybe not
in ourselves in all the ways but there's an autonomy in being aware
there's a capacity to be attentive without being entangled or caught or
reactive to what is happening it maybe it would be a little bit like being at a gathering of people who are
maybe they're you know having an angry shouting match between each other maybe
they're um I don't know what being really afraid
and running around kind of not knowing what to do and you stand in the middle of them and
you care for them you're supporting them friend of them but it's clear that you've kind of like you're not in the
quicksand with them you're not kind of involved with the anger and caught up in
the fear but your presence it's a little bit like you're been
standing on a stool maybe Above The Fray looking down that it all kind of amazed
what's going on here this is quite something an experience my first experience of
this possibility that was kind of an inkling a glimpse that made a big difference for me
was my second year in college I guess I was 19 or so we were living in US my four other
guys and I were living in a apartment three-bedroom apartment
and uh with a balcony sliding door to the living room and I was out on the balcony with a
sliding door closed and two of my roommates were on the couch the living room having an animated conversation
and all I could see was their gestures and animation I couldn't hear the words
and and not knowing what they were talking about but just watching how animated they were I could feel that was
present and attentive but there was no entanglement I wasn't caught in what they were saying it was like I was
autonomous I was free I was available I was there and that experience of being
aware of people actively kind of having an animated
conversation in my being free of it was that was the first Glimpse I had of that
possibility this is not the same thing as aloof this is not the same thing as being
removed or indifferent it's just that we might have all kinds of feelings and
connections to them attunements and aspirations and interest in them but there's a way in which the awareness
is calm is peaceful it's not ruffled or agitated is not leaning into and one way
that the awareness gets mixed up to and identified with what's happening is when
the awareness is pulled in to the thoughts we're having the
discursive thoughts and and it's almost as if we identify we
become the discursive thoughts and the awareness then is happening through through the filter of those discursive
thoughts or we get caught up in the emotions and feelings we have and the awareness gets
kind of channeled through those in order to be aware of the world and um and with a clear awareness
awareness is its own thing it's a um it's a kind of a when it's
really kind of strong it's there's a clarity that it's above The Fray or step back
from being entangled or it's just there present very present there but is the
upright then autonomous clear open available not identified by anything not
caught by likes and dislikes it knows that like likes and dislikes it knows
discursive thinking but it's not those things to cultivate this kind of a kind of
sense of autonomy in the awareness itself is very very important for compassion
because then compassion has a channel from which to be clean
a Channel with which not to be entangled not to be reactive not to be mixed up
with the whole range of emotions that might be coming not mixed up with all the story making of the Mind discursive
thinking and beliefs and judgments that we might have and um
and uh so the um so it kind of creates a
context and a foundation for being compassionate without that if there's a headlong rush
into being compassionate then awareness gets pulled along we're
not so present and attentive to what we're doing that whatever little awareness is present is being being
hijacked or being mixed up with our reactivity our sense
of Duty our sense of alarm our sense of being in a hurry our sense of um
requirement obligation our sense of distress all kinds of things come along
if awareness is not autonomous if awareness has this kind of upright
autonomy where it's standing on its own two feet and is not being pushed around by The Winds of life
then there's a lots of room for some of the deeper Wellsprings of of our the
best qualities we have to flow into that space but if awareness has been hijacked and
is caught up and not quite there then these deeper qualities are not as easily
available so awareness mindfulness attention to
really learn it develop it being grounded it have faith in it if someone
if you hear the idea the you should be more compassionate I would propose that the best way to
interpret that or take that on is don't be compassionate Begin by slowing down
standing straight and tall and being metaphorically and just being aware and
see if you can find that place where awareness is autonomous
or free kind of like Lotus blossoming above the
Muddy Waters so
the healthy foundation for compassion begins
with awareness and with that kind of autonomous
awareness then we're ready for the Attunement with someone else
that Attunement to their suffering and what that means I'll talk about tomorrow and so what I'd like to recommend if
you're interested in some an exercise for the next 24 hours
is when you're it's in some situation where maybe where nothing's really
required for you to do anything but you're aware of someone else's suffering
see what you can see what you can discover about an autonomous awareness
being really present for the person for the situation not removed not
aloof but to really kind of
open to the situation with clear awareness but where the awareness is autonomous
where the awareness is not entangled or caught up in the situation
to them again so the best situation options for this to doing this is a
situation where you're not going to be acting to help someone do something
um it's some situation you know in the public where you you see something that's someone's suffering but there's other
people helping you're not going to help or you read about someone in the news or something
so um thank you