so hello everyone nice to have you
here so begin with this talk with uh evoking
a simple maybe obvious idea that our lives are often
challenging that being a human being is challenging in so many different ways small ways every day and big
ways existential ways and sooner or later in life and um and then how do we respond
to those challenges and there are two ways that I'd like to
suggest uh one is a way that uh closes
possibilities that we narrow our Focus close down and the other way is we open
possibilities we create more possibilities we're open to things being different
one way uh closes our minds our hearts another way opens it one
way um um kind of uh Marshalls more
self-centeredness in the process that it kind of supports self-centeredness and
the other one supports kind of a a decrease in self-centeredness so there's
some other way of being in the world that's much more satisfying than
that and for these uh division between these two different ways I want to talk
about the hindrances and what I call their near
opposites or near friends to use kind of a Buddhist terminology and for those of you who
don't know the hindrances are very common teachings in the inside tradition World in
Buddhism and um people who want to develop this the Insight practice that
we teach and um you're supposed to become an expert on the hindrances uh this you know there's a
lot of things you know that these are really the primary considered to be some of the primary forces in the mind that
you want to be mindful of because they're the forces that um hinder
mindfulness and the principle is the more you can become aware of what hinders your ability to be present in a
clear open way the EAS e it is to be open in a clear open way rather than
running away from the challenges to being present we want to be present for
the CH very challenges of being present so that we can work through them or not have them be such
challenges and the five hindrances uh I'll give you a list in a few minutes is
are one of the primary strategies uh that people have that um
to cope with the human challenges in unuseful
ways and it's helpful to see them as strategies rather than just kind of innate things that how we are that we're
challenged and we kind of try to react to it in a way and the then there's the opposite of
the hindrances and there's many opposites we can call them the near opposites or the near friends are those
that resemble the very problem that we're addressing so things that resemble the hindrances
but are doing are not the hindrances they take us in the opposite direction and so it's easy to confuse the two or
to think that these near Friends of the hindrances are also hindrances we're supposed to kind of not have but if we
can appreciate that there's something that's very closely related that uh is actually has a very different effect on
us then we can maybe it's easier to kind of slide over from the hindrances to the
the near friends or it's easier to kind of just kind of feel our way maybe both are existing together sometimes and we
can find the beneficial one and avoid the one that is not so
beneficial so the five hindrances to give the simplest version of the list is
sensual desire uh ill
will and ill will and then um uh rigid I
call it rigidity and then
restlessness and doubt so we'll go into those a little bit more and um their
near friends the near friend of sensual desire is um uh is kind of a healthy
desire a wish that I'll talk more about there are healthy Desires in Buddhism
and sometimes the popular idea of Buddhism is that uh it teaches that
desires are the cause of suffering and so get rid of all your desires and uh this is not
possible U maybe not without becoming
seriously psychologically troubled the um and so there are healthy
desires the opposite their near friend of um of ill will
uh many people immediately go to Goodwill but that's kind of like the far opposite the near opposite of it is to
avoid because uh uh sometimes the ill will is called
aversion and um and so but there is healthy averting and so much so that one
Buddhist teacher I know in America has complained to us people like me you guys
are using the word aversion but aversion is good sometimes and then I've argued
back or say say no no in the English the way we speak use the word aversion has always as negative that's just the way
we use it it's it's a kind of a hostility little kind of like don't like something you're pushing something away
and he said no no it just means to turn away and so Latin means to turn away so
avert you avert yourself sometimes in a good way so but avoid so there's ill
will and then there's healthy avoiding of things that don't doesn't involve any
hostility there is this rigidity and uh and the opposite is a
relaxation rest becoming still without being rigid becoming still by relaxing
deeply and then there's uh restlessness and um and the opposite the
near enemy of that near friend of that is uh to be um en life
Vitality to be vitalized and those are good things to be have a sense of
wonderful calm but engaged flowing vitality and
um without being restless and then the opposite of
Doubt is questioning to question things to have
inquiring mind so so we find our way and to kind
of feel their way what's the difference between these two and as we Fe recognize we have the hindrances
operating uh and their strategies to somehow cope with unhel strategies of
coping with some challenge we can ask ourselves what is the way of coping with
a challenge that doesn't close us down that opens us up to possibilities that
opens up the mind that doesn't overwhelm us doesn't have us kind of
um yeah so so um um so the first one and so sensual
desire that is uh it's can be so strong sometimes that we can call it sensual
hunger uh or thirsting for things and uh and we know that some people are
addicted to what could be called Pleasures uh and it makes a huge it's a
huge cost to people's lives to their families to their friends to their careers when the addictive approach to
sensual desires takes over but even way short of that people can spend an
inordinate amount of time being uh attached to comfort and seeking comfort
in as a way of of Solace as a way of uh feeling stressed feeling troubled by
challenged by something and then using Comfort to not address the issue but rather to get away from it rather to
somehow you know one of my strategies that uh in my life that doesn't serve me
very well I call it the ostrich approach and so sometimes when things
are really challenging I kind of pull in and kind of get really quiet
and kind of like get involved in something and I just not notice the problem just like it's going to go away
it doesn't work so you never see me that way just G Gill you don't have to be an ostrich
right now so this idea of you know so but Comfort is one of those ways
where some people eating a lot maybe or some people I've known people who um
watch uh I keep wanting to say TV who has a TV
anymore uh but they um you know to watch Netflix or watch a movie or something or
YouTube or something and um and they um
and now people can tell me you know I just like I binged watched and I just feel awful you know really feel bad stay up
late and uh and just you know just just kind of it it can drain one's Vitality to spend
too much too time too much time watching something on the screens but you know to be Comfort to
avoid some kind of chall we have the near friend of this is a
healthy desire but in particular one that I think is fascinating to think about that I learned from Zen practice
is uh has to do with uh the request and um and Zen they had the the
question what is what is a situation what is it what's being requested of me
right now so rather than being self asserting oneself what do I want here
what do I need here and Zen the question is what's the request of me from reality
so any circumstance and it was sometimes it was just a small thing like if you
had to put away a book that you were looking at I of people have books but
TVs books but um if you want to put away your shoes let's say
that um and uh and so you um the
question would be uh what's the request of the shoes or what's the request of the shoe rack and that's a way of
breaking through kind of like just doesn't matter you know or I'm just going to put it anywhere I damn please
or you know and so but actually what's the request and you look at the shoe rack and you look at your shoes and you
look at who's coming and you say well if I put them over a little bit to the right there's a little more space for
more people who are coming that's the request of the moment so what's the request what what's being asked of me um
some people that what's being request what what we do that's beautiful what's the what's the thing that shows a kind
of mindfulness in what we're doing so that it spreads out from us to others because things are taken care of in a
way that supports other people to be present in a caring way to whatever they
do and so um uh I saw this with shx you know it's
interesting to study Buddhism if you if you do a sociological study of different cultures of Buddhism by how the
different uh places treat their shoes it's fascinating there are some places where
uh the shoes are just fanned out in front of the entryway and you have to kind of step over them to get to the you
know you put your shoes on the far end of the Fanning in other places like in Zen Japanese Zen where it's just so
orderly um that was really valuable for me to when I went into Zen Japanese
anden Buddhism was uh I learned to Delight in how I put
my shoes on the shoe rack it was like oh do this with care like this is important
as opposed to this is you know I have more important things to do than put my shoes on the shoe rack in Zen everything
is important and to learn this kind of presence okay here so what's the request
here is what they say in Zen but to turn that around and you can also say what is
your request of reality rather than what is your desire what's the heart's request is there something
that if you take time to ask yourself what's what do what do I really want right now what's the request and I love
I love uh language you know words and atmology so request the spiritual
Quest the quest what's your life Quest what's your spiritual Quest and now what
is the request what's the deeper Quest here in this situation now and um what
do you really most want from the situation as opposed to censal desire so
if we have a sensal desire for something say we want to have sensual we have desire for comfort
food and we stand in front of the cabinets or the refrigerator and you
stop and say what's the request right now what is my deeper Quest how does this what I'm doing right now tie into
the deeper Quest purpose that I have for my life um what's my heart's deep deeper
request than simply Comfort to take that time and ask that question maybe you'll
see there's a different desire uh I've done that sometimes and said oh I don't need to do this but it
would be nice to meditate right now because that's a deep request that really Taps into something for me very
deep inside with with it with a deeper sense of Integrity than just having more
chips that uh so here just sit and be present here so what's the request so the near
friend of sensual desire is this deeper desire the
quest so then there's uh ill will aversion in some schools of
Buddhism and that always has a quality of hostility in it and um and some even
though can quite mild annoyance with things and uh this always closes down
the heart always closes the mind when there were caught in ill will and um and it's always a kind of reinforcement of
self-centeredness if if you know but to to avert to avoid things which are
unhealthy that doesn't have to be self-centered that can be actually the opposite so for example to avoid the
tendency to be hostile to feel you have ill will towards whoever comes along um
and you say you know I think I'm going to be careful today maybe I'll go for a walk around the block before I go to
this meeting where I'm just angry at everyone so we're averting
avoiding how we're feeling not just going along like usual and and trying to
find another way that's not hostile so there is a healthy way of saying not
this not now let me stop doing this let me turn away from this kind of thing and
some of us do that regularly in meditation I've I go to um you know I we're sitting
here meditating and after a while you're tracking a little bit noticing what you're thinking about in meditation kind
of distracted thoughts and so you know I don't need to think about that anymore this is not the
time and place for this uh and so there can be hostility to that angry with
yourself for having one more distracted thought but that doesn't help you to do
that that kind of creates more self-centeredness because it's about me not liking something me being the wrong
doing the wrong thing but if it's instead you say you know this is not useful what is the request now or the
request is to open up in some deep way to my experience here and now and for
that for that purpose let me stop thinking about these things let me avoid
it let me avert myself attention from those thoughts to being here with this
deeper request this deeper intention we might have and this is where the first
uh thing request this deeper desire comes back over and over again to support us because if we know we have a
deeper desire deeper quest of what our life is about then it's easier to avert from
things that don't serve us oh let's come back back to the request that's the Deep
spiritual Quest something that we have and then the third hindrance is
usually uh classically described as sloth and torper and um and some people love this
word sloth I I noticed that because I I I've been avoiding the I've come up with a
different translation for the the original poly but some people have protested to me because I guess that's
cute SL or or or they like to do things slow or
you know the kind of sloths AR inspiring for people who are always hectic and running around and so so you're welcome
to keep sloth if you're one of those people but um these are these whatever
it is they are ways of shutting down they're ways of resistance there's a
challenge and we shut down it's a challenge and we um are closing down
we're not open to to being present we're not vitalized and and engaged and and
you know um enlivened in a good way the opposite happens and um and uh you know
and it's classic for children to do this if they don't like what's going on and
oh I'm so tired and it's amazing how quickly they can switch that over to be fully
energized I mean just like in a moment's notice all you have to do is say ice cream and you know and they have all the energy
they need but you know oh it's so difficult I'm so tired and um but adults
do this too as a strategy is it's kind of sometimes if we're overwhelmed if
we're deeply bored if it's our our self-centeredness is not being supported
that there's a shutting down a quieting down a closing down that goes on in the
extreme version It's I like the word the classic word is not in meaning of the
classic po word um Mida is not is um
that is literally means rigidity and this works really well for one of the one of the ways we really
shut down that based on fear the freeze Instinct that we have and uh and this is
one of the really great challenges for people who go around with chronic builtup anxiety they shut down they
freeze in certain situations and um it is necessarily that because
the mountain line has come in um the one of the earliest memories I have of really freezing and kind of
disassociating in that fear uh was my freshman year in college and everyone in
the English class was required to go see the alone to see the professor in office
hours and that for me was so intimidating uh and uh and I remember
going in there and sitting there opposite the professor and the
and I I had such a complete feeling of Disappearing sowh is this person looking
at the wall because I wasn't there and uh that's the last thing I was aware of
before I was aware of walking down the hallway and what happened between having that feeling question why is this person
looking at the wall and may be walking down the hallway I have no idea I just
kind of disassociated and it was because I was for me that was so anx anxiety produced in to be in front of this
authority figure when I was 18 and
um and uh so this freezing this rigidity that goes on and this is not healthy for
us to do because it's all kinds of terrible things can happen in that disassociated rigid
State and uh and then there's also lethargy this is the kind of kids kids strategy and oh it's so hard I'm so
tired we we kind of get heavy and resistant by being tired and sleepy and
not a few people end up sleeping in meditation U one of the reasons for that is because there's too many too much
difficult material coming up strong emotions begin opening up meditation is not
a a straight route to becoming calm and happy and meditation is a straight route
to discovering straight a straight route to disc meeting yourself discovering who
you are and that's not always good news and uh but it's but it's real
news and if you really want to meet yourself in a productive and useful way
Med mindfulness is the way to do that and that's and but the the benefit of
that is if you're really meet yourself deeply even to the most challenging things in the middle of that ask what's
the request here what's being requested of me in these
challenges what is my heart request give given that I have these challenges and so when you have deep
fear deep anger deep grief deep sadness what is the request what's the deepest
request is uh is always useful so then um um you know so the
opposite of you know this um rigidity and lethargy is to have Vitality is to
be enlivened and this is something that can become slowly second nature if you
ask yourself the question what is the posture that I should take now that is a little bit more lively a little bit more
engaged has more energy to it that feels good sitting in a chair i' I can easily
sit in a couch and with such a uh slouching in such a kind of way that it
actually begins draining my energy and I can also capable of sitting sitting away from not use the backr sitting upright
and I can feel there's more energy here I feel more alive and good how do you
walk I'm easily Poss I can easily walk kind of me feeling sorry for
myself and it's I walk kind of slow and kind of like doesn't doesn't feel good I
could also pick up the pace and it feels like oh now I'm engaged nicely there's a more sense of Engagement and vitality it
doesn't take so much to shift little bit to choose where the Vitality is where's
the vit where where there where's their Vitality right now and um and this can be a great
antidote to um to um no no I'm I'm confusing that
that oh I'm so sorry to tell you this I'm I'm I'm confusing the pairings so so
lethargy and um and uh and rigidity the opposite of
that the near enemy of that is rest and relaxation what needs to be rest and
relaxed right here and um so both of them involve a
Stillness a quieting but there's a healthy one and an unhealthy one now we get to the other one so make
up F this so um so the um uh the hindrance is
um restlessness and classic language is restlessness and
regrets they both have the effect of creating agitation and this is why they're together here and so we can
become so agitated by all kinds of reasons um
frustration we can get agitated because we have unfulfilled desires we can agitate because we have unexpressed
hostility that we just don't know what to do with we can be restless because um
we have a lot of self remorse and self-criticism uh uncertainty about
ourselves we can be restless and agitated because of what we've done and will people find out what we've done and
will we be blamed and will people not like us and and so it's uh kind of U
sometimes anxiety produced uh the anxi the agitation we live
with the near enemy or the near friend of uh this kind of agitation that's a
healthy in Vitality there is a kind of energy which is strong that we can live with that's I
call Vitality or being feeling physically enlivened and this is what I'm proposing
is that we can do a lot of small things through the day choosing H how to be present for
something in a way that's enlightening ing or not enlivening and if you're standing in
line at at a supermarket uh you might just stand there and just judge what other people
are buying or how quickly the clerk is you know doing the checkout or look at the
magazines or wonder about you know which of these Like These are nice all these chocolates they're selling here and you
know and think I want chocolate that's one option but what is what would be if feel like a nice clear
sense of physical and vitality standing here oh if I stand on both feet if I
kind of sit in St stand facing a certain way maybe I don't need to be looking at everything around me and losing track of
myself maybe I can sit up a little stand up a little bit stronger a little bit
straighter and they're just not that anyone has to notice dramatically but there's vitality and there's presence
there's attention and ask yourself the question while you're looking at the
national Inquirer ask your question what is your heart's deepest
request and probably you'll bat it away that question but ask the question what is your deepest request when you're
standing upright straight present in a nice way and then you might get a deep
answer right there in the supermarket who would have believed and then we come to the the
last these doubt and remember doubt here as a hindrance is always something which
closes us down so always involves some kind of narrowing of attention some kind
of um um narrowing possibilities it involves in uncertainty
indecisiveness um and confusion about what to do the near friend of it that can look
like that is healthy doubt a healthy questioning a what's going on here in uh
inquisitiveness let me take it deeper look here let me find out what's happening here I'm sure i'msure what's
what this is about I'm unsure what I want I'm unsure of things but let's now
reflect on this and consider and and then you can ask the question again
given my heart's deepest request what perspective does that
give with what I have doubts about or uncertainty about does that offer some
clarity and one of the clarities about the deepest request question is that you
might not have an answer to what you're uncertain about what you have some questions
about but you might have some answer about how you want to be in relationship
to it you want to be in relationship to the the challenge you have with presence with
attention with uprightness turning towards the challenge you
have rather than being pushed around by or caught up in the agitation of Doubt
of uncertainty of indecisiveness and so in this
mindfulness practice a lot of it comes down to how do you want to show up for
your life how do you want to be present what kind of attention do you want to bring to
your whatever you're doing and that those questions are
relating to every time we're involved in something that's a challenge how do I
want to be now with this challenge all too often we have some
serious Challenge and the old operating systems kick in operating princip
principles kick in the habits kick in I want to look for something pleasant
instead I want to blame someone I want to shut
down I just I don't know if I want to but I just kind of running around like a chicken without its
head or I'm just filled with indecisiveness these are all
optional we don't have to believe these hindrances this way of being we don't
have to prioritize them we don't have to uh think that they're true to be this
way because they all represent ways that we are being not true decisions
understandings of how reality is how situations are they're the response
within us and these are responses the hindrance of responses that close down
the range of possibilities we have in responding and if we'd have a smaller
range of possible ideas of how to respond or possible possibilities
available that can make the whole thing even more challenging and can reinforce the very
strength of the hindrances but if we can come into a a way of being that opens up the field of
possibilities that can give us a lot more confidence that can a lot more
creativity then we can move in a different direction and one of the ways we do that with mindfulness practice is
how we show up and to show up asking the question
what is the request here the request of the situation the request of my heart
what's a deeper request that I have that this is part of what is it that would be healthy to
stop doing so I can know better what is healthy to
do what is it that needs to um relax
here maybe it's the ill will maybe it's essensual desire the tension of that
what is it that needs to rest what kind of wrist bite do I
need rest relaxation is an important part of human life and a lot of people
in our culture here locally don't get enough and then uh what you know in what
way do I want to um be vitalized be
enlivened by this life show up in a way that I feel energized in a good way I don't know what to do the situation is
difficult but at least I'm sitting in a way that feels Lively I'm not going to give up my my
uprightness my sense of Vitality which we often give up I've
give I've seen myself give it give up so subconsciously you don't even know I'm doing it oh
oh the computer is not working oh not
again I don't know how it works and I don't even know that I'm
doing it but you know oh look the computer's not
working look at that I'm I'm being given another
opportunity to sit up straight and then um
so what's the what's the what's the what what's the inquisitiveness the
Curiosity the questioning we can have that opens the field and one question
for that is what am I not seeing here what am I
overlooking I don't know what's happening here I don't know what to decide to do but am I missing something
are there more possibilities here so hindrances are an important part
of our practice studying them getting to know them and as we study them in our
practice then we can also then know we have these things that look like them
that I'm calling the near friends that uh are our friends these kind of the
opposite ways of being and they make the whole study of the hindrances I think more interesting to have something close
by that can get offer you an alternative so maybe the hegemony of the hindrances
kind decreased a little bit and um so next time you find
yourself in a personal challenge take the opportunity to kind of pause and ask
yourself which hindrance is operating here and what alternative is there rather than to give to live with
this hindrance operating and interfering with all the possible ways of
responding so thank you so those are my thoughts on this topic and uh so we do
have the potluck lunch today it usually happens at the last Sunday of the month
and uh we have about you know eight seven minutes left eight minutes before
the usual time we end so everyone's welcome to stay for the potluck whether
you brought something or not it's just a nice way to hang out it's an excuse to hang out with each other so don't don't
feel like you have to have brought something and um some of us will have
tables here sometimes are tables set up outside too yeah so there's tables outside as well they can eat
outside and um but because if it's a puthu and it's nice to kind of meet people say hello and if especially if
you've never been here um if you if you're willing to stay for a few minutes you're welcome to leave if you prefer
but uh just a turn to maybe two people next to you and look around make sure no one's left out that way and just look
around and say hello say hello and introduce yourself and maybe you have one or two things that were interest
interesting for you from this talk you'd like to share with your new friend and then in about five minutes there'll
probably be a bell or something for the puck thank you