e
e [Music]
good morning and again welcome come to IMC good morning
Gil so I have an announcement to make the um some years ago uh there was
a group of people at IMC who formed a subgroup called U the Earth Care Group
is it louder not is that good should be louder it feels a little louder and here already oh it's too loud
here yeah so is this okay for still it feels a little loud there's a ringing going
on so let's see I was going to try to turn up the volume over there do we still hear the
ringing so a little bit lower still so how's that now is that good
now okay so there is a hearing system devices if this is uh not loud enough
okay good now great so the earthcare group um started
to kind of have a group people focused on how in our Buddhist practice we could
care for the Earth for the environment for this world of climate change and
climate crisis and uh over the years that's grown and I just learned recently that uh they're they're doing some
really wonderful things sometimes which is um kind of a speaker series they have a monthly meeting and
sometimes those monthly meetings now on Zoom they invite some pretty interesting people who are doing this kind of Earth
care kind of work and on the end of the month last Saturday the October 28th
they're going to have there's these children in Montana I think it is they're called children um who have are
suing the state for uh you know for climate reasons and U it's kind of made national
news well they're going to come to the earthcare group to to talk about what they're doing so that was pretty cool I
thought so I thought maybe some of you'd like to know and so the information is on the imc's calendar under the Earth
Care on that Saturday and probably a zoom link there and so and they're
they'll do other kind of they do they invite other interesting people to come and speak as well so um yes there's also
a flyer the for the 28th October 28th event so if you have your phone if you can take a
picture is there I just put a few copies out yeah so in case you didn't hear so
there's a flyer about this event on October 28th that uh there's only a few copies so take a
picture so um
okay so I'm going to tell you a tale about a monk and
um and I want to dedicate the tale to a wonderful monk that I met many years ago
named Yanda and uh he was the the the monk
responsible for the Burmese temple in back then back in Daily City eventually
he moved down and built the temple that's now in um just south of Half Moon Bay and back then um uh the so the soc
called Temple was just a small house in Daily City kind a regular looking house in Daily City
and and um and when I was going to um go
to practice in Burma I heard about this Monk and so I went to to um I called him
up and said can I come visit you and he said sure So I think I took some bus and
walked some way into the neighborhood into the neighborhood and I knocked on the door the and he he answered the door
and the remarkable thing about how he received me I immediately felt like I'd
been his friend for decades like we were like he was like we were like old friend
old friends was the best way I could describe how he received me he never met me and he brought me in and we sat and
talked and it was the the kindness and warmth and friendship and friendliness
that he offered was kind of standing given that We Were Strangers so the tale is dedicated to
yil andand and hopefully he will proof so there was this monk Buddhist
monk who was traveling around and he came to a town where um there had never
been any Buddhists there before people kind of hardly knew what Buddhism Buddhism was and he stayed there for
some for some while some days and and the people in the town kind of liked him
and he seemed to be remarkably calm and peaceful and U people felt really safe
with him and so actually some people started telling them telling him their life story what was going on with them
their challenges and it was just so nice and he didn't seem to have a lot to tell
them but they left those encounters with him kind of changed just because he was
so so friendly and kind and receptive to
what they had to to say so that was nice and uh so then a
local professor of religion heard about the Monk and I was interested in Buddhism what is this Buddhism never met
the Buddhist before and so there was a chance maybe to learn something about Buddhism so she came to visit him and
um and uh you know she wanted to find out what Buddhism is so she asked maybe
for her what seemed like the obvious questions she asked him what do you
believe and he answered long ago I believed but now I
act she was a little confused by this answer doesn't all religions have
beliefs and couldn't he just have told her so she asked again a different way
what teachings do you rely on long ago I relied on
teachings now I rely on what I
know what but of course he was a Buddhist monk right so she let's try
again aren't you devoted to the Buddha because the follower of the Buddha right
and aren't you devoted to the Buddha long ago
I was devoted to the Buddha but now I am devoted to
nonharming but what do you have faith in she said
us trying again all the ways in which he understood what religion is what do you have faith
in I don't have faith I have confidence in nonharming
action but but what is your ultimate
truth the end of doing harm ended doing any harm to myself or
to others but but
but this is nothing like religion in her mind but then you're are left with no
desire for Good Life Hereafter many religions that's an important part of their religion but
then are you left with no desire for a good life Hereafter I have no
desire for a life Hereafter I desire a good life now the
rest will take care of itself but but
but what is the good life now a life lived without any deliberate
Act of body speech or mind that harmed self or
others but then she had heard you know in Buddhism you're not supposed to have any desires so she thought she would ask
you know finally ask kind of a Buddhist question she did she was so confused by this
time do you have no desires no I I
desire a world committed to
non-harming and he answered her questions so kindly and calmly
and without any sense that she was wrong or any hostility
or she didn't she was left confused didn't fit any of her ideas of
what religion is but she left transformed in some way way
changed so I offer that tale as a way of
suggesting that Buddhism has a radically different orientation than what most people think
about as religion and that this idea of non-harming lays at the center of what
Buddhism is it maybe as in the ultimate goal to non harm and some people feel
feel feel that's not good enough because religions have ultimate truths ultimate purposes ultimate goals ultimate
experiences of Enlightenment wouldn't that be nice to be enlightened what is
Enlightenment so transformed so fully transformed that a person will have no
deliberate attempts to harm anyone in the world including themselves that's what enlightenment is
but we don't usually say that because I don't think you get so much people don't get so excited by
non-harming you know even if you said you know the ultimate goal is to realize the truth oh that gets that seems pretty
good you know or the ultimate ultimate Enlightenment is to
you know realize the highest possible human realization of of
Liberation you know then I get liberated that's really great isn't it don't you want to be liberated so that's exciting
but to realize nonharming that is a
transformation it is a Liberation it's a Liberation for doing anything at all
that causes harm but but but that's not about
me isn't Enlightenment about something for me well you you you stop causing
harm to yourself isn't that pretty good you know I don't harm myself that
much I just
suffer so then the monk would say well in that case you should look more deeply see
what you're doing because the core teachings of Buddhism it's often called the four
noble truths uh it doesn't have the word harm in it it has the word du which is
usually translated to English as suffering it literally means
pain but um the causes of that suffering the causes of that pain our activities
that what we're focusing on is not what the world does to us but what we do to
ourselves so if the world does something unfortunate to us that's unfortunate and
that we have to do our best to figure out what to do but if because of that we
now want to hate and because that we want to now harm others because of
that in that momentum we're harming ourselves hate always harms the
hater violence intentional violence always harms the one who is violent it
can't not because but they're not often we're not paying attention that way so that's why study yourself see what's
going on deeply and if you go really deep you also see that the suffering that we can
can have some role in changing and transforming is the ones that arise from our own
attachments to cling is to harm ourselves and it's not necessarily an
ethical thing like so often we think of harming others as being unethical but to
um but uh you know being attached is not you know it's not an ethical issue but it is a issue of whether you are happy
or whether you suffer and there's a way in which attachment is the uh is the
root way in which we harm ourselves and chances are it's the root for why we harm
others and so uh so but at the heart what i is the Dharma is this non-harming
Instinct this movement towards this but is it
ultimate shouldn't religion be about ultimate things that uh you know that you can't
really know for yourself but you take it on faith because because it comes from your Scriptures it comes from the Buddha
it comes from your teachers you now I know what's ultimate people involved in religion like ultimate
things and uh and partly it's because people religious people tend to put a
lot of themselves into the religious life there's a kind of a commitment to
something that's maybe bigger than themselves or something other and for that level of a commitment people really
want to know that it's this is really the best this is really good this is
Ultimate in the earliest teachings of the Buddha uh he he he he explicitly was
not interested in having ultimate truths so and now this professor is even
more confused um that that the pursuit of ultimate truth was a
detour what the task was he said was to let go of clinging let go of craving let
go of attachments and uh to have ultimate
truths for some people it's just another attachment it's another detour it's a distraction from doing this deep work
but that's not you know just letting go of my attachments I mean that's kind of like isn't that kind of like a small
thing isn't that like that's not so how can that be so great and wonderful and
ultimate and I don't get real credit among my religious friends when I tell them what
well our ultimate is just letting go of clinging that doesn't seem very
good so so I think the best thing to do is to grant them that that is not that
good it's not that ultimate and uh and
however it's that it might not be ultimate might be the greatest thing you can do with your life
however it's the fundamental thing we should do in our life it's the beginning
of what we should do in our life we should um uh at least live a life of
non-harming at least find a way not to cause harm to oursel and
others at least do that important work our world will be transformed if we did
that we might will be transformed for you do that and once we learn once we
discover how to live without causing harm to self and other once we learn to live without
clinging and craving once we have that level of
Liberation well then if you're still interested in Ultimate truths help
yourself please that's good and maybe you'll have some Wonder wonderful ones
that are inspiring and wonderful and poetic and and uh fun to read about and
listen to and and be amazed by yes but
let's do this first thing and uh and what not a few Buddhists have discovered that doing the
Deep work the inner work uh of becoming free in this
way is pretty ultimate pretty fantastic the love level of Peace the level of
well-being the well level of of safety that that provides is
astounding and uh and on the way to there there starts to be becoming an
appreciation of how difficult and deep this at work is it's a task of a lifetime to really
settle and find and come to what I would like to suggest that what I'd like to believe is a you know a really good
fundamental place for all of us to be all of us to begin begin everything
from the Buddha said that if you cling and you crave you can't really
see what's really true and so if you're in a religion and
you're craving and clinging as part of it it might obscure your ability to really understand even what your
religion is talking about and um and some people will say that once we once and there's not
Buddhism not the only religion that talks about non- clinging nonattachment and um and a lot of the
mystics and Rel and religions of all kinds um the beautiful teachings by a
Catholic Mystic named Mr Master E eart is that his name who uh talked
explicitly about the value of non-attachment non- clinging in ways that completely would be home in
Buddhism and um and uh it's not a surprise because uh
the way we can see clearly see something beautiful here in this world is so
fantastic when we do this inner work in the teaching in in Buddhism in
Mahayana Buddhism in Zen Buddhism is it goes something like this uh when your
mind is pure the world is pure when the mind is pure you see the world in a
certain kind of Purity and um so this work on your your
own heart your own mind understanding it seeing how it is doing that work of
really recognizing where the harming is how we harm
ourselves and um and finding a way not to do it and for many of us part of that
work is to deal with all the lawyers in the mind there are some really clever
lawyers in there who will make a really good case
that it's okay to harm sometimes it's to harm other people
they deserve it how else am I going to take care of myself what other choice do we
have and and uh sometimes the lawyers represent
you of course I have to harm myself I'm such a terrible person you know I
deserve it so part of the task in this practice is
to question the lawyers but when the lawyers
come remember don't harm them receive them as old
friends receive them calmly kindly listen to
them but don't believe them believe in
non-harming and then finally what I'd like to offer around this thing
believing uh many of us believe things that maybe we shouldn't be
believing um recently I talked to someone who said
that I don't I don't believe I'm capable of doing something that needs to be done
I don't think I'm capable that's my belief and um and instead of uh when
when you have when that when you that occurs to you change that your language
don't say don't say this is what I
believe say this is what I'm
believing and if you want to get extra credit you
say for right now this is what I'm believing the difference is huge if you
say I believe it's like now it's a solid truthful statement like this is how it
is and like who's going to find a way out of that but if it's just an act of
believing right now this is what I'm believing then it's not so solid it's
like well it's just right now it's just NE and it's an activity of the
mind and the focus on on Buddhism is not so much on belief or at all on belief
but rather on the activity the mind is doing and turns out that
believing when there's a belief there's an activity of the Mind
happening and that is called believing and now we're all that and
that puts the mirror back on the mindfulness back on what's the
nature what's the the quality the characteristic of that act the act of
believing and um so um what do you
believe long ago I believed now I act we're always acting there's always
action and so um what's the so then um
um what teachings do you rely on now long
ago I relied on teachings now I rely on what I
know so and what what can you know maybe you don't know ultimate
truths but if you pay attention you can know the actions that you're involved in
and if the action has to do with thinking then you know oh I'm thinking something I'm thinking about I'm
thinking about an ultimate truth I'm thinking that I believe in this this
that this is ultimately true the action of thinking is happening
and we often Overlook the action because we get caught up in what we're thinking
about we Overlook the fact that I'm believing because we're caught in the
belief this is what's true oh now I'm believing this now I'm
reacting to this now I'm feeling this now I'm wanting this happen there's
always an action so what teachings do you rely on I rely on what I know and what you can
know is you can know the activities we're involved in that is a core Central
activity that we mindfulness brings attention to aren't you devoted to the Buddha long
ago I was devoted to the Buddha now I am devoted to
non-harming once you start tracking the activities of the mind and speech and
body then you can start noticing oh this hurts there's an ouch in this there's
harm in this there's harm for me and maybe there's harm for others and then we can
question is this how I want to live my life is this the activity that I want to
be part of well then the lawyer comes and says it has to be this way there can't be any
other way oh that's a clever
lawyer but the lawyer is not the judge who has to decide don't let the
lawyers decide but what do you have faith in I
don't have faith I have confidence in non-harming
action what is your ultimate truth the end of doing anything any harm
to myself or others what is the good life now a life
lived without deliberate act any deliberate Act of body speech and mind
that harm self or others do you have no
desires no I do have desires I desire a world
committed to non-harming it's fine to have desires in
Buddhism but the desires have to be when then you're
Desiring so as you're Desiring desire in a way that doesn't cause harm find a way
to have desires that actually can be nourishing and supportive and helpful for you some desires are actually
helpful healing beneficial inspiring and any desire that has to do
with living a life of not causing harm living a life that does the opposite that lives with love and care and
respect for self and others those desires have desire them in ways that
are inspiring that that don't cause more harm someone can have the desire to be
non-harming God I I get I have to get on with it here I'm such a lousy person I need to have to desire
non-harming you know and not to be the best non-harming person on my
block the very Act of wanting to non-harm is now harming you so we're always looking what in what
way am I ining what way what way what way am I
acting here what way am I thinking here what way am I intending here is the very
way in which I'm intending wanting thinking thinking does that
Inspire this inner beauty of non-harming we're always tracking this
looking at it and now over time it has phenomenal results over time it creates
so much inner well-being and peace and space and goodness that um maybe you'll be the
person the Buddhist so-called Buddhist that goes into a where there's
never been any Buddhists and the religious Professor will come to you what do you believe
in I believe it's po important
to notice how I'm
believing now you understand why that's an important answer I believe it's
important to study how I'm believing so that I believe in a way
that doesn't cause any harm does the opposite it's it's nourishing it's supporting
it's it's liberating so those are my thoughts for
today so um now what do the lawyer
say or what questions you have or comments might you have yes
please
this topic was spoton for something I'm struggling with right now I realized that I am harming myself
through perpetuating suffering over a loss I've experienced so you harm yourself but by perpetuating the
suffering yes and so um I realize it's coming from clinging a
wonderful friendship I had and it's not wonderful at all anymore and I keep clinging to what it
was so the Buddha was so wonderful at giving us lists but I don't find a list
for how to let go I think that's just the hardest thing for me oh there's a
there's a really there a really good list which
one it's a list that has only one item in it yeah I need steps I need 12 steps to
learn to let go it's repeatedly my biggest okay well then problem well then I'll give you four steps
okay be mindful of your body be mindful of your feelings be mindful of your mind
States and be mindful of uh the activities of your mind the four
foundations of mindfulness so when you when you have the particular suffering that you have um go through the
checklist of those four and and if you haven't if you're not really recently familiar with the four foundations of
mindfulness really kind of study them a little bit and uh and then um you know
that's a checklist it just it takes a lot of familiarity a lot of mindfulness a lot of looking at it and seeing what's
going on here um not analytically but uh what What's the ining what's the
activities that are happening now in the body in the the mind in the heart and you have to spend a lot of time just
being mindful of it and um um and um and so also remember that mindfulness is
also not quite a good word we're we're
mindfulness we're doing mindfulness we're practicing the activity of mindfulness and then the question is how
are you being mindful are you doing it holding on for dear life are are you holding on are you doing it with with uh
greed with aversion to what's happening and uh uh do the mindfulness
sing in a way that feels good I must be missing something because
I'm actually doing a practice so similar I mean it's like almost dad on my coach was taking me through I catch myself I
wake up almost every morning with these thoughts so I catch myself oh I wish I had said that or oh
it hurt so much when she said this or oh my gosh that was so wonderful when we were friends like that okay it's POS
possible but then I stop I look I say oh I'm saying this and then I rub my
fingers together I check in with my body my breathing every damn morning it comes
back so I don't know you that well in this regard right but I suspect that you're doing all this from the neck
up and that uh do it once your belly is really
relaxed find a way good posture really find your let your belly be deeply relaxed and then do the work do the
practice I will try that from the bottom up rather than the top down yeah yeah I think you're right I'm doing it in as a
mental construct I'm going step one step two step three yeah
yeah okay that'll be weird thank you you have go
ahead but let's stay on topic if you have looks like you have an announcement non but it's an announcement right it
might be how about waiting a couple of minutes because I think I think it's better to kind of stay on track a little
bit here rather than changing the topic we end with you then we can you give the mic to the
person out there in the outer Hall the outer hall and then we can do you after her
thank you you have to turn it on the green
light light goes on thank you um isn't having
expectations of others it's always um harming them and harming yourself and if
you have no expectations then you are all alone I think having expectations when
there's been I think having uh an expectation when there's been an
agreement is reasonable you know so if someone
promises something and you agreed like together like this is what we're going to do I think that's that's that's one
of the functions of an of an agreement is now we can expect that something will happen we can trust something will
happen in a particular way and then if the agreement is broken we feel kind of
hurt but if there has been no agreement between the people then I have to we have to be very
very careful about the expectation because then we're projecting something on the situation and um that might not
other people don't agree haven't agreed to we're bringing our values and putting it on other
people and um now there might be implicit agreements we have in our
society you know like um when the traffic light is red we don't drive
through it we have that expectation that that's how we all agree to drive but you never
asked the other driver you promised not the drive you know we kind of have all kinds of
sometimes implicit agreements um so I think that when there's an agreement we it's reasonable
to have some expectation and then people are accountable to the agreements say I
I expected that what happened what was going on you can you have something you can talk about but expectation for on one for one
on oneself and expectations on others uh are also source of a lot of suffering
other people suffer suffer we suffer uh we have standards we hold people ourselves to standards we hold hold
other people to that's much higher than they can actually live by and and we can
be it can be oppressive it can be harmful to ex to have expectations of self and others which are
unreasonable and um and so this is why this this mindfulness where we're
looking at how again the not the expects expectations are important to look at
but the uh what's going on for you when you're expecting when you have an when you're doing the action of expecting
expectation um are you what do you want what are you attached to what are you hoping for what are you afraid
of this gives you enough to think about thank you what if it's a kind of complicated
situations I'm thinking of an example let's say I have a pond and I have some fish in it and then there's an invasive
species that now live in the pond that's killing my fish
so if I don't harm that species of some sort my fish will all
die then then what should I do in that case
there's all kinds of things first of all I love it when people ask the question I
have this problem invasive fish I don't want to kill them but what can I do that
people that ask that question I I I welcome so much this is fantastic that they're asking rather than immediately
go get the poison to kill the fish and then the question well let's think about it maybe let's do some
research and find out what we can do and um and maybe there's something can be
done maybe there are traps you can put in that can trap the fish and take them
where they belong which is maybe expensive but maybe that's nicer than just killing them um so maybe there's
something can be done maybe uh the your fish are really small and that's a
really big fish and if you take a big net fishing net through the pond you get
all the bad fish on one side and the all the small fish stay on the other side of
the net and then you can kind of let's figure out what we can do now maybe we maybe that's a good way of living and
maybe they can just kind of you know share share the pond together that way
or maybe um you realize the reason why the big fish are eating the small ones
is because they're hungry but they actually have in their where they came from they have a preferred
diet and so let's get let's bring in the preferred diet and they'll leave the small fish alone so I'm just making up
ideas but it's possible by thinking about it and exploring and but sometimes
it takes a while sometimes just killing them seems like it takes care of it really quickly but then because you killed them
the other your fish now think oh killing is
right and so they start killing each other for this slightest little you know they' learned that killing was possible
in this Pond and you know you don't know the repercussions that killing has so um
and then there's also the it could also be that the um the invasive species was
coming like the the the fish the person didn't read the news and didn't read
that if you bring in this particular kind of feed it has this fish eggs in it
and you have to be really careful oh but it's so much work who cares about doing that and I don't believe in it anyway
and and so then there's no preventive work done so if you have the equivalent today
of a pond with fish in it think ahead notice what's happening
sit set up a situation so in the future there's not that
problem so so if people who want to live a nonharming life they also need to be
uh proactive they need to set the conditions in now so that uh so that in
5 10 20 years 50 years that um uh there's not any problems and to only
look at the present moment uh is very myopic when it comes to living a life of
non-harming so does that give you some ideas yes there was not an ultimate
answer it's it's it's a
beginning maybe last one thank
you so what I'm thinking about invasive fish and a fish pond I'm thinking about
Israel and Gaza and I'm wondering I don't know how to how to think about it and I wonder if
you have any suggestions yes I mean the talk today was partly a response to that without
mentioning it explicitly and um and one of the reasons
not to mention explicitly is I'll tell you a story about tikn
Han uh tikn Han lived in Vietnam during the war between Northern Vietnam and
Southern Vietnam he lived right in the area where the conflict was most active
battles back and forth and fields nearby and um and he was dedicated to
doing it a different way not fighting he was dedicated to non-harming and he had a whole group of
monastics and women and men who were out there trying to support everyone both sides of the conflict and offer a
different approach to it all and because of that both neither side trusted
him the PE because he was supporting the northern Vietnamese you trying to help
them and maybe even offer Medical Care the southern Vietnamese didn't trust him and vice
versa and so the situation in Gaza in Israel is awful there so much
pain but and to uh and even so uh to
take the middle view the middle way that really wants the best for both
sides uh is kind of difficult to say because one way or the other people on either
side gets upset that you don't understand how terrible it is for us and and how much we've been violated and and
so how much we've been kind of forgotten by the world or all kinds of things and so um and so I didn't want to talk about
it directly and uh and and not talking about it is also very difficult because
and then you're ignoring you know and people say you're ignoring my people I don't feel safe and but when there's
both people who feel that way then you know it's a very difficult thing to be
in that to have that middle so the middle for me is not being aloof or indifferent but is um having a heart
that's really concerned for everyone involved and um and is dedicated to
finding best we can way of non-harming
without
um I don't know without
um I don't know without maybe giving the question earlier today without um
projecting expectations on what people
do thank you so now you can have your
announcement know to Gil thank you so very
much so in following up of what you had said um one person from the community who's
been with you I can't quite hear maybe you hold it up if you hold it up maybe I take the thing but also also when the
mic is better held when it's held horizontally and then close to them M okay uh one person who's helped in the
formation of IMC for couple of decades has helped write this up last night a
dear friend I can't I can't really do okay so this is uh been written up by
someone who's been involved helping with IMC for a couple of decades and it's just a piece of
information if people want to try to help in the non-harming situation
just contacting their Congress person and saying please support an immediate
ceasefire it's just straightforward that's it and do you find your
representative by just going on the computer to house.gov put in your ZIP code I see
that's it but that's a really great start and from there God willing do
Buddha wheel we have you know just peace accept humanitarian Aid great great
thank you so thank you all for being yes
announ as just very thinking about the future
we have our mindful parents program today and I just wanted just to announce it and we have a kids program this
afternoon and seriously it does it does ride on what you've been talking about because we really are talking about um
talking about parenting our children for the future so and a future of peace and non-harming so thank
you great so thank you all and uh I'll be leaving shortly because I I have to
I'm going down to uh Santa Cruz today to uh at 1:00 there's uh one of the IMC
students and and teachers and training or teachers is going to become the installed as the resident teacher for
the inside Santa Cruz Community Center like we have here so it's kind a special
and then uh I start a retreat to IRC this afternoon so that'll be going pretty soon thank
you
e