good morning good morning welcome welcome good afternoon good evening and
for even if the future you is listening to this you know maybe you listen to it
again or maybe you don't listen to them in real time and just a warm welcome maybe
you're even out for a walk listening on a podcast sometimes I'm doing this imagine others do this as
well so today is the last day I'm talking about faculties for
fearlessness been going through the five faculties this is a you know standard list those of you who have been around
Buddhism for a while know the five faculties but I've been doing them a little bit differently in a different
order and I've been highlighting particular aspects of each faculty
rather than kind of like flushing out the fullness of each faculty I've been just highlighting a
particular I guess aspect a particular um way of looking and considering each
faculty and applying it to fearlessness like how can it support us for our fear
because fear is just a part of this Human Experience it's just all of us have it
whether it's obvious or subtle it's there in some way maybe not every moment
but uh it does have a impact on our lives and so part of finding freedom is
to meet fear to be with fear and not to be afraid of fear so with that let's start with a
little guided meditation
here maybe starting with some deep
breaths our physiology is such that with some extended
exhales help us to settle as you know with this practice we
are not manipulating the breath we're allowing the breath to be normal just
how it is however it can be helpful to do a few
breaths where we are intentionally extending the exhale just a tiny
bit low in the breath breath to return to normal trusting that the body knows how
to breathe we do not need to breathe in any particular
way maybe just opening the awareness recognizing that there are
sounds maybe quiet maybe not so
quiet and just receiving the sounds we don't have to go out and get
them for me I can hear little birds probably you can't hear
them through my microphone allowing myself to feel that
little bit of uplift good morning little birds
and then bringing attention to the bodily experience feeling the contact of
whatever surface we're sitting on or lying on
laying on feeling the pressure against the
body the bcks against the cushion the
chair back of the
legs the
feet and the back maybe you're leaning against the
back bre maybe you're lying
down maybe you can feel the clothing on the back or the temperature of the air
on the back whatever it is that the back is in
contact
with
feeling connected grounded we're
here now with these
experiences
maybe you notice some areas of constriction tightness
tension I often like to check around the eyes and the jaw places where I hold tension
allowing some softening
relaxing
[Music]
shoulders the front of the body the
chest maybe it can open just a tiny bit more very very small
movement moving the shoulders
back and the belly letting it relax and
soften
and can we let this softening opening relaxing
releasing be a support for a tone of warmth and
kindness towards our
ourselves towards whatever experiences are being
had and toward everything that isn't ourself
everybody just setting a intention a Direction a mood of warmth and
kindness and then resting the attention on the sensations of
breathing tuning into being sensitive
to the experience of
breathing not the idea of breathing the concept or the
notion but the experience what does it feel like from the
inside
what does an inhale feel
like that's and exhale feel
like what about the transitions between inhales and
exhales
it doesn't have to be a problem when the mind
wanders we just simply gently with warmth and Care Begin
Again
[Music]
good morning welcome welcome everybody today is our last day talking
about faculties for fearlessness fine fabulous faculties for
fun fearlessness forever for freedom I have many alliterations is that in a
row fine I didn't put the word fine in there probably there I could get that in there somewhere too I'm just playing around I like
alliterations but um maybe I'll just start with a quick review of what we've
talked about earlier in the week and as you know I've been looking at the five
faculties and you know not the conventional way not the usual order and
not necessarily the ual way that we think about the five faculties and I've been applying them like how can it help
us with fear how can it help us that with um this uh pervasive feeling that
we often have that oh I have to protect myself oh I'm feeling a little bit uh
threatened and this fear shows up some like really subtle as way as well as in
really obvious ways in which there's like some imminent danger as well as maybe just this low
grade kind of anxiety that it's not even clear what we're afraid of there's just
this sense of not feeling safe so fear shows up in so many
different ways in our lives and it has an impact on us it's
taxing and not only is it taxing it can uh kind of like diminish our life in
terms of we're always trying to avoid greater fear or things that we're not comfortable
with and not only is it texting but it also kind of like uh it robs us of some
Freedom we're getting pushed around by this trying to avoid things that are
fearful and then in these preceding days of this series on the faculties for
fearlessness I started off talking about SA and I um emphasize the element of
noticing so part of Sati is noticing and it was a way if we're
experiencing fear or we have some anxiety it can be enormously helpful to
notice our environment like really mundane things like there's a computer
screen there's a corner of the desk there's a keyboard you know just really
mundane things and help us to get um collected and grounded here there's also
there's this a way that we also can notice this strong sense of no we have this way in which we're
resisting we're pushing back no I don't want this experience and to notice that how does
that feel in the body and in the mind and then that second day I went to
collec in this this sense of getting Center Ed and gathered and collected and maybe this wholehearted or
wholeness around something so stopping the fragmentation and I emphasize
looking at the this sense of no this resistance it turns out this is so
powerful we often think that we have to deal with the fear directly we can do
that but it's not always available to us so part of Sade is to have this
collectedness around the resistance and we shouldn't underestimate how powerful and
transformative this can be and then on the third day we went to
Sada or S is confidence is is to have some confidence that this practice does
lead to Greater Freedom greater ease and well-being and also confidence in
ourselves that we can do this and we just need enough confidence to do the
next be present for the next breath go to the next sit listen to the next
Dharma talk whatever it might be and so confidence in ourselves and
confidence that other people have this capability as
well what the things unfold differently if we're assuming that they have this uh
this capacity to be with what's needed also and also this Sada or Sada as trust
trus in this inner process towards greater wisdom towards wholeness towards
Freedom towards healing there's something inside of us that we can trust we we don't have to
make everything happen there is also something that just naturally
happens and I don't want to say that we have to be passive and not putting any effort because we do but it's not 100%
about us making effort part of uh s is trusting the
process even if it is uncomfortable and then yesterday I talked about Viria as
courage sometimes Viria we don't talk about this as much as the courage aspect
but this courage to meet whatever it is the courage to do the preceding steps
that I've talked about the courage to be curious about fear and the resistance to
fear some courage to stop avoiding stop distracting ourselves
which you know of course we do of course we don't want to feel fear or the
resistance to fear so yesterday was about Viria as courage and today i' like like to talk
about the fifth one the fifth uh faculty
for fearlessness and that is Pa and maybe I'll start before I give
the usual uh translation I'll talk about PA as both a distinguishing and
discernment is this ability that we all have this capacity that we all have to
make distinctions so I'm not talking about some sophisticated
philosophical thing you know about knowing some esoterica I'm talking about
this we can make this distinctions that starts to grow out of the clarity of
mind and this Clarity of Mind arises just through practice mindfulness in
general some if we some settledness but there's a way in which
we can distinguish fear and the resistance to
fear this can be such a great starting point as well as something that matures with
our practice to be able to recognize fear feels like this it's a lump in the
throat maybe some tightness in the chest and the resistance is maybe this
uh if for for me often it is kind of like maybe a little tension in the shoulders maybe some tension around the
jaw turns out the tension in the jaw in particular is really related to a sense
of resistance so part of this
PA is to know the difference between fear and the resistance to
fear and to know the physical Sensations away from the mental
events physical Sensations are the lump in the throat or the tightness in the
jaw the mental events are the thoughts of like oh if only I were somebody else
then I wouldn't be having this fear or this anxiety or you know if only um I
had more time to practice if only I meditated for 28 hours a day then I
wouldn't be having this you know or oh only if H that thing over there that would if they would just stop doing that
then I would feel safe all the time and I wouldn't have this fear but there's a lot of stories that are
accompanying these feelings of fear anxiety this idea of like oh I
couldn't survive if this or that happened or somebody did this or they
didn't do that this you know without concerning
ourselves whether these things are true or not just Noti saying oh this is
thinking and this is a experience this lump in the throat I keep on pointing to
my throat because for me fear is often a lump in the throat all of us have our
own ways have our own signatures if you will of how these fear and resistance
show up in our body but PA this fifth faculty is this
distinguishing between fear and resistance physical and mental and
distinguishing or discerning between cusa and ausa these are poly
words we might um I translate them as
helpful unhelpful skillful
unskillful wholesome UNH wholesome more suffering less suffering so just being
able to like notice in our life like tease this apart oh yeah when I show up in this way me to more
suffering however when I show up in this other way which always involves some
openness and ease as best we can always leads to less
suffering this resistance really tightening it always leads to more
suffering and this opening and spaciousness leads to less suffering
it's easy for me to say this I know it's not easy to do this but this is just to
acknowledge that there are ways in which we show up in the world that bring some
greater I'm using this word ease or peace or freedom than others so PA as
distinguishing and discernment and then also I will say
that PA is Insight if I haven't said it already PA
is of translated as wisdom but P can we can might think of it as
Insight insight as this maybe a change of heart a opening a realization maybe
an expansion a vision a clear seeing seeing the world in a different way that
leads to less suffering so it has this insight has two
components it's uh seeing things differently and in a way that leads to
less suffering and sometimes we focus on how we see things differently but we can
focus on how it leads to less suffering oh yeah since I had that realization now
there's a little bit less suffering now now that I see that
there's fear and fear uh resistance to fear together tangled up and I'm able to
tease them apart oh yeah and I can see how this resistance I tend to get angry angry and
blame and having that little bit of insight brings a little bit less
suffering so insights might be big bang ones or they might just be oh yeah a
little bit greater self- understanding I see now how my getting angry and and
lashing out is not the same thing as the fear but it's often it's my pattern of
reacting to fear for example and maybe I'll say that I want to also
highlight that this idea of insight right to we Insight we're the inside meditation center right we kind like
like this inside stuff but I want to highlight that we can learn from every
experience including fear sometimes we think that oh I just
you know have to have meditative experiences and then I'll have insights then but but fear and our resistance to
fear are also great places to have Insight so we don't have to wait for the
perfect conditions Pleasant conditions in which we can have some really transformative and impactful
insights and then some of you know about these three characteristics things are
inconstant they're unsatisfactory and there isn't an inherent
core to the experiences an du
an I'm not going to say more about them I'll just point them that all these
there's insights that are smaller and some insights that are bigger but all of them involve a little bit of letting
go so that we can let go into greater and greater freedom and of course
freedom is fearlessness so thank you all for this
uh Journey being on this journey with me uh for this week before I sign off I want to mention
that there are um if you're interested in exploring fear some more there is
some classes that are um coming up about fear and if I can figure out how to put
them in the chat box I will
I'm not exactly sure how to do this I'm looking at this but while I'm doing this I'll describe it there's
um there something called fear dread and
freedom that um I'll be teaching with some of my friends in uh in
December maybe if you just Google fear dread and freedom you'd find it I don't actually know and then um then there's also the
path of fearlessness that I'll be teaching oh here we go so now I can I
think I can chat now okay so I I think I put this in the
chat box just you know of course if just only
if you're interested and um oh I have too many words sorry about this
um I should have figured this out earlier
right so that's this one fear dread and freedom that's at the sa Center and then
um this other one is called path of fearlessness and it's
a it's uh with IMC and this is a more of
a a um um we'll be meeting once a month for I
think six or seven months these are all freely offered and this is only if you're interested in um exploring more
about fear I'll be talking about it in some different ways with some of my friends I'll be a co- teaching with some
of my friends and I'd love to see some of you there it'll be on Zoom both of
them are completely on zoom and so there will be a chance for interaction with us teachers and with uh each as well as
some learning some guided meditations and some kind of whatever um way that
you feel comfortable with oh say that
um yes I'm sorry if you hear this loud loud sound up
there yes R said um it's listed on the homepage yes the
path of fearlessness is on the homepage of IMC and fear dread and freedom is on the
Sati Center sa.org sa a TI so I'm just
I'm just offering this in case it's helpful and you want to explore this whole idea of fearlessness more we won't
be covering any of the things that I covered here in these uh five days it'll be a little bit different uh each of
them will so what a pleasure it's been to spend
these days with you and to be exploring these faculties for fearlessness and
freedom find faculties for Fearless freedom
forever so I wish you all a wonderful rest of the day and may you find some
fearlessness and if fear shows up maybe you can tune into the resistance to that
fear rather than feeling like you have to dive right into the fear that's not always available for us thank
you