okay so welcome welcome everyone welcome to happy hour lovely to see you all
and lovely to be with you feel your presence from around the country and the world
so so for today's practice ah and I wanted to bring in the sense of
um of uh patience as meta patience as meta
patience with ourselves patients with others patients with this body
patience and kindness with causes and conditions not being what we want them
to be patients with our to-do list patience patience patience patience can be such a
beautiful um practice it's really an aspect an
expression of love and and again to have discernment patience is not just oh
postponing and I'm procrastinating that's not patience but there is a wholeheartedness there's a kindness
there is a a gentleness to appreciating when is
um when it's appropriate to have patience and when it's appropriate to lean in and and not impatience but but
of course holding ourselves or others accountable so so and that is the role
of wisdom because compassion and kindness without wisdom
become what Tibetans like to call idiot Compassion or idiot kindness so so in
that way what is the appropriate
expression of patience as kindness as love as meta for ourselves and for
others without veering into enabling and unhealthy enabling so
so I leave that as as a little contemplation and then knowing the guided meditation that I lead us to
explore that a little bit so so let's uh let's begin let's land in our
seeds let's arrive
here here In This Moment
In This Moment In Time in this body
starting with patience with this body
with this mind the body might still be settling
reverberating from the busyness of the day
patience with this mind might still be running around like a
little puppy can we have patience with ourselves in this moment as we start to
settle connecting with the breath
and the attitude of spacious patients with the breath
as it finds its way
through our bodies
having patience with the hard mind
as it connects with the sensations of the body feet the feet on the Earth
hands and lap on our lap your sit bones and
the cushion
patience with the unfolding of settling and arriving
patience with this body maybe it's a key or
creaky your little unsettled thank you or sleepy
or whatever else might be arising as if we're opening our hearts
kindness with patience accepting the body just as it is in this
moment
with each breath
accepting the body just as it is
not Waiting to Exhale when the conditions are right that relaxing exhaling right now
and can we have patience with the mind and this mind if it's drifting here and
there thinking about the past and future it's okay it's okay dear it's all right
not judging not attacking
noticing noticing it's like this right now
welcoming awareness to reconnect
with the breath right here with patience
leaning in gently kindly lovingly connect with
the breath
leaning in landing Landing it Landing with
wholeheartedness
notice what happens if awareness connects with with patience
to the breath to this Breath Right Here
like a scientist of your own mind a relaxed scientist
notice what happens if you're not reaching for the next breath or the next
moment or the next thing but
connecting awareness connecting with the breath with the Body Sensations of the
breath in the body with a lot of patience nowhere to go nothing to do but just to
be just to honor just to love be patient
with this breath right here this in breath this
out breath it's our training today it's our exploration
relaxing the body connecting with the breath in the body
connecting with the body with a lot of patience
Kanti in Pali a lot of patience glorious glorious patience
an expression of love an expression of peace
be curious you can be non-patient in a few minutes
right after this practice but right now try it on for size what
happens see what happens
patient with your own heart this heart and might and body
patience as love love
kindness Goodwill as patience right here
this body mind and heart
and you be patient if their judgments are rising
can you be patient loving with the judgmental mind
if it's arising
thanking it thank you
thanks for trying to help me the best way you can you know
there's plenty of patience with whatever is arising
plenty of love for it to transform into wisdom
I love and be patient with myself
as much as it's available in this moment not pushing as much as it's available
and can we open up this space of patience
patience has love love has patience Good Will can we open it up
include others can we offer our patience
to someone we care about
in our life as an expression of care Goodwill
taking the long-term View
what they are doing or not doing part of it is of course there
militia and responsibility and a lot of it is part of the causes and conditions
and we offer our support our patience
not our judgment
Transformations happen more readily in a loving patient
container than one that is filled with impatience and judgment
we know this
loving patience foreign
loving patients
and patience not as a chore but as a gift
it's a gift of generosity from our heart
and then can we expand further to have patience loving patients
with causes and conditions
that feels too abstract and stay with a being stay with
someone in your life or with yourself
unless we're bringing this sitting to a close
and reconsider the gift of patience is it gifts with as a gift with no
strings attached to ourselves to a loved one
release
pressing that patients Conte is one of the ten
Perfections and parames
exploring the equivalence of love and patience and
offering this goodness the equivalence of this goodness love and patience loving patience
as a gift may I love and accept and be patient
with myself
just as I am to create the conditions for growth
not for impatience and judgment
and sharing our goodness sharing our cultivation the seed of goodness and
cultivation with all beings everywhere may all beings including myself
be happy be well and be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so so much to say and explore with with patience and and the way we
try to approach and and poor patients in the sitting was um
as an ex as an expression of love as expression of Goodwill for ourselves
and others and in this container of loving patience again it's not
idiot patients but it's one that enables transformation in Naples growth
um enables wisdom whereas if we're just impatient with
ourselves seeking the next thing or the judgments it just contracts the whole
heart both for ourselves and for others anyway get a lot this is a very rich
topic but but maybe just a bit of exploration today so select invite us to uh
explore this topic this practice together in small groups with patience
for ourselves patience for one another and um
and the the question to explore in the breakout rooms for with one another
um it could be about this this guided meditation if there was something that showed up for you something that
revealed itself something that was surprising um or maybe this just the general
question of um how does patience and lack of patience patience and its opposite
patience and impatience how does it show up in your life and
um is it supportive when you lean into patience for yourself and for others
and by and the opposite of it impatience is it uh
what do you notice it's just exploring exploring a little bit the invitation is
for you to say just if you have 10 things to say just say one nugget just one thing maybe it takes a 30 seconds or
a minute and then the next person will say something if they want or they can say pass
just bow and hold silent presence and then the next person will say something and then your turn again go around and
round a few times and please use I statements just share whatever you want
to share from your own experience not asking questions from others not directing the group
um just showing up with your own kindness and experience and humility um and patience patience and let's Go
reverse alphabetical order today so I'm going to open the rooms right now take
care of yourselves be kind be patient with one another here we go
okay all the rooms are closed everyone is back welcome back and
um I'm going to open chat right now if you have any Reflections you would like
to share with me privately you can uh send them in the private chat I'll read
only the Reflection not your name or if you send it to everyone I'll read out the reflection and your name and if you
haven't shared um in the group for a while you're welcome to raise your hand with
questions with reflections with practice reports and or group report whatever
you like to share for the benefit of yourself and everyone
Malaya please foreign
I wanted to say that um that during the during during the um meditation I was
thinking about how um how not having patience
um and busyness that that they are they they kind of
like are a way to sort of distract from um from thoughts like from a
person's own thoughts and also like from being in the present moment
and a way to escape reality and um
and then uh yeah it also can cause suffering and then I was thinking about
how like where my mother's family is from the Philippines how
um my memories from when I was a teenager there and how there's no internet there's no cell phone service
there's no running water there's no electricity and so when we're not like
working or doing things like that we passed the time by telling each other
stories and then how people would tell the same stories over and over again but you'd be
patient and you don't tell someone oh you already told me that story because they enjoy telling the story so
much you just let them tell you the same story again day after day
and then when we don't have anything to say we would just look at each other and then
when we were really bored and it was getting late we would just go to sleep
sweet beautiful thank you so much for bringing that in Malaya that is lovely this gift
of kindness and patience and letting people tell the same story that they
enjoy telling over and over again there's such sweetness about that and and uh just patience with life patience
with one another patients with ourselves or something about the pace of the the
um the modern world especially with social media that it's it's unimaginable
to be quote unquote bored a single minute that you just have to pick up
this this uh device and keep scrolling and news and information and this and
that sort of just be here just be patient just cultivate patience so maybe
the next time each of us find ourselves with moment of waiting the doctor's
office or here or there can we just ah take that moment to cultivate loving
patience loving patience for ourselves as a gift
so beautiful thank you so much Malaya that was lovely Vicky I see your hand and then Quentin
oh you're still muted let's try that again
still muted still muted
okay not working Vicky so tell you what we'll go to Quentin and you can figure out
what's what's going on technically we'll come back to you okay Quentin please
hi can you can you hear me yes absolutely good um I I experienced something uh with my
partners that was very unique from me um that I definitely think relates to a
lot of a lot of experiences including patients um I've been I've been studying Buddhism a
while and um I'm trying to say this in a gentle way um many of the practice groups that I've
been to mostly have been Western Buddhists there is a lot of philosophizing
and the politeness feels very very surface
and my partners were able to share their thoughts and I was able to share my
thoughts with kindness at the same time it wasn't the affect the facial expressions of
warmth but still speaking intellectually and so sometimes over the years
I have not been able to feel comfortable sometimes with speaking intellectually feeling that the body was left behind
but my partner showed up with this kind of boundary of like I will get to know them over time and I
will still receive and give kindness and I will get to know them over time and I will still receive kindness and it was
just really nice to be felt that I was being received of kindness and still
allowing people to express themselves without having to be vulnerable in a particular way to feel connected
um and that that's very different I haven't experienced that before in a long time so I really appreciate that it
definitely helped me with the idea of being patient and being comfortable with being intimate as things grow
beautiful thank you so much Quentin thank you so much for articulating that
um and and feeling touched by that noticing that and articulating it so
beautiful and also I want to reflect back in just the way you were actually speaking about it was you were sharing
this intellectual idea this thing that you had noticed in the space that's interesting to put it into words and yet
you were so embodied sharing your own care your you being touched your own
vulnerability of oh it's been challenging in the past and this was really different tonight I so thank you
for you modeling what touched you in the community in the group tonight
um and and I do want to say I think this is something that I love about about the happy hour Sangha because there is this
sense kindness embodiment not an idea but an embodied kindness through our practice that we show up for one another
holding one another holding ourselves and of course we discuss our practice what arose challenges and yet there's an
embodiment of kindness which is our Our intention in these hard practices so
right on thank you Clinton really appreciate you reflecting that thank you so beautiful okay Vicky I think you've
succeeded in unmuting yourself yes I did thank you I loved the thought
of finding wisdom as you are having patience
and I remembered a yoga teacher a long time ago saying that rushing equals
violence and I thought about that with patients that a lot of it is holding one's desire
to fix something or make it different and having that that calm to do it in
the middle of being really wanting to get things done or wanting to move things in a different
way yeah yeah beautiful thank you Vicky beautifully said yeah this the gift of
patience in so many different ways in the midst of busyness in the midst of oh impatience can we feel into it as not as
violence the impatience as violence of our minds but uh yeah thank you
beautifully said and and um one of you sent me a direct reflection having patience with mind was
a beautiful concept during sitting beautiful having patience with our own mind yay having patience with our bodies
if it's not exactly you know the cause and conditions are challenging right now
so so thank you all I appreciate your practice your wholeheartedness your
goodness cultivating loving patience together as a gift may we all wake up
may are waking up um or our cultivation our practice
support the waking up of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may
all beings be free including ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone be well and now