welcome to Monday night I am here for Diana who is on retreat
conducting a retreat I have all kinds of things hanging off my ear here just a moment while I
make sure it's all secure so um
what I'd like to talk to you about has to do with the experience of being at ease in
practice however as I was considering that I realized
that there was a tendency on my part to jump right into the middle of the discussion and that maybe it would be useful to
have some place to start from and since I'm going to be here two Monday nights in a row
I'm going to start not talking about that what I would like to do
is talk about the importance of how we understand mindfulness what it means in
the practice and the value of long-term practice the valley the value of not giving up on
practice so first I would I'm going to tell you a story
so recently I watched a movie a film called the way back
and it's not the latest one by Ben afflecked about a
sports team this is the one that was made a number of years ago about
a group of prisoners in who were in a gulag in Siberia
who escaped and walked four thousand miles to India
now when I first when the when the movie comes up the first thing that is shown is it says this is based on a real life
experience so it turns out turns out that not everything in the
movie is entirely true or defensible nevertheless
the movie really impressed me with what it took to get those prisoners who were
starving and sick and in the dead of winter to leave a gulag in Siberia and
make their way all the way to India now
in the process there were there were uh there was
six of them and not all of them made it to India there were only three that made
it to India and um turns out one of the characters was
entirely made up but the movie was based on a real life experience and a memoir
that maybe this person had or maybe he was talking about someone else's experience and so what's interesting to me is how
the movie impacted me with the one characteristic that was
most important which was you just did not stop you kept walking
no matter what happened you just kept going and he there was one particular leader
who was a Polish engineer and he had been accused of spying so he
he was in Poland and this is in 1939 and the Russians were occupying Poland at
that time and he had said some inflammatory things against Stalin and
so he was arrested and he never
agreed that he had done any of these horrible things but they tortured his wife who testified against him
so he got he got a sentence of 25 years in this Gulag and off he went and
all the trials and tribulations of being in this Gulag and they set out on the road and he said the one thing I have to
do is I have to get back to Poland I have to get back so that I can tell my
wife not to feel guilty about doing this
he had that was his primary motivation I mean obviously he wanted to escape he wanted out but mostly he worried that
his wife was going to be carrying this burden and that was the thing that kept him going and so he was constantly
encouraging people as he went along you've got to keep going you've got to keep going
they left with a hatchet a knife and a week's worth of food
he was uh this character was the leader of the group because he believed they
could do it he believed they could do it everybody else said okay it's worth a try I'm just
going to die here otherwise and so they followed him religiously
what do you think are we going the right way you know I don't think we're going the right way are you sure we're going the right way constantly wanting
reassurance and we do that we do that in our practice we say well am I getting to
where I need to go how am I doing you know the answer you have to tell me how
this happens how do I make this happen what am I doing wrong why can't I concentrate why can't
why am I not there how come I can't measure that I am better on the path
that I'm I'm the person that I want to be how can I what's happening they were constantly asking him
and he would go on ahead and come back and get them
and all of the characters changed over the course of this Trek
they changed in ways they didn't expect mostly they tended to be very
distrustful of one another and independent totally isolationist and what they
discovered is it took all of them to survive it took all of their skills whether they
particularly valued those skills or not it took everyone to make that happen and
they began to feel the the lines between them
totally unintentionally of course they set out with a yeah we all have to
be together but I'm keeping mine to me and then discovered that didn't work
they had to keep going they had to depend on one another and this one could cook and that one could
hunt and that one could fish and that one knew how to make the directions work and it took all of them
they took the guy who was willing to risk being found to go ask people why
are the why are the mosquitoes so bad and why aren't you affected by the mosquitoes oh well you have to use this
particular thing which is a mosquito repellent you just go over here and pick oh okay and all of a sudden all that
misery went away foreign
they didn't know they thought they knew what the obstacles were going to be but they
actually didn't know the path that we set on out on
we don't know the outcome we don't know what's going to come up what's going to be an obstacle for us
what's going to not fit the vision we have
and then what happens when that obstacle arises
okay I guess I wasn't meant to or or can we say well that's interesting
now what and what we learn along the way
is how the idea that we have about what the path is how we're going to get where
we're going maybe it's just an idea
and it may be something that gets us started or gets us moving but what truly has value is what's
actually true where am I on the path am I have I found
the lake have I not found the lake mostly they trekked across Siberia they went to
Mongolia and they thought okay when we get to Mongolia we'll be safe we'll be out of Russia but then the first thing
they saw when they got to Mongolia was a picture of Stalin and they said whoops
it seems that this country is also not safe for us and so they decided to go on to Tibet
which meant crossing the Gobi Desert
they lost a couple of the people in the desert that was hard that was difficult that
was terminal for some
and they kept going at the beginning of the trip one of the characters who was an American
told the leader he said well I'm going to go with you because you have a fatal flaw that will work in my favor
and he said what's the flaw and he said kindness I've watched you you're kind and when I
am really failing I'm going to count on you to carry me and that actually happened
you know he didn't actually have to physically carry him but he had to literally drag him along and know we're
not going to leave you and yes we can do this and
what we think of is our flaws or our gifts are not necessarily so
not necessarily so and very often we get caught in the Trap in our practice
how we think it ought to look how we think we ought to be
there were two major things that happened to this man as they as they went along
they eventually got to Tibet and the American went off and joined in an American
group somewhere out of Tibet and three people went on over the Himalayas
and when they got there the first thing is they said well where are your passports and they you know they left and and the and the the man said well
how did you get here from Siberia and they said we walked
I think it was that the repetition of that phrase we walked we just did it
we just did it we just kept going and we didn't stop
now the rest of the story is that the the poll eventually got back to Poland
now he was arrested in 39 he arrived in India in 42.
he didn't get to go to Poland until 1989
when the Communists left Poland after the after the Berlin Wall fall fell and like
the lesson in the solidarity movement took over in Poland then in 1989 he went
to Poland and he found his wife and told her it was okay
the determination and the willingness to say I don't want you to have to carry
this so there were kind of the two tracks it was the determination to keep going and
the issue of what are you carrying on your journey what is it that you're
carrying mostly what we carry on our journey is
memories we carry memories
we carry our beliefs on how things should be locked up in the process that
we call memory and part of what we do on our path is we
lay down some of those memories or we shift those memories you know when I was
in high school I was fascinated by the idea of memory and I wanted to the the reason I became
a scientist in the first place was I wanted to understand how the brain
chemically created a memory what the hell does that mean how do we
do that and at the time actually that wasn't as strange a way of thinking about memory
but over time neuroscientists have come up with other explanations for how memories are formed and what actually a
memory is so the brain
operates on a kind of it's it's kind of a way to think about the brain is a very
sophisticated chat bot what it does is take information that
has been that it receives about experience and it forms meaning boxes
you know little little synaptic circuits of with this set of conditions
with these things that happen this means there's danger here and the reaction
should be fair the memory is actually a process it's a
series of synaptic firings that form patterns that we
assign meaning to
so that the the brain actually works as a kind of predictive device it says oh
oh I see this is happening this is the reaction giving an example of what what that might be you might
say well um I'm thinking of ice cream as soon as I say ice cream something happens in you
you either have a you have a visual idea of ice cream or you have a giant X in
front of ice cream and the ice cream might be vanilla or it might be chocolate or it might be pistachio and
if it's pistachio then maybe your salivary glands start moving because now
you're you have a memory of taste all right Incorporated in this circuit
is the process by which we make sense of what our experience is and we predict
what we need to be how we need to approach something so hearing ice cream
all kinds of things get triggered off triggered
and the ice cream isn't even real it's not even here
so the way memory Works memory has a it has a number of uh you know it's it
it has some characteristics so memory I looked up what's the definition of memory memory is the continued process
of information retention over time continued process of information
retention over time it's a process it's not a chemical
stored somewhere in the brain and memory has has some characteristics so
there's the encoding how do how is the memory laid down there is the uh
uh let's see no yeah it's laid down it's
stored how is it encoded it's stored and then it's retrieved that's you know that's
functionally that's what the memory does right so it turns out and there are different
kinds of memory they're short-term memory and long-term memory short-term memory only lasts for a few seconds
and it's usually auditory in in nature so we can remember lists of numbers for
example long-term memory is encoded a different
way it's not just repetition it has associated with it some other
kinds of encoding how something looks how something sounds somatic
coding throws it definitely into the long-term memory what that means is it has a
meaning when we store it with a meaning it goes into long-term memory
so when we say uh
a siren going off we hear siren then in that siren we can hear danger or
we can hear safety depending on what we laid down how we think about that sound does that
sound mean somebody is coming to save me or does that sound mean oh there's people in danger somewhere what what is
what is the emotional thing laid down in that memory circuit along with what you
hear now the reason I'm talking about all of this is it affects how we view our experience
just the process of how the brain works so for example
um when I smell yeast I get happy
automatically my mood goes up and I go oh it is associated with a very old memory
of my mother baking bread and when she baked bread
at the time I initially started thinking about this and the neuro circuit was set
up I felt very safe
really safe there's my mother making bread and I'm just standing there while she's making
bread now the details of that I actually don't have in my memory bank
but as I tell the story I'm reinforcing that association between yeast the smell
of yeast and the memory of being safe
and every time I tell myself that story I embellish it a little bit you know it's like well yeah I kind of remember
she had this aluminum bowl that she's just no maybe that was for the biscuits but but I do remember right and so as as
you begin to expand the story you start creating other associations
just the smell of yeast
all of the things that we conjure up about our experience
can be found in these memory banks that consist of neural circuits
now the reason I'm spending so much time on this is I want us to understand
the depersonalizing that occurs when you look at it as just a neural circuit and
not from the point of view of ownership this is me and who I am
as soon as we make this Association where we say the this experience this sensory input
has this meaning we are shifting away from the experience
into what we think about the experience
we've added things together and homogenized them in such a way that we begin to think that this memory
this process of putting together data is who I am
it's me when it's just a process
it's just a process so when we obsess about something
we're reinforcing it as a neural circuit in our brain as we retell a story to ourselves we're
reinforcing it so if I tell a story um
these people have upset me these people are really terrible people this person
is really a horrible person I'm laying down a memory Trace that says
when I hear the sound of this person's voice
I have a bad reaction a reaction this is bad this is undesirable
this is unpleasant maybe when I said ice cream you imagined
the ice cream splotch on your favorite shirt and ice cream is not a pleasant thing
for you at all and for someone else is a very pleasant thing it's just ice cream
and in fact it's not really ice cream it's the idea of ice cream
to my knowledge there's no ice cream in this room and we're not directly experiencing it
or we see a highway patrolman what happens do you automatically step on the brake
and look at to see what your speed is I do
it's amazing to me how quickly that happens and I say well why are you doing that I'm not necessarily speeding
break first thing break somewhere in the in the laying down of
that with that car the appearance of that car means is some fear associated
with authority discipline something and the reaction is I have to I have to
be sure I have to be I have to be safe
when we think you know well the fear reaction comes is you know
an automatic reaction comes from the amygdala we have all these stories about the location of these thoughts and the
source of fear really it can be found in these memory
circuits that aren't necessarily true
aren't necessarily real they're just habits of mind
so when we talk about habits of mind we're not really just talking about
our tendency to do something we're actually talking about not seeing
how this set of conditions is triggering some circuit
that calls for a certain reaction
it's you know it's not really our fault it's kind of how the brain works
but when we see it when we see oh look I'm reacting
we can say but I don't have to because it is not me
it's just something that you know what it's misinterpreting what's going on
so this afternoon my husband came to me and he said uh no I said let's have some tofu and
vegetables for dinner he said okay great he said you know uh we'll try out that
new press that we've got and he said we'll put some olive oil on it
so I looked at him and I thought olive oil now the way he interpreted that was I
did not want olive oil under any conditions to be put on the tofu so he baked the tofu
which turned out to be really you know hard and and kind of crisp and tasteless
because he interpreted my look to be oh whatever you do don't put oil on the
tofu and no amount of my saying you know it kind of depends on what you're doing
with the tofu whether you put oil on it had any impact
he had already heard that I didn't want oil on the tofu now all of this is just
interpretation
it wasn't my intention it's not what he wanted to do but he wanted to please me
okay that's interesting this happens all the time
in order for us to learn from our mindfulness what's
actually happening we have to watch what the Mind does we
have to be able to see oh this is the mind doing that
so in uh in the last month despite all my efforts and good actions
I managed to contract covid and it was interesting to get coveted
because well there were all kinds of ways to watch my my mind work under those
conditions so I noticed anger coming up I told the FDA they should be freeing up
that next booster shot and I'd laughed at this what am I being angry at you
know some faceless government organization that I felt should have been doing something they didn't do and sure enough
I got coveted and it's their fault
we often assign blame when we feel discomfort
and it's very difficult to appreciate the fact that we are causing that
suffering not they it is our reaction to that suffering to
that stimulus it is totally owned by us
that anger is my fault well maybe not my fault it's just that
narrow circuit but I have to own it it's still my choice
to allow it to stay there it arises it passes away unless I keep
telling my story about how the FDA was remessed for not releasing the shot right the more often I tell that story
The more often I have a justification for being angry
or I watched my energy level being really low really
low energy and I was starving all I wanted to do was eat
I was just starving well I wasn't starving but my body was reacting to low energy
by saying we got to get the energy up let's eat some food because the energy that was being used
up all the ATP was being used up fighting off the infection
and I was unable to say you know you're not starving and then I would catch myself and say
you know Maria you're not starving you don't have to eat you don't have to chew
to to watch the reaction and say I don't have to I don't have to
so that it's not me saying well I'm not going to allow myself to eat so that I'm denying something I'm
saying the urge to eat is definitely here I feel like I'm starving
but what's actually happening is I feel this hollowness in my stomach well the hollowness in the stomach can
be caused by any number of things sadness feeling of isolation
I got caught after all I made a contract with the universe if I
always wore my mask and got my shots this wouldn't happen and look what happened
and to feel that caving in part and say you know that's not actually
hunger it's the caving in so that I can separate what is the
experience from the meaning that has been assigned based on
how the brain is working
you have to actually catch yourself doing this and it takes a lot of practice
you have to just keep walking you have to say oh
look at that it's doing that again
we come to recognize the tendency of the Mind to correlates around a concept
around any around sensory input hearing taste smell feeling
oh this means and to watch the Mind say this means
in Buddhist practice when we talk about what is experience we talk about the
Aggregates and we say okay here's how we know we're having an experience the features of the experience
or the physical sensory input the the feeling tone this is Pleasant
unpleasant or neutral the naming the concept this is you know
I picked this up this is round it's cool there's some fluid in here and I call
this a glass that's a concept as soon as I name it now I've given it function and meaning
and usefulness it's still just a piece of glass which
you know glass is a liquid actually but okay
it makes sounds when I tip touch it with my fingernail okay so there's the concept and then
there's a well this is a nice glass I like the lines on the glass now I'm thinking about the concept so there's
the thinking part the thinking mind and then there's the awareness
until I looked down at this glass it didn't even exist
until I look up I could sit here with my eyes closed talking and none of you would be here you might as well be
uh listening on YouTube or something
so those pieces of the experience
can be found in all of our experiences and when we look at them closely
we can distinguish between The Experience itself
and the meaning we've assigned to that experience the concept attached to that experience
so why is that important as we look at what is the experience
happening In This Moment a it means we're in this moment and not
in our memory we're not relating it to what happened before that kind of reflective thinking
can be very useful when you're solving problems but if you're just looking at an experience
to see just the experience it's all extra stuff
and it can be misleading and the concept that we attached however
we describe the experience then conditions us for the next moment
when we are here in this moment having a new experience with conditions that are not exactly the
same because now we've added the preconception to the next moment
I'm depressed I have low energy and I'm depressed
oh and now there follows from that all the things I'm looking for around depression and the feeling that I need
to get out of depression and why am I depressed I shouldn't be depressed and know I'm I'm criticizing and I'm lost in
the self-critical mode and each of these things is building on the other
when really it was just low energy and maybe the problem is
I have covered and I'm weary maybe the problem isn't depression to
begin with but created by my adding a concept to the feeling of
very low energy
and so when we tell people you know when you notice that you are
anxious just stay with the anxiety let it be the just let it be there
I wonder how useful that is because as soon as we call it anxiety
we have a whole string of meaning to attach to that word anxiety
and anxiety is not a momentary thing but it becomes another thing and we reify it
we make that experience into something rather than the process that it began
with
and we get trapped into cycles of suffering having to do with just the way the brain
works and are saying yeah yeah I get it I know what that is so
I have I've been working on a major project
for three years for my homeowners association having to do with installing EV Chargers
this was it unpopular project nobody really wanted it
and when I started out three years ago it was just an idea let's see how we can
make EV charging capability possible in our apartment complex because we're
limited it's an old complex and I have a charger
but that means other people in the building may not be able to put it in because there's a limited capacity
so I started looking into this and lo and behold as time went on Peninsula clean energy came up with some
incentives for people like us to install EV Chargers and so now we have a project
and last week the board approved it and pce approved
the incentives and it's actually going to happen but the last six weeks of the project
were hell I kept thinking we already decided we
were going to do this let's go let's go and everybody was moving at a different pace
and I was thinking all the things that could happen because I'm used to Big projects and
that they always have something happen and Things fall out of bed and then you have to pick them up
but for sure it's not going to happen if you don't start
and I noticed patterns of stress being set up that we're very familiar to me
from my work life and I thought wait a minute wait a minute what's going on here I could feel
the reactions the reactions that would set in and and how I was going to solve these and how important it was
hmm and as I asked more and more questions of myself what's really happening here
what's really happening here I came to understand that I was falling into an old pattern
that I didn't have to there were several things that happened
one of them was that because I'd been working on it so long I owned it it was
mine my project
my very important project as soon as I said it's not your project
you don't need this to happen there's nothing if this doesn't happen
there are no consequences to you and in fact it just means you know
there'll be another solution in the future but it won't be this solution and so what are you attached to that is
causing the suffering
and I realized I was attached to a feeling of ownership responsibility
competence I could make this happen and as soon as I let go of that all of
the stress went away as soon as I said I don't actually have to do this
I don't have to make this my project it doesn't have to be about me
I don't have to be embarrassed because they've asked me to go get somebody to get in writing what they've told me
verbally I don't have to be feel like this is a failure for me I
don't have to react this way but I have to see it really carefully I
have to see that's what's happening in order to stop creating my own
suffering
I have to see what's being triggered
I have to see how the mind is interpreting everything that's
happening and that I don't have to interpret it that way
I don't have to look at the people who are dragging their feet
and think negative thoughts about them
I don't have to I can say oh they're really worried
about something and not make it about
me really really
actually difficult actually difficult to rephrase
the meaning that the brain assigns to something
so another thing that's going on is around me that there's a golf course and they're re -constructing this golf
course and they've cut down trees huge huge redwood trees and
digging up the yard and they're all these strange pieces of equipment
and I watched the pieces of equipment moving around and I try to imagine what
they're doing what is that thing that looks like a dungeon beetle that big thing that's got
that big thing on the front of it and what is it doing and why are they doing that
and the process of watching The Mind curious
I can see that the mind is trying to establish meaning around every piece of equipment
they're doing this so that this is true they're doing this because and to watch the mind doing that allows
me to feel what the Mind feels like when it's creating Concepts
does that make any sense sort of the experience of watching The
Mind make new connections
make new stories and what was interesting was to have my
husband and I both looking at the same dung beetle piece of equipment which was his phrasing for that by the way
I called it a rake to look at that and see that we were forming different meanings for what that
device was doing he says oh well it's digging up the
roots I said no no no no it's sorting through those piles of debris you know just
different stuff not important not significant but to realize that the meaning that is
established by the mind is based on experiences that have come before
all of the conditions of our lives have conditioned the way we react to what's coming next
we have to see that and the way we see that
is by constantly
being mindful watching watching what's happening seeing what's happening we just keep
walking and the longer the more consistently we walk
the more we see the more we see
the more clearly we see we just keep practicing
and what comes out of it is the realization that we don't have to judge what we see
oh oh that's happening
we replace judgment with discernment Ah that's what's happening
know where you're going and go there
be aware of your intentions and take the next step
that's it thank you
so I'm sorry I talked a little longer than I expected but if you have any questions we can talk
afterwards or now if you have something you want to say
okay may you watch the mind
it's a magical device but it doesn't do magical things
it just does what it sees may you see clearly and well thank you
good night