all right so let's go ahead and get started as you're settling me in and
saying hello now finding a posture for meditation
just sitting
allowing yourself to feel the body and the sitting posture
feeling the contact where you're sitting
your seed against the chair or the cushion
or what you're lying on just having a sense of being here
sometimes meditation is called taking the one seat
you take your seat in the middle of experience
okay in a sense is to stay there
not get drawn away by things that come and knock on the door
or wave at you through the window you're just sitting in your seat
resting
and yet you're aware of all of experience so
we'll expand our awareness piece by piece so beginning first
with this sense of the body sitting in the room where you are
can feel the space around you
and then opening further to other aspects of
physical experience so you can sense the sounds
there's the sound of my voice there may be other sounds around you
from the household or from nature or outside
or maybe you are outside sitting in nature opening to The Sounds
and also the silence in which those sounds are occurring
and then we become aware of the inner experiences in the body
so allowing awareness to include the sensations of grieving
the inner sensations of the body
feelings like the clothing against the skin
the natural strength and straightness of the spine
pressure where you're sitting
the various movements of energy through the body
allowing all of these to enter into awareness
now beginning to include also the mind
different aspects so noticing if there are any
emotions presence in your experience
that may be very clear or maybe not maybe there's just a general mood
or maybe the mind is quite neutral and they're just emotional shifts now and then
just see how it is and include those in awareness
all while sitting in the one seat not getting drawn in
and opening awareness further to include thoughts
if there's any thinking or thoughts going on in the mind
we just open the space of the mind so that those come in and out
the way clouds come in and out in the sky
forming out of nothing drifting around sometimes dissipating in
the Wind
so the space of the Mind
holds the thoughts that come and go
now letting the mind be so large and vast that
can even hold our background assumptions and views
ways that we see the world just one more aspect of the Mind actually
[Music]
these things too or phenomena that can be seen and held in the
vast Stillness of the Mind
foreign
all of experience space around us the sounds
bodily Sensations [Music] emotions thoughts
I use
these are all things that we can be aware of
within a large sky like or ocean-like mind
all of experience can come and go and it's multitude of varied forms
we can also ask what knows this
times there's a shift in experience
when we turn to include even the knowing
in the realm of what we can be aware of
so just resting foreign
totality of experience
even allowing the sense of practicing or observing
to Fall Away
that too is extra
just this
foreign
attention gets drawn into something
when you notice that gather what energy is available
and put it back into awareness
re-strengthen awareness and rest there
foreign
sensing the great peace that is available
in awareness
feeling how it can fill and pervade experience
such that everything that comes and goes just feels like part of nature
and what a valuable way of being this is to bring to the world
there's so much struggle in the world trying to get this or that trying to
stop this or that
it's not that we would never make any movements or choose any actions
but doing so from a place of vastness where it can all be
held and seen
means that our actions come from wisdom and compassion
they actually do real benefit in the world help to align things balance things
rather than contributing to the lurching around and imbalance
that so much characterizes
our unaware life
so let it be that we contribute to the awareness of the world
trusting that our cultivation of that quality extends out
from us into others into the world
since awareness is not something that we just hold for ourselves
it's more like something that's available we increase its availability
eye opening to it and that's a gift to the world
[Music]
so we've made it to the last item in our list of seven methods for letting go
but first there was a question in the chat yesterday for the pseudo-reference
we are broadly following the teaching found in mn2 the savasa vasuta
but I've I've brought in other teachings as needed
so we've talked about letting go or abandoning by seeing by restraining by
using by avoiding by enduring and by removing
and many of the earlier ones were about somehow getting free of unwholesome
states of mind and that is great and necessary but it's not the whole story
we also have to develop wholesome States and we're in a position to do that very
effectively once the unwholesome ones are not dragging us down
so today we have Letting Go by developing and there will also be a kind
of a reprise of Letting Go by seeing so to be clear it is wholesome to let go
of the unwholesome of course but imagine now that you've cut away a hundred
pounds of weight that you were dragging behind your bicycle now you can really Cruise you can go
around corners more smoothly you can do tricks you can ride up steep hills
you know it's one kind of development to develop the skills to abandon what is
unskillful and it's a different kind of development to actively pursue what is
skillful the Buddha differentiated different types of wise effort and half of them
are about handling what is problematic and half of them are about fostering
what is beautiful so what are we developing
broadly speaking we're developing the Eightfold Path so that's right or we
could also say wise or appropriate Right View intention speech action
livelihood effort mindfulness and concentration and when they're appropriate and right
all of these are wholesome and skillful and they pervade all aspects of our life
they touch into all different um aspects of our being
and then in meditation specifically there are
also many important qualities to develop and they're developed more in meditation but then they also bleed out into our
daily life also and in particular the the suta and then two names the seven factors of Awakening
as appropriate things to develop so the first of those is something that
we're all familiar with which is mindfulness that's the first of the factors of Awakening and it's said to be
always useful you know like you can't kind of can't have too much so awareness ends up being our greatest
resource on the path something that we continually develop and strengthen
and also which supports the whole process of the path
by helping us to see where we're starting to go off track or what else we
might need to bring in it's a it's a balancing factor in the mind also foreign
and then the other six factors of Awakening are divided into two different
uh two different types let's say the first type is the energizing three of them are
energizing qualities and those are investigation and energy and joy
and note in particular the last one that Joy is a factor of Awakening so we're
moving toward having a deep sense of inner well-being and happiness that's
regardless of conditions you know we can think about Joy because the sunrise is beautiful this morning or
Joy because of our family or our material circumstances in some way
but those conditions are quite unreliable and there are other forms of
joy that go very deep that are more about the quality of our heart
and you know it takes a while to really cultivate this and bring it to the fore and of course it's fine to have other
kinds of Joy but you know we're just aware of the role that that can play and
it is energizing it brings in aliveness to our being
and then the investigation is the you know the continual checking into experiences they're suffering here or
not is this skillful or not am I aware or not
and that that brings Natural Energy spiritual energy to our being so we have
ways of enlivening ourselves and we can see this in very Advanced Spiritual
Beings teachers and others that are um you know they always
have an aliveness to them their eyes are bright faculties are fresh even when they're very old
so that's these these factors and then in addition the other three
Awakening factors are calming factors and those are Tranquility concentration
and equanimity so we there's a supreme balance and
calmness that comes and it comes from what for knowing from knowing how things actually work from knowing that
everything's going to change and so I don't need to grasp on to things
and from also just knowing that that kind of peace is better than the piece
of sensual stimulation say or the Joy or the happiness from that
that the the calmness is such a needed quality not only for us but for others
so these seven factors together mindfulness investigation energy Joy Tranquility
concentration and Equanimity uh form a very beautiful set in the mind and they
sometimes if you look at them carefully they include seeming opposite movements energizing and calming and so we're
asked to consider maybe how the mind can expand to hold all of these how can we
be highly energized and joyful and also tranquil and the corners
in fact the mind can be energized and calm at the same time when those are
spiritual qualities so is it strange that developing can
lead to letting go no actually it's not strange it is one of it's one of several different fruits
that can come from developing but let me name first one of the initial
fruits of doing some development of Olson States and that is that the Mind
gains genuine protection so there's a story of a king who wanted
to make his kingdom safe for people to walk in by covering everything in
Leather so there wouldn't be any Thorns or sharp stones or you know things to trip on so we wanted to cover the whole
Kingdom in leather and his wise advisor pointed out that it would be much better
to give everyone shoes and so it's like that in our practice
you know we can look out at the world and see all kinds of dangers and problems we might be afraid to go out
and walk or we can put on shoes and go so if our heart is strong it's okay to
go out and walk among the thorns and the rough patches that could literally be outside in the world or it could be the
thorny patches in our own mind and heart where we haven't ventured yet part of this practice is to keep
uncovering more and more in our heart and we do that by getting stronger in
one area and then using that strength to go into new areas
and that's just the initial benefit and what further fruit is that when our mind is fortified with mindfulness and
Clarity and calm we will begin to naturally release more subtle forms of
dukkha so development does lead to letting go we're not always just working
with blatantly on wholesale landscape mind States and unskillful behaviors we
also have you know we have these more subtle forms of Duca that we need to let
go of also we have various ways of subtly identifying with experience you know
thinking that it's about me maybe we are genuinely kind and generous
much of the time and that in itself is a great accomplishment if we can get
ourselves to that state but in the background we might subtly believe that
I am a generous person that's who I am and once you know once we start having
these more refined qualities of heart mindfulness energy Joy Equanimity the
things that I named we start to feel a little bit of tension or wind drag as
Gil would say when the mind is enacting these more subtle patterns of eye making
in my making and those can be released by noticing how they cast a shadow on the wholesome
mind you know the Buddha says very clearly that we should be virtuous but not
identify with our virtue and then there's this teaching from the
samyuta mikhaya it says whatever our haunts perfectly Enlighten
ones arose in the past all those blessed ones had first abandoned the five
hindrances the Corruptions of mine that weakened wisdom and then with their
minds well established in four ways of establishing awareness they had developed correctly the seven
factors of Enlightenment and thereby they had awakened to the unsurpassed perfect Enlightenment and similarly for
our haunts of the future and and the present so
the that the language is a little bit uh complex and characteristic of the sutas but it says
every Buddha has abandoned the five hindrances established the four foundations of mindfulness and developed
the seven factors of Awakening and that's what makes a Buddha I think it will be the same for us
so then we can have a reprise of seeing if
you will so recall from Monday that seeing is the most fundamental way of
letting go we talked about it then in terms of seeing clearly whether the trend in the mind is toward unwholesome
or wholesome and making sure we're going in the right direction and you know once we've engaged in the
development of wholesome states which becomes easy when the unholesome ones are at Bay
then we get to a deeper level of seeing where it's even more effective as a way
of letting go so the most basic and skillful way that we can attend to experience is to see in
terms of the Four Noble Truths so we see this is suffering this is the
arising of suffering or the the conditions that are leading to suffering this is the cessation of suffering and
this is somehow part of the path that's going to lead to the cessation of suffering
we can see what aspects of experience are part of the first Noble Truth No Duco what is Duca
and then we know that those are to be fully comprehended and we can see which parts our experience are the conditions
for Duca where where's the grasping and the clinging that are conditioning this Duca and we can abandon that
and then we can see which parts relate to the path that's toward the ending of duga and we can know that ah developing
this is going to be good for my mind and we actually do see moments of Duke
of ceasing and we acknowledge and realize those so that they will
strengthen so that they will create momentum for us to continue on the path
and when we start to see in terms of these four noble truths these four lenses of seeing things instead of in
Terms of me and what I like and I don't like whole new Direction can open up and we
can find the path of letting go so our job is to do the practices to see
in the terms of the four noble truths and to cultivate the means of letting go and then the Letting Go will take care
of itself at some point was once criticized for telling one
person one thing and another person another thing you know the student basically said you're inconsistent in
what you tell people how is that correct and he laughed and said I'm like someone
who's watching people walk down a road and if they're going off to the right then I call out go left and if they're
going off to the left then I call out go right so you know those would sound like contradictory instructions if they're
taken out of context but they're each correct for that person's situation
so it's like that with our practice too sometimes we're going left or right sometimes we avoid sometimes we use
sometimes we restrain sometimes we cultivate it's good to develop the skill
of knowing how to nudge ourselves in the right direction in a given case and of course sometimes everything is
fine and you don't need to change anything just live just live your life
and it might be that these seven different methods we talked about this week are not always so distinct you know
which one exactly am I doing that don't worry about it just be aware that there
are different aspects of how we can move toward letting go so next time you ask how can I let go of
my anger consider that there are a variety of practices to engage in that could lead
to that letting go and we just have to do them with diligence with Good Will without grasping to the result
and then someday the Dharma will surprise you with a release Letting Go does happen
so I hope this week of teaching says giving you some sense of The Art of
Letting Go and that it will continue to fill and nourish and enrich your life
thank you be well