hello everyone and welcome and here we are the
the fifth of these five part series on I'm calling locations for awareness
and one of the kind of uh maybe difficult things to
understand about awareness is a degree to which it's a condition constructed phenomena
that uh the mind to some degree
and to some degree constructs its ideas of what it means to be aware
and so the idea that there's a location for awareness
has some truth and it also has some sense of a choice and a construction
and what happens when awareness is not constructed when it's allowed to just be
and this comes into a play particularly with the idea that there's a here and
there that there's a place to be aware from and there's something that we're being
aware of and at times this is completely normal and natural to have that sense
and there are times when the mind gets quiet enough for still enough that where we are very aware
but awareness has no location it's just everywhere in a sense if or
nowhere we're very aware very clear there's a lot of clarity
and but the objects of awareness are not objects they are there's not like awareness and
then objects the there's just a things that are known
and the knowing arise together and it can be a little bit feeling like
um you know like um you know objects in space
deep and darkest space I suppose there's just something exists without any reference to anything else
so an object can exist without any reference to anything else exist in awareness and attention
so uh might be difficult unusual to understand
what I'm trying to say but uh we'll do a little meditation and see if uh maybe you can get some feeling
for this so to assume a meditation posture
and to
gently close your eyes
and to gently
become aware gently
gently come aware of your body
thin feeling the substance of your body the weight against your chair or your
cushion
to feel the weights of your hands and if their hands are resting upon
something feeling that resting of the weight
and then within this body to take a slow long slow deep breath
and as the Torso expands to feel it as a massage from the inside
a stretching and opening and as the inhale as the Torso contracts
again feel it the other half of the rhythm of a massage
a gentle
caring for the body
letting the breathing return to normal
and as you exhale to relax the body
soften the different parts of your body scanning through
and then gently as you exhale to relax the thinking mind
the energy agitation of thinking any sense of contraction or pressure
coagulation and the thinking mind
and then at the end of the exhale a really feeling for a world
the exhale whenever you're exhaling a heightened kind of sensing
the physical experience of exhaling
how the chest moves the diaphragm the belly
and when you come to the end of the exhale for a second or so
pause before you inhale
and in that pause maybe you can let go more relax more
for there to be more of the exhale
and if that happens and pause again at the very end
one way or the other let there be a pause at the end of the exhale
feeling the sensations in your body where that pause occurs
and then allow for the inhale to begin
allow the sensations of inhale
to come into awareness
if pausing at the end of the exhale causes some discomfort and breathing that
throws it off a little bit let there be almost a pause at the end
so that there's a little heightened ability
to receive the inhale
and allow for thee exhale
allow the body to release as you exhale
receiving the inhale allowing the exhale
noticing if more your awareness is in the sensations of breathing
awareness is more maybe in the head or the knowing of
breathing
is there a distance between awareness the knowing
and the breathing
is there a sense that there's an object that Sensations to be aware of
and you being aware
and if there is what are the sensations what's the
feeling what's the location of the U that's
aware what's the feeling what's the sensation
of that which is aware
that's which is receptive that which is allowing
and if there is a U or that which is receptive or allowing
on the exhale see let that relax let that soften
letting the sense of a do or of mindfulness
recede into the background let it evaporate
and there's no receiving no allowing
the sensations of breathing just are they appear
in awareness
no distance between awareness
and what you're aware of
the sensations of breathing appear
in vast space each sensation each experience of
breathing just is
an awareness of breathing just is
inseparable
knowing
has no location apart from the sensation
heat sensation no need to
for it to exist in a reference to anything else
breathing breathing itself
no watcher
just aware
no distance just awareness
no location
just awareness
no receiver of experience
no victim of experience
no actor of experience just knowing just awareness experience
by itself
Breathing by itself is not thinking
breathing is free of thinking
thinking is an overlay isn't is a separate process than breathing
to be aware of breathing without thinking
that reference to thought just breathing
foreign
when there is no thinking or beyond the edges of thinking
awareness experience just is
without location distance here or there
thought about conceived conceptualized
take awareness with that self experience without a experiencer
nothing extra nothing added
to the basic simplicity
of experience
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
take a few moments to relax on the exhale
soften whatever is
energized or contracted or
and with any doubt any sense of
distance close or far away no sense of receiving or being active
hello there to arise some notion of care and kindness
kindness that for now has no object
nothing not thinking of anybody just kindness which has no
reference point of other people other places other times
just kindness care love
within an outen object
maybe love that has no
location because it's everywhere
everywhere in the field the range the range of how far away you can
hear or sense or feel or imagine
that love is part and parcel of whatever way
whatever field of awareness there might be here
and in this objectless love for care
to fill it with universal Goodwill for others
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may all beings
be known peacefully within this within the range of
awareness within mindfulness
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this fifth talk on locations for awareness or perspectives
on awareness and this theme for this week
is was selected because last time I was
here I talked about compassion and this week next week next week I'd
like to continue this theme of compassion but in between I wanted to
explore the medium through which compassion travels or occurs or is
is stimulated and that Medium is our capacity for
attention if we have compassion for another person who's suffering
then um only way that we know they're suffering is we know it there's an awareness of it
there's a attention experience it in some way
and and that act that they were Act of knowing Act of being aware can often go
unexamined unconsidered it's almost as if there is no separation
it's just suffering and that we experience that suffering almost sometimes and sometimes the
empathy so-called empathy of other people suffering uh is experienced and
it's too hard for people they feel overwhelmed they feel like they're way too sensitive they feel that they get exhausted or
from it or they don't quite understand how to have
compassion because they don't quite they feel kind of apart from other people's suffering and don't feel like
doesn't touch them in some way so a lot of this has to do with the
nature of how we're being aware and we can be aware in different ways
and so to begin knowing the range and the variety of ways in which knowing
comes into existence um you know we know something because we
see it we know something because we hear it if someone tells us a story about someone who's suffering the medium
through which that's coming is through the hearing if we're with someone who's suffering we
see it then it's through the seeing and um if we're sitting you know by
ourselves and we remember that someone who's suffering then it's through the medium of our thoughts our images in the
mind our memory so these are all different means of becoming aware
and then there's a sense of uh how we're aware from where we're aware of this
and often enough the locus of awareness is our sense of self
in fact that Locus sometimes is what around what we construct a sense of self
also um and so how we're aware the location which we're aware from
is are we is something that we can change and adjust that's been the theme for this week
and a skilled use of awareness of mindfulness is to be sensitive to how
the different ways in which we can be aware and then be able to have some skill in choosing how to be aware
if we don't choose the difference between all the different modalities of awareness than if the modality of
awareness which we have is not serving us when we're with suffering then we're just going to keep touching
into that to this unhelpful way of sharing and suffering of others in a way
that it's exhausting or there's or it's uh debilitating or we just feel too much
pain to really have effective compassion so to find a way of being aware that
allows us to be balanced allows us not to be to suffer more than the person who's suffering
to suffer less to but to be empathic to feel to know what's happening
so we can move around our awareness we can sometimes sometimes it helps to feel
like we're really removed like the Mind steps back and gets the bird's eye view sometimes we can get really close we
don't physically get close but it really kind of the sense close to what's happening and maybe it's feeling closely
what's happening to ourselves because if we're not if we use this medium awareness to only be aware of
others then we're missing out on the impact and what how we're participating in it in
the in the experience that we're having and if we're only with ourselves then it
also can be imbalanced the whole situation so yesterday I talked about the 50 50 approach to being aware of 50
here 50 there as meditation as mindfulness becomes
richer and Fuller for people um one way that we can be aware of in of
people suffering beware of compassion be aware in general is to have the awareness not be yoked
to our sense of self to Me Myself and mine that to have that part of the mind not a
hijack or not engaged with how we're aware what we're aware of
and um and just just be aware and not even being aware receptively
because of a receptive awareness there's something someone who's receiving
not be actively aware of going out to be aware out there because then there's an actor someone who's doing the the
awareness there's this marvelous kind of middle way that we just can be aware without being
the receiver and without being the actor who goes and it can be there could be a lot of
clarity it's not being aloof or disconnected but it's a connection which
is not um doesn't have a receiver doesn't have a thought idea concept
stories about who I am and what I have to do and my responsibilities and and uh
this is the you know that this is something I have to deal with I have to respond to and this is happening to me
there's a victim here here I go again and there's a lot of extra stuff that
comes along that has a lot to do with our conceptual mind that our thinking
mind and our our that something it's kind of activation is going on that we
don't even know we're activated it just it seems like this is how it always is
meditation as we get quieter and quieter settled more and more settled then at
some point the construct of a receiver even receiving is not needed
the construct of having the mind go towards something and become aware of it does not need it
there's just allowing whatever arises in Awareness whatever it might be without choice
just arise without a sense of a doer or receiver without a sense of it's out
there and I'm here without distance without and the same
time is no distance there is a
no concern for distance it isn't like we're glued to anything that's not that
kind of lack of distance it's it's because there's no reference point
for distance no reference point for being glued to something just arises
and um and it can be phenomenally respectful for oneself and for others
this kind of very relaxed open awareness because it allows each thing to be just
what it is for itself so the
um so sometimes it's completely wonderful and fun even and appropriate
to be to take agency over how we're aware and
to adjust how we're aware and find how to be aware that's the right way for the moment the appropriate way for us for
the situation and then sometimes what can we be available to us is just dropping away of
self dropping away of a reference point and isn't that we're becoming shut down
or Aloo for disconnected there's a lot of sensitivity to our you
know our body our mind our thoughts What's Happening Here it just it's not
organized around this idea of a central person who's having this experience
but we're responsible for all of this we know all of this but we're not engaged in that kind of preoccupation agitation
Around Me Myself and mine and there can be a lot of presence for
another person and um and there's just kind of a sense of Freedom a sense of Infinite Space
that things just exist there in their own simplicity in a ways at times when it's really
strong there's no future and past it's just what it is there's no here nor
there it's just what it is there's no closeness and no aloofness or
distance it's just what's there and everything is just there
and um and that's a marvelous way for compassion just to arise and compassion
is just there compassion has been triggered has been awakened but there's no burden to
compassion there's no obligation to compassion there's no me that has to do something with this it's all just kind
of allowed to arise and be there compassion arises and if there's a
something we can do the motivation to do it arises in that same freedom
um it's a deep deep trust in allowing this deeper stuff to occur
and as long as we have this heightened sensitivity it's heightened Clarity to what's up in your body our minds and
thoughts then uh the intuition is not going to be a hijacked by our preferences our
our unhelpful desires or our ego some people let go of just really trust
their intuition in this kind of way that I'm talking about but they're not really in touch with themselves very well
they're not really aware of what's happening in themselves and sometimes they do mistakes and they act
impulsively or they don't realize how much they're acting on ego or desires it just feels like they're just free and
allowing things to happen so um
so next week I'll talk about compassion and I'm hoping that this prepares the
ground that as you hear about compassion and how I'm going to talk about it that
uh you will have you will consider how to adjust the medium for how to be aware
the way to be aware of suffering in the world and to so that how you're aware
allows for something deeper to happen which is what I'll talk about tomorrow next week
and so in preparation for that if you have the time and the inclination for
this weekend as you become aware of your own Suffering The Suffering of others
explore a little this thing about the medium of awareness how are you aware
what's the location from which from which you're aware what's the me the way in which you know it is it more feeling
in the body it's more in the head with thoughts it's more from a distance more close in
which of all those is a useful way to be there and then maybe they they all have their
own use at different times and and then is there something about uh
being with suffering that um is a radically simple so simple that
it's just suffering just compassion just presence just attention without all the crowd being
crowded in by thoughts
uh obligation responsibilities fixing it
experiencing and being the experiencer how it is for me just allowed to be so so explore this and um
and then maybe uh you the more you can explore this over the weekend I'm hoping the more you'll understand
the uh the tremendous value of that compassion has for this path of
mindfulness and how it really can there's a very significant way to learn about mindfulness and how to um develop
on this path so thank you very much
and maybe I've said this before a reminder not this Sunday but the
following one on the 16th uh IMC is going to have an online community meeting at 11 o'clock Sunday morning so
after the Sunday morning program and your important part of the community All of You Who Come here to at the 7 A.M
and um you're very heartfully welcome to come and be part of the discussion about
the community life of IMC and what's happening with the pandemic and at the
stage and other things about this community so the zoom link will be available a
couple of days before an imc's calendar so thank you very much