good morning everyone good morning welcome it's lovely to see all of the names and
the warm greetings popping up on the chat all of your locations
California Oregon Washington Calgary Chicago Bainbridge it's really
lovely to see people from all over warm welcome to you
so just as you're greeting each other maybe um
if you don't already do it take a moment to scroll through the chat and just appreciate all the warmth and
friendliness in this online Sangha that has been cultivated over these years now
of every weekday meeting 7 A.M Pacific time
it's really quite something
[Music] warms my heart inspires me
so we're about to get started um
for those of you who haven't seen me yet or we haven't met yet my name is Dawn Neil I am
covering for Gill this week and the topic the topic we are covering is inner and
outer Harmony of mind and
so just a refresher on that and um
the invitation as you start to settle in make your greetings read your greetings
to tune into your heart notice how it feels
to see everyone greeting each other maybe participate in it receive my welcome my appreciation
and just really feel it here tune into it for a minute
and then settling settling and
taking a couple of intentional breaths maybe with your hand on your heart just like I have it right now
breathing in as if you could breathe in directly into your heart
breathing out
ah and let that appreciation
sense of community
to being linked all over the world to people practicing now or
at other times well that to sort of enter
your body your mind
and allowing your gaze to be internal
perhaps closing your eyes
from the sensations having arrived here
the feelings of the greetings noticing all of the sensations in your
body and welcoming those to
welcoming your heart and mind as well exactly as they are
and if it feels right setting the intention of this meditation
to greet all experienced that arises with meta kindness
friendliness
doesn't mean condoning subject matter of thoughts necessarily
liking everything but just greeting it reading whatever arises
this too welcome
and then returning to your surroundings as well the soundscape
whether it be a bird song or far off City Escape noises
something else
in creating your internal atmosphere
settling in tuning in to the breathing
to the goodness of the moment wherever it is in the moment
allowing the mind the heart to rest
best in the gentle rising and falling of the belly your chest
we're simply rest in the gentle flux
whatever is arising in now this moment
settling
appreciating me Pleasant Sensations
any feelings warmth connection
acknowledging all that's there
just there's
from time to time reattuning at the moment
seeing how kindly graciously invite to reconnection
with awareness
perhaps you're engaging with loving interest
in the felt sensation known experience of now
and stay immersed in the object of attention breath or sound
or if the awareness feels steady opening up to all that is arising and
flowing through
appreciating allowing being with
foreign
final moments of this meditation
the invitation is to gather up soak in
find any little Glimpse in of goodness
well-being kindness peace any goodness
and favorite appreciate it
allow it to make an impression and the heart mind and body
and then when you're ready
to begin to turn that internal gaze
of your heart your mind outwards to all of those
your life touches
casting your internal Vision far and wide
and perhaps setting the intention that others may also benefit from your practice
that others be peaceful
but they be well
notice how this well-wishing feels in your heart
[Music]
[Laughter]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
[Music]
so dear Sangha welcome welcome to day two of a series on inner and outer
Harmony qualities that we can cultivate that help and gender promote
inner and outer Harmony
yesterday we covered the lives down the practicing for the
benefit of ourselves and for others and for ourselves and
others at the same time and for all beings today I'm just going to touch on the
many benefits personal and interpersonal benefits of Good Will loving kindness
it's one of the qualities that the Buddha taught about both as a meditative practice
as a quality mind heart and as an invaluable
quality in the ways that we show up with other people and most of his teachings were about
asanga but he also taught us to lay people daily life
it's well documented both in the ancient Buddhist teachings and in modern science
that there are many benefits of cultivating an attitude a disposition of good will
kindness Mecca so I'm just going to start with inviting
you to take in some of the different translations for the word meta most
often called loving kindness just feel them in your body and feel maybe a
memory or a felt sense of what resonates in your own life
in your circumstances your personality okay so the word called unless there's
no one single translation for any poly word it seems
is meta as friendliness
non-hatred
sympathy Amity
kindness benevolence
beneficent
Goodwill love
and active interest in others
active interest in others
so maybe some of these qualities seem familiar maybe all of them do
either having been on the receiving end of them or feeling them noticing them in
your life and it's really true that for many people go
fronstop being one of them loving kindness and compassion can naturally lead to the emergence can
actually come from the emergence of mindfulness practice sorry so
for some people the cultivation of this practice mindfulness practice just
kind of at some point transforms their hearts the way they show up
and for others it's also helpful to cultivate it directly and the Buddha offers practices
for that specific ones
I'll explore the benefits and techniques in detail of that practice actually in a
loving kindness an introduction to loving kindness course that I'm teaching in March through the Sati Center
so I'm not going to really go into it here so today I'm actually mostly going to
talk about how those benefits support our overall meditation practice and
relationships so
we get to the right page
[Music] a kind attitude an inner posture of good
will and the mind and the Heart is a huge benefit a huge boob support
for mindfulness practice Insight practice
some of the um known benefits both in the ancient discourses and in modern science
include a reduction of anxiety lessening ill will or hostility
enhancing concentration bolstering confidence
and all of this of course bolsters the capacity for Clear seeing
insight and all of this can emerge as I was saying naturally
from dedicated mindful awareness practice over years or from the specific
practices and techniques the Buddha outlines part of the way that the attitude either
way becomes a part of our hearts and minds and natural part part of the way that the
attitude and practice of meta Goodwill towards ourselves and others
does this is by reducing preoccupation reducing preoccupation especially
self-judgment and self-criticism but also
inordinate judgment criticism or blame of other people and it makes sense right I if I'm
preoccupied on what they did wrong or what I did wrong mind is agitated it kind of stands
and that it's not so conducive to a peaceful meditation it's not so conducive to a peaceful mind and heart
and life so the calming of that the settling of that
and eventually the lessening of it is a treat of this tendency to
blame or judge or criticize all of that has
benefits that bolster maturity and inclusion in our hearts and Minds in
meditation practice and it has health benefits it turns out
better sleep improved immune response
and better Mental Health and all of these are outlined maybe not using those specific words
in the Buddhist ancient teachings and they're also touched on in a lot of the contemporaries and it's
and of course these qualities don't just appear in and benefit our meditation and one's
personal experience they've still over into the rest of our
lives and benefit relationships
every interaction we have there's a story I've told this recently
in another context the story about a wise gatekeeper that
highlights this so picture back in Ancient India Bronze
Age and there's all these different little city-states sprinkled around and there's one or more Gatekeepers at
each one and um their job is to kind of monitor who flows through and who comes out
and also to orient newcomers all right tell them where to go or
help them get settled in just a little bit give them directions
so there's a wise gatekeeper it's ancient gate of this little city
and one day a group of people comes through getting ready to settle and the head of
household asks the gatekeeper thanks for all the information you know what I really want
to know tell me what people are like here the gatekeeper contemplates for a moment
and they look at the person and they say what were people like where you came from
and a person says oh they were awful mean conniving you
couldn't trust them impolite rude and the gatekeeper kind of nods and says
I think you'll find people much like that here the group goes on and a few hours passed
and another family comes by and that head of household ends up asking the gatekeeper
much the same question so tell us what are the people like here
I'm the gatekeeper asks the same question back what were they like are you
and this person said you know
we came here for this new job but we didn't want to leave they were trustworthy kind
really had your back they did everything good neighbors would do
we're really gonna miss them good people the gatekeeper nod say Julian says I
think you'll find people much like that here
so as the story highlights of course the mental templates the predispositions
that we carry around influence all of our interactions all of our relationships
just as they influence our relationships with ourselves and this might seem really obvious until
one looks at the opposite right the habit of criticizing oneself or
others many of us in Western culture might
default to criticizing ourselves and this can often flip to being
critical of other people particularly in conflict the Buddha points out the dangers of
this attitude towards conflict he says and this this comes from the dhamapada
during conflict it's easy to see The Faults of others hard to see one song
if one focuses on others faults and constantly takes offense one's own toxins flourish
when Zone toxins flourish that can be true even if we're overly
focused on our own effects right
it's really important not to take on all the blame or to shift all the blame somewhere else
rather than blame the practice or the emergence of meta
kindness asks us to notice to learn
or the sense of compassionate understanding for foibles our own and others
bitter seeds of blame or criticism reap a bitter fruit in the mind and heart and
in our relationships right and happily the opposite is also true
kindness and good will create a beneficial resonance and contagious
this from Dr David Hamilton an act of kindness is like a pebble
dropped in a pond just as the pebble lifts lily pads at the other side of the pond
so an act of kindness lifts the person you help and also many others connected to that
person as their own Spirits are lifted their behavior towards others is Kinder to
so as many of you have heard me talk about there is this ripple effect of our practice of kindness
that has an uplifting effect on our lives on our relationships physical health
and the well-being of others and ever widening ripples
so over the next 24 hours perhaps notice notice how you already
might bring all these different flavors of meta Goodwill to your meditation
practice or your life or your interactions and notice where you might want to bring
in just a little bit more maybe talk about it with a friend or write about it or just take a moment or
two in your downtime so those are my Reflections for today
thank you so let's just saying
a little dedication of the benefits of our craft may all beings everywhere
be happy may all beings be safe
May our beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music] [Laughter]
thank you thank you for the sincerity and consistency of your practice
[Laughter]
foreign
[Music]