good morning good morning all what a pleasure it is to be here and
what a warm welcome I received in the chat so thank you for that as many of you can see from the
title of the YouTube that we're going to do poetry of practice again with some different poems I was here I think it
was uh in August couple months ago doing some poetry and I had so much fun doing
that and um I heard from a number of you that you enjoyed it too so here we are
again the Poetry of practice maybe I'll start in a similar
way that I started with uh back in August and that is to just recognize that there is a way in which we can
engage with practice and we can engage
with the Buddhist teachings in a way that is maybe focused on
learning understanding and maybe learning or understanding technique or
teachings and right there's all these Buddhist lists right and but there's this
uh emphasis on learning like gaining something that we didn't have gaining
some knowledge that we didn't have and to be sure I love this way I'm I like to
learn new things and to uh like explore new topics but that's not the only way
right that's not the only way to engage with teachings and practice this way in which we feel like we have to consume
lots of information it can be helpful but there's also a way that invites a
another type of knowing like this way in which we might touch with awareness or
something like that there's this uh maybe a caress
of information a caress of something I don't even quite know how
to explain it but this way in which poetry allows this opening of the heart
and the softening of that which wants to know more and learn
more and maybe poetry also is like a type of coming home that is that we have
to be here and present to feel the poem to touch into the poem so the way that
I'm describing it poetry is maybe a little bit more of a somatic experience
and maybe even the way that I'm using that type of language is maybe like a little not so straightforward but I'm
hoping that you all of us have read poems poetry and maybe you understand what I'm talking to that there's a way
in which poetry sometimes invites this recognition recognition of something
that's true and pure inside of us as opposed to just
like amassing more information allows us to soften this always this leaning
into evaluation or leaning into the next moment do I understand it do I got it as
opposed to maybe the question is oh what does this feel
like as opposed to what am I supposed to
learn so poetry is a way that we allow language to touch us in a different way
different way than our normal way of interacting with perhaps Buddhist teachings or perhaps even just the world
in general many of you know that there's plenty of verse in the PO canon in the
earliest Buddhist literature there's lots of verse there's the Awakening poems there's the dapada there's this
ATA the book of eights the suata you know all all these and so
today I'll drop in some vers is from contemporary
times I'll drop in some during our sit and then during the little daret um
maybe unpack it a little bit what this uh poem means and I'm
delighted to share these with you not necessarily because all of you will love these poems but hopefully just with the
introduction of poetry itself is a pointing towards there's different ways
different ways of being with our experience different ways of being with
[Music] information and we can use all these ways to support our
practice okay with that isn't
introduction and just take a moment to really settle
in maybe a large exhale as
we sit whether that's literal or figurative
that we take a meditation
posture and perhaps feel these sensations of
sitting feel the pressure of the chair cushion the couch the bed whatever
you're sitting on feeling the pressure against the
body feeling the body in cont
we're here connected
grounded just here
can we feel the sensations on the back of our legs that are in
contact our feet that are in
contact in the sensations on the back if we're leaning against a the back of a
chair feel the sensations on the back side where we're
sitting bringing an aliveness of
attention to this experience of being connected to whatever it is we're
sitting on and connected to
here can we bring some mindfulness into the bodily
experience inhabiting the body with presence with
aliveness alive to the body and the way it feels right
now and then setting the sense of direction the
orientation of this meditation is one of
kindness kindness to
ourselves and openness to the
experience as best we can
can if you work with chronic pain or acute pain at this
moment is there a mutual or pleasant experience you can rest your attention
on rather than the
uncomfortable not deny not pretending that the uncomfortable isn't there just
choosing as best we can to rest our attention
elsewhere maybe it is the pressure against the buttocks as we're sitting
that's
neutral and tangible
holding yourself in care holding yourself with a kind
attitude with
warmth
so we're here with an attitude of
care and then rest your attention on the sensations of
breathing feeling the bodily experience of inhales and
exhales
feeling the stretching and the release of the
stretch that occurs with
breathing
tuning into coming sensitive to the experience of
the movements in the body as the body
breathes
feeling the beginning middle and end of an
inhale
feel the beginning middle and end of an
exhale
and feeling the transitions between inhales and
exhales
when the mind wanders we don't have to make it a
problem we just very simply gently Begin
Again
I'm going to drop in a
poem you don't have to do anything with this
poem allow it to be
received I don't have to try to understand it
or apply it just hear
it this is about somebody going their experience
and a Meditation
Retreat when I first floundered in no one knew
me not even myself staggering under a Saratoga trunk
crammed with humiliations bottled like urine samples nail cakes of anger
carbons of abusive letters chemistry quizzes with FS even the horse I never
had and two casseroles left over from the diam dip
supper no one remarked that I had brought too
much I was wearing three fur hats donated by opulent cousins my feet
encased in cement ever since the failure of the patio project and my mouth full
of barbs as an old trout no one praised my
appearance the trunk fell off my back disgorging
its unusual contents at my stone feet which also came off the fur hats tumbled like a moth
eaten Avalanche burying a small monk no one
noticed no
one now no
one I'll read it
again when I first floundered in no one knew me not even
myself staggering under a Saratoga trunk crammed with humiliations bottled like
urine samples nail cakes of anger carbons of abuse of letters chemistry
quizzes with FS even the horse I never had and two casseroles left over from
the diip supper no one remarked that I had brought too
much I was wearing three fur hats donated by opulent cousins my feet
encased in cement ever since the failure of the patio project and my mouth full
of barbs as an old trout no one praised my
appearance the trunk fell off my back disgorging its unusual contents at my
stone feet which also came off the fur hats tumbled like a moth
eaten Avalanche burying a small monk no one noticed no
one
for
[Music]
[Music] for
so for those of you we're here for the poem this called zazen by Virginia
Hamilton Adair again that's zazen by Virginia Hamilton
Adair and um I don't know if you can hear this I have this background noise going on I'm just G to close my door
here for a moment I'll be right
back
okay sorry that I had to make that sound go
away so the this poem some of you who have
um listened to some of the like happy hour I've done or some of Dhat talks or
path of fearlessness know that um I I really enjoy poems that have a certain
amount of Whimsy to them and that are really uh a lot of imagery in them so I
think that's part of the power of poems is right is they're not being explicit
but they're pointing to something that um we can feel or imagine or you know a
different way of understanding something so this poem zazen by Virginia
Hamilton Adair is uh describing a meditation you
know maybe it's a day long or a retreat or something and uh it seems like there's so many wonderful and the the
poet is using like so many wonderful uh like image images here
and maybe I'll um just I'll begin by reading it
again when I first floundered in no one knew me not even
myself staggering under a Saratoga trunk crammed with humiliations bottled like
urine samples nail cakes of anger carbons of abusive letters chemistry
quizzes with EPS even the horse I never had and two casseres left over from the
diamond dip supper no one remarked that I had brought too
much I was wearing three fur hats donated by opulent cousins my feet
encased in cement ever since the failure of the patio project and my mouth full
of barbs as an old trout no one praised my appearance the trunk fell off my back
discouraging its unusual contents at my stone feet which also came off the fur
hats tumbled like a moth eaten Avalanche burying a small monk no one
noticed no one I kind of like this unconventional
but like evocative imagery that's used here and for example like the
poet she uses this first line is like when I first floundered in this like
floundered in this clumsily maybe with some confusion like some staggering and
makes me reminds me of when I first came to a meditation hole like I really didn't know what to expect what was do
what was happening and kind of like you know what I was supposed to do and may there maybe there's a way
that uh we feel that way with our own meditation practice or even if we go to
meditation centers or the med meditation Retreats we feel like okay is there like a protocol here here that I'm supposed
to follow I feel a bit
awkward and then um the poet she also writes no one knew me not even
myself oh I just love this line because such a big part of meditation practice
is a self- understanding for example like I had no idea how much planning I
did when I until I started meditation practice and I just saw what was going on in my my mind and then then as I you
know continued with meditation practice I discovered that probably like underneath all this planning was some
fear you know I couldn't even necessarily tell you exactly what the fear was about but I just knew that I
had to be prepared just in case maybe I didn't have confidence that I could handle whatever it was that was going to
happen and like I just this is for me part of the power of poetry that just a
few lines can be really evocative of so much because also we might understand
this line no one knew me not even myself is this recognition that sometimes you
know that meditation centers or can't be initially like this really warm
welcoming place maybe some are maybe some aren't if they're filled with some shy
introverts or if you come a little bit late and some people maybe not late but maybe not too early and some people are
already meditating so they're sitting there with their eyes closed and so there's a way in which you
just come in and you kind of like is this okay and for some people and certainly
for some communities this is can be really off-putting this sense of just going into a meditation Hall meditation
space and there isn't necessarily warm welcoming and then the poet she
continues staggering under a Saratoga trunk crammed with and then she gives this big
long list of things right it's true we bring baggage
wherever we go whether we realize we're doing it or not there's this kind like heaviness
that can follow us and she puts this uh long list um Som
of what I kind of like is these carbons of abusive letters like you know these
things we keep copies of things that are painful harmful you might even use the
word trauma here like these are carbon copies they aren't the original things
but there's these carbon copies that were keeping with us you know I don't know exactly when
this uh poem was written but uh again those of you probably many of you
remember right we used to use carbon paper and type on things to keep a copy and it was the carbons are always a
little bit fuzzy not quite as clear I mean they were obviously carbon and they were on a different piece of paper so
this recognition that it's not the original harm but a copy of it that
we're carrying with us and these chemistry quizzes with FS
that the poet is also bringing yeah right the things that um
happened to us when we're young I was just sharing with some friends recently that
when I was um I don't know maybe 11 years old or something that uh I wanted to sign up for choir practice or chorus
you know at the my school because my friends were and the chorus teacher asked me d
uh maybe you can just mouth the words because my voice I don't I don't
know how to carry it to it's just not possible for me and then this shows up when I'm
starting to begin a Meditation Retreat and I'm supposed to be leading the chant and I have a microphone on and
everybody's going to be hearing me chanting I feel like oh yeah this little voice that like Dan you're not a very
good uh V chanter or singer or something like this so these things that we carry
around with us that are extra he
extra but uh I appreciate that the PO concludes like no one remarked that I
had brought too much well maybe there's no nobody's talking at all or maybe they
didn't see what she had brought or maybe they saw but wasn't saying
anything there's a way in which this can be helpful but it also can be a little bit disconcerting like doesn't anybody
ackowledge what's happening here and so we might say that there's a
sense of progress or a sense of uh movement during this uh poem because
first is like the arriv and then maybe it's the sense of
practicing she the poet writes as wearing three fur hats donated by
opulent cousins for me I'm thinking like these are things that you know our family kind like puts on us expectations
they have or things that they think we like or oh you're the one you're the
smart one you're the funny one you're the dumb one you're the silly one you
know like these things that kind of like family gives to us maybe I'm reading too much into this poem but there can be a
way in which um what we are carrying what we're holding with us or things that family
has given us then she the
poet again Virginia Hamilton Adair she continues my feet incased in cement ever
since the failure of the patio project right the sense of stuckness we get when
we have a sense of failure and then she also says in my mouth full of barbs says
an old trout might even say maybe she's doing a
little bit of body scanny right she's talking about her head
hats the mouth full of barbs and feet encased in
cement and full of barbs as an old trout right this is trout they take the bait
and then they get caught so what are the things that we do to take bait that we get caught CAU
with and then there's this sense of shame or inadequacy that's part of this
uh poem sense of not being good enough
right there's nothing in this poem where she's feeling comfortable or at ease or
with warmth towards herself this sense of lack this sense of
inadequate inadequacy often drives a real strong sense of seeking that shows
up in our spiritual practice convinced that the sense of lack this moment is
lacking this self is lacking so we're always like spilling over into the next
moment that holds the promise of somehow being better more
satisfying and then the part describes the trunk
fell off my back dis gorging its unusual contents disgorging what a fantastic
verb like this discharging this expelling this emitting which isn't
smooth or effortless like this letting go that happens often is something that's
uh not easy not straightforward and part of what's
getting discouraged are these identities for her maybe I'm the one who
doesn't do well in chemistry I'm the one who failed the patio project and meditation in some ways is a
purification practice maybe an extraction practice where the removal of everything that's extra and part of
what's extra are the ways that we identify with what's happened to us in the past and
limit ourselves with these types of ideas and to be sure these moments of
Freedom can feel like an unburdening discouraging the Saratoga
trunk falling off our back
like the lightning and then lastly I'll
close with this use of the poet using this word no
one no one knew me not even myself no one remarked that I had
brought too much no one praised my appearance no one
noticed and then she ends just with no
one recognition that not even she was there
no one there's not a self there aren't we have all these identities that we take up but part of this practice this
discouraging if you will this purification you will is a letting go of these selves that we create and
feel so much like we have to bolster and support and
defend so this poem zazen by Virginia Hamilton
Adair just for me just brings a sense of delight and I hope maybe it did for you
today for you this morning and maybe you can bring this sense of delight with you as you go throughout your day thank you
very much for joining me this morning and I'll see you tomorrow thank
you