so hello and warm greetings
and happy to be back here at IMC at 7 00 a.m sitting here with
all of you and um
and um so the last three weeks was at the
Sahara Zen Monastery in deep in the Los Padres National Wilderness which is kind
of in Monterey County and it's several mountain ridges over from
the Big Sur Coast deep in the mountains and um
up and over one of the mountains in a kind of 14 mile dirt road coming down steep valley and narrow Valley too this
beautiful Creek river called tasahara Creek tasara river and in there there's a now for 55 years
a Zen monastery I trained there many years ago and it was formative for me to be there
in many ways and it was very significant to go back there to actively support people who
were practicing in that ballet in that monastery and to be in conversations with them
and I'm reminded over and over again but
certainly being there for something which I feel is quite sacred
and uh and that's uh and what we might call everyone's hearts
the depths of people's inner life inner
capacity for feeling connected and belonging and and
alive in this world and how that deep inner sacred dimension
of our heart that which maybe is in some ways most personal and at the same most impersonal
most transpersonal is sometimes
buried sometimes wounded in deep ways hurt sometimes difficult to access
uh sometimes people are afraid of it
but to come close to it and support people and meet people in the depths of
their inner kind of the most valuable most important parts of what their inner
life is about their full life is about uh that's where we're not distracted not
caught up in the things of the world or in our conceit
is um for me that's that's a sacred Dimension and and to care for that
sacred Dimension to meet it to be part of each other's sacred kind of inner life
and perhaps you could use a different word than sacred just the word I like
um and but I do feel that coming here and surprisingly coming here at 7 A.M with
uh alone in this room with the camera on the wall opposite me and
two monitors in front of me a laptop and a large screen so I can see more easily you all in the chats
surprising that for me that this uh is a vehicle a means for feeling something
that again I call sacred kind of a very special the profound maybe profound is another
possible word than sacred maybe heartfelt Maybe
something very core or essential so it's very nice to be here it's very
nice to be able to share this part of myself and hopefully touch this part of you
and coming from dasara I feel kind of it kind of
inspired quite a bit by all this and I I offer this introduction because
this week I'll continue this series I've been doing now for about I don't know six maybe seven weeks related to
compassion and um and the uh
the poly Sanskrit word for compassion is karuna
and there is a kind of I don't know if wordplay is fair but there is a kind of Association in the word and how it was
used in ancient India with the word Karma they both have the word the the root to make or to do
and uh and they also have a strong Association to pre-buddhist uh
associations to Sacred action and um especially with the idea of
sacred rituals and things like that and the Buddha took the ancient brahmanical
religious orientation and adopted some of these words that they use but moved
them away from the idea of ritual to being something deeply personal and so here we have this a word that uh
Karma that has a variety of meanings but has association with um with sacred ritual
and now karuna so there are some Scholars who have said that karuna as
has this kind of meaning or association with a sacred ritual sacred activity
sacred doing that comes out of us and so you know my association with the
sacredness of the profunda in the profound aspect of our human life
and how do we care for each other and how do we meet that and how do we come from our own
depth in order to support other people and their capacity for depth or profundity or fullness or
sacredness or something um so here we are
the enactment of something that touches
the sacred with care with love with compassion what a wonderful thing and to learn that
or to feel like we're in the in in the neighborhood of it that it's being
discussed and being explored in a world where this may be a stuff not common enough to do is a remarkable
thing and I feel grateful to be here with you so to begin this meditation
to assume a meditation posture that's appropriate for you
and and this idea of appropriate and wise posture for yourself
that is considered is can be seen as an act of compassion
or inner care or kind of being attuned to you know
something deep inside for what really feels most connecting
the most enlivening most personal way of meditating
and gently closing your eyes
and one of the ancient Pali words Buddhist words that I love is a word for
Assurance to be confident or assured
and it means to breathe that the literal me the word comes from the poly root or
meaning to breathe easily and to find a way to breathe easily to
be at ease in this world and have the breath be free and easy is a wonderful task a task of a lifetime
and not always easy but to know that that's the direction we're going
because the breathing for many of us kind of sits at the Nexus
the meeting place of so much of our life that is closely related to this
profundity of possibility within us and so to take a few long slow
gentle breaths a little bit deeper than usual
so it feels good it feels nice just to the extent in which it feels nice maybe even delicious
to breathe in deeply and to relax as you exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal and again at the in the exhale to relax
the body not thinking that relaxing is superficial or rudimentary or
relaxing is really a whiff beginning to approach or settle into
a profound connection to oneself
relaxing the face
around the eyes as you exhale
softening the shoulders
relaxing in the area of your heart the heart center
maybe even loosening up in the diaphragm
and to soften the belly
as you exhale to relax the thinking mind
a gentle and slow quieting of the thinking
the settling into a calming calmness
in the mind
and then relaxing into the place within
someplace within your body within your heart
or maybe within your mind if that's what it is where you feel most at home or most safe
most comfortable
and in that comfort that safety may be profundity Within
breathe breathe with
with it breathe through it
let breathing with to accompany that place that sends that intuition of
what is most profound or most safe or most at the Home Place Within
settling into it each time you exhale
letting the thoughts about other times in other places distracting thoughts
float away recede in the background
as you settle in
to what within feels most home
most intimate Here and Now
having sat these minutes together in silence and quiet
might there be some way that you can sense or feel or into it
something that's below the usual discursive mind the usual daily concerns and feelings
can you drop into some Dimension Within
that feels like the most intimate the most profound most centered place within
a place which is both very personal
and very non-personal Maybe transpersonal
so personal that is no longer
part of your ideas of Who You Are fears of Who You Are
no longer part of how others see you and how you want to be seen
for every exhale settling into this place
Within
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider how the depths of your being
the depths of your heart and capacity to feel and connect to others
can at times be a source of care of compassion and love
concerned with the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello on this Monday morning and now happy to be here with you all also quite
happy to have had my wonderful colleagues uh teach while I was gone
it's a pretty wonderful thing for me to have such wonderful teachers as uh kind
of colleagues companions Dharma friends who I feel like we're you know kind of a
team together now that are teaching uh here at 7 A.M on YouTube and to feel to
know to hear from some of you that I've heard how much you appreciate
the so-called guest teachers who come when I'm gone and now for me it's
wonderful to feel that we're I'm teaching together with them overall we're kind of a team or come you know
together so it's nice to thank you for I thank them for being here when I was
gone and and as it turns out that um
uh uh I'll be here this week and then I'll
be gone again for two or three weeks and um so then I'll be back for a couple of
weeks then gone for a few weeks and then back a little bit just be a lot a lot like this through the end of the year
and maybe next year I can settle down to be here more so um
but I feel very fortunate to be here today with all of you and to continue the series I've been
doing for maybe six seven weeks now on compassion different aspects of
compassion the foundations for compassion and uh hoping I'm hoping or trying to
expand outwards for you the richness of what compassion is and all the
dimensions of it and aspects of it so that you can appreciate the
they you know the the you know how to be compassionate in this
world how to bring forth this beautiful quality we have in a way that is
nourishing for you and nourishing for others
um it's been the first person I heard really teach this was that it was Dalai
Lama that if you want to be happy be compassionate care for others
and um and so disassociation with personal happiness
and well-being in having Compassion Care love for others is a really profound
aspect but to find that uh we really I think it really helps to understand more
deeply the different aspects the different things that come together to
support the healthy forms of compassion it's too easy for compassion to be feel
like it's an obligation it's too easy for a compassion to be a reaction to our
own distress our own pain sometimes what looks like compassion is really trying is trying to certainly
trying to help others not suffer but the motivation is mostly so we don't suffer so we're we're too uncomfortable trying
to you know make ourselves more comfortable or it could come with an excessive
feeling of responsibility or or a feeling of you know trying to it's kind
of an exchange the wanting to be compassionate to others so that we can get something back from them their
approval or something but to have clean compassion compassion
that needs nothing in return compassion that is does not come out of
our distress does not come out of our conceit does not come out of our fears
and doesn't come out of obligation a sense of obligation but rather it comes out of some
Wellspring within that that is sweet
that is satisfying that has a rightness to it and sometimes the suffering of the world
that we contact UM it just doesn't you can't really feel
like the The Compassion is sweet or has a right has a you know even Joy or
happiness in it because it's the suffering is so great but we don't feel still we don't feel
distressed or obligated it doesn't trigger our conceits and self-concepts
of what who we are and who we're trying to prove to be or something and so there's a kind of feeling of
rightness or feeling of yeah kind of yes this is
painful this is difficult this is terrible and
I'm here in a clear and clean way to do the best I can and that Clarity that
cleanness that openness is um is kind of what contributes to in the
long term that stepping out of our own little inner dramas about ourselves and
into the wider world of caring for the world and being open and available is one of the really fantastic things that
the person can do and so hopefully these talks have been supportive for this
and um and so I've kind of uh
look now at Compassion I'm kind of looking at the compassion through five lines of five different aspects of
compassion or five different supports for compassion and uh a week on each of these of
awareness Attunement appreciation
aspiration and this week it's action and many people think of action almost
first and foremost with compassion we have to do something we have to step up
and and uh and save save others or step up and somehow take care of them and
certainly sometimes it what's needed is needs to be done immediately but to um to have cultivated and
developed a capacity to to show up to be mindful to be present
in a full and embodied and and Wise Way supports the possibility that when it's
a my immediate action is needed that it comes along almost a second
nature a capacity for wise awareness
a capacity for wise Attunement to the situation a capacity for really a deep
appreciation of the people the persons that we're involved in respect for them
and appropriate aspiration for what we want to do
and then that supports the action an action maybe is uh you know is one of
the Central features of compassion it isn't just simply wanting people not to suffer
feel their suffering have empathy for it and wish that they don't suffer that's significant but there's one more
step and that is action to do something and uh some people it's only by doing
something in the world doing something acting that we begin
dissolving some of the crusts some of the hardness of our
sometimes our laziness sometimes our indecisiveness sometimes there are hurt
sometimes our stubbornness sometimes our our way we're closed the way we're
afraid all kinds of things where we get stuck and um and uh may be frozen in despair
that we have sometimes with and but to step forward and act there's something
about the movement of activity that begins loosening us up that begins
almost getting ourselves out of ourselves and so to do an action that's beneficial
for some other someone else besides ourselves where the focus of attention part of the focus of attention is on the
other person enough so that self-pre-occupation self you know
sometimes a self-pre occupation for some of us is almost like kind of an addiction that we're so kind of centered and so
concerned maybe because our life has been very confusing and very
disorganized and very disorienting and very painful and so of course in those kinds of
situations it's it's almost necessary to have a lot of attention on oneself in
order to find one's way in order to survive and to somehow continue
and I don't want to belittle how some people really need as a first step in
their lives essential step is to be focused on themselves but it's easy to get stuck there it's
easy for that to be built up in such a way that there's a wall between self and
other there's a closeness there's a collapsing inwards
so how do we loosen that up and and action makes a big difference
and so to act for the sake of someone else
to such a degree that some there's some kind of self-forgetting some kind of dropping of
self-concern some kind of of um of lacking of lacking or dropping
conceit and I keep saying some kind because we
don't want to lose ourselves in the compassionate action we don't want to lose touch with what's happening inside
of ourselves we want to be responsible we want to be mindful and monitor ourselves and what's happening
and that's why these words these concepts of developing awareness
Attunement is such an important foundation for my for mindfulness and to
really have a strong foundation in Awareness practices so you're tracking and knowing what's happening within when
we stress when we're getting caught up or getting afraid or getting overly
ambitious and kind of can track ourselves but there's a way of tracking ourselves and being present that's not
exactly focusing on ourselves it's kind of being present and aware of the whole
environment including self it's kind of like if you turn on a light small light
in the middle of a dark room in a sense it's a very fast super fast so you can't
tell but the light radiates outwards and it it first lights up the part of the
room that's closest to the lamp and then outward and outward until it gets to the walls of the room
and you know with the kind of speed in which we can notice in the eye it's all instantaneous with but um
uh but so the same thing with awareness is it spreads outwards from ourselves
and first it touches us and knows what's happening here without it being
the kind of confused by self-preoccupation defining ourselves by what's going on
limiting ourselves by our identity of who we are in the moment and trying to prove ourselves trying to
protect ourselves trying to defend ourselves whatever it might be so we want to be aware of ourselves but
in that awareness the self-park begins Falls away we're aware of the emotions and feelings and
Sensations here and we're very aware of the people we're helping we're extending ourselves
opening ourselves letting self almost disappear in the process so in this way the action of compassion
is focused on supporting and helping others
but it also is supportive of ourselves support of our own inner freedom to offer our
compassion with a sense of freedom without resistance without attachments
and to find our own Freedom this is where compassion can be beginning of a
source of Joy a source of sweetness a source of goodness a sort of a source of rightness
and a source of a deeper connection to what I call the sacred aspect of life
compassion ideally but being deeply attuned and appreciative of other people
and ourselves we're not just putting Band-Aids on people's cuts
we are putting Band-Aids on people's Cuts as a way of communicating a deep
care for their hearts for their inner life for
their fullness as a human being and it's a way of offering our respect and our
Fuller love in our appreciation and delight and joy in the other person as a
human being in their Humanity no matter who they are so yes the putting a Band-Aid on
someone's cut is valuable but the but the deeper forms of compassion that what
brings Joy is that's the vehicle for a deep connection to our own sacredness the sacredness of
others and the meeting of those two in the act of compassion
so to this week the idea is um to talk about action the fifth of these
parts of compassion and um and when that wave started
so if you'd like over these next 24 hours until we meet again
you might see and study the ways in which you
do nice things for other people whether you open a door whether you let
someone else have um the Short Line in the supermarket and
let them have it first whether it's smiling at a supermarket checkout Clerk
and being kind to them and whether it's helping someone and with some little
tasks they need or offering to do someone a favor or
do an errand for someone else so many different ways is we might actually do something for other people for strangers
for people we know well colleagues as you do these small things for others
or big things for others monitor yourself see see what's happening here
and in that doing for others uh is there contraction is there fear is there
self-preoccupation is there conceit is there concern about their desire for how you're seen in a good way
or or is there a way to drop all that and to have the care to be somehow a
beautiful Act of generosity a beautiful Act of opening and letting go of self-concern appropriately letting go of
self-concern a certain kind of self-concern so that it's there's a feeling of freedom and
openness in the care for others and maybe also a sense that you'd be
doing more than simply um
you know offering someone to have the shorter line in the supermarket or
giving people the right of way on the freeway there's some deeper sense of these other people as being the depths
of their humanity and and care that we want to offer so
thank you and um
then thank you and I'll be here again tomorrow