hi Audrey you're testing all of you are testing my my uh voice my um uh voice
recognition my speaker recognition so I'm GNA stop guessing your names you can just say your
name Peter in the [Music] Mid-Atlantic in Dallas
hello Amy across the ocean in aahu
iy this is this is
fun across the freeway in
Fairfield this is William just on the other side of the high school in Redwood [Laughter]
City oh uh audio is
hi podma is this PMA or Claudia I wasn't quite sure who was speaking just now Claudia Claudia hi Claudia great yeah hi
this is Padma from Belmont in on the peninsula hi PMA hi Jerry from Toronto
hi Jer and Neil says D geography go great
together that's funny hi sir from Toronto hi Karen from pet s Washington
Hina from oh who says hello from way across the ocean in Japan Hina good
morning too loveely you can join and bill says the audio is garbled is my
audio garbled or not yes it is garble a little bit really yes a little
bit still having trouble with with we're still taking names I'm
CLA New York I was getting my earphones out so I
could hear you that's great anybody else who wants
to share their hello and and geographical location before
the oh we have we have YouTube friends who join you say hi B in Australia SC
from Missouri I'm so very
[Music] cool let's [Music]
see I just checked my audio settings there the usual so we
just could oh
let me check something that's
[Music] curious oh that's funny it's not picking
up something hold on it's not [Music] Pi let's try that
again okay let's try that again right is
that any better that is better it was okay it wasn't picking up my uh
um my microphone and and it was picking up the laptop mic which is pretty far
away so amazing that you could hear me at all thank you all this is thanks for
the community support to debug this great okay so audios I always do the
check at the beginning if the audio is okay give me thumbs up you guys gave me the thumbs up it's not my fault just
kidding it's all good great okay so so thank you all let's begin my heart is
warmed up um now we have more hellos Lynn from Belmont and and Rosa gives a
warm Autumn greetings so thank you Neil for posting information uh about happy hour Google
groups if you're new to happy hour we invite you to join the um mailing list
it's a low traffic mailing list and there's also a um little document we
have uh for later when you join the small groups breakout groups how to uh
offer yourself and others care so with the preliminaries out of the way
actually well couple more preliminaries going to change the settings
so that we keep the zoom room quiet and also chats will only come to me but I
ask that you you keep those U keep that channel quiet and last but not least I'm
going to turn recording on for the sake of Audio
Dharma here we go great okay so hello hello hello
everyone it's lovely to be with you lovely to see you and um and I really enjoyed our
hello saying at the beginning um with the different geographical locations and
with relation to one another that was that was fun and and and I truly feel
that when we do that when we say hello and just share our voices or Goodwill
our meta it it brings me more present a sense of community a sense of shared
community that here we are from different places in the world we're
coming together to do this cultivation of kindness goodness
practice together and it's in this light in this
spirit that for today's practice I would like to offer uh
[Music] um really two practices that are related
together and the first one is as we come together as all of us come together from
different places in the world as you creatively mentioned shared them at the beginning um coming together to hold
Sacred Space together to hold Sacred Space together it's quite a doing for
it's um you know it's it's lovely that we especially because we're not in the
same room but we can hold Global space Sacred Space together
across the ocean many oceans and to hold
this Sacred Space for for both grief for sadness for whatever might be arising
right now for each of us individually and and also for us
collectively with what is happening in the world
geopolitically and I know that there is for many people there is grief sadness
anger arising and um and to hold a space of is it just a
simple Sacred Space to hold it all not turning our Hearts away but when we hold
it together it it becomes lighter to hold not that the situation is light at
all it's it's egregious it's Grievous and it's getting worse um the
humanitarian crisis worsening and and to
meet it in our hearts with this with stability of care and
compassion and I know that for me as I've been listening to the news I've
been finding myself crying um there human beings who are suffering
regardless of their belief and religions and and
background um and maybe also personally I I share with you that you know I've
identified myself jokingly with friends as a Muju you might have heard of a juu
people who are who've been Jewish and and practiced Buddhism and I've also been raised
Muslim I went to a um Jewish grade school for five years in in back in Iran
and and um um and now I'm a Buddhist
teacher so there is this sense of um really so many people I know and care
about being being affected and so many people I don't know uh being being
impacted and maybe I'll share one one other thing which is um today I was
listening to a a rabbi and an Imam on
the radio on NPR and they were talking about um how they're supporting how
they're supporting uh various you various practitioners and and um
the rabbi said something very profound that the Imam loved and and re re-echoed
at the end which was that there is not a dividing line
there's not so much of a dividing line between different people of different religion
uh in this scenario what's happening in the world but it's really a dividing line between people who believe that
violence is the only solution and people who do not believe violence is the only
solution and that is so profound so let us count ourselves count ourselves add
our name as signaries to not believing that the violence is the only solution
to the world's problems but actually compassion understanding dialogue and
care and let us be a part of um at least least as we engage with our own heart
and practice and the way that our actions in the world re reverberate um to
be voices for for love for care for compassion for
dialogue for understanding and not for hatred and violence
so so with that I'd like to share practice of
um of both settling into a Sacred Space and
then opening our hearts for holding whatever is arising with compassion for
ourselves and and other beings in this world who are just like us they're not
different from us at all and just caught in this Tangled mess
because of where they're they're born so so let us arrive let us
arrive in our
bodies and In This Moment feeling our feet on the
earth and this Earth that houses so many
of us is the only
home to us so many of us beings
humans nonhumans
animals letting this body rest letting our heart
rest feeling a shared space
of care and wishes for
peace that soothe calm hold
us as well as everyone else on this
planet a Sacred
Space that holds
wishes her peace can also hold sadness and grief if it's
present and letting our presence our bodies Our Living bre breathing
bodies be a signatory to a prayer for peace in the
world and with each
breath deepening our
commitment to peace to Inner Peace first inner
peace so that we can enact outer
peace
letting the breath be supportive grounding grounding us to this present
moment
feeling both importance the gravity of our
practice in this moment come together in
peace in kindness how important this is in our troubled
world how important just sitting and
kindness not adding fuel to the fire of
hatred how important this is in our
world and connecting receiving each
breath as an offering as a
gift as a peace offering to this
world to
yourself internally and externally each breath a peace offering
with every out breath with every out breath breathing
out peace good will
care both onto [Music] yourself and onto
others internal
external if you're suffering in this moment if your heart is
breaking it's heavy let yourself receive the care The Compassion
first establish a sense of stability and if
there is groundedness let the
care be outwards touching those who are suffering In This Moment bringing them
sucker bringing them
e maybe just a bit of
lightness in a moment of darkness bit of
uplift spreading your wish of
Goodwill
and if might be supportive adding the phrases of of
compassion may I may you
you have ease in the midst of this sorrow this
pain this suffering may you be free
from
suffering May you be safe as much as
possible or simply I care about your sorrow your
pain what you're going
through I wish you is
and if you wish can either stay with yourself their
suffering their sorrow and pain or
expand externally to those who are suffering In This Moment especially
in the Middle East the whole region so much
pain so many
humans and sorrow and danger and grief right
now regardless of the borders rationalities beliefs they're
human beings just like
us just as I wish to be free from sorrow suffering I wish you ease may you have
ease may you be
free from pain from
sorrow
and if at any point your practice of compassion veers into empathic
distress make sure to bring compassion home
internally calming soothing your own aching
heart so that you can have stability again and be available for others
through your through the actions of your mind your speech the actions of your
body thoughts speech and physical
actions
wishing ease and freedom from sorrow suffering
pain
Danger
wishing e peace and goodness to all those who are
suffering in our world World In This Moment wherever in the world they may
be wishing you well for all those
who wish for
peace and wishing Clarity of
vision for those who think that hatred violence is the
solution to Humanity's problems may all beings everywhere
including ourselves be free from suffering
sorrow May may all beings everywhere be happy and have the causes
for happiness may all beings be
free thanks for your practice
everyone I had this sense I have this image of each of us praying or
practicing with each breath for for compassion for peace in the
world each of us is holding this
candle together and may may there be peace May There Be
Peace On Earth war is Hell war is
hell and saying this I um I actually
when I was growing up in Iran I lived through the bombing of tan
in the Iran Iraq war and it was nothing like what we hear
on the radio right now and uh just remember how painful and
difficult and uncertain it was
so may there be ease and peace for those who are in grave danger and suffering in
our world extending our hearts to them
practicing compassion one breath at a time one breath at a time and of course
it's so important not to lose our own stability with the practice of
compassion because the pain of the world sometimes can feel so
overwhelming that it can feel easy to Veer into empathic distress and that's
not helpful that doesn't help anyone and that not
compassion empathic distress is is what when we're falling into the waves of the
ocean with the people who are suffering we're bobbing up and down with them without the ability to to extend a
holding hand compassion has more stability has care has love and more
stability it's not overwhelmed it feels the pain but but holds the pain with
equal amounts of care and love and compassion so that it doesn't become a
practice in self flagellation and just feeling pain over and over again so be
very careful and and um and
clear when you're practicing compassion if it veers into empathic
distress it's it's wise to pull back and turn to compassion for yourself because
you're the one in that moment who's suffering and have lost your balance
you're more and the balance again really think of it compassion is a
balanced an action of a feeling another person suffer another
person's sorrow and pain could be your own as well as care and love to hold
hold it then if there's not enough love and it's just pain that's not compassion
that's empathic distress so be be clear and wise
about um how your practice shows up internally for
you and again if it veers into empathic distress it's not a sand don't self
flatulate it's just the practice has gotten out of balance it's fine
no problem it's time to to bring more balance into it turn turn more into
bringing more care more love and turning to yourself so that there is balance
till you can turn outside again outward again
so so so I'd like to invite us if
you would good to uh let this for us to
carry this Sacred Space that we're holding together into the small groups
holding Sacred Space together small groups of roughly size three and sharing
if you wish and you can also just hold space in silence you can just be these candles that show up and hold space
together for other human beings in the world maybe that's enough maybe you want
to just show up in silence that's perfectly fine and if you want to say a few words the invitation is just a self
exploration of how this practice um was for you in this evening and there's no
right or wrong answer you can say I fell asleep I was I I don't know what she's talking about
it doesn't matter just an exploration if you wish or can say past
um and just hold compassionate space so so I will create the small groups
with the invitation to take care of yourselves take care of each other each
person just offering one nugget and leaving space for others and let's go um
the order of um reverse um uh birth date order so
whoever whoever was born closest to December 31st will speak first so at the
beginning you'll just have a little bit of exchange to share what your birth date not birth year but birth date
is and and please turn on your cameras uh when you go into groups just to
create the sense of um safety for one another and uh take care of yourselves
and take care of each other um be kind be compassionate and be be be um be a
candle be a candle how can you be a candle of
Light Of Peace okay I'm opening the rooms now
take
care
okay welcome back everyone all the rooms are breakout rooms are closed
everybody's back and um thank you for your practice
tonight [Music] and would love to hear from you any
Reflections any comments any you discovered in the practice especially if
you haven't spoken in the uh large group recently um also in
uh the chat is open now if you like to share your Reflections if you just send
them to me privately I will not read your name just your reflection if you type it to everyone I'll I'll read your
name and the reflection as well any thoughts any discoveries with
this compassion practice this
uh In This Moment In Time
maybe as I take a moment they could pause to see if you have any Reflections
you want to share what I'll say about practicing compassion especially when
they challenging events in the world feels like the appro apprpriate response
instead of getting entangled in in anger and blame and overwhelming grief um
practicing compassion practicing compassion which then leads to actually
actions of compassion instead of being devastated or angry and inflaming
actually it is the appropriate response um both for ourselves and for the world
World wholesome actions can come out of this instead of unh wholesome actions
not just for our own sake but for the sake of humanity training our hearts
training ourselves as we are one drop in this ocean of
humanity yeah thanks Neil Neil says I try to remember the environmentalist
statement of think globally act locally
yeah the same is true for peace and kindness exactly and in this practice tonight we
definitely thought globally and acting locally
here each one of us Kevin I see your hand
please hey um yeah so last night I spoke with a friend
who um is Jewish and from Ukraine so has been you know profoundly in affected by
both of the wars going on um also had a an extremely heavy
meeting a work meeting uh immediately before this sitting um and so I just um
really really appreciate this space and to be um in community with others
um um I think this uh practice of
compassion is so important and to be able to
um yeah hold this Sacred Space for all of the suffering and um yeah I just
really want to Express gratitude um for this space and for everyone's practice
and that um yeah so much appreciation for it a lot of um Goodwill towards everyone for
that support and um yeah thank gratitude for everyone's practice um and just want
to remind everyone that um um yeah so much meta for all everyone
so thank you thank you Kevin thank you so much for your share yeah and I saw lots of
Hearts showing up while you were speaking Jennifer says thank you Nikki
for your compassion and wisdom this was a powerful met tonight thank you
Jennifer and na says Mr Rogers advise children in times of distress and
troubling news to focus on the helpers he said when I was a boy and I would see
scary things in the news my mother would say to me look for the helpers you will
always find people who are helping indeed thank you enough thank you and
Ellie I see your hand hi Nikki thank you thank you for
the teaching and bringing the the subject in the Forefront ah yeah it's it's h hard
actually I mean I've been getting more of the like the uh as you said the
uh empathy uh uh distress more so um so
but takes a while to have the other for me uh you know to have the other part
underneath it the other part of the compassion to hold it both and then as we know I mean Buddhism is full of the
paradoxes but just being so close uh you know originally from that part it's hard
to you know keep both sides hard to not to take sides or or whatnot and
especially when a million people people being you know displaced tomorrow have to move so it's just I know it's having
to hold both sides is kind of difficult when when you're uh close and then uh
yeah that's what comes to mind yeah thank you Alie thank you yeah it's Paradox of Buddhism I was
just going to ask you to maybe just like expand on that portion of it just holding this and that and everything
else yeah yeah Paradox well I mean we live in Paradox this is um and it that's
in some ways it's a paradox and in some ways it's it's um the truth of how
things are you know many things can be uh many things that seemingly for our
limited cognition seem at odds they're actually quite uh consistent with one another
grief sadness sorrow coexist consistent with kindness love and care it's it
seems like a paradox and yet it isn't at the same time it's it's the natural response of the heart and and
um you know it it's maybe what you sh shared um maybe I'll say a word about
you know sometimes the Mind wants to have a a binary or or the mind you know
kind of sticks to wants to have a binary like it's either this or that and and
like a loving parents say sweetheart it doesn't have to be binary it doesn't have to be so strictly one way or
another I you have much more capacity to hold multitudes to hold multitudes to to
feel the pain of people who are being displaced and the and feel the pain of
the people who were surprised and and hurting in fact you can hold pain
there's just pain there are human beings all around and if you want to take sides
Dear Heart advise your heart perhaps take the heart take sides with peace
take sides with nonviolence take sides with compassion take sides with humanity
take sides with human beings all around in that region that complicated complex
region of the world that I'm from as well that has just hurting so much has
been hurting for so long um taking and and also compassion isn't just um tender
it's both tender and it's also Fierce it's also protective it's also loving
it's also gives it's also shares of itself but it's not it doesn't include
hatred it doesn't have any hatred in it it it loves it it sees the suffering and
it sees the the ignorance of the world it sees the ignorance of of human beings
that that keep [Music]
perpetrating pain on each other and forgives loves doesn't
condone but but but loves as deeply and
as as painful as it might be as it can feel to continue to love and see under
the humanity that everybody's hurting everybody's hurting hurt people hurt
people anyway thank
you yeah so two one one minute left and I get get
this big question Jerry says are the relationships between compassion and
Justice and peace yes absolutely um how can I address this in
30 seconds
um yeah maybe I'll say this I trust you
have heard of restorative justice restorative justice is justice that
doesn't blame shame hate restorative justice that has compassion and wish for
peace as as an integral part of it and there so that's what I would say in 30
seconds that's how compassion and Justice and peace coexist together and
there are a lot of resources on on on what I just mentioned so I'll leave it
at that and maybe what I'll do very quickly is I will share I mentioned to
you that I listened to this NPR um uh
report yeah it was from NPR interviewing an Imam and and a rabbi and I just found
it beautiful so I put that in chat and if you just Google NPR Imam and and uh
Rabbi you you'll hear the little conversation they had
today so yeah last words Vicki seeing the D L cry
and then laugh joyously one minute later was informative years ago to hold both yes
exactly exactly yeah holding also joy and sorrow I think that those are other
and and holding pain and gladness pain and joy joy and sorrow the holding these
multitudes our hearts are so vast we have so much capacity all right dear one
on we're off time thank you so much for this very rich practice conversation
holding space together I am moved to go now and light a candle and I invite you to feel the same if you're moved to
thank you all may all beings be well may all beings be
free take care see you on Monday and I'm going ask you all if you
like on Zoom to unmute yourself and say caka this goodbye if
you like here we go thank you
all thank you everyone have a
Beau bye bye be well
bye watching events in Israel and Gaza over
the last week has brought grief and pain to many Jews and Muslims us Hamas
surprise attack last Saturday and