so good morning and it would be nice for me to do a sound
check and uh
reducing a different sound system than at IMC and so make sure that it's all working
sound is fine sounds good great this is wonderful thank you it's also nice to
get a little bit of exchange going back and forth between saying something getting replied
directly so thank you very much
so hello and greetings from inside retweet Center
and it's like I feel kind of delighted to be here with you today and being here in
this room so thank you for being here and um
um so in doing mindfulness practice
one of the simple ways of describing it is that we are
recognizing what's happening in the moment as it's happening and there are two general ways that
maybe people are pro can approach this recognition in the present moment being aware of the present moment
one is um to see things as they are
where how they are is a is a conclusion so when we're mindful we're concluding
something this is what's happening so if we're mindful of the breathing say we're mindful of the in-breath
the recognition of the in-breath is kind of like the end of the story like breathing in
and then I'm you know breathing out and that's the end of the story or you hear sound the recognition the
sound is the recognition of that brief event or the sound and I recognize it if the sun might go on but it's kind of
like the recognition is a conclusion or as a is a thing in itself that's
has recognized what has just happened the other way of doing it is not to be
aware of things as they are but be aware of things as they are occurring things as they are becoming
and so there now mindfulness is not a conclusion
but rather it's a beginning and so to be aware of a sound it's kind
of like you're in in maybe if you use Mental noting or something you know you're quiet or quieter where there's a
decision to to then turn your attention to feet you're not just recognizing the sound but it's kind of like you're
making yourself available to experience it as it's occurring
if you're recognizing breathing the the mindfulness of breathing is not a conclusion about yes now I'm breathing
but rather is it's a beginning of the experience of being available
to know feel experience breathing as it's occurring
and if there's a brief sound um the recognition can still be that way
so it's kind of like you're opening the door say you're in a in a
in a stuffy room and you open the door to the outside and it becomes a beautiful wonderful fresh Breeze coming
in and you just make yourself available for feeling that fresh Breeze
and so the idea is to always kind of use the mindfulness to help you be available
for for the fullness of the experience as it's occurring and it might just be momentary
so being available for the in-breath breathing in and then but then there's a
kind of opening to that the very very recognition is a opening the door to be
aware of the of of the full inhale or if you're in the exhale be aware of
the exhale to be really aware of it as it's occurring letting it register as
it's occurring the ongoing experience of it and if you get to the end of the exhale
and that being available door being open is still there that spills over into
being aware of the transition from breathing out to breathing in
if you're thinking it's useful to note that be really clearly aware that you're thinking
but not as a conclusion but as a beginning of making yourself available
to register to feel to experience to know what this is like
even if the thinking stops the particular thoughts you have they're still lingering kind of what's
that lingering effect and what's the effect of being available
so you're also letting yourself be available to the experience of being available
so things as they're occurring so um
so assuming a meditation posture
and
gently closing closing your eyes
and just checking in with yourself if you are mindful at this moment if you
open your awareness at this moment what do you become aware of
what is occurring within you
and what would it be like to
open yourself to experience what is occurring as an ongoing event
where the mindfulness is being making ourselves available
for the occurring to feel it to know it to be aware of it
and then to do this with a breathing in taking a gentle long deep inhale
and exhale being available
in your body in your mind to know to experience the full
occurring of breathing in
being available to experience the full occurring of breathing out
and letting your breathing return to normal
and the inhale is a process it takes a little bit of time
however short or long it might be
pretty relaxed easy way
open the door of awareness to let the breeze of breathing come in
if something else has happened happening that you become aware of
open your awareness to register to feel
how that is occurring
mindfulness is a as a particular continuing action
of opening to things as they occur
where each moment of allowing being available
might be quite brief before you open the door again
through mindfulness to be in availability
an opening to experience
it's important that we're not crowded with thoughts and agendas and wants
desires and thoughts agendas become quiet
so when we open the door of awareness
what we're mindful of can flow through it
whatever is occurring is allowed to pass through
for however long awareness
is open and then we do it again
when awareness is an opening to experience as it's
occurring when we're allowing something to register or be felt or
known there can be a subtle Joy or pleasure
in the allowing even when the experience might be
unpleasant see allowing the experience to be
registered allowing it to arise and Flow in Awareness however brief it is
can have a feeling of freedom pleasure
Joy
in the openness in the allowing
in the feeling of being available to know and to feel
putting aside what you want to have happened
putting aside what you expect to have happened
so that you can better be available
for the next moment as it's occurring
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
if you're able to have a sense of this opening awareness to what's available
or to what's happening to what's occurring in availability
and allowing of things to register to be felt
and if that could be a light feeling Happy Feeling or some pleasure and that
availability then maybe you couldn't under also do
the same for opening to experience
the suffering of others the challenges they have
or your own suffering where oddly enough
opening to be aware of it this way
there's a good feeling a rightness a kind of subtle pleasure or even Joy
not in the suffering but in our wonderful capacity
to be to open to it
to allow ourselves to feel it as it's occurring
lightly calmly
opening to The Suffering of the world
being available the sense of availability
as it's occurring
where there's no conclusions
there's no fixed ideas just a continual opening
to things as they are coming to be things as they are occurring
and in being aware of others and their suffering
the door of availability that's open door
can then be the door out of which our care and love
and good will flow
an Open Door for what comes in
an open door for what goes out
an open door for breathing in open door for breathing out
and on the exhale
let the last words of these phrases
flow out of you into the world may all beings
be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
foreign
thank you
so I saw some of the messages that the sound was low so I turned up the input for the
microphone on this laptop but in doing that I had to use laptop
and some of you heard the clicking so I apologize for that that and I don't know if they now the sound
is a little bit got louder and better
all right
foreign
okay so today the topic is uh the joy
factor of compassion and I think compassion is often not
associated with joy maybe it could be Associated better with joy if we realize that the word Joy is
of maybe a a um you know has a wide range of what
it can mean but it was a big surprise to me very big surprise the first time that I
was feeling I was I was caring for someone someone who was challenged to make her way
around and needed support and and help
and I was just doing it in a matter of fact way it was just I was happy it was kind of like just it was natural to do
it but what surprised me as I was doing it um the sense of pleasure and joy and
well-being that seemed to well up in my chest as I did it and um
and that it was um and I wondered is this okay to feel this
uh kind of sense of well-being and joy in helping this person or supporting this person
and and I and then I've even wondered how am I
doing it for the pleasure of it or doing it to to to help her get her get around her
um but I was so surprised by how good it felt and and since then I've discovered that
that uh when I feel compassion that um it's possible that compassion
comes with a sense of rightness a sense of Joy a sense of pleasure
and sometimes when the suffering is really huge it's a little hard to see it's being or see it or recognize that
it's being joyful or you know or exactly like pleasure exactly but it just feels
really good it feels right to be a witness for the suffering to be open to
it and um and the uh
um and so how is it that compassion which is the awareness of suffering and
oneself and others how is it that that can be associated with joy
um the dilemas I think is you know has gone around the world with their teaching that if you want to be happy be
compassionate and um so how is it what's associated with that there's many answers to that
it's a you know our inner psychology has many different facets but one of them is
um that uh how we're being compassionate that if compassion comes along with a
lot of sense of Duty and obligation it can feel quite heavy if it comes along with a sense of uh
conclusions like deciding that this means that life is really frightening and terrible it can really feel also
oppressive to experience compassion but if compassion comes along with an
awareness that's open and available like an open window where the wind can
flow through um Nothing Stops it it doesn't nothing
blocks it it just kind of just goes right through US almost but we're available for this opening we um we have
this availability for as things as they occur it's part of that Joy is in that
availability because we're not Contracting we're not resisting we're
not coming to conclusions we're not uh elaborating with you know this means
that the world is a terrible place or whatever it might be and we're not kind
of immediately caught up in I have to do something I'm responsible but this the
simplicity of compassion the simplest version of it to be open to experience what is
and this openness this ability to be available is a is a kind of a very
important aspect of mindfulness practice um the mindfulness
some people use mindfulness as as like the end of a the end process of a very
short few moments of concluding oh this is what's happening done I've concluded
it's got some it's extreme version It's a checklist approach to mindfulness people use Mental noting
um and I used to do that I would I would note that breathing in in just as I began breathing in
and if the if the in-breath was a little bit long I would kind of check out I would kind of wonder if draw from my
thought for the last three quarters of the inbred because I'd already done my mindfulness practice
and then I would try to be the beginning of the exhale and out you know and and done that and then I would kind of
wouldn't be there very present for the out breath and I learned that rather than you know
to do what instead is to be available to be open to experience
so the word in for me if I do is um is an invitation is an opening like
okay it's the beginning of a process okay I'm breathing in that's what's
happening now let's feel that it registered let it let it be felt more
deeply in the system in the body and um and uh exhaling
this is the beginning of really feeling this now it might be very brief something might
be very fleeting and that's okay and one of the things one of the great Treasures is as we do this availability
being available to what's happening is um
is we're also then feeling what it's like to be available
we're feeling what it's like to have the door open as opposed to having it closed and that feels good
that has a nice feeling so when we do that with compassion we're open we feel so we see the
suffering of the world we don't come that's not a time to come to conclusions this is it for compassion's sake this is
a time to allow something to begin and at the minimum it's a beginning of
becoming more fully aware of it and um and so this sense of being aware
is the joy of compassion at least for me
so the we're doing the uh the
the seven factors of compassion today this week and so we're back into this
mindfulness how mindfulness is and as mindfulness is we're being mindful of it in a calm relaxed way
we become aware of how we're not open how we're closed or resisting or or
we're tight or we're suffering in terms of compassion we become aware of how
we're suffering because of the suffering we're laying air laying layers of suffering on top of experiencing the
suffering of the world their judgments our fears and taking it
personally and all kinds of things so then we learn to make a distinction
between these other layers of suffering and just being open to the Simplicity of
the original suffering we're present for as we make that distinction we learn how
to be mindful in a more relaxed way in an open way and we make the effort to do
so we make it at a different kind of effort to be be present for the suffering where
we're not tightening up and stressing around it and that leads us to This Joy Factor the
network available we're open in Awareness without stress and awareness without force and awareness which is
calm light open and in some ways the lighter and more
calm the awareness can be the cleaner and Fuller can be the
experience of compassion experience or the way of experiencing suffering
and that can be against the grain for some people because with when we feel suffering of the world suffering of
others we better take it seriously we better get gear up and do something big
and this is really important there's some some sufferings are huge and so it can be very counterintuitive
that the way forward is not to take it too seriously or take it so seriously
that it's so important that you can't afford to get tense you can't afford to
get stressed out that they it's so important that to let
the best qualities of who you are come forward forward and your best ability to think and to act and to do
is in fact to relax and open and be available in like a nice way
so to go back to the example I gave the first day about the girl in The Playground who's
uh injured herself scraped her knee um if the caretaker comes over he cares
for her is distraught is upset is angry is feels
like that this is a disaster it's a crisis and and as yelling for help and
saying this is a serious problem the poor girl is going to learn all
kinds of unhealthy things she's going to feel frightened she's going to feel oh maybe things are much
worse than I thought and uh it's bad enough I got my knee my knee scraped now it's maybe it's a
disaster I wonder if they're going to call 9-1-1 and the ambulance for me or or now now that now the little girl
learns that the world is a frightening place to be in that all kinds of secondary things
because the caretaker got so alarmed and took it so seriously
if the caretaker takes it respectfully carefully lovingly fully but has a
lightness and ease and a calm and even has a sense of of uh
enjoying or appreciating or feeling the rightness of him here are they
comfortable in being here doing this this little girl learned something very different about life
she learns that this is available in life she learns that life is a place where things are not a crisis that you
meet your experiences and difficulties with a certain level of calm and lightness and ease and love and care
so the ability to find sweetness and compassion
is one of the Great powers of compassion it's one of the
great capacities compassion has so the in this week we're calling it The
Joy factor of compassion so I would like to suggest
that if you have occasion today to encounter suffering however small or
large it might be and you don't have to maybe it's best if you don't have to
act you know quickly and immediately for it that you have you know that doesn't
require that of you see if you can find a way to register
and feel and know that suffering clearly not not denying
it not dismissing its importance but that you can take take the time to let
it register and be known in you that in the knowing in the being available for
it you actually feel some sweetness you feel some goodness it feels some rightness
and then what difference does it make for you If you experience compassion that way
how do you then maybe respond differently with that
so the joy factor of compassion so thank you and um
I look forward to continuing tomorrow