good morning and welcome again to IMC our teacher this morning is di our
own Diana Clark thank you
Diana and could I please make an announcement before the Talk starts um my name is Gloria Schulz I'm a
longtime member of IMC um and about 10 years ago I heard a
threshold choir presentation here and knew right away that I wanted
to join um it has become a very
meaningful um volunteer job for me next Sunday we will be offering a special
program from 1 to 2 um it is quiet meditative
music uh followed by silence and then another song um
we uh offer our songs primarily for people who are in a
hospice hospitals Extended Care Facilities or in
crisis thank
you good morning it's nice to see you all and
it's nice to be here some of you may know me I'm Diana Clark I teach her on Monday nights and
uh here I am on a Sunday
morning and some of you may be listening to gills 7 a and you may know that I
substitute for him a couple of weeks ago when I talked a little bit about poetry
and practice and I like to like extend a little bit what I spoke about then and
if you didn't hear that it's perfectly fine too but what I'd like to talk about is
the way that uh practice meets our life and I know certainly for me at the
beginning there was a clear distinction between practice and life I would uh listen to Dharma talks
or read Dharma books and they really touched me and felt like some something
really powerful was there but then I would just go off into my life my regular life right whatever that
was but as the more I read Dharma books listened to Dharma
talks and meditated the more I started to see that
these two things kind of like practice and life started to come closer and closer together and the distinction
between them started to blur and things that I thought were you know
like these conceptual understandings that I had started to just show up in the way
that I was being in the world and I've told this story a number
of times but uh a really clear example for me is this idea of Behaving
ethically I thought of myself as an ethical person I wasn't going around stealing things or harming people
but I was doing an awful lot of Little White
Lies just to you know when I looked at it to make myself look better or not to hurt the feelings of other people
and and so when I started to like take seriously well what is this thing about
the Buddhist life talking about you know behaving ethically and this wish to not
harm others and I said okay I'm going to stop these little white
lies such as oh I'm sorry I'm late the traffic was really bad the traffic wasn't bad I just was
disorganized and then when I realized that I okay I'm going to have to say why I'm really
late I started to get more organized because I didn't want to have to lie and
there's all these small ways in which I just started to you know treat the people that I were meeting with respect
showing up on time and that just started to shift a little bit my life and how the way that
I was showing up so this small thing was kind of like
how my practice and life started to come together and you know how we now here we
are all these years later and I find myself in the seat as a Dharma teacher certainly not expecting that way back
when so I'd like to talk a little bit about this you know when practice meets
life and what does that mean how does it show
up and first of all I'd like to say that there's a way in which we can practice
there's different ways in which we might approach practice or understand
practice one way is that there's particular steps there's directions
there's things that we do 16 steps of anapanasati one two three and go through
the way or maybe there's like we have to balance the five faculties okay is energy concentration wait what was the
other one you know often we can't keep them in our minds or this real clear set of there's lists and there's a ways to
practice and we have a certain direction and a certain approach in which we practice and certainly this Works in
other areas of our lives in our professional life in our educational
life and it it works in our practice life too until it doesn't right so that's
certainly one way to practice beneficial supportive appropriate but I also want to mention
that there's another way to practice and this is with the same
directionality with the same sense of more freedom freom and more ease but instead
being I don't being supported by lists and directions it's more supported by a
sense of feeling
experience this way leads to more freedom and when I behave or experience
things this way it leads to less Freedom more Dua this way feels more spacial
ious easeful open expansive this other way
feels a little more forced and pushing so feeling our way with
practice not so much a conceptual understanding but more just
experiencing then I want to say that the Buddha before his uh Awakening right before he had this insight into the Four
Noble Truth that characterized his Awakening this understanding about Dua he describes what it was like right
before he had this lifechanging insight and he describes that his mind
was malleable and wieldy so there's this sense that
there's not just one way but the sense of
flexibility to what's appropriate what's happening so there's a way that which we
can practice in which it is about the directions and these numbered lists and these conceptual
understandings and a way in which we're feeling experiencing our way towards
greater peace ease and freedom and part of practice is to be
able to do both and chances are all of us have preferences for one way or the
other but can we practice in a way in such that we stretch our Bend we stretch
what's comfortable for us so that we can do both so that we can find our way to the
greatest ease and freedom using whichever approach is appropriate at
that time so these two different ways kind of
one I'm calling maybe feeling or experiencing versus more of a conceptual
understanding we might say has some similarity in which
poetry is more about feeling experiencing versus Pros Or List just
more maybe conceptual understanding to be sure we need both but I like something that e
said many of you all know he's a famous American poet in the 20th
century and he said or wrote
a poet is somebody who feels and who expresses their feelings
through words this may sound easy it isn't a lot
of people think or believe or know they feel but that's thinking or believing or
knowing not feeling and poetry is
feeling so in this way i' like to talk of a little bit about poetry and
practice and how practice meets our life you think kind of poems or a
poem to help maybe point the way in which we might feel this
way so the poem I'd like to talk about is the one that I dropped in during our guided meditation is called
Tree by Jane hersfield Jane hershfield is an American poet she
lives here in Marin County she is a Zen practitioner she lived at tsah hor in
fact I think she uh overlapped with Gil down in tahar at the same time and she practiced at San Francisco Zen Center
and green gge farm so I kind of like to think that she's uh one of our Brethren one of part of our
community she's a also a translator she translates or helps she she with another
person translates po poems from Japanese poems from about a thousand years ago of
some women poets some of their Awakening poems she has a books of her poems but
she also has books about poetry so here's Jane Hirshfield's poem
called tree it is
foolish to let a young Redwood grow next to a house
even in this one lifetime you will have to choose that great calm
being this clutter of soup pots and
books already the first Branch chips brush at the
window softly calmly
immensity TAPS at your your
life those of you couldn't hear I tried to tap here and this if it wasn't that loud
but what does this mean this idea of a
tree we know like for the Buddha he sat underneath a bodh tree and a Bodhi Tree
has a lot of significance in Buddhism the kind of like the icon for inside Meditation Center this place is a little
B Leaf from a b tree for Jane herfield here in the Bay
Area and Marin County here is a redwood tree we have a redwood trees you know
just right out here and something that I I love about redwood trees maybe all of you do too
there's something Majestic about them there's something they also like Cathedral like
when you're in a Grove of redwood trees the RO redwood trees are so
powerful too some of you may know that just a I don't
know how many years ago maybe 5 years ago the redwood tree out here in front
was causing the sidewalk to buckle The Roots were getting in the way and it was a tripping Hazard and we thought okay we
we have to take care of this we don't want people to trip on the sidewalk so we uh partnered with the
city to come in and redo the sidewalk sidewalk I think everybody was as small
I should say I was very surprised the city was quite
wise they didn't build a sidewalk over the tree roots they built around it they
recognize the power of these trees to like disrupt Whatever Gets in their ways they weren't going to set up a battle
with this tree they just went around so if you go out there right now you'll notice at the sidewalk around this tree
so there's this way in which you know a tree can represent practice in which
that it grows and certainly we have in the teachings this idea of something that
gets cultivated and developed in the same way that trees get cultivated and developed and
grow and then this idea of that to let a young rud would grow next to a house for
a house where you see in the Buddhist teachings the Buddha after his Awakening
I spoke a little bit about before his Awakening his mind being wieldy and after his Awakening the tradition holds
that he said this short verse kind of describing the experience
of Awakening this is captured in the
dapada houseb Builder you are seen you will not build a house house again all
the rafters are broken the ridgepole dismantled this mind gone to the
unconstructed has reached the end of craving so the Buddha is kind of like uh
equating this Awakening with the end of the houseb Builder that house is a way
can represent the sense of self this thing that we create and that we believe that we're
inhabiting in something that we that protects us and we can hide behind and
but all the while maybe not recognizing that it is
constructed and that it doesn't have to be there but we are so accustomed to it
of course we have houses and we want to have houses but there's a way in which a house can also be this way in which we
set up our identities the things that define who we are which in the same way
limit Who We Are
it is foolish to let a young Redwood grow next to a
house this idea of foolish I like in pully the language of
the Buddhist scriptures of the early Buddhism they use the same word in poly
means foolish and child so it's just the same way that
somebody doesn't know yet they just have learned yet somebody a fool who just
hasn't you know gained some particular knowledge or some particular
wisdom it is foolish to let a young Redwood grow next to a
house even in this one lifetime you all have to
choose that great calm being this clutter of soup pots and
books so practice disrupts the way that we
consider ourselves even in this one time we will have to choose this recognition that if
we want to continue to practice we can't have our life be exactly the way that it was including this house this way that
we consider ourselves so often we want to be exactly the same not change things but just want
less suffering of course we do but not recognizing that having less
suffering means that some things have to shift and change about ourselves the way that we think about ourselves the way we
think about the world think about others way that we feel about ourselves feel about others that's where the real
Freedom comes and part of practice is to help us
to gain the confidence that we can make these
changes part of practicing is to help us to
feel more clearly what is the direction for more
spaciousness and ease and freedom what is the direction for leads
to more Dua more suffering there's so many ways that
certainly for me when I first started practice I had no idea all the settle ways in which I was holding on to these
ideas of myself I was still working in Corporate America I had a great job and I didn't
realize how I was identified with that job and how every little slight thing
that didn't go well really kind of like really rocked me but practice is a way that it kind of
like grows and we start to see see more clearly maybe gain more wisdom and feel
more clearly and not only that have the confidence to maybe let go of some of
the ways that we think about ourselves or we think about the world or the way we set up of Me versus you US versus
them and we start to see how that is such a great source of
suffering for us for everybody but you have to choose that
great calm being this tree say trees have especially redwood
trees in my view have a certain Mobility steadiness calmness
stability maybe this is something that you've touched into with your meditation practice recognize oh yeah there this
calmness is possible it's available I'm not saying it's always easy and we always have access to it but
to even recognize that that is possible for our
lives and possible to be more and more in our life
this clutter of soup pots and books I love this line in my mind it's a
little bit autobiographical in my mind Jane herfield has a kitchen full of all kinds of pots and and books being a poet
it's not surprising maybe she has a lot of books I have a lot of books I can't help
myself and so practice isn't asking us to let go of all of our soup pots and
books whatever the equivalent of that might be for you practice isn't saying that you can't
have any of those things instead I think what the keyw
here is clutter things that aren't tended
to things that are like getting in the way of something else that we want to do maybe getting in the way of some of this
calmness or stability that we know is possible
so it's not so much that we have to get rid of all these objects in our life that fill up our
house instead it's about a shift in our relationship to them maybe we're not
clinging or maybe we're not dishonoring them and just letting them fill up our
life instead of taking care of them so the Clutter maybe it's literally
maybe it's figuratively but this kind of like
choosing recognizing seeing feeling yeah there's this uh something deep inside
maybe it's not even deep inside maybe it's just found when we go for a
walk versus some of the agitation that we feel in so many areas of our life
possibly we might ask ourselves what is our life filled with that's the opposite of
calm can we choose what would it mean to choose choose the
calm not the
clitter and so there's also this way in which practice asks us to
soften let go of all the ways in which we build these
selves ways in which we limit ourselves and instead to feel the freedom that is
available maybe we've all had just a glimpse of what's available chances are you have otherwise you wouldn't like be
coming to a place like this so here's another poem that's a
very short this one's translated by Jane herfield the same poet who wrote the other poem she translated this with Maro
aratani and this poem was written in Japanese by isumi shiku around the year
1000 I love this poem it's very uses metaphor and it's very evocative I think
and the poem goes like this although the wind blows terribly
here the Moonlight also leaks between the roof planks of this ruined
house although the wind blows terribly here the
Moonlight also leaks between the roof planks of this ruined
house this ruined house maybe this way of we're letting our sense of self or
this identity these things that we hide behind maybe we're letting some uh ruined planks the roof isn't quite
as tight as it used to be and Moonlight is shining
in some of you know like in Buddhism often the full moon is a symbol of Awakening
Enlightenment but no matter about that if there's something at least I feel this when I go outside
oh it's a full moon I've done that a number of times here when I taught on a Monday nights
and uh to walk outside after teaching and to see this big moon it just feels
like oh something's special and so the way that this when
this house kind of starts to crack and the roof still has leaks in it maybe
it's windy which means we feel things
but their Moonlight is shining through there's this way in which there's this
um sense of freedom and Beauty possibility that the full moon can
represent although the wind blows terribly here the Moonlight also leaks
between the roof planks of this ruined house by isumi
iabo another woman poet so then returning back to this poem
Tree by Jane hersfield it continues and it says already the first Branch tips brush
at the window by the time I read with tree the
branch tips are brushing on the window the roots are already underneath right they're in the sewage system they're
under the house they're making their sidewalk buckle you know hear at IMC we have to call RoR rder on a regular basis
because that red with tree out there is like getting into our
pipes so maybe before by the time we already notice that something's here
it's already touched us it's already a part of our life in
some way but maybe it's under we haven't quite seen it the way that Roots we don't see it maybe until they are
disruptive or something like
this also this idea of Branch the branch tips uh meeting the
house so much about practices about meeting meeting
ourselves maybe in a way that we haven't before and let's be honest it's not
always good news I know for me it wasn't always always good news noticing all these wh lies I was doing and all these
ways in which I was holding and Clinging On to these ideas about myself and I wanted people to make sure that they saw
me in one particular way and certainly not this other particular way which I was trying to secretly
hide but I also like this expression that Jack cornfield uses kind of like
meeting ourselves he uses this expression The Unfinished Business of
the heart there's a way in which meeting ourselves is a way of recognizing this unfinished
business of the heart and maybe it allows this business of the heart to get
finished to be metabolized and worked through and met and
seen so often we're trying to discard or disown or somehow excise the these
portions of ourselves because they're painful or they're ugly or whatever it might be we
think that it might be but so much about practice is meeting
all of these aspects of ourselves when we're
ready when we're ready we don't have to jump into the
most difficult parts of our lives at the outset instead we allow practice to
grow we water it we let it have sunshine
good soil and then practice grows as it grows we don't have to make it
grow maybe it's just a way in which we come back we come to MC on Sunday mornings or whatever it might be listen
to YouTube and
then there's this way in which this poem ends for me it's kind of like powerful I
love this line softly calmly
immensity TAPS at your
life this invitation for all of us to maybe like
step into the what's possible for us our biggest life our best
life and it's softly calmly
it's not with a sledge Hammer sometimes it feels that
way but maybe you know there's a maybe a certain
insistence of an invitation asking us to be the best
versions of ourselves the bringing our best wisdom bringing our best compassion to whatever life brings us
after all what else can we do we can't control the whole world I know we try certainly I
try it doesn't work we know that and instead there can be this
invitation to bring our best
selves and I love this word immensity like maybe it's bigger than what we can
imagine maybe it's bigger than what we suspect is
available or what it would be like to have more
freedom and in this way in this poem and I would say in practice this freedom is
in is tied up with this house that we're building and constructing and you know
renovating maybe but still you know having constructed it's a way in which
it can be a in inhibition to Freedom so freedom is a way of maybe we let some of
this building just naturally deteriorate we wouldn't want to do this
in our actual houses but in these sense of selves is there a way that we can let
some of these Moon beams of Freedom shine
in and allowing ourselves to be touched by
it softly calmly
immensity TAPS at your
life thank
you and so maybe as an ending here can
just turn to some people near you and let's all take care of each other let's not let anybody be left behind with
nobody's talking to them we don't want that and just say what did you think of this poem maybe it's like poetry is just
not your cup of tea perfectly fine or maybe you're like I don't know I don't get it that's perfectly fine too or you
might feel like I don't know I'm kind of curious I'm going to go outside look at this tree now or whatever it might be
whatever it might be just turn to somebody and maybe say a little bit about how this poem touched you thank
you