so hello everyone greetings from the dark from uh
still I guess it's Dawn here it's um came down here to IMC in the dark
and delighted and kind of cozy to be here with you all this
way it's one of my favorite things to do is take it up in the morning and go to a meditation
Hall and um did it many times in monasteries and temples where it involved going
outdoors and uh dark and following a path to the meditation Hall and such a
wonderful way to begin the day so um one of
the approaches is one of the supports for meditation
practice that is usually not emphasized and that is uh having a
vision and the reason it's not emphasized is that a vision seems to be
something in the future something elsewhere and not about what's here and now and mindfulness is so much about
being present here and now but the more we're present here and now the more we really settle here and
let go of our distractions let go of our attachments that uh more at peace
here at some point almost like built into that experience of here and now is
a strong sense of it possible to expand that peace further it's possible to let
go more fully it's possible to be more
fully Here and Now not just here and now but somehow fully inhabiting Here and
Now Fully Alive in this fullness of the here and now in the fullness or
wholeness of ourselves and um it's kind of like if
you hold your hand in a fist for a long time and then something happens that you
get distracted from the important task of being all clenched up and you notice
that the hand relaxes a bit and then you might clench up again but you now you
know something and you now you have a vision oh there's a possibility here it's right here and now as well the
possibility of further releasing that that hand so the hand can be relaxed
finally so in in Buddhism at some point
there comes a time when uh a meditator
acquires knowledge and vision it's a technical word and there's knowledge and
visions of different things but the knowledge is something that comes from our direct experience here something we
now know something about the quality the potential of this practice something about the
um Freedom or the peace and then there's a vision that
comes from that knowledge that yes more is possible more is
available um and uh in a wonderful way in which this vision is
experienced is that um it isn't so much that more for me to acquire me to
experience me to do but rather there's an invitation a vision of an invitation
an vision of a request a vision of a door that says
here here the door is open open here freedom
is so meditation as Vision so
to assume a meditation
posture and spend some time refamiliarizing yourself with your body in this
posture some of you have been meditating for a long time
and the posture becomes your Meditation Center your temple meditation
Hall your posture your body becomes kind of the homecoming or
the the meditation Hall
coming so to re familiarize yourself with how your posture feels in your
body as the place you're going to meditate as a support as the home for
meditation and gently closing your
eyes and becoming more sensitive to the experience of your body
how your body feels to feel the request or the call to
relax the body maybe you can feel the vision the
possibility of softening in the
body and if you have a vision or see the
possibility as you exhale may let it be so
relax maybe less that you are relaxing
as you're allowing the body to relax on the
exhale the knowledge of where your tense can translate into a
vision of the possibility of
relaxing and that in the middle of that tension you might sense a request
invitation to
soften
e
for
centering yourself on the body exper the body's experience of
breathing and gently in the middle of the body
breathing maybe at the center of it a
vision of the breathing being easeful soft
light it might not be that way
but when it's not that way right there in the middle of it there can be a sense
of a possibility invitation don't expect it don't try to
make it be that way if just
appreciate that such a vision is
possible it's a vision that makes makes it
possible in its own time in its own
way
e
for
if you find yourself thinking a lot with pressure in the mind
or contraction in the mind or if you find yourself emotionally
troubled with anything know that know it well know it
fully feel it in your body
and in The Knowing deep inside of it maybe there's a
vision of letting go of relaxing opening
up without expectation without making anything
happen maybe just know having that vision is a possib
abbility opens the Mind opens the
heart expands the context for how you can be with any
difficulty you have a vision of
Freedom release an
invitation to be become [Music] more than anything that limits
you
for
e
letting go of your thoughts quieting the
inside to feel deep inside or to
feel where there can be a vision a
sense of Freedom here and
now a sensing a knowing a vision
it's almost like an invitation here this is where you can let
go this is where you can release the grip in the
mind the contraction of the
heart the knot in the belly
here is where you can let go of the bracing that spreads through the whole
body a bracing against
life and being happy to have such a
vision just having it is
enough it opens the
door
e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to open the heart the mind to the challenges of this
world which are
immense and to know that the world has its challenges and to have a vision of
Peace a vision of the letting go of hostility and
greed to have a vision of the world at
peace not in a naive way not expecting it'll happen overnight
or maybe ever but without that
Vision Without that invitation for another way it certainly won't be possible to
change this world take refuge in that
Vision that comes from knowing suffering
well suffering doesn't have to be a burden in the middle of it there's an
invitation of vision for a better
world and may we remember that vision and may it Inspire
us to contribute to that
possibility each of us is important each of us counts however small contribution we
make May through our speech our body and our
mind may we promote good will compassion generosity and peace in
this world may all
beings be happy may all all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
[Music]
free
thank
you
so hello and continue with this story of my life
now as a coming into becoming a teacher and I guess I am enjoying
talking about this uh sometimes I've become bored telling my story few the
times I have and um it's kind of May maybe gives
me a chance for reconsider it and look at it in new ways from this perspective
for today this age so in 1990 I came to graduate school
at Stanford University I moved back into San Zen Center I started teacher training with
Jack cornfield and within a year or so I started kind of training to be a zen
teacher and get Dharma transmission by 1992 I was
married and um it was kind of a wonderful time looking back at it and um and uh my scholarship my was a
three-year scholarship at at Stanford they gave me living
expenses um I was able to spread it out over four years so I went to school two
quarters a year rather than three and uh and that allowed me to go
and do the teacher training to go on Retreats and to start teaching Retreats and I very quickly understood
that um the kind of uh courses graduate courses that I took um uh the primary
way in which we were graded was by turning in a final paper and because I was doing other
things as well uh the Dharma things and Retreat things um uh at least one uh
summer I wrote my final paper before the class began I kind of understood how the
topics were what the subject was I knew the subject I signed up for for the course and I kind of knew how this went
so I knew I would be busy and one of the things that I was busy with or engaged in was at every fall I for pretty much
the whole 1990s um beyond the time I was at um in
graduate school I um taught a 10day uh experienced student
Retreat uh in just North of San Francisco and uh so that was right near the end of the quarter you know just
before everything was due and so you know so I had to really plan ahead to be
ahead of the game in order to be able to get the cours work done but that seemed to always work out and in fact uh when
it was time for me to defend my dissertation uh I
um uh it happened to be in the middle of that 10 uh day Retreat and um and
looking back now I kind of Marvel that that it worked out this way but I was kind of matter of fact about things back
then and just kind of like okay I just did it so it was in the middle of that Retreat so I was at the retreat teaching
it and one morning I got up and put on a jacket nice nice jacket to someone had
given me and uh drove down to Stanford and did the defense and then drove back
to the retreat and just continued uh the teaching there uh so this integration
this going back and forth worked very well I felt very fortunate the way it worked for me at graduate school that
way and um and then I also I was teaching and uh the sitting group in
paloalto that I joined started teaching for in August of
1990 and uh that group began to grow and I very quickly had some sense that there
was a vision I had a vision or knowledge of what was possible for people when
they enter into the world the Buddhist practice and I knew that there was much more to be done in practice than just
coming to A A Monday evening sitting group and I knew that volunteering uh
you know caring for the place you practice in is really valuable for one's own practice so there wasn't much to be
done there was just a key to get into the room in the church and there was um
uh uh taking home every day every Monday the flyers from Spirit Rock um for
programs up there and then putting them out the next day when we next Monday when we came back and so I immediately
early on and asked for volunteers for that and uh and uh the person who I I
gave the key to I kind of said you're now the president of uh of our sitting
group and kind of wanted to really promote people to have some sense of ownership involvement and responsibility
for what was going on and um and uh I taught happily for
about six months without any thought and concerns about any compensation for teaching it was having kind of grown up
for these 10 years in the Buddhist world where I practiced at Zen Center and in Asia um um being paid and getting money
and being compensated was completely out out of the picture the idea was just to
engage in the practice and if you were invited to teach then you would teach and now I would been invited to teach
for this group and I had no thoughts about any any compensation at all and
then after 6 months uh they had a little basket to collect money to pay rent for the church
and after six months there was a $100 an extra and uh what do we do with this and
someone said let's give it to Gil and uh and then maybe another 6 months there was another $100 and so that was the
beginning of uh kind of living um you know being supported to live and teach
the Dharma and uh as that group began to grow I started to have uh vision and I I
realized later it was a vision and I began realizing later that part of the
responsibility of caring for a meditation group was to have a vision of what was possible for them that people
were doing practice and uh and uh it was wonderful and now
there was a vision they could do more it would be helpful so I remember we um this I said you know we this group can
probably now ready to do a halfday retreat and uh so someone uh had access
to a small conference room I guess it's kind of small uh at the uh third floor
fourth floor of the aerodynamics department at Stanford and we went there on a Saturday or so Sunday when it the
building was closed and and and there was a deck and there was some hallways there and that's where we did our first
half day sitting and uh and so then we did more of those and had Vision now these people
are ready for a whole day retreat at some point I said I said uh there are
people who come here don't know about meditation so I think we it's time for us to offer an intro class so I'd
offered an inter class before and um and I write in the next IMC newsletter I write about the
beginnings of this intro class and um and then um and so I
started having you know my job my responsibility I felt or my my caretaking was to have this vision of
what was possible and then at some point someone suggested we move to the Quaker
Meeting House which had a bigger room and uh that turned out to be really wonderful and I love the Quakers I love
the kind of the ethos the atmosphere the I felt like there was something we I
took in deeply from being among not so much among the Quakers but sharing their space with
them and um and there we I decided the we're ready now to take a deep dive into the
Buddhist precepts and we did a class on the precepts and and um and then I did now he's ready
for loving kindness and we did a class on loving kindness and now we're kind of full on Monday nights and so let's start
Thursday nights and so we Quaker place was available for us and so then we started Thursday nights and I a little
different vision for what Thursday nights was about there I Monday nights was more about Buddhism Buddhist
practice and and Thursday night evenings was most about coping how to cope in this difficult life of ours and and uh
in fact the people who came Thursday night were in fact people who are much more on the edge of just managing and cope and wanting some kind of basic
support and and I loved having both those possibilities and then at some point we um uh we used
to we kept kind of wondering what to do and at some point um well I had a vision
of of uh my involvement with the group at some point uh and the vision
was not about staying with the group The Vision for myself was that I was so inspired by the people who are coming
and how serious they were about practice and and I felt the responsibility to caretake and support these people and so
I had this idea that well what we're going to do is to grow this group to be big enough that we can invite an other
teacher to come to take over so I can leave and the idea is I wanted to live
in the country I had this Vision this idea of living um near Point Rays on up
the coast North of San Francisco in a place that's kind of halfway between the Green Gul Z Center where I practiced and
Spirit Rock where ID also practiced I had a strong connection to both and I thought my vision I would live up
there halfway and and be involved in both worlds so um but at some point I think
by 19 uh 1996 I was so inspired and impressed by
this growing Community I I decided you know I'm I guess I'm committed now I'm
going to commit myself to stay here and support this group stay here in the peninsula it was a kind of a big deal
for my wife who she had I she didn't want to meet to live in an urban
area but uh so that's what we did made that I made that commitment but I didn't
require or want anything from the community with that commitment but except I wanted them to know that that
was the case and um and so I uh asked for a meeting among
I don't know I forget who was invited to it but I think there was maybe a dozen or 15 people who are by this time were
kind of more Central than everyone else maybe or I don't remember but we met at someone's
home and I explained to them that I just you know what was happening and I was just felt like I needed to tell people
about this commitment and you know there was no expectation of anything as a result but that stimulated a
conversation and in that conversation then there was a a a vision that was
evoked and I might have had certainly part of that vision and I forget who who initiated it that uh we should have our
own home we should have our own place to practice and and um and I had a full
vision of that I had a really clear sense that uh there so much more was possible if we weren't uh if we could
really have our own place and um and uh where we didn't have
to move zafus and mooving things in and out where people felt like this was where our you know they come here now
this is our place and it was open it could be available 24/7 it could be be kind of people's spiritual home in a way
it couldn't be in a church room and um and that as the as the community grew
and the depth of practice grew maturity grew that we were able to do more more different kinds of programs and support
people and um and uh so then we decided to get
Incorporated and uh as a nonprofit a religious nonprofit and that took a little while and back then coming out of
the kind of maybe alternative culture that I'd grown up in in United States theya have consensus and equality and
everyone in it together was kind of Paramount and so I the idea that we
would have a all consensus-based model for governance for this new center uh
was kind of in the Forefront of our minds and and um and so there was a
group of people that came up with bylaws but when they presented it to me and we had this meeting where we were going to
ratify them I was kind of shocked at what was presented because it was very
open everyone had a vote uh and there was no membership exactly so I guess anybody who came to a meeting or
something everyone had a vote except one person and that was me
the teacher and you know in this consensus model where we're all supposed
to have a vote and decide together um and to you know to not grant me just
that one vote I mean that's just one that didn't seem right to me and it was so complicated what was set up I said
this is not going to work and so I said to the committee that um well I'm not
ready to R there for us to ratify this um uh I'd like us to put on hold while I
have some time to think about this and um and so some people were angry with me but that was the decision
and then about nine months later I felt ready and then I re reassembled some of the people from that committee uh to
come up with new bylaws which is ones we have today and um and
uh and so then we we're ready to start thinking about a center and uh and then
um and keep growing and developing and and uh and following the maturity of
this community and as I come to the end of this little talk that at some point
around that time it was clear to me that I was also maturing that there was something about
the inter relationship the the back and forth connection to a community that was
growing and developing and maturing and my teaching the community and and them
asking questions and growing and that affected me and in this role of being a
teacher um that was a very important time to
really understand myself much better and um you know being a teacher is not free
of attachments not free of certain shortcomings and
Oddities so I had lots of opportunity to see parts of myself that I hadn't seen in years of meditation practice and U
because it was elicited in that Community Dynamic and so it was wonderful to watch the mutual mature ing
of the community and myself the growing that was going on there and um that um
so it was a a very important choice I made uh the community made at that point
and that incorporation then open the door for uh much more to happen here at
IMC so thank you very much and I'll continue with this
tomorrow