good morning and those of you online who are also attending good morning to you or good day
and I'll start with an announcement so we have you know over time
change some of the covet protocol from the when we first opened up and it feels like we're ready to do
another small change big change and that is the Sunday morning here
has been by registration it's supposed to sign up ahead of time in order to keep the numbers within about 50 or so
and it seems like it's things have changed enough that it seems time not to
do that register sign up anymore and now to limit the numbers
so so starting in April that's the way it works and I don't know if any of you
have already signed up for next week but but there's no longer a need and for the
time being we'll keep the room set up the way it is with the chairs and stuff because it does kind of create a little bit of social distancing
and we'll um uh maybe put out more chairs in the outer Hall you can get a
pretty good view in from the other other side and some people used to before the pandemic people Some people prefer to
sit out there they thought the sound was better out there and um and then at some point we'll
we'll rearrange the room the way it used to be pre-pandemic which puts the chairs closer together
so that's a change and then uh we're still uh requiring the n95 masks and I
can very much appreciate that some of you feel maybe that's not needed anymore and feel maybe even a little annoyed that we
should still be old-fashioned this way but I think it's still very helpful and
um and uh for the most part the discomfort that comes with wearing them it makes
for great practice and we have a practice that's supposed
to help us with this kind of discomfort to find our comfort with this discomfort so so you know if we were some other
kind of place maybe you know if we were a Bowling Club maybe there's no practice then to maybe
that kind of practice but we have one so hopefully we can just fold it in and and work with it for a while longer and then
at some point uh probably the masks will become optional but when that is it's
not so clear we're just feeling our way step by step as we go along here
and I think the need for a level of inner safety inner Comfort around not
being afraid about covet or something or less is actually quite important for people who are meditating because as we
get quieter and quieter Stiller and Stiller um if it does happen where in some ways
more tender more sensitive more more impacted by very subtle things and so
this the level of safety around this covet thing and can have an effect on people's meditation I think
so
so yesterday I was doing my taxes
and um and that seemed to go fine more or less
until I try to submit them electronically and then it became Kafkaesque
and uh it was like you got to be kidding me really but that's not just doesn't work
one of the things was I had to submit the first four letters first four letters of my wife's last name but she
only has three letters in her last name
so a lot of people do so I like how do you I couldn't figure out how to get around that and
and then it's later they wouldn't the IRS wouldn't accept her
personal information so you have to contact Social Security Office office to get it sorted out but
they're closed so anyway so that was frustrating because I was more
humbled by my level of frustration then you know anything is done for a long
time so that's a long way of saying that if I
hadn't given any thought to what to talk about today as I woke up this morning
a little bit teeny bit of a hangover from that experience
and um and I thought well what am I going to talk about and now so sometimes well I'm going to
do my early morning meditation and sometimes something comes up in that so I was doing my minding my own
business doing my morning meditation at some point I took her to me well I'll
talk about what I've been thinking about the most in the Dharma lately I'm kind of instead of interested in it and that
seems obvious okay back to my meditation and then floated up his thought later on
well I need to have an example illustration to talk about this Dharma thing
back into my meditation and then at the end of it the pup is floated up
this meditation will be the example so that's what we're doing today
so the example in meditation was that um I sat down to meditate
and my mind was still I think little bit in the leftover frustration level with
having done the taxes so it was kind of racing or kind of spinning and more than usual
and it felt a little bit like my mind was a if it was mine was a car
I would still be in second gear but driving at the speed for the fourth gear
and you know it's kind of like racing and you know really high winding kind of like something's racing here
you know like wow and um like you know this is this is not me there's something that's taken over
here there's a compulsive or drivenness in my thinking and then you know I thought maybe maybe
it's a little bit like being in a terrible storm with strong wind and kind of hunkering down making your way
through it you know like it's making yourself small or something Because by the end of the meditation the
storm had cleared and it wasn't that I got into the fourth gear I think I got into neutral even better
and there was this wonderful feeling of being released from this drivenness the compulsivity of
these thoughts that went on but that took you know the duration of the meditation
and uh and part of that Journey was going through at the beginning and say wow
45 years of meditation and this is what it comes to [Laughter]
and I thought yeah okay well I have to accept this I have to let go of this
this is a bit humbling or a little bit you know so that's okay maybe it's good to be humbled or good to kind of let go
and accept this is how it is and so okay so I'll just I'll just this the freedom was found just accepting this is how it
is my mind is out of control it's spinning it's going fast and um and okay well that's the deal so
there was a certain kind of freedom but it wasn't like celebratory freedom
but you know okay this is the way it is so then as I meditated I could feel slowly my body was tense and that began
the tension kind of settled after the attention my body started settling I could feel my mind beginning
to settle just by doing the meditation just showing up and being present and being present
I didn't feel like I could address the compositivity the drivenness directly it
just felt like that was just getting mired in the mud mired and you know just adding fuel to the second gear
so I just kind of like let out away get out of the way let myself be humbled or simple or just kind of
and um and then after you know the end of the meditation things had settled enough that there was a sense of relief
release and now the feeling was one of kind of delight
like ah this is nice something has let go and then I got to a point where tax
thoughts that if they arose I could just let go of them
they could release them and now the releasing of them letting go of them just felt like a pleasure like a
delight like I wonder what a wonderful thing to be able to do this and come back to this kind of much more simple
relaxed peaceful way of being
so that was that's the example for what I'll talk about and um
so in the Buddhist in the Buddhist vocabulary the ancient Indian vocabulary
the language that Buddha taught there's a whole family of words related
to liberation and and the different words have
different nuances of associations with them and some of them have directly to do
with the word Liberation in English or Liberation Freedom emancipation these
kinds of um you know kind of release kind of like kind of
positive words we would have in English but some of the words
um if uh are often translated into English in Words which for some English
speakers are not celebratory words like Freedom or something
um actually so they're actually maybe a little bit off-putting so uh some words for example
um is translated sometimes translated into English as giving up
now the tone of the voice maybe has a lot to do with how that's taken of giving up you know oh no we have to give
up again and it's kind of a surrender kind of hopelessness okay this is it
um the word relinquishment is used for one of this family of words
and um and uh so I looked up the synonyms for relinquishment in the thesaurus
they're not good news [Laughter] one other one with a lot of most of them
are not good news you wouldn't be happy with if we use these words so one of them one of them is abdicate
you know and uh so maybe the association of the relinquishment is not automatically you
know so great and then there's the word letting go maybe the tone of voice also has
something to do with it letting go for some people is not a good idea not a not
welcome news you have to let go of that in fact sometimes people will tell you just let go
and like you it's kind of infuriating you know what are you telling me you know as if it's easy to let go or
and then people tell you to let go of things you shouldn't let go of let go of everything let go of your
house your you know your possessions let go you know just let go of doing your taxes
and um so um so letting go sometimes doesn't have positive connotations
but it turns out that in English some of these words that are kind of not
necessarily good news anymore for us had an if you do the archaeological
digging in the word the etymology of the word is actually quite wonderful
it seems like the word giving up originally meant offer up to the altar
so that's kind of a sacred Act uh you know someone tells you got to
sacrifice that but the word sacrifice originally meant to make in Latin to make sacred
well that's a beautiful thing so you know back there in the background there they were just something quite lovely
and uh apparently the word surrender also uh surrender doesn't seem like a
good idea but apparently it meant kind of a superior super kind of rendering a
giving again this giving so all these words uh there's a kind of uh
so have a positive connotations originally turns out in Pali in the Buddhist
language the same thing occurs but not so much in the etymology of the
word but in the meaning of the word that some of these family of words having to do with Liberation means both
something like letting go and generosity letting go and giving
and uh and depending on the context of what's being taught and sometimes it's
translated as relinquishment or letting go
and giving up but sometimes actually translated as giving
uh you you know and then when it's translated as giving it's directly
connected to feeling Delight just you're feeling the Delight of giving
feeling the light of Letting Go feeling the Delight of giving feeling the light
of relinquishment so Nepali those words are kind of all the same there's a word chaga which
means both generosity and letting go there's The patini Saga which means
relinquishment and giving there is vasoga which means both
relinquishment and giving so when you hear these at these words
you know have this double meaning then translating as letting go or
relinquishment doesn't capture some of the richness or the association to it
so I've tried you know well let's let's just let's use giving as part of it and um
and um so maybe giving up
but you know but but and then I thought well how about giving
away but but it doesn't quite maybe so so
I'll just forget about the the up and the away or let's just call
it giving and I like that but then but then you don't get a sense of what
it means for The Giver that it's a beautiful feeling of release that goes on to give with release
to give we're giving is free kind of a freedom to give we're giving is a kind of a
you know just feels like fresh air it feels like the you know
the over-rev cars back in neutral and resting or the feel like the storm is
over and it's gotten to be calm and peaceful so what is this release that we can have
this giving that feels wonderful celebratory
and this is a clear Association that the Buddha has with the deepest forms of
letting go of Liberation that we can have it's clearly a release it's clearly
something disappears it's given up is let go of
but uh it's not a diminishment but rather a kind of a feel it feels
great in fact the Buddha said something like
um if relinquishing something and the word he
uses here can mean both giving and letting go
um if relinquishing something
brought about unwholesome states of mind I would not teach you to do so
but if relinquishing something letting go of something giving up something giving away something
um results in wholesome statements of mind for you
then I recommend you do it so this is not a blanket teaching just
let go let go let go no matter what it's letting go
in a way that leads to positive states of mind
and so to be able to discern that that that's part of the criteria for knowing when to let go oh I'm
actually better by not holding on to this there's something gets free it's something good happens
and then when the Buddha describes the things we actually what he recommends we relinquish we let go of
and then some sometimes he actually uses words that there's no
um Redeeming the words I'm trying to redeem some of these words right there's a
family of words so Freedom you don't have to redeem Liberation that's good right but relinquishment giving up
that's you have to redeem a little bit here that's what I'm trying to do but there are some words he uses which
have no redeeming he uses like words like abandoned so uh
oh but what do we abandon what do we relinquish and um and all my wealth
you know my friends my possessions my sexuality right all these party pooping
things
and I'm not going to say you're not supposed to do that but here's a list
you can leave now before you hear it
oh here he comes
lust hatred delusion anger hostility
denigration insolence Envy miserlessness deceitfulness craftiness
obstacy vehemence conceit arrogance
intoxication heedlessness it's a great list
so what do these have in common are they all these words they all have to do with inner states in
our mind in our hearts that nothing to do with things of the world and what's out there
these are things to um
that to be let go of but to let go of them to relinquish to
give up to give up to give to something
how do we do that and that's actually the full context of this quote how do we accomplish this
what help what what what states of mind can be cultivated to make this possible
and the Buddha says you want to cultivate a deep capacity for tranquility it's serenity
and insight what the practice we do here to really see clearly
so that when you let go you see you understand really deeply
what you're letting go of and why without seeing clearly letting go is not
wise we want to let go in Wise ways so that without wisdom that we can
um it's easier to let go we know why we're
letting go and so we're not letting go of the wrong things and so we can better appreciate the
benefits that come from letting go we learn how to let go
how to relinquish how to give it all away or to be generous it's
an act of generosity the movement of the movement of freedom
so when I was sitting in my meditation this morning you know kind of putting up with my
State of Mind grumpy State of Mind spinning mind mostly what I had to do was kind of like
okay well I guess I can be humbled sometimes okay you have to accept this too I'll
let go of you know probably have to let go of some kind of conceit of
I'm a great meditator today and so that didn't wasn't inspiring
but you know it was what was needed Maybe just okay I just have to practice with
this and then with by the end it was an act of generosity oh there's
those thoughts again but now I had enough Serenity enough Insight just okay I'll I'll release
those and I could feel the goodness of it I could feel how it felt good to do it and
it kind of felt like a generous thing to do because the alternative was not generous the alternative was not
good for me to go back into those thoughts I could feel what it was you know I had
the choice Easy Choice was like you take your hand off the hot stove kind of with the
and so I could appreciate it I could value it and so part of the wisdom of
letting go is learning to recognize the goodness of doing so
to recognize how we're better because of it what gets released the space that's
created the room it gives for beneficial states to Bubble Up and to flow
and um the Delight the joy
so there's a family of words connected to freedom and Buddhism the goal of Buddhism
liberation some of them more literally means liberation
some of them have this dual meaning of giving and giving up
relinquishing and giving something away and where does it go
if you're grumpy give it away but don't give it to anyone
give it to space give it to the ocean give it to the sky it knows what to do
with it and many years ago I discovered that at
the end of meditation the end of retreat whatever calm I had would usually go
away after some time and I used to be a little bit grumpy then like or
and what I learned was if it's going to go away anyway why don't I set the intention to give it
away I'll just give it to the world and just that shift
made me feel so much better rather than holding on to it or feeling disappointed if my good state was
leaving I said great another thing to let go of and other things to be generous to
so if you permit permit me allow me there is a kind of children's song I
think I think it's children's song Maybe it's an adult song maybe it should be an adult song that goes something like love is
something if you give it away okay you only end up with more
this in Buddhism they say the same thing for merit that if you give away all the Merit from
the good things you've done that's really meritorious you get more merits
what is Merit marriage is all the good feelings all the happiness that comes from the good
things you do so do good things feel the happiness
and give away that happiness share it with others don't hold on to it for yourself
and you'll end up more with more so the intimate Connection in Buddhism
between letting go and generosity and giving freedom and generosity
the intimate connection Buddhism in the other way too between giving and generosity and freedom
where do we start do we start with freedom and get generosity
or to start with generosity and then blow and behold we get freedom
so I just left you with a big problem and to figure that one out
aren't you lucky that's your problem just start anywhere makes sense either
one it's a great thing it's a celebratory the wonderful thing
that in these two languages maybe many other languages that there's such an recognize such a
close connection between letting go and generosity
may you come to appreciate that and value it and find a way
so thank you so we have a little bit of time we can do a few questions or
comments in here testimonials about letting go and generosity
and then uh maybe in about 10 minutes or so those of you who want to stay we can
go out to the parking lot and take some folding chairs and sit out there in a circle and if you'd like we can take off
the mask there and all of us and just have a continued discussion there but for now any any comments or question
in here that someone foreign
my question is when you realize that there's a state to let go of
um how do you make the choice between trying to
relax and do nothing to allow it to pass or to
try to engage loving kindness with yourself
so there's so many strategies to learn what's needed any given time and some of
it just comes from practice you just try different things so you know now apparently you know two things now you
know letting go and loving kindness right what a good what what good fortune that you have these two tools
so now you've got to practice with them until you get the street smarts you understand how it works and when when
one works when one doesn't work when one feels like the best thing for you and um and then you learn also through
trial and error you know well I'm not sure but right now I feel I feel more attracted to the loving kindness and you
do it and after a while you know actually that doesn't work that's not that's not really working
today so I think that's the best way rather than give you some formula
is that okay yeah thank you
I understand I understand the topic of today's letting go but my question is
why acquire uh what why acquire to begin with to begin with yeah you know there's this
thing that like a nouns of prevention is worth a pound of cure
so why be agitated about doing taxes why don't just laugh at IRS who has all
these problems and it's their problem not yours right like why do you get agitated
now you're asking such profound questions I cannot answer
but uh you know you said after 45 years this is what it amounts for so for you
it's easy to say that right like you have such a confidence in your practice but for us we're looking up to you as a
teacher and we don't have 45 years right so what do we do I hope I didn't how do
we get the confidence in our practice I hope I didn't discourage you today no no it's fine that's fine it is a little
discouraging to be completely honest it is discouraging
the um I think that 45 years ago what I didn't have was any ability to get some
perspective on my grumpiness in the race and the rising mind I would have been
sucked into it and caught in it and I was not today it's like oh look at that that's interesting
so there was some Freedom there oh as always there is two sides right so
one side I am a little discouraged on the other side I'm very inspired by your
ability to talk openly about this topic and you know being relatable to us and
uh it's it makes me more willing to listen actually to you because it seemed
like you're willing to be honest very honest great great oh so in this regard
I think I said I might have said this last Sunday or somewhere I don't know I teach so much so who knows where I said
it um is um uh I think in this practice we do we're
all of us all the time beginners but what happens when you practice for 45 years
you're just an experienced beginner which makes it easier
makes it a lot easier but you're still just a beginner so don't get too don't don't expect too much
hi Gill um I really liked an analogy used today
that I hadn't heard before about letting go which was to take your hand off the hot stove
I'm whenever someone says relax to me I tense up and whenever someone says let
just oh I love it when they proceed with the word just just let go I cling so
um at least I've arrived at that awareness um yeah
hold up hold on there's the aspiration right and so I thought of removing the
hand off the stove and then I thought take my hand out of the fire
when I think about the thing that will grab me is a feeling that somebody is really wronged me or dissed me or
something in a way that will have consequences not just gee I didn't like that that's a
feeling I can get that but oh 12 other people who I cared about heard that and were influenced
that's a problem um and so I I'm going to work with this idea of taking my hand out of the fire
but whenever I want to give up something I need something to go to if I'm going to give up sugar I need to go to
vegetables or something I need to have a goal I need to not give up as much as I
get something different can you give me any guidance around that process what can I substitute okay it's
got wonderful things you said so first I want to say that what are the functions
of developing mindfulness is developing heightened sensitivity to recognize the hot stove or the fire
and so then we if it's really a hot stove you don't need anything better to go to
it just it just you want to get out of it because it's so it's so obvious so instinctual and so as we get more
sensitive we feel the suffering in fact if some of you have heard me say that I recommend that we should learn how to
suffer better in this practice and that's also discouraging
foreign better means you don't go out to make better suffering it means that you feel
you're suffering more acutely so that you can learn the lessons of it so that
you can the Instinct not to be there to pull back or step away can operate so
sometimes like sometimes that's the only thing that helps and sometimes some of the deepest deepest attachments
um you at some point in this practice it just like you reach rock bottom and there's you have to give up
sometimes giving up is what's called for surrender okay I Surrender there's
sometimes there's no other way because you've tried every option other option none of it works
and um I mean in my first retweets that I sat I was
miserable until I I finally gave up because not because I knew it was wise
just nothing else I just I didn't know what to do anymore I was
hopeless and then the retweet started something with I had to let go so deeply
and give up all hope kind of and then something was able to happen so that happens sometimes but your
question sometimes you need a reward you need something positive I think that's really wise also
and this is where I think much of the western Buddhist teaching
that I grew up with when I was you know just 40 years ago and so it was so much On Letting Go and letting go and letting
go and there was even an emphasis a clear emphasis not not to emphasize the
good mental states that can come with practice because you have to let go of that too you have to let go of that tattoo and not have a goal
but if you read the teachings of the Buddha there's a lot of carrots in there
there's a lot of emphasis on cultivating and developing beautiful states of mind
and um and uh and and developed into the point of abundance
we let go of things that harm us but things that benefit us we let them
grow and develop in abundance so what are those things
Joy peace peace happiness Equanimity is one of them generosity
wisdom equanimity um
um compassion and loving kindness and
anacampa care and ethical Integrity these are all
beautiful states that exist in us so so as we practice and clear kind of the
debris from our mind we start seeing the feeling and getting a visceral kind of embodied
experience of what these states are like so then we say oh when I let go I can
return to those and a turning point for me in my practice was to start feeling
feelings of peace and love and love was one of them
that they just felt like that that was almost like the natural state
and so the commitment in practice that kind of The Vow that I made in practice was to orient my life to stay true to
those because that's was more who I was than the opposite and but that was because I had learned
to recognize it and it wasn't there was it wasn't always readily accessible those States
but I knew that that's what the practice was helping me do so so sometimes you don't get the
rewards right away sometimes you have to wait a while for them so does this address your
question well enough yeah it really did um you triggered a memory for me my life
coach is always saying that in these difficult moments there is gift and
opportunity and I always groan at him but I think now I get what you said and
I get what he said so that's that's what I will look for is the gift and
opportunity for all of these more beneficial States
yeah and um and so in in one of the you know great
gifts of this mindfulness practice is when we see that just to be mindful in a
situation that is its own reward you know I mean wow you step back you
step away you open up and you're really here and yes you're grumpy yes you're whatever
but wow this is like the the the the the you know the clouds just parted
so thank you all very much and um so we have about five minutes before
the formal ending so what I'd like to ask for you because I feel like Community is such a hugely
important part of what's happening in this post-pendemic pandemic world if um
you'd be willing to just turn to someone next to here here and welcome them here even if this is your first time here you
can welcome them and say your name or something and talk a little bit if you want and then in about five minutes I'll
go out and we can meet in the and we can meet in the parking lot
I'm Ann