so I'll just mention a word or two about our theme for today
uh or a game for this week actually is factors that build a wise stability in
unity or unification especially in meditation and also in
daily life I'll be spending most of the time talking about the meditative aspects and
a little bit in how to apply it in the rest of our lives which is where this practice really matures
so good morning good to see all of you and the invitation is after you've greeted your friends
to settle back relax and take a good posture for a
balance of relaxation and alertness
allowing yourself to go inward
starting with a few slightly deeper slower belly breaths allowing your belly to
relax stop it
[Music] and allowing your breathing to return to
normal
I'm taking a moment to acknowledge take stock of whatever is happening
in your body your heart your mind In This Moment acknowledging with kindness
whatever's here
and sweeping through the body allowing the eyes to relax and soften
the tongue and lips and jaw
soften
inviting the occipital muscles at the base of the skull between the skull and
back the neck to relax just a little
[Music] sweeping mindful awareness through your neck throat shoulders
an inviting relaxation
perhaps noticing the breathing the nostrils the back of the throat
windpipe the chest in the valley
and tuning in tuning in to the act of breathing
emotion warmth
appreciating your life's breath
and inviting a softening through this Attunement to the breath and the Torso
arms and hands
buttocks hips legs
ankles feet
allowing your awareness to fill your whole body
noticing the vibrancy of aliveness pulsing or tingling warmth or cool
and then tuning in tuning
to breathing more sound if that's a better object of
attention for you or the whole field of Sensations in your
body I'll be giving instructions mostly for
the breath please adapt as it works for you
tuning in settling on the sensations of breathing
acknowledging everything else nothing left out
allowing everything else to fade to the background of the periphery
sinking into relaxing into the sensations of in and out
Rising belly falling behind foreign
reconnecting
the attention with breathing what's this Breath Right
in the invitation is to sustain that connection
staying in close contact with feeling feeling into all the sensations and
emotions of life's breath
noticing expansion relaxation
natural [Music] lowering of the belly
inward movement to the ribs more motion of air on the out breath
really sustaining that connection
through every little motion the first inkling of breath coming in
all the way through to the top of the top of the in-breath the fullness of lungs resting there
before releasing the out breath
you want to sing any pleasure or comfort
in the letting go of the out breath
perhaps resting for a moment at this Stillness Still Point
the end of the Opera
from time to time rededicating the attention
foreign
noticing enjoying any feelings of ease
and allowing kindly compassionately everything else
inviting the attention in the mind to be immersed in
the moment and the sensations
gently
now in each breath to nourish replenish
it's best I can
noticing their returning of awareness reconnecting with the moment
and staying in contact with
sustain me attuning
with breathing Sensations
[Music]
unifying the attention
with the moment
foreign
allowing the attention to reconnect
stay with sustain
noticingly appreciating any pleasure is
contentment happiness or joy
allowing the rest with kindness
unifying the attention [Music] in the moment
does this meditation formal meditation draws to a close
the invitation is tune into your heart Your Heart Center
and gather up any goodness little corner of kindness
of comfort or peace
that emerged in this time together
and cast your internal eye outwards to the others in your life
the people animals even plants
and to make the determination to share some of this goodness with the
others that you encounter
offering a sense of kindness wish
for freedom [Music]
may all beings everywhere be free of suffering
[Music]
thank you
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
foreign
special welcome to those of you who tiptoed into the YouTube session a
little bit late and a warm welcome to those of you who have been here for the whole meditation
the theme for this week is factors of wise stability and unification
which is um otherwise known as five qualities of
mind that are called the jonic factors because when balanced
and in play they are supports for deep meditative States known as Jonas
and my focus to speak is not going to be on those deep States
instead we'll cover how recognizing and navigating these five factors of mind
with the support of mindfulness and intelligence supports the deepening of
our meditation practice and it supports wisdom more broadly
I also will touch on how recognizing and cultivating these capacities of our
minds beneficial not just to meditation but a little bit to our relational life as
well so that's the overview today I'll talk about how mindfulness
and practice intelligence our helpful Foundation to cultivate meditative stability and
these factors and then over the course of the week we'll cover the mental factors of
connecting and sustaining otherwise known as a vitaka and Bichara
joy and happiness and Pali
unity and unification which is a kaga or a kagata in Pali
and so that will take us through Thursday and then Friday to wrap up
I'll talk about how these factors when imbalance contribute to a refinement of
meditative practice stability and wisdom so that's the overview
hope you stay for it and today
mindfulness and practice intelligence and these this sort of broad base of
overall mindful awareness of the entire process of what's happening within us as
best we can see lends itself to developing a kind of understanding of practice intelligence
that is a super helpful context when wanting to deepen meditation that's
already a sign of a certain kind of depth and breadth and
the five tonic factors exist within this Ecology of our minds just like
everything else that exists in their distraction or love or Joy or
whatever right like many other mental factors or
qualities of our heart to mind they can be beneficial to our lives in some ways
and if misdirected they can be unbeneficial
so that's why it's so important to cultivate mindful awareness awareness as
a foundation there's a simile that I'm going to use
this is a modern simile but let's say you're a bicycle writer okay
the handlebars are the intelligence the bicycle Rider themselves is
mindfulness and Equanimity steadiness balance is the
balance of the bicycle as it moves along and then the bike path or the road is
the noble Eightfold Path so it gives you an idea that the
mindfulness and the intelligence practice intelligence are kind of in charge of where we go on the path right
so as many of you know from having been here some of you for quite some time
mindful awareness Sati mindfulness is the capacity to know what's going on
while it's happening within and around us right
and this is especially true when starting to deepen our practice of being
aware of the qualities or attitude of our own heart and mind
one of my Burmese teachers talks about the way that mindful awareness gathers
data gathers information like a scientist or a researcher might
and this Gathering process is helped by being able to settle back
soft and open be aware without an agenda in the moment
aspiration is great aspiration for Freedom more healing more more love whatever it is
and lack of agenda helps us to see it all
see all of it the good bad the ugly the Beautiful
all of it it's also really helpful to engage
intelligence practice intelligence and by that I mean it's okay to bring your whole mind to
bear on meditation get curious get interested in the information that mindfulness is
gathering in the moment start to connect the dots practice intelligence begins to connect the dots
and this emerges it's not a discursive kind of analysis but an emergent kind of understanding
that naturally develops in each of us over time regardless of age or IQ or of
grade level whatever formal education this is a different kind of intelligence
it's our natural Birthright this kind of intelligence or wisdom
begins to seek cause and effect Discerning what's beneficial or
unbeneficial right and that's especially in terms of these
factors of mine sometimes the these words translate
which is skillful or unskillable wholesome or animals and that's a very
simple incisive discernment and is this good right now or is it not
helpful there's a simile in the ancient
teachings I believe this is from the numerical discourses that the Buddha talks about mindfulness as a gatekeeper
and he uses the gatekeeper as a simile quite often this particular one
is a gatekeeper who is in front of a walled city as they were in those days
city state and he or she lets in has the discernment to
really let in and direct people who are good for
contributing to the city or have Messengers for the leader and directing them to the right place to go the center
of the city and then for others he directs them to what they need
and for the people who aren't so helpful for the city
criminals for example you might not let them in at all
so this is a factor of intelligent mindfulness
it's accepting whatever is arising if it's already in the city the city being our body
it's accepting that it's there while Discerning whether or not it's helpful
to continue to feed it or to let it go and Usher it away
we begin to see with mindfulness and practice intelligence
when conditions are in place for meditation to take a certain direction including developing meditative
stability and unification
some mindfulness and practice
reveal practice intelligence reveal whether or how any particular mental factor is
useful or not in the sort of purpose for the purpose
of cultivating meditation or for cultivating other activities and I'll get into that more as the week goes
along so again be takan Bichara connecting and
sustaining Piti and sukha Joy
contentment happiness and akaga or kagata One pointed
Focus immersion absorption and the intelligence of prey and the
mindfulness at play helped to steer this whole process is this the time to unify
and gather is this particular factor of joy for example helpful or distracting right now
or is something else called for sometimes a broader knowledge
a broader understanding of what is operating in our hearts and Minds
it's actually more helpful and integrating
stabilizing prior to cultivating more of these factors
there's an example from my own life I I was an artist for many years practicing artists
and I attended this group of figure drawing people for years it was a lot of
fun but we got to see each other work as well as as drawing and inevitably it
would happen especially for those of us who are newer that someone would be focused in on this
detailed gorgeous rendering of say a hand or an ear or a face
however they were still focused on the details that they didn't step back to notice
that the hand was five times too big or the head was half the size it should
be in proportion to the rest of the drawing it's kind of like this
the mindful awareness the practice intelligence help us understand when it's helpful
to dive into the details and absorb and be focused and when maybe it's helpful
to step back and take a look at the bigger picture
we never have complete knowledge but a sense of how the proportions of
what's happening in our minds and hearts are and lives are working can be really
helpful before absorbing into details so
mindfulness and practice intelligence are the foundation for the cultivation of these
five hydronic factors five factors of wise stability and unity unification
they operate in our minds and hearts and deep practice and they provide a resource and sometimes a frame for
understanding our relational lives tomorrow I'll shift to the five factors
proper with the first two connecting and sustaining meanwhile perhaps just notice the range
of mindful awareness in your heart mind life and if it makes sense maybe talk about
what kind of intelligence emerges for you with a Dharma friend between now
so it's a delight to be with you Sangha we look forward to being with you tomorrow
thank you
[Music]