welcome and warm greetings to this time
these next 30 minutes for our meditation and um
meditation has a lot to do with being local
uh everything from you know the Dharma point of view in a sense is local it's
here local means in the Locale of this body this time here now
and um and so it's possible to have a bird's
eye view of something I was struck by I was in New Zealand in
February during the cyclone and the bird's eye view of the intensity
of the storm was terrible and the News was focusing on some of the
great damage that was being done and people killed and the bullet was not being shown shown
from this kind of high-end View where all the people who were helping
each other locally a lot of people coming to the aid of
neighbors and friends and a lot of people mobilize to try to help
so we got closer and closer to where we were the people right there in the little
place that I was staying and practicing was they were so kind and so friendly
and so supportive and and that didn't make the front news that
there were kind supportive helpful people so we begin being really local
and here the most local is here with ourselves
and here we try to
care appreciate for the people who are most
close with you which happens to be you you yourself
not in some kind of sentimental way not in some kind of conceited way
but kind of a straightforward very simple appreciation and respect for the life that's being lived in this
body in this heart in this mind that this life too if you come in close
is something to care for support and do and to appreciate and to respect
we come to our mind we learn over time that everyone it can be respected
including ourselves deep respect everyone can be appreciated a deep
appreciation including ourselves partly because
the alternative of not having respect and not having appreciation is not very healthy it's not doesn't
it's actually in some ways takes more work takes more mental power even though
sometimes people have it as a habit and it's so easy to do and and the most local most deep place
to be is to be here caring for
respecting appreciating this life life around us people people around us
and the most local of it all is here with ourselves and with the eyes closed in meditation
it's a training ground of letting go of all that is not
respectful all that is unappreciative about yourself
and you'll find you don't have to do appreciation or do respect
if you let go of all that disrespect and non-appreciation
then you'll find that it's kind of like the appreciation is there the respect is there it's just
there the deepest respect is not something we have to muster up
so to assume hey respectful meditation posture that posture in which you're going to
appreciate this body this life now
so no not no posture that requires excessive
strain no heroic posture
gently closing your eyes
and becoming aware of your body breathing
your body has breathed many many many breaths in this lifetime
breathing has been a companion support the helper
in all its different ways it cares for you the best it can
and deeper than the breathing is your heartbeat
sometimes in meditation you can feel it sometimes you can't
the heart's been beating for you for as for longer than you've been
breathing
some people consider the heart beating
the body breathing
to be the source the origin the beginning
of this life we're living now here
breathing and heart beating and blood moving through the body
are part of a vast physiological system neurological systems
that are here to support you operating often without any thanks or
even recognition here
and to have some modicum of appreciation
and respect for this body
even with all its challenges
and rather than appreciating yourself for now
appreciate that you can appreciate the body be the appreciator
the respecter of this body
This Heart
and this mind they're appreciating it respecting it
even though they all have their challenges and and difficulties
still close up there's a lot of goodness a lot of help
a lot of things that are working a lot that's a miracle to be sitting
here
in every breath every heartbeat every sensation in the
body even every thought feeling emotion
is a bit of a miracle that it should even exist
all part of a large cooperative
effort on the part of this Mind Body to care for you
and for you to care for to appreciate
settling yourself into this breathing body
with appreciation for all maybe even a sense of awe
that quiets and stills the thinking mind
and as we come to the end of this meditation
to drop the word into you to drop the word
appreciation
dropping it like a pebble into a pond and where does the word appreciation
land in you
where does it come to rest not pushed away not questioned
doubted but let the word the concept appreciation
settle in and come to rest someplace Within
and maybe from there to gaze upon the world
with appreciation gaze upon the people in your life and your neighborhoods
appreciating them respecting them
and with that appreciation simple and direct
to wish them well
imagine them well and wish it for them
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
may all beings be free of unhappiness
may all beings be free of fear
may all beings be free of war and fighting and
aggression and may all beings be free
of their bondage to create hatred and delusion
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
then this will be the third talk on the elements the aspects of compassion
one way of thinking about this there are the building blocks for compassion
compassion is such a wonderful ideal and wonderful attitude to have
this and it's championed in many ways but it's often presented I think that
you're supposed to be compassionate or you want to be compassionate or as if you could just kind of mustard up and
just do it from you know you know on a moment's notice
but I think more realistically is that there's a foundation put in place for healthy compassion
for compassion that doesn't slide into distress or slide into a kind
of losing ourselves in other people excessive preoccupation with others and
losing touch with ourselves and um and so putting in the foundation having
the building blocks and on Monday I talked about having awareness not just being aware
but having a sense of autonomy in that awareness a sense of stability and strength in the
awareness so that the awareness is almost something that is not entangled
or caught in what we're aware of that kind of healthy very healthy insane
and kind of distance or openness or
bigness so awareness is bigger than anything that we are aware of or awareness is a step back and can gaze
kindly upon what's there so a sense of autonomy in the awareness
that sense of autonomy then is something that we can that comes into
um kind of a fullness as we get in get put these elements into place for compassion
so finally when compassion is mature there's a clear sense of autonomy or
Independence or or freedom in the their compassion itself
so yesterday it was Attunement one of the meanings of it to admit is to come into harmony with something
so rather than headlong rush into having compassion caring for someone helping
them fixing them doing something um is taking the time with that sense of
autonomy to find what's the harmonious way of being here what's the way to be attuned
or resonant with someone that's appropriate for both of us together
and uh and that effort to find that and you know it means we're up we're exercising a certain degree of autonomy
we're not lost in the experienced or lost in our preoccupation where they were kind of like standing there you
know upright and and uh and stable and then
finding where where is the residents where how do I be here in an appropriate
way to not identify with the person's suffering or become it but rather how do
I um uh be attuned to it to recognize it to
accompany it to to be present in that way that's helpful
and then the next step in this these five elements of compassion is appreciation
and uh and appreciation carries a lot more value if we're autonomous if we're our own
person kind of who then can meet someone with appreciation if we kind of sink or
less than a full person or if we kind of feel like we have to kind of take care
of someone or join them in their misery or what's going on then they might feel like there's some
companionship and some people want to be have people kind of proving that they
um you know that they're committed to some kind of
way caring for them but but there's less there to offer but
if we can be kind of upright and autonomous then we can really come with certain kind of
healthy strength healthy presence where we're radiating more so that our appreciation
and our respect for others as a fuller field a fuller kind of there to be
recognized and um and so uh
uh appreciation is a lot to do with valuing someone else valuing who they
are it also means appreciating the wholeness of a person and not getting stuck on a
particular things they've done particularly things they said particularly quirks they have
that you might like or not like but to step back and appreciate this is
a human being who's been born who's been a baby who's gone through the
tremendous different kind of Life Experiences growing up some very challenging some may be
wonderful this is a person that's had to navigate so many things in this life in a
complicated life we all have and challenging lives and and here's a
person who's kind of you know taken a lot of knocks in this life and had a lot of challenges perhaps or
this is a person who's finding their way and this is a person to grant them their
autonomy there's a the respect that's in appreciation is one especially an
important thing because of respecting their autonomy their ability to make choices for themselves their ability to
be a dignified valued person who has whose opinions that matter who's whose
experience matters who's life matters but not to interfere not to kind of come
with compassion and try to tell them what to do and what you have to do and all these things
and um so to um to appreciate others
and part of uh uh the appreciation Factor where that can come from
is it begins not necessarily with gazing up
on the other person thinking about the other person thinking about what to appreciate but rather it begins with in ourselves
to get settled in the place of awareness
settled in our bodies settled in the present moment so that the reactive mind the judging
mind the opinionated mind the scared mind that the the the
that's involved with you know lack of that offers disrespect or
disappreciation or worse you know Prejudice and bias and or resentment or
or Envy or uh blame or all kinds of things that the
Mind does one of the functions of meditation and mindfulness is to settle all that so
that we can live in the world from a different place and that different place
is a place where we appreciate how special it is
to be grounded centered calm we appreciate
being aware it's a miracle to be aware it's a
miracle to be mindful and and to be but to be busy in life
running around doing all the things we do we don't realize how to remember what a miracle it is
and so to come to a place where we simply appreciate being aware it's such a miracle
then the Gaze of appreciation is one that appreciates regardless of
what it sees so it's not really so dependent on the
other person being just right and just perfect and doing everything the way you want the person to do
the person can even do things which maybe are unethical
and now to the appreciation is not an approval of that or letting them get letting them get away with it
but it's not being limited to that and seeing the whole person
I've known people who did live an unethical life and it all changed for them the thing
that transformed them when they met with someone who didn't see them through the
lens of what they had done but saw them as a whole person just appreciate who they were and to be seen
that way by someone else they kind of wow they kind of opened them to a more
fullness of who they are and what they can be that was powerful for them and
they kind of stepped into this Fuller person who they were and their unethical
Behavior stopped the kind of Miracle story maybe but it's
powerful to have this kind of be gazed on and be seen this whole way with appreciation rather than anything that
we're limiting people to a particular kind of small part of who they are
and so uh to have compassion without appreciation might not be
compassion to have a compassion without appreciation and respect for the person
I don't think that the compassionate action we do will be so clean or so
effective or touch something so deep it might be fixing or helping or it might
be enabling even something that they shouldn't be enabled to do
there's something about engaging someone with Compassionate Care
where they in the care they feel the appreciation the respect they feel like
we're being it you're being treated as a dignified autonomous person who can make your own decisions and you're there to
again to be their friend their accompany them to be available to offer what support might be needed
but you're not asserting ourselves we're not proving ourselves we're not
um uh feeling sorry for someone or have pity for someone they appreciation is
there the Deep respect I like to believe that this Dharma
practice is a practice that brings forth a lot of respect for
ourselves for the world for others and to live with mindfulness is to live
with respect the kind of respect that we're always
ready to bow to every everyone
if the step hour of respect that bow may be even a little reverence about deep appreciation
sometimes bowels of gratitude sometimes bows of delight and joy
something like that that we're always ready to Bow we might not actually bow
but the heart is always ready for that that kind of appreciation that kind of
respect even of our enemies to bow
at least bow in our hearts to always be ready
this is a tall order but some modicum of this
awareness Attunement and then appreciation is
really the really this building block for us than to eventually get to compassion
so um so why don't you go around the day today I think it would be fantastic if you
would explore this this concept of appreciation and or respect
for others how often do you have appreciation for the people you pass on
the street or in the stores or at work or in neighborhoods is that part of your
your social orientation is to appreciate or respect the people who come around
you or does that something you have to remind yourself to have appreciation
what's it like for you to bring forth can you bring forth an
appreciation and respect that's less a doing and more and allowing of some deep
almost innate capacity for respect and appreciation
when disrespect the non-appreciation
have fallen away so if you wish explore that during the day
and until we meet again and that may be a foundation for
tomorrow where we talk about aspiration as part of an element of compassion
thank you