readings greetings everyone good morning good afternoon good evening whatever
your time zone might be my name is Nikki merkafori and I'm delighted to be
joining you this week supporting um us and Gail who's teaching a retreat
this week so um
the theme that I like to invite us to explore this week is
um the five Aggregates and I'll say a lot more about it later but for now let's just uh begin meditating together
sitting together so let's let's begin let's arrive
to arrive in our bodies
let's arrive in this moment in time
and let us let us sit with a sense of
Integrity on this Earth a sense of dignity
internal dignity dignified
no matter what is going on whatever the conditions of the mind and the body
and we meet them with a physical form
that is dignified
if you're sitting allowing your spine to be a straight sense of integrity
dignity
if you're lying down and standing also
letting the body have a sense of dignity in its posture
and while and we said with
our back straight aligned as if
an invisible string is pulling up
on our head ever so gently straight straightening aligning our
vertebrae one vertebrae at a time
we also want the body to be relaxed
so that the sense of uplift is not forced feels natural the body is being uplifted
this form and at the same time is being pulled
down by gravity the muscles are relaxed by gravity
offering their weight to the Earth
as if we have wings and have roots
ah and suspended with ease
inviting defeat to feel the Earth to feel the contact
points or sit bones to feel the contact points
hardness softness heaviness the edges
the sensations of aliveness
and inviting awareness too
hold the breath relaxing and receiving the breath in the
abdomen one breath at a time
and offering the heart the mind
inviting a sense of spaciousness In This Moment
so that if thoughts are arising reoccupations ruminations they come and
they go they are not like Kryptonite
locking up the mind but they come and they go they're like a river they flow there's
so much space
and the breath receiving the breath each breath
each in breath each out breath provides
connection to the spaciousness to the steadiness of the heart and mind
letting there be more awareness
of the body
the way this body is sitting
whatever posture this body is in bringing awareness to the posture
the sense of preoception we have as humans
having a sense of the internal orientation of the body in the sota's
identified as the body postures
know that you're sitting and breathing
also knowing being aware that the experience of this body
internally is composed of
many different Sensations
sensations of hardness softness flow
temperature coolness and Heat
pressure
release
letting ourselves become curious in a relaxed way let the body be relaxed the
heart be relaxed
curious about the experience of this body internally
so much as a concept body and
leg but the constituents of the experience the flow of experience
the Marvel the Marvel of the flow of experience
touch vibration [Music]
eat I share all of these Sensations
your heart can relax actually when we simplify we go down to the constituents
of the experience
with a sense of awe curiosity Marvel
as we turn towards the experience of
Being Human this experience of
this body in its constituents
Sensations the flow the vibrations
hardness softness temperature throughout the body
opening up making this the measure of our attention
we begin to perceive to see differently
our usual preoccupations soften
they release see for yourself the transformation
when you open up your awareness relax
into the awareness of the Body Sensations knowing the body
this form
not through interpretation of Concepts but through the elemental
experience of Sensations
no conception there's so many Sensations sensors through this body
see for yourself
art the mind can relax the body can relax
but a different way of being and seeing
as if we're gently tethering
the mind to the body to the sensations to knowing the body
eyeing the mind the busy mind to opposed
so it can settle and see differently
and as we bring this meditation period to a close
letting there be appreciation for yourself for your dear self
for having brought yourself to this meditation at this moment in time
planting seeds planting seeds
and not judging how this period was whether it was distracted sleepy
or deeply concentrated or whatever not judging not attaching to outcome in
this moment but trusting that you're planting seeds
shifting turning the flow of patterns of the heart and mind
little by little through your intention
with gratitude for yourself and all the causes and
conditions that have enabled you to be a part of
this practice with the Sangha
and the community with appreciation for them and the teachings
and all the costs and conditions again that have brought us to this point many
of them challenging of course to be human is challenging and many of them
wonderful blessings and sharing the goodness of our practice
with all things everywhere may my practice
a single moment of awareness of kindness wisdom may be of service not
just to myself definitely to myself to my loved ones
it was like no and those I don't know all things everywhere
may my life be of benefit in ways I cannot understand
may it be of service to all beings everywhere
[Music]
say everyone thanks for your practice
hello again and uh good day
so so for this week I'd like to invite us to explore the teachings on
the five Aggregates so I was thinking about what might be a good topic to uh
to discuss this week and and so many beautiful topics I've been
covered in these um 7 A.M Pacific Time teachings and and I looked back and I
saw that the five Aggregates hasn't been um discussed as a series for a long time
for years so so and it's such a rich uh teaching and I wanted to to do my best
to bring heart to the five aggregate teaching because even the word the name
five Aggregates like what what is the aggregate thing it just seems kind of complex and and
um very heady but it's not heady it's it's um so let's let's explore so
so the five condas condos can also be translated as heaps as these five things
and these five things they are the constituents of experience they are the
way that um as human beings we experience the world and experience
um uh all the ways that we experience the world are through the the combination of
these five aspects of course experience could be cut up in so many different ways and this is one way to to cut the
pie so so what are the five
um heaps what are the five heaps the the aspect of the the Heap and and the
reason so let me mention that and and I'll unpack a little bit so the five are the first one is is form
or Rupa uh internal external stuff Rupa
form um and and also notice that these go from course to to subtle so Rupa being
the more the coarsest level of of how we experience reality our reality as humans
then there is uh vedana or failing tone the feeling tone Pleasant unpleasant and
neither unpleasant nor unpleasant neutral so the sense of
um impression this this what the the The Impressions the sense Impressions the
feeling tone the valence on the mind and the next is Sanya perception which
is is our how we perceive um objects internally externally
um and I'm just going to name them because each of these will go through them each uh every day
um and then sankara's um which often translate as mental
formations mental activity and the leading uh the lead being volition
intentioned relational activity volitional activities of the mind of
speech of body and the last one being Consciousness or vinyana
is the most subtle of them all so these five so today I like to spend
more time with form or Rupa but in order to to talk a little bit about
um what Heap or kinda con the the scandas are
it's it it in in a way if you think of say
um our experience is is an amalgamation it's it's a heap It's a combination it's
a um um it's a Gestalt It's a combination of
of these five aspects these five aspects form our experience
so the same way in in a way we can think of say water when we talk about water
water is water and yet there is the aspect of say turbidity whether the
water is turbid or whether it's it's clear the color of it what color water
has whether um what the temperature of the water is these different aspects of water and all
of these different dimensions and aspects of the water then how much salt salty you know whether there's sugar in
it saltiness and then the various aspects constituents so these aspects of
experience that really come together and yet we can lean into one or the other we
can really become tuned into the color of the water what color is it is it
does it have dye in it so we can lean into knowing these different aspects
these constituents of experience and instead of just seeing it as a compact
experience comp so so why many many reasons we want to do this why do we
want to to engage with this practice of seeing the different constituents of experience separating it out
foreign so very briefly
um often we take our experience as this act this aggregate this this you know
perhaps we're lost in our thoughts um we are overwhelmed by thoughts and
and we're ruminating and it's just kind of a it becomes a mess maybe there's body pain and the body pain becomes why
me and and everything just kind of like this actually maybe a better example is
the the sensations of a body pain then give rise to late enough feeling tone
and that gives rise to send a particular formations mental formations and our
Consciousness is perceiving in a particular way so these five Aggregates as you can see are kind of coming
together and then the Mind rumination these mental formations can just kind of go off the rails so so pause pause right
we can actually start to see all your these if I if I get to see the
constituents of my experience for what they are for what they are
um then it it doesn't become so overwhelming and so messy all of a
sudden and also we take it a little less personally it's it's it's not
um we we have a foothold in the middle of this experience of being human it
becomes a little ah more manageable the same way that you know if you wake up in the morning and
and like I'm overwhelmed there's so much I have to do but if you actually create
your to-do list okay I need to do grocery shopping okay I need to buy this and that and that okay that's that I
need to make you know an appointment I need to call this person okay yeah there's a sense of ah it's it's becomes
um becomes not as entangled not as entangled so
um and of course the the five Aggregates um of these constituents of experience
um also as I mentioned we can when we lean into each and every one of them we
can get to see the the flow of experience as it arises and passes it's
impermanence it's in personality and it's unsatisfactory and it's in in a heartful way like oh yes there is more
freedom available there's so much more freedom than what what the the
a mind is clinging to is mere mine is fixed so
so I um so given the time I've spent with setting the
stage of why it's interest why it's important and many other reasons this could be our long Dharma talk about five
Aggregates why it's important but I want to spend a little bit of time with the
first one so that we can spend time with the other ones this week um so so form form or Rupa
so form internally externally the our experience
of the world is um is through um is through our pers perception Sonya
we'll get to that in a couple of days of form of form and
and consider that um the in in the teachings in the teachings
form um uh is um is talked about in terms of the four
elements and the four elements actually the four elements in many ways seem like this to
to the modern mind seem like an archaic teaching oh really like you're saying that the body and externally everything
in the world is made up of of Earth uh Earth element Water Element fire element
and and air element like that this seems so basic and I have to say that was my
perception too when I started to practice and and through years and years of practice and also um exploring
exploring scientific understanding there are many interesting corollaries that I
can see and actually I gave a long hour long talk at IMs about the four elements
practice and modern science so maybe I'll put the link in that later if anyone's interested but ever so briefly
to say that um if if we first of all if we consider that the point of this
teaching really in Buddhism is for us to get an understanding of four elements just bear bear with me for
a moment these aspects elements inside elements outside and that's also the
same thing that modern science tells us in fact Alan Lightman the well-known
um astrophysicist it has famously said that if you take every atom of your body
and if you put a if you could put a tag on it and if you could go back million
billions of years you could really see the it is Stardust it is Stardust you
know we aren't Stardust ever this is Stardust Stardust inside Stardust
outside internal external it's just these elements there's no difference
and that to me blows my mind it Stardust this this Striker it's it's this this
um similar this yeah a kinship a form internal external
another way to relate to four elements is also um
as you know this this um if we think of the way in science or
solids and liquids and and gases and also an energy so E equals to MC squares
there's energy and there's matter so so fire as this energy as as energy element
and and being able to be um uh trying being transformed one way or
either energy or or matter and then so and thinking of matter as the three ways
that it shows up either as solids liquids or or or gases so it's a way to
to for us as modern um modern folks to relate to this concept of four elements inside and
outside gases and and solids and um and uh liquid inside outside and of
course energy energy and movement um inside and outside so and of course
[Music] um relationally as we experience the four elements it comes down to our our
um uh maybe else you know I'm gonna pause here because we're out of time I'll say more about that tomorrow because there
are two ways that the four elements teachings can we can relate to both as
matter inside outside the four elements inside outside as well as our Sensations
the way we um we perceive our perception which relates to death anyway I'll say
more about that I'll just pause here so there's so much here to explore this is fun
so so thank you so much for your practice so or the invitation I wanted
to invite you today as we explored in the meditation to lean into a
constituent of your experience with the body as you move around the world as you
feel your body as you sense the body internally externally matter form inside
form outside Stardust inside start us outside for elements in out relating to
the constituents of your experience leaning into that and see
um see how that might shift and change the way we are okay we experience the world thank you so much everyone be well
and see you tomorrow bye