you know good Day greetings to this
beginning of the week Monday and
and as uh to begin on this topic of the theme
Stephen just saying good day to you and greeting you is a form of communication
and humans have the ability of communicating with each other but we also have the ability to
communicate to ourselves and to some degree whenever we're thinking we are
communicating to ourselves there's some kind of communication going on we're telling us ourselves a memory or
planning of an event or anticipating something or fantasizing
and to think of thinking whether we think in words or in
images as a form of communication and then to consider
um how it's being communicated what's the choice that we are maybe unconsciously making
for that act of communication are we choosing a form of communication
that is enjoyable that is the way we
speak to ourselves in meditation the way that we think the way that we create images and relate to them in our minds
and is there some choice to in how we think and how we engage in
this inner communication so that the communication is done in a
way that feels supportive feels Pleasant it's calming or settling
and to begin today with that using that choice often in meditation the emphasis is On
Letting Go of thoughts and thoughts get in the way and just kind of stay with breathing or some object of meditation
stay with a quiet awareness but to begin this meditation
with a few moments here looking at your thinking
so to assume a meditation posture
and to take a few moments to find that comfortable find a comfortable
posture a calming posture
posture that's not being shaped by whatever way art
desires are driven
posture that might support the settling of desires quieting
and then to close your eyes or lower their gaze
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing on the exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal and for a few moments
as you breathe as you exhale relax in your body
and then maybe continuing gently with your breathing as a grounding as a
reference point to come away come become aware of
how you're thinking the kind of inner Communications
and to the grid which you have some choice about how you think
can you think in a more pleasant way a calmer way
maybe think more gently or peacefully
you're welcome to think whatever you're thinking
but to do so in a calm or
Gentle Way
perhaps thinking slower
perhaps whatever way you're relating to this exercise
maybe relax that
relax any tension or straining or the resistance there might
be
engage upon your thinking calmly kindly
and to be tracking how you're thinking
and letting it become calmer and slower does require some degree of mindfulness
of awareness
and as you're attending to your thinking
in what time are your thoughts concerned with
are you concerned with the past the future
the Timeless time of fantasy
in what place are they concerned with are they concerned whether some place or
something happened in the past place where something will happen in the future
to recognize when you're thinking is not about Here and Now
this place at this time
and now to be against that or have a problem with it but be aware all this thinking is about
another time another place it's not about Here and Now
just to see that clearly
and then gently calmly see if you can switch your thoughts
do thoughts about Here and Now gentle calm thoughts of recognition
thoughts of instructions for yourself in being present in your meditation
it is a form of communication to have your thoughts help you recognize
What's Happening Here and Now
to let your thoughts provide you with very simple
instructions to do this very thing that we're doing
and then Center yourself on your breathing if you'd like
or Center yourself on your embodied feeling of
being in your body
but if you start thinking take a good look
if the thoughts are about this time and place what's happening now for you
or about something else and if it's something else
change the channel to the channel that's about Here and Now
instructing yourself
Here and Now to be involved in your meditation
meditation is a Time for thinking only about the present
and only about the experience that's here and now
and not judging it or making plans around it
simple thoughts of recognition in simple thoughts of
that encourages you to be present lots of instructions
here with this breath this inhale here with this exhale
foreign
and then as we come to the end of this meditation
if thinking is a form of communication what thoughts would you like to
communicate out into the world
and if it is your heart that wants to communicate your care Your Love
what thoughts would you like to have sent out into the world
if your thoughts can touch the hearts of others
with what thoughts would you touch them
perhaps to end now with an aspirational thoughts
who well wishing wishing others well
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may it be that through our thoughts our words and our Deeds
that we find ways
to contribute to this possibility
so it's not just wishes good wishes upon which we act into the
world may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so hello on this Monday as we begin a new
five-part series and the topic for this week is
conventionally or normally would be called uh why speech right speech
and a few things introductory words about this one is that um
that um in the time of the Buddha the ways people communicated with each
other was a only through speech maybe through gesture as well they're bought
but there was no writing to speak of there was no certainly no other forms of
communication no no telephones no email
and so speech was you know the center of the focus for how to communicate wisely
I suspect that if the Buddha was alive today he would call this wise
communication rather than why speech because his teachings apply also to what
you know would apply to all the ways in which we communicate to each other and now we have so many different ways
that are more than just speech email for example is uh is an important example of
how to learn how to communicate wisely and um
and overall this year that of 2023 the orientation around these 7
A.M 7 30 the teachings is support for working
with the difficulties and challenges of life maybe all of Buddhism is that so it
doesn't need to be said but uh that's kind of one of the focus is and so learning how to communicate
and conflict communicate when things are challenging is really a crucial a skill
to learn to be in Conflict B and challenges in a useful way in a
productive way in a way that causes less harm the way to communicate so we don't make
a situation worse ideally we make the situation better and just that is a I think a powerful
principle the simple principle of or instructions don't make it worse whatever is
happening don't make it worse and um
so communication to communicate in a way that doesn't make it worse makes it
better communicate in the ways that the communication is effective that we take care of ourselves we take
care of what needs to be done but we do it in ways that um that lead to long-term benefit
not excessively focused on just the results of now but uh but looking at what are we
creating for in the long term for the relationship of their people if we if we say something harsh and
strong and know and angrily to people we might have an immediate effect maybe the effect that we want but in the long term
we've now kind of diminished the strength of that relationship we have to administer the trust the sense of safety
that people have or the interest people have to be with us and so to find a way to communicate so
that we're creating long-term uh connections long-term well-being and the ones that help develop healthy
relationships as opposed to pulling back from that or severing healthy relationships or creating unhealthy
relationships so um the Buddha had a number of
principles or advice for wise communication wise speech
and um and there's some places where he has five and so we'll do those five over
today this week and um these are um this uh for speech to be timely to be
spoken at the right time speech which is truthful
speech which is uh Pleasant or soothing or um for people calming
uh uh Speech which is um
beneficial and speech which is kind
with a mind of loving kindness so timely speech so one of the questions
and all these are questions we can use to ask ourselves when we're about to
speak is it Timely is it true is it uh being spoken in a way that's
Pleasant for people and settling for people is it beneficial to say what I'm going
to say and is it uh kind what I'm going to say so these are five different
things we can ask ourselves wondering should I speak right now and and um or how can I speak so it's this
way so the first one is a timely this is the right time
this is hugely important because especially when there's conflict and challenges that
um different people have different needs and and conflict some people need
to have time to process and be quiet and be by themselves for a while before
they're ready to be in conversation about a conflict some people need to kind of address it right away and and to
let it stay in their mind and fester is difficult for them and in order to find out what's going on they need to be in
conversation so these if the if there's this range of how people are can mean
that we have to be very careful to understand is what's the right time for this conversation is the person ready
for it is the circumstances of life such that now is the time
that the person is ready to talk about this sometimes when we talk about something
when we want to talk about it it actually makes the situation worse and people are not ready maybe they're going
through some other difficulty and they can't add one more to their difficulty or maybe they're um in a kind of a lousy
mood and to try to approach them with some important difficult topic when their mood is just lousy when they're
tired or upset or something else that it's not going to go very well
so is it so you have to we have to assess the situation that people we want to talk to and assess ourselves it's the
right time for me to do this conversation am I ready am I in a good
mood am I in a way that I'm most likely the best of whom who I am can come
forward for this communication and um and so for example maybe if
you're hungry if it's going to be a difficult conversation make sure you you drink and eat first and maybe that will
just put you in a whole different state of mind that you're actually able to be more patient or more accepting or even
more intelligent in the conversation you have so this question is it the right time is
I think a very helpful question and um to uh
um is it the right time for you is it the right time for the other person is the right time for the situation to have
this conversation and um and I find that in certain kind of things that uh I would like to talk
to with to people about some difficulty we have that sometimes I'll wait until I feel
the person's open to the conversation and sometimes I've waited weeks or months for this to happen uh and and uh
and and productively so sometimes the person opens the door
themselves for the topic and then it's much easier to step in people are less defensive
but to bring it up bring something up that's difficult immediately as soon as there's a challenge
sometimes it's really good it's clear and clean and sometimes it's not helpful
because a person will be resistant defensive they'll shut down
then they were not ready to hear something and so and so to kind of consider
it's a little bit hard to consider when some people what they want to say there's a lot of impulse a lot of
impatience a lot of like this has to happen now feeling and sometimes it does
and so yeah then you should you need to do it perhaps but to have a feeling this needs to be taken care of now
and maybe it should ideally be taken care of now but when you realize the person's not ready the person can't deal
with us now I can I can insist on my way but it's not going to go well
and I've done that I've had conversations with people right away and it just got worse because the person
wasn't ready and sometimes even waiting a day or waiting an hour waiting five minutes is
enough to kind of be ready so to
to ask the question of what you want us about what you want to speak about is
this the right time to speak and is there a better time is it what's the most useful time to
have this conversation and um and there's a lot of criteria that
you want to kind of look into about what's the right time is the person ready is the person in a good mood for
it is a person going to be receptive are you going to are you going to be able to speak
clearly have you understood this situation well enough and considered what's going on so that you can come for
the clearest understanding that Claire's articulation of what you want to say and what you need to say
and um do you need to calm down a little bit do you need to kind of change your mood and
come back in a way that's better and one suggestion I have is that um generally there's a kind of useful
guideline is that if you're angry this
is not to have not the time to have an in-depth conversation about something with other people
and if you can learn to find a way to settle the anger to even just going for
a walk around the block and coming back or meditating for 10 minutes or waiting to the next day then and then address
the issue this is not supposed to be avoiding avoiding issues when you ask
guys it's the right time and you said decide I'll wait that is to be able to
have the conversations be productive and useful and and supportive for everyone
so um so asking the question in your communication is it Timely
the email you're writing is this the right time to write this email
the I've written the emails in a hurry when I felt impatient and then I had to
I didn't communicate well and then I had to spend a lot of time cleaning up explaining doing something
and um and so sometimes I've written emails and not sent them sometimes I've
just bookmarked the email and say I'm going to reply to this sometime when I don't feel impatient or don't feel
rushed this needs a different kind of care and um so is it the right time to write
an email and um and does this require more consideration
than a quick reply what's the wise way to find what where what's the wise reply the supportive we
reply so uh communication we communicate all the time if nothing
else to ourselves and um and even there how do we communicate to ourselves are we
thinking about things which are timely in a timely way the right time for it
is there something that's more timely to be concerned with and be focused on just that questions I think a wonderful
question that opens doors opens possibilities can kind of change the the mindstream in
which we're flowing when that mindstream maybe is not very useful for us and helpful for the world
so why is communication why speech
and Begins by asking the question is what I'm going to say the right is this
the right time for what I'm going to say so thank you very much and um