good evening welcome welcome it feels like the volume's just a tiny
bit low can we make it just a little bit louder so I don't have to project my
voice and I have to keep on talking maybe just a tiny bit louder there we go thank you
thank you Jim no just a little bit this it feels funny for me to be saying no higher lower higher good just right
okay so welcome welcome nice to see you all
so there's different ways in which the Buddha's teachings are conveyed or you
know kind of like described of the ways that they've been preserved sometimes they describe a path of practice
and it can seem like it's pretty straightforward just do one two three
four then Bang You're awakened but you know I don't think that's anybody's practice unfolds that way in this
particular sequence and in a way that's like so clear
or maybe there's a way in which the practice is described as a the goal of
practice that is nabana you know what Jim before you leave can we make it just a little bit louder because
I waited I'm sorry wait till you leave but I've noticed that my voice will probably go out by the end
maybe there's just can be a tiny bit louder just so that I don't have to there we go thank you
so it can be the describing the path of practice describing the goal of practice
or maybe they describe what is an ideal awakened person like what do they look
like with somebody who is awakened so these are these three different ways in
which uh the teachings are conveyed and when there's these qualities or
characteristics of an awakened person there's this way we can feel like
wow I'm not like that I I don't think that I will ever be like that I'd like
just there's this sometimes the Buddha is described with lots of colorful languages or the our Huts you know
talking about purity and Perfection it might feel like there's a way in which it's easy to be
dismissive like okay well that was thousands of years ago and I can't even relate to what they're talking about
not only that there's this way if they describe the Buddha as the sometimes they call them the Seer or the sage or
the Kinsmen of the Sun or destroyer of the dart of craving this can just feel conceptual and not
really helpful at all that we can't quite relate to it and instead it might just be feeding our
inner critic like oh that's how they are but I'm not like that
for all these reasons it can be really helpful to this for me to look at some
of these characters that are showing up in the suit does as having a hard time
not following this perfect path and they still become awakened
so I'd like to start with uh this a poem by uttama
this was a woman who was having a hard time and here's some teachings
practices and then becomes a weekend so what are the teachings that she heard
like what helped turn it around I think this can be useful and helpful to look at you know this seems like maybe a
little bit more of a real life for example something that's maybe a
little bit more relatable less just this conceptual and something that's maybe inspiring and supportive
so in my mind um uttama is living in a cootie these are
like small just really simple dwellings I know they have them now in Thailand that meditators monastics they live in
these very simple maybe and that's where they would meditate or maybe even live and then
like the meditation hall or the regular Monastery from the dining hall and all that kind of stuff would have been another place
so in my mind she's living in one of these little huts and trying to meditate
and this is her Awakening poem so she becomes awakened and it was the
tradition for some of these poems to be preserved and this is what uh how she
describes her own process so it goes like this
you know what before no also I could say this afterwards so here's utama's poem
four times five times I left my dwelling
I had failed to find peace of mind or any control over my heart
I approached a nun in whom I had faith she taught me the Derma the aggregates
the sense fields and the elements
when I had heard her teachings in accordance with her instructions I sat cross-legged for seven days
given over to joy and happiness on the eighth day I stretched out my
legs having shattered the mass of Darkness
so she received these teachings that enabled her to shatter the mass of
Darkness the mess of Darkness sometimes stands for ignorance but maybe it also even
sounds can be like the darkness this feeling of hopelessness like I can't do
this nobody else can do and do it you know she leaves this her
dwelling like she keeps on leaving and then she finally just goes and asks for help
so what were these teachings that she received
this poem says the nun taught me the Derma the Aggregates the sense fields
and the elements and I'm going to talk just a little bit about these
so these are three different ways in which we might consider The Human
Experience in the same way that today we could have said that the weather was
warm or we could have said 78 degrees Fahrenheit or 26 degrees Celsius now
these are all pointing to the same thing but they're using different scales different vocabulary but they are
pointing to the same thing so not something completely separate or maybe in the same way that there's
these different perspectives of modern psychology and maybe there's the
psychodynamic perspective or there's this behavioral perspective or the
cognitive perspective or the biological perspective right there's all these different ways in which we think of
modern psychology and they're taking kind of like the experience of a human and emphasizing different aspects or
looking at them through different lenses but they're all kind of looking at the human psychology
so in the same way five Aggregates six cent spaces four elements or three
different ways in which we might look at The Human Experience so just briefly I would say the five
Aggregates I'm not going to go through the whole list but first one is Rupa which refers to form
which can be pointing to like the body like the physical body and the other form other four or
different aspects of the mental experience the five Aggregates has something about
the body but something about the mind The Sixth Sense bases there's the these
are what are the senses we have four of them or the often ones
that we think about seeing hearing tasting smelling one of them is the body kind of like the
tactile experience and the sixth one is the mind so again
another way in which to look at The Human Experience the mind and the body
and then the fourth one are the four elements and then we'll talk a little bit more about this one
but I'm going to introduce them as Elemental qualities
which might be like a better translation or a better way to understand it
so these different ways in which the experience of the body
so we might say look at the solidity feeling the experience of solidity
say that's the Earth element we might look at the feeling or the experience of fluidity
we might say that's the water element look at the experience of temperature
hot or cold it's the fire element we might look at the experience of
motion or movement as the air element
and so these four elements solidity fluidy temperature motion
or we might say earth water fire air they are all independent on each other
right they are like adjectives they're like describing their perspective in which to look at The Human Experience
so in that way that they are all interdependent they don't stand alone there isn't like solidity just we don't
have solidity right it's the solidity of something in the same way that we have fluidity
it's the fluidity of something but in the body there's
of course all of these and we can look at it with these different emphases emphasizing the motion or the solidity
or the movement or something like this and so there's a way even when we hear
this word for elements that this might think this is like
too simplistic anachronistic and like oh isn't that cute back in Ancient India
they had four elements I think we have like 118 in the modern
periodic table I think I have that right if we're going to think about the body
we might you know for me trained as a biochemist I'm like well I know there's four more more than four in the body so
there might be a way in which we kind of like want to be dismissive and think okay that's odd I don't want to practice
with it it turns out working with these is
really powerful and I like to kind of like explore and
talk about these a little bit today so some of you may know the Sati
patanasuta that look maybe the primary sutone which points to mindfulness
and it has mindfulness of the body as the First Foundation is the first
support for mindfulness and within mindfulness of the body we find mindfulness of breathing which we often
talk about in often is like the first instructions that we would give a meditator is
mindfulness of breathing but under that same heading of mindfulness in the body is also
mindfulness of the elements and it uh when the Sati patanas who
decodes like this so One reviews this body
however it is placed however it is disposed so in whatever
posture it's in or whatever is happening with the body One reviews this body
however it is placed however disposed by way the elements thus
in this body there are the Earth elements the water element
the fire element and the air element okay pretty straightforward just look at
these four different elements but somehow I'll just speak for myself I just couldn't relate to this I thought
this just sounds odd but there's a way in which it can be really powerful and
helpful and one way is because if we look at these ideas of the solidity
fluidity temperature and motion then this points to shifting our ideas
about the body to the experience of the
body and so often the ideas we have about
bodies in general or our own body or other people's bodies whatever it might
be it's a lot of suffering a lot of suffering associated with the ideas that
we have some of the obvious ones some of the
ideas are that well the body should have a certain appearance they should look a certain way
and we have this entire advertising agency or phenomenon in the modern world
right billions of dollars being sent to make sure that we all agree on how bodies should appear
so much suffering so much suffering associated with this
but there's also this way that um we might also think that our idea about
the body is it's somehow like stable or constant it's always with us whatever
we're doing so there's this way we can't think yeah this is my body and it's like
this I have that look at this thing in my knee because of
that accident that happens when I sit a particular way it hurts it's painful this is you know my body or
we might think like okay this is mine and it's separate from everything else
so there's a way in which we might there's a kind of kind of subtle but it can have an impact this idea of
being really isolated and distinct and separate like nope there's this that's here and then there's everything else
and this body is trying to manipulate and control things out there and things
out there or having impacts on this body and there's can be some tension with that there can even be some suffering
without some duka oh with that or there might be this idea that okay
because this is my body I should be able to control it I can choose to move my arm
but it turns out right we don't get to control it but they're so right this is a whole nother industry out there like
this health industry eat this don't eat the exercise this way don't exercise that way do this first thing in the
morning do sleep this way right wow there's a lot thinking that we can control it
and in some ways you know there are some things we can control but really our body is not controllable
it's get sick it hurts
it ages we can't control this
and so the ways that we can control other aspects we think that you know maybe we can we should naturally be able
to control these other aspects but yeah so much Duke associated with our
ideas about the body
and so this today's we start looking at the solidity fluidity temperature or
motion we can move toward the actual phenomenological experience
what does it feel like to be having this bodily experience as opposed
to what our our ideas about it
so for example instead of thinking the abdomen is rising and falling
with the breath or my knees hurt or my bladder is full
instead we could say things like expansion and contraction kind of like
feeling the expansion and the contraction stretching and the release of the
stretch or say things like tingling
pressure you know these types of words throbbing
really different feeling right feeling but it's a different uh emphasis to talk about
these because maybe they're more like adjectives or expressions of what's happening in
the bodily experience and when something important really happens when we start to use these types
of words expansion contractions throbbing tingling stabbing warm cold
we notice it's changing the body is changing
intellectually we all understand this we know there's aging we know that we're
not the same that we were a decade ago see it like just
free day at the is the most mundane life experiences anytime we tune into
these different aspects we start to see oh yeah yeah there was some tingling
there before it's not really tingling now it's a little bit more stabbing or maybe the area where it was tingling is
now shifting around and then so this impermanent inconstant
nature of the body starts to become more and more apparent
is that a way you start to notice oh yeah I can't control this as much as I
thought I could and when the changing nature starts to
become more apparent we start realizing yeah I can't hold on to my the sense of
how my body is it just doesn't really make sense it's always changing
and in this way there's a certain amount of letting go there's a certain certain amount of no
longer grasping or clinging or demanding that the body be a particular way
so our relationship to our body's shifts
maybe we've been disappointed and angry or something but now it can shift
when we start to pay attention more to this the sensations
and of course many of you know that impermanence is one of the three characteristics one of the qualities of
everything essentially and the real deep understanding of this
can lead to a really deep letting go that leads to greater and greater
Freedom peacefulness and ease
but not only does paying attention to the elements in this way solidity
fluidity mature emotion but it also emphasizes
that we are not our bodies and you might say well of course I know
I'm not my body but there's a way
well maybe I'll say first this simile that the Buddha offered of it's kind of
a gruesome simulated it's often a little bit surprising to find this uh in the suit does but
it said this was you know how life was in Ancient India so the similes of to
imagine that there is a butcher who Slaughters a cow
and then Cuts up the cow into the different pieces of meat and you know maybe there's bones and meat and liver
and whatever else they would sell and take him to the market and sell them
so they're saying well before the slaughtering
the butcher considered this a cow they took care of the cow they fed the cow they gave cow the water they took
care of it and then as soon as you look at it in terms of its parts
meat or bones or liver it's like really different they no longer think of it as a cow
so there's this way and when we kind of are like teasing apart the different elements the different aspects there's a
way it just kind of like shifts our relationship to it it's no no longer a
body but it's solidity and one way that we might think about
this also in modern times is like to imagine like
whose body would you like to have you can imagine anybody it's like anybody's body alive
or dead like who's if you could you know have somebody's body
who's would you have I'll give you a few seconds to think about this
so it turns out this is a trick question because
even the whole idea that you
could be in a different body suggests that you kind of think that you
are you know independent or some like like you could exist independent of your
body you know that it's that there you could you could still be
who you are but in a different so there is a way in which we often are
identified with our body or we think that somehow we're separate and unique
and somehow the body is different I don't
know it's just that we're not seeing the like the interconnectedness of it all so there's these many subtle ways
which we identify with the body and there's
so there's another advantage of looking at the practice of looking at the elements
is that the when we look at the self in terms of the
elements it helps um maybe break down this idea that we are
separate and distinct because of course not only do human bodies have solidity or emotion but you
know so does everything else in some regard then we could even say if we if we
instead of using solidity and fluidity if we change the words and say Earth
element and we could say that it stands as a kind of a symbol
for any type of hardness or softness in the body just as the Earth itself can be
hard or soft so there's a way in which we can
experience the body is hardness and softness for the solidity
or the roughness or the smoothness heavy or light
so for example right now or maybe you could feel just like the
heaviness or the pressure of the body against whatever it is you're sitting on
or you could clamp your teeth together and to feel like the hardness
and the tongue has some softness in comparison to that or maybe you could clench one hand and make your fist and
if you have fingernails you could feel the hardness touching the softness
so as we get more familiar with this quality we start to recognize that just as their equality solidity hardness Etc
there are elsewhere and not only that
that you know the words just as their solidity Etc out there just as there's Earth element out there
there's Earth element here and when we die
all the Earth element the plants and animals if you eat animals all of those
all the earthness you know went into this body and then when we die of course it's
going to get returned to the elements right there's I appreciate I think it was West nisker
who said we're all made out of star stuff it's all going to go back
it's not so separate and I was just teaching a retreat and I
appreciated uh my co-teacher she was giving a teaching
and she uh went to the kitchen and I've got the ingredient list for the dinner
or the lunch or some with a meal that we had all just had and she read the
ingredients and said you know this this this isn't I'll use her example here is
not how she did it but you know this is all the Earth element too the the lentils the cheese the
onions you know the grapes the olive oil all these uh ingredients
so it was was Earth elements and it was out she got cultivated and grown
and in some way we could just say you know now it's here just in a different container
as it gets uh metabolized and changed right so the Earth element is still getting converted but it's still the
Earth element going through transformation and maybe turns from solidity to
fluidity and as things get metabolized but just this recognition that what's outside is also what we're made out of
so the water element has fluidity liquidity as well as the
opposite kind of like cohesion or stickiness and you might notice the fluidity in
your own experience around the eyes like we have tears and we can move our eyes because there's
this fluidity that allows that or of course the saliva
in our mouth and the water inside the body is exactly
the same as the water outside the body of course it is water is water is water
H2O and so the water of the rain is the same
as the water that's inside of us and when we die the water within our bodies well go down to the Earth or evaporate
and go up into the clouds condense and rain and be part of the rivers
and then of course the fire element which symbolizes temperature heat and
coolness and in the bodies we think about it as metabolism and digestion
and some might even say it's a type of Life Energy
so we could feel in our body and we were some places of warmth
maybe where parts of the body touch other parts this is of coolness maybe where that's
feeling that air conditioning come out we can feel the coolness on the air
so there's this way in which everything has temperature of course it does
I'm sorry yes
temperature I looked at my notes and I got a little bit confused where am I
Air element is next sometimes this is referred to as wind an
air element of course it's like the breath in and outer
even the gas in our GI tract also symbolizes movement
and you know and the way that we're breathing in oxygen and breathing out carbon dioxide
so again we're exchanging the elements these
qualities with the environment
and when this body dies of course the air is going to go back to the atmosphere
so uttama's Awakening poem here's somebody who had some difficulties
and it was with some of these teachings of kind of like deconstructing experience is what helped
her find her way and so often that when we give in
teachings here I know it often on Retreat and certainly here with the introduction to meditation
program there's a real emphasis on mindfulness of the body but but that's not always
accessible for people I would say
the clear majority of people if I'm having a practice discussion with them
will say I'm one of those analytical people and I'm not quite so connected with my body
this is like such a common way that people talk about their experience
and so I was thinking that maybe think about the elements the fluidity solidity
motion might be a way to be tuned in to the bodily experience
in a way that's a little bit different because sometimes we are thinking about
the body and so to have some way like use this as maybe a entryway in
and then with the body we can see the that's not self that can lead to Awakening we could see that it's
impermanent that can lead to Awakening and we could see that there's suffering
Duca associated with it because it is always changing and we can't control it
so I'll read utama's Awakening poem again
four times five times that left my dwelling
had failed to find peace of mind or any control over my heart
I approached a nun in whom I had faith she taught me the Dharma
Aggregates the sense fields and the elements
when I had heard her teachings in accordance with her instructions I sat cross-legged for seven days given over
to joy and happiness on the eighth day I stretched out my
legs having shattered the mass of Darkness
I think I'll end there and I'll open it up to see if there are any questions or comments
oh hi there thank you for your dog I have two questions can I have two
questions yes first question is that I don't find it relatable to a person who
were sitting for seven days I can see for now
right yeah but she was she stretched the
legs on the eighth day hi I'm for myself I'm interpreting this
as that she didn't didn't sit Non-Stop
oh okay um and the second question may be more
serious is that so I heard this explanation about this here element
um like this tradition they say that pay attention to the rising and the falling
of belly instead of like between the nose and the reason for it is because of this
Air element do you like know or understand what this is about I like heard something but like I don't
quite understand maybe I don't know if you know maybe you can explain a little better
so this is my understanding and it has to do with more kind of like the uh I'll
use this word political I don't know if that's right so when mahasi said I said okay to watch
at the um at the abdomen I don't remember all the details of this but whoever like the
more senior leaders of the the I guess this is in Burma the um of
the meditation said no no uh mindfulness of the body has to be somewhere has to
be done a particular way maybe here at that per lip or it made somewhere and then mahasi said no no no this is the
elements we're doing elements practice we're not doing bodies practice and that's why it can be different
so it was a workaround so that's this is what I've heard but whether that's true
I don't know thank you and maybe that's not very satisfying but
yes maybe you can pass it back there
I'm wondering if you could reread her comment about control of the
heart because I had sort of a odd reaction to that
um what what what what she was struggling with there
yeah so the expressionist I had failed to find peace of mind or any control
over my heart and you might know that that word for heart is chitta and could
also be translated as mind so have any control over my mind or or
control over my heart so it could be either or it could be both you could say heart mind or so
if that is if that's helpful well it's just I guess I understand you
know the struggle for control of the Mind more than I do the other you know the control of the
heart so I was just kind of puzzled by that yeah in my mind I was thinking that
maybe there was like feelings you like the heart is maybe associated with some
emotions or something but we can interpret it whatever ways we find okay well it's good to know that
the the the heart and mind in this instance is kind of interchangeable yeah
okay okay
anybody else have a comment or question or something they'd like to share
okay okay well thank you for your kind attention
and I wish you a good rest of your evening thank you