good morning good morning Sango nice to see all of you in Virtual form in the
chat happy to be here with you today
I'm seeing all the greetings from the morning good morning
yes um preventing the reverberation so um it really warms the heart warms my
heart to see all of your warmth all of your friendliness to each other
and I hope wherever you are whatever whether you're having
that this is a good morning for you I'm grateful to be here
and um it is time so
taking in how it feels to be here this morning to be settling into your own practice in the field of
these good people
looking at names of old friends friendly greetings from those who we
only know from imagination and from these
textual greetings and savoring in your heart
and when you're ready Shifting the attention inwards
noticing noticing how it feels in your heart how
it feels in your body
[Music]
perhaps taking a couple of slight wave slower deeper breaths
feeling a sense of being connected
immersed in this moment this place
noticing the weight of your body and the chair or cushion mat
sense of rootedness belongingness here
and allowing the breathing to return to normal
softening relaxing on the out breath
appreciating nourishment of the in-breath
and connecting to the felt lived experience of this
moment this breath this body
will be giving instructions for mindfulness of breathing
if you connect more with another object of attention
please adapt and do what is right for you sound
the entire body whatever it is
sustaining the attention
when any ease motion contentment of the in-breath and the out
breath
allowing the heart and mind to soften into the Still Point at the
end of the out breath and rest there just for a moment
for feeling into enjoying
the flow of the in-breath
all the way to the top of fullness
and pausing there for just a moment before releasing
inviting relaxation letting go
on the out breath
turning into the felt sense of the whole body
and allowing any other thoughts concerns to feed into the background
to voting the attention just for now
being fully completely cure
loaning in and if it feels right on where in the body the breath feels
most soothing relaxing pleasurable
it might be a sense of the transpiration of breath in your whole body
the Rhythm breathing and aliveness
might be the full body of the breath and it's more obvious form and the tip
of the nose back through the throat to the chest
like singing of the ribs diaphragm and belly
for all of the little sensations of warmth
alive yes
settling in no matter the way
the rising and falling waves of sensation
perhaps each out breath feels like an offering
each in-breath for receiving
in writing the breath to massage your body
from the inside out
maybe noticing it in the chest the back of the rib cage
massaging the back
or the movement of the belly and diaphragm and perineum in up and down
out and in
foreign
appreciating any Sensations there
needing awareness through the whole body
cripples or lands
foreign
well I know behind the heart the body the attention
to collect and gather In This Moment
perhaps noticing a Wellspring
the energy your ease contentment imagining it like
nourishing the spring emerging from deep within
filling the whole body with awareness
is
just to be alive as well foreign
reading the whole body
to be immersed corrected
unified In This Moment
foreign
open the field of attention
through all of the processes all the things coming and going
rising and passing in the present moment
Sensations sounds
General sense of mood the sense of knowing
anything floating through the mind and heart
all seen
flowing through unimpeded like birds flying through the sky
who does this meditation draws to a clone
please gather up collect saber any good feelings
moments of awareness or mindfulness
glimmers of Joy or peace or contentment is required
gather those up in your mind and heart and Savor them
really take them in
and also being with the kindness and compassion any moments of difficulty
challenge this too is a beautiful thing to do
and then you feel ready casting your internal gaze outwards
towards the others in this world in your life directly and indirectly
in considering ways that nourishing yourself this practice
might be refracted outwards to shine on their lives to benefit them
if only through your kind gaze
may all beings be happy [Music] may all beings be saved
may all beings be peaceful and to me everyone everywhere
be free of suffering
[Music]
thank you
thank you for your practice
[Music]
so good morning Sangha good morning and welcome to the fifth
and Final of five talks on factors of mine that support stability of meditation practice
deepening of practice and that can support us in daily life
so a brief recap we started this week with the fundamentals of
mindfulness and practice intelligence kind of a queer comprehension and
curiosity about the present moment we've uncovered connecting and
sustaining the taka and Bichara and the emergent mental faculties
embodied faculties of Joy PT and happiness their contentment sukkah
and then how it all collects together unifies
into a kakata unification today I'm going to talk about how wisdom
supports fruitfully working with these mental faculties and how these factors
also support wisdom they can help us attune more to our own
wisdom inwardly for the purpose of freedom from suffering for the purpose of
happier and more content lives and for awakening
I'm also going to take a few minutes in the middle to answer some of the wonderful questions that came in through
the chat so
as I mentioned yesterday remember I translated as unification or
collected calm is also translated as the capacity to
make distinctions the capacity to make distinctions discernment wisdom is cultivated right
in the process of what you've been learning which is how to recognize distinctions between these different
mental factors and others and how they contribute to the meditative process
wisdom is also cultivated in the process of learning to savor and be nourished by
the goodness of these qualities the Piti the sukkah the mindfulness
itself and wisdom is developed by learning to
let go of eventually any energetic or exciting pleasurable aspects of
experience and letting go into the more refined experiences of peace
Equanimity even little tiny glimmers of it there's wisdom in learning what feeds
our practice what is onward leading for us at different phases in our own practice
lives and at different pages in our own development as humans
so equanimity Equanimity which is
um part of that fourth most soft still Fades is very closely related
to wisdom and to a kagata unification
wisdom and Equanimity in particular both have kind of a settled back quality to them
there is a wise separation from reactivity to events in the moment
mindfulness and practice intelligence the five faculties cultivate a greater
stability capacity that can be directed towards this big picture towards
wisdom of knowing and seeing what's hard to see wisdom about conditionality
cause and effect and a lack of self-centeredness or even
sense of a separate solid reified concretized self
that wisdom can begin to develop through seeing the impermanence and inconstancy
in life and moment to moment experience and that can yield a sense of gratitude
for what is the precious and kind of um
ephemerality of experience
so that wisdom that also develops can understand the contributing factors of
Duca or suffering in the heart and mind
as I mentioned earlier in this series mindfulness is kind of a gatekeeper
maybe see a comment in the chat about this too that discerned what's helpful to let in and what's not helpful to let
it and guides that's helpful to nourish our practice the most
this is where mindfulness and wisdom begin to shade together
mindfulness and wisdom and this naturally develops
so for all of this the attention does not need to be completely totally unified in Jonna one pointed
and that said there are powerful forms of wisdom that can be cultivated by Deep
Retreat and experiencing these states particularly industrating between them and in letting
go of them and reflecting back on them
so that brings me to answering a few of the great questions people put in the chat yesterday
so the first question is a kagata unification Serenity the
same thing as samadhi and I'll just say this briefly at kagata
unification refers to being focused on one meditative object or on one point
especially in somebody overall meditative concentration or stability so
in that sense the terms are synonymous but ikogita is one small part of a
broader experience of samadhi settlements
the territory of samadhi is varied and vast and ikogita is one part of that
much larger landscape so I'll just say now for details on more
detailed answers each of these questions for time's sake I did not I'm not speaking all of it but you can
go to my website and I did post
detailed answers to these questions and that is in the chat right now
please don't read it right now wait till I'm done talking but um there are more detailed writings on
this if you're interested in it second question is the unification and serenity
of ekakata the same thing as equanimity so they can be is the answer in the
refined mind state of fourth Janna in particular that place of complete
Stillness unification and Equanimity have merged
and that kind of unification is indeed one way that Equanimity shows up and
there are many others there are other forms of equanimity that
are not so still or gathered around a single meditation point that are part of a broad flexible awareness
and then there's Equanimity in these forums
that's receptive to this wide variety of experiences many many things coming and going
so both kinds of equanimity are very powerful and beautiful and each can be
healing and transformative however Equanimity is experienced it
tends to be onward leading towards Freedom onward leading
the third and last question kind of overlaps with the one I just answered
someone wrote when I try to do single pointed meditation my mind guides me
away it feels like it's not skillful yet I remain interested because so many people report that it's very healing
so if this is you and I'm confident there's more than one of you I really want to encourage you to work
with what feels skillful in your own practice in your own mind trust your practice
some Minds benefit more from single pointed concentration unification than
others do in the way that we've been talking about it this week that said if you're still curious an
option is to experiment with other objects of attention like meta or full
body breathing there's many many different objects and
it's helpful to know that some people's minds are just more naturally inclined
towards samadhi in general and unification in particular
one of my teachers talks about these differences in our minds as being like left-handed or right-handed it's not
good or bad it's just different and if your mind isn't inclined that way
right now there's still plenty of wisdom healing open awareness that can
develop I hate so
different kinds of practices work for different people at different phases
and to maybe back off from a style that doesn't seem to be working and experiment with something else for a
while let the practice mature and experiment again in a few years if
it's still of interest but there are many different Dharma doorways into
maturity greater freedom
so those are some of the answers I do want to acknowledge that
um how do I want to say this I want to acknowledge that there were a few questions that came in that I didn't have time to answer one in particular on
Yogi mind and that doesn't fit so well into this very short talk but I will post about it
sometime in the next week or two on the website the longer kind of discourse to talk about
so as I mentioned for some people meta Rama biharas are another way into this
kind of unification that was how I started concentration practice in my own practice
and there are resources available if you're interested in that
so to wrap up as I mentioned yesterday we don't need
uncommon states to learn and start to develop wisdom and maturity
Discerning relating to factors of Mind as factors of mind starts to train our
capacity and our ability to experience beautiful
qualities in ourselves and our meditation practice and in others
and the five factors have corollaries in daily life we can bring mindfulness and
intelligence to that bigger picture in relating to our lives and to others
we can connect and give full attention to other people or to whatever's in front of us
sustain those important connections develop relationships
based on respect close attention consideration
notice and resonate with joy PT
and allow any initial Joy of connection deepening
to soften into contentment practicing contentment with what is
that would be a corollary to sukkah and finally allowing different ideas and
deliberations all to occur in the field of understanding and acceptance
of ourselves and with others and when appropriate Gathering Together towards any Harmony
common purpose integration that happens to be present
these are not the soul guidelines for interpersonal relationships just a few Notions of how these particular factors
might apply so and finally I'll just say these
capacities these factors are also helpful to tap into within yourself in
daily life there's kind of this feeling of being at
home in our own bodies and Minds that can be tapped into an inner access to a
certain kind of Stillness or contentment that can then be like carrying around
our home with us inside us wherever we go a little bit like a snail carries its
shell or a turtle carries it show home is always there and this this can reduce grasping
and discontent so these are some of the gifts of
finding stability and connection to new practice however you practice however you find it
thank you Sangha for your kind attention it's been a joy to be with you this week
be well