warm greetings from this dark
Dawning morning in Redwood City and I'm happy to be here with all
of you and to share this time together and I do think of more than I
think I've kind of based my adult life on the idea that Buddhist practice is a
peacemaking PR practice it uh uproots
the the impulses to violence and harm making in
ourselves and is and it's a practice which is devoted
towards bringing peace to this world in its own way in it's in a
Buddhist way and the way that Buddhist specializes in it and um so so to sit now and
meditate is in fact an act of peacemaking and it begins Buddhism
emphasizes that peacemaking begins with oneself that in a sense the source of
peace that we can have some role in begins with
ourselves that if we can't be peaceful how can we expect others to do
so and if we sit in meditation as the closer we get to ourselves the more we
have a chance to discover how to keep the peace how to
stay in a mode of being where
we uh do not pick up to not get involved in any kind of harm making activity in
our own mind and the deeper the sensitivity the
deeper our ability to be mindful the more the subtlety we pick up the
subtleties of ways in which the Mind operates that does in fact cause maybe
subtle harm but subtle harm compounded over years and years
applied in so many different ways in our lives uh can actually be a source of
tremendous pain and harm and so to think of meditation as an
exercise in finding peace in being peaceful being
nonharming and that mindfulness is the representative state of attention
way of attending being aware for doing so in a peaceful
way so as we do this meditation today perhaps you
can keep a dedication
to having a peaceful way of
recognizing what is happening to you in the present moment take refuge in the awareness in
the simplest knowing that knows in a way that
contributes to the peace Within it doesn't contribute to further
conflict to further
animosity shame
discouragement greed conceit it doesn't
encourage it doesn't feed into the mental States and the
me mental States and the mental kind of activities which have within them which
have come along with subtle ways in which uh undermine us deflate
us harm us bring
unnecessary despair or discomfort or
pain
so to assume a meditation
posture whatever posture you're going to sit but let it be a
posture the posture that allows you to be
peaceful and to orient Orient yourself around being
peaceful and either lower your [Music] gaze or close your
eyes in such a way that you can begin monitoring
yourself tracking what is going on within you in your mind your
thoughts in your reactions to what is
happening and to sit quietly without contention with anything
that's happening without condemning anything
or without any Greed for
anything allow yourself to be as you are but in the in the
middle of how you are let there be
knowing and knowing which
radiates a peaceful way of being to know to be
aware
peacefully a peacemaker in the middle of your
life peaceful knowing even when there are thoughts and
impulses which are not peaceful let them be
known
peacefully
in whatever ways that you're not peaceful don't struggle with that or be
opposed to it but find that peaceful place
within that knows it peacefully and radiates peacefulness out
outward so the example the radiance the influence of
peacefulness spreads throughout your being with each moment of knowing the
breath your body your feelings your
thoughts and take your time time to stay close to a peaceful way of
knowing and if you can't find that be as close to peace as you
can
calm
for
below any tension you carry any
agitation below any way in which your mind is outwardly direct directed into
the world the future the past Underneath It All deep
inside can you find a place of peace of
calm maybe a place of being
centered and being in touch with this peaceful place
within to
know what's happening to you as it's
happening to be in the middle of your ongoing present moment
experience with an awareness that has a calming peace peacemaking
influence on whatever is going on for you
for
e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to now after this periods of meditation find within
you the place where there's the clearest feeling of
Peace calm non
agitation is there some place in the body that you associate with
this and if you
do Center yourself there as if that's who you
are
and then from there imagine yourself gazing out upon
the world a world that in many ways is on
fire with war and climate change and
people suffering uing dying people afraid and people
struggling and to gaze upon it from whatever peaceful place you
have letting your inner peace calm radiate outwards through the ways
that you are afraid or dismayed the ways that you are one of
the suffering
people and let whatever peacefulness you
have the kind of peace that we would wish on
everyone and wish that for others wish this for our world may our world be
peaceful May the fevers of greed hate and
delusion cool down for
everyone May the agitation of dismay and
fear calm down so everyone has the ability to tap
into their best wisdom and
love from whatever well-being we have wish others well may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
safe may all
beings be peaceful happy may all beings be
free
thank
you
one of the most repeated teachings of the Buddha is that of living a life of
nonharming nonviolence Aima and um sprinkle throughout the
teachings all kinds of little quotes in this regard and if we ask our ourselves why
the Buddha emphasized this we could uh maybe get a
clue in uh the way he described himself before he was awakened and this is
uh uh description where you get a sense of the Buddha's
own dismay challenge the way he was troubled by the state of the world of
his time this is from um uh a discourse called the discourse on
being violent at and it's
um it's um in a book that I've uh teachings I've translated in a book
called the Buddha before Buddhism the book of eights it's chapter
11 chapter not 11 it's U chapter
15 so the the Buddha uh States violence gives birth to
fear just just look at people and their
quarrels I will speak to you of my dismay and the way that I was
shaken seeing people thrashing about like fish in little water and seeing them feuding with each
other I became afraid the world is completely without a core
everywhere things are changing wanting a place of my own I saw
nothing not already taken I felt
discontent at seeing only conflict to the very end then I saw an arrow here hard to see
embedded in the heart pierced by this Arrow people Dash about
in all directions when the arrows pulled out they don't run and they don't
sink so the pathos of the Buddhist time
before his Awakening how he looked around the world and was deeply moved disturbed by it it's very different
contrast to kind of idea that many of us have of who the Buddha Buddha was after he was
awakened and here the suggestion is that it was his seeing the violence in the
world the way people are fighting uh the way that the fighting is they saw no end
to the fighting that uh the people had have um that this sounds like it
motivated him to find an alternative way of living that he didn't see any solution place
for him uh as a refuge any place in the world that he could go to be
safe um and so he looked within and lo and behold he found what he called an
arrow that uh was is not inherent to in the heart but can pierce the heart
causing a lot of pain and because it's not inherent to it because it's not um
you know part of the heart that Arrow can be taken out and that's what he
did and then he says as he did that then
um one doesn't run about and one doesn't sink one is not agitated or one doesn't
give up and just kind of collapse and um so that's a to me I'm
very touched by this description that uh it feels much more you see the humanity
of the Buddha compared to some of the descriptions of his Enlightenment where it seems a little bit more almost maybe
sometimes it could say disconnected from the world or very much in focusing on his own personal suffering seemingly and
uh the way description is and what about the world around us and um the Buddha then emphasised
emphasis for the next 40 45 years of his teaching career on the importance of non
violence and the importance of discovering the roots of violence in oneself and pulling out that Arrow um
became a common theme one way or the other of what he taught and
um and um and part of the reason for that
was I think that there was plenty enough violence in his times there descriptions
of the wars and the fighting that went on around him um the cruelty of rulers
and uh Bandits and robbers and it was a dangerous time and the sad thing is that
it's been this world has been dangerous ever since and um I don't think that
given the history of humanity we can expect that the dangers the horrors of
it are going to stop um they'll probably continue but there has to be
Alternatives there has to be some people who find that Arrow embedded in the
heart so that we're not motivated by our reactions to that pain that doesn't have
to be there and not a few people their anger their despair their dismay their
um fear uh the way that we run around and act impulsively and maybe act
violently either with our words our Deeds even our thoughts uh are those are
born from trying to struggle with our own pain not knowing how to be with our
own pain feeling the suffering of the world and having that be like U salt on
our own wound having that be to evoke the pain of this arrow that we have
within and so then the response to the world is not uh trying to stop what's in
the world from being terrible but we're trying to raise react to the world to try
toage this this pain of Our Own in our own heart by looking in the wrong
direction and um and so in the Buddhist practice the idea is to to turn oneself
inside out go in find the arrow and then in turning on inside out then step into
the world uh with that peace with that capacity of um being a non-reactive
presence for this world and does that mean that we become passive
no um the Buddha stepped forward into the world uh uh and sometimes moov
towards where the violence was the kind of the representative example of this in
the sutas is the story of a mass murderer named anguli Mala who uh was a
bandit and robbed people but killed people and he was apparently quite vicious and and uh killed many many
people and uh the people at times were quite afraid of him and uh when the
Buddha heard about it U the Buddha went into the jungle to find him and uh
people try to stop the Buddha and said it's too dangerous don't go there you're an unarmed mendicant but the Buddha went
anyway and the City of go and and and went there and was able to pacify the
murderer and was was able and actually converted him to become a Buddhist monk the um uh this idea of going
towards where the conflict is and uh
firefighters go towards the fires Medics sometimes go towards the
war not to fight but to help people who are deeply trained
deeply liberated have pulled out the heart are people who then have the the
fearlessness to go towards conflict towards violence and
um and uh another kind of Representative example of the power of being
peaceful is a story of King Ashoka and one of the first uh uh rulers of a huge
vast of India one of the first empires of India and uh he went apparently was a
vicious conqueror large army going around conquering and killing
and um at one point he was involved in a very large battle where thousands upon
thousands of people died on the battlefield even though he won and um the day after the battle he
was walking across the battlefield looking at the Carnage and walking right through the
middle of the battlefield was a Buddhist monk and that Buddhist monk had a
demeanor had a way of a bearing which was so peaceful and calm there was such
a radical contrast to the Carnage of the war that uh this got the um the king's
attention and um and the King asked him you know what who are you and what's going on here with you and and um he
explained that he was a Buddhist monk and and what is it your teacher teaches and the monk calmly said hate is
not overcome by hate hate is overcome by love this is
the ancient teaching so to have the demeanor of
peace to step into the battlefield after the fact to be able to have a presence
that somehow influenced this person to be calm uh and then to um have these
teachings that touched his heart uh and then this king of shoka then became
known as a proponent of nonviolence he became the first seemingly righteous or
just king of India and he created lots of shelters and hospices and fed the
poor and created shelters for animals and and uh and kind of completely turned
around how he was a king it's supposed to have been a true
story with there lots of stories about King akoka being transformed from a vicious King to a
a nonviolent King whether that story is accurate or not I don't know but it's a
wonderful representative example Tik nadan use a similar example to talk
about the boat people who who fled Vietnam in the 1970s maybe early 80s on
very flimsy boats packed with people trying to get to the Philippines and um
and there were storms in the middle of the ocean and big waves and tikah is for
me a powerful teaching that um that if one person could stay calm on
the boat um the boat would stay calm enough so it wouldn't tip over in the
big waves and everyone be would be safe one person to be calm one person to be
peaceful and uh one of the fallacies about pulling out one's own arrow and
being peaceful is that it's avoiding uh taking care of the world and taking
care of others and the Buddha was very adamant about don't sacrifice yourself
don't in order to take care of others take care of yourself
first so you can be a effective Peacemaker in the world and a very
challenging teaching I think a very evocative teaching provocative teaching of the Buddha is the one where he says
don't give up your own welfare for the sake of others welfare however great
clearly know your own welfare and be intent on the highest
good this is also not meant to be don't ignore other people but the
highest good elsewhere he talks over and over again also about live a life um uh
that is intent on the welfare of self and other the welfare and happiness of
everyone involved and so the and then we want to look for examples of people who are
doing this to see how we can support that kind of activity instead of the
activity of endless war endless conflict endless ways in which we continue to
evoke fear and people's hearts endless ways in which we keep driving that uh
Arrow deeper and deeper into people's hearts because we are just continuing the cycles of conflict that go on and
on and um and the more we
feel deeply moved by violence in the world whether it's the violence in Gaza
and Israel or the Ukraine or Syria there's places in the world right now
where thousands of people are being killed and um fighting in these conflicts and horrific ideas of what's
happening and um where are the peacemakers do we support them can we
bring them into the Forefront uh there's an organization in Israel called standing together where uh
Palestinians and uh Jewish Israelis are working together to bring humanitarian
Aid to people who need it and this idea of working together is
um and finding a common ground it goes against what many many people maybe the
majority of people are doing but uh that example of people walking across
the battlefield the example of someone else who's helping um this is I think
what we want to highlight and shine a light on uh on our on our world and can
we be a person like that can we be a person who lives uh uh
peacefully so here is um a king who uh at the time of the
Buddha who uh came to see the Buddha and made this comment that what he saw the
Buddha together with his monastics venerable sir Kings quarrel with Kings nobles with
Nobles brahin with brahin householders with householders mothers quarrel with
children children with mother father with children children with Father
Brothers quarrel with Brothers Brothers with sisters sisters with brothers
friends with friends but here I see monastics living in Concord
with mutual appreciation without disputing blending like milk and water
viewing each other with kindly eyes so there are people who live this
way may we shine the light and appreciate those people who are doing
this may we be that kind of person may we feel that it's that being a
peacemaker to Turning towards the violence in a peaceful way bringing a
peaceful influence is a revolutionary act and may we be courageous may we have
faith in that may we trust that so that um we can find an alternative to
violence without an alter uh alternative to violence do we want to live in such a
world do we want to live in a world where our so-called peace is at the expense of others
people's s suffering one way or the other can we be an example of someone
who has pulled out the arrow in our own heart and then becoming
a a calm force a peaceful influence into
this world around us thank you and um May you
become a peacemaker in your world