so good morning everyone and welcome good day I trust that you can hear me and um
and here I am the last day here at IRC
and um you know I haven't seen much of it
except for this you know the Altar and it's me sitting here but
I do feel very kind of content and happy to
introduce you to IRC for those who've never been here kind of have you here in a sense
and um so
so one of the wonderful Expressions that I like is the two words together
her breathing room and since I do a lot of my time
connected to my breathing meditation throughout the day as I go about things it's kind of second nature for me to
stay connected to breathing the idea breathing room having room to breathe such a you know
I think it's a sense of relief that people can have and a space you know to
have a lot more personal space when we feel claustrophobic and feel really nice
to be in a large vast natural setting
where it seems that the vastness of the setting can hold all the way we are
without any judgment that um maybe in some ways I've been in some
settings where it's vast natural settings where I felt simultaneously
very small like a small little piece of this universe and the same time kind of
acutely aware of being alive and the sensations and the
body being conscious being aware and being aware of it where there was lots of space to be as I am
and so meditation is a place to create space create room to create time
lots of time and maybe one definition of meditation is to
give ourselves infinite time as if we have all the time in the world
as if there is no time give ourselves all the space in the
world as if there's no limitation to the fast space in which we belong or
which holds us or allows all of us to be and one of the ways that Buddhism has
um kind of use this kind of ideas is to liken awareness to space
or to the sky and when birds fly through the sky they
don't leave any traces they don't disturb the sky this guy has infinite room for the birds
to fly through in a sense or if a rock gets thrown through the air there it doesn't mind words go through
the air the air doesn't mind there's lots of space for it and so awareness is that way
that awareness is like space there's something about knowing sensing feeling
know that being aware that can be vast and
open and lots of breathing room
so perhaps for this morning sitting there can be as we connect Here and Now
to our present moment experience maybe there can also be a sense of ass
space lots of breathing room for whatever is here
in a sense not disturbed by anything not bothered by anything
not needing anything not wanting anything to be different except
to hold whatever is including desires and wants in vast space
so to begin
assuming a posture that may be
takes up more space than usual another way it may be saying
being a little more erect and open in the chest and
with an head and neck that a little bit alert upright
gently closing the eyes
and slowly gently expanding
the Torso as you breathe in deep inhales
making space becoming larger Biggers lungs fill with air
as a diaphragm pushes down and the stomach out
and releasing relaxing as you exhale
and letting the breathing return to normal
and as you inhale maybe you can see imagine that your
awareness also expands now with the inhale
expands out to stretch and to meet wherever in your body there is tension
expand outward to touch caress tension and tightness
as if it's no problem but just being touched with the inhale with awareness
and on the exhale relaxing the tension
softening in the body
breathing normally imagine that you have lots of breathing
room in which to breathe
Maybe there's a lot of space around your body
and imagining that two three four five feet distance
from your body is a broad soft welcoming space
into which two breathe in breathe out
in exhaling exhaling and settling in relaxing in
deeply into the body
inhaling from the depths of your body outwards
with the expansion of the Torso in the chest and inhale
an expensive expansiveness that spreads beyond the body even
sometimes the more the thinking mind relaxes quiets
the more space quiet silent space there can be
for the breathing room for all things
that are occurring in the present moment
each thing allowed to be its own thing
as it comes and goes
wherever you're sitting now imagine the space around you
between you and the walls and the ceiling
or if you're outside in vast space beyond you
and however far away you can imagine the space
in a certain kind of way that's the distance how large
the bubble of awareness is
in some movements of the Mind contract
the awareness sets limits on it boxes it in
other movements of the Mind open it expand it
with no limits
the Buddha said that greed
boxes limits the mind creates a limit about boundary to the Mind awareness
generosity expands animosity
boxes the mind in love
expands it without limit
delusion Narrows the mind
wisdom makes awareness expansive
[Music]
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to mention that the love the compassion that
can flow out of Buddhist practice is a love compassion that has lots of
room lots of breathing room
so much room at some point it can hold all the suffering of the
world without being oppressed by it or troubled by it
and it's an amazing phenomenon that the heart has the ability
to be present for suffering without being troubled
we can be the opposite that if we practice and are mindful
aware it's almost as if we're making more room
all the room that's needed
and by not being troubled there's more
opportunity more space in our hearts to care
to Aspire to move into action to care and care for
others care for oneself
to wish others well to love others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
and may those who can use companionship know that we accompany them
with our care our good wishes our our love
may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
foreign
and welcome to this final talk about
the seven factors of compassion and um we were talking about compassion
for some time two weeks ago and now this week and one of the things I would try to
convey is that um there are many characteristics of
compassion or many supportive conditions that come together in order to have a healthy form of
compassion that maybe many people don't realize that if
people are have a capacity to feel compassion they might just kind of assume that
whatever way they happen to feel compassion as though a way to experience it
and it might be that in doing so having just one way that um it might be a good way sometimes but
it might not be universally useful if for example
uh the suffering of the world uh kind of touches in wounds that we have or
insecurities we have if uh if the being present for the
suffering of the world frightens us or
distresses us or depresses us that all those things can happen and if
that's mixed up or entangled with the compassion then the compassion is not
you know it you know is being kind of influenced by It or The Compassion might
not be the most healthy way to be in the world and to learn to bring in these other
qualities to bear on a compassion and to have them included is a protection
from the suffering of the world
harming us and causing us to be exhausted and fatigued and troubled and
depressed it kind of keeps it keeps US fluid Keeps Us open Keeps Us kind of
um transparent in a certain way to the suffering of the world
so they're suffering the world it doesn't land on the places we're holding
on to a sense of self protecting a sense of self or asserting a sense of self or the ways that we want to see ourselves
or know ourselves and and so sometimes that suffering it
doesn't you know get interfered with our desires and our animosities
and so to begin appreciating that these different characteristics of qualities
that can come along with compassion so for example that there's awareness
that can come along mindfulness can come along that there is a sense of Investigation
of really seeing the distinction between being present for suffering in ways that
cause a harm to ourselves to limit ourselves cause causes us suffering in
ways of being present with it there's more opening and freeing to really feel that and see what's
happening inside as we meet suffering to be able to make effort to make to be able to choose the fork the path of less
suffering of less strain less tension that the path of creating more space more
peace more openness around the capacity to meet suffering
to appreciate the uh that that compassion can come with a Sweetness in
fact if there isn't something that feels sweet or feels a rightness in it then
probably it's the compassion is mixed up with things which are unnecessary and then we go back to the awareness
practice to really see what's going on here and back to this making a distinction
seeing clearly the two Paths of what leads to what's leading us to feel
stressed and what's leading us away from that and then choosing it acting on one
living in in the one that's more beneficial
and then compassion can have a Tranquility for it and so if if we're compassionate and we
feel agitated Restless um that's on you know it's it's very
easy to add that to happen but to know that then the compassion it
is not going to be so clean or so spacious or then we're more vulnerable to some of the kind of
undermining ways that we can be impacted by suffering if we if we're agitated
and then the samadhi factor a sense of being really at home
stable unified centered in this bubble of compassion of care
love it's kind of like our home we feel like we're home with it as opposed to
something that we should do or we have to kind of gear up or you know tense up to try to have it
or constantly being distracted from it and then finally today the Equanimity
factor of compassion and sometimes it's hard for people to
appreciate that compassion and Equanimity can come together so there's can be a very strong kind of
feeling or idea that we have to um we were supposed to be distressed
we're supposed to be upset we're supposed to feel the suffering of the world in a way that we suffer as well
and if we don't feel it that way and suffer then we're not really connected to it but in fact we don't have to feel the
suffering of the the same suffering of the world the feeling or sensing the suffering of others is a a is a is a
kind of a a kind of a loving recognition it's a
kind of a it's sensing without suffering we're not suffering with them
then it's a kind of you know I don't know I don't know if there's any hope then but it is feeling them knowing
them fully so there's a kind of accompanying a kind of recognition a kind of kind of sense of uh capacity of
caring and accompanying and and respecting others but without us
suffering as well and Equanimity is part of that that heart of compassion
the capacity to be untroubled or unagitated or non-reactive
in the encounter with suffering and um and for some people hearing that
it can seem like and then the compassion is aloof or indifferent but in fact it's
it's the opposite that the capacity the ability to have compassion have lots of breathing room
before suffering lots of space for it without clamping down without
creating limits and contractions and tightness and awareness actually allows us to be more fully
present to be more sensitive to be more sensing and intuitive and and attuned to
other people so one of the one of the meanings of
equanimity is a very satisfying
kind of peaceful non-reactivity of the Mind
and I say satisfying and peaceful because
non-reactivity by itself can be a kind of a indifference or disassociation or
something like not caring but or kind of closing down neutrality
but this is not a neutral State it's very satisfying it's very it's a peaceful
and it's available to be present for things and it's not reactive
and it's a it's such a delightful kind of medicine relief for a joy for the mind
to feel like the mind is not being hijacked by
reactivity it's kind of a bit like kind of when we're no longer being having a reactive
mind they can finally say oh now I'm home now
you know um you know I can now and more fully myself
now this is a kind of a healthy state that we're very reactive agitated mind
it doesn't really feel like it might if you don't know anything else it might feel like that's who we are
but the Deep back when emanates while I go now I am who I am it's that
satisfying so the um um
so these seven factors of compassion are reference points for understanding
the full potential in the full Beauty and the full strength of compassion
and so to have these as a kind of list to kind of refer back to when you're
encountering suffering and feeling compassion and care for it and and
bringing along mindfulness in the middle of it don't forget to be mindful
or recognize that mindfulness is coming along it's a sense them
recognize how it how being careful about where the suffering
is where the freedom of suffering is is the movement of compassion
and effort and joy and tranquility and
samadhi and equanimity it they're part of the reason why it's such a beautiful thing reference point
and maybe sometimes practice is to bring this along with compassion is that
when compassion is strongest and most healthy and most I don't know
and itself clean these seven factors of compassion
come along with them effortlessly we don't have to practice them they're
just there and uh so if they're not there
then uh you know then we know where to work we know what to explore and
practice with so we can evoke or release this natural capacity of compassion to
have these seven beautiful qualities so um
it's uh it's a kind of a life work to explore
this it's not something that we can expect to do overnight or do well all the time or
but rather compassion is a wonderful mirror for ourselves to see ourselves
better and see where we get hung up see where we limit the mind or limit awareness to some more contracted state
and uh and you know it's a lifetime exploration and and the idea of spending
a lifetime on the Journey of discovering and
practicing and enacting and living by compassion it's a great journey it's a
great adventure it's a great kind of valuable treasure it's a gift we
do to ourselves in a gift we do to others so um
May compassion be a heightened these talks this week
May give you a heightened appreciation maybe even love for compassion
as it does a heightened appreciation and love for people maybe all people that
you meet so thank you very very much
and then I have some announcements there's three announcements about the upcoming 7 A.M YouTube
program here and a program at IMC tomorrow and then a
community meeting we have at IMC for all you know online on Sunday
so the first I'll be I'll be away for the next couple
of weeks and um and uh and then I'll be away for
a couple of weeks in May and then I'm going on a self retreat in June I'm going to go do a month-long
Retreat um in a cabin somewhere and um so you know uh
through a good part of the next uh you know I guess 10 weeks or so I'll be
away and uh and uh I have we have wonderful guest
teachers coming I think they're all people who have taught here before from on the YouTube
and uh it'd be nice if you would remember to support them a little bit as
they teach that kind of enriches the whole
the whole our whole community in many ways the other thing is
um so tomorrow for those people who live close enough to IMC the Earth care uh
committee at IMC is having a redwood Redwood City has a creek kind of running
through it that goes down to the bay and there's going to be a a Creek Cleaning
morning from 8 30 to 12. and um that uh that the city is
organizing but the Earth care is going as a group to go and participate in that and
um if you're close enough would like to do that you can look at the IMC website under what's new and there there's a
description and there's also a little sign up you can do if you want um and the IMC members who are
organizing it are RAM apalaraju and Hillary borison they'll be there and and
they're wonderful people and it should be a nice time and then Sunday at 11 o'clock here in
California the um we have a online community meeting for
anybody who part of the IMC Community or feels part of it or like to be a part of
it or just simply wants to learn a little bit about what's happening at IMC in the state kind of the state of State
of the Union for IMC and what's happening is we come out of the pandemic and some of the issues around covid here
and how they're shifting and some of the ideas for as we go forward from here
so I'll be hosting it and the the zoom link is right now it's available on the
what's new on the home page for imc's website where it's there is a little
announcement and also on the IMC calendar for Sunday at 11 o'clock California time
so uh I hope you come I'd love to see you there or participate and wait to tell
you and with that kind of event and um
thank you all very much