oh good morning everyone and welcome to IMC
and um the only announcement I have before beginning the talk is that
um in two weeks and on April 12th we'll have
um a community meeting here at IMC in person it will have been just about
three years since we closed with the beginning of the pandemic and it seems
like a nice time to Mark where we're at and where we're going and kind of the
vision of things and the needs how they changed and anything else and um so anyway so it'll
happen after the sitting so I think maybe at 11 o'clock or so yeah
March 12th what did I say April sorry yes thank you very much so
March 12th in two weeks um and then in April somewhere around April that maybe April 12th or no end
sometime in April we'll have a online community meeting like that as well for
the online community which is quite large but it feels important also for the people who are local who come here to
have a meeting to talk about kind of the in-person dimensions of our community
and so please come and anybody's welcome to come I think for
March we're still following the protocol for covid that we're doing with people to sign up for Sunday morning but it
will um but for the 11 o'clock community meeting I think that's going to be open to anyone so maybe we'll have more
people uh we'll wear with masks inside but I think that we're getting into a period of time now I think they're also
seriously considering how to change our kind of covid protocol is it time to
change it and how to change it and then maybe I was thinking the beginning of
April but probably we'll do some kind of change and exactly what that change will be I don't know
I just came back from teaching in New Zealand and I was asked and uh and both to teach
a retreat there but also to teach for a evening sitting group and it was kind of fascinating to go from here
to there where just by no one was wearing masks and to sit in a big room like this you know
with no one almost nowhere again there were two people there game wearing masks it was quite different and so I don't
know if that marks anything for us in terms of our changes but I think that um
it's certainly time to discuss it and consider what you know step by step what we're going to do that's going to be
different and I thank you for all of you for wearing your masks here and some of you
probably don't see the need for it and I know that things have changed quite a bit but I appreciate very much that
we're still doing it and I think it does make a difference
so um
for this talk I would like to begin with a story that's attributed to the
Cherokee People and it's a story that circulated quite a bit right after nine at 9 11 and 9 11
you know September 11 2001 was a big deal and the impact and the
on this country and on the world was quite huge and the emotions were quite strong and
so the story circulated and had to do with a Cherokee grandfather and talking to his
grandson and he says there are two wolves
battling inside of us all one wolf
is angry and greedy and wants to destroy and has envy and conceit and all these
kinds of powerful negative forces that we can have inside of ourselves
and the other wolf has love care and generosity and
nurturing and all these positive forces that we can have so the grandson sits there quietly for a
couple of minutes taking this in and then says to the grandfather which one will win the battle
and the Grands and the grandfather says whichever one we feed
so that's the kind of strong message of this of the story whichever one we feed
that if we don't pay attention to what we're feeding that who knows what we're feeding we
might be inadvertently feeding the wrong wolf inside of us we might be doing
things that support to anger support greed support conceit rather than supporting being nurturing
and loving and generous and all these other kind of ways of being
and um so what's fascinating a little bit in comparison to Buddhism the story
that Buddhism kind of says the same thing but um but in the story there are two
kind of equal forces two wolves that are there and in Buddhism the similar kind of
processes in play within us I maybe not called it a battle but certainly a balancing act and of what has what gets
prominence for us but there are considered to be two radically different systems so then it
wouldn't be like two wolves I don't know what it would be um the the Buddha sometimes gives his
Lions Roar so I don't know if the difference between a lion and that hyena
within us I was trying to think of something a little bit nicer than that because lions are a little bit you know
carnivorous and so what is there so I was thinking
about maybe a whale I love whales the biggest mammals you know that are you
know and uh and a hyena so these two two different kind of animals within us
and uh we usually don't give prominence to our our whale you know to this
whatever that is and um so Buddhism also has these two different
forces and what's fascinating to me is that uh The Hub uh the characterizations
of these two different processes inside of us that the Buddha gives
and because it kind of speaks to how they're very different from each other
that um one of them the Buddha described as being artificial
being he used the word constructed but it's clearly constructed by the mind
in a way that's artificial meaning it's not part of the natural world the natural system of things
and we have the same kind of division in popular English between
um we talk about you know something that's been made artificially like artificial sugar versus what's in a
natural product are synthetic Plastics synthetic clothes versus you know something that's naturally made cotton
clothes for example and this distinguish between things that don't exist in nature on their own but
have but which are products of the human mind that have created and invented and
made something and uh you could argue that's natural as well but there's still a distinction
between what is um kind of uh human-made
and has a source that is independent of what can be found on its own in the natural world
and so the Buddha kind of plays up that distinction and he uh he uses the word Sankara which
means constructed but the the idea of being constructed is that it's constructed in a way that's unnatural
it's part of a man a human-made kind of kind of uh invention construct that just
put together and in the ancient world the word Sankara could mean a cooking soup
cooking a meal constructing it preparing it it could also mean uh and I think this
is one of the plays that the Buddha had word plays he had it could refer to the construction of a brahmanical ritual
something rituals were actually called sankara's and um but a way of making them was
constructing them which that you know in contrasting themselves to this to the brahmanas the Buddha was focusing not on
what can be constructed by humans but a very different process so not these rituals that are made and built he
didn't put emphasis on that but on something else different the the image that's used in tibetan
tonkas Tibetan paintings of Buddhist paintings of this Sankara is a Potter
making a pot and it always seemed like a very nice image but here we have a something
that's humanely made something fragile that's the image of Sankara and so there's a humanly made is the important
uh distinction being here in the suit those teachings of the Buddha one of the images that's used for
becoming fully awakened is um a broken pottery shards
resting at the bottom of a very clear lake the the Clear Lake represents the
enlightened mind the enlightened awareness and somehow with a light Enlightenment the human constructed
categories beliefs conceits that we can live by have been shattered
and uh and they lay there peacefully on the pottery shards lay there on the on
the bottom of the lake some of you know a very famous verse attributed to the Buddha where he
says that the point of his Enlightenment saying house Builder you have been seen
your rafters have been shattered have been destroyed
and I have attained the the destruction
and um and the word for Destruction is uh has again has the word Sankara in it
it's the destruction of the sankara's the construct the destruction of what's
been constructed and so it's not pointing to something which is unnatural in US
it's pointed to something which is an artifice that's a creation that's unnecessary
and some of you might go along with that that conceit for example that other people have
uh is uh you know kind of has an artificiality to it it's something
constructed and made up and you know it's it's like a little bit of oppressive and it's problematic
uh you could you know certainly make the argument that that's natural to it where else does it come from but you know
where does anything come from but the whole natural world everything's natural right but the distinction is between what is
an artifice just made by humans versus what comes from the natural world
so what is it that's part of the natural world that's this other system that the Buddha is talking about
and um and for that he uses very natural metaphors
to bring it forth or to kind of describe it and one fascinating one is
um is uh he has this little metaphor that's just a description of a hen
that has a whole bunch of eggs that she's sitting on incubating
and if she uh keeps them warm sits on them incubates them along then those
healthy eggs will certainly hatch they'll take and pick out pick their way
out of the shell soon enough uh and the Buddha says even if the hen
does not want them to hatch they will hatch
and so this idea that there's a natural process that doesn't require even the hens desire or mental you know wishes or
constructs it's just happening on its own and he said in the same way people
who practice well in the Dharma they don't have to even want to be enlightened
they will be they'll and he says they'll they will break through the shell or whatever that might be that
keeps us in so that's kind of a remarkable teaching about this practice that it's a natural
process like you're incubating something so um and uh and the Buddha says the same
thing and uh in a number of places and one of the places he says that um
if you really have uh endowed with or living in harmony with
or living out of the Eightfold Path you know fully then even if you don't
want to be enlightened you will become it's a powerful message about there's
something inside of us a natural process that's set in motion by certain conditions certain incubate incubating
support that's hears it's not something we have to huff and puff to get Enlightenment but it's something we
nurture we nourish it's a part of our nature that we nourish nurturing our nature to
allow something to grow and develop to unfold and but uses a lot of words from the
natural natural world to describe this process of Buddhist practice he talks
about it being a process of growth approx a process of development and he
the word is used sometimes is translated as cultivating
and developing and I think of it like cultivating a plant you don't engineer the plant you don't
tug on it so it grows faster you nourish it nurture it protect it so
the natural process of the plant can grow and so the natural process that leads to
Awakening is the languages it's called it brings it goes to fruition
the someone is enlightened has attained the fruit but in order to have a fruit grow the
tree has to be protected and supported and allowed to grow
so there was that egg analogy which I don't know how you feel about that but
one of the most common reference points the Buddha uses for the kind of care
kind of attention the kind of inner life that we need to have to bring about
Awakening full Awakening he uses them as a metaphor a word in
Pali Sanskrit which is Yoni and exactly what Yoni means is not you know it's a
little bit variable it depends on how it's but uh in the most literal meaning for
humans it means the womb it could also mean the the fundamental
source for something the poly English dictionary gives Matrix as one of the meanings of it and Matrix
it comes from the Latin word mother and uh Matrix is a place where this
Matrix of things that allows things to develop and to grow so by the study of a womb I think is one
of the most primary representations of what is a natural process that we're
part of as human beings what could be more natural than producing children and
growing children and developing having them develop Within certainly a person might want to have
children and desire children and tend to have them but at some point you have to
you know once you're pregnant you let this natural process unfold and you have
to kind of support it to nourish and protect it that natural process the best you can I mean eventually I guess we'll
start doing genetic engineering but I don't know if we're quite there yet for the embryo are we starting to do
it anyway traditionally you know it's a completely natural process that is not
part of the you know human artifice and and Engineering that we do
and so it's representative of this natural process and um and so the word the phrase that's
very important in the Buddha's teachings is yoniso manisikara and I translate it the manisikara means
the doing the activities of the of the intellect of the mental activities so
that somehow our inner mental life our inner spiritual life is something that yoniso means it comes
from the womb comes from a deep Source Within the sankara's these uh mental formations
and constructs that the Buddha wants to shatter and be an end with are products
of clinging in the mind and the mind becomes free of the
clinging when the constructs are shattered that doesn't mean that we stop thinking
and working and having Concepts we live by but we're no longer living by the artifice that constructs the
artificiality that the mind can create and instead the source for where our
life comes from is not the clinging of the mind but rather the the the the the
supportive flow of inequalities that come from this deep
Source within so this is why I wanted to say this this the analogy of the two
wolves doesn't quite work for Buddhism because wolves are two equal things as
opposed to um you know the attachments of the Mind versus the the natural growth that can
come from a womb-like source Within and so uh I sometimes I've tried calling
this the gestational forces within us this is the gestational energies or
impulses because the idea that we're gestating something we're incubating something in practice
and we're allowing something to unfold and to grow and to move through us as opposed to being the engineer for our
practice not a few people have entered practice with full of conceit I'm going
to be the first one on my block to be enlightened you know I'm just going to go through this I'm going to go to this Retreat I'm going to huff and puff I'm
capable I'm smart I'm energetic I've been successful in whatever I do in my
life you have a PhD from Stanford and I can certainly do this and boom you know there they go you know
and and uh generally it's understood if you have that kind of attitude it'll take you about 10 times longer to get
enlightened partly because you're not allowing for this natural incubation to happen
making room and space for this natural growth that needs to occur and what we do as practitioners and we
can do a lot it can take a lot of effort to practice but we understand what we're doing is develop is providing the
conditions the nurturing supportive conditions for this natural process to
unfold we're nurturing nature and um so
um so how do we do this and there's many ways of doing it but I
want to offer you the middle way Buddhism is famous for them calling the middle way
and uh and one technique the first time being I'll call it that it doesn't have
to be considered that is the practice of doing nothing
and but doing nothing while either literally or metaphorically
sitting in meditation in an upright still posture
it can be other postures it can be done lying down this way but it's a clear posture of negative Dignity of nobility
of uprightness of balance and we sit there in a good posture and in Zen practice
they put us a lot of care into sitting in this really good upright posture that
actually takes a lot of sometimes physical effort to kind of keep the posture going and stay stay alert
but you stay there and you and then the practice is to have this Middle Way posture
and don't move and on the surface of it initially
all the impatience all the reactivity that's expressed through the body moving
is not expressed and so you have an itch you're not
supposed to scratch yourself I mean you're allowed if you want to it's not like no one's preventing you in our tradition in Zen you're kind of
prevented [Laughter] and um but uh you know you know but we
don't you don't you don't give in to the the reactive impulses uh you feel impatient and you want to
look at your phone like you know I must have gotten it in five minutes I must have gotten a new text message
and so you know what can be wrong with checking my text right but what's wrong about it is what what
we're doing now injecting the text more likely is reinforcing the reactivity of
the Mind and the the constructs of the mind this this sankara's uh are belong to the
world of reactivity the world of reactivity belongs to this world of attachments and clinging that
belong to this place in the mind this place that is artificial or superficial doesn't really come from the depths so
we sit there and we don't give in to the impulse to check the phone we don't give in to sometimes in
meditation even if our body feels uncomfortable we don't give in to
changing and reacting and moving but learn to stay still in the discomfort when we sit
so a number of things happen then this way physically if we don't move and sit
still some of the layers of tension We Carry in our body which are born which
arise from the reactivity of in the mind this world of sankara's world of
constructs is what contributes to physical tension in our body
so as we're sitting and not moving some of it for some of us some of the daily tension that's built up begins to
relax and you know it's important the first for some people is the shoulder I mean it's still to this day sometimes when I
sit down to meditate my shoulders give it give a give me oh yeah you know give
give away a little bit and settle to this day still when I sit down my stomach will relax a little bit just
sitting there just the ordinary tension of daily life kind of have a chance to settle
as I keep sitting in meditation my breathing begins to change because I'm
busy running around doing things before I come to sit and it affects my breathing and and so then my breathing
begins to relax and this relaxing is beginning to uh
settle the reactive constructing kind of uh force in the mind this artifice this
construct this humanly created things that go on all the tension that you care in your
body don't blame the world for it don't blame others for it don't blame
your don't blame your boss all the tension you have is a product of
your own mind somehow the processing of your own mind the processes of the world
the conditions for your attention might definitely be out there and sometimes it's appropriate to address those
conditions out there but uh but in Buddhism the primary kind
of understanding of how tension occur builds up inside of us is goes through this constructive reactive qualities of
the mind that are based on clinging of something something or other and so we sit in this middle way and sit
still and and we start seeing our reactivity we don't give in to it and
within some with some some degree maybe there's some relaxing that goes unsettling
as we do this we also start seeing sooner or later that we have a reactive mind
and so we're sitting there sitting there sitting quietly minding your own business and we're
starting feeling impatient the meditation is not over and so the logical thing to do is to be
angry at the bell ringer you know you know it's not we can't it
can't be this long and um and so I'll look at my watch
no I'm supposed not supposed to look at my watch don't give in to the reactivity I'll keep I'll just look and see I'll
stare at the bell ringer no no I'm not supposed to do that I'm supposed to stay still that's the middle
way just still with the eyes closed stay still and um and so then we see that the mind
what the mind is doing more oh I'm starting to write letters to the president of IMC
that is that the sittings are too long and if this Buddhism is really up to
snuff like you know the com app 10 minutes should be enough
and this 45 you know 35 minutes for Sunday morning is just I have to you
know this is like old-fashioned you know if we have our meditation Technologies really up to Snuff you know
10 minutes should be plenty and you guys get you know old-fashioned and not really up to date with
so you start seeing the Mind writing letters in reacting it's like reacting and and then you're reciting the letters
you know you know with the exclamation point thanks or good luck or something
and you start seeing that the Ang the mind is angry the mind is upset the mind
it gets goes carried away and these trains of thoughts and it does that's not the middle way
the middle way is to stay still in the mind there's and then next time it happens
you start writing these letters he said no I don't know how to do that let's not get involved in that let that act let's
not get into that activation of the Mind and lo and behold over time you start
seeing more and more how the mind gets caught in thoughts and reactivity and emotions
and you learn the difference between being involved in those and staying on
the middle path staying in that middle way so it's not just the body that stays still it's also the Mind begins to stay
still but it's not a frozen Stillness it's the Stillness of a hen sitting on
our eggs it's the nurturing Stillness that allows
for something that needs supportive conditions to come forth to grow
something inside of us wants to be born the Dharma that's in you wants to be
born the path to Liberation wants to be born the what wants to be born is these
beautiful qualities that arise out of non-clinging and the primary this there's lots of
things like this but in the in Buddhism there's seven qualities that it most
emphasizes that are supported by this yoniso money sikara this um
inner life that arises out of this deep profound Source within us
and these are the seven factors of Awakening and what's interesting about these is
that in this form as the unit is coming out of the out of the womb what's going
to be born they are not practices we do but qualities that flower inside of us
that come to fruition so they are so first is mindfulness and
in popular Society these days mindfulness is a technique in Buddhism mindfulness is not a
technique but it's more like a state that we become endowed with that grows and develops
there is the capacity to see clearly usually called investigation
there's no investigating going on it's a natural capacity to start seeing what's
happening clearly when the mind the reactive mind has gotten still
there is uh engagement a natural kind of you can see it's
beautiful to feel that in the Stillness of this middle way of sitting upright
and being present there's a certain Vitality animation in being really
embodied in here this is not a passive thing but the
embodiment the animation is from an inner source that keeps us kind of
engaged that doesn't it's not the mind applying effort
but rather we're receiving than this animated animation from inside that's
flowing and it's not automatic but it's beautiful to feel in meditation the flow
of being alive the flow of being being energized the flow that's being energized that's
intelligent and the intelligence of this effort that the the Buddhism emphasizes is the
intelligence that flows into what is wholesome that's a healthy that's nourishing and
stays away from what's unhealthy unwholesome reactive
and then the fourth of these seven factors of Awakening is joy Joy is not a technique Joy is a
byproduct of this what wants to be born coming out of this it's part of the gestational forces that we have inside
Tranquility a deep abiding feeling of oceanic tranquility
that can come and then the the sixth one which is where there's a lot of reactivity a lot
of constructing and trying to make happen around this is samadhi and concentration
but here again at samadhi is not something we construct and make happen but we create the nurturing conditions
that allows for this deep stability deep unification of mind to come together
it's not something we have to do but something we allow for and that's in the seventh of these
factors is a deep profound sense of equanimity that is a sweet and feels sweet and
freeing and feels like a phenomenal gift Equanimity being a mind which is
non-reactive the reactivity of the mind has stopped but our lit life force is fully alive
and flowing so that's why it feels so good to have this flowing flowingness and aliveness
and presence without the the the static
of reactivity in the mind so in Buddhism then the teachings of the
Buddha there are these two different systems processes within us
one which is um synthetic
Greek word for constructed put together and the other which is natural
which is just if you allow me to try this out gestational
and the what we're trying to do in Buddhist practice is support the gestational
processes the natural processes that exist inside of us
and so we see a phenomenal celebration I call it a phenomenal
appreciation or valuing of a natural process that we all that exists in all
of us that often get submerged or cut out or rejected
in when we're too much in the mind or too much in our constructs and our beliefs in our reactivity
but to but to but be able to calm down the reactivity enough
to start feeling the flow the warmth the the the the the the generosity of it can
flow from inside from inside out that the Buddha is a little bit Likens to in a different in a certain analogy
to a underwater spring that flows a spring of water where water flows up
inside the spring and flows out and spreads out in a nourishing way throughout the spring throughout the
lake so in the same way there's this nourishing flow that can happen
for people who've never practiced generally is to somehow live in that middle way
follow the middle path of being still enough that we're not giving into our reactive forces
so they have a chance to relax that we have a chance to see them clearly
and in seeing them clearly especially the ones of the mind of not feeding them
not nourishing them because where they were nourishing the wrong thing
our capacity to nourish to support to feed
to um is one of the primary
wealths that we have the richness of human life is our human capacity that our attention
what we bring attention to and how we bring attention is you know is where the
where we have the opportunity to give birth to what is most healthy
so what is it in you that wants to be born
not what in you that you want to acquire
not in you what you want to accomplish
in the world but what is it that deep inside that in
the deepest place you have what wants to be born
how would you know that how would you have discovered that and one of the ways is to become quiet
and still enough to distilling of the reactive mind
and when there's enough stilling and attention I think you start you'll start feeling or sensing that yes in
fact something wants to be born and and then to nourish that to support
it to make room for it which you can't do you cannot do if
you're too busy if you're running around trying to accomplish all the things that's possible to accomplish in Silicon Valley
yeah you probably won't have room in a time
that is needed for such deeper Wellspring to come forth
and for in the in the Buddhist tradition part of that deeper Wellspring of what
wants to come forth is liberation is freedom from these reactivities
freedom from construct freedom from attachment it's a biological Force
biological imperative almost that exists within us
it won't Liberation wants to be born
so um two forces within us which will you feed
whichever one you feed to a win but I think the world loses
if reactivity wins maybe you'll become a billionaire
with your reactive mind but the world will lose because the world benefits from people
when the best inner qualities of who we are have a chance to flower and develop
and grow and and then we become a gift for the world Who We Are
and which is one of the greatest things to do in human life so in this way also with this kind of
way of understanding this early Buddhist teachings naturalistic quality of it
um it's uh it's kind of uh it's I wouldn't call it World affirming but
it's it's nature affirming it's affirming something very powerful and meaningful in our life
that sometimes we don't understand in Buddhism if we if teachers like me talk
too much about letting go just let go let go let go but now if teachers like me to talk too
much about letting go just reinterpret it as being let go so this natural process can can flower in
you so thank you and we have about five six minutes if
any of you would like to have questions or comments or clarification you're welcome to do it
ah thank you it's uh it was very enlightening yeah probably not a good word to use here but uh I mean yeah
a practical question I have you mentioned um resisting to look at the
phone or the watch watch actually specifically yeah resisting uh desire to look at the watch
or the oh yes yes yes so is it better to not bring a device whether it's watch or
phone again at all or is it better to resist the desire
well there is um kind of a
without any other context for the question the generic answer is
um don't bring the watch and that's you know that's kind of a standard kind of thing but uh I prefer
the contextual answer and that is what would be most interesting for you what would be useful
for you if you're so compulsive that uh that you
you can't even meditate because you're always looking at your watch maybe leave it behind for a while
until you've settled down enough that you can keep it on that is not an issue
or or maybe it's an issue but it's not that terrible but it's still an issue
anything you know I need to deal with my reactivity so this is an opportunity I'm going to
definitely wear my watch but I'm not going to look at it and I even if I have to break out in the sweat
you know just like hold on to my knees you know or just cross my arms so I don't look or something I'm gonna not
look at it because I want to deal with it I want to get to the bottom of it so I prefer my second answer
because whatever is useful for you whatever helps you find your way is that okay
thank you um I am very curious about the middle
path and one of the ways that I come to understand something more deeply is to understand what's around it
can you describe because where there's a middle path there's usually a high and a low also or a left and a right can you
describe the other two because I think that'll help me understand how to maintain the middle
path right good that's very good question the language of the middle path the
middle way is used in so many different ways for so many different contrasts you know to sides of it what it might be
today I think I was using it with the idea the difference between
being reactive and doing absolutely nothing kind of
giving up collapsing into the situation and so because some people just give up and
just like this hopeless and just kind of like you know just spend the day in bed or something it's fascinating this idea of I think
of a middle way of kind of not doing in conventional ways not doing anything but
in unconventional way you're really staying alert and present and still
so it means that we're not actively going out to do something but we're also not collapsing
for is this fascinating to do very helpful to do for example if there's a lot of sadness or grief
we don't want to block or resist sadness and grief but we also don't want to collapse in it
and so uh and so to be able to sit upright this way and just let the tears flow
uh without going oh no poor me you know just don't go oh you might feel that way but you're going to keep you're not
going to resist it or block it or judge the sadness okay you're allowed to be sad here let it flow but let me just
kind of stay this way and the advantage of that is that is that then this deeper
natural process that can support or process our sadness has a chance
if we collapse to it then we're actually reinforcing the reactivity around it
that is often a big can be a big component part of some people's sadness and grief that we don't see
so that's the kind of the contrast I was setting up in the most classic uh idea in Buddhism
the middle way is that the middleweight between the
essential desires pursuing all kinds of sensual desires and essential denial
asceticism so somehow the middle way between that another middle way that Buddhism
Composites is the middle way between the idea that anything really exists
or the idea that nothing really exists
so that's a little bit more philosophical but that's that's also profound thank you that actually helped me a lot
getting it for just this context so what explaining as you did for just this
example today yeah great seeing the two sides that helps me a lot wonderful thanks yeah thanks for asking the
question so maybe one more and then
point is it reacting to your emotions versus
um self-soothing as an act of self-compassion
well you know this is where uh you know giving these kinds of talks
lends itself to a certain kind of reductionalism it's a little bit too much at times I can't really explain everything
so I like I appreciate your question a lot sometimes reactivity
is uh is wise sometimes reactivity we react in a way
to care for our worst regular activity so maybe uh uh you know
our anger is so strong and we feel so much challenged by it and we want it to
go away and and we so we want to get making go away in a reactive way but we
don't reject it we bring a soothing compassion to it
and that's compassion may be as close to being this gestational Force within us
but we're initiating it in a reactive way because we really don't want to be angry
but it's successful maybe the anger calms down enough that way so we're using a wiser reactivity
to address a reactivity which is worse
so we don't want to be too black and white or blue you know absolute between these two different worlds that one is
all bad and one is all good or something so sometimes reactivity can support us
from settling you know stronger reactivity
but when when but when is but when is bringing compassion to the anger not a
reactivity but a source of wisdom I think that's also a good question there's not that doesn't have to have
any reactivity to it that has just like some deeper knowing inside knows to
bring this compassion and hold it kindly and supportively uh nurturingly like a
mother would hold an angry little child um you know just love and care it's part
of the nurturing and loving um and and how to know the difference
between this um I think that over time you start being able to identifying the difference
and one of the differences is that reactivity always has some quality of
tension with it whereas the nurturing qualities have no tension with it
but to be able to identify that in subtle ways it takes a lot of practice and sensitivity
what do you think of my answer I liked your question
um what I heard when you said that is that there's a difference between reaction and responding to something
when we choose the reaction or we allow the reaction we might be responding to
it um I've learned sometimes to just let go of that reaction and allowing myself to
Despair and making room for it it makes it last for a lot shorter period of time
and I can see it and I can almost get tired of it or laugh at myself for
it and then it disappears but the more I fight it it's uh it does not work very
nice so a very dramatic person I am so I need that but yeah great lovely
so thank you all so I it's kind of wonderful I think that people are coming
together in such a you know Community I wonder if you'd be willing to just give give a couple of minutes more just say
hello to someone near you and even if it's your first time here you can welcome them and if you want to say a
couple of words about what we talked this Dharma talk and the impact it had on you you're welcome to do that too and
um thank you for being here