hello everyone and happy to have you here as I
return from being gone for a week and um to be able to share this time
together and to uh begin kind of right
away I want to say that um meditation is often associated with becoming calm
and um relaxed and that when people sometimes show up to meditate they might feel
agitated they might feel all kinds of difficult emotions or spinning minds and
the idea that as meditation is an antidote for that and that we're trying to calm that down or settle something
and become more peaceful and that's all fine and it's actually part of
meditation but there comes a time when
uh what we want to do in meditation is not calm ourselves down is not make
things Pleasant for ourselves but rather learn to
be present equanimous present wisely present non reactively present for how
things are difficult if we always need to change how we are and change how we feel
we're not really finding the full Freedom that meditation mindfulness
meditation can provide us if we always need to make ourselves feel better then
we're still caught and uh probably still attached to something and thereby
setting up the conditions for us to get caught again if we're reacting towards
our tension and only calming down then we don't learning how to become wise
non-reactive kind of peace and maybe peaceful about being not
peaceful so we've been doing these 7 AMS many of us for over three three and a
half years now so I'd like to uh suggest that uh we
don't use this meditation to relax intentionally maybe unintentionally that
might happen but to assume a meditation
posture and either lower your gaze or close your
eyes and to begin directly without relaxing without settling
in to Simply recognize how you are right
now you might be sleepy you might
be a little bit dull you might be agitated you might be have some tensions
in your body don't automatically relax the
tensions just be present for how you
are and think of meditation as making room for how you
are creating space breathing room for
tension for agitation for an overactive
mind for sorrow and
grief for anger and
whatever whatever is happening and as we sit
this next 20 25 minutes or
so don't try to change anything don't try to let anything go
don't try to relax don't try to only change how how you are with
things so that you can be present for whatever way you are with an attention
and awareness which is nonreactive that allows yourself to be
just the way you
are to be able to have the inner strength to be present for how you are
even if it's not what you want
and then breathe with
that breathe so that you stay in touch with it and keep finding your way to a
non-reactive mode of awareness of
attention that doesn't need anything to change
except to be aware of how things are
directly and giving room for how things are to be just the way they are as they
exist in the present moment for this meditation past and
future are Irrelevant for the purpose of being
present here for how we
are
e
for
sitting here being aware without trying to change anything
to improve on things to push something
away without giving into your preferences or
being pushed around by what you like and what you don't
like let how you you are be just the way it
is while being clearly aware this is how it
is finding a nonreactive
awareness that is able to look at reality directly as it
is without being
agitated about being being
agitated
e
for
for not drifting off in
thought rather clearly recognizing that's what's
happening not reacting to what's happening clearly knowing what's
happening finding a kind of peace with how you are as you are
a peace which is only about the present moment here as you are
independent of What's Happen in the past what's going to happen in the
future just now peace with how you
are
e
for
to know how to be present to
discomfort and be comfortable with being with discomfort
be at ease with being
uneasy being able to see clearly what is difficult without
changing it this is a kind of
superpower that can bring many benefits as we go into our
lives we can be a gift to others because we know how to be
present when things are challenging we know how to have a
nonreactive presence we know how to be comfortable
with disc Comfort when others may not know
that and so we bring with us a different way of
being that doesn't perpetuate the cycles of reactivity that
people can live in but rather demonstrates the
possibility of being
peaceful when there's conflict being
non-reactive when things are not to our
preferences may it be that our capacity to be
present for discomfort serves
our ability to care for the welfare and happiness of
Others May it provide us with patience may it provide us with the
ability to learn understand others
better may it provide us with the time so that we can be wise in how we
respond to the challenges of
life may nonreactive presence be a gift to ourselves and
others so we can connect to the deepest parts of ourselves and to
Others May this practice that we do support the welfare and happiness of all
beings everywhere may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be healthy and may all beings everywhere be
free
[Music]
thank
you
e
so so that meditation we just did I feel is phenomenally important to
learn and maybe it's not something that people who are beginners of meditation would focus on but sooner or later if we
really want to be free we have to be free even when we're uncomfortable even when things are not
what we prefer them to be and if we want to be able to care for
the world well wisely uh uh we need to learn how to be
comfortable with the discomforts of the world so that we don't um
we're not reactive our reactivity doesn't override our ability to see clearly to think clearly to care carely
clearly and um the
um um it's a phenomenal skill to learn and so maybe this week that can be
the focus I know some of you may have a deep need for relief for relaxation
for some kind of um calm in the middle of your storm and
you're welcome always to practice as you see fit but I'd like to this week help
us kind of explore the um uh you know the the full benefit of this practice
that comes when we understand when we know how to practice with what's difficult
and um so part of the reason for this is that uh I want to talk about the central
Buddhist teaching on
nonviolence and uh nonharming an ancient teaching in
Buddhism is that the primary characteristic of the Dharma is non-harming
and um and nonharming is very challenging
State and in order to be able to live wisely with a dedication to
nonviolence it's important to be able to be wise about the challenges that our
life brings us challenges of living this life in the world where there is so much
violence and um and it begins by knowing H how to be
present for tremendous difficulties and not being pulled into our reactivity
pulled into our fear or our anger our distress our alarm our um all kinds of
things that we get caught in and then if we get caught in those things and act
from them then we're probably not going to act with much wisdom we're probably not going to act in ways that lead to
everyone's long-term benefit so in the teachings of the
Buddha there's a phenomenal emphasis on non-harming you see it scattered
throughout the importance of it and um it's uh so fundamental that uh it's what
brought me to the Dharma I came to the Dharma during the Vietnam war
time and I was of the draft age and uh
it was possible that I would when I turned 18 that I would they had a lottery for
the draft and it was possible that I would get a number that low enough number that uh I would be uh you know
called in to to the military and then maybe sent to Vietnam
to fight and I was a dedicated uh uh
pacifist it was I was certainly incapable of picking up a rifle and
fighting and killing other people so I I
assumed that I would figure out some way to be a conscientious objector or find some way to avoid uh going to fight but
it was still very active among those of us in the first year of college most of us were you know a draft
age and um and one of the things that um so we had a lot of conversations about
this and a lot of conversations about war and violence and and as those conversations went I was a person on the
kind of the most extreme kind of the one end of the spectrum that was dedicated
to nonviolence finding non-violent ways of dealing with conflict and um so then you know I had
to defend it I had to stand up for it in some ways and uh as I looked at myself with
this dedication this way that I was I could see that there was a problem I had
between there was a gap between uh the Deep kind of beliefs of that came out of
kind of felt like it came out of who I am rather than came out of just a belief
but this deep belief I had uh about nonviolent uh and there was not a belief
that you should be passive and do nothing it was a belief that um
uh that when there is conflict when there is war that uh a person who is
dedicated to nonviolence is a nonviolent Warrior would respond and deal directly
in some way with the violence in order to um stop the violence and there's lots
of phenomenal examples in the 20th century of people who have done this and
examples where it didn't work but uh I was inspired by the examples that did
work but the problem I had was I was afraid of dying and I could feel that whereas my
beliefs were that that I should be able to uh be a non-violent
Warrior um uh I felt that my fear of death fear
of the harm that I could receive because of that got would gotten the way and I didn't feel good about this Gap and I
felt I had to address it and um and my first interest in Buddhism was uh
somehow I picked up in my teenage years this idea that Buddhist practice uh
address this fear Buddhist practice would somehow address this concern I had
that so that if the time came for me to be involved in
nonviolent civil disob obedience nonviolent action that I would
um be prepared be ready for it so that was kind of the beginning of my interest
in Buddhism and it didn't really get me practicing regularly it took a few more years before I started practicing
regularly but what it has meant is that I was very attracted then to the teachings in Buddhism for uh uh the
non-violent teachings the emphasis in in that and uh um and I knew that just you
know being dedicated to that was not enough that uh there had to be uh wisdom
about how to do that and I came across a book by a scholar academic named Jean
sharp it's a three volume little book called uh uh nonviolence and he was a a
a scholar of non-violence around the world and it studied it in its different manifestations and its techniques and
its ways and it was uh that
um uh and you know it's not enough just to be dedicated to it it's a
sophisticated strategy to addess the world this way and um and so I studied his book and
I was interested in more of this and but as I got involved in Buddhism I got pulled into this world of of practice
and um feeling very confident that this practice practice would make people
better able to live in the world in a nonviolent way to some
degree and um and uh but I always wanted to address it more and I did some
workshops on this topic of non Buddhism and non-violence the Buddhist teachings on
non-violence and um and it's always been a strong current that I've wanted to
address and talk about and so I'm going to take this week to talk about it a bit
um and I want to say first that um Peace
is not is not the absence of
conflict that um conflict is an inevitable part of human
life however peace is knowing how to work with conflict work with differences
works with uh disagreements in such a way that uh we try to benefit
both sides of the conflict and this might sound naive it
might sound like it's ridiculous and
um the um maybe if you if we
don't educate ourselves if we don't prepare for it it's not something we
jump into if we get out of bed and today we're going to address the violence in the world
non-violently maybe it takes years of dedication and practice and learning when I was uh I'm originally
from Norway and in Norway there's a mandatory military service for a
year and uh there is an option for being a conscientious objector and in which
case a person has to serve two years uh doing some kind of uh community service
maybe working in a hospital and as a hospital Aid or something so everyone in
Norway has to do back then it was all the men all the men men had to do some
kind of service for the country whether it was military or conscien objector
some other way and some of the conscientious objectors objected to
this because at that time there was a feeling that uh Russia was a threat and
and uh there could be you know World War II is not so far not so long before and
Russia the Cold War was happening and uh some of the non-violent uh some of the
conscience obors wanted to have training equivalent to military training in
nonviolent strategies so that uh they could and and to develop themselves so
they could be prepared for uh engaging very actively in nonviolent ways if the
country was invaded Martin Luther King when he did his phenomenal civil rights
movement that was dedicated to nonviolence they just didn't wake up in the morning and just practice
nonviolence they prepared the non-violent protesters there was
preparation and training to be ready for what they did and I think in the long run there was some of those protesters
died some of them were severely hurt but probably um less
people got hurt that way than if there been a violent attempt to try to rectify
this uh unjust Injustice that existed then somehow we justify violence almost
like it's okay to die if we're fighting but it's not okay to die for
nonviolence so peace being learning how to be with
conflict so that it supports both people so I'll talk more about this in the
course of the day of of the week and I hope you stay for this week uh I hope
that uh that that uh you your desire for pleasure for delightful meditations for
deep states of calm uh to learn inspiring teachings for you
know about joy and love or something um don't
uh uh cause you to be disinterested in learning how to be with
conflict and how to be wise about it being with our discomforts in life this
is a phenomenally important part of Dharma practice to uh do
this um and so I want to read finally uh there's many many quotes from the Buddha about
this kind of thing but I I'll read some of them the course of the week but I want to read this one as we end
today the strong that those people who are strong seek the best for themselves and
for others understanding an other P other
people's anger they cultivate calm and
Stillness and thus they heal both themselves and
others those who call this weakness do not understand the
Dharma so that's in chapter 11 of the connected
discourses so um so I'll talk more about this in the
course of the week and in a sense this is also a response to the horrendous
violence that's going on in the world right now and um and it violence that's a
continuation of what's been going on in the world for thousands of years one with place or
another and um so um thank you for being
part of this this is a very important part of who I am and what I want to teach and so
um I appreciate the chance to do it thank
you