yeah so good to be with you all again how's the sound sound works okay yeah
okay and welcome to those who are on YouTube
joining us as well from afar
um
so today I brought a story um and those of us who I like to read the
ancient Pali Canon sutas they're often the kind of names and
locations are showing up when we read the the sutas and and if you're like me
I get curious you know who are these people what do they live what their
lives are like you know and how did they practice and and um
so today I like to share a story of
um this person whose name is ananta pindica
some of you may know this and um the story and and I brought in was
based on a compilation um that helmuth hacker did collecting various
pieces of information from suitors and commentaries and jatica tales and kind
of put it together to give us a little picture of what this person's life is like
um this you know usually when you read sutas you have a little glimpse of what
this person is but you don't get quite a story so I'm grateful that uh hacker had
brought this together and um in the Suites
often and The Suitor has the opening line that sounds like this
have I heard one time the blessed one and the Buddha was staying at the sabati
in the jatas Grove in ananta pentecas monastery
and that shows up a lot in the Suites so who is this guy another pindica and
so another Pinnacle was a wealthy family Merchant or born out of a very
wealthy family and um we don't know exactly what his
profession was but um sometimes it's a set of wealthy Merchant
or wealthy Banker that's what they do back then being born
in a wealthy family and he was he lives in sabati and so this place that the
opening line stays states often and this person is known for his
boundless generosity so this name ananta pindica actually
means one who gives to the poor or one who gives to those who are unprotected
that's what the name amings that was not his birth name his birth
name is a sudata um but even before he met the Buddha
before he was a Buddhist disciple he was already known as anantapindica kind of
people had forgotten his birth name and they just call him another pindica
and so I wanted to maybe start um by telling the story of how he
encountered the Buddha and so this is the first year after the Buddhist Awakening Buddha had a very
small monastic order you know maybe just handful of people who joined him and
practiced and became awakened individuals as well and they don't have a place and to live
and this is this is around a place called rajagaha
and often this monastic order would live
in the forest near nearby they would stay in the mountain tops or by the
river or on the metal Open Fields and so that's kind of how they wandered around
they wandered about another Pinnacle I had a brother-in-law
who lives in rajakahan is from that household he is also quite wealthy
and uh being close by to the Buddha he also became a faithful disciple of the Buddha
and so he saw how the monastic lived and so he
went and asked the Buddha is it okay if I'm gonna build some Dwelling Places for
your order I write around rajagaha and the Buddha said yes
I loved it this you know kind of I'm going to
recognized that was kind of challenging living conditions um and when when the condition came and
arose that this was offered and he agreed yeah so it'll be it would be nice
to have a more permanent space too to stay and so
and this brother-in-law began to build a monastery and Dwelling Places for the
monastic order now one day another pentica as a businessman who traveled to rajagaha he
came to see his brother-in-law apparently they too have a really a cordial relationship they're very warm
and caring for each other they love each other very much and but when the non-bindica showed up at
his door he was so busy making preparations for
some big event very elaborate thing and that I he almost like didn't pay
attention to another Pentagon so that was very unlike of him so he said
what are you really busy doing here you know are you preparing for a wedding or
you're gonna see a king or what are you busy doing
um and the brother-in-law said um
I'm inviting the enlightened one the Buddha and his order to come for the alms
tomorrow had the thought what the enlightened one
the Buddha coming to your door tomorrow just have arms it's not like it
happening every other week right and so I think in the culture they know this
notion of enlightened being the Buddha but somehow it's just gonna show up next
door at his brother-in-law's house you know that's like unheard
and that's not common back then that's not common right now so imagine you know somebody tell you I mean I'm gonna offer
obviously with it tomorrow for a monastic order or enlightened individual
you'd be like what so he asked him three times he's really enlightened one and
the brother-in-law said yes yeah the Buddha is coming tomorrow morning
so that God another Pentacles attention so that night
he couldn't sleep he was tossing back and forth and this idea that he's gonna see a enlightened
enlightened individual was so intriguing he just at some point he decided okay
I'm not gonna sleep so he got up the middle of the night and he decided that
he's gonna walk out of the city and walk towards where the monastico
order stayed right kind of in the countryside so that was in the dark
so he walked out and to the countryside I imagine you know being a born out of a
wealthy family has a lot of supports and he probably never had to go walk out of
the city in the dark you know in the countryside all by himself so he got
scared walking walking but he got scared but then this idea of a sea in the
Buddha was like so strong so so somehow he managed to
calm his mind they said I'm gonna go anyhow so he kept on walking
and at some point um in the midst day down he saw a person walking back and forth
back and forth so he stopped
and and that he heard this person calling in this indescribably harmonious voice
come sudata what no one knew him by the name of a
sudeta at that time right like what so he thought that must be the Buddha
so who else would know right and so he bowed down immediately at the Buddhist
feet and I used this shaky boy since how are
you the Buddha and that was a conventional greeting right how are you
and then Buddha answered in a very unconventional way
and so he said and the Buddha said well the arahans the awakened
individuals are always well and they are beyond the possibilities
for suffering he can just feel the another draw a job
properly dropped it was beyond the possibility of
suffering is that even possible yeah and so
and so the Buddha in that first encounter offered a step-by-step
teaching and ghosts from generosity but she is all very very steeped in
Sila which is ethical Behavior I imagine he is very ethical in his behavior
already and then the heavens the perios the harmful nature of essential Pursuits
benefits of a renunciation and this is known as a gradual training
of the Buddha at some point and the Buddha sense that
Ananda Pentacles are hard to mind maybe ready and quite receptive quite open
available and he offered him the liberative teachings of the vulnerable truth
upon receiving this teaching Ananda pindica and the Dharma eye opened for
him he knew the truth of what the Buddha said
right there and I received it and he felt it in his being
so he has no doubt anymore that this is the way this is the way
and so it is said that he entered the stream that to take him onwardly towards
Awakening in the future times Nancy can imagine this is touched him
quite deeply so add to the end of that encounter he invited the Buddha and his monastic
orders for alms food after his brother-in-law had done so
and then at the end of that meal offering Ananda pindica went up and
asked the Buddha if he could build a monastery in his hometown savati
and the Buddha said the enlightened ones love peaceful places
take that yes so I'm so happy because he's okay that was the conception of the
ananta pentecas monastery in savati so once he went back to savati his
hometown he immediately began to search up and down for this peaceful place where the
monastics might be able to stay and he founded this place and that
belonged to Prince Jetta jetta's glove this is jet of jetta's
place and so he's the son of the king passanadi
so he asked a prince Jackie if the place is on sale and and Jetta said nope this
place is not on sale and he says so firmly he said even if you're giving me
18 million dollars and this is not on sale
and anything Milling sounds a lot right but he's a businessman so another guy
not budging on this that I'm going to give you 18 million dollars right now
but Prince Jetta also didn't barge and he said no this is place is not on sale
so they but another bindica didn't give up so they eventually
two of them went to the an arbitrator who kind of managed to get them to agree on
something and so what was agreed upon was another pentica is going to get to the
land and that is coverable by 18 about whatever number of coins that aim 18
million dollar a month to again that if you lay the coins one by one on the land
that would be the space you get so
so another thing to get to pull the cards and cards of the coins start to
lay it on the ground and and it just happens so that there's only
a little corner that isn't um covered but in this whole process Prince
Jetta got so inspired by this being wow this is unheard of
and so he came and he said well uh okay even though there's not enough coins to
cover this corner I'm gonna build the gateway gateway for this Monastery for
free and apparently and Jetta spent the 18 million dollars to build this gateways
and offered it as part of the monastery and so that's how the monastery got
built and then after that another petica also
spent a lot more to furnish it and put buildings on and put a huge
celebratory event invited all the monastics and everyone to come to kind
of um take the joy of this and even after all of this and he
continued to support the a monastic order and the broader field
that he's in and so in this way he is known to be the foremost in his generosity
kind of a the as one of the great Disciples of the Buddha
um so I would also wanted to mention that this
Monastery another pentecas Monastery is a place that the Buddha spent a lot of
his time in out of the 40 45 or so years of a teaching career
he had to spend about 19 somewhere between 19 and 25 of them the ring
retreat in another Pentecost Park and so a lot of teachings flow out of this
place out of the generosity of this being I feel this deep gratitude for this
and I want to say a little bit about another Pentecost relational world and
so he has a family he has a friends was a happily married and his wife is
also a devoted a disciple of the Buddha and she's very kind and to
um you know maybe the big household as well as all the people who work in the
family business and then he has four children three
daughters and one son and two daughters were
steeped in the Dharma and also happily married the youngest daughter
is very sharp and wise also has a deep understanding of the Dharma but also
struggled in uh maybe we feel not phenomenal ways
she I saw that her two two sisters got married happily
for whatever reason she couldn't get married she got really sad and lonely and
depressed and eventually starved to death
I was very touching to kind of hear the stories of this and another Pentecostal family had to deal with
the loss like this just like many of us all kinds of ups and downs even was
you know immense conditions wealthy and uh good conditions he live in
he had to endure the loss um he has a son where he has kind of a
um I guess ups and downs or down UPS you know
and um his son for a long while
didn't want to have anything to do with the Dharma so he's busy you know he's a busy business businessman I guess he
inherited the big business of the family and he's always busy
and um ananta printica it took a while you know the story was that at some point he
had to bribe his song with thousand dollars for him to comfort
which is a practice day basically and uh and I thought wow poor parents
that's kind of what do we do sometimes there was a little happy ending in that
somehow the bribe worked I guess he's a businessman so the father promised a
thousand a thousand dollar that may be a lot in the first time it worked because he was so busy and just having a upper
Sasha Day means he actually stopped working for a day that was good and it
finally took a break so that wasn't so bad and the second time so he bribed with another thousand
dollars to say oh you know anyone to come with me to uh the
spend an afternoon at the monastery and that's where he met the Buddha and
he didn't receive the teaching and they connected with the teaching
and so over time he also became a devoted Buddhist disciple and he's
known as the little Ananda pindica so maybe we're benefiting from there as
well I also wanted to say that and
I wasn't so straightforward for another Pinnacle right you can imagine the many years that
son just had no connection it was so busy with his business and I imagined
another pentica at times might be pretty frustrated about oh you wouldn't listen
to me so and
um Ananda pentecas broader Social Circle
consists of a lot of different kind of individuals as a businessman he has people who maybe
like-minded but he also has a lot of people who drinks
I don't know maybe business people drink together when they're on business trip or something
and it was said that another pinkica never diminished them or try to fix them
he just modeled um what he could model and he maintained
the relationship with them friendship with them he never forced of his way unto this
individuals I was very touched by this that Ananda
pindica wasn't just generous in the material holistic way
but also it was he has a Generous Heart he wasn't trying to go around kind of
fix everybody I mean let people be and at the same time he's doing the best
that he can to model what could be modeled so very a kind of moderate way living in
the world that way also there is this story about he had a
friend who he befriended from a very young age
and and there's a friend had a very unfortunate name unlucky bird
I suspect that this may be from a different cast maybe a lower caste this
is a you know the uh Indian history of the caste system that was very prominent
back then even now it's still there and uh
when he this friend needed money he helped him out and offered a job even
offered a job that takes care of the family and his friends were all criticizing him
like oh you know this is very unfortunate and very unuspicious
but he didn't I wasn't concerned about it and so he just gave him a job and one
time apparently he was on a business trip and there was a lot of theft who
heard that he's out and so they kind of schemed a robbery
and this Vigilant unlucky bird heard about this and he started drumming you
know in the middle of the night or when the robbers were all kind of circling in on the house
and the big loud drum sounds scared
everybody away and so he came back I heard about this he said oh look you tell me this is
unlucky you know I'm very fortunate that he's helping us out in this way so I'm very fortunate
as it has this heart that is you know it's kind of wide open receiving all of
this different forms of beings around him
and then in terms of his relationship with the Buddha and so
after the monastery was built the Buddha came to a savati yetas Grove and under
pentecas a park very Monastery very often and it's said that as a great disciple
Ananda pindica would often visit the Buddha he would go to see the Buddha
twice a day and interestingly he would just sit right by
on one side of the Buddha and it's said that he usually does not ask about
Buddha questions because he didn't want to create
impression that he get a special treatment because he contributed to the
community so much it's really humble being
and he would come to see the Buddha and he would sit by one side and he would
wait to see the Buddha would say something either give a Dharma talk or ask him a
question and then he'll respond and if the Buddha also didn't say anything
then he would say something about maybe a situation he is in or how he had done
his things outside and then he'll wait to see what the Buddha respond
that the Buddha respond was approval or offer something and then use
that way as a way that he's engaging with the with the teachings
so um and the times when another pentica and
the Buddha spent time together apparently the Buddha had given a wide range of teachings ranging from how to
behave in very mundane situations all the way to liberative teachings
and so in this way um if the teachings are flowing down
towards all of us as well
maybe the most profound teaching that Ananda pentica received
I was on his Deathbed and there is a suta in Machu manikaya
143 that spoke about the time when he was
really sick he was probably very old also and it's just not getting any
better and there's this kind of
horrific description of how much pain he had endure
unbearable pain like you know like cards pulling the limbs all apart or
something physically and and he was not getting any better
and so he asked and to get Ananda and asare puta to come
and see him help him out so Ananda and Sarah puta are two of the
great Disciples of the Buddha and sariputa was an arahunt and Ananda at
that time was not quite yet so they came they came to see another
pentica knew that oh you know this man is not
getting any better he's near his death
so sariputa offered a whole set of a profound instruction
that is probably very appropriate for what another pentica was experiencing
and this set of instructions invited Ananda to pintika to not cling
to the six senses and the eye ear smell time taste
body touch Sensations in the mind and he went through this instruction one
by one through each of the senses and then he also went through the five
Aggregates for those who knew this is a teaching um uh the
Corrections of a body and mind and said not cling to each of this
and not cling to the four elements and I just gave a talk a while ago about the
four grade elements earth water fire and air that made up our bodies and not to
depend on them and then not just that it went through all the immaterial ram Realms and said
not to cling to any of those either and he ended by saying
not to claim this world or the the other world or anything in
between and not to depend on any of those
and half a sense reading the suta that ananta pentica was already ready
for this he knew you know he started he's dying
and having any form of a cleaning on this fading body makes no sense
so as sorry puta was offering this
I have a sense that he's offering almost a guided meditation
there went through each of the senses the repeating of this race you know not
clinging to the eye to the ear and and all the way to anything in this world
and another penteca was ready
and this guided meditation he probably rode in with cesari puta
he felt the truth of that and so at the end
another Pinnacle bursted into tears and not that I didn't quite know that oh
you know something bad happened as he said a householder are you failing are you
failing and another pinky guy responded no venerable Ananda I wasn't fading or
failing or or failing it's just that for a long time I've paid
the whole match to the Buddha the estate is deemed mandikins
yet I have never before heard such a Dharma talk
is being around the Buddha a lot I mean he's never heard this
and Ananda explained well this instructions usually weren't given to
the laypeople another pintika asked
um sorry puta and Ananda please let those teachings be offered to
the lay practitioners as well because there are people with little
dusts in their eyes there will be those who can't understand
this for this I am forever grateful for what
he did as teachings who weren't as kept to the
monastics anymore they were offered to those who were
ready lay or monastic
yeah I remember at one time when I heard this suta
I said I'd like someone to read this to me on my deathbed
and I had went ahead and recorded this is to tell myself I read it and recorded
it if somebody is not reading it I'm gonna listen to my all recording
um so holding that possibility for each of
us holding that possibility for each of us
and that were great beings like Ananda pentica 25 2600 years ago
and there are great beings now and there's a great beings that come to
be through the practice so the May the story of Ananda pindica
be an inspiration for all of us
so thank you for your kind attention
hmm I have a few minutes if there are any reflections
sharing comments
people on YouTube can hear you how is it like a rock
thank you um thank you for the the really beautiful Dharma talk what was the name
of the suta that was said to oh man
look it up yeah I think it might be another I can't remember for sure now and I'll
give you the number it's 143.
143 okay of the of the uh at the middle length of discourse
thank you
how many sutras are in this middle length this course 152 okay towards the
last towards the left yeah okay
I especially appreciate your talking about um Amanda pinticus family
that really put it in a broader context for me that's right yeah knowing that
people back then have families and go through all kinds of up and ups and
downs just like us for me kind of brings what being taught
alive you know it's true that they may be living in a
different way very different than what we how we live there's also a lot in
common there is a lot in common as well and that it was so special to for this
layperson to receive the teachings in this way yes yeah that's right yeah
thank you well maybe that's enough then
um you know I'll be around if there are questions and comments you'd like to come up and and chat and welcome that
yeah thank you everyone