good evening good evening because there aren't so many do you guys
want to come a little bit closer instead of like being you know the you can move wherever you want but just you know
maybe bring a chair in a little bit closer
and actually it's better if you're not on top of this blue line right here so you can be on either side of it yeah
and then maybe I'll begin by apologizing by about last week maybe some of you on
YouTube or some of you here I am I had to cancel at the last minute I had laryngitis and I'm hoping that my
voice holds up it's recently I still have it here a little
bit a week later so apologies for last minute having to
cancel on Monday last Monday
so today I'd like to continue on this theme that I've been doing talking about
like what is the Dharma like we have this expression you know the Dharma and
I think we all have a sense of what it is but been poking around a little bit and what does the Buddha say explicitly
when he says like you know this is the Dharma or I'm gonna Proclaim that our
mind it's um you know it's this
and I have been looking at this like on some other earlier talks through stories
I've been done the story I read to Paula that was a few weeks ago when the story
of kisakotami talking about the Dharma and tonight I had intended to use this
other story but I was really working with this story
I kind of like you know this story really doesn't make any sense
so I think I'm going to like abbreviate a part of it and really emphasize the
part where the Buddha is talking about the Dharma I'll abbreviate the part of like how it gets that this person is
asking and part of the reason why I feel okay about doing this is because this story
is from the last section of the pariah navaga this is a part of this who does
that Scholars think that is like the oldest part of the Buddhist literature
and for some people this is really meaningful because if it's oldest that means it's the closest to the time of
the Buddha not everybody thinks it's that meaningful but some people do
and then maybe I'll just say why they think it's the oldest is because elsewhere in the Polly Canon they talk
about the what's said in the part of August sometimes the Buddha asks I think he asks Ananda hey do you know about
this verse that's in the Para Pariah navaga so he's or he asks sorry
he asks different people so we know it's old because
referred to then but there's a
there's a part of this story that comes at the beginning but that's a completely different flavor
that Paulie's a little bit different and everybody thinks oh this is its own
little Standalone story that got tacked on on the beginning and that's the part that I think I'll abbreviate here a
little bit but one thing that's interesting and why
I kind of like chose to do this uh this uh oh Pariah navago but I'll
translate it um chapter on the way to the Beyond
so we've like how do you get there somewhere else other than here
the Beyond being kind of like you know nabana complete freedom
so I'm gonna I'll talk about this and I'll say a little bit that this is my own rendition I've done a little bit of
tweaking looking at the pulley looking at it with different translators have done as well as wanting to make it
accessible so
maybe I'll um I'll just say it starts with this first part is there is a
Brahman who you know at the earlier time at the time of the Buddha the dominant
religious tradition was the brahmanas can think of it as like proto-hinduism
and they had a real emphasis on rituals like you could please the Gods
by doing rituals and if things weren't going your way it's because either you hadn't done the
right rituals or you there was a mistake in them and the rituals were done by the
brahmanas like the Priestly cast so people would ask you know the priests to
do rituals for something and then the Buddha comes along and it's really something very different than
rituals you know just this belief that certain movements or certain words are
what's needed to make the world go correctly or
and suffering or something like that so really different emphasis
and so there's this uh one problem and his name is bavari and he has a uh I'd
say it's like a Hermitage and he um wants to do a ritual
and it's uh and he spends all his money to do this ritual
but it's uh I don't know all the details of like what's required but you know like everything he has he puts towards
this maybe he's believing that then you know his life is going to go okay
so after he does this he goes back to uh this Hermitage and there's this other person that shows up there that looks a
little unkept and they talk about how his feet are
dirty and messed up in his hair is dirty messed up in his teeth and uh bavari says uh
though something like this and uh and this visiting he doesn't ever
um he's never given a name um
so he approaches the Barbary and he says give me 500 coins
this is kind of the way he uh he introduces or asks himself and Bobby says I can't I don't have anything I
just gave it all to this sacrifice and this visiting Brahman says well
either you give me these 500 coins or I'm going to place this curse on you
that in seven days your head will split open so maybe right this is part of the
bramonical thinking I'm not sure and then the visiting brahmana leaves
and Barbary is very worried he's afraid like maybe my head's gonna split open maybe there's some truth to
this and then um this is a story right so we don't have
to take this literally but maybe we can I don't know but a Deva which is a
disembodied entity and a reminder Javas are just like humans in the sense that they are not
free they're not in they don't have a like if they don't have they're not
awakened hmm so that's what Deva
comes to bavari and says um
and now I forget exactly what he says that um so this benevolent
um Deva shows up and says oh and tells Barbary you know that uh that visitor is
actually a charlatan and actually he doesn't really know anything about heads and head splitting
but before he's still worried so he asks well if he doesn't know about
head splitting we'll maybe you do you do so he asked the devil what it's about head splitting
David says I don't know either Bobby says well who knows about head
splitting Pottery is really nervous and anxious about this and the Davis as well
there's this person
they call him the Buddha and he's way on this other part of India
and Bobby says you know I'm too old I can't travel there but I have these students I'll send them
so he sends 16 of his students to go
us to find the Buddha and ask about head splitting
so these students have followers of their own so this whole Entourage goes
all the way across India and I get to that Buddha they check to make sure is
he really the awakened one and they have these little tests that I won't go into
and keep a Buddha pass through the test so then the most senior of the students
asks the Buddha about head splitting and it goes like this
so agita who is the lead student says to the Buddha
Avery asks about the head and the splitting of the head
explain this blessed one and remove our doubt
and then the Buddha says ignorance
is the head and non-ignorance when combined with faith mindfulness
concentration zest and energy is the splitting of the head
thereupon the brahmana student uplifted by great exhilaration arranged
his cloak over one shoulder fell with his head at the Buddhist feet and bows and says the Brahman bavari together
with his students exultant and mine joyful worships your feet a one with vision
okay so this is a story so the Buddha just says one sentence and
all this exaltation and stuff but this is the way that I'm holding it
is that they were ritualists they were used to this idea that you have to like
appease the gods and you have to behave perfectly you know to do these rituals
but instead to realize oh no no this is about like the head and splitting the
head what's really important is actually about what one does
in terms of practice mindfulness Faith concentration zest and energy we
hear all about all these things and and the Buddhist practice so
Ajit ajita and is very excited and says
thank you and Bows to the Buddha and I'll confess it's not clear to me
why the head is ignorance and non-ignorances the splitting of the head
we could say splitting of the head is like having an open mind
but I think that would be more like a modern interpretation I'm not sure that they had that back then
but we could say well then this curse definitely came true because they had
some uh some knowledge so their heads got split open
okay so that's like the preamble to the story and maybe it sets the tone a
little bit about what happens next so the Buddha says well
I'm glad I answered your question but uh all of you all 16 of you you're welcome
to answer ask me any question you like and I'll answer it this makes sense in
the sense of if it's about knowledge and uh
non-ignorance so you know he's the Buddha is asking them
okay you can ask me whatever you like so one of the students metagu
goes up to the Buddha and asks him metagu we can translate his name as master of Mehta so somebody who has a
lot of loving kindness friend and he goes up to the Buddha and he says
I ask you o blessed one for I think you are a knowledge master and well
cultivated tell me this
from where has all this duka and it's countless forces in the world
and it's countless forms in the world where has all this Duca come from
I think this is a great question like where like you know Duke probably
you guys know right it's this uh represents this big range of experiences from just a mild
irritation or the sense of things not being right to just horrifying
terrifying pain so Duca has this wide range often translated as suffering but
maybe even like stress or unsatisfactory or you know really painful
so where has all this pain come from
and the Buddha answers of duka you ask me the origin maybe I
should say that this is all in verse of Duca you ask me the origin as one who
understands I will tell you dependent on
appropriation this Duca and its countless forms in the
world has sprung appropriation
like we don't hear this word as much it's this idea that it's a translation
of the word upadi and I like this word appropriation because it it has this uh
uppity has his two related means like what's causing what's the origin of suffering
it's like this uh our Acquisitions our belongings our possessions we might save
in like our baggage that's one form of upity and the second
form is the attachment to these Acquisitions this inner sense of
ownership so the Buddha is saying Appropriations
are a source of Duca the sense of acquiring things and making them mine
this attachment to them and wanting to get and and not only objects but
creating an identity like I'm the one that has this
even if it's not a exact object as we could even say I'm the one who doesn't
meditate well or I'm the one that meditates great look at me
like appropriating the meditation experience and making it mine and making an identity out of it
or even the like I'm the one that needs to get it together or I'm the one that's stressed or whatever we take as
something that too defines us as a part of our identity
or even it can be like this sense of ownership of like this is my meditation period why is everybody else making
noise don't they know that uh this is a precious time and I'm trying
to concentrate and get settled and you can notice on all these things
that I'm describing that there's a sense of me versus the world
or US versus them there's this real sense of you know when there's a strong sense of identity there's a real strong
separation and then when there's that there has to be all this like protection or maybe we have to protect this me that
gets created or we have to bolster it up make sure it looks good for everybody
so Ubuntu is like both the things one owns
and this internal claim of ownership
and one way that I like to think about this is that if we just modify the language
the language that we use for ourselves and that language is clunky we probably wouldn't do this in regular life or
conversation but it's a way to help kind of understand this point
we could say feeling frustrated with meditation has
arisen we wouldn't say that but
feeling frustrated with meditation has arisen has a different flavor that I'm
frustrated you can feel like I'm frustrated like it defines me and like there's nothing else
happening it's just this so to like turn the language around like
feeling lost is happening so like I'm lost and I'm the one that
has to get it together it's like feeling lost is happening it just kind of reminds us that these
things arise and pass away there not always there and they don't Define us they're
just experiences that we're having
so the Buddha says you asked me the origin as one who understands I will
tell you dependent on appropriation
this Duca and its countless forms in the world has sprung
an ignorant person so this is getting back to like head splitted and headed
stuff an ignorant person a knowingly appropriates and again and again
encounters dukkha one who understands does not appropriate
seeing it as the Genesis and origin of dukkha so
recognizing that like accumulating whether it's objects
or identification leads to suffering
leads to Duca and maybe the suffering is really subtle
but there's a way in which this uh it's like it's the opposite of
like letting go it's the opposite of having Freedom it's more this like pulling towards and getting stuck
so then uh metagu he responds what I asked you've explained so he
feels very happy but I ask you another question please tell me
how do the wise cross the flood of rebirth old age sorrow and
lamentation please Sage answer me clearly for truly you are one who has
discovered the Dharma how do the wise cross the flood
so maybe metagu is like okay you talked about the origin of dukkha but how do I
like not have duka how did the wise cross the flood
and if we think about ancient India right which has Monsoon seasons in the
and in the plane of the Ganges where a lot of the Buddha's teachings was this idea of crossing the flood was a real
concern right there's times of the year when you simply could not get from one location to another you had to wait for
the waters to subside probably many of you have heard this too
that there's this well-known simile where the Buddha talks about crossing
the flood getting from here this Shore where there's dukkha
to the other Shore which is Awakening and then how do you get there is with a
raft and the Dharma is the raft and in this
teaching this other assembly the Buddha says and just in the same way that you take the raft across the water you get
to the other Shore the way to the Beyond we might say
and then you're like all happy that the raft brought you there but you don't like pick up the raft put it on your
head and start walking with it once you're on the other Shore no you leave it
it was helpful to get over the shore but it's not helpful when you're already on land
to the Buddha is pointing to we don't even grab or hold on to the Dharma the
raft so
the Buddha continues so he says
um the meticu has asked how do the wise cross the flood and then the Buddha
answers this question I shall proclaim the Dharma to you
seen in this very life not involving hearsay
knowing which one may fairing mindfully cross over entanglement with the world
I appreciate that that Buddha is saying I proclaim the Dharma that is seen in this very life not on hearsay so he's
not giving metaphysical claims he's not saying oh you just have to believe stuff
you say no this is something that you can experience right now this is something that you everybody can
see in this life in this whatever life it is that you have now we don't have to depend on you know
somebody that told somebody that once knew something like no you can see this for yourself
I'm going to proclaim the Dharma that you can see
knowing which one may fairing mindfully cross over entanglement with the world
I like this word entanglement like it's this is a translation the word
facetica just not a common word we don't see so much
and it's um related to like being interlaced with or
somehow complicated or uh when we're in Tangles like something
that's impeding us from where we want to go it's opposite of being you know
disentangled so this disentanglement is another way
of talking about not appropriating like not making things
mine as a way of getting when we make things mine is the way we
get tangled up with them so we're not saying we have to get rid of everything we're not saying we can't
have both objects and that we can't have um identities
what's being pointed to is not getting tangled up in them
in a way that there's no freedom the Buddha is not saying you know don't
own anything or don't get involved with the world but just notice
how you are with the world is there a way that you can pick up and
engage with what's needed to be engaged with play work love
discipline you know all these types of things and then put them down when they're not
needed or when it's not appropriate come up when it's needed appropriate and
put them down sometimes we get entangled and we just can't put up our pick down we're just
like stuck maybe some ways entangled I kind of often imagining like a spider web or you
know something like this something sticky that's
I shall proclaim the Dharma to you seen in this very life
not involving hearsay knowing which one may very mindfully
cross over entanglement with the world so here's the Dharma that he's going to
give expel relishing and dogmatism
regarding everything you are aware of above below all around between
and Consciousness should not take a stance in becoming
expel relishing and dogmatism so again this is kind of an unpacking
what is this entanglement mean dogmatism right we can imagine as this
side like you know again this real distinct sense of me I'm right
and you're wrong we are right they are wrong
this kind of you know this fundamentalism this tendency to like just lay down these principles of just
you know this is incontrovertibly true this is just the way it is
and it's Associated dogmatism of course it's associated with intolerance and arrogance and in some ways we might even
say it's a certain amount of stuckness entanglement
and then this relishing way to expel relishing I think relishing in this way
is just uh this way of like taking too much
pleasure in maybe there's a sense of gluttony or just rolling around in it in a way
that's not helpful to be sure pleasure is a part of our
life and as part of the path and joy is but there's a way that we could just get
entangled and be pursuing you know pleasure after pleasure after pleasure and our whole life we're just all
tangled up with this and certainly addictions right or a sense of entanglement
spell relishing and dogmatism regarding everything you are aware of
above below all around between and then this last sentence Consciousness should
not take a stance in becoming
so I'm using tan Jeff's translation here because the pulley is a little bit weird but we could
relate this idea of becoming with this idea of me or Society of selfie and me
when there's a me that gets related to there's a sense of mine so we can see how all these ideas are
getting related that it's a way in which we
like Consciousness not taking a stance in becoming like not making like here
there's a me here I'm going to become this identity the one that has problems
the one that has to meditate the one then whatever it is you could there
so maybe instead of this becoming this me
what's being pointed to is like to what is our
visceral embodied experience
like what's actually happening in without we having this conceptual
idea or conceptual analysis or not a theoretical or abstraction but what's
being experienced sounds
movement in the body as it breathes maybe there's a sense of tightness or
openness be the activity of thinking
maybe a little bit of discomfort in the body like trying to simplify here
and it turns out that our life can unfold in a way that works fine if we
stay with this Simplicity of our experience when problems need to be
solved the mind just naturally comes together and works on them and then puts them down when they're no
longer needed so this instead of getting entangled or
making things more complicated what's being pointed to is you know just keeping it simple
not being as simple 10 necessarily but recognizing that what our senses are
telling us to stay there rather than always being in the head or in the mind
so the Buddha continues with this and he's saying a person dwelling thus
mindful heedful having given up taking things as mine
right here such a wise one abandons dukkha
abandoned Stuka birth old age sorrow and lamentation sometimes duka gets a
translated that way and then upon hearing the semeticus
says I rejoice in the words of Gautama the great Sierra well proclaimed was the
teaching of not appropriating clearly you the blessed one have
abandoned duka and this Dharma is known to you
and surely those you regularly teach could also abandon duka
therefore having met you I bow To You O spiritual Giant
perhaps the blessed one may regularly teach me
so he asks to become a student and then later in another setting we learned that he becomes awakened
so I I appreciate this uh teaching that you know we hear and other
settings about how that what is like the source of dukkha
often it's said like you know tanha is like you know clinging or craving but
this is pointing to another way like what clinging is
associated with or maybe it fleshes out what is this idea of clinging it's a big
part of it which goes under the radar result is definitely more subtle
but working with the clinging of that's creating an identity yes it is subtle
but it's really worth so much duka is
and the Buddha is really powerful like pointing to these powerful teachings
that the ending of dukkha I mean that's like quite something to
think about that this is possible
and it's just about our relationship to our experiences and what we're having
in the world are we grabbing on to them appropriating them are we getting
entangled with them or are we allowing them to arise and pass away as they do
are we allowing the experiences to come and go as they do without like
placing some big conceptual framework on top of them because this experience that
happened it means X Y or Z and everything else is wrong
instead it could be well because this experience is there I'm thinking my
current understanding is that it's x y and z it makes sense to me that it's x y and z
I wonder if it is X Y and Z it seems like it might be X Y and Z you can see
how that's very different and then saying it is X Y and Z and then we're kind of saying I'm the one that knows
it's X Y and Z and then we've like set up all these barriers and uh
separation and that have to be defended and upheld and
propagated and there's all these subtle ways in which Duca shows up
so that is the story of metagu talking to the Buddha
and he was there talking to the Buddha because bavari was afraid that his head was gonna get split open and so he sent
some of his students including metagu
I'll end there and open it up if there are any questions or comments
thank you
okay oh I spoke too soon
so so what is the Dharma so this is so that he is saying here
right it's about not getting entangled right and what are how many ways we get
entangled right it's countless ways that's the countless ways that uh duka
shows up
we have a very large
go to hundreds many hundreds of dark talks thousands I would say thousands
virtual real let's use a different microphone
maybe um you know there's this big quite public candidate and teachers give lots of
Dharma talks but because there's many ways that our minds
getting tangled I would say I would say what would you say Bill
I'm not going to say it because just lately I've been wondering what is the Dharma I
mean I'm right I'm rethinking a lot I like that question I asked a few
weeks ago you know what's and uh and and it's also
it's hard to remember all this suit is I've read
I read I listen to the expositions in our in our groups pay attention I don't you know write
down key points I try to to internalize all this but there's a
lot to remember so
I like that's part of what seems to he's saying the Dharma that is seen here and
now and it's not hearsay so he's really pointing to experience and I've kind of
getting entangled is more like an experience right it's not
um it's not just wisdom you know sayings that we've heard there's a way in which
we feel or as I'm saying saying entangled leads to dukkha is saying that
uh there's a way in which sometimes we feel stuck a little bit or we don't feel free or open
and what you said a few weeks ago when I asked the question was well guilt's been teaching
present experience so it's like a theme when we were going
through the Mantra matakaya right we were kept on pointing to the importance of experience as opposed to philosophy
and the Buddha in this in early bosom is definitely about one's experience it's
not a metaphysicist so I I guess what I've been the conclusion I've come to after many years is that well the darn
what the Buddhist teaching basically was understanding suffering and the source
of suffering and release from suffering in
maybe some course teachings maybe some subtle teachings um
and maybe how we get entangled is the same as that but I'm anyway I'm still
turning it over in my mind nice nice I love it I love it that you're still targeted it over that's perfect
and and can you tell us where to find this suda yeah yeah it's a
in the suit and apata yes which is in the Cayenne
yes and it's the last chapter of this
five four metaku the questions of metagu it's not
in the book of eights it's after the book The Book of eights is the fourth the sutinapata is Big the book of eights
is the fourth chapter we could say the Pariah navaga is the fifth chapter it's
after the book of eights I can find it now thank you very much
yeah another yes
um I guess earlier I heard you talk about fundamental kind of thinking and whatnot I was thinking to myself like
would we ever be able to all be on the same team or something like that and I thought probably no impossible
um it made me think of a philosopher I forget who it was but he pretty much talked about our past experiences kind
of inter influence the way we interpret stimuli and things coming in in life and so I was just thinking we all are headed
in different directions or have different experiences and interpret things differently and as we go through life you know something that may have
been important at one point May totally be you know foreign later on in Life or
vice versa or whatnot but it was interesting to hear you talk about fundamental kind of thinking or interpretation and whatnot
yeah and I think what's been important too is this idea of like holding on and like this is the truth and everything
else is wrong kind of that that there's different saying this makes sense to me
it's that second step and everything else is wrong that it gets us into trouble because I think you're right all
of us of course we're not going to have the same understandings at the same time but it's the way that we make other
people's or other ideas wrong I guess is the what's being pointed to you here
dogmatism fundamentalism yeah thank you
so during during part of that discussion you mentioned specifically
getting entangled with objects meaning both physical objects but also mental
constructions and I think that you implied and maybe you said directly
the sign that this is happening the entanglement is is an i statement I me
or mine is the beginning and so if you will this is the
the signpost that you're heading into entanglement I guess that's also
the signpost the other direction which is the non-self to not being entangled
means not being tied up with I Me Mine
exactly that's pretty much the the Nugget there yep yep yep that
entanglement and selfing and Duca right these are almost we could even say are synonyms yeah then the cell phone shows
up when we're of course we use I mean mine in language it would be really awkward and odd if we didn't but uh just
with we could use that language without creating this entity that's separate and
distinct and everything else thank you
okay so we're at the or did you want to say something quickly no no Jim I thought somehow you did okay so thank
you all uh for your attention and I wish you all a wonderful rest of the evening
and a happy and safe Fourth of July tomorrow thank you
and if you'd like you're welcome to come up and talk to me now afterwards