so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be with you to hear
you to see you saying hello it's very sweet um I always have a mixed feeling about
the hell who's not getting recorded on the Audio Dharma recording because they're so warm they're so sweet they're
just set the stage and yet we go into the meditation so whoever's listening to the guided meditation now please know
that there are lots of warm hellos from different places in the world and and receive that as a part of being part of
this community part of this community that comes together and practices together and supports each other with
their presence and Good Will so so with that
um let's um let's start meditating together and the theme
I will share with you uh through the the guidance little by
little slowly slowly so so let's learn let's arrive arrive in
this body in this moment
ah with an exhale letting go
let's try three deep diaphragmatic breaths together
we'll breathe in into the lower belly hold for a few seconds and let go with the sound
to really arrive let's start
breathing in cold
without her
feeling the spaciousness next breath breathe in
called and let go of the sigh
feeling your body one more
holding
um you could do more if you want in your own time really subtle or you can turn
the natural breath which is what we use as our anchor
a natural breath however it is short long deep shallow however it is we don't
change it we receive it as the anchor calming
soothing settling
relaxing and receiving relaxing and receiving
breath the sensations of the breath
just this bread in breath out breath
I'm gonna invite you to explore something if you like you can imagine yourself maybe being on top of the hill
sitting on top of a mountain beautiful scenery and all the
preoccupations thoughts plans memories this that are all down below we're far
away they're receded into the background here you are
with a sense of perspective ease peace taking Refuge
to calm Center yourself so that you can engage with more wisdom instead of being
contracted
and entangled the air is fine
maybe there's some birds Pleasant to have this moment of Refuge
in-breath out breath
I think the body relax especially the forehead
your jaw neck and shoulders
your abdomen
your whole body let it offer it's a weight to the Earth
we're saving each breath with patience
and continuing with this theme of
sitting on a mountain a mountain top
having a sense of perspective wherever you are having a sense of perspective could also be a beach or ever
you like to imagine you have a sense of perspective
space all around space all around can see the Horizon far
away huh
not crowded by demands by thoughts memories this bad
entanglements but space there's so much space
the valley below you're on the mountain The Village sleeps
peacefully
or the village there's a lot of ongoing muscle hustle
and bustle you have time
you've taken Refuge
You're Building moments of Refuge intending
the support yourself with calm stability
spaciousness equanimity
Equanimity equipoise and evenness of heart
it's not cool not aloof but present fully present
without toppling over into or away from
there is a power strength in equanimity amazing stability warm-hearted stability
for the period of this practice let us work with intention a power of
intention feel it into your
feel the power of intention in your sit bones your lower belly intending
towards spaciousness equanimity with each breath
your deepest wisdom you know what Equanimity is what it feels like
your heart knows your body knows
and if In This Moment it's not as accessible as usual
conjure up your inner your inner Buddha your inner
equanimous wise being your inner Buddha nature
let it show you the way relax rest
open your heart and let yourself be surprised
all spacious with each breath
so much space around you
strength of stability within you warm-hearted presence
warm-hearted unmoving non-reactive
not afraid
and Equanimity breathe breathed in and breathed out with every breath
limited this warm-hearted
unwavering
presence
your body be upright not uptight and teach you with each breath
Let the Body be soft relaxed receptive to each breath
will he present
warm-hearted spacious unwavering
the madness now let us imagine
of having space away with a sense of perspective The Mountaintop
we can relate more wisely more compassionately with the comings and goings of Our Lives
entanglements it demands expectations
the full catastrophe with an open heart open arms
such an amazing life full of ten thousand Joys ten thousand
sorrows as is everyone else's
a rising passing
so many gifts and blessings and challenges to stretches
having perspective with Equanimity doesn't mean we push them away
means we're more prepared to be with them
with all of it whenever you feel already imagining
yourself walking down the hill back into the village
With A New Perspective
with warm-heartedness with appreciation
not entangled engaged but not entangled
space in your heart and your mind if you need to stay more
on top of the mountain
with the breath it's okay too see what your heart needs
if it helps to bring an Equanimity phrase
may I accept they're rising and passing the calmings
and goings
with kindness and wisdom
may I engage with all comings and goings
spaciousness stability warm-heartedness
unentangled engaged
and non-reactive
may I recognize the peace and spaciousness that's available
and be present in my life or my life for myself others
from a place of stability care
non-reactivity calm
may I know may I appreciate that calm is my true nature
calm and spacious in here
it's caring
may I know that is always available
and it can be access to it can be cultivated with each breath like this one
and as we turn to bring this practice to a close
appreciating accepting acknowledging
my own practice the goodness of my own practice whatever showed up or did not show up
no attachment to results no expectation I've planted seeds I've planted
wholesome seeds yes yay celebrate the goodness
celebrate the cultivation and trust it
and offering this goodness this co-created goodness
in this time for the benefit of all beings sharing it with all beings may my
life may my practice be of benefit to all beings in ways I cannot imagine
may all beings everywhere be well may all beings be free including
this being who is myself
[Music]
thanks for your practice everyone so we practiced we explored equanimity
practice of opeka in Pali Equanimity which is the fourth Brahma vihara
forth Heavenly Abode first being meta loving kindness second
one being karuna compassion third one vicarious joy joy for Joy of others and
the fourth one is equanimity ah it's related to all of the other Brahma biharas it it supports them it's the
basis of them it's the the foundation and
the invitation tonight was to relate to it from this this image of sitting on
the mountain there's space all around so so there is a sense of perspective so
that we can then be with what is in our life with a sense of spaciousness with
calm with with care Equanimity is is kind is it has warm-heartedness in it it
has care this caring presence without entanglement it doesn't fall
into and it doesn't push things away like oh I don't want to deal with this it's present it's just present in the
middle of everything so we played around with that image a bit to get a little bit of presence we
had a little bit of space and then walking down back to the village and and be in our lives and but relate from that
space so so
I'd like to invite us now to transition into the sense of
equanimity holding the sense of presence the sense of stable presence
um for ourselves and in relationship to others because it is a skill to of
course it's it's a cultivation to feel it for are in in our own heart in our own uh
bodies and then the rubber meets the road when we start to interact with others of course our families and
colleagues and friends it's a higher bar but you get the chance to explore uh now
in small groups for those who are on Zoom to explore in small groups to show up with the sense of equanime to
interact with other human beings which are stand-ins for for all of humanity which are standards
and and the um question the the inquiry for us to explore together is
um is in our bodies so is the physical explosion so when you
have a sense of equanimity how does it feel in your body how does your body
feel and we'll we'll go around each person will say one one nugget and then the
next person the next person will come back to you and it'll be a spiral if it comes to you and you can also say I
don't know um I don't quite know right now I'm still exploring it that's perfectly fine
you can say pass in that way and then later say oh actually maybe I feel a sense of uprightness or maybe I feel
like my arms are wide open I want to embrace the whole world with a sense of
equanimity and my hands are in the fist anymore anyway they're they're my fingers are open or whatever
physicality you associate with Equanimity I think this can be such a powerful exploration
um and inspiring to to yourself and and to each other supporting each other in this very interesting exploration
so I'm going to create the zoom uh the breakout rooms they'll be roughly of size three and I
invite you to be kind to yourself kind to um each other of course and not asking
questions not directing it's just offering what what you have and if somebody says something and it's you're
confused it doesn't matter don't explore don't interrogate just let each person have their own experience in this way
being supportive okay all right the rooms are created yes oops all the numbers keep changing
here we go okay the rooms are created uh and let's go alphabetical order just for
the fun of it first name okay take care be kind and the rooms are open
now rooms will close in about 20 seconds so we'll wait until everybody's back
and in the meanwhile I will change the chat settings so that those who have
uh come back to the main room if there's any Reflections you'd like to chat you like to type in chat you are welcome to
do that
okay okay welcome back everyone
um so we have a few minutes for Reflections comments questions
discoveries aha moments confusions how was how is it either the meditation
or the um exploration of the physicality of
equanimity what it feels like what did you discover and especially if you haven't spoken recently with happy hour
we'd love to hear from you um if you have spoken pull back if you haven't pull forward for the benefit of
yourself and others there any aha moments questions
nav please now from Japan uh I'd love to share something that Fred
inspired which um which is an idea from a permaculture
uh thought leader called massanobu Fukuoka and he believes that the act of
farming is not to produce vegetables or or to grow anything it's really about
the cultivation of human beings so this idea of approaching any practice
with without the end in mind but rather falling in love with the practice
beautiful beautiful that's lovely thanks so much for sharing that now bearing
that into the big circle beautiful love it yes falling in love with the practice
exactly yeah any practice
agriculture Horticulture meditation practice beautiful growing food
Nancy please thank you Nikki
um I'm just off Retreat so I'm very tenderhearted and
um this was such a perfect evening for me for beginning of the evening
and um so it was a perfect subject and a perfect sit and a perfect little group
to be in so just bows to everybody ah thank you Nancy thank you for
bringing this this beautiful calm and sense of appreciation fresh from sitting
in Retreat so lovely to be sharing that to be bringing that to happy hour and
sharing that both in your small group and and big group it's just yeah yay
feeling you would call and and appreciating it thanks Nancy
um Claire I see your hand I also see a question from Gita let me get to this
one first um Nikki we shared about consolidating Equanimity with feeling safe do you have
thoughts on this yes I have thoughts on everything um
um so um let's see so I would not consolidate
um Equanimity with feeling safe they're they're uniquely different they're related like a Venn diagram there is a
relationship but I would definitely not consolidate them together so so here's how and it's an important
distinction so I do want to take time to to tease this apart um so Equanimity and the practice of
equanimity um as an uprightness has a strength to it
and has a sense of equipoise basically the classical definition of equanimity is is
um is equipoise with everything that arises and passes away okay
so is this feeling I mean it has to do with vedana the feeling tone actually with that teaching of pleasant
unpleasant and neutral so the idea is that the mind and heart is so still so calm that it doesn't fall into
what's Pleasant it doesn't want more of it it doesn't fall into greed I wanted I
wanted more of oh I want more and more and more and more and it doesn't push away what's unpleasant oh make that go
away I don't want it like ah so it's not aversive and it's not graspy that is
an important element of equanimity okay and safety doesn't quite approach that
safety has different qualities to it which are beautiful and important for us to give it to ourselves and give it to
others but it's not Equanimity so I would not consolidate them so I can say
more but maybe I'll just leave it at that hopefully that's clear enough Claire your head
I don't know if this will be helpful to anybody but I mentioned in my group that within the last 10 years or so in the
course of my spiritual actually longer spiritual journey I've adopted two
practices that I didn't do as a young person that have led me to real uh
true State I believe true states of equanimity one is cycling on a bike
because all you think about is the relationship of your body to the motion that's all you have no
other there's nothing going on in your head at all um and the other is dancing Tango
um and again it's all about being with your body beautiful so I I'm
loving this clear both of these practices that you talked about I love the practices you mentioned and and I
would I would add some Nuance to what you said because they're beautiful embodiment practices they're beautiful
embodiment practices for the mind to be really present right here not to think
not to be entangled and that call that sense of presence can be a
um a a ground for Equanimity to grow in but I wouldn't say that these are
Equanimity practices so it's very important to make a distinction I was trying to figure out yeah
these are a great embodiment practices but not equanonymity practices but they
they create the ground for Equanimity but they're not Equanimity practices right thanks Claire the other thing I
just wanted to add for a benefit or a friend from Japan name I didn't hear is
there's a wonderful book called chop wood carry water I don't know if you've ever read it
that's related to this yeah yeah chocolate carry water yeah yeah I love
that thing what do you do before Enlightenment shop would carry order what do you do after Enlightenment chop
would carry water so I'd love that thanks Claire thanks for bringing that in and Christine you get the last word
great thank you Nikki this is I got a lot out of the practice I uh just first
of all want to say thank you this has been in my groups it was uh a lot about
Equanimity and just right now it's like this for me you know and we're going through
the last six weeks I've had to wear a a brace on my legs so I haven't been able to straighten my leg and I'm back
upstairs in my meditation room I can go up and down the stairs again and just so much gratitude
tonight when I was with the the two people that I was with and just all of you I just feel so
cared for being being able to share my you know all sharing with all the
wonderful things I've learned and just a great place to be it like someone was saying to start my evening so thanks for
everything that I've gotten from you Nikki and all of you and yeah much thanks so thank you
thank you Christine thank you for your beautiful wholehearted practice and and
supporting yourself and supporting others through your practice showing up and in so many ways hear it in your in
your practice report how challenging and how in in you know the challenges of
having your foot your leg in a cast and movement and and yet so much gratitude so much joy you're bringing
beautiful thank you so much for sharing all that and being part of the Sangha Christine yay and thank you all all of
you every single one of you for being part of the Sangha ah thank
you so much for your practice um just feeling such goodness such
goodness and let us spread share the goodness of our practice with all beings everywhere
again may all beings be well may all things be free including ourselves
thanks dear ones be well take good care
thank you