so it's uh particularly wonderful for me to be back here
it's been a number of years since I've been at IMC teaching
um and it was very sweet you know because I um one of my good friends
um Peter Medina some of you might know him died last year and over 20 years ago he he was a monk
in Asia and he um gave IMC his clock his travel
clock you know and and so it's still here it's survived all the modernization
and improvements and it's still here so it's kind of sweet to see that
um uh so
um I'll start with um a metaphor that really helped me in
my early practice which was the metaphor of the snow globe you know when you shake a snow globe you
know all the snow just you know is all over you can barely see anything inside it but if you just let it settle it just
kind of very gently eventually it settles down and that image was very helpful for me
in my early meditation you know I'd sit down and my mind would be so chaotic there's so much happening but just
thinking the snow globe was like okay okay I just have to sit here and in time it will settle
and uh for what for quite a while that was like a really helpful
piece of my practice that patience of just okay it will settle but at a certain point
um I realized that I was thinking of those first 15 20 minutes that it took me to
settle as not really being part of my meditation and so I just kind of sat down and it was just like okay I'll
think about whatever I want an occasional breath and I start really taking it for granted and and just
assuming that that was just kind of you know this part of my mind wasn't even worth paying attention to it was so so
irrelevant and as he started learning more the subtleties of practice I began to really
understand that my thinking this thinking messy mind is what's here right now and that
that first 15-20 minutes of lots of messiness and chaotic thinking and busy
and Restless was really worthwhile to pay attention to that it was a very rich part of my
practice and I found that no matter how restless and agitated my mind was in
that time that by becoming mindfully aware of it I could there would be a
little bit of space around it there was the agitation and there was that little bit of sweet space and you know and I
recognized that that agitation it was unpleasant you know and so I was trying
to avoid it I didn't want to feel that agitation as you know really not liking
the the how my mind felt at those times so I just started folding all of that
into my practice so that my practice is just as Rich whether my mind is busy or
my mind is still it's still just as close and intimate as
regardless of the state of the Mind
you know the practice teaches us to um to show up for any mind State whether we
like it or judge it as not interesting
foreign
I wanted to talk about three kind of related mental states that arise
commonly in meditation and um and because they're kind of they're
related because we tend to not find them all that compelling to pay attention to
and they're impatience boredom and complacency
and all of those are kind of these kind of subtle States like we tend to like to you know if you've got a strong emotion
in meditation that's really juicy that's really interesting um oh a fantasy oh yeah I've been you
know it's very strong very compelling but these states of um or even physical
pain we can get very interested in you know trying to fix it try and trying to you know there's a lot to grab on to a
lot to to engage with but boredom and patience complacency they're all mental
states that we tend to not like we don't like them but we don't hate them enough to pay attention to them
so um so they tend to kind of go under the rate radar
you know for instance did any of you um you know maybe not today maybe on
rare occasion are kind of waiting for the Bell to ring you know I've been very few people who
haven't had that experience at least once um when I was
um for for a long time in practice you know I used to keep a clock in front of me you know and
and I'd also have a uh a timer that would go off so I didn't
really need the clock the timer did its job but I would just open my sun Peak
you know and um you know if there was 15 minutes I'd like ah 50 more minutes you know and and
you know the idea the idea that there was 15 more minutes was unpleasant more
unpleasant than the moment itself the idea of 50 more minutes and you know
so I'd get really involved in my impatient thoughts I'd get very engaged like okay so 50 more minutes that's 150
breaths you know I I negotiate my way through it you know
totally involved you know much more interested interesting at the moment um
but then if it was like five minutes you know my whole heart would lift it's like
oh only five more minutes great and suddenly I'd settled my mind would
settle and would actually enjoy my meditation and I could go longer you
know because the idea of all this long time period of of possible not not
enjoying it you know was I got in the way you know and um so these are the
games we play because we don't like that feeling of the impatient mind it's just a slight
unpleasantness right nothing so terrible nothing's that awful that time it's just
a slight low level unpleasantness but I find it really interesting
um that the English word for patience
comes from the Latin word Pati which means to suffer
and it means to suffer with you know the definition is a delay
difficulty and annoyance you know so it's the ability to to
suffer with to feel the pain of delay you know have you felt you know waiting
in traffic you know uh impatience arises right waiting in line and patience
arises you know that ability to be with that with patience
um you know with annoyance with with you know somebody who's just non-stop talking you know and you you know
they're knowing uh annoying us right and you know the ability to be patient with
that the ability to be with difficult things
um
when when we're feeling impatient what's really helpful is to realize that
there's something in our experience we're resisting we're actually resisting
there's actually a version when we're feeling that impatience I don't want something
and so the practice calls enough to turn towards it how do some patients feel in
the body you know maybe you feel you know maybe the body is tense maybe the body's
relaxed maybe part of the body is tense your shoulders are up the face different
parts how's the belly when we're feeling impatience um
or how does the mind what is impatient the flavor of the mind I don't know do
you know what I mean by the flavor you know like how do we know the difference between this is anger and
this is fear you know this is love you know it's a flavor of the mind and so what is the
flavor of the impatient mind how does that actually feel you know so we turn our attention to the actual felt
experience of the moment the actual felt experience of impatience
with patience you know we're practicing patience you know patience is uh
considered one of the most really important qualities to develop
and practice um you know in uh in the Buddhist
teachings you know many of you are familiar with the 10 part of me um the 10 Perfections the qualities that
we have to develop to wake up you know such as virtue patience loving kindness
you know energy uh wisdom you know all these wonderful qualities that we
develop uh but patience is a particularly uh interesting one because
um I think Gill is the one who told me this he he actually you know once we got
digitized digitized versions of the sutas he counted how many times the word
patients appeared in the majakaya compared to the other parmes I guess he
had a lot of time in his hands but um that they but um you know so it's
like it's that that commonly the Buddha you know said how essential patience is
to wake up now patience is only needed when there's
something happening that we don't want you know when there's nothing if we're
not resisting anything patience is no longer needed it no longer takes effort
and so there's always something going on that we don't want to see we don't want
to know we don't want it to be there we're pushing something away
um you know one kind of patience is patient perseverance
and that's for instance we can persevere and let's say we're
training for a marathon I don't know if you've ever trained for something that that you're really trying to get really good at you know and and so every day
you go out there regardless of how you feel regardless of how you feel and you can do that with the attitude of
gritting your teeth you know I'm gonna go out there and I'm gonna do this and and you can do it
or you can do that with a relaxed attitude you know oh um you know I'll show up every day but you can be very
relaxed they both get to the goal you know but the difference is is an
attitude with kindness you know and uh how happy we are you know how how at ease we are
and uh with almost anything we do bringing in kindness the quality of
kindness is what makes uh patience really possible the real patience
persevering patience it has to be with the softness with the kindness
you know and sometimes meditation is difficult it is unpleasant
you know and we can appreciate that this is hard sometimes sometimes it is hard
and and uh when things are painful and hard uh kindness is appropriate you know
it's it's like we uh bring that into our our space you know oh yeah this is I'm
suffering here this is hard you know my body's uncomfortable I'm in pain I just
I don't like doing this I don't you know at this moment this this moment I don't like you know oh yeah I'm suffering here
I can bring kindness and compassion to that moment
it's a couple of things you know sometimes when we're feeling that way it's hard to put our arms around it we
may have kind of an intellectual understanding of it so you can help to just remember that the first part of
working with this impatient stay is to recognize it
just recognize that it's there that already gives us a little bit of objectivity oh it's just impatience it's
only impatience it's just something that comes and goes you know and then we turn to our bodies you know this is
impatience in the body and we start getting interested in what is it really like what is it like to be impatient
sometimes focusing on a bigger picture can be really helpful sometimes that directness
doesn't quite work for us and for instance we can be stuck in in gridlock for
instance and we can instead of being all caught up in oh my how much longer and
it's going to take forever and all those kind of thoughts you know oh what a great opportunity to practice you know
we sometimes go I only have half an hour here I'm going to sneak it in now this is a great time to practice
um you know or if if you feel tight you know you can bring loving kindness into
into your space I know uh people uh some people who make it a habit whenever
they're stuck even at a red light they just like and look around and do loving kindness towards the people they see in
the other cars you know it's this very sweet thing to do it makes it a kind of
a joyous a choice thing to to happen
um you know or you can just settle into just meditating just watching the breath
open eye you know just just just want to make sure I say that
I gave um uh walking instructions once you know and um and at the end of The Walking
instructions they send people out to go for their walk and one of the young men said um
do we do this with our eyes closed it didn't never occur to me
um you know um and one of the things said to me is always a go-to and I'm suffering is
humor um like Chad cornfield used to say I'll be the first meditator to die of
impatience yeah and um I would just think of that you know and it would just kind of you
know break break a little bit of my serious seriousness out
um there's a cartoon you know it's in the New Yorker a long time ago and
um you know you see this group of meditators and um you know the teachers sitting in a Podium just like this and you know
there's like a poster you know it says journey to Enlightenment you know and then they have a little thought bubble
one of the mid I mean voice bubble one of The meditators Whispers to another one are we there yet
so a little bit of humor
so a kind of close relative of impatience is boredom
um boredom if you haven't noticed it's a state none of us like
we don't like to be bored and if we look at boredom a little bit more closely we
see that often what's happening is that the mind has very little stimulation
going on you know if we're in pain we're not bored we may not like it but we're
definitely not bored but in boredom there's just very low stimulation now in daily life in Norm in
regular life usually when we're bored we either go to sleep or we go do something different you know
we stimulate ourselves and as we get calm the Mind begins to
get calm it stops stimulating itself so much with all this thinking all that's going on
and we initially that calmness it's a little bit unfamiliar it's it's
not what we're used to during the day and it can feel really boring you know
is this it I mean you know I've been meditating and it's this sin it just says yeah a little bit of calm but hey
you know this isn't Fun you know and so um you know so there's a little bit of
something unpleasant not enough something going on in that state
and again we can turn our attention right to the boredom we can get
interested in the boredom what is boredom really like what is it really
like you know what is it like in what's the flavor of the mind that we don't like what is that flavor you know I really
notice how what that feels like what does it feel like in the body sometimes it's actually there's actually other
things going on underneath but it's not thinking about it and figuring it out it's like really seeing what is this
moment really like what am I resisting what don't I like what am I pushing away
um I read somewhere I don't know where they get these statistics but um 31 of Americans
wonder if heaven will be boring
um now what's interesting about it is that
um you know when we think of heaven we think of everything being good and everybody being nice
you know and you know it says something that we think that everybody being good
and everybody being nice is boring you know so we look all we have to do is
look at her entertainment and you know we're um what sells the most are horror movies
uh war movies violent uh Thrillers all this uh things that aren't good and nice
you know um and so even a lot of humor is about you
know you think about um uh slapstick you know people are falling you know uh a lot of humors put
down humor laughing at pain or laughing at other people's pain you know it's um
so there's something about all those things are very stimulating to the mind and the mind really likes being
stimulated and uh boy with no devices really stimulate us
we prefer a lot of us prefer Doom scrolling
looking at bad news after bad news after bad news for long periods of times over
being bored over that terrible horrible feeling of being bored let me look at how horrible
the disasters in the world are there's so much more stimulating than being bored so it's really interesting you
know to look at this at these aspects of mind
so we're used to um you know either stimulating ourselves externally
you know by the we can do it um as I mentioned you know in unskillful
ways watching things that are actually dark in our minds or we can
stimulate ourselves externally with wholesome things you know watching a movie that that has a lot of depth
reading a biography that connects us with people listening to wonderful music
having meeting with friends there's lots of wonderful stimuli out in the world
going out into nature going hiking there's a lot of wholesome things it's
not I'm not pointing at being wrong to stimulate the mind you know that's how
we learn that's how we grow you know it's really great for the cognitive mind
to stimulate it in ways that are productive um but we also stimulate the Mind
internally and how do we do that you know we can
stimulate the Mind internally with planning you know which can be really useful or it can be compulsively uh done
in a minute during meditation in particular sometimes especially in Retreat I find
myself like planning when I was going to say to the teacher when I met with them over and over and over again and just
kind of rehearsing you know this is what I'm going to say to them and and um you know and totally missing out on
my process just planning planning planning um
so so we do stimulate ourselves internally um and because we like stimulus
um
sometimes just to avoid feeling boredom we'd rather we'll stimulate ourselves
with really uh thoughts that upset us even more because we'd rather have
upsetting thoughts than um then be bored
one of the things that happens you know with um giving something attention when we
become attentive of the Mind energy arises
when energy arises kind of Interest follows
um and so we um by turning our attention to boredom
that we bring energy to it and we bring interest and or the quality of or beingness kind
of increases in its uh um in its energy and its aliveness we
start getting connected with ourselves just by giving attention just an open
attention to what's really going on in the moment um
knowing boredom just knowing it really being close to it
transforms it into something interesting
and um you know when I say just one word about intimacy you know if you think about an
intimate moment you know maybe you know a young child or a lover you know where
you're maybe touching their face very gently you're very close to them you're very close to you know you you're right
there you're very soft there's there's no distance between the two of you and
this is the intimacy that we develop in meditation it's a little bit of a love
affair with with with the moment you know just being very close very close to
that breath very intimate very very open to it you know and if you touch if if
the if what you're touching is a child that starts to cry because they're sad that you don't lose that intimacy
because they're sad you don't lose their intimacy because they're laughing you know the intimacy
is there because of your willingness to be close your willingness to be connected that way
and in the same way you know we can be intimate with our experience being very close to it whether it's laughter
whether it's a wonderful sense of peace permeating or whether it's a really
agitated mind just like the agitated child we can stay intimate
you know in the um 60s
Aldous Huxley wrote a novel I don't know if anybody ever read read it called Island
you know it was like a utopian novel you know I I don't remember hardly any of it
you know I was pretty young and but I remember it had birds that flew around
and you know they they'd go near humans and go pay attention pay attention
and it's one of the things that that periodically shows up in my meditation
when I'm distracted you know it's uh
um so um you know many of you um are familiar with mbsr mindfulness-based stress
reduction it's um secular mindfulness meditation program
that junk about Sin created in the when did he do that in
the early 80s you know for the medical community to
make mindfulness available to people who were having you know major surgeries
cancer diagnoses terminal terminal illnesses you know and so it needed to
be you know very very secular very specific and they would they do it in like
sessions of eight eight weekly trainings
and it encompassed you know sitting meditation similar to what we do here
but it also included a guided body scan that's done lying
down where it guides you through relaxing each part of your body connecting with each part of your body
and it lasts about 45 minutes it's a long long guided scan
and um at the time that it was just beginning to take off and gains a little
bit of renown in the medical world the teacher said IMS which is a retreat
center in Massachusetts they thought well you know while we're you know we should know about this so
why don't we do the training and so we know how it is and so we know what people are doing you know and so several
of the teachers went to this class where they were the only people who didn't have either a thermal illness or
something severe really going on in their lives and you know they they did the sitting
meditation everything you know and then they went to do the guided the guided body scan and everybody in the room laid
down and did this and um every one of the teachers fell asleep
uh none of the students none of the other students and
um you know and one of the teachers was for you know after that she was reflecting back about it and she
realized that what had happened in in her practice or you know after all the years of like lots of Duke and lots of
suffering her practices gotten to a point and her life where everything was pretty good everything was was pretty
good she'd sit and meditate was pretty Pleasant it was kind of nice and she'd
become really complacent and um and it's it's such a tricky
seductive little thing you know to just oh yeah it's good enough it's good enough you know not that you know we
don't want to mistake it with the mind that says that's never good enough you know but but there's this quality of it
of of where we stop um uh we stop really paying attention to
what's going on and um a definition of complacency is
self-satisfaction especially when accompanied by unawareness of actual dangers or
deficiencies so what does that mean in meditation
and it's not seeing the dangers of
reinforcing certain habits of mind which gets strengthened when we become complacent
we just strengthen the part of our minds that don't pay attention
um the teachings guide us to allow our
experience to accept or experience not to strive not to push not to have to
really be at ease with or experience but again that comes back to the issue of
intimacy when we allow we accept we allow and
accept something by being close to it by being intimate with it you know we
allow it accept that my my body hurts right now oh yeah my body's hurting you
know we're close I feel it I'm not pushing it away I'm right there with it
allowing it I see the reality of it complacency says oh yeah it's hurting I
don't have to pay I'm not going to pay attention to it I'm not going to be near it you know it's a distancing ourselves
from our experience
um you know the practice points to a balance between tranquility and
alertness we're trying to you know we kind of go to a meeting of those two where the mind is really at peace but
really bright and alert really curious and the words that I like that that have
been like a guiding guiding words for me in my practice is so much and tomato he
calls that affectionate curiosity it's it's the quality that we want to
bring into those moments that's what's missing in the complacency complacency
doesn't have either the affection or the Curiosity it's just kind of nice or good
enough um like those first 15-20 minutes of my
sitting oh yeah that's good enough you know good enough
um
you know when um some people when they first start meditating you know they take to it right away and they like it right away
and and they have nice pleasant sits right away that wasn't me you know for
me meditation was really hard earned you know the fact that I persevered was I
just had a such a strong intuition in you know in me I had a certain level of
trust that that this was the way for me even though mostly my first
quite a fairly long period of time was not very pleasant for me
and so when I finally finally started experiencing like this really nice
periods of calm you know and they'd go into this nice drifty peaceful calm
they're so nice it was so nice and there was so little sharpness or alertness but
it was such a pleasant change from from my agitated state that I I hung in there
for a long time and you know and it was very healing you know it was very healing for me to
do that and um and it allowed me just be feel enjoy
being with myself you know but as my practice grew then I saw that uh there
was more there was more and more engagement you know I don't want to make that wrong you know but then I would
find my patterns you know like I would be um like especially in Retreat you know if
any of you have done Retreat we have a lot of ups and downs on Retreats sometimes we have uh you know a lot of
stuff can come up and sometimes really painful emotions would come up or really
intense physical Sensations would come up that weren't Pleasant you know and and you know maybe I'd spend
um you know like spend a couple of uh sittings just crying or or just feeling
all sorts of painful feelings and then it would be over and it'd be like ah
and then I'd reward myself with a fantasy you know it's like okay that was good enough I worked hard fantasy time
you know and uh you know and I kind of had that pattern for a while where I'd get really complacent instead of like
really okay now let's stay really engaged with what's next um so it took a while for me to see that
to notice that um
you know and as I mentioned I really want to stress that that as we meet complacency when it arises to really
notice a difference between that and not good enough you know it's um you know like the the
Taipei personality or the workaholic personality you know they'd get a lot
done you know they accomplish a lot uh but it's very tight very tight you know
and so um really you want to caution that attitude in in how we work with our
minds um we're more aiming for the quality of a musician really enjoying playing the
music but really be really listening to carefully not doing it automatically
really you know maybe they fight that song a hundred times but they still find something new in it
or maybe the the runner you know really engaged in the running and they might
notice oh yeah my shoulders are a little tense let me relax them a little bit
or maybe the artist who's you know painting you know and and um you know they they notice oh the
sunset could use a little more red over here you make adjustments but the adjustments are just part of the play part of the
play part of the engagement it's not that there's something wrong that we have to fix it's just an
adjustment always see that okay that's what we do there's no fixing needed we
don't need to fix complacency we don't need to fix some patience we just need
to get to know them and once we get to know them as we engage in them they reveal themselves
they transform
one of them real benefits of turning towards the challenging towards the
difficult in this practice this practice says if it's hard you turn towards it
you turn towards it we turn towards the wonderful we turn towards the difficult with the equal interest we can bring the
equal interest to it and by doing so by developing patients
we increase our capacity to be with a difficult I like to say we become comfortable
being uncomfortable we we can you know tolerate
be there for things that are very hard to tolerate and be there for and it and that capacity works both ways
it increases her ability to feel Joy to feel all the really wholesome happy
enjoyable things in life it allows that connection to so we increase that that practice of of
really being here fully full-heartedly into the moment
you know and I'll say the last thing I'll say you know sometimes the magic word for me in my mind is to relax just
relax let go and at other times the magic word for me
is like a very strong here now you know just here now show up you know and so
different times we we need like different little um this is my level of my pep talks to
myself usually these little singular little little words I shortcut them you
know that um you know I might sit up straight or pay attention you know little birds you
know pay attention you know um so you know keep folding in
everything that happens in the practice belongs it all belongs you know the the deeper states of mind
you know when you um we develop samadhi the the in meditation where the mind's really
steady we call it a unification of the Mind where the mind is United
and it includes everything and that's the thing about this practice
it does not exclude any part of who we are any part of our experience it all
fits in there it all belongs um
so I'd like to end with a poem by
Rosemary watola traumer I don't know if you know her work
um
so in in May I planted a whole row of beans
along the back fins of the garden pushed each of the small white seeds one
inch into the spring damp soil I waited weeks not one came up not one
I planted them again planted them in twos two inches apart
I waited weeks three came up there were over a hundred seeds
I'm trying to tell you that sometimes that we wish for doesn't happen
though we do everything by the rules that we have known success before
that we long for our plans to take for our plans to take root
to bloom to fruit then all through the rows
emerged this spring emerged this spring dozens of volunteer Cosmos
this morning a generous Riot of pink dark pink and white fluttering in the
spaces where I envisioned only the green of beans
so thank you