this so like this I suppose yeah there you go hi I'm Michael from San Jose Milo
Michael Michael Alex from Vancouver BC
Alex yeah oh from Vancouver fantastic well welcome welcome
Jim Bill Natalie Michael and Alex and I'm Diana
at least today I am we'll see you how I am later so thank
you all for that so
turn on the recording so last week I spoke a little bit about
this concept of not self and I thought I'd build a little bit on that
and that is this idea that or the teaching or that
realization or the notion that we there we don't have like a core we don't have
an Essence oh are you looking for this here we go
we don't have a core or an essence unto Which
experiences get added it's not like we have this thing in the middle that stays the same
that then I guess it tastes good food comes from meditation or
speaks into a microphone that doesn't work necessarily there there isn't like this core thing
that experiences get added onto instead there's just experiences that's
all there is and this is one of the key teachings of the Buddha and it's one of the characteristics of
things and people that they don't have this inherent stable
core or Essence this is a teaching that's a little bit
difficult to understand and sometimes it feels a little bit silly
because like well of course of course things have existence I'm here you guys are there there's
chairs there there's a bell here but we're talking about there's not a
permanent unchanging core Essence at the middle
is that it's just a collection a collection of experiences all kinds of like
experiences being anything that arises in the senses including the mind
so one thing I wanted to talk about a little bit today is these like misconceptions some of these ideas that
we might have about the teachings of not self that when we hear this we might like
misinterpret it we might think well let me something else and this is something from Jack
cornfield and he writes that um sometimes there's this idea that okay
well there's this egocentric or there's this self-centered
ego and we have to get rid of that but that's not not actually right
because it's not there's nothing to get rid of it's not actually there this is like an
old religious idea that some religions have that there's like this bad part that has to be gotten rid of and there's
this good part that has to get rid of the bad part so that's not what we're talking about
here when we talk about not self-teachings it's uh this idea that we have to get
rid of a bad part is sometimes like why there's aesthetic practices or why sometimes people will do some extreme
things as they think that it's going to purify or get rid of or something that's
unwanted part of themselves but that's not how the Buddhists see this practice
it also this idea of not self doesn't mean that there's this inner sense of
apathy or meaninglessness it doesn't feel like there's
it doesn't mean and it doesn't feel like there's this emotional poverty we might
say that there's just this uh sense of
hollowness as opposed to some Vitality or juiciness
or um some some thing that uh
it's going to say innervates us or excites us instead there's this way in
which we might have this feeling that there's this lack of well-being inside and that somehow
that's what's being pointed to when we talk about not self it really couldn't be further from the
truth or than the experience so we might hear these and feel like oh there's a reason
in which we might have this um sense of like inside of ourselves might
feel a little bit hungry or desolate or something like
that and that's really is not what's getting pointed to with the not self teachings and I'll talk a little bit
more about that sometimes when we hear this we might think oh yeah I do have this inner
hollowness that's inside that and so I must be on the right spiritual practice
or write spiritual path but that's not what's being pointed to
and it's it's this idea or this teaching this experience of not self also is not
an excuse to withdraw from life it's not a way to reinforce any of these
maybe underlying depressive feelings like where we kind
of feel diminished and don't really have energy to be with the world or nor do we even want to want to be with the world
or maybe we even have this fear of the world or maybe we have this lack of motivation
so not self is not pointing to that either
maybe one thing I'll say is that these not self-teachings are not suggesting
that we should like wipe out any of the ways in which we can function in our
lives in a way that we can get up get dressed have a breakfast go
to work or you know do or stay home at work or do whatever it is that we're going to do with our days
so it's absolutely not pointing to that either that somehow we would like lose capacities that we have or
the way that we can just run our lives I'm trying to think of a
way to say that but just our normal way of operating not self-teachings is not
pointing to like okay we're gonna get rid of that or somehow it's going to fall away
in contrast to some of these ideas that we might have
this uh joy and freedom is what
characterizes the experience of not self so it's this joy and freedom that's
getting pointed to when you talk about not self this maybe this beautiful spaciousness or this
unburdening that arises
and so we definitely need to like honor our personal identities so we're not
saying that to get rid of those either with us at not self-teaching
so that we can recognize the Deep patterns and the archetypes that we have that make up our individuality and then
honor them and transform them in a way that really
support us and so this practice is about how we can do this transformation so
we're not getting rid of anything or discarding something or
throwing something away instead it's it's all about a transformation
so some of these uh personal identities or maybe we have like this uh a critical
intellect there's a way that we use that to have some discriminating wisdom
that helps us with this path of practice or maybe we have this appreciation and
desire for beauty maybe you're an artist then we use that as a way to notice and
build and cultivate Harmony to use this force that creates Harmony so that we're not in contention with our
experience or maybe that we have this capacity for
this intuition of a way of sensing the way things are then we can transform that into a
capacity for healing ourselves and others being sensitive to what's needed
next so again this not self-teaching is not pointing to that we have to abandon or
somehow be different than how we are it's more of a transformation that
allows This Joy and freedom that arises
so and to be sure that it's strong and healthy sense of self is needed for this
about the practice definitely required in part of this path
of practice is developing this strong and healthy sense of self
part of the reasons why we need a strong healthy sense of self is part of that is just the developmental course of a human
is to have a distinct sense of self the Buddha certainly had that he had no uh
confusion about who he was he had no confusion about what he did or was going
to do or anything like that used to the personal pronoun all over the place in his teachings so he certainly had his
very strong sense of self had a sense of boundaries this is appropriate this is not appropriate
and so for us having a strong sense of self really supports that in some
meditative experiences regular can start to be a sense of dissolution a
fading away or maybe even pixelating or something like a sense of self
can be a meditative experience and this can be really disorienting or even
frightening if a person doesn't already have a strong sense of self so we need
one as we so that as we go deeper into this practice and not start having more
experiences that they it doesn't derail us or frighten us or confuse us or
make us run away or because we feel like oh I'm
definitely going the wrong direction or something like this
so the interesting thing is this development of a strong sense of self
as well as a greater recognition or realization of not self so that this
recognition that there isn't this this core or this Essence at the inherent or inside any of us that's
permanent and going along with us in our life these two ideas evolve together
so a strong sense of self supports this insight into not self having experience
into not self also supports him in a strong sense of self and in our path of practice there might
be times in which or Seasons we might say in which uh one or the other of
those are emphasized but they're definitely part of the practice both of them are part of the practice
but one thing is you know sometimes when we hear these teachings about not self we might think like
either like some puzzlement like really what I certainly feel like I have a self
I'm not quite sure what they're talking about those Buddhists so I appreciate very much that uh Andy
olensky he's a scholar and an author he wrote uh something about he's uh he
titled this article said I think I am and he pointed to different ways in
which we think that we are I think it can be helpful to point these
so one Andy olinski says I feel like the occupant of my body
okay this makes sense that when we like stand or sit in one location
like everything around us seems like it's relative to us like that's farther
and this thing is near and that's to the right and that's to the left so it seems
like everything is like we're the center and everything's around us
and when we walk when we go somewhere right the center moves kind of like the
whole world is kind of like moving with us in some kind of way
like intellectually we understand that uh it doesn't it's not exactly like that
but if we're if we're just with our experience we will notice that what's near and far of course is adjusting as
we're moving through space so we're still the center
and so there's a way in which we might view this body as the basis of this world that's surrounds us
we might even say the world that we're constructing so the first one is I feel like the
occupant of my body is the first way in which we feel like we have a self
the second is I have a strong sense of being the beneficiary of the feeling tones
when things are Pleasant or unpleasant I'm the one that enjoys things that are
Pleasant and when they're unpleasant I'm the one that wants to get rid of the things that
are unpleasant and when the we feel like maybe I'm the victim of the pain or of the discomfort
I'm the one to whom it happens so when there's Pleasant or unpleasant
or neutral experiences we feel like oh that we are the beneficiary
for whether it's positive or negative of those feeling tones
and then the third one is I am a person who expresses myself
I am the artiste I find there's so many different ways in
which we express ourselves you know artistically or just speaking or writing
or sending emails or the way that we dress the cars that we
drive there's so many different ways in which we express ourselves so we might feel
like that we're the ones that are expressing something something unique
about ourselves and we might even feel like
no matter like how humble these creations are or maybe even how subtle they are there's a sense that they are
uniquely coming from us like nobody else could do it like
like just from only I could do this only you could do this only you could do whatever it is that
you do and then this the fourth one is I feel
like an agent I feel like the one who makes choices
I I feel like the one that has the decision and affection and responsibility and moving through the
world doing things and I inherit that and consequences of those things
that's the fourth one and then the fifth one is I have the view that I am some sort
of essence this idea that well it seems like
there's a continuous sense of self inside so maybe it is permanent
or maybe the sense of that there's just something inside around which everything
else congeals but there's something inside that's
feels like the heart of what's unfolding
of whatever it is means to be me
for some of you might have recognized there's these five ways in which we might we feel like
I am that we that we have a sense of self
the Buddha categorized all experiences into groups of five Andy olinsky I kind of I appreciate he
used the language to put this into something that we can relate to different ways these five different ways
in which we feel like we have a sense of self we could say this one way in which we
are constructing a sense of self or we feel like we have one is we feel like the center of experience
the beneficiary of feeling tones the artiste the agent and
the essence some of you will recognize that this is
the five aggregates the Buddhist teaching on these psychophysical
expressions or experiences five different
aspects of what it means to have experiences and as humans we often in one of these
five ways we feel like a self things where there's a certain type of clinging onto one of these five
Aggregates and I'm not going to go into the details about the aggregates
this all that really matters is that there's five different ways in which we can hold on to something some part of
our experience and it's that holding on that's creating a sense of self in that moment
but there's a way in which right to all of those experiences of course are not
constant they're changing all the time and they're unfolding
without any Essence without any
core they're just unfolding there isn't a me that's making them
happen whose experiences aren't mine I don't
own them I'm not controlling them they're just arising and passing away
and we're clinging to them in a really subtle way and it's the
subtle way that makes us believe that we have this sense of self
and the sense of self is always changing depending on what it is that we're Clinging On whether we're the
beneficiary of feeling tones or whether we're the artiste or we're the one who is expressing or the one who is doing
so this sense of self is actually just a collection of
the variations of these five different types of experiences
so rather than a core this Essence there's just five different types of experiences that are always
changing and this this is The Human Experience
and so but what I describe to you is kind of like this more conceptual way of
understanding it and some of the Buddha's teachings certainly are conceptual certainly in this tradition it's these
aren't like philosophical but maybe there's a way in which it's more
helpful to feel into this experience of self or
not self and certainly that's been my experience
is that it's more of an meditative experiences that helped me to really understand what's being pointed to
because intellectually or conceptually these paradigms like of the five aggregates
I don't know they've okay I guess you know I just didn't when I heard them I
felt like okay am I supposed to believe this what am I supposed to do with this
so it wasn't until I you know I had some meditative experiences and started to feel like some of the freedom that's
possible when the clinging gets less and less and less and less right the suffering is
diminishing and more and more Freedom more and more ease
so there's this way that we can go beyond like the intellect and instead have this like this visceral embodied
experience of not self so rather than a theoretical or abstract
exploration so when we are
sensitive to the sense of self or not self
well actually I think I'd rather like point to this with a poem
and this poem is entitled zazen many of you will recognize it know that
this word this is individuals in the Zen Community the zod's and is the word that says
meditation practice sitting in meditation and this was written by a practitioner
perhaps beef Virginia Hamilton Adair she was in the
Zen tradition and maybe we can imagine that she's describing what happens
during a retreat
and maybe I'll make one explanatory note uh early in the poem she uses the
expression Saratoga trunk and that's just like one of these big uh
trunks that we could imagine that long ago people were like put on the
ships when they were going across the ocean or something like this big giant uh
giant suitcase we might think something like that okay so here we go zazen by Virginia
Hamilton Adair and I learned about this poem from Brian lessage I should say
when I first floundered in no one knew me not even myself
staggering under a Saratoga trunk crammed with humiliations bottled like
urine samples nail kegs of anger carbons of abusive letters chemistry quizzes
with F's even the horse I never had and two casseroles left over from the
diamond dip supper no one remarked that I had brought too
much I was wearing three fur hats donated by
opulent cousins my feet encased in cement ever since the failure of the
patio project and my mouth full of barbs as an old trout
no one praised my appearance
the trunk fell off my back disgorging its unusual contents at my stone feet
which also came off the fur had stumbled like a moth eaten
Avalanche bearing a small Monk
no one noticed my sweat began to dry
I folded myself into one piece no one
that's the end of the poem the love of the sway right that all
these things that we put in these trunks that we carry around these memories these things that we are making up the
sense of what we think it means to be me things that entangle us with this sense
of self that we get tangled with the stories and the narratives about what it means
things that happened to us before I appreciate so much in this poem
he talks about like these casseroles from this dinner or the horse she never
had or grades she got and and chemistry
so these stories that we mean like what does it mean how we were as a student are you really smart or maybe not so
smart or these casseroles maybe we're a good cook a bad cook or maybe nobody
likes our cooking whatever it might be but we think that these things Define Us in some ways
and we carry them around and it's heavy it's burdensome
so there's nothing wrong about having narratives with our life but it's the of
course we have narratives about our life right we want our lives to make sense so we create these narratives
we need them but what's being pointed to is the
clinging to them the way that we can we can
pick them up but can we also put them down when they're not needed
because there's a way in which we start accumulating all these ideas about ourselves and things that it means to be
our set what it means to be me and then we have this contraction this clinging
binding tension stress this way in which we feel limited we feel penned in we
feel imprisoned we feel burdened by this sense of self
and we're so used to it we don't even notice it
until we have some other experiences some of them may be in meditation but we
all have Expressions maybe of ah beautiful sunsets seen big vast expenses
of Ocean City being on a Mountaintop and seen for large distances there's a way
in which the sense of self often diminishes there and we can have this bigger sense of what's possible
but it might mean to be a human so instead we might have this
experience of this ease or spaciousness or flexibility or
softening allowing relief freedom
for this type of healing or this strong sense of like just putting down
everything that's extra and it turns out everything is extra
we can just pick things up when they're needed and put them down
and so this not self-teaching is pointing to this movement from feeling imprisoned and trapped by this idea of
what it means to be me and instead to align with notice be
sensitive to just the flowy nature of experience things are unfolding
and there's a caricature there's a there's a an
individual who makes decisions and then does things but it's more of a flowing
as opposed to this stayed self that's at the center and making things happen and
to which things happen so this idea or this notion of not self
it's not a belief that we have to adopt it's not something that we have to
pretend or make force ourselves in any way that's just pointing to a potential
potential for all of us as the sense of self softens
and this will happen right is it in when we're doing our favorite things dancing
to our favorite music humming maybe when we're doing sports or dancing
and these types of things when there's there's not so much self-centeredness or self-consciousness
pointing to the same thing the same movement not self-teaching
so maybe I'll end there and open it up and see if there's any
comments or questions thank you
now I know now I know your names I can I can call on you I want to worry
any comments or questions you don't have to but
I just like to make this space in case you do you're thinking okay
Bill's trying to come up with a doozy of a comment
we we don't have to we don't have oh Alex has a
all those people online okay
um I think my question is like I've been meditating for about two and a half three years like kind of
more seriously and before that I meditated sort of on and off
um do you think could you talk a little bit about how like the experience of not self might
like evolve over time as we meditate more
how it might evolve over time or how it maybe evolved for you yeah maybe I'll
say this that sometimes uh when we maybe this is part of the way that I
think about it and I end up using this little analogy and all kinds of different uh teachings this idea of a
children's slide or you know a slide that's in the playground so there's a ladder up and then there's a slide that
goes down so often there's effort that uh you know for this slide it has to go up and often
there's a sense of self that's like okay I have to do this I have to cultivate this I have to develop that I'm
you know we have all these lists right a full path some factors Awakening all this kind of stuff right
so there's a sense of self that's developing and cultivating qualities and
behaving ethically meditating all this kind of stuff so that is probably like
maybe doing the sense of uh getting up onto the top of the slide but then
there's a a way in which oh things are just unfolding
there's a sense that not so much effort and this can be experienced a little bit of maybe in concentration States when
the when the mind and the body start to settle it doesn't have to be really giant concentration States but sense of
settling then there can just be a sense of sometimes you use this expression
effortless effort that's more like oh things are happening
but I'm not like making it happen I'm here I'm not a victim it's not happening
to me but there's this ease and just this way of flowing with what's arising
does this make sense you're welcome
okay
lately I've thought that I would like to cut through the philosophical Thicket of
weather there's a self or not and instead just think of not self this
way whenever I think in terms of myself I create my own suffering oh
and I think that relates to something that you said but maybe you'd
like for you to remind me of what you said about when when you have concepts
of self you you're trapped yeah did you say that yeah yeah can you
kind of reiterate or elaborate yeah so often these ideas of self-rich there are
limits right I'm a person who likes vanilla but I don't like chocolate and
you know I'm a person that does this but doesn't that every time we Define something about ourselves implicit in
that is what we're not and some of that might be true but there's also a way that we're kind of
like defining or imprisoning or trapping ourselves as opposed to yeah allowing
kind of like the flowing of experience or something like this your your self-limiting
yeah and then very actually there's a way in which it's a it's a subtle feeling of
contraction too well maybe I should use this word separation when there's a strong sense of self then there's a real
strong sense of me and everybody else so there's a strong sense of separation
and that's also a certain amount of suffering to feel isolated and to feel disconnected from others or from around
and our experience our experience around yeah
thank you Bill great thank you
okay okay so thank you thank you
and maybe I'll just say a warm welcome to to Alex from Vancouver from coming
all the way down here are you here just for friends or family or work or
you're on a road trip excellent is it a Dharma road trip a little bit well welcome I'm sorry that there aren't
more people here on a Memorial Day right here have you been like listening uh online to IMC or something
excellent okay well welcome welcome we're happy later
and what about Michael have you do you come here yeah yeah
nice welcome
and it's a road trip so that's a long drive I can't get all the way down here
oh nice very nice
and Natalie I think you said you're in Mountain View right yeah so not so far away
oh excellent well welcome welcome are happy to have you here have you also
been listening online and then
okay great great so
um I guess if you're if any of you would like to ask me a question not in front of everybody you're welcome to come up
otherwise I wish you all a wonderful rest of the evening thank you