readings friends good morning afternoon evening whatever
your time zone might be wonderful to be with you and to um
practice together as we are as we all join from different places in the world
um so this week we are exploring um
the five Aggregates the five kandas which is one of the important teachings
um of the Buddha and and a way for us to
consider the constituents of our experience of reality to be experienced
with the Gestalt of these five Aggregates these five heaps that's
really the way the word Aggregates can make sense because they come and they they can join together so yesterday we
started with a form um the body form internal external
and um today was touching to form a bit and then continue with with the second one
being vedana or feeling tone so
so let us meditate together and uh and I'll share Reflections afterwards
so let's arrive now let's arrive in this
body In This Moment In Time
humming together different parts of this
Planet this precious Planet coming together
with wholeheartedness
feeling this body this sitting breathing human body
connected to the Earth
feeling our sit bones sensations of
contact
and becoming curious about Sensations
of hardness heaviness pressure
heat and cold
it's often hard to tell where our sit bones or bottom begins and
chair and vice versa the cushion begins
however we can have this this Sensations
spread these vibrations
or the concept of the bottom and the cushion breaks down
it's just Sensations raw Sensations
so many Sensations in our feet and our legs
vibrations pressure
do you notice Heat
the entire lower body feet the legs sit bones
Awash and Sensations
and
including the upper body in the face chest neck shoulders
relaxing relaxing and receiving this flow this
waterfall of Sensations
quite awesome
pausing breaking a break to notice to receive
this miracle
low Sensations here there everywhere
wherever they call your attention
resting enjoying sea of Sensations
rest in it
and the sensations of this thing called the breath or breathing included
known experienced as a flow of Sensations
and allowing awareness to know to be tethered
in the flow of Sensations
both to better see perceive understand
and also for this dream of thoughts to settle a
bit so the heart the mind can become more
stable in our learning in our observation
let the flow of Sensations throughout the body knowing this have premising
relax and receive
vibrations pressure
love hate coolness
asked for this
period of the in-breath can we make
the sensations
of the body primary
really receiving this giving it our complete
tension just during this Ingress
and then renewing a resolve
for just this Opera completely dedicated devoted to knowing
the sensations of the body throughout during this out breath
just this and then renewing our intention our dedication again
one in breath out breath at a time
heroic dedication but just for a tiny
bit of time and then renewing and then renewing
I need packets of heroic dedication strung together
just this in-breath Justice out breath
just for the duration not this in breath so
or the out breath
as awareness perceives
the flow of Sensations let us now so open to knowing
whether there is whether a sensation that is known as
pleasant
or unpleasant
and if it's neither then it's neither Pleasant nor unpleasant the third
category become aware become sensitive to how
the mind is labeling
is perceiving given Sensations
and don't let it be so effortful trying to categorize every sensation let it be
relaxed
as your knowing Sensations still come to you you'll all of a sudden you're see oh
yeah that's Pleasant that's unpleasant
it's neither
becoming sensitive sensitized to know in this way
to know your experience your Human Experience
in this particular way
Pleasant unpleasant neither
there may also be sounds
that are known and whether they're Pleasant unpleasant or neither
as well as mental objects thoughts streaming through are they Pleasant unpleasant or neither notice notice
how the mind is relating to them labeling them they're vedana their feelings Pleasant
unpleasant neutral
really turning into this overlay of pleasant unpleasant or neutral
for the flow of experience
and how it impacts
colors or experience these labelings
as we keep tuning
as we keep tuning into knowing
feeling tone vedana Pleasant unpleasant or neither
star two notice it everywhere starts to pop up
reconstructing the nature of our experience
and as we bring this meditation to a cause together
bowing and releasing whatever it was or wasn't
without judgment and only with appreciation
that we have brought ourselves with wholeheartedness
to plant seeds and trusting that they were
come to fruition in their own time not our time
May our practice together be of benefit to all beings everywhere including
myself may all beings be happy and free
thank you for your practice everyone
greetings all lovely to be with you in this moment in time
always makes my heart just so happy but technology allows us to come together
from so many different places and yet we come
together it's so sweet so sweet
so this week as we are exploring the
[Music] um the the five Aggregates the five condos
these five constituents of our experienced the Gestalt
of which really creates our reality what we consider our Human Experience or
human reality is made up of these five nothing else which is quite profound what the Buddha
has included in the five and it's not just what the Buddha has included but but really as you as a human being
yourself it's not so much a teaching to to like something to take on faith but
any stretch at all it's not to take these five condos as Faith but just to experience for yourself yeah these are
my the five constituents of my experience it's pretty wild when you really pay attention it's just this it's
just it's just this so we started yesterday with introduction and we had some time also
to to uh talk about um form Rupa
um and and there was a piece left over that I wanted to cover today
um before talking more about vadana so so with the discussions with the teachings on Rupa and form
uh often it is related relayed through the four elements and I talked about
four elements inside four elements outside as these elements I talked about
that enter so there's one way that this teaching is is relayed in terms of
elements inside elements outside and I talked about that and and that we are Stardust remember and there is a second
way that this teaching can be uh related to these four elements and that is in a
phenomenological way which is through the first person experience not in terms of what's inside what's outside this
this physical science uh conception of the world what's inside what's outside
but through the phenomena terminological lens of our experience which is our
first person experience of being human beside because that's really all we know
we um we can assert what's in the world but it's really through our lens it's
through our conception and perception so another way to relate to form is is for
example for the body is through our Sensations is through the flow of our
Sensations that we sense our experience of the word and of course if we were another animal another being our
sensation of the world our perception of the world would be very very different and and
um there's this wonderful book that came out uh last year I believe
um uh it's um it's by Ed young and it's called an immense World many maybe one
of you is familiar can put it in chat and this book beautifully talks about different animals having different um
given their perception given their their sensory uh system their sensory
apparatus they have a very different perception of the word umweld of the
world so given that we're human our phenomena analogical experience of the world this is a particular way
so so for us for example uh in our bodies there are mechanoreceptors The
receptors that detect stimuli such as touch and pressure and vibration that's
our experience you know there's really no experience of hand or leg or breath
it's really these these mechanoreceptors as well as the nociceptors that
um are receptors specializing in detecting pain and noxious stimuli such
as in the in both throughout the body including the skin muscles and organs as
well as thermoreceptors of course the cold receptors and warm receptors that we have throughout our bodies and
proprio receptors that inform us what the position of our body and body parts
are and baroreceptors detect changes in blood pressure Etc so
through many many receptors many receptors that we have so the phenomenological experience of
this world this is really the the four elements practice is also taught through
the What's called the 12 characteristics method and the 12 characteristics method
is just sensing these raw Sensations pushing heat cold heaviness lightness
these are the characteristics that I'm naming uh there are 12 characteristics they're in the visudi Maga the path of
purification teaching a thousand page book I think somewhere behind me it's that middle one the the thickest one so
it's another way to experience or practice the four elements practiced through this phenomenological way of
knowing the world so so I wanted to bring that in because sometimes the four elements practice is
only taught as inside outside and the elements but actually this these 12 characteristics through their our
phenomenology of our experience is is a very important way it's also taught through these 12 characteristics and and
just the raw Sensations that that we have so so and and we can tune into the uh
constitution of our experience again the concept of body and leg and arm all of
that drops away when we just experience it through these Sensations when the
mind gets very concentrated in fact it starts to feel like just points in space it's there's no location there's no it's
just Sensations in space now this other important constitution of
our experience which is vedana feeling tone which I invited you to turn towards today
is um is is a fundamentally important uh
aspect of our experience um and we often miss it it's so important that
we often miss it and we actually uh miss it in the fall in in this way I miss it in that we something is Pleasant or
unpleasant and then we just we take it to be that and then
the Mind develops a preference for it like it don't like it hate it make it go
away and then narrative start we get into these Loops of thinking and thought
whereas a very very powerful tool
is to Simply notice that a stimuli
the mind is labeling it as Pleasant unpleasant or neither and this
neither this third category by the way some people try to keep looking for the neutral oh is this neutral is not
neutral well if it's neither Pleasant nor unpleasant then it's just neither is that neither category so I've had some
practitioners get a little uh wound up by this third category it's it's simpler
than you think but when you tune into seeing the the uh how the mind is
labeling stimulus as either Pleasant or unpleasant
it can lead to not getting wound up by it not getting
tripped by it so um and also there are many aspects to this
practice to the value to it one is
sometimes for example we hear say a a loud noise right and the mind labels
that noise that sound let's say that sound as unpleasant okay so these are
happening very very quickly in succession every mind month sound arises there's contact with the sound that
awareness makes contact with the sound and and uh this labeling of of
unpleasant arises so Pasa is contact arises and then vedana which is this
labeling the Mind labels in the particular way given the mood it's in
given all the previous history we have had Etc it's very so so these labels these vedanas are kind of Laden with
with causes and conditions um so the Mind labels in a particular way and then
if we don't we don't usually notice that so much but then what happens after that labeling is like oh I don't like it then
pushing starts I don't like this then then uh we cling we push it away cling
to not liking it and make it go away Etc et cetera Etc so an amazing practice is
especially if you notice that you are in a doom Loop in a loop
just notice what just noticed the vedana of of what it's just unpleasant it's
just unpleasant maybe even oh sweetheart it's just unpleasant can I be with the
unpleasant it's just unpleasant vedana is just unpleasant fade enough
and this practice is so powerful so powerful to completely unhook unhook the
the selfing the me mind the mind getting all tied up like it's it's awful I don't
like it I hate it make it go away it's just unpleasant feeling tone
dear um try this practice for yourself it's
really powerful it can happen with anything any stimulus sounds Sensations uh pain
in the body is just unpleasant deer it's just unpleasant feeling tone even bring
the word vedanine because it brings more specificity it's just uh unpleasant fade
enough it's just unpleasant fate enough that's all unpleasant
um it's so powerful it's really the way that not self-teaching impersonality can
come in in a very subtle way not in this heady way of it's impersonal but it's like it's just unpleasant it's that's
all it is it's just unpleasant so so um
what this is a one practical way that you can practice with the with vedanta
similarly if it's Pleasant if you find yourself really wanting wanting something more and more and more notice
sweetheart it's it's just Pleasant Veda now I'm just
lusting after Pleasant vedana maybe if you're
daydreaming and you're lost in thought and Castles in the Air oh sweetheart it's just Pleasant it's just Pleasant
fate enough and also notice this is the last thing I say as an invitation for you to uh to
practice with vedanta today v-e-d-a-n-a feeling tone Pleasant
unpleasant and neither is malleable it's not inherent to the
stimulus it's not inherent to the stimulus so for example uh a sound of a
bell uh can sound really Pleasant um
and or or it can if if or can sound very unpleasant and actually it can switch
back and forth and back and forth It's not inherent in the sound of the Bell
um it's really how our mind given the state and expectations and all of that
that cluster of of of all these five condos really the especially the mental
phenomena is is labeling it labeling in a particular result so here see how how
flexible really it is it's not fixed um and that brings a sense of Freedom
that also brings a sense of impersonality it's not personal it's just oh how this mind and this
particular moment given all these cause and conditions that keep changing and shifting and moving uh label this
um this phenomena in a particular way oh sound Pleasant sound unpleasant I notice
sounds because the sounds are one of the easiest wine wants to um uh to ascribe meaning to
ascribe uh vedanta but Sensations too Sensations as well
um but only as only the I may maybe I'll just make one exception no keyceptors
when no conceptors in the body detect pain or noxious stimuli there is a
tendency there they tend to uh inherently feel unpleasant but even them
even them when their mind is really concentrated I I know I've had experiences where sense of pain actually
can even feel wow this is like fireworks in the body there's pain everywhere but
the sensation is so interesting the mind is so concentrated that even this
quote-unquote unpleasant sensation can can feel quote unquote Pleasant because
mind is so concentrated and has so much peace and curiosity about it okay so
thank you so much for your practice for your interest and we will continue with
the five Aggregates tomorrow so please pay attention to vedana today and a whole world will will uh reveal itself
to you be well tomorrow