so hello everyone welcome and
sometimes I think of mindfulness practice as having adventures with
awareness and that uh
life is very different when we're aware so much so that sometimes I think of we
have you know many bodies the body we have and we're not aware and then the bodies we have
when we're aware just all these different ways of experiencing the body and um the mind that's when we're not
aware and the mind that's aware which is so fascinating and the the emotions and what we're aware
and when we're not aware our social life when we're aware and
when we're not mindful it's so varied and become so rich when the mindfulness
is there the awareness is there and it becomes so variable
um it becomes almost like three-dimensionalers four-dimensional or something
um when there's a clear sense of mindfulness and without clear mindfulness and
kind of uh almost intentional mindfulness or awareness
life can start becoming two-dimensional or one-dimensional
so the um one of their great skills that I've
found very useful for me is being able to sometimes almost
simultaneously be aware of others and myself if I'm in conversation
with people and I like to have this general idea that I'm 50 of my attention is with the
others and 50 attention is here with this person with myself and um and that's why there's a
wonderful balance and there's a check and balance system and so this ability to shift where we
bring our attention to be able to get a richer uh experience
of what's actually happening here uh it can can be involved in any given
moment of mindfulness that we can be aware of an object of
attention and we can be aware of How It's what it's like to be aware of the object of
attention so I can be aware of my breathing and I can be aware of how I am being
aware of the breathing that I'm that I'm straining or pushing or lackadaisical or
lazy or resistant I can be aware that of how uh I'm aware
of it you know that I'm aware of an emotion and I can be aware of where I'm
aware from where I'm aware of it am I aware of it in my head my way with my body uh which of these two is a useful
way of taking in and registering the emotion and um so sometimes I'm with the
emotions sometimes I'm with how I am taking it in oh it's in that place in my body my
place and body feels this way and this is my reaction to it my response to it
and so for this meditation I'd like to suggest that there'd be a very simple alternation for you
maybe almost with the alternation of breathing between being aware of something
and then being aware of how it is for you to be aware of it what's it what's a subjective experience
like for you to be engaged in the mindfulness of something so to clearly see something in its own
right and how then then how is it like to be aware of it and this adventure of kind
of going back and forth not one or the other if it's only how you are about it the
subjective experience which is one extreme that some people take then it's all living inside of this kind of
Labyrinth of self and me and the the impact and what I should do and
you know and judgments about it but if it's all about the object then
there can be losing touch with oneself there can be a strain there can be
attitudes about the object that go unseen but to go back and forth to see both
sometimes to be seemingly simultaneously sometimes by kind of back and forth
so to begin
with the meditation posture
and then gently closing the eyes
and mindfulness awareness practice begins with doing so intentionally
doing so knowingly
consciously
choosing to be aware and to begin by choosing to be aware of
your body
and taking some time to feel your body familiarize yourself with your
body
and then how are you being aware of your body are the judgments fears
resistance ideas
might it be possible to
simplify how you are being aware just aware of
the body
and then to become aware of your body breathing
familiarize yourself with how breathing is at this time
and then how are you in being aware of breathing
do you have judgments ideas of what should be and shouldn't be
do you have expectations and things you're trying to do with your breathing
is there fear is there
concerns about breathing is there enthusiasm
how is it how are you about your breathing
and can you simplify how you are
with mindfulness of breathing so it's simply being aware of the body
breathing
and then gently
going back and forth between how you are in being aware of breathing
and the breathing take a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and then continuing quietly with the meditation
but in some relaxed rhythm
move back and forth between what you're clearly mindful of
a sense of choice to be aware and
intentional about it and then
becoming aware of the subjective experience of what it's like to be aware
how are you being aware
it may be moving back and forth with these two modes
can be done in a way that's quieting
stealing calming here
and as we come to the end of the sitting
who first check in with how you are
how are you and your body and how my things have shifted for you
how are you in your mind
and how my things have shifted for you
how are you emotionally
now how might that have shifted from the beginning of the meditation
and then with how you are what if what's available inside of you
for kindness for Goodwill
for compassion
and how Now to turn your attention to the people of your lives the people you
might see today encounter today
and to consider them to think of them
kindly with friendship Goodwill
have thoughts of appreciation for them
maybe being aware of
appreciating that you can have this ability to appreciate others
to enjoy others to care for others
and then in whatever way that you have benefited from this meditation
Maybe you can
want to use that benefit
to benefit others use that benefit of meditation
to enter into the world caringly kindly
with warmth and friendship for others even if they are not that in return
may we go forth from meditation for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
and may we contribute even in small ways to that possibility
[Music]
thank you
so hello and uh
welcome to this fourth talk on on the shifting perspectives for
awareness or locations for awareness we could ask you know different places
for from which we're aware we could also ask
different locations for what where awareness lands what the focus of
awareness is and we have some Choice around that and
a lot of what the emphasis this week is they use your capacity to for choice and discernment
to become wise about how to use attention
and to begin feeling you have some agency and engagement with how you're
aware so you're aware and effective in a useful way
and this is becomes you know the overall overarching kind of theme since the beginning of the year has been how to
work with challenges and um and the um
and this is an actually an important part challenges of all kinds are challenging
and because of that we tend to be swept into them or focused on them or
but it could also we can we can be very impacted by them and they can be difficult emotionally
physically psychologically and we get wrapped up in that in our
reactivity to them and the impact it has on them but these uh challenges we have
will have uh will be less vulnerable or more or less kind of um
impacted in a negative way if we are engaged in being aware if we
are kind of navigating swimming in the waters rather than just floating and
letting whatever waves come kind of wash over us we're also swimming in the ocean
of change and the world and we're kind of adjusting ourselves according to the
situation so we have some agency some engagement and just the very engagement
of being a whip of exploring how to be mindful is a kind of a protection
from just being too open and too receptive to be impacted by everything
we're still feeling things deeply but we're not uh as vulnerable for it
all if we have some sense of Engagement we have something to do we're
not a helpless and hopeless in a situation so um so one of the things that's uh
very useful to do with awareness practice or with awareness is um when we're in social situations or
in the world especially is to have 50 of the attention on
the people we're with the social situation we're in and 50 of the tension on oneself
this is not an exact number 50 50 but just kind of like approximately half and half
and uh and the idea is to go back and forth or to be aware of both at the same time
and um and if we do only aware of the other person then we're not aware of the impact the
situation has we're not aware of our attitudes and judgments that are coming up we're not aware of
um uh our responses and our intuitions and all these things
and but if we're only aware of ourselves then we're not really taking in all the
information of the other person about listening really well we're not you know a lot of communication is non-verbal and
so if we're not really there to pay attention we don't pick up the non-verbal cues of what's going on in
the conversation and um so to go back and forth and be
aware of both brings us into a nice balance uh if we're paying attention to ourselves we might notice something like
we're not paying attention we're not listening and that's pretty you know dramatic we might also notice that we're
having judgments so we're starting to plan what we're going to say next we might also see that we are impacted
by what's being said and now we're swimming in the in the our the impact
and uh maybe we're crumbling under it or getting tense around it or or getting
assertive and you know and feeling angry all this information is useful
because that comes into play but in the act of communication the act of kind of exchange with people and it's good to be
a knowledge about it to know it also by being aware of ourselves in some
higher quality way we have access to a much greater set of information about
what's happening in the exchange with other people are are psychophysical I'd like to think
of our psychophysical body as being an antenna or many antennas
we have amazing capacities for sensing and feeling and receiving information
from the world around us much of it which people don't Avail themselves to
and uh and so to really begin taking that in by being present to oneself
we're not just aware of ourselves it's not like self-focused we're aware of uh
we're much more present for all the sense apparati all the ways in which
we're taking information and responding and and mirroring the person and all kinds of things
so it's not so much that we're paying attention to ourselves with emphasis on self
we're paying we're here 50 percent here in this body in this
psychophysical system that we happen to be in in order to really take in what's
happening in some deeper way so we're actually better able to pay
attention to others and know people through this kind of being grounded in oneself
by being grounded in other people though we we start we are able to take in more information and we understand them
better and and we offer our kindness I mean paying attention well to other people is a kind thing
the 50 50 division of of attention actually can
make us better listeners the people being listened to might think that you're really present in a full way
uh but uh and they feel it because you are the heightened awareness the
heightened listening I can heightened attentiveness when you can also be present for 50 here in your experience
as I said because of all these different ways that we're attending we're aware of
our posture and posture says a lot about how we're with some other people and if you're
aware of your posture then maybe you would adjust it in a way that you're more connected to what's happening
rather than turning towards the door or ready to leave so one of the choices then we have about
mindfulness and awareness is where is our attention and to be attract
that oh it's mostly with a person of being pulled in and um and one of the places to kind of
start experimenting with with this is if someone's telling a wonderful story or a wonderful joke or or you're listening to
a wonderfully engaging speaker and you're getting pulled into the story of the idea
uh to be to then to kind of how does that feel to lose touch with yourself and be absorbed in what's going on
um if you're really angry with someone are you absorbed in them as the object
of your of blame and are you losing touch with yourself and how to come back into balance is 50
50. and how to take care of yourself so that you can be a better companion a
better listener better participant in whatever situation you're in so we have some choice
about where we put our attention and then how we're aware
and when we're bringing the attention to ourselves we can Are we more
experiencing all this in the body and feeling the feelings we're centered in
the feelings of how it feels to be with the other person hear what's being said and they're internally we're reacting to
our feelings that's one way it's a it's a good way at times
and or am I more in my thoughts and planning what I'm going to say and reacting and reflecting what the
person's saying that's good sometimes but both of these ways sometimes has their their weaknesses to them and is
this really the best way to be with the situation and maybe we should shift or back and
forth and these kinds of kind of Engagement with it
um is a kind of protection from getting uh overwhelmed or being
too impacted by what the situation they're going on uh there's no not as much room in us to
be overwhelmed if we're engaged in a you know in a intentional clear way we
um what's what's going on and um
so this attention 50 to 50 back and forth and um
and um the beautiful thing that can happen is that uh
um it's possible to be very aware of what's happening in the body what's
happening in thoughts what's happening in feelings and all this and very aware of the other person
and somehow The self-concern Falls away the
self-preoccupation the the self-definition the self kind of self
thing that we're so often caught in can fall away so that it's almost like we're
not there but for a very pre but there's a lot of presence we're not there but we're not checked
out we're acutely sensitive to what's happening in this psychophysical body so
we're responsible and caring and and involved but this ego and and uh and
self kind of coagulation around self can relax and Fall Away
as we engage in this kind of full attention and this whole attention is partly
defined by this this half with the other person or the situation and half for ourselves
so I would encourage you to today to look for situations where it might not
be too complicated or difficult to do this kind of work back and forth and um and uh maybe uh
you're listening to some you know a lecture being talk talked or something maybe you're even listening to this one
the YouTube or maybe to me or maybe you
listening to a podcast or something so it's kind of a safe place and then kind
of have a nice rhythm of going back and forth listening and then how does it feel what's how are you as a listener
listening and how are you um or maybe there are certain friends that you can make sense to do this
you're going for a walk with them and that's a great place to kind of do do both
so um um you have an amazing capacity to be
aware and awareness is multifaceted many ways of being aware
and uh that's a very rich life to be able to kind of find your way and
have choice and navigate the different ways that we're aware for the benefit of ourselves and the
benefit of others so thank you and um I look forward to
the last talk in the series tomorrow