good morning and
welcome nice to be back after being gone for a
while so
most recently I was at Spirit Rock teaching a week-long retreat
and I'll be here this week and then I'm going off to teach another Retreat next Sunday
so it is uh poignant for me to be back I appreciate so much the opportunity to do
this teaching and to be with all of you on YouTube and see your names in the chat thank you
very much so
during this week I'd like to generally continue with the topic of compassion that I've
done the last few weeks that I've been here and as we begin today for guided
meditation I would like to suggest a way of beginning
that may come a bit as a bit of a surprise to mindfulness practitioners
and that is to begin by thinking rather than putting your thinking aside
and not giving it any role for this practice
begin with uh thinking for just maybe a minute or two
to think about how you are right now
not just uh you know how are you but to think about it you know what what is it
really and how is it and what might be a wise way
of being with yourself the Way You Are what might be a useful way to practice
given how you are what might be a useful
um what might be a useful posture to be in for meditation
if you're tense Maybe a more relaxed posture if you're tired
maybe a more alert upright posture
if you're aware of how you are feeling emotionally
what would be a useful attitude to have as you meditate
so these are all questions you can ask yourself questions that
attune yourself to what's happening for you and how to meet it in practice how
to include it or how to maybe even what to ignore at times because it's not really to the point
maybe if you're mostly concerned about menus dinner menus for the rest of the
week maybe you don't have to spend meditation thinking about those menus
but maybe there's some anxiety underneath those thoughts sort of think about and recognize What's Happening
Here and if there is anxiety what would be useful
so we'll spend so I encourage you to spending about two minutes now just thinking about
what's happening how to be with it as a way of attuning yourself dialing in
in preparation for meditation
and then if you are concerned with some challenge in your
life and you're thinking about it
is the thinking somehow identified or entangled with the story the events the
situation are there stories though that are self-critical or
involves self-pity feeling sorry for yourself
kind of thoughts do you have if you're aware consider concerned with
some challenge
and then see if you can step away a little bit
and look upon what's happening with the challenge your thoughts and take a minute or so to think about
it as an objective Observer
not identified not critical not wanting anything or not wanting
anything just thinking about it looking upon it
objectively thinking about given that this is going on what's a
useful way to practice with it was a useful way to meditate
maybe to put it aside for now and return to it later when you're
more centered
and now having to spend some time thinking
let the thinking mind rest let it relax
it's done its job and me now it does not need it so much
and now it takes some long slow deep breaths and as you exhale to relax into the body
letting your breathing return to normal and again as in the exhale
softening relaxing the tensions in the body
as you exhale calming the thinking mind
as you exhale letting the Mind rest in the body
the Mind does not have to work so much let it rest in the body
with awareness centered in the breathing
the rhythm of breathing
so then as we come to the end of the sitting
let yourself think again freely about
whatever benefit that has come from this minute sitting meditating
are you more self-aware
are you calmer
are you more centered more grounded
is your heart more open
maybe you're not so aware of specifics
but you appreciate the opportunity to meditate
and imagine what it'd be like think about what it'd be like
to live in the world with those benefits
as you go about your daily life today
how might those personal benefits
be shared with others
so they can benefit as well
may it be to this practice that we do
benefits the world those close to us
those not so close those people we don't know
all beings may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free from all
suffering May beings be free of Oppression
War starvation poverty
and may it be how we live this life of ours
that we support these possibilities
may all beings be happy
[Music]
so thank you all and while I take a moment to
drink my water I'd be curious if some of you would put in the chat
what was beneficial or what was it like to spend the first few minutes of the meditation
thinking in the way that I suggested I'd like to maybe read a range of how it
was
so thank you for that those of you who put chats and I read a good amount of
them but I'll when we finish I'll read them all I appreciate it
so now to give some context for that so this week I'm going to continue with
the topic of General topic of compassion that I've done the last number of weeks
that I've been here and kind of fill in some of the gaps
from before so I did
um some weeks ago I talked about five building blocks
for compassion and that all the building blocks ideally
would be there when we act in the world compassionately or when we feel
compassion and so those are uh you know five A's
so awareness Attunement appreciation
aspiration and action and
I did spend earlier the week before all that a whole week on awareness
different ways of being aware in preparation for looking at compassion
today I'd like to talk about the second building block which is Attunement
and um and as an introduction to this topic of
compassion and Attunement I'd like to repeat something I've tried to say
before is that if we have just one mode of
being compassionate it's easy to be overwhelmed it's easy easy for that mode
to not be the the appropriate mode for some situations we find ourselves in
some people have never kind of considered what compassion is never considered
um different modes and ways of being with suffering some people have only one mode of being
with suffering they're suffering in oneself suffering in others and it's overwhelming or it just kind of awakens
all kinds of feelings of soreness of overwhelm of of life is difficult or I'm
a victim you know it's so hard for me I don't know what to do and this is too much I don't feel safe
there's many kind of ways that people can be impacted by the presence of suffering
some people rush to fix it sometimes they rush to fix the suffering
in the world suffering of others is not really caring for others as it is
trying to stop being uncomfortable oneself they're trying to fix oneself by
fixing others and so there's many ways in which we can find ourselves in relationship to
suffering some of them are not very healthy and some of them are
some of them we identify too much with the suffering or we receive it or take
it in in such a way that we feel challenged by it or feel like now we
have even more suffering of Our Own especially if empathy is understood to be a plain and simple feeling what other
people feel then and it somehow ties into some previous suffering that we carry with
ourselves feeling the suffering of others can trigger our own background and just
cause everything to be so much more difficult so the idea in understanding the
different building blocks of compassion the different qual aspects of compassion is start having some agency in working
with our minds our hearts in such a way that we can be with suffering in a
useful way in a healthy way for ourselves and for others and one of those ways is Attunement
to take time to attune ourselves to the suffering that we're encountering suffering in ourselves or suffering at
others and as soon as we have the notion of we're doing something Attunement
there's a number of things that can happen one is what is Attunement
the other is now we're bringing some ideas some practice
to Bear to address to meet the suffering which is just not just feeling the
suffering uh in some kind of unmitigated way or
feeling of suffering in the old way in which we identify strongly with it or the suffering touches our own wounds
that we may be carrying now we're beginning to engage in agency
that oh I have some ability to do something here to question to wonder to
look at and this kind of arising to the occasion Rising kind of rising to the
occasion to meet it we start bringing I kind of um
kind of personal that keep using the word agency personal
wherewithal a personal involvement that's something different than just being impacted by the suffering
or fixing the suffering so just asking the question what is Attunement
so for this week I'd like to offer five different aspects of that I think are
important for this Attunement coming into harmony with the suffering coming into a healthy balance in relationship
to the suffering and I have the acronym for a touch for
this and it begins with thinking and then
openness to suffering and then
um uprightness in relationship to suffering
and then um communicating that actually talking and communicating
is extremely important part of Attunement and then the last one is helping to you
know that part of Attunement is to figure out how it can be helpful or how we can serve the situation the best we
can and so the first one involves thinking
um so again this use of agency like okay here's I'm encountering suffering
maybe I feel it deep deeply maybe I Feel It In A moderate way or aware of it some way
now let me think about a little bit how is this impacting me what's a useful stance to be present for
it what background do I have that influences how I experience it and how I
think I should address it and do something with it maybe I carry with me a sense of responsibility for everyone in my family
or everyone in my neighborhood and so when I encounter difficulty it automatically means I have to do
something to fix it I have to solve the problem and to begin thinking about this this is
this really the case is there another way of being with us is there another way of experiencing it or
understanding it and what like for example I'd like to propose that
compassion has a very different it can have a very different quality if if we read about suffering in the
news or hear about suffering from the news where it's far away unconnected to us
versus being present for someone close to us who's suffering in some way we can
feel and read them and know what's going on know the context in the situation in the news we know so little about the
context we know so little about it all that there's a rush to
relying on our thinking mind of what it means and and what the
opinions we have and the imagination about what this affects people and and
so it's a kind of cognitive uh explosion
that might not be the best source for compassion it might be the best source
for alarm it might be a best source for anger for distress
but and and those emotions can then get confused for Compassion or feel like of
course this is part of compassion to have those but to to spend some time not just being
mindful of the impact and how we're feeling but to actually think it out
that because in our mindfulness tradition we don't talk much about actively thinking having critical
thinking skills that's easy to imagine that this practice of ours does not
involve wise thinking there's there's wise mindfulness this
wise concentration that often isn't presented as a letting go of the
thinking mind and that can be do us a disservice if we
think that we're not supposed to think or we don't kind of we become kind of
lazy with the thinking mind thinking is a rich part of our life it
gets us in trouble into big trouble at times but thinking also is very
helpful if we can think out what does it mean to be attuned here what is a certain kind of balanced way
of being present for suffering what is the way of being in harmony with it
rushing to judgment is not Harmony rushing to fixing is not Harmony
uh immediately kind of feeling and getting
it preoccupied with the impact that the suffering has on us is not really in harmony so what is what
is it to be harmonious even just that question begins creating space
create a little bit of healthy distance Maybe and healthy receptivity
and um and so partly the part of this kind of ability to think about
situations where suffering is involved is to think about the common responses
that we have think question them is this really the best way is this really wise is this really coming from some place of
love or care or is it um is it appropriate for the situation
to think about a situation where they're suffering is to think about what's the
context of this suffering what's my role in it and what's the role of other
people given the context given the people who are suffering do I understand them well
or am I projecting my own assumptions on them I've sometimes have compassion for
people suffering who were not suffering but I've been in similar situations they
were in and and so I I was kind of thinking of course they're going to have
the bad experiences one of the places I saw that was with my kids when I had challenges in elementary
school and um and uh often when I also I started a lot of
different schools Growing Up So changed schools a lot so kind of a new kid in the school and
and question for example being accepted or being bullied or different things that were kind of a concern
and so simplistically to say it like when my sons went into this in the I
mean I knew they were going to go into the playground I had this concern for their well-being oh they're certainly going to suffer they're going to get the
same experience and so I tried to wanted to intervene or say something
but it was all based on my own history my own idea there was no compassion needed uh some of the situations where I
was so concerned and it was more kind of legacy of my own challenges
so there's something about using the thinking mind to think out some people like to journal Journal out and really
think what's going on here in some deeper Fuller way that might not happen if we simply allow
simply rely on our capacity to be mindful to be aware just oh let's just be aware here let me be aware that's it
so to be attuned the first element of Attunement is thinking
don't overthink but don't under think so what I'd like to suggest for you is
that you experiment today with this thinking aspect of Attunement
if you find yourself in a situation where there's some suffering your own or others or something of challenge
don't rush to do something don't shut down but go get a cup of coffee go get a cup
of tea or water or um you know go for a little walk sit quietly for if you can excuse yourself
to go to the bathroom to breathe for a little bit and think it out what's going on here and what just happened and and
what are some of the elements contexts and what does it mean to be attuned here
if um and one one reference point for this Attunement how to be attuned is ask
yourself kind of the exercise how would you like other people to be attuned to you
maybe then you can get some sense of what Attunement means what you can bring
to others and then have conversations with people today about what is Attunement for you
it's not a common word so maybe you're discovering together what is it to be attuned
to the suffering we encounter so thank you very much